The Hallerbos forest is near in Brussels, Belgium.
It is very famous.
Thousands of people visit the forest every spring.
They want to see bluebells.
A bluebell  is a small plant.
It often grows in forests.
It blooms in the middle of April.
It's flowers are blue.
Many bluebells are in holler boss.
It looks like a blue carpet.
Sequoia trees are in the forest, too.
Authorities close the parking lots near the forest.
They cancel buses.
They say that it is better.
If people stay at home, some people still come.
They say that they feel good in nature.
Restaurants and bars closed because of the Coronavirus.
People cannot go to many places.
It is still important to go outside and spend time in nature.