CHAPTER ONE
Mr Murdstone
I disliked Mr Murdstone the first time I met
him.
Perhaps I was just jealous or perhaps it was
more than that.
Certainly he was a handsome gentleman with
dark hair and dark whiskers but there was
something in his eyes that made me feel uneasy.
He began to call at our house and then my
mother started putting on her prettiest dresses
and going out in the evenings.
One such evening my nurse, Peggotty, suggested
that I go with her to visit her brother in
Yarmouth for a fortnight.
I agreed immediately, happy at the thought
of an adventure.
I did not realize how different things would
be on my return.
The day of our departure soon arrived and
Peggotty and I climbed into the carrier's
cart that was to take us to Yarmouth.
My mother and I kissed each other and we both
cried.
When the cart started off she ran after it
to ask for another kiss.
As we rode away I saw Mr Murdstone speak to
her disapprovingly and she lowered her head
submissively.
I shall never forget that holiday.
Peggotty's nephew, Ham, was waiting for us
when the cart set us down.
He swung me on his broad shoulders and took
us to their home.
The Peggottys lived in a boat that had been
taken from the water and made into a small
cosy home.
For a young boy like me it was magical.
My nurse's brother, Mr Peggotty, greeted us
warmly and introduced Little Emily, his niece.
Both she and Ham were orphans.
She was about my age with blue eyes and curls
and I quickly became devoted to her.
When it was time for me to leave we were both
inconsolable.
As we approached home, however, I became excited
about seeing my mother again.
She was not at the gate to greet me and Peggotty
led me into the kitchen.
Now I was worried.
'Where is Mama, Peggotty?
What has happened?
She isn't dead, is she, like Papa?'
Tears filled my eyes.
'Good gracious, no, Master Davy!'
she replied shocked.
'But there is something I must tell you.
You have a new pa!
Come and see him.
And your mama.'
We went into the best parlour.
My mother was sitting on one side of the fireplace
and Mr Murdstone sat on the other side.
As soon as she saw me, my mother smiled and
hugged me timidly.
'Now, Clara, control yourself,' Mr Murdstone
said.
She kissed me avoiding looking at me under
Mr Murdstone's watchful eye.
As soon as I could, I went to my room.
Miserable, I thought of how different things
used to be, how loving and affectionate my
mother had been under Peggotty's indulgent
eye.
I knew that happy life was over and I cried
myself to sleep.
I was awoken by my mother and Peggotty who
had been looking for me.
'Davy, what is the matter?'
my mother asked.
She tried to put her arms around me but I
pushed her away.
'Oh, this is your fault, Peggotty!'
she cried.
'You have turned my boy against me!'
I heard other footsteps and Mr Murdstone entered.
'Clara, my dear, remember yourself!'
'Oh, it is too much!'
my mother exclaimed.
'Can I not have some peace and happiness?'
Mr Murdstone calmed her with a kiss and I
saw immediately that she would do whatever
he said.
'Go downstairs while David and I talk.
We'll join you shortly,' he said with a smile.
When we were alone he asked me, 'Do you know
what I do with a disobedient dog?
I beat it.'
He gave me a hard look and I understood all
too well.
'Now, come downstairs and do not displease
your mother or me again.'
After dinner that evening Mr Murdstone's sister
arrived.
She was dark like him, with the same stern
look, but had a large nose and thick eyebrows
which almost met in the middle.
She had come to help my mother, and started
the next morning by rearranging all our store
cupboards.
From then on she took control of everything.
On the one occasion that my mother asked to
be consulted occasionally Mr Murdstone accused
her of being ungrateful and expressed his
disappointment.
It was enough.
My mother never protested again.
I resumed my lessons with my mother but these
were no longer the happy times they had been
before.
Mr and Miss Murdstone were always present,
always ready to criticize my mother for her
lack of firmness with me and myself for every
mistake.
Mr Murdstone made me nervous and forgetful.
My mother in turn became anxious.
When she thought no-one was looking she tried
to help me but was immediately rebuked by
Miss Murdstone.
My poor mother suffered as much as I did,
if not more.
This continued for several months until one
morning I entered the parlour for my lessons
and saw my mother looking more nervous than
usual.
Mr Murdstone was holding a cane in his hand.
'Now, David, you must be very careful over
your lessons today,' he said.
The effect was, of course, that I became particularly
forgetful and things went from worse to worse.
Finally my mother burst into tears.
'David, you and I will go upstairs,' Mr Murdstone
said, taking my arm.
My mother ran after us but Miss Murdstone
stopped her.
My mother's crying accompanied me up the stairs.
When we got to my room Mr Murdstone suddenly
pinned my head under his arm and raised the
cane in his other hand.
'Please, sir!
Don't beat me!
I'll do better!'
'Really?' he replied and hit me hard.
The hand holding me was near my mouth and
I bit it.
He beat me then again and again with renewed
fury.
I heard my mother and Peggotty crying outside
the door and then it was over.
He left me and locked the door behind him.
I was kept in my room for five days.
The only person I saw was Miss Murdstone who
brought me food but never spoke to me.
On the fifth evening I heard whispering at
my door.
'Davy, my darling?'
It was Peggotty.
'Oh, Peggotty!'
I cried.
'Hush or they will hear us, my lovely.
Listen!
You are going away to school tomorrow.'
CHAPTER TWO
School
I left after breakfast the following morning.
My mother, her eyes red from crying, embraced
me and told me to be good.
Then Miss Murdstone took me to the awaiting
cart.
It was the same carrier that had taken Peggotty
and myself to Yarmouth.
I cried heartily as we drove away.
Then, about half a mile from the house, Peggotty
suddenly appeared from behind a hedge and
got into the cart.
She hugged me tightly, put some cakes into
my pockets, and got out again, all without
saying a word.
I felt a little happier after this and even
more so when I found two half-crowns wrapped
in paper, sent with my mother's love.
As the morning progressed, I shared my cakes
with the carrier and learnt that his name
was Mr Barkis.
He asked a few questions about Peggotty and
then asked me to give her a message when I
wrote to her.
'What message is that.
Mr Barkis?'
I asked.
'Tell her: Barkis is willing', he replied.
I thought it a strange message but kept the
thought to myself.
I very soon fell asleep.
Mr Barkis set me down at the inn in Yarmouth
where, after some dinner, I took the stagecoach
to London.
We travelled through the night and I sat pressed
in between two gentlemen.
Unlike the other passengers I was unable to
sleep.
We arrived in London the next morning.
Nobody was waiting for me at the inn so the
coachman left me in the booking office.
I began to think I might never be claimed
and that perhaps this was Mr Murdstone's revenge,
when a thin young man entered.
His name was Mr Mell and he was a schoolmaster
at my new school.
Salem House was an unwelcoming, square brick
building.
As we crossed the courtyard I remarked to
Mr Mell how quiet it was.
He seemed surprised.
'Copperfield, don't you know it is the school
holidays?
There are no boys here, except you.'
Mr Mell left me in the classroom for a while.
It was a soulless, dirty, long, room which
smelt stale and unhealthy.
I walked up and down the rows of desks, noticing
the scraps of paper on the floor and the ink
splashed liberally about.
At one end of the room I saw a beautifully
written sign lying on a desk.
It said: "Be careful.
He bites."
I imagined it was for a fierce dog and felt
rather alarmed.
So I quickly climbed up onto the neighbouring
desk and proceeded to peer under the other
desks in search of it.
When Mr Mell returned he found me like this
and asked what I was doing.
'I'm looking for the dog, sir,' I replied.
He looked at me gravely.
'I'm sorry, Copperfield,' he said, 'it's for
you.
I've been instructed to make you wear it.'
He helped me down from the desk and put the
sign over my head so that it hung on my back.
How mortified I was!
How I suffered!
I was glad there was nobody there to see it.
As the days and weeks passed I began to dread
the end of the holidays but it was inevitable.
Preparations were made for the boys' return
and one morning it was announced that the
headmaster, Mr Creakle, would return that
evening.
After supper I was summoned before him.
Mr Creakle, who was almost completely bald,
had an angry face with small eyes and nose
and a large chin.
He never spoke above a whisper and, judging
by the veins protruding on his forehead, the
effort cost him dearly.
'I know your step-father, boy,' he said, as
I stood before him.
'And I know something about you: you bite.'
I lowered my head and he continued: 'Let me
tell you something about myself - I'm a Tartar
and very determined.
I do my duty and make sure what I want done
is done.
Nobody stands in my way.
Do I make myself clear?'
'Yes, sir,' I replied, trembling under his
fiery gaze.
'Good.
Now go,' he replied.
I hurried away as quickly as possible.
The first boy I met was Tommy Traddles.
He found the sign on my back so amusing that
he immediately introduced me to all the other
boys as they arrived back.
However, the most important introduction took
place in the playground and was to a boy some
six years older than myself, who was respected
and admired by all the boys in the school.
Steerforth, for this was his name, asked me
why I had to wear the sign and, hearing my
story, declared it was a shame.
I became devoted to him immediately and he
took me under his wing.
School was a sorry business.
Mr Creakle was indeed a Tartar and took great
delight in using his cane.
He seemed to particularly enjoy caning the
chubbier boys and a day never passed without
poor Traddles receiving a beating.
The only exception was Steerforth who Mr Creakle
never raised his cane to.
The months passed and finally the holidays
came and I went home.
I was so excited to see my mother and Peggotty.
My mother was sitting in the parlour when
I arrived, with a baby in her arms.
She looked thinner and more fragile than before,
although still pretty.
On seeing me she got up to embrace me.
'Davy, my boy!
I'm so happy to see you!
This is your little brother,' she said showing
me the baby.
Peggotty came running in then and held me
to her.
'Oh, Master Davy!
Let me look at you!'
That evening was the best day of the holiday
Mr and Miss Murdstone were not at home and
we three all dined together.
I told them about Mr Creakle and Steerforth
and we talked and laughed.
I almost believed Mr Murdstone did not exist
until we heard the door open later on.
My mother suggested I went to bed quickly:
Mr Murdstone did not approve of going to bed
late.
I said goodnight and slipped out of the room.
The next morning Mr Murdstone was sitting
in the parlour.
I approached fearfully and apologised for
biting him.
He accepted my apology coldly but nothing
changed between us.
The rest of the holidays were quite miserable.
Whenever I entered the room in the middle
of a conversation, Mr Murdstone or his sister
stopped speaking and became serious while
my mother looked anxiously from one to the
other.
I, therefore, tried to remain out of the way
and sat silently through meals.
This behaviour drew criticism too and if my
mother attempted weakly to defend me, she
was also rebuked.
Finally, the day came to return to school.
My mother came to the gate to say goodbye.
When I was sitting in the cart, she held up
the baby for me to see and stood that way
as we drove away.
I did not know it but this would be my last
image of her.
Now I must relate the saddest time of my life.
My birthday was about two months after my
return to school.
After breakfast, I was told to go to the parlour.
I imagined that Peggotty or my mother had
sent something for me but was conscious of
something like pity in the schoolmaster's
eyes.
Mr Creakle was still at the breakfast table
when I arrived but he quickly left the room.
His wife sat me down beside her and, with
a sad look, took my hand.
'My poor boy sit beside me.
I'm afraid I have some very sad news: your
mother has died.'
I cried long and hard while Mrs Creakle held
me.
The news quickly spread through the school
and I had the bitter satisfaction of a new-found
status among the boys.
CHAPTER THREE
Everything changes
And so the worst period of my life began.
I was sent home the next day but any hope
I had of finding much comfort there was immediately
dashed.
Mr Murdstone ignored my presence entirely
and sat consumed by his own grief while his
sister busied herself with practical matters.
I saw little of Peggotty except at night when
she sat by my bed and offered me the only
comfort I found under that roof.
The time before the funeral is confused in
my memory but I remember the day itself clearly.
I can still see the best parlour readied for
mourners and later the coffin containing my
mother and baby brother as it was lowered
into the ground.
That evening Peggotty came to my room.
She held me close and told me that my mother
had died in her arms, her last thoughts of
me.
The baby had died the following day.
The first thing Miss Murdstone did after the
funeral was over, was to give Peggotty a month's
notice.
Poor Peggotty was as upset as I was at the
thought of our separation.
After her departure I was almost entirely
neglected.
I ate with the Murdstones when they were at
home, alone when they were not.
Mr Murdstone tried to see as little of me
as possible, my presence, perhaps, irritating
his conscience, and I spent many lonely hours,
weeks, months.
Peggotty, now married to Mr Barkis, came to
visit as often as she was allowed but it was
never often enough.
Then, one day, Mr Murdstone decided I should
be sent to work in his business in London.
I was ten years old.
Murdstone and Grinby's warehouse was in Blackftiars,
on the waterfront.
It was an old building, overrun with rats.
My job, along with four other boys was to
wash, label and pack the bottles of wine the
warehouse shipped overseas.
For this I received six shillings a week.
Lodgings were arranged for me with Mr Micawber,
who I was introduced to on my first day.
He was a rotund middle-aged man with a shiny
bald head.
His clothes were shabby yet he had an air
of kindness.
Mr Micawber lived with his wife and four children
in a house which was as shabby as he was worked
from morning to night and spent all my earnings
on my breakfast and supper, which was often
an inadequate affair.
I was quite miserable at work, feeling the
full shame of my situation and the divide
between myself and the other men and boys
there.
I had no friends, so I became attached to
the Micawber family.
Mrs Micawber freely confided all of her husband's
financial problems to me and enlisted my services
in selling household possessions.
Thus I bore not only my own misery but also
my worries for this kind family.
Finally Mr Micawber's problems reached a crisis.
Unable to repay his creditors, he was arrested
and taken to a debtors' prison.
Soon afterwards the family furniture was sold
and Mrs Micawber and the children moved into
his cell with him.
I did not want to be separated from the only
family I knew in London so lodgings were found
for me near the prison.
After several weeks Mr Micawber was released
from prison and we were all reunited.
However, he decided to leave London and wasted
very little time in preparations.
We spent their last evening together and Mr
Micawber offered me some fatherly advice.
'My dear Copperfield,' he said, 'learn from
my mistakes.
Never put off until tomorrow what you can
do today.'
I promised not to.
After my friends left I felt I could bear
it no longer at Murdstone and Grinby's and
a plan formed in my mind.
I would run away.
I remembered my mother telling me about my
father's aunt, Betsey Trotswood.
Disappointed that I was a boy and not a girl,
she had severed all ties with my mother at
my birth.
Despite this, I decided to find her and ask
for her help.
I shall not relate my journey: how I was robbed
almost immediately of my possessions, how
I walked all day and slept in fields at night,
selling my jacket and waistcoat in order to
buy food.
It is enough to say that six days after I
left London I arrived, exhausted, starving
and half-clothed in Dover and began to enquire
after my aunt.
I was lucky and after no more than half a
day I was following her maid along a cliff
road to the pretty cottage in which my aunt
lived.
There, aware of my terrible appearance, my
courage failed.
Having stood outside for a while I was intending
to leave when an elderly lady came out of
the cottage.
She was wearing gardening gloves and a handkerchief
over her bonnet and held a large knife in
her hand.
'Go away!
I'll have no boys here!'
she said angrily before turning away.
I approached and, timidly touching her, said,
'Please, ma'am.
I'm your nephew, David Copperfield.'
'Good gracious!'
she exclaimed, sitting down quickly.
A series of emotions passed across her face.
I hurriedly told her all my story and then
burst into tears.
Seeing this she took me by the collar, led
me into the cottage and lay me on the sofa.
She then instructed her maid, Janet, to ask
Mr Dick to come downstairs.
Soon afterwards a grey-haired gentleman appeared.
'Mr Dick, do you remember my nephew David
Copperfield?'
she asked him.
'Well, this is his son and he's run away.
What should we do?'
Mr Dick considered for a moment and then said
'Give him a bath.'
And so I was bathed, fed and, much restored,
put to bed.
The following morning I entered the parlour
feeling quite hopeful.
My aunt was an austere woman but not unkind.
Perhaps she would let me stay with her.
'Good morning, David,' she said.
'I have written to your step-father and told
him to come.'
'Oh, must I go back?'
I asked, my voice failing.
'I haven't decided.
We shall see,' she replied.
My hopes died.
On the morning Mr Murdstone came, we were
sitting in the parlour.
Aunt Betsey suddenly saw a lady on a donkey
approach the house.
My aunt never allowed donkeys on the grass
and angrily shook her fist at the rider from
the window.
Recognising Miss Murdstone, I quickly informed
my aunt of the rider's identity.
'I don't care!'
she cried and ran outside, shaking her fist
again.
Mr Murdstone was walking up behind his sister.
They both looked at my aunt in surprise.
She ignored them and chased away the boy leading
the donkey.
Then she marched back into the house and waited
for Janet to announce the visitors.
'Miss Trotswood,' said Mr Murdstone on entering,
'I have come to take this ungrateful boy back.'
'Really?
David, are you ready to leave?'
my aunt asked me.
'No!
They never liked me and made Mama unhappy
about me too!
Please don't send me back with them!
I was so miserable!'
I exclaimed.
'This is ridiculous!' said Miss Murdstone
indignantly.
'I wonder, would you treat your own son like
this and send him to work?' my aunt asked
Mr Murdstone.
'I can do what I like with the boy.
I must warn you, Miss Trotswood, if you decide
to keep him I shall close my door to him forever,'
Mr Murdstone said sternly.
'So be it!
I shall take my chances with him.
Good day to you both,' my aunt replied coldly.
'Janet, show them out!'
Furious, the Murdstones marched out of the
house and out of my life.
CHAPTER FOUR
A new life
My life now took a happy turn.
I became good friends with Mr Dick and my
aunt, who called me Trot, grew very fond of
me.
She decided to seek the advice of a certain
Mr Wickfield, her lawyer, regarding a suitable
school for me in Canterbury.
I accompanied her to his house.
When we arrived a pale youth of about fifteen
opened the door to us.
He had extremely short red hair, no eyebrows
or eyelashes and was bony and ill-proportioned
with skeleton-like hands.
His name was Uriah Heep.
'Uriah, is Mr Wickfield at home?'
my aunt asked.
He showed us into the study.
Mr Wickfield soon arrived.
He was an affable gentleman with white hair
and a complexion which suggested a little
too much port.
He was able not only to recommend a school
but to offer me lodgings in his house.
Then he introduced me to his daughter, Agnes.
She was about my age with a gentle face and
such a calm spirit that I have never forgotten.
I knew immediately that we would be friends.
So time passed.
I attended Doctor Strong's school.
It would be impossible to find someone more
different from Mr Creakle: Doctor Strong was
one of the kindest, gentlest men I have ever
known and my schooldays there were happy ones.
I was also happy living in Mr Wickfield's
house and grew close to Agnes, coming to consider
her as a sister.
The only person I did not like there was Uriah
Heep.
I had disliked him instinctively on first
meeting him and the years did nothing to change
this.
He continually referred to himself as 'a humble
person' and had snakelike movements and ingratiating
ways which repulsed me.
Finally, the time came for me to leave school
and take my place in the world.
I was seventeen.
At my aunt's suggestion, I took some time
to think about what I wanted to do next, and
decided to visit my dear old nurse, Peggotty.
I took the stagecoach to London, stopping
for the night at an inn there.
As I sat near the fire, a handsome, well-dressed,
young man entered the room.
It was Steerforth!
'Steerforth!
Don't you recognise me?'
I asked, approaching him, hand outstretched.
He looked at me hard and then I saw recognition
light up his face.
'Why it is Copperfield!' he exclaimed, shaking
my hand heartily.
'I'm so glad to see you!'
I said, tears coming to my eyes.
We sat and talked.
He was on his way from Oxford University to
see his mother and suggested I went with him.
I agreed happily and we set off the next morning.
I spent a delightful week with them during
which Steerforth taught me to ride.
When I finally made up my mind to continue
my journey, Steerforth decided to accompany
me.
And so, we travelled to Yarmouth together.
When Peggotty recognised me, joy spread across
her face and we fell into each other's arms.
Steertorth charmed Peggotty with his easy
ways and affection for me.
That evening, we all went to Mr Peggotty's
little boat and knocked on the door.
We could hear the sound of laughing and celebrating
coming from inside.
'Look who is with me, brother?'
Peggotty said, indicating myself.
'Why, Master Copperfield!'
Mr Peggotty exclaimed, shaking my hand and
then Steerforth's.
'What are you celebrating, if I might ask?'
I enquired, looking round the room at everyone.
'Such good news!
My Emily is to marry Ham!'
Mr Peggotty said happily taking Emily's hand
in his.
She blushed prettily.
What a beauty she had become!
Ham stood grinning with pride.
'Well!
Congratulations!'
I said, shaking his hand and smiling at Emily.
We spent a happy evening.
Steerforth entertained everyone with stories
of the sea.
Emily sat in a corner but observed and listened
to everything.
When we left her blue eyes followed Steerforth.
We remained in Yarmouth for a fortnight although
not always together.
I enjoyed wandering on my own and went to
visit my childhood home.
Sadly, I found the windows closed up and the
garden overgrown.
Steerforth spent a great deal of time with
Mr Peggotty, sailing.
At last, a letter arrived from my aunt, reminding
me of my purpose and inviting me to join her
in London.
It was decided: I would become a proctor.
My aunt found me a position as a clerk with
'Spenlow and Jorkins' and we found lodgings
nearby.
Imagine my delight when I met Traddles again
in London, lodging with my old friend Mr Micawber!
After a trial period, I was articled.
Mr Spenlow invited me to his house, Norwood,
for the weekend.
When we arrived, he immediately called for
his daughter.
We entered a room and there she was.
Dora Spenlow!
I fell in love instantly.
Later, we walked in the garden together.
She wore a straw hat and, had such blue eyes
and curls!
A little black dog, Jip, was by her side.
We made idle conversation and walked together
to the greenhouse.
There, she stopped to admire the geraniums
and, laughing charmingly, held Jip in her
arms.
I followed her from flower to flower, her
slave.
Dora became my life.
I thought of her constantly and walked along
the road to Norwood so many times hoping to
see her that I soon became well- known there.
I saw Steerforth occasionally when he came
up to London.
On one such occasion he brought me news from
Yarmouth.
Mr Barkis, Peggotty's husband, was dying.
I resolved to go to Peggotty and obtained
permission from Mr Spenlow.
In the days following Mr Barkis's death, I
helped settle his affairs for Peggotty and
then stayed for the funeral.
That evening we were all to meet at Mr Peggotty's
house but Ham and Emily did not arrive.
After a while, I went outside and saw Ham
there, his head in his hands.
'Ham, what is the matter?'
I asked.
He looked at me with dead eyes.
'How can I tell him, Master Davy?
How can I tell him that Emily has run away?'
he exclaimed.
'Run away?
Where to?
Who with?'
I asked.
I looked at Ham's face and knew.
Steerforth.
You may well imagine the misery that I witnessed
that evening and the feeling of loss greater
than death that fell upon the house.
Mr Peggotty resolved to find Emily and never
rest until he did.
My sadness at the Peggotty's troubles weighed
heavily upon me and was lightened only by
an invitation to Dora's birthday party.
It was a picnic in the countryside.
A young man with red whiskers claimed Dora's
attention and in a state of jealousy, I flirted
with the nearest girl I could find.
I was miserable all afternoon.
I was planning to leave when Dora approached
with a friend.
'Mr Copperfield you are unhappy.
Dora so are you,' the wise friend said.
'Stop this silliness now before it is too
late.'
Without thinking I took Dora's hand and kissed
it and she let me.
I offered her my arm and we walked together.
I do not know where.
What joy!
The next day I determined to declare myself.
Alone with Dora I told her how happy I had
been with her the day before.
When she doubted it, I took her in my arms
and told her that I worshipped her.
Jip barked and growled but I did not stop.
I told her I could not live without her.
She cried and I held her more tightly.
Soon we were engaged.
CHAPTER FIVE
Dora
Apart from Agnes, to whom I wrote immediately,
and Dora's wise friend, Miss Mills, who she
was staying with, we told no-one of our engagement.
We met when we could and exchanged letters
daily.
We were so happy and in love!
However, this carefree existence did not last
long.
A series of events tested our love.
The first was the discovery that my aunt was
ruined.
I found her, and Mr Dick, sitting outside
my rooms one day.
This news was a terrible shock and I confess
my thoughts were not only for my aunt.
I was poor now too and not the same man Dora
had given her heart to.
My aunt stayed with me and we found accommodation
for Mr Dick.
I immediately spoke to Mr Spenlow about my
circumstances but he was unwilling to release
me from my articles.
Consequently I determined to find additional
work to support myself.
I was lucky.
My old teacher, Mr Strong, needed a secretary
and we arranged that I should work for him
for a couple of hours in the mornings and
evenings.
The following Sunday I went to confess everything
to Dora.
'My darling, could you love a poor man?'
I asked, kissing her hand.
'Don't be so silly, Doady,' she replied, calling
me by her pet name for me.
'I shall make Jip bite you if you don't stop!'
When she realized I was serious she began
to cry.
I comforted her and promised to work hard
and make everything right.
'Don't talk about hard work,' she said.
She was terrified by the idea and more so
when I suggested she learn something of how
to keep house and cook.
She trembled and cried.
I resolved not to worry Dora again with such
matters.
The second and third events came together.
Mr Spenlow discovered our relationship and
threatened to change his will if I refused
to give Dora up.
He gave me a week to consider.
That same night he set out for home but died
on the way.
Dora was distraught at her father's death
and refused to see me.
In fact there was no will, but there were
debts and Dora was sent to live with two old
aunts.
I was very depressed by my separation from
Dora and, seeing me in this state, my aunt
sent me to Dover to check on her cottage and
its new tenant.
I stopped in Canterbury on the way back to
visit Agnes.
Mr Micawber was now working for Heep.
He opened the door to me.
We talked for a while before Agnes arrived.
I confided all my problems to her and felt
peace in doing so.
She was always so kind and tender.
She advised writing to Dora's aunts, telling
them everything and asking for permission
to visit from time to time.
I immediately saw the wisdom of her words
and resolved to write that day.
Uriah and his mother now lived in the house
and so were present at dinner.
I was conscious of them both watching Agnes
and me throughout the evening.
They seemed like a pair of evil bats to me.
The mother was constantly present the next
day too until, unable to bear her presence
any longer, I went for a walk to escape.
I soon heard footsteps behind me.
It was Uriah.
'Why do you and your mother keep watching
Miss Wickfield and I?'
I asked him.
'You are a dangerous rival, Mr Copperfield,'
he replied.
'Rival?
Do you think I consider Miss Wickfield other
than a sister?'
'Perhaps, perhaps not,' he said, 'but you
must know, I hope to make her mine one day.'
'She is as far above you as the moon,' I said
with feeling.
He smiled slyly.
That evening after dinner Mr Wickfield, Uriah
and I were alone.
Uriah encouraged Mr Wickfield to drink and
proposed a toast to Agnes.
'Ah, Mr Wickfield, to be her husband....'
I heard a terrible cry from Mr Wickfield.
'Oh, this is torture!' he exclaimed.
'Is it not enough that I have let him into
my business and my house?
That I have lost my good name and reputation?
No, he wants my daughter too!
It is too much.'
'Be careful what you say!
Remember I know things, Mr Wickfield,' Uriah
said menacingly.
Agnes arrived then.
'Papa, what is wrong?'
she asked.
'Come, let me help you to bed,' she said,
then looked at myself and Uriah.
I left Uriah there too and went upstairs.
I was greatly troubled by what I had seen.
Agnes came to me later.
Her eyes were red from crying but she smiled.
'Agnes, promise me you will not think of sacrificing
yourself to Uriah.'
She smiled sadly and left me.
I left the next morning full of concern.
The letter I wrote to Dora's aunts on Agnes's
advice bore fruit.
I was invited to call.
The aunts had considered my letter carefully
and would allow me to visit every Sunday and
twice during the week.
I agreed immediately.
Dora came in then.
How happy I was to see her and how she cried!
Let me turn my recollections to a later date.
I am twenty-one and Dora and I are married.
Among my other occupations I have begun writing
and Dora is never happier than when she sits
next to me in the evenings, a supply of pens
in her hand.
She feels she is helping me and I indulge
her, loving to see her so happy.
I remember it all so well!
We had a little house in Highgate but Dora
proved incapable of mastering accounts or
cookery.
One evening after a disastrous dinner she
sat on my knee with her arms wrapped around
my neck.
'Doady, I'm so sorry.
Will you do something for me?
Will you think of me as your 'child-wife'?
Then, when I do something wrong, perhaps you
will forgive me more easily,' she said, earnestly.
'My child-wife,' I said, holding her close.
I was rewarded by her beautiful laugh.
I never forgot this heartfelt appeal and,
although I sometimes wished she were more
practical, I learned to accept her as she
was and always loved her dearly.
In our second year of marriage Dora fell ill.
We thought she would soon be her old self
again but it was not to be.
She spent more and more time resting on the
sofa during the day and I carried her tenderly
to bed in the evenings.
News came of Emily.
She had been found!
Mr Peggotty thought it would be best for her
to start a new life far away and decided to
emigrate with her to Australia.
He asked me to accompany him to Yarmouth to
tell everyone and, leaving Dora in my aunt's
care, I agreed.
I did not feel I should be present when he
told Ham so I left him to break the news.
Later I saw Ham standing alone looking out
to sea.
We talked briefly but never directly about
Emily.
Feeling he wanted to ask me something I went
to look for him the next day.
'May I ask you something, Master Copperfield?
Should I see her before she leaves?' he asked
me.
'No, I don't think so.
I think it would be too hard for her,' I replied.
'If you want to tell her something, I could
write a letter for you, Ham,' I offered.
'Thank you.
You are a gentleman and so much better with
words than I am.
I don't think I can forgive her or forget
her but I don't want to weigh heavy on her
heart.
Tell her that I'm fine.
Not that I shall ever marry or anything, but
I'm fine,' he said.
Poor, honest Ham!
I promised to write for him.
Mr Peggotty emptied his little home the next
day and packed the few things he wanted to
take away and we travelled back to London
together.
CHAPTER SIX
Endings and beginnings
I shall now relate how Uriah Heep was exposed
for the villain he was but, to do so, I must
first go back a little in time.
Shortly before Emily was found I received
a mysterious letter from Mr Micawber: he was
coming to London and wished to meet with me
and Traddles.
We waited for him at the appointed time and
found him to be quite agitated.
Wanting to get to the bottom of things, I
invited him to come to Highgate with me, where
I would introduce him to my aunt.
He accepted.
My aunt and Mr Dick welcomed him warmly.
He was moved by their hospitality but was
clearly upset about something.
'Mr Micawber, you are among friends here.
Won't you tell us what is wrong?'
I asked him.
'What is wrong?
Heep, that is what is wrong!
He is a villain!
When I think of poor Miss Wickfield, so good,
so loving and her poor father...'
Here he became extremely agitated.
'I shall not rest until I have exposed him.
You must all come to Canterbury - one week
from now.'
He left us then abruptly, too upset to continue.
The next day a letter arrived repeating his
request and giving us instructions.
When the time came, my aunt and I were reluctant
to leave Dora but she coaxed us prettily,
saying she was not so very ill.
Not wanting to alarm her with our concerns
for her health, we agreed to go.
So, as instructed, we went to Canterbury and
called at the agreed time to see Agnes.
Mr Micawber opened the door to us, pretending
to be surprised.
Uriah certainly was.
Agnes soon arrived.
Uriah then instructed Mr Micawber to leave
on some business but my old friend refused.
Irritated, Uriah called him a scoundrel and
threatened to dismiss him but still Mr Micawber
stayed.
'The only scoundrel here is you, Heep!
' Micawber declared.
Uriah looked at us all, surprised and then
suspicious.
Ah, this is a conspiracy, is it?
Well, Copperfield you always were jealous
of my rise.
Miss Wickfield, if you love your father, do
not join in this plot.
Miss Trotwood too, if you know what is best
for you,' Uriah said, dropping all pretence
of humility.
The change in him was astonishing.
With his mask off, all his hatred and malice
were apparent.
He seemed to grow in height like an evil genie
and I readily imagined him towering over poor
Agnes and her father, frightening them into
submission.
Or, as he had threatened, turning his attention
to my aunt.
He was dangerous like a cornered wild animal.
Unafraid, Mr Micawber took a burnt pocket-
book from his pocket.
'My wife found this in the fire when we moved
into your house, Heep.
Do you recognise it?'
Uriah tried to snatch it but Mr Micawber was
too quick.
Addressing us he explained, it contains proof
of fraud and treachery carried out over a
number of years.
You see, Heep falsely obtained Mr Wickfield's
signature on important documents and has held
him in his power ever since.
First he obliged him to make him a partner.
Then he systematically forged Mr Wickfield's
signature on accounts and documents.
Poor Mr Wickfield lost his reputation with
his clients and investors and just recently,
believing himself bankrupt, signed a document
giving all of the business to Heep.
I have it here.'
Uriah did not speak.
Agnes cried quietly, thinking of how her poor
father had suffered.
My aunt's reaction was quite different.
'So, you are responsible for ruining me!'
she declared furiously, trying to take hold
of Uriah.
'It is quite clear what must be done,' Traddles
said.
'We must destroy the document giving Heep
the business.
Then, Heep, you must repay every penny you
have stolen.
If you don't, we can arrange for you to spend
some time in prison.'
I still remember the look of defeat and hatred
on Uriah Heep's face.
My darling Dora grew worse.
She no longer left her bed and my aunt and
I spent many hours sitting with her.
Yet she was always so happy and loving, never
complaining.
Time rolls back and I can see it all so clearly.
It is night and I am sitting by her bed holding
her hand in mine.
'Doady, I think I was too young and inexperienced
to be a wife.'
'Don't say such things, my darling,' I say,
laying my face on her pillow.
'No, Doady, it is true.
We are happy now but I am sure as time goes
on you will want more from your companion,
more than a foolish child-wife.
It is better this way.'
'Oh, Dora don't!'
I cry and she comforts me.
'Hush my sweet boy,' she whispers.
'Doady, I would like to talk to Agnes.
Can you send her to me?'
I leave reluctantly to fetch Agnes, who is
downstairs with my aunt.
I sit by the fire while Agnes is with Dora.
Jip, old now, is near me.
My thoughts turn to Dora's words and I feel
full of remorse for ever wishing her different.
I sit like this for I do not know how long.
Then Jip looks towards the stairs, whines
once and dies.
Agnes comes down soon after, tears running
down her face.
My Dora is gone.
My grief was frozen for a time, waiting to
explode fully.
I do not know how but it was decided that
I should travel abroad for a period.
Preparations were made.
The time was nearing for Mr Peggotty and Emily
to depart too.
Mr Peggotty showed me a letter from Emily
to Ham and I offered to take it to him before
they left.
So, once again, I went to Yarmouth.
There was a terrible storm coming.
I could not find Ham and, worried, returned
to the inn.
Later, I was woken by voices calling out that
a ship was going down so, along with others,
I hurried to the beach.
The broken ship was hit by wave after wave.
We watched helplessly as men disappeared under
the sea.
Then I saw Ham and I understood his intention
immediately.
I tried to stop him but he pushed me aside
gently saying,
'If it is my time then so be it, Master Copperfield.'
With ropes around his waist, he went into
the water.
Only one man remained on the ship now, clinging
to a mast.
He waved his red cap in a gesture I thought
familiar.
Ham almost reached him but an enormous wave
hit the ship then.
The seamen pulled on the ropes and brought
Ham back to shore.
He was dead.
Poor honest Ham!
I remained with him until a fisherman asked
me to follow him.
'Is there another body?'
I asked.
He did not reply but walked to the shore.
There, lying as he used to at school, was
my old friend Steerforth.
We carried his body to the inn and, in a dream-like
state, I travelled to break the news to Mrs
Steerforth and then directly on to London.
I was determined to keep the news of Ham's
death from Mr Peggotty and let them leave
happy.
Consequently I assured him that Ham had received
the letter and his thoughts were with his
uncle and Emily.
Mr Peggotty boarded the ship.
As he waved goodbye from the deck I saw Emily
appear next to him and, placing her head on
his shoulder, she waved too.
I travelled abroad from place to place, the
burden of my grief growing heavier and heavier.
I mourned my pretty Dora, my old friend and
kind-hearted Ham.
At times I wanted only to die and end my sorrow.
Then a letter from Agnes arrived.
Her gentle confidence in me gave me heart
and I slowly started to mend and to write.
My feelings for Agnes began to change, or
rather, I understood them better.
I realized I loved her and had always done
so.
I returned to England three years later and
went to my aunt's house in Dover.
We had an emotional reunion.
Talking, I asked her if Agnes had a lover.
My aunt thought there was someone.
I was not surprised and I resolved to hide
my true feelings from Agnes, and this I did
in all my visits.
It was Christmas.
I had understood from my aunt that Agnes would
soon marry.
'Agnes, my sister, do you not trust me with
your secret?'
I asked her.
'Do you think I cannot be happy for you in
your marriage?'
Agnes became upset and started to cry.
Her look gave me hope.
'If I thought you could ever love me as more
than a brother...
you must know I love you.'
'Oh, Trotwood.
I have always loved you!'
she said through her tears.
As I held her close, I fancied I saw Dora
smiling at us happily, giving us her blessing.
We were married two weeks later.
- THE END -