PART ONE
Young love
CHPATER ONE
Two young lives
March 1945
'Megan, make me a cup of tea, will you?'
shouted Harry Jenkins from the front of his
small shop.
'And then come in here and talk to me.'
'Here you are, Dad,' said Megan, giving him
a big cup of hot tea and trying to smile.
Every day it was the same.
As soon as Megan got home from school, her
father asked for his tea and then he wanted
to know everything about her day - what she
had done at school, if the teachers were pleased
with her work, who she walked home with.
She was sixteen years old and she was fed
up with it all.
Why did he have to be so interested in her?
'So, Megan, how was school today?'
'OK,' said Megan.
'Did the teacher tell you about last week's
exam, then?'
'Yes.'
'And?' asked Mr Jenkins.
'And what?' said Megan, knowing very well
what he wanted to know.
'And, how did you do?
Come on, girl, if you're going to go to college,
it's important that you do well at school.'
Nobody from Mr Jenkins' family had ever gone
to college, but now there might be a chance
for Megan.
He wanted, her to get away.
The Welsh village of Tredonald where they
lived was a coal mining village.
Nearly all the men worked down the mine, getting
the dirty black coal out of the ground.
Mr Jenkins didn't want his daughter to marry
a coal miner, or even to spend her life working
in the shop - she was too good for that.
He hadn't asked Megan what she wanted.
At the other end of the village, Megan's friend,
Huw Thomas, was finishing his work for the
day.
Huw was also sixteen years old and already
tired of life.
He worked eight hours a day, five days a week
in the village coal mine.
There was nothing much else for people in
the village.
You either worked underground, or you didn't
work at all.
That was it.
But it was better than being a soldier and
fighting in some foreign country, like a few
of the men in the village.
The prime minister in London kept saying the
war was nearly over, but Huw wasn't sure if
he believed it.
Huw got into the lift at the bottom of the
mine with a group of other tired-looking men.
Their faces were black from the coal and at
first he didn't see his older brother, Gareth,
standing opposite him.
They smiled at each other, but didn't speak.
The lift climbed slowly and noisily up from
the dark underground world.
Fen dirty faces looked up towards the light.
At the top, it took a few seconds for their
eyes to get used to the daylight.
They walked over to the bath house, taking
in the fresh air.
For Huw this was the best moment of the day.
He had only been a miner for six weeks, but
it felt like longer.
Gareth was waiting for him outside.
'All right, Huw?' asked Gareth.
'How was it today?'
'OK,' Huw said.
'It'll get better, I hope.'
'It will,' his brother replied.
'Look at you.
Your arms are stronger already, after only
five weeks.'
'Six weeks,' said Huw.
Gareth laughed.
'It's hard work, all right.
But we're lucky to have jobs.
We need the money, with Dad not working.'
Huw couldn't remember the last time his father
had had a job.
Some days, his father left the house early
in the morning and came home with a bit of
money, or something for them to eat.
And some days he didn't come home at all.
Life was not easy for the Thomas family.
The two brothers walked down their street
and said 'hello' to the wives, sisters and
daughters who had come out of their houses
to welcome home their returning men.
But outside Huw's house there was no-one to
welcome them home.
Huw had never known his mother.
She had died when he was born.
His father and his two brothers, Richard and
Gareth, had been his family.
And now there was no Richard - killed two
years ago while fighting in North Africa.
'Dad!' shouted Gareth.
'We're home.
What's for dinner?'
There was no answer.
'Must be out,' said Huw.
'Or in bed,' Gareth said.
'I'll go and look.'
As soon as Gareth entered the bedroom the
smell of whisky hit him.
His father was asleep on the bed with all
his clothes on.
'Drunk again,' Gareth told Huw.
'Where does he get the money from to go to
the pub?
You didn't leave any in the house, did you?'
'No, of course not.
Except for the money in the box to pay Mr
Jenkins for last week's food.
But he doesn't know where we keep that, does
he?'
Huw took out the small box from its hiding
place.
He opened it.
'He's taken it all!'
'Well,' said Gareth, 'you'll have to go and
explain to Mr Jenkins that we can't pay him
until the end of the week.'
Gareth moved around the small kitchen angrily
opening cupboards looking for food.
'And ask him if he'll give us some bread or
potatoes.
He can add it to next week's bill,' he said.
'Why is it always me who has to explain?'
asked Huw.
'Because you're the youngest and Mr Jenkins
might feel sorry for you,' replied Gareth.
'Go on, Huw.
I'm hungry.'
Huw knew why his father got drunk, but knowing
didn't help.
He was angry with his father.
Nobody would give work to a forty-year-old
man with a drink problem, so Huw had had to
leave school and start earning money.
Megan looked up from her book and saw Huw
coming into the shop.
She thought he looked tired and angry.
'Hello, Huw,' she said smiling.
'You OK?'
'Not really...
the usual things,' said Huw.
Megan and all the village knew about Huw's
father.
Mr Jenkins listened while Huw explained the
latest story.
Mr Jenkins felt sorry for Huw, but there was
nothing he could do about it.
Life was hard for everybody.
It was wartime.
Other families had lost sons in the war: David
Thomas was not the only one.
But he was the only one who had started drinking,
leaving his two sons to look after themselves.
Megan said, 'Feel like going for a walk later,
Huw?'
She and Huw had been friends for years.
They used to sit together at school, and out
of school they spent a lot of time with each
other.
Now their friendship seemed to be getting
even stronger.
'Yeah, great,' replied Huw.
'I'll come here at about seven.
Is that all right, Mr Jenkins?'
'Yes, but not for long, Megan,' said Mr Jenkins,
putting a few potatoes in a bag for Huw.
'You've got school tomorrow, remember.'
But Megan knew the real reason that her father
didn't want her to be out with Huw for long
- he was worried about their continuing friendship.
They were not children any more and Mr Jenkins
had seen how Huw looked at his daughter.
CHAPTER TWO
The friendship continues
Megan lay on the grass by the river with her
hands behind her head, looking up at the sky
and singing softly.
'Don't move, will you?' said Huw with his
back against a tree.
'I'm trying to draw you.'
Megan lay there and enjoyed the warm evening.
Sometimes she didn't know what to say to Huw.
Since he had started work, their lives were
no longer the same, and she knew he was not
happy down the mine.
But this evening, she felt he was the best
person in her life.
'What do you think?'
asked Huw as he gave her the drawing.
He lay down beside her.
'One day, I'll be rich.'
'Oh yeah, how?' she asked.
'I'll sell my drawings to someone, or maybe
I'll go to London and find a good job,' he
replied.
'I like your drawings.
I think you're a really good artist,' she
said.
'But nobody around here has got any money
to spend on things like that.
And going to London is a bad idea - the war
has made it a dangerous place to be.'
'Oh Megan, I can dream, can't I?' replied
Huw.
'Don't you have any dreams?'
'Yes, but they seem to change every day,'
she said laughing.
'Come on!'
Megan jumped up and pulled Huw to his feet.
'Let's walk a bit more, then I'll have to
go home.'
'Can I touch your hair, Megan?' asked Huw
suddenly.
'It looks so soft.'
Megan was surprised, but she said he could.
It was nice to feel his fingers running through
her hair.
Her face began to burn.
Huw looked at her and kissed her.
It seemed the right thing to do.
'Don't,' said Megan, but didn't move away.
'If my father could see us now, he'd never
let me come out with you again.'
'Sorry,' said Huw, not quite knowing what
to do next.
There were all sorts of feelings inside him
that were new and wonderful.
'Megan, do you like me?' asked Huw, still
standing close to her.
'Yes, of course I do,' replied Megan.
'We've been friends for long enough - you
know I like you.'
'But I mean...
"like" in a different way, not just as brother
and sister,' said Huw.
'I think you're wonderful.
Will you be my girl?'
'Oh Huw, yes, I will be your girl,' said Megan.
'But we mustn't tell anyone.
My parents...'
But Huw stopped her.
'And if we both feel the same in two years'
time, then I shall ask your father if I can
marry you.'
Huw's mind was running ahead.
Megan laughed.
'Yes, but for now we must make everyone think
that we're still just friends.
Nobody must see us holding hands or anything.
If my father hears about us, he'll stop me
from seeing you.
You know what he's like.'
They walked home, happy in each other's company.
Huw forgot his problems at home and work,
and Megan forgot the college plans her father
had for her.
She knew he had high hopes for her.
And a poor coal miner with a drunken father
was not one of them.
CHPATER THREE
Romance grows
Over the next few months, life in the mining
village continued in much the same way.
When the war in Europe ended, there were wonderful
parties in the streets of Tredonald.
Everybody hoped that life would be a lot easier
- but it wasn't.
People worked as hard as ever, and there was
still very little to buy in the shops.
Megan and Huw spent as much time as possible
together, taking long walks in the evenings
or sometimes going to the Saturday night dances
in the village.
'Will you dance with me on Saturday, Huw?'
Megan asked as they sat together one evening
on top of the hill, looking down on the village.
'Of course, if you're not too busy dancing
with other men,' he replied.
Huw loved dancing with Megan.
It was the one time he could put his arms
round her in public.
And if they planned it carefully, they were
sometimes able to walk home together.
They had become good at keeping their love
hidden.
But they had to dance with other people, too,
and Huw hated the way other men held Megan
so close that her body was pressed against
them.
'What about you?' said Megan.
'You danced with Ruth Hopkins for ages last
month... and you were laughing!'
Huw remembered that evening, too.
He had enjoyed Megan watching him dancing
with Ruth.
But it had been a quiet walk home that night.
In winter, it became difficult to go for walks.
It was dark when Huw finished work and the
weather was cold.
And every time he went to the shop, Mr Jenkins
was there.
'I wish we had somewhere warm to go,' said
Megan one cold and windy day in February.
'What are you doing on Saturday evening?'
asked Huw.
'Nothing - studying or helping at home.
Why?'
'Do you think you could come out?' said Huw.
'There's a new American film on in Afon.
Let's go.'
'It's a long way.
How will we get there?'
Megan asked...
'I'll borrow a couple of bicycles,' said Huw.
'Can you think of something to tell your parents?'
'Not at the moment, but I will before Saturday,'
replied Megan.
The thought of sitting in a warm, comfortable
place with Huw for two hours was wonderful.
She would think of some story to tell her
parents.
Anything.
On Friday afternoon, Huw was on his way home
from the mine when he met Gareth on his way
to work.
The mine was open twenty-four hours a day
and Gareth was working nights that week.
Huw didn't like it when he and Gareth worked
at different times - they never seemed to
see each other.
At home, Huw took some money out of the money
box.
He tried not to think what Gareth would say
if he knew.
But he wanted to buy Megan a present.
This Saturday was going to be a night to remember.
* * *
Saturday evening at the cinema was wonderful.
Being away from the village made Megan and
Huw feel free.
For once, they were able to walk down the
street holding hands, without thinking about
other people seeing them, and in the cinema
they both found it difficult to watch the
film.
'Huw, stop...
please,' said Megan quietly after a long kiss.
'We should try and watch a bit of the film.'
But they soon turned to each other again.
The lights went on as the film ended and they
stood up slowly.
Neither of them wanted to leave.
Outside was real life; inside they could be
together.
They cycled back towards Tredonald and Megan
could feel her heart getting heavier as they
got nearer.
They stopped just round the corner from her
flat.
'This is for you, Megan,' said Huw, giving
her a small box.
'I hope you like it.'
He watched her face as she took out the silver
necklace.
'It's only second-hand,' he continued.
'One day I'll buy you a new one.'
'Oh Huw, I don't want a new one, this is lovely,'
said Megan, putting it round her neck.
'But it must have cost you a lot.'
She knew he didn't have much money.
'Come here, my girl,' he said.
'Stop talking and give me a goodnight kiss.'
But suddenly there was a loud noise from the
mine.
'Christ!' said Huw.
'What the hell was that!'
But they both knew what it was.
It was the sound the village hoped they would
never hear.
All along the street, doors opened and men
and women came out.
They ran towards the mine, all thinking of
the men who might be caught five-hundred metres
below the ground: 'Please God, don't let it
be my husband, my brother or my son.'
CHAPTER FOUR
Death at the mine
People of all ages stood around in small groups,
talking in low voices, it was three o'clock
in the morning, four hours later.
Huw was standing with his father.
One look at his father's face had told Huw
what he didn't want to know: Gareth was down
the mine.
Part of the roof of a tunnel had fallen down
and some miners were on the wrong side of
the fallen rock.
A team of men had been called in to help and
had brought up ten men safely.
As this group arrived at the top, the waiting
families pressed forward looking for their
loved ones.
Gareth was not one of the ten.
The mine manager came over to Huw and his
father.
There's still hope, David,' he said.
'The team say they can hear noises behind
the rock,'
'How many are still down there?' asked Huw.
'Five.
It'll take some time before we reach them.'
Huw and his father said nothing, and the mine
manager walked away to say the same thing
to another family.
During the long wait David Thomas and his
son, Huw, stood together without speaking.
From time to time, one of them lit a cigarette
and they drank tea which was given to them
by kind neighbours.
Megan came and stood with them and put her
hand into Huw's.
She looked into his eyes and saw he was afraid.
It was ten o'clock when they brought out Gareth's
body.
He and two other men had died in the rockfall.
The two others had been lucky.
Gareth came home to the small house.
His body lay in the front room and his father
sat beside him.
The neighbours came to say a sad goodbye to
the young man they had known so well.
Huw's father said nothing as people came and
went.
He sat by Gareth's side until it grew dark.
When Huw came in to say goodnight, it was
as if his father hadn't heard.
Huw woke in the middle of the night and couldn't
get back to sleep.
It seemed wrong to be safe and warm in bed
while his brother lay cold downstairs.
He decided he would go and sit with Gareth.
He got out of bed and walked towards the front
room.
As he got there, he saw the door was open
a little.
He stopped.
By the light of the moon, Huw could just see
his father: he hadn't moved from his son's
side.
In the quiet, Huw could hear his father's
crying and his low voice asking again and
again why this had happened.
But his words fell into darkness and were
lost.
Slowly, Huw turned and went back to bed.
He stared into the night for a long time and
let the hot wet tears run down his cheeks.
For a few days after Gareth's death, Huw's
father sat at home.
He and Huw slowly began to talk - first about
Gareth and then about Richard's death in the
war in North Africa.
Both of them cried and tried to help each
other, but Huw could see that deep inside,
his father was angry.
Angry because death had taken away three people
he loved - his wife, Richard, and now Gareth.
'Just you and me now, boy,' said his father.
'I don't want you to go back down that mine.'
'I've got to, Dad, you know that,' replied
Huw.
'What else can I do?
There's nothing in Tredonald - only the mine.'
His father said nothing.
That evening Huw met Megan down by the river.
It was their first time alone since Gareth's
death.
She listened as he talked about how empty
the house was without his brother.
Gareth had taken care of Huw when he was younger
and together they had looked after their father.
Without him, he felt alone.
'You're not alone,' said Megan.
'You have me.
Nothing will change that.'
She could see that Huw was hurting inside.
She wanted to wash it all away, but knew that
the only thing she could do was listen.
Huw loved her for being so strong and understanding.
Suddenly, he took hold of both her hands.
'Will you marry me?' said Huw.
'What?
Yes, of course I will,' smiled Megan.
'But
'Don't say "but".
I know all about the "buts",' replied Huw.
'It's enough that you've said "yes".'
They kissed and only stopped when Megan felt
the tears running down Huw's face.
Megan and Huw walked slowly back towards her
home.
'Hey look, there's your Mum and Dad,' said
Huw, watching as Mr and Mrs Jenkins closed
the front door of the shop behind them.
'Yes, they're going to visit Aunt Mary,' replied
Megan.
'You can come in, if you like.'
They went upstairs to the flat above the shop
where Megan and her family lived.
Megan realised it was the first time she and
Huw had been there alone.
There was a warm fire burning in the sitting
room.
They sat together on the sofa and talked,
and Huw cried some more.
Megan held him in her arms until he was quiet.
Then they started kissing and their kisses
became stronger and stronger.
Megan got up and went out of the room.
Huw didn't know what to do, but just then
she returned.
She had taken off all her clothes and was
standing there with the light of the fire
behind her.
'Oh Megan, you're beautiful,' said Huw.
'But... are you sure this is what you want?'
'Yes, Huw,' said Megan in a quiet voice.
'Don't talk, just come to me.'
They made love on the floor.
For both of them it was the first time and
it was wonderful.
CHPATER FIVE
Leaving Tredonald
The day that Huw went back to work, his father
started drinking again.
It was a terrible day for both of them.
Huw had to make himself get into the mine
lift.
It was very difficult for him to go down to
the place where Gareth had died only a week
before.
Half an hour after Huw had left the house,
David Thomas walked into the Red Lion pub
and stayed there all day.
His own house was too quiet, and remembering
was too painful.
Drinking took away all the hurt.
So, in the Red Lion, he drank and forgot.
Over the next few weeks, there were days when
father and son never met.
But one day, Huw got a call from the police
station.
David Thomas had started a fight in a pub.
The police were called and Mr Thomas was taken
to the police station.
'He broke some tables and chairs in there,
you know,' said the policeman to Huw.
'He's a strong man, your Dad - and even stronger
when he's had a bit to drink.'
'I know,' said Huw.
'What happens now?'
'Well, you're lucky,' replied the policeman.
'Old Brian Morgan, the pub manager, said he
won't take the matter any further.
And we won't either...
this time.
But it must never happen again.'
'We can't go on like this,' said Huw to his
father, as they walked back home.
'I know, son, I know.
I promise I'll stop.
It won't happen again, you'll see.'
But David Thomas's promises didn't last very
long.
Soon he started drinking again.
The people in the village had understood at
first: 'Poor David, he's had a lot of sadness
in his life.'
Now it had all changed.
Even his friends were no longer so patient
with him.
Huw's time with Megan was the only time he
felt really happy.
Their love for each other was strong.
They talked about their present and their
future.
They talked about Gareth, which was good for
Huw.
His father often got angry when Gareth's name
was spoken at home, but Huw needed to remember
his brother.
'You know, Megan,' said Huw very quietly,
as they sat on top of the hill.
'My father has got to get away from here.
I think it's his only chance of getting his
life together.
If he stays here, the drink will kill him
- one way or another.
And I don't think I can let that happen.'
'What are you saying, Huw?' said Megan.
She could see from his face that it was difficult
for him to speak.
And there was a bad feeling growing inside
her.
Huw looked at her and continued.
'We had a letter, when Gareth died, from Uncle
Edward in Canada.
He's Dad's brother.
He went to Toronto when I was about four.
Anyway, he's asked us to go and live with
him.
He says he'll send the money for the boat.'
And do you want to go?'
Megan asked.
'Oh Megan, how can you ask that?
You know I don't ever want to leave you,'
answered Huw.
'But if...
'
'Can't your Dad go on his own?'
Megan's voice was very quiet.
'Don't you see?
I'm part of the problem,' said Huw, holding
Megan's face in his hands.
'He won't go and leave me working in the mine.
I see him looking at me and remembering what
happened to Gareth.
He hates the mine and everything in Tredonald.'
'And what about us, Huw?'
There was sadness in Megan's voice.
'You are the most beautiful thing in my life,
Megan,' said Huw.
'I won't lose you.
But I have to go with him.'
Huw pulled her into his arms and for a few
minutes they held each other.
'Do you think you can wait for me?' asked
Huw.
'I don't know.
What do you mean?
Wait until you come back, wait for how long?'
Megan began to cry, Huw held her closer.
'Uncle Edward says there's lots of well-paid
work in Toronto.
It's a big city, not like here.
I might even be able to do something with
my art.
I know I'll be able to earn money quickly,
and I won't spend much.'
Huw was talking fast now.
And then, say, in a year I'll be able to pay
for you to come out and join me or... or I'll
come back here and we'll get married and both
of us can go back to Canada.'
'You seem to have everything planned,' said
Megan in surprise.
'No, I haven't, but do you think it's possible?'
'Yes... oh I don't know...' said Megan.
'Shall I talk to your parents about our plans?'
asked Huw.
'No, not now,' answered Megan.
'I'll talk to them.
I'll have lots of time to choose the right
moment.'
'And another thing.
If I can earn some good money in Toronto,
your father may realise that I'm different
- not just a village coal miner, but someone
with a future, someone good enough for his
darling daughter.'
Huw knew Mr Jenkins would be happy to see
him go to Canada.
'Oh, Huw,' said Megan.
She couldn't believe how this evening's conversation
had completely changed her world.
***
So on April 28th 1946, David Thomas and his
only son, Huw, left the village of Tredonald
for a new life in Canada.
For Huw and Megan, saying goodbye was the
hardest thing they'd ever had to do.
They met in their usual place by the river.
'I'll think about you every day,' Huw said,
holding her close and never wanting to let
go.
And I'll write the minute I get there.'
Megan was crying onto his shoulder.
'I know you think I'm a strong person, but
when you're in a new country, everything will
be different for you.
You'll meet a lot of new people.
I'll be here doing all the same things.
Do you think we'll feel the same about each
other in a year's time?'
Huw pulled back and looked deep into her eyes,
'I will, Megan,' he said.
'I know I'll never change.'
They kissed one last time and then she watched
as he disappeared.
The minute he was gone, Megan felt that a
part of her had died.
PART TWO
Fifty years later
CHAPTER SIX
A surprise find
Tredonald 1996
Megan and her daughter, Beth, sat in the front
room of Megan's home.
They were going through some old boxes full
of cards, old newspapers, photographs and
letters.
'Well!' said Beth, looking up from her box.
'I can't believe Grandma and Grandpa kept
all these things!'
'I know,' said Megan.
Her parents had died some years ago and she
had found all these boxes in their bedroom.
But until now she had never really looked
through them.
'Well,' she continued, 'only one box left.'
I have to go now, actually,' said Beth looking
at her watch.
'Philip's expecting me home by five,' Philip
was Beth's husband.
'You go then, dear.
I don't want to stop until I've finished everything
up here,' Megan said.
I'll ring you this evening, Mum,' said Beth.
'Don't do too much and make yourself tired.'
'I won't.
Thanks for your help earlier,' said Megan.
She heard her daughter close the front door.
Megan wanted to finish.
She wanted to ring Paul and tell him how well
she had done that day.
They were getting married in two months and
she was moving into his house in London.
It was quite a big house, but it was already
full of his things.
She couldn't take all her parents' things
with her as well as her own.
She had to throw away a lot.
Megan pulled the last box towards her.
She looked inside.
More letters.
She took out a few and looked at the envelopes.
She couldn't believe what she saw.
They were all addressed to her and they were
all from Canada.
And none of them had been opened.
She looked at the dates - 1946 and 1947.
'Oh, my God,' she said.
'Huw!'
Her hands were shaking as she started to read
one of the letters, dated August 1946.
My lovely Megan
I still haven't received a letter from you.
I can't believe it takes four months for letters
to cross the Atlantic.
What's happened'?
Is something wrong?
Megan sat for hours reading every letter.
At the end she felt completely empty and tired
and her heart was full of pain.
She remembered all the love that she and Huw
had felt for each other when they were young.
But more than that, she remembered how terribly
hurt she had been when no letters had arrived
from him.
She had spent many nights crying in her room.
Now she realised what her father had done.
He had hidden the letters and watched her
unhappiness.
She knew that her father had thought Huw was
not good enough for her, but she never realised
he'd been so much against him.
Megan took the letters downstairs.
She sat with them beside her, drank a large
whisky and then wrote a letter to Huw.
She had no idea if he would ever receive it.
'He won't be at the same address after fifty
years - he might even be dead,' she thought
to herself.
But she knew she had to write.
* * *
Toronto 1996
'Dad, letter for you,' shouted Mike Thomas.
His father was working in his painting studio
at the top of the house.
'OK, Mike, I'll be down in a minute,' said
his father, Huw.
Mike put the letter on the kitchen table,
and went back into the garden.
It was June and the weather was hot, but there
was a light wind.
'Where's the letter then?' asked Huw Thomas,
standing at the door and holding two cans
of beer.
'On the table,' replied his son, taking one
of the beers.
Huw picked up the letter and read the postmark
'Tredonald'.
'Wales!' said Huw in surprise.
'Who's writing to me from there?
It's years since I had any news from back
home.'
Huw still talked about Wales as 'home', although
he had lived in Toronto all his adult life.
He saw that the letter was addressed to Huw
Thomas, 2300 Ontario Drive, Toronto.
That was where he and his father had lived
in their early years in Toronto.
Someone there had discovered where he was
living now and had re- addressed the letter.
So who was writing to him?
He turned the envelope over in his hands several
times.
Then he took out the letter and read:
Dear Huw
I don't know if this letter will reach you,
and I don't really know why I'm writing to
you after all these years but...
Huw turned to the end of the letter and saw:
With best wishes
Megan
He couldn't believe it.
He turned back to the first words of the letter
and read:
...after all these years but I've just found
your letters to me from Canada, when you first
got there.
Believe me, this was the first time I'd read
them and they made me cry, even after fifty
years.
I found them in a box of my father's papers.
They were unopened.
Huw, I never knew that you'd written to me.
I thought your new life in Canada had made
you forget me.
Now I realise that my father kept your letters.
I can still remember asking him if there was
any post for me and he always said, 'No, he's
forgotten you, my girl.
I told you he was no good.'
Finally, after about a year, I believed him.
But why did he keep the letters?
Do you think he waited me to find them when
it was too late?
Anyway, he's dead now so I can't ask him.
All I can say is I'm sorry.
Sorry for what my father did, sorry that you
never heard from me, and sorry for... everything.
I hope that at least this letter reaches you.
Of course, I'll understand if you don't want
to write back to me, but if you do, I am still
Megan Jenkins and I still live at the same
address in Tredonald.
Best wishes
Megan
Huw read the letter again.
Megan and their time together in Tredonald
came back to him.
He had never forgotten her.
He couldn't.
Every day he looked at her face on the wall
of his studio.
He had a drawing of her which he'd done when
they were sixteen.
It had travelled everywhere with him.
But to hear from her again...
'Are you all right, Dad?' asked Mike, coming
into the room.
'I've just heard from someone I knew a long
time ago,' Huw replied.
'Is it someone you knew back in Wales?'
'Yeah.
I can't believe it really.'
Huw explained about Megan and their young
love and what he had thought when there were
no replies to his letters.
He tried to keep his voice light.
Mike didn't need to know how deeply they had
loved each other.
'Her father sounds terrible,' Mike said when
his father had finished.
'Not really.
He just wanted the best for his daughter,
and he didn't think I was the best,' replied
Huw.
'And he never read my letters so he didn't
know I was doing well over here,'
'Did Mum know anything about this Megan?'
asked Mike carefully.
'I told her that there had been someone else
at home, but...
I mean, I didn't meet your mother until...
what... ten years after I'd left Wales.
So Megan was part of my past - part of another
life.'
Huw stood up and looked out of the kitchen
window across the garden, thinking about Megan
- and his ex-wife, Josie.
He and Josie were married for twelve years
before they got divorced.
They said it was because there were too many
differences between them, but Huw knew that
Megan was part of the problem.
Josie always thought he loved Megan more than
her.
So what he had just said to Mike wasn't really
true.
Megan had not been only in Huw's past.
Mike came and stood next to him.
'Are you going to write back to her?'
'I don't know,' replied Huw slowly.
'I need time to think about it all.
It's all so sudden.'
Huw took the letter and went back upstairs
to his studio.
He did no painting for the rest of the afternoon.
He just sat looking out of the window.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Time to decide
Megan's letter had turned Huw's world upside
down.
In the days after he received it, he went
for long walks by himself.
His head was full of things that had happened
to him over the last fifty years.
He remembered how alone he had felt when no
letters had arrived from Megan all those years
ago.
At the end of his second year in Toronto,
he had had enough money to go back to Wales,
but he hadn't gone.
He believed that Megan no longer loved him
and had forgotten him, so he tried to do the
same - forget her.
Both Huw and his father had worked hard in
their new country.
They had found work in a factory that made
cars and David Thomas had stopped drinking.
He'd married again and been happy.
The Canadian years had been good for his father
until he'd died eighteen years ago.
Now Huw was a well-known artist and people
paid thousands of dollars for his art.
Two months ago, Time magazine had even written
about him and his latest paintings.
His love life, however, had not been so great.
Since his divorce from Josie, there had been
other women in his life, but as he got older
these friendships seemed less important.
His life was full and interesting in other
ways - painting, of course, fishing and walking
in the forests and mountains.
He was happy that Mike and his family were
sharing his house.
He had more than enough money to do what he
wanted.
But now Megan had come back into his life.
On one of his many walks, he read Megan's
letter for the twentieth time.
She said she was still Megan Jenkins.
'So,' Huw thought, 'she never got married.'
He remembered her as a warm, loving and intelligent
person and thought it was sad that she had
never shared all this with a man.
Then he laughed at himself.
'Maybe she was happy to be single,' he thought.
'Or maybe she was married and something happened
and she changed her name back to Jenkins.
What does it matter?
It's all in the past now.'
When he arrived back home that evening he
told his family that he had made a decision:
he was not going to write back to Megan.
His life was here now.
Better to let the past stay in the past.
Later in the evening, Huw went back upstairs
to his studio and, for some reason, started
looking through some of his early work.
There were paintings and drawings of his that
he hadn't looked at for years.
He found some drawings he'd done in the first
few months after he'd arrived in Toronto.
Most of them were of ships.
He remembered he used to think about getting
on one of the ships and sailing away.
Sometimes he had wanted to sail back to Wales
and Megan, and then later he'd just wanted
to escape to anywhere.
He spent the next few hours lost in his thoughts.
It was five o'clock in the morning when he
looked at his watch and slowly went to bed,
his head still full of the past.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Telling Beth
On Saturday, Megan drove out of Tredonald
towards Cardiff.
She was on her way to Beth's house for lunch.
Her thoughts, however, were not really on
the road but on the letters and Huw.
She didn't know if she'd done the right thing
writing to Huw.
Was it brave or was it just stupid?
And what was she going to say to Beth today?
And what about Paul?
Did she need to tell him about the letters,
too?
Of course they'd talked about Huw, but it
was different now.
Huw was no longer safely in the past: he was
once again very much part of the present.
But Paul was her present - and her future.
At the age of sixty-six, and for the second
time in her life, she was making plans to
get married.
She'd met Paul Henderson some years ago through
her work for the Welsh Tourist Office and
they'd become good friends.
Neither of them were working now so they were
able to go on holiday together.
Paul had taken her to places like Japan and
Peru - places she'd always wanted to visit.
And slowly the friendship had developed into
something more.
Megan stopped the car outside Beth's house.
Beth was in the front garden, waiting for
her.
'Morning, Mum,' she said, giving her mother
a kiss.
'Journey OK?'
'Yes, fine.
It's much quicker now they've opened that
new bit of road, isn't it?'
Megan followed her daughter into the house.
'Where's Philip?'
'Playing golf,' replied Beth.
'He'll be back this afternoon.'
Megan was pleased.
She loved her son-in-law but what she had
to say was for Beth.
It would be easier to talk to her alone.
After they'd finished eating, Megan took some
of Huw's letters from her handbag and put
them on the table.
'I found these the other day,' she said.
'You know, in that last box.
After you'd gone home.'
'Who are they from?' asked Beth as she passed
her mother a cup of coffee.
'Well, that's just it...'
Megan stopped.
She knew that this moment was important for
Beth.
'They're from Huw...
Huw Thomas...
your father.'
'My father!
Good God!'
Beth looked at the envelopes on the table
and then looked at her mother.
She'd always known about her father - her
mother had told her everything when she was
young.
But for years she'd never thought about him
- Huw Thomas was just a name, not a person.
'Here,' said Megan, giving Beth one of the
letters.
'You can read this one.'
Beth read it quickly.
'How many more letters are there?'
she asked.
About fifty.
They stopped in 1947,' said Megan quietly.
'He didn't write after that.'
'So you never knew anything about them...
That means grandpa or grandma just hid them
from you and...'
'Yes, it was my father, I'm sure.
I don't think my mother knew about them either.
It was my father who was so against Huw.'
'But you were going to have a baby, you were
expecting me.
Huw was my father.
How could he?'
Beth was lost for words.
'I know, Beth.
It's difficult to understand.
All I can say is my father was doing what
he thought was right for me.
He wasn't a terrible person.'
'I know,' said Beth.
'I loved him.
He was great to me when I was little.
That's why it's so hard to believe.'
'My father always wanted me to do well in
life,' said Megan, trying to explain.
'He wanted me to go to college and be better
than the other young people in the village.
He never thought Huw was good enough for me
and he clearly thought I would have a better
life without him.'
'But that was your decision to make, not his,'
said Beth.
'Remember, I was only seventeen - still a
child in his eyes.
Maybe he was right.
I mean, they looked after you when you were
a baby and I was able to go to college.'
Megan turned to her daughter.
'And we had a good life together, didn't we?
We made a happy family.'
'Yes, Mum, it's OK,' said Beth putting her
arm round her mother.
'And what about you?
How do you feel about it all now?'
'I've written a letter to Huw, but it probably
won't reach him.
I just felt I had to say something - better
late than never.'
Megan laughed sadly.
'Did you tell him about me?'
Beth asked.
'No, I thought we should wait until...
if... he writes back.
I hope he does write back.
I want to know about his life.
Was I wrong not to tell him, do you think?'
'I want him to know about me, if he's still
alive,' replied Beth.
'Yes, I understand,' said Megan.
'To tell you the truth, Beth, it's brought
back a lot of old feelings.
We were very much in love, even though we
were so young.'
'I remember you used to talk about him.
And he always seemed so wonderful to me as
a child.'
Neither of the women said anything for a few
minutes.
Then Beth asked, 'And are you going to tell
Paul about all this?'
'Yes, of course.
But it doesn't change anything,' said Megan.
'I'm still going to marry Paul.'
CHAPTER NINE
A second letter
Huw got another surprise when a second short
letter arrived from Wales.
Dear Mr Thomas
I know that my mother, Megan Jenkins, wrote
to you two weeks ago.
I hope you got that letter.
For some reason, I think you did.
'Ah!
So she did get married,' thought Huw.
She told me about your letters that she'd
found, and I've talked a lot about you.
But there was something in her letter that
she didn't say.
It's quite easy for me to write, but probably
not easy for you to read.
I am your daughter.
I was born on November 14th, 1946, seven months
after you left Tredonald.
So you can see - if you get this letter - that
both of us really would like to hear from
you.
With best wishes
Beth Jones
Good God!
Was it true?
Did he have a daughter?
It could be true - the dates were right.
He remembered the one and only time that he
and Megan had made love.
It was quite soon after Gareth's death down
the coal mine, and they'd been alone in her
parents' flat for the first time.
'I'm sorry, Megan,' said Huw, talking to his
drawing of her.
'Did you hate me for what happened?'
He had to write back to Megan.
They had a daughter!
How strange that sounded!
What was she like?
There was nothing in Beth's letter to help
him get any idea of her.
He wanted to meet her, but would she want
to meet him?
It'd be very difficult for all three of them
- there was fifty years of nothing between
them.
That night Huw told Mike and Mike's wife,
Rebecca, about the letter.
Neither of them really knew what to say.
Mike found it hard to understand that his
father had a daughter, a daughter his father
had never known about.
To Rebecca it all seemed unreal.
'Wait a minute, Huw,' she said.
'Someone writes to you saying she's your daughter
and you believe her?
How do you know for sure?'
'It's true,' said Huw slowly.
'In my heart, I know it's true.'
He looked at Mike and Rebecca and said, 'Anyway,
I've decided I am going to write back to Megan.
We'll see what she says.'
CHAPTER TEN
Writing back
Two weeks later, it was Megan's turn to receive
a letter.
When she saw it lying on the floor by the
front door, her heart jumped.
She knew it was from Huw.
She sat with a cup of coffee, looking at the
envelope.
Finally, she opened it.
Some photographs fell out.
And there he was - smiling at her.
She smiled back at him, her eyes full of tears.
My dearest Megan - after fifty years it's
good to say that again.
Thank you for writing to me, but why didn't
you tell me about Beth?
No, I don't think I need to ask that question.
As I'm sure you know, she wrote and explained
everything.
I think it's wonderful that we have a daughter.
But, Megan, I wish... so many things!
I'm trying to picture your life with a baby.
Did you marry?
Did Beth grow up with a father?
How much did you hate me all those years for
leaving you alone?
I need to know more than letters and photographs
can tell me.
Would it be all right if I came to Tredonald
to see you and Beth?
I want the three of us to get to know each
other.
I'm sending you some photographs of me and
my family.
I have a son, Mike, and two lovely grandchildren...
Megan read to the end of the letter.
Beth had told her about writing to Huw, so
that wasn't a surprise.
But to actually read his words and see his
face again - it was almost too much for her.
It was time for Megan to speak to Beth.
They had to make a decision together.
Did they want Huw back in their lives, or
should they continue as before - just the
two of them.
And then there was Paul to consider.
Huw waited impatiently for an answer from
Megan.
In his head, he had many wonderful conversations
with the two of them.
But he knew that it was not going to be that
easy.
Then soon after his letter to Megan, he received
a reply - just a short letter with a photograph
of two women.
'My God!' he said quietly, talking to her
photo.
'Just look at you!
You're still my lovely Megan.
And this is our daughter, is it?
Yes it is, I can see it is.'
He then turned to the letter and read it through
until he reached the final two lines:
PS Here's a photo of Beth and me which was
taken in the sitting room above the shop.
Remember?
How could he forget - they had loved each
other in that same room fifty years before.
He remembered the feel of her soft lips and
the smell of her dark hair.
He looked back at the photograph.
The two women were sitting on a sofa together
and holding hands, both of them looking at
the camera and smiling.
Huw stood in front of the studio window and
cried.
So many years had passed and so much time
lost.
Seeing how close Megan and her daughter were,
it was painful to think that he had not been
a part of it.
He turned the photograph over.
On the back was the date and the words, 'Beth
and I would like to meet you.'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Home to Wales
Huw, Mike and Rebecca were sitting in the
garden of their house, drinking wine on a
warm evening.
'So that's my half-sister, is it?' asked Mike,
looking closely at the photo.
'Let's see,' said Rebecca.
'Oh yes!
Look at her nose, Mike.
It's just like yours!'
'Rubbish!' said Mike.
He turned the photo over and read the message.
'Are you going over to see them, Dad?'
'Yes, I think so.
Is that OK with you?'
'It's a big step, but how can you not go and
see your daughter?'
replied Mike.
'You'd never be able to live with yourself.'
And Megan, too,' said Huw.
'I do want to see her again.'
'Hey, how about this for an idea?' said Mike
suddenly.
'I'll come with you.
I'd be really interested to see Tredonald.
It's part of our family's life, isn't it?
You and grandpa never really talked much about
the place.
You just used to say that Toronto was much
better.'
'Yes, I know,' said Huw with a laugh.
'We arrived just after the war in Europe.
Life was very difficult in Wales when we left.'
'How about it then?
You and me,' said Mike.
He was getting quite interested in the idea
of travelling with his father.
'Another time, Mike,' said Huw quietly.
'This time is for me.
OK?'
'OK,' said Mike, and then added, 'as long
as you don't decide to stay in Wales.'
'Don't worry,' said Huw.
'I'm not going to stay there.
My home is in Canada, my work is here, you're
here.
I'll be back.'
* * *
So at the end of the month, Huw flew to London.
He'd written to Megan, and to Beth, to say
that he was coming, but hadn't said which
day.
He'd decided not to, then he could change
his mind at the last minute if he wanted to.
But now the plane was about to land.
His hire car was waiting for him outside the
airport.
He had slept well on the plane so he was able
to keep a clear head for driving.
And he needed it - driving on the left was
not easy!
The nearer he got to Tredonald, the more unsure
he became.
He realised that he was afraid of what might
happen.
Half of him was afraid that he wouldn't like
Megan, or Beth, and the other half of him
was afraid he would like them too much.
He was a man who liked to know what he was
doing and why.
Before he'd received Megan's first letter,
his life had been well organised, but now
it was different - he felt like a sixteen-year-old
again.
It was not just Megan and Beth - it was also
Tredonald.
He and his father had left it so long ago
and at a really bad time in their lives.
He had no idea how he was going to feel when
he saw the place again.
Just outside Tredonald, he stopped at a pub.
He needed a drink.
The barman put a glass in front of him.
'Are you here on holiday?' he asked,
'Sort of,' replied Huw.
'We don't get many people here on holiday.
There's nothing to do here, nothing to see
really.'
'I used to live here many years ago,' said
Huw.
'Did you now?'
The barman looked a bit more interested.
'You'll see some changes then.'
'Mmm,' said Huw, trying to enjoy his rather
warm beer.
'What about the mine in Tredonald?
Is it still working?'
'No, it closed about fifteen years ago.
Well, it's still open but only for tourists,
not for coal.'
But Huw didn't want to talk any more.
'Is there a public phone I can use?' he asked.
'Through there,' said the barman showing him
a door to the left of the bar.
Huw went through it.
He picked up the phone and rang Megan's number.
CHAPTER TWELVE
A new start
'Oh damn!' said Megan.
'Why does the phone always ring when I've
just sat down?
Hello?'
'Hello, this is Huw.
Is that Megan?'
'Huw!
Where are you?
You sound so close!'
Megan began to shake.
'I'm in the Rose and Crown, just outside Tredonald,'
said Huw.
'Oh, Huw, why didn't you...'
And then she couldn't continue.
Neither of them spoke for a few seconds.
Neither could quite believe they were so close
to the person they'd lost fifty years ago.
When Megan finally said something, her voice
was lull of tears.
'Let's meet in the Tredonald Arms Hotel.
It's on Bridge Street.
Do you remember it?'
'No, but I'll find it.
See you there in half an hour?'
'No, I need a bit more time,' said Megan.
She wanted some time to get herself and her
thoughts together.
'Let's meet a bit later...
say seven o'clock?'
'Fine,' replied Huw.
'And Megan... it's good to hear your voice.
I can't really believe I'm talking to you
again.'
From the moment Megan had answered the phone,
Huw had felt sure again.
He wasn't worried about how the meeting would
be - he was just impatient to see her.
'I know, Huw,' said Megan quietly.
'I'm happy you're here.'
As soon as she finished talking to Huw, Megan
rang Beth.
'He's arrived,' she said, knowing she didn't
need to say who had arrived.
'And?
Have you seen him?' asked Beth.
Megan didn't reply immediately.
Are you all right, Mum?'
'Yes, sorry dear, I'm meeting him at seven.
But I don't feel very brave.
I think I'm sorry I wrote to him.
I mean...
what are we going to talk about?
Oh Beth, it's all too much for me!'
'Don't worry, Mum,' said Beth.
'I'm sure it'll be fine.
Just take it as it comes.
Ring me later.
And remember, I love you.'
At seven o'clock that evening, Megan walked
into the Tredonald Arms Hotel.
Huw was sitting in a big armchair, opposite
the front entrance where he could watch everybody
who came in.
They saw each other immediately.
What he saw was a slim woman with grey hair
and a strong face.
What she saw was a tall, handsome man whose
face was brown from the sun.
They shook hands, and then he kissed her on
both cheeks.
They both stood looking at each other for
a few moments without saying anything.
Then Megan sat down in the soft armchair.
For the next two hours, they talked.
At first, the conversation had been a bit
difficult with lots of 'I can't believe it!'
and 'Is it really you?' and 'After all these
years'.
But slowly they began to talk as old friends.
It was easy to talk about their homes, work,
Tredonald and Toronto.
But it was more difficult to find the right
words when they talked about Beth.
'Megan, tell me about Beth, our daughter.
I want to know everything,' said Huw.
'I don't think of her as our daughter, I'm
afraid,' replied Megan carefully.
'I've been her only parent all her life.
Of course I've talked to her about you, but
you've never been a real person for her.'
'I'm sorry,' said Huw quickly.
'I didn't mean to...
You're right, of course.
But I want to know all about her.'
'Well,' replied Megan in a more friendly voice.
'She lives in Cardiff, she's married with
three grown-up children, so you have three
grandchildren as well.'
'That makes five.
My son Mike has two - David and Amy.'
Megan nodded and continued.
'She and her husband have their own business
- they're architects.
Beth was always interested in drawing'.
'Like me,' said Huw, pleased that he shared
something with his daughter.
Then he became more serious.
'Your father really hated me, didn't he?
He preferred to let you be an unmarried mother
rather than marry me.'
Huw felt himself getting angry.
'I don't think he hated you - it was more
that he really loved me, or maybe his ideas
for me,' replied Megan.
'Was it hard for you when she was born?'
'Yes and no,' replied Megan, sitting back
in her chair.
'When I told my parents I was pregnant, they
were angry... sad, hurt... everything.
My father had big plans for me - do you remember?
After I had Beth, I went to college and became
a teacher, and he and my mother looked after
Beth.
They were wonderful, really.
They loved her and she had a happy time as
a child.
It was only when she used to ask about her
daddy that the conversation went cold.
But she soon learnt.
Her daddy was somebody she asked me about,
not her grandparents.'
A little bit of sadness had come into Megan's
voice.
Huw took her hand and, for a few seconds,
she didn't realise.
Then she gave a smile and took her hand away.
Anyway, now it's your turn.
I want to know more about you.
You've done very well with your art, haven't
you?
I'm so pleased.'
She was able to look at him as he talked about
his work and she could see the same Huw that
she'd known all those years ago.
She wanted to reach across and touch him,
to reach across fifty years...
But how could she?
It was a fine evening so they went for a short
walk.
Huw needed some fresh air.
He felt tired after his long journey from
Toronto, but he didn't want to say goodnight
to Megan.
They stood looking down at the river.
'We used to spend a lot of time walking by
this river, didn't we?' said Huw.
'Do you remember?'
'Yes, we did,' laughed Megan.
'Well, we didn't have many places.
It was either here or up on the hill, wasn't
it?'
'True,' said Huw.
'And the cinema.
We went there the night Gareth was killed.
'Yes, I remember it well,' replied Megan.
I often think of Gareth.'
'Really?
Why's that?' asked Huw, surprised.
'I sometimes take groups of visitors on tours
down the mine,' replied Megan.
'The tour takes people past the entrance to
the tunnel where the roof fell.
Gareth is always in my thoughts when we pass
it.'
Huw turned towards her.
'But why are you - I mean, when did you start
going down the mine?'
'Oh, it's a long story,' said Megan.
'But when we knew that the mine was going
to close, I had the idea of trying to do something
with it.
I'd stopped teaching so I had the time.
I don't go down very often now.
Most of the tours are done by the older ex-miners.
That was another reason for not letting it
die.
There was nothing else for the men to do.
Now at least some of them have jobs.'
'Good for you,' said Huw.
'You always were a fighter, weren't you?
I think I'd like to go down again.
Would you come with me?'
'You don't need me.
You know it better than I do,' said Megan.
'I did, but not now.
Come with me.'
'OK,' said Megan.
'If you really want to.'
As they walked back towards the hotel, Megan
told him more about her work for the mine.
She explained how difficult it had been to
get money to develop the mine so they could
open it to tourists.
'It took five years, and it was hard work
- but I met some interesting people, including
a very dear person, Paul Henderson, who...
helped me a lot.'
Megan had meant to say 'who I'm going to marry
next month', but she didn't.
At least she'd introduced Paul's name into
the conversation: now she could talk about
him, and maybe the next time she met Huw she
would tell him she was going to get married.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Lunch with Beth
Huw was working down the mine.
Suddenly there was a loud noise and the roof
of the tunnel began to fall.
He put his arms over his head, but the falling
rock knocked him to the ground.
He could see Megan's hands reaching out to
him, but he couldn't quite touch them.
Then more rock fell and all was black.
He cried out and woke up.
He sat up in bed and for a moment couldn't
remember where he was.
He looked around and slowly realised that
this was his hotel room in Tredonald.
He was safe, not down the mine.
He lay down again, but couldn't go back to
sleep.
It was five o'clock in the morning.
He got up and sat by the window of his room
watching the darkness disappear and the sun
rise.
His head was full of thoughts - Megan, Gareth,
his father, Beth - and how life threw things
at you when you were least expecting them.
One thing was clear to him, however, and that
was how he felt about Megan.
He loved her.
Maybe not in the same way as he had when he
was seventeen, but he knew that she was still
the only one for him.
Being with her again felt right - it was like
coming home.
He wanted to be with her for the rest of his
life.
He was sure about this.
And Megan?
What did she feel about him?
In the next few days, he would find out.
He got back into bed and fell into a deep
sleep.
It was the sound of the telephone that woke
him.
'Mr Thomas' said a voice.
'There's a lady here in reception for you.'
'Thank you,' said Huw, looking at the clock.
'Tell her I'll be down soon.'
It was ten o'clock!
Megan was waiting for him.
They were going to Cardiff to meet Beth.
He had the fastest shower ever, got dressed
and was downstairs in the hotel reception
in fifteen minutes.
'Sorry, Megan,' he said, giving her a kiss
on the cheek.
'I had a bad night.
I was still asleep when the phone rang.'
Megan smiled.
'Would you like me to drive?
You can take it easy.'
'Good idea,' replied Huw, returning her smile.
He was happy to see her and to know that they
were going to spend the day together.
As Huw opened the door of the car for Megan,
he saw that she was wearing a silver necklace.
'Megan, you've still got it!'
'What?' said Megan, but her hand immediately
moved to touch the necklace.
'Oh, the necklace.
Yes, of course I've still got it.
I often wear it.'
Huw sat beside her as they drove out of Tredonald.
She told him how important the necklace had
been to her in the early days.
It was the only thing she had from him - except
for Beth, of course.
Huw told her about the drawing he had of her
and how it went everywhere with him.
Megan felt comfortable with Huw next to her.
She, too, had not had a very good night's
sleep - too many things going round in her
head.
But today she felt better.
She started talking about Beth.
She knew that Beth was a bit worried about
meeting her father for the first time, and
she thought that Huw was probably feeling
the same.
Megan and Huw entered the cafe where they
were meeting Beth.
Huw's eyes searched left and right, looking
for the right face.
A tall woman with dark hair stood up and walked
towards them.
She put her arms round Megan and held her
for a moment.
Then she looked at Huw, put out her hand and
said, 'Hello, I'm Beth.'
'Hello, I'm...'
Huw stopped himself from saying 'I'm your
father' and said, 'I'm Huw.'
He took both her hands in his.
They looked long and hard at each other, searching
for something that showed they were father
and daughter.
Megan spoke.
'Look, I'm going to do some shopping.
I think it's better if you two talk without
me here.
I'll be back in about an hour or so.'
And without giving either of them time to
say anything, she walked out of the cafe.
From the moment Huw and Beth sat down, they
didn't stop talking.
She told him about growing up in the flat
above the shop in Tredonald, about her life
now, her kids, her husband.
She was completely comfortable with him.
'Mum loved you, you know,' said Beth.
'Even when she didn't hear from you, she still
loved you.
In fifty years, she didn't say one bad thing
about you.
Not like grandpa - he didn't like hearing
your name.'
Beth laughed.
'I loved her, too,' said Huw.
'The first years in Canada were so difficult
for me without her.'
'She's a wonderful person,' said Beth warmly.
'I hope she's going to be happy now.'
'I want to make her happy,' replied Huw, not
understanding Beth's words.
'Beth, I still love her.
I want to marry her.'
'Oh!' said Beth, and realised her mother had
not told Huw about Paul.
She had to say something.
'Huw, has she talked to you about Paul, Paul
Henderson?' asked Beth.
'She said he was a friend - why?'
Beth was quiet and Huw added, 'Is there something
more between them?'
'Yes,' said Beth.
'They're planning to get married next month.
Mum's going to move to London.'
'Does she love him?' asked Huw, quietly.
'I think so...
I don't know really...
You'll have to ask her.'
Beth liked Paul very much and believed that
he was good for her mother.
She thought they would have a happy future
together.
But she also knew that things were no longer
that easy now Huw had come back into their
lives.
She knew her mother still felt very deeply
about Huw - but it wasn't for her to say anything.
Her mother must decide for herself.
'Have you told her how you feel?' asked Beth.
'No, it's too soon.
I want to give her time to love me again.
Then I will.
I'm not going to lose her a second time,'
said Huw quietly.
'I'm sure Mum will tell you about Paul.
She doesn't like hiding things.
And anyway, he's coming to Tredonald at the
weekend.
We're all having dinner together.
Maybe you can meet him and see what you think.'
Beth looked at Huw carefully and added, 'Please
be careful.
I love my mother very much.
I don't want anybody to hurt her.'
Huw touched Beth's hand and said, 'I won't
hurt her - not again,'
Beth smiled at him and then looked up to see
her mother coming into the cafe.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
In love
On the drive back to Tredonald, Huw talked
about Beth - how much he liked her, what a
warm person she was, how he wanted to see
more of her.
He'd decided it was safer to talk about Beth
rather than about him and Megan.
'She's coming up to Tredonald on Saturday,
to have dinner with you and Paul, isn't she?
Perhaps I'll be able to spend a little more
time with her then,' said Huw.
'Yes, that's a good idea,' said Megan.
'Beth's told you about Paul - that we're getting
married?
Yes, of course, she did.
I'm sorry, Huw, I did mean to tell you yesterday,
but it didn't seem the right time.'
'When are you marrying him?' asked Huw.
'21st September.
I'm in the middle of selling the shop and
the flat at the moment.
And when that's all finished, I'll move to
London.'
Megan didn't feel very comfortable talking
to Huw about her future life with Paul.
However, he seemed to be OK about it.
'And what about Tredonald and all your friends
here?
And Beth in Cardiff?
Won't you miss it all?' asked Huw.
'Yes, of course,' said Megan quietly.
'It'll be strange at first, but I'm ready
for a change.
The mine is working well - they don't need
me anymore.
Beth and the grandchildren have their own
lives.
And Paul and I haven't hurried - we've got
to know each other very well - and I know
we'll be happy together.
I've told him about you, and I'd like you
to meet him on Saturday.
Will you join us for dinner?'
'Thank you, I'd like to.
And can I ask you, Megan...
do you love him?'
Huw had to ask.
He couldn't just continue being nice.
He couldn't hide what he felt any longer.
'Do you feel that you can't live without him?
Are you happy every time you see him or hear
his voice on the phone?
Can you....?'
Huw had many more questions that he wanted
Megan to answer, but she stopped him.
'Huw!
Why are you asking me all this?' asked Megan,
in surprise.
'It isn't any of your business how I feel
about Paul!'
'Maybe not,' replied Huw.
'But I want you to be sure that you're doing
the right thing, and for the right reasons.'
Megan stopped the car at the side of the road
and turned to face Huw.
'Of course I'm sure,' replied Megan a little
angrily.
'Because I think we still love each other,'
said Huw.
'Well, perhaps I should say that I know I
love you.
I've always loved you.
Even when I was married to Josie, deep inside
I knew that - and I think she did too.
And I think you still feel something for me,
don't you?'
Megan sat looking straight ahead.
She didn't know what to say.
'I don't want you to marry Paul,' he continued.
'I want you to marry me.
And I've got about two weeks to make you feel
that, too.'
Huw hadn't meant to say it quite like that,
but he wanted Megan to be clear about how
he felt - and he didn't have very much time.
'Huw, you can't just come back into my life
after fifty years and start organising everything.
You don't love me, how can you?
You don't know me.
I think it's wonderful that we've been able
to meet again and become friends.
But my future is with Paul.'
'Megan, I won't say any more about it.
But I just want you to promise that you'll
think about what I've said,' Huw said quietly.
'How can I forget it?'
thought Megan to herself.
Megan started the car and they drove back
to Tredonald without saying a word to each
other.
Huw got out at his hotel and they said goodbye.
He said he would phone her the next day, but
they made no other plans.
Huw felt it was better to give Megan some
time alone - even though he wanted to be with
her every minute of every day.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
An old photograph
Huw was right.
Megan did need time alone.
Here she was, a woman of sixty-six, and two
men wanted to marry her!
Of course she was not going to marry Huw.
He didn't really love her.
He'd just flown half way around the world,
and in two days had met his old love and a
daughter he never knew he had.
It was not surprising that he was saying things
he didn't really mean.
The next morning, Megan did some more packing.
But it was difficult for her to escape from
thoughts of Huw.
Everything that she put into boxes or cases
seemed to throw her back to some time in the
past.
And the past was Huw.
She rang Paul to check what time he was arriving
the next day.
He asked her how things had gone between Huw
and Beth and she told him it had gone well.
They talked for a while about other things
and then Megan told him that Huw was joining
them for dinner.
Paul said that was fine.
She didn't know if that was how he really
felt.
But it was nice and easy talking with him,
and she felt safe.
After she'd put the phone down, she remembered
what Huw had asked her: Are you happy every
time you hear his voice?'
What kind of question was that?
It was the sort of thing you felt when you
were in love for the first time, not when
you were her age.
Then the phone rang again and this time it
was Huw.
He told her he'd been walking round the village
and had met someone that they'd been at school
with, and how they'd had a laugh about the
old days.
Then he said that he'd like to meet her for
a drink and maybe dinner if she would like
to.
'Seven o'clock at your hotel?' asked Megan.
'It'll be good to escape from the flat tonight.'
'Wonderful.
See you then,' said Huw.
The conversation had been light, friendly
and... and Megan had been very happy to hear
his voice.
Just after seven that evening, Megan joined
Huw in the dining room of his hotel.
Huw could see that she was a little tired
so he didn't talk about the two of them.
He told her about the wonderful wild areas
in the north of the country, and funny stories
about the art world in Canada and how much
he loved living there.
Two hours passed in easy happy conversation.
'Now, you tell me something,' said Huw, smiling
at her.
'Well, you know you said you saw Brian Perkins
earlier today,' said Megan.
'I found this - look.'
And she passed Huw a black and white photograph.
He looked closely at it and saw a group of
about thirty children aged thirteen or fourteen,
all standing very straight and smiling at
the camera.
It was an old school photograph.
'And look, there's you at the back with Brian
Perkins,' Megan laughed.
'And there's me, just below you.
We all look so young and fresh, don't we?'
'And I'm the only one not looking at the camera.
I'm looking at you!
You see, even then I was only interested in
you,' said Huw.
Megan moved on.
She didn't want to give Huw the chance to
talk about her.
She had brought some other photos for him
to look at - photos of friends and her family,
and photos of Beth when she was a baby.
She gave the ones of Beth to Huw, saying,
'Would you like to keep these?'
Huw put them in his pocket.
'Time for me to go, I think,' said Megan.
'I'll walk home with you,' said Huw.
They walked to her home through the quiet
streets of the village.
'I'm happy I came back to see Tredonald,'
said Huw.
'It's not the terrible place I remember.
I'm sure I can put the past behind me now.'
'Good,' said Megan - and then thought, 'Does
that mean me as well?'
But at her front door Huw said, 'Megan, I
can feel that all evening you've been hoping
that I won't say anything about us.
And I won't, except I meant what I said yesterday.'
'Please Huw, let's not talk about it,' said
Megan.
'Tomorrow you're going to meet Paul - the
man I'm going to marry.'
Megan took hold of his hands.
'Thank you for a lovely evening.
I'll see you here tomorrow.'
Megan went to bed that night knowing that
tomorrow's dinner was going to be difficult
for all of them.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Dinner for five
'Paul, this is Huw.
Huw, Paul.'
Megan introduced the two men who shook hands.
Then she disappeared into the kitchen and
left them to make conversation.
Beth and Philip were late.
She wanted them here now - she needed help.
'I don't know what's happened to Beth and
Philip,' she said, walking over to the window
of the sitting room.
Huw and Paul seemed to be talking quite happily.
'Probably Philip was late finishing his game
of golf,' said Paul, going over to stand by
Megan's side.
'He lives for his golf at the weekends, doesn't
he?
Do you want another drink, love?'
'No, I'd better not.
Oh, here they are now.
Good.'
And Megan once again disappeared out of the
room.
'Sorry we're late, Mum.
My fault,' said Beth.
'That's OK,' she said.
Beth and Philip both gave her a kiss.
'I'll just go and finish off in the kitchen.
Dinner will be about ten minutes.
From the kitchen she could hear Paul laughing,
and then Beth.
'Oh good,' she thought.
'Maybe it's all going to be fine.
Maybe I don't need to worry at all.'
At dinner the conversation went well.
Beth and Philip wanted to know all about Huw's
art, and Huw enjoyed talking about it.
Paul also joined in - he knew an artist in
London who had bought one of Huw's paintings.
Megan was able to sit back and listen; Paul
looked over at her and smiled.
Megan watched, listened, joined in the conversation
- and compared.
It was a terrible thing to do, but she found
that she was comparing Paul and Huw.
Huw with his brown face, his stories and the
past that they shared.
And kind Paul who'd made her feel good again,
and who was her future.
It was strange to see the two halves of her
life here in the same room.
Once or twice she saw Huw looking a little
sad - when Beth had said something about her
younger life.
And she realised that he was trying hard to
keep the conversation light, and not ask too
many questions about the past.
At midnight, Huw stood up to go.
The others were staying the night at Megan's.
'Don't forget, Megan, we're meeting at ten
tomorrow morning for our tour of the mine.'
'I haven't forgotten.
I'll leave everybody here doing the washing-up
and I'll see you at the entrance to the mine.'
Everybody stood up to say their goodbyes.
Paul shook his hand and said, 'I've enjoyed
meeting you, Huw, and maybe some day Megan
and I can visit you in Canada.
I'd love to try that fishing you were telling
me about.'
Huw said nothing but just smiled.
At the door, he turned and said, 'Paul, I
believe that you're a good man and I hope
you and Megan will be very happy together.'
He kissed Beth and Megan.
As the door closed behind him, Beth looked
at her mother.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Time to go
At ten the next morning, Huw and Megan stepped
into the lift to go down the mine.
It was a modern lift - not like the one that
Huw remembered.
He felt as if he was in a large shop rather
than a coal mine.
But when the doors opened at the bottom, he
was immediately taken back fifty years.
It was the smell.
You might be able to make everything modern,
but you could never lose the smell of coal,
he thought.
He followed Megan down one of the tunnels.
It was lit now, but he didn't need the light.
He knew that he'd be able to find his way
around with his eyes closed.
It was a quiet world down there.
The last miner had left years ago.
'Do you mind if I walk a bit by myself?'
Huw asked Megan.
He wanted to have some private time to remember
Gareth.
'Of course,' said Megan.
'I'll wait here.'
She watched him walk away from her with his
hands in his pockets.
This morning she felt flat - maybe even a
bit sad.
The feeling had come to her last night, when
Huw had wished her and Paul a happy life together.
She realised that Huw had accepted her and
Paul as a couple.
So he didn't want to marry her after all,
he didn't love her - why did that make her
feel sad?
She should be pleased that he was not going
to make things difficult for her.
Huw came back.
'What a short life poor Gareth had,' he said
quietly.
'I know,' said Megan, and she reached out
to take his hand.
'The night he died was just...'
Huw didn't continue, but Megan knew what he
felt - she remembered that terrible night
too.
They walked towards the lift hand in hand.
'You OK?' asked Megan quietly.
'Yes and no.'
Huw looked down at her and said, 'I've decided
to go back to Toronto.
I'm flying tomorrow evening.'
'Oh Huw, why so soon?'
Megan was completely shaken.
'It's no good, Megan.
I realise that I can't just arrive after fifty
years, tell you I love you and expect you
to leave everything and come away with me.
So I've decided to go back early.
There's no reason for me to stay any longer.'
'But what about Beth?' asked Megan.
'Don't you want to spend some more time with
her?'
'Yes, and I will, but not now,' answered Huw.
'I'll write to her, of course, and I hope
I'll be able to see her again either here
or in Canada.'
'So, you're going away again, and leaving
us,' said Megan.
'Beth is going to be very sorry.'
'I don't feel, there's anything else I can
do, Megan.
I've told you how I feel - I love you and
I want to marry you.
It would hurt too much to watch you and Paul
together, or to hear you talking about him.'
They reached the top of the mine and walked
out into the sunshine.
'Oh Huw, I don't know what to say,' said Megan.
'I don't want you to go, I feel as if I'm
just getting to know you again.
Everything has happened so quickly in the
last few days - but they've been wonderful
days.'
Outside Megan's home, Huw turned and took
her hands.
'I'm leaving Tredonald after breakfast tomorrow,
so I think this is goodbye - for now,' Huw
found it difficult to speak.
'I'll keep in touch with you and Beth, of
course.
I'm not sorry I came back, but I wish with
all my heart that the ending could be different.
Goodbye, sweet Megan.
Be happy.'
Huw kissed her lips, her eyes, her nose - everywhere
on her face.
Then he walked away.
He turned around once and saw that Megan was
still standing outside her front door.
He gave a little wave.
His face was wet with tears.
* * *
The next morning, Huw packed his suitcase,
feeling bad.
He stopped when he came to the photo of Megan
and Beth, and looked at it with love.
He remembered how fifty years ago, when he
was about to leave for Canada, he had packed
his drawing of Megan with the same feeling
of love.
Then, there had been all those years without
her.
Finding her again had been so wonderful, but
now the future seemed empty.
Downstairs, Huw paid his hotel bill at reception
and walked out to his car.
As he was getting in, he heard someone behind
him and turned round.
There was Megan.
They looked at each other for a few seconds
and then fell into each other's arms.
'Oh, Huw, I've been awake all night thinking
about you.
I kept remembering how I felt when you left
me fifty years ago.
I can't let you leave me again.
You're part of me - I feel complete with you.'
'What do you want me to do then?' asked Huw
softly, loving the sound of Megan's words.
'Ask me to marry you again,' she replied in
a shaking voice.
'Megan, marry me.
Be my girl again,' Huw said.
'Of course, Huw,' she answered.
'Of course.'
They were both crying.
They cried because of the years they had lost
- years they would never get back.
But they also cried because they were happy.
They still had time: they had tomorrow and
the next day and the next...
They had a second chance of a wonderful future
together and this time nothing would go wrong.
- THE END -