Mr Boggis was driving the car slowly, leaning
back comfortably in the seat with one elbow
resting on the sill of the open window.
How beautiful the countryside, he thought;
how pleasant to see a sign or two of summer
once again.
The primroses especially.
And the hawthorn.
The hawthorn was exploding white and pink
and red along the hedges and the primroses
were growing underneath in little clumps,
and it was beautiful.
He took one hand off the wheel and lit himself
a cigarette.
The best thing now, he told himself, would
be to make for the top of Brill Hill.
He could see it about half a mile ahead.
And that must be the village of Brill, that
cluster of cottages among the trees right
on the very summit.
Excellent.
Not many of his Sunday sections had a nice
elevation like that to work from.
He drove up the hill and stopped the car just
short of the summit on the outskirts of the
village.
Then he got out and looked around.
Down below, the countryside was spread out
before him like a huge green carpet.
He could see for miles.
It was perfect.
He took a pad and pencil from his pocket,
leaned against the back of the car, and allowed
his practiced eye to travel slowly over the
landscape.
He could see one medium farmhouse over on
the right, back in the fields, with a track
leading to it from the road.
There was another larger one beyond it.
There was a house surrounded by tall elms
that looked as though it might be a Queen
Anne, and there were two likely farms away
over on the left.
Five places in all.
That was about the lot in this direction.
Mr Boggis drew a rough sketch on his pad showing
the position of each so that he'd be able
to find them easily when he was down below,
then he got back into the car and drove up
through the village to the other side of the
hill.
From there he spotted six more possibles - five
farms and one big white Georgian house.
He studied the Georgian house through his
binoculars.
It had a clean prosperous look, and the garden
was well ordered.
That was a pity.
He ruled it out immediately.
There was no point in calling on the prosperous.
In this square then, in this section, there
were ten possibles in all.
Ten was a nice number, Mr Boggis told himself.
Just the right amount for a leisurely afternoon's
work.
What time was it now?
Twelve o'clock.
He would have liked a pint of beer in the
pub before he started, but on Sundays they
didn't open until one.
Very well, he would have it later.
He glanced at the notes on his pad.
He decided to take the Queen Anne first, the
house with the elms.
It had looked nicely dilapidated through the
binoculars.
The people there could probably do with some
money.
He was always lucky with Queen Annes, anyway.
Mr Boggis climbed back into the car, released
the handbrake, and began cruising slowly down
the hill without the engine.
Apart from the fact that he was at this moment
disguised in the uniform of a clergyman, there
was nothing very sinister about Mr Cyril Boggis.
By trade he was a dealer in antique furniture,
with his own shop and showroom in the King's
Road, Chelsea.
His premises were not large, and generally
he didn't do a great deal of business, but
because he always bought cheap, very very
cheap, and sold very very dear, he managed
to make quite a tidy little income every year.
He was a talented salesman, and when buying
or selling a piece he could slide smoothly
into whichever mood suited the client best.
He could become grave and charming for the
aged, obsequious for the rich, sober for the
godly, masterful for the weak, mischievous
for the widow, arch and saucy for the spinster.
He was well aware of his gift, using it shamelessly
on every possible occasion; and often, at
the end of an unusually good performance,
it was as much as he could do to prevent himself
from turning aside and taking a bow or two
as the thundering applause of the audience
went rolling through the theatre.
In spite of this rather clownish quality of
his, Mr Boggis was not a fool.
In fact, it was said of him by some that he
probably knew as much about French, English,
and Italian furniture as anyone else in London.
He also had surprisingly good taste, and he
was quick to recognize and reject an ungraceful
design, however genuine the article might
be.
His real love, naturally, was for the work
of the great eighteenth-century English designers,
Ince, Mayhew, Chippendale, Robert Adam, Manwaring,
Inigo Jones, Hepplewhite, Kent, Johnson, George
Smith, Lock, Sheraton, and the rest of them,
but even with these he occasionally drew the
line.
He refused, for example, to allow a single
piece from Chippendale's Chinese or Gothic
period to come into his showroom, and the
same was true of some of the heavier Italian
designs of Robert Adam.
During the past few years, Mr Boggis had achieved
considerable fame among his friends in the
trade by his ability to produce unusual and
often quite rare items with astonishing regularity.
Apparently the man had a source of supply
that was almost inexhaustible, a sort of private
warehouse, and it seemed' that all he had
to do was to drive out to it once a week and
help himself.
Whenever they asked him where he got the stuff,
he would smile knowingly and wink and murmur
something about a little secret.
The idea behind Mr Boggis's little secret
was a simple one, and it had come to him as
a result of something that had happened on
a certain Sunday afternoon nearly nine years
before, while he was driving in the country.
He had gone out in the morning to visit his
old mother, who lived in Seven-oaks, and on
the way back the fan belt on his car had broken,
causing the engine to overheat and the water
to boil away.
He had got out of the car and walked to the
nearest house, a smallish farm building about
fifty yards off the road, and had asked the
woman who answered the door if he could please
have a jug of water.
While he was waiting for her to fetch it,
he happened to glance in through the door
to the living-room, and there, not five yards
from where he was standing, he spotted something
that made him so excited the sweat began to
come out all over the top of his head.
It was a large oak armchair of a type that
he had only seen once before in his life.
Each arm, as well as the panel at the back,
was supported by a row of eight beautifully
turned spindles.
The back panel itself was decorated by an
inlay of the most delicate floral design,
and the head of a duck was carved to lie along
half the length of either arm.
Good God, he thought.
This thing is late fifteenth century!
He poked his head in further through the door,
and there, by heavens, was another of them
on the other side of the fireplace!
He couldn't be sure, but two chairs like that
must be worth at least a thousand pounds up
in London.
And oh, what beauties they were!
When the woman returned, Mr Boggis introduced
himself and straight away asked if she would
like to sell her chairs.
'Dear me,' she said.
'But why on earth should she want to sell
her chairs?'
'No reason at all, except that he might be
willing to give her a pretty nice price.'
'And how much would he give?'
'They were definitely not for sale, but just
out of curiosity, just for fun, you know,
how much would he give?'
'Thirty-five pounds.'
'How much?'
'Dear me, thirty-five pounds.
Well, well, that was very interesting.'
She'd always thought they were valuable.
They were very old.
They were very comfortable too.
She couldn't possibly do without them, not
possibly.
No, they were not for sale but thank you very
much all the same.
They weren't really so very old, Mr Boggis
told her, and they wouldn't be at all easy
to sell, but it just happened that he had
a client who rather liked that sort of thing.
Maybe he could go up another two pounds - call
it thirty-seven.
How about that?
They bargained for half an hour, and of course
in the end Mr Boggis got the chairs and agreed
to pay her something less than a twentieth
of their value.
That evening, driving back to London in his
old station-wagon with the two fabulous chairs
tucked away snugly in the back, Mr Boggis
had suddenly been struck by what seemed to
him to be a most remarkable idea.
Look here, he said.
If there is good stuff in one farmhouse, then
why not in others?
Why shouldn't he search for it?
Why shouldn't he comb the countryside?
He could do it on Sundays.
In that way, it wouldn't interfere with his
work at all.
He never knew what to do with his Sundays.
So Mr Boggis bought maps, large-scale maps
of all the counties around London, and with
a fine pen he divided each of them up into
a series of squares.
Each of these squares covered an actual area
of five miles by five, which was about as
much territory, he estimated, as he could
cope with on a single Sunday, were he to comb
it thoroughly.
He didn't want the towns and the villages.
It was the comparatively isolated places,
the large farmhouses and the rather dilapidated
country mansions, that he was looking for;
and in this way, if he did one square each
Sunday, fifty-two squares a year, he would
gradually cover every farm and every country
house in the home counties.
But obviously there was a bit more to it than
that.
Country folk are a suspicious lot.
So are the impoverished rich.
You can't go about ringing their bells and
expecting them to show you around their houses
just for the asking, because they won't do
it.
That way you would never get beyond the front
door.
How then was he to gain admittance?
Perhaps it would be best if he didn't let
them know he was a dealer at all.
He could be the telephone man, the plumber,
the gas inspector.
He could even be a clergyman...
From this point on, the whole scheme began
to take on a more practical aspect.
Mr Boggis ordered a large quantity of superior
cards on which the following legend was engraved:
THE REVEREND
CYRIL WINNINGTON BOGGIS
President of the Society for the Preservation
of Rare Furniture In association with The
Victoria and Albert Museum
From now on, every Sunday, he was going to
be a nice old parson spending his holiday
travelling around on a labor of love for the
'Society', compiling an inventory of the treasures
that lay hidden in the country homes of England.
And who in the world was going to kick him
out when they heard that one?
Nobody.
And then, once he was inside, if he happened
to spot something he really wanted, well - he
knew a hundred different ways of dealing with
that.
Rather to Mr Boggis's surprise, the scheme
worked.
In fact, the friendliness with which he was
received in one house after another through
the countryside was, in the beginning, quite
embarrassing, even to him.
A slice of cold pie, a glass of port, a cup
of tea, a basket of plums, even a full sit-down
Sunday dinner with the family, such things
were constantly being pressed upon him.
Sooner or later, of course, there had been
some bad moments and a number of unpleasant
incidents, but then nine years is more than
four hundred Sundays, and that adds up to
a great quantity of houses visited.
All in all, it had been an interesting, exciting,
and lucrative business.
And now it was another Sunday and Mr Boggis
was operating in the county of Buckinghamshire,
in one of the most northerly squares on his
map, about ten miles from Oxford, and as he
drove down the hill and headed for his first
house, the dilapidated Queen Anne, he began
to get the feeling that this was going to
be one of his lucky days.
He parked the car about a hundred yards from
the gates and got out to walk the rest of
the way.
He never liked people to see his car until
after a deal was completed.
A dear old clergyman and a large station-wagon
somehow never seemed quite right together.
Also the short walk gave him time to examine
the property closely from the outside and
to assume the mood most likely to be suitable
for the occasion.
Mr Boggis strode briskly up the drive.
He was a small fat-legged man with a belly.
The face was round and rosy, quite perfect
for the part, and the two large brown eyes
that bulged out at you from this rosy face
gave an impression of gentle imbecility.
He was dressed in a black suit with the usual
parson's dog- collar round his neck, and on
his head a soft black hat.
He carried an old oak walking-stick which
lent him, in his opinion, a rather rustic
easy-going air.
He approached the front door and rang the
bell.
He heard the sound of foot-steps in the hall
and the door opened and suddenly there stood
before him, or rather above him, a gigantic
woman dressed in riding-breeches.
Even through the smoke of her cigarette he
could smell the powerful odour of stables
and horse manure that clung about her.
'Yes?'
she asked, looking at him suspiciously.
'What is it you want?'
Mr Boggis, who half expected her to whinny
any moment, raised his hat, made a little
bow, and handed her his card.
'I do apologize for bothering you,' he said,
and then he waited, watching her face as she
read the message.
'I don't understand,' she said, handing back
the card.
'What is it you want?'
Mr Boggis explained about the Society for
the Preservation Rare Furniture.
'This wouldn't by any chance be something
to do with the Socialist Party?'
she asked, staring at him fiercely from under
a pair of pale bushy brows.
From then on, it was easy.
A Tory in riding-breeches, male or female,
was always a sitting duck for Mr Boggis.
He spent two minutes delivering an impassioned
eulogy on the extreme Right Wing of the Conservative
Party, then two more denouncing the Socialists.
As a clincher, he made particular reference
to the Bill that the Socialists had once introduced
for the abolition of blood - sports in the
country, and went on to inform his listener
that his idea of heaven - 'though you better
not tell the bishop, my dear' - was a place
where one could hunt the fox, the stag, and
the hare with large packs of tireless hounds
from morn till night every day of the week,
including Sundays.
Watching her as he spoke, he could see the
magic beginning to do its work.
The woman was grinning now, showing Mr Boggis
a set of enormous, slightly yellow teeth.
'Madam,' he cried, 'I beg of you, please don't
get me started on Socialism.'
At that point, she let out a great guffaw
of laughter, raised an enormous red hand,
and slapped him so hard on the shoulder that
he nearly went over.
'Come in!'
she shouted.
'I don't know what the hell you want, but
come on in!'
Unfortunately, and rather surprisingly, there
was nothing of any value in the whole house,
and Mr Boggis, who never wasted time on barren
territory, soon made his excuses and took
his leave.
The whole visit had taken less than fifteen
minutes, and that, he told himself as he climbed
back into his car and started off for the
next place, was exactly as it should be.
From now on, it was all farmhouses, and the
nearest was about half a mile up the road.
It was a large half-timbered brick building
of considerable age, and there was a magnificent
pear tree still in blossom covering almost
the whole of the south wall.
Mr Boggis knocked on the door.
He waited, but no one came.
He knocked again, but still there was no answer,
so he wandered around the back to look for
the farmer among the cowsheds.
There was no one there either.
He guessed that they must all still be in
church, so he began peering in the windows
to see if he could spot anything interesting.
There was nothing in the dining-room.
Nothing in the library either.
He tried the next window, the living-room,
and there, right under his nose, in the little
alcove that the window made, he saw a beautiful
thing, a semicircular card-table in mahogany,
richly veneered, and in the style of Hepplewhite,
built around 1780.
'Ah-ha,' he said aloud, pressing his face
hard against the glass.
'Well done, Boggis.'
But that was not all.
There was a chair there as well, a single
chair, and if he were not mistaken it was
of an even finer quality than the table.
Another Hepplewhite, wasn't it?
And oh, what a beauty!
The lattices on the back were finely carved
with the honeysuckle, the husk, and the paterae,
the caning on the seat was original, the legs
were very gracefully turned and the two back
ones had that peculiar outward splay that
meant so much.
It was an exquisite chair.
'Before this day is done,' Mr Boggis said
softly, 'I shall have the pleasure of sitting
down upon that lovely seat.'
He never bought a chair without doing this.
It was a favourite test of his, and it was
always an intriguing sight to see him lowering
himself delicately into the seat, waiting
for the 'give', expertly gauging the precise
but infinitesimal degree of shrinkage that
the years had caused in the mortice and dovetail
joints.
But there was no hurry, he told himself.
He would return here later.
He had the whole afternoon before him.
The next farm was situated some way back in
the fields, and in order to keep his car out
of sight, Mr Boggis had to leave it on the
road and walk about six hundred yards along
a straight track that led directly into the
back yard of the farmhouse.
This place, he noticed as he approached, was
a good deal smaller than the last, and he
didn't hold out much hope for it.
It looked rambling and dirty, and some of
the sheds were clearly in bad repair.
There were three men standing in a close group
in a corner of the yard, and one of them had
two large black greyhounds with him, on leashes.
When the men caught sight of Mr Boggis walking
forward in his black suit and parson's collar,
they stopped talking and seemed suddenly to
stiffen and freeze, becoming absolutely still,
motionless, three faces turned towards him,
watching him suspiciously as he approached.
The oldest of the three was a stumpy man with
a wide frog-mouth and small shifty eyes, and
although Mr Boggis didn't know it, his name
was Rummins and he was the owner of the farm.
The tall youth beside him, who appeared to
have something wrong with one eye, was Bert,
the son of Rummins.
The shortish flat-faced man with a narrow
corrugated brow and immensely broad shoulders
was Claud.
Claud had dropped in on Rummins in the hope
of getting a piece of pork or ham out of him
from the pig that had been killed the day
before.
Claud knew about the killing - the noise of
it had carried far across the fields - and
he also knew that a man should have a government
permit to do that sort of thing, and that
Rummins didn't have one.
'Good afternoon,' Mr Boggis said.
'Isn't it a lovely day?'
None of the three men moved.
At that moment they were all thinking precisely
the same thing - that somehow or other this
clergyman, who was certainly not the local
fellow, had been sent to poke his nose into
their business and to report what he found
to the government.
'What beautiful dogs,' Mr Boggis said.
'I must say I've never been greyhound-racing
myself, but they tell me it's a fascinating
sport.'
Again the silence, and Mr Boggis glanced quickly
from Rummins to Bert, then to Claud, then
back again to Rummins, and he noticed that
each of them had the same peculiar expression
on his face, something between a jeer and
a challenge, with a contemptuous curl to the
mouth and a sneer around the nose.
'Might I inquire if you are the owner?'
Mr Boggis asked, undaunted, addressing himself
to Rummins.
'What is it you want?'
'I do apologize for troubling you, especially
on a Sunday.'
Mr Boggis offered his card and Rummins took
it and held it up close to his face.
The other two didn't move, but their eyes
swivelled over to one side, trying to see.
'And what exactly might you be wanting?'
Rummins asked.
For the second time that morning, Mr Boggis
explained at some length the aims and ideals
of the Society for the Preservation of Rare
Furniture.
'We don't have any,' Rummins told him when
it was over.
'You're wasting your time.'
'Now, just a minute, sir,' Mr Boggis said,
raising a finger.
'The last man who said that to me was an old
farmer down in Sussex, and when he finally
let me into his house, do you know what I
found?
A dirty-looking old chair in the corner of
the kitchen, and it turned out to be worth
four hundred pounds!
I showed him how to sell it, and he bought
himself a new tractor with the money.'
'What on earth are you talking about?'
Claud said.
'There ain't no chair in the world worth four
hundred pound.'
'Excuse me,' Mr Boggis answered primly, 'but
there are plenty of chairs in England worth
more than twice that figure.
And you know where they are?
They're tucked away in the farms and cottages
all over the country, with the owners using
them as steps and ladders and standing on
them with hobnailed boots to reach a pot of
jam out of the top cupboard or to hang a picture.
This is the truth I'm telling you, my friends.'
Rummins shifted uneasily on his feet.
'You mean to say all you want to do is go
inside and stand there in the middle of the
room and look around?'
'Exactly,' Mr Boggis said.
He was at last beginning to sense what the
trouble might be.
'I don't want to pry into your cupboards or
into your larder.
I just want to look at the furniture to see
if you happen to have any treasures here,
and then I can write about them in our Society
magazine.'
'You know what I think?'
Rummins said, fixing him with his small wicked
eyes.
'I think you're after buying the stuff yourself.
Why else would you be going to all this trouble?'
'Oh, dear me.
I only wish I had the money.
Of course, if I saw something that I took
a great fancy to, and it wasn't beyond my
means, I might be tempted to make an offer.
But alas, that rarerely happens.'
'Well,' Rummins said, 'I don't suppose there's
any harm in your taking a look around if that's
all you want.'
He led the way across the yard to the back
door of the farmhouse, and Mr Boggis followed
him; so did the son Bert, and Claud with his
two dogs.
They went through the kitchen, where the only
furniture was a cheap deal table with a dead
chicken lying on it, and they emerged into
a fairly large, exceedingly filthy living-room.
And there it was!
Mr Boggis saw it at once, and he stopped dead
in his tracks and gave a little shrill gasp
of shock.
Then he stood there for five, ten, fifteen
seconds at least, staring like an idiot, unable
to believe, not daring to believe what he
saw before him.
It couldn't be true, not possibly!
But the longer he stared, the more true it
began to seem.
After all, there it was standing against the
wall right in front of him, as real and as
solid as the house itself.
And who in the world could possibly make a
mistake about a thing like that?
Admittedly it was painted white, but that
made not the slightest difference.
Some idiot had done that.
The paint could easily be stripped off.
But good God!
Just look at it!
And in a place like this!
At this point, Mr Boggis became aware of the
three men, Rummins, Bert, and Claud, standing
together in a group over by the fireplace,
watching him intently.
They had seen him stop and gasp and stare,
and they must have seen his face turning red,
or maybe it was white, but in any event they
had seen enough to spoil the whole goddamn
business if he didn't do something about it
quick.
In a flash, Mr Boggis clapped one hand over
his heart, staggered to the nearest chair,
and collapsed into it, breathing heavily.
'What's the matter with you?'
Claud asked.
'It's nothing,' he gasped.
'I'll be all right in a minute.
Please - a glass of water.
It's my heart.'
Bert fetched him the water, handed it to him,
and stayed close beside him, staring down
at him with a fatuous leer on his face.
'I thought maybe you were looking at something,'
Rummins said.
The wide frog-mouth widened a fraction further
into a crafty grin, showing the stubs of several
broken teeth.
'No, no,' Mr Boggis said.
'Oh dear me, no.
It's just my heart.
I'm so sorry.
It happens every now and then.
But it goes away quite quickly.
I'll be all right in a couple of minutes.'
He must have time to think, he told himself.
More important still, he must have time to
compose himself thoroughly before he said
another word.
Take it gently, Boggis.
And whatever you do, keep calm.
These people may be ignorant, but they are
not stupid.
They are suspicious and wary and sly.
And if it is really true - no it can't be,
it can't be true...
He was holding one hand up over his eyes in
a gesture of pain, and now, very carefully,
secretly, he made a little crack between two
of the fingers and peeked through.
Sure enough, the thing was still there, and
on this occasion he took a good long look
at it.
Yes - he had been right the first time!
There wasn't the slightest doubt about it!
It was really unbelievable!
What he saw was a piece of furniture that
any expert would have given almost anything
to acquire.
To a layman, it might not have appeared particularly
impressive, especially when covered over as
it was with dirty white paint, but to Mr Boggis
it was a dealer's dream.
He knew, as does every other dealer in Europe
and America, that among the most celebrated
and coveted examples of eighteenth- century
English furniture in existence are the three
famous pieces known as 'The Chippendale Commodes'.
He knew their history backwards - that the
first was 'discovered' in 1920, in a house
at Moreton-in-Marsh, and was sold at Sotheby's
the same year; that the other two turned up
in the same auction rooms a year later, both
coming out of Raynham Hall, Norfolk.
They all fetched enormous prices.
He couldn't quite remember the exact figure
for the first one, or even the second, but
he knew for certain that the last one to be
sold had fetched thirty- nine hundred guineas.
And that was in 1921!
Today the same piece would surely be worth
ten thousand pounds.
Some man, Mr Boggis couldn't remember his
name, had made a study of these commodes fairly
recently and had proved that all three must
have come from the same workshop, for the
veneers were all from the same log, and the
same set of templates had been used in the
construction of each.
No invoices had been found for any of them,
but all the experts were agreed that these
three commodes could have been executed only
by Thomas Chippendale himself, with his own
hands, at the most exalted period in his career.
And here, Mr Boggis kept telling himself as
he peered cautiously through the crack in
his fingers, here was the fourth Chippendale
Commode!
And he had found it!
He would be rich!
He would also be famous!
Each of the other three was known throughout
the furniture world by a special name - The
Chastleton Commode, The First Raynham Commode,
The Second Raynham Commode.
This one would go down in history as The Boggis
Commode!
Just imagine the faces of the boys up there
in London when they got a look at it tomorrow
morning!
And the luscious offers coming in from the
big fellows over in the West End - Frank Partridge,
Mallet, Jetley, and the rest of them!
There would be a picture of it in The Times,
and it would say, 'The very fine Chippen dale
Commode which was recently discovered by Mr
Cyril Boggis, a London dealer....'
Dear God, what a stir he was going to make!
This one here, Mr Boggis thought, was almost
exactly similar to the Second Raynham Commode.
(All three, the Chastleton and the two Raynhams,
differed from one another in a number of small
ways.)
It was a most impressive handsome affair,
built in the French rococo style of Chippendale's
Directoire period, a kind of large fat chest-of-drawers
set upon four carved and fluted legs that
raised it about a foot from the ground.
There were six drawers in all, two long ones
in the middle and two shorter ones on either
side.
The serpentine front was magnificently ornamented
along the top and sides and bottom, and also
vertically between each set of drawers, with
intricate carvings of festoons and scrolls
and clusters.
The brass handles, although partly obscured
by white paint, appeared to be superb.
It was, of course, a rather 'heavy' piece,
but the design had been executed with such
elegance and grace that the heaviness was
in no way offensive.
'How're you feeling now?'
Mr Boggis heard someone saying.
'Thank you, thank you, I'm much better already.
It passes quickly.
My doctor says it's nothing to worry about
really so long as I rest for a few minutes
whenever it happens.
Ah yes,' he said, raising himself slowly to
his feet.
'That's better.
I'm all right now.'
A trifle unsteadily, he began to move around
the room examining the furniture, one piece
at a time, commenting upon it briefly.
He could see at once that apart from the commode
it was a very poor lot.
'Nice oak table,' he said.
'But I'm afraid it's not old enough to be
of any interest.
Good comfortable chairs, but quite modern,
yes, quite modern.
Now this cupboard, well, it's rather attractive,
but again, not valuable.
This chest-of-drawers' - he walked casually
past the Chippendale Commode and gave it a
little contemptuous flip with his fingers
- 'worth a few pounds, I dare say, but no
more.
A rather crude reproduction, I'm afraid.
Probably made in Victorian times.
Did you paint it white?'
'Yes,' Rummins said, 'Bert did it.'
'A very wise move.
It's considerably less offensive in white.'
'That's a strong piece of furniture,' Rummins
said.
'Some nice carving on it too.'
'Machine-carved,' Mr Boggis answered superbly,
bending down to examine the exquisite craftsmanship.
'You can tell it a mile off.
But still, I suppose it's quite pretty in
its way.
It has its points.'
He began to saunter off, then he checked himself
and turned slowly back again.
He placed the tip of one finger against the
point of his chin, laid his head over to one
side, and frowned as though deep in thought.
'You know what?' he said, looking at the commode,
speaking so casually that his voice kept trailing
off.
'I've just remembered...
I've been wanting a set of legs something
like that for a long time.
I've got a rather curious table in my own
little home, one of those low things that
people put in front of the sofa, sort of a
coffee-table, and last Michaelmas, when I
moved house, the foolish movers damaged the
legs in the most shocking way.
I'm very fond of that table.
I always keep my big Bible on it, and all
my sermon notes.'
He paused, stroking his chin with the finger.
'Now I was just thinking.
These legs on your chest-of-drawers might
be very suitable.
Yes, they might indeed.
They could easily be cut off and fixed on
to my table.'
He looked around and saw the three men standing
absolutely still, watching him suspiciously,
three pairs of eyes, all different but equally
mistrusting, small pig-eyes for Rummins, large
slow eyes for Claud, and two odd eyes for
Bert, one of them very queer and boiled and
misty pale, with a little black dot in the
center, like a fish eye on a plate.
Mr Boggis smiled and shook his head.
'Come, come, what on earth am I saying?
I'm talking as though I owned the piece myself.
I do apologize.'
'What you mean to say is you'd like to buy
it,' Rummins said.
'Well...'
Mr Boggis glanced back at the commode, frowning.
'I'm not sure.
I might... and then again ... on second thoughts
... no...
I think it might be a bit too much trouble.
It's not worth it.
I'd better leave it.'
'How much were you thinking of offering?'
Rummins asked.
'Not much, I'm afraid.
You see, this is not a genuine antique.
It's merely a reproduction.'
I'm not so sure about that,' Rummins told
him.
'It's been in here over twenty years, and
before that it was up at the Manor House.
I bought it there myself at auction when the
old Squire died.
You can't tell me that thing's new.'
'It's not exactly new, but it's certainly
not more than about sixty years old.'
'It's more than that,' Rummins said.
'Bert, where's that bit of paper you once
found at the back of one of them drawers?
That old bill.'
The boy looked vacantly at his father.
Mr Boggis opened his mouth, then quickly shut
it again without uttering a sound.
He was beginning literally to shake with excitement,
and to calm himself he walked over to the
window and stared out at a plump brown hen
pecking around for stray grains of corn in
the yard.
'It was in the back of that drawer underneath
all them rabbit-snares,' Rummins was saying.
'Go on and fetch it out and show it to the
parson.'
When Bert went forward to the commode, Mr
Boggis turned round again.
He couldn't stand not watching him.
He saw him pull out one of the big middle
drawers, and he noticed the beautiful way
in which the drawer slid open.
He saw Bert's hand dipping inside and rummaging
around among a lot of wires and strings.
'You mean this?'
Bert lifted out a piece of folded yellowing
paper and carried it over to the father, who
unfolded it and held it up close to his face.
'You can't tell me this writing ain't bloody
old,' Rummins said, and he held the paper
out to Mr Boggis, whose whole arm was shaking
as he took it.
It was brittle and it cracked slightly between
his fingers.
The writing was in a long sloping copperplate
hand:
Edward Montagu, Esq.
Dr
To Thos.
Chippendale
A large mahogany Commode Table of exceeding
fine wood, very rich carvd, set upon fluted
legs, two very neat shapd long drawers in
the middle part and two ditto on each side,
with rich chasd Brass Handles and Ornaments,
the whole completely finished in the most
exquisite taste 87 pounds.
Mr Boggis was holding on to himself tight
and fighting to suppress the excitement that
was spinning round inside him and making him
dizzy.
Oh God, it was wonderful!
With the invoice, the value had climbed even
higher.
What in heaven's name would it fetch now?
Twelve thousand pounds?
Fourteen?
Maybe fifteen or even twenty?
Who knows?
Oh, boy!
He tossed the paper contemptuously on to the
table and said quietly, 'It's exactly what
I told you, a Victorian reproduction.
This is simply the invoice that the seller
- the man who made it and passed it off as
an antique - gave to his client.
I've seen lots of them.
You'll notice that he doesn't say he made
it himself.
That would give the game away.'
'Say what you like,' Rummins announced, 'but
that's an old piece of paper.'
'Of course it is, my dear friend.
It's Victorian, late Victorian.
About eighteen ninety.
Sixty or seventy years old.
I've seen hundreds of them.
That was a time when masses of cabinet-makers
did nothing else but apply themselves to faking
the fine furniture of the century before.'
'Listen, Parson,' Rummins said, pointing at
him with a thick dirty finger, 'I'm not saying
as how you may not know a fair bit about this
furniture business, but what I am saying is
this: How on earth can you be so mighty sure
it's a fake when you haven't even seen what
it looks like underneath all that paint?'
'Come here,' Mr Boggis said.
'Come over here and I'll show you.'
He stood beside the commode and waited for
them to gather round.
'Now, anyone got a knife?'
Claud produced a horn-handled pocket knife,
and Mr Boggis took it and opened the smallest
blade.
Then, working with apparent casualness but
actually with extreme care, he began chipping
off the white paint from a small area on the
top of the commode.
The paint flaked away cleanly from the old
hard varnish underneath, and when he had cleared
away about three square inches, he stepped
back and said, 'Now, take a look at that!'
It was beautiful - a warm little patch of
mahogany, glowing like a topaz, rich and dark
with the true colour of its two hundred years.
'What's wrong with it?'
Rummins asked.
'It's processed!
Anyone can see that!'
'How can you see it, Mister?
You tell us.'
'Well, I must say that's a trifle difficult
to explain.
It's chiefly a matter of experience.
My experience tells me that without the slightest
doubt this wood has been processed with lime.
That's what they use for mahogany, to give
it that dark aged colour.
For oak, they use potash salts, and for walnut
it's nitric acid, but for mahogany it's always
lime.'
The three men moved a little closer to peer
at the wood.
There was a slight stirring of interest among
them now.
It was always intriguing to hear about some
new form of crookery or deception.
'Look closely at the grain.
You see that touch of orange in among the
dark red-brown.
That's the sign of lime.'
They leaned forward, their noses close to
the wood, first Rummins, then Claud, then
Bert.
'And then there's the patina,' Mr Boggis continued.
'The what?'
He explained to them the meaning of this word
as applied to furniture.
'My dear friends, you've no idea the trouble
these rascals will go to to imitate the hard
beautiful bronze-like appearance of genuine
patina.
It's terrible, really terrible, and it makes
me quite sick to speak of it!'
He was spitting each word sharply off the
tip of the tongue and making a sour mouth
to show his extreme distaste.
The men waited, hoping for more secrets.
'The time and trouble that some mortals will
go to in order to deceive the innocent!'
Mr Boggis cried.
'It's perfectly disgusting!
D'you know what they did here, my friends?
I can recognize it clearly.
I can almost see them doing it, the long,
complicated ritual of rubbing the wood with
linseed oil, coating it over with french polish
that has been cunningly coloured, brushing
it down with pumice- stone and oil, beeswaxing
it with a wax that contains dirt and dust,
and finally giving it the heat treatment to
crack the polish so that it looks like two-hundred-year-old
varnish!
It really upsets me to contemplate such knavery!'
The three men continued to gaze at the little
patch of dark wood.
'Feel it!'
Mr Boggis ordered.
Put your fingers on it!
There, how does it feel, warm or cold?'
'Feels cold,' Rummins said.
'Exactly, my friend!
It happens to be a fact that faked patina
is always cold to the touch.
Real patina has a curiously warm feel to it.'
'This feels normal,' Rummins said, ready to
argue.
'No, sir, it's cold.
But of course it takes an experienced and
sensitive fingertip to pass a positive judgement.
You couldn't really be expected to judge this
any more than I could be expected to judge
the quality of your barley.
Everything in life, my dear sir, is experience.'
The men were staring at this queer moon-faced
clergyman with the bulging eyes, not quite
so suspiciously now because he did seem to
know a bit about his subject.
But they were still a long way from trusting
him.
Mr Boggis bent down and pointed to one of
the metal drawer-handles on the commode.
This is another place where the fakers go
to work,' he said.
'Old brass normally has a colour and character
all of its own.
Did you know that?'
They stared at him, hoping for still more
secrets.
'But the trouble is that they've become exceedingly
skilled at matching it.
In fact it's almost impossible to tell the
difference between "genuine old" and "faked
old".
I don't mind admitting that it has me guessing.
So there's not really any point in our scraping
the paint off these handles.
We wouldn't be any the wiser.'
'How can you possibly make new brass look
like old?'
Claud said.
'Brass doesn't rust, you know.'
'You are quite right, my friend.
But these scoundrels have their own secret
methods.'
'Such as what?'
Claud asked.
Any information of this nature was valuable,
in his opinion.
One never knew when it might come in handy.
'All they have to do,' Mr Boggis said, 'is
to place these handles overnight in a box
of mahogany shavings saturated in sal ammoniac.
The sal ammoniac turns the metal green, but
if you rub off the green, you will find underneath
it a fine soft silvery-warm lustre, a lustre
identical to that which comes with very old
brass.
Oh, it is so bestial, the things they do!
With iron they have another trick.'
'What do they do with iron?'
Claud asked, fascinated.
'Iron's easy,' Mr Boggis said.
'Iron locks and plates and hinges are simply
buried in common salt and they come out all
rusted and pitted in no time.'
'All right,' Rummins said.
'So you admit you can't tell about the handles.
For all you know, they may be hundreds and
hundreds of years old.
Correct?'
'Ah,' Mr Boggis whispered, fixing Rummins
with two big bulging brown eyes.
'That's where you're wrong.
Watch this.'
From his jacket pocket, he took out a small
screwdriver.
At the same time, although none of them saw
him do it, he also took out a little brass
screw which he kept well hidden in the palm
of his hand.
Then he selected one of the screws in the
commode - there were four to each handle - and
began carefully scraping all traces of white
paint from its head.
When he had done this, he started slowly to
unscrew it.
'If this is a genuine old brass screw from
the eighteenth century,' he was saying, 'the
spiral will be slightly uneven and you'll
be able to see quite easily that it has been
hand-cut with a file.
But if this brass work is faked from more
recent times, Victorian or later, then obviously
the screw will be of the same period.
It will be a mass-produced, machine-made article.
Anyone can recognize a machine-made screw.
Well, we shall see.'
It was not difficult, as he put his hands
over the old screw and drew it out, for Mr
Boggis to substitute the new one hidden in
his palm.
This was another little trick of his, and
through the years it had proved a most rewarding
one.
The pockets of his clergyman's jacket were
always stocked with a quantity of cheap brass
screws of various sizes.
'There you are,' he said, handing the modern
screw to Rummins.
'Take a look at that.
Notice the exact evenness of the spiral?
See it?
Of course you do.
It's just a cheap common little screw you
yourself could buy today in any ironmonger's
in the country.'
The screw was handed round from the one to
the other, each examining it carefully.
Even Rummins was impressed now.
Mr Boggis put the screwdriver back in his
pocket together with the fine hand-cut screw
that he'd taken from the commode, and then
he turned and walked slowly past the three
men towards the door.
'My dear friends,' he said, pausing at the
entrance to the kitchen, 'it was so good of
you to let me peep inside your little home
- so kind.
I do hope I haven't been a terrible old bore.'
Rummins glanced up from examining the screw.
'You didn't tell us what you were going to
offer,' he said.
'Ah,' Mr Boggis said.
'That's quite right.
I didn't, did I?
Well, to tell you the honest truth, I think
it's all a bit too much trouble.
I think I'll leave it.'
'How much would you give?'
'You mean that you really wish to part with
it?'
'I didn't say I wished to part with it.
I asked you how much.'
Mr Boggis looked across at the commode, and
he laid his head first to one side, then to
the other, and he frowned, and pushed out
his lips, and shrugged his shoulders, and
gave a little scornful wave of the hand as
though to say the thing was hardly worth thinking
about really, was it?
'Shall we say... ten pounds.
I think that would be fair.'
'Ten pounds!'
Rummins cried.
'Don't be so ridiculous, Parson, please!'
'It's worth more'n that for firewood!'
Claud said, disgusted.
'Look here at the bill!'
Rummins went on, stabbing that precious document
so fiercely with his dirty fore-finger that
Mr Boggis became alarmed.
'It tells you exactly what it cost!
Eighty-seven pounds!
And that's when it was new.
Now it's antique it's worth double!'
'If you'll pardon me, no, sir, it's not.
It's a second-hand reproduction.
But I'll tell you what, my friend - I'm being
rather reckless, I can't help it - I'll go
up as high as fifteen pounds.
How's that?'
'Make it fifty,' Rummins said.
A delicious little quiver like needles ran
all the way down the back of Mr Boggis's legs
and then under the soles of his feet.
He had it now.
It was his.
No question about that.
But the habit of buying cheap, as cheap as
it was humanly possible to buy, acquired by
years of necessity and practice, was too strong
in him now to permit him to give in so easily.
'My dear man,' he whispered softly, 'I only
want the legs.
Possibly I could find some use for the drawers
later on, but the rest of it, the carcass
itself, as your friend so rightly said, it's
firewood, that's all.'
'Make it thirty-five,' Rummins said.
'I couldn't sir, I couldn't!
It's not worth it.
And I simply mustn't allow myself to haggle
like this about a price.
It's all wrong.
I'll make you one final offer, and then I
must go.
Twenty pounds.'
'I'll take it,' Rummins snapped.
'It's yours.'
'Oh dear,' Mr Boggis said, clasping his hands.
'There I go again.
I should never have started this in the first
place.'
'You can't back out now, Parson.
A deal's a deal.'
'Yes, yes, I know.'
'How're you going to take it?'
'Well, let me see.
Perhaps if I were to drive my car up into
the yard, you gentlemen would be kind enough
to help me load it?'
'In a car?
This thing'll never go in a car!
You'll need a truck for this!'
'I don't think so.
Anyway, we'll see.
My car's on the road.
I'll be back in a jiffy.
We'll manage it somehow, I'm sure.'
Mr Boggis walked out into the yard and through
the gate and then down the long track that
led across the field towards the road.
He found himself giggling quite uncontrollably,
and there was a feeling inside him as though
hundreds and hundreds of tiny bubbles were
rising up from his stomach and bursting merrily
in the top of his head, like sparkling-water.
All the buttercups in the field were suddenly
turning into golden sovereigns, glistening
in the sunlight.
The ground was littered with them, and he
swung off the track on to the grass so that
he could walk among them and tread on them
and hear the little metallic tinkle they made
as he kicked them around with his toes.
He was finding it difficult to stop himself
from breaking into a run.
But clergymen never run; they walk slowly.
Walk slowly, Boggis.
Keep calm, Boggis.
There's no hurry now.
The commode is yours!
Yours for twenty pounds, and it's worth fifteen
or twenty thousand!
The Boggis Commode!
In ten minutes it'll be loaded into your car
- it'll go in easily - and you'll be driving
back to London and singing all the way!
Mr Boggis driving the Boggis Commode home
in the Boggis car.
Historic occasion.
What wouldn't a newspaperman give to get a
picture of that!
Should he arrange it?
Perhaps he should.
Wait and see.
Oh, glorious day!
Oh, lovely, sunny summer day!
Oh, glory be!
Back in the farmhouse, Rummins was saying,
'Fancy that old bastard giving twenty pound
for a load of junk like this.'
'You did very nicely, Mr Rummins,' Claud told
him.
'You think he'll pay you?'
'We don't put it in the car till he do.'
'And what if it won't go in the car?'
Claud asked.
'You know what I think, Mr Rummins?
You want my honest opinion?
I think the bloody thing's too big to go in
the car.
And then what happens?
Then he's going to say to hell with it and
just drive off without it and you'll never
see him again.
Nor the money either.
He didn't seem all that keen on having it,
you know.'
Rummins paused to consider this new and rather
alarming prospect.
'How can a thing like that possibly go in
a car?'
Claud went on relentlessly.
'A parson never has a big car anyway.
You ever seen a parson with a big car, Mr
Rummins?'
'Can't say I have.'
'Exactly!
And now listen to me.
I've got an idea.
He told us, didn't he, that it was only the
legs he was wanting.
Right?
So all we've got to do is to cut 'em off quick
right here on the spot before he comes back,
then it'll be sure to go in the car.
All we're doing is saving him the trouble
of cutting them off himself when he gets home.
How about it, Mr Rummins?'
Claud's flat bovine face glimmered with a
mawkish pride.
'It's not such a bad idea at that,' Rummins
said, looking at the commode.
'In fact it's a bloody good idea.
Come on then, we'll have to hurry.
You and Bert carry it out into the yard.
I'll get the saw.
Take the drawers out first.'
Within a couple of minutes, Claud and Bert
had carried the commode outside and had laid
it upside down in the yard amidst the chicken
droppings and cow dung and mud.
In the distance, half-way across the field,
they could see a small black figure striding
along the path towards the road.
They paused to watch.
There was something rather comical about the
way in which this figure was conducting itself.
Every now and again it would break into a
trot, then it did a kind of hop, skip, and
jump, and once it seemed as though the sound
of a cheerful song came rippling faintly to
them from across the meadow.
'I reckon he's balmy,' Claud said, and Bert
grinned darkly, rolling his misty eye slowly
round in its socket.
Rummins came waddling over from the shed,
squat and froglike, carrying a long saw.
Claud took the saw away from him and went
to work.
'Cut 'em close,' Rummins said.
'Don't forget he's going to use 'em on another
table.'
The mahogany was hard and very dry, and as
Claud worked, a fine red dust sprayed out
from the edge of the saw and fell softly to
the ground.
One by one, the legs came off, and when they
were all severed, Bert stooped down and arranged
them carefully in a row.
Claud stepped back to survey the results of
his labour.
There was a longish pause.
'Just let me ask you one question, Mr Rummins,'
he said slowly.
'Even now, could you put that enormous thing
into the back of a car?'
'Not unless it was a van.'
'Correct!'
Claud cried.
'And parsons don't have vans, you know.
All they've got usually is piddling little
Morris Eights or Austin Sevens.'
'The legs is all he wants,' Rummins said.
'If the rest of it won't go in, then he can
leave it.
He can't complain.
He's got the legs.'
'Now you know better'n that, Mr Rummins,'
Claud said patiently.
'You know damn well he's going to start knocking
the price if he don't get every single bit
of this into the car.
A parson's just as cunning as the rest of
'em when it comes to money, don't you make
any mistake about that.
Especially this old boy.
So why don't we give him his firewood now
and be done with it.
Where d'you keep the axe?'
'I reckon that's fair enough,' Rummins said.
'Bert, go fetch the axe.'
Bert went into the shed and fetched a tall
woodcutter's axe and gave it to Claud.
Claud spat on the palms of his hands and rubbed
them together.
Then, with a long-armed high-swinging action,
he began fiercely attacking the legless carcass
of the commode.
It was hard work, and it took several minutes
before he had the whole thing more or less
smashed to pieces.
'I'll tell you one thing,' he said, straightening
up, wiping his brow: 'That was a bloody good
carpenter put this job together and I don't
care what the parson says.'
'We're just in time!'
Rummins called out.
'Here he comes!'
- THE END -