CHAPTER ONE
The Grey Family
My father, Richard Grey, was a vicar in the
north of England, who was respected by everybody
who knew him.
He lived quite well on a small salary and
had a pleasant little house of his own.
My mother was the daughter of a rich landowner
and she married my father against the wishes
of her friends and family.
If she became the poor vicar's wife, they
told her, she would have to give up her carriage,
her lady's maid and the chance to live in
a large, beautiful house.
A carriage and a maid were certainly nice
things to have; but luckily my mother had
feet to carry her and hands to dress herself.
And a large, beautiful house would be pleasant,
but she would rather live in a cottage with
Richard Grey than in a palace with any other
man in the world.
Her father told her that she could marry the
vicar if she wanted to, but that if she did,
she would lose her fortune.
However, my mother was a strong woman who
knew what she wanted.
So the couple got married and my mother's
fortune was given to her sister.
Despite these difficulties and their simple
life, I believe that you could search the
whole of England and not find a couple who
were happier than they were.
My mother gave birth to six children, but
my sister Mary and I were the only two that
survived the dangers of early childhood.
I was six years younger than Mary, so I was
always a little spoilt because I was the 'baby'
of the family.
We lived a very protected life and my sister
and I did not go to school.
Instead, our mother, who was hardworking and
very well educated, taught us at home.
Sometimes we went to a tea party at a nearby
house or visited our father's parents and
other elderly family members.
Mostly, however, we heard about the world
through the stories our mother told us about
her younger days and of carriages, parties
and big elegant houses.
While these stories entertained us, they often
made me secretly wish that I could see more
of the world.
My mother seemed very happy and told her husband
that she had everything that she needed in
life.
However, my father worried that his wife had
given up too much in order to marry him.
As a result, he was always thinking about
how he could make more money.
One day, a kind friend suggested to him a
way of making a lot of money within just a
few weeks.
This friend was a merchant, a man who made
money by buying and selling goods.
If my father lent him some money, he said,
he would make them both rich.
My father took the chance and gave the man
all the money he had.
The friendly merchant used the money to buy
goods and then arranged for them to be sent
abroad on ships to be sold.
My father was excited and so were we all.
We were going to be rich!
We spent happy hours by the fire talking about
what we would do, where we would travel and
what we would buy with the money that would
surely soon arrive.
The weeks passed but then the terrible news
came.
The ship, which contained the goods and therefore
our fortune, had been caught in a terrible
storm.
It had sunk to the bottom of the sea along
with the goods it carried and the unlucky
merchant himself.
I was young and did not understand how serious
this loss was, but I could see how it had
upset my parents and this worried me.
My mother concentrated on taking care of what
little money we still had, and on cheering
up my father.
He, on the other hand, lost all hope and became
desperate.
He believed that this recent poor decision
had made his wife's life even worse.
Over time, he became ill with the worry of
it all and none of us could give him any hope.
We had a pony - a little horse - but we had
to sell it.
We stopped buying new clothes and we used
everything we had as carefully as we possibly
could.
My father dismissed one of our two servants
and my mother and sister began to help with
the cooking.
I offered to help, too, but although I thought
of myself as a young woman, I was still a
child in the eyes of my family.
My mother would send me away, saying, 'No,
Agnes, there's nothing here you can do.
It's much easier for me to do it myself.
Go and help your sister.'
Then I would go to my sister and say, 'Mary,
Mother says that I should help you.'
To which Mary used to reply, 'No, you are
too young to help me, sweet Agnes, go and
play the piano, or play with the cat.'
During this difficult time, I never once heard
my mother complain.
When the summer came, though, she and Mary
talked about ways in which they could make
a little more money.
They wanted to give Father a much-needed holiday
by the sea.
'I wish I could do something,' I said one
day.
'You, Agnes!'
they both cried.
'Yes, I've had an idea...,' I began nervously.
'Really?' said my mother.
'Tell us what it is.'
'I would like to be a governess,' I replied
quietly.
My mother said nothing and Mary, who had been
holding a book, dropped it in surprise and
cried, 'You, Agnes?
You want to be a governess?'
'Well, yes.
I don't think it's such a strange idea.
Surely, I could teach little children... and
I think I would enjoy it...
I like children,' I explained, 'Please let
me, Mother!'
'My child,' said my mother kindly, 'You have
not learnt to take care of yourself yet.
Young children need someone who is experienced
to look after them.'
'But I am eighteen now,' I told her, 'and
I can take care of myself, and others too.
You do not know how capable I am, because
I haven't had a chance to try.
Just let me try, that is all I ask of you.'
At that moment, my father came into the room
and heard about my idea.
He agreed that I was not ready to become a
governess and gently said that I was too young
to leave home.
The subject was not mentioned again, but I
could think of nothing else.
How wonderful it would be to be a governess!
To go out into the world; to start a new life;
to make my own decisions; to earn my own money,
and give some help to my family; to show them
what 'little' Agnes could do.
I felt sure that I would be a good governess.
Three or four days later, I mentioned the
idea again to my mother.
With some difficulty, I persuaded her to speak
to my father.
It was not long before my father and sister
had warmed to the idea and my mother began
to look for a job for me.
After a few weeks, I was offered the job of
taking care of the young family of Mrs Bloomfield,
who was a friend of one of our distant family
members.
The salary was only twenty-five pounds a year
and my parents advised me not to take the
job.
However, I had no other job offers and because
I was young and wanted to work, I happily
accepted the offer.
Several weeks of preparation followed and
I could not wait to start my new job.
Finally, September came and my new clothes
had been made and my bags had been packed.
I had taken my last walk with Mary, I had
sung my last song to my father; and I had
said goodbye to the little cat.
When it was time to go to bed and I saw my
empty cupboards, I suddenly felt nervous and
wondered if I had made the right decision.
But in the morning I felt excited again.
I washed, dressed, ate breakfast and kissed
my family goodbye.
I climbed up into the small, open carriage
and waved to my mother and sister as the carriage
began to move away down the hill.
Then, and not before then, I burst into tears.
CHAPTER TWO
The Bloomfield Family
The journey was cold and long and it was one
o'clock in the afternoon when I arrived at
Wellwood House.
As the carriage moved through the large gates
and the impressive house and gardens came
into view, I began to feel very nervous.
There was no going back now.
How would I introduce myself?
What would my new life be like?
I hoped that Mrs Bloomfield was a kind, generous
woman and that I would get on well with the
children.
'Be calm, be calm, whatever happens,' I said
to myself as I entered the house and met Mrs
Bloomfield for the first time.
She was a tall, serious-looking woman, with
thick black hair, cold grey eyes and very
pale skin.
I was so nervous that I almost forgot to reply
when she introduced herself.
She showed me my bedroom and then told me
to come down for lunch in a few minutes.
With some difficulty, I found my way into
the dining room where some lunch had been
put out on a long table.
As I ate, she sat opposite me, watching me
and asking a few questions.
When she spoke, she spoke quite formally,
and most of the time I ate in silence.
When I had finished eating, she led me into
the sitting room.
She rang a bell and when a servant appeared,
she asked for the children to be brought to
meet me.
'I think they are clever children,' said Mrs
Bloomfield as we waited for them to arrive,
'and very keen to learn, especially the little
boy; he is generous and always tells the truth.'
I was pleased to hear this good news.
'His sister, Mary Ann,' she continued, 'is
generally a very good girl, but you will need
to watch her carefully.'
At that moment, my two young pupils came into
the room.
Master Tom Bloomfield was a handsome, tall
boy of about seven with fair hair, blue eyes
and a small turned up nose.
Mary Ann, who was a year or so younger than
her brother, was also a tall girl for her
age.
She was dark-haired like her mother, but with
a round face and pink cheeks.
We spent a few minutes talking and I saw that
they seemed to be very confident, lively children.
Mrs Bloomfield then suggested that Master
Tom should show me where I would teach them
and so he led the way to the schoolroom.
As soon as we were in the schoolroom, the
children began to argue with each other and
Tom pushed his sister roughly.
This was very shocking, but I hoped that in
time I would be able to change their behaviour.
Later that evening, after the children had
gone to bed, Mrs Bloomfield talked to me again.
She told me in great detail about her wonderful
children, what they must learn and how I should
manage them.
At about half-past nine, she invited me to
eat a supper of cold meat and bread.
I was glad when that was over and I was able
to return to my room.
Although I really wanted to like her, I could
not help feeling that she was cold, serious
and even a little frightening - the very opposite
of the kind, gentle woman I had hoped she
would be.
Despite the disappointments of the previous
day, I woke up the next morning feeling excited
and hopeful.
I was going to spend my first morning in the
schoolroom with the children.
However, the morning turned out to be full
of challenges.
Tom, although he seemed quite clever, was
very lazy.
Mary Ann could hardly read at all and kept
looking out of the window, or walking away.
We had made very little progress by the end
of the lesson.
'Now you must put on your coat,' Tom told
me, 'I want to show you the garden.'
'I'm not sure that's a good idea,' I told
him.
'It looks like it's going to rain and...'
'That doesn't matter,' he interrupted.
'You have to come with us.
And I won't allow any excuses,' he added rudely.
It was our first day together and I did not
want to get into an argument, so I agreed
to go with the children.
The garden was large and beautiful, but I
was not allowed any time to admire it.
Instead, I was taken to a distant corner of
the garden.
There Tom showed me different traps he had
made to catch birds and other small animals.
He proudly told me how he liked to cut the
birds up with a knife, or pull off their wings.
'Don't you know it is extremely wicked to
do those things to animals?'
I cried, shocked by what he had told me.
'Oh, what nonsense!' he replied.
'Father knows what I do to them and he says
it's just what he used to do when he was a
boy.'
'Well, I still think it is wrong,' I told
him.
'And you will certainly not hurt any animals
as long as I have the power to prevent it.'
Next, they took me to a pond - a small area
of water - in the corner of the garden.
Mary Ann started to throw stones into the
water.
The children's clothes became wet and dirty
and I told them to come away from the pond.
But I had no control over them - they did
exactly what they wanted to and ignored what
I said to them.
After a few minutes of trying to persuade
them to leave the pond, I suddenly saw a man
riding a horse towards us.
He shouted loudly to the children, 'Get out
of that water!'
then he came towards me.
'I suppose you are Miss Grey,' he said coldly.
'I am surprised that you are allowing them
to get their clothes dirty like this.
Can't you see that Miss Bloomfield has dirt
on her dress?
And that Master Bloomfield's socks are wet?
I request that in future, you at least keep
their clothes clean!'
Then he turned and continued his ride up to
the house.
This must be Mr Bloomfield!'
I was surprised that he had called his young
children 'Miss' and 'Master' and I was shocked
that he had not spoken to me in a more polite
way.
When the children and I were called into the
dining room for lunch, I saw him again.
He was quite a short man and was rather thin.
He was between thirty and forty years of age:
he had a large mouth, pale skin, dull blue
eyes, and the sort of hair, which is neither
fair nor brown.
During lunch, he complained about the food,
said the kitchen servants were lazy and told
his wife that she was not even capable of
organizing a meal.
'Perhaps, Mr Bloomfield, you will order lunch
yourself in future,' she told him, angrily.
Nothing more was said and I was very glad
to leave the room with the children.
I was not used to hearing people talk to each
other in this way; I had never felt so embarrassed
and uncomfortable in my life.
In the afternoon, I tried to teach Tom and
Mary Ann once more, then they took me outside
again, then we ate supper together in the
schoolroom.
Much later, when they had gone down to see
their parents, I had some time to myself at
last.
I sat down and started to write a letter to
my lovely family, but the children came back
upstairs before I had finished it.
At seven o'clock, I had to put Mary Ann to
bed and then I played with Tom until he went
to bed at eight.
Then I finished my letter and spent some time
hanging up my clothes, something I had not
yet managed to do.
Finally, I got into bed and because I was
so tired, I fell asleep in just a few minutes.
I did not know it at the time, but this had
been a good day compared to many of the days
that would follow.
CHAPTER THREE
The Bird's Nest
Teaching and looking after the children became
harder, rather than easier, as I got to know
them.
Master Tom not only refused to be controlled,
but tried to control me and his sister.
He often refused to do his lessons.
Sometimes I had to sit with my chair against
the door in order to keep him in the schoolroom.
At last, after trying to push me out of the
way, and making faces at me, he would finally
do his work.
Tom, however, was not as bad a pupil as Mary
Ann.
If I asked her to read a book or do some writing,
she would drop to the floor and yell loudly.
She was too heavy for me to pick up, and so
she would lie there until the lunch bell meant
that she could escape.
Then she would jump up with a big smile on
her face.
She knew she had won.
The children's behaviour meant that it was
almost impossible to get them to the dining
room at the right time, or make sure they
were dressed correctly.
Mrs Bloomfield would then give me black looks
and Mr Bloomfield would make disparaging comments
about me to his wife while I was in the room.
This upset me.
I had tried everything I could think of to
teach and control the children.
In desperation, I decided that I should focus
on two very important things in order to change
their behaviour.
I had to be patient and I had to be strict.
So I focused on doing this with all of my
strength over the coming weeks.
However, it did not matter how hard I tried.
Their behaviour did not get better.
I will never forget one cold, snowy January
afternoon.
The children had come into the schoolroom,
shouting that they planned 'to be naughty,'
and they had done exactly that.
While I was holding Tom down on his chair
and making him do his work, Mary Ann took
my workbag and started to look at what was
inside it.
When she saw that it only contained my work
papers and books, she threw it into the fire!
Letting Tom go, I ran to the other side of
the room and pulled the bag out of the fire.
Then Tom jumped up from his chair and yelled,
'Let's throw her desk out of the window!'
He grabbed my desk, which contained my letters
and the little money I owned.
I quickly went to rescue it.
Both children then ran away from me, out of
the house and into the snow, where they rolled
about, shouting with happiness.
I stood in shock, watching them.
While I was wondering what to do next, I heard
a voice behind me.
'What on earth are the children doing?'
It was Mr Bloomfield.
'I can't get them to come inside, sir,' I
said, turning round.
'Come in now, you dirty brats; or I'll hit
both of you!' he yelled.
The children ran into the house.
'There, you see!
They come at the first word!' he commented.
'Yes, when you tell them what to do, sir,'
I told him.
'And it's very strange that you don't seem
to be able to control them, isn't it?' he
said.
'You're meant to be their governess.'
It was true: I could not control them.
At least not without hitting them or saying
that, I was going to hit them, which was what
their father did.
But I felt sure that hurting them was not
the right thing to do.
Later that evening, just before I entered
the dining room, I heard Mr Bloomfield telling
his wife about the afternoon's events.
'Goodness!'
I heard Mrs Bloomfield say, 'Do you really
think the children are safe with her?
I'm beginning to wonder...'
I heard no more, but that was enough.
From that day forward, Mr Bloomfield would
often come and check on the children while
we were in the schoolroom or in the garden.
Of course, Tom and Mary Ann were always doing
something they should not be doing.
If I was quiet at the moment Mr Bloomfield
appeared, he said that I was not doing enough
to control them; if I was telling them off,
he complained that I was being too strict.
I could not win.
One day in May, Tom came out of the bushes
in the garden carrying a nest of young birds,
with Mary Ann running behind him.
He put the nest on the ground and stood over
it with his legs wide apart, his hands pushed
into the pockets of his trousers.
'You're not having any of the chicks, Mary
Ann!
They are all mine and I'm going to take them
out and pull their legs off!'
Tom cried.
'But, Tom,' I said calmly, 'I will not allow
you to hurt birds.
The nest must be carried back to the place
you took it from.'
'No!
I won't move from here!
And I won't tell you where we found them!'
he replied,
'Then if you don't change your mind and tell
me,' I replied, 'I will carry them back into
the bushes and leave them there, even though
their mother may not find them.'
When Tom still refused to return the birds,
I decided that I must do what I had said I
would do.
I picked up the nest and walked quickly into
the bushes and trees nearby.
Luckily, Tom did not attempt to follow me,
but starting yelling loudly instead.
I walked until I was far away from the main
garden, then I pushed the nest into a bush.
When I returned to the garden, I saw that
Mr Bloomfield had appeared and Tom had begun
to angrily tell him what I had done.
Mary Ann stood nearby, crying.
'I see,' said Mr Bloomfield, when Tom had
finished his story.
'Never mind, Tom, I'll find you some more
chicks tomorrow and you can do what you want
with them.'
Feeling anger rising up inside me, I turned
to Mr Bloomfield and told him, 'And if Master
Bloomfield tries to hurt them, then I will
feel it is my duty to take those away from
him, too.'
'Will you?' he said and then he looked at
me for a long moment before walking away with
the children towards the house.
When I reached the house myself, it was clear
that Tom had told his mother about the nest.
'I am sorry, Miss Grey, that you stopped Master
Bloomfield from enjoying himself,' she said
coldly.
'When Master Bloomfield's enjoyment involves
injuring animals,' I answered, 'I think it
is my duty to stop it.
I believe that it is wrong to hurt animals
for our enjoyment.'
'But I don't think,' she said, becoming impatient,
'that a tiny animal is more important than
my son's enjoyment.
Do you?'
I took a breath and thought carefully before
I spoke.
'For the child's own education, he should
be taught to be respectful and kind,' I answered,
as politely as I could.
'Oh!
Of course!'
she replied, 'But respect and kindness are
for people, not animals.
And I do not think that you have shown much
respect and kindness to my son by taking away
something he had spent a long time looking
for.'
I decided it was best to say nothing more.
This was the nearest I had come to having
an argument with Mrs Bloomfield.
It was also one of the longest conversations
I had ever shared with her.
Not long after this Mrs Bloomfield told me
that after the summer I would be no longer
needed.
She explained that while my general behaviour
had been acceptable, she and Mr Bloomfield
felt that the children had made very little
progress since my arrival.
Although the children were more intelligent
than most children of a similar age, she told
me, their school work was a disappointment
and they were not well behaved.
She believed that this was because I had not
been patient and strict enough with them.
But these were exactly the things that I had
been focusing on with all my strength!
I wanted to tell her how hard I had been trying,
but I began to feel upset.
I was worried that I would start to cry.
So I said nothing and that is how I was dismissed
from my first job.
What would my family think of me?
After everything, I had told them, I had not
been able to keep my job as a governess.
However, as upset and disappointed as I was,
I knew that all parents were not like Mr and
Mrs Bloomfield, and all children were not
like theirs.
Surely, the next family would be different,
and any change must be for the better.
There was no doubt that I had learnt a lot
at Wellwood House.
I felt confident that I could be more successful
with a new employer.
CHAPTER FOUR
Horton Lodge
I returned to my parents' house and for a
few months, I enjoyed a much more relaxing
life at home.
However, it was not long before I was ready
to look for another job.
After a few weeks of searching, I was offered
a job as a governess for the family of Mr
Murray.
The family lived at Horton Lodge, which was
a large house about seventy miles away from
our village.
I had never travelled further than twenty
miles from home before, so I was excited by
the idea of seeing a little more of the world.
The Murray children were a little older than
those of the Bloomfield family and so I hoped
that teaching them would be less challenging.
In addition, my salary was going to be fifty
pounds a year so I felt sure that I would
be able to send a good amount of money back
home to help my family.
It was decided that I would start my new job
at the end of January.
When at last the morning came, it was a wild,
stormy day and it was snowing heavily.
My journey was long and difficult and it was
dark when I finally arrived at the impressive
front door of Horton Lodge.
A servant invited me inside and took me straight
to the schoolroom, which was at the back of
the house.
There, two young ladies were sitting by the
fire.
I supposed that they must be my new pupils.
After we had been formally introduced, the
older of the two girls spoke.
'Miss Matilda, why don't you show the new
governess her room?
I'm sure she is cold and tired after her journey,'
she said to the other girl.
Miss Matilda was a strong-looking girl of
about fourteen.
She stood up and, a little shyly, asked me
to follow her.
She took me to a room at the very top of the
house.
Although small, the room was comfortable enough
and I was pleased to be able to take off my
wet coat, Matilda left me alone to organise
my things and change into dry clothes.
A few minutes later, the maid brought me some
tea and bread.
Feeling a little sad and lonely, I then sat
down on the bed and cried.
The next morning I woke up feeling nervous,
but also curious to know what my new life
would be like in this house, I went down to
the school room to begin what would be the
first day of two years of teaching the girls.
I do not want to bore you with all the details
of the first year or two with this family.
I will simply describe the family and give
you a general idea of this time.
The head of the family, Mr Murray, was a tall,
well-built man who I did not see very often.
Apart from going to church on Sundays, he
spent his time horse-riding, fox-hunting,
laughing loudly and yelling at the servants.
Mrs Murray was not an unattractive lady.
She was about forty years of age and she certainly
enjoyed her food.
Her main interests seemed to be either holding
or going to parties and wearing the very latest
fashions.
When I met her for the first time, which was
not until half way through my first day, she
told me what my duties were going to be.
'And remember,' she said after she had explained
the importance of good manners and not working
the girls too hard, 'that it is best to be
gentle with them,' While Mrs Murray talked
a lot about the comfort and happiness of her
children, she never once talked about my comfort
and happiness.
The eldest daughter, Miss Rosalie Murray,
was about sixteen years old.
She was tall and slim with pale blue eyes
and long fair hair.
She really was a very beautiful girl.
If only I could say such good things about
her character!
To begin with, she was cold and unfriendly.
And, rather like her mother, she was generally
only interested in how she looked and in the
idea that she might in the future marry someone
rich.
The fourth person, in the family, Miss Matilda,
was a tomboy and was very different from her
sister.
She did not care how she looked and was much
more interested in riding her pony or playing
with the family's dogs.
She was not a good student.
She often did her schoolwork too quickly,
made little effort and would run outside as
soon as she saw the chance.
Once or twice, I told her off for not making
any effort.
However, her mother became so angry with me
that I decided that it was best to allow Matilda
to do as little as she always had.
You may want to know how I spent a typical
day at Horton Lodge.
This is not easy to describe.
I ate all of my meals in the schoolroom with
my pupils, at whatever times suited them each
day.
Their hours of study were managed in a similar
way.
Sometimes the girls decided that they wanted
to get all of their studying finished before
breakfast and I would be woken up by the maid
at half-past five in the morning.
On one of these occasions, I ran downstairs
and waited, only to be told that they had
changed their minds and had stayed in bed.
On other days, they would simply decide that
it was a sunny day and they did not want to
study at all.
When they were in the schoolroom, they were
lazy and often rude.
The servants, who saw how the parents and
children of the family showed me so little
respect, did not make much more of an effort
themselves.
I sometimes felt disappointed and upset by
the life I led at Horton Lodge.
But, with time and patience, things did get
a little better.
Rosalie became a little more friendly.
When she was not, being difficult, she could
be fun and pleasant to be with and I grew
to like her.
Sometimes, when she forgot for a moment that
I was the daughter of a poor vicar, I think
she may even have loved and respected me.
What is more, the house was attractive and
spacious and was better in every way than
Mr Bloomfield's house.
It had a large garden and was in beautiful
countryside.
Every Sunday morning the whole family and
I would leave the house and go out in the
carriage.
We travelled through this beautiful scenery
and along the two miles of country roads to
the village church.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Ball
Not long after Rosalie's eighteenth birthday,
the time came for her to be formally introduced
to society.
She had now finished her education and was
old enough to look for a husband.
Mrs Murray was clearly very excited about
this fact and had decided to hold a ball for
her daughter at Horton Lodge.
It was going to be held on 3rd January and
all the rich people (and especially the men)
for twenty miles around were invited.
Months of preparation began.
One evening, about a month before the ball,
I was sitting reading a long letter from my
sister, Mary.
Rosalie came into the room and said, 'Miss
Grey, put that boring letter away because
I want to talk to you about my ball.
I don't want you to go home over Christmas.
You must stay here and help me plan!'
'But I'm afraid I can't stay,' I replied,
'I very much miss my family, and this letter
that you call "boring" tells me that my sister
is going to get married.
I want to be at home with her to help her
prepare.'
'Oh!' cried Rosalie.
'Who is she going to marry?'
'Mr Richardson, a vicar who lives just a few
miles away,' I explained.
'Is he rich?'
she wanted to know.
'No, not really,' I said.
'Is he handsome?'
she asked.
'Not really,' I told her.
'Then what sort of a house does he own?'
'A quiet little vicarage,' I said, 'with a
small old-fashioned garden and -'
'Oh stop!
I don't want to hear any more,' she cried,
'How on earth can she live there?'
'I expect that she'll not only manage to live
there, but will be very happy,' I told her,
'You did not ask me if he is a good, kind
or wise man.
I could have answered yes to all those things.'
From this conversation, alone it was clear
to see what Rosalie considered important,
and the type of man she wished to marry.
When I returned to Horton Lodge after the
Christmas holidays, Rosalie and Matilda began
to argue about who should tell me their news
first.
Rosalie, of course, could not wait to tell
me about the ball, Matilda was not in the
least interested in hearing about her sister's
party, but wanted to tell me about her new
pony.
Matilda had the loudest voice and so it was
she who won the argument.
After hearing everything about the pony, including
how high it had jumped and how well Matilda
rode it, I heard every detail of the ball
from Rosalie.
Of all the women at the party, she had worn
the most beautiful dress, she had danced the
most elegantly and she had attracted the most
attention.
I could only take her word for how the evening
had gone, but one thing seemed clear to me.
She had certainly flirted with almost all
of the men who had been invited.
She told me about two lords (who unfortunately
were already married) and there was Sir Thomas
Ashby (who was very rich, but ugly).
Then there was Sir Meltham (who was good-looking,
but too old) and the younger of his two sons,
Harry Meltham (who was good-looking, but too
young).
There were a few I had not heard of before
and then finally there was Mr Hatfield, the
local vicar.
While he was not impressively rich or from
a well-known family, Rosalie seemed to find
him acceptable, perhaps because he had been
chosen for his job by God himself.
'And which of them do you like the best?'
I asked her once she had finished naming them
all.
'Oh, I hate them all,' Rosalie replied coldly.
'But old Sir Meltham is the most handsome
and the funniest, Mr Hatfield is the most
intelligent and interesting and Sir Thomas
the most wicked.
If I had to choose one of them, I suppose
I would have to choose Sir Thomas Ashby.'
'But why would you choose him if you hate
him and he is wicked?'
I asked her.
'Oh, I don't mind his being wicked - that
would make him more fun,' she explained.
'And as for hating him, that doesn't really
matter, because I would be Lady Ashby of Ashby
Park, in that wonderful house!
But the truth is that I would much rather
remain single because I want to really enjoy
myself.
I would love to spend years and years flirting
with anyone I want to.
Then, when I've broken ten thousand hearts,
I will stop.
I will find one man who is rich, generous
and from an excellent family.
And I will escape all the black looks that
I will be getting from people by marrying
him.'
CHAPTER SIX
The New Curate
The next Sunday, I accompanied the whole family
to church as usual.
Rosalie was very keen to go as she had heard
that there was a new curate.
As we left the church later that morning she
said, 'Well, Miss Grey.
What did you think of the new curate - Mr
Edward Weston?'
'It is hard to say,' I replied, 'since I have
seen him, but I haven't yet spoken to him.'
'Well, no.
But aren't his clothes old-fashioned?
And isn't he ugly?'
she asked.
'No, he didn't seem unattractive to me,' I
replied.
I thought for a moment and then added, 'and
when he read to us from the Bible, I thought
that he read very well.
He seemed more interesting and more sincere
than Mr Hatfield.'
'Well, anyone can read from the Bible, can't
they?
But did you see how he walked out of the church?'
she said.
'He walked along, not looking left or right,
as if there was nobody there apart from himself!'
'Ah, I see,' I said and smiled.
'You mean to say that he made no effort to
look at you, or come and speak to you.'
'Well,' she said and gave me a black look,
'I suppose he's good enough for this place.
But have you seen how Mr Hatfield comes straight
to speak to father and me before anyone else?
And he always makes sure that he's waiting
outside to help me climb into the carriage.'
'Yes,' I answered.
Then I silently thought that it was not good
that the vicar had ignored everyone else in
the church to go to speak to the Murray family
so quickly.
I was also offended that he had helped the
ladies to get into the carriage and then had
closed the door and walked away.
He had left me to open the door again and
climb up by myself.
The following Sunday we went to church as
usual.
This time we heard Mr Weston preach the sermon.
I thought that his sermon was well written
and he preached it in a warm and simple way.
I was pleased that it was the opposite of
Mr Hatfield's sermons, which were usually
boring and full of self-importance.
When we left the church this time, it was
young Harry Meltham who quickly came to talk
to the girls and to help them get into the
carriage.
He did not help me, but at least he looked
at me and smiled as I climbed in.
I then spent the whole of the return journey
listening to Rosalie and Matilda argue over
which of the two of them Mr Meltham preferred.
My life was easier now that I now only had
one pupil and I therefore did not have to
suffer the girls' arguments so frequently.
It also meant that I had a little more free
time to look around the family's estate.
On several occasions, I had gone with my pupils
to visit the poor workers who lived in the
estate cottages.
We had taken them food, medicines and a little
money.
I had become friendly with one or two of the
cottagers and now I started to visit them
on my own.
On one bright day near the end of February,
I went to one of the cottages to see Nancy
Brown, a widow - a woman whose husband had
died - who had been ill and could not see
very well.
She loved books and so I went to read to her.
The cottage was small and dark, but Nancy
had a small fire burning and she kept the
place as clean and as tidy as she could.
When I had finished reading to her, she spoke
to me.
'Miss Grey, what do you think of Mr Weston,
the new curate?'
'I don't know,' I replied, a little surprised
by the suddenness of the question, 'I think
he preaches very well.'
'Yes, he does.
And he talks well too!'
she added.
'Oh, does he?
I haven't had a chance to speak to him yet,'
I explained.
'He's such a patient, thoughtful and generous
man,' she said, smiling.
'He comes to see me a lot more than Mr Hatfield
used to.
Mr Hatfield just used to come to tell me that
I had to go to church.
Once when he came he kicked my cat.
But Mr Weston... he reads to me, and sits
and listens to my troubles and talks to me
with kind words.
And he even lets my cat sit on him!'
'And how often does he come?'
I wanted to know.
'Oh, every few days,' she said and then went
on, 'and he goes to see all the other sick
cottagers, too.
I heard that he spent his own money on coal
for one family and took food to another.'
I was surprised and pleased to hear this news.
I knew that Mr Hatfield, the vicar, rarely
came to the cottages and was not interested
in the cottagers' needs.
But Mr Weston...
well, he really did seem like a breath of
fresh air.
For two years, I had been with silly girls
and people who thought that parties and marriage
were the only important things in life.
At last, someone had arrived in the village
who would rather spend his money on helping
others, than on buying the latest fashions.
I very much hoped that I would soon be able
to talk to him myself.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Chance Meetings
When we were in church the following Sunday
I looked at Mr Weston in a different light.
He was quite a short man, with brown hair
and a square face.
He was not handsome, but he was not, in my
opinion, ugly either.
When I had first heard him preach, I thought
that he was intelligent and sensible but also
quite serious.
Now I knew that he was also truly generous,
gentle and caring and this made him seem more
attractive to me as a result.
I started to look forward to seeing him every
Sunday at church.
A few weeks later, I went to see Nancy again.
I stayed with her a little longer than usual
because her cat had been missing for a couple
of days.
I tried to tell her that the cat would surely
return and that it was probably just out hunting,
but Nancy was sad and worried.
However, just as I was about to leave there
was a knock at the door.
The door then opened and in walked Mr Weston,
who was smiling and carrying Nancy's cat!
'Here you are, Nancy,' he said warmly and
gave the cat to her, 'I told you I would find
him.'
Then he smiled at me and said, 'I do hope
that you are not planning to leave now, Miss
Grey.
I'm afraid that it has just started to rain.'
Before I could speak, Nancy had pulled another
chair near the fire and said, 'You must both
stay here by the fire until the rain has stopped.
There's plenty of room for us all.'
We sat together as Nancy thanked Mr Weston
several times, and Mr Weston explained how
he had found the cat.
After a few minutes of conversation, Mr Weston
said that he was very pleased to have returned
the cat, but that he must now go and visit
another neighbour.
He politely said goodbye and then left.
I had very much enjoyed my visit to Nancy's
cottage despite, or perhaps because of, the
rain.
Rosalie was now so keen to flirt with as many
men as possible that she usually went to church
twice on a Sunday, Happily for me, I was always
expected to accompany her.
Often, if the weather was good, both she and
her sister would walk home instead of taking
the carriage.
Rosalie preferred to do this, as there was
always the chance that a man would offer to
walk some of the way home with her.
On one sunny day near the end of March, I
accompanied the girls, and three of their
admirers, on one of their walks back from
church.
I felt uncomfortable on these walks - I did
not want to walk next to them and be ignored
by them, but neither did I want to walk behind
them like a lonely servant.
Instead, I pretended to study flowers at the
side of the road so that I had an excuse to
walk behind them on my own.
As I was walking, I saw some yellow primroses
growing high on the top of a bank that was
covered in grass.
These small, beautiful flowers reminded me
of my garden at home, where lots of these
flowers grew each spring.
I wanted to pick some of the flowers to take
with me.
I started to climb the bank, but found that
it was too difficult for me to climb easily.
At that moment, I heard someone walking behind
me, and a warm, well-known voice suddenly
said, 'Allow me to pick them for you, Miss
Grey.'
Within a few moments, the flowers had been
picked and were in my hand.
It was Mr Weston, of course!
Who else would make the effort to do something
so thoughtful for me, an unimportant governess?
I was not used to anyone in the village being
so kind to me and I felt very grateful.
I thanked him nervously and began to walk
down the country road towards Rosalie, Matilda
and their group.
'Your young ladies have left you alone,' he
commented as he began to walk next to me.
'Yes, they are busy with more interesting
people,' I replied.
'Then slow down a little.
If I were you I wouldn't go so quickly to
catch them up,' he said and smiled.
For a few moments, we walked in silence and
I could not think of anything to say to him.
Then he spoke and asked me if I especially
liked primroses.
'Oh, yes.
I love them,' I said, 'I miss my family so
much and primroses remind me of home.'
'How lucky you are, Miss Grey, to have a home
that you love and know that you can return
to,' he told me.
'Yes,' I agreed.
'It gives me so much comfort that I don't
think I could live without it.'
'I'm sure you could,' he said thoughtfully.
'The human heart is much stronger than we
might think.
You might be miserable if you lost your home,
but you would survive and you would be all
right.'
He was quiet for a moment before continuing
quietly, 'Take my word for it because I speak
from experience.
There was a time when I, like you, believed
that a home and family were the only things
that made life bearable.
But both of my parents have now died and I
no longer have a home.
All I have are two rented rooms in this village.
And yet not only have I survived, but I still
have hope.'
'And you don't know what happiness there may
be in the future for you,' I said quickly,
'you are still young.'
'I am already very happy,' he replied, 'because
I know that I can be useful and help people
who are less fortunate than me.'
When the walk was finished, I could not stop
thinking about Mr Weston.
He seemed such a sensitive, caring, thoughtful
man.
I felt very sorry for him because he had no
mother, no father and no real home.
Perhaps this was the reason why he often looked
so serious.
But I also thought that, over the months,
he would surely make friends in the village.
If he wanted to he could make a home for himself
and in time, he might meet a woman.
Someone as honest and as good as him, who
he could many and share his new home with.
What a happy life they could lead together
and how lucky that woman would be...
I put the primroses in some water in my room
and looked at them every day.
When they finally began to die, I took one
of them and placed it between the pages of
a large book so that it would dry.
I still have that dried flower today, and
I plan to keep it forever.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Mr Hatfield
The following day was as sunny as the previous
one.
I spent the first part of the morning trying
to teach Matilda, who was in a terrible mood
because she wanted to go outside and ride
her pony.
After just a couple of hours, she gave up
and said that she was going to play with the
dogs.
When she had left, I started to draw.
Rosalie had gone out that morning to enjoy
a quiet walk and to sit and read her book
in the fields.
She had told me to finish a drawing that she
herself had started several days earlier.
At my feet lay a small dog with rough hair.
The dog belonged to Matilda, but she hated
the animal and said that it was not well behaved.
It really was quite a good dog, but she said
that it was not even clever enough to know
who its owner was.
The truth was that to begin with, she had
played with the dog all the time, but she
had soon got tired of having to look after
it.
Then, of course, the job became mine.
Because I was the person who gave Snap food
and took him for walks, he grew to love me.
I became very fond of him too.
Matilda, seeing that the dog preferred to
be with me than with her, decided she did
not like him and often said that she might
sell him.
While I was sitting like this trying to finish
Rosalie's drawing, Mrs Murray suddenly came
into the room.
'Miss Grey,' she began, 'How on earth can
you sit inside drawing on such a wonderful
day as this?'
Of course, I would not have been doing this
for my own pleasure, but Mrs Murray did not
understand that.
'Why don't you go outside with the young ladies?'
she added.
'I think, Madam,' I replied, 'that Miss Murray
is out reading somewhere and Miss Matilda
is spending time with the dogs.'
'Well, I think if Matilda spent more time
here, in the classroom with you, she wouldn't
need to spend so much time with those silly
dogs!'
she said.
'And if you were a little more cheerful and
friendly towards Rosalie, then perhaps she
wouldn't spend so much time walking around
the fields with a book in her hand,' she added.
Then, after a pause, 'And why does she like
to be on her own so much?'
'She says that she likes to be alone when
she has a new book to read,' I explained.
'But why can't she read it in the garden?
Why should she go into the fields?
And why does she so often seem to bump into
Mr Hatfield when she is out?'
Mrs Murray was full of questions now.
'And I'm sure I've just seen him from my window,
this very minute, walking very quickly in
the direction of that field where she often
sits!'
she cried.
'You should know exactly where she is at all
times.
Please go and see if she is there,' she continued.
'It is not right for a young lady to be walking
alone like that.
Any man at all could approach her and talk
to her!
And she is often far too friendly with them.'
As Mrs Murray had suggested, I found Rosalie
walking by the fields with Mr Hatfield.
As I got near them, I thought that Rosalie
certainly did look elegant as she smiled and
chatted to Mr Hatfield.
She was walking slowly under the trees, with
her closed book in one hand, a flower in the
other hand and her long dress moving gently
with the light wind.
Snap, running ahead of me, interrupted the
romantic moment by grabbing her dress in his
teeth and pulling at it.
This carried on for a moment until Mr Hatfield
kicked the dog.
Snap ran back to me and as I walked forward
to touch him, I heard Mr Hatfield speak.
'When will I see you again, Miss Murray?'
he asked.
He had realised that my arrival meant that
the time for him to leave had come.
'At church, I suppose,' Rosalie replied, 'unless
your work brings you here again, at the exact
moment that I happen to be walking in this
field.'
'Well,' he said, 'I could always manage to
have business here, if I knew exactly when
and where to find you.'
'Oh,' she said, smiling flirtatiously, 'I
couldn't possibly know today what I might
be doing tomorrow!'
'Then let me have that flower you are holding,
to comfort me and remind me of you,' he said,
half-joking and half-serious.
He reached his hand out to take the flower.
'No,' she said and moved the flower away.
'I won't give you the flower.'
'Oh, please do!' he cried, 'I will be a miserable
man if you don't.
Don't be so wicked to me.
Why say no for something, which is so easily
given, yet would mean so much to me?
Please!'
He could not have sounded more desperate had
he been begging someone to save his life!
Rosalie was clearly enjoying the power she
had over this man.
After a few moments, she finally said, 'Oh,
here then,' and gave the flower to him.
'Take it and go!'
He received the gift happily, said something
quietly into her ear that made her laugh and
go red in the face, then he left.
'I'm so glad you came,' Rosalie said to me
when he had gone.
'I was beginning to think he would never leave!
He's always coining here, pretending that
his work for the church has brought him out
this way.'
'Well,' I began, 'your mother doesn't want
you to go beyond the garden without someone
like me to accompany you and fight off all
the men.
She saw Mr Hatfield walking towards the fields
and sent me out to take care of you straight
away.'
'Oh, as if I couldn't take care of myself!'
she cried.
'She was telling me to keep away from Mr Hatfield
the other day.
But I wouldn't fall in love with him, or with
anyone!
I hate the word 'love'.
I might prefer one man to another, but even
then, I would never prefer Mr Hatfield.
I like talking to him because he's clever
and funny, but I'm not at all interested in
him - he hasn't got any money!
But I must have someone to flirt with and
he's the only person who comes here.
When we go out, Mother will only let me flirt
with Sir Thomas Ashby because the plan is
that I will marry him and it's not good for
me to be seen with other men.
But he's boring and not half as nice as Mr
Hatfield.'
'Is he?'
I asked, 'then why do you want to marry him?'
'Well, it doesn't matter that he's boring,'
she replied, 'he's rich, and he'll be all
right when he's married.
I just wish he wasn't so ugly, but then there
aren't very many men to choose from here in
the countryside.'
'But wouldn't Mr Hatfield be a better choice?'
I asked.
'Well, he would be if he was the lord of Ashby
Park, but he isn't.
And the fact is that I must have Ashby Park
and it doesn't matter who I share it with.'
I was shocked by Rosalie's attitude.
'But Mr Hatfield clearly thinks that you like
him!'
I said.
'He will be very disappointed when he realizes
he is wrong.'
Well, it is his own fault for making assumptions
about what I might feel.
Why on earth does he think that I like him?
In fact, I'm looking forward to seeing his
face when I tell him that I don't,' she replied.
There was nothing I could say that would change
her views.
Three days went by before Rosalie went to
the fields again.
I went with her, but after walking for half
an hour or so she suddenly asked me to go
back to the house to get her book for her.
When I returned, sometime later, she ran towards
me.
Her cheeks were pink and she was waving to
'Miss Grey!'
she called, 'I have some exciting news!
Just after you left to get my book, Mr Hatfield
suddenly appeared from nowhere.
He chatted for a while and was very polite
and said all sorts of things about me.
But he is so full of himself!
You won't believe this... he actually asked
me to marry him!'
'And you...'
I started.
I was worried about what she was about to
tell me.
'I stood tall and proud and said how shocked
I was that he had proposed,' Rosalie explained,
'I said that surely he had seen nothing in
my behaviour to make him think that I would
want to marry him.
You should have seen him!
His face went white.
I told him that I did not want to marry him
and that my parents would never agree to it.
He looked terribly sad and I almost felt sorry
for him.
Then he seemed angry.
He told me that he loved me greatly and that
I had broken his heart.
That I had flirted with him and played with
him like a toy without any thought of marrying
him.
Can you believe that he said that?'
I certainly did believe it and I agreed with
Mr Hatfield, but I said nothing.
'Then he asked me to keep his proposal to
me a secret and tell no one,' she went on.
'He said that if I didn't keep it a secret
he would tell people what I had done.
He said no one would want to marry me if they
knew how badly I had behaved!
So I promised and then he left.'
'But you have broken your promise already!'
I said, truly shocked by how she was talking.
'Oh, but it's only you.
I know you won't tell anyone,' she said.
'And I will tell my mother, just to show her
how wrong she was when she thought that I
might fall for him.'
Suddenly I realized why Rosalie seemed so
happy - she could now prove to her mother
that she had been wrong.
I was shocked by how she had behaved toward
Mr Hatfield and by how much pleasure she seemed
to get from seeing the poor man suffer.
The only positive thing I saw in the situation
was that Mr Hatfield had escaped what surely
would have been a very unhappy life with Rosalie.
CHAPTER NINE
The Change of Heart
Oh!
I wish Mr Hatfield hadn't proposed so soon!'
said Rosalie to Matilda the next day at four
o'clock, She was looking out through the window
at the fields.
'Now there is no reason to go out and nothing
to look forward to,' she added.
'It's a pity you were so hard on him,' said
Matilda.
'He'll never come again and I think that you
actually rather liked him.
I hoped that you would marry him and leave
all the other men free for me to flirt with.'
'Well, I'm sorry to lose Mr Hatfield, I have
to admit.
But there will be other men like him, I suppose.
It's Sunday tomorrow...
I wonder how he'll look and whether he'll
be able to read his sermon.
He'll probably have to pretend he is ill and
make Mr Weston give the service.'
'No, he won't,' said Matilda.
'He's a stronger man than that.'
Rosalie was a little offended by Matilda's
comment, but it seemed that Matilda was right.
Mr Hatfield spoke during the church service
as normal.
But he never once looked towards where the
Murray family were sitting and he did not
leave the church until we had gone.
Rosalie was clearly disappointed that he had
not looked at her once.
However, she said, it proved that he was thinking
of her all the time, or he would have looked
at her if only by chance.
But if he had looked at her, she would have
said it was because he thought her so beautiful
that he had no choice.
After a few more days of being bored at home,
Rosalie asked me to walk with her into the
village.
She said that she needed some new pencils
for her drawing.
Really, I think she wanted an excuse to see
Mr Hatfield, or flirt with some other men.
I have to admit that on the way I also started
to wonder whether we might see Mr Weston in
the village.
While Rosalie was in the shop buying her pencils
she made me stand by the door to tell her
if anyone interesting passed by.
No one did, apart from two of Rosalie's friends,
who stopped and chatted to her for a while
when she came out.
While they were talking, I walked a little
way down the street to look in a nearby shop.
After only a few minutes, Mr Weston appeared
beside me.
'You are alone again, Miss Grey!' he said.
'Yes, but only for a few minutes while Miss
Murray talks to her friends,' I told him.
'But aren't they your friends, too?' he asked.
'No,' I replied, 'I don't really have any
friends here in Horton.'
We stood for some time talking in a friendly
way.
We discussed all sorts of things and he asked
me what type of books I liked to read.
He listened carefully to what I said, asked
thoughtful questions and seemed interested
in my answers.
Why would he be interested in what I liked
to read and in what I thought and felt?
My heart started to beat faster when I thought
about the answer to that question.
Soon Rosalie arrived and saw that I was talking
to Mr Weston.
Rather than being cold to him, as I expected,
she smiled and talked to him with unusual
cheerfulness.
The three of us began to walk along the country
road towards Horton Lodge.
Before long, Rosalie was talking to Mr Weston
in such a way that there was no space in the
conversation for me.
I started to feel upset by this as I listened
to her speak so confidently to him.
She smiled at him, laughed at what he said
and swung her fair hair from side to side.
After a while, the road divided so we said
goodbye to Mr Weston and turned towards Horton
Lodge.
'I thought I could do it!'
cried Rosalie once we were some distance away.
'Do what?'
I asked.
'I have shot him through the heart,' she said.
'He will go home and think of nothing but
me.'
'How do you know?'
I questioned,
'Oh, there were many things that gave it away,'
she told me, 'but especially the way that
he looked at me when he said goodbye to us.
It was such a gentle, caring look, Ha!
He's not quite as stupid as I thought!'
I did not answer.
My heart felt as if it was in my throat, I
was worried that if I spoke I would cry.
'Please, please do not let this happen,' I
said silently to myself, 'for his sake, not
mine.'
As we continued the walk back to the house
all I could give were one-word answers to
Rosalie's cheerful chatter.
I was in shock and I wanted to go straight
to my room and cry.
The next Sunday was one of the greyest days
of April, with dark clouds and heavy rain
showers.
I went to church with Rosalie and despite
the recent conversation between Rosalie and
Mr Weston, I was still very much looking forward
to seeing him and hearing him preach the sermon.
It was raining heavily and as we were leaving
the church, Rosalie said that she wanted to
wait inside the door for the carriage.
Of course, a few moments later Mr Weston came
to the door and Rosalie started a conversation
with him.
She asked him if he would come and see a young
girl who was ill and who lived in one of the
estate cottages.
He promised that he would go to see her the
next day.
'And what time do you think you might go to
see her?' asked Rosalie, 'I'm sure her mother
would like to know so that she can tidy up
the house and make you feel welcome.
Perhaps I could come and introduce you to
them.'
Rosalie, who usually only thought of herself,
had suddenly become helpful and generous.
Mr Weston said that he would try to be there
at eleven o'clock in the morning.
I felt sure that this was just an excuse for
her to meet him again.
The carriage had now arrived and the footman
was waiting with an open umbrella to help
Rosalie get into the carriage.
Straight away Mr Weston stepped forward and
offered to cover me with his umbrella.
'No, thank you.
I don't mind the rain,' I said.
I always said the most stupid things when
I felt shy and did not have much time to think!
'But you don't actually like the rain, I suppose?'
he replied, with a smile that showed me that
he was not offended.
I could not disagree with that comment and
so I allowed him to cover me with his umbrella
as I walked to the carriage.
He put out his hand to help me climb up the
steps.
Then he looked directly into my eyes and smiled
as he closed the little door behind me.
It was only a small smile, and it was only
for a moment, but I saw in it, or I thought
I saw in it, a meaning of great importance.
It gave me more hope than I had ever had before
that he might care about me.
The next morning, Rosalie came into the schoolroom.
'Matilda, I want you to go for a walk with
me around eleven o'clock today,' she said.
I remembered that that was the time Mr Weston
was going to visit the cottagers.
'Oh, I can't possibly go for a walk, I'm busy,'
said Matilda, 'Miss Grey must go with you,'
'No, I want you to come,' said Rosalie and
explained why in a whisper, so Matilda agreed
to go.
That night at dinner, the girls told me about
their walk.
They had bumped into Mr Weston, and had a
long enjoyable walk with him.
They found him surprisingly pleasant and interesting.
And he had clearly enjoyed walking with them
too, they said.
CHAPTER TEN
Hope is Lost
A few weeks later Rosalie went to a party
that she had been looking forward to since
the winter.
It was a ball at Ashby Park and she wore an
elegant dress for the occasion.
Early the following morning she came to tell
me her news.
Sir Thomas had proposed to her at the ball,
just as she and her mother had hoped and planned.
Rosalie was very pleased that she was going
to become Lady Ashby and Ashby Park would
he hers.
She also loved the idea of a big wedding,
an impressive party and a honeymoon - a special
holiday after the wedding - that would be
spent abroad.
However, the one thing that she seemed disappointed
about was the date of the wedding.
It was planned to take place in only six weeks'
time, on 1st June.
This meant that she only had a few weeks more
to flirt with other men and enjoy being free.
During this time, she took every chance to
meet Mr Weston and tried every way she could
to make him interested in her.
She started to visit the poor cottagers, simply
because she knew that she would bump into
him there.
Of course, she never asked me to go with her.
She persuaded Matilda to go with her instead
as she had done that first morning.
She made sure that I stayed at home by asking
me to copy out a piece of music or finish
a drawing for her.
I could not understand why she was doing this.
If someone had told me how she was behaving,
I would not have believed it.
But I saw it with my own eyes and suffered
from it too.
During those six weeks, I was only able to
go to church once or twice.
Rosalie and Matilda found any excuse for me
to stay at home - I was ill or had some work
to finish in the schoolroom.
On these days, when they returned home, they
would sometimes tell me about the conversations
they had had with Mr Weston.
'He asked if you were ill, Miss Grey,' said
Matilda one day, 'and wondered why he never
saw you with us anymore.
So we told him you were very well, but that
you just didn't want to come to church and
that you preferred reading your books at home
to going out.'
I wondered what on earth he must think of
me, but there was no point in arguing with
Rosalie and Matilda.
And if I disagreed too strongly with what
they had said, then they would surely realise
how much I liked and respected Mr Weston.
So I said nothing and kept my feelings for
him a secret.
I tried to feel better by telling myself that
Rosalie would soon be married and gone.
In a few weeks, I would be able to spend the
holidays at home.
During this time, I heard that Mr Weston and
Mr Hatfield could not agree on anything.
This did not surprise me, as they were as
different from each other as two men could
be.
But I was shocked to hear that because of
this, Mr Weston was soon going to move to
a different job in another place.
What if he had left Horton by the time I returned
in the autumn?
I could not stop thinking about him.
It seemed that I may not ever see him again
and this made me feel desperate and alone.
There were two other things that added to
my problems at this time, one small and one
much more serious.
I was told that Snap, my rough but bright-eyed
little friend, was going to be taken away
from me and given to someone in the village
to look after.
The second thing was that each time I received
a letter from my sister Mary, she told me
that my father's health was a little worse.
This worried me very much.
He had not been at all well the last time
I had seen him.
I could not help feeling that something terrible
was going to happen.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Celebration and Sadness
The first day of June arrived and Miss Rosalie
Murray became Lady Ashby.
She certainly looked beautiful on her wedding
day.
After returning from the church, she came
running into the schoolroom to see me.
'Miss Grey, I am Lady Ashby!'
she said excitedly, 'It is done, there is
no going back now!
I've come to say goodbye because I am going
on my honeymoon now - I'm going to Paris...
Rome...
Naples...
Switzerland...
London...
Oh!
I will be away for months and see and do so
much before I see you again!
Goodbye - the carriage is waiting and they
are calling me.'
She gave me a very quick kiss on the cheek
and then began to leave.
But then she turned, came back into the room
and put her arms around me with more love
and warmth than I had thought she was capable
of.
After this, she left with tears in her eyes.
Poor girl!
I really loved her then and chose to forget
everything she had done that had hurt me and
others.
She had not really known what she was doing,
I felt sure.
I hoped with all my heart that she would be
happy with her new life.
Now that Rosalie had gone, I had much more
free time and I started to visit the cottagers
again.
I went to see Nancy, partly in the hope that
she could tell me about Mr Weston.
But she had not seen him for a while.
I have to admit that I even stayed a little
longer at her cottage in case he came to visit,
but he did not.
Sunday came and I was able to go to church
and hear Mr Weston preach.
It had been several weeks since I had been
to church and I was happy to be able to see
him and listen to him.
I walked home afterwards with Matilda, but
he did not come to talk to us and nor did
he walk home with us.
Matilda was as disappointed as I was that
we had to walk home alone.
Now that her sister had got married, Matilda
had started to think about when her time would
come to do the same.
Mrs Murray, too, had time to worry about her
younger daughter and to look for a husband
for her.
I was told that I must work extra hard because
the young lady's manners needed to be much
better.
Matilda was told that she was no longer allowed
to go riding every day or play with the dogs.
Just when I thought, my job had become much
easier, it began to get harder again.
In addition to long hours in the schoolroom,
Mrs Murray had decided that Matilda needed
exercise and should go on walks every day.
It was on one of these walks that Matilda
and I saw Mr Weston by chance.
I had hoped this would happen for such a long
time, but now I felt very nervous.
My heart was beating very fast.
I was worried that how I was feeling would
be clear to both Matilda and Mr Weston himself.
However, I need not have worried because he
hardly looked at me and spoke first to Matilda.
He asked if she had heard from her sister,
Rosalie.
'Yes,' she replied, 'She was in Paris when
she last wrote to us and she was very well.
And very happy, of course.'
After these last few words, she looked at
Mr Weston carefully, waiting to see what he
would say.
'I hope she will continue to be very happy,'
he commented, in what seemed like a sincere
way.
'Do you think it is likely?'
I asked him once Matilda had walked away to
look at some horses in a field nearby.
'I don't know,' he replied.
'According to what people have told me about
Sir Thomas and from what I have seen myself
of his behaviour, I have my doubts about Miss
Rosalie's happiness.
It is a pity that she has married him.
Even though Miss Rosalie can be very thoughtless,
she is so young and cheerful and... well,
interesting.
I suppose that she has married him because
that is what her mother wanted her to do.
Is that right?'
'Yes, and it is also what she wanted, I think.
She always laughed when I tried to persuade
her not to marry him,' I explained.
'Well, if you told her not to marry him then
at least you know that you are in no way responsible
if the marriage is an unhappy one!' he told
me.
At that moment, Matilda appeared again.
After talking for a little while longer, Mr
Weston said goodbye and continued on his journey
down the road.
However, just a few minutes later he returned
with some bluebells in his hand.
He offered the beautiful blue flowers to me
and smiled.
'I haven't forgotten how much you like spring
flowers,' Mr Weston said, 'even though I have
hardly seen you over the last two months.'
He gave the flowers to me in a very simple,
polite way.
But it meant a lot to me - he had thought
of me and had remembered the type of flowers
that I liked!
'Miss Rosalie and Miss Matilda told me that
you were so busy reading and studying that
you never left the house,' he said.
'Yes,' said Matilda very quickly, 'and it's
true!'
'No, Mr Weston, don't believe it,' I told
him.
'It's a terrible lie.
Some young ladies say things which aren't
true without worrying if it might upset their
friends.
You should be careful not to believe everything
they say.'
'Well, I certainly hope that in this case
it is a lie, Miss Grey,' he said.
'It would be a great shame if you chose to
read and study so much that you had no time
for anything else.'
Then we said goodbye again and he left.
You might be wondering why I have written
down all of this detail.
You may think it is not interesting enough
to write about.
But these conversations were important because
they gave me hope.
That evening I spent time remembering how
kind and thoughtful Mr Weston had been towards
me.
I dreamt that night of his smiling face.
The next morning I woke up full of happiness
and I was not able to think of anything else
other than him.
Hope, however, can leave as quickly as it
can arrive.
Later that same morning I received a letter
from my mother, which told me that, my father
was now very seriously ill.
Just two days later another letter came, this
time from my sister, Mary.
In her letter, she told me that she thought
my father was going to die very soon.
I went straight to Mrs Murray, explained the
situation to her and asked her if she would
let me go home to my family.
At first, she just looked at me.
Then she asked me why I was so upset - my
father may not be as ill as my mother and
sister had said, she told me.
And if not, well, we must all die one day,
she added.
Finally, she agreed to let me return to my
family.
I packed my things and left as soon as I could.
It was a long journey and it was half-past
ten at night by the time I finally arrived
home.
My mother and sister met me at the front door.
Both of them looked serious and were tired
and pale.
'Oh, Agnes!'
cried my mother and Mary started to cry.
'How is he?'
I asked.
'Dead!' came the reply.
It was the answer I had expected, but it was
still a terrible shock to me.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Saying Goodbye
My father was buried a few days later.
My mother, sister and I then sat down together
at home and talked about what we should now
do.
After a long discussion, it was decided that
the family home would be sold.
My mother's plan was to buy a smaller house
near the coast and turn it into a school for
young ladies.
In this way, she believed she could earn enough
money to live on.
'What do you think of the idea, Agnes?'
she asked me.
'Would you leave your job with the Murray
family to come and help run a school with
me?'
'Yes, of course,' I told her, 'and the money
I have earned will buy us furniture and equipment.'
It was sad to say goodbye to the old family
home.
I had been born in that house and had spent
my early years there.
My mother said she would stay until the house
was sold and she would make all the preparations
for the new school.
So I went back to Horton Lodge to work the
last six weeks that were still left before
the summer holidays.
Having explained to Mrs Murray what had happened,
I told her that I would not be returning in
the autumn.
During those last six weeks at Horton, I hardly
saw Mr Weston.
Every day I hoped I would bump into him on
my walks, but for the first two weeks, I saw
him only at church.
I felt disappointed and I told myself that
he clearly did not care for me.
If he loved me, would he not come to find
me?
How silly I had been to hope that he might
care about me.
I should forget all about him.
But then, at last, I saw him.
He was on the path walking towards me as I
was going through the fields to Nancy Brown's
cottage for a visit.
He must have heard from people in the village
that my father had died, but he did not mention
it.
But almost the first words he spoke were,
'How is your mother?'
It was a sincere question that seemed full
of warmth.
I thanked him for asking about her and told
him she was as well as could be expected but
sad, of course.
'What is she going to do?' he asked kindly.
I explained to him that my mother was planning
to open a new school and that I was going
to help her to run it.
'Then are you going to leave Horton Lodge
soon?' he said.
'Yes, in a month,' I replied.
He said nothing for a minute and it seemed
as though he was deep in thought.
Then he spoke again, 'And do you want to leave
here?'
'Yes, in some ways,' I told him.
'Only "in some ways"...
I wonder what things might make you want to
stay?' he said.
He sounded surprised.
I did not like this question, partly because
it embarrassed me.
I had only one reason to want to stay and
that reason was a big secret.
'Why have you made the assumption that I am
not happy in this place?'
I asked.
'Because you told me yourself that you missed
your family terribly and that you had no friends
here,' Mr Weston said.
'Well,' I replied, 'that may be true, but
it would be impossible to live somewhere for
two years without feeling some sadness when
you leave.'
'Will you be sad to leave Miss Matilda, who
is your only pupil and friend now?' he asked.
'It will probably be a little difficult to
say goodbye to her, I did feel sad when I
said goodbye to her sister,' I admitted.
'Yes, I can imagine that,' he commented.
'Well, Miss Matilda is as nice as Miss Rosalie,
or perhaps actually nicer than her in one
way,' I told him.
'In what way is that?' he wanted to know.
'She usually tells the truth,' I said simply,
'so at least I can say she is honest.'
'And her older sister is not?' he said.
'Well, perhaps she is not actually dishonest,
but I have to admit that she can be quite
creative with the truth,' I told him.
'Ah,' he said thoughtfully, 'so she is creative
with the truth?
I could see that she was a bit silly and loved
to talk about herself, yes.
And now I can believe that she wasn't fully
honest either.
That would certainly explain a few things
that I hadn't understood before.'
After that, he changed the subject and talked
about more general things.
He did not leave me until he had walked with
me to the gates of Horton Lodge.
He must have gone out of his way to walk that
far with me.
He had not mentioned love, or led me to believe
that he cared for me, but I was very happy
despite this.
To be near him, to hear him talk, to know
that he wanted to speak to me was enough to
make me happy.
'Yes, Mr Edward Weston.
If I had one friend here, one friend who truly
loved me and if that friend were you... then
I would definitely want to stay here.
I would be happier than I can imagine,' I
thought to myself.
'Who knows what can happen in a month?
I am twenty-two years old and the last few
years have been hard.
But perhaps I will be lucky now, perhaps the
sun will shine on me at last...'
I remained hopeful for a while but the time
I had left in Horton slowly passed away, one
week after another, and I hardly saw him.
And then the last Sunday came and I went to
the village church for the last time to hear
him preach, I listened to his sermon, surely
the last one of his I would hear, and I tried
hard not to cry.
After the service, I was leaving the church
when I heard a quiet voice just behind me.
'I suppose you are leaving Horton this week,
Miss Grey?' said Mr Weston.
'Yes,' I replied.
I was surprised to see him standing there.
'Well,' he said, 'I just wanted to say goodbye
before you leave.'
'Goodbye, Mr Weston,' I said.
How difficult it was to say that calmly!
I gave him my hand and he held it gently in
his own hands for a few seconds.
'It is possible that we may meet again in
the future,' he said.
'Would it make any difference to you whether
we did or not?'
'Yes,' I said.
'I would be very glad to see you again.'
He held my hand gently in his for a moment
and then left.
Now I was happy again, although probably more
likely to burst into tears than ever.
I walked home with Matilda, but I could not
concentrate on what she was saying.
All I could think about was Mr Weston... how
he had held my hand, how he had smiled kindly
at me and what he had said.
After several minutes, Matilda suddenly shouted
at me.
'Are you deaf or stupid, Miss Grey?
Have you not heard anything that I have been
telling you?'
she cried.
Matilda had woken me from my daydreams about
Mr Weston.
I looked up at her and asked her to tell me
again what she had been saying.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The School
I left Horton Lodge and went to join my mother
in Scarborough, a popular town on the coast
in Yorkshire.
She seemed to be in good health and had organised
the new schoolhouse well.
To begin with, we had nine students but we
hoped to have more pupils in the future.
I was happy to start work with my mother and
it was certainly different compared to the
jobs I had already had.
In the first few weeks, I enjoyed teaching
the pupils and I was happy.
When I was not busy, I daydreamed about Mr
Weston.
'It is possible that we may meet again in
the future,' and Would it make any difference
to you whether we did or not?'
- I repeated his words over and over again
in my head.
They gave me great hope.
'I will see him again.
He will come and visit me or he will write
to me,' I told myself.
Whenever I heard a knock at the front door
and the maid came to say that a gentleman
was there, I hoped it was him.
And every time the postman came I felt sure
that he was going to bring a letter from Mr
Weston.
But each time I was terribly disappointed.
Mr Weston did not come and no letter arrived.
I began to wonder if I had imagined the moment,
I had shared with him on that last Sunday
outside the church.
As the months passed, I began to lose hope.
I told myself I had been stupid to think that
he liked me.
He had just been trying to be polite.
'Agnes, you do not seem very well,' said my
mother one day in April.
'I don't think this change has done you any
good at all.
I've never seen you look so sad and tired.
You should relax and go out a little more.'
My mother was right.
I had given up hope and now felt miserable.
I often did not feel hungry and I was beginning
to feel weak and ill.
I told myself that I needed to look after
myself for my mother's sake.
She needed me with her and needed my help.
If I could not be happy myself, at least I
could make sure that she was happy.
I decided not to think about Mr Weston anymore,
or at least I would try not to.
I told myself that I would go for walks and
eat well.
By following these rules I made for myself,
I started to feel a little better.
In June I received a letter from Lady Ashby,
or as I had known her before her marriage,
Miss Rosalie.
In her letter, she told me that life was very
boring at Ashby Park and that she would very
much like to see me.
To my dearest Miss Grey,
I hope you are well and are not missing Horton
Lodge too much.
I have been at Ashby Park a little while now
and it is beautiful, but so dull!
I do not have a single friend here.
And you know that I never liked the idea of
just my husband and I living tightly together
like two birds in a nest.
I am sure that your holidays will begin in
June.
When they do, please come and see me straight
away!
In fact, if you do not come I think.
I might die.
I want you to come and see we a friend, and
not as my old governess.
You will have your own room and as many books
as you can read.
Do you like babies?
I can't remember if you do or do not.
If you do, you will want to meet mine.
It well behaved and thankfully I have a maid
here to look after it for me.
Unfortunately, it is a girl and Sir Thomas
is disappointed that I did not give him a
son instead.
But if you visit me I promise that you will
be its governess as soon as it can talk.
You can teach it and make it into a much better
woman than its mother.
You will be able to see my wonderful new home
and I am sure that you will love it.
It is full expensive Italian paintings and
all sorts of things that I bought while on,
my honeymoon.
And you can meet my new dog, which I had sent
over all the way from Park.
Write to me as soon as you can and tell me
when your holidays start.
Tell me that you will come on, the very first
day that you can and that you will stay until
the moment you have to return.
Your friend, Rosalie Ashby
I showed this strange letter to my mother
and asked her what I should do.
She advised me to go to Ashby Park and visit
Rosalie, I liked the idea of going to see
her and her new baby.
I hoped that I could help her if she were
unhappy.
Of course, I imagined that she must be unhappy,
or she would not have written to me in this
way.
I wrote back to her and agreed to go and stay
with her for a few days.
I had partly agreed to go because Ashby Park
was not far from the village of Horton.
I secretly hoped that I might see Mr Weston
while I was there, or at least hear something
about him.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
A Visit to Ashby Park
There was no doubt that Ashby Park was a wonderful
place to live.
The house itself was impressive and elegant
and the large park was beautiful.
There was a big lake, ancient woods and herds
of deer.
I could see why Rosalie had been so keen to
become the lady of an estate like this one.
She seemed pleased to see me and although
I was just a poor governess and a schoolteacher,
she welcomed me warmly to her home.
However, I did not like her efforts to make
me feel comfortable.
She told me that I should not be embarrassed
about how I looked.
She also said I should not worry if I felt
that the beauty of the place was too much
for me.
I did not feel at all embarrassed about how
I looked.
And nothing that I saw around me in Ashby
Park shocked me half as much as the changes
I saw in Rosalie herself.
During the twelve months since I had last
seen her she had changed in a way you might
expect to see after twelve years, not months.
She was much thinner, looked very tired and
seemed sad.
Her new baby girl, who Sir Thomas felt should
have been a boy, was just seven or eight weeks
of age.
I was surprised to see that Rosalie did not
seem to be interested in the baby.
She was happy to let the maid take care of
everything that the baby needed.
My bedroom was small but pleasant.
Rosalie also showed me a small sitting room
where I could spend time alone and read if
I wanted to.
I was taken on a tour of the house and was
shown the fine Italian paintings and the fat
French dog that was lying on an expensive-looking
cushion.
Rosalie seemed very pleased with all these
things.
However, when we had finished the tour she
took me into the main sitting room and then
sat down in a chair.
We sat in silence for a moment.
Despite all of these impressive things that
she had wanted so much, Rosalie did not seem
happy.
I asked her some questions, deciding to save
my most important question until last.
I started by asking her how her parents were.
She told me that they were well enough.
'And how is Matilda?'
I asked her.
'Oh, she is very well,' Rosalie replied.
'She is still wild and a little silly, but
she has now got a new, fashionable governess.
At last her manners are improving and Mother
will soon hold a ball at Horton Lodge so that
she can be introduced to society.'
'And how are the other people in the village?'
I asked.
'Mr Hatfield, for example?'
'Ah, Mr Hatfield!'
she said with a smile.
'I heard that he proposed to an old spinster
and married her not long ago.
He must have decided that he had not been
lucky when he chose someone young and beautiful,
so now he has chosen someone old and rich!'
'And the Meltham family?'
I continued, ignoring her comment about Mr
Hatfield.
'Oh, I don't know much about them.
I suppose they are all right,' she told me.
'Well, I think I have asked about everybody...
oh, but not Mr Weston,' I said.
'What is he doing?'
'I don't know.
He's not in Horton anymore,' Rosalie told
me.
'How long ago did he leave?
And where has he gone?'
I asked, trying not to sound too interested
to hear her reply.
'I don't know anything about him,' she said,
looking out of the window.
'Only that he left about a month ago.
I didn't ask where he had gone.
It seems that all the people in the village
were very upset when he left because they
liked him so much.
Mr Hatfield did not like them all making a
fuss about him leaving, of course.
He did not like Mr Weston because he was so
popular and he did not do things the way he
was told to.'
Then Rosalie stood up.
'Anyway, I really must go and rest for a while
before dinner.
I will have to eat with Sir Thomas and his
mother, old Lady Ashby, in the formal dining
room.
It's so dull.
But I'll ask the maid to bring your dinner
to you in the sitting room, if that is all
right?'
I told her it was.
She had invited me to her home, as her 'friend'
but we both knew that the social rules meant
that it would not be correct for a poor schoolteacher
to eat dinner with people as important as
Sir Thomas and Lady Ashby.
I walked back to the little sitting room where
I could relax and look out onto the gardens.
I ate my dinner there and then sat for a while
thinking about Lady Ashby's present life and
her past life, and about the little information
she had given me about Mr Weston.
I was not rich enough to own a watch, so I
did not know what time it was or how long
I had been sitting and thinking.
The sun began to disappear behind the trees
of the estate.
As it began to get dark, I felt lonely.
I was tired and wished that I could go home.
I was thinking about going back to my room
when Rosalie appeared.
She apologised several times for having left
me alone for so long.
She blamed her 'horrible old mother-in-law',
who she said had made her stay longer in the
dining room.
'But I don't know why I had to stay there
so long,' she added.
'Sir Thomas never really listens to me.
When he is in a bad mood all he does is complain
and when he is in a good mood all he does
is talk nonsense.
And then, in either situation, he always drinks
too much and falls asleep on the sofa!'
'Could you not ask him to drink less and keep
him busy with something else?'
I suggested.
'After all, you are very persuasive and are
very good at keeping a man entertained.'
'You think I am here to entertain him!'
she cried.
'That's not my idea of a wife.
It is the husband's job to keep his wife happy;
it's not her responsibility to please him.
And no, I will not persuade him to change
his habits.
I have enough work just putting up with him
as he is without making even more of an effort
in order to change him.'
She paused to take a breath.
'But I am so sorry that I left you alone for
so long.
What have you been doing?'
'Well, mainly sitting here looking at the
park,' I admitted.
'Goodness!
How boring that must have been!'
she told me.
'Well, let's go to bed now, but tomorrow I
will show you around the park.'
The next morning after breakfast Rosalie took
me to see the gardens as she had promised.
We walked through the park, talking about
what Rosalie had seen and done on her honeymoon.
While we were walking, a gentleman on a horse
rode towards us.
As he passed us, he looked straight at me,
so I could clearly see what he looked like.
He was tall and very thin with a pale face
that was a little grey.
He had dull, cold eyes.
He made no attempt to say hello to us.
'I hate that man,' Lady Ashby said quietly
as soon as he had ridden away.
'Who is he?'
I asked her.
'Sir Thomas Ashby,' she replied coldly, 'my
husband.'
I was shocked, but I asked her, 'Do you really
hate him?'
'Yes, I do, Miss Grey, and if you knew him
you would not blame me for hating him,' she
told me.
'But you knew what he was like before you
married him,' I commented.
'No, I only thought I knew him,' she said.
'I remember that you told me not to marry
him.
I know that I should have listened to you,
but it's too late to say that now.
At first, I thought that what he was like
wouldn't matter.
I thought he would let me do whatever I liked.
But he keeps me here like a prisoner and he
pays me no attention.
He won't let me go to London and have fun
with my friends because he says that I flirt
with other men and spend too much money.
But he does exactly what he wants!
He goes to London and leaves me here alone.
He gambles and flirts with other women and
is almost always drunk.
Oh, I would give anything, anything at all
not to be married to that horrible man, but
to be Miss Murray again!'
Then she stopped speaking and burst into tears.
Of course, I felt very sorry for her, I tried
to comfort her and give her some advice.
I told her to keep calm and try to be polite
to her husband.
I suggested that she should try not to think
about him and keep herself busy with other
things, perhaps reading and especially her
new little daughter.
I reminded her that her little baby would
grow into a young woman who would truly love
her.
'But what if the child grows up to be just
like its father?'
cried Rosalie.
'I don't think that is likely.
She is a girl and she looks very much like
you,' I told her.
'Even so, I can't put all of my hopes in a
child,' she said.
'It is only one step better than focusing
your whole life on a dog.
And I can't spend my life reading.
I am young and I should be having fun!'
'The best way to enjoy yourself,' I told her,
'is to do what is right and hate nobody.
The more wise and good you are the more happiness
you have.
And I have one more piece of advice to offer
you - don't make an enemy of your mother-in-law.
I have never met her, but I have heard good
things as well as bad things about her.
If you could be kind to her I believe that
in time she could become a good friend for
you here.'
But I am afraid that Rosalie did not really
listen to any of the advice I had given her.
I realized that I could be of little help
to her and this made it even more painful
for me to see what her life had become.
Rosalie begged me to stay longer, but after
two more days, I told her that my mother needed
me at the school.
I was very sorry to say goodbye to Rosalie
and leave her in her wonderful, but sad, house.
I knew she was very unhappy but I could see
no easy way out of the life, which she herself
had chosen.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
A Walk on the Beach
The school that my mother owned in Scarborough
was a short distance from the sea.
I loved being near the sea and I would sometimes
walk along the beach in my free time.
I awoke on the third morning after my return
from Ashby Park and saw that the sun was shining.
Knowing that my mother would still be asleep,
I quietly got dressed and left the house to
go for an early-morning walk.
The sea air was fresh and the summer sky was
a clear blue.
I walked along the long, empty beach and watched
the white waves as they came up onto the sand,
I felt full of life and as I walked along,
I forgot all of my worries.
At first, I was alone on the beach, but as
the sun rose higher in the sky, I saw that
a few people had appeared.
There were now several figures ahead of me
exercising horses or taking dogs for a walk.
As I approached the end of the beach I heard
a dog bark behind me, then suddenly a small
animal came running round in front of me and
stopped right at my feet.
It was Snap - the rough little dog that had
been mine at Horton Lodge!
I called his name and he jumped up into my
arms, I was so pleased to see him and he was
clearly excited to see me.
But how had he got here?
He could not have come so far on his own,
so I looked to see who he might be with.
I turned around and saw...
Mr Weston!
'Your dog remembers you well, Miss Grey,'
he said warmly, 'You must get up very early.'
'Not often as early as this,' I said, still
very much surprised to see both Mr Weston
and Snap.
'I imagine you must live quite close to the
beach, then.
In what part of the town do you live?' he
asked.
'I never managed to find out.'
Never managed to find out?
Had he been looking for me, then?
I felt my heart jump in my chest.
Then I remembered that he had asked me a question,
so I told him where our house was.
He asked if the school was doing well, I told
him that several more pupils had come to join
the school since the new year had started
and that we were doing very well.
'People must have heard that you are a very
good teacher, then,' he said.
'No, it is my mother they have heard about,'
I replied, 'she works very hard and manages
things so well.
And she is so active, clever and kind.'
'I would like to meet your mother.
Will you introduce me to her one day if I
come to your house?' he asked.
'Yes, of course I will,' I told him.
'And would it be all right if I came to visit
you every now and then?'
Mr Weston wanted to know,
'Yes, I don't think my mother would mind,'
I replied.
We turned and started to walk back along the
beach together.
'You haven't asked me why I have come to Scarborough,'
he said after a few moments' silence.
'Surely you can't think that I am rich enough
to be here on holiday.'
'Well, I heard that you had left Horton,'
I said.
'But you hadn't heard that I am the new vicar
of a parish just two miles from here?' he
asked.
'No,' I said.
'I don't receive much news from Horton.
Well then, congratulations!
I very much hope that you like your new parish
and your new job.'
'I think I will like it more in a year or
two,' he said, 'when I have made some of the
changes there that I think are needed.
It is certainly wonderful to have a parish
all to myself with nobody to disagree with
me and tell me how I should do things differently.
Of course, he was talking about Mr Hatfield.
Then he added, 'And I am lucky enough to have
a nice house in a good area and a salary of
three hundred pounds a year.
In fact, I have nothing but loneliness to
complain about.
And there is nothing I could wish for apart
from someone to share all of that with.'
He looked directly at me as he spoke these
last few words and I felt my cheeks go red.
I felt embarrassed.
'Oh, I'm sure that when you are well known
in your new parish,' I said quickly, 'there
will be many women there who will be keen
to share that life with you.'
'I am not so presumptuous as to expect there
will be a lot of women who want to marry me,'
he said.
'But even if there were so many, I am looking
for a very special type of person to share
my life with.
Perhaps I wouldn't find that person among
the ladies of my parish.'
'If you are looking for perfection - to find
someone who has no faults at all,' I told
him, 'then I don't think you will ever find
that person.'
'No, I am not looking for perfection,' he
replied.
'I have no right to because I am certainly
not perfect myself.'
We had reached the town now and before we
walked up the bank onto the street, he offered
me his arm to support me.
I put my arm in his.
Once we were in the street the horses, carriages
and men moving around us made it difficult
to talk.
We walked in silence for a few minutes, arm
in arm, before he spoke again.
'You don't often go down to the beach, do
you?' he said.
'I have walked there many times since I have
come here.
I have come both morning and evening and I
have never seen you until now.
And I have looked for your school as I have
walked about the town, but have never found
it.
Once or twice I asked if anyone knew of the
school, but no one could tell me where the
house was.'
He walked with me to the end of the street
where I lived.
'I'll leave you here, Miss Grey,' he said
kindly.
'And when will you come to meet my mother?'
I asked him.
'I hope to come tomorrow,' he told me.
He said goodbye and then called Snap to him.
The dog did not know which one of us he should
follow.
'I'm afraid I won't offer to give him back
to you,' said Mr Weston, smiling, 'because
I like him.'
'Oh, I am happy not to have him,' I replied.
'Now that I know he has a very good owner
I won't need to worry about him anymore.'
'You believe that I am a very good owner then?'
he said and smiled again before walking away.
I returned home full of happiness.
I had been given another chance and I hoped
that this time I would be lucky.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
The Happy Ending
'Well, Agnes, you must not take such a long
walk again before breakfast,' said my mother.
'Are you feeling ill?'
She had seen that I had drunk an extra cup
of coffee but had eaten nothing, I told her
that I just did not feel hungry because I
was hot and tired after my walk.
The truth was that I was too busy thinking
about how to tell my mother about Mr Weston
to think of eating.
If he was coming to visit the next day, then
I had to tell her that I had met him on the
beach.
I waited until breakfast had been taken away
and until I had calmed down a little.
Then, once I had sat down and started to do
some drawing, I began...
'I bumped into an old friend on the beach,
mother,' I said.
'An old friend?'
she said, 'Who on earth could that be?'
'Two old friends, in fact,' I told her, 'One
was a dog,' and then I reminded her of Snap,
who I had told her about in my letters from
Horton Lodge.
I now told her how he had suddenly appeared
on the beach and had run to me.
'And the other friend,' I continued, 'was
Mr Weston, the curate of Horton.'
'Mr Weston?
I've never heard of him before,' my mother
said.
'Yes, you have,' I corrected her, 'I've mentioned
him several times, I think, but you don't
remember.'
'I've heard you talk about Mr Hatfield,' she
told me.
'Mr Hatfield was the vicar and Mr Weston was
the curate.
Anyway, he was on the beach this morning with
the dog - he must have bought it from someone
in the village at Horton.
We talked for a little while after the dog
had found me.
He asked about our school and how well it
was doing.
I told him it was doing very well thanks to
your clever management.
When I mentioned you, he said that he would
like to meet you.
Then he asked if I would introduce you to
him, if he happened to come by and visit tomorrow.
So I said that I would.
Was it all right for me to say that?'
'Of course,' replied my mother, 'What type
of man is he?'
'He is a very good man, I think, but you will
meet him yourself tomorrow,' I told her.
'He is the new vicar in a village just two
miles from here and he has only been in that
parish for a few weeks.
I imagine that he has not yet made any new
friends and would like some company.'
I spent the next morning feeling nervous and
excited while I waited for him to come.
He finally came at noon.
Having introduced him to my mother, I moved
away to the other side of the room to carry
on with my drawing while they talked.
They got on extremely well together.
I was so pleased because I had been worried
about what my mother would think of him.
He did not stay long that time, but when he
left, she said she would be happy to see him
whenever he found the time to visit us again.
After he had left, she said to me, 'Well,
I think he is a very sensible man.
But why did you sit over there, Agnes?
And why didn't you join in with the conversation?'
'I didn't join in because you were having
a good conversation and did not seem to need
any help from me,' I explained.
'And anyway, he had come to see you, not me.'
After that, Mr Weston often came to visit
us.
As it was the summer holidays and my mother
and I were not teaching, he could come at
any time during the day.
When he came he spoke mostly to my mother,
but I did not mind that.
She loved to talk and I was happy to sit and
listen to the two people I loved most in the
world.
Formality was quickly forgotten and Mr Weston
began to call me 'Agnes' instead of 'Miss
Grey'.
The days when he did not visit seemed long
and very dull but I always had his next visit
to look forward to.
One evening, near the end of the summer holidays,
he came to the house and asked me to go for
a walk with him.
He wanted to show me the wonderful view over
the sea from a nearby hill.
With my mother's permission, I agreed to go
and went upstairs to get ready.
I took a little longer than usual.
When we left the house a few minutes later,
I put my arm into his and we went through
the busy streets of the town.
As we walked quickly, along he said very little
and I began to think that something was wrong.
But as we came out of the town he slowed down
a little and he seemed cheerful again,
'I'm sorry Agnes,' he said, 'I think that
I have been walking too fast for you.
I was keen to get out of the town but we can
walk as slowly as you wish now.
I think there is going to be a wonderful sunset.'
We walked in silence up the hill for a few
minutes before he spoke again.
'It is still quite lonely in my house,' he
said and smiled at me.
'And I have now met all of the ladies in my
parish and quite a few in this town, too.
But I'm not interested in any of them.
In fact, there is only one person in the world
that I want to share my life with... and that
person is you, Miss Grey.
Agnes, will you marry me?'
'Are you serious, Mr Weston?'
I asked him, because I could not believe what
I had heard.
'Serious!' he cried, 'How could you think
that I would joke about something like this?'
He put his hand gently over mine as it rested
on his arm; he must have felt that I was feeling
nervous.
'I hope that I have not shocked you,' he said
in a serious way looking at me closely, 'You
must have known that I am not the sort of
man to flatter you all the time and talk romantic
nonsense.
I hoped that you would know that a single
look or a single word of mine meant more than
the many things that most other men use to
flirt with women.'
I said nothing for a moment.
Many thoughts were going through my head.
'So, what is your answer?' he asked me.
'But what about my mother,' I said nervously,
'I'm not sure I could leave her to run the
school on her own.'
'You don't need to worry about that,' he told
me gently.
'While you were getting ready to come out
for this walk I talked to your mother.
She said that she would be happy for you to
marry me if that's what you wanted to do.
I also suggested to her, in case you said
yes, that she could come and live with us,
I thought that you would like that.
But she refused and said that she could now
afford to employ an assistant to help her
teach the pupils.
So, you can see that your mother will be fine.
Is there anything else that you are worried
about?'
'No,' I said, 'no, there isn't.'
'Do you love me then?' he asked, holding my
hand tightly in his.
'Yes,' I replied.
'Yes, and I will be very happy to marry you!'
And here I will stop writing.
My diary, in which I used to write these chapters,
does not continue any further.
I will just say that I will never forget that
wonderful summer evening.
I will always remember how we stood and watched
that beautiful sunset together.
My heart was filled with so much love and
happiness that I could not have imagined being
any happier.
A few weeks after that, once my mother had
found an assistant to help her at the school,
I married Edward Weston, And I am so pleased
that I did.
We have had difficult times and we know that
we will have more, but we deal with them welt
together.
We try to make the most of life and we enjoy
each other's company.
Edward has made some surprising changes in
his parish.
He is a good man and the people there love
and respect him.
Whatever his faults are as a man (and of course,
everybody has their faults) no one could say
that he is not a good vicar, husband or father.
Our children, Edward, Agnes and little Mary,
are doing well.
At the moment they are mostly taught by me
and I try to give them as much love and care
as a mother can.
Edward's salary is more than enough for what
we need.
We try to be careful with the money we have.
In this way, we live a comfortable life and
manage to save a little which we will give
to our children when they leave home.
We even have enough left to give something
to others who might need it.
I am grateful for the life that I have led
so far.
It is not the life of big houses and expensive
parties that other people may have, but I
think of myself as being lucky.
And now I will end my story, because you can
now easily imagine how I might happily spend
the years that I have left to live.
- THE END -