CHAPTER ONE
Finding Fossils
On a cold winter's day in 1811, a boy and
a girl were walking beside the sea in Lyme
Regis, south-west England. They were alone,
and they walked slowly, looking at the stones
under their feet. The sea on their right was
still and grey. On their left, near the land,
there were a lot of large, broken rocks.
The children were looking for something.
The girl, Mary Aiming, was about twelve years
old. Every few minutes, she picked up a stone,
looked at it carefully, and put it in her
bag. Then the boy, her older brother Joseph,
began to climb over the broken rocks. It was
dangerous; both children knew that. There
had been a storm the night before, and some
rocks had fallen into the sea. Another big
rock could fall at any time.
But the morning after a storm was also the
best time to look for fossils - the bones
of animals or parts of plants that had become
hard and changed into rock.
After a few minutes, Joseph called out to
his sister, 'Mary! Quick! Come and look at
this!'
When Mary climbed up to him, he showed her
a line of teeth, half a metre long, in the
broken rock. And behind the teeth, there were
some bones, like the head of a strange animal.
'It's a crocodile, isn't it?' Joseph said.
'We've found a crocodile in the rocks!'
Mary looked carefully at the head of the strange
animal that Joseph had found.
'What's that round thing?' she asked. 'Look,
there, behind the teeth.'
As she cleaned away some sand from the head,
a bony circle stared back at them.
'That must be its eye,' Mary said. 'Look - it's
almost as big as my head!'
Her brother laughed. 'And its mouth is as
big as your body. Be careful, Mary. Look at
those teeth! It's going to eat you!'
'Don't be silly,' Mary said. 'It's dead. It
died hundreds of years ago. Come on, we've
got to find the rest of its body too.'
Some men helped the children to get the bones
of the dead animal out of the rock. It was
about four metres long, with flat, bony hands
and a long tail. It had huge eyes and a long
mouth full of sharp teeth. At first, people
thought it was a crocodile, but it was not.
It was an animal quite different from anything
alive in the world today. In 1818, two scientists
called Henry de la Beche and William Conybeare
gave it the name Ichthyosaurus.
Mary Arming was wrong about one thing. The
ichthyosaur did not die hundreds of years
ago; it died millions of years ago, at a time
which scientists today call the Jurassic period.
But Mary Anning was very clever - she knew
how to find the bones of dead animals. All
her life, she looked for bones and fossils
near her home in Lyme Regis. She found many
more ichthyosaurs, and a different sea animal,
a plesiosaur. The plesiosaur had a round,
flat body, four flat hands, and a very long
neck - several metres long - with a very small
head at the end of it.
She found a strange flying animal too - a
pterosaur. Pterosaurs had long beaks full
of sharp teeth and wings made of skin. Some
of them had wings as big as the wings of a
small plane.
***
At this time, in the early 1800s, people were
very interested in bones and fossils. Lots
of people came to Lyme Regis to see the strange
animals that Mary Anning had found. Among
them were William Buckland and Gideon Mantell.
William Buckland was a clever scientist from
Oxford University. He was very interested
in animals, and he liked to watch them and
learn about them. In fact, he kept a lot of
animals in his house - not just cats and dogs,
but snakes, insects, a lot of birds, and a
real live bear.
Some of Buckland's ideas were very unusual.
He liked to eat animals - but not just the
animals that people usually eat, like cows
and sheep. He wanted to taste every bird,
fish, insect, and animal in the world. So
every time he found a new type of animal,
he cooked and ate it.
Buckland was also interested in rocks and
fossils, and he rode all over England on his
old horse, looking for fossils. He often visited
Mary Aiming in Lyme Regis, and wrote about
the ichthyosaurs and pterosaurs. Then one
day, in the village of Stonesfield near Oxford,
he discovered some fossil bones and teeth.
The bones were enormous, and the teeth were
sharp, like those of a meat-eater. So, in
1824, Buckland wrote about his animal. He
called it Megalosaurus - 'big lizard'.
Gideon Mantell was also very interested in
Mary's work. He was a doctor who lived in
the town of Lewes, in south-east England.
One day, in 1822, his wife met some workmen
who were using rocks to mend the road near
her house. They gave her an interesting rock
that they had found. She showed it to her
husband when he came home. Dr Mantell was
surprised.
'That's not a rock at all,' he said.
'It's a tooth - a fossilized tooth!'
'But look how big it is,' she said. 'What
animal does it come from?'
'I don't know,' Dr Mantell said. 'I don't
know of any animal with teeth as big as this.'
Dr Mantell went back to the place where the
workmen had got the rocks, and found some
huge bones there. He decided that the bones
and the tooth came from the same animal. But
what was the animal like? For three years
he wondered about this. He talked to his wife
and friends, but he did not tell the world
about it. He decided that the tooth was like
the tooth of an iguana, a kind of large lizard
up to two metres long. But the bones came
from an animal much, much bigger - 18 metres
long. At last, in 1825, Dr Mantell wrote about
his animal, and he called it Iguanodon. Later,
he sometimes said that he found the tooth,
and sometimes that his wife did.
Seven years later, in 1832, Dr Mantell found
some bones from a very different animal. This
animal, he said, had a very thick skin. He
called it Hylaeosaurus.
***
Another English scientist, Richard Owen, read
about these strange animals. Owen knew a lot
about bones, and he loved to cut up dead animals,
often in his own home. When Owen spent months
cutting up a dead rhinoceros, his wife was
very unhappy about the terrible smell! In
1842, Owen wrote a book about the animals
that Buckland, Mantell, and other people had
found. He called his book Dinosauria and he
was the first person to use the name dinosaur,
which means 'terrible lizard'. He said that
Megalosaurus, Iguanodon and Hylaeosaurus came
from three different groups of dinosaur, and
scientists still use these three groups today.
Owen was not a very nice man, but he was a
great teacher. He wanted everyone to know
about the dinosaurs, so he had some models
of dinosaurs made for a park in Crystal Palace,
in London. The models were as big as real
dinosaurs, and you can still see them there
today. On 1 January 1853, Owen held a dinner
party for twenty-one scientists, inside the
model of the iguanodon. But Dr Mantell was
not there. He had died the year before.
Scientists all over the world read Owen's
book. Some of the scientists inside the iguanodon
came from Germany and Belgium. They found
dinosaurs in their countries too. And in the
1870s, two Americans, Othniel C. Marsh and
Edward Drinker Cope, began to find dinosaurs
in North America - lots and lots of them.
It was an exciting time in the American West,
but it was a difficult, dangerous place to
work. There was a lot of fighting everywhere,
and the scientists carried guns to defend
themselves. But people were building railways,
and sometimes the railway builders found bones
when they were digging through rocks, so it
was just the right place for dinosaur hunters.
Marsh and Cope were not friends; in fact,
they hated each other. They hid bones from
each other, spied on each other, and sometimes
they stole each other's bones too. They argued
with each other in newspapers and books. Each
man tried to find more dinosaur bones than
the other. The fight between them, which went
on for about twenty years, was called the
'Bone Wars'.
Marsh won the Bone Wars - he discovered eighty
new types of dinosaur, while Cope only discovered
fifty-six. But the Bone Wars made dinosaur
hunting very popular, and by the time Marsh
and Cope died, everyone knew about dinosaurs.
Since then, scientists have found dinosaurs
in South America, Asia, Africa, India, Europe,
and Australia. Some of the most interesting
dinosaurs today are the ones that scientists
are finding in China. People have even found
a few dinosaurs in Antarctica.
In fact, just like people, dinosaurs lived
all over the world.
CHAPTER TWO
Dinosaur Numbers
Everything about dinosaurs is extraordinary.
Many of them were big - much, much bigger
than humans. The biggest of all, Argentinasaurus,
weighed more than fifteen elephants. The tallest
dinosaur, Sauroposeidon, could lift its head
18.5 metres above the ground. That is tall
enough to look in through the sixth-floor
window of a modern building. The longest dinosaur,
Diplodocus, was 35 metres long - longer than
three buses - and its tail was 21 metres long.
The end of that tail could move frighteningly
fast - fast enough to knock a man's head off.
Many dinosaurs were very, very dangerous.
Spinosaurus, for example, was much bigger
than an elephant. It had a mouth like a crocodile,
but much, much bigger. It had a hundred sharp
teeth. An animal like that could probably
kill and eat a human in two or three minutes.
Luckily, however, there were no humans alive
at the time of the dinosaurs. That is because
the dinosaurs lived an enormously long time
ago. It is really hard to understand how long,
but it is important to try.
How long have there been people like us - modern
humans - on Earth? Well, scientists say that
we have been here for about 190,000 years.
But before that, there were early humans - people
who were almost human, but a little bit different
from us. The oldest early human that scientists
have found died 3.2 million years ago.
That is a very long time ago. But it is nothing
to the time that the dinosaurs lived. The
last of the big dinosaurs died 65 million
years ago, so all dinosaur bones are at least
65 million years old. But many of them are
a lot older, of course, because that is when
dinosaurs ended. When did they begin?
The first small dinosaur appeared about 230
million years ago. So dinosaurs lived on Earth
for 165 million years. That is more than fifty
times longer than any kind of humans have
lived on Earth.
There were three time periods - the Triassic,
the Jurassic, and the Cretaceous. The first
dinosaurs appeared during the Triassic period.
A lot more dinosaurs appeared during the Jurassic
period. And even more dinosaurs lived until
the end of the Cretaceous period. Then they
all disappeared, very suddenly.
CHAPTER THREE
The First Dinosaurs
Because the dinosaurs lived for such a long
time, their story is a story of change. Slowly,
over 165 million years, the world changed.
And the dinosaurs changed too.
The first dinosaurs were not very big or frightening.
They looked like small chickens. They ran
around on two legs, but instead of wings they
had hands with five fingers. They had long
tails, small heads, and a mouth with teeth
instead of a bird's beak.
In the time before the dinosaurs, there were
lots of different animals. But about 250 million
years ago, something terrible happened. Thousands
and thousands of volcanoes exploded. This
made the sky very dark, so it was impossible
to see the sun, perhaps for years. Not surprisingly,
95 per cent of all animals and plants died.
Only a few kinds of small animals, which did
not need much food, stayed alive.
Some of these small animals were called archosaurs.
The Earth they lived in was a very different
place. There were plants, but no grass, no
flowers, and no fruit. And all the continents
that we know today - Europe, North America,
South America, Asia, Africa, Antarctica - were
quite different. All the land was just one
large continent, called Pangaea. So these
little archosaurs could walk from one side
of Pangaea to the other.
In the 1960s, an archosaur called Marasuchus
was found in Argentina. It was very small,
just 10 centimetres high. It ran on two legs
and had hands with five fingers. It had a
long tail and a mouth with lots of very small
teeth, and it probably ate insects and little
animals. But it could run very fast. One of
the important things about dinosaurs was that
they had legs under their bodies, like birds.
That helped them to run away from enemies
like crocodiles, which have their legs beside
their bodies. It helped them to grow tall
too.
Another archosaur was Eoraptor, also found
in Argentina. It was a little bigger than
Marasuchus, about 30 centimetres high, like
a small dog, and 1 metre long. It also ran
on two legs and ate insects and small animals,
but it only had three fingers on each hand.
It is one of the earliest dinosaurs of all.
These little archosaurs were not the only
animals that were alive on Pangaea. There
were animals like crocodiles, and there were
also small flying animals, like the pterosaurs
that Mary Aiming found. The pterosaurs had
wings made of skin between their fingers.
They had long tails and beaks with teeth.
They flew all over Pangaea, and sometimes
they killed the little archosaurs, and ate
them.
All the rest of the world was sea - lots and
lots of it. The sea was full of ichthyosaurs
and plesiosaurs. These were in the same family
as the archosaurs, but they had learned to
swim and live in the sea. Some ichthyosaurs
were small, but others were huge, more than
15 metres long. They had long mouths full
of teeth, and huge eyes to see in the dark.
As millions and millions of years passed,
all of these animals evolved in different
ways. The small two-legged archosaurs, like
Marasuchus and Eoraptor, evolved over time
into the first real dinosaurs. Scientists
make a picture, like a family tree, to show
this. In the picture, the oldest animals - the
archosaurs - are at the bottom, and the most
recent dinosaurs are at the top.
Richard Owen, in 1842, said that there were
three main types of dinosaur: meat-eating
dinosaurs, and two types of plant-eating dinosaurs.
Scientists today agree with him. The meat-eating
dinosaurs are called theropods. The plant-eating
dinosaurs with long necks and tails are called
sauropods, and the ones with extraordinary
thick skins are called ornithiscians.
One of the first theropods was Coelophysis.
It ran on two legs, like Marasuchus and Eoraptor.
But Coelophysis was much bigger, about 1 metre
high and 2 or 3 metres long. It had three
strong claws on its hands, and a long tail
and long mouth like a crocodile. It could
probably stand up on its back legs, as tall
as a man. But it was not heavy, because its
bones were full of air, like the bones of
a bird. It was as long as a small car, but
it weighed the same as a seven-year-old child.
So it could run very fast, and hunt smaller
animals for food.
The first coelophysis was found by an American
scientist called David Baldwin in New Mexico
in 1881. Baldwin often spent months looking
for fossils all alone, in the middle of winter,
with only his horse beside him. He sent the
bones of the coelophysis to Edward Drinker
Cope during the Bone Wars. Sixty years later,
in 1947, lots more coelophysis were found
at a place called Ghost Ranch, in New Mexico.
It is New Mexico's most famous dinosaur.
A very early sauropod was Thecodontosaurus,
found near Bristol in England in 1836. It
was only the fourth dinosaur ever discovered.
It was not very tall, but up to 2.5 metres
long. It probably walked on two legs, and
used its four- clawed hands to help it eat
plants and small insects.
A much bigger Triassic sauropod was Plateosaurus.
Plateosaurus was up to 10 metres long and
weighed 700 kilograms. It was 3 metres high
when it stood on its back legs. This plant-eating
dinosaur probably walked on two legs and used
the claws on its hands to hold the branches
of trees while it ate. The first plateosaur
was found in Bavaria in Germany in 1837. It
was the first dinosaur found outside England,
and the fifth dinosaur to be given a name.
Since then, fifty more plateosaurs have been
found, in France, Germany, Norway, Switzerland,
and Greenland.
An even bigger early sauropod was Riojasaurus,
found in Argentina. It was up to 2.75 metres
high, 11 metres long, and weighed up to 3
tonnes. It needed to eat a lot of plants every
day in order to stay alive. And by the end
of the Triassic, there were a lot more plants
for these dinosaurs to eat.
By the end of the Triassic, the little two-legged
archosaurs had evolved into two main types
of dinosaurs: the plant-eating sauropods like
Plateosaurus, and the meat-eating theropods
like Coelophysis. The third type of dinosaur,
the ornithiscians, came later.
But slowly, over millions of years, the Earth
continued to change. And as the Earth changed,
the dinosaurs changed too. They grew bigger,
and stronger - and much, much stranger.
CHAPTER FOUR
Bigger and Stronger
As the Triassic period changed into the Jurassic
period, the Earth got warmer. And as the Earth
got warmer, the dinosaurs got bigger. There
was more water in the air, and this helped
plants to grow. As the plants grew bigger,
there was more food for the animals to eat.
So the plant-eating dinosaurs grew bigger
and bigger.
The largest Jurassic dinosaurs were the sauropods
- the big plant-eaters. They had very big,
heavy bodies with long necks and tails. Because
their bodies were so heavy, they walked on
all four feet. They used their long necks
to eat leaves from tall trees, and they used
their long, strong tails to defend themselves.
They had small heads with very small brains
- often about 100 grams, or as big as an orange.
One of the earliest Jurassic sauropods is
Barapasaurus, which was found in India. It
was 18 metres long, and weighed up to 55 tonnes.
But that was only the beginning. In the middle
and later Jurassic periods, the sauropod dinosaurs
began to grow very big indeed.
By the mid-Jurassic, some sauropods could
reach leaves that were 10 metres from the
ground. The bones in these dinosaurs' necks
were hollow in places, so they were not as
heavy as other bones. That made it easier
to lift these very long necks.
The sauropods' hands still had fingers, which
they could use to hold trees and plants, but
they mostly walked on four legs. They could
not run, because they were too heavy. In some
ways, they were like elephants - they probably
moved slowly, and they lived in large family
groups or herds.
Most big sauropods had at least 100 teeth;
some had 600! But even for an animal with
so many teeth, some plants were probably hard
to eat. Scientists have found stones in sauropod
stomachs; they think that the dinosaurs ate
the stones, which then helped to break up
the leaves that they ate.
Two of the largest sauropods were Diplodocus
and Apatosaurus. These were found in America
in the 1870s by Cope and Marsh. They had small
heads, heavy bodies, and big stomachs. They
ate a lot of food, and grew very quickly:
a young apatosaur probably grew 15 kilograms
heavier every day! All these animals had very
long, strong tails which they used to defend
themselves. Shunosaurus, a dinosaur from China,
actually had sharp bony spikes on the end
of its tail, to hit its enemies with.
Another big Jurassic dinosaur was Brachiosaurus,
found in the USA and Africa. An adult brachiosaur
weighed up to 50 tonnes and was 26 metres
long. Unlike most dinosaurs, its front legs
were longer than its back legs. This meant
that it could lift its huge head, on its long
neck, about 16 metres above the ground. On
top of its head, between its eyes, Brachiosaurus
had a big, hollow nose, full of air. Scientists
think that it used this nose to make loud
noises, perhaps to sing to its friends and
frighten its enemies.
Then there was Mamenchisaurus, another enormous
Jurassic dinosaur from China. This huge dinosaur
was 25 metres long. Its neck was 12 metres
long - one of the longest necks of any animal
ever discovered.
But why were these dinosaurs so big? Well,
one reason is that the world was getting warmer
and wetter, so there was more plant food for
them to eat. But there was another important
reason - safety. It is easier for big animals
to defend themselves against their enemies.
And these big Jurassic sauropods had a lot
of very big, dangerous enemies.
One of their most dangerous enemies was Allosaurus.
Allosaurus was a big theropod - a meat-eating
dinosaur. It was about 5 metres high - much
taller than a man - and 12 metres long. It
weighed 2 tonnes or more. It ran on two legs
and had three-fingered hands with long, sharp
claws. It had small horns over its eyes, and
a mouth full of sharp teeth like kitchen knives.
It used these terrible claws and teeth to
kill and eat its food. And its favourite food
was big sauropods like Apatosaurus, Diplodocus
and Brachiosaurus.
But how did it kill these enormous animals?
Allosaurus was big, but Apatosaurus was much
bigger - it was one of the biggest animals
on Earth. It was 20 to 25 metres long and
weighed up to 28 tonnes - more than a family
of elephants! And with its long, strong tail,
it could kill a small dinosaur in a second.
Sometimes, perhaps, a brave, hungry allosaur
jumped onto the back of an adult apatosaur,
and tried to kill it with its terrible teeth
and claws. But that was very difficult and
dangerous, so perhaps they did it a different
way. Some scientists think that allosaurs
hunted in family groups. So, perhaps four
or five terrible meat-eaters all jumped onto
the back of one apatosaur together. That was
probably easier, and there was plenty of meat
for all of them when they killed it.
And like lions today, they probably did not
try to kill the biggest and strongest apatosaur.
They looked for an animal that was old, or
ill, and killed that. And sometimes they found
an animal that was already dead.
But Allosaurus was a very good killer. Scientists
are sure about that. The dinosaur scientist
Thomas Holtz says that dinosaurs like Allosaurus
changed very little over 100 million years.
That means, of course, that they were very
successful at what they did. And what they
did was hunt, kill, and eat sauropods.
Another terrible Jurassic meat-eater was Ceratosaurus.
This dinosaur was smaller than Allosaurus,
but it was still taller than a man. It was
6 to 8 metres long, and heavier than two horses.
Ceratosaurus also ran on two legs. It had
long, sharp claws on its four-fingered hands,
and a mouth full of very sharp teeth. It had
three small horns on its head and an unusually
strong tail. But unlike Allosaurus, it did
not always hunt big sauropods. The scientist
Robert Bakker has found lots of Ceratosaurus
teeth near the bones of fish and small crocodiles.
He thinks that Ceratosaurus used its big,
strong tail to swim, and hunted for its food
in the water.
During the Jurassic period, the continent
of Pangaea began to break into two continents,
Laurasia and Gondwana. The Atlantic Ocean
appeared - at first, it was about fifty kilometres
wide. Much of modern Europe was under water
then. So there were lots of fish for Ceratosaurus
to eat in Jurassic seas, lakes and rivers.
But there were lots of other animals there
too.
In the Jurassic seas, the ichthyosaurs grew
even bigger and stronger. They were hunters,
with enormous eyes and long mouths full of
sharp teeth - and they could swim very, very
fast, probably at 30 to 50 kilometres per
hour.
There were plesiosaurs in the sea too. Plesiosaurs
did not look like fish: they had round, flat
bodies, with four huge, flat hands that they
used to push themselves through the water.
They had short tails but very long necks,
sometimes over 10 metres long. Some had very
small heads, but others had huge heads, 3
metres long, bigger than any other dinosaur
head.
In the Jurassic skies, a new type of pterosaur
appeared - the pterodactyl. Pterodactyls had
longer necks than Triassic pterosaurs, and
they had bigger brains too. Most of them had
long mouths full of sharp teeth, and many
of them ate fish. Most pterodactyls were as
big as large birds today, but a few were much,
much bigger. In fact, the largest pterodactyl
of all - Quetzalcoatlus - had wings 12 metres
wide: bigger than a small plane.
But Quetzalcoatlus lived in the Cretaceous
period, which came after the Jurassic. It
was in the Cretaceous that dinosaurs grew
really big.
CHAPTER FIVE
Big, Bad, and Dangerous
During the Cretaceous period, Pangaea, which
was once a single continent, continued to
break into smaller parts. The Earth began
to look more like the world today: several
different continents, with large seas between
them. This meant that, as time passed, different
dinosaurs evolved in each continent. The dinosaurs
of China, for example, were different from
those of South America.
But in every continent there were large, plant-eating
sauropods. They grew even larger because the
Cretaceous world was warmer and wetter than
before, so plants grew bigger and stronger.
And for the first time, some plants had fruit
and flowers. So there was a lot more food
for the big dinosaurs to eat.
The biggest dinosaur of all was probably Argentinosaurus.
This enormous animal was between 33 and 41
metres long, 6 to 7 metres high, and weighed
between 75 and 90 tonnes. That is more than
several families of African elephants. To
keep its huge body alive, one argentinosaur
probably needed to eat two or three large
trees every day. There were probably thousands
of these enormous animals in South America,
so just think about the number of trees that
were eaten every day!
It is hard to understand how any enemy could
kill Argentinosaurus. It was just too big.
Most meat-eaters probably just waited for
it to die, and ate it then. But there were
plenty of large, meat-eating dinosaurs in
the Cretaceous. Perhaps from time to time
some of them did try to kill a baby argentinosaur,
or a sick or old animal. If they tried to
kill a healthy adult they probably got hurt
or killed.
***
Not all of the terrible killers in the Cretaceous
were big. In 1964, John Ostrom, a scientist
from Yale University in America, discovered
Deinonychus. This animal was too small to
kill Argentinasaurus, but it was still very
dangerous. It was about 3 metres long, as
tall as a man, and probably covered in feathers
like a bird. It had a big brain, and a mouth
as long as a man's leg, full of sharp teeth.
Its hands had three fingers with long, sharp
claws, and on the second toe of its back feet
there was another big, dangerous claw.
Deinonychus weighed about 80 to 100 kilograms,
and it could run very fast. Scientists think
that Deinonychus hunted in groups, like lions
today. When they found a large, plant-eating
dinosaur, five, ten, or even twenty deinonychus
jumped onto it, all together. They bit it
with their sharp teeth, and cut it with their
terrible sharp claws, until it died. Then
they ate it.
Deinonychus was very frightening, but Utahraptor
was even more dangerous. It had terrible teeth
and claws like Deinonychus, but it was much
bigger. It was 6 to 7 metres long, taller
than the tallest horse, and it weighed up
to 1.1 tonnes. It had a big brain too, so
it was probably very clever. And just like
Deinonychus, these dinosaurs hunted together
in groups. For plant-eating dinosaurs, this
was like a really bad dream. They could look
up, and see not one, but five or ten terrible
killers running towards them, very fast. It
was usually the last thing they ever saw.
However, Utahraptor was not the biggest killer.
In 1983, an Englishman called William Walker
discovered an enormous fossil in Surrey, near
London. He called it Baryonyx, which means
'heavy claw'. This dinosaur was much bigger,
and so a lot slower, than Utahraptor. It weighed
up to 5.4 tonnes, it was 13 metres long, and
2.5 metres high. It had strong, sharp claws
on its three-fingered hands, and a long mouth
like a crocodile.
We know that Baryonyx ate meat, because inside
its stomach scientists found the bones of
an iguanodon, and a lot of fish bones too.
Baryonyx probably lived near water, and used
its big, sharp claws and its long crocodile
mouth to catch fish, like some North American
bears today.
An even bigger meat-eater than Baryonyx was
Spinosaurus, which was found in Africa by
Ernst Stromer, a German scientist. Spinosaurus
looked like Baryonyx, but it was much, much
bigger. It had a long crocodile mouth, sharp
claws on three-fingered hands, and a huge
sail on its back. It weighed 8 to 13 tonnes,
as much as the biggest African elephant. It
was 14 to 18 metres long and 3 metres tall.
A spinosaur head that was discovered recently
was 2 metres long - longer than a tall man.
All these dinosaurs were terrible. But the
most famous and terrible of all the meat-eating
theropods is Tyrannosaurus rex. This animal
was also enormous. It weighed 6 to 7 tonnes
and it was over 4 metres tall - taller than
Spinosaurus. Unlike most dinosaurs, it had
very small arms and hands, so it probably
used its mouth to kill and eat things. But
this was no ordinary mouth - it had over 50
teeth, some as big as a large banana. And
its jaws were extraordinarily strong - much
stronger than the jaws of a lion or a bear.
So just how strong were those jaws? What is
there in the modern world that is like them?
Recently, scientists measured the 'bite' of
a modern machine which picks up old cars and
breaks them into small pieces. Then they measured
the bite of the jaws of a tyrannosaur - and
it was 50 per cent stronger than the machine.
So a tyrannosaur could easily bite right through
a car - in a world with both tyrannosaurs
and cars, of course!
Because they were so big, tyrannosaurs could
probably not run very fast. So some scientists
think that they did not hunt like Deinonychus;
they just found dead animals and ate them.
But other scientists disagree. They say that
really big sauropods, like Diplodocus and
Argentinosaurus, could not run fast either.
And scientists have found damage from tyrannosaur
teeth on the bones of two dinosaurs which
escaped. This shows that tyrannosaurs tried
to kill living dinosaurs.
Tyrannosaurus was a North American dinosaur:
in Hell Creek, Montana, scientists have found
fossils from more than fifty tyrannosaurs.
But in China and Mongolia, they have discovered
fossils of Tarbosaurus, a dinosaur in the
same family as Tyrannosaurus. Tarbosaurus
also had small hands, and big jaws full of
sharp teeth. It had a large brain, and it
could smell and hear well, which helped it
to hunt. Perhaps it also had feathers around
its neck.
Velociraptor is a much smaller theropod from
China and Mongolia. The first velociraptor
was found in the Gobi Desert in 1922, by an
American called Roy Chapman Andrews. It was
a small dinosaur, 2 metres long and about
60 centimetres tall, and it was covered in
feathers. Velociraptor did not weigh much
- 15 to 18 kilograms, which is less than a
large dog. But unlike a dog, it ran on two
legs, and had hands with three sharp claws.
And like Deinonychus, it had another very
long, sharp claw on each foot. Velociraptor
probably ran very fast and hunted in groups,
like Deinonychus and Utahraptor. Like them,
it was a very frightening killer.
But even the most terrible killer can get
things wrong sometimes. In the Gobi Desert
in 1971, scientists discovered two extraordinary
fossils. One was a velociraptor, the other
was a plant-eating dinosaur called protoceratops.
The two dinosaurs had died when they were
trying to kill each other. The protoceratops
had the velociraptor's right arm in its jaws.
It was trying to bite its arm off. The velociraptor
had its claws in the head and neck of the
protoceratops. It was trying to cut the protoceratops's
neck open.
This terrible fight happened beside a hill
of sand. As the two dinosaurs were fighting,
the hill fell on top of them. So they both
died. And there they stayed, for millions
of years, under the sand, until one day the
scientists found them.
But what about Protoceratops? What type of
dinosaur was that?
CHAPTER SIX
Strangest of All
Protoceratops is one of the third type of
dinosaurs: the ornithiscians. The ornithiscians
are the strangest of all dinosaurs. They were
plant eaters, but many of them had horns,
and they defended themselves with their very
thick, strong skin.
There were very few ornithiscians in the Triassic
period. They began to appear in the Jurassic,
and there were lots of them in the Cretaceous.
Protoceratops was a very successful small
dinosaur. Its mouth was like a bird's beak
and had a very strong bite. And behind its
head, Protoceratops had a large frill of skin.
This frill was probably brightly coloured,
and the dinosaur used it to frighten its enemies
and attract females.
Triceratops was like Protoceratops, but much
bigger. In fact, Triceratops was huge: it
was 8 metres long, and weighed 11 tonnes,
much more than the largest African elephant.
Like Protoceratops, it had a mouth like a
bird's beak, and a large frill of skin and
bone behind its head. Its head was enormous,
and it had three large horns. Triceratops
used these horns to defend itself against
its enemies. We know that this happened because
some Triceratops horns have damage from Tyrannosaurus
teeth on them.
The ornithiscians had many ways to defend
themselves against enemies like Tyrannosaurus.
Huayangosaurus, found in China in 1982, had
lots of sharp spikes all along its back. There
were bony spikes on its shoulders too, and
on the end of its tail. Stegosaurus, from
North America, was much the same. These dinosaurs
used their strong, bony tails to hit their
enemies. Several meat-eaters, like Allosaurus,
have been found with holes in their bones
made by the spikes on the tail of a Stegosaurus.
Animals like these from the late Jurassic
have been found in Europe and Africa. All
of them were huge, as big as a modern rhinoceros.
Ankylosaurus lived in the late Cretaceous.
It had a really thick skin, with spikes all
over its back, head and sides. It had a very
strong tail with a heavy club at the end,
which was excellent for fighting enemies.
Ankylosaurus was up to 9 metres long, and
weighed up to 8 tonnes - much more than an
elephant. So when that tail hit something,
it hurt.
Tenontosaurus was another big, plant-eating
animal, but it was not as strong or dangerous
as Ankylosaurus. It lived in large herds in
North America; in fact, some scientists call
it 'the cow of the Cretaceous', because there
were so many of them. Tenontosaurus was an
everyday food for meat- eating hunters like
Deinonychus.
Iguanodon was an ornithiscian too. It lived
in large family groups or herds, like cows
or sheep today; in Belgium, the fossils of
forty of them were found in the same place.
Iguanodon had a long face like a horse, with
a mouth like a beak for eating plants. It
could eat plants well, moving both jaws at
once (we humans only move the bottom jaw).
Iguanodon sometimes walked on two legs, and
sometimes on four. Each hand had a sharp spike,
like a thumb, which it used to fight its enemies,
and it could also pick things up with the
help of its little finger. It was as big as
a large African elephant.
Hadrosaurs were in the same family as Iguanodon,
but they were even stranger. These plant-eating
dinosaurs had flat, wide beaks with teeth
inside them - lots of them. In fact, some
hadrosaurs had up to 720 teeth (humans only
have 28). New teeth were growing all the time
to take the place of any teeth that fell out.
Hadrosaurs had long faces like horses too,
and they lived in large herds all over North
America. The smallest was as big as a horse,
but many were bigger than elephants. One of
the strangest hadrosaurs was Lambeosaurus.
It was 3 or 4 metres high, and weighed up
to 8 tonnes. On its head was a large bone,
like an enormous hat. The 'hat' was as big
as a man.
The male Parasaurolophus had an even bigger
'hat' on the back of its head. This 'hat'
was really a long, hollow bone, about 1 metre
long, joined to its nose. At first, scientists
could not understand this. What was it for?
Then they found a possible explanation. When
they blew air through this long, hollow bone,
it made loud musical sounds.
Was Parasaurolophus a musical dinosaur? It
is quite possible. The males could make wonderful
sounds with these long, hollow bones on their
heads. Perhaps they did this to attract the
females, or to call to their children. They
probably did it when they saw an enemy. And
maybe sometimes they did it just for fun,
because they liked singing to each other.
But the hadrosaurs were interesting for another
reason - their family life.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Family Life
In 1923, the American scientist Roy Chapman
Andrews discovered something very strange.
In the Gobi Desert, in Mongolia, he found
the bones of a new dinosaur. It was about
2 metres long, with a strong beak, no teeth,
and a thin 'hat' on top of its head. And it
was probably covered with feathers, like a
very big chicken.
Underneath this dinosaur there was a nest
full of eggs. This was the first time anyone
had found dinosaur eggs. At first, Roy Chapman
Andrews thought that the eggs belonged to
a different dinosaur, Protoceratops. The new
dinosaur, he thought, was trying to steal
them when it died. So he called his new dinosaur
Oviraptor, which means 'egg stealer.'
But later, in the 1990s, another oviraptor
was found on a nest of eggs. Scientists looked
at these eggs very carefully, and decided
that the eggs did not belong to Protoceratops
after all - they belonged to Oviraptor. The
female oviraptor was sitting on her own eggs
when she died. She was keeping them warm with
her body, like a bird.
This was a surprise. At this time, nobody
thought that dinosaurs could be good parents.
Most scientists thought that dinosaurs just
laid their eggs on the ground, and walked
away. But the oviraptor was taking care of
her eggs like a good mother.
Most dinosaurs could not do this. They were
much too heavy to sit on their eggs. In Montana,
scientists found hundreds of dinosaur nests,
but the eggs in the nests came from a type
of hadrosaur that weighed 3 tonnes. Were these
mothers interested in their babies? Probably
not, the scientists thought. They probably
just laid their eggs, and forgot all about
them.
But there was a problem. They found a lot
of baby dinosaurs in the nests beside the
eggs. These baby dinosaurs were very small,
no bigger than a chicken. They could not walk
far, because their bones were not strong enough.
But their teeth showed that they had eaten
plants. How did the baby dinosaurs find these
plants, when they were too young to walk?
The scientists thought hard about this. The
baby dinosaurs did not find the plants, they
decided. That was impossible; they could not
walk. So it must be the parents who found
the plants. They brought them to their nests,
for their children to eat. These dinosaurs
were looking after their children, like good
parents. So the scientists called this new
dinosaur Maiasaura, which means 'good mother
lizard'.
Maiasaurs laid twenty or thirty eggs in each
nest. Then they covered the eggs with dead
plants, to keep them warm. When the babies
came out of the eggs, they weighed about 1
kilogram, but they grew very quickly. Ten
years later, they were adults, weighing 3
tonnes. This shows they were warm-blooded,
because cold-blooded animals cannot grow that
fast.
When they could walk, baby maiasaurs followed
their parents around, looking for food. Maiasaurs
were very successful: in one fossil site,
there are over 10,000 animals. They lived
in huge herds, like many animals in Africa
today. And all around them, like lions in
Africa, were the hunters - tyrannosaurs, deinonychus,
utahraptors. When the baby maiasaurs saw them,
perhaps they ran under their parents' legs,
to stay safe.
Tyrannosaurs probably fed their babies too
- but with meat, not plants. As the young
tyrannosaurs grew, they probably hunted together
in groups. Young tyrannosaurs had long legs,
but they were not heavy, so they could probably
run much faster than their parents. Perhaps
the adults and children hunted together, the
young tyrannosaurs chasing an animal towards
their enormous parent. Or perhaps the young
hunted the smaller animals, and their parents
hunted the big, slow-moving ones. Tyrannosaurs
did not always kill their food, of course.
Sometimes they just found it lying on the
ground. And a dead dinosaur was a free meal
for all the tyrannosaur family.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Birds
In 1861, a small fossil was found in Germany.
It was very small - no bigger than a chicken.
Its bones looked like those of Compsognathus,
a small theropod dinosaur which was found
in the same place ten years earlier. But this
new fossil's arms and legs were covered with
feathers. Scientists called it Archaeopteryx.
When the English scientist T. H. Huxley looked
at Archaeopteryx, he noticed something else.
Its bones were hollow, just like the bones
of birds. There was a lot of air in them,
so they did not weigh very much. Archaeopteryx,
like Compsognathus and most theropods, ran
on two legs. And because Archaeopteryx had
feathered wings, it could probably fly. This
gave Huxley an idea: perhaps birds evolved
from theropods.
For the next hundred years, scientists argued
about this. It is a crazy idea, some people
said: how can a dinosaur like Tyrannosaurus
be in the same family as the birds we see
in our gardens?
But then, in 1964, the American scientist
John Ostrom discovered Deinonychus in Montana,
USA. Deinonychus was a theropod, like Tyrannosaurus,
but its bones were like those of birds. It
could move its wrists and arms in the way
a bird does, and its bones were hollow. Tyrannosaurus
also had some hollow bones, and so did the
big sauropods like Diplodocus - that is why
its enormously long neck and tail are not
as heavy as they look. So Ostrom decided that
Huxley's idea was right.
In 1996, scientists in China made another
extraordinary discovery - a small dinosaur
called Sinosauropteryx. It was very like Compsognathus,
but there was an important difference: Sinosauropteryx
had feathers all over its body. The sand where
it had died was very fine and soft, so scientists
could see that it had had feathers. Sinosauropteryx
was a theropod, like Tyrannosaurus, but it
was covered in feathers like a bird.
No other animals have feathers - only dinosaurs
and birds.
In the next few years, Chinese scientists
discovered many more feathered dinosaurs.
The one most like a bird was Microraptor,
which had a long tail, a beak with small teeth,
and claws on its hands and feet. It was smaller
than Archaeopteryx, but it also had long feathers
on its arms and legs. So perhaps it flew with
four wings, not two.
Other Chinese dinosaurs, like Oviraptor, had
feathers but could not fly. So which came
first - feathers or flying?
Today, scientists think that many dinosaurs
had feathers. The feathers kept the dinosaurs
warm. They also helped dinosaur mothers, like
Oviraptor, to keep their eggs warm in their
nests. So the feathers probably came first.
Much later, some small feathered dinosaurs,
like Microraptor and Archaeopteryx, probably
learned how to climb into trees. They used
their claws and beaks to help them climb.
They slept in the trees at night, safe from
their enemies. In the morning, they came down
from the trees. As they came down, they sometimes
opened their wings and jumped. This helped
them to fall down more slowly.
Over millions of years, they learned to do
this better. Sometimes, when they jumped from
trees, they were able to catch small animals
by surprise. Those with the best wings and
feathers caught more food, so they lived longer,
and had more children. Some of their children
were born with better wings and better feathers.
And one day, they learned to fly.
Even dinosaurs which could not fly, like Oviraptor,
were like birds in other ways. They laid eggs
in nests, and sat on the eggs to keep them
warm. And dinosaurs like Maiasaura brought
food to their babies in the nests, like birds.
Even Tyrannosaurus probably had feathers around
its neck, and hollow bones with air in them.
Tyrannosaurus, in fact, was not very different
from an enormous, terrible chicken!
Dinosaur scientists are very sure about this.
Thomas Holtz says it clearly: 'Birds are dinosaurs.'
CHAPTER NINE
A Sudden End
Birds, of course, are still with us. But all
the other dinosaurs disappeared, 65 million
years ago. Why? What happened?
Scientists wondered about this for a long
time. Dinosaurs, after all, were very successful
animals indeed. They had lived on Earth for
165 million years, and they were the biggest,
strongest, and most successful animals of
all time. In the late Jurassic and Cretaceous
periods, there were dinosaurs all over the
Earth. They lived on every continent - even
in Antarctica, which was much warmer at that
time than it is today. And then, 65 million
years ago, they all disappeared, very suddenly.
There are no dinosaur fossils anywhere on
Earth from after that time. Something terrible
must have happened to them. But what was it?
In the 1970s, a scientist called Walter Alvarez
tried to answer this question. He looked at
the rocks from the Cretaceous, and the time
after that - the Tertiary. There were hundreds
of dinosaur fossils in the Cretaceous, and
none in the Tertiary. But in between the Cretaceous
and the Tertiary, he found a thin line of
clay, a kind of soft, wet rock.
He found this line of clay all over the world,
and everywhere it was the same. In it, he
found a silver-white metal called iridium.
Iridium is very unusual on Earth, but there
is a lot of it in meteors - the rocks that
sometimes fall onto the Earth from the sky.
So the iridium came from a meteor, Walter
Alvarez said - a meteor that hit the Earth
65 million years ago.
We know it was a big meteor, Alvarez said,
because there is so much iridium everywhere.
He thought that the meteor was a rock between
10 and 15 kilometres across, which hit the
Earth with an enormous BANG! It made a crater
- a very big hole in the ground - that was
160 kilometres across. A huge ball of fire
destroyed anything near the crater, and the
ground shook violently. In the sky, dark clouds
hid the sun for months, perhaps years.
Without sunlight, almost all the plants on
Earth died. The big plant-eating dinosaurs
- like Argentinosaurus - soon died, because
they had nothing to eat. The meat-eating dinosaurs,
like Tyrannosaurus, lived a little longer,
because there were lots of dead plant-eaters
to eat. But then the meat went bad, and there
was nothing left to kill. So they died too.
Well, it is an interesting idea, people said,
but where is this crater? A hole in the Earth,
160 kilometres across - that cannot be difficult
to find. Why has nobody seen it?
Walter Alvarez looked for this big crater,
and with the help of a scientist called Glen
Penfield he found it. There was a reason why
nobody had seen it before: it was under the
ground, in the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico.
In the past 65 million years, the rocks had
moved and covered it up, but it was still
there. It measured 180 kilometres from one
side to the other, which was even bigger than
he had expected. He called it the Chicxulub
crater.
So scientists think the Age of the Dinosaurs
ended like this. One day, 65 million years
ago, the world was full of dinosaurs. It began
like any other day. Huge herds of dinosaurs
were walking slowly across Mexico. Oviraptors
were sitting on their nests, and maiasaurs
were finding food for their babies. Small
feathered dinosaurs were flying from trees.
Huge stegosaurs were walking slowly through
the forest, and argentinosaurs were eating
the tops of trees. Tyrannosaurs were watching
the plant-eaters carefully, hoping for a meal.
And dinosaurs from the parasaurolophus family,
with their strange, hollow heads, were singing
to their friends far away.
The plant-eaters kept their eyes open, as
they did every day. They were looking for
danger - for tyrannosaurs and utahraptors,
the enemies that wanted to kill them.
But none of them looked up into the sky, where
the real danger was.
Then, suddenly, in a few seconds, it happened.
A bright light filled the sky, and there was
an enormous BANG! - louder than anything they
had ever heard. A great wind knocked all the
trees flat, and a few seconds later, everything
in the forest was on fire.
All the dinosaurs nearest to the meteor were
burned in a few minutes. There was nothing
left of them, nothing at all. Those more than
50 kilometres away died more slowly. But all
of them, all over the world, began to die.
In a few seconds, 165 million years had ended.
Not everything died, of course. Some small
animals, like insects, snakes, and small birds,
lived. Because they were not very big, they
did not need much food. One of these small
animals looked a bit like a mouse. It was
a warm-blooded animal, covered in soft hair,
and it probably lived in holes in the ground.
Dinosaurs ate lots of them every day - but
now, suddenly, the dinosaurs were gone. So
now this animal could come out of its holes,
and feel a little bit safer.
This small, unimportant animal was an early
mammal. Over the next 64.5 million years,
it slowly evolved into many different types
of mammals - elephants, lions, bears, horses,
sheep, and humans.
And today there are mammals all over the Earth,
just as, once upon a time, there were dinosaurs.
CHAPTER TEN
Studying Dinosaurs
But how do we know all this? There were no
humans alive when the dinosaurs lived, and
we cannot travel back in time to watch them.
So how do we know?
We can learn a lot about dinosaurs from fossils.
There are two types of dinosaur fossils: body
fossils, and trace fossils.
Body fossils are what is left of the real
bones from dinosaur bodies. Over time they
have changed and become hard, like rock. Sometimes
scientists are lucky, and find all the bones
of a single dinosaur in one place, but that
is very unusual. Usually, they just find a
few bones, and the other parts of the body
have disappeared. This may be because when
the dinosaur died, some other animals ate
it, and carried away the bones. Sometimes
water has washed some of the bones away, or
the rocks that contained the fossils have
broken into smaller pieces.
But even from one fossil, we can learn a lot.
Dr Mantell learned a lot from the single iguanodon
tooth he found in 1822.
It was very big, so it came from a very big
animal. It was not a very sharp tooth, so
he knew the animal ate plants, not meat. And
it looked different from the teeth of almost
every animal alive today. The only living
animal with teeth like that was the big lizard
called an iguana. So Dr Mantell called it
Iguanodon. Later, when he found some more
bones, he learned more about its legs, arms,
and head.
In the same way, when William Buckland found
Megalosaurus, he knew that it was a meat-eater,
because of its sharp teeth.
Trace fossils are things like dinosaur footprints,
eggs, and dung. Dinosaur footprints can tell
us how it walked. Did it walk on two feet
or four? How fast could it run? The footprints
of one theropod from Texas show that it was
running at 39 kilometres per hour, faster
than a horse!
The eggs and nests tell us about dinosaur
babies and family life. And dinosaur dung?
Yes, scientists look at this carefully too.
When they find bits of plants or animals in
it, they know what the dinosaur was eating.
(The dung is millions of years old, and has
become hard like rock, so it does not smell
bad.)
Today, scientists use computers to make pictures
of dinosaur bones, to see how they worked.
They can watch the dinosaurs moving on the
computer.
How do we know that meat-eaters like Tyrannosaurus
rex killed other dinosaurs? The scientist
Robert Bakker answers that. He calls himself
a murder detective. Dinosaur scientists, he
says, 'dig up murder victims from 144 million
years ago. Then we figure out who killed them.'
How does he do that? He looks for 'bullets'
and 'bullet wounds'. The 'bullets' are dinosaur
teeth. Meat-eating dinosaurs often lost one
or two teeth when they killed, or were eating,
other dinosaurs. They grew new ones later.
So when Bakker finds teeth near a dead diplodocus,
it is like finding a bullet near a dead man.
If he finds allosaur teeth, he knows that
an allosaur was the killer.
And when he finds tooth damage on bones, the
damage is like 'bullet wounds'. It also gives
him information about the killer.
Were dinosaurs cold-blooded, like lizards
and fish, or warm-blooded, like mammals? Cold-blooded
animals do not need much food, and move slowly
when it is cold. Warm-blooded animals need
much more food, and move quickly, even in
cold weather.
Lizards are cold-blooded, and until the 1970s
scientists thought that dinosaurs were big
lizards. But today, most scientists think
that dinosaurs were warm-blooded. John Ostrom
thinks Deinonychus was warm-blooded, because
it could move so quickly. And some dinosaurs
lived in Antarctica, which was not always
warm even in the Cretaceous. We know that
dinosaurs grew very quickly too, and cold-blooded
animals do not do that. So most dinosaurs
were probably warm-blooded, like us.
But there are plenty of things we do not know.
What type of noise did Parasaurolophus make?
Did it really sing? Lots of dinosaurs probably
made noises, but nobody has ever heard them.
And what colour were dinosaurs? Again, nobody
knows, because colour does not stay in fossils.
But dinosaurs were probably colourful, like
birds and animals today. Think of the large
frills on the heads of Protoceratops and Triceratops,
or the 'hat' on Lambeosaurus. They were probably
there to frighten enemies, and to attract
females. And a brightly coloured frill is
much easier to see.
Lots of birds today are brightly coloured.
And many dinosaurs, like birds, had feathers.
So lots of dinosaurs were probably covered
with beautiful feathers, just like birds.
But what colour were they?
Nobody knows.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Dinosaurs Today
In 1896, the rich Scottish-American businessman
Andrew Carnegie built a Museum of Natural
History in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Carnegie
wanted the biggest dinosaur in the world for
his museum, so he asked his scientists to
find one. At Sheep Creek, near the Freezeout
Mountains in Wyoming, they found what they
wanted - an enormous diplodocus. At that time,
it was the biggest dinosaur in the world.
They called it Diplodocus carnegii, giving
it Carnegie's name. Carnegie was very happy.
But he had a problem: his museum was not big
enough. So he had to build a huge, new room,
just to keep his diplodocus in.
When King Edward the Seventh of England visited
Carnegie at his castle in Scotland, he saw
a picture of Carnegie's diplodocus.
'I say, Carnegie, what in the world is this?'
the king asked.
Carnegie smiled and told him that it was the
biggest animal that ever lived - and that
it had Carnegie's name.
'Oh! I say, Carnegie,' the king said. 'We
must have one of these in the British Museum.'
Carnegie loved to be important, so in 1905,
he sent a model of his diplodocus to the Natural
History Museum in London. Later, he sent models
to museums in Berlin, Paris, Vienna, Bologna,
St Petersburg, Buenos Aires, Madrid, Mexico
City, and Munich.
Carnegie's diplodocus is one of the most popular
dinosaurs in the world. Millions of people
see it every year, all over the world. In
London, the diplodocus is called 'Dippy.'
Children sometimes spend the night in the
Natural History Museum, sleeping under Dippy
and learning about other dinosaurs.
In Carnegie's Pittsburgh Museum, there is
a tyrannosaurus rex called 'Samson'. Children
love that too. It is fun to sleep under a
diplodocus, or to stand in front of a tyrannosaurus
like Samson in a museum. There are many other
museums with dinosaurs to see too. Some of
the best are the Field Museum in Chicago,
the American Museum of Natural History in
New York, the Natural History Museum in Beijing,
and the Royal Tyrrell Museum in Alberta, Canada.
If you cannot see a real dinosaur, you can
still play with one on your computer. And
you can have fun with dinosaur games too.
Dinosaurs have appeared in hundreds of computer
games since 1986. In 1990, a likeable green
dinosaur called 'Yoshi' appeared in the computer
game Super Mario World - he soon became famous,
and even had his own games. But with their
sharp teeth and claws, and enormous bodies,
dinosaurs are more often seen in fighting
games. Since 1997, millions of people have
enjoyed fighting dangerous dinosaurs in the
seven very successful Turok games. And in
the last five years, dinosaur games have become
even more popular, with new games like Dino
Run, Dino D-Day and Velociraptor Safari.
But can you imagine a world with dinosaurs
and humans together? In the 1900s, people
began to write books about this idea. One
of the first was The Lost World by Sir Arthur
Conan Doyle. In this book, a scientist called
Professor Challenger discovers dinosaurs still
living on a mountain in South America.
More recently, Michael Crichton's book Jurassic
Park - later a popular film by Steven Spielberg
- uses the same idea. In this book, scientists
find dinosaur blood in the stomach of a fossilized
insect. They use this blood to make new dinosaurs.
Is this really possible? Scientists say no
- well, not yet. And that is a good thing.
After all, dinosaurs are much, much bigger
than us. If we bring back dinosaurs, we will
not be able to talk to them, or make friends
with them. And when a tyrannosaur sees a human,
it will think just one thing-lunch!
Remember, birds are dinosaurs. Tyrannosaurus
was, in some ways, like an enormous chicken.
So if you want to see a real living dinosaur,
watch a group of hungry chickens eating their
food. Then think of a chicken as big as a
house.
Do you really want the dinosaurs to come back?
- THE END -