CHAPTER ONE
The Worst Kind of Mark
He was an old man who fished alone in a skiff
in the Gulf Stream and he had gone eighty-four
days now without catching a fish.
During the first forty days without a fish,
the boy's parents had told him that the old
man was now definitely and finally salao,
which is the worst form of unlucky.
The boy's parents had ordered him to go in
another boat, which caught three good fish
the first week.
It made the boy sad to see the old man come
back each day with his skiff empty.
He always went down to help him carry the
lines, or the gaff and harpoon and the sail
patched with flour sacks, so that when it
was furled it looked like the flag of permanent
defeat.
The old man was thin and gaunt with deep wrinkles
on the back of his neck and deep scars on
his hands from handling lines of heavy fish.
The dark spots of the benign skin cancer that
the tropical sun brings were on his cheeks.
His scars were as old as forgotten memories.
Everything about him was old except his eyes.
They were the same color as the sea and were
cheerful and undefeated.
"Santiago," the boy said to him, "I could
go with you again.
We've made some money."
The old man had taught the boy to fish and
the boy loved him.
"No," the old man said.
"You're with a lucky boat.
Stay there."
"But remember how you went eighty-seven days
without fish and then we caught big ones every
day for three weeks."
"I remember," the old man said.
"I know you did not leave me because you doubted."
"It was papa who made me leave.
I am a boy and I must obey him."
"I know," the old man said.
"He hasn't much faith."
"No, but we have.
Haven't we?"
"Yes.
Can I offer you a beer on the Terrace and
then we'll take the stuff home."
"Why not?"
the old man said.
"Between fishermen."
They sat on the Terrace and many of the fishermen
made fun of the old man, but he was not angry.
The older fishermen looked at him and were
sad, but they did not show it.
The successful fishermen of that day had already
butchered their marlin and carried them to
the ice truck that would take them to the
market in Havana.
Those who had caught sharks had taken them
to the shark factory on the other side of
the cove.
When the wind came from the east a smell came
from the shark factory.
"Santiago," the boy said.
"Yes," the old man said.
He was thinking of many years ago.
"Can I go out and get sardines for you for
tomorrow?"
"No.
Go and play baseball.
I can still row and Rogelio will throw the
net."
"I would like to go.
If I cannot fish with you, I would like to
serve in some way."
"You bought me a beer."
the old man said.
"You are already a man."
"How old was I when you first took me in a
boat?"
"Five and you were nearly killed when I brought
the fish in too green and it nearly destroyed
the boat.
Can you remember?"
"I can remember the tail slapping and the
noise of the clubbing."
"Can you really remember that?"
"I remember everything from when we went together."
The old man looked at him with his confident,
loving eyes.
"If you were my boy I'd take you out," he
said.
"But you are your father's and your mother's
and you are in a lucky boat."
"May I get the sardines?
I know where I can get four baits too."
"I have mine left from today."
"Let me get four fresh ones."
"One," the old man said.
His hope and his confidence had never left
him.
"Two."
the boy said.
"Two," the old man agreed.
"Yon didn't steal them?"
"I would," the boy said.
"But I bought these."
"Thank you," the old man said.
"Tomorrow is going to be a good day with this
current."
He was too simple to wonder when he had attained
humility.
But he knew it carried no loss of pride.
"Where are you going?"
the boy asked.
"Far out.
I want to be out before it is light."
"Are you strong enough now for a truly big
fish?"
"I think so.
And there are many tricks."
"Let us take the stuff home," the boy said,
"so I can get the cast net and go after the
sardines."
They picked up the things from the boat.
The old man carried the mast on his shoulder
and the boy carried the wooden box with the
fishing gear.
They walked to the old man's shack and went
in through its open door.
The shack was made of the tough part of the
royal palm called guano.
In the shack there was a bed, a table, one
chair and a place on the dirt floor to cook
with charcoal.
On the brown walls there was a color picture
of the Sacred Heart of Jesus and another of
the Virgin of Cobre, both relics of his wife.
Once there had been a photograph of his wife
on the wall but he had taken it down because
it had made him lonely.
Now it was on the shelf in the corner under
his clean shirt.
"What do you have to eat?"
the boy asked.
"A pot of yellow rice with fish.
Do you want some?"
"No.
I will eat at home.
Do you want me to make a fire?"
"No.
I will make it later on."
"May I take the cast net?"
"Of course."
There was no cast net and the boy remembered
when they had sold it.
But they went through this fiction every day.
There was no pot of yellow rice and fish and
the boy knew this too.
"Eighty-five is a kicky number," the old man
said.
"How would you like to see me bring one in
that weighed over a thousand pounds?"
"I'll get the cast net and go for sardines.
Will you sit in the sun in the doorway?"
"Yes.
I have yesterday's paper and I will read about
baseball."
The boy did not know whether yesterday's paper
was fiction too.
But the old man brought it out from under
the bed.
"Perico gave it to me at the bodega." he explained.
"I'll be back when I have the sardines.
I'll keep yours and mine together on ice and
we can share them in the morning.
When I come back you can tell me about baseball.
Now keep warm, old man.
Remember we are in September," the boy said.
"The month when the great fish come," the
old man said.
"Anyone can be a fisherman in May."
'I'm going for the sardines now," the boy
said.
When the boy came back the old man was asleep
in the chair and the sun was down.
The boy took the old army blanket off the
bed and spread it over the back of the chair
and over the old mail's strange but powerful
shoulders.
His shirt had been patched so many times that
it was like a sail.
The old man's head was very old and with his
eyes closed there was no life in his face.
He was barefoot.
The boy left him there and when he came back
the old man was still asleep.
"Wake up, old man," the boy said.
The old man opened his eyes and for a moment
he was coming back from a long way away.
Then he smiled.
"What have you got?" he asked.
"Supper," said the boy.
"We're going to have supper."
"I'm not very hungry-"
"Come on and eat.
You can't fish and not eat."
"What are we eating?"
"Black beans and rice, fried bananas and some
stow."
The boy had brought them in a metal container
from the Terrace.
"That's very kind of you," the old man said.
"Should we eat?"
"I've been asking you to," the boy told him
gently.
"I didn't want to open the container until
you were ready."
"I'm ready now," the old man said.
"I only needed time to wash."
Where did he wash?
the boy thought.
The village water supply was two streets down
the road.
I must have water here for him, and soap and
a towel.
Why am I so thoughtless?
I must got him another shirt and a jacket
for the winter and some sort of shoes and
another blanket.
"Your stew is excellent," the old man said.
"Tell me about baseball," the boy asked him.
"In the American League it is the Yankees
as I said," the old man said happily.
"They lost today," the boy told him.
"That means nothing.
The great DiMaggio is himself again."
"They have other men on the team."
"Naturally.
But he makes the difference," the old man
said.
"Do you remember when he used to come to the
Terrace?
I wanted to take him fishing but I was too
timid to ask him.
Then I asked you to ask him and you were too
timid.
I would like to take the great DiMaggio fishing.
They say his father was a fisherman.
Maybe he was as poor as we are and would understand."
"I used to sail on a big ship that went to
Africa and I have seen lions on the beaches
in the evening."
"I know.
You told me."
"Should we talk about Africa or about baseball?"
"Baseball.
Tell me about the great John Jota McGraw,"
the boy said.
"He used to come to the Terrace sometimes
in the older days.
But he was rough and harsh-spoken when he
drank too much."
"Who is the greatest manager, really, Luque
or Mike Gonzalez?"
"I think they are equal."
"And the best fisherman is you."
"No.
I know others that are better."
"Que va," the boy said, "There are many good
fishermen and some great ones, but there is
only you."
"Thank you.
You make me happy.
I hope no fish will come along so great that
he will prove us wrong."
"There is no such fish if you are still strong
as you say."
"I may not be as strong as I think," the old
man said.
"But I know many tricks and I have resolution."
"You ought to go to bed now so that you will
be fresh in the morning."
"Good night then.
I will wake you in the morning."
"You're my alarm clock," the boy said.
"Age is my alarm clock," the old man said.
"Why do old men wake so early?
Is it to have longer days?"
"I don't know," the boy said.
"All I know is that young boys sleep late
and hard.
Sleep well, old man."
They had eaten with no light on the table.
The old man rolled his trousers up to make
a pillow, putting the newspaper inside them.
He rolled himself in the blanket and slept
on the other old newspapers that covered the
springs of the bed.
CHAPTER TWO
Far Out to Sea
The old man dreamed of Africa when he was
a boy and the long, golden beaches.
He lived along that coast now every night
and in his dreams he heard the surf roar and
saw the native boats come riding through it.
As he slept he smelled the smell of Africa
that the land breeze brought in the morning.
He no longer dreamed of storms, nor of women,
nor of great events, nor of great fish, nor
of fights, nor of contests of strength, nor
of his wife.
Now he only dreamed of places and of the lions
on the beach.
They played like young cats in the dusk and
he loved their, as he loved the boy.
He never dreamed about the boy.
He woke up, looked out the open door at the
moon and unrolled his trousers and put them
on.
He went up the road to wake the boy.
The door of the house where the boy lived
was unlocked and the old man opened it and
walked in quietly.
He took hold of the boy's foot gently and
held it until the boy woke and turned and
looked at him.
The old man nodded and the boy took his trousers
from the chair by the bed and, sitting on
the bed, pulled them on.
The old man went out the door and the boy
came after him.
He was sleepy and the old man put his arm
across his shoulders and said.
"I am sorry."
"Que va," the boy said.
"It is what a man must do."
They walked down the road to the old man's
shack and all along the road, in the dark,
barefoot men were moving, carrying the masts
of their boats.
When they reached the old man's shack the
boy took the rolls of lute in the basket,
the harpoon and gaff, and the old man carried
the mast with the furled sail on his shoulder.
"Do you want coffee?"
the boy asked.
"We'll put the gear in the boat and then get
some."
They had coffee from condensed-milk cans at
an early morning place that served fishermen.
"How did you sleep, old man?"
the boy asked.
He was waking up now although it was still
hard for him to leave his sleep.
"Very well, Manolin," the old man said.
"I feel confident today."
"So do I." the boy said.
"Now I must get your sardines and mine and
your fresh baits."
"I'll be right back."
the boy said.
"Have another coffee.
We have credit here."
The old man drank his coffee slowly.
It was all he would have all day and he knew
that he should drink it.
For a long time now eating had bored him and
he never carried a lunch.
He had a bottle of water in the bow of the
skiff and that was all he needed for the day.
The boy was back now with the sardines and
the two baits, and they went down to the skiff,
feeling the pebbled sand under their feet.
They lifted the skiff and slid her into the
water.
"Good luck, old man."
"Good luck," the old man said.
He fitted the rope lashings of the oars onto
the thole pins and, leaning forward, he began
to row out of the harbor in the dark.
There were other boats going out to sea and
the old man heard the dip and push of their
oars even though he could not see them.
The old man knew he was going far out and
he left the smell of the laud behind and rowed
out into the clean early morning smell of
the ocean.
In the dark the old man could feel the morning
coming and as he rowed he heard the sound
of flying fish leaving the water.
He was very fond of flying fish as they were
his principal friends on the ocean.
He was sorry for the birds, especially the
small delicate dark terns that were always
flying and looking and almost never finding.
And he thought, the birds have a harder life
than we do except for the robber birds and
the heavy strong ones.
Why did they make birds so delicate and fine
as those sea swallows when the ocean can be
so cruel?
She is kind and very beautiful.
But she can be so cruel.
He always thought of the sea as la mar which
is what people call her in Spanish when they
love her.
Sometimes those who love her say bad things
about her but they always speak of the sea
as though she were a woman.
Some of the younger fishermen, who had motorboats,
speak of her as el mar which is masculine.
They speak of her as a contestant or a place
or even as an enemy.
But the old man always thought of her as feminine
and as something that gave or withheld great
favors, and if She did wild or wicked things
it was because she could not help them.
The moon affects her as it does a woman, he
thought.
He was rowing steadily and it was no effort
for him.
"Today I'll row out where the schools of albacore
are and maybe there will be a big one with
them."
Before it was really light he had his four
baits out at different depths and he was drifting
with the current.
There was no part of the hook that a great
fish could feel which was not sweet-smelling
and good-tasting.
The boy had given him two small fresh tunas
which hung on the two deepest lines and on
the others, he had a big blue runner and a
yellow jack.
Each line was as thick as a big pencil and
was looped onto a stick so that any pull or
touch on the bait would make the stick dip.
Now the old man rowed gently to keep the lines
straight and at their proper depths.
The sun rose thinly from the sea and the old
man could see the other boats, low on the
water and well in toward the shore.
He looked down into the water and watched
the lines that went straight down into the
dark water.
He kept them straighter titan any other fisherman.
I keep them with precision, he thought.
Only I have no luck anymore.
But who knows?
Maybe today.
Every day is a new day.
It is better to be lucky.
But I would rather be exact.
Then when luck comes you are ready.
Just then he saw a man-of-war bird with his
long black wings circling in the sky ahead
of him.
He made a quick drop and then circled again.
"He's got something," the old man said aloud.
"He's not just looking."
"Dolphin," the old man said aloud.
"Big dolphin."
As the old man watched, a small tuna rose
in the air, turned and dropped into the water.
Another and another rose and they were leaping
in long jumps alter the bait.
After a while the stern line became taut under
his foot.
He dropped his oars and felt the weight of
the small tuna's shivering pull.
He could see the fish in the water as he pulled
it in.
The old man hit him on the head for kindness
and kicked him under the stern.
"Albacore," he said aloud.
"He'll make a beautiful bait."
He did not remember when he first started
talking to himself.
Probably when the boy had left him, but he
did not remember.
The sun was hot now and the old man felt it
on the back of his neck, and felt the sweat
trickle down his back as he rowed.
Just then, watching his lines, he saw one
of the projecting green sticks dip sharply.
"Yes." he said.
"Yes," and he moved his oars inside the boat.
He reached out for the line and held it delicately
between the thumb and forefinger of his right
hand.
Then it came again.
This time it was a tentative pull and he knew
exactly what it was.
One hundred fathoms below a marlin was eating
the sardines that covered the point of the
hook.
This far out, he must be huge, he thought.
Eat them, fish.
Please eat them.
He felt the light delicate pull and then a
harder pull when a sardine's head must have
been more difficult to break from the hook.
Then there was nothing.
"Come on," the old man said aloud.
"Just smell them.
Aren't they lovely?
Eat them now and then there is the tuna.
Don't be shy, fish.
Eat them."
Then he felt something hard and unbelievably
heavy.
It was the weight of the fish and he let the
line slip down, down, down.
Now he was ready.
He had three forty-fathom coils of line in
reserve, as well as the coil he was using.
"Eat it a little more." he said.
"Eat it well."
Eat it so that the point of the hook goes
into your heart and kills you, he thought.
Come up easy and let me put the harpoon into
you.
Are you ready?
Have you been at the table long enough?
"Now!" he said aloud and struck hard with
both hands, gained a yard of line and then
struck again and again, swinging with all
the strength of his arms and the weight of
his body.
Nothing happened.
The fish just moved away slowly and the old
man could not raise him an inch.
The boat began to move slowly toward the northwest.
The fish moved steadily and they traveled
slowly on the calm water.
"I wish I had the boy," the old man said aloud.
"I'm being towed by a fish.
I must hold him all I can and give him the
line when he wants it.
Thank God he is traveling and not going down."
Four hours later the fish was still swimming
out to sea, towing the skiff, and the old
man was still braced solidly with the line
across his back.
CHAPTER THREE
The Battle Begins
He looked behind him and saw that no land
was visible.
That makes no difference, he thought.
I can always come in on the glow from Havana.
Maybe he will come up before sunset, or with
the moon.
I have no cramps and I feel strong.
It is he that has the hook in his mouth.
But what a fish to pull like that.
I wish I could see him only once to know what
I have against me.
The fish never changed his course.
It was cold after the sun went down, he tied
the sack that covered the bait box around
his neck so that it hung down over his back
and he cautiously worked it down under the
line that was across his shoulders now.
I can do nothing with him and he can do nothing
with me, he thought.
Once he stood up and urinated over the side
of the skiff and looked at the stars and checked
his course.
They were moving more slowly now and the glow
of Havana was not so strong, so he knew the
current must be carrying them eastward.
I wonder how the baseball came out in the
grand leagues today, he thought.
It would be wonderful to do this with a radio.
Think of what you are doing, you must do nothing
stupid.
Then he said aloud, "I wish I had the boy.
To help me and to see this.'
No one should be alone in their old age, he
thought.
But it is unavoidable.
I must remember to eat the tuna before he
spoils in order to keep strong.
Remember, you must eat him in the morning,
he said to himself.
During the night two porpoise came around
the boat and he could hear them rolling and
blowing.
"They are good," he said.
"They play and make jokes and love one another.
They are our brothers like the flying fish."
Then he began to pity the great fish that
he had hooked.
He is wonderful and strange and who knows
how old he is, he thought.
Never have I had such a strong fish nor one
who acted so strangely.
Perhaps he is too wise to jump.
He could ruin me by jumping.
But what a great fish he is and what he will
bring in the market if the flesh is good,
he took the bait like a male and he pulls
like a male and his fight has no panic in
it.
I wonder if he has any plans or if he is just
as desperate as I am.
"I wish the boy were here," he said aloud
and settled himself against the bow and felt
the strength of the great fish through the
line he held across his shoulders.
My choice was to go out to find him beyond
all people in the world.
Now we are joined together and no one to help
either one of us.
The fish made a surge that pulled him down
on his face and made a cut below his eye.
The blood ran down his cheek a little way.
But it coagulated and dried before it reached
his chin and he worked his way back to the
bow and rested against the wood.
I wonder why he made that surge, he thought.
The wire must have slipped on the great hill
of his back.
Certainly his back cannot feel as bad as mine
does.
But he cannot pull this skiff forever, no
matter how great he is.
"Fish." he said softly, aloud.
"I'll stay with you until I am dead."
When the sun had risen further the old man
realized that the fish was not getting tired.
There was only one favorable sign.
The slam of the line showed he was swimming
at a lesser depth.
That did not mean that he would jump.
But he might.
"God, let him jump," the old man said.
"I have enough line to handle him."
"Fish," he said, "I love you and respect you
very much.
But I will kill you dead before this day ends."
A small bird came toward the skiff from the
north.
He was a warbler and the old man could see
he was very tired.
He flew around the old man's head and rested
on the line.
"How old are you?"
the old man asked the bird.
"Is this your first trip?"
The bird was very tired and he teetered on
the line as his delicate feet gripped it.
"Take a good rest, small bird," he said.
"Then go and take your chance like any man
or bird or fish."
Just then the fish gave a sudden lurch that
pulled the old man down to the bow and would
have pulled him overboard if he had not braced
himself and given some line.
The bird flew away and he felt the line carefully
with his right hand and noticed his hand was
bleeding.
Shifting the weight of the line to his left
shoulder and kneeling carefully, he washed
his hand in the ocean.
The cut was in the working part of his hand.
He knew he would need his hands before this
was over and he did not like to be cut before
it started.
"Now," he said, "I must eat the small tuna."
he knelt down and found the tuna under the
stem.
He put one knee on the fish and cut strips
of dark red meat from the back of the head
to the tail.
"I don't think I can eat an entire one," he
said.
He could feel the steady hard pull of the
line and his left hand was cramped.
"What kind of a hand is that," he said.
"Cramp then if you want.
Make yourself into a claw.
It will do you no good."
He picked up a piece of tuna and put it in
his mouth and chewed it slowly.
It was not unpleasant.
"How do you feel, hand?" he asked the cramped
hand that was almost as stiff as rigor mortis,
"I'll eat some more for you."
I wish I could feed the fish, he thought.
He is my brother.
But I must kill him and keep strong to do
it.
Slowly he ate all the strips of fish.
"God help me to have the cramp go," he said.
"Because I do not know what the fish is going
to do."
What is his plan, he thought.
And what is mine?
His left hand was still cramped, but he was
unknotting it slowly.
I hate cramps, he thought.
It is a treachery of one's own body.
Then, with his right hand he felt the difference
in the pull of the line.
"He's coming up." he said.
"Come on, hand.
Please come on."
The line rose slowly and steadily and then
the surface of the ocean bulged ahead of the
boat and the fish came out.
He came out unendingly and water poured from
his sides.
He was bright in the sun and his head and
his sides were wide and colored a light lavender.
His sword was as long as a baseball bat and
tapered like a rapier and he rose his full
length from the water and then re-entered
it, smoothly, like a diver and the old man
saw the great scythe-blade of his tail go
under, and the line started to race out.
"He is two feet longer than the skiff," the
old man said.
He was trying with both hands to keep the
line just inside of breaking strength.
He knew that if he could not slow the fish
with a steady pressure, the fish could take
out all the line and break it.
He is a great fish but I must convince him
that he is no match for me, he thought.
I must never let him learn his strength nor
what he could do if he made his run.
The old man had seen many great fish.
He had seen many that weighed more than a
thousand pounds and he had caught two of that
size in his life, but never alone.
Now alone, and out of sight of land, he was
tied fast to the biggest fish that he had
ever seen and bigger than he had ever heard
of, and his left hand was still cramped.
I wonder why he jumped, the old man thought.
He jumped almost as though to show me how
big he was.
I wish I could show him what sort of man I
am.
But then he would see the cramped hand.
At noon the old man's left hand was uncramped.
He was comfortable but suffering, although
he did not admit the suffering at all.
"I am not religious," he said.
"But I will say ten Our Fathers and ten Hail
Marys so that I can catch this fish, and I
promise to make a pilgrimage to the Virgin
de Cobre if I catch him.
Christ, I did not know he was so big."
"I'll kill him though," he said.
"In all his greatness."
Although it is unjust, he thought.
But I will show him what a man can do and
what a man endures.
"I told the boy I was a strange old man,"
he said.
"Now is when I must prove it."
The thousand times that he had proved it meant
nothing.
Now he was proving it again.
"If you're not tired, fish." he said aloud,
"you must be very strange."
He felt very tired now and he tried to think
of other things.
He thought of the Big Leagues, and he knew
the Yankees of New York were playing the Tigers
of Detroit.
This is the second day that I do not know
the result of the juegos, he thought.
But I must have confidence and I must be worthy
of the great DiMaggio who does all things
perfectly.
Do you believe the great DiMaggio would stay
with a fish as long as I will stay with this
one? he thought.
I am sure he would and more since he is young
and strong.
Also his father was a fisherman.
CHAPTER FOUR
An Even Eight
As the sun set, to give himself more confidence,
he remembered the time in the tavern at Casablanca
when he had played the hand game with the
great negro from Cienfuegos, who was the strongest
man on the docks.
They had gone one day and one night with their
elbows on a chalk line on the table.
Each one was trying to force the other's hand
down onto the table.
They changed the referee every four hours
so that the referees could sleep.
The odds would change back and forth all night.
Once the negro had the old man, who was not
an old man then but was Santiago El Campeon,
nearly three inches off balance.
But the old man had raised his hand again.
He was sure then that he had the negro, who
was a fine man and a great athlete, beaten.
And at daylight he had forced the hand of
the negro down and down until it rested on
the table.
The match had started on a Sunday morning
and ended on a Monday morning.
For a long time everyone had called him "the
Champion."
After that he had a few matches and then no
more.
He decided that he could beat anyone if he
wanted to badly enough and he decided that
it was bad for his right hand for fishing.
Just before it was dark, as they passed a
great island of Sargasso weed, his small line
was taken by a dolphin.
He saw it first when it jumped in the air,
bending and flapping wildly.
When it was at the stern the old man leaned
over and lifted the burnished gold fish with
its purple spots over the stem.
Its jaws were working convulsively in quick
bites against the hook.
It pounded the bottom of the skiff with its
long flat body, its tail and its head until
he clubbed it.
Then it shivered and was still.
The old man watched the sun go into the ocean
and the slant of the big cord.
"He hasn't changed at all," he said.
But watching the movement of the water against
his hand he noted that it was a bit slower.
"I'll lash the two oars together across the
stern and that will slow him in the night,"
he said.
"He's good for the night and so am I."
I'm learning how to do it, he thought.
This part of it anyway.
Then, too, remember he hasn't eaten since
he took the bait and he is huge and needs
much food.
I have eaten the whole tuna, tomorrow I will
eat the dolphin.
"How do you feel, fish?" he asked aloud.
"I feel good and my left hand is better and
I have food for a night and a day.
Pull the boat, fish."
He did not truly feel good because the pain
from the cord across his back had almost passed
pain and gone into a dullness that worried
him.
But I have had worse things than that, he
thought.
My hand is only cut a little and the cramp
is gone from the other.
My legs are all right.
It was dark now as it becomes dark quickly
after the sun sets in September.
The first stars were out.
He did not know the name of Rigel but he saw
it and knew that soon they would all be out
and he would have all his distant friends.
"The fish is my friend too," he said aloud.
"I have never seen or heard of such a fish.
But I must kill him, I am glad we do not have
to try to kill the stars."
Then he was sorry for the great fish that
had nothing to eat and his determination to
kill him never relaxed in his sorrow for him.
How many people will he feed, he thought.
But are they worthy to eat him?
No, of course not.
There is no one worthy of eating a fish with
such great dignity.
The old man rested for what he believed to
be two hours.
The moon did not rise until late now and he
had no way of judging the time.
He was still bearing the pull of the fish
across his shoulders.
"But you have not slept yet, old man.
It is half a day and a night and now another
day and you have not slept," he said aloud.
"I must devise a way so that you sleep a little
if he is quiet and steady.
If you do not sleep you might become unclear
in the head."
I could go without sleeping, he told himself.
But it would be too dangerous.
He worked his way back to the stern.
The stars were bright now and he saw the dolphin
clearly and he pushed the blade of his knife
into his head and pulled him out from under
the stern.
The dolphin was cold and gray-white now in
the starlight and the old man skinned one
side of him while he held his right foot on
the fish's head.
Then he skinned the other side and cut fillets.
He leaned over the side and put his hand in
the water.
The flow of the water against it was less
strong.
"He is tired or he is resting.
Now let me eat this dolphin and get some rest
and a little sleep."
Under the stars he ate half of one of the
dolphin fillets.
"What an excellent fish dolphin is to eat
cooked," he said.
"And what a miserable fish raw.
I will never go in a boat again without salt
or limes."
The sky was clouding over to the east and
one after another the stars he knew were gone.
It looked now as though he were moving into
a great canyon of clouds and the wind had
dropped.
"There will be bad weather in three or four
days," he said.
"But not tonight or tomorrow.
Right now to get some sleep, old man, while
the fish is calm and steady."
The moon had been up for a long time but he
slept on and the fish pulled on steadily and
the boat moved into the tunnel of clouds.
He woke with the jerk of his right fist coming
up against his face and the line burning out
through his right hand.
He could not feel the line with his left hand
but he braked all he could with his right
and the line rushed out.
Finally his left hand found the line and he
leaned back against it and now it burned his
back and his left hand.
His left hand was taking all the strain and
it was cutting badly.
Just then the fish jumped making a great bursting
of the ocean and then a heavy fall.
Then he jumped again and again and the boat
was going fast although line was still racing
out and the old man was raising the strain
to the breaking point.
He had been pulled down tight onto the bow
and his face was in the cut slice of dolphin
and he could not move.
This is what we waited for, he thought.
So now let us take it.
Make him pay for the line.
Make him pay for it.
He could not see the fish's jumps but only
heard the breaking of the ocean and the heavy
splash as he fell.
The speed of the line was cutting his hands
badly but he had always known this would happen.
If the boy were here he would wet the coils
of line, he thought.
Yes.
If the boy were here.
The line went out but it was slowing now and
he was making the fish earn each inch of it.
Now he got his head up from the wood and out
of the slice of fish that his cheek had crushed.
He was on his knees and then he rose to his
feet.
He was giving line but more slowly all the
time.
I wonder what started him so suddenly?
Could it have been hunger that made him desperate,
or was he frightened by something in the night?
Maybe he suddenly felt fear.
But he was such a calm, strong fish and he
seemed so fearless and so confident.
It is strange.
"You better be fearless and confident yourself,
old man," he said.
The old man held him with his left hand and
stooped down and scooped up water in his right
hand to get the crushed dolphin flesh off
his face.
He was afraid that it might nauseate him and
cause him to vomit and lose his strength.
He washed his right hand in the water and
then let it stay in the salt water while he
watched the first light come before the sunrise.
He's headed almost east, he thought.
That means he is tired and going with the
current.
Soon he will have to circle.
Then our true work begins.
After he judged that his right hand had been
in the water long enough he took it out and
looked at it.
"It is not bad," he said.
"And pain does not matter to a man."
He took hold of the line carefully so that
it did not fit into any of the fresh line
cuts and shifted his weight so that he could
put his left hand into the sea on the other
side of the skiff.
"You did not do so badly for something worthless,"
he said to his left hand.
'But there was a moment when I could not find
you."
Why was I not born with two good hands? he
thought.
Perhaps it was my fault in not training the
left one properly.
But God knows he had enough chances to leant.
He did not do so badly in the night, though,
and he has cramped only once.
If he cramps again let the line cut him off.
The sun was rising for the third time since
he had got out to sea when the fish started
to circle.
"It is a very big circle," he said.
"But he is circling."
I must hold all I can, he thought.
The strain will shorten his circle each lime.
Perhaps in an hour I will see him.
Now I must convince him and then I must kill
him.
But the fish kept on circling slowly and the
old man was wet with sweat and tired deep
into his bones two hours later.
But the circles were much shorter now and
from the way the line slanted he could tell
the fish had risen steadily while he swam.
For an hour the old man had been seeing black
spots before his eyes and the sweat salted
his eyes and salted the cut under his eye
and on his forehead.
He was not afraid of the black spots.
Twice, though, he had felt faint and dizzy
and that had worried him.
"I cannot fail and die on a fish like this,"
he said.
"Now that I have him coming so beautifully.
God help me endure.
I'll say a hundred Our Fathers and a hundred
Hail Marys.
But I cannot say them now."
Consider them said, he thought.
I'll say them later.
Just then he felt a sudden banging and jerking
on the line he held with his two hands.
It was sharp and heavy.
He is hitting the wire with his sword, he
thought.
He may jump and I would rather he circled
now.
The jumps wore necessary for him to take air.
But after that each jump can widen the opening
of the hook wound and he can throw the hook.
"Don't jump, fish," he said.
"Don't jump.
The fish hit the wire several times more,
and each time the old man gave up a little
line.
After a while the fish stopped beating at
the wire and started circling slowly again.
The old man was gaining line steadily now.
But he felt faint again.
He lifted some sea water with his left hand
and put it on his head.
Then he put more on and rubbed the back of
his neck.
"I have no cramps," ho said.
"He'll go up soon and I can last.
You have to last.
Don't oven speak of it."
He kneeled against the bow and, for a moment,
slipped the line over his back again.
I'll rest now while he circles and then stand
up and work on him when he comes in, he decided.
I'm more tired than I have ever been, he thought,
and now the trade wind is rising.
But that will be good to take him in with.
The sea had risen considerably.
But it was a fair weather breeze and he had
to have it to get home.
"I'll just steer south and west," he said.
"A man is never lost at sea and it is a long
island."
It was on the third turn that he saw the fish
for the first time.
He saw him first as a dark shadow that took
so long to pass under the boat that he could
not believe its length.
"No," he said.
"He can't be that big."
But he was that big and at the end of this
circle he came to the surface only thirty
yards away and the man saw his tail out of
the water.
It was higher than a big scythe blade and
a very pale lavender above the dark blue water.
As the fish swam just below the surface the
old man could see his huge bulk and purple
stripes.
His dorsal fin was down and his huge pectorals
were spread wide.
Then the old man could see the fish's eye.
The old man was sweating now but from something
else besides the sun.
On each placid turn the fish made he was gaining
line and he was sure that in two turns he
would have a chance to get the harpoon in.
But I must get him close, close, close, he
thought.
I mustn't try for the head.
I must get the heart.
"Be calm and strong, old man," he said.
The fish was coming in on his circle now,
calm and beautiful with only his great tail
moving.
The old man pulled on him to bring him closer.
For just a moment the fish turned a little
on his side.
Then he straightened himself and began another
circle.
"I moved him."
the old man said.
"I moved him then."
He felt faint again but he held on to the
great fish with all his strength.
I moved him, he thought.
Maybe this time I can get him over.
Pull, hands, he thought.
Hold up, legs.
Last for me, head.
Last for me.
You never went.
This time I'll pull him over.
But when he put forth, all of his effort,
the fish righted himself and swam away.
"Fish."
the old man said.
"Fish, you are going to have to die anyway.
Do you have to kill me too?"
That way nothing is accomplished, he thought.
His mouth was too dry to speak but he could
not reach for the water now.
I must get him alongside this time, he thought.
I am not good for many more turns.
Yes, you are, he told himself.
You're good forever.
On the next turn, he nearly had him.
But again the fish righted himself and swam
away slowly.
You are killing me, fish, the old man thought.
But you have a right to.
Never have I seen a greater or more beautiful
or a calmer or more noble thing than you,
brother.
Come on and kill me.
I do not care who kills who.
Now you are getting confused in the head,
he thought.
You must keep your head clear and know how
to suffer like a man or a fish.
"Clear up, head." he said in a voice he could
hardly hear.
"Clear up."
He tried it once more and he felt himself
going when he turned the fish.
The fish righted himself and swam off again
slowly with the great tail moving in the air.
I'll try it again, the old man promised, although
his hands were mushy now and he could only
see well in flashes.
CHAPTER FIVE
Shark Attack
He took all his pain and what was left of
his strength and his long-gone pride and he
put it against the fish's agony.
The fish came over onto his side and swam
gently and started to pass the boat.
The old man dropped the line and put his foot
on it and lifted the harpoon as high as he
could and drove it down with all his strength
into the fish's side just behind the great
chest fin.
He felt the iron go in and he leaned on it
and drove it further and then pushed all his
weight after it.
Then the fish came alive, with his death in
him, and rose high out of the water showing
all his great length and width and all his
power and his beauty.
He seemed to hang in the air above the old
man in the skiff.
Then he fell into the water with a crash.
The old man felt faint and sick and he could
not see well.
But he cleared the harpoon line and let it
run slowly through his raw hands and when
he could see, he saw the fish was on his back
with his silver belly up.
The shaft of the harpoon was projecting at
an angle from the fish's shoulder and the
sea was red with the blood from his heart.
The fish was silvery and still and floated
with the waves.
The old man laid his head on his hands.
"Keep my head clear," he said.
"I am a tired old man.
But I have killed this fish which is my brother
and now I must do the slave work."
Now I must prepare the rope to tie him alongside
the skiff, he thought.
This skiff will never hold him.
He started to pull the fish in to have him
alongside the skiff.
I want to see him, he thought, and to touch
and to feel him.
He is my fortune, he thought.
But that is not why I wish to feel him.
I think I felt his heart when I pushed on
the harpoon the second time.
Bring him in now and get the noose around
his tail and another around his middle to
tie him to the skiff.
"Get to work, old man," he said.
He took a very small drink of water.
"There is much slave work to do now that the
fight is over."
He looked up at the sky and then out to his
fish.
"Come on, fish," he said.
But the fish did not come, instead he lay
there and the old man pulled the skiff up
to him.
When the fish's head was against the bow he
could not believe his size.
"It was the only way to kill him," the old
man said, he was feeling better and his head
was clear, he's over fifteen hundred pounds,
he thought.
Maybe much more.
"I think the great DiMaggio would be proud
of me today."
He fastened the fish, to the bow, to the stem
and to the middle thwart.
He was so big it was like lashing a much bigger
skiff alongside.
He could see the fish and he had only to look
at his hands and feel his back against the
stem to know that this had truly happened
and was not a dream.
They were sailing together lashed side by
side and the old man thought, let him bring
me in if it pleases him.
I am only better than him through trickery
and he meant me no harm.
It was an hour before the first shark hit
him.
The shark had come up from deep down in the
water as the dark cloud of blood had settled
and dispersed in the mile-deep sea.
He had come up so fast that he broke the surface
of the blue water and was in the sun.
Then he fell back into the sea and picked
up the scent and started following the skiff
and the fish.
Sometimes he lost the scent.
But he would pick it up again and he swam
fast and hard.
He was a very big Mako shark built to swim
as fast as the fastest fish in the sea and
everything about him was beautiful except
his jaws.
His back was as blue as a swordfish's and
his belly was silver and his hide was smooth
and handsome.
Inside the closed double lip of his jaws all
of his eight rows of teeth were slanted inwards.
They were not the ordinary pyramid-shaped
teeth of most sharks.
They wore shaped like a man's fingers when
they are curled like claws.
They were nearly as long as the fingers of
the old man and they had razor-sharp cutting
edges on both sides.
When the old man saw him coming he knew that
this was a shark that had no fear at all and
would do exactly what he wished.
He prepared the harpoon and the rope while
he watched the shark come forward.
The old man's head was clear and good now
and he was full of resolution but he had little
hope.
It was too good to last, he thought, it might
as well have been a dream.
I cannot keep him from hitting me but maybe
I can get him.
Dentuso, he thought.
Bad luck to your mother.
When the shark hit the fish the old man saw
his mouth open and his strange eyes.
He heard the clicking sound of the teeth as
he tore into the meat just above the tail.
He rammed the harpoon down into the shark's
head and into his brain.
He hit it with his bloody hands driving the
harpoon with all his strength.
He hit it without hope but with resolution
and complete malignancy.
The shark swung over and the old man saw his
eye was not alive.
The old man knew that he was dead but the
shark would not accept it.
It ploughed over the water as a speed boat
does.
Then he lay quietly for a little while and
went down very slowly.
"He took about forty pounds and my harpoon,"
the old man said.
He did not like to look at the fish any more
since he had been mutilated.
When the fish had been hit it was as though
he himself were hit.
It was too good to last, he thought.
I wish it had been a dream now and that I
had never hooked the fish and was alone in
bed on the newspapers.
"But man is not made for defeat," he said.
"A man can be destroyed but not defeated."
I am sorry that I killed the fish though,
he thought.
Now the bad time is coming and I do not even
have the harpoon.
"Don't think, old man," he said aloud.
"Sail on and take it when it comes."
He knew quite well the pattern of what could
happen when he readied the inner part of the
current.
But there was nothing to be done now.
"Yes, there is," he said aloud.
"I can lash my knife to the butt of one of
the oars."
So he did that.
"Now, I am still an old man.
But I am not unarmed."
He watched only the forward part of the fish
and some of his hope returned.
It is silly not to hope, he thought.
Besides I believe it is a sin.
Do not think about sin.
There are enough problems now without sin.
I have no understanding of it and I am not
sure that I believe in it.
Perhaps it was a sin to kill the fish.
I suppose it was though I did it to keep me
alive and feed many people.
But then everything is a sin.
Do not think about sin.
You were born to be a fisherman.
You did not kill the fish only to keep alive
and to sell for food, he thought.
You killed him for pride and because you are
a fisherman.
You loved him when he was alive and you loved
him after.
If you love him it is not a sin to kill him.
Or is it more?
But you enjoyed killing the dentuso, he thought.
"I killed him in self-defense," the old man
said aloud.
"And I killed him well."
Besides, he thought, everything kills everything
else in some way.
Fishing kills me exactly as it keeps me alive.
The boy keeps me alive.
I must not deceive myself too much.
CHAPTER SIX
The Final Battle
He had been sailing for two hours when he
saw the first of the two sharks.
"Galanos," he said aloud.
He took up the oar with the knife lashed to
it.
He lifted it as lightly as he could because
his hands rebelled at the pain, and he watched
the sharks come.
They were hateful sharks, bad-smelling scavengers
as well as killers, and when they were hungry
they would bite at an oar or the rudder of
a boat.
"Ay," the old man said.
"Galanos.
Come on, galanos."
They came.
One turned and went out of sight under the
skiff and the old man could feel the skiff
shake as he jerked and pulled on the fish.
The other watched the old man with his yellow
eyes and then came in fast to hit the fish
where he had already been bitten.
A line showed clearly on the top of his brown
head and back where the brain joined the spinal
cord and the old man drove the knife on the
oar into the brain, withdrew it, and drove
it in again into the shark's yellow cat-like
eyes.
The shark let go of the fish and slid down,
swallowing what he had taken as he died.
When he saw the other shark he leaned over
the side and punched him.
The blow hurt his hands and his shoulder.
But the shark came up fast with his head out
and the old man hit him squarely in the center
of his flat-topped head.
The old man withdrew the blade and punched
the shark exactly in the same spot again.
The old man stabbed him in his left eye but
the shark still hung there.
"No?"
the old man said and he drove the blade between
the vertebrae and the brain and he felt the
cartilage break.
"Go on, galano.
Slide down a mile deep.
Go and see your friend, or maybe it's your
mother."
The old man wiped the blade of his knife and
laid down the oar.
Then he brought the skiff onto her course.
"They must have taken a quarter of him and
of the best meat," he said aloud.
"I wish it were a dream and that I had never
hooked him.
I'm sorry about it, fish.
It makes everything wrong."
He stopped and he did not want to look at
the fish now.
"I shouldn't have gone out so far, fish,"
he said.
"Neither for you nor for me.
I'm sorry, fish.
God knows how much that last one took," he
continued.
"But she's much lighter now."
He did not want to think of the mutilated
under-side of the fish.
He was a fish to keep a man all winter, he
thought.
Don't think of that.
Just rest and try to get your hands in shape
to defend what is left of him.
The next shark that came was a single shovel-nose.
He came like a pig to the trough if a pig
had a mouth so wide that you could put your
head in it.
The old man let him hit the fish and then
drove the knife on the oar down into his brain.
But tire shark jerked backwards as he rolled
and the knife blade snapped.
The old man did not even watch the big shark
sinking slowly in the water.
"I have the gaff now." he said.
"But it will do no good.
I have the two oars and the tiller and the
short dub."
Now they have beaten me, he thought.
I am too old to club sharks to death.
But I will try it as long as I have the oars
and the short club and the tiller.
It was getting late in the afternoon and he
saw nothing but the sea and the sky.
"You're tired, old man," he said.
"You're tired inside."
The sharks did not hit him again until just
before sunset.
He blocked the tiller and reached under the
stern for the club.
It was an oar handle from a broken oar.
The two sharks closed together and as he saw
the one nearest him open his jaws and sink
them into the silver side of the fish, he
raised the club high and brought it down heavy
on the top of the shark's broad head.
He struck the shark once more hard across
the point of the nose as he slid down from
the fish.
The other shark now came in again with his
jaws wide.
The old man could see pieces of the meat of
the fish spilling white from the corner of
his jaws.
He swung at him and hit only the head and
the shark looked at him and tore the meat
loose.
The old man swung the club down on him again.
"Come on, galano," the old man said.
"Come in again."
The shark came in and the old man hit him
as he shut his jaws.
He hit him solidly and front as high up as
he could raise the club.
This time he felt the bone at the base of
the brain and he hit him again in the same
place.
The old man watched but neither shark returned.
He did not want to look at the fish.
He knew that half of him had been destroyed.
The sun had gone down while he had been fighting
the sharks.
"It will be dark soon." he said.
"Then I should see the glow of Havana.
If I am too far to the east I will see the
lights of one of the new beaches."
He could not talk to the fish anymore because
the fish had been ruined too badly.
Then something came into his head.
"Half-fish," he said.
"Fish that you were.
I am sorry that went too far out.
I ruined us both.
But we have killed many sharks, you and I,
and ruined many others.
How many did you ever kill, old fish?
You do not have that spear on your head for
nothing."
I have half of him. he thought.
Maybe I'll have the luck to bring the forward
half in.
I should have some luck.
''No," he said.
"You violated your luck when you went too
far outside."
"Don't be silly," he said aloud.
"You may have much luck yet.
I'd like to buy some if there were any place
they sell it," he said.
What could I buy it with? he asked himself.
Could I buy it with a lost harpoon and a broken
knife and two bad hands?
"You might," he said.
"You tried to buy it with eighty-four days
at sea.
They nearly sold it to you too."
He saw the reflected glare of the lights of
the city at what must have been around ten
o'clock at night.
He steered inside of the glow and he thought
that now, soon, he must hit the edge of the
stream.
Now it is over, he thought.
They will probably hit me again.
But what can a man do against them in the
dark without a weapon?
I hope I do not have to fight again, he thought.
But by midnight he fought and this time he
knew the fight was useless.
They came in a pack.
He dubbed desperately at what he could only
feel and hear and he felt something seize
the dub and it was gone.
He jerked the tiller free from the rudder
and beat and chopped with it holding it in
both hands and driving it down again and again.
One came, finally, against the head itself
and he knew that it was over.
He swung the tiller across the shark's head.
He swung it once and twice and again.
The shark let go and rolled away.
That was the last shark of the pack that came.
There was nothing more for them to eat.
The old man could hardly breathe now and he
felt a strange taste in his mouth.
It was coppery and sweet and he was afraid
of it for a moment.
He spat into the ocean and said, "Eat that,
galanos."
He knew he was beaten now finally and without
remedy.
He put the sack around his shoulders and put
the skiff on her course.
He had no thoughts nor any feelings of any
kind.
He only noticed how lightly and how well the
skiff sailed now that there was no great weight
beside her.
He could feel he was inside the current now
and he could see the lights of the beach along
the shore.
When he sailed into the little harbor the
lights of the Terrace were out and he knew
everyone was in bed.
He pulled the boat up and then he stepped
out and tied her to a rock.
He took the mast out of its step and furled
the sail and tied it.
Then he put the mast on his shoulder and started
to climb, it was then that he knew the depth
of his tiredness.
He stopped and looked back and saw the white
naked line of the fish's backbone and the
dark mass of the head with the bill and all
the nakedness in between.
He started to climb again and at the top he
fell and lay for some time with the mast across
his shoulder.
He tried to get up.
But it was too difficult and he sat there
with the mast on his shoulder.
Finally he put the mast down and stood up.
He picked the mast up and put it on his shoulder
and started up the road.
He had to sit down five times before he reached
his shack.
Inside the shack he leaned the mast against
the wall.
In the dark he found a water bottle and took
a drink.
Then he lay down on the bed.
He pulled the blanket over his body and he
slept face down on the newspapers with his
arms out straight and the palms of his hands
up.
He was asleep when the boy looked in the door
in the morning.
The boy saw the old man's hands and he started
to cry.
He went out very quietly to get some coffee
and all the way down the road he was crying.
Many fishermen were around the skiff looking
at what was lashed beside it and one was in
the water, his trousers rolled up, measuring
the skeleton.
The boy did not go down.
He had been there before and one of the fishermen
was looking after the skiff for him.
"How is he?" one of the fishermen shouted.
"Sleeping," the boy called.
He did not care that they saw him crying.
"Let no one disturb him."
"He was eighteen feet from nose to tail,"
the fisherman who was measuring him called.
"I believe it."
the boy said.
He went into the Terrace and asked for a can
of coffee.
"Hot and with plenty of milk and sugar in
it."
"Anything more?"
"No.
Afterwards I will see what he can eat."
"What a fish it was," the proprietor said.
"There has never been such a fish.
Tell him how sorry l am."
"Thanks," the boy said.
The boy carried the hot can of coffee up to
the old man's shack and sat by him until he
woke.
Finally the old man woke.
"Don't sit up," the boy said.
"Drink this."
He poured some of the coffee in a glass.
The old man took it and drank it.
"They beat me, Manolin," he said.
"They truly beat me."
"He didn't beat you.
Not the fish."
"No.
Truly.
It was afterwards."
"Pedrico is looking after the skiff and the
gear.
What do you want done with the head?"
"Let Pedrico chop it up to use in fish traps."
"And the spear?"
"You keep it if you want it."
"I want it," the boy said.
"Now we must make our plans about the other
things."
"Did they search for me?"
"Of course.
With coast guard and with planes."
"The ocean is very big and a skiff is small
and hard to see," the old man said.
He noticed how pleasant it was to have someone
to talk to instead of speaking only to himself
and to the sea.
"I missed you," he said.
"What did you catch?"
"One the first day.
One the second and two the third."
"Very good."
"Now we can fish together again."
"No.
I am not lucky.
I am not lucky anymore."
"The hell with luck," the boy said.
"I'll bring the luck with me."
"What will your family say?"
"I do not care.
I caught two yesterday.
But we will fish together now for I still
have much to learn.
You get your hands well, old man."
"I know how to care for them.
In the night I spat something strange and
felt something in my chest was broken."
"Get that well too," the boy said.
"Lie down, old man.
I will bring you your clean shirt.
And something to eat."
"Bring any of the papers of the time that
I was gone," the old man said.
"You must get well fast for there is much
that I can learn and you can teach me everything.
How much did you suffer?"
"Plenty," the old man said.
"I'll bring the food and the papers," the
boy said.
"Rest well, old man.
I will bring something from the drugstore
for your hands."
As the boy went out the door and down the
road he was crying again.
That afternoon there was a party of tourists
at the Terrace and looking down in the water
among the empty beer cans and dead barracudas
a woman saw a great long white spine with
a huge tail at the end that lifted and swung
with the tide.
"What's that?"
she asked a waiter and pointed to the long
backbone of the great fish that was now just
garbage waiting to go out with the tide.
"Tiburon," the waiter said, "Eshark."
He wanted to explain what had happened.
"I didn't know sharks had such handsome, beautifully
formed tails."
"I didn't either."
her male companion said.
Up the road, in his shack, the old man was
sleeping again.
He was still sleeping on his face and the
boy was sitting by him watching him.
The old man was dreaming about the lions.
- THE END -