PART ONE
CHAPTER ONE
A Warning
A letter arrived for Sherlock Holmes. We were
sitting in our rooms at 221b Baker Street.
'It's Porlock's writing,' he said. 'It must
be very important.'
'Who is Porlock?' I asked.
'Porlock is just a name: it's not his real
one. He is a man who is in touch with the
great criminal mastermind, Professor Moriarty.
You've heard me talk about him?'
'Yes, he's famous among criminals but unknown
to the public.'
That's right. He's the "brain" that controls
all crime; we'll catch him one day, Watson.'
'Anyway, what about this letter and Porlock?'
'He works for Professor Moriarty. He has sent
me information twice before which has helped
to prevent crimes.'
Holmes opened the letter and read it. The
message said that a man called Douglas at
Birlstone Manor House was in great danger.
There was a knock at the door and Inspector
MacDonald of Scotland Yard walked in. Holmes
looked pleased to see him.
'You're out early,' he said.
But the inspector had stopped suddenly. He
was staring at the message.
'Douglas! Birlstone? What's this, Mr Holmes?
Magic? How did you get those names?'
'Why?' asked Holmes. 'What's wrong with those
names?'
'Mr Douglas of Birlstone Manor House was murdered
this morning.'
Sherlock Holmes explained to the inspector
how he had just received the letter.
'I was on my way to Birlstone,' said the inspector.
'I came to ask if you and Doctor Watson wanted
to come with me but, from what you say about
this Porlock, we'll find out more in London.'
'I don't think so,' said Holmes.
'Well, if there's a man in London who knew
about the crime before it happened, then we
need to find him!'
'And how do you suggest we find Porlock?'
asked Holmes. 'I don't know him, I've never
seen him, I don't know where he is and, what's
more, I know that Professor Moriarty is involved.
We'll find nothing in London, MacDonald, we
must go to Birlstone to solve this crime.'
The inspector stood up.
'Let's go. Can you be ready in five minutes?'
On our way down to Birlstone, the inspector
told us what he knew about the case, which
was not very much. John Douglas of Birlstone
Manor House was shot in the head with a shotgun.
It happened at around midnight the night before.
The police had not yet arrested anyone.
Birlstone was a small village in Sussex. About
half a mile from the village was the Manor
House of Birlstone. It was a very old house,
built in the seventeenth century. A moat surrounded
the house. The only way to get into the house
was over the drawbridge. This drawbridge was
raised every night and lowered every morning
by the owners of the Manor House. This meant
that the house was like an island during the
night. This was a very important fact in the
mystery at Birlstone.
The owners were Mr John Douglas and his wife.
Douglas was a handsome American man about
fifty years old. He was popular in the village
because he was friendly and also rich. He
had earned his money in California, then came
to live in England, where he met his wife.
Mrs Douglas was a beautiful woman, about twenty
years younger than her husband. They were
very happy together, although it seemed that
Mrs Douglas did not know everything about
her husband's past.
There was one other person who often stayed
with the couple and was also at the Manor
House at the time of the murder. His name
was Cecil Barker. He was a good friend of
John Douglas and was the only person from
Douglas's unknown past life. Although Barker
was English, he had met John Douglas in America.
Barker was friendly with both Douglas and
his wife. Sometimes his friendship with Mrs
Douglas seemed to irritate John Douglas. The
other people who were in the house at the
time of the murder were Ames the butler and
Mrs Allen the housekeeper.
It was at eleven forty-five at night on 6th
January that Cecil Barker told Sergeant Wilson
at the local police station that someone had
murdered Mr John Douglas.
When he reached the house, Sergeant Wilson
found the drawbridge down and everyone was
confused and alarmed. Only Cecil Barker seemed
calm and in control.
The dead man was in the center of the room,
lying on his back. The shotgun was lying on
his chest; the end of the gun was sawn off.
The murderer had fired the gun very close
to his victim and the shot had almost blown
his head to pieces. The doctor was called
but he knew there was nothing he could do.
The country policeman was not used to such
serious crime.
'We won't touch anything until the officers
from London arrive,' he said.
'I haven't touched anything,' said Cecil Barker.
'This is exactly as I found it. It was just
after half past eleven and I was sitting in
my bedroom when I heard the shot. It wasn't
very loud. I rushed down.'
'Was the door open?'
'Yes, it was open. Douglas was lying just
as you see him now. There was a candle burning
on the table. I lit the lamp.'
'Did you see anyone?'
'No, I heard Mrs Douglas coming down the stairs
behind me and I rushed out to stop her from
seeing this terrible sight.'
'But wasn't the drawbridge raised as usual?'
'Yes, it was up until I lowered it,' said
Barker.
'Then how could the murderer have got away?'
'Look.' Barker pulled back the curtain. One
of the windows was wide open. 'Look at this.'
He pointed to a blood stain that was shaped
like a footprint. 'Someone has climbed out
here.'
'You think that someone waded across the moat?'
'Exactly.'
'Well, you were in the room half a minute
after the murder, so this means that he was
in the water then.'
'I know. I didn't know the window was open
because it was hidden by the curtain.'
The policeman was thinking.
'You're saying that the man escaped by wading
across the moat. But how did he get into the
house if the drawbridge was up?
'That's a good question,' agreed Barker.
CHAPTER TWO
Murder at Birlstone
'What time was the bridge raised?' asked the
policeman.
'It was six o'clock,' said Ames the butler.
'Mrs Douglas had visitors so I raised it after
they left.'
'So if anyone came in from outside - if they
did - then they came into the house before
six and hid there until Mr Douglas came into
the room at about eleven o'clock.'
'That's right. Mr Douglas always checked all
the lights in the house before he went to
bed. He came in here, where the man was waiting
to shoot him. Then the murderer got away through
the window and left the gun behind. That's
what I think.'
The policeman picked up a card which was lying
on the floor beside the dead man. The initials
V.V. and the number 341 were written on the
card.
'What's this?' asked the policeman.
Barker looked at it.
'I didn't notice it before. The murderer probably
left it behind.'
'V.V. 341. What does it mean? Somebody's initials,
maybe.'
The policeman walked slowly around the room.
He pulled back a window curtain. 'Look at
this!' he said excitedly. 'Someone was hiding
here, look at these muddy footprints.'
'What's this mark on his arm?' asked the doctor.
On the dead man's right arm was a strange
brown design: a triangle inside a circle.
'It's not a tattoo,' said the doctor. 'I've
never seen anything like it. This mark has
been burnt onto the man. What does it mean?'
'I don't know what it means but Douglas has
had that mark for at least ten years,' said
Cecil Barker.
'Yes,' agreed the butler. 'I've often noticed
it and wondered what it is.'
'Then it has nothing to do with the crime
anyway,' said the policeman.
The butler suddenly gave a shout of surprise.
'What is it now?' said the policeman.
'They've taken his wedding ring! He always
wore his wedding ring below this other one
with the snake on it,' said the butler.
'You mean that the murderer first took off
this snake ring, then the wedding ring and
afterwards put the snake ring back on again?'
'It looks that way,' said the butler.
The policeman shook his head. 'The sooner
the London police get here the better,' he
said.
The Chief Detective for Sussex was Mr Mason.
He was waiting for us at the railway station
in Birlstone the next day.
'A very interesting case, MacDonald,' he said.
He took us to our hotel. We sat down and Mason
told us the details. Sherlock Holmes listened
carefully.
'So what have you discovered so far?' he said
when Mason had finished.
'I examined the shotgun,' said Mason. 'The
gun wasn't very long and could easily be hidden
under a coat. It was made in America. The
butler says he has never seen it in the house
before. It suggests that the stranger who
entered the house and killed Douglas is American.'
MacDonald shook his head.
'I've heard nothing that proves that a stranger
was even in the house.'
'What about the open window, the blood by
the window, the muddy footprints?'
'They are all things which can be set up.
The business with the ring and the card suggests
premeditated murder for a private reason.
But why would the murderer choose such a noisy
weapon if he wanted to get away unnoticed?
What do you think, Holmes?'
'It does seem strange,' agreed Holmes. 'Can
we go to the house now? There may be some
clues that will help us,' he added.
We walked through the village towards Birlstone
Manor. Sergeant Wilson was still there.
'Anything new?' Mason asked the policeman.
'No, sir.'
'Then go home. You're tired. The butler can
wait outside. Tell Cecil Barker and Mrs Douglas
we want to talk to them in a short while.
Now, I'll tell you what I think so far. I
think it's murder. The question is, was it
done by someone from outside or inside the
house? It doesn't seem likely that it was
someone inside the house: they did it at a
time when the house was quiet but no one was
asleep, and used the noisiest weapon possible,
which hasn't been seen inside the house before.
So we come back to the theory that it was
done by someone from the outside.'
Holmes nodded in agreement.
'So, the man gets into the house sometime
between four thirty and six. He hid behind
the curtain until about eleven, when Douglas
entered the room. If the two men spoke, then
it was not for long. Mrs Douglas said her
husband had left her only a few minutes before
she heard the shot.'
'The candle shows that. It's a new candle
but it has only burnt down a little,' said
Holmes.
'Exactly. That means he put it on the table
before he was attacked. This shows he wasn't
attacked as soon as he entered the room. When
Barker arrived, the candle was lit and the
lamp was out.'
'That all seems clear,' said Holmes.
'So Douglas enters the room. He puts down
the candle. A man appears from behind the
curtain with a gun. He asks for the wedding
ring - we don't know why but it seems so.
Mr Douglas gives it to him. Then the man shoots
Douglas. He drops the gun and this card "V.V.
341", whatever that means, and then escapes
through the window and across the moat, just
as Cecil Barker discovers the crime. How does
that sound, Mr Holmes?'
'Interesting, but not very believable,' said
Holmes.
'What's your theory then, Holmes?'
'I'd like a few more facts before I come up
with a theory,' said Holmes. 'Ames, can you
come in here for a moment please?'
The butler came in. 'Now, you've seen this
mark on Mr Douglas's arm before?'
'Often, sir,' agreed Ames.
'There is also a small piece of plaster on
Mr Douglas's chin. Did you see that when he
was alive?' asked Holmes.
'Yes sir, he cut himself shaving yesterday
morning,' said Ames.
'Did he often cut himself shaving?' asked
Holmes.
'Not for a very long time, sir.'
'Interesting!' said Holmes. 'This might mean
he was nervous and knew that he was in danger.
Did you notice anything unusual in his behavior
yesterday, Ames?'
'He did seem a bit nervous, sir,' said the
butler.
'So, perhaps the attack wasn't unexpected
then. Now, what about the card - V.V. 341.
What do you think that means, MacDonald?'
'It seems like a secret society of some sort.
I thought the same about the mark on the arm.'
'Someone from a secret society gets into the
house, kills Mr Douglas and leaves this card.
The newspapers will report it, so other members
of the society will know that vengeance has
been done. But why this gun? Why the missing
ring? Why has no one been arrested yet?'
Holmes walked over to the window and examined
the blood stain.
'It's a footprint but it looks very wide to
me, wider than the other footprints over in
the corner. What's this under the table?'
asked Holmes, bending to pick up the object.
'Mr Douglas's dumbbells,' said Ames.
'Dumbbell,' corrected Holmes. 'There's only
one of them. Where's the other?'
'I don't know, Mr Holmes. Perhaps there was
only one. I haven't noticed them for months.'
Holmes looked serious. 'One dumbbell...' He
was interrupted by a knock on the door. Cecil
Barker came in.
'Sorry to interrupt,' he said, 'but they've
found his bicycle. The man left it behind.
Come and look.'
CHAPTER THREE
The People of the Drama
The bicycle was hidden behind some bushes.
'Well, it's something,' said Mason. 'But why
has the man left it behind? How did he get
away without it? We are no closer to solving
this mystery, Holmes.'
'Aren't we?' answered Holmes thoughtfully.
We moved to the dining room to hear evidence
from the people who were in the house at the
time of the murder. Ames the butler told us
what he had heard and seen. He had not heard
the shot because he was at the back of the
house in the kitchen. He heard the ringing
of the bell which called for the servants
of the house. He and the housekeeper went
to the front of the house together. When they
got to the bottom of the stairs, Mrs Douglas
was coming down. She was not hurrying and
she did not seem agitated. Then Mr Barker
came rushing out of the study telling Mrs
Douglas to go back.
'Go back to your room! John is dead! There
is nothing you can do! Please go back to your
room!'
Mrs Douglas did as he said. She did not scream.
The housekeeper went with her. Barker and
the butler went into the study, where they
found everything just as the police had seen
it. The candle was not lit at that time but
the lamp was. They looked out of the window
but it was very dark and they had seen and
heard nothing. The housekeeper said that Mrs
Douglas had been scared but had not tried
to go downstairs. The housekeeper stayed with
her that night.
Cecil Barker was next. He told the police
his theory about the murder. There were some
events in Douglas's life that he never spoke
about. Barker had met Douglas, who was a widower
at the time, in California. They ran a successful
mining company together. Douglas had suddenly
sold his share and gone to England. Afterwards,
Barker also sold his share and went to England
where he and John Douglas met again. Barker
thought that Douglas was in some danger. He
thought that a secret society was after John
and wanted to kill him.
'How long were you together in California?'
asked MacDonald.
'Five years altogether,' said Barker.
'And he was a widower, you said? Do you know
where his first wife was from?' he asked.
'No, but I saw a picture of her. She was a
very beautiful woman. She died the year before
I met him.'
'Was there anything strange about him in California?'
Only that he didn't like to be near other
men. That's why I thought someone was after
him. I think he had a warning of some sort,
that's why he left so suddenly for Europe.
Only a few days after he left, some men were
asking about him,' said Barker.
That was six years ago. Before that you were
together for five years in California. Eleven
years is a long time to keep a fight going.
It was definitely something serious. Did you
know Mrs Douglas before the marriage?'
'No, I didn't.'
'But you've seen a lot of her since?'
'What are you saying, detective? I've seen
a lot of him since. And so of course I have
become friends with Mrs Douglas.'
'Was Mr Douglas happy about your friendship
with his wife?'
'You have no right to ask such questions!'
said Barker angrily.
The inspector waited.
'Well, I suppose you have to do your job.
Please don't ask Mrs Douglas about this. She
is worried enough. Douglas had just one fault
and that was his jealousy. But no man had
a more loving and faithful wife or a more
loyal friend.'
'But the fact that the wedding ring has gone
suggests that the marriage and the murder
are connected, don't you think?'
'I don't know what it suggests,' said Barker,
'but I think you're on the wrong track.'
The next witness was Mrs Douglas. She was
a tall, beautiful woman of thirty. Her face
was very white but she seemed calm. 'Have
you found anything out yet?' she asked.
'We are doing all we can, Mrs Douglas. Perhaps
you may be able to help us. Mr Barker said
that you were never actually in the room where
the tragedy took place.'
'That's right. He told me to go back to my
room.'
'You have only known your husband in England,
is that right?'
'Yes, we've been married for five years.'
'Have you heard him speak of something that
happened in America which may be dangerous
for him?'
Mrs Douglas thought carefully before answering.
'Yes,' she said finally. 'I have always felt
that there was some sort of danger from his
past, but he didn't talk to me about it.'
'How did you know then?' asked the detective.
'In many ways,' she replied. 'Because of the
way he didn't talk about some parts of his
life in America. Because of some of the things
he said. The way he looked at strangers. I
always felt sure that he had some powerful
enemies and that he was always ready to defend
himself.'
'What sort of things did he say?' asked Sherlock
Holmes.
'"The Valley of Fear",' replied Mrs Douglas.
'He said, ''I have been in the Valley of Fear
and I'm not out of it yet." I asked him, "Can
we ever get out of the Valley of Fear?" and
he said very seriously, "Sometimes I don't
think we ever will".'
'But didn't you ask him what he meant by "the
Valley of Fear"?'
'Of course, but he never told me. All I know
is that it was a real valley that he lived
in once where something terrible happened.
I can't tell you anymore.'
'Did he ever mention any names?'
'Yes, once, when he had a fever, he said the
name "Master McGinty". There was definitely
a connection between the Valley of Fear and
Master McGinty.'
'You've heard that his wedding ring was taken;
why do you think that is?'
'I really don't know,' she replied. 'It's
an extraordinary thing.'
'Well, we won't keep you any longer. Thank
you for your time, Mrs Douglas. If there is
anything else, we can ask you later.'
Mrs Douglas left the room.
'She's a very beautiful woman,' said MacDonald
thoughtfully. 'This man Barker has been here
a lot. There may be something between them.
He admits that the dead man was jealous. Then
there's that wedding ring. What do you think,
Mr Holmes?'
CHAPTER FOUR
The Missing Dumbbell
Holmes called the butler in.
'Can you remember, Ames, what Mr Barker was
wearing on his feet when you joined him in
the study?'
'Yes, Mr Holmes. He had a pair of bedroom
slippers on. I brought him his boots when
he went for the police.'
'Where are the slippers now?'
'They are still under a chair in the hall.'
'Good. It's important to know which footprints
belong to Mr Barker and which come from outside.'
'Yes, sir. I noticed that the slippers were
marked with blood, sir. So were mine.'
'Thank you, Ames.'
We returned to the study. Holmes brought the
slippers with him from the hall. The slippers
were dark with blood.
'Strange!' said Holmes. He was examining the
slippers by the light of the window. 'Very
strange indeed!'
He placed the slipper on the blood stain under
the window. It matched exactly. Holmes looked
at the others.
MacDonald looked excited. 'Barker made the
mark under the window himself! What's going
on Holmes? What does it mean?'
'That's the question,' said Holmes. 'What
does it mean?'
The three detectives had many small details
to investigate. I decided to return to the
village on my own. I walked through the garden
of the house. At the far end was a hedge of
yew trees. Behind these was a stone seat,
hidden from view. As I approached, I heard
some voices coming from the area of the stone
seat. I came around the trees and saw Mrs
Douglas and Mr Barker. They did not see me
straight away. I was shocked by Mrs Douglas's
appearance. Before, she had been very quiet.
Now her eyes were shining and she was laughing
at something Barker had just said. Barker
was also smiling. Just too late they both
saw me and assumed more serious expressions.
They spoke briefly to each other, then Barker
got up and walked towards me.
'Excuse me sir, but are you Doctor Watson?
Mrs Douglas wants to ask you something.'
I did not really want to talk to her. I saw
clearly in my mind the body of the dead man
lying on the floor. Here, only a few hours
after the tragedy, was his wife laughing with
another man. But I went over to them.
'You're a good friend of Mr Holmes. Tell me,'
she asked, 'if I told him something, does
he have to tell the detectives? Is he working
on his own or is he with them?'
'Mr Holmes is independent,' I replied, 'but
he won't hide anything from the detectives.
You must ask Holmes himself.'
I left them and continued walking.
When I told Holmes what had happened, he said
that he did not want to hear anything from
them.
'It can get complicated if we have to make
an arrest for murder,' he said.
'Why, have you solved it, Holmes?'
'Oh, not yet, but when we find the missing
dumbbell-'
'The dumbbell?'
'Watson, you must realize how important that
missing dumbbell is! What use is one dumbbell?'
He continued talking.
'A lie, Watson - that's what we have here.
A great big lie. Barker's story is a lie and
Mrs Douglas is helping him. They are both
lying. So why are they lying and what is the
truth that they are trying to hide?'
'How can you be so sure they're lying?' I
asked.
'Because it simply can't be true! According
to their story, the murderer had less than
a minute after the murder to take the wedding
ring, which was under another ring, then to
replace the other ring and put the card by
the victim. This is impossible. I don't think
that the ring was taken before the victim
was killed. The candle was lit for only a
short time. I think the murderer was alone
with the dead man for some time with the lamp
lit. But the gunshot was the cause of death:
therefore the gun was fired much earlier than
we have been told. So the two people who heard
the gunshot, Mr Barker and Mrs Douglas, are
obviously both lying for some reason. And
now we can also show that Barker put the footprint
under the window. It doesn't look good for
Barker.'
'So what time did the murder actually occur?
The housekeeper said she heard a noise at
about quarter to eleven, about half an hour
before Barker called them. I think that this
was the gunshot and the real time of the murder.
If I'm correct, what were Mr Barker and Mrs
Douglas doing, if they aren't the actual murderers,
from a quarter to eleven when they heard the
shot, to a quarter past eleven when they rang
the bell for the servants?'
'I'm sure there is something going on between
those two,' I agreed. 'Do you think that they
are guilty of the murder?' I asked.
'I think that Mr Barker and Mrs Douglas know
the truth about this murder. I'm not sure
that they are the murderers themselves. I
think that an evening alone in the study will
help a lot. Can I borrow your umbrella please,
Watson?'
I was confused, but I gave him my umbrella
anyway.
Later that evening, Inspector MacDonald and
Mr Mason returned. They had found out more
about the owner of the bicycle: he was an
American who was staying at a hotel in the
nearby town of Tunbridge Wells. According
to the people at the hotel he was a tall,
handsome man of about fifty. He was dressed
in a grey suit and a short yellow coat and
cap.
'He sounds very similar to Mr Douglas,' remarked
Holmes.
Holmes told the detectives about his theories
and what he intended to do that evening. The
detectives asked if they could help.
'No, no,' said Holmes. 'All I need is darkness
and Watson's umbrella.'
CHAPTER FIVE
The Mystery is Solved
The next morning, the detectives were trying
to find the owner of the bicycle.
'Any luck?' asked Holmes.
'Well, so far, we have reports of a man in
a yellow coat in Leicester, Nottingham, Southampton
and Liverpool. The country seems to be full
of people in yellow coats,' replied MacDonald.
'What about you? Did you find out anything
last night?'
'I can't really tell you at the moment. However,
I have found out that Charles I was once hidden
in this house for several days during the
Civil War,' said Holmes.
'I don't see what that has to do with this
case,' said Mason.
'Well, I want to give you both some advice.
I can't tell you everything that I know yet,
but my advice to you is to abandon the case
for today. Meet me here this evening and things
will become clear.'
The detectives were not very happy about this
but eventually agreed.
'One more thing, I want you to write a letter
to Mr Barker. Write this down. "Dear Sir,
we have decided to drain the moat in the hope
that we may find some-"'
MacDonald interrupted. 'It's impossible. We've
already made inquiries.'
'"- in the hope that we may find something
which will help in the case. I have made arrangements
and the workmen will begin tomorrow morning."
Now sign that and deliver it this afternoon.
Then meet me here when it gets dark.'
The detectives were obviously annoyed but
agreed to do as Holmes asked.
Later that evening, Holmes took us outside
into the grounds of the Manor House. We stopped
opposite the windows of the study. 'Now what?'
asked MacDonald.
'We must wait,' said Holmes. 'We need to be
patient.'
We waited and waited.
'What exactly are we waiting for?' asked MacDonald
finally. 'And how much longer do we have to
wait?'
'I don't know how long we'll have to wait
but I can tell you what we are waiting for.
Look - that's what we're waiting for!' As
he spoke, we saw a man open the window of
the study. We heard the splashing of water
as the man searched for something. Then suddenly
we saw him raise a large round object from
the moat and take it into the study.
'Now!' shouted Holmes. 'Now!'
We all jumped to our feet and ran into the
house and into the study: there was Cecil
Barker.
'What do you want?' he said.
'That's what we want,' said Holmes. 'That
package, weighted with the dumbbell that you
have just pulled from the moat.'
'How do you know about it?'
'Well, I put it there,' said Holmes, 'or,
rather, I "replaced" it there after hooking
it out last night with the handle of Watson's
umbrella.'
He opened the package. Inside was a pair of
boots, a grey suit, a yellow coat and a dangerous-looking
knife.
'The label in the coat is from Vermissa, USA.
Earlier today, I found out that Vermissa is
a mining valley. Perhaps the V.V. on the card
might stand for Vermissa Valley and may even
be the Valley of Fear, I think. This seems
clear. Perhaps you could explain further,
Mr Barker?' asked Holmes.
Barker did not know what to say. Eventually
he said, 'Well, if you know such a lot, Holmes,
why don't you tell us?'
Mrs Douglas came in. She had heard everything.
'You have done enough for us, Cecil. Whatever
happens in the future, you have done enough.'
'More than enough,' said Holmes. 'Now I think
it is time to hear the truth from Mr Douglas
himself.'
We were all astonished at Holmes's words.
As he spoke, a man seemed to have come out
from the wall in a dark corner of the room.
Mrs Douglas turned and put her arms around
her husband.
'I'm sure it's best this way, John,' she said.
The man looked at us. He came to me and gave
me a package.
'I've heard of you,' he said. 'Well, Doctor
Watson, you've never heard a story like this
one. Tell it your own way, but these are the
facts. I've been hiding in there for two days
and I've written it all down. This is the
story of the Valley of Fear.'
MacDonald was staring at John Douglas in amazement.
'Well, if you're John Douglas, whose murder
have we been investigating for the past two
days? And where did you just come from?'
'Don't you remember me telling you that Charles
I was once hidden in this house?' Holmes reminded
him. 'When I found the clothes in the moat,
it became clear that the body was not that
of John Douglas, but must be the body of the
cyclist from Tunbridge Wells. So, then I had
to find out where Mr Douglas was hiding.'
'He's right. I won't start at the beginning,'
said John Douglas, 'but there are some men
who won't leave me alone until I'm dead. They
forced me out of America. I wanted to spend
my last years here in peace. I never told
my wife how things were because I didn't want
to worry her.
'I was in Tunbridge Wells the day before these
events, and I saw a man in the street who
I recognised immediately. He was my worst
enemy, so I knew that there was trouble coming.
I came home and prepared myself. All day I
was nervous but when the drawbridge was up
I felt safe. Then, when I was checking the
lights before going to bed, I saw his boot
under the curtain. I put down the candle and
he jumped out at me and got the gun from under
his coat. We were fighting and I was trying
to take the gun out of his hands before he
could fire.
'Maybe it was me that pulled the trigger or
maybe it just went off in the fight. Anyway,
he took the shot full in the face. I was looking
at all that was left of Ted Baldwin. I was
in shock when I heard Barker and my wife coming.
I ran to the door and stopped her. We thought
that the servants would be there any minute.
But they didn't come. They hadn't heard anything.
That was when I thought of the plan.
'The man has the same mark as I have, the
mark of the lodge. He was also about the same
height and size as me. His face was unrecognizable.
We tied his clothes to the dumbbell and threw
them out of the window. Then we put my clothes
on him. The card that was meant for my body
was lying by his and we put my ring on his
finger. I didn't want to part with my wedding
ring, but as you can see, I can't get it off
anyway. I put a plaster on his chin where
I have one myself at the moment.
'I thought that if I could hide for a while,
we might, at last, have a chance to live the
rest of our lives in peace. So, I hid in the
hiding place and Barker did what he had to
do. He made the mark by the window and then,
when everything was fixed, he rang the bell
for the servants. That's the truth.'
Holmes looked serious. 'I don't think this
story is over yet, Mr Douglas. I see trouble
ahead.'
And now, let us go back twenty years in time
and travel thousands of miles to the west,
so that I can tell you the beginning of this
terrible story of John Douglas. And then,
we will meet in the rooms of Baker Street
once more to hear how it ends.
PART TWO
CHAPTER ONE
Vermissa
It was 4th February, 1875. It was evening
and the train was travelling to Vermissa,
U.S.A., the small town at the top of the valley.
The train was full of miners, who had been
working all day. In the first carriage there
were also two policemen and one other young
man sitting alone.
He was about thirty years old, with brown
hair and grey eyes. He stared out of the window
into the darkness. At one point, he took a
large gun from his pocket. It was loaded.
He checked it quickly then replaced it, but
a miner sitting near him had noticed it.
'Oh!' he said. 'You seem ready for action.'
The young man smiled. 'Yes,' he said, 'we
need them sometimes where I come from.'
'And where's that?' asked the miner.
'Chicago,' answered the young man.
'You might find that you need it here too.'
'Is that right?' asked the young man, surprised.
'I'm looking for work here.'
'Do you have friends here?'
'No', but I can make them,' answered the young
man. 'I belong to the Ancient Order of Freemen.
There's no town without a lodge so I'll find
my friends there.'
The other man's manner changed. He got up,
came over to sit next to the young man and
held out his hand. The two men shook hands
in a special way.
'I see you're telling the truth,' said the
miner. Then he raised his right hand to his
right eyebrow. The young traveller raised
his left hand to his left eyebrow.
'Dark nights are unpleasant,' said the miner.
'Yes, for strangers to travel,' answered the
young man.
'That's good enough for me. I'm Brother Scanlan,
Lodge 341, Vermissa Valley. Welcome.'
'Thank you. I'm Brother Jack McMurdo, Lodge
29, Chicago, Master, J. H. Scott. I'm lucky
to meet a brother so early.'
'But why did you leave Chicago?' asked the
miner.
McMurdo nodded towards the policemen.
'They'd be very interested to know,' he said.
'But I don't really want to talk about it.
I've my own good reason for leaving Chicago.'
'Okay. Where are you going tonight?'
'To Vermissa.'
'That's the third stop. Where are you staying?'
'With Jacob Shafter, Sheridan Street.'
'Well, I'm getting off at the next stop. But
I'll give you some advice. If you're in trouble
in Vermissa, go and see Master McGinty. Maybe
we'll meet at the lodge one evening.' The
train stopped and the miner got off.
The train moved off.
'You're new around here then?' one of the
policemen asked McMurdo.
'What if I am?' he answered rudely.
'Just be careful who you choose to be your
friends. I wouldn't start with Mike Scanlan
and his gang if I were you.'
'What business is it of yours who my friends
are?' shouted McMurdo. Everyone looked round
at him. 'Did I ask for your advice?' The two
policemen were shocked.
'No offence, stranger. It was a warning, seeing
that you're new here.'
'I'm new here but I'm not new to you and your
kind,' shouted McMurdo. 'You're all the same,
giving your advice when nobody asks for it!'
'Well. We'll probably be seeing more of you
by the sound of it,' said one of the policemen.
'You're a troublemaker if ever I saw one!'
'I'm not afraid of you!' cried McMurdo. 'My
name's Jack McMurdo and if you want me, I'm
staying at Jacob Shafter's at Sheridan Street,
Vermissa, so I'm not hiding from you, am I?'
A few minutes later the train stopped at Vermissa
station and McMurdo and many of the other
workers got off the train. McMurdo was about
to walk off when one of the miners stopped
him.
'You really know how to talk to the police,'
he said admiringly. 'I'm passing by Shafter's
place. Let me carry your bag and I'll show
you where it is.'
Many of the other miners said goodnight as
they left. Before he had even arrived in the
town, Jack McMurdo had a reputation in Vermissa.
The two men walked along.
'That's the Union House,' said the miner pointing
to one of the bigger buildings. 'Jack McGinty
is the boss there.'
'What's he like?'
'Haven't you heard of him? He's been in the
papers often enough because of the Scowrers.'
'The Scowrers? Aren't they a group of murderers?'
asked McMurdo. 'Sssh!' cried the miner. 'You
won't last long here if you talk like that,
on the street so that anyone can hear you.
There are murders but McGinty's name mustn't
be connected with them. He hears everything.
Now, here's Jacob Shafter's house.'
'Thanks,' said McMurdo. He knocked on the
door.
It was opened by a beautiful young woman.
She was blonde with dark eyes. McMurdo stared
at her, lost for words.
She spoke first. 'I thought it was Father,'
she said. 'Are you looking for him? He'll
be back soon.'
'I'm in no hurry,' said McMurdo at last. 'But
I'm looking for a place to stay and your house
was recommended to me.'
'Well then come in, sir. I'm Ettie Shafter,
Mr Shafter's daughter. My mother's dead, so
I run the house. You can wait by the fire
for my father. Ah, here he is now.'
An old man walked slowly up the path. The
two men talked and Jack McMurdo agreed to
pay seven dollars a week to stay with them.
McMurdo quickly became popular at the Shafter's
house. Within a few days everyone knew who
he was and they liked and respected him. He
had also fallen in love with Shafter's daughter
Ettie and told her so everyday. He was determined
to marry her even though she told him that
she had already promised to marry someone
else.
CHAPTER TWO
Meeting Boss McGinty
One evening, Mike Scanlan came to see McMurdo.
'McMurdo, why haven't you been to introduce
yourself to Master McGinty?' he asked.
'I had to find a job,' replied McMurdo. 'I'm
working as a bookkeeper now.'
Scanlan seemed worried.
'But you have to see Boss McGinty,' he said.
'The lodge isn't the same here as it is in
Chicago. Go tonight.'
But someone else wanted to talk to McMurdo
that evening Mr Shafter called McMurdo into
his room and asked him about his feelings
for Ettie, his daughter.
'It's no good, McMurdo,' said the old man.
'Someone has got there before you.'
'Yes, Ettie told me so, but she won't tell
me his name. So who is it?' said McMurdo.
'It's one of the Scowrers,' said Shafter.
'His name is Teddy Baldwin.'
'Who are these Scowrers? Why are you all so
afraid of them?'
'The Scowrers are the Ancient Order of Freemen,'
replied the old man.
'But I belong to that order myself,' said
McMurdo.
'You! I wouldn't have let you into my house
if I had known that!'
'But why? The Order is for charity and friendship,
the rules say so.'
'Maybe in some places but not here,' said
the old man. 'Here they are a group of murderers.
It's bad enough that I have one of these people
coming after my Ettie and that I cannot say
no to him. I won't have another one staying
in my house. You must leave!'
McMurdo went to see Ettie.
'If I had been first Ettie, would I have had
a chance?' he asked her.
Ettie started crying. 'Things would have been
very different if you'd been the first,' she
cried.
'We can't be together because of a promise
to someone you don't love? That's wrong, Ettie.'
'But I'm afraid of him, Jack, both for myself
and my father. Can't we go away together somewhere
else? We can take Father with us!'
'I can't take you away, I can't leave here
yet. But I promise you, no harm will come
to you or your father. But you may find that
I am as bad as other men, Ettie,' said Jack.
'Oh no, Jack. I trust you,' replied the girl.
The door opened suddenly and a handsome young
man walked in. Ettie jumped to her feet looking
alarmed.
'I'm glad to see you, Mr Baldwin. You're early.
Please sit down.'
Mr Baldwin did not sit down. 'Who's he?' he
demanded.
Ettie explained that McMurdo was staying with
them.
'Well, McMurdo, this young lady is mine. Perhaps
she told you.'
'No, I didn't know there was anything between
you.'
'Well, you know now,' replied Baldwin. 'Perhaps
you're ready for a fight, Mr McMurdo?'
McMurdo jumped up. 'I am!' he cried. 'Come
on, outside!'
'Oh, Jack, Jack, be careful! He'll hurt you!'
cried Ettie.
'Oh, it's "Jack" is it? I see how it is. Well,
I'll sort this out without getting into a
fight.' He rolled up his sleeve and showed
McMurdo a strange mark on his arm. It was
a triangle inside a circle. 'Do you know what
that means?'
'I don't know and I don't care!'
'Well, you will know, I promise you that.
Perhaps Miss Ettie can tell you about it.
And you, girl, you'll come back to me, do
you hear?' He turned and left the house.
McMurdo decided to go straight down to the
Union House and introduce himself to Boss
McGinty, whose bar was crowded as usual. Boss
McGinty was not an honest man and he was getting
richer and richer. As a councilor, he controlled
taxes, roadwork's and various accounts for
the area. The citizens of Vermissa were blackmailed
into silence, scared that they might be killed.
McMurdo went into the bar. He saw a tall,
strong, heavy looking man with black hair
and a beard who had to be McGinty. He looked
friendly, but he had evil eyes. McMurdo walked
up to the man, looked him in the eye and introduced
himself. He made a signal so that McGinty
would know he was also a Freeman.
McGinty looked surprised, but then he took
McMurdo to a back room. He sat down and, without
saying a word, examined McMurdo carefully.
For a couple of minutes he sat in silence.
Then, suddenly, he pulled out a gun.
'If this is a game of yours, it won't last
long,' said McGinty dangerously.
'That is a strange welcome from one brother
to another,' replied McMurdo calmly.
'That's just what you have to prove - that
you really are a brother!'
McGinty then asked him some details about
where he was made a Freeman and the reason
why he had left Chicago. McMurdo gave him
a page from a newspaper. McGinty read it quickly;
it was about the shooting of a man called
Jonas Pinto in the Lake Bar in Chicago in
January 1874.
'Did you shoot this man?' asked McGinty. 'Why?'
'I was making fake dollars. This man Pinto
was helping me; then he said he wanted to
go to the police. Maybe he did but I didn't
wait to see. I just shot him and came down
here.'
'So can you still make these fake dollars?'
asked McGinty. McMurdo gave him a handful
of notes. 'Well, these aren't real,' he said.
At this moment, Ted Baldwin walked in.
'So, you got here first, McMurdo,' he said
angrily.
Boss McGinty wanted to know what the problem
was. McMurdo told him about Ettie.
'She's free to choose for herself,' he finished.
'Between two brothers of the lodge, she certainly
is,' agreed McGinty.
'And that's your answer?' shouted Ted Baldwin.
'You've known me for years and now you take
the side of this newcomer?'
McGinty jumped on him like a tiger. He grabbed
his neck and threw him across the room.
'While I'm the Master of this lodge, you had
better accept my rules,' he shouted.
Ted Baldwin nodded.
'So we're all friends, right?' said McGinty.
'And there's an end to the matter.'
Ted Baldwin was back on his feet. He nodded
again but he did not look happy.
CHAPTER THREE
Lodge 341, Vermissa
The next day, McMurdo moved from Jacob Shafter's
and went to stay with Mrs MacNamara, who was
a widow. Scanlan now also worked in Vermissa
and so he stayed at the same house. McMurdo
was still allowed to go for meals with the
Shafters, so his relationship with Ettie continued
to develop.
One Saturday night, McMurdo was made a full
brother of the lodge in Vermissa. He was warned
that something might happen to him but he
did not know what it was. Many men had gathered
for the ceremony. McMurdo was tied up and
blindfolded. Then they took off his coat and
rolled up the sleeve on his right arm.
It was very dark and McMurdo could hear the
voices of the men around him. Then he heard
Boss McGinty's voice.
'Jack McMurdo, are you a member of the Ancient
Order of Freemen?' McMurdo nodded.
'Are you from Lodge No. 29, Chicago?' Again
McMurdo nodded.
'Are you ready to be tested?' asked McGinty.
'I am,' replied McMurdo.
'Very well.'
McMurdo wanted to cry out because of the terrible
pain in his arm. He felt faint but he bit
his lip and he did not cry out.
'I can take more than that,' he said. There
was loud applause. 'I welcome you to Lodge
341, Vermissa. Let's drink to our new brother!'
said McGinty.
McMurdo took off his blindfold and examined
his arm. There was a circle with a triangle
in it, burnt deep and red onto his arm.
'So, now to business,' said McGinty. 'How
is our bank balance?'
And so McMurdo learnt of the way this community
worked. Small companies gave money to the
Order so that they were protected. If they
did not give money, machinery went wrong,
buildings burnt down and men were murdered.
Nothing could be proved against the Order
as most of the policemen were paid by the
society and the others were too scared to
do anything. Nobody wanted to give evidence
against the Order.
But towards the end of the meeting, another
man spoke. Brother Morris told them of how
one large company had forced - all the smaller
companies out of the valley and bought their
businesses.
'I don't see that it matters to us who has
bought the businesses, Brother Morris,' said
Boss McGinty.
But Brother Morris continued. 'With respect,
sir, I think it will matter very much to us
in the future. If big companies like the Railroad
or General Iron own large parts of this valley,
and their bosses are in New York or Philadelphia,
they won't care about our threats. The small
men can't harm us. They haven't the money
or the power. But if these big companies find
that we are stopping their profits, they won't
stop until they have brought us to justice.'
But McGinty took no notice of Brother Morris.
'I expect the big companies will find it easier
to pay than to fight, the same as the small
companies,' he said. 'And now, let's drink.'
There was one last piece of business to be
sorted out that night. The editor of the local
newspaper, the Herald, had recently printed
an article criticizing the lodge. His name
was James Stanger. The headline was 'Reign
of Terror in the Coal and Iron District'.
McGinty read the article to the men, who were
by now drunk and restless.
'That's what he says about us. Now what shall
we say to him?' he shouted.
'Kill him!' shouted back many voices.
'No, we must be careful. But he must get a
severe warning,' ordered McGinty. 'Who will
go this evening?'
Ted Baldwin volunteered, with five or six
other men.
'Take our new brother with you,' added McGinty.
Baldwin did not look pleased. 'You can come
if you want,' he said to McMurdo.
It was a very cold night. The men walked through
the town and stopped outside a high building.
'You stay down here, McMurdo. Watch the door,'
said Baldwin. 'You others come with me.'
The men went in and up some stairs. From the
room above came a cry for help, then the sound
of crashing chairs. A gray-haired old man
rushed out of the room. He was grabbed before
he could go any further and his glasses came
falling down the stairs to McMurdo's feet.
The old man was on his face and the men hit
him again and again with sticks. The others
stopped, but Baldwin kept attacking the old
man, who was now covered in blood.
McMurdo went up and pulled Baldwin away.
'Leave it! You'll kill the man! The boss said
that we shouldn't kill him and look what you're
doing! We'd better go home.'
The others agreed with McMurdo.
Hurry! said one of the men. 'There are lights
coming on. All the town will be here in a
minute. Run!'
They left the beaten body of the editor on
the stairs and moved quickly away up the streets
and back to their homes.
CHAPTER FOUR
The Valley of Fear
When McMurdo woke up the next morning, his
head ached and his arm was very painful from
the mark. Because he had his own illegal way
of making money, he did not always go to work
and this morning was one of those times. He
sat and read the paper. There was an article
about last night's events. 'Editor Seriously
Injured at the Herald Office' was the headline.
McMurdo put down the newspaper. The landlady
bought him a note. It read 'I want to speak
to you. Meet me on Miller Hill. I have something
important to tell you.' The note was not signed.
McMurdo was surprised but decided to go.
When he got to the hill, Brother Morris was
waiting for him.
'I wanted to ask you something. But please
don't tell Boss McGinty. When you joined the
Freemen's Society did you think that it would
lead you to a life of crime?' he asked.
'If you call it crime,' said McMurdo. 'Some
call it war.'
'Of course it's crime,' cried Morris. 'When
I arrived here, I wanted to do the best for
myself and my family. But then I was forced
to join the lodge and ordered to carry out
a murder. I went but I couldn't do it. But
it made me a criminal. I was a good Catholic
but now the priest will no longer speak to
me. I see you going the same way. Can't we
do anything to stop it?'
'What are you going to do?' asked McMurdo.
'I think you're making too much of this.'
'Too much? Wait until you've been here longer.
Then you'll understand how it is. There is
a cloud over this valley, a cloud of murder.
It is the Valley of Fear, the Valley of Death.
These people are terrified from morning until
night. Wait and you'll see.'
'I'll tell you when I've seen more. You're
not the man for this place, that's clear.
Why don't you sell your business and leave?
What you have said is safe with me. I'm going
now.'
'Just one thing. Perhaps someone has seen
us together. McGinty will want to know what
we're talking about. Tell him that I offered
you a job in my shop.'
'Good thinking. And I refused your offer.
Goodbye Brother Morris.'
The same afternoon, McGinty came to McMurdo's
house and asked why he had been with Morris.
McMurdo told him the story. 'Did Morris say
anything against the lodge?' asked McGinty.
McMurdo told him that he had not. Just as
McGinty was about to leave, the door crashed
open and Captain Marvin of the police walked
in with two other policemen.
'You're coming with me, McMurdo. Take his
gun,' said Marvin.
'What have I done?' asked McMurdo.
'You can't do this,' said McGinty.
'You stay out of this, Councillor,' said the
policeman. Then he turned to McMurdo. 'You
were involved in the beating of Mr Stanger
at the Herald office last night.'
'Well, he can't have been,' said McGinty.
'This man was at my bar all night playing
cards with me.'
'Well, we'll see about that in court,' replied
Marvin. 'Come on, you're coming with me.'
But the Freemen had power even over the courts.
The next morning in court, the witnesses were
uncertain as to the identity of the men who
had attacked Mr Stanger. Stanger himself said
that he was so taken by surprise that he did
not see his attackers. McMurdo was released.
The court was full of brothers who cheered
and applauded. But there were others there
who looked less happy. One man shouted as
they went out, 'You murderers! We'll catch
you yet!'
McMurdo's arrest made him even more popular
in Vermissa. Only Ted Baldwin and a few other
members of the lodge did not like him. But
McMurdo also lost favour with another person
far more important to him: Ettie. Her father
wanted nothing to do with him. Ettie was very
much in love with McMurdo but her common sense
told her that it was better not to marry a
criminal. She decided to go and see him one
last time, to try to get him away from the
evil influence of the lodge.
'But you don't know what you're asking me!
Do you think the lodge will let a man go free
knowing all its secrets?'
'But I've thought of that. Father has some
money saved up and he is ready to leave this
place. Let's go together to New York or Philadelphia.'
'But they have lodges there too. We can't
get away that easily,' said McMurdo.
'Well, to England or Sweden or anywhere to
get away from this Valley of Fear!'
'Look, Ettie, the best I can say is that in
six months or so, I'll find a way so that
we can leave here with no problems.'
'Really? Six months?' Ettie was happy. 'Is
that a promise?'
'I promise,' said McMurdo.
Life in the valley continued as before. The
Scowrers murdered people and terrorized the
district. McMurdo was given a job of his own
to do; he had to blow up the house of a man
named Chester Wilcox. There was no other way
of doing it except at night when his wife
and two small children were also in the house.
McMurdo set the explosives and the house blew
up. However, someone had told Wilcox that
he was in danger, and the night before the
explosion he and his family moved to a safe
place. But in general, life had never seemed
so hopeless and dark in the Valley of Fear.
One Saturday evening in May, Brother Morris
came to see McMurdo again.
'I must speak to you,' he said. 'I spoke to
you once before and you didn't tell McGinty
so I know I can trust you. I have something
to tell you.'
The man was white and shaking. McMurdo gave
him some whisky and waited.
'There's a detective after us,' he said. 'You've
heard of Pinkerton's? When they send a man
after you, they don't stop until they have
what they want. The lodge will be finished.'
'We must kill him,' said McMurdo at once.
'Who is he? Where is he? How do you know about
him? Tell me the facts.'
Morris answered all McMurdo's questions. 'His
name is Birdy Edwards, but here he is using
Steve Wilson as his name. He's staying in
Hobson's Patch. I know because I have a friend
who works for the telegraph service. He told
me about him. Those big corporations have
hired Pinkerton's best man!'
'Leave this to me,' said McMurdo. 'Don't worry.'
McMurdo went to the Shafter's. He told Ettie
the news and asked her if she was willing
to go with him when the time came to leave.
'Day or night, Jack, I'll be ready when you
come for me,' she said.
CHAPTER FIVE
Birdy Edwards's Trap
Later that evening, McMurdo went to the lodge.
As it was Saturday, the brothers were already
there. Jack went to his seat.
'Master,' he said. 'I have urgent news.'
McMurdo told them what he knew and what he
planned to do about it.
'There's only one answer,' said McMurdo.
'Birdy Edwards must never leave the valley,'
said Baldwin. 'Exactly,' agreed McMurdo. 'Here's
what we'll do.'
He told them his plan. Birdy Edwards was pretending
to be a journalist called Steve Wilson. He
had spoken to McMurdo, offering him money
for information on the Scowrers. McMurdo had
told him some stories that he had made up
and Wilson gave him twenty dollars. Wilson
offered him more money for more information.
McMurdo arranged for Wilson to come to his
house so that he could tell him all the secrets
of the lodge in exchange for more money. Wilson
was to come to Mrs MacNamara's house at ten
o'clock. The house was isolated and Mrs MacNamara
did not hear very well. Seven of the other
Freemen were to come to the house at nine
o'clock, ready for Mr Wilson.
'Once we get the door shut behind him, that'll
be the end of Birdy Edwards,' said McMurdo.
McMurdo returned home and prepared for the
evening ahead. He cleaned and oiled his gun.
He spoke to Scanlan who was also staying at
the house. Although he was a Scowrer, Scanlan
did not like what the men did. McMurdo told
him to go out that evening and stay away until
the morning.
The seven Freemen, including Boss McGinty,
arrived at nine o'clock. McMurdo put the whisky
on the table and the men began to drink, ready
for the job that was ahead of them.
'Maybe he won't come, maybe he knows there's
danger,' said one of the men.
'Don't worry, he'll come,' said McMurdo. 'Listen!'
There were three loud knocks on the door.
'Be quiet!' whispered McMurdo to the others.
He went down the passage to the door. The
others heard McMurdo open the door, then an
unfamiliar voice. Then they heard the door
close. Birdy Edwards was inside. The door
opened and McMurdo reappeared. He came to
the end of the table and looked at the men.
He said nothing.
'Well,' said McGinty impatiently, 'is he here?'
'Yes,' replied McMurdo slowly. 'Birdy Edwards
is here. I am Birdy Edwards!'
The room was silent. Then the windows were
suddenly broken and guns were pointing in
through them. McGinty jumped up from his chair
and ran for the door, but Captain Marvin of
the police appeared and pointed his gun at
him.
'Stay where you are, McGinty,' said the man
they had known as McMurdo. 'Take their guns,
Marvin!'
The men could do nothing. They were trapped.
They sat around the table, staring at McMurdo
with confusion and hatred in their eyes.
'I'd like to speak to you before we leave,'
said the man who had trapped them. 'I am Birdy
Edwards of Pinkerton's Detective Agency. I
was chosen to break up your gang. It's taken
me a long time and it's been hard and dangerous,
but I've won! Maybe you think the game isn't
over yet. I'll take my chances. You and sixty
more of you will be in prison tonight. Before
I took this job, I never believed that there
was a society like yours. In Chicago, the
society of Freemen weren't bad men. I never
killed a man in Chicago, I never printed any
false money. I gave Chester Wilcox a warning
so that when I blew up his house, he and his
family were already gone.'
'You traitor!' shouted McGinty.
'You can call me a traitor, but there are
many people in this valley who will call me
a savior. I've been here three months in order
to get to know every man and every secret.
I never want to live another three months
like it, not for all the money in the world.
Now, Captain Marvin, take them away.'
Scanlan had delivered a note to Ettie and
her father. The two left the Valley of Fear
and never went back. Ten days later, Ettie
and Birdy Edwards were married in Chicago.
The trial of the Scowrers was held and McGinty
was hanged, along with eight others. Many
other men went to prison. Birdy Edwards's
job was done.
But, as he had thought, it was not over. Ted
Baldwin was not sentenced to death. He was
in prison for ten years, but when he came
out, he spent all his time looking for Birdy
Edwards. Birdy Edwards changed his name again
and moved to California and it was there that
Ettie Edwards died. He took the name John
Douglas and was nearly killed when he was
working in the mining industry with an English
partner named Barker. A warning came just
in time and Douglas left for England, where
he married for the second time. And so we
return to Sussex, and the fate of John Douglas.
At the trial, John Douglas was freed for having
acted in self-defense. But Holmes's advice
was to leave England.
Two months had gone by and we had nearly forgotten
about the case. But then, one night, a message
arrived for Holmes. All it said was 'Dear
me, Mr Holmes! Dear me!' It was from Moriarty.
Holmes looked very serious. Later that night,
Cecil Barker came to visit us.
'I have very bad news, Mr Holmes,' he said.
'I thought so,' said Holmes.
'It's poor Douglas. They tell me his real
name is Edwards, but he'll always be Douglas
to me. I told you that they left for South
Africa three weeks ago?'
Holmes nodded.
'I received this message from Mrs Douglas
last night: "John has been lost overboard.
No one knows how the accident occurred. Ivy
Douglas".'
'It was no accident,' said Holmes.
'He was murdered? These Scowrers, these criminals,
why couldn't they leave him alone-'
'No, no,' interrupted Holmes. 'There has been
a master at work here. This is the work of
Moriarty.'
'But what has he to do with all this?'
'The Americans had a job to do in England.
Like any other criminals they asked Moriarty
for help. From that moment, John Douglas was
doomed.'
'But what can be done? Can't this Moriarty
be stopped?' asked Barker.
'Oh yes,' said Holmes, 'he can be stopped
- I just need more time.'
- THE END -