CHAPTER ONE
The Earth's climate
Today, the Earth's climate has a huge effect
on the daily lives of all the people in the
world.
It has always had a big effect on life on
Earth, and it had a big effect on how life
started billions of years ago.
So, what is climate?
Climate is the usual weather in a place over
a long time - normally thirty years or more.
Weather can change quickly, and a place can
have very different weather from one day to
the next.
But climate is those weather patterns over
a long time.
On Earth, lots of things have an effect on
the climate - the atmosphere, the oceans,
the land, ice, people, plants and animals,
and the light and heat from the Sun.
The Earth's atmosphere is a thin layer of
gases above the Earth.
The Earth's atmosphere
Most of the atmosphere is nitrogen (N2) and
oxygen (O2), but there are other gases in
the atmosphere, too.
Some of the gases in the atmosphere are called
greenhouse gases because, like the glass in
a greenhouse, they keep the Earth warm.
They do this by stopping some of the Sun's
heat from leaving the Earth.
They are very important because they help
to keep the Earth at the right temperature
for life to grow - not too hot and not too
cold.
Carbon dioxide (CO2) is a very important greenhouse
gas.
Without the greenhouse gases, the Earth would
be very, very cold.
Many scientists study the Earth's atmosphere.
They do this from satellites and from the
land, and their studies show that the amount
of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere is growing.
This is making the temperature on Earth get
warmer, and this warming is having a big effect
on the climate.
We are already seeing the effects of this
all over the world.
Weather patterns are changing; the water in
the oceans is getting warner; snow and ice
are melting in the Arctic and Antarctica;
and sea levels are increasing.
These effects can cause many problems for
the people on Earth, and for the beautiful
plants and animals that live on Earth, too.
They could mean there is not enough food and
water for everyone; they could have a damaging
effect on people's health; and they could
make some people poorer.
We need to act now to stop climate change
and to make a better future for our world.
If we do not act now, we will put the future
of our world in danger.
CHAPTER TWO
A warmer world
Weather stations across the world give us
information about the temperature on the Earth's
surface.
We also get information from ships and buoys
in the oceans.
All this information helps scientists to decide
if the temperature on Earth is going up or
going down.
Information from the last 150 years shows
that the temperature on the Earth's surface
has gone up.
The temperature in some places has increased
more than others, and the warming in the Arctic
is greater than in all other places on Earth.
Some years have always been warmer or colder
than others, and the Earth's climate has changed
a number of times in the past.
This is because natural things can cause the
Earth's temperature to change from one year
to the next, or to change over a longer time.
These things include the amount of heat coming
from the Sun, the effect of volcanoes and
weather patterns like El Nino.
But, for many years, scientists have talked
about climate change and the warming of the
Earth.
Each of the past four decades has been warmer
than the one before.
The information we get from weather stations,
ships and buoys shows that, since the year
2000, the Earth's temperature has been 0.75
degrees Celsius warmer than it was 150 years
ago.
But, in 2015, the temperature became 1 degree
Celsius warmer than 150 years ago.
This is a big increase, and scientists are
worried about it.
Other studies also show that the Earth is
getting warmer.
For example, studies show that the temperature
of the oceans is increasing - from the surface,
right down to the bottom of each ocean.
Other studies show that the amount of snow
and ice on the Earth's surface is getting
smaller.
Melting ice and increasing sea levels
The warming of the Earth is causing the Arctic
sea ice to melt.
In the 2010s, at the end of the summer, the
Arctic sea ice was one third smaller than
at the end of the 20th century.
That's a change of the same size as the UK,
Ireland, France, Spain, Germany and Italy
put together.
When the Arctic sea ice melts, it can change
the weather patterns in Europe, Asia and North
America.
As the Earth gets warmer, the water in the
oceans gets warmer, too.
This makes the water expand get larger.
This makes sea levels increase.
Also, the land ice in Greenland and Antarctica
is melting, and this, too, causes sea levels
to increase.
Studies show that sea levels across the world
are increasing.
When sea levels increase, floods from storms
can be more dangerous for people living near
the sea.
Many of the world's biggest cities, like Shanghai
in China, Jakarta in Indonesia and Mumbai
in India, are very close to the sea.
Higher sea levels put these cities in danger
of floods.
The floods in New York City in 2012 showed
the damage that big storms can do.
These floods caused huge problems for the
people of New York City.
They damaged homes and other buildings, and
many people had no electricity in their homes.
This meant no heat, no light and no way to
cook food or heat water.
The damage caused by big storms can have an
effect for many years and can cost billions
of pounds.
For now, the Thames Barrier on the River Thames
in London protects the city from floods, but,
if sea levels increase, the barrier might
need to be bigger.
And many other cities across the world do
not have anything to protect them from higher
sea levels and the floods they can cause.
The warming of the Earth puts all of these
cities in danger.
In many places, building a barrier like the
Thames Barrier is either not possible or too
expensive.
CHAPTER THREE
The effects of a warmer world
Heatwaves, droughts, floods and storms
Heatwaves, droughts, floods and storms are
all extreme weather.
A heatwave is very hot weather for many days,
and a drought is very little rain for a long
time.
Extreme weather can cause huge damage to buildings
and roads, and to people and animals.
The damage caused by extreme weather can cost
billions of pounds, and many people can lose
their lives.
In 2016, there was an extreme heatwave in
India.
The country had its highest-ever temperature
at 51 degrees Celsius, and many people died.
In Europe in 2003, there was a summer heatwave
that killed tens of thousands of people.
Most of these people were old, because very
hot weather can cause more problems for older
people.
In Australia, there have been many large fires
over the last few years.
In the Australian summer, the land, and the
plants growing on the land, can get very dry.
It is then easy for a fire to start and to
become very large, very quickly.
These fires badly damage people's homes and
other buildings, and many people lose their
lives in the fires.
Since the year 2000, parts of the UK have
had floods again and again, and these floods
have caused huge amounts of damage.
In 2010, there were extreme floods in Pakistan.
These floods had a terrible effect on 20 million
people in the country.
Many people lost their lives, and even more
people lost their homes.
It takes a huge amount of time and money to
help people after damaging weather like this.
All over the world, we are seeing patterns
of extreme weather.
Many places are having their highest-ever
temperatures, and other places are having
more rain than ever before.
The effects of this extreme weather are very
dangerous for all the living things in our
world.
The number of heatwaves, droughts, floods
and storms we are seeing is increasing in
many places.
Extreme weather is now becoming normal for
many people.
There has always been extreme weather, but
studies show that climate change has increased
the risk of extreme weather.
A warmer world increases the risk of Europe
having a big heatwave, for example.
Studies on the floods in the UK show that
the risk of extremely heavy rain is greater
because of climate change, and this has made
the risk of floods in this part of the world
higher.
One reason for this is because a warmer atmosphere
can hold more water, so the rain is heavier
and the risk of floods is greater.
The effects on people and where they live
Climate change can also have an effect on
our food and water, and on our health.
All over the world, we grow food on farms.
Much of the food we buy at supermarkets starts
its life in a field or on a farm.
But the food we grow needs the weather to
be just right - not too hot, not too cold,
not too wet and not too dry.
Droughts and floods have a very damaging effect
on how much food we can grow.
When fields become too wet or too dry, plants
cannot grow.
This can increase the price of food, and then
poor people cannot buy it.
These people then have to go hungry.
Some plants may grow better in a different
climate.
But scientists think that the effects of climate
change will make it much harder to grow enough
food for everyone.
Climate change may also have an effect on
the amount of water that we have, and many
places may not have the water they need.
Across South Asia and China, water for drinking
and farming comes from large rivers.
The water in these rivers comes from rain
and snow, and from ice melting high up in
the Himalayan mountains.
Climate change can have an effect on all of
these things.
This means lower amounts of water in the rivers
and lower amounts of water for people to drink
and use.
Climate change and extreme weather can also
have a damaging effect on our health.
More people could catch some diseases in a
warmer world.
Dirtier air can also damage the health of
all living things.
The many effects of climate change can make
people feel worried about their lives and
their families.
When people do not have the food and water
they need, it can cause problems between groups
of people and communities.
Sometimes people move from their homes to
try to find a better place to live or to find
enough food and water.
The effects on animals
Climate change is causing problems for many
of the animals that live on the Earth.
Changes in temperature, the seasons (spring,
summer, autumn and winter) and the amount
of food and water animals can find all make
life much more difficult for animals in different
parts of the world.
When changes to the climate are slow, animals
can find ways to live with the changes.
But when changes to the climate happen very
quickly, it is much more difficult for animals
to do this.
The climate change we are seeing right now
is happening very quickly, and it is damaging
for many of the living things on Earth.
At the same time, animals are losing their
habitats - the places they live.
People cut down trees to build towns and cities
and to grow food in fields.
All of these things take habitats away from
animals.
Together, climate change and losing habitats
make life very difficult for the animals of
this world.
We may see some animals become extinct in
the future because of climate change.
Many animals already have problems, and there
are very low numbers of some animals in today's
world.
More climate change may mean that these animals
become extinct, and we never see them again.
Many people already know about the polar bear
and the problems it now has in its habitat,
the Arctic.
The Arctic ice is melting.
This makes catching seals to eat very difficult
for polar bears, because they walk on the
ice to do this.
Polar bears are not the only animals at risk
from the warming of the Earth.
All over the world, there are other animals
that could become extinct because of climate
change.
Many others will find life much more difficult.
Many of Australia's animals have lost their
habitats because of climate change.
These animals include the yellow-footed rock
wallaby, the golden-shouldered parrot and
Lumholtz's tree-kangaroo.
Many of our medicines, and all the plants
and animals we use for food, come from the
natural world.
In the future, we may not have the large numbers
of different animals and plants that we see
on Earth today.
This will make the world a poorer and sadder
place for the people living on Earth in the
future.
The effects on companies and communities
Some companies and communities are already
seeing the bad effects of climate change and
extreme weather.
People buy insurance to protect their homes
if something bad happens.
But it is going to become more difficult for
these companies to give insurance against
floods, for example.
When floods happen more often, the cost of
insurance increases.
Insurance companies will find it more and
more difficult to protect these homes because
it costs so much money.
Food and water companies are also seeing the
effects of droughts, floods and other extreme
weather, and these effects are increasing.
In 2011, there was an extreme drought in Texas,
in the United States of America.
Many farms could not grow food, or grass for
cows, because there was no rain.
The farmers lost billions of dollars because
they had no food to sell.
Other companies make electricity using the
water moving in rivers.
But when there are lower amounts of water
in these rivers, they cannot make the electricity
they need.
This has been a big problem for many communities
in Brazil.
All of these things can make the price of
insurance, food, water and energy go up.
Doing nothing to stop climate change now may
make prices higher for companies and for people
in the future.
Many companies are now trying to stop climate
change and the warming of the Earth.
They are trying to find ways that the world
can grow and develop without putting more
carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
Together, companies are working towards a
future that makes money, but does not damage
the Earth.
Finding ways to live in our warmer world and
to stop the temperature increasing could mean
more jobs and a better future for communities.
CHAPTER FOUR
Climate change, then and now
Climate change in the past
The Earth's climate has always changed, and
this has had a huge effect on life on Earth.
Over millions of years, the climate has changed
many times.
It has been very, very cold, with lots of
snow and ice everywhere.
It has also been very, very hot, with forests
of trees growing in the Arctic and Antarctica.
For the past 2.6 million years, the Earth
has always had some ice in the Arctic and
Antarctica.
But the climate has changed in a pattern - sometimes
warmer and sometimes colder.
This pattern comes from the natural changes
in the way the Earth moves around the Sun.
There have been many "Ice Ages" in the Earth's
past.
At these times, there was a large amount of
ice over North America, Europe and Asia.
The amount of ice was last at its largest
about 22,000 years ago.
At this time, the sea levels across the Earth
were about 130 metres lower than they are
today.
There were fewer people in the world then,
and scientists think that there were only
about 130,000 people living in Europe.
Between the Ice Ages, the Earth was warmer,
and there was not as much ice.
At these times, the sea levels were higher,
and there were different plants and animals
living on the Earth.
At the end of the last Ice Age, there were
fast and extreme changes in the climate that,
together with people killing animals to eat,
may be the reason why the woolly mammoth became
extinct.
Climate change today
Many scientists study the climate and climate
change.
Their studies show that people are the biggest
cause of climate change today.
Many of the things that people do increase
the amount of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere,
and it is these gases that are making the
temperature of the Earth increase.
More greenhouses gases in the atmosphere carbon
dioxide (CO2), methane (CH4), nitrous oxide
(N2O) and others - mean more of the energy
we get from the Sun cannot leave the Earth.
This makes the Earth warmer.
Plants and animals take carbon (C) from the
atmosphere.
These plants and animals then die, and their
bodies go into the ground.
Over millions of years, the bodies of plants
and animals can become fossil fuels.
People then burn these fossil fuels in their
homes, in factories, and in cars, buses and
planes.
When we burn fossil fuels, the carbon inside
them is put back into the atmosphere as carbon
dioxide.
People do many other things that put greenhouse
gases into the atmosphere.
Cutting down trees in forests (deforestation),
growing food and keeping animals on farms,
and making things in factories all increase
the amount of greenhouse gases in the Earth's
atmosphere.
Across the world, levels of carbon dioxide
in the atmosphere are over 45 percent higher
than in 1750.
In 1750, there were about 280 parts per million.
But, in June 2016, even at the Halley Research
Station in Antarctica there were high levels
of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere - over
400 parts per million.
CHAPTER FIVE
The causes of climate change
Carbon sinks and carbon in the atmosphere
On Earth, there is a carbon cycle.
Carbon dioxide is a very important gas for
life on Earth.
Plants need it to live.
They take in carbon dioxide, use the carbon
to grow and then put oxygen back into the
atmosphere.
People and animals then take in this oxygen,
use it to live and put carbon dioxide back
into the atmosphere.
When plants and animals die, the carbon in
their bodies can go back into the atmosphere
as carbon dioxide, or it can go into the ground
in their bodies.
The carbon dioxide on Earth moves between
the land and the atmosphere, and between the
ocean and the atmosphere, too.
A carbon sink is something that takes in carbon
and holds it for a long time.
The land and forests on Earth are huge carbon
sinks because they take in a lot of carbon
dioxide.
This is called the land sink.
The oceans also take in a lot of carbon dioxide,
so they are huge carbon sinks, too.
This is called the ocean sink.
Together, the land sink and ocean sink take
in and hold over half the carbon dioxide that
people put into the atmosphere.
The other half stays in the atmosphere because
there is nowhere for it to go and no way for
it to get out.
The carbon sinks on Earth are very important.
They stop the Earth from getting even warmer.
Every year, people put about 40 billion tonnes
of carbon dioxide into the Earth's atmosphere.
Most of this carbon dioxide comes from burning
fossil fuels and from factories, but some
of it comes from deforestation and from changing
the way, we use the land.
Over the years since the last Ice Age, the
Earth has become about 4C to 5C warmer.
This warming was because of the natural changes
in the way the Earth moves around the Sun.
This change in temperature has had a huge
effect on the Earth, its climate, and the
plants and animals that live here.
If we do not stop putting so much carbon dioxide
into the atmosphere, the Earth's temperature
may increase by another 4C to 5C by the end
of the 21st century.
This would cause huge problems for all the
living things on the Earth.
The energy we use now and in the future
Across the world, people use twenty times
more energy today than they did in 1850.
In this time, there has also been a change
in the energy we use.
In the past, we burned wood and used energy
from the wind and from the water in rivers.
Today, we burn a lot more fossil fuels than
we did in the past.
As we built more and more factories, we started
to use more and more fossil fuels.
We also started to drive cars and travel in
planes, and this burns fossil fuels, too.
Today, 80 percent of the energy we use comes
from fossil fuels.
Energy from other things, including wood and
water, is just 20 percent of the energy we
use.
Right now, energy from the Sun and from the
wind is just 3 percent of the energy we use,
but this is growing quickly.
The energy we get from the Sun and wind is
much better for the Earth than fossil fuels
because it is clean and does not put any greenhouse
gases into the atmosphere.
Countries need to work hard to increase the
amount of clean energy they use.
For countries around the world, getting clean
energy to people at a low price is one of
the biggest problems of the 21st century.
As the number of people in the world grows,
the amount of energy we need also grows, and
this is becoming a bigger and bigger problem
for everyone.
Around the world, more than 1 billion people
live without electricity for heat and light
in their homes.
Most of these people live in Africa and Asia.
Over 3 billion people still use wood in their
homes for cooking, and this can make the air
inside their homes very dirty and dangerous.
It can have a very bad effect on their health,
and millions of people die every year because
of dirty air inside their homes.
Outside, fossil fuels also have a bad effect
on people's health.
Burning fossil fuels in factories, and in
cars and buses, causes millions of people
to die every year from dirty air.
Clean energy from the Sun, wind and water
is the best way to give people the energy
they need without having the damaging effects
on people's health and on the Earth's climate.
Cutting down forests and damaging soils
Forests are one of the biggest carbon sinks
on Earth.
Across the world, forests take in carbon dioxide
and hold it in their trees, plants and the
soil under them.
When we cut down trees, most of that carbon
dioxide goes back into the atmosphere.
For thousands of years, people have cut down
forests to use the land for farming.
This deforestation put a lot of carbon dioxide
into the atmosphere and also caused some animals
to become extinct.
Tarpans were wild horses and aurochs were
wild cows, and both of these animals became
extinct when people cut down forests in Europe,
Asia and North Africa.
In the last century, the deforestation of
rainforests in some parts of the world has
become a big problem.
Some of these rainforests are on soils that
hold a huge amount of carbon.
These soils have taken in the carbon slowly
over thousands of years.
When people cut down the trees in these rainforests,
they damage the soil under the trees, and
this puts the carbon dioxide back into the
atmosphere.
Farming can also damage soils and put even
more carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
Today, people are still cutting down forests,
often to build huge farms.
Over the last 150 years, 25 percent of the
carbon dioxide put into the atmosphere by
people is because of deforestation.
Cutting down forests has a bad effect on the
water cycle, too, and this can make droughts
worse in some parts of the world.
Deforestation also puts many animals and plants
in danger because it takes away their habitats.
It may cause many animals to become extinct
in the future.
Past and present changes in carbon dioxide
The carbon dioxide levels in the atmosphere
today are much higher than at any time in
the last 800,000 years.
We know this because many scientists work
in Antarctica and study the ice there.
Scientists take ice cores from the Antarctic
ice and use them to find out about the Earth's
climate in the past.
These ice cores show that the changes in the
last century are not part of Earth's natural
cycles.
The ice in Antarctica has built up over hundreds
of thousands of years.
Over this time, snow fell and made layers
that built up to make the thick ice that we
see in Antarctica today.
Every time the snow fell, small amounts of
air also got inside the ice and could not
get out.
Scientists can take ice cores from more than
3,000 metres down to find air from hundreds
of thousands of years ago.
By studying this air, they can find out about
the atmosphere in the past.
We can also study the soil at the bottom of
the ocean to find out about the Earth's atmosphere
a very long time ago.
All of these studies show that carbon dioxide
is going into the atmosphere more quickly
now than at any time in the past 50 million
years.
Today's changes in carbon dioxide levels are
not because of natural causes, but because
of people.
Most of the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
today will be there for many years.
Some will stay in the atmosphere for thousands
of years.
This means that we will see the effects of
this carbon dioxide for many years to come.
CHAPTER SIX
The risks of climate change
Acidic oceans
The high levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
are having a bad effect on our oceans.
Across the world, oceans are becoming more
acidic.
The last time the oceans on Earth were so
acidic was about 250 million years ago.
At this time, a huge number of animals became
extinct.
About 30 percent of the carbon dioxide people
put into the atmosphere goes into the oceans.
This stops so much carbon dioxide staying
in the atmosphere.
Ocean sinks stop the temperature on Earth
from getting even higher, but they also make
the water in the oceans more acidic.
Scientists are starting to understand the
effects that acidic water has on the animals
that live in the ocean.
Many of the very small animals in the ocean,
like corals, are really important for other
ocean animals and for people.
For example, people eat a lot of fish, and
these fish eat smaller fish and other small
animals in the ocean.
If the numbers of these smaller animals get
very low because they are killed by acidic
water, there will be lower numbers of bigger
fish.
This could then cause a problem for all the
animals that live in the ocean, including
those that people eat.
So, acidic oceans may cause a big problem
for people, too.
Lower numbers of fish and other sea animals
will make life very difficult for communities
that live near the sea and catch and sell
them as food.
It will also make food that comes from the
sea more difficult to buy and more expensive.
Coral reefs are in danger
Acidic oceans and warmer seawater are both
very bad for corals, and many corals are dying
in oceans across the world.
Storms, dirty seawater and other ocean animals
also damage coral reefs.
People are now very worried about the future
of the oceans' beautiful coral reefs, including
Australia's Great Barrier Reef.
The risk of large climate changes
As the world gets warmer, there is a risk
of large and dangerous changes to the Earth's
climate.
And, once these changes happen, we may never
be able to go back to the climate we have
today.
Even small increases in temperature can have
a big effect on the thick ice over Greenland
and West Antarctica.
If this ice melts, it will cause sea levels
to increase, maybe by many metres.
This would have a huge effect on the land
next to the sea all around the world.
Studies show that the ice in Greenland is
melting more every summer.
There is also information to show that the
thick ice in West Antarctica is melting and
that the damage to the ice is very large.
Some scientists think we may never be able
to stop this ice melting.
Changes to rain patterns can cause forests
to become very dry, and this can increase
the risk of fire.
Fire and drought can really damage thick forests.
Then the forests may become dry land, with
only grass and no trees.
This land cannot hold as much carbon, so more
carbon stays in the atmosphere.
This increases temperatures and causes more
changes to rain patterns.
Many people are worried that this cycle may
cause many of the trees in the Amazon rainforest
to die.
There are many other large changes to the
climate that may happen in the future.
These include huge droughts, huge changes
in natural rain patterns and huge changes
in the ocean.
The ocean moves warm and cold water around
the Earth, and this has a big effect on the
climate.
Changes in how this water moves can cause
huge changes to the climate in different parts
of the world.
Scientists are also worried about the increase
in temperature in the Arctic.
The Arctic holds a large amount of the greenhouse
gas methane (CH4).
As the temperature increases, this methane
can get into the atmosphere.
This is a huge problem because methane is
a much stronger greenhouse gas than carbon
dioxide.
Increasing sea levels
Over the last few decades, we have seen the
effects of climate change all over the world
- in all places and all oceans.
Climate change has had an effect both on the
natural world (plants and animals) and on
people and communities.
Today, the Earth's temperature is about 1C
warmer than it was 150 years ago.
The warmer the world becomes, the worse the
effects are for the natural world and for
people, communities and companies.
Many people live on small islands around the
world, and these people are very worried about
the effects of climate change.
Some islands are only a few metres above sea
level, so floods are a huge problem for them
if sea levels increase.
Studies show that, 400,000 years ago, the
Earth was warmer, and a large part of Greenland
had no ice over it for a long time.
The melting ice caused sea levels to increase,
and they became more than 6 metres higher
than they are today.
Scientists think that the temperature at this
time was only a little warmer than the temperature
today.
This shows how important it is to stop the
Earth's temperature increasing any more.
What to do about climate change
In 2015, the world's countries met in Paris
in France to talk about climate change and
what to do about it.
They agreed to take steps to keep the Earth's
warming to well below 2 degrees Celsius.
They agreed to try to keep warming below 1.5
degrees Celsius, but they know that this will
be difficult.
To try to do this, they agreed to cut the
amount of greenhouse gases they put into the
atmosphere.
This was a very positive step.
These plans will help to stop the warming
of the Earth and are good in many other ways.
The plans could help to make the air cleaner,
stop the water in the oceans becoming so acidic,
and help people to live a healthy life.
All of these things can have a positive effect
on people's lives.
Cutting carbon
In Paris, in 2015, countries agreed to cut
the amount of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse
gases they put into the atmosphere.
To stop the Earth's warming going above 1.5
degrees Celsius, people need to stop putting
any carbon dioxide into the atmosphere by
the middle of this century.
This means that we need to cut the amount
of carbon dioxide we put into the atmosphere
right now.
The amount of carbon dioxide we can put into
the atmosphere before there is a large risk
of dangerous levels of warming is called a
carbon budget.
The more of the carbon budget we use now,
the lower it will be in the future.
Together, countries must plan how to use the
carbon budget so that we do not use it all
too quickly.
For the Earth's warming to stay below 1.5
degrees Celsius, the carbon budget is about
2,600 billion tonnes.
But scientists think that, since 1870, we
have already put 2,200 billion tonnes of carbon
dioxide into the atmosphere.
This means we have already used 2,200 billion
tonnes of the carbon budget, and we only have
about 400 billion tonnes left.
400 billion
tonnes of carbon dioxide sounds like a huge
amount, but right now people across the world
put more than 40 billion tonnes of carbon
dioxide into the atmosphere every year.
We need to stop burning fossil fuels, cutting
down forests and damaging soils.
If we do not, we will use all of the world's
carbon budget to stay below 1.5C in the next
10-15 years.
Even if we stop putting any carbon dioxide
into the atmosphere, the temperatures on Earth
will stay warm, and this will cause changes
to the climate for hundreds of years in the
future.
Because of the greenhouse gases already in
the atmosphere, the oceans will slowly warm,
the ice in the Arctic and Antarctica will
melt, and sea levels will increase for many
years to come.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Solutions
Energy solutions
To make a better future for the Earth, people
all over the world need to cut the amount
of greenhouse gases they put into the atmosphere.
Today, we burn a huge amount of fossil fuel,
and this is one of the biggest reasons why
we put so much carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
We need to stop burning fossil fuels and to
only use clean energy in the future.
We can get clean energy from a number of places
the wind, the Sun, plants, the water moving
in rivers and the ocean, hot rocks under the
ground, and other new ways of making energy.
Nuclear energy also puts very few greenhouse
gases into the atmosphere, but it is expensive.
In the future, scientists also need to find
ways of making better batteries so we can
keep electricity and it can be used at a later
time.
The batteries we use today do not hold enough
electricity.
Better batteries will also help us to move
from cars and buses that burn fossil fuels
to cars and buses that use electricity.
There is another step we can take to help
to stop climate change.
Scientists need to find ways of taking carbon
dioxide from factories and other places that
make it, and keeping it under the ground.
Making new carbon sinks can help to cut the
carbon dioxide going into the atmosphere.
We must also try not to use more energy than
we need.
We need to find ways of using a smaller amount
of energy in our homes and in factories.
People are now using computers to help to
cut the amount of energy we use, and to put
more clean energy into people's homes.
Scientists also need to find ways of taking
large amounts of carbon dioxide out of the
atmosphere without causing any other problems
for the world.
This needs to happen quickly - very quickly
if we want warming to stay below 1.5 degrees
Celsius.
Forest solutions
The Earth's forests are an important part
of the solution to cutting greenhouse gases
in the atmosphere and stopping climate change.
Forests are one of the biggest carbon sinks
on the Earth.
We need to stop deforestation, protect the
Earth's natural forests, and grow more trees
and forests.
This includes growing forests on land that
is not good for farming.
Stopping deforestation is a very difficult
thing to do.
Around the world, people cut down forests
to use the land for farming.
This is an important way for many countries
to make money and for people to make money
to buy food and clothes for their families.
People need to see how important forests are
because then they will stop cutting them down.
This has already happened in many places around
the world.
Many countries now understand that their rainforests
help to protect and to develop their communities.
These forests have a positive effect on the
amount of rain and clean water communities
have for farming and on the rivers that some
companies use to make electricity.
Forests also help to protect the land and
soil, and to lower the number of floods communities
have.
Forests do a natural job of protecting soils,
and this is important for the food and water
we need and use every day.
Protecting forests is a good way to cut the
amount of carbon dioxide we put into the atmosphere,
and it has a positive effect on many other
things, too.
In West Africa, people are helping cocoa farmers
to make more money from the cocoa they grow
without cutting down more trees and forests.
This includes growing cocoa plants and trees
together in ways that give farmers more food
from the same land.
Farmers are then making more money for their
families and for their countries, but carbon
stays inside the trees in the rainforests
and does not go into the atmosphere.
Food and farming solutions
Farming can also be part of the solution to
climate change.
Farmers can use ways of farming that build
up carbon levels in soils.
Soils are a very important natural carbon
sink.
Some soils are better than others.
For example, soils that have very small living
things in them can change dead plants into
food for new plants to grow.
This can help farmers to grow the plants we
eat.
These soils are also very good at holding
carbon.
Farmers can help to make these good soils.
They can do this by often changing the plants
that they grow on their land and by not always
growing the same plants.
They can also help by sometimes-growing plants
on the land, and sometimes keeping animals
on it.
These two steps can help to make soils healthy.
These good soils also hold more water.
This means that they can protect plants from
drought, and this makes farming easier in
a warmer climate.
The amount of carbon dioxide we put into the
atmosphere can also be cut by thinking about
the food we eat.
Only growing the food, we need and not throwing
food away will help.
Not eating so much meat and other foods that
come from animals will also help to cut the
greenhouse gases we put into the atmosphere.
Earth's natural cycles
The Earth and its living things run in cycles.
The water cycle and the carbon cycle are very
important patterns for life on Earth.
Soils use the good things from dead plants
to grow new plants.
In natural cycles, everything is used again.
But, in today's world, people often do not
do things in cycles.
We make things, and then we use them.
When we finish using things, we throw them
away.
When we throw things away, they often go into
the land, the atmosphere or the oceans.
We do not use them again, or get back the
energy or things we used to make them.
This means that we use a lot of energy and
natural things.
But doing things in cycles does not use as
much energy or natural things, and does not
put so much carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.
Companies need to do things in new and different
ways.
They must try to find ways of using everything
again and throwing nothing away - just like
natural cycles.
We need to look at the natural cycles on Earth
and try to do things in the same way.
Many companies are already using these ideas
to make new things and to help stop climate
change.
For example, companies are using natural cycles
to develop new fuels.
CHAPTER EIGHT
The future
Coming together to stop climate change
Climate change is a problem for all the people
of the world.
One country on its own cannot find the solution
- all the countries of the world need to work
together on this problem.
Countries also need to work together to develop
in a way that is good for the Earth and does
not damage it.
Together, they need to help poor countries
and communities to have a positive future.
Many people from across the world have asked
for countries to do more to stop climate change.
In 2015, in Paris, countries agreed to cut
the amount of fossil fuels they burn, to protect
forests and to increase the health of their
soils.
This was a very positive day for climate change.
The steps that countries agreed to take in
Paris are still not enough to stop warming
going above 2 degrees Celsius, but the countries
all agreed to do more in the future.
Cutting the amount of greenhouse gases we
put into the atmosphere will help to stop
the temperature on Earth increasing more.
This is very positive for the future, but
many people around the world will still have
to live with the effects of climate change.
So, in Paris, countries also agreed to help
people to find ways to live in our warmer
world and to protect them from the effects
of higher temperatures.
Making a better life for everyone
Trying to find solutions to the problem of
climate change can be a very positive thing
for many people and many companies.
Across the world, companies can look for new
things to make and new ways of doing things.
They can work together with new people and
can make new jobs.
Finding solutions to climate change could
make life better for people in many different
ways.
Lots of companies are now developing clean
energies, and this is making many new jobs.
Building companies are making new houses that
are comfortable, use very little energy and
are cheaper to live in.
All the large car companies are now moving
away from fossil fuels and are making cars
that use electricity.
Companies are also looking at ways of using
new fuels in their cars and aeroplanes, including
fuels from plants.
This will cut the amount of carbon dioxide
we put into the atmosphere.
A lot of companies are now working with the
idea of "zero deforestation" in everything
they do.
People cut down trees in forests all over
the world.
But, in some forests, people cut down a tree
and then grow a new tree - this is called
zero deforestation.
Companies across the world are now only using
trees from forests like this.
Countries, communities and companies are trying
to build a different future, without people
putting greenhouse gases into the atmosphere.
This idea is growing fast and is now making
a lot of money.
Countries can help this change happen faster
- they can make it cheaper to make and use
cleaner energy, and more expensive to make
and use fossil fuels.
Asking companies to develop clean ways of
doing things can make more jobs, stronger
communities and a better climate for everyone.
One Earth
For hundreds of years, we have used more and
more from the natural world, but there is
still only one Earth.
The number of people living on Earth grows
every day, and every day we have a bigger
and bigger effect on the Earth.
For the communities of the world to have a
positive future, we must find ways of living
on the Earth without damaging it in the way
we do today.
We are already seeing the bad effects of climate
change, but things may be much worse for our
children and our grandchildren.
We need to see that the Earth is in danger
and act now to find solutions.
Everyone must work towards stopping climate
change - on our own and together.
We can all help.
Every day we can decide to do things that
cut the amount of carbon dioxide we put into
the atmosphere.
Every day we can take positive steps to keep
the natural world healthy.
We have had a bad effect on the natural world
for too long, and we need to stop now.
If we are good to the Earth, only then can
the Earth be good to us.
- THE END -