The West of Ireland, with its rivers full
of salmon, is a grand place to go fishing.
Sinclair Yeates has been trying to catch
salmon for three days, but without success.
He starts his journey home, travelling by train,
which in the early years of the twentieth century
is an experience full of interest and surprises...
People say there is no smoke without fire.
But that was not true in the station
waiting-room where I had to wait for my train.
There was certainly plenty of smoke
but the fire seemed quite dead.
When I complained to the stationmaster, he said
that any chimney in the world would smoke in a
south-easterly wind. He was, however, sympathetic,
and took me to his own fire in his office,
where the steam rose in clouds from my wet boots.
We talked of politics and salmon-fishing, and
I had to confess that on my three-day
trip I had not caught a single fish.
Before the signal for my train was received, I
realized for the hundredth time the wonderful
individuality of the Irish mind and the
importance of the 'personal element' in Ireland.
If you ask people for help, they will break rules,
ignore official advice, make special
arrangements - all just to please you.
I found a seat in a carriage, and the train
dragged itself noisily out of the station.
A cold spring rain - the time was the middle
of a most unseasonal April - poured down
as we came into the open. I closed both windows
and began to read my wife's letter again.
Philippa often says I do not read her letters,
and as I was now on my way to join her and
my family in England, it seemed sensible to
study again her latest letter of instructions.
'Such bad luck that you haven't caught any
salmon. If the worst comes to the worst,
and you still haven't by the time
you join us, couldn't you buy one?'
I hit my knee with my hand. I had forgotten about
the damn fish! Philippa would say, 'Sinclair,
I was right! You don't read my letters, do you!'
It's a pity she never learns from these frequent
experiences; I don't mind being called a fool,
but then I should be allowed to forget things, as
fools do. Without doubt, Philippa had written to
Alice Hervey, whose house we were staying in for
the next week, and told her that Sinclair would
be only too delighted to bring her a salmon. And
Alice Hervey, who was rich enough to find much
enjoyment in saving money, would have already
planned the meal down to the last fish bone.
Anxiously thinking about this, I travelled through
the rain. About every six miles we stopped at
a station. At one, the only event was that the
stationmaster presented a newspaper to the guard;
at the next, the guard read aloud some
interesting facts from it to the driver.
The personal element was strong on this line
of the Munster and Connaught Railway. Routine,
hated by all artistic minds,
was disguised by conversation.
According to the timetable, we were supposed
to spend ten minutes at Carrig station,
but it was fifteen before all the market people
on the platform had climbed onto the train.
Finally, the window of the carriage next to mine
was thrown open, and an angry English voice asked
how much longer the train was going to wait. The
stationmaster, who was deep in conversation with
the guard and a man carrying a long parcel wrapped
in newspaper, looked round and said seriously.
'Well now, that's a mystery!'
The man with the parcel turned away and studied
an advertisement, his shoulders shaking.
The guard put his hand over his mouth.
The voice, even angrier now, demanded the
earliest time its owner could get to Belfast.
'Ye'll be asking me next when I take me
breakfast,' replied the stationmaster calmly.
The window closed with a bang,
and the man on the platform
dropped his parcel, which fell to the ground.
'Oh! Me fish!' cried the man, carefully picking up
a remarkably handsome salmon that
had slipped out of its wrapping.
Suddenly I had a bright idea. I opened my
window and called to the stationmaster.
'Excuse me, would your
friend sell me that salmon?'
There was a moment's lively discussion, and the
stationmaster replied, 'I'm sorry, sir, he's only
just bought it, in this little delay we have. But
why don't ye run down and get one for yourself?
There are six or seven of them down at Coffey's,
selling cheap. There'll be time enough. We're
waiting for the mail train to pass through in the
other direction, and it hasn't been signaled yet.'
I jumped from the carriage and ran
out of the station at top speed,
followed by a shout from the guard that he
wouldn't forget me. Congratulating myself
on the influence of the personal
element, I hurried through the town.
On my way I met a red-faced, heated man carrying
another salmon, who informed me there were still
three or four fish at Coffey's, and that
he was running for the train himself.
'Coffey's is the house with
the boots in the window!'
he called after me. 'She'll sell at ten
pence a pound if ye're stiff with her!'
'Ten pence a pound,' I thought, 'at
this time of year! That's good enough.'
I saw the boots in the window,
and rushed through a dark doorway.
At that moment I heard, horrifyingly near,
the whistle of the approaching mail train.
The fat woman who appeared from a back
room understood the situation at once,
and in one rapid movement picked up a large fish
from the floor and threw a newspaper round it.
'Weighs eight pounds!' she said. 'Ten shillings!'
I realized she was charging more than ten
pence a pound, but this was not the moment for
stiffness. I pushed the coins into her fishy
hand, took the salmon in my arms, and ran.
Needless to say, it was uphill, and at the
steepest point I heard another whistle, and feared
that the worst had happened. When I reached the
platform, my train was already out of the station,
but the personal element was still working for me.
Everybody in the station, or so it seemed to me,
shouted loudly to the driver. The stationmaster
put his fingers in his mouth and sent an
unearthly whistle after the departing
train. It took effect; the train slowed.
I jumped from the platform and followed it along
the rails; there were passengers' heads at all
the windows, watching me with deep interest. The
guard bent down and helped me up onto the train.
'Sorry, sir, the English gentleman going to
Belfast wouldn't let me wait any longer,'
he said apologetically.
From Carrig station came a delighted
cry from the stationmaster:
'Ye told him ye wouldn't forget him!'
My very public return to my seat
was greeted with great sympathy
by the seven countrywomen who were now in
my carriage. I was hot and out of breath,
and the eyes of the seven women were fixed on me
with deep and untiring interest. After a while
one of them opened the conversation by
supposing it was at Coffey's I got the salmon.
I said it was.
There was a silence, during which it was
obvious that one question burnt in every heart.
'She's sure to have asked for
ten pence!' said one woman.
'It's a beautiful fish!' I said bravely. 'Eight
pounds weight. I gave her ten shillings for it.'
This confession produced a
wave of shock and sympathy.
'Sure, and Eliza Coffey would rob her own mother!'
'How could an honest gentleman
win a battle with her!'
'Eliza Coffey never paid a
penny for that fish! Those
boys of hers stole a whole
lot of them last night.'
At the next station they climbed out. I helped
them with their heavy baskets, and in return
they told me I was a fine man, and they wished
me well on my journey. They also left me with the
information that I was soon to present the highly
respectable Alice Hervey with a stolen salmon.
The afternoon passed cheerlessly into evening,
and my journey did not get any better.
Somewhere in the grey half-light I changed trains,
and again later on, and at each change the salmon
lost some of its newspaper wrapping. I wondered
seriously whether to bury it in my suitcase.
At the next station we paused for a long time.
Nothing at all happened, and the rain
beat patiently on the carriage roof.
I closed my eyes to avoid the cold
stare of the salmon, and fell asleep.
I woke up in total darkness. The train was not
moving, and there was complete silence. I could
see a lamp at the far end of a platform, so I knew
we were at a station. I lit a match and discovered
from my watch that it was eleven o'clock, exactly
the time I was supposed to board the mail train.
I jumped down and ran along the platform. There
was no one on the train; there was no one even
in the engine, which was making sad
little noises to itself in the silence.
There was not a human being anywhere. The name
of the station was just visible in the darkness.
With a lighted match I went along it letter
by letter, but it was so long that by the
time I got to the end, I had forgotten the
beginning. One thing I did realize, though,
was that it was not Loughranny, the station
where I had planned to catch the mail train.
For a moment I had the feeling
that there had been an accident,
and that I now existed in another world. Once more
I investigated the station - the ticket office,
the waiting room - and finally discovered, at some
distance, the stationmaster's office. As I came
closer, I could see a thin line of light under
the door, and a voice was suddenly raised inside.
'Let's see ye beat that. Throw down your King!'
I opened the door with understandable violence,
and found the guard, the stationmaster,
the driver, and his assistant seated
around a table, playing a game of cards.
I was angry, and with good reason, but I
accepted what they said in their defense:
they thought there was no one left on the train,
a few minutes here or there wouldn't matter,
they would soon get me to Loughranny,
and the mail train was often late.
Hoping they were right about my
chances of making the connection,
I hurried back to my carriage, with the
officials running enthusiastically ahead of me.
'Watch out for the goods train, Tim!'
shouted the station-master to the driver,
as he banged my door shut. 'She
might be coming any time now!'
The answer travelled back proudly from the engine.
'Let her come! She'll have us to deal with!'
The train moved forward and gained speed
rapidly. We had about fifteen miles to go,
and we went as fast as the engine could manage.
But it was no good - we arrived too late.
'Well,' said the guard, as I stepped onto
the deserted platform of Loughranny station,
'that old mail is the most unpunctual
train in Ireland! If ye're a minute late,
she's gone, and maybe if ye were early,
ye'd be half an hour waiting for her!'
On the whole, the guard did his best. He
said he would show me the best hotel in town,
although he feared it would be hard to get a bed
anywhere because of the Feis. A Feis, it seems,
is a festival of Irish songs and dances, where
people compete for prizes. He picked up my case,
he even carried the salmon, and as
we walked through the empty streets,
he explained to me how easily I could
catch the morning boat from Rosslare,
and how it was, in fact, quite an
improvement on my previous plan.
All was dark at the uninviting door
of the hotel chosen by the guard.
For five whole minutes we rang the bell
hard. I suggested trying a different hotel.
'He'll come,' said the guard confidently.
'He'll come. It rings in his room, so it does.'
A boy, half awake, half dressed, opened the door.
'There's not a bed here,' he said,
yawning, 'nor anywhere in the town either.'
'I'll sit in the dining room till the
time for the early train,' I said.
'To be sure, there's five beds in the dining
room,' he replied, 'and there's mostly two
people in every bed.' His voice was firm,
but he had a hesitating look in his eye.
'What about the billiard room,
Mike?' said the guard helpfully.
'We have blankets on the
billiard table at this minute,
and the man that won first prize
for reels asleep on top of it!'
'Well, can't ye put some blankets on
the floor under it?' said the guard,
putting my case and the salmon in the hall.
'To be sure, there's no better place in the
house! Now I must go home, before
me wife thinks I'm dead and buried!'
His footsteps went lightly
away down the empty street.
'Nothing troubles him!' said the boy bitterly.
And I realized that only the
personal element stood between me
and a sleepless night on a
cold, wet station platform.
It was in the dark of the early morning that I
woke again to life and its troubles. A voice had
woken me, the voice of the first prize for reels,
descending through a pocket of the billiard table.
'Excuse me, sir, are ye going
on the 5 o'clock train to Cork?'
'No,' I said crossly.
'Well, if ye were, ye'd be late,' said the voice.
I received this useful information in annoyed
silence, and tried to wrap
myself in a disappearing dream.
'I'm going on the 6.30 me
self,' continued the voice,
'and it's unknown to me how I'll put on
me boots. Ye would not believe how me feet
swelled up in me dancing shoes last night.
Me feet are delicate like that, ye see.'
I pretended to be asleep, but the dream was
gone. And so was any chance of further sleep.
The first prize for reels got
down from the billiard table,
presenting an extraordinary picture. He was
wearing grass-green breeches, a white shirt,
and pearl-grey stockings. He undressed,
and put on ordinary clothes, including
his painful boots. He then removed
himself and his things to the hall,
where he had a loud conversation with the boy.
Meanwhile, I crawled out of my hiding-place to
renew my struggle with life. Fortunately,
the boy soon appeared with a cup of tea.
'I've wrapped the salmon up in brown paper
for ye, sir,' he said cheerfully. 'It's
safe to take across Europe with ye if ye
like! I'll just run up to the station now,
with the luggage. Would ye mind carrying the
fish yourself? It's on the table in the hall.'
My train went at 6.15. The boy had put my
case in one of the many empty carriages,
and stayed with me, making pleasant
conversation, until the train departed.
'I'm sorry ye had a bad night, sir,' he said,
'and I must tell ye, it was only that Jimmy
Durkan - he's the first prize for reels, sir
- had taken a few drinks. If he'd been sober,
I'd have put a gentleman like ye on the billiard
table instead of him. He's a baker, ye know,
in the town of Limerick. And he's engaged to my
sister. Well, any girl would be glad to marry him.
He dances with a beautiful straight back, and
he makes grand bread!' Here the train started.
It was late that night when, stiff, dirty,
with tired eyes blinded by the bright lights,
I was taken by the Herveys' well-trained doorman
into the Herveys' huge grand hall, and was told
by another of the Herveys' beautifully dressed
servants that dinner was over. I was just hoping
I could go quietly upstairs to avoid meeting
anyone, when a voice cried, 'Here he is!'
And Philippa, looking lovely in evening dress,
came into the hall, followed by Alice Hervey,
and my niece, whose wedding party this was,
and by all the usual relations who hate to
miss anything that's going on before a wedding.
'Is this a wedding present
for me, Uncle Sinclair?'
cried the future bride, in the middle
of a flood of questions and sympathy.
As she spoke, she eagerly took hold of the
brown-paper parcel that was still under my arm.
'I advise you not to open
it!' I cried. 'It's a salmon!'
The future bride gave a little scream of distaste,
and without a moment's hesitation, threw it at
her best friend, a girl standing near her. The
best friend gave an answering scream, and jumped
to one side. The parcel that I had looked after
with a mother's care across two countries and a
stormy sea fell with a crash on the stone floor.
Why did it crash?
'A salmon!' cried Philippa, staring at the
parcel. There was now a small pool around it,
spreading over the floor. 'But
that's whiskey! Can't you smell it?'
The servant came respectfully forward. He
knelt down, and cautiously picked pieces
of a broken glass bottle out of the brown
paper. The smell of whiskey became stronger.
'I'm afraid the other things are ruined, sir,'
he said seriously, and pulled out of the parcel,
one after the other, a very
large pair of dancing shoes,
two long grey stockings, and a
pair of grass-green breeches.
They were greeted with wild enthusiasm, in
doubtless much the same way as when they
shared the success of Mr Jimmy Durkan at
the Feis, but Alice Hervey was not amused.
'You know, dear,' she said to Philippa
afterwards, 'I don't think it was very clever
of dear Sinclair to take the wrong
parcel. I had wanted that salmon.'
- THE END -