CHAPTER ONE
A Man in a Hurry
Emil Harker was a rich man.
But this particular Tuesday evening, he was
a worried man.
He was more worried than he had ever been
in his life.
Harker was sitting at a desk in his office.
His office was in a small forest hut.
Harker sat at his desk and looked at the piece
of paper in front of him.
There was something written on the piece of
paper - a short poem.
Harker had written the poem himself.
It was not a very good poem, but then Harker
was not a poet, and he had written the poem
in a hurry.
He hadn't got much time left.
About an hour earlier, the phone had rung
in the hut.
Harker had answered it.
'Harker?' said a voice.
Harker recognized the voice.
'Ezra,' said Harker.
'What do you want?'
'Where is it?' asked Ezra.
'Where is what?' asked Harker.
'You know,' said Ezra.
'I don't know,' said Harker.
'Stop playing games,' said Ezra.
'I'm not playing games,' said Harker.
'Oh yes you are,' said the voice.
'I'm coming to see you.'
'Now look,' began Harker.
But Ezra had put the phone down.
It was then that Harker wrote the poem.
He sat at his desk and wrote fast.
He tore up two or three pieces of paper before
he was satisfied.
At last the poem was finished.
Harker folded the paper and wrote across the
front:
To John Samuel Fame - please read carefully.
Harker put his pen in his pocket and looked
at his watch.
It was half past nine.
Without warning, the hut door opened.
A tall man with a pale face and a moustache
stood in the doorway.
Behind him were two other men who carried
guns.
Harker stood up.
'Now just a minute Ezra,' he said, 'Let's
talk.'
'You're the one who's going to talk,' said
Ezra.
'Where is it?'
'I've told you,' said Harker, 'I don't know
what you're talking about.'
'Hold his arms,' shouted Ezra to the two men.
The men moved fast across the room and got
hold of Harker.
Ezra walked over to the desk.
He saw the folded piece of paper and picked
it up.
He looked at it, then unfolded it and read
the poem.
'What's this?' he said.
Harker said nothing.
He was sweating.
CHAPTER TWO
At the Frontier
Harker wasn't the only person who had an important
phone call that Tuesday evening.
At ten o'clock, the phone rang in the customs
shed at the frontier.
The phone rang three times and then one of
the two customs officers in the shed answered
it.
'Hello.
Frontier Customs here,' he said.
'Hello,' said a voice, 'Inspector Roland here.'
'Hello, Inspector,' said the customs officer,
'what can I do for you?'
'Do you know a man called John Samuel Fame?'
asked the Inspector.
'Yes,' said the customs officer, 'he crosses
the frontier a lot.
Perhaps two or three times a week.
He's a businessman.'
'That's what he says,' said the Inspector.
'Do you know him?' said the customs officer.
'Very well,' said the Inspector.
'What do you want me to do about him?' asked
the customs officer.
'Watch him,' said the Inspector.
'Search his car.'
The customs officer, whose name was Silver,
put down the phone.
Silver was a thin man with a high forehead
and large ears.
He crossed the room and sat down on a chair
by the window.
'Who was that?' asked Rank, the other customs
officer.
Rank was a much fatter man than Silver, with
a small moustache.
'Inspector Roland,' said Silver.
'What did he want?' asked Rank.
Rank was sitting on a chair with his legs
up on a table, reading a newspaper.
'He asked me about John Samuel Fame,' said
Silver.
'Who?' asked Rank.
'John Samuel Fame,' repeated Silver, 'the
businessman who crosses the frontier two or
three times a week.
He always drives a smart grey car.'
'Oh yes,' said Rank.
'What about him?'
'Inspector Roland told us to watch him,' said
Silver, 'and search his car.'
'Why?'
asked Rank.
'The Inspector didn't say,' said Silver.
'Oh,' said Rank, and turned over a page of
his newspaper.
Silver opened a large exercise book that was
lying on the wooden table in front of him
and began to write in it.
A fly landed on Rank's head and crawled down
his forehead and nose.
Rank brushed it off and went on reading the
newspaper.
The clock on the wall behind him ticked loudly
and the fly crawled across the lightshade
over his head.
Just then, both customs officers heard a car.
Silver looked up and stopped writing, and
the guard outside moved out into the middle
of the road.
The car came round the corner and stopped
beside the guard.
The guard told the driver to get out.
The driver switched off the engine and the
headlights, got out, and followed the guard
up the wooden steps of the customs hut.
The guard opened the door for him and the
man went inside.
Silver, the thin customs officer, looked up.
John Samuel Fame was standing in front of
him.
Fame was wearing a smart dark suit and an
open-necked shirt.
He was a tall thin man - and rather good-looking.
'It's me again,' said John Samuel Fame.
'Your passport, please,' said Silver without
smiling.
Fame gave his passport to Silver.
Silver opened it and turned over the pages,
while Rank went on reading the newspaper.
Fame stood the other side of the table and
waited.
'Are you John Samuel Fame?' asked Silver.
'Yes, you know I am,' said Fame smiling.
'And are you a businessman?' asked Silver.
'Yes, of course!' said Fame.
'Why are you crossing the frontier?' asked
Silver.
'On business, as usual,' said Fame.
'How long are you going to stay here?'
asked Silver.
'Two days, as usual,' said Fame.
'What is all this...?'
'Have you anything to declare?' asked Silver.
'Nothing,' said Fame.
'Have you got any luggage?'
asked Silver.
'One suitcase,' said Fame.
Silver turned to the fat customs officer.
'Go and have a look in his car,' he said.
Rank nodded, folded the newspaper, and went
outside.
Fame followed him.
'Where's the case?' asked Rank
'In the boot,' said Fame.
'Let's have a look,' said Rank.
Fame opened the boot and pulled out the case.
'Open the case,' said Rank.
Fame opened it.
Rank put his fat hands inside the case and
felt among the clothes.
He pulled out a thick brown bottle.
'What's this?' he asked Fame.
'Medicine,' said Fame, and laughed.
'Hm,' said Rank, and put the bottle back.
Then Rank looked inside the car, and under
the car and on the roof.
Fame stood and watched him.
Rank found nothing.
'Follow me,' Rank said to Fame, and the two
men went back into the customs shed.
'He hasn't got anything,' said Rank to Silver.
'Right, Mr Fame,' said Silver.
'You can go.
Goodnight.'
'Goodnight,' said Fame.
He went out and shut the door, walked down
the steps, and over to his car.
He got in and shut the door.
The guard walked over to the pole across the
road, and lifted it up.
Fame started the car and drove off.
The guard lowered the pole and watched Fame's
car disappearing into the distance.
Inside the customs hut, Rank, the fat customs
officer, picked up his newspaper again and
went on reading.
CHAPTER THREE
Strange Meeting
John Samuel Fame drove very fast along the
white road.
There was a full moon and there were no clouds
so he could see clearly, even without the
headlights.
The road was straight and flat and empty.
Fame looked at his watch.
The time was half past ten and Harker had
told him to be there at ten o'clock.
Fame realized he was already half an hour
late for his appointments He knew that Harker
would be angry with him, because Harker didn't
like people who were late for appointments.
John Samuel Fame accelerated and the car roared
forward down the white road.
After about ten minutes, Fame saw the turning
to Harker's hut.
Fame turned left and drove up a hill.
'When you get to the top,' Harker had said,
'stop the car on the edge of the wood and
walk until you reach the hut.'
Fame stopped the car and walked into the wood.
In the moonlight, it was easy to see his way,
and he walked quietly between the trees.
After about three minutes, he saw the hut.
There was a light on inside and Fame saw Harker's
car parked outside.
'When you get to the hut,' Harker had said,
'whistle three times and wait for an answer.'
Fame whistled, once, twice, three times, and
waited.
There was no answer.
He whistled again.
There was still no answer.
Where was Harker?
What was wrong?
Fame whistled again.
Still no answer.
Something was wrong.
Fame carefully walked towards the hut.
Silently, he reached the door.
It was half-open.
Fame pushed the door right open and went inside.
There was no one there.
In the middle of the room was a chair and
a desk with a lamp on it.
There were some books and papers on the desk
too.
In one corner of the room was a small black
cupboard.
The cupboard door was open and there were
some cups and glasses inside.
On one wall, there was a photograph of a young
man on a horse.
Next to the photograph, there was a large
map.
Fame crossed over to the desk.
A green pen and a small notebook were on the
desk, among the books and papers.
Fame recognized them.
They belonged to Harker, but where was Harker?
Fame was three-quarters of an hour late, so
perhaps Harker had gone.
But Harker's car was still there and his pen
and his notebook were still on the desk.
Suddenly Fame noticed the shadow.
It was moving backwards and forwards across
the opposite wall.
Fame looked up.
Hanging from the ceiling of the hut, just
to the left of the door, was a man.
He was swinging from the end of a rope.
It was Harker.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Narrow Escape
Fame stood still, looking at the swinging
man.
Below him, a chair lay on its side on the
floor.
So, thought Fame, Harker had stood on the
chair, tied the rope to the roof, tightened
the rope around his neck and jumped.
Fame picked the chair up, put it underneath
the swinging man, and climbed up on it.
He put out his hands and felt Harker's body.
Harker was still warm - he hadn't been dead
long.
Fame took a small knife out of one of his
coat pockets and putting one arm round Harker's
body, cut the rope.
Harker was a heavy man and Fame couldn't hold
him.
Harker, Fame, and the chair fell to the floor.
Fame got up and looked at Harker.
Then he knelt down and loosened the rope round
Harker's neck.
Then Fame saw some blood on Harker's shirt.
He lifted up the shirt and looked underneath.
There wasn't a mark on Harker's body.
The blood on Harker's shirt wasn't Harker's
blood.
Someone had been in that room before Fame.
Someone had fought with Harker.
Fame looked round the room.
Fame noticed a broken bottle on the floor
near the door, which he hadn't seen before.
The bottle had broken into three pieces and
the three pieces lay on the floor near the
door.
Someone had attacked Harker.
Harker hadn't hanged himself.
Some men had been in the hut before Fame.
They had fought with Harker, and then they
had hanged him.
Fame began to look through Harker's pockets
but they were empty.
Someone had already gone through Harker's
pockets and taken everything.
Fame looked round the room again.
Then he saw the bit of paper lying on the
floor, near Harker's desk.
Fame picked it up.
There was writing on the paper - Harker's
writing.
Fame looked at the writing but he could not
understand it.
It was a poem.
So Harker had written a poem.
But why?
Harker wasn't a poet.
He didn't even read poetry.
Harker was a clever man, a tough man, but
he was interested in money, not in poetry.
He read newspapers, he didn't read poetry.
Fame was about to put the poem in his pocket,
when he saw what was written on the front:
To John Samuel Fame - please read carefully.
So it was a message - a message for him.
Fame read the poem carefully but he still
did not understand it.
Do not walk easy roads.
Tall men strain under heavy loads.
They bend beneath the weight, get tired beneath
the load
They go in pain and hate they wander down
that road,
But then against the wall they stand and near
one rock they rest their hand.
Emil Harker
Just as Fame was finishing the poem, he heard
voices.
Men's voices.
The men were coming towards the door.
Fame just had time to get to the window, raise
it silently and get through before the men
reached the hut.
He landed on his feet and leant against the
outside wall of the hut.
He listened.
He could hear the two voices, one deep and
strong, the other high and nervous, with an
Italian accent.
'Someone's been here,' said the man with the
high voice.
'Someone's been here and cut him down.'
'Where's the piece of paper with the poem
on it?' said the other man, with the deep
voice.
'I don't know,' said the first man.
I can't see it.
I'm sure I must have dropped it on the floor.'
There was silence for a moment.
'It's not here,' said the man with the high
voice.
'Someone's been here and taken it,' said the
man with the deep voice.
'The window!'
shouted one of the men suddenly.
Fame didn't wait.
He ran through the trees and towards his car.
When he reached the car, he took the keys
out of his coat pocket.
Behind him, Fame could hear the shouts of
the two men running from the hut.
Fame unlocked the car door, jumped in and
started the car.
As the car roared away down the hill in the
moonlight, Fame heard the sound of guns.
CHAPTER FIVE
A Night in Darna
Fame didn't stop until he reached the town
of Darna.
It was after midnight when he stopped the
car outside the Garden Hotel.
Fame always stayed at the Garden Hotel when
he went to Darna.
There was a light on in the hotel entrance
but the door was shut.
Fame rang the bell and waited.
After a minute, the door was opened a little
and an old man put his head round.
It was the night porter at the Garden Hotel.
He'd worked there for years.
'Hello, Mr Fame,' said the porter smiling.
'You're late.'
'Yes,' said Fame, 'I had a bad journey.'
'Oh, I'm sorry,' said the porter.
'But your room's ready.'
'Good,' said Fame, 'I'm tired.'
The porter took Fame's case and led Fame into
the hotel.
Fame's room was number 18 on the first floor.
Fame had stayed there before.
It was a nice room with a view over the lake.
But tonight Fame wasn't interested in the
view.
When the porter left him, Fame sat in a chair
by the window, thinking.
Harker was dead.
That was certain.
And Harker had been murdered.
That, too, was certain.
He had probably been murdered by the two men
at the hut.
They had killed him and then hung his body
from the ceiling.
They had wanted people to think Harker had
killed himself.
But Fame knew better.
Why had they killed him?
And why had they returned to search for that
piece of paper?
The piece of paper was addressed to him.
Fame took it out of his pocket, unfolded it
and read the poem again:
Great men
Do not walk easy roads.
Tall men
Strain under heavy loads.
They bend beneath the weight,
get tired beneath the load.
They go in pain and hate
They wander down that road,
But then against the wall they stand
and near one rock they rest their hand Emil
Harker
What was the message hidden in this strange
poem?
Harker wanted Fame to understand the message
but he didn't want the other men to understand
it.
Fame tried to think about Harker.
Harker was rich, he was a smuggler, he was
powerful, and he was Fame's boss.
Harker had many enemies.
Probably he had many secrets.
Now he was dead - murdered.
What was Fame to do?
He couldn't go to the police.
The police were no friends of Harker's or
Fame's.
He couldn't go back across the frontier, not
yet.
Fame had a job to do.
He decided to ring Zara.
There was a telephone on a small white table
next to the bed.
Fame rang Zara's number and waited.
'Hello,' said Zara.
'Zara?' said Fame.
'Who's that?' said the voice.
'It's me,' said Fame, 'Fame.'
'Fame,' said the voice.
'What are you ringing at this time for?'
'I'm sorry, Zara,' said Fame, 'but I've got
to see you very soon.
Harker's dead.'
'Dead!' said Zara.
She sounded shocked.
'Yes,' said Fame.
'Look, can you come over here first thing
in the morning?
I'm at the Garden Hotel.
I'll meet you on the terrace at half past
eight.
OK?'
'OK,' said Zara, 'see you then.'
'Goodbye,' said Fame, and he put the phone
down.
Fame undressed and got into bed.
Next to the bed on the small white table was
a radio.
Fame turned on the radio to listen to the
news.
'The golden head of the Pharaoh Chefren IV,
which was stolen from the Darna Municipal
Museum yesterday evening, is still missing.
The police under Inspector Francis Roland
are still looking for the head.'
Fame smiled.
He hadn't heard about the stolen head, but
he knew Inspector Roland.
Fame turned off the radio and was asleep within
a few minutes.
CHAPTER SIX
On the Terrace
The next morning Fame was awake early.
The first thing he did was to make a copy
of the poem and then he went downstairs.
It was getting light and people were beginning
to move in the streets.
Fame went out onto the terrace.
Zara arrived an hour later.
She was looking very pretty in a light blue
dress and a dark blue headscarf.
'Hello, Zara,' said Fame.
'Hello, Fame,' said Zara.
'Sit down,' said Fame.
When they had both sat down, Fame called the
waiter and ordered two coffees.
'Well,' said Zara, 'so Harker's dead.'
'Yes,' said Fame.
And he told her what had happened.
He told Zara how he had found Harker hanging,
how the two men had then arrived and looked
for the piece of paper, how he had escaped
and spent the night at the hotel.
'And where's the poem?' said Zara, when Fame
had finished.
'Here,' said Fame.
He handed her the piece of paper and Zara
read the poem.
'There's a message hidden in the poem,' said
Zara.
'I know there is,' said Fame, 'but what is
the message?'
'I don't know,' said Zara, 'but we can find
out.'
It'll take time,' said Fame.
'And before we try and find out the answer,
what are we going to do next, now that Harker's
dead?'
'Well,' said Zara, 'the business can go on.
Don's waiting for you and the car in the hide-out
as usual.'
'Yes, but who'll be the boss now that Harker's
dead?' asked Fame.
'Ezra?'
'Not Ezra,' said Zara.
'That's something I was going to tell you.
Ezra and Harker had an argument last week
and Ezra left the gang.
He's working on his own now.'
'I see,' said Fame.
'Who's in charge then?'
'I am,' said Zara, smiling.
'You?' said Fame.
'Yes,' said Zara, 'why not?
Or don't you think a woman can lead a gang?'
'Well,' said Fame, 'I don't know...'
'Anyway,' said Zara, I'm the new boss, so
I give the orders.
And I want you to keep your appointment with
Don this morning.
Where's the car?'
'Outside,' said Fame.
Just then, the waiter came back with the two
coffees and put them down on the table.
Fame paid the waiter and he went away.
'Why did Harker and Ezra quarrel?' asked Fame.
'Ezra never liked Harker,' said Zara, 'and
then last week they argued over a job.'
'What job?' asked Fame.
'I don't know,' said Zara, 'but I think it
was something important.
Ezra shouted at Harker and Harker told him
to get out.'
'I see,' said Fame.
He was quiet for a moment.
'You don't think,' Fame asked suddenly, 'that
Ezra might have killed Harker, do you?'
'I don't know,' replied Zara.
'It's possible.'
Fame and Zara were the only two people on
the terrace.
It was already quite hot and most people were
indoors, eating their breakfast in the shade.
Then another waiter came out of the hotel
and came up to Fame.
The other waiter was a bald-headed man with
a scar on his left cheek.
'Telephone call for you, Mr Fame,' he said.
'Thanks,' said Fame.
'Excuse me a minute, Zara.'
'Of course,' said Zara.
'I'll wait here.'
Fame crossed the terrace and went into the
hotel.
The phone was lying on the desk in the hall.
Fame picked it up.
'Hello,' he said.
No answer.
'Hello?' said Fame again.
Still no answer.
'Hello, who is it?' asked Fame.
Then he heard the phone put down on the other
end.
What was going on?
Fame put his phone down and went back onto
the terrace.
Zara wasn't there, nor was the bald-headed
waiter.
Fame began to sweat.
'Waiter!'
shouted Fame.
The waiter who had brought the coffee came
out of the hotel.
'Yes sir?' he said.
'Where's the other waiter?' asked Fame.
'What do you mean?' said the waiter.
'I'm the only waiter on duty at the moment.'
'A bald man,' said Fame, 'with a scar on his
left cheek.'
A bald man with a scar,' said the waiter.
We haven't got a waiter who looks like that,
sir.'
Fame didn't wait to hear any more.
A car was starting up on the other side of
the garden wall.
Fame ran to the edge of the terrace, jumped
over the wall and down onto the pavement below.
A long black American car was pulling away
from the pavement and Fame could see the driver.
It was the bald-headed waiter.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Keeping an Appointment
Fame ran across the street and jumped into
his own car.
He started the engine and accelerated away
from the pavement.
The American car was turning into the main
road that went out of the town and into the
hills.
Fame followed it.
As long as they were in the town, Fame kept
close to the American car.
But when the two cars had left the town and
were on the hill road, the American car moved
further ahead.
Fame could just read the car number, ZX 425.
He wrote it with his finger on the dust of
the window.
Then after another minute, Fame could no longer
see the American car, but he kept going.
He was driving in the hills above Darna, looking
down over the town and the lake.
Fame knew the road well.
He took it each time he came to Darna.
The road to Don's hideout turned off this
road a few miles ahead.
Well, Zara had told him to go and see Don,
and at least he would get help there.
Don was a member of their gang.
Fame drove on as fast as he could.
He was just coming round a long left hand
bend when he saw a girl in a blue dress standing
at the side of the road and waving at him.
It was Zara.
Fame put on the brakes and the car stopped.
'Get in!' he shouted.
Zara got in.
She looked pale and worried and her right
cheek was bleeding.
'Are you all right?' said Fame.
'Yes,' said Zara, 'but he's got the poem.'
'Don't worry,' said Fame, 'I've got a copy
of the poem.
What happened?'
'Well,' said Zara, 'as soon as you'd gone
in to answer the phone, the bald-headed waiter
came over to our table.
I thought he was going to take my coffee cup.
But he suddenly held me tightly and put his
hand over my mouth.
I tried to escape but he was very strong and
had a gun.
In the car he took the poem from me and then
he left me on the side of the road.'
'Well,' said Fame.
'I've got the car number.'
'And he's got the poem,' said Zara.
'Don't worry,' said Fame, 'I've got a copy.'
'Oh yes,' said Zara, 'I forgot.'
She looked at him.
'Where are we going now?'
she asked.
'We're going to Don's,' said Fame.
'We're going to keep that appointment.'
Fame and Zara drove slowly up the road until
they came to the turning to Don's hideout.
The sun was now high in the sky and the day
was very hot.
Fame turned the car into the narrow dusty
road.
Then the road went down to a small valley
and crossed a dried-up stream.
Three or four goats were trying to reach the
few dusty leaves of an old white tree.
Fame sounded his horn twice so that Don would
know Fame had arrived.
Then he turned in at an open gate.
They were in a small yard.
To the left was a long brown shed.
To the right was a small flat-roofed house.
Some chickens ran across the yard and behind
the shed.
A fat man with a short black beard and a blue
apron came out of the shed as Fame stopped
the car.
'Hello, Don,' said Fame.
'Hello, Fame,' said Don, and seeing Zara,
he added, 'Hello, Zara.'
'Hello,' said Zara.
'We've got a lot to talk about, Don,' said
Fame.
'Go in and sit down,' said Don.
'I'll follow you.'
He spoke slowly and smiled.
When he smiled, he showed a row of shining
white teeth.
Fame and Zara got out of the car and went
into the house.
Don drove the car into the shed.
Inside the house, it was dark and cool.
The shutters were closed and there was a large
wooden table in the middle of the room.
There was a rocking chair in one corner and
several stools.
Zara sat down in the rocking chair and Fame
sat down on one of the stools.
Don came in from the yard and joined them.
He gave Fame his car keys and he sat down
on a stool.
He took a cigar and a box of matches from
his apron pocket.
He put the cigar in his mouth, struck a match
and lit the cigar.
'Well,' he said, sending a cloud of smoke
up to the ceiling, 'what's the news?'
'Harker's dead,' said Fame.
Don nearly dropped his cigar.
He opened his mouth to speak, but before he
could speak, two cars came roaring into the
yard.
Some men dressed in black jumped out of the
cars and ran towards the house.
They were policemen.
The leading man was not dressed in black.
Fame recognized him.
It was Inspector Roland.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Inspector Roland
Well, well,' said Inspector Roland, coming
into the room.
'Mr Fame.'
'Hello, Inspector,' said Fame, 'what can we
do for you?'
'You can stay where you are,' said the Inspector.
There were four policemen with the Inspector
and one of them was a very tall man.
He was holding a large gun.
He stood by the door and kept the gun pointing
at Fame, Zara, and Don.
'Excuse me, Inspector,' said Don, 'but this
is my house.'
'Shut up,' said Inspector Roland.
The other three policemen began to search
the place.
One of them crossed the yard to the shed,
one of them walked round the yard, and the
other began searching Don's house.
The tall man stayed by the door pointing the
large gun.
A clock on the wall above the rocking chair
ticked loudly.
Fame looked at Zara, Zara looked at Fame.
They both looked at Don.
All three looked at the Inspector and the
man with the gun.
Nobody said anything.
Everything was silent in the house, except
for the clock.
After a few minutes, Fame spoke to the Inspector.
'What are they looking for?' he asked.
No answer.
'What are they looking for, Inspector?'
Fame asked again.
'Shut up,' said the Inspector.
'All right,' said Fame and he was silent.
For half an hour, they sat in the cool room.
Zara looked straight ahead of her.
Don finished one cigar and lit another one,
and Fame tapped his fingers on the wooden
table.
'Don't do that!' said the Inspector suddenly.
'Don't do what?' asked Fame.
'Don't tap your fingers on the table,' said
the Inspector.
'Sorry,' said Fame and stopped tapping.
Just then, one of the men came in from the
yard.
'Inspector!'
shouted the policeman.
'There are two cars in the shed,' said the
man.
'Shall I search them?'
'I'll search them myself,' said the Inspector
and he went out with the man.
Fame looked at Don and raised his eyebrows.
Don shook his head.
The very tall policeman with the gun looked
suspiciously for Don to Fame, and his finger
tightened on the gun.
Don smoked his cigar and looked straight ahead
of him, while Fame looked at the ceiling.
Zara just smiled.
'What are you smiling at?' said Fame to Zara.
'Nothing,' said Zara.
'Nothing?' asked Fame.
'I was thinking,' said Zara.
'What about?' asked Fame.
'Life,' said Zara smiling.
Nobody talked or moved again until Inspector
Roland came back a few minutes later.
'The boot of one of the cars is locked,' said
the Inspector.
'Who's got the key?'
'I have,' said Fame.
'Give it to me,' said the Inspector.
Fame gave him the key and the Inspector went
outside again.
In a few minutes, he was back.
He called the other three policemen and they
all hurried into the room.
The Inspector and all the policemen stood
and looked at Don, Fame and Zara.
Suddenly the Inspector walked across the room
and hit Fame across the face.
'Now,' said the Inspector, 'let's talk.'
CHAPTER NINE
The Photograph
'What did you do that for?' asked Fame.
The Inspector smiled.
'I just wanted to wake you up,' he said.
'I was awake already,' said Fame.
The Inspector stopped smiling.
'I'm not here to waste my time,' said Inspector
Roland.
'I'm looking for something.'
'We noticed that,' said Don.
'You know what I'm looking for, don't you?'
said the Inspector, turning to Don.
'No, I don't,' said Don.
'Don't lie to me,' said the Inspector.
'I'm not lying,' said Don.
'What are you looking for?'
The Inspector looked hard at Don.
Then he turned to one of the policemen.
'Have you got the newspaper?' asked Inspector
Roland.
'Here it is, Inspector,' answered the policeman,
taking a newspaper from his pocket and handing
it to the Inspector.
'Yesterday's paper,' said the Inspector.
'Listen.'
And the Inspector began to read:
Famous Treasure Stolen From Museum
DARNA, Tuesday.
Late yesterday, it was discovered that the
museum's most valuable treasure, 3,000-year-old
Egyptian gold head of the Pharoah, Chefren
IV, was missing.
The Director of the Museum, Professor K. Tan
said he had no idea how the head was stolen.
The head, which is the museum's treasure,
only arrived there last week.
The Darna Police, under Inspector Francis
Roland are investigating the crime
The Inspector stopped reading and looked up.
'I heard about that,' said Fame.
'When?' asked the Inspector sharply.
'Yesterday evening,' said Fame, 'on the radio.'
He smiled.
So did Zara.
Don laughed.
The Inspector looked annoyed.
'Don't waste my time,' said the Inspector.
'What do you know about the head?'
'Nothing,' said Fame.
'Is that what you're looking for?'
'Perhaps,' said the Inspector.
Fame laughed.
'Look, Inspector,' he said, 'I didn't steal
that head.
Nor did he.'
He pointed at Don.
'Nor did she.'
He pointed at Zara.
'None of us stole it.
You're wasting your time.'
'I'm not so sure,' said the Inspector.
'Look at this.'
He handed Fame a photograph.
Fame looked at it.
The photograph had been taken inside the museum.
It showed a group of men standing round the
golden head of Chefren IV.
The men were all holding glasses and smiling.
'A lot of important people came to the museum
last week,' said the Inspector.
'There was a reception to celebrate the arrival
of the Pharaoh's head.
That photograph was taken at the reception.'
'I see,' said Fame.
'Now look very closely at the men in the photograph,'
said Inspector Roland.
Fame looked - a group of happy smiling men
at a party.
Fame didn't recognize any of the men at first.
Then he looked more closely.
There was a man on the left, half hidden by
the man in front.
It was Harker.
'Do you recognize anybody?' asked the Inspector.
'Yes,' said Fame.
'Who?' asked the Inspector.
'The man on the left,' said Fame.
'It's Harker.'
'Exactly,' said Inspector Roland, 'Harker.'
'OK,' said Fame, 'so Harker was at the reception.
What does that prove?'
'Look at the back of the photograph,' said
the Inspector.
Fame looked.
On the back of the photograph was written:
C 304 Monday
It was Harker's writing.
'Do you recognize the writing?' asked the
Inspector.
'No,' said Fame.
'Don't you?' said the Inspector.
'Well I'll tell you whose writing it is.
It's Harker's.'
'How do you know?' asked Fame.
We found the photograph in Harker's house,'
said Inspector Roland.
'And we are sure that the writing on the back
of the photograph is Harker's writing.'
'What were you doing in his house?' asked
Fame.
'Searching it,' said the Inspector.
'Why?'
asked Fame.
'We had a phone call,' said the Inspector.
'Someone told us to go to Harker's house.
They said we'd find something interesting.'
Fame was thinking fast.
So Harker had stolen the golden head, or arranged
for someone to steal it.
Someone had told Inspector Roland.
Someone who didn't like Harker.
Now Inspector Roland suspected Fame, Don and
Zara because they all worked for Harker.
But did the Inspector know that Harker was
dead?
'Have you got Harker?'
Fame asked the Inspector suddenly.
'Not yet,' said Inspector Roland, 'but we'll
get him soon.
Anyway we've got you.'
So the Inspector didn't know that Harker was
dead.
Good, thought Fame.
He had an idea.
'Inspector Roland,' Fame said.
'You're quite right.
You've got us.
But we don't know anything about the head.
Harker planned this on his own.'
Inspector Roland looked at Fame, then at Don,
then at Zara.
'It's quite true, Inspector,' said Zara, 'we
know nothing about this business.'
'In fact,' said Fame, 'Harker should have
told us about the head, but he didn't.
We don't like that.
I'm going to suggest an arrangement with you.'
'What kind of arrangement?' asked Inspector
Roland.
'You let us go,' said Fame, 'and we'll get
Harker for you.'
Inspector Roland laughed and so did the policemen.
'I can't do that,' said the Inspector.
'If I let you go, you'll leave the country
tonight with Harker and the head.'
'Look,' said Fame, 'I'll tell you what I'll
do.
Don here can stay with you, as a hostages.
Let me and Zara go and we'll get Harker for
you.'
There was silence in the room.
Inspector Roland was thinking.
Use a thief to catch a thief, thought the
Inspector.
Not a bad idea.
Fame and Zara would get Harker for him, and
then he, Inspector Roland, could get Harker
and Fame and Zara.
Not a bad idea at all.
'OK,' said Inspector Roland.
CHAPTER TEN
Room 304
Inspector Roland accepted the arrangement
and his men took Don back to the town.
Fame and Zara took one of the two cars from
Don's shed.
Now they were driving back along the hill
road towards Darna.
'Hungry?'
Fame asked Zara, as they began to drive down
to the town.
'Yes,' said Zara.
'Right,' said Fame.
'I know somewhere nice where we can eat.'
They could see the lake now.
The early afternoon sun was shining on the
little boats.
Near the bottom of the hill, Fame turned the
car off the main road and drove towards the
lake.
By the lake, there was a little restaurant.
The restaurant had a garden beside the lake,
and there were tables and chairs in the garden.
People were eating their lunch at the tables.
Fame turned the car into the little car park
by the entrance and stopped.
'Come on, Zara,' he said.
'Let's go.'
But Zara didn't move.
She was staring at the car parked next to
them.
'What is it?' asked Fame.
'Look at the number,' said Zara.
Fame looked.
ZX 425.
Of course!
It was the car in which Zara had been taken
away earlier that day.
'What shall we do?' asked Zara.
'Go and eat,' said Fame.
'We're both hungry.'
'What about our bald-headed friend?' asked
Zara.
'He won't dare do anything in public,' said
Fame.
'Come on.'
So they both went into the garden and sat
down at a table by the edge of the lake and
ordered a meal.
'Can you see him?' asked Fame, as they were
eating.
'Who?' asked Zara.
'Our bald-headed friend,' said Fame.
'No,' said Zara, 'he must be inside.'
Both Zara and Fame were very hungry and they
ate a lot.
'Well, what are we going to do next?' asked
Fame, as they were drinking coffee.
'You tell me,' said Zara.
'I thought you were the boss,' said Fame.
'I am,' said Zara, smiling, 'but this is your
plan.'
'OK,' said Fame.
'Do you remember what was written on the back
of that photograph?'
'A letter and a number and a day,' said Zara.
'C...'
'C 304 Monday,' said Fame.
'What does that mean?' asked Zara.
'Well, first of all,' said Fame, 'what happened
on Monday?'
'Lots of things,' said Zara.
'One particular thing happened,' said Fame.
'Think.'
Zara thought.
'Oh yes,' she said, 'the golden head was stolen.'
'Exactly,' said Fame.
And the golden head is supposed to be the
head of the Pharaoh Chef...'
'C for Chefren,' said Zara excitedly.
'Exactly,' said Fame again.
'The golden head of the Pharaoh which was
stolen.'
'But what about 304?' asked Zara.
'I'm not sure,' said Fame, 'but I can guess.'
'What's your guess?' asked Zara.
'I think it's a room number,' said Fame.
A room number in a hotel and I only know one
hotel which has so many rooms.'
'Which hotel is that?' asked Zara.
'The Imperial Hotel,' replied Fame.
'Ssh!' said Zara suddenly.
She was looking past Fame towards the restaurant
building.
Fame turned and looked too.
The baldheaded 'waiter' was coming out into
the garden with two other men.
One of the men was tall and dark and dressed
in a white suit.
He looked Italian.
The other man was much shorter and rather
fat.
They didn't notice Fame and Zara, but went
and sat down at another table, half hidden
by a tree.
'They didn't see us,' said Zara.
'But we saw them,' said Fame, 'and we can
watch them closely from here.
Another cup of coffee?'
'Yes please,' said Zara.
And Fame poured Zara another cup of coffee.
'Shall we go to the Imperial Hotel?' asked
Zara after a few minutes.
'Yes,' said Fame, 'but there's no hurry.
I'd like to watch those three men over there
and see what they do.'
So Zara and Fame sat in the afternoon sun
by the side of the lake drinking their coffee
and watching the three men.
Zara suddenly turned to Fame and touched his
arm.
The bald man and his two friends had finished
their lunch and were crossing the garden towards
the car park.
Fame made a sign to Zara to sit still.
They both watched the three men get into their
car and drive slowly off.
Fame paid the bill and he and Zara got into
their car.
They followed the other car into Darna.
When the car reached the town, it turned into
the market and followed the narrow streets
down to the main square - Parliament Square.
In Parliament Square, the car turned right
and followed a wide street towards the richer
part of town.
This part of town was called The Park, because
of the large public park in the middle of
it.
Along one side of the park, there was an avenue.
The avenue was full of hotels, and the largest
of the hotels was The Imperial.
The car with the three men in it stopped outside
The Imperial.
Fame stopped a little way behind them, in
the shade of some trees.
'Well,' he said to Zara, 'that's interesting.
The Imperial Hotel.'
'Are you going in?' asked Zara.
'Of course,' said Fame, 'but I want you to
stay here.'
'Why?'
asked Zara.
'In case anything happens,' said Fame.
'OK,' said Zara.
'Good luck.'
'Thanks,' said Fame and went into the hotel.
He went straight up to the reception desk.
'Is the gentleman in Room 304 in?' he asked
the porter.
The porter looked at the rows of keys behind
him.
'No sir,' he said, 'not yet.
But his friends have just arrived.
They are all up in Room 303, if you want to
go and join them.'
Fame hesitated.
So the bald-headed man and his two friends
were staying in Room 303, next to Room 304.
Who was staying in Room 304?
Fame decided to wait.
'No,' said Fame, 'I'll wait here.'
Fame went and sat in the far corner of the
foyer, just behind a pillar.
From here, he could see everyone who came
in without being seen.
He had been waiting for about five minutes,
when a tall man with a fat pale face and moustache
came in.
Fame knew him immediately.
It was Ezra.
Ezra went up to the desk.
The porter said something and pointed in Fame's
direction.
Fame turned and walked fast out of the foyer
and into the coffee lounge.
He knew the hotel well.
At the end of the coffee lounge were some
stairs, which led down to a side door; on
the other side of the door was the street.
'Well,' said Zara as Fame climbed into the
car beside her, 'you weren't long.
Did you find out anything?'
'Yes,' said Fame, 'the man staying in Room
304 is Ezra.'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Return Journey
At ten o'clock the next morning, Fame was
driving towards the frontier.
He had left Zara in Darna.
Whatever else happened, it was important for
Fame to attend to his business.
This had always been Harker's first rule:
'Keep the business going.
The business must go on.
Business first.'
And so Fame crossed the frontier three times
a week, every week of the year on business.
Nobody outside Harker's gang knew what that
business was.
Even Inspector Roland didn't know, although
he wanted to know.
And he had often tried to find out.
At the frontier post, the two customs officers
Silver and Rank were busy.
Earlier that morning, they had caught two
men trying to smuggle a large amount of money
across the border.
Silver was writing his report about the smugglers,
when the phone rang.
He picked up the phone.
'Hello,' he said, 'Frontier.
Silver speaking.'
'Inspector Roland here,' said the voice on
the other end.
'Oh hello, Inspector,' said Silver, 'what
can I do for you?'
'Keep your eyes open,' said the Inspector.
'Who for?' asked Silver.
'John Samuel Fame,' said the Inspector.
'Him again?' asked Silver.
'Yes,' said the Inspector.
'If he comes through, search his car very
carefully.'
'What are you looking for?' asked Silver.
'The golden head of Chefren IV,' said the
Inspector.
Silver whistled.
'Did Fame steal the head?' he asked.
'I don't know,' said the Inspector, 'perhaps.
Anyway, keep your eyes open and search his
car.'
'Of course, Inspector,' said Silver.
When Fame arrived at the frontier post about
half an hour later, Silver and Rank were waiting
for him.
'Good morning, Mr Fame,' said Rank.
'Going home?'
'Yes,' said Fame.
Anything to declare?' asked Silver.
'Nothing,' said Fame.
'We'd like to have a look at your car,' said
Rank.
'OK,' said Fame.
And he smiled.
For the next hour, Rank and Silver searched
Fame's car.
They searched every part of the car twice
and they even took up the carpet inside the
car.
But they found nothing - or, almost nothing.
'Have you had a crash?' asked Rank, pointing
to the side of the car.
There was a scratch above one of the wheels
and someone had tried to paint over it.
'No,' said Fame.
'Well, I don't remember this mark before,'
said Rank.
'That scratch has always been there,' said
Fame quickly.
Rank looked at Fame.
'All right, Mr Fame, you can go now.
Everything's in order.'
'Thank you,' said Fame, 'I'm glad you're satisfied.
See you tomorrow.'
'Are you coming back tomorrow?'
'Oh yes,' said Fame.
'Don't forget to search my car will you?'
And he drove off in a cloud
of dust.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Ambush
Less than twenty-four hours later, Fame was
back at the frontier.
Once again, his car was thoroughly searched,
but once again Rank and Silver found nothing.
They did not even find the scratch on Fame's
car.
Fame told them he had covered it with paint.
Fame left the frontier and drove towards Darna.
He was in no hurry and he decided to stop
for a coffee on the way.
He knew a small cafe nearby.
Fame parked his car outside the cafe and went
in.
He ordered a coffee and sat down at a small
table.
A radio was playing and Fame sat there listening
to the music.
The cafe was almost empty.
The music on the radio stopped and a voice
started to read the news.
Fame had been out of the country for a day.
He was interested in what had happened while
he had been away.
Suddenly Fame sat up straight in his chair.
The news on the radio was about Harker.
The radio said that the police had just found
the body of a man called Harker.
Fame listened.
The news said that Harker's body had been
found in a hut in the forest.
The police thought that Harker had been murdered.
Fame finished his coffee quickly and left
the cafe.
So now, Inspector Roland knew that Harker
was dead.
Don was still a hostage and now the Inspector
would be looking for Fame.
Fame decided to drive straight to Zara's house.
So he hurried over to his car, got in and
drove off towards Darna.
It was a beautiful day without a cloud in
the sky.
A slight wind moved the tops of the cypress
trees along the straight white road.
Fame began to forget his worries as he drove
along under the cypress trees in the morning
sun.
Fame didn't notice that there was a big blue
car behind him.
The blue car followed Fame for about a kilometer
along the road.
Then, just before the road began to climb
into the hills, the blue car pulled out and
accelerated past Fame and disappeared round
the bend in front.
Fame saw the blue car go past him, but he
was only half - looking at the road.
Above him, hanging in the sky, was a golden
eagle.
The eagle was hardly moving - its wings were
spread and still.
Fame slowed the car down and watched.
Suddenly the eagle dived towards the ground
and disappeared behind the cypress trees.
Then there was a scream of a small animal.
The eagle had caught something - a hare perhaps,
or a rat.
Fame drove on.
The road was now climbing and turning through
the hills.
On the other side of the hills was the valley
and the lake and the town of Darna.
Near the highest point of the road, Fame saw
a sign at the side of the road as he came
round a comer.
The sign had one word written on it: SLOW.
Fame slowed down.
Someone must be working on the road, mending
it.
Fame couldn't see anybody.
The ground on the left side of the road climbed
steeply to some trees; on the right, it fell
steeply into the valley.
The road itself was narrower than anywhere
else between the frontier and Darna.
Suddenly Fame heard a shot.
There was a loud noise very close to him and
then another.
Someone was shooting at Fame's car.
Fame tried to accelerate but the car was out
of control.
Fame tried to keep the car on the road.
Bullets were hitting the car from all sides.
Then there was a loud crack, and the windscreen
broke into hundreds of pieces of glass.
Fame could see nothing.
Fame put the brakes on as hard as he could
and felt the car slide to the left, then to
the right.
Then the car turned a complete circle and
stopped.
Fame opened the door and ran.
Then the shooting stopped.
Fame jumped over the edge of the road and
rolled down the slope.
Over and over he went until he reached the
bottom.
There were some bushes at the bottom of the
slope and Fame pulled himself into the middle
of them.
He lay there, breathing heavily.
From above him, Fame heard a voice.
It was Ezra's voice.
'All right, Fame, we've got you,' shouted
Ezra.
'Come out of those bushes with your hands
up.'
CHAPTER THIRTTEN
Another Journey
Fame got up, put his hands above his head,
and came out of the bushes.
He looked up.
Ezra was looking down at him from the top
of the slope.
Next to Ezra was the bald-headed 'waiter'
with the scar.
There were also two other men.
Fame and Zara had seen these two men at the
lakeside restaurant.
One was tall and dark, the other was short
and fat.
'Well, Fame,' said Ezra, 'nice to see you
again.'
Fame said nothing.
'Go down and search him, boys,' said Ezra.
The tall dark man and the short fat man came
down the slope towards Fame, while the bald-headed
man pointed his gun at him.
Fame kept his hands up while the two men searched
his pockets.
'He hasn't got a gun, Boss,' said the tall
dark man.
Fame recognized the voice; he had heard it
somewhere.
It was a high voice with an Italian accent.
'OK, Guido,' said Ezra, 'tie his hands.'
Guido took a piece of rope from his jacket
pocket and tied Fame's hands behind his back.
Then he and the fat man pushed Fame back up
the slope towards the road.
Fame's car was right in the middle of the
road.
Broken glass from the windscreen lay all-round
the car, and one of the tyres was flat.
'Skull,' said Ezra to the bald man, 'you stay
with his car.
Change the wheel and knock out the rest of
the glass.
Then follow us.'
'Right, Boss,' said Skull.
Ezra turned to Fame.
'You're coming along with us,' he said.
'I've got a few things to ask you.'
Ezra turned and crossed the road.
Guido and the fat man pushed Fame along behind
him.
Ezra walked a little way up the white road
and then turned off down a lane.
The branches of the trees hung low, shutting
out the sun and making the lane dark.
A big blue car was parked there.
Fame recognized it.
It was the car that had passed him earlier
while he was watching the eagle.
'Put him in the back, Robert,' said Ezra to
the short fat man.
Robert pushed Fame into the back of the car.
Then Robert sat on one side of Fame and Guido
sat on the other side.
Ezra got into the driver's seat and started
the car.
The car moved slowly forward, down the dark
lane under the low hanging trees to the main
road.
Ezra turned left and drove towards Darna.
Looking back, Fame saw that Skull had got
his car to the side of the road and was changing
the wheel.
They drove steadily towards Darna.
Ezra didn't seem in a hurry.
A few miles out of Darna, Ezra turned onto
a small road.
Fame knew this road.
It also led into Darna.
There was less chance of meeting any police
cars on this road.
'Well, Fame,' Ezra said, after a few minutes,
'so you and I are enemies now.'
Fame said nothing.
'And Harker's dead,' said Ezra.
'So I heard on the radio,' said Fame.
Ezra looked at Fame in the driving mirror.
Then he laughed.
'You heard about Harker's death on the radio,
did you?' said Ezra.
'Yes,' said Fame.
'It's a bad business.'
A very bad business,' said Ezra and laughed
again.
Fame looked out of the window.
They had reached Darna.
Ezra turned the car into a narrow lane.
The car bumped down the lane until it came
to the last house.
Ezra stopped the car.
'Take him out,' said Ezra to the two men,
'and take him inside.'
'Which room shall we put him in, Boss?' asked
Robert, the fat man.
This was the first time he had spoken, and
Fame recognized the voice immediately.
It was the voice he had heard in Harker's
hut two days ago when he had discovered Harker's
body.
And that's where he had heard Guide's voice
too.
Now Fame remembered.
Guide's voice had an Italian accent.
Robert's voice was strong and deep.
'Put him in the cellar, Robert,' said Ezra.
'We don't want to make him too comfortable,
do we?'
And Ezra laughed again.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Ezra's Place
The cellar was not a comfortable room.
It was dark and small.
Guido and Robert pushed Fame inside and locked
the door.
Fame was alone.
Hundreds of questions raced through Fame's
mind, as he stood in that small dark cellar.
What did Ezra want?
What was Ezra going to do with him?
What was Zara doing?
Where was Don?
What was Inspector Roland doing?
Where was the golden head?
What did that poem mean?
Fame wanted answers to all these questions.
The door opened and Guido came in.
'The Boss wants to see you,' he said.
'Upstairs.'
Guido pushed Fame out of the cellar and up
some stone steps.
At the top of the steps was a door.
Guido knocked.
'Come in,' said a voice.
Guido opened the door and pushed Fame inside.
Fame found himself in a large comfortable
room.
Ezra was sitting behind a large desk with
his back to a large window.
The window opened out onto a balcony.
On the floor of the room, there was a Persian
carpet and on the walls, there were tall bookshelves
full of books.
On Ezra's desk, there was a photograph.
Fame saw that it was the same photograph Inspector
Roland had showed him - the photograph taken
at the museum reception.
'Sit down,' said Ezra, pointing to a chair
in front of the desk.
Fame sat down.
Guido left the room.
'Cigar?' asked Ezra, opening a box of cigars
and holding the box out to Fame.
'My hands are tied,' said Fame.
'Of course,' said Ezra, 'how stupid of me.
Guido!' he shouted.
Guido, who had been waiting outside, came
in.
'Untie his hands,' ordered Ezra.
Guido untied Fame's hands.
'You may go,' said Ezra to Guido.
Guido left the room.
'Cigar?' said Ezra again.
'Thank you,' said Fame and took one.
'Light?' asked Ezra, picking up a cigarette
lighter from the desk and holding it out to
Fame.
'Thank you,' said Fame, leaning forward with
the cigar in his mouth.
Ezra lit Fame's cigar and sat back in his
chair.
There was a silence while both men smoked
their cigars.
'Now,' said Ezra, after the silence, 'where
is it?'
'Where's what?' asked Fame.
You know,' said Ezra.
'I don't know,' said Fame.
'The head,' said Ezra.
'Oh, the head,' said Fame.
'Yes,' said Ezra, 'the head.
The golden head - the golden Egyptian head
from the museum.'
'I don't know,' said Fame, 'I didn't steal
it.'
'I know,' said Ezra, 'I know you didn't steal
it.
Harker stole it.
But you know where it is, don't you?'
'No,' said Fame, 'I don't.'
Ezra took the cigar from his mouth and looked
hard at Fame.
Then he blew some smoke straight into Fame's
face.
'Now, Fame,' he said, 'don't be stupid.'
'I'm not being stupid,' said Fame.
'I've no idea where the golden head is.'
Ezra put his left hand into his jacket pocket
and pulled out a piece of paper.
He pushed it across the desk to Fame.
'Have you seen that before?' asked Ezra.
'Yes,' said Fame.
It was the poem Harker had written to Fame
before he was killed.
'What does the poem mean?' asked Ezra.
'I've no idea,' said Fame.
'Read it aloud,' said Ezra.
So Fame read the poem aloud.
'Well, what does it mean?' asked Ezra again,
when Fame had finished reading the poem.
'I don't know,' said Fame, 'I don't understand
it.'
Ezra pressed a little button on his desk.
The door behind Fame opened, and Guido and
Robert came in.
'Tie him up again,' said Ezra, pointing to
Fame.
Guido held Fame's hands, pulled them behind
his back, and tied them with the same piece
of rope.
Robert knocked the cigar out of Fame's mouth.
Ezra stood up and walked over to the window.
He turned round and looked at Fame.
'I've been gentle with you so far,' said Ezra,
'but I'm getting a little impatient.'
'But I don't know any...' began Fame.
'You listen to me,' said Ezra.
He was suddenly angry.
'Harker and I planned to steal the golden
head together.
We planned it.
Harker wanted the golden head and I said I'd
help him steal it.
We planned the robbery together.
I agreed to steal the head for Harker and
take it to my room in the Imperial Hotel.
But we argued.
Harker and I had an argument.
Harker got that head by himself - he got there
before me.'
Ezra paused and wiped his hand over his mouth.
At last, he was telling Fame what had really
happened.
Fame stared at Ezra, waiting for Ezra to continue
his story.
'When I discovered that Harker had stolen
the head; by himself,' continued Ezra, 'I
was angry.
Very angry.
I went to Harker's hut in the forest and we
argued.
He wouldn't tell me where he had hidden the
head of the Pharaoh.'
'So you killed him,' said Fame simply.
'Shut up,' said Ezra, 'I haven't finished
yet.
We killed Harker, but only after, we had argued.
I found this poem on Harker's desk, addressed
to you.
I asked him what it meant.
He wouldn't tell me, but I knew it was important.
I knew that there was a message hidden in
the poem - about the head.
Harker said that you would understand the
poem.
We argued.
I lost my temper and we killed him.'
'Who do you mean by "we"?' asked Fame.
'Guido, Robert and myself, of course,' said
Ezra.
'We killed Harker, hung him up and then we
left the hut quickly.'
'Why didn't you take the poem with you?' asked
Fame.
Ezra looked at Robert, who was standing behind
'That fool Robert,' said Ezra, 'had the poem,
but he must have dropped it as we were leaving.
When we realized we had lost the poem, Robert
and Guido hurried back to Harker's hut to
look for the piece of paper with the poem
on it.
But instead of finding the poem, they found
you.
And you escaped with the poem.'
Ezra paused.
He was now red in the face and breathing hard.
Fame sat still in his chair, and Guido and
Robert stood behind him.
Outside the house, a car stopped.
Fame heard the sound and realized that it
was his car.
Skull had returned.
Then Fame spoke.
'Now you have the poem,' said Fame.
'Why do you need me?'
'We need you,' said Ezra to Fame, 'because
you understand the poem.
I'll give you one more chance to tell me what
the poem means.
Where is the golden head?
What does the poem say?'
Fame said nothing.
'What does the poem say?' asked Ezra again.
Fame still said nothing.
Then Robert hit him.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Escape
Fame didn't remember afterwards how many times
they hit him.
He heard Ezra's voice asking the same question.
But he said nothing.
Ezra was very angry.
He started shouting.
'Take him back to the cellar!'
shouted Ezra.
'Leave him there for the night!
Bring him back here in the morning!
Take him away!'
So Fame was taken out and carried down the
steps to the cellar.
Guido and Robert threw him inside and locked
the door.
For a long time, Fame lay on the cellar floor.
There were several cuts on his head, and his
back and shoulders ached.
Fame fell asleep.
It was early evening when he finally woke.
With difficulty, Fame stood up and walked
towards the window.
His face and shoulders still ached and there
was dry blood on his shirt.
But he felt quite calm and his head was very
clear.
Fame thought about Ezra's story.
He now knew for certain who had killed Harker
and why.
Ezra and his men had killed Harker, because
Harker had stolen the golden head.
Harker had stolen the head, without telling
Ezra where he had hidden it.
If Fame could understand the poem, he could
learn where Harker had hidden the golden head.
Fame had to learn the meaning of the poem.
But first he must untie his hands and escape
from Ezra.
Fame looked round the cellar.
In one corner, there were a few broken chairs
and some wooden boxes.
Near the boxes was an old iron bed.
Fame walked across the cellar to the bed.
He knelt on the stone floor with his back
to the bed.
Then he moved his arms against the side of
the bed until the rope around his hands was
right against the sharp comer of the iron
frame.
Then Fame began to rub the rope against the
frame, slowly at first, then faster.
After about five minutes, the rope began to
break.
Fame rubbed harder and a moment later, the
rope broke.
His hands were free.
Slowly Fame moved his arms round to the front.
His fingers were so stiff that he could hardly
move them, and there were deep white marks
on his wrists where the ropes had been.
Fame picked up one of the broken chairs and
carried it over to the window.
He put the chair against the wall under the
window, and stood rather unsteadily on it.
Now he could see through the window.
He was looking into a yard.
In the middle of the yard was his car.
Someone had mended the windscreen.
Skull, the baldheaded man, was standing beside
the car.
It was now nearly dark.
The sun had gone and Fame could hear the evening
noises beginning - insects, children playing,
and the noise of plates as someone prepared
supper.
Fame decided to wait until it was completely
dark.
He looked at the window.
It was small but it was the only way out of
the cellar.
The window had a wooden frame and wire had
been nailed to the frame.
Fame got down from the chair and felt on the
floor for a tool to pull off the wire.
In the darkness, his hands felt something
cold and hard.
It was a large bent nail.
Fame got back on the chair and looked out
again.
Skull had disappeared.
Very gently, Fame pushed the nail under the
wire and began to pull the wire away from
the frame.
It was slow work but after about quarter of
an hour, Fame had pulled one corner of the
wire back from the frame.
Fame worked on.
It was not completely dark.
There was one dim light in the yard.
Someone came out of a door and crossed the
yard.
Fame saw his face as he passed under the light.
It was Ezra.
It took Fame about an hour to pull off the
wire.
Once he heard footsteps coming up to the cellar
door, but nobody came in.
Then Fame could hear laughter from one of
the rooms across the yard.
Ezra and his men must be having supper.
When Fame had removed the wire, he put his
head through the window and looked out.
There was no one in the yard.
He pulled his head back in and waited a moment.
All was quiet.
He started to go through the window but it
wasn't easy.
The window was small.
But Fame pushed and turned his body until
at last he was through the window.
As soon as he was in the yard, Fame went to
his car.
He looked inside.
To his surprise, Skull had left the keys in
the car.
Fame was about to get in, when a door opened
and two men came into the yard.
Fame dropped down and lay flat on the ground
beside the car.
'Well now,' said a voice, 'I think it's time
we asked our friend Fame some more questions.'
It was Ezra's voice.
'Shall I go and get him, Boss?'
It was Guide's voice.
'OK,' said Ezra.
'Bring him up to my room.'
'Right, Boss,' said Guido.
Both men moved away.
Fame did not wait.
He jumped into the car, turned the key to
start the engine and accelerated out of the
yard.
There were shouts behind him.
Looking in the mirror, Fame saw that both
Ezra and Guido, the Italian, were running.
Fame accelerated down the narrow street.
He was in a poor part of town, where all the
streets were narrow and badly lit.
There was no traffic and there were few people
in the streets.
Fame looked in the mirror again and saw that
the big blue car was following him.
Ezra was driving the blue car and Guido was
sitting beside him.
Fame drove fast but he didn't know the streets.
Ezra did.
Slowly the blue car came nearer to him.
Fame turned his car into another sloping narrow
street.
Both cars were going very fast.
Suddenly Fame saw that there was a wall ahead.
The street had no exit.
There was no way out.
Fame put on the brakes to stop the car.
The tyres screamed on the dry road and the
car moved wildly from left to right and then
came to a stop.
Fame pulled the keys out of the car and jumped
out.
To his left, there was an opening in the wall.
Beyond it was another street.
Fame ran through the opening.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Trapped!
In front of Fame was a high wall; behind him
were Ezra and Guido.
Fame could hear Ezra and Guido shouting behind
him.
They were following him through the opening
and down the narrow street.
Fame turned right suddenly and ran back down
a very small path.
There were no lights at all in the path and
once he fell over a broken box lying against
the wall.
At the end of the path, there were some steps,
which dropped into the darkness.
As Fame ran down the steps, he fell over onto
the stone pavement at the bottom.
By now, Ezra and Guido had reached the top
of the steps.
Fame couldn't see them, but he could hear
them shouting to each other.
Fame got up and ran on.
He couldn't see anything in front of him and
there was a sharp pain in his left leg, but
he had to keep going.
After about another ten metres, he suddenly
saw the black shape of a wall in front of
him.
He saw the wall too late and ran straight
into it.
Fame was trapped.
There was no way that he could escape.
On one side of him was a high wall; on the
other side were Ezra and Guido.
The wall was too high to climb, and Fame could
find no door or window that led through it.
He turned to face Ezra and Guido.
He could hear them both breathing, only a
few metres away.
'Fame!
Where are you?'
called Ezra.
'We're coming to get you,' said Guido.
'You can't escape now.'
So far, Ezra and Guido hadn't seen Fame.
They were both coming forward very slowly
towards the wall.
Fame moved a little to his left.
As he did so, he felt a piece of metal in
the wall.
It was a door handle.
Very gently, Fame turned the handle and silently
opened the door.
He opened the door wide enough to slip through.
Then, quick as a cat, he closed the door behind
him and felt to see if there was a key.
There was a large key and Fame turned it to
lock the door.
He heard an angry shout from Ezra, on the
other side of the wall.
Fame had escaped.
Fame seemed to be in a garden.
There was a smell of lemons and he could just
see the shape of a large bush to the left
of the door.
In the distance, there was a light and Fame
began to move slowly towards it.
He was walking on soft earth and the smell
of lemons was very strong.
The light was coming from the window of a
house, and Fame could see the dark shape of
the building against the sky.
He walked carefully on until he had reached
the side of the house just below the window.
There was a pile of boxes directly under the
window.
Fame reached up to pull himself on top of
the pile so that he could look through the
window.
As he was pulling himself up, Fame knocked
one of the boxes with his knee.
The whole pile of boxes fell to the ground
and Fame fell with them.
Almost immediately, Fame heard voices coming
towards him.
Suddenly someone shone a torch on Fame as
he lay among the broken boxes.
Then Fame heard a voice that he knew very
well.
'Well, Mr Fame,' said the voice.
'What a surprise to see you.
Welcome to police headquarters.'
Fame looked up from the pile of boxes on the
ground.
Looking down at him was Inspector Roland.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Plans
Fame picked himself up.
'Hello, Inspector,' he said, 'I've come to
see you.'
'So I see,' said Inspector Roland.
'Are you staying?'
'If you want me to,' said Fame.
Inspector Roland smiled.
'You're staying,' said the Inspector.
And two policemen took Fame by the arms and
led him into the police headquarters.
Fame was led into a large room with a lot
of maps on one wall and a very large painting
of the president on the opposite wall.
In the middle of the room was a long table
with eight chairs round it.
'Sit down, Fame,' said Inspector Roland pointing
to one of the chairs.
Fame sat down.
So did the others.
Apart from Inspector Roland, there were three
other people in the room - two policemen and
a woman holding a notebook.
'Well,' said Inspector Roland cheerfully,
looking at Fame.
'And where have you been?'
'Here and there,' said Fame.
'Doing what?' asked the Inspector.
'Thinking,' said Fame.
'Did you find Harker?' asked the Inspector.
'Harker's dead,' said Fame.
'I know,' said Inspector Roland.
'Did you kill him?'
'No,' said Fame, 'but I know who did.
Ezra.
Ezra and his men killed Harker.'
There was a silence.
'Do you want to tell us what happened?' said
the Inspector.
Fame began to tell the Inspector what had
happened.
He told Inspector Roland about the hut in
the forest, the argument between Harker and
Ezra, and about Harker's plan to steal the
golden head.
He told the Inspector how Harker had stolen
the head and how Ezra, Guido and Robert had
killed him.
Inspector Roland listened to Fame's story.
Then Fame told the Inspector how Ezra and
his men had captured him and asked him many
questions.
Fame explained how he had escaped from Ezra.
'I see,' said Inspector Roland when Fame had
finished.
'Very interesting, but there's something else
I'd like to know - something you haven't told
me.'
'What's that?' asked Fame.
'Where the head is.
The golden head.
Where is the golden head of the Pharaoh, stolen
from the museum by Harker?'
'I don't know where it is,' said Fame.
Inspector Roland leant forward.
'Look, Fame,' he said, 'you're an intelligent
man.
I'm an intelligent man.
Let's not play games.'
'What do you mean?' said Fame.
'Listen,' said the Inspector, 'I know you
worked for Harker and I know Ezra worked for
Harker.
Harker had a gang, didn't he?'
'Yes,' said Fame.
'Now I've been trying to catch Harker and
his gang for a long time.
You and he and the gang have been smuggling
for years, haven't you?'
'Well...' said Fame.
'Yes you have,' said the Inspector.
'I know you have.
But I don't know what you've been smuggling.
But if you don't help me, you and your friends
are going to go to prison.'
'What for?' asked Fame.
'For stealing the golden head of the Pharaoh
Chefren IV.'
'But...' began Fame.
'You could never prove that we stole the head.
You know we didn't steal it.
I've told you that Harker stole the head.'
'I think I could prove that you stole the
head,' said Inspector Roland.
'There's a lot of evidences against you.'
Fame was silent.
It was true.
There was a lot of evidence against him.
He was Harker's most important man.
He had the mysterious poem.
He had had an appointment with Harker the
night Harker was killed...
Inspector Roland took a piece of paper off
the desk and showed it to Fame.
Fame immediately recognized what was written
on the paper.
It was Harker's poem.
'Where did you get this?' asked Fame.
'From your friend,' said Inspector Roland.
'Which friend?' asked Fame.
'Your girlfriend,' said the Inspector.
'Zara?' asked Fame, amazed.
'Zara,' said the Inspector.
As he spoke, the Inspector picked up a small
silver bell from the table and rang it.
Almost immediately, the door opened and Zara
and Don came in, followed by a policeman.
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
The Poem
'Zara!' said Fame.
'Hello, Fame,' said Zara.
'Hello, Fame,' said Don.
'Hello, Don,' said Fame.
'Well,' said Inspector Roland, 'now you've
all met, I'll tell you what I'm going to do.
I'm going to leave you in this room with two
of my men to guard you, and...' he held up
Harker's poem, 'with this piece of paper.
Now, I'll give you until morning to tell me
the meaning of this poem.
If you work it out and tell me where the golden
head is hidden, you'll be free.
If you don't work it out, you'll be charged
with stealing the golden head of the Pharaoh
Chefren IV.'
'But we didn't steal it,' said Zara.
'There's a lot of evidence against you,' said
Inspector Roland, smiling.
Then he left the room while the two policemen
stayed behind.
Zara, Fame and Don looked at each other.
'Well,' said Zara, 'let's have a look at the
poem.'
Fame picked up the piece of paper.
Fame read it out:
Great men
Do not walk easy roads.
Tall men
Strain under heavy loads.
They bend beneath the weight,
Get tired beneath the load.
They go in pain and hate.
They wander down that road,
But then against the watt they stand
And near one rock, they rest their hand.
When Fame had read the poem, he looked at
Don and Zara.
'Well?' he asked.
'It's nonsense,' said Don.
'It doesn't mean anything.'
'It's a poem,' said Zara.
'It means a lot.'
'It's more than a poem,' said Fame.
'There's a message in it.'
'What message?' asked Don.
'I don't know,' said Fame.
'Let's try and find out.'
'How?' asked Zara.
'Well,' said Fame.
'Let's look at the letters at the beginning
of each line.'
Fame took another piece of paper from his
pocket and wrote down the letters at the beginning
of each line.
GDTSTGTTBA
'What does that spell?' asked Don.
'Nothing,' said Zara.
'Let's try the letters the other way round,'
said Fame.
'How do you mean?' said Don.
'Like this,' said Fame, and he wrote the letters
backwards:
ABTTGTSTDG
'What does that spell?' asked Don.
'Nothing,' said Zara.
'OK,' said Fame, 'let's try something else.
Let's take the first letter of the first line,
and the last letter of the second line...
and soon...'
'How do you mean?' asked Don.
'Like this,' said Fame, and he wrote down:
GSTSTDTDBD
'What does that spell?' asked Don.
'Nothing,' said Zara.
'Try the letters the other way round,' said
Fame.
And this time Don wrote them down:
DBDTDTSTSG
'It still doesn't spell anything,' said Zara.
'I know,' said Fame.
'It's nonsense,' said Don.
Fame shook his head.
The two policemen were watching them from
the other end of the room.
'I've got an idea,' said Zara suddenly.
'Take the first letter of the first line and
the second letter of the second line, and
so on.'
'How do you mean?' asked Don.
'Like this,' said Zara.
'Fame, what's the first letter of the first
line?'
'G,' said Fame.
'And the second letter of the second line?'
asked Zara.
'O,' said Fame.
'And the third letter of the third line?'
'L.'
'And the fourth letter of the fourth line?'
'A.'
'And the fifth letter of the fifth line?'
'B.'
'And the sixth letter of the sixth line?'
'R.'
'And the seventh letter of the seventh line?'
'I.'
'And the eighth letter of the eighth line?'
'D,' said Fame.
'And the ninth letter of the ninth line?'
'G.'
'And the tenth letter of the tenth line?'
'E,' said Fame.
'What does that spell?' asked Don.
He was laughing.
'Let's see,' said Fame.
GOLABRIDGE
Fame looked at Zara.
She was looking at Fame.
She was going to shout but Fame stopped Zara
from shouting.
They had discovered the message hidden in
the poem, but Fame didn't want the policemen
to know.
Fame made a sign.
'Oh dear, it doesn't spell anything,' he said
loudly.
He looked at the two policemen.
They weren't even looking.
'Gola Bridge,' whispered Zara.
'So that's the message in the poem.'
'Gola Bridge,' whispered Don, 'of course,
the bridge over the River Gola, not far from
my hideout.'
'So that's where the head's hidden,' whispered
Fame.
Fame looked at the policemen again.
One of them was looking out of the window
and the other was yawning.
Fame looked at Zara.
Zara nodded.
She understood what Fame wanted to do next.
She coughed.
The two policemen looked at her.
'Excuse me,' said Zara.
'What do you want?' asked one of the policemen.
'I'd like a drink of water,' said Zara.
'I'm thirsty.'
'All right,' said the policeman.
'I'll get you a drink of water.'
And he went out of the room to get a glass
of water for Zara.
There was now only one policeman in the room.
'Excuse me,' said Fame to the policeman.
'What do you want?' said the policeman.
'We want some help,' said Fame.
'What with?' asked the policeman.
'This poem,' said Fame.
'What's the difficulty?' asked the policeman,
coming over to Fame.
'Is this letter a G or a Y?' asked Fame.
The policeman bent over the bit of paper.
Very quickly, Don moved behind the policeman
and hit him hard on the back of the head with
his open hand.
The policeman fell onto the floor.
'Quick,' said Don, 'the other policeman will
be back soon.'
Don stood behind the door and Fame and Zara
stood in front of the fallen policeman.
The door opened and the other policeman came
in, carrying a glass of water.
'I've brought you your...' said the policeman.
But he didn't finish the sentence.
Don held him from behind and hit him.
The glass dropped onto the carpet.
Don caught the policeman as he fell.
'Into the garden,' said Fame to Don and Zara.
They opened the door into the garden and went
out.
Behind them on the table lay the piece of
paper with 'GOLABRIDGE' written on it.
CHAPTER NINETEEN
The Search
Fame led Zara and Don back through the garden
to the door in the wall and out into the street.
They walked back quietly to where Fame had
left his car.
The moon had come up, lighting the paths and
the streets.
There was no sign of Ezra or Guido.
There was no sign of their car either.
But Fame's car was still there.
Zara, Don and Fame got into the car quickly.
Fame backed the car up the narrow street,
turned, and drove out of Darna.
Zara and Don didn't ask where they were going.
They knew where they were going.
The moon was shining brightly and it was a
warm night.
Fame drove fast through the empty streets
and into the country.
They passed the turn to Don's hideout and
then Fame turned the car off the main road
and down a lane.
After about two kilometres, they heard the
sound of running water.
It was the sound of the Gola river running
down to Lake Darna.
Fame stopped the car before the bridge and
the three of them looked out.
They could see the huge black shape of the
Gola Bridge in front of them.
Above them on one side of the road, was a
steep hill.
On the other side, was a steep drop down to
the river.
'We're here,' said Fame.
They looked at the bridge.
'Where do we begin the search?' asked Zara,
'The bridge is so big.'
'I don't think the head is hidden on the bridge
at all,' said Fame.
'Where is it hidden then?' asked Don.
'Look at the poem again,' said Fame.
He took the poem out of his pocket.
Then he got a torch from the car and switched
it on.
They all looked at the poem.
'Right,' said Fame, 'listen.
Zara discovered the most important thing:
the words "Gola Bridge".
But the bridge is very big and there's nowhere
very safe to hide the head.
I think the head is somewhere very near the
bridge.
Now there are some clues in the poem.
Listen:
'"Great men Do not walk easy roads."'
'What does that mean?' asked Don.
'You know the old quarry up there on the hillside,
don't you?' asked Fame.
'Of course I do,' replied Don.
'My father used to work in the quarry.'
'Well,' said Fame, 'the path to the quarry
is rough and difficult, isn't it?'
'Yes, it is,' Don agreed.
'And the workers who went up and down to the
quarry carried heavy loads, didn't they?'
asked Fame.
'That's in the fourth line of the poem: "Strain
under heavy loads.'"
'Then the Pharaoh's head must be hidden in
the quarry,' said Zara.
'Yes, it must be hidden very near the quarry,'
replied Fame.
'But listen to the last two lines of the poem.
There are two more clues in the poem:
"But then against the wall they stand And
near one rock, they rest their hand.'"
Fame looked up at the others.
They were all silent for a moment and then
Don shouted out.
'I know what the last two lines of the poem
mean,' he shouted.
'The wall is the wall of the quarry.
When you get to the quarry, you come to the
quarry wall, don't you?'
'Yes, you do,' said Zara.
'And next to the quarry wall there is a large
rock,' said Don.
'In the rock there is a small cave.'
Don looked at Zara and then at Fame.
They all smiled.
So the Pharaoh's head was hidden in the rock,
next to the quarry wall.
They got out of the car and walked up the
narrow path to the quarry.
The moon threw the shadows of the bushes across
the path.
It was very quiet.
When they got to the quarry, they walked to
the quarry wall.
They could see the shape of a large rock by
the wall.
'Come on,' said Fame and began to climb up
the side of the rock.
Don and Zara followed him.
The rock was quite easy to climb.
Near the top of the rock was a small cave.
Fame flashed the torch in the darkness.
Something shone.
Fame ran forward and picked up something.
It was the golden head of the Pharaoh.
'What are you going to do with it?' asked
Don.
'Send it to Inspector Roland, of course,'
said Fame.
'He wants the head.
We don't want it.
We just want to continue with our usual business.
Yes, we'll send the head to Inspector Roland.'
'Oh no, you won't,' said a voice.
It was Ezra, standing just below the rock
with a gun in his hand.
With him were Guido the Italian, fat Robert,
and Skull.
They all had guns.
CHAPTER TWENTY
Shot Dead
'Come down,' said Ezra.
Fame, Zara and Don came down, carrying the
head.
'I'll take that,' said Ezra, pointing to the
golden head.
Fame gave the head to Ezra, and Ezra smiled.
'At last,' said Ezra.
'Very clever,' said Fame.
'Yes, it was quite clever, wasn't it?' said
Ezra.
'We simply followed you here.'
'How?' asked Fame.
'I knew you'd come back to your car,' said
Ezra.
'We simply waited round the corner until you
did come back.
Then we drove behind you, parked the car a
little way from the bridge and walked.
We could hear you up by the quarry, so we
followed you up the quarry path.'
'And now, here you are,' said Fame.
'Exactly,' said Ezra.
'What are you going to do with us?' asked
Fame.
'Well,' said Ezra, 'we don't really need you
anymore, so I think we'll send you on a journey.'
'A journey?' asked Don.
'Yes,' said Ezra.
'Come with us.'
He pointed with his gun to the path from the
quarry down to the road.
'That way,' he said.
So Fame, Don, and Zara walked back down the
path followed by Ezra and his men with their
guns.
When they reached the road,
Fame's car was still parked on the road facing
the bridge.
Ezra whispered something to Guido.
Guido got into Fame's car and turned it across
the road.
Fame's car now faced the edge of the slope
that dropped steeply down to the river.
'Now,' said Ezra, 'you three are all going
to get into your car, and then you Fame, are
going to drive it over the slope and into
the river.
I hope you can swim, because if not, there'll
be a little accident.'
Ezra smiled; the Italian smiled; Robert smiled;
even Skull smiled.
Fame, Zara, and Don, didn't smile.
'Come on,' said Ezra, 'get into the car.'
Fame opened the door slowly.
'Why don't you let us go?' he asked Ezra.
'Because I don't like you,' said Ezra.
'Get in!'
Fame got into his car and so did Zara and
Don.
In front of them was the steep drop down to
the river.
'Now start the car,' said Ezra.
Fame started the car.
Below them lay the river.
The moon was reflected in the river.
'Goodbye,' said Ezra, waving at them and smiling.
'Have a safe...'
But Ezra never finished his sentence.
Suddenly, there was the sound of a gun up
the lane.
Ezra stood with his mouth open, and one arm
in the air.
Then he turned slowly and fell.
Fame looked down the lane and saw three men
running towards the car.
Fame recognized the man who was carrying the
gun.
It was Inspector Roland.
Fame did not wait.
He turned his car back onto the road and accelerated
towards the bridge.
Inspector Roland saw the car race across the
Gola Bridge and disappear.
The Inspector bent down beside the body of
Ezra and quietly picked up the golden head
of the Pharaoh Chefren IV.
His men were taking away Guido, Robert and
Skull.
'Well,' said the Inspector to the Pharaoh,
'welcome back.'
CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE
A Long Time Later
It was five years later.
Chief Inspector Roland was abroad, on holiday.
He was staying in a small fishing town beside
the sea.
One evening, he was sitting at a cafe table
on the pavement, drinking a cup of coffee
and smoking a cigarette.
He leant back and blew a puff of cigarette
smoke into the sky.
It was a beautiful warm night with a full
moon.
The sky was full of stars.
He felt very happy.
Inspector Roland shut his eyes...
'Inspector Roland!' said a voice.
The Inspector opened his eyes.
Someone was calling him.
Standing on the other side of the cafe table
was John Samuel Fame.
There was a woman beside him.
It was Zara.
Inspector Roland stood up.
'Fame,' he said, 'and Zara.'
'Hello, Inspector,' said Zara.
'Sit down,' said Inspector Roland.
Please sit down.'
So Fame and Zara sat down, and Inspector Roland
ordered two more coffees, and they talked.
They talked for a long time - into the early
morning - like old friends.
Inspector Roland told them about the golden
head, which was now safe in the Darna museum,
and about Guido and Robert and Skull, just
out of prison and now leading honest lives.
The Inspector told them about Harker and Ezra,
buried side by side in the hill cemetery above
Darna.
Fame and Zara told the Inspector about their
marriage, about their two children, about
their house and garden and their happiness
together.
It was one o'clock in the morning when Fame
looked at his watch.
'We must go,' he said to Zara.
'I'm tired.'
They both stood up.
'Goodbye, Inspector,' said Fame, shaking hands,
'it's been wonderful meeting you again.'
'I've enjoyed it,' said the Inspector smiling.
'Goodbye, Zara.'
'Goodbye, Inspector,' said Zara.
And she smiled.
They turned and started to walk down the street.
Inspector Roland watched them.
Then he remembered.
'Fame!' he shouted.
Fame stopped and turned.
'Yes?' he said.
'One question,' said the Inspector.
'What were you smuggling all those years,
when you worked for Harker?'
There was a silence.
Fame looked at Zara.
She nodded.
Fame turned to the Inspector again.
'Cars,' he said.
The Inspector stood with his mouth open.
'Cars!' he said, amazed.
'Yes,' said Fame, 'cars.'
'But,' said the Inspector, 'you only had one
car.'
'That's what you thought,' said Fame, smiling.
'You mean that every time you crossed the
frontier you were driving a different car?'
asked the Inspector.
'That's right,' said Fame.
'The number plate was always the same and
the colour and type of car was always the
same, but it was a different car each time.'
'But how...?' said the Inspector.
'Why...?'
He was speechless.
'Very simple,' said Fame.
'On my side of the frontier, we made cars;
on your side of the frontier you needed cars.
On my side of the frontier, cars were cheap;
on your side of the frontier, cars were expensive.
So, I drove a new car from my country into
your country.
I told the customs it was my car.
When I got to Don's hideout, Don took the
new car.
Then he gave me a secondhand car same color,
same type as a new car and I drove back to
my country.
Each time I came into your country, I was
in a new car but the car's number was the
same.
So we made a lot of money; we paid no tax
and we sold the new cars for a good price.
And nobody guessed.
You all looked inside the car; you didn't
look at the car itself...'
There was a silence.
'Well,' said the Inspector, 'I don't know
what to say.'
'Say nothing,' said Fame.
'It was all a long time ago.'
And turning, Fame took Zara by the hand and
walked away.
- THE END -