The Jacket
Young people should be given chances in life
- especially the chance of a good education.
Sometimes that means going to study in another
country, far from home and family.
Young Tuaine is at school in New Zealand,
but her home is on a South Sea island, where
the warm waters of the lagoon are as blue
as the sky above...
June 24
I am going to use this big notebook for my
diary, and write down everything I feel and
do.
I brought the book with me when I left home.
I used it for English at my school back home,
and when I left, there were still plenty of
pages not written on, so it will be good for
a diary.
At home I read a story called The Diary of
Anne Frank.
It was a very sad story, but I read it lots
of times.
Anne said it made her feel better to write
things down, it helped her with all those
troubles she had, so maybe my diary will help
me feel better too.
Tomorrow it will be two months since I left
home to come here.
61 days.
Just two numbers when I write it like that,
61 days, but it is the slowest and longest
time I can remember.
How can 61 days go so slowly?
I still think of home all the time, and I
can remember every little thing about the
island, except how warm it was.
I can't remember that, because here it is
so cold all the time, but when I lie here
and close my eyes I can see my friends, and
my family, and all my favourite places.
Mama and Papa, and Mele and Metua, and Rima,
and the big black rock where we swam in the
lagoon, and the path that goes to the top
of our mountain, and the cool wind at the
top.
And if sometimes I can't remember everything,
there are the photos by my bed, and all my
seashells.
When I was a baby, I was given to my grandparents,
because I was the youngest in our family,
and that is our custom.
My real parents live on another island.
Our village is called Vaipaka, and our house
is a little bit back from the road that goes
through the village, by the hill.
When the last big storm - called Sharon - came,
the waves from the lagoon came right over
the road, but not as far as our garden, which
was lucky.
The wind blew all the flowers out of our garden,
but at least the roof stayed on our house,
not like at Mele's place.
A great piece of metal blew off their roof,
right over the house, and cut their goat's
head off.
It was terrible for the poor animal.
There were some bad things that happened in
our village, like Sharon, and some accidents
on the motorbikes, but mostly there were good
things, and I remember the good things, not
the bad things.
School was good too, I liked it at the college,
and I nearly always came top of my class.
But I'm sorry about that now, it was coming
top that probably sent me away.
We had exams in the first term, and I came
first or second in every exam.
Mr Ashton, the teacher, came to our house
and said to Mama and Papa that our school
on the island wasn't good enough for me, that
I should go to school in New Zealand.
Mama and Papa talked about it to Uncle George.
I was worried, because I didn't want to go
away, but they talked about it again with
Mr Ashton, and all my family put in some money
for the plane and sent me here to Aunty Vaine's.
Aunty Vaine is my mother's cousin, and she
has been living in Auckland for over twenty
years.
There's four of us here in her house: Aunty,
Ta (he's seventeen), Marlene, and me.
Marlene and I sleep in the same bedroom.
She's six.
The week after I arrived, Aunty bought me
a uniform, and I started at the girls' college.
I've got to stop my diary now, the video has
finished, and Marlene wants to go to bed.
JUNE 25
At first, Aunty was friendly.
She asked me all about home and all the relations
she hadn't seen for so long, and she told
me the things she used to do when she was
a girl on the island.
Then she asked me how much money did I bring
with me from the island, and I said I didn't
bring any, and she got a bit angry.
I told her Mama and Papa didn't have any money
to give me, and they told me that Aunty had
a good job and earned plenty of money.
Aunty said she worked in the chicken factory,
but she didn't get much money and most of
it went on paying the rent for the house.
Then I asked her where was my uncle?
I didn't like to ask about him at first because
perhaps he had left her or something.
Aunty started crying then and told me about
the accident.
Uncle Ben worked for a building company that
made bridges.
One day one of those very long, heavy pieces
of metal fell on him.
His back was broken, and he died in hospital.
I told her I was very sorry I didn't know
about the accident, nobody at home heard about
it.
She said Uncle Ben didn't come from our islands,
he was from Niue, so she only told his family.
I felt really sad for Aunty then, and bad
that I came to live with her when she didn't
have enough money.
JULY 1
I haven't been able to write in my diary recently.
I have had too much schoolwork to do.
School is very hard here, but the teachers
are nice.
My class teacher Mrs Price is best, she's
great, she introduced me to lots of girls.
But they aren't from my island, they're Samoans,
and their language is very strange to me.
The school is so big, too, over a thousand
girls, and so many rooms.
It is scary, in a school where there are so
many strangers.
Everyone seems cleverer than me, their English
is so good.
I try hard to keep up, but I get much lower
marks than I did at home.
I don't have enough time to do my work, that's
the trouble.
Aunty is working evenings at the chicken factory,
and I have to get the dinner every night.
The only place I can study is in the bedroom,
and the noise from the video is so bad.
Every night Ta gets some videos, and always
they are noisy, full of shooting and wars
and shouting.
I hate that Sylvester Stallone.
I think it's bad for Ta to watch just that
kind of video.
Marlene too.
Yesterday I went and asked Ta please could
he turn the video down because I was trying
to study in my room, and he got angry and
shouted bad words at me.
He thinks he's so special.
What a laugh, he's just a stupid boy who can't
get a job.
He won't turn down the video.
I'm going to bed now.
JULY 5
It's Sunday, but we didn't go to church.
Aunty used to go to church but she never goes
now.
When I asked why, she said she didn't believe
in God any more.
I thought that was terrible and I asked her
why.
She said it was because God took Uncle Ben
away from them, and left them with no one
to take care of them, and not enough money.
I don't know if that's right, but I can understand
the way Aunty feels.
I'm not sure about God.
He can be very cruel sometimes, even to good
people like Anne Frank and Uncle Ben.
In the afternoon we took the bus to visit
Uncle Ben's grave.
There is a smiling photo on the grey stone,
and shiny black letters,
BENJAMIN FILIGI, AGED 48 YEARS, MUCH LOVED
HUSBAND AND FATHER.
We all cried at the grave, even Ta, when Aunty
put the flowers on it.
In the photo on his grave, Uncle Ben looks
like he was a nice man.
JULY 10
I didn't go to school today.
I wanted to, but it's a long way and I have
to get the bus, and the bus ticket costs a
lot of money.
Aunty said she didn't have any money left.
She was getting angry with me, so I thought
I will walk to school tomorrow instead of
getting the bus.
Today I tried to do my schoolwork by myself
at home, but I didn't do very well.
JULY 11
I am very tired tonight.
This morning I got up at six o'clock and made
some sandwiches for my lunch, and I left before
any of the others were up.
It was still dark, and very scary because
there was nobody in the streets.
I walked right down Dominion Road, and slowly
the sky got lighter.
My school bag was hurting my shoulder, and
I was trying to remember the way the bus went
from the time when I had a ticket.
In the end I got to the school, but it took
a long long time and I was late, and the teacher
at the gate took my name and I had a detention.
That was the first time I ever had one.
My class teacher Mrs Price asked me why I
was late.
I didn't like to tell her my Aunty didn't
have any money for the bus, so I said I slept
in.
Mrs Price asked me how I was getting on here,
and she seemed a bit worried.
At lunchtime she brought a fifth-form girl
called Moana who was from my country to see
me.
Moana and I talked in our language.
She doesn't come from my island, but I knew
some cousins of hers.
I enjoyed talking to Moana, but it made me
sad because I began thinking about home and
all the people I knew.
When I told Moana about walking to school,
she took me to the school library and showed
me a street map.
We saw that there was a much shorter way for
me to come to school, I don't have to follow
the bus route.
Moana asked me if I would like to come to
her place one day, but I saw on the map that
she lives at Te Atatu, too far away from my
place.
I walked home that quicker way that I found
on the map, but because of my detention I
didn't get home until six o'clock.
I am very tired tonight, I can't write any
more.
JULY 12
Aunty gave me two dollars this morning.
I had to decide if I will spend it on the
bus fare or some lunch.
There was only fried bananas for breakfast
because Aunty doesn't get paid until tomorrow,
so I decided to walk to school and buy my
lunch.
At the end of one street there was a bridge
over the motorway that was just for pedestrians.
I stopped and looked down at the motorway.
All those cars!
It was like a great river running into the
city.
Then it started to rain.
It rained and rained, very heavy, like it
does at home, but very cold.
I don't have a coat or jacket, so I got wet
through, on my hair, down my neck, on my legs,
in my shoes.
I kept on walking towards school, and getting
wetter and wetter and colder and colder.
Then I saw a clock on a building that said
five minutes to nine.
That was too late for school so I turned round
and walked home again, and I was so cold I
had to get into bed to keep warm.
I didn't get up until Marlene came home from
school.
JULY 13
Aunty is working daytime at the factory now,
so she told Marlene and me to stay home from
school and do the shopping.
We walked to the supermarket and after we
had done the shopping there was some money
left over.
We were very hungry, so I got us some Kentucky
Fried Chicken for lunch.
It was so good!
Marlene and I took the chicken to the park
and ate it there.
When people went past us, they stared.
I knew they were thinking, why aren't those
girls at school?
Maybe they would tell the police, so I said
to Marlene come on, we ought to get home now.
I felt bad about using Aunty's money for Kentucky
Fried Chicken, and I told Marlene not to say
we had it.
I won't do that again.
I went to bed in the afternoon, I didn't feel
very well.
My head aches and I think I'm getting a cold.
JULY 18
I didn't write in my diary for a few days,
because I stayed in bed with a really bad
cold.
I felt miserable.
I've missed a lot of school now, and I don't
know how I will catch up.
Exams are next month and I'm very worried
about them.
Always at home I did well in exams, but I
can't here.
I lie on my bed and stare at my photos and
the trochus shell that Papa gave me.
When I put the shell to my ear, I can hear
the lagoon whispering to me.
The trochus shells are very special to us.
Once every year the people from the villages
can get the trochus from the lagoon, but only
a few for each family, so there will always
be more for next year.
The shells are polished for the tourists.
But Papa polished this trochus just for me,
and it is so beautiful with all the different
colours, it is like holding a rainbow in my
hand.
Even the darkness here doesn't stop the trochus
from shining.
JULY 19
I had a very bad day today.
When I woke up, I decided I must go to school
and catch up my work so I will do well in
exams and get a good report to send home to
Mama and Papa.
So I said to Aunty 'I'm going back to school,
'I'm walking but please could I have some
money for my lunch?
Then Aunty got very mad, and she shouted at
me: 'I've got no money left for you!
I haven't even got enough money for my own
children!
Why did you have to come here anyway?'
I told her I didn't really want to come, and
I'm sorry for all this trouble I am giving
her.
I said I don't like it here and I want to
go home.
Aunty got even angrier and said she didn't
even have enough money for the bus, so how
is she going to pay for a plane ticket?
She said she didn't ask me to come here, she
only said yes because she couldn't say no
to her family.
She said if I want to go home my family should
send the money to pay, and I said they couldn't
because they spent all their money sending
me here.
I felt really miserable then and ran out of
the room, crying.
Everything here is money.
Money for food, money for buses, money for
warm clothes, money for shoes.
Back home we only need money for the motorbike
and a bit of food from the shop.
We get everything from the lagoon and the
fields, and we don't worry about money.
But here money makes me frightened, because
there isn't enough, and I feel bad that Aunty
has to get more because of me.
I don't know what to do.
There is no telephone here to ring, or at
home.
All I can do is lie on my bed and stare at
my photos and hold my trochus shell.
No school again today.
JULY 20
Raining again.
I didn't go to school.
I did some cleaning in the house and watched
some TV There was a knock on the door but
I didn't answer it.
The person put a letter in the letter box,
and later I went out to get it.
It was addressed to Aunty, and I opened it.
It said because I hadn't been to school, my
Aunty should visit the school immediately.
I put the letter in the rubbish.
I don't want Aunty to get mad again, but I'm
worried.
I know it's against the law to not go to school
but I can't go back.
I'm too far behind.
Perhaps I can leave school and get a job in
an office.
That would help Aunty with the money.
JULY 21
So much happened today, I never had a day
like it in my life.
Ta gave me some money for the bus, and told
me how to get downtown.
I caught the bus and ended up in Queen Street,
the first time I have been there.
So many grand buildings!
It was like a TV programme.
I began to walk up Queen Street, but there
was a freezing cold wind, and then it started
to rain, and felt even colder.
I couldn't stop staring in the shop windows.
All those lovely things!
In one shop they were selling holidays, and
there was a big photograph of home, showing
my island!
It was a very beautiful picture, the lagoon
so blue, and the sea all around so dark, and
the whiteness where the waves break on the
reef round the lagoon.
I wanted to say to people in the street, 'Look,
there's my island, isn't it beautiful?'
But all the people were just hurrying past,
not stopping, not noticing.
I kept on walking up Queen Street, I was looking
for a clothes shop, because I needed a jacket.
The wind went right through my clothes, I
felt I wasn't wearing anything at all.
I came to a very big shop and went in.
There were lots and lots of jackets, but I
saw one of the shop people staring at me,
so I went back out into the cold and kept
on walking.
After a while I came to another shop which
sold jackets.
I was very worried about what I was going
to do, but I was so cold and I didn't really
care how wrong it was.
I just didn't want to get caught.
I went into the shop and started looking at
the jackets.
I had a white supermarket bag in my pocket,
and I got it out, took a blue jacket and put
it in the bag as quickly as I could.
My hands were shaking, and I wanted to run,
but instead I walked around slowly and pretended
to look at some coats, then I walked out.
I didn't stop until I got to the bridge over
the motorway.
I took out the jacket and saw the price on
it - 125 dollars!
I put it on.
It was so warm!
It's got wool inside and it keeps the rain
out and everything.
I wore it to just before I got home.
Then I put it back in the bag and hid it under
my bed.
JULY 22
I couldn't sleep all last night.
It was very bad to take that jacket from the
shop.
The church says you must not steal, and I
can't forget that.
I have heard it all my life.
I won't wear the jacket again.
I am too ashamed.
Anne Frank did not steal, not even food when
she was nearly dead from hunger.
JULY 23
Saturday today.
Ta got three videos, all fighting and shooting.
I can hear through the wall, and it sounds
like a war is going on.
At home on Saturday night we used to go across
to the big holiday hotel on the little island
of Tokoa.
We used to sit under the trees and have fruit
drinks, and watch the dancing for the tourists.
It was beautiful there, and I loved the dancing
and the music.
I want to dance at Tokoa when I am older.
I decided what to do about the jacket.
On Monday I will take it back to the shop.
JULY 25
So much happened today.
I will have to write it down very carefully
to make sure I don't miss anything.
When I woke up I put the jacket in my school
bag and told my Aunty I'm going to school.
I walked into town and waited until it was
after nine o'clock, then I walked to the shop.
There weren't many people inside, and I went
over to where the jackets were and quickly
started to take the jacket out of my bag.
But as I did it, I looked up and saw a lady
with grey hair watching me from the other
side of some dresses.
She saw what I was doing and came over.
'What are you doing?
Did you take this?'
she said.
Her voice was very cross.
I couldn't explain to her that I was bringing
it back because I had taken it before.
I thought she wouldn't believe me.
She said, 'Come with me,' and she took my
arm and we went over to the back of the shop.
I started to cry.
We went into an office, and there was a man
in there sitting at a desk.
He was a young man in a suit.
The lady told him she had found me taking
the jacket, and the man said, 'Is this right?'
and I just nodded.
I couldn't stop crying, so I couldn't explain.
I will have to go to court, I thought, and
my family will be so ashamed of me.
The man told me to sit down and he rang someone
on his telephone.
'It's a shoplifter,' he said.
Then the man asked me my name and my address
and my school, and I told him those things.
After a bit a police lady came in, and the
shop lady went out.
The police lady was young and pretty, with
dark hair.
She sat down and asked me questions in a kind
voice, and it was easier to talk to her than
those other ones.
I told her all about the jacket and what I
did.
She said to the man, 'I think she's telling
the truth, and I think we should talk to someone
from the school first.'
The man looked cross, but he said, 'All right,
I have to agree.
This is unusual.'
'Very unusual,' the police lady said.
'I never heard of a shoplifter who took back
what she stole.'
She smiled at me, and asked, 'Who would you
like us to talk to from school?'
When Mrs Price came in, she looked just as
usual, not worried or anything.
But I started crying again because I was so
ashamed, and she sat down next to me and said,
'Don't worry, Tuaine, everything will be all
right.'
Then she and the police lady talked, and they
seemed really friendly to each other.
I don't think the shop manager liked that
and he still looked angry.
Mrs Price asked me why I hadn't been to school.
She has got grey hair, but her face is young
and she talks in a very kind way.
I told her about the money, and Aunty and
my uncle and how he was killed.
And about the exams and how I was worried
about them, and how I got cold when I went
out and how I took the jacket.
I said I was very ashamed for what I did.
When my story was finished, Mrs Price looked
at the police lady, and then they both looked
at the manager.
The police lady said, 'The jacket has been
returned, Mr Jackson, and I really don't think
this girl is a thief.'
The manager didn't look at her, but he nodded
his head.
I said to him, 'I'm very sorry I took your
jacket.
I will never do it again.'
He stood up and nodded again, and Mrs Price
said, 'I'll take you home now, Tuaine.'
Mrs Price and I sat in her car outside my
house.
She talked slowly and I felt she was thinking
deeply about everything she was saying.
She said, 'We can give you extra lessons at
school to help you catch up.
And I'll find out if your Aunty can get some
money from the government, I'm sure she can.
That will help with the clothes problem...'
Then Mrs Price stopped, and she looked at
me for a long time without speaking.
She has very clear grey eyes, very kind and
understanding, and her eyes seemed to see
a long way into me.
'Or,' she said in a slow voice, 'would you
just like us to arrange for you to go home?'
I looked back into those grey, kind eyes.
The way she said it, I knew it was really
possible.
Tears came back into my eyes.
Through them I saw a house, and faces, and
the lagoon, shining and blue.
'I would like to go home,' I said.
- THE END -