CHAPTER ONE
The Greek World
On his black warhorse Bucephalas, Alexander,
king of Macedonia, rode at the head of his
army.
Unlike most of his soldiers, he had no beard.
His skin was fair and his light-coloured,
wavy hair grew long and low on his neck.
He was in India, and proud of the past few
years.
Finally, he had proved that he was the greatest
general in history.
And he now ruled the greatest empire that
the world had ever seen.
His soldiers had joined him from many parts
of the world.
There were Thracians, Macedonians and Greeks
from southeastern Europe; Scythians, Bactrians
and Sogdians from central Asia; and Indians,
riding their enormous, armoured war elephants.
It seemed that no one could stop the march
of this extraordinary army.
Certainly not the Persians, who had once ruled
much of Asia but were now completely defeated
by Alexander the Great.
Two centuries earlier, the Persians' enemy
in Europe was Greece, not Macedonia.
In those days, and during Alexander's lifetime,
Greece was not a country.
It was a collection of independent city-states
which shared a language, a religion and a
way of life.
Athens and Sparta were two of the most famous
city- states, but there were almost 1,500
others.
They were not only found in the area that
we call Greece today.
Greek people lived in coastal areas all around
the Mediterranean and the Black Sea.
Naples in Italy, Marseille in France and Izmir
in Turkey all started life as Greek city-states.
By 500 BC, the Greek city-states in Asia had
lost their independence.
They were under the control of the Persian
Empire and had to pay high taxes to the Persian
king, Darius I. In 499 BC, they fought for
their independence, with the help of the Athenians.
Unfortunately, they suffered a serious defeat.
As punishment for this trouble-making, Darius
decided to conquer the whole of present-day
Greece.
In 490 BC, he sent an enormous army to Athens,
but the Athenians defeated it at the Battle
of Marathon.
After the battle, a messenger called Pheidippides
ran straight home to Athens to tell everyone
the good news.
From Marathon to Athens was a distance of
42.195 kilometres - the same distance is called
a 'marathon' today in memory of that great
run.
When King Darius died, his son Xerxes continued
the war against Greece.
In 480 BC he sent another army, even larger
than his father's one.
It defeated the Spartans at Thermopylae (which
means 'Gates of Fire') and marched towards
Athens.
The Athenians had to leave their city to escape
the Persian army.
While the Athenians were away, the Persians
destroyed the buildings on the Acropolis,
the religious part of the city.
To the Greeks, this was unforgivable.
But the Greeks soon made the Persians pay
for their crimes.
Athenian ships beat the Persians at sea in
the Battle of Salamis, and then the armies
of all Greece fought side by side to defeat
the Persians at Plataea.
Soon the Persian army returned to Asia.
The danger had passed.
But the Greeks never forgot that they had
nearly become part of the Persian Empire.
Although they had fought together in the Persian
Wars, the city-states continued to be independent
from each other.
Some were ruled by a king, or a small group
of noblemen.
Others, like Athens, were democracies and
were ruled by the people.
Unlike our democracies today, the ordinary
people made all the political decisions.
At least forty times a year, they came together
in enormous numbers to discuss and vote on
matters of government - whether to go to war,
when to have public holidays, or how to reduce
the number of accidents at sea.
Women could not vote, but the ordinary men
of these Greek democracies had real power.
Religion was an important part of Greek life.
There were many Greek gods.
Zeus was the king of the gods, and he used
thunder and lightning to punish the people
on earth and send messages to them.
He had many children, and they too were gods.
His son Dionysus was god of the forces of
nature; his daughter Athene was connected
with learning; and there were many more.
All over the Greek world, people used to visit
special places to ask the gods for advice.
They asked whether they should start a new
business or choose a wife; as city officials,
they asked whether they should build a new
temple or go to war.
Communicating through religious officials,
the gods gave them complicated answers that
could often be understood in different ways.
In the sixth century BC, for example, the
Athenians sent officials to the Greeks' most
important religious centre, Delphi.
They asked the god Apollo how they should
protect themselves from attack by the Persians,
and were told that they would be safe from
the Persians behind a wall of wood.
After much discussion, the Athenians decided
that the 'wall of wood' meant ships.
They built warships and learnt to sail them.
A few years later, they defeated the Persians
at sea.
The Greeks believed that the greatest heroes,
like Hercules, went to live with the gods
when they died.
Ordinary people went to a dark place below
the earth called the Underworld.
Each Greek city-state was under the protection
of one or more of the gods.
Each of these gods usually had a temple, built
in a style that has been copied in the Western
world for almost 2,500 years.
To keep their gods happy, the people of the
city held regular religious celebrations.
They brought gifts, and performed special
songs and dances.
The Greeks are remembered for their love of
the theatre, which they performed in celebration
of the god Dionysus.
The plays of great writers like Euripides
are still performed today.
Other forms of literature were popular too.
The Iliad and The Odyssey by Homer were long
poems which told stories about the heroes
of the Trojan War.
Other Greeks wrote beautiful love poems and
the Western worlds earliest works of history.
Philosophy was invented in Greece, and the
work of Plato and Aristotle is still important
today.
The Greeks also made many discoveries in mathematics
and science.
Hippocrates, a doctor of the fifth century
BC, is now called 'the father of medicine'.
Medical students all over the world have to
promise to follow his rules for looking after
patients.
The Greeks thought it was important to exercise
both their minds and their bodies.
They were great admirers of physical beauty
in men as well as women.
The social centre of a typical Greek city
was its gymnasium, where rich citizens took
physical exercise.
Every four years, the city-states sent their
best sportsmen to the city of Olympia for
the Olympic Games.
There, competitions were held in running,
jumping, fighting, horseriding, chariot racing
and spear throwing.
The greatest sportsmen at the Olympic Games
became heroes of the Greek world, and were
celebrated in poems by writers like Pindar.
But the competition between Greek city-states
was not always peaceful.
There were often wars too.
Except in Sparta, Greek armies did not have
professional soldiers; the soldiers were usually
farmers.
Fighting took place in the summer months,
and the soldiers went home in the autumn to
look after their fields.
The wars were usually about land.
No city wanted other cities to control too
much land or become too powerful.
At the end of the fifth century BC, Athens
and Sparta were at war for twenty-seven years.
It was a time of great suffering all over
the Greek world.
At that time, Macedonia in the north was not
an important part of Greece.
In fact, most Greeks did not think that Macedonia
was part of Greece at all.
The Macedonians spoke a strange form of Greek
that other Greek speakers had difficulty understanding.
Macedonian noblemen liked horse-riding, hunting,
eating meat and drinking wine.
They did not share other Greeks' interest
in literature, science and philosophy.
Macedonia was ruled by a royal family that
believed they were relatives of the great
god Zeus.
The king lived in Pella, Macedonia's capital
city.
The palace was as beautiful as the finest
buildings in Greece, and the Macedonian kings
wanted their country to be more Greek.
They welcomed several important Greeks there,
including many who were escaping the wars.
The writer Pindar and the doctor Hippocrates
were guests of the Macedonian kings, and Euripides
wrote one of his greatest plays in Pella.
And then, in 359 BC, Alexander's father Philip
became king, and Macedonia's relationship
with the rest of Greece changed forever.
CHAPTER TWO
A Macedonian Prince
Although Alexander's achievements were extraordinary,
in many ways his father, King Philip, was
responsible for his success.
When Philip became king of Macedonia, he threw
all his energy into increasing his power.
He conquered the lands east of Macedonia,
which were rich in gold.
With this gold, he was able to pay for a full-time,
professional army, which gave him a great
advantage over the part-time armies of the
Greek city-states to his south.
It was a well-trained, well-organized army,
and soon it had defeated all Macedonia's neighbours.
When he died, Philip's empire covered most
of modern-day Macedonia, Greece, Albania,
Bulgaria and European Turkey.
In Macedonia, men were allowed to have more
than one wife at the same time.
Philip had six wives.
His first wife, his queen and the mother of
Alexander, was called Olympias.
Olympias was a princess from the neighbouring
state of Epirus.
She had a strong character and a quick temper.
If she had a serious argument with someone,
that person was unlikely to stay alive for
long.
There were many stories about her wild behaviour
and her love of the god Dionysus.
In the Greek world it was normal to kill a
few animals as gifts to the gods.
But when Olympias organized religious celebrations,
thousands of animals were killed as gifts
to Dionysus; then Olympias and her friends
drank the animals' blood.
They played with poisonous snakes too; it
was said that Olympias liked to sleep with
a snake in her bed.
It is not surprising, with parents like this,
that Alexander was brave and adventurous.
His teachers too helped to make him a strong
and successful leader.
His first teacher was a relative of Olympias
- a man called Leonidas.
Alexander hated him.
Leonidas made Alexander exercise without having
breakfast, and gave him only a small snack
for his evening meal.
He even checked Alexander's school bags, so
Olympias could not hide food in them.
Alexander loved music and literature, but
his favourite hobby was hunting.
He hunted with dogs, and he was always fond
of them.
Many years later he even named a city in India
after his pet dog Peritas.
A hunter also needed a horse, and Alexander's
horse was one of the most famous in history.
A Greek friend of Philip bought it for an
enormous sum of money and gave it to Philip
as a present.
Alexander, aged twelve, went with his father
to see this gift.
It was a powerful black warhorse, but it was
wild.
It jumped and kicked and turned.
Nobody was able to ride it.
When Philip ordered his men to take the horse
away, Alexander asked his father to wait.
He turned the horse towards the sun, so it
could not see its own shadow.
It immediately became less frightened.
Whispering in its ear, Alexander gently climbed
on the horse's back and rode it proudly round
the field.
Everyone was full of admiration.
Philip, it was said, had tears in his eyes
as he watched his smiling son.
Alexander kept the horse, which he called
Bucephalas, and for the next twenty years
man and horse were rarely separated.
As Philip became richer and more powerful,
he hired philosophers, artists, musicians
and engineers from all over the Greek world.
His court at Pella was an exciting place for
a young prince to grow up.
Alexander could talk to people who had lived
in Egypt, and made friends with a man who
had been a governor in the Persian Empire.
Macedonia was now well-connected in the wider
world.
Philip was too busy leading his army to spend
much time with his son.
But he made sure that Alexander's teacher
during his teenage years would be the best
that money could buy.
When Alexander was thirteen, his father hired
Aristotle, a student of the great philosopher
Plato.
At that time, Aristotle was an unknown teacher
with thin legs and small eyes.
He also had one of the sharpest and most questioning
minds in history.
Aristotle later wrote many important works
of philosophy.
He was one of the first people to use scientific
methods to learn more about plants and animals.
He studied the stars and the way that the
sea shapes the land.
He wrote about politics and literature.
The list of his interests and achievements
is extraordinary.
Nobody knows how much he taught Alexander.
Aristotle later wrote that it was a waste
of time teaching political science to a young
man, because 'he has no experience of life,
and still follows his emotions'.
Was he describing his pupil Alexander here?
Perhaps.
But as Alexander grew up, like his teacher
he never stopped asking questions.
Whenever Pella had visitors from other parts
of the world, Alexander learnt as much as
he could from them.
Alexander, like Aristotle, had a hunger for
knowledge.
Alexander was not Aristotle's only pupil in
Macedonia.
Aristotle also taught the sons of leading
noblemen, and among them were many of Alexanders
future commanders: Ptolemy, Perdiccas, Seleucus,
Nearchus, and Alexanders best friend Hephaistion.
These friends, like the horse Bucephalas,
followed Alexander loyally to the ends of
the earth.
Alexander grew up quickly into a responsible
and intelligent young man.
When he was sixteen, he was allowed to take
charge of the government while Philip was
away with the army.
Soon after this, a tribe to the east of Macedonia
started to cause trouble, and Alexander himself
led a small army to defeat it.
Then, when he was eighteen, he commanded part
of his father's great army at the Battle of
Chaeronea.
In this battle the Macedonians finally defeated
the Greek city-states and forced them to accept
Philip as their leader.
Philip started to make plans to free the Greek
cities in Asia from Persian rule.
Alexander felt that he would have an important
part to play in his father's war against Persia.
The future looked good.
But then his father fell in love.
Eurydice was the daughter of a Macedonian
nobleman.
She was young and very beautiful.
Soon Philip was planning their wedding.
Olympias was very angry because, as Philip's
new wife, Eurydice would be more powerful
than she was.
And if Eurydice had a son, he could be chosen
as king instead of Alexander.
At the wedding, there was a big argument.
Alexander attacked his father, although no
one was hurt.
Alexander and his mother left the court immediately;
Alexander soon returned, but his mother went
to live in her home country, Epirus.
Without his mother, Alexander was very nervous
about his position at court.
Then he heard news that made him even more
worried.
In preparation for his war on Persia, Philip
was in contact with the king of Caria, on
the western edge of the Persian Empire, and
the two rulers wanted to arrange a family
marriage.
As well as Alexander, Philip had another son,
Alexander's half-brother Arrhidaeus.
He had learning difficulties and could never
be given adult responsibilities.
Philip suggested that Arrhidaeus should marry
a Carian princess.
Alexander could not understand why his father
wanted this royal marriage for Arrhidaeus
and not for him.
He sent friends to the Carian court to say
that he would make a much better husband than
his half-brother.
The Carian king was pleased at first.
But Philip was very angry when he heard what
Alexander had done.
He did not want to waste Alexander on a small
country like Caria.
Alexander's friends were sent away from Macedonia,
and soon the Carian king got worried and lost
interest in a marriage with anyone in Philip's
family.
Alexander had ruined everything.
His position at court became even weaker than
before.
As Philip sent part of his army into Asia
to start the war against Persia, he planned
another wedding.
Cleopatra, Alexander's sister, was marrying
her uncle, the king of Epirus.
All the local rulers in Philip's empire were
there.
But Olympias, who was Cleopatra's mother as
well as the king of Epirus's sister, was not
at the wedding.
Since he was joining the royal families of
Epirus and Macedonia with this new marriage,
Philip did not need Olympias and her Epirote
connections.
After the wedding, Philip was walking to the
celebrations with Alexander and his daughter's
new husband.
His endless battles had left him with one
eye and a bad leg, but he was still full of
energy, dreaming of a successful war in Persia.
Suddenly, a man moved towards them.
It was one of Philip's bodyguards.
Without a word, he pushed a knife into Philip's
chest.
Then he ran.
But he fell as he tried to get on his horse,
and Philip's other bodyguards soon killed
him.
There was no hope for King Philip.
He was dead.
CHAPTER THREE
The Young King
We will never know why Philip was killed.
He certainly had many political enemies inside
and outside his empire who had the money to
pay for his murder.
Some people at the time said that Philip and
his murderer had argued about a lover.
But it is more likely that Olympias was responsible.
Philip had not included his first wife in
his plans for Macedonia's great future, so
Olympias, quick-tempered and dangerous, had
arranged his murder.
She would have more power as King Alexander's
mother than as King Philip's unwanted wife.
But in Macedonia, rule did not always pass
to the dead king's oldest son.
At the time of his father's murder, many people
did not want Alexander as their king.
He was still only twenty - too young, they
said, to take on the responsibility of Macedonian
rule.
He was half Epirote, not a true Macedonian,
because his mother was from Epirus.
And his Epirote mother was wild and irresponsible
- perhaps even her husband's murderer.
There were two other serious possibilities
for the next king.
One was General Attalus, Eurydice's uncle,
who wanted to rule Macedonia through Eurydice
and Philip's new baby son.
The other was Amyntas.
Twenty-three years earlier, Amyntas had been
a child of two when his father, King Perdiccas,
had died.
Philip was Perdiccas's younger brother and
had ruled in the place of his baby nephew;
when Amyntas became an adult, Philip was so
powerful and successful that nobody questioned
his right to continue ruling.
Amyntas was now twenty-five.
Compared to Alexander, he had the advantage
of age and experience, and his blood was equally
royal.
He was popular with the noblemen of Macedonia.
But Alexander stayed one step ahead of his
enemies.
He ordered the murder of Eurydice's baby,
his own half-brother.
General Attalus, who was with the army in
Asia, could do nothing to stop him.
Soon Attalus and Amyntas were murdered too.
This was not unusual - in those days the rule
of a new king almost always started with a
few murders.
Alexander reduced taxes for the people of
Macedonia and, since no other suitable kings
were left alive, they seemed happy to accept
him as their new ruler.
The situation was more difficult abroad.
When news of Philip's murder spread around
his empire, the tribes in the north and the
city-states in the south decided to free themselves
from Macedonian rule.
Within a few months of his fathers death,
Alexander had to fight to keep the empire
together.
He first went to the Greek state of Thessaly.
The usual route was along a narrow valley
in the mountains, but this was now guarded
by the Thessalians.
Alexander decided that it was too dangerous
to take the Macedonian soldiers and warhorses
this way.
Instead, he created a new path.
He ordered the soldiers to cut steps in the
steep rockface of a mountain on the border
between Macedonia and Thessaly.
After weeks of hard work, his army entered
Thessaly by the new road, took the Thessalians
by surprise and defeated them easily.
The Thessalians welcomed Alexander as their
new leader.
A march at lightning speed then took Alexanders
army on a tour of Greek city-states.
One by one, they realized that battle would
end in disaster, so they quickly made peace
with him instead.
Only Sparta refused to accept Alexander as
their leader, sending the message: 'It is
our fathers' habit not to follow others but
to lead them.'
Alexander was not too worried.
The rest of the Greeks hated Sparta more than
they hated Macedonia.
He could manage without Spartan help.
There were also problems in the north.
After his tour of Greece, Alexander had to
fight the Thracians, who lived beside the
River Danube.
They could not defeat Alexander's well-trained
army and soon they were forced to accept Macedonian
rule.
But bad news followed.
The Macedonian forces in Asia were retreating;
Attalus, murdered on Alexander's orders, had
been a good general, and his death had probably
weakened the army there.
In Macedonia itself, Olympias was behaving
typically and had murdered Eurydice.
And in Greece, news was spreading that Alexander
had been killed on the Danube; the city-state
of Thebes was leading a new fight for independence
which was fast growing out of control.
Alexander knew that he had to act quickly.
He rushed his army to Thebes and started a
siege of the city.
When an unguarded gate in the city wall was
found, the Macedonians soon forced their way
into the city.
Alexander called a meeting with the neighbouring
Greek city-states, who had for many years
suffered bad treatment at the hands of power-hungry
Thebes.
When he asked them what should happen to Thebes,
they voted to destroy it completely.
Thebes came to a violent end.
The city's riches were taken.
A few houses were left untouched - 150 years
earlier the Theban writer Pindar had written
poems for the Macedonian king, and now his
house was safe - but the rest were burnt to
the ground.
30,000 Thebans, including women and children,
were taken prisoner and sold as slaves.
The terrible news soon spread around Greece.
No other city-state was interested in continuing
their fight for independence now.
Everyone rushed to prove that they were Alexander's
greatest allies.
At last Alexander could turn his attention
to Asia.
It was time to plan his war against the Persian
Empire.
Alexander called together forces from many
lands - foot soldiers from Illyria and Thrace,
horsemen from Thessaly, warships from Athens,
archers from Crete, as well as the highly
trained Macedonian army.
To this he added doctors, long-distance runners,
engineers, religious men, specialists in digging
for gold and jewels, and a historian called
Callisthenes to record his great achievements.
Alexander left his mother Olympias in charge
of Macedonia, with his father's loyal general
Antipater to lead her army.
Then he marched to the Dardanelles, a narrow
piece of water that separates Europe from
Asia in present-day Turkey.
While Alexander's second-in-command, General
Parmenion, led the mam army into Asia by the
shortest sea crossing, Alexander himself decided
to see some sights.
His destination was the ruined city of Troy,
scene of the legendary Trojan War, where Greeks
and Asians had fought for the first time.
The Greeks believed that the war had started
1,000 years before the time of Alexander,
when Paris, a Trojan prince, stole the beautiful
Helen from her Greek husband Menelaus.
***
Of all the heroes of the Trojan War, the greatest
was Achilles.
When he was a baby, his immortal mother had
held his heel and covered the rest of his
body in the water of the legendary River Styx.
After this, he could only be hurt on his heel.
Achilles grew up handsome and brave.
At the start of the Trojan War, his mother
gave him a choice: he could stay at home,
live a normal life and die an old man, or
he could go to Troy, die young and be famous
for ever.
Of course Achilles chose Troy.
He was the fastest runner and the strongest
fighter in the Greek army.
But he also had a quick temper.
After an argument about a female prisoner
with his general, Agamemnon, Achilles decided
to stop fighting in the war.
Without Achilles, the Greeks were nearly defeated.
Patroclus, Achilles's best friend, fought
in Achilles's armour to give the Greeks confidence;
but soon he was killed by the Trojan hero,
Hector.
Achilles felt very sad and very guilty.
It was his fault that his best friend was
dead.
Dressed in new armour created by the gods,
he returned to battle and did not stop fighting
until he had killed Patroclus's killer, Hector.
He tied Hector's body to his chariot and pulled
it through the dust.
But later in the war, Achilles himself was
killed when Paris shot him in the heel with
a poisoned arrow.
This was a story that Alexander had read from
his early childhood.
He was even thought to be a relative of Achilles,
through his mother, Olympias, and the royal
family of Epirus.
His teacher Aristotle had prepared for him
a special copy of The Iliad, Homer's great
poem about Achilles; this copy was so important
to Alexander that he liked to rest his head
on it when he slept.
For many years people had compared Alexander
and his best friend Hephaistion to Achilles
and Patroclus.
And now Alexander, like the Greeks of the
Trojan War, had come across the Dardanelles
to attack the people of Asia.
As Alexander's boat touched the beach, he
threw his spear at the ground as a sign that
this land was now his.
With his friends, he walked up the hill to
the ruins of Troy.
He gave gifts to the gods.
Then he and Hephaistion ran - Alexander to
the tomb of Achilles, his best friend to the
tomb of Patroclus.
Next he went to the temple of Athene, where
he exchanged his own armour for a shield which,
according to legend, had been used in the
Trojan War.
With his beautiful shield from the Age of
Heroes, he went to rejoin his army as the
new Achilles.
We can only wonder if he thought about the
choice of futures that Achilles had been given
by his mother.
Like Achilles, Alexander chose to fight battles
and live famously.
Did he guess that, like Achilles, he would
never return to his homeland or live to middle
age?
CHAPTER FOUR
First Battles in Asia
Until Alexander could prove that he was stronger
than the Persian Empire, the Greek cities
in Asia refused to help him.
He had very little food or pay left for his
men.
He needed to defeat the Persians in battle
quickly.
But the Persian commanders were discussing
other plans.
At this time, the soldiers in the Persian
army were mostly Greek.
People talk of Alexanders Greeks' defeating
the 'Persians', but there were 50,000 Greeks
in the Persian army and only 7,000 in Alexander's.
In Greece, it was difficult to earn a living
if you did not own land.
There were plenty of slaves, so landowners
and businessmen rarely wanted to employ paid
workers.
The shipping business was a possibility, but
storms at sea were common and fortunes were
lost as often as they were made.
For many, the most attractive choice was a
life in the highly paid Persian army.
The army was full of failed Greek farmers
and businessmen, younger sons who owned no
land, and politicians who were not welcome
in the city of their birth.
A Greek general called Memnon had been responsible
for the Macedonians most recent defeats.
He had grown up on the island of Rhodes, spent
some time living in Macedonia, and come to
Asia fifteen years before Alexander.
His wife Barsine was Persian, and he now owned
a large farm, a present from the Persian king
for his loyal service.
Memnon now had a plan to defeat Alexander.
The Persians should not face the Macedonians
in battle, he advised.
Instead, they should burn their own farms
and make sure Alexander's army could get no
food.
If Alexander did not win a battle, the Greek
cities would not help him.
Soon his hungry soldiers would have to return
to Europe.
The rest of the Persian commanders disagreed
with Memnon.
Instead, they decided to defend their country
in battle.
The Persian army grouped on the east bank
of the River Granicus.
When Alexander heard the news, he realized
his luck and ordered his soldiers to march
there as quickly as possible.
Some of Alexander's advisers warned him that
for religious reasons it was not a good month
for a battle.
Alexander acted typically: he created a new
month.
Alexander and his army reached the Granicus
in late afternoon.
The Persians had chosen their position well.
The river was twenty metres wide and ran fast
between steep, muddy banks.
If Alexander ordered his army to cross the
river, it would be easy for the Persians to
cut them down in the mud.
Alexander had read in the work of a Greek
historian that the Persians liked to camp
some distance from their chosen battle ground
and did not march before the sun came up.
The Macedonians crossed the river in the early
hours of the morning and found it undefended.
They now had the advantage of surprise.
Alexander led his horsemen against the enemy.
The Persian horsemen fought back, but they
were badly organized because of the surprise
attack.
When Alexander's spear broke during the fighting,
a Persian commander saw his opportunity and
struck Alexander on the head.
But Alexander was not hurt, and before the
Persian could strike again, a Macedonian called
Cleitus came to protect his king.
Cleitus's sister had been Alexander's nurse
as a baby, and now Cleitus saved his life.
As the fighting continued, the Persians failed
to organize a strong defence.
Many of their commanders were killed, several
by Alexander himself.
Soon the Persians on horseback were retreating.
As the Macedonians surrounded the Persian
camp, about 17,000 hired Greek foot soldiers
tried to defend it.
They managed to hurt Alexander's horse, but
there were many more Macedonian attackers.
They could not hope to win. 2,000 were taken
prisoner, and later sent to Macedonia as slaves;
the rest were killed.
Alexander used this cruel treatment as a message
to other Greeks: 'Leave the Persian army and
stop fighting your own countrymen - if you
don't, your suffering will be worse than the
Persians'.'
After his success at the Granicus, the Greek
cities in Asia quickly opened their gates
to Alexander.
He sent messengers to all the cities that
he had already passed, telling them to become
democracies, to create their own laws, and
to stop paying tax to the Persian king.
This was a clever trick, because it made Alexander
popular with tax-payers.
The tax to the Persian king was not really
stopped; it was given a new name, and paid
as a 'gift' to the Macedonian army instead.
But the trick was successful.
The Persian-supported local rulers lost their
power without any danger to the Macedonian
army.
The cities became democratic, and Alexander
grew so popular that many people in the area
started to think of him as a god.
Alexander marched south into Caria, where
he had in the past hoped to marry the daughter
of his father's ally, the Carian king.
At the border, he was met by Queen Ada, who
had been the wife of an earlier king.
Now she was almost a prisoner in her own home
under the new king, a Persian called Orontobates.
She had a strange suggestion for Alexander:
he should become her adopted son and take
Orontobates's place as the true king.
But first he had to defeat King Orontobates.
Orontobates and General Memnon, who was then
commander of the whole Persian army, were
preparing a defence of Halicarnassus (now
called Bodrum, in Turkey).
The city was famous for its Mausoleum - the
great tomb of Ada's brother, King Mausolus,
which was one of the Seven Wonders of the
World.
Halicarnassus had the strongest city defences
on the Asian coast, circled by walls and with
a well-built castle.
Persian warships defended it by sea; Alexander,
who had sent his Athenian warships home a
few months earlier because they were so expensive,
had no warships at all.
The siege was difficult.
The Macedonians broke part of the city wall,
but the Persians pushed them back.
Many lives were lost from both armies.
In the end, the Persians had too few soldiers
to defend the city.
They retreated to the castle, which they held
for a year.
But Alexander was able to move his forces
into the main part of the city.
As Queen Ada's adopted son, Alexander became
king of Caria.
Preparations now had to be made for the winter.
Alexander decided to send home to Macedonia
all the soldiers who had married just before
the start of the war.
This was a popular decision.
Alexander's army now loved their leader more
than ever.
Alexander left his 'mother', Queen Ada, in
charge of Caria.
With the rest of the army, he marched to Gordium
(in central Turkey), and waited there for
the return of the newly married soldiers.
During the winter Alexander became interested
in a local legend.
In the palace at Gordium, which had in the
past been the home of the kings of Phrygia,
there was an old chariot.
It was tied to a piece of wood by a complicated
knot that no one had ever managed to untie.
According to legend, Asia would one day be
ruled by the person who could untie the knot.
Alexander decided that he would untie the
knot.
In front of all his soldiers, he moved towards
the chariot.
After some minutes, the knot was broken.
But there were two different stories from
the people who were watching.
Some said that Alexander's success with the
knot was real; others said that they saw him
use his knife to cut it.
We will never know.
But that night the gods seemed to send a sign
of their support when thunder and lightning
filled the sky.
Word spread among his soldiers and the local
people: Alexander, who had untied the Gordian
Knot, was the future ruler of all Asia.
CHAPTER FIVE
Face to Face with Darius
While Alexander was at Gordium, the Persians
started to make more plans to defeat him.
The Macedonians had no warships; the Persians
had 300.
It was time for the Persians to take advantage
of their power at sea.
Led by General Memnon, they took back the
Greek islands of Chios and Lesbos.
They planned to continue by sea towards central
Greece, and they hoped that Sparta would soon
lead a Greek independence movement against
the Macedonians.
If the Persians created enough problems in
Greece, Alexander would have to go home.
They also decided, finally, to burn all the
fields before Alexander reached them, so his
army would have nothing to eat.
Marching south, Alexander found burning fields
everywhere.
Then, when he got to the city of Tarsus (in
present-day southern Turkey), he became ill
with a high fever, perhaps because of a swim
in an icy river.
His doctors feared for his life.
But a Greek doctor called Philip, who had
looked after Alexander as a boy, suggested
a treatment that might help.
As the doctor went to prepare the medicine,
Alexander was given a letter from General
Parmenion, his second-in-command; it said
that Philip had been paid by the Persian king
to kill Alexander.
But when Philip returned with the medicine,
Alexander drank it immediately without questioning
his doctor's loyalty, and after several weeks
he got better.
In Alexander's world, death by poison was
not uncommon and the ability to know friend
from enemy was very useful.
Memnon was not as lucky as Alexander.
While fighting on Lesbos, he suddenly became
ill and died.
This was a serious problem for the Persians.
Without Memnon and his knowledge of Greece,
they did not feel confident that they could
fight a war successfully against the Macedonians
in Europe.
Although Memnon's plan had worked very well
until then, they decided to change it completely.
The Great King of Persia, Darius III, took
personal control of the situation.
We know little about this king.
Although he had royal blood, he was not a
close relative of the Persian kings that had
ruled before him.
He had been the governor of Armenia and fought
bravely in battles there; he had then become
king of Persia after many members of the royal
family were poisoned by a power-hungry politician
called Bagoas.
Persia itself was in present-day Iran, but
the Great King controlled all the lands from
Egypt to Pakistan, and from Uzbekistan to
the Arabian Sea.
His riches were legendary, and he received
the treatment of a god.
He was protected by a bodyguard of 10,000
soldiers; they were called the Immortals because
when one man died or became ill, his position
was immediately filled by another man.
The Great King gave land to the men that served
him well.
The land-owning Persians had a very comfortable
way of life that was often a subject of wonder
among the Greeks.
They had soft carpets on their floors and
beautiful gardens full of flowers; they ate
the finest food, and hundreds of servants
looked after all their needs.
But with one word, the all-powerful king could
take away their good fortune for ever.
Wide, well-built roads connected the Great
King's most important cities, Babylon, Susa
and Persepolis, with the far corners of his
empire.
The best of these roads was the Royal Road,
which led 2,300 kilometres from Susa, in the
heart of the empire, to Sardis, on the Mediterranean
coast.
Every twenty-five kilometres along the route,
there was a place to buy food and stay the
night.
Only the Greek cities in the west of the Persian
Empire paid tax in the form of money.
Everywhere else, tax to the Great King was
paid in food; in silver and gold; and in horses,
war chariots and fighting men.
King Darius now put together an enormous army.
Only the lands on the eastern borders of the
empire did not send men; they were too far
away to be useful.
The Persian army's strength lay in its well-trained
archers and horsemen, because riding and archery
were the traditional hobbies of the Persian
landowners.
Tens of thousands of these men joined their
king, but foot soldiers were less easy to
find.
Darius's army included a large number of teenage
boys with no experience of battle.
To help them, the King also called for the
hired Greek soldiers who had been fighting
with Memnon at sea; he needed them now for
a great land battle.
Historians at the time wrote that he had between
300,000 and 600,000 men in his army, but not
all of them were soldiers.
Each Persian horseman, for example, had twelve
servants.
And when the king commanded the army, his
politicians, his wives and his children came
with him.
The Macedonians, whose army only numbered
about 50,000 men, received reports that the
enemy had camped near the Syrian border with
Cilicia (southern Turkey).
They marched along the Mediterranean coast
towards the Persian camp, covering the distance
in half the usual time.
Unknown to Alexander, the Persians had left
their camp and were also marching.
While the Macedonians followed the coast road
south, the Persians followed the inland road
north.
Although they were only a few kilometres away
from each other, neither army knew where the
other one was.
Such confusion is hard to imagine today, in
a world where cameras in space can be used
to spy on every movement that an army makes.
The Macedonians realized first that the two
armies had passed each other by mistake.
They had already had several days of hard
marching.
Now Alexander asked his soldiers to turn round
and march again.
After an evening meal, they marched north
in the dark, had a short sleep, then marched
again at first light.
Around midday they came to a river near the
town of Issus.
On the far side of the river stood the Persian
army, on a flat piece of land about two kilometres
wide.
To the west there was beach and the Mediterranean
Sea; to the east there were mountains.
The fighting area was too narrow for Darius
to take advantage of his greater numbers of
soldiers.
It was a good battlefield for the Macedonians.
Alexander, riding Bucephalas, led a charge
of horsemen across the river towards the enemy.
The Persian horsemen rode to meet them, and
the battle began.
In the centre of the battlefield were the
Macedonian foot soldiers, who fought with
six-metre-long spears.
Although they were difficult to defeat on
flat ground, the Macedonians were having problems
on the steep river banks.
They were close to defeat at the hands of
the hired Greek soldiers who fought for the
Persians.
But just in time, Alexander's horsemen broke
through the Persian line and came to help
the foot soldiers.
Soon the Macedonians were winning the battle.
King Darius was watching the fighting from
his chariot.
As Alexander and his Macedonian horsemen moved
towards him from two sides, the eyes of the
two kings met for a moment.
Then Darius, realizing that the battle was
lost, turned his chariot and quickly retreated.
CHAPTER SIX
South to Egypt
Darius escaped over the mountains on horseback,
leaving his spear in his chariot.
But the Battle of Issus was a serious defeat
for the Persians.
Enormous numbers of Persians died.
The rest of the Persian army broke into small
groups, and most of the hired Greeks sailed
home in Persian warships.
King Darius lost much more than his soldiers
and ships.
The Macedonians found extraordinary riches
left near the battlefield, and even more at
the city of Damascus.
There were 220 kilograms of silver, and as
many gold coins as Alexander's father, King
Philip, had received in tax from his empire
in a whole year.
There were piles of cups, bowls and boxes
made of gold.
Alexander liked one gold box so much that
he decided to keep his favourite copy of The
Iliad in it.
There were thousands of servants, including
329 female musicians, 319 cooks and 70 wine
waiters, who had come to look after the Great
King while he commanded the army.
And, most important of all, the Macedonians
took prisoner Darius's wife, mother and children.
Alexander made sure that the Persian royal
family received royal treatment.
They were given fine clothes and jewellery
to wear, and had a comfortable place to live.
Soon Darius wrote to Alexander asking for
his family's return.
But Alexander replied that the royal family
would only be freed if Darius called him King
Alexander of Asia.
'If you think you have a right to your empire,
stand and fight for it,' wrote Alexander.
'Do not run away, because I will come after
you, wherever you go.'
Another prisoner was the dead General Memnon's
beautiful Persian wife, Barsine.
She had lived for a short time in Macedonia
when her father, a Persian governor, had become
unpopular with the Persian king.
In Macedonia, Barsine had known Alexander
as a boy.
Now he was a man and she was his prisoner.
Alexander fell in love with her and they were
close for the next five years.
Alexander now needed to take the ports in
Phoenicia (present-day Lebanon).
Most of them were happy to welcome the Macedonians
and say goodbye to Persian rule, but the city
of Tyre was different.
Tyre stood on an island about a kilometre
out to sea and was ringed by a wall fifty
metres high.
Few cities were as difficult to attack, but
Alexander, as usual, wasted no time in worrying
about the difficulty of his job.
He told his engineers to build a wide road
across the sea to the island of Tyre.
Using stone from coastal ruins to fill in
the sea, the first part of this road was built
quickly.
But the last 200 metres cost many lives.
The Tyrians shot arrows at the Macedonians
as they worked, but the Macedonians used stone-throwing
machines to clear the archers from their shooting
positions.
The machines were also used to make holes
in the city walls, but the walls were soon
rebuilt.
When the Tyrians sailed burning ships into
enemy lines to destroy the Macedonians' wooden
war machines, the Macedonians found other
ways to destroy the Tyrian defences.
The Macedonians tried to climb the walls,
but the Tyrians showered them with red hot
sand that poured inside their armour and burnt
their bodies horribly.
As time went on, Alexander was helped by other
Phoenician cities, and by the Greeks who lived
on Cyprus and Rhodes.
More than six months after the start of the
siege, the Macedonians and their allies attacked
the island on all sides with ships and machines
of war.
Finally, Alexander and his soldiers managed
to fight their way over the walls.
The Tyrians defended themselves bravely, but
the city was taken.
10,000 Tyrians were killed and 30,000 were
sold as slaves.
The results of Alexander's siege can still
be seen.
Tyre exists today, but it is not on an island.
The coastline was changed for ever by the
road that Alexander's soldiers built across
the sea.
South of Tyre, Alexander took the city of
Gaza after a two month siege.
The whole male population was killed.
Then Alexander tied the feet of their dead
king, Batis, to his chariot and pulled it
round the city.
His hero Achilles had done the same in The
Iliad, with the body of Patroclus's killer,
Hector.
Alexander then marched south to Egypt, a land
rich in gold and farmland.
In later years, when Rome was all-powerful
and had a city population of one million,
most of the Romans' food came from the valley
of the Nile.
The Egyptians were understandably proud of
their long history.
Their religion and their writing had begun
almost 3,000 years before the time of Alexander,
and their form of government had too.
The Egyptians had built extraordinary tombs
for their kings, or 'pharaohs'.
The greatest of these, the tomb of Khufu at
Giza, continued to be the tallest building
in the world until the nineteenth century.
But when it was built in the twenty-sixth
century BC, the Greeks had not yet even learnt
how to write.
For centuries, Egypt had been one of the most
powerful countries in the Middle East, but
in 525 BC it had fallen under Persian rule.
Its people had never fully accepted this situation,
and had regularly fought for their independence.
Now they welcomed Alexander as their new ruler.
They were deeply religious, and they saw that
Alexander had a better attitude than the Persian
kings to the Egyptian gods.
They gladly made him their 'pharaoh'.
As Pharaoh, he was believed to be a living
god, son of the Egyptian creator-god Amun.
After spending time in Egypt's capital city
Memphis (near present-day Cairo), Alexander
travelled north to the mouth of the River
Nile.
There he organized the building of a new city,
Alexandria.
It was not the only city of that name; one
had already been built near Issus, and before
he died Alexander built more than twenty others.
But this Alexandria was perhaps his greatest
gift to the future.
In the centuries that followed, it became
one of the Mediterranean world's most important
centres of learning and of political and economic
power.
Leaving most of his army in Alexandria, Alexander
travelled 200 kilometres west along the Mediterranean
coast with a small group of soldiers.
He came to the Greek city of Paraitonion,
then turned south into the Libyan desert.
This time his destination was not an enemy
city - it was Siwah, home of the Libyan god
Ammon.
Siwah, in Libya, was known all over the Greek
world as a place where people could ask Ammon
for advice and receive an honest answer.
The answers were communicated to visitors
by Ammon's religious officials.
Ammon was connected with the Egyptian god
Amun and the Greek god Zeus.
It seems that Alexander had an important question
to ask the god.
But his journey across the desert to Siwah
almost cost him his life.
For four days the travellers were lost in
a sandstorm.
They drank all their water and soon became
very thirsty.
But suddenly there were clouds in the sky
and it started to rain - 'not without the
help of the gods', according to Alexander's
friends.
They travelled at night, when it was cooler,
and soon they lost their way again.
This time, it was said, they were helped by
birds and snakes which showed them the right
direction.
Finally, after more than a week in the desert,
they reached Siwah.
Alexander communicated privately with the
god Ammon, possibly about his hopes of becoming
King of Asia.
Later, in public, the religious men of Siwah
welcomed him as 'Son of Zeus'.
Was this just a Greek translation of the Pharaoh's
title, Son of Amun?
Or had they heard that Alexander's mother
Olympias sometimes told strange stories about
a god being her son's father?
We do not know.
But certainly Alexander's visit to Siwah had
a powerful effect on him.
According to his soldiers, he started to believe
that he truly was the son of the great god
Zeus.
Like the Greek hero Hercules, he was more
than human; because of this, there was nothing
that he could not achieve.
CHAPTER SEVEN
King of Asia
During the siege of Tyre, King Darius had
written another letter to Alexander.
He had offered him all the lands west of the
River Euphrates, a fortune in gold, and marriage
to his daughter; in exchange, Darius had asked
for peace and the return of his wife, mother
and children.
It was a generous offer, but Alexander had
refused it.
Darius then realized that he had no choice
- he had to fight again.
While Alexander was in Egypt, Darius called
together a new army.
Soldiers came from the farthest corners of
his empire, and it was a whole year before
the army was ready to fight.
Alexander marched from Egypt to Tyre and waited.
In his next battle, he wanted to defeat the
Persians completely, and he could not do this
against an incomplete army.
To entertain his bored soldiers, he organized
the performance of Greek plays and musical
concerts.
Then finally the Macedonians marched east.
By burning the Euphrates valley, the Persians
forced Alexander to take the only other possible
route east.
This brought him to Darius's choice of battlefield:
Gaugamela, in present-day Iraq.
Darius made sure that, unlike at Issus, the
battlefield was wide enough for him to take
advantage of his enormous army.
Although Alexander had been joined by new
soldiers from Macedonia, Greece and the Asian
Mediterranean coast, these only took the place
of the men who had died.
Against Alexander's 7,000 horsemen and 40,000
foot soldiers, Darius's had 30,000 horsemen
and 200,000 foot soldiers to send into battle.
At first Alexander planned to take the Persians
by surprise in the early morning.
But when it became clear that Darius was expecting
them, the Macedonians took time to look carefully
at the battlefield.
In the centre of the field, they saw that
spears had been stuck in the ground to hurt
any horses that ran at the enemy lines.
They saw elephants, a frightening sight for
men who had never met such enormous animals
before, and for their horses.
They also noticed that uneven ground had been
flattened to help the drivers of the famous
Persian war chariots.
Darius had 200 of these chariots, with spears
pointing out in front of the horses and long
knives fixed to the wheels.
It is unlikely that the ordinary Macedonian
soldiers were feeling confident before the
battle.
The following morning, Alexander spoke to
his men and their confidence returned.
He called to the gods, 'If I am truly the
son of Zeus, you will defend us and help to
make us strong.'
Then he led the attack.
Horsemen and foot soldiers charged towards
the centre of the Persian line, then suddenly
turned right to an area where there were no
spears or elephants.
Darius's horsemen from the centre rushed to
meet them, but they were unable to surround
the Macedonians as they had hoped.
Fighting hard, the Macedonians drove them
back.
At the same time, the Persian chariots charged
at the foot soldiers in the Macedonian centre.
But Alexander's archers managed to kill many
of the chariot drivers before they reached
the soldiers.
When a chariot came close, the Macedonians
moved sideways and the chariot, which could
not turn quickly, went straight through the
hole in the line.
The chariots were not causing the damage that
Darius had hoped for.
On Alexander's left, the Persians broke through
the Macedonian defences.
But they did not use the situation to their
advantage.
Instead they went in search of the Persian
royal family and tried to free Darius's mother.
Now Alexander took his chance.
When the enemy horsemen had rushed to meet
the first Macedonian charge, they had left
a weak point in the centre of Darius's line.
Alexander attacked at this point, passing
the elephants and going straight towards the
chariot of the Persian king.
Alexander, it is said, threw a spear at Darius,
but it missed and killed his chariot driver
instead.
Soon, as at Issus, Darius was rushing from
the battlefield in his chariot.
This time Alexander did not want him to escape.
He took 2,000 horsemen and hurried after him.
But the dust made it difficult to see, and
many Persians were trying to follow their
king as well.
In the confusion, Hephaistion and many of
Alexander's other friends were hurt.
The Macedonians continued the chase at high
speed, but Darius managed to get away.
With the disappearance of their king, the
Persian soldiers were soon defeated.
As at Issus, enormous numbers of Persians
died.
The Macedonians too lost many men, and more
than a thousand horses died in the battle
or from their race to catch Darius.
Alexander marched through rich farmland to
Babylon.
Its governor came to meet him, and offered
him the city without a fight.
Alexander entered the city gates in his chariot,
riding through streets covered with flowers.
The Babylonians, like the Egyptians, had suffered
200 years of unpopular Persian rule, and welcomed
a change enthusiastically.
Alexander was careful not to follow the Persian
habit of insulting the Babylonian gods.
He gave gifts to the great god Bel Marduk,
and paid for the rebuilding of temples which
had been damaged under the Persians.
He spent a few weeks relaxing in the great
city with his army.
He probably found time to visit the famous
Hanging Gardens - a park planted with trees
and flowers on many different levels.
Like the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus, this
was one of the Seven Wonders of the World.
Alexander left Babylon to be ruled by its
Persian governor, who had fought against the
Macedonians at Gaugamela just a short time
before.
Many people were surprised at this, thinking
that only Greek speakers should rule Alexander's
new empire.
But later there were other Persian-born governors.
The next great city on Alexander's route east
was Susa.
The climate there was so hot, it was said,
that at midday snakes could not cross the
road for fear of being burnt by the sun.
But its people gave Alexander a warm welcome,
and its great riches made it an attractive
destination.
After sitting in the royal seat of gold in
Darius's palace, Alexander took control of
one and a half million kilograms of gold.
His financial difficulties at the start of
the war were now just a memory.
Then came Persepolis, in the heart of Persia
itself.
It was natural to expect the Persians to defend
their homeland.
Alexander led a small group of horsemen and
foot soldiers through the mountains to defeat
any Persian forces that were defending the
mountain roads.
The path was steep, narrow and covered in
snow.
After four days' climb, the Macedonians came
to the Persian Gates, a wall of rock in the
mountains that marked the entrance to the
Persian homeland.
As they passed, they were attacked by an enemy
army which was much larger than their own
small group.
Great stones fell on top of them from the
mountain heights, and they were shot at on
all sides by Persian archers and stone-throwers.
Alexander had no choice: he had to order a
retreat.
If Alexander left these Persians undefeated,
they could attack his main army, led by his
second-in-command, Parmenion, on its way to
Persepolis.
There was only one hope of success, but it
was very dangerous.
With half his soldiers, Alexander followed
a local guide along a small path used only
by animals and their owners.
At night, as the wind blew snow in their faces,
they ran through the mountains.
In the early morning, they rejoined the main
path beyond the Persians' position and took
the Persians by surprise.
With Macedonians in front and behind them,
the Persians suffered a terrible defeat.
Only a few escaped death.
Finally, in January 330 BC, Persepolis lay
undefended.
Alexande's soldiers moved through the city,
destroying everything and everyone in their
path in their search for riches.
For many, the long journey from Europe was
now well rewarded, as they found extraordinary
quantities of gold and silver, jewellery and
expensive clothes.
But the greatest riches were saved for the
Macedonian king.
At Persepolis, Alexander found three million
kilograms of royal Persian gold.
It took 15,000 animals to move it, under Alexander's
orders, to Susa.
Alexander chose a new governor for Persepolis
- a Persian nobleman whose father had been
killed at the Granicus.
It seemed that Persepolis was going to receive
similar treatment to Babylon and Susa.
Then, after a celebratory meal, the Athenian
girlfriend of Alexander's friend Ptolemy made
a suggestion.
Alexander should burn the palace where they
were eating, she said, to punish the Persians
for burning the Athenian Acropolis many years
before.
Alexander and his friends agreed, and soon
the historic palace of the kings of Persia
was in flames.
While Alexander was in Persepolis, Darius
and about 10,000 soldiers waited 700 kilometres
north in Ecbatana (present-day Hamadan).
But when Alexander led his army north, Darius
ordered a retreat.
First he planned to go far away to Bactria
(part of present-day Afghanistan); then he
decided to defend the Caspian Gates, which
were much closer.
His men were getting annoyed with these changes
of plan.
Eventually some of them took their king prisoner.
When Alexander heard what had happened, he
followed as quickly as he could.
Racing through the desert, by day and night,
he finally caught up with the Persian soldiers.
But their prisoner king was not with them.
Tired and thirsty after the long and unsuccessful
chase, one of Alexander's officers left the
road in search of water.
By chance he found a dead body.
It was King Darius, murdered by his own men.
Exactly 150 years after King Xerxes's wrongdoings
in Athens, the rule of the Persian kings was
at an end.
Alexander started wearing the Great King's
royal hat and purple-edged clothes, making
it clear to the Persians that he was now their
Great King.
It was a shock for the Macedonians to see
their king in Persian clothes.
They did not understand why he wanted to look
like the enemy.
They had won battles that no one had expected
them to win, and had become rich beyond their
wildest dreams.
Now their thoughts turned to home.
To his soldiers' surprise, Alexander made
no plans to go back to Europe.
Instead he continued to march east, and it
is a sign of his extraordinary skills as a
leader that his soldiers agreed to follow.
CHAPTER EIGHT
To the Ends of the Earth
The first aim was to defeat Bessus, one of
Darius's murderers.
Bessus was now in Bactria, calling himself
King of Asia.
General Parmenion, Alexander's second-in-command,
stayed in Ecbatana with 25,000 men.
Cleitus, who had saved Alexander's life at
the Battle of the Granicus, was given 6,000
foot soldiers and was told to protect the
gold in the city.
The other 32,000 soldiers in the Macedonian
army marched with Alexander towards Bactria.
The quiet complaints about Alexander's new
Persian habits now grew more serious.
A group of Macedonians planned to murder their
king.
Philotas, son of General Parmenion and commander
of the Macedonian horsemen, was told about
these plans but failed to warn Alexander.
When the murder plans were eventually known,
Philotass earlier silence seemed strange.
People began to wonder if the murder had been
his idea.
Philotas was found guilty and killed.
We know that Philotas was a powerful commander
who had openly criticized Alexander.
We do not know if he was really responsible
for the murder plans.
Now, though, Alexander had real cause to worry,
because Philotass father, General Parmenion,
controlled half of the army at the time of
his son's death.
It was possible that Parmenion would turn
against Alexander in anger at the treatment
of his son; it was even possible that Parmenion
himself had made the plans to murder Alexander.
Alexander could not afford to wait and see
what Parmenion would do.
Instead, he organized the murder of this great
general, who had been such an important commander
in the Macedonian army since the days of Alexander's
father, King Philip.
After this, Alexander was very careful.
His soldiers' letters to their families were
secretly opened.
A special group of soldiers was formed of
people who had criticized the king.
In this way, their dangerous views could not
spread to other soldiers who were still loyal
to Alexander.
In future battles these soldiers fought especially
bravely, to prove that they deserved to stay
with the army and not be left behind.
After these unpleasant events, the Macedonians
marched again towards Bactria.
Their route took them straight over the mountains
now called the Hindu Kush ('Killer of Hindus').
They climbed 3,000 metres through snow and
ice.
The army suffered terribly from cold and hunger,
and found it difficult to breathe in the thin
air.
Alexander walked beside his soldiers, helping
men
who had fallen.
The horses suffered most, and were eventually
killed and eaten - uncooked, as no firewood
could be found under the thick blanket of
snow.
Finally they arrived in Bactria.
Bessus, who had not expected Alexander's winter
crossing of the Hindu Kush, decided to retreat
beyond the River Oxus.
Most of his soldiers left his army, annoyed
that he did not want to stand and fight.
Alexander took Bactria's capital city, Bactra,
then marched in the footsteps of the retreating
Bessus.
Two months before, his men were freezing.
Now they had to suffer the terrible heat of
a stony desert.
They travelled eighty kilometres with almost
no water.
Alexander shared their suffering, refusing
to drink a small cup of water that had been
found for him.
Soon they reached the River Oxus.
Bessus had destroyed all the bridges and boats,
so Alexander ordered his men to fill their
leather tent-bags with dried grass and use
them to sail across the wide river.
On the far side, they discovered that, like
Darius before him, Bessus had been taken prisoner
by his own men.
Now he was given to Alexander.
Alexander sent him back to Ecbatana, where
his ears and nose were cut off and he was
later killed.
This was the traditional Persian punishment
for killing a king.
To please his new Persian allies, Alexander
was punishing the murderer of Darius, who
he himself had wanted to kill for so many
years.
Alexander now learnt of trouble in the lands
that he had already conquered.
The people of Sogdiana (present-day Uzbekistan)
and Bactria were angry at the way that Alexander's
hungry army had taken food and animals from
their farms, and started fighting for their
independence.
There were sieges in seven cities.
Eventually the cities were taken, the enemy
soldiers killed, and the women and children
sold into slavery.
Then news came of trouble at the city of Maracanda
(now Samarkand).
The Macedonian soldiers there were surrounded
by an enemy siege.
Alexander had to send an army to help them.
But the Scythians on the far side of the River
Jaxartes seemed dangerous too.
He decided to send only a small force to Maracanda,
and to use his main army to defeat the Scythians.
His own battle against the Scythians was successful,
and their leaders were soon asking for peace.
But in Maracanda, the situation went from
bad to worse.
The Macedonians were met by enemy horsemen.
Without Alexander to lead them, they fought
badly, were forced onto a river island and
were killed.
More than 2,000 men were lost.
It was the first real defeat that Alexander's
army had suffered.
Alexander spent the summer of 328 BC trying
to win back control of Sogdiana.
Before he had fully succeeded, a terrible
argument started over dinner one night.
It was between Alexander and Cleitus, the
man who had saved Alexander's life at the
Battle of the Granicus.
It is possible that the argument was about
Alexander's attitude to his older commanders,
and to his dead father Philip's memory.
Since his visit to Siwah, Alexander believed
that he was the son of the god Zeus; perhaps
Cleitus thought that Alexander was forgetting
the importance of his human father.
Certainly many insults were exchanged, and
in the end Alexander killed Cleitus with a
spear.
In the morning, Alexander felt terrible about
losing his temper so violently.
He went to his tent and refused to come out
for several days.
But the murder could not be undone.
After this, it seems likely that his relationship
with his commanders was different.
Cleitus had been killed because he had criticized
the king.
Nobody else wanted to die for the same reason.
The war, though, started to go better after
this.
The Sogdians, led by Oxyartes, waited behind
steep hilltop defences.
They told Alexander that they would only become
his allies if he could find soldiers with
wings.
Instead, he chose 300 soldiers to climb the
rockface during the night, just like modern
rock climbers.
They climbed to a position above the Sogdians.
When the Sogdians woke up and saw the rock
climbers, they thought for a moment that the
Macedonian army really had grown wings.
They immediately accepted defeat and were
taken prisoner.
Among the prisoners was Oxyartes's beautiful
daughter Roxane.
Alexander fell in love with her and soon they
were married.
Politically, this was a good idea too.
Oxyartes was a powerful nobleman in Sogdiana,
and now he had a strong reason to stay loyal
to Alexander.
Others were less loyal.
Alexander soon learnt of another plan to murder
him.
Callisthenes, who was a pupil and close relative
of Aristotle and was writing the history of
Alexanders heroic adventures, was blamed for
the plan and killed.
Beyond Bactria lay India (present-day Pakistan
as well as India).
Very few Greeks had ever been there, but many
strange stories were told of this mysterious
land.
People said that it was rich in gold, which
was dug by enormous insects, and that Indian
wool grew on trees.
(Cotton was not known in the Mediterranean
area at that time.)
They said that people lived for 200 years;
that there was a tribe of one-footed men;
and that to the east of India lay the Eastern
Ocean, the edge of the world.
Alexander led his army east into India, more
for the adventure than to build an empire.
By now, the soldiers were mostly Asian, not
European.
Asian Greeks from the eastern Mediterranean,
and Bactrian, Sogdian and Scythian horsemen
and archers.
But his most important commanders were his
loyal childhood friends, including Perdiccas,
Ptolemy and Seleucus.
His best friend, Hephaistion, was now his
second-in-command.
At first Alexander was surprised by the warm
welcome that he was given.
A group of Indian kings asked to be his allies
and sent him twenty-five elephants to use
in battle.
But other tribes were not as welcoming.
One after the other, their cities were taken
and their people killed, until most of the
local kings accepted Alexander as their conqueror.
If they did this, they were allowed to continue
their rule in peace.
But one king, Porus, preferred to fight.
He positioned his army and more than a hundred
war elephants on the far bank of the River
Hydaspes.
Alexander's horses were frightened of elephants,
and because it was the rainy season the river
was very deep and fast.
Alexander could not cross the river and hope
for an easy battle.
Every night, Alexander's soldiers pretended
to start an attack, shouting the Macedonian
war cry 'Alalalalai'.
Every night, Porus's men got ready to defend
themselves, but as soon as the enemy had got
out of bed, Alexander stopped his 'attack'.
Soon Porus's men were suffering badly from
too little sleep.
Porus saw that Alexander had collected enough
food to feed his men until the end of the
rainy season, and decided that in fact he
was not planning to cross the river for many
months.
He ordered his men not to listen to the nightly
Macedonian warcries.
Then Alexander attacked.
On a rainy night, he sailed across the river
about twenty-five kilometres away from the
main armies.
His boats landed on an island in the middle
of the river, not on the tar bank.
By the time the mistake was discovered, it
was almost light.
There was no time to go back to the boats.
Instead, Alexander climbed onto the back of
his horse Bucephalas, who walked the rest
of the crossing with water up to his shoulders.
Alexander's soldiers followed, some on horseback
and some on foot.
Soon the fastest of Porus's soldiers arrived,
but their chariots got stuck in mud and they
were quickly defeated.
Then Alexander marched on Porus's main army,
twenty-five kilometres away.
At the front of Porus's battle line were the
elephants.
Alexander's friends Hephaistion and Perdiccas
led horsemen to the far left of the line,
beyond the elephants, and Porus's men moved
to meet their attack.
Then Alexander sent soldiers to attack their
right, which was almost undefended.
Soon Porus's army was in a state of confusion,
and many fighters used their elephants for
protection.
While Alexander's archers shot at the elephants'
drivers, his foot soldiers cut at their legs.
The elephants went mad, picking men up and
throwing them violently to the ground.
Then, frightened and tired, they walked slowly
backwards.
The battle had ended.
For Alexander, there was just one sad result
of the battle.
Bucephalas was hurt by Porus's chariots soon
after he had crossed the river.
A few hours later, he died.
Alexander built a new city on the banks of
the river and called it Bucephala, in memory
of his much-loved horse.
Alexander's army continued east, through the
mud of the Punjab's rainy season.
When rivers broke their banks, the men had
to escape the water in local hilltop villages.
The snakes of the area did the same, and many
men died from the poisonous bites of snakes
hiding in tents, clothes and cooking pots.
They reached the banks of the River Hyphasis,
and at this point a local king gave Alexander
some unwelcome information.
They were still a long way from the Eastern
Ocean, which for Greeks meant the edge of
the world.
To get there, they had to cross the River
Ganges, more than five kilometres wide, and
fight the powerful King of Maghada and his
4,000 elephants.
Alexander was not especially worried by this
news.
He had defeated elephants before, and destroyed
an empire greater than Maghada's.
He called his men together and told them about
the adventures and achievements that the future
held.
But his men greeted his words with silence.
Some of them had marched 18,000 kilometres
since they had first arrived in Asia.
They had not seen their families for eight
long years.
And after three terrible months of rain, they
were muddy, wet and tired.
They did not want to cross the Hyphasis and
attack another great empire.
They wanted to go home.
Finally, one of the commanders told Alexander
their feelings.
Soon all the commanders refused to continue
east.
The first personal defeat in Alexander's life
came from his own army.
He realized that he had no choice.
Many of his men had tears in their eyes as
they heard the good news: Alexander was going
to lead them home.
In his tent, Alexander was not as happy as
his men.
His defeat had been very public, and it hurt
him greatly.
There was a philosopher called Anaxarchus
who was travelling with the army.
He tried to make Alexander feel better.
But according to legend, Alexander cried when
Anaxarchus talked about the number of worlds
beyond the stars.
He explained his tears: 'There are so many
worlds, and I have not yet conquered even
one.'
CHAPTER NINE
The Last Years
Alexander refused to go back the way that
he had come.
His taste for adventure was satisfied a little
when his men agreed, instead, to build boats.
They planned to follow the Hydaspes and Indus
rivers south to the Arabian Sea.
The journey started well, but it was difficult
to sail so many boats on unfamiliar waters.
When the river was too fast, the boats lost
control, and many crashed into each other
and broke.
On one occasion, Alexander had to swim for
his life.
Alexander wanted to conquer all the tribes
that he passed.
The Malloi, who lived in and around the city
of Multan, caused him the most trouble.
With a small force, Alexander surrounded Multan.
Then he led an attack on the city walls.
He climbed a ladder and jumped down inside
the city.
But the enemy managed to break the rest of
the Macedonian ladders, and only three of
his bodyguards were able to follow him.
They fought bravely, but they were attacked
on three sides.
Other Macedonians arrived as quickly as they
could, climbing on each other's shoulders
to get to the top of the walls.
But when they reached their king, he had a
metre-long arrow deep in his chest.
They defeated his attackers, then carried
him away on his shield, but they had little
hope that he would live.
The Malloi were killed - men, women and children
- and the other tribes rushed to accept defeat
peacefully.
But news reached the main army on the river
that Alexander was dead.
When he finally arrived, not only alive but
able to ride and walk, they cried with happiness.
They thought that Alexander must truly be
protected by the gods.
Alexander's soldiers fought bloody battles
against the Brahmins, which brought the total
number of Indian dead in the last six months
to a quarter of a million.
Then the rainy season began again, and there
were terrible storms.
When they finally reached the Arabian Sea,
they gave thanks to the gods.
They did not know that the most difficult
part of their journey was still ahead of them.
Two hundred years before, the Persian king
Cyrus the Great had lost a whole army in the
Gedrosian Desert.
The desert, now called the Makran, covers
62,000 square kilometres of present-day southern
Pakistan and Iran.
And their route led across it.
Alexander led a force by land, carrying water
for the men who sailed the ships.
Alexander's friend Nearchus was in charge
of the ships, which brought food for the land
army.
It was impossible to pull enough food for
everyone through the sand of the desert.
The sailors and soldiers needed each other.
But the storms of the rainy season delayed
the ships after Alexander's army had already
entered the desert.
Then the local people started fighting, and
the ships were unable to take on board all
the food that they needed.
In the desert, the sand was deep and the soldiers'
legs sank into it.
It had been blown into steep mountains and
valleys, so every kilometre felt like ten.
Occasionally they came to a watering-place.
There, thirsty men dived into the water and
drank so greedily that they died.
The expected rains came late, and when they
did, they arrived very forcefully.
Most of the women, children and animals following
the army were washed away and killed.
The Gedrosian Desert was a hell on earth.
Soon the men started to die of hunger.
If they left the army in search of food, they
were likely to be killed by poisonous plants
or snakes.
Then they discovered that their guides had
lost their way.
Eventually, eight weeks after entering the
desert, they came out on the other side.
But the desert had proved a much stronger
enemy than an army.
Tens of thousands of men, women and children
had died on the march.
At this time, Nearchus and the ships were
only just leaving India.
They too were hungry and thirsty on their
journey, but Nearchus led them well and they
lost few men.
Eventually, the ships reached Carmania (in
present-day southern Iran), on the far side
of the desert, and Alexander was there to
welcome them.
There were wild celebrations.
Sailors and soldiers were together again,
and they knew that they were lucky to be alive.
When Alexander had marched over the Hindu
Kush, few Persians had believed that he would
ever return.
Since then, there had been stories that he
had died in Multan or in the Gedrosian Desert.
They were very surprised when he arrived in
Carmania, an easy march from Persepolis.
Few of the conquered lands had stayed loyal
in the six years since the Battle of Gaugamela.
Some governors had become disloyal as soon
as Alexander had left.
Others, including the governor of Babylon
and Queen Ada of Caria, had died of illness
or in battle, and disloyal men had taken their
place.
Many Greeks and Macedonians had been left
as the populations of Alexander's new cities;
some had hated their new life and killed their
governors.
And in Ecbatana, a group of Alexander's generals
had behaved very badly, insulting the local
religion and attacking the local noblewomen.
Alexander punished his disloyal governors
and generals with death.
He chose new governors from among his European
commanders; too few of his Persian appointments
had been a success.
Alexander next planned a great wedding celebration,
choosing Persian wives for ninety of his officers.
He himself was already married to Roxane,
but he decided to follow royal Macedonian
tradition and take two more wives: the eldest
daughters of Persia's most recent kings, Darius
and Artaxerxes.
He asked his best friend, Hephaistion, to
marry Darius's younger daughter, so that Hephaistion's
children could be his own nephews.
The weddings were celebrated for five days,
in an enormous tent in Susa that had been
richly decorated with gold and jewels.
Alexander had taken the power of government
away from the Persians; now he was including
them in his empire in another way.
More and more soldiers from the eastern half
of the empire were joining Alexander's army.
When he asked his oldest Macedonian soldiers
to go home, they felt insulted that he did
not need them any more.
After ten years in Asia, they now wanted to
stay and enjoy the lands that they had conquered.
They refused to leave.
The rest of the Macedonian soldiers supported
them.
'If you send the old soldiers home, you must
send us all,' they told Alexander.
But Alexander's decision was final, and he
said that they could all go home if they wished;
Persians would take their place in his army.
Immediately the Macedonians changed their
minds.
They asked Alexander to forgive them.
They wanted him to send the old soldiers home,
but allow the rest of them to stay.
The problem was solved, and Alexander organized
a great dinner to celebrate the friendly relationship
between Macedonians and Persians.
Alexander and his friends spent the next few
months relaxing and being entertained by theatre
performances and sports competitions.
But Hephaistion caught a fever, became ill
and died.
His death was a terrible shock to his lifelong
friend and king.
For many weeks he was unable to think about
anything else.
Slowly Alexander returned to his usual business.
He planned to send ships and a land army around
the coast of Arabia from Persia to Egypt.
Other ships were going to check if the Caspian
Sea was part of a northern ocean or joined
the Black Sea; although its southern coast
was part of the empire, no one seemed to know
at that time that the Caspian Sea was actually
a lake.
But in Babylon, Alexander suddenly became
ill.
Possibly he had been poisoned by his officers;
probably he had caught a disease carried by
insects while he was travelling on Babylon's
waterways.
He had a high fever, and after a week he could
not talk.
On the tenth day, his court and army were
given the unthinkable news: Alexander the
Great was dead.
CHAPTER TEN
After Alexander
Although Alexander's achievements had spread
Greek customs far into Asia, the Greeks in
Europe were pleased about his death and decided
to fight for their independence.
To them, he was still a foreigner.
But the Persians, who had lost an empire and
hundreds of thousands of men because of Alexander,
were very upset when they heard that he had
died.
King Darius's mother, who had become Alexander's
prisoner after the Battle of Issus, stopped
eating when she heard the news, and was dead
herself five days later.
Alexander had become the Persians' Great King,
whose rule followed the traditions of the
past.
He had been their friend as well as their
conqueror.
And, rightly, they feared a future without
him.
Alexander died with no close male relative
except his brother Arrhidaeus, who had learning
difficulties.
But Roxane, Alexander's first wife, was soon
going to have a baby.
Alexander's friends decided to make the unborn
child the next king, if the baby was a boy.
Alexander's friend Perdiccas, who had been
his second-in-command after the death of Hephaistion
and had royal blood himself, would rule until
the baby grew up.
But the common soldiers wanted Arrhidaeus
as their king, as he was fully Macedonian
and Roxane's baby had Asian blood.
Less than a week after Alexander's death,
fighting began.
It was only stopped when Perdiccas ordered
the death of thirty of the soldiers leaders
and they were thrown to the elephants.
It was agreed that rule would be shared between
Roxane's baby and Arrhidaeus.
There were many years of confusion in the
empire that Alexander had built.
The story of Alexander's dead body is typical
of the times.
It was believed that the body's final resting
place would bring good luck to the local people.
Perdiccas ordered his men to take it from
Babylon to Macedonia in a box of gold.
But Ptolemy, who had been a close friend of
Alexander and had recently made himself king
of an independent Egypt, took the body in
secret to Egyptian Alexandria, where it stayed
for hundreds of years.
During the years after Alexander's death,
Roxane poisoned Alexander's other wives to
protect the power of her baby son, also called
Alexander.
Perdiccas ruled for a short time, until he
was murdered by his bodyguards.
Alexander's most loyal commanders all wanted
power for themselves, and they were willing
to murder people to get it.
Antipater was the general who had controlled
the Macedonian army in Europe while Alexander
was in Asia.
When Antipater died of old age, his son Cassander
took control of Macedonia.
Alexander's mother, Olympias, was officially
in charge of Macedonia and tried to protect
her power.
She murdered King Arrhidaeus, her husband's
son and Alexander's half-brother, and defended
herself in the Macedonian town of Pydna.
But Cassander put the town under siege.
After nine months she had no food, and she
died proudly.
Cassander then killed Roxane and her son,
who were visiting Greece, and made himself
King of Macedonia.
The Macedonians soon sold the lands that Alexander
had conquered in India; they received 500
elephants for them.
Many years later, these lands were reconquered
by the Greek-speaking kings of Bactria, whose
family had been started by one of Alexander's
Macedonian governors.
After years of fighting, two of Alexander's
commanders controlled most of his empire.
Ptolemy was King of Egypt and Seleucus king
of the Asian empire.
The families of both men stayed in power until
their lands were conquered by the Romans in
the first century BC.
All over Alexander's empire, Greek-style cities
had been built.
Their populations were mostly European, and
became perhaps more Greek in their habits
as the years passed.
In some areas, they preferred to marry their
sister, niece or granddaughter than to join
their family with the foreigners that surrounded
them.
Each city had a gymnasium, and held sporting
competitions and theatre performances.
In Afghanistan, buildings and works of art
have been discovered which copied exactly
the artistic styles of Greece.
The works of Homer, Plato and Aristotle were
read and enjoyed in India and even across
the sea in Sri Lanka.
The greatest of Alexander's new cities was
Alexandria, the capital of Egypt under the
Ptolemaic kings.
While many parts of Alexander's empire suffered
from continued fighting, Egypt lived in peace
and grew in power.
Its economy was very successful; from Alexandria,
ships took paper, medicines, jewellery and
art all over the known world.
The Ptolemaic kings mixed Greek customs with
Egyptian traditions, and built temples to
both Greek and Egyptian gods.
They were very interested in literature, philosophy
and science, and invited the most famous writers
of their age to live in Alexandria.
Out of this collection of great men grew a
great idea: a library that brought together
all Greek knowledge and included every book
that had ever been written.
At its largest, this library held 50,000 books
- not a lot compared to the great modern libraries,
but in a world before printing machines this
was an extraordinary number.
Among these books was a growing collection
of histories of Alexander's life.
Some of them were interested in the facts;
others told romantic stories that were completely
untrue.
They said that he and his warhorse Bucephalas
each had two horns on their heads.
They told of strange flying machines, a Valley
of Diamonds, and the secret of immortality.
Alexander's legend was told from Iceland to
China; in death he travelled far beyond the
borders of his own empire.
Over the years, interest in Alexander has
been shown in many different ways.
He appears in the Book of Daniel, which was
written in Hebrew in the second century BC
and now forms part of the Christian Bible.
He was the hero of Julius Caesar, Rome's greatest
general.
The Italian artist Michelangelo created a
square in Rome to look like Alexander's famous
shield.
The French ruler Napoleon used to read about
Alexander in bed every night.
In the early 1900s, tribal kings in Afghanistan
still went into battle carrying a red flag
which, according to their legends, had belonged
to Alexander.
And in 2004, Alexander's extraordinary story
was brought to life in a $155 million Hollywood
film.
It starred Colin Farrell as Alexander and
was watched in cinemas all around the world.
Alexander the Great may be more famous in
the twenty-first century than he ever was.