CHAPTER ONE
Ireland's story
There are many different Irelands.
One Ireland is a country with beautiful high
mountains, big empty beaches, long deep rivers.
People go there to fish and swim and walk.
They love Ireland because it is so quiet,
and because the Irish people are so nice and
friendly.
Another Ireland is a country of stories and
music.
Most Irish people can sing, and many famous
musicians are Irish.
A lot of the most famous writers in the English
language are Irish too.
But some people in Ireland speak only or mostly
Irish.
Now look again at Ireland.
It is not only a quiet, beautiful, friendly
place; it is also a country of blood, bombs,
and death.
Between 1968 and 1998 thousands of people
in Northern Ireland died.
But most Irish people are not interested in
bombs and guns.
What is Ireland really like?
What can you see there?
And what happened hundreds of years ago, in
Irish history?
Turn the page to begin reading Ireland's story.
CHAPTER TWO
Around the island
Ireland is an island like a plate: it is higher
on the outside than in the centre.
Because of this, the centre of Ireland is
full of beautiful lakes and rivers, and many
people go there to fish and sail.
Ireland's largest lake is Lough Neagh.
Its longest river, the Shannon, is 260 kilometres
long.
It goes through many small lakes and two large
ones, Lough Ree and Lough Derg.
Most of Ireland's mountains are near the outside
of the plate, near the sea.
They are not very high - the highest is Carrantouhill
(1,040 metres) in the south-west.
But they are beautiful, and good places for
walks.
At the Cliffs of Moher, in the west, you can
look 200 metres straight down into the sea.
The Giant's Causeway, in the north, is made
of strange rocks two metres tall with six
sides.
There are hundreds of small islands in the
sea around Ireland.
On the Aran Islands, in the west, most people
speak Irish, not English.
Life has changed very little here in a hundred
years.
Much of the north and west of Ireland is very
beautiful.
There are hundreds of flowers in the green
fields, and there are wonderful beaches and
lakes (called 'loughs' in Ireland).
The weather is warm and wet, with rain and
sun nearly every day.
But it is hard to farm here because of the
rocks and mountains.
The centre and east of Ireland are very different.
The land is good here, and Irish milk and
meat are some of the best in the world.
Farming is one of the most important jobs
in Ireland.
Thousands of horses live here too.
Some of the best horses in the world come
from Ireland, and Irish people sell horses
to Britain, America, Australia, and Japan.
People go to watch horse races in many Irish
towns, and in Lay town, north of Dublin, there
are horse races along the beach every September.
All Ireland's important cities - Dublin, Belfast,
Derry, Galway, Limerick, Cork, and Waterford
- are near the sea.
If we look at Ireland's history, we will see
why.
CHAPTER THREE
Celtic Ireland
The Irish are a Celtic people.
Thousands of years ago, the Celts came to
Ireland from western France and northern Spain.
They loved singing, and horses, and stories,
and they made beautiful gold and silver jewellery.
Many men wore gold rings round their necks
and arms.
A Greek writer, Diodorus Siculus, wrote this
about the Celts:
The Celts are... tall and strong.
They wear colourful shirts and trousers.
Before they fight they hit their long swords
on their shields, and shout with loud voices....
They are very good fighters.
When a Celt kills a man, he cuts off his head
and puts it above the door of his house.
Finn Mac Cool was a famous Celtic fighter.
There are many stories about Finn and his
men, the Fianna.
When he was a boy, he cooked a fish on a fire.
This fish knew everything about the world.
Finn touched the hot fish with his finger,
and put his finger in his mouth.
Then he knew everything about the world too.
'I know what is going to happen tomorrow,'
he said.
Another famous Celt was Cuchulainn.
Cuchulainn's father had a brother called Conor,
who was king of Ulster, in the north of Ireland.
Conor had a big, dangerous dog which killed
many men.
Cuchulainn liked to play a Celtic game called
hurling.
In hurling, the players can carry a small
hard ball in their hands and also hit it with
a stick.
One day, when Cuchulainn was a boy, Conor
called everyone into his house to eat.
But Cuchulainn and his friends wanted to finish
their game of hurling, so they stayed outside.
Conor's dog came out of the house, attacked
(he young boys and tried to kill them.
But Cuchulainn hit the hurling ball into the
dog's mouth, and then killed it with his stick.
A big fighting dog is called a hound, and
so after this, Cuchulainn was called 'The
Hound of Ulster.'
Celtic games, like hurling, are very popular
in Ireland today.
Irish people play the Celtic game called Gaelic
football.
In Gaelic football the players can use their
feet and hands.
Celtic stories and music are popular too.
There are many Celtic rock bands - one of
them is called Finn MacCool.
And some people in Ireland speak the Celtic
language called Irish.
Irish is very different from English - for
example, the Irish for tree is craw, and the
word for woman is bean.
But Celtic people in Wales, Scotland, western
France, and northern Spain have languages
very like Irish.
A hundred years ago, Irish was nearly a dead
language.
Most Irish people spoke English, and only
the poor people in the west of Ireland spoke
Irish.
No one taught Irish in schools.
Most Irish people speak English today too,
but many children learn Irish at school, and
many older people in Dublin and Belfast learn
it too.
They can listen to the Irish language radio
station, Raidio na Gaeltachta, and watch Irish
language television on TG4.
The Irish language is popular again.
CHAPTER FOUR
St Patrick, the Church, and the Vikings
In 401 some Irishmen came to Britain.
They took many people back to Ireland and
sold them.
One of these people was Patrick, who was only
sixteen.
For six years young Patrick worked with sheep
on a farm.
Then, when he was twenty-two, he ran away
to France.
He learned about God from monks at a school
in a French monastery.
In 432 he went back to Ireland to teach the
Irish about God.
The Irish kings listened to him, and he built
an important church in Armagh.
A hundred years later, Ireland was one of
the most important Christian countries in
Europe, with beautiful churches and monasteries
everywhere.
Irish writers wrote famous, important books
like the Book of Kells, which you can see
in Dublin today, and there are pictures of
St Patrick in many Irish churches.
Another Irish churchman, called Brendan, sailed
to Scotland, Iceland, Greenland, and America
in a small leather boat.
Some people said that this was not possible,
but in 1976 an Englishman, Tim Severin, built
a leather boat called Brendan and sailed it
from Ireland to Iceland and America.
You can see the Brendan at Craggaunowen in
County Clare in the west of Ireland.
There were many beautiful, expensive things
in the Irish churches and monasteries, and
Norwegian Vikings came to Ireland to steal
them and kill the monks.
Because of this, the monks built tall round
towers beside their monasteries.
When the Vikings came the monks ran into the
towers to hide.
You can see these towers in Irish villages
today.
One of the most interesting Irish monasteries
is on Skellig Michael.
It is an island in the Atlantic sixteen kilometres
south-west of Ireland.
It is a beautiful, windy place.
The island is 240 metres high, and in bad
weather no boats can get there.
'There is no danger here,' the Irish monks
thought; but they were wrong.
In 824, Vikings came in their long ships to
attack Skellig Michael too.
But some Vikings came to Ireland to stay.
They built towns by the sea - Dublin, Cork,
Waterford, and Limerick.
The Celts liked to live in the country, but
the Vikings lived in towns.
Some of the Vikings married Celts, and learned
the Celtic language.
The Vikings came to the north of Ireland too.
One day two different Viking ships came to
a beautiful place in Ulster.
Both groups of Vikings wanted to stay there
and build a town, but there were too many
of them.
The two groups of Vikings looked at each other
angrily.
'We must fight,' said a Viking from the first
ship.
'The winners will live and keep the land,
and the losers will die.'
'No,' said a man from the second ship.
'I have a better idea.
Let's race to the beach in our ships.
The first man who holds the land in his hand
can keep it.
His people can stay, and the others must leave.'
So the two ships raced towards the beach.
One man stood at the front of each ship, ready
to jump down to the beach.
Then one ship went in front of the other.
The man in the first ship looked back at the
second ship, and laughed.
'We're going to win,' he said.
'This land will belong to us.'
'No, it won't,' said the man in the second
ship angrily.
'You will never win.
Never!'
Suddenly, he took out his sword, and cut off
his hand with it.
Then he threw the hand over the heads of the
men in the first ship.
The hand fell on the beach, and its bloody
fingers closed on the land.
'This is our land,' said the man with one
hand.
'It will never belong to you.
Never, never, never!'
That, is the story of the Red Hand of Ulster.
You can see the Red Hand on the flags of Northern
Ireland.
To learn why it is so important, we need to
learn a little more about Irish history.
CHAPTER FIVE
The English come to Ireland
A thousand years ago, Ireland had many kings
and they often fought each other.
In 1152 one Irish king, Dermot MacMurrough,
attacked another Irish king, Tiernan O'Rourke,
and took his wife.
Tiernan O'Rourke was the friend of a third
king, Rory O'Connor.
In 1166 Rory O'Connor was made king of all
Ireland.
At this time, Tiernan and Rory attacked Dermot
MacMurrough, but Dermot escaped to England.
Dermot then asked the king of England, Henry
the Second, to help him to fight Rory and
Tiernan.
So in 1169 Henry's men came to Ireland and
fought Rory and Tiernan, but they did not
go home again.
They took more and more of the land for themselves.
They built cities by the sea, and big castles.
Henry called himself King of England and Ireland.
But not all the Irish were happy about this.
For the next four hundred years, English kings
tried to rule Ireland from Dublin.
But it was very difficult.
The Irish did not listen to the King of England
- he was too far away.
In 1536 the English church changed from Catholic
to Protestant.
So England was a Protestant country, but Ireland
was still Catholic.
For the Protestant English, their king was
the most important man in the Church, but
for the Catholic Irish, the most important
man was the Pope - the leader of the Catholic
Church - in Rome.
There was a lot of fighting in Ireland about
this, and usually the English won.
The kings of England took more land from the
Catholic Irish, and gave it to Protestant
Englishmen and Scotsmen.
This plan was called the Plantation of Ulster,
because much of the land was in Ulster, in
the north of Ireland.
Englishmen from London built a new town in
a place called Derry, and called it Londonderry.
The Catholic Irish were angry about this and
wanted their land back.
In 1641 the Catholics attacked the Protestants
in Ulster.
They took their houses and clothes and killed
thousands of people.
Eight years later, in 1649, Oliver Cromwell
took an English army to Ireland.
Cromwell was the leader of the English after
the death of King Charles the First.
The English soldiers killed thousands of Catholics
in a town called Drogheda.
In 1685 the people of England and Scotland
got a new king - James the Second.
He was a Catholic, and he was not very popular.
Many people wanted a different king, and in
1688 William of Orange, a Dutch Protestant,
came to England.
He was married to James's daughter Mary, and
he wanted to be king of England, Scotland,
and Ireland.
In those three countries people who wanted
James to be king fought against people who
wanted William to be king.
Most of James's friends were Catholics in
Ireland.
With his help, they tried to get their land
back again.
They got most of it, but they could not get
Londonderry.
When they attacked it, the Protestants ran
inside the city walls and closed the gates.
For 105 days, the Catholic soldiers tried
to get inside and kill them.
The Protestants were cold and afraid and hungry.
They ate cats and dogs and horses, but they
did not open the gates.
15,000 people died during this time, which
was called the Siege of Derry.
At last, three Protestant ships came to Londonderry
with food and soldiers, and the siege was
over.
After that the new Protestant English King,
William of Orange, won two very important
battles against the Catholics: the Battle
of the Boyne in 1690, and the Battle of Aughrim
in 1691.
The Catholic Irish didn't fight a big battle
again for 100 years.
So for the next hundred years life was very
difficult for the Catholic Irish.
Keeping their land or going to Catholic schools
or Catholic churches was very difficult and
they could not speak or vote in Parliament.
All the important people in Ireland were
Protestants, and all the big, beautiful houses
and the best farms belonged to Protestants.
In most countries, people read about history
in books; in Ireland, history is alive today.
Every year, Protestants in Londonderry march
to remember 1688.
In Belfast, on 12 July, Protestant Orangemen
march with music and songs about King William
of Orange - often called 'King Billy'- and
the Battle of the Boyne.
Every year, Catholics are angry about these
marches.
CHAPTER SIX
The Great Hunger
In 1795 and 1798 the Irish, with the help
of French ships and soldiers, fought the British.
But the British won, and many Irishmen - mostly
Catholics - were killed.
Three years later, in 1801, the Act of Union
made Ireland and Britain one country, with
one Parliament, in London.
For a hundred years after this, Catholic Irishmen
(called Nationalists) wanted to change the
Act of Union, and Protestants (called Unionists)
wanted to keep it.
At this time, in the west of Ireland, many
poor Catholics lived on very small farms.
They had very little money, and often they
had only potatoes to eat.
The poor, stony land was not good for many
things, but it was good for potatoes.
But in the 1840s something killed the potatoes.
One day they were fine, and then suddenly
they were black and dead.
The poor Irish farmers and their families
had nothing to eat.
Thousands of them died, and many more went
on ships to America, to find a new and better
life.
Some rich Protestants were happy when the
poor farmers started to leave.
They wanted to keep cows on their land, so
they asked the ships to take the poor people
away from Ireland to America.
But hundreds of people died on the ships too.
When the Irish people came to America, they
lived in big cities, like New York.
Every year on St Patrick's Day thousands of
Americans march through New York, and remember
how Irish people died, because there was no
food.
It is the biggest St Patrick's Day parade
in the world, because so many Irish people
live in America.
When these poor Irish people died, the Irish
language nearly died with them.
Most Catholic churchmen spoke English, and
the government told Irish teachers to use
English in school.
Only poor people spoke Irish.
'Irish is not important,' the teachers and
churchmen said.
They thought that speaking English was more
modern.
But some people thought that this was wrong.
In 1893 a group of Irish writers tried to
help the Irish language.
'Irish is the language of the Irish people,'
they said.
'Many countries have a language, games, music,
and stories that belong to them.
We must have those things too.'
A lot of people agreed with them.
These people called themselves Sinn Fein,
which is Irish for 'We Ourselves.'
At first, the people in Sinn Fein were only
interested in Irish language, music, and games.
But later, they began to think about other
things too.
'We don't want to belong to Britain,' they
said.
'We want Ireland to be a free country.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
Fighting to be free
By 1900, life was a little better for Catholics
in Ireland.
They could have land, they could vote and
speak in Parliament, they had Catholic schools
and churches.
But most Catholics were very poor, and every
year, thousands of them went to America or
Britain to look for work.
Catholic Irish Nationalists wanted to end
the Act of Union.
They wanted an Irish Parliament to decide
about things in Ireland.
But the Protestants did not want to give it
to them - and, not for the first time, they
were ready to fight for the things that they
wanted.
In 1914, the British government decided to
give Ireland an Irish Parliament.
'Ireland will still belong to Britain,' they
said.
'But the Irish Parliament will decide on Irish
things, like Irish schools, roads, and police.'
Most Irish Nationalists were happy about this,
but the Protestant Unionists were angry.
Most Protestants lived in Northern Ireland
near Belfast.
This part of Ireland is called Ulster.
Soon the Protestant Unionist army began marching
through the streets of Belfast with their
leader, Sir Edward Carson.
They wanted to keep the Act of Union.
'Ulster will fight,' they said, 'and Ulster
will be right!'
The British government did not know what to
do.
They wanted to give Ireland a Parliament,
but they did not want to fight the Unionists.
But then, in 1914, the First World War started.
Most of the Protestant Unionists, and many
thousands of Irish Catholics, went with the
British army to fight against Germany.
But many Irish Nationalists stayed in Ireland.
'We don't want to fight the Germans,' they
said.
'We want the British to leave Ireland.
Perhaps the Germans can help us.'
In 1916, a group of Irish Nationalists-mostly
Catholics - decided to fight for a free Ireland.
They were interested in Irish music, Irish
history, the Irish language, and Irish games.
But now they bought guns in Germany and tried
to bring them to Ireland in a German ship.
Their leader, Patrick Pearse, wanted much
more than an Irish Parliament.
He wanted Ireland to be free from Britain.
On Easter Monday 1916, Pearse and his men
went into the Post Office, in the middle of
Dublin.
Pearse walked to the door.
'Irishmen and Irishwomen,' he said.
'Ireland belongs to the Irish people!
Today Ireland is a free country!'
But the British did not agree.
For six long days there was a battle in Dublin,
and many men died.
After the battle, the government said that
Pearse and fourteen other important men had
to die, and they died in prison.
Nearly two thousand other Sinn Fein men went
to prison.
Easter Monday 1916 was a very important day
in Irish history.
After that day, everything was different.
In his poem Easter 1916 the Irish writer William
Butler Yeats wrote:
All changed, changed utterly.
A terrible beauty is born.
In 1919, Sinn Fein started to fight the British
again.
The Sinn Fein army was called the Irish Republican
Army, or IRA.
From 1919 to 1921 the IRA killed hundreds
of policemen and soldiers, and the police
and soldiers killed hundreds of IRA men too.
In Dublin, there were IRA men and women everywhere,
but it was very hard for the British soldiers
to find them.
The IRA leader was Michael Collins, but the
British government didn't even have a photo
of him!
In 1921 the British government decided to
talk to Sinn Fein and the IRA, and in that
year, for the first time in history, most
of Ireland had an Irish government, with an
Irish President in Dublin.
But the Irish Republic is only three-quarters
of Ireland.
One quarter, in Northern Ireland, stayed British.
And here, fifty years later, the trouble between
Protestants and Catholics started again.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Northern Ireland
In 1921, about 60 percent of the people of
Northern Ireland were Protestant, and about
40 percent were Catholic.
Today the numbers are about 53 percent and
40 percent.
Most of the Protestants want to be British,
and most of the Catholics want to be Irish.
Hundreds of people have died because of this.
From 1921 to 1971 Northern Ireland had a Parliament
at Stormont.
There were always more Protestants than Catholics,
so the Protestants could do what they wanted.
Protestants had most of the best jobs and
the best houses.
Most of the police were Protestant too, and
they were afraid of the IRA.
At the same time, many Catholics were afraid
of the police.
Sometimes the IRA tried to kill the police,
and the police hit back at the Catholics.
It was a circle without an end.
In 1968 Catholics started to ask for a better
life.
They marched through the streets of Belfast
and Derry, asking for better jobs and houses.
But the Protestant police and Orangemen attacked
the Catholic marchers.
Many marchers were badly hurt, and all of
them were angry and afraid.
In 1969 British soldiers came to Northern
Ireland to try to stop the fighting, and at
first many Catholics were happy to see them.
But then the IRA started to kill soldiers
and policemen, and so the British soldiers
and police tried to find the IRA and put them
in prison.
Sometimes they put the wrong people in prison,
and so the Catholics didn't like the British
soldiers.
Over the next thirty years, many terrible
things happened.
On 'Bloody Sunday' - 30 January 1972 - British
soldiers killed 14 Catholic marchers in Derry.
'The marchers had guns,' the soldiers said.
But nobody found any guns.
On 'Bloody Friday' - 21 July 1972 - the IRA
put 22 bombs in Belfast, all at the same time.
9 people died and 130 people were hurt, Protestant
and Catholic, British and Irish.
Some of them lost arms and legs.
The IRA put bombs in pubs and streets and
shops.
They killed soldiers and policemen, but they
also killed thousands of ordinary people.
Protestants in the Ulster Defence Association
- the UDA - killed thousands of ordinary Catholics
too.
These Protestant fighters are called Loyalists.
By 1979 there were hundreds of IRA and UDA
men in prison.
At first they were political prisoners, like
soldiers in prison during a war.
They could wear ordinary clothes, and they
did not do prison work.
Then Margaret Thatcher, the British Prime
Minister, decided that this must stop.
'These men are criminals,' she said, 'so they
must be the same as other prisoners.'
Because of this some prisoners decided in
1980 to stop eating.
They drank water but they did not eat.
Day after day, they got thinner and thinner.
After 66 days, the first man, Bobby Sands,
died.
Then another man died, and another.
Ten men died in prison, because they wanted
to be political prisoners.
Most British people thought Mrs Thatcher was
right, but a lot of Irish Catholics didn't
agree.
More and more of them started to vote for
Sinn Fein.
In many parts of Northern Ireland there are
Nationalist or Loyalist paintings on the walls
of houses.
The Loyalists usually show the Red Hand of
Ulster, or King William of Orange and the
Battle of the Boyne.
The Nationalists show Celtic pictures, and
pictures of Bobby Sands.
Both of them often show men with guns.
In 1998, the British and Irish governments
met with Sinn Fein and the Ulster Unionists.
They wanted to end the fighting in Northern
Ireland.
Together, they made the Good Friday Agreement.
This Agreement said that Catholics and Protestants
must work together in the government of Northern
Ireland.
Today, Catholics and Protestants still do
not agree about many things in Northern Ireland.
But after thirty years of fighting, people
are starting to talk to each other.
And most people are happy about that.
CHAPTER NINE
Dublin and Belfast
Dublin.
Dublin is the most important city in the Republic
of Ireland.
Its population (the number of people who live
there) is 496,000.
The River Liffey goes through the centre of
Dublin.
Some people say that Ireland s famous black
beer, Guinness, is water from the River Liffey,
but it is not true.
But you can walk beside the river, and drink
Guinness in a pub when you are thirsty.
One of the most beautiful buildings beside
the river is the Custom House.
There is a nice walk along the river from
the Custom House to the O'Connell Bridge.
North of the bridge is O'Connell Street.
Here you can see the Post Office, famous for
Easter Monday 1916.
Not far from here is St Mary's, Dublin's biggest
Catholic church.
South of O'Connell Bridge is Trinity College,
Ireland's oldest and most famous university.
In here you can see Ireland's oldest books,
like the Book of Kells, which is a thousand
years old.
The beautiful Bank of Ireland is opposite
Trinity College.
Ireland's first Parliament was in this building.
Near Trinity College you can see the famous
statue of Molly Malone.
People say that she was a poor but beautiful
girl, who sold fish called cockles and mussels
on the streets to make money.
But sadly, she died when she was still young.
There is a famous Irish song about Molly:
In Dublin's fair city
Where the girls are so pretty
I first set my eyes on sweet Molly Malone
As she wheeled her wheelbarrow
Down streets broad and narrow
Singing 'Cockles, and mussels, alive alive-oh!'
Some of Ireland's best town houses are in
Merrion Square.
Many of Ireland's most famous writers, soldiers,
and leaders lived here.
They walked and talked in the small park in
the square, or in St Stephen's Green, not
far away.
Between Merrion Square and St Stephen's Green
is Leinster House, the home of Ireland's Parliament
today.
Dublin also has Phoenix Park, one of the largest
parks in Europe.
Ireland's President lives here, in a house
called, in Irish, Aras an Uachtarain.
Not far away from the Phoenix Park is the
old Kilmainham Prison.
Here visitors can see how some of Ireland's
most famous men and women lived in prison.
Dublin is a city of theatres, music, and fine
shops too.
And there are dozens of pubs, big and small.
Many people like to go to the pub to drink
beer, talk, and tell stories.
For example, there is a story about a visitor
and an Irish farmer in the country.
'Excuse me, can you tell me the way to Dublin,
please?'
the visitor asks.
The farmer thinks for a long time.
Then he says: 'No, I'm sorry.
If you want to go to Dublin, this is the wrong
place to start.'
Belfast.
Belfast (population 276,000) is the biggest
city in Northern Ireland, famous for the ships,
aeroplanes, and clothes that were made here.
The Titanic was built here in the Harland
and Wolff shipyard.
In 1912 the Titanic was the biggest, fastest,
most expensive ship in the world.
'This ship can never sink,' people said.
But when the Titanic went to sea for the first
time, it sank, and about 1,500 people died.
Many of them were poor Irish people who wanted
to start a new life in America.
Now this part of the city is called the Titanic
Quarter, and it has new shops, offices, bars,
cafes, and hotels.
But you can still see the big Harland and
Wolff cranes, called Samson and Goliath, from
all over Belfast.
At Victoria Square, in the centre of Belfast,
there are new shops, restaurants, and cinemas.
And there are fine old buildings to see - City
Hall, the Custom House with its wonderful
statues, the Ulster Bank, and McHugh's Bar
- the oldest building in Belfast.
Once it was a house by the Belfast River,
and today it is a modern bar.
CHAPTER TEN
Four Irish cities
Cork.
Cork is the second largest city in the Republic
of Ireland.
In 820 the Vikings attacked a Christian monastery
here, and then stayed to build a town by the
River Lee.
Cork is in the south-west of Ireland and it
has a wonderful harbour for ships.
Many poor Irish people sailed from Cork to
America at the time of the Great Hunger, and
today ships and planes go from Cork all over
the world.
123,000 people live here today, and the city
of Cork is famous for music, dancing, theatre,
and film.
Many visitors come here too, on their way
to the beautiful south-west of Ireland.
In 2005 Cork was the European Capital of Culture.
Londonderry, or Derry.
Derry, with a population of 105,000, is the
second city of Northern Ireland.
Protestants call it Londonderry, because in
1600 English Protestants from London built
a city here, but Catholics call the city Derry.
There was a small monastery here, beside the
River Foyle, in the time of the Vikings, but
the great walls of Londonderry were built
in the 1600s.
You can walk around these walls today: they
are one and a half kilometres long and nearly
six metres wide.
The old guns from the Siege of Derry are still
there on the walls.
But many people want to forget the battles
of the past.
In the last week of October, thousands of
people come to Derry for the Halloween festival.
There is music, theatre, and a big parade,
in the biggest street party in Ireland.
Galway.
Galway (population 65,800) is in the west
of Ireland, at the mouth of the River Corrib.
In this part of the country the Irish language
is very strong, and you will see it and hear
it everywhere.
It is a centre for Irish music, singing and
dance, and there is an Irish language theatre
in Galway too.
From Galway you can visit Connemara, with
its beautiful wild lakes and mountains.
The Aran Islands are close by too.
People speak Irish here, and many visitors
like to come to these wild, lonely islands
to hear Irish music in the pubs and see the
difficult life of the islanders.
Waterford.
Waterford (population 45,000) is in the south-east
of Ireland.
It was Ireland's first city; the Vikings came
here in the 850s, and they came back in 914
to make the city.
It is famous for its glass (people have made
glass here since 1783) and for the ships that
were built here.
Three rivers meet the sea at Waterford - the
Rivers Barrow, Nore and Suir - and there are
fine mountains and beaches to visit in this
part of Ireland.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Stories, music, and dancing
Irish people love stories, and many great
writers were born in Ireland.
Jonathan Swift (1667-1745) was a churchman
in Dublin.
In his book Gulliver's Travels a man called
Gulliver visits many strange countries.
In Lilliput all the people are about ten centimetres
high and in the country of the Houyhnhnms
horses are cleverer than people.
But when Gulliver comes home, nobody believes
his stories.
James Joyce (1882-1941) wrote all his stories
about Dublin.
His most famous book, Ulysses, is 700 pages
long.
It is the story of everything that one man,
Leopold Bloom, does in Dublin in one day - 16
June 1904.
And every year on 16 June - 'Bloomsday' - people
visit Dublin to talk about Ulysses and to
visit the places in the story.
Joyce's friend, Samuel Beckett (1906-89) won
the Nobel Prize for his work in the theatre.
His most famous work, Waiting for Godot, is
about two poor Irish men who are waiting for
a man called Godot.
Perhaps Godot is a man, perhaps he is God
- they don't know.
But he never comes.
Joyce and Beckett were born in Ireland, but
they went to work and live in France.
They had new and exciting ideas, and some
people in Ireland did not like them.
To the Irish government and the Catholic Church,
books like Ulysses were wrong, and after 1929
Irish people could not buy books like these
in the shops.
Life was difficult in other ways too - many
people had large families and little money.
Ireland was a poor country, and it was difficult
to find work.
Every year, many young people left Ireland
to look for work in other countries.
Because of these things some singers too were
very angry about life in Ireland.
Bob Geldof was born in Ireland in 1951.
His mother died when he was seven, and his
father was often away from home, so young
Bob was often alone.
He saw many poor people in Dublin, and his
band, the Boomtown Rats, sang loud, angry
songs.
In their song Banana Republic, they said Ireland
was a poor country with a bad government,
and too many police and churchmen:
Everywhere I go now and everywhere I see the
black and blue uniforms Police and priests
Bob Geldof wanted to change the world, and
in 1985 he planned some concerts called Band
Aid and Live Aid.
He used the money from the concerts to help
hungry people in Africa.
In 2005 he did this again, with a concert
called Live 8.
With another Irish musician called Bono, Bob
Geldof asked the presidents of many countries
to give help to Africa.
Bono is from an Irish group called U2.
Some people say that U2 are the biggest rock
band in the world.
Like Bob Geldof, the band do a lot of work
to help the poor people of the world.
Two other famous Irish pop groups are the
boy bands Boyzone and Westlife.
There are famous women singers too, like Sinead
O'Connor, Enya, and Aoife Ni Fhearraigh.
There are many famous singers and writers
from Northern Ireland too.
Seamus Heaney was born in 1939 on a farm near
Derry.
In 1995 he won the Nobel Prize for his poems,
and people read them all over the world.
The famous singer Van Morrison grew up in
Belfast in the 1950s.
Most people in Ireland love music.
People sing in pubs in every Irish town, and
Irish songs are very popular on television
in other countries.
Ireland has won the Eurovision Song Contest
for the best pop song in Europe seven times;
this is more than any other country.
The Irish word for party is ceili - a time
for people to play music, tell stories, and
dance.
For hundreds of years, the Irish people have
loved dancing at ceilis.
In the 1700s, dancing teachers went from town
to town.
People lived in small houses, so they often
danced on the country roads.
They wore their best clothes to dance, and
played music all day and all night.
In many Irish dances, the dancers keep their
hands still by their sides, and move their
feet and legs very quickly.
Today thousands of Irish children learn Irish
dancing, and the best dancers from all over
the world come to dance in Ireland too.
The Irish dancers Michael Flatley and Jean
Butler are famous in many countries - thousands
of people have seen them in Riverdance and
Lord of the Dance.
CHAPTER TWELVE
A country for young people
Today, many things are changing in Ireland.
It is a country of young people: nearly 50
percent of its people are under twenty-five.
Fifty years ago, the Catholic church was full
of old men, and they decided what people could
do.
Life was difficult for women and young people.
Today, the church is important, but the ideas
of women and young people are important too.
Two of Ireland's presidents were women - Mary
Robinson and Mary McAleese.
For Ireland's young people the future is about
pop music and computers as well as farming
and horses.
Ireland is a part of the European Union, and
most Irish people are very happy about this.
Ireland is not a poor country anymore; a lot
of business people come to Ireland and build
factories.
Now, perhaps 10 percent of Ireland's population
are people who have come from other countries
to find work there.
Many come from Poland and other countries
in Eastern Europe, and others come from China
and countries in Africa.
Today, young Irish people do not have to leave
their country to find work; they can find
work at home.
Ireland is an interesting, exciting place
for young people.
But of course, there are always problems.
There is more crime in Ireland than before.
And in Northern Ireland, the problems are
not over.
Every year the Protestant Unionists march
through the streets with their music.
We will always be British,' they say, and
they sing about William of Orange.
'The British must leave Ireland,' say the
Catholic Nationalists in Sinn Fein.
The Unionists and the Nationalists cannot
both have what they want.
Here, history helps no one.
But most Irish people, in the north and south
of Ireland, do not want bombs, guns, and fighting.
They want to enjoy life.
They want people to visit their island, to
walk in their beautiful mountains, fish in
their quiet rivers, drink and sing and laugh
in their pubs, dance at their ceilis, and
most important of all, to talk.
Most of the time, the Irish are the friendliest
people in Europe.
And the three most important words in the
Irish language are:
Cead mile failte
'A hundred thousand welcomes'
- THE END -