CHAPTER ONE
Creativity
On a cool fall evening in 2008, four students
decided to change an industry. They were all
deep in debt, and they had all lost or broken
their glasses. They were shocked at how much
it would cost to replace them. One of them
had been wearing the same pair of broken,
and repaired, glasses for five years. He refused
to pay for an expensive new pair.
Luxottica, the biggest company in the glasses
industry, controlled more than 80 percent
of the market. To make glasses cheaper, the
four students would need to fight a giant.
The four had watched Zappos change the shoe
market by selling shoes online, and they wondered
if they could do the same with glasses.
They discussed the idea with friends, most
of whom were very negative. Nobody would buy
glasses over the internet, they said. People
needed to try them first. OK, Zappos had done
it with shoes, but there were reasons why
it wouldn't work with glasses. "If this were
a good idea," people said, "someone would
have done it already."
None of the students had worked in internet
sales or technology, and they knew nothing
about glasses or fashion. But they agreed
to start a company. They decided to sell glasses
that would cost 500 dollars in stores for
95 dollars online, and they would also give
another pair of glasses to someone in the
poorer countries in the developing world for
each pair that they sold. They called their
company Warby Parker.
The most important part of the business would
be its website, and their Warby Parker website
was ready in February 2010. They expected
to sell one or two pairs of glasses a day,
but in less than one month, they had 20,000
customers on a waiting list.
In 2015, the magazine Fast Company published
its yearly list of the world's most innovative
companies. Warby Parker was the first company
on that list. In the three previous years,
the winners had been Google, Nike, and Apple
- companies with over 50,000 employees. Warby
Parker had just 500 employees, but in five
years, the company had given more than 1 million
free pairs of glasses to the developing world.
The company was making 100 dollars million
a year and was worth more than 1 billion dollars.
Back in 2009, one of those four students asked
me to invest in Warby Parker. I refused. It
was the worst financial decision I have ever
made. I needed to understand where I went
wrong.
Conformity and originality
Years ago, psychologists discovered that there
are two roads to success: conformity and originality.
Conformity means following the crowds down
the usual paths. Originality means taking
unusual roads and developing new ideas that
are accepted only by a few people, but that
succeed in the end.
Of course, nothing is completely original:
our ideas are affected by the world around
us. We all borrow thoughts, sometimes by accident,
sometimes not. What I mean here by "originality"
is introducing and advancing an idea that
is quite unusual in a particular area, and
may improve that area.
Originality begins with creativity: having
an idea that is both new and useful. But it
doesn't stop there. Originals are people who
can make their new idea really work. The Warby
Parker people had the originality to think
of selling glasses online, but they became
originals by taking action to make those glasses
cheap and easy to buy.
This book is about how we can all become more
original. There's a surprising clue in the
web browser that you use to search the internet.
The problem with defaults
In a recent research project, Michael Housman
was investigating why some people who worked
in customer call centers for big companies
stayed in their jobs longer than others. He
collected information on 30,000 employees
who answered phones for banks, airlines, and
cell phone companies. He expected to find
that their employment histories would give
him an answer. He thought people who had changed
jobs often in the past would leave their present
jobs more quickly. But that wasn't true.
Looking at his research, Housman noticed that
his team had collected information about the
internet browser that the employees had used
when they applied for their job. He didn't
think he would find anything interesting there,
but the results were amazing. Employees who
used Firefox or Chrome stayed in their jobs
15 percent longer than those who used Internet
Explorer or Safari.
Housman thought this was strange, so then
he looked at absences from work. Again, Firefox
and Chrome users were 19 percent less likely
to miss work than Internet Explorer and Safari
users.
Then Housman looked at how employees performed
in their jobs. The Firefox and Chrome users
had higher sales, and their call times were
shorter. Their customers were happier, too.
Housman knew it wasn't the web browser that
made these people good employees. What made
the difference was how they had gotten their
browsers. If you buy a PC, Internet Explorer
is built into Windows. If you buy a Mac, it
comes with Safari. But if you choose to use
Firefox or Chrome, you are not accepting the
default.
It's the same at work. The people who didn't
accept the default for their browser did their
jobs differently. They didn't always accept
the usual answers, and they helped their customers
with new ideas.
Accepting the default is easy, but it doesn't
ask us to look at new ways of doing things.
Before the four people behind Warby Parker
started to think about their company, they
knew glasses were expensive, but that had
always been true. That was the default; everybody
thought there was a good reason why glasses
were expensive. After all, these are health
products: a doctor is selling them.
Then, Dave Gilboa, one of the four, was buying
an Apple iPhone. Why was this phone, a piece
of modern technology, cheaper than a simple
pair of glasses? Warby Parker decided to look
at the glasses industry more closely. One
company, Luxottica, was the biggest in the
market. Simply, Luxottica could charge what
it wanted: twenty times the cost of the glasses.
And this meant that a different company could
do things very differently.
Accepting defaults
We begin to accept defaults when we are very
young. When researchers interviewed schoolteachers,
they asked them to list their favorite and
least favorite students. They then asked the
teachers which students had the most creativity,
and these were often the least favorite students.
Teachers found that the creative students
often made trouble, while most children learned
to do what the teacher wanted.
You might think it is the most intelligent
children who change the world when they become
adults. But that doesn't often happen. They
may become excellent doctors, but they don't
ask why some people cannot afford healthcare.
They may become lawyers who defend people
against unfair laws, but they don't question
the laws themselves. They may become teachers
who teach exciting lessons but without asking,
what their students really need to learn.
The problem for many intelligent children
is that we expect them to achieve. It becomes
so important for them to achieve that they
start to fear failure, which can hold back
creativity.
Fear of failure held back some of the most
original people in history, people who, instead
of pushing ahead with confidence, held themselves
back through fear of failure. They only took
action because other people persuaded them
to do so.
The men who signed the American Declaration
of Independence were not natural revolutionaries.
George Washington just wanted to go back to
his farm and only became involved because
John Adams asked him to command the army.
"I have used everything in my power to avoid
it," Washington wrote in a letter to his wife,
Martha, in 1766.
Two hundred years later, Martin Luther King,
Jr. wanted to work in the church and as a
teacher. But, when Rosa Parks refused to give
up her seat on a bus to a white man, some
people in Montgomery, Alabama, decided to
organize a group to support her. At a meeting,
someone suggested King as president of the
group. King didn't have time to think, and
he accepted. He said afterward that, if he
had had time to think, he would probably have
refused.
When the Church asked Michelangelo to paint
the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel in Rome,
he wasn't interested. He didn't want to take
on such a huge job and ran away to Florence.
But he was asked again and again, and after
two years he agreed to start work.
Nearly 500 years later, in 1977, an investor
offered Steve Jobs and Steve Wozniak 250,000
dollars to help them start Apple. But the
investor demanded that Wozniak leave his job
at Hewlett- Packard. Wozniak was afraid to
leave his job, and he only agreed when he
was encouraged by Steve Jobs, other friends,
and his parents.
We can only wonder how many Kings, Michelangelos,
and Wozniaks had original ideas but were never
pushed to develop them. Many of us have ideas
to improve our workplaces or schools, but
we don't give voice to them. Originality can
get you into trouble, and most of us prefer
to conform.
What are the habits of people who are original,
and who take action to develop their original
ideas?
How to be an entrepreneur
To be an original you need to take big risks.
That's what most people think. We admire astronauts
like Neil Armstrong and Sally Ride, who left
the only planet we know and went bravely into
space. We admire leaders like Mahatma Gandhi
and Martin Luther King, Jr., who risked their
lives for the things they believed in. And
we admire entrepreneurs like Steve Jobs and
Bill Gates, who dropped out of school and
worked in dark garages to develop the products
of the future.
The word "entrepreneur" was created by Richard
Cantillon, and it means someone who takes
risks. When we read about the rise of Warby
Parker, we see the four friends who started
the company as great risk-takers. But is it
true?
Six months before Warby Parker started business,
Neil Blumenthal, one of the four friends,
was one of my students. He came to see me
because he wanted me to invest in their company.
I told him that it was an interesting idea,
but I wasn't sure that people would buy glasses
online. As it would be difficult to persuade
people to buy online, I felt it would need
an enormous amount of work to get the company
going. And, when I discovered what Neil and
his friends were planning to do with their
own lives, I was even less sure.
The first problem was that Neil and his friends
were still in school. If they believed in
Warby Parker, they should all drop out and
work full time on Warby Parker.
"No," said Neil. "We're not sure it's a good
idea, and we don't know if we will succeed.
We're working on it in our spare time."
However, they were all finishing school at
the end of the year. So after that they could
work full time on the project.
"No," said Neil. "If things don't work out,
I'm taking a full-time job after I finish
school. And so are the others."
That was enough for me. I decided not to invest.
The Warby Parker friends did not fit my picture
of successful entrepreneurs. They weren't
prepared to risk everything on one idea. I
thought they were going to fail because they
didn't want any risk. But, in fact, that is
why they succeeded.
In an interesting piece of research, Joseph
Raffiee and Jie Feng studied 5,000 entrepreneurs
over fourteen years. They wanted the answer
to one simple question. When people start
a business, is it better for them to leave
their present job, or to stay employed?
If you think like most people, you would expect
the risk-takers who leave their jobs to be
more successful. But the opposite happens.
Entrepreneurs who keep their original jobs
are 33 percent less likely to fail than the
risk-takers who leave their jobs.
If you don't like to take risks, and have
some doubts about your business, you will
build your business more carefully. If you
take risks in your life, then you may take
risks with your business, too.
Like Warby Parker, many successful businesses
were started by people who did not give up
their jobs - at least at the beginning. After
inventing the first Apple I computer, Steve
Wozniak started Apple with Steve Jobs in 1976
but continued to work for Hewlett- Packard
until 1977. Larry Page and Sergey Brin developed
a better way to search the internet in 1996
but didn't stop work on their higher degrees
at Stanford University until 1998. They tried
to sell Google for less than 2 million dollar
in 1997 because their new company was making
it difficult to study -luckily, nobody made
an offer.
Brian May was doing a higher degree in physics
when he started to play guitar in a new band.
He continued to study for several years before
he started to play full time for Queen. Stephen
King worked in a gas station and as a teacher
for seven years after writing his first story.
He finally gave up work a year after his first
novel, Carrie, was published.
These people were all balancing their risk:
taking a big risk in one part of their lives
but playing safe with another. Keeping things
safe meant that there was space to be original.
And because the entrepreneurs were not taking
such a big financial risk there was more time
available: there was less danger of starting
the business with a poor-quality product in
an effort to get the money back quickly. As
Malcolm Gladwell wrote in the New Yorker,
"Many entrepreneurs take plenty of risks - but
those are generally the failed entrepreneurs,
not the success stories."
From idea to action
Having revealed that successful originals
often begin by questioning defaults and balancing
risk, the rest of this book is about moving
from original ideas to action. I have spent
more than ten years researching originality
and studying some of the most successful originals
of our time. I want to share with you how
we can all be more original, without taking
too many risks with our personal, financial,
and professional lives. I hope that what I
have discovered will help people develop their
originality and will help leaders develop
originality in their organizations.
The first part of this book looks at how to
manage the risks in developing, recognizing,
and pushing forward original ideas. New ideas
are risky, and we need to learn how to recognize
good ideas and avoid the bad ones. Once you
are sure that you have a good idea, the next
step is to get other people to understand
it. You'll discover how the most popular television
show ever nearly didn't get made, and why
an entrepreneur told investors the reasons
why they shouldn't invest in his company.
The second part of this book looks at the
choices we need to make when developing original
ideas. There are the risks of being first
to the market: it's sometimes riskier to move
early than it is to be late. Delaying can
help entrepreneurs build businesses that are
stronger over time, and it can help originals
remain creative. I will also look at building
coalitions of people to work together, and
how sometimes it can be useful to work with
your enemies.
The third part of this book looks at how to
develop originality in children and explains
how our family, and others, make us more or
less likely to question defaults. You'll see
how whether or not baseball players are the
first child in a family affects the risks
that they take. I'll also look at how leaders
can encourage the development of creative
ideas in their companies.
To finish, I'll look at what stops us from
developing our originality. The originals
are the people who push us all forward. On
the inside, they are not that different from
the rest of us. They have the same fears and
doubts. What makes them different is that
they try, even though they have fears and
doubts. They know failure is a smaller disappointment
than failing to try.
CHAPTER TWO
Ideas and inventors
Around the year 2000, a lot of people in Silicon
Valley were very interested in a new invention.
Steve Jobs said it was the most exciting technology
since the computer. He offered the inventor
63 million dollars to buy 10 percent of the
company, but the inventor wasn't interested.
The man behind Amazon, Jeff Bezos, told the
inventor, "You have a product so revolutionary,
you'll have no problem selling it."
The inventor was described as a modern Thomas
Edison, and he was behind a number of exciting
medical inventions. He thought his new invention
would have sales of 10,000 a week in its first
year. But, after six years, he had only sold
30,000, and the company still wasn't making
money. The invention was expected to change
lives and cities around the world, but today
it is only used in a few special markets.
The revolutionary product was the Segway - a
machine with two wheels that carries you around.
Why did so many people think it was going
to be a success? Why did they get it wrong?
A few years earlier, two writers wrote a 90-minute
television program. They had never written
for television before, and they soon found
they didn't have enough material for 90 minutes,
so they decided to write a weekly half-hour
show. But when they sent their work to a television
company the people there either didn't like
it, or didn't understand it.
One program was made and shown to a test audience
of 100 people. The viewers didn't like it.
600 more people in four different cities watched
it. The report on those test audiences said:
"Nobody in the audience wanted to watch the
show again."
Surprisingly, the program did make it to television,
and, as expected, it wasn't successful. But
one person at the television company believed
in it and argued that they should try making
some more shows. These were made, and shown
a year later, and, again, they weren't popular.
The television company were going to cancel
the program but agreed to do a few more shows
when another program was canceled. One of
the writers almost left the show - he had
no more ideas.
It's a good thing he changed his mind. For
the next ten years, the program was one of
the most popular on television, and it made
more than 1 billion dollars. TV Guide named
it the greatest television program of all
time. Why did the television companies not
believe in Seinfeld?
When we say there is not enough originality
in the world we think it is because there
is not enough creativity. We think that if
only people had more new ideas we would be
better off. But the real problem is not new
ideas - it's selecting the right ideas. Our
companies and countries have many people with
new ideas. What they don't have are people
who can choose the right new ideas. Segway
was a false positive: people thought it would
be a success, but it wasn't. Seinfeld was
a false negative: people expected it to fail,
but it succeeded.
This chapter is about selecting the right
ideas. We'll look at two people who did expect
the Segway to fail, and at the one person
in the television company who believed in
Seinfeld. We'll see how these people made
the right decisions, and how we can become
better at choosing the right ideas.
Judging creativity
The inventor of the Segway was a brilliant
man called Dean Kamen. He had started inventing
when he was sixteen, and some of his inventions
were very successful. In the 1990s, he designed
the iBOT, a wheelchair that could climb stairs.
He realized that the technology of the iBOT
could be used more widely, and he put together
a team to design the Segway. He wanted something
that would be safe, friendly for the environment,
and would help people to move around busy
cities. Because it was small, light, and easy
to ride, it would be great for mail carriers,
police officers, and golfers, but it could
also change the way everybody traveled. The
Segway was the most amazing technology he
had ever created. Kamen thought it would,
replace the car, in the same way that the
car had replaced the horse.
But inventors are not the best people to judge
their own inventions. Studies show that most
of us are bad at judging ourselves. For example:
: 70 percent of high school seniors think
they are "above average" leaders; 2 percent
think they are below average
: 94 percent of college professors think their
work is above average
: in two different companies, 32 percent and
42 percent of engineers estimated they were
in the top 5 percent in their work.
When we have developed an idea, we are usually
too close to it to judge it accurately. In
music, many experts think Beethoven was a
good critic of his own music. But Beethoven's
own favorite pieces have not been the ones
played most. Aaron Kozbelt looked at letters
where Beethoven judged seventy of his works
and compared Beethoven's estimates with those
of other experts. Of those seventy works,
Beethoven estimated fifteen false positives
- works that he thought were important, but
that are not - and eight false negatives - works
that he thought unsuccessful, but that are
now judged very highly. That's 33 percent
wrong, even though Beethoven was judging his
work after audiences had heard and judged
it.
Kissing frogs
If originals are not good at judging their
own work, how do they create great products?
They have a lot of ideas. Dean Simonton has
looked at many really successful creators
and discovered that they didn't have better
ideas than others; they had more. By producing
more ideas, they had a better chance of originality.
Think about William Shakespeare. In twenty
years, he wrote thirty-seven plays and 154
poems. In order to judge how popular they
were, Simonton looked at how often the plays
were performed. Three of Shakespeare's five
most popular plays, Macbeth, King Lear, and
Othello, were written in the same five years
that he wrote Timon of Athens and All's Well
That Ends Well, which many people feel are
among the worst of his plays.
Pablo Picasso produced more than 1,800 paintings,
12,000 drawings, and thousands of other works,
but only a small number of these are widely
admired. Albert Einstein published 248 papers
over his life, but most of them are not considered
important. We know Maya Angelou's poem "Still
I Rise" and her book I Know Why the Caged
Bird Sings, but we forget about her other
165 poems and six books. If you want to be
original, "the most important possible thing
you could do," says Ira Glass, "is do a lot
of work."
Many people think that if you want to do better
work you should do less and spend time on
delivering high-quality work. But having a
lot of ideas is the best way to get to quality.
Original thinkers will have many ideas that
are of no use, but, because they develop so
many ideas, it is more likely some of them
will be successful.
When he was developing the Segway, Dean Kamen
knew it was important to explore as many ideas
as possible. "You've got to kiss a lot of
frogs," he would say to his team, "before
you find a prince." He encouraged them to
look at hundreds of different ways of solving
the problems they met. The problem was that
he decided to develop the Segway without knowing
whether, in the end, it would be a frog or
a prince.
One of the best ways of judging our ideas
is to get feedback. One of the writers of
The Daily Show, Lizz Winstead, still doesn't
know, after years of working on the comedy
program, what will make people laugh. In the
past, she would try jokes out on stage, to
an audience. Some jokes made people laugh,
some didn't. Now, with social media she can
get feedback more quickly. When she thinks
of a joke, she shares it on Twitter. When
she has something longer to share, she uses
Facebook. At the end of the day, the feedback
tells her whether an idea is worth developing
or not.
When developing the Segway, Dean Kamen didn't
look for feedback. He was afraid that somebody
would steal his idea, so he kept the program
secret. Many of his own employees weren't
allowed to see the Segway while it was being
developed. So the team working on the Segway
developed a huge number of ideas, but they
didn't get any feedback from customers. No
customers saw it when it was being developed.
But Kamen and his team weren't the only people
who were enthusiastic about the Segway. Why
did Steve Jobs and Jeff Bezos make the same
mistake? To find the answer to that question,
let's first look at why so many people were
wrong about Seinfeld.
The danger of false negatives
When the television company first looked at
Seinfeld, they didn't know what to do with
it. It wasn't like other television programs.
They didn't want to take a risk on something
new like this. It would be better to develop
a safe idea than take a risk on this new one.
This way of thinking produces false negatives.
The false negative is something that happens
often in the media. Film companies rejected
movies like Star Wars, E. T, and Pulp Fiction.
Publishers refused books like The Diary of
Anne Frank, Gone with the Wind, and Harry
Potter - by 2015, J. K. Rowling's Harry Potter
books had brought in over 25 billion dollars
and sold more copies than any book series
ever. And in business there are hundreds of
examples where employees were ordered to stop
work on projects that were later successful.
The Xbox was almost stopped by Microsoft,
and the laser printer was nearly canceled
by Xerox because it was too expensive.
When we see something unusual, we often refuse
it and look for reasons why it may fail. When
managers see something new, they compare it
to things that were successful in the past.
So some publishers thought Harry Potter was
too long for a children's book. And television
company managers thought Seinfeld was too
much about New York to be of interest to the
rest of the country.
Test audiences are no better than managers
at judging new television shows. They make
the same mistakes. When you watch a show at
home, in your living room, you get interested
in the story. If you laugh a lot, at the end
you will think it was funny. But in a test
audience you don't watch in the same way.
You know you are there to judge it, and so
you compare it with shows you know are funny.
Neither test audiences nor managers are a
good way of deciding whether a show is funny
or not.
Wide experience and deep experience
When the test audiences were negative about
Seinfeld, the project nearly stopped. But
one man, Rick Ludwin, believed in it. Rick
Ludwin worked on special programs, not comedy,
so Seinfeld wasn't his department. But, because
his experience was in a different type of
television, he felt differently about the
project. Most comedy programs before Seinfeld
had a few complete stories, with endings,
inside 22 minutes of television. Seinfeld
started a lot more stories but sometimes didn't
finish them. That worried most television
managers, but Ludwin worked on specials, where
each program is organized in its own way.
Ludwin had written jokes for Bob Hope in the
1970s and had worked on comedies in the past.
Because Ludwin had some experience of comedy,
he understood how it worked. And, although
he hadn't worked in comedy for many years,
he had a wide experience of television, and
he was happy to explore new ways of making
people laugh. He combined a wide experience
of television outside of comedy with a deep
experience of comedy from his days writing
jokes. And combining wide and deep experience
is very important for creativity.
A recent study looked at every Nobel Prize-winning
scientist from 1901 to 2005 and compared them
with other scientists who had not won Nobel
Prizes. Both groups knew their science well
- they had deep experience. But the Nobel
Prize winners were more likely to be doing
other, artistic, things as well. Here's what
the fifteen researchers at Michigan State
University found when they compared the Nobel
Prize winners with the
other scientists.
A study of thousands of Americans showed similar
results for entrepreneurs and inventors. These
people were more likely than others to take
part in activities like drawing, painting,
or writing.
In a study of the fashion industry, a team
of researchers led by Frederic Godart looked
at the cultural experience of fashion designers.
The most creative work came from designers
who had worked in foreign countries, but Godart
found three especially interesting things
about this experience.
Firstly, living in a foreign country didn't
help creativity. It was working there that
was important. The most original work came
from designers who had worked in two or three
different countries. Secondly, the more foreign
the country the better. For an American, working
in Canada didn't help a lot. Working in Korea
or Japan helped more with originality. Thirdly,
the experience was better if it was deep.
A few weeks wasn't useful; the most creative
designers had spent thirty-five years working
in other countries.
Where Steve Jobs went wrong
When Steve Jobs first got on a Segway, he
refused to climb off. When Dean Kamen wanted
other investors to try it, Jobs let them,
but soon got back on again. He invited Kamen
to dinner and told him his Segway was as original
as the computer, and he wanted to be involved.
Steve Jobs was famous for making decisions
through intuition, rather than investigating
carefully. Why did he get it wrong this time?
There were three main reasons: he didn't have
experience of this area of business; he felt
too confident because of his success in other
areas of business; and he was very enthusiastic.
Let's start with experience. Jobs and the
other early investors in Segway, like Jeff
Bezos, knew nothing about transportation.
They were originals in their area, but that
did not make them good in other areas. Intuition
can be helpful, but it works best when we
have experience of what we are looking at.
The Segway was a brilliant machine, and it
was huge fun to ride it. But it was difficult
for people with no transportation experience
to judge it.
One man who did understand the problems with
Segway was Randy Komisar. He looked at the
transportation market and realized that the
Segway wasn't going to replace the car: it
would replace walking or cycling. But he didn't
think it was a product many people would want.
It was exciting to ride, but it was a lot
of money to pay for something that replaced
walking. And, at that time, nobody knew whether
governments would allow it on sidewalks. Komisar
thought there would be a market in mail or
police services, or for golfers. But Jobs
still thought that Segway was too exciting
to fail.
Jobs' next problem was that he had been very
successful in one area of business, so he
thought he understood all areas of business.
The more successful people are in the past,
the worse they perform when they work in a
new area. He was so sure his intuition was
right that he didn't check his intuition with
people who understood transportation.
When Kamen talked with investors like Jobs
about Segway, he spoke about countries like
China and India, which were building cities
the size of New York every year. These cities
would be full of cars, and that would be really
bad for the environment. He was enthusiastic,
and the investors liked that enthusiasm. When
we look at a new idea, the enthusiasm of the
inventor can make a big difference. Enthusiasm
is important for inventors, but entrepreneurs
need to be more careful.
Thoughts on selecting ideas
My failure to invest in Warby Parker was a
big false negative. I had never owned glasses,
so it was hard for me to think about people
who did. I had deep experience of glasses:
I had spent two years doing research in a
company that made and sold glasses through
stores. But I didn't have wide experience.
Three of the four men behind Warby Parker
wore glasses, and the fourth, Neil Blumenthal,
had worked for five years in Asia, Africa,
and Latin America, helping women to start
businesses. One of the businesses he helped
with was selling glasses, so he knew that
glasses could be made much more cheaply than
people think.
The Warby Parker entrepreneurs were also careful
to get everybody in the company involved in
development. Nothing was secret, and ideas
were shared on a Google document, where everybody
in the company could read them. And people
could give feedback on new ideas as they appeared.
If Segway had done the same as Warby Parker,
they may have avoided some of their problems.
But Kamen is still a great inventor, especially
in the area of healthcare. As an inventor,
he should be having the great ideas but then
sharing them with others and getting feedback
on which inventions are the most useful.
In 2013, 300,000 patents were taken out in
the United States. The chances that any of
these inventions will change the world are
tiny. One creative inventor, with lots of
inventions, has a better chance that one invention
over his or her whole life will make a difference.
And when we judge these inventors, we don't
look at their least successful ones: we look
at the best.
CHAPTER THREE
Speaking the truth
In the early 1990s, a CIA (Central Intelligence
Agency) employee called Carmen Medina worked
in Europe for three years. When she returned
to the United States, she found that leaving
the United States had made it difficult to
get an interesting job in the CIA, and she
began to look for other ways to help the organization.
During the time she worked for the CIA in
Europe, she had noticed that there was a big
problem with information sharing in the organization.
Information was shared by "finished intelligence
reports," which were sent out once a day.
The experts who wrote them had no way of sharing
ideas before the reports went out. Things
change very quickly in intelligence, and it
was taking too long for the right information
to reach the right people. Carmen Medina suggested
that, instead of using printed-paper documents,
departments could put their ideas immediately
on to Intelink, a secret internet used by
the CIA.
Her managers weren't interested. The internet
was dangerous, and intelligence had to be
secret. With printed documents, you could
be sure the right people had the right information.
It would be very dangerous if the wrong people
got secret information.
Medina kept talking about her idea, but everybody
told her to be quiet. Finally, she decided
to leave the CIA, but she couldn't find another
job. She ended up working in a boring CIA
desk job, and she kept quiet about her idea
for a while. Three years later, she decided
to argue again for online information sharing.
Less than ten years later, Carmen Medina was
involved in creating Intellipedia, a Wikipedia
for intelligence organizations. It allowed
departments to read reports from other organizations.
It was a big change to the secret culture
of the CIA, and it helped with intelligence
for the Beijing Olympics and after the Mumbai
attacks in 2008. In a few years, Intellipedia
had half a million users and over 1 million
pages. It achieved this very quickly and very
cheaply, too.
Why did Medina fail the first time she talked
about information sharing, and why was she
heard the second time? In between, the world
had changed. The internet was much more widely
used, and the attacks of September 11, 2001
made it clear that intelligence organizations
needed to be better at sharing information.
Medina had also become deputy director of
intelligence at the CIA, which gave her the
power to follow her idea. She got that position
by learning to speak in ways that made people
listen to her and believe her.
We have all sometimes wanted to speak about
something that seems wrong either inside or
outside of an organization. This chapter is
about how to do this well, and without risks.
What are the right times to speak, and how
can we make sure people hear us? As well as
Carmen Medina, we'll hear about an entrepreneur
who tells investors why they shouldn't invest
in his companies; a manager who argued with
Steve Jobs; and why managers who appear to
support you sometimes provide the least support.
We'll also see how gender and race affect
our ability to be heard, and why the photos
we like of ourselves are the opposite of the
ones we like of our friends.
Power without status
Leaders and managers like it when employees
offer help, do research, or ask for feedback.
But there's one thing that is not so popular:
making suggestions. In one piece of research
in an industry, it was found that the more
employees made suggestions to their managers
the less likely they were to get promoted.
To understand what happens in organizations
when people like Carmen Medina object to something,
we need to think about power and status. Power
is being able to control what other people
do; status is being admired by other people.
When people without status make suggestions,
we don't think they should tell us what to
do, and we refuse. That is what happened to
Carmen Medina; her years working outside of
the United States meant she had low status.
She hadn't been able to show people what she
could really do, so people didn't value her
ideas.
Years later, she had earned status because
she had slowly gotten jobs with more responsibility
in the organization. Then she got a job where
she had to protect sensitive information.
Now, when she talked about sharing information,
it was part of her job. People saw that she
stood for something and not against it. They
started to admire her work, and this made
it possible for her ideas to be seen as original.
We don't like originality in low-status people,
but we admire it when their status is high.
The Sarick Effect
After having their first child, Rufus Griscom
and Alisa Volkman were shocked by the false
advertising and bad advice being offered to
parents. They started an online magazine called
Babble that aimed to tell the truth about
being a parent. In 2009, when Griscom tried
to get investors for the project, he did the
opposite to what every entrepreneur is taught
to do. He told the investors the top five
reasons for not investing in his business.
That should have killed the idea. Investors
are looking for reasons to say yes, and he
was giving them reasons to say no. Entrepreneurs
are supposed to talk about the great things
in the company, and he was doing the opposite.
But it worked. That year, Babble got 3.3 million
dollars from investors.
Two years later, Griscom went to see Disney
to see if they were interested in buying Babble.
He did the same thing again and told them:
"Here's why you should not buy Babble.'' Then
he explained that people who looked at the
Babble website didn't stay very long. And
Babble was supposed to be for parents, but
40 percent of the messages people wrote on
it weren't about parents at all. What's more,
the technology behind the website needed some
serious work. Disney bought the company, for
40 million dollars.
This is called the Sarick Effect, after Leslie
Sarick. Griscom was talking to people who
had more power than him. He was asking them
to give him money. Usually you would tell
people what was good about your project, but
that only works when people are already on
your side. When you're talking to investors,
they are looking for reasons why your idea
won't work. In that situation, it may be better
to talk about what is wrong with your idea.
Here are four reasons why the Sarick Effect
can work.
First, beginning with what is weak about a
business helps to put the audience on your
side. When we know somebody is trying to push
us into buying something we usually refuse.
But when Griscom said the words "Here's why
you shouldn't buy this company," they laughed
and then relaxed. He had given them a problem
to solve.
Second, talking about what is wrong with an
idea makes you look intelligent. People who
say and write negative things are usually
seen to be more intelligent than people who
say and write positive things. When you say
something negative about an idea, it shows
you have thought about it. In Griscom's case,
it showed he knew there were problems, and
he wasn't trying to hide them.
Third, talking about the problems with your
business means that investors will trust you
more. When Griscom talked about his problems,
it made him look honest. Of course, talking
about the problems doesn't work if your audience
doesn't know about them, but Griscom's audiences
were going to give him a lot of money. They
were looking at his business very carefully,
so he couldn't hide the problems anyway; they
would find them. Also, investors thought that,
if he was admitting what was wrong with his
business, there was probably a lot that was
right.
Fourth, audiences are more likely to support
an idea when the problems are made clear.
When Griscom told investors about the problems
with the business, it made it difficult for
them to think of other problems with it, and
they began to think that maybe Griscom's problems
weren't too bad.
The unfamiliarity problem
When you have spent weeks, months, or even
years thinking about your idea, you know it
perfectly. It's not possible to imagine what
the idea sounds like to someone who is hearing
it for the first time. So we often present
our ideas to people without enough information.
If we want people to accept our original ideas,
we need to speak about them often, and then
repeat what we said. To illustrate, which
of these two words do you like better?
If you're like most people, you will choose
sarick.
Robert Zajonc has described this. He showed
people nonsense words like iktitaf and sarick
and asked them which they preferred. If they
had never seen either word before, they liked
them equally. But when they had seen one of
the words twice before the test, they preferred
that one. And if they had seen it five, ten,
or twenty-five times, they liked it even more.
I used sarick four times earlier. There is
nothing called the Sarick Effect, and there
is nobody called Leslie Sarick. I invented
them to show how seeing the word already can
affect you. (Rufus Griscom is real, however,
and so is everyone else in this book.)
My favorite test of this is when people looked
at photographs of themselves and their friends.
Some of the photos were inverted - as though
in a mirror - and some were not. People liked
the photos of their friends when they weren't
inverted - because that's how they are used
to seeing them. But they preferred photos
of themselves that were inverted - because
we're used to seeing ourselves in the mirror.
One reason for this is that the idea or picture
we're used to is easier to understand. Something
that we don't know takes more effort, and
that makes us uncomfortable.
Making people uncomfortable
When Carmen Medina made no progress the first
time she talked about information sharing,
she thought about leaving the CIA. She stayed,
but she didn't speak up to her managers again
about her ideas for a long time. When she
did, it was because of her manager, Mike.
I guessed Mike would be a friendly, relaxed
man, but he was the opposite. He was not friendly,
and he got angry quickly. So why was he the
right manager for Medina?
Although he was a difficult man, Mike did
care about the future of the organization.
Friendly people like everyone around them
to be happy, so they are less likely to push
difficult ideas forward. A man like Mike didn't
mind making people uncomfortable, so he was
ready to give Medina time to develop her uncomfortable
ideas.
Another thing that Medina noticed was that
middle managers were the most unhappy with
her ideas. It is often the people in the middle
who don't want to make difficulties. They
have made some progress in the organization
and don't want to go backward.
The difficulties of speaking up
Speaking up to, an audience of middle managers
is always a risk, but it was especially difficult
for Carmen Medina because she was a woman
in an organization where most of the employees
were men. I thought the days when women could
not speak up in work were in the past. But
I soon realized there is still a problem with
gender. In organizations around the world,
people expect men to speak up, and to lead.
But when women speak up they can be seen as
angry.
When I looked at my own research, I was very
disappointed. In an international bank and
a healthcare company, I found that suggesting
good ideas led to promotions for men, but
not for women. Other research shows that male
employees who talk more than others are rewarded
and promoted. But women who talk more are
judged negatively by both men and women. When
women suggest changing something at work to
improve it, their bosses don't trust them
and are not as likely to change anything.
There is no doubt things were difficult for
Medina because she was a woman in an organization
of mostly men. But she was also a Puerto Rican.
Being from two groups like this makes a difference.
Ashleigh Rosette, an African-American researcher,
found that people behaved differently when
she spoke up than when white women and black
men did. When black women leaders failed,
they were judged harder than black men, or
than white men and women.
The road not taken
In 1985, Donna Dubinsky was working as Apple's
distribution and sales manager. It was a busy
job, as sales of Apple computers were increasing
quickly. Then Steve Jobs suggested that Apple
stop using its six distribution centers and
move to "just-in-time" distribution: computers
would be finished in the factory when they
were needed and would be delivered to customers
direct from the factory.
Dubinsky thought this was a big mistake. She
knew that Apple's success depended on successful
distribution. She objected, but nobody listened.
For several months, she worked in a group
that looked at just-in-time distribution.
Everyone seemed happy to go ahead with the
new just-in-time system, except Dubinsky.
She spoke up against the idea and told Apple
they must give her thirty days to create a
different system - and if they didn't give
it to her she would leave.
She was taking a big risk, but she was given
the time. At the end of the thirty days, she
suggested a new distribution system, and it
was accepted. People knew she had done a good
job in the past - she had status. Many people
would think that arguing with Steve Jobs,
known as a difficult man, would not be a good
idea. But Jobs liked people who argued with
him, and he was open to new ways of doing
things. And Dubinsky wasn't doing it for herself,
she was doing it for Apple. Jobs understood
that.
In 1991, Dubinsky left Apple. She met Jeff
Hawkins and joined Palm Computing, which produced
the PalmPilot, one of the first small handheld
computers. But when Palm was bought by 3Com
she was again unhappy with the management.
She and Hawkins left to start a new company,
Handspring, which made handheld computers
and developed a smartphone. A few years later,
Apple developed the iPhone.
Medina had wanted to leave the CIA but couldn't.
That was why she stayed and, in the end, changed
the organization from the inside. Dubinsky
did leave and helped to begin the smartphone
revolution. Although Medina stayed and Dubinsky
left, they both chose to speak up rather than
remain silent.
CHAPTER FOUR
Taking time
Late at night in a hotel room, a young man
stared at an empty piece of paper on the desk.
Nervously, he called a friend in a room several
floors down to talk through some ideas. The
friend ran up the stairs to discuss a speech
that would change history. At 3 a.m. the young
man was still working. It was August 1963,
and, although he expected to speak to 100,000
people in Washington the next day, Martin
Luther King, Jr. still hadn't finished his
speech.
"He worked on it all night, not sleeping,"
King's wife, Coretta, remembered. "He was
to be the final speaker, and his words would
be carried on television and radio to millions
of people in America and across the world."
The speech had been announced two months earlier,
and King knew how important it would be. It
would only be five minutes long, so he had
to be very careful in choosing his words.
You might think he would begin writing the
speech immediately, as soon as he knew about
it. But he didn't begin writing until 10 p.m.
the night before.
Parents and teachers usually ask children
to begin work on their homework early, instead
of waiting until the last minute. But maybe
it was because King procrastinated that he
gave the best speech of his life. I've studied
originals for a long time, and I've learned
that arriving early is not always a good thing.
It's sometimes better to arrive at the last
minute.
This chapter looks at the question of when
to take original action. I'll discuss how
delaying can be useful, and why procrastinating
can be a good thing. I'll look at how entrepreneurs
who are first to market with a product can
have difficulties; why older innovators are
sometimes better than younger ones; and how
leaders who want to change things wait patiently
for the right time. You don't have to be first
to be an original; you don't even have to
arrive on time. Originals are often late to
the party.
Great procrastinators
Recently, a student of mine, Jihae Shin, came
to me with an interesting idea: procrastinating
might be good for originality. When you procrastinate
you may be thinking about the thing you have
to do, but you delay doing it. Shin wondered
whether the delay meant that you had time
to think about a number of different possibilities,
rather than just one idea. As a result, you
may have more original ideas. I asked her
to test her theory.
There was an empty building at college, where
there had been a small food store. Shin asked
students to write ideas for using the empty
space. When the students started work immediately,
most of their ideas weren't very original
- they suggested things like another food
store. But Shin asked some students to procrastinate
by giving them computer games to play first.
The business ideas these students produced
were more original. The ideas from the procrastinators
were 28 percent more original.
We were excited by these results but wondered
whether playing the games had helped creativity.
But when people played games before they were
asked for ideas, it didn't help originality.
It also didn't help to start work, then stop
and take a break, and then return to work.
Once the students had started work, they had
made too much progress to stop and start again.
They had to know what was wanted, and to procrastinate,
in order to have the most creative ideas.
Shin then did some more research, looking
at a Korean furniture company. Managers thought
employees who procrastinated a lot were more
original than those who didn't. But procrastinating
wasn't always a good thing: if the employees
weren't really determined to solve a big problem,
delaying just made things late. But, when
they were excited about looking for new ideas,
procrastination helped a lot.
Leonardo da Vinci was a famous procrastinator.
Experts think he took sixteen years to paint
the Mona Lisa, stopping and starting many
times. He also spent fifteen years thinking
about The Last Supper, working on many other
things at the same time.
In American history, there may be only one
speech as famous as King's: Abraham Lincoln's
Gettysburg Address. In just 272 words, Lincoln
made clear that the Civil War was about freedom
and equality. Lincoln was invited to give
the speech two weeks earlier. By the day before,
he had only written about half of the speech.
He didn't write the last paragraph until the
night before, and he didn't finish it until
the morning. He waited because he wanted to
be sure the speech was right.
In the summer before his "I have a dream"
speech, King got advice from three people
about what he should say - and how. He also
discussed the speech for a long time with
Clarence Jones, who had written some of his
other speeches. Jones and another man began
to write some ideas for the speech. King waited
until the last four days before he began to
work on the speech. Then, the night before,
he met with his advisors, and they started
again.
By delaying the work on the speech, King was
giving an example of the Zeigarnik effect.
The Russian psychologist Bluma Zeigarnik showed
that people remember unfinished things better
than finished things. Once something is finished,
we stop thinking about it. But if it's not
finished, it is still there in our minds.
When King finally asked Jones to write the
complete speech, he had a wide range of ideas.
But that wasn't the only good thing about
procrastinating.
"I have a dream"
Fifty years after King's famous speech, we
can all remember four words: "I have a dream."
I was very surprised when I looked at the
speech King had written, and the words were
not there. Jones didn't put them in, and King
did not add them.
While he was speaking, the singer Mahalia
Jackson was behind him. She shouted, "Tell
them about the dream, Martin." He continued
with his speech, but she shouted it again.
In front of a crowd of 250,000, with millions
more watching on television, King pushed his
notes to one side and talked about his dream.
According to Drew Hansen in his book, The
Dream, King was still cutting out lines and
writing new ones just before he started to
speak. He was even making changes as he walked
up to give the speech. And he didn't read
the words exactly, he changed things slightly,
like a jazz musician. It was eleven minutes
into the speech that he started to talk about
his dream, and he added so much to the speech
that he spoke for much longer than expected.
King had procrastinated, but he had given
more than 350 speeches in the year before
the "I have a dream" speech. He had material
in his head that he could use when he needed
it. He put his speeches together from pieces
of all his other speeches.
Pioneers and settlers
After working on starting over one hundred
new companies, Bill Gross did some research
to find out why some companies succeeded and
others failed. The biggest reasons were not
the quality of the ideas, the people in the
team, or the amount of money invested. "The
number one thing was timing," Gross said.
42 percent of the difference between success
and failure was timing.
Most Americans believe it is better to be
the first mover. We want to be leaders, not
followers. If you are the first to market
with a new product, you can learn about the
market more quickly and get the most customers.
By doing that you stop the competition, because
it will be hard to persuade those customers
to change.
In a famous study, researchers Peter Colder
and Gerard Tellis compared the success of
companies that were either pioneers or settlers.
Pioneers were the first movers: the first
company to make or sell a product. The settlers
arrived later; they waited for the pioneers
to create a market first. When Golder and
Tellis looked at hundreds of products in more
than thirty different areas of business they
found a huge difference in failures: 47 percent
for pioneers and just 8 percent for settlers.
And even when the pioneers did survive they
only got around 10 percent of the market compared
with 28 percent for settlers.
Surprisingly, the problems for the first mover
are often huge. Pioneers may sometimes get
a big part of the market, but they usually
have a big risk of not surviving, and they
often don't make much money. If you're thinking
of moving into a new area of business, you
need to stop and think about timing. But researcher
Lisa Bolton found something more frightening.
Even when entrepreneurs know it is risky to
be the first mover, they don't believe it.
We can all think of pioneers who succeeded,
and we've forgotten those who failed. So what
are the reasons that settlers do better than
pioneers?
First, many people think that settlers are
just copying the pioneers, but that isn't
really true. They may be waiting before introducing
something new. They may be working on something
that is better than the products in the market
now. In home video games, the pioneer was
Magnavox Odyssey, which started with simple
sports games in 1972. A settler, Nintendo,
started to manage the distribution for Odyssey
in Japan in 1975 and then, in the 1980s, started
to sell the Nintendo Entertainment System,
with games like Super Mario Bros. Nintendo's
games improved on the older games; it was
easier to play them, and the characters were
interesting. You don't have to be first to
be original. You have to be different and
better.
In the 1990s, a banker, Joseph Park, was at
home in his apartment. He was annoyed because
he wanted to stay home and watch a movie,
but to do that he had to go out to a store
and rent one. Why couldn't he go to a website,
choose a movie, and have it delivered to his
door? As there didn't seem to be a company
that provided this service, Park decided to
create one.
Although Park collected 250 million dollars
from investors, his company, Kozmo, only survived
until 2001. The biggest mistake was that Kozmo
promised to deliver movies in one hour, and
spent a lot of money on distribution to try
and make that possible. If Park had moved
more slowly, he might have realized that delivering
movies in an hour wasn't going to work. A
lot of people wanted online movies, and Netflix
was just beginning. Maybe Kozmo could have
competed with movies by mail, and then it
might have been able to move to delivery online.
Second, it seems that people who choose to
move late may be better suited to succeed.
Risk-takers like to move first, and they may
make their decisions too quickly. Entrepreneurs,
who want to avoid risk, watch the market and
wait for the right time. In research into
software companies, Elizabeth Pontikes and
William Barnett found that when entrepreneurs
waited for the market to cool down, they were
more likely to succeed.
Third, as well as avoiding some risk, settlers
can look at their competitors' products and
make their own products better. When you are
first, you have to make all the mistakes yourself.
Settlers can watch you and learn from your
mistakes.
Fourth, pioneers often stay with the first
products they sell. Settlers can watch how
the market changes and change their products
so they remain right for the changing market.
Settlers can also wait for the market to be
ready for them. When Warby Parker started,
people had been selling products online for
ten years, even though the idea hadn't worked
before for glasses.
The theory of pioneers and settlers is true
outside of the world of business as well.
In the 1840s, the Hungarian doctor Ignaz Semmelweis
discovered that if medical students washed
their hands the number of women patients who
died giving birth was much lower. Other doctors
laughed at him. He became sick and died a
young man. Twenty years later, the research
of Louis Pasteur and Robert Koch showed Semmelweis
to be right.
I don't want to say that it is never good
to be first. If we all wait for someone else
to move first, nothing original will ever
be created. Someone has to be the pioneer,
and sometimes they are successful. This is
often true when there is a patent behind the
product, or when a product becomes more valuable
as more people use it, such as social media.
But in most cases the chances of success are
not higher if you move first. And when the
market is not clear, or unknown, then being
a pioneer is a huge risk. The lesson here
is that, if you have an original idea, it's
a mistake to think you must move first, before
your competitors. Procrastinating can make
it easier to achieve something, and, in the
same way, delaying market entry can give us
the chance to learn more and reduce risk.
But what happens if we take a wider view than
ideas and products? If we look at the whole
life of a person, is there a risk in waiting
too long?
Conceptual and experimental
It is widely believed that originality is
something we find in young people. Vinod Khosla
said at the National Association of Software
and Services Companies Product Conclave in
2011: "People under thirty-five are the people
who make change happen. People over forty-five
die in terms of new ideas." Albert Einstein
also said that a scientist had to make his
discoveries before the age of thirty. And
it is true that people do often lose their
originality over time.
But this doesn't always happen. When companies
have suggestion boxes, it seems that older
employees have more and better ideas than
younger employees, with the highest-value
ideas coming from employees over fifty-five.
And in new technology companies, the average
age of entrepreneurs is thirty-eight.
In art and science, David Galenson shows that
we're quick to remember the exciting young
people, but there are a lot of older people
who succeed much later. In film, for example,
Orson Welles made Citizen Kane when he was
twenty-five; Alfred Hitchcock made his three
greatest films when he was much older, at
ages fifty-nine (Vertigo), sixty (North by
Northwest), and sixty-one (Psycho). Why are
some people creative early, while others start
to be creative later?
The creative age depends on the way we think.
When Galenson studied creativity, he discovered
two very different types of thinking: conceptual
and experimental. Conceptual people think
of a big idea and try to achieve it. Experimental
people work by trying different things, some
of which succeed, while some don't. They are
thinking about a problem, but they don't think
about the answer to the problem when they
start work. They don't plan; they decide things
as they work.
Galenson believes conceptual thinkers move
quickly, while experimental thinkers take
longer. He studied economists who had won
the Nobel Prize and discovered that on average
the conceptual economists had done their best
work at forty-three, while the experimental
economists had done theirs at sixty-one. A
study of physicists who had won the Nobel
Prize discovered that half of those under
thirty were conceptual, while 92 percent of
those over forty-five did experimental work.
Conceptual people can work quickly because
they don't need to do years of careful research.
They are also usually young, because young
people find it easier to approach a problem
in a new way. But as they get older they find
it more difficult, and they become less original.
This was Einstein's problem. His most important
discoveries were made in his head. They were
ideas that explained things that had been
discovered by experimental scientists. As
he got older, he found it more difficult to
work with some of the newer ideas in physics.
Conceptual people have ideas earlier, but
then they risk copying themselves and producing
very similar ideas. Being experimental takes
longer, but it means the scientist or artist
is able to discover new ideas. Mark Twain
published Adventures of Huckleberry Finn when
he was forty-nine, changing the story as he
wrote it. When he started, he didn't know
how it was going to end.
As we get older, it helps to be more experimental.
Leonardo da Vinci was experimental, taking
years to finish his greatest paintings. Martin
Luther King, Jr., too, was experimental, giving
thousands of speeches and changing them as
he did so. Moving quickly is fine for the
young, and creativity can be both conceptual
and experimental. But slow and thoughtful
can often work better for the older person.
CHAPTER FIVE
How to build coalitions
Many people have forgotten her, but no one
did more for women's suffrage in America than
Lucy Stone. She was the first woman in America
to keep her own name after getting married.
She was the first woman in Massachusetts to
earn a college degree. She was the first American
lecturer in women's rights. She was one of
only a very few women who spoke in public
at all. She started the country's leading
women's newspaper, the Woman's Journal, which
was published for fifty years.
In 1851, Stone organized a women's rights
meeting, but she wasn't persuaded to speak
until the last day. In her speech, she suggested
that women should ask the government for the
right to vote and to own houses and land.
Her speech became known for pushing the women's
rights movement forward. Her words were read
by John Stuart Mill and Harriet Taylor Mill
in England, who later published a famous letter
about women's rights.
After the speech, two other great women, Susan
B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton, joined
Stone, and together they worked for women's
suffrage. But a long time before they reached
their goal the three women broke apart. In
1869, Anthony and Stanton left Stone's organization
and started their own. Working separately,
the two organizations had little success,
and the arguments between the three women
made many people think women weren't able
to be leaders. When Stanton and Anthony wrote
a book about the history of the women's rights
movement, Stone's name wasn't mentioned, if
all three leaders wanted the same thing, why
did they fight so bitterly?
This chapter looks at how originals build
coalitions to reach their goals and how to
solve the problems that can lead to coalitions
failing. Coalitions can do a lot, but they
can also break apart easily because they depend
on people's relationships. We will look at
the difficulties of coalitions, at an entrepreneur's
battle to persuade people to try her idea,
at a Disney movie that almost didn't get made,
and at how Occupy Wall Street failed. You
will see how building good coalitions requires
a lot of work.
The important lesson is the "Goldilocks" theory
of coalitions, which looks at the ideas within
groups as too hot, too cold, or just right.
The originals who start a coalition are often
the most enthusiastic people in it, and sometimes
their ideas are too hot for others. It's sometimes
necessary to cool the message to encourage
other groups to join the coalition. The message
needs to be neither too hot, nor too cold.
It needs to be just right.
Groups that break
We would expect that having similar goals
holds groups together, but very often, these
goals drive groups apart. Even though people
share the same goals, some groups push their
ideas further, and these groups are often
very critical of those who are less enthusiastic.
In one study, vegetarians (who don't eat meat)
and vegans (who don't eat meat or any other
animal products like milk or eggs) gave their
opinions about one another. Vegans disliked
vegetarians three times as much as vegetarians
disliked vegans. The vegans with the strongest
opinions thought that vegetarians were weak:
if they really cared about animals, they wouldn't
eat animal products like eggs. The more strongly
you feel about something, the more you want
to show you are different from people who
have some of your goals but who don't push
their ideas as far as you do.
This is why Anthony and Stanton broke away
from Lucy Stone. They wanted to push things
further. Things got really bad when Anthony
and Stanton argued against giving African-American
men the vote. If women couldn't vote, they
said, these men shouldn't be able to vote
either. Stone did not agree; she wanted suffrage
for African Americans. Anthony and Stanton
were very angry; they thought Stone was not
serious about women's suffrage, and they started
their own women's suffrage organization. Stone
tried to calm things down, but for twenty
years their two groups worked separately,
sometimes even against one another.
Now there were two separate groups, they needed
to find new people to help them and form new
coalitions. They all found help from an unexpected
group, the Women's Christian Temperance Union,
a women's group that was trying to stop people
drinking alcohol. Men who drank alcohol were
often violent with their wives, and their
families became poor. But the WCTU members
were very different from the women's suffrage
groups. They were often women from rich, usually
very religious, families who did not support
modern ideas. Yet the groups managed to work
together. Many people across the country disliked
the idea of women's suffrage, and it's a surprise
that the WCTU was happy to work with groups
who were pushing for it. But they did make
progress, and, in several states, women achieved
the right to vote.
The following example of a young, creative
entrepreneur shows how business coalitions
can be built successfully.
Building and breaking coalitions
In 2011, a student called Meredith Perry realized
that there was a big problem with the world
of technology. She didn't need a wire to make
a phone call or connect to the internet. Everything
was wireless. Except for one thing. To use
her phone and her computer she still had to
connect them to the wall to charge them. She
wanted wireless electricity.
She thought about things that can send energy
through the air, like radio waves. But they
wouldn't work well for electricity. What about
ultrasound? You can't see ultrasound, and
it is silent. Could it be used to carry electrical
energy without wires?
Her physics teachers said it was impossible;
so did ultrasound engineers. A lot of important
people told her she was wasting her time.
Then she won an invention competition. But
as an entrepreneur on her own, with no money,
she needed help.
Three years later, I met Meredith Perry. She
had managed to get 750,000 dollars from investors,
and she had the first example of a wireless
charger. It could charge things faster than
a wire, and over longer distances, and it
would be in the stores in two years. By the
end of 2014, her company, uBeam, had eighteen
patents, and investors had given it 10 million
dollars. "Every single person that is now
working for the company didn't think it was
possible," she said.
Perry had had the same difficulty that all
originals have when they want to do something
different. Most people don't want to change
things. She had talked to a lot of experts,
and they all told her about the problems in
her math and her physics. In the end, she
realized there was a problem with her message.
She had been saying: "I'm trying to build
something that can send electricity through
the air." Instead, she said: "I'm looking
for someone to make a part for this new product.
Can you help?"
This worked. By breaking up the project into
parts, she found people who would design those
parts. Soon she had people working on the
project. She stopped talking about the most
exciting part of her idea, the wireless electricity,
because that shocked people. She had moved
her question from why, to how. Instead of
talking about why she wanted something, she
talked about how she needed to get there.
By talking about smaller parts of the project,
she found people who would work with her.
When she couldn't find engineers to make a
big jump, she found engineers who would take
a few small steps.
Although it's usually a good idea for creative
people to explain why they want to do something,
if their idea moves too far from what people
think is possible, it may just frighten them
away.
Coalitions often break up when one group is
more extreme than the other groups. Occupy
Wall Street started in 2011, to argue against
the unequal sharing of money across the United
States by the financial center of Wall Street
in New York. In 2011, most Americans supported
the coalition, but support started to fall
as some groups in the coalition became too
extreme. Srda Popovic has suggested that the
movement's mistake was to use the word "Occupy"
in their name, which was about people camping
in the streets outside of banks and financial
businesses. Although many people approved
of the general goals of the movement, they
didn't like the idea of "occupying" a place,
because it was too extreme.
In the women's suffrage movement, something
similar happened. Anthony and Stanton built
a coalition with George Francis Train in 1867.
Train was popular, but he was strongly against
giving African-American men the right to vote.
It was a dangerous coalition that didn't work.
The state of Kansas was close to approving
women's suffrage but failed. And African-American
men didn't get the right to vote in Kansas
either.
Later, Anthony and Stanton put together a
coalition with Victoria Woodhull, who was
a woman with very strong views and believed
that women should have the right to love who
they wanted, and, as she said, "to change
that love every day if I please." This was
too much for many people and frightened away
some of the supporters of women's suffrage.
Many people think that this delayed women's
suffrage for twenty years.
A recent study by Blake Ashforth and Peter
Reingen shows an interesting thing about coalitions.
For people inside a coalition, the most important
people are the people at the center of the
group. For the women's suffrage coalition,
this was Anthony and Stanton. But for people
outside of a coalition, the person they notice
is the one with the most extreme ideas. In
the women's suffrage coalition, that person
was Woodhull.
Enemies are better than frenemies
In The Godfather: Part II, Michael Corleone
says, "Keep your friends close, but your enemies
closer." But what do we do with people who
are neither our friends, nor our enemies?
Usually we see people as friends, enemies,
or as somewhere in between. Our closest friends
support us all the time; our enemies are always
working against us. But in fact there are
also people who we can call "frenemies." These
are people who sometimes support you and sometimes
work against you.
Michelle Duffy, a professor at the University
of Minnesota, did a study of police officers
and how they felt supported, or not, by the
officer that they worked with. Not surprisingly,
negative relationships led to stress. When
officers felt they weren't supported by the
officer they worked with, they didn't work
so hard and took more time off of work.
But what happened when the police officer
felt supported by the other officer for some
of the time? Things didn't get better; they
got worse. Negative relationships aren't good,
but at least you know what is going to happen,
and you can be ready for it. But when you
don't know whether someone will support you
or not, your stress increases. In another
study, Bert Uchino found that "frenemy" relationships
like this were unhealthier than bad relationships.
People with a lot of relationships that were
neither friends nor enemies had higher stress,
were unhappier, and found life more difficult
than other people.
We may feel it is better to keep away from
our enemies and to try to improve our relationship
with frenemies. But that is probably not the
best idea. It's better to keep away from frenemies
and try to turn enemies into friends. Very
often, the best supporters we have are people
who didn't support us in the past, but who
have now come over to our side.
First, when someone has always supported us,
we expect it and don't think it is that wonderful.
But, when someone who didn't support us starts
to become a friend, we like them even more.
Second, they will feel the same about us.
They've worked hard to beat their negative
feelings about us, and now they feel much
more positively toward us.
Third, and most important, our old enemies
are the best at persuading other people to
join our movement. They felt negatively about
our ideas before, so they understand the people
who still feel negatively. And they know why
they changed their minds, so they can explain
this to others. People will listen to them
because they know they weren't always our
friends.
When Lucy Stone, who was working for both
women's suffrage and African-American suffrage,
walked around towns putting up posters for
meetings, young men often followed her, pulling
the posters down. Stone asked them if they
loved their mothers. Of course. Did they love
their sisters? Certainly. She then explained
that in the south of the United States, African-
American men of their age were sold and would
never see their families again. She then invited
the young men to her meetings as her special
guests. Some of these men helped her, and
they were very useful when other young men
started to make trouble.
From unknown to known
In the 1990s, a group of writers suggested
something that had never been done at Disney.
Instead of the old stories like Cinderella
and Snow White, they wanted to write something
completely new. Nobody at Disney really thought
it was a good idea.
The story became The Lion Lang, the most successful
film of 1994, winning two Oscars and a Golden
Globe. Disney hoped the film would make 50
million dollars. By 2014, it had made more
than 1 billion dollars.
Early in the project, five of the writers
had a meeting with Disney management, where
they explained their story about lions. Michael
Eisner, Disney CEO (Chief Executive Officer),
tried to find something he could understand
in it. "Could you make this into Shakespeare's
King Lear?" he asked.
That wasn't really possible. But then, from
the back of the room, Maureen Donley said,
"No, this is Hamlet." Suddenly, everyone understood.
The uncle kills the father, and then the son
has to kill his uncle. So the film became
Hamlet with lions, and Disney decided to make
it.
Justin Berg, a professor at Stanford University,
has explained that the writers had to start
with the lions. If they had started with Hamlet,
the story would have been too much like Shakespeare's.
Beginning in a different place, with lions,
made the story more original, but it provided
other difficulties. With a completely original
story, people very easily get lost. After
starting with the original lions, the writers
found that Hamlet could help them a lot. For
example, they realized that they needed Simba
to think about his future, as Hamlet does
in his "to be or not to be" speech, so they
wrote a new conversation in the film, where
Rafiki tells Simba that he must remember where
he comes from.
Creating coalitions
Frances Willard became leader of the WCTU
after the group began working with the women's
suffrage groups. How could she link women's
suffrage to the problems of alcohol, which
were the WCTU's first interest?
Willard didn't talk about suffrage, but about
home protection. The idea of home protection
was central to many women, especially religious
women. Willard used religion a lot in her
speeches, and the WCTU supporters liked that.
But she also explained that women's suffrage
was the best way of protecting women from
men drinking alcohol and being violent.
To return to the Goldilocks idea again, the
idea of women having the right to vote was
"too hot" for some people. The idea of home
protection was "too cold" for others. But,
when women's leaders explained how women could
make things better for everybody, things were
neither too hot nor too cold, and soon women
achieved the right to vote in a number of
states.
After twenty years of fighting, the two women's
suffrage organizations wanted to work together
again. But it was very difficult for Stone
to work with Anthony; they had been fighting
for years, and the relationship was broken.
After three years, in 1890, Stone realized
it was impossible. She asked her daughter
and her daughter's husband to take on the
job, and the two organizations did come together.
When Lucy Stone was dying, in 1893, she whispered
to her daughter: "Make the world better."
It took another twenty-seven years before
women's suffrage was achieved in the United
States, in 1920, but Stone had done a lot
of the early work toward it.
CHAPTER SIX
How to be a rebel
A few seconds ago, he was standing calmly
on third base. Now his feet are dancing. He
is ready to run to home base.
He has been here before. He is one of the
greatest players ever to play baseball. Four
times, he has led his team to the World Series,
and all four times, they have lost to the
Yankees. Now his team is down 6 - 4 in the
eighth inning. Is it time to try to steal
home?
Stealing a base is one of the riskiest moves
in baseball. It increases your team's chances
of scoring by only 3 percent, and to do it
successfully you have to slide into the base
at high speed, and there is a good chance
you will hurt yourself. Stealing home base
is even riskier than stealing other bases,
because the pitcher can see you and he has
an easy throw. The pitcher has to throw the
ball 60 feet; you have to run 90 feet, so
you have to run faster than the ball. And
your chances of getting hurt when you are
running to home base are four times higher.
In the whole of the 2012 season, only three
players tried to steal home.
This man, though, is different. He has stolen
home base more than any other player of the
day - nineteen times. In 100 years, only two
other players have managed more than nine.
But if you think stealing base is about speed,
think again. He's thirty-six now, no longer
a young man. He's been injured for part of
the season. Six years ago, he stole thirty-seven
bases in a season, but he has stolen far fewer
in the last two seasons. His hair is silver,
and he weighs more than he used to. This will
be his last season.
But this man has spent his life taking action
when others stood and watched, and he's not
going to stop now. He waits for the right
time and then runs. He slides into home base
just in time.
It's too little, too late. His team loses
the first game to the Yankees. But the effect
on the team is enormous. They are on fire
for the rest of the season and go on to win.
Years later, a journalist said that this man's
attempts to steal home base were the second-bravest
thing he had ever done.
The first was becoming Major League Baseball's
first black player, in 1947.
To become original we need to take some risks.
We can never be sure that we will succeed.
As journalist, Robert Quillen wrote in 1924,
"Progress always involves risk. You can't
steal second and keep one foot on first base."
From the start, Jackie Robinson had to deal
with white players who refused to play with
or against him, as well as hate mail. What
made him so brave? We can begin to find the
answer by looking at the families of players
who are good at stealing bases. Since 1962,
only ten players have stolen at least seventy
bases in two different seasons. Do you see
anything interesting here? Look at the table
on the next page.
Trying to find out why some baseball players
steal more bases than other players, Frank
Sulloway and Richard Zweigenhaft found more
than 400 men who played professional baseball.
Then they found something surprising. Birth
order can tell you which man will try to steal
most bases. Younger brothers were 10.6 times
more likely than older brothers to try to
steal.
Younger brothers weren't better players in
other ways. The big difference was in how
often they took risks. And they didn't just
take more risks; they were 3.2 times more
likely to steal a base safely.
The desire to take risks actually means that
younger brothers are less likely to play baseball.
Across twenty-four studies of more than 8,000
people, younger brothers and sisters were
1.48 times more likely to choose sports where
there are more injuries, such as football,
rugby, diving, skiing, and car racing. Older
brothers and sisters preferred safer sports:
baseball, golf, tennis, rowing, and cycling.
If we look at the three players who have stolen
the most bases, Jackie Robinson was the youngest
of five children. Rod Carew, who comes second
in the number of steals, is fourth of five
children. And third is Paul Molitor, who is
the fourth child of eight.
Younger children are not just risk-takers
in baseball. There are differences in politics
and science, too. Sulloway researched nearly
4,000 scientists to see what they had said
when revolutionary ideas appeared. He looked
at the ideas of major scientists such as Copernicus,
Darwin, Newton, and Einstein, and he researched
what 4,000 other scientists had written at
the time. Had they supported these revolutionary
ideas or not?
Compared to firstborn children, scientists
who were younger children were three times
more likely to support Newton and Einstein
at the time when their theories were revolutionary.
In the fifty years after Copernicus published
his idea that the earth went around the sun,
scientists who were younger children were
5.4 times more likely to support Copernicus'
ideas than firstborn scientists.
We often expect that younger scientists are
more likely to support new ideas. But Sulloway
shows that birth order is actually more important
than age.
As a firstborn myself, I was a little upset
by this research. But, as I learned more,
I realized that the effects of birth order
can be avoided. By bringing up all children
in a similar way to younger children, we can
raise any child to be more original.
This chapter looks at how the family affects
originality. What is special about being a
younger child does family size matter, and
how can this affect the way we raise our children?
I'll use birth order as a way of looking at
the effect family has on how likely we are
to take risks. To see how brothers and sisters
are more different than we expect, we'll look
at how Jackie Robinson was raised, and also
at the early years of some of the greatest
comedy stars in America. You'll also find
out how parents congratulate children in the
wrong way and how reading stories can help
originality.
Born to be a rebel
One day in 1944, when he was still in the
army, Jackie Robinson refused to sit at the
back of a bus with other African Americans.
The driver "shouted that if I didn't move
to the (back) of the bus he would cause me
plenty of trouble," Robinson remembered. Robinson
told the driver he couldn't care less about
the driver causing him trouble. When Robinson
talked about his attempt to steal home base
in the World Series, he used similar language.
"I just took off and did it. I really didn't
care whether I made it or not."
"I really didn't care," tells us something
important about Jackie Robinson and what he
had learned about risk. Many people, when
they are deciding what to do, think about
how to get the best results. But someone like
Robinson thinks differently. What is the right
thing for someone like me to do? These people
don't look at other people. They decide by
looking at themselves. The first group of
people, who think about the results and what
other people will think, can always find a
reason not to take a risk. And this sort of
decision can be decided by birth order.
For many years, experts have argued that it
is helpful to be firstborn. When he or she
is born, the first child doesn't have to share
parents with brothers or sisters and gets
a lot more of their parents' time. Firstborns
are more likely to win a Nobel Prize for science,
or to get into the United States Congress.
Research into 1,500 CEOs shows that 43 percent
of them were firstborn.
In Europe, it was shown that firstborns earn
salaries that are 14 percent higher than their
younger brothers and sisters when they start
work. But the situation changes by the time
they reach the age of thirty. The salaries
of those born later grow faster because they
are willing to change jobs sooner and more
often. Firstborns avoid risk more than those
born after them. Those born later are more
likely to drink or smoke, and they are less
likely to have good insurance.
Although many people now think that birth
order has some effect, the science of birth
order has many critics. Birth order doesn't
fix you in any way, it only affects the direction
in which you will probably develop. There
are a lot of other things that can affect
you. It's difficult for research to look at
birth order on its own; there are too many
other things that can affect development.
But when I looked at birth order I discovered
that it was a better way of deciding whether
a person would be a risk-taker than I had
expected.
In one study, people scored their brothers
and sisters and themselves on school achievement
and on whether they were rebels or not. A
rebel is someone who doesn't accept the default.
People with high school achievement were 2.3
times more likely to be born first than last.
Rebels were twice as likely to be born last
than first. There are two possible ways to
explain the risk-taking in those born later.
One is about how children deal with arguments
with their brothers and sisters. The other
is about how parents raise younger children
differently. Although we can't control birth
order, we can change some of its effects.
Niche picking
Look at a lot of brothers and sisters and
you will see the big differences in personality
aren't between families, but between children
in families. As adults, brothers and sisters
from the same family are different in how
much risk they want to take, or how much they
rebel, even though they have been raised by
the same parents.
Niche picking may help to explain this. The
idea was developed by Alfred Adler, who thought
that Sigmund Freud's theories about parents
didn't explain the part that brothers and
sisters play in the development of one another's
personality. Adler suggested that because
firstborn children start life as only children
they learn from their parents. When second
or third children come along, the first child
risks losing its first place, so may decide
to take on the job of being a parent and give
orders to the younger child. The younger child
answers this by becoming a rebel.
It can be difficult to compete with an older
brother or sister, so the younger child has
to choose a different path. The niche of the
responsible academic achiever is often taken
by the first child. Once the first child has
taken this niche, it can be difficult for
the next to compete. This depends on the age
difference; if it's only one year, the younger
child may be able to compete. And if it's
seven years, the niche may be open again.
In baseball, brothers who were between two
and five years apart were more likely to play
in different positions than brothers who were
less than two or more than five years apart.
Jackie Robinson was a runner at college, but
he couldn't compete with his older brother
Mack, who was five years older and won a silver
medal at the 1936 Olympic Games. Jackie Robinson
changed to basketball, football, and then
baseball.
Outside of the world of sports, I decided
to look at comedy. Comedy seems like a risky
job, so we would expect younger children to
be more successful. I looked at a 2004 list
of the 100 greatest comedy performers. You
would expect an equal number of any group
of 100 to be born first, or born last. However,
when I looked at these 100 people, forty-four
of them were born last, while only twenty
were born first. They came from families with
an average of 3.5 children, but nearly half
were the baby of their families.
When I looked at particular performers, I
found that their older brothers and sisters
were often responsible achievers. For example,
Chelsea Handler's five older brothers and
sisters are an engineer, a chef, an accountant,
a lawyer, and a nurse.
Niche picking shows how younger children often
try to be different from their older brothers
and sisters. Parents may try to give each
child the same experience, but birth order
pushes their personalities in different directions.
Less responsibility
If Jackie Robinson had been a first child,
he would have been raised mainly by his mother.
But, with five children to feed, Mrs. Robinson
needed to work. Robinson's older sister, Willa
Mae, washed him, dressed him, and fed him.
And when she went to school, she took her
baby brother with her, and he played outside
of the classroom. And, if he got into fights,
his older brother Frank was there to defend
him. When older brothers and sisters behave
like parents, there aren't as many rules or
punishments, and younger children take risks
earlier.
Parents often become more relaxed with the
younger children, and things are not so strict.
And as the older children take on more responsibilities,
there is less need for the younger child to
be responsible. The larger the family, the
more the younger children can escape responsibility.
We can explain the risk-taking of many originals
by their position in the family and the fact
that this gives them more freedom and allows
them to be rebels. But parents can encourage
children to be original whether they are the
first or the last. But one of the dangers
of originality is that being a rebel is not
always positive; it can also be negative.
Some research into how parents deal with good
or bad behavior will be helpful here.
Explaining and correcting
Some years ago, researchers found that, between
the ages of two and ten, parents ask their
children to change their behavior once every
six to nine minutes. This means perhaps fifty
times a day, or more than 15,000 times a year.
For their Altruistic Personality Study, Samuel
and Pearl Oliner studied people who had taken
great risks to save Jews during the Holocaust
between 1940 and 1945, when 6 million Jews
were murdered. They discovered there was a
difference in how parents had corrected the
mistakes of those risk-takers when they were
children. Their parents explained why they
were correcting them 21 percent of the time,
compared to 6 percent of the time for other
parents. One interviewee said that her mother
"told me when I did something wrong... She
tried to make me understand with my mind what
I'd done wrong." The Oliners also found that
explaining was especially useful when it made
children think what would happen to other
people as a result of their actions.
This can also work with adults. In hospitals,
to encourage doctors and nurses to wash their
hands more often, David Hofmann and I put
two different signs next to soap machines.
Over the next two weeks, we counted the number
of times doctors and nurses washed their hands,
before and after seeing a patient. The sign
on the left made no difference. But the sign
on the right made a big difference: using
the word "patients" instead of "you" resulted
in 10 percent more hand washing and 45 percent
more soap being used. Thinking about other
people changed doctors and nurses behavior
more than thinking about themselves.
Behavior and character
Good behavior is encouraged partly by what
parents say after a child has done the right
thing. The last time you saw a child doing
something good, you probably talked about
what they had done. "That was so sweet." By
talking about their behavior, you encourage
them to do it again. But Joan Grusec did an
interesting experiment about this. After some
children shared toys with other children,
some of them had their behavior mentioned
in feedback: "It was nice of you to share
those toys with other children. That was a
nice and helpful thing to do." Others were
given feedback on their characters: "I guess
you are the kind of person who likes to help
others. You are a helpful person."
Later, in a similar situation, the children
who had received character comments were 45
percent more likely to share toys, while those
who received behavior comments were only 10
percent more likely to share. When our character
is mentioned, we begin to build up an idea
of ourselves as a good person.
It has been suggested that the message "Don't
drink and drive" might be better if it were
changed to "Don't be a drunk driver." The
same idea can be used for originality. When
a child produces a good painting, rather than
saying that their work is creative we could
say, "You are creative." When we move from
talking about behavior to talking about character,
people think differently.
Why parents aren't the best role models
We can give children quite a lot of freedom
if we explain how what they do affects other
people. They will be more likely to be original
in a positive way, rather than a negative
one. But, as they grow up, they often don't
aim high enough.
Parents can begin the development of originality
in their children, but as children get older,
they need role models people who have been
original in their own area of work. Jackie
Robinson, for example, found a role model
in a young mechanic. As a boy, there was a
danger that Robinson would become a member
of a criminal gang, but this mechanic explained
to Robinson that he was hurting his mother.
Martin Luther King, Jr. had Gandhi as a role
model, as did Nelson Mandela.
Some originals have found role models in fiction.
For example, Sheryl Sandberg and Jeff Bezos
have both mentioned finding a role model in
the book A Wrinkle in Time, in which a young
girl learns to bend the laws of physics and
travel through time. There are studies that
show that, when children's stories show original
achievements, people innovate more twenty
to forty years later. In one study, psychologists
noted that original achievement increased
in American children's books by 66 percent
between 1810 and 1850. Between 1850 and 1890,
the number of patents increased by 700 percent.
Children's books reflected popular values
at the time but also helped to create values.
It takes time for children to learn originality
from characters in fiction. We can be sure
that the next group of originals will have
been affected by Harry Potter, books where
there is a lot of original achievement. When
children read about heroes who are also originals,
it may change the way they pick their niches
in the family. Wherever we are in family birth
order, there are niches for us, and role models
for originality.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Groupthink
Standing on stage in front of his audience,
a technology inventor pulled something out
of his pocket. It was so much smaller than
competing products that nobody in the room
could believe it. He was a man known for his
originality and creativity, and he didn't
believe in market research. He said his company
makes products that people do not even know
they want. This man made his company great,
only to be forced out, and then watch his
company disappear.
The story seems to describe Steve Jobs, but
actually, this man was one of Jobs' heroes:
Edwin Land, the man behind Polaroid. Today,
Land is remembered for inventing the instant
camera. But Land also invented something much
more important: the light filter that is used
in billions of products, from sunglasses to
watches. Land was responsible for 535 patents,
more than any American before him except for
Thomas Edison.
Land was certainly a great original, but his
company did not encourage originality. Polaroid
was one of the companies that started work
on the digital camera, but in the end, the
company failed because of it. Polaroid's engineers
had a high-quality digital camera ready in
1992, but the inventors couldn't persuade
the company to start selling it until 1996.
By then, there were more than forty other
digital cameras on the market.
Polaroid made a basic mistake. Within the
company, many people thought that customers
would always want to have printed pictures,
and the important people in the organization
didn't question this idea. It was a case of
groupthink - the desire to reach agreement
instead of allowing disagreement. Groupthink
is the enemy of originality.
In a famous study, the psychologist Irving
Janis argued that many bad decisions made
by the United States government were caused
by groupthink. Janis believed that groupthink
occurred when people felt they were deeply
involved in a group and they wanted to agree
with the group, instead of suggesting different
ideas. He said that it was the safe, friendly
feelings inside a close group that created
groupthink.
People accepted Janis' theory for a long time,
but it isn't true. Janis did his work in 1973,
but researchers now have seen a lot more government
documents, and it's clear that these bad decisions
were not made by one small, close group. And
there was another problem with Janis' theory.
Most of the time he looked at groups making
bad decisions. But how do we know that it
was actually the closeness of the group that
caused the bad decisions? Janis needed to
compare good and bad decisions to see whether
close groups are more likely to make decisions
through groupthink.
The theory of close groups causing groupthink
isn't true in business either. When researchers
looked at successful and failed decisions
in management teams at seven major companies,
they discovered that close groups weren't
more likely to want to agree with each other
and refuse different ideas. In fact, close
groups often made better business decisions.
The same was true in politics.
In this chapter, I want to look at what really
causes groupthink and what we can do to prevent
it. Why do some close groups make bad decisions
while others make good ones? I want to see
how to fight groupthink and allow original
opinions. I'll look at Polaroid's mistakes,
and I'll also examine an organization that
has an interesting new way of avoiding conformity.
You'll see why people often don't listen to
original ideas, and why it's sometimes better
to ask people to complain about problems rather
than to solve them. In the end, you'll see
what ordinary people and organizations can
do to allow originality to develop.
Commitment to organizations
In the 1990s, a group of experts led by James
Baron interviewed 200 people who had started
technology companies in Silicon Valley. They
asked these leaders what sort of organization
they were trying to develop when they started
out.
They found three major organizational plans:
professional, star, and commitment. In a professional
organization, managers tried to hire people
with the right skills - engineers who could
write in JavaScript or C++, for example. In
a star organization, managers were not so
interested in skills as in the future; they
looked for the brightest people and didn't
worry so much about their skills, because
these people would learn quickly.
In a commitment organization, employees were
hired to fit company culture. Skills and intelligence
were useful, but the important thing was that
the employee believed in the company. Commitment
organizations wanted to build strong emotional
links between employees and to the organization.
They often used words like family and love
when they talked about the company.
Baron's team wanted to see which type of organization
led to the most success. They followed the
200 companies through the 1990s, into the
2000s. They discovered that one organizational
culture was much better than the others: commitment.
Where a company had a commitment culture,
the number of failures was zero. Not one of
them went out of business. But the number
of failures for star organizations was high,
and professional companies did even worse.
We can see that a commitment culture worked
well in the early days of Polaroid when everybody
worked hard and there was a desire for originality
and quality. When Edwin Land was developing
his instant camera, he once worked for eighteen
days without stopping, not even changing his
clothes. While his competitor, Kodak, hired
scientists, Land looked for a mixed group
of employees, including women with artistic
experience. Just like the commitment organizations
in Silicon Valley, he didn't worry about skills
or star qualities. He wanted people who would
have original ideas and work hard for the
company. His employees developed strong emotional
links with the company. When you feel like
that, it's hard to imagine working somewhere
else.
After the instant camera, Polaroid was responsible
for two other important new developments in
film technology. The first was the use of
sepia, or brown, photos. Black-and-white instant
photos often faded, and sepia worked better.
The person who discovered that was Meroe Morse,
who had been a student of art history and
had not studied either physics or chemistry
in college. She worked so hard that her laboratory
worked twenty-four hours a day. The second
new product was instant color photography.
Howard Rogers, who had been a car mechanic,
worked for fifteen years to solve that problem.
Problems with growth
Commitment cultures are very useful at the
beginning of the life of an organization,
but, over time, things don't usually go so
well. Although these companies grow well at
first, growth slows down after a time. When
employees share a commitment to the company's
clear goals, they can work well in a business
situation that they understand. But if things
keep changing, as they do in the computer
or airline industries, the positive things
about this strong culture disappear. When
the market is changing, these companies find
it difficult to look outside of themselves,
and they fail to learn and change.
This is what happened with Polaroid. After
Land invented the instant camera in 1948,
the company went from making under 7 million
dollars in 1950 to making 950 million dollars
in 1976. During this time, there were no big
changes in the industry; customers loved high-quality
cameras that printed instant pictures. But,
with the development of digital technology,
the market began to change, and Polaroid's
culture didn't allow the company to move as
fast as market developments.
In 1980, Land was contacted by Akio Morita
of Sony who suggested that film was not the
future and wanted Sony and Polaroid to work
together on an electronic camera. Land wasn't
interested. He thought only about the chemistry
and physics in photography and didn't believe
digital photos would ever be good enough.
As Polaroid began to have difficulties, Land
didn't look outside of his organization. Instead,
he worked only with his supporters inside
the company. He wanted to make an instant
movie camera, and he wouldn't listen to any
critics. When it was ready, it wasn't a success.
It made only a few minutes of video, while
competitors already had cameras that could
make several hours. The company lost 600 million
dollars, and Land lost his job.
Land was not alone in the way he behaved.
Research shows that the worse a company does,
the more the bosses get advice only from the
people who agree with them. But this is the
opposite of what they should do; different
opinions are useful even when they are wrong.
The evidence suggests that it isn't social
links that create groupthink, but too much
confidence. Polaroid had too much confidence
that customers would always want printed pictures,
and they refused to look at other original
ideas. So how can you build a strong culture
that welcomes disagreement?
Think differently
When I asked entrepreneurs and students about
the strongest culture they had ever met in
an organization, the winner was Bridgewater
Associates. This company in Connecticut manages
over 170 billion dollars for governments,
universities, and other organizations. The
company culture is explained in a book of
200 key ideas. Although the company manages
money, none of these ideas are about money.
They are about how to behave in any situation
that you meet at work or outside.
New employees are hired only if they fit in
with the company's ideas, and there is a camp
where they study and discuss them. Although
there is a lot of discussion, Bridgewater
is a close, friendly organization. Many employees
call it a family, and people often work there
for a long time.
Although Bridgewater has a strong commitment
culture in an industry that changes all the
time, it has continued to be successful for
twenty years. Its secret is that it encourages
original ideas.
If you are an investor, you can only succeed
if you think differently from everyone else.
Bridgewater avoids groupthink by inviting
different opinions from everyone in the company.
When employees share independent ideas instead
of agreeing with everyone else, there is a
much better chance that Bridgewater will make
decisions no one else has thought of. And
then there is a better chance they will be
right when the rest of the market is wrong.
I want to look now at the culture of the company,
which lies behind its brilliant decisions.
Bridgewater's success begins with the man
who started the company, Ray Dalio. He's been
called the Steve Jobs of investing, but employees
don't behave as though he is special. They
are expected to be critical of him, and employee
comments are shared across the company. One
of the 200 key ideas is: "No one has the right
to hold a critical opinion without speaking
up about it." Dalio wants people who think
independently and believes that this will
make the culture richer and stronger, and
better able to avoid groupthink.
Finding complainers
If you're a leader talking to your employees,
how would you complete this sentence?
Don't bring me-; bring me-.
I learned about this question from David Hofmann,
and I've presented it to thousands of groups
of leaders. They always shout out the same
answer: "Don't bring me problems; bring me
answers."
This seems wise. We don't want people just
to complain; when they see something wrong,
they should find a way to fix it. But when
it comes to groupthink this isn't always a
good thing. Hofmann has done a lot of research
in this area, and he found that a culture
that looks mainly at solving problems doesn't
encourage people to investigate. If you are
expected to always have an answer, you come
to meetings ready with your answers, and you
don't get the chance to learn from others.
To try to avoid this problem, Google has created
a team of "complainers" - engineers across
the company who are well known for recognizing
problems and saying what they really think,
even if it is negative. Before a major change,
managers often ask this team to give critical
feedback. By talking to the complainers early,
the managers get the feedback, and the complainers
often then become the key people to support
the change.
Ray Dalio, at Bridgewater, doesn't expect
employees to bring him answers. One of the
first things he did in the company was to
create a list of problems, which any employee
could add to. Getting problems noted is half
the battle against groupthink; the other half
is listening to the right ideas for solving
them. Bridgewater collects a group of people
to look at the problems, share their ideas,
find out what has gone wrong and why, and
suggest ways of solving the problems. It is
important that ideas are shared. As Karl Weick
advises, "Argue like you're right and listen
like you're wrong."
Critical feedback
Even if an organization doesn't encourage
critical feedback from its employees, there
may be ways of changing the culture. At Index
Group, the company CEO, Tom Gerrity, brought
in an expert to tell him everything he did
wrong in front of his 100 employees. By showing,
he was happy to get feedback, he found that
employees from across the company were more
likely to challenge his ideas, and to challenge
one another.
I've learned to do something similar in my
classroom. I collect feedback from students
after the first month, asking for suggestions
for improvement. I then email all the feedback
to the class. In the next class, I discuss
the suggestions, ask for more feedback, and
suggest changes. Students often say that this
helps them to feel comfortable about becoming
more involved in improving the class.
It isn't just the open culture at Bridgewater
that makes it easier for employees to challenge
managers. When they are new in the company,
employees are encouraged to question the company's
key ideas. In most companies, the employee
is busy learning the job for the first few
months and isn't encouraged to think about
any problems. But in fact those early days,
when employees have more time, and before
they see the world in the company way, are
a good time for them to think about improving
the culture.
A few years ago, I was hired by Goldman Sachs
to help them attract and keep excellent employees
by encouraging those employees to improve
their place of work. One thing we introduced
was an entry interview. Managers have meetings
to ask new employees for ideas when they start,
instead of waiting to ask employees what they
thought of the company when they leave. It's
easier to start a relationship with the door
open than to try to push open a door that
has already been closed.
Movers and shapers
Ray Dalio at Bridgewater is interested in
understanding people who shape the world and
in finding out how they are similar. He's
interviewed many originals of our time and
has studied originals from history like Benjamin
Franklin and Albert Einstein. Of course, all
of these people were enthusiastic and had
great imagination, but Dalio has three other
qualities on his list of similarities. First,
"shapers" are independent thinkers and rebels
who ask a lot of questions. Second, they are
honest critics and don't care who they are
talking to. And third, they are not afraid
of risk; their fear of not succeeding is greater
than their fear of failure. If Dalio doesn't
find a shaper to follow him, Bridgewater may
go the same way as Polaroid. But Dalio knows
that preventing groupthink is about more than
the ideas of one leader. The greatest shapers
don't stop at introducing originality into
the world; they create cultures that encourage
originality in others.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Working with emotions
In 2007, a man called Lewis Pugh jumped into
the Arctic Sea. The ice was not completely
frozen, and Pugh's plan was to be the first
person to survive a long-distance swim across
the North Pole. Pugh had been in the British
Special Air Service before becoming the best
cold-water swimmer on the planet. Two years
earlier, he had jumped off of the ice to swim
a kilometer in Antarctica. But he doesn't
do it just to be the best in the world; he
wants to make people think about climate change.
Before he swims, something happens to Pugh
that has never been noticed in any other human;
his body temperature goes up from 98.6F to
101F. When it is time to get into the freezing
water, his body prepares.
The passengers on the Titanic died in water
that was 41F. In Pugh's Antarctic swim, the
water had been 32F. At the North Pole, it
was less than 29F. After falling into that
water, a British explorer had lost fingers
in three minutes; Pugh's team estimated that
his swim would take twenty minutes. But a
five-minute test swim at the North Pole went
badly and, instead of imagining success, Pugh
began to imagine failure. If he failed, he
would die. He became very afraid and questioned
whether he would survive. So would it have
been better for him to imagine success?
This chapter looks at the emotional cost of
going against the crowd. In my own research
in a healthcare company, I tested how much
employees knew about how to manage emotions.
Those who showed up well in the emotion test
also spoke up more with ideas and suggestions
in the workplace, and their managers thought
they were better employees. They had the courage
to challenge, but they were also able to control
their emotions when they were doing it.
To understand these emotional skills, I'll
look at how Pugh got ready for the freezing
water, and how Martin Luther King, Jr. prepared
civil rights workers to keep calm. I'll explore
how one group managed to throw out a dictator,
and how a leader in technology persuaded engineers
to make a major change to their product. By
studying how to manage emotions, you'll discover
whether it's better to plan for success or
failure, whether calming yourself down can
light fear, how to deal with your anger, and
what it takes to keep going when everything
seems to be against you.
Optimism and pessimism
Although many originals seem to be confident
on the outside, inside they often worry and
doubt their own abilities. When United States
government leaders described their most difficult
decisions, they didn't talk about difficult
problems but about choices that needed courage.
And research by Scott Sonenshein has shown
that people working for a better environment
are often uncertain about whether they can
succeed. Challenging the present situation
is often hard work, and there will be problems
and failures along the way.
Psychologist Julie Norem studies two different
ways of managing these challenges: optimism
and pessimism. Optimists expect that the best
will happen; they stay calm and expect to
succeed. Pessimists expect the worst; they
worry, and they imagine all the things that
can go wrong.
Most people think it's better to be an optimist
than a pessimist. Yet Norem found that, although
pessimists worry more and are less confident,
they do their jobs as well as the optimists.
And Norem soon realized that pessimists did
well because of their pessimism.
Norem explains that pessimism works as a way
of managing fear and worry. When pessimists
start to doubt themselves, they don't allow
themselves to freeze with fear. They imagine
an enormous failure to make them worry more,
and that gives them reasons to succeed. Once
they have imagined everything that can go
wrong, they look at how to avoid those problems,
and this makes them feel they can control
things. They worry most before they act, so
when they start to move they are ready to
succeed. They are confident because they know
they have prepared as well as possible. If
they don't worry, then they relax and don't
plan. It's important that pessimists don't
feel comfortable.
Lewis Pugh was usually an optimist. He took
risks when other people would give up. But
in the weeks before a major swim he was often
more of a pessimist. It was not the words
of his own team that encouraged him, but the
words of people who doubted him. Two years
earlier, before another freezing swim, an
expert had told him that it was impossible
and that he would die.
As Pugh stood shaking at the North Pole, his
pessimism told him that things were not going
to go well. But, instead of trying to find
reasons to be happier, he started to think
about every possible risk. He made plans to
be sure that he spent very little time on
the ice before the swim and to get to the
boat as quickly as possible afterward. "The
trick is to make fear your friend," he says
on his website (www.lewispugh.com). But this
isn't enough. Pessimism can be helpful when
you're sure about what you want to do. But,
when you're not so sure, doubt can get in
the way.
Keep believing
When most people list the things that frighten
them, one thing comes up very often: speaking
in public. If we want to understand how people
manage fear, we can just put them on stage.
Alison Wood Brooks asked college students
to give a speech about why they would be good
to work with. The speeches were filmed, and
a group of students was ready to watch them
and score them. With only two minutes to prepare,
many of the students were actually shaking.
If you were in this situation, how would you
manage your fear? When 300 professional workers
were asked, 90 percent suggested, "Try to
relax and calm down." But this is not the
best advice.
Before the college students gave their speeches,
Brooks asked them to say three words out loud.
Half of them were asked to say, "I am calm."
The other half were asked to say, "I am excited."
Changing one word was enough to change the
quality of the speeches. When students attached
the label "excited" to their emotions, they
were scored as 17 percent better at persuading
and 15 percent more confident than those students
who said they were "calm". The excited students
also gave longer speeches than the calm students.
In another experiment, when students were
nervous before a math test they scored 22
percent better if they were told "Try to get
excited" instead of "Try to remain calm."
Brooks wanted to find out if it's better just
to accept worry, so she gave students another
frightening task. They were asked to sing
in public, and they would be scored on the
quality of their singing. This time, one group
wasn't asked to say anything before singing,
another was asked to say "I am worried," and
a third "I am excited." The group who said
nothing scored 69 percent; the group who said
"worried" scored only 53 percent. But the
group who said "excited" scored 80 percent.
When we are frightened, why is it better to
make ourselves excited than to try to stay
calm? Fear is a strong emotion; when we are
frightened, our heart gets faster. If we then
try to relax, it's like trying to stop a car
suddenly when it's going fast. It's better
to take a strong emotion and turn it into
something different but equally strong.
Author Susan Cain says that we have a stop
system and a go system. When we haven't decided
what we are going to do, pessimism is dangerous.
Thinking too much about the dangers makes
us worry and "stop." Being optimistic makes
us more likely to do something-to "go." However,
in a situation where we have already decided
what we are going to do, and start to worry
about it, it is better to be a pessimist and
turn our worries into positive emotions like
excitement. This switches on our go system.
In previous cold-water swims, Lewis Pugh was
certain he would succeed, so being a pessimist
was helpful: looking at all the possible dangers
made him ready for anything. At the North
Pole, this worked at first, but after the
five-minute test swim, which went badly, he
started to worry: "What I felt on that stupid
test swim wasn't like anything I'd felt before.
I don't believe I can do this."
It was time to move away from pessimism. A
friend gave him three ideas to get excited.
First, he reminded Pugh that twenty-nine people
from ten countries had helped him, and he
put flags from those countries along the water.
Second, the friend told him to think of his
parents and how they had helped him. And third,
he told him to think about climate change
and how the swim might help. After listening
to his friend, Pugh was ready to do the swim.
He jumped into the freezing water and Finished,
successfully, in eighteen minutes and fifty
seconds.
For Pugh, the most difficult thing was managing
his own emotions. But other originals have
to manage other people's emotions. When others
are afraid to act, how can we encourage them?
In 2009, fifteen young tourists visited Belgrade,
the capital of Serbia. After walking them
around part of the city, their guide, a Serbian
in his thirties, talked about the country's
recent history of high potato prices and free
concerts. But they weren't ordinary tourists,
and they were getting impatient. They had
come to Belgrade to learn how to get rid of
their own country's dictator.
They asked the guide how the people of Serbia
had removed the Serbian dictator Slobodan
Milosevic. You don't need to take big risks,
the guide told them. You can do lots of little
things - drive more slowly than usual, push
televisions through the streets, or turn lights
on and off. The tourists just laughed. Small
things like that would never work for us,
they said. If we did that, we would be arrested
and then disappear. How can we have a revolution
when we can't meet in groups of more than
three?
They didn't know it, but the guide had heard
all this before - from Georgians in 2003,
from Ukrainians in 2004, from Lebanese in
2005, and from Maldivians in 2008. In each
case, they had gone back to their countries
and removed a dictator. The guide, Srda Popovic,
had taught them all. He was one of the people
behind Otpor!, the non-violent organization
of young people who had helped remove Milosevic.
Popovic had been attacked by the dictator's
police and had spent time in jail.
When psychologist Dan McAdams and his team
asked adults to tell them their life stories,
and how they felt at different times, they
saw two patterns. Some people had mostly good
experiences and were fairly happy during most
of their lives. But people who had found original
ways of helping others often had stories that
started badly when they were young but got
better later. Although they had more bad experiences
than the other group, these originals had
more happiness. They managed their problems,
and in the end, their lives were happier and
fuller.
After leading the group that removed their
dictator, Popovic began to help other groups
that were trying to remove dictators without
violence. Not every group succeeded, but we
can learn a lot from Popovic's way of managing
emotions.
Using users to excite teams
When Josh Silverman took over at Skype in
February 2008, the company had problems. Skype,
a leader in free computer-to-computer calls,
was no longer growing as fast as before. Silverman
decided he had to do something big. In April,
he announced that Skype 4.0 would appear before
the end of the year, and it would include
full-screen video. Most employees were deeply
negative about this. They thought there wasn't
enough time; the video quality would be poor;
and users would hate using a full screen.
Silverman didn't try to calm them down but
decided he needed to get them excited about
video. He talked to employees about the big
idea: "It's not about making cheap phone calls.
It's about being together when you're not
in the same room." Silverman talked about
how Skype allowed his children to keep close
contact with their grandparents, who were
thousands of miles away. Then he let other
Skype users talk about what Skype had done
for them. A married couple talked about how
Skype kept them together when they had to
spend a year living apart. A man in the army
talked about how he could be with his children
even when he was in another country; they
even opened Christmas presents together.
As they began to understand that Skype was
about connecting people, the team's worries
turned to excitement. Their go system was
switched on. Skype 4.0 was ready on time with
high-quality full-screen video calls. Soon,
Skype was adding 380,000 new users every day.
Less than three years later, Microsoft bought
Skype for 8.5 billion dollars; the company
had increased in value by 300 percent.
In Serbia, Popovic knew he had to show people
something to encourage them to act. People
were too afraid to listen, so Popovic used
a picture of a fist to encourage people's
go system.
Strength in numbers
If you are the only person with an idea, it
can be hard to defend it. But people can get
strength from just a small number of people
who think like them. To feel that you're not
alone, you don't need a whole crowd. Research
by Sigal Barsade and Hakan Ozcelik has shown
that, in business or government, even having
one friend may be enough.
If you want people to take risks, you have
to show them they aren't alone. This was the
first part of Otpor!'s success. In 1998, they
painted a fist on buildings all around Belgrade,
together with sentences like "I am against
the government because I love Serbia," "Bite
the system," and "Argue until we win." Before
they saw the fist, people who were against
Milosevic were afraid to say what they thought.
But, when they saw it, they realized there
were others who were happy to take a risk.
Later, when police arrested members of Otpor!,
those members were often asked who was their
leader. Popovic and his friends taught them
to answer, "I am one of the 20,000 leaders
of Otpor!"
Around the world, different organizations
have used small actions to show they are part
of a larger group. In Chile, to complain about
the dictator Pinochet, people turned their
lights on and off. When people saw their neighbors
doing that, they weren't afraid to do the
same. Then people were invited to drive slowly.
Taxi drivers slowed down, and so did bus drivers.
Soon people were walking slowly in the streets.
People understood there was no risk: it's
not against the law to drive or walk slowly.
In Poland, when people were unhappy about
government news on televisions, they knew
that just turning off the television wasn't
enough. So they took their televisions outside
and pushed them through the streets. It's
not against the law to push your television
through the streets.
In Serbia, Otpor! Found a clever way to change
people's fear to excitement: comedy. They
sent birthday presents to Milosevic: a ticket
out of the country, and a prison uniform.
It's hard to be afraid of speaking up against
a dictator when you are laughing at him.
Laughter can work in other situations where
people are afraid, too. When you have no power,
laughter is a powerful way to change strong
negative emotions into positive ones. After
hearing Popovic's story, a group of students
wanted to do something about the very high
cost of lessons at their university. They
decided to show the university president pictures
of their cheap and simple meals and invite
themselves to dinner at his house.
But Popovic also has a message that isn't
funny at all. At first, Popovic seems to be
an optimist. When others were ready to give
up, he thought there was a better future for
Serbia. But when I asked him if he was ever
unsure, he told me he had doubts for all of
those ten years. Even today, he worries about
the people who died, and he feels responsible.
The importance of now
On New Year's Eve in 2000, Popovic and his
friends organized a celebration in the main
square in Belgrade, with music and dancing.
At midnight, the famous band the Red Hot Chili
Peppers would appear, and everyone was very
excited. One minute before midnight, the square
went dark and people began counting down.
But when it was midnight, no famous band appeared.
Instead, a voice said, "We have nothing to
celebrate. This has been a year of war. But
it doesn't have to be that way. Let's make
the coming year count. Because 2000 is the
year."
When John Kotter studied 100 companies that
were trying to make major changes, he discovered
that the first mistake they made was to fail
to make people understand that acting quickly
was important. Kotter noted that managers
didn't realize how difficult it was to persuade
people that change needed to happen, and it
needed to happen now. If they don't understand
the importance of speed, employees sit back
and refuse to change. Otpor! Made people in
Serbia understand the importance of speed
when they announced: "This is the year."
To understand this more, let's look at another
piece of research by Amos Tversky and Daniel
Kahneman. Imagine you are the manager of a
car company. Sales are down, and you need
to close three factories and lose 6,000 employees.
You can choose between two different plans.
Plan A will save one of the three factories
and 2,000 jobs. Plan B has a one-third chance
of saving all three factories and 6.000 jobs,
but a two-thirds chance of saving no factories
and no jobs.
Most people, 80 percent, prefer Plan A.
But let's now look at the choice in a different
way.
Plan A will lose two factories and 4,000 jobs.
Plan B has a two-thirds chance of losing all
three factories and 6.000 jobs, but a one-third
chance of losing no factories or jobs.
These are the same choices as the first time,
but they don't feel like it. In this case,
82 percent of people prefer Plan B.
In the first case, the choices show what we
could gain. We prefer Plan A because it looks
less risky. When we are sure we will gain
something, we want to keep and protect it.
We want to save 2,000 jobs, rather than take
a risk and save no jobs. In the second case,
we are told what we are going to lose. Now
we want to avoid losing anything, even if
it means taking a bigger risk. We're going
to lose thousands of jobs anyway, so we decide
to take a big risk and hope that we lose nothing.
If we want people to change, is it better
to show them why it is helpful to change,
or the costs of not changing? According to
Peter Salovey, it depends on whether people
think the change is safe or risky. If they
think it is safe, it is better to talk about
the good things that will happen if they do
it. They will want to act immediately and
get there quickly. But if they think it's
risky, that doesn't work. They are comfortable
where they are, so they don't see why they
should change. If we want them to change,
we have to talk about the bad things that
will happen if they don't change. It's easier
for people to take a risk when they know they
will definitely lose something if they don't.
At Merck, the medicine company, they wanted
managers to be more involved in making changes.
Managers were asked to think of ideas that
would put Merck out of business. They imagined
that they were one of Merck's competitors
and developed ideas for new medicines that
were better than Merck's, or looked at markets
Merck had missed. Then they had to find ways
to defend the company against these competitors.
This "kill the company" exercise is strong
because it asks people to think about what
they might lose. Before, when managers thought
about new products, they didn't want to take
risks. But when they thought about their competitors
they realized it was a risk not to innovate.
Popovic realized that strong emotions were
needed to change the situation in Serbia.
By stopping the concert and sending people
home on New Year's Eve, he was reminding them
to act now.
Deep and surface acting
Anger is a good way to get people to do something.
We feel we have to fight when someone has
done the wrong thing. But, although anger
can encourage people to speak and to act,
it can also make them do it the wrong way.
Debra Meyerson and Maureen Scully suggest
that the key is to be hotheaded and cool-headed
at the same time. The heat pushes us toward
action and change; the coolness gives the
action a useful shape.
Arlie Hochschild has suggested that if you
are feeling a strong emotion like worry or
anger there are two ways to manage it: surface
acting and deep acting. Surface acting means
changing your face, speech, and actions to
show you are calm. If you are working for
an airline and an angry passenger starts to
shout at you on a plane, you may smile and
try to show some warmth. You change on the
outside, but inside you haven't changed. You
are angry with the passenger, and the passenger
probably knows it. But if you are deep acting
you might imagine that the passenger is under
stress, is afraid of flying, or has problems
at home. You feel sorry for the passenger,
and your smile is warmer.
Before Lewis Pugh starts out on one of his
swims, he uses deep acting. He listens to
music and remembers jumping from a plane in
his army days. He is returning to the excitement
that he felt then, and which he wants to find
again. Deep acting is a better way of managing
emotions than surface acting. If we want to
show our emotions, we have to feel them.
The dangers of venting
Less than a year after Rosa Parks refused
to give up her seat on a bus in Montgomery,
a United States court decided that separating
black and white people was against the law.
Now that black people could sit anywhere on
a bus, Martin Luther King, Jr. and others
realized they needed to help black people
reply to the violence that they might meet.
The team put chairs in rows, like a bus, and
asked audience members to play "black" or
"white" passengers. The "white" passengers
called the "black" passengers names, pushed
them, and threw things at them. The "black"
passengers needed to act deeply. King wanted
them to be angry enough to speak out, but
not to be so angry that they became violent.
What would be the best way to manage their
anger? Many people suggest that venting works
best, turning the anger against something
else like hitting a pillow, or screaming.
But studies have shown that venting doesn't
help, even if you think it does or it makes
you feel good. After venting, most people
are even angrier than before.
When King and his team worked on anger, they
were careful to stop people venting. Sometimes
a person playing a "black" man would get so
angry that he hit back. They would work with
him so that what he said and did was less
violent.
To use anger in a positive way, it is better
to avoid thinking too much about the person
we are angry with. It is better to think about
the people who have been hurt by the person's
actions. Martin Luther King, Jr. often did
this. He said he was not trying to beat the
white man; he wanted to free black children.
Thinking about those who have been hurt can
lead to a different kind of anger. Research
has shown that when we are angry with someone
we want to hurt them. But when we are angry
for someone we want to make things better
for them. We don't want to punish; we want
to help.
When a voice told Serbians there was nothing
to celebrate on New Year's Eve, they felt
an angry energy. Popovic said, "There was
an energy in the air that no rock band could
ever recreate. Everybody felt that they had
something important to do." The next fall
Milosevic lost the election, and the man who
told the people to go home became the president
of Serbia four years later.
E.B. White once wrote that he woke in the
morning unable to decide whether he wanted
to improve the world or to enjoy the world.
He commented in an interview with The New
York Times, "This makes it difficult to plan
the day."
As we search for happiness, many of us choose
to enjoy the world as it is. Originals take
a more difficult path, trying to make the
world what it could be. They may have to forget
about their own happiness for a time. Becoming
original is not the easiest way to find happiness,
but the journey brings its own happiness.
- THE END -