CHAPTER ONE
As a child I had been impressed by the Boerum
House.
It was fairly new then, and shiny with new
paint - a huge Victorian building.
Standing in front of it this early Christmas
Eve, however, I could find no echo of that
youthful impression.
It was all a depressing gray now, and the
curtains behind the windows were drawn completely
so that the house seemed to present blindly
staring eyes to the passerby.
When I knocked my stick sharply on the door,
Celia opened it.
'There is a doorbell,' she said.
She was still wearing the long unfashionable
and badly wrinkled black dress which must
have been her mother's, and she looked more
than ever like old Katrin had in her later
years: the thin bony body, the tight thin
line of her lips, the colorless hair pulled
back hard enough to remove every wrinkle from
her forehead.
She reminded me of a steel trap ready to shut
down on anyone who touched her incautiously.
I said, 'I am aware that the doorbell is not
connected, Celia,' and walked past her into
the hall.
She banged the door shut, and instantly we
were in half-darkness.
I put out my hand for the light switch, but
Celia said sharply, 'This is no time for lights!
There's been a death in this house, you know
that.'
'I have good reason to know,' I said, 'but
your manner now does not impress me.'
'She was my brother's wife, and very dear
to me.'
I moved towards her and rested my stick on
her shoulder.
'Celia,' I said, 'as your family's lawyer,
let me give you a word of advice.
The inquest is over, and you've been cleared.
But nobody believed you then, and nobody ever
will.
Remember that.'
She pulled away.
'Is that what you came to tell me?'
'I came because I knew your brother would
want to see me today.
I suggest you keep away while I talk to him.'
'Keep away from him yourself!'
she cried.
'He was at the inquest and saw them clear
my name.
In a little while he'll forget the terrible
things he thinks about me.
Keep away from him so that he can forget.'
I started walking cautiously up the dark stairs,
but she followed me.
'I prayed,' she said, 'and was told that life
is too short for hatred.
So when he comes to me, I'll forgive him.'
I reached the top of the stairs and almost
fell over something.
I swore, then said, 'If you're not going to
use lights, you should at least keep the way
clear.
Why don't you get these things out of here?'
'They are poor Jessie's things,' she said.
'Ready for throwing out.
It hurts Charlie to see anything of hers.
I knew it would be best to throw them out.'
Alarm came into her voice.
'But you won't tell him, will you?'
I went into Charlie's room and closed the
door behind me.
The curtains were drawn, but the ceiling light
showed me that he was lying on his bed with
an arm over his eyes.
Slowly, he stood up and looked at me.
'Well,' he said at last, nodding towards the
door, she didn't give you any light on the
way up, did she?'
'No,' I said, 'but I know the way.'
'She gets around better in the dark than I
do in the light.
She'd rather have it that way, too.
Otherwise she might look into a mirror and
be frightened of what she saw.'
He gave a short laugh.
'All you hear from her now is how she loved
Jessie, and how sorry she is.
Maybe she thinks if she says if often enough,
people will believe it.'
I dropped my hat and stick on the bed and
put my overcoat beside them.
Then I took out a cigarette and waited until
he found a match to light it for me.
His hand shook violently.
Charlie was five years younger than Celia,
but seeing him then I thought he looked ten
years older.
His hair was so fair that it was difficult
to see whether or not he was going gray.
He had not shaved for several days, and there
were huge blue-black bags under his eyes.
He stared at me, pulling uncertainly at his
mustache.
'You know why I wanted to see you,' he said.
'I can imagine,' I said, 'but I'd rather you
told me.'
'It's Celia,' he said.
'I want her to get what she deserves.
Not prison.
I want the law to take her and kill her, and
I want to be there to watch it.'
'You were at the inquest, Charlie,' I said.
'You saw what happened.
Celia's cleared and, unless more evidence
can be produced, she stays cleared.'
'What more evidence does anyone need?
They were arguing violently at the top of
the stairs.
Celia threw Jessie down to the bottom and
killed her.
That's murder, isn't it?'
I was tired, and sat down in the old leather
armchair.
'There were no witnesses,' I said.
'I heard Jessie scream and I heard her fall,'
he said, 'and when I ran out and found her
there, I heard Celia bang her door shut.
She pushed Jessie!'
'But you didn't see anything.
And Celia says she wasn't there.
As you weren't an eyewitness, you can't make
a murder out of what might have been an accident.'
He slowly shook his head.
'You don't really believe that,' he said.
'Because if you do, you can get out now and
never come near me again.'
'It doesn't matter what I believe.
I'm telling you the legal position.
What about motive?
What did Celia have to gain from Jessie's
death?
There's no money or property involved.'
Charlie sat down on the edge of his bed.
'No,' he whispered, 'there's no money or property
in it.
It's me.
First, it was the old lady with her heart
trouble whenever I tried to do anything for
myself.
Then when she died and I thought I was free,
it was Celia.
She never had a husband or a baby - but she
had me!'
'She's your sister, Charlie.
She loves you.'
He laughed unpleasantly.
'And she can't let me go.
When I think back now, I still can't understand
how she did it.
She would look at me in a certain way and
all the strength would go out of me.
And it was like that until I met Jessie ... I
remember the day I brought Jessie home, and
told Celia we were married.
There was a look in her eye - the same look
that must have been there when she pushed
Jessie down those stairs.'
I said, 'But you admitted at the inquest that
you never saw her threaten or do anything
to hurt Jessie.'
'Of course I never saw!
But Jessie would go around sick to her heart
every day without saying a Word, and would
cry in bed every night and not tell me why.
I knew what was going on.
I talked to her and I talked to Celia, and
both of them just shook their heads.
But when I saw Jessie lying there, it didn't
surprise me at all.'
'I don't think it surprised anyone who knows
Celia,' I said, 'but that isn't evidence.'
He beat his hand against his knee.
'What can I do?
That's what I need you to tell me.
All my life I've never done anything because
of her.
And that's what she expects now - that I won't
do anything, and that she'll get away with
it.'
He stood up and stared at the door, then at
me.
'But I can do something,' he whispered.
'Do you know what?'
I stood up facing him and shook my head.
'Whatever you're thinking, put it out of your
mind,' I said.
'Don't confuse me,' he said.
'You know you can get away with murder if
you're as clever as Celia.
Don't you think I'm as clever as Celia?'
I held his shoulders.
'Don't talk like that, Charlie!'
He pulled away.
His eyes were bright and his teeth showed
behind his lips.
'What should I do?' he cried.
'Forget everything now Jessie is dead and
buried?
Sit here until Celia gets tired of being afraid
of me and kills me too?'
'You haven't been out of this house since
the inquest,' I said.
'It's about time you went out.'
'And have everybody laugh at me!' he said.
'Al Sharp said that some of your friends would
be at his bar tonight, and he'd like to see
you there,' I said.
'That's my advice - for whatever it's worth.'
'It's not worth anything,' said Celia.
The door had opened and she stood there, her
eyes narrowed against the light in the room.
Charlie turned towards her.
'I told you never to come into this room!'
he said.
Her face remained calm.
'I'm not in it.
I came to tell you that your dinner is ready.'
He took a threatening step towards her.
'Did you have your ear at the door long enough
to hear everything I said?' he asked.
'Or shall I repeat it for you?'
'I heard an invitation to go drinking while
this house is still in mourning,' she said,
'and I object to that.'
He looked at her, amazed.
'Celia, tell me you don't mean that!
Only the blackest hypocrite alive or someone
mad could say what you've just said, and mean
it.'
'Mad!'
she cried.
'You dare use that word?
Locked in your room, talking to yourself.'
She turned to me suddenly.
'You've talked to him.
Is it possible-?'
'He's as sane as you, Celia,' I said.
'Then he knows he shouldn't drink in bars
at a time like this.
How could you ask him to do this?'
'If you weren't preparing to throw out Jessie's
things, Celia,' I said, 'I would take that
question seriously.'
It was a dangerous thing to say, and I immediately
regretted it.
Before I could move, Charlie was past me and
was holding Celia's arms tightly.
'Did you dare go into her room?' he shouted,
shaking her.
And getting an immediate answer from her face,
he dropped her arms as if they were red hot,
and stood there with his head down.
'Where are her things?'
'By the stairs, Charlie.
Everything is there.'
He walked out of the room, and Celia turned
to look at me.
There was such terrible hatred in her face
that I desperately wanted to get out of that
house.
I took my things from the bed, but she stood
in front of the door.
'Do you see what you've done?'
she said in a rough whisper.
'Now I will have to pack them all again - just
because of you.
You old fool!
It should have been you with her when I-'
I dropped my stick sharply on her shoulder.
'As your lawyer, Celia,' I said, 'I advise
you to speak only during your sleep, when
you can't be made responsible for what you
say.'
She said no more, but I made sure she stayed
safely in front of me until I was out in the
street again.
It was only a few minutes walk to Al Sharp's
bar, and I was grateful for the clear winter
air in my face.
Al was alone behind the bar, polishing glasses.
'Merry Christmas,' he said, and put a comfortable-looking
bottle and two glasses on the bar.
'I was expecting you.'
Al poured two drinks.
We drank, and he leaned across the bar.
'Just come from there?'
'Yes,' I said.
'See Charlie?'
'And Celia,' I said.
'I've seen her too when she goes by to do
some shopping,' he said.
'Runs along with her head down, as if she's
being chased by something.
And I guess she is.'
'I guess she is, too,' I said.
'Did you tell Charlie I'd like to see him
some time?'
'Yes,' I said.
'I told him!'
'What did he say?'
'Nothing.
Celia said it was wrong for him to come here
while he was in mourning.'
Al whistled softly, and moved a finger in
circles at his forehead in a silent, 'crazy!'.
'Tell me,' he said, 'do you think it's safe
for them to be alone together?
The way things are, the way Charlie feels,
there could be more trouble there.'
'It looked like that for a while tonight,'
I said.
'But then it calmed down.'
'Until the next time,' said Al.
'I'll be there,' I said.
Al looked at me and shook his head.
'Nothing changes in that house,' he said.
'That's how you can work out all the answers.
That's how I knew you'd be standing here now
talking to me about it.'
I could still smell the dampness of the house,
and I knew it would take days to get it out
of my clothes.
'This is one day I'd like to take out of the
year permanently,' I said.
'And leave them alone with their problems,'
agreed Al.
'They're not alone,' I said.
'Jessie is with them.
Jessie will always be with them until that
house and everything in it is gone.'
Al frowned.
'It's the strangest thing that ever happened
in this town.
The house all black, her running through the
streets like something hunted, him lying there
in that room with only the walls to look at,
for -how long?
When was it Jessie had that fall?'
By moving my eyes a little I could see my
face in the mirror behind Al: red, deeply
lined, a little amazed.
'Twenty years,' I heard myself saying.
'Just twenty years ago tonight.'
- THE END -