CHAPTER ONE
My first home
The first place I can remember well was a
pleasant field with a pond of clear water
in it.
Trees made shadows over the pond, and water
plants grew at the deep end.
On one side was another field, and on the
other side we looked over a gate at our master's
house, which stood by the roadside.
At the top of our field were more tall trees,
and at the bottom was a fast-running stream.
While I was young, I lived on my mother's
milk, but as soon as I was old enough to eat
grass, my mother went out to work during the
day and came back in the evening.
There were six other young horses in the field,
although they were older than I was.
We all galloped together round the field,
and had great fun.
But sometimes the others would kick and bite.
'They are young farm horses and haven't learned
how to behave,' my mother told me.
'You are different.
Your father is well known, and your grandfather
twice won the most important race at Newmarket.
Your grandmother was quiet and gentle, and
you have never seen me kick or bite, have
you?
I hope you will grow up to be gentle and a
willing worker, and never bite or kick.'
I have never forgotten my mother's advice.
She was a clever and sensible old horse.
Her name was Duchess, but our master often
called her Pet.
He was a good, kind man, and my mother loved
him very much.
Whenever she saw him at the gate, she trotted
across.
He used to pat her and say, 'Well, old Pet,
and how is your little Darkie?'
I was a dull black colour, so he called me
Darkie.
He sometimes brought a piece of bread for
me, or a carrot for my mother, and I think
we were his favourites.
When I was two years old, something happened
which I have never forgotten.
It was early spring, and there was a light
mist over the trees and fields.
I and the other young horses were feeding
at the lower end of the field when we heard
the distant cry of dogs.
The oldest among us lifted his head to listen.
'There are the hounds!' he said, and immediately
raced off.
The rest of us followed him to the top of
the field, where we could see several fields
beyond.
My mother and another old horse were standing
near.
'They've found a hare,' said my mother, 'and
if they come this way, we shall see the hunt.'
Soon the dogs were all racing down the field
next to ours, making a loud 'yo-yo-yo-yo!'
sound at the top of their voices.
After them came men on horses, some in green
coats, and all galloping as fast as they could.
Suddenly, the dogs became silent and ran around
with their noses to the ground.
'They've lost the smell of the hare,' said
the old horse.
'Perhaps it will escape.'
But the dogs began their 'yo-yo-yo-yo!' again
and came at full speed towards our field.
Just then, a hare, wild with fear, ran towards
the trees.
The dogs jumped over the stream and ran across
the field, followed by the huntsmen.
Six or eight jumped their horses over the
stream, close behind the dogs.
Before the hare could get away, the dogs were
upon her with wild cries.
We heard a terrible scream, and that was the
end of the hare.
One of the men picked her up and held her
by the leg.
She was covered in blood, but all the huntsmen
seemed pleased.
I was so greatly surprised that at first,
I did not see what was happening by the stream,
but when I did look, I saw a sad sight.
Two fine horses were down, one in the stream
and the other on the grass.
One rider, who seemed unhurt, was climbing
out of the water, but the other lay quite
still.
'His neck is broken,' said my mother.
'I can't understand why men are so fond of
this sport.
They quite often hurt themselves and ruin
good horses, all for one hare that they could
get more easily some other way.
But we are only horses, and don't know why
men do these things.'
They carried the dead rider to our master's
house, and I heard afterwards that it was
George Gordon, the only son of a local landowner,
and a fine young man.
A man from the village came to look at the
black horse on the grass.
The animal was in great pain and one of his
legs was broken.
The man began to feel the horse all over,
then he shook his head.
Someone ran to our master's house and came
back with a gun.
Soon after, there was a loud bang and a terrible
cry, then all was still.
The black horse did not move again.
My mother was very unhappy.
'I've known that horse for years,' she said.
'His name was Rob Roy.
He was a good brave horse.'
She never went near that end of the field
again.
Not many days after, we heard the church bell
and saw a long, strange black carriage, pulled
by black horses.
They were taking the body of young George
Gordon to the churchyard to bury him.
He would never ride again.
I never knew what they did with Rob Roy, but
it was all for one little hare.
CHAPTER TWO
Birtwick Park
I was beginning to grow handsome.
My coat was fine and soft, and was a shiny
black.
I had one white foot, and a pretty white star
on my forehead.
When I was four years old, Mr Gordon came
to look at me.
He looked closely at my eyes, my mouth, and
my legs, and then I had to walk and trot and
gallop for him.
'When he has been trained,' Mr Gordon said
to my master, 'he will do very well.'
My master liked to train his horses himself
before selling them, and the next day my training
began.
To train a horse is to teach him to wear a
saddle, and to carry a man, woman or child
on his back.
The horse must also learn to wear a collar,
and to stand still when it is put on; then
to have a carriage fixed behind him, and to
go fast or slow, whichever his driver wishes.
He must never bite or kick or talk to other
horses, and must always do what his master
tells him, however tired or hungry he feels.
Like all horses that have grown up, I had
to wear a bit and bridle.
A bit is a great piece of cold hard metal,
as thick as a man's finger, which is pushed
into a horse's mouth between his teeth and
over his tongue, with the ends coming out
at the corners.
It is held there by straps, which go over
the horse's head, under his neck, round his
nose and under his chin.
Reins, which the rider holds, are fastened
to each end of the bit.
Slowly, with my master's kind words and gentle
ways, I learned to wear my bit and bridle.
Next, there was the saddle.
My master put it on my back very gently, then
fixed the straps under my body, speaking quietly
to me all the time.
Then one morning, he got on my back and rode
me round the field on the soft grass.
He did this every day until I was used to
it.
Then he took me to the village where a man
fixed metal shoes on to each hoof.
My feet felt heavy and strange, but I got
used to this, too.
There were more new things to wear.
First, a heavy collar on my neck, and a bridle
with great sidepieces against my eyes, called
blinkers.
With these on, I could only see in front of
me.
But in time I got used to everything, and
could do my work as well as my mother.
For a fortnight, my master sent me to a neighbour's
farm for another kind of training, which was
very useful to me.
One field was next to the railway and had
sheep and cows in it, and I was put in among
them.
I shall never forget the first train that
thundered by, and how I galloped to the far
side of the field, trembling with fear at
this terrible noise.
But after a few days I cared as little as
the sheep and cows when a train passed by.
It was early in May when a man came to take
me away to Mr Gordon's house.
My master said, 'Goodbye, Darkie.
Be a good horse, and always do your best.'
I put my nose into his hand and he patted
me kindly, and then I left my first home.
Mr Gordon's house, which was called the Hall,
stood in Birtwick Park, near the village.
We went into the Park through a large gate,
then trotted along a smooth road between some
trees to the house and gardens.
Beyond this were the stables.
There was room for many horses and carriages.
My stable had four good stalls and a large
window.
It was very pleasant.
The first stall was called a loose box, where
a horse is not tied up all the time but is
free to move around, as he likes.
It is a great thing to have a loose box.
The groom put me into it and gave me some
oats.
Then he patted me, spoke kindly, and went
away.
In the stall next to mine stood a little fat
grey pony.
'Hello,' I said.
'What is your name?'
'Merrylegs,' he said, turning round.
'I'm very handsome.
I carry the young ladies on my back, and sometimes
I take Mrs Gordon out in one of the carriages.
Are you going to live next to me in the box?'
'Yes,' I said.
'Then I hope you are well-behaved,' he said.
'I don't like anyone who bites.'
A horse's head looked over from the stall
beyond.
It was a tall brown mare, and she did not
look pleased.
'So it's you who has turned me out of my box,'
she said.
'I'm sorry,' I said, 'but the man put me in
here, so it is not my fault.
I don't want to argue with anyone; I just
wish to live in peace.'
Later, Merrylegs told me about the tall brown
mare.
'Ginger has a bad habit of biting people,'
he explained.
'One day, she bit James in the arm, and Miss
Flora and Miss Jessie, the children, were
afraid to come into the stable after that.
If you don't bite, I hope they'll start to
come again.'
I told him I never bit anything except grass
and could not understand why Ginger bit people.
'No one was ever kind to her before she came
here,' said Merrylegs.
'John and James do all they can to please
her, and our master is never unkind.
I'm twelve years old, and I know that there
isn't a better place for a horse all-round
the country than this.
John has been here fourteen years and is the
best groom there ever was.
And you never saw a kinder stable boy than
James.
There was no reason for Ginger to bite anyone.
It's her own fault that she did not stay in
the box.'
The name of the groom was John Manly.
The next morning, he got out his brushes and
gave me a good grooming, then put a saddle
on me.
He rode me slowly at first, then at a trot,
then at a gallop.
As we came back through the Park, we met Mr
and Mrs Gordon.
They stopped and John jumped off.
'Well, John, how does he go?' said Mr Gordon.
'He's a fine horse, sir,' said John.
'He's fast, but the lightest touch of the
rein will guide him.
They were shooting birds near Highwood, and
a gun went off close by.
He pulled up a little, but I just held the
rain and he wasn't frightened at all.
It's my opinion he was never frightened or
beaten when he was young.'
'Good,' said Mr Gordon.
'I'll ride him tomorrow.'
I remembered my mother's advice, and the next
day I tried to do exactly what my master wanted
me to do.
He was a very good rider, and when he came
home, his wife was waiting for him at the
door.
'How do you like him, my dear?'
she asked.
'I have never ridden a more pleasant horse,'
answered Mr Gordon.
'What shall we call him?'
'What about Blackbird like your uncle's old
horse?' said his wife.
'He's far handsomer than Blackbird,' said
Mr Gordon.
'Yes,' she said, 'he's quite a beauty, and
he has a kind, intelligent face.
Shall we call him Black Beauty?'
'Black Beauty - why, yes, I think that's a
very good name,' said Mr Gordon.
John went into the stable and told James.
'I'd call him Rob Roy,' said James, 'if it
did not remind everyone of the past.
I never saw two horses more alike.'
'That's not surprising,' said John.
'Didn't you know that Farmer Grey's old Duchess
was the mother of them both?'
So poor Rob Roy who was killed at the hunt
was my brother!
Now I understood why my mother was so unhappy
when he died.
John was very proud of me, and seemed to know
just how a horse feels.
And James was kind, too.
A day or two later, I went out in the carriage
with Ginger.
I wondered how we would get on together, but
I found it easy to trot along beside her.
Merrylegs was a happy little pony and was
everyone's favourite.
We were soon great friends and I became quite
happy in my new home.
CHAPTER THREE
Gingers story
What more could I want?
Freedom!
For the first four years of my life, I had
a large field where I could gallop around
at full speed - with no straps, no bit, and
no blinkers.
Now I stood in a stable, night and day, except
when I was wanted for work, and sometimes
when John took me out, I felt so strong, so
full of life, that I wanted to jump or dance.
'Calm down, boy!' he would say.
Then, as soon as we were out of the village,
he would let me trot fast for a few miles.
Some grooms punished a horse for getting too
excited, but not John.
He knew how to control me with only the sound
of his voice, and I was very fond of him.
Sometimes we did have our freedom in the field
for an hour or two.
This was on fine Sundays in the summer, because
the carriage never went out on Sundays.
It was wonderful.
The grass was cool and soft to our feet, and
the air was so sweet.
And we could gallop or lie down or roll over
on our backs, or do what we liked.
One day Ginger asked me about my old home
and my training.
When I finished telling her, she said, 'Life
has been different for me.
I was taken from my mother when I was young,
and there was no kind master like yours to
look after me.
I had a bad time when I was trained.
Several men caught me in a corner of the field
and one held my nose so hard that I could
only just breathe.
Then another pulled my mouth open to put the
bit in, and I was pulled along and beaten
from behind.
They didn't give me a chance to understand
what they wanted.
'The old master, Mr Ryder, knew about horses,
but he gave up most of the business to his
son, who was tall and strong, but not gentle.
They called him Samson, and he said that no
horse could throw him out of the saddle.
One day, he made me run round the field on
a long rein until I was very tired and miserable.
The next morning he did the same again, then
he put a saddle and bridle on me, and a new
kind of bit into my mouth.
'The new bit was very painful and I pulled
away and stood up on my back legs, which made
him very angry.
He stayed in the saddle and beat me with a
whip, but after a long and terrible battle,
I threw him off and galloped to the other
end of the field.
'I watched him go into the stable, but no
one came to fetch me.
Time went on and the sun was very hot.
I was hungry and very thirsty.
At last, just as the sun was going down, the
old master came out with some oats.
He spoke kindly and held out the oats for
me to eat, then patted me gently and looked
at the blood on my sides where Samson had
whipped me.
'"Poor girl!" he said, then led me to the
stable.
Samson was there.
"Keep out of the way," said the master.
"You've done a bad day's work for this horse
with your bad temper.
A bad-tempered man will never make a good-tempered
horse."
He led me into my box and took off my saddle
and bridle.
Then he called for some warm water and gently
cleaned the blood from my sides.
'After that, he often came to see me, but
a man called Joe went on training me.
He was quiet and thoughtful and I soon learned
what he wanted.
'After my training,' Ginger went on, 'I was
bought by a dealer to match another horse
of my colour.
But then we were sold to a man in London who
drove us with a bearing rein - a rein to hold
our heads up unnaturally high and to keep
them there, for hours and hours, until the
pain was terrible.
We had to wear two bits instead of one, and
mine was so sharp that it made my mouth bleed.
Sometimes we waited for hours while our master
or mistress was at parties or the theatre,
and if we weren't patient, the driver would
whip us.'
'Didn't your master care about you at all?'
I said.
'Only about how we looked,' replied Ginger.
'He knew very little about horses.
The driver told him I had a bad temper but
would soon get used to the bearing rein.
I was willing to work and learn, but they
were so cruel that it made me angry.
Then I broke away from the carriage one day,
and that was the end of that place.
'I was sold to another man, but he had a groom
as bad- tempered as Samson.
He hit me across the legs with his stable
brush if I didn't move quickly.
I hated him, and one day when he made me angry,
I bit him!
He never came into my stall after that, and
I was soon sold again.
'A dealer heard of me and said he thought
he knew one place where I should do well.
"It's wrong for a fine horse to go bad like
that," he said.
And I was brought here, not long before you
came.
Of course, it's very different here.
But who knows how long it will last?
I've decided that all men are my natural enemies.'
I was sorry for Ginger, but as the weeks went
on, she became happier and more gentle.
'I do believe Ginger is getting quite fond
of me,' James said one day.
'She'll be as good as Black Beauty one day,'
replied John.
'Kindness is all she needs, poor thing!'
CHAPTER FOUR
Kindness and cruelty
A neighbour of the Gordons', Mr Blomefield,
had a large family of boys and girls who often
came to play with Miss Jessie and Miss Flora.
One of the girls was the same age as Miss
Jessie, two of the boys were older, and there
were several little ones.
Whenever they came, the children loved to
ride Merrylegs.
One afternoon when they were visiting, James
brought Merrylegs in and said, 'Now, behave
yourself.'
'What did you do, Merrylegs?'
I asked him.
'Those young people didn't seem to know when
I was tired,' he said, 'so I just threw them
off backwards.
It was the only thing they could understand.'
'You threw the children off!'
I said.
'Oh, no!
Did you throw Miss Flora or Miss Jessie?'
'No, of course not!
I'm quiet and careful with them, and with
the little ones.
I'm the best friend and riding teacher those
children have.
It's not them, it's the boys,' he said.
'The other children rode me for nearly two
hours, then the boys rode me, one after the
other, for an hour, hitting me with a stick.
I didn't get annoyed but I did get tired,
so I stopped once or twice to let them know.
But boys think a horse is like a machine and
can go on as long and as fast as they want
it to.
They never think that we get tired.
As one was whipping me, I stood up on my back
legs and he fell off.
He got on again and I did the same.
Then the other boy tried and I put him down
on the grass.
They're not bad boys, and don't mean to be
cruel, but they have to learn.
'When they told James, he was angry to see
those big sticks and told the boys not to
use them again.'
'I would give those boys a good kick,' said
Ginger.
'I know you would,' said Merrylegs.
'But they expect me to look after those children,
and they expect me to be good- tempered, and
I will be.
You never had a place where they were kind
to you, Ginger, and I'm sorry for you.
But good places make good horses, and I wouldn't
make our people angry for anything!
If I started kicking people, they would very
quickly sell me, perhaps to someone cruel.
I hope that never happens.'
I often wondered why Sir Oliver, the oldest
horse in the stable, had so short a tail - only
about twenty centimetres long - and one day
I asked him, 'Did you have an accident?'
'It was no accident!' he said, angrily.
'My long and beautiful tail was cut off when
I was a young horse.
At that time, some owners thought it was fashionable!'
'How terrible!'
I said.
'Yes, terrible and cruel,' said Sir Oliver.
'Now I can never brush the flies off my sides
or back legs, and all because of fashion.
Some owners cut off the tails of their dogs
to make them look brave, or cut their pretty
little ears to make them look fashionable.
They don't cut off the ends of their children's
ears, do they?
Why do they think it's all right to do these
things to their animals?'
Mr Gordon was never cruel, and he would not
stand by and watch others be cruel to animals.
We were riding home one morning when we saw
a big man driving towards us in a small carriage,
pulled by a beautiful little pony.
As he got to the Park gates, the pony turned
towards them.
Without warning, the man pulled the pony's
head round so roughly that the little animal
almost fell over.
Then he began to whip the pony, angrily.
The animal tried to move forward, but the
man held it back and continued to whip it.
'Sawyer!'
shouted my master.
The man looked up.
He was a builder who often came to the Park
to do work.
'He's too fond of going his own way!' he told
my master.
'He's not supposed to turn in through your
gates; the road is straight on.'
'You often drive that pony to my house,' said
my master.
'It only shows that the horse is intelligent
and remembers these things.
How could he know you weren't going there
today?
I've never seen a horse beaten so cruelly
or with so much anger.
What will people think of you, Sawyer?
As well as hurting the horse, you hurt your
own good name - do you want people to think
of you as a cruel, bad- tempered man?'
We went home slowly, and I could tell by his
voice that the master was unhappy at what
we had seen.
CHAPTER FIVE
The storm
One day in the autumn, my master had to go
to a distant town on business.
John harnessed me to the carriage and the
three of us went off.
There had been a lot of rain, and the wind
was very strong.
When we came to the river, the water was so
high it nearly reached the wooden bridge,
and many of the fields were under water.
In one low part of the road, the water was
half-way up to my knees.
We got to the town and the master's business
took a long time.
It was late in the afternoon when we started
back for home.
The wind was much stronger, and as we drove
through a wood, I heard my master say, 'I've
never been out in a storm as bad as this,
John.'
Indeed, I thought so too, hearing the terrible
noise of that wild wind in the trees.
'I wish we were out of this wood,' said my
master.
'Yes, sir,' agreed John.
'We don't want one of those branches coming
down on top of us.'
But just as he finished speaking, there was
a great noise of wood breaking, and a big
tree came crashing down through the other
smaller trees and fell across the road right
in front of us!
I was very frightened and I stopped immediately,
but I didn't turn round or try to run away.
John jumped out and quickly ran to my side.
'What can we do now, John?' said my master.
'We can't drive over the tree or get round
it, sir,' said John.
'We'll have to go back to the crossroads,
and take the longer road round to the wooden
bridge.
It will make us late, but the horse isn't
tired.'
It was nearly dark when we got to the wooden
bridge.
We could see water over the middle of it,
but this often happened when the river was
high.
But the moment my feet touched the first part
of the bridge, I was sure something was wrong,
and I stopped suddenly.
'Go on, Beauty,' said my master, and he touched
me with the whip.
I did not move, so he hit me sharply, but
I would not go forward.
'There's something wrong,' said John, and
he jumped from the carriage and began to look
round.
He tried to lead me forward.
'Come on, Beauty, what's the matter?'
Of course, I could not tell him, but I knew
the bridge was not safe.
Just then, a man ran out of the house on the
other side of the bridge.
'Stop!'
Stop!' he cried.
'What's the matter?'
shouted my master.
'The bridge is broken in the middle,' said
the man, 'and part of it was carried away.
If you come across, you'll fall in the river!'
'Thank you, Beauty!'
John said to me, and turned me gently round
to the right-hand road by the riverside.
It got darker and the wind got quieter as
I trotted towards home by another, much longer
road.
The two men were quiet for some time, but
then my master spoke.
'We were very close to drowning in that river,
John,' he said.
'Men may be clever enough to think of things
for themselves, but animals know things without
thinking, and that's often saved a man's life,
as it has ours tonight.
People don't realize how wonderful their animals
are, nor do they make friends with them as
they should.'
When we arrived back at Birtwick Park, the
mistress ran out to meet us.
'I've been so worried!'
she said.
'Are you all right?
Did you have an accident?'
'We nearly did,' said my master.
'But Black Beauty was cleverer than we were,
and saved us all from drowning!'
One morning early in December, the master
came to the stable with a letter in his hand,
looking very serious.
'Good morning, John,' he said.
'Tell me, does James work hard and do what
you tell him to do?'
'Yes, sir, always,' replied John.
'And he doesn't stop work when your back is
turned?'
'Never, sir.'
'And if he goes out with the horses, does
he stop to talk to friends, or go into houses
where he has no business, leaving the horses
outside?' said the master.
'No, sir,' said John.
'And if anybody has said that about James,
I don't believe it.
I never had a pleasanter, more honest young
man in this stable.'
The master smiled and looked across at James,
who was standing by the door.
'James, I'm glad John's opinion of you agrees
with my own,' he said.
'I've had a letter from my wife's brother,
Sir Clifford Williams.
He wants me to find him an honest young groom
who knows what he's doing.
The man who drives his carriage is getting
old and needs a young man who will work with
him and be able to do his job one day.
How old are you?'
'Nineteen next May, sir,' said James.
'That's young.
What do you think, John?'
'It is young, sir,' said John, 'but he's tall
and strong.
He doesn't have much experience of driving,
but he has a light touch and a quick eye.'
'Well, James,' said the master, 'talk to your
mother at dinner-time and let me know what
you want to do.'
A few days later, it was agreed that James
would go to Clifford Hall in a month or six
weeks, and for the next few weeks, he drove
the carriage.
We went in and out of town, through busy streets,
and to the railway station, where the road
was narrow and there were lots of other carriages
hurrying to and from the station.
Then my master and mistress decided to visit
some friends who lived about seventy-five
kilometres from our home.
'You can drive us, James,' said my master.
CHAPTER SIX
The fire
The first day we travelled about fifty kilometres,
but James drove carefully and made sure that
Ginger and I were always on the smoothest
part of the road.
It was evening when we reached the hotel where
we were going to stay that night.
It was in the Market Place and two stablemen
came out to us.
The chief stableman was a pleasant old man,
and he led me into a long stable with six
or eight stalls in it, and two or three horses.
The younger man brought in Ginger, and James
watched while we were groomed.
'I thought I was quick,' James told the old
stableman, 'but you're quicker than anyone.'
'I've worked with horses since I was twelve
years old, and I can tell you it's good to
be able to work with a well- behaved, well-cared
for animal like this,' said the stableman,
patting my neck.
'Who is your master?'
'Mr Gordon of Birtwick Park,' said James.
'I've heard of him,' said the stableman.
'He's a good judge of horses, and the best
rider in this part of the country.'
'He doesn't ride very often now,' said James,
'not since the poor young master was killed.'
'I read about that in the newspaper,' said
the stableman.
'A fine horse was killed too, wasn't it?'
'Yes, an excellent horse,' said James.
'He was the brother of this one, and just
like him.'
'Terrible!' said the old man.
'It was a bad place to jump, wasn't it?
A man's life and a horse's life are worth
more than a hare - or they should be!'
Later that evening, the younger stableman
brought in another horse, and a young man
with a pipe in his mouth came into the stable
to talk to him.
'Towler, go up and get some hay and put it
down for this horse, will you?' said the stableman.
'But put down your pipe first.'
'All right,' said the other man, and went
up a ladder and through a little door.
I heard him step across the floor over my
head and push down some hay through a hole
in the roof, into the new horse's feeding
place.
James came in to look at us before he went
to bed, and then the door was locked.
I don't know how long I slept, or what time
it was when I woke up, but the air seemed
thick and I heard Ginger and another horse
moving about worriedly.
It was quite dark and I could see nothing.
The stable was full of smoke, and it was almost
impossible to breathe.
The smoke seemed to come from the little door
above me, and I could hear a strange noise
up there.
The other horses were now all awake, moving
about restlessly.
At last, I heard someone outside, and then
the younger stableman ran in with a light.
He began to untie the horses, and tried to
lead them out.
The first horse would not go with him, nor
the second or third.
He tried to pull me out, but he was so frightened
himself that he frightened me, and I would
not move.
The noise above was louder now and there was
a shout of 'Fire!'
outside.
The old stableman came in quietly and quickly
and got one horse out, then another.
By now, the flames were coming down through
the roof and the noise was terrible.
Then I heard James's voice, quiet and friendly
as it always was.
'Come on, Beauty,' he said, 'we'll soon get
you out of this smoke.'
He took off his scarf and tied it over my
eyes, then led me out, patting me all the
time.
He took the scarf off, then shouted, 'Take
this horse, somebody, while I go back for
the other!'
Windows in the hotel were open and people
were shouting.
I watched the stable door, where the smoke
came out thicker than ever.
Then I heard one voice above all the others,
and recognized it as my master's.
'James Howard!
James Howard!
Are you there?'
There was no answer, only the crash of something
falling in the stable - but the next moment
I saw James coming through the smoke, leading
Ginger with him.
'My brave boy!' said the master.
'Are you hurt?'
James shook his head, unable to speak because
of the smoke.
Suddenly, I heard the sound of wheels and
galloping horses.
'It's the fire-engine!'
shouted someone.
Two horses ran past me, pulling the heavy
fire engine.
The firemen jumped out, and we went quickly
into the wide, quiet Market Place, out of
their way.
The master led us to a large hotel on the
other side where a stableman came to take
us in; then the master hurried off to find
his wife.
The next morning, he came to see how we were
and to speak to James.
I did not hear much, but James looked very
happy and the master looked proud of him.
How did the fire start?
Someone said they saw Dick Towler go into
the stable smoking a pipe, but that when Dick
came out he didn't have it.
The young stableman said that he asked Dick
to go up the ladder to put down some hay,
but also told him to put down his pipe first.
Dick said that he did this, but nobody believed
him.
James said the roof and floor had all fallen
in and only the black walls were standing;
the two poor horses who could not get out
were buried under the fallen roof.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Joe Green
The rest of our journey was very easy, and
the next evening we reached the house of our
master's friend, where a groom took us to
a comfortable stable.
We stayed two or three days, then returned
home.
John was glad to see us, and we were glad
to see him.
'I wonder who will come in my place,' said
James.
'Little Joe Green,' said John.
'He's only fourteen and a half but he has
a kind heart and wants to come, so I've agreed
to try him for six weeks.'
The next day, Joe Green came to learn all
he could before James left.
He was a nice happy boy and always came to
work singing.
But then the day came when James had to leave
us.
'I'm leaving a lot behind,' he said sadly
to John.
'My mother, and you, a good master and mistress,
and the horses.
And I shan't know anybody at the new place.'
'It's hard to leave your home for the first
time,' said John, 'but if you get on well
- which I'm sure you will - your mother will
be proud of you.'
Everyone was sorry to lose James, but Joe
tried hard to learn, and John was pleased
with him.
One night I woke up to hear the stable bell
ringing loudly.
I heard the door open at John's house, and
his feet running up to the Hall.
He was back quickly.
'Wake up, Beauty!' he said, coming into the
stable.
'We must go quickly now!'
And before I could think, he had the saddle
on my back and the bridle on my head.
The master was waiting at the Hall door with
a letter in his hand.
'Ride for your life, John!' he said.
'Give this to Dr White, then rest your horse
and be back as soon as you can.
Mrs Gordon is very ill.'
Away went John and I, through the Park, through
the village, and down the hill.
There was a long piece of flat road by the
riverside, and John said, 'Now Beauty, do
your best!'
I needed no whip, and for two miles, I galloped
as fast as I could - perhaps even faster than
my grandfather, who won the race at Newmarket.
When we came to the bridge, John slowed me
down a little and patted my neck.
'Well done, Beauty!' he said.
Then I was off again, as fast as before.
The air was cold and the moon was bright,
and it was a pleasant night.
We went through a village, then a dark wood,
then uphill, then downhill, and after twelve
kilometres, we came to the town.
It was three o'clock when we stopped by Dr
White's door.
John rang the bell, then knocked on the door
like thunder.
A window was pushed up and Dr White's head
appeared.
'What do you want?' he said.
'Mrs Gordon is very ill,' said John.
'You must come at once, or she'll die.
Here's a letter.'
The doctor was soon at the door.
'My horse has been out all day and is exhausted.
Can I take yours?'
'My master told me to rest him,' said John,
'but take him if you think it's best, sir.'
'I'll soon be ready,' said the doctor.
John stood by me and patted my neck.
I was very hot.
Then the doctor came out with his riding whip.
'You won't need that, sir,' said John.
'Black Beauty will go until he drops.'
The doctor was a heavier man than John, and
not so good a rider, but I did my very best.
Joe was waiting at the gate and the master
was at the Hall door.
He did not say a word.
The doctor went into the house with him, and
Joe led me to the stable.
My legs were shaking and there was not a dry
hair on my body.
The water ran down my legs and I was hot all
over.
Poor Joe!
He was young and knew very little.
He did the best he could, cleaning my legs
and my chest, but he did not put a warm cloth
on me; he thought I was so hot that I would
not like it.
He gave me some cold water to drink, then
he gave me some food and went away.
Soon I began to shake and tremble with cold,
and I ached all over.
I wished John was there, but he had twelve
kilometres to walk, so I tried to sleep.
After a long time, I heard John at the door.
I gave a low cry, and he was at my side in
a moment.
I could not tell him how I felt, but he seemed
to know immediately.
He covered me with three warm cloths, then
ran for some hot water and made me a warm
drink.
John seemed very angry.
'Stupid boy!' he said to himself, over and
over again.
'No cloth put on, and I suppose the water
was cold too.
Boys are no good!'
I became very ill, and could not breathe without
pain.
John looked after me day and night, and my
master often came to see me too.
'My poor Beauty,' he said one day.
'My good horse, you saved your mistress's
life.
Yes, you saved her life.'
I was very glad to hear that.
John told my master that he never saw a horse
go so fast.
One night, Tom Green, Joe's father, came to
help John give me my medicine, then stayed
for a while.
At first, both men were silent, then Tom said,
'John, please say a kind word to Joe.
The boy is heart-broken; he can't eat his
meals, and he can't smile.
He knows it's his fault Beauty is ill, but
he did his best.
He says if Beauty dies, no one will ever speak
to him again.
But he's not a bad boy.'
After a short pause, John said, 'I know he
meant no harm, but I'm proud of that horse,
and I hate to think his life may be thrown
away like this.
But I'll give the boy a kind word tomorrow,
if Beauty is better.'
I heard no more of this conversation, as the
medicine did well and sent me to sleep, and
in the morning, I felt much better.
Joe learned quickly after this, and was so
careful that John began to give him many things
to do.
One day, John was out and the master wanted
a letter taken immediately to a gentleman's
house about five kilometres away.
He told Joe to saddle me and take it.
The letter was delivered and we were returning
through a field where we saw a cart full of
bricks.
They were so heavy that the wheels of the
cart were half-buried in the soft ground,
and the horses could not move the cart at
all.
The man leading the horses was shouting and
whipping them without stopping.
'Don't whip the horses like that,' Joe shouted
at him.
'The wheels are half-buried and won't move.
I'll help you take some bricks out to make
the cart lighter.'
'Mind your own business!' said the man angrily.
He was in a terrible temper and more than
half-drunk.
Joe turned me, and we galloped towards the
house of the brick maker, Mr Clay.
Joe knocked on the door.
The door opened.
'Hallo, young man,' began Mr Clay.
'There's a man in your field whipping two
horses to death!'
Joe told him, his voice shaking with anger.
'I told him to stop, but he wouldn't.
I offered to help him lighten the cart, but
he refused.
I think he's drunk.
Please go, sir!'
'I will!' said the man, and hurried off.
When we got home, Joe told John all about
it.
'You did the right thing,' said John.
'Many people would ride by and say it was
none of their business.
But cruelty is everybody's business.'
Just before dinner, the master sent for Joe.
The drunken man was accused of cruelty to
horses and Joe was wanted to tell his story
to the police.
'I'll tell it gladly,' said Joe.
We heard afterwards that the poor horses were
so exhausted and so badly beaten that the
man might have to go to prison.
Joe came across and gave me a friendly pat.
'We won't allow cruelty, will we, old friend?'
he said.
And he seemed to have grown up suddenly.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Earlshall Park
I lived at Birtwick Park for three happy years,
but then changes came.
Our mistress was often ill and the doctor
advised her to go and live in a warm country
for two or three years.
Everyone was very sorry, but the master immediately
started making arrangements to leave England.
John did his work silently and sadly, and
Joe didn't sing any more.
Then we heard that the master had sold Ginger
and me to an old friend of his, Lord Gray.
Merrylegs was given to the neighbour, Mr Blomefield,
and Joe was employed to look after him.
John was offered several good jobs but he
wanted to wait and look around.
'I want to train young horses,' he told the
master.
'I cannot think of anyone more suitable for
that work than you, John,' said the master.
'If I can help you in any way, write to me.'
The next morning, John took Ginger and me
to Earlshall Park where Lord Gray lived.
There was a very fine house and lots of stables.
John asked for Mr York, who was going to be
our new driver.
Mr York was a good-looking man of about forty,
with a voice that expected to be obeyed.
He called a groom to take us to our boxes,
then invited John to have a drink with him.
We were taken to a pleasant stable and put
in boxes next to one another, then we were
groomed and fed.
Half an hour later, John and Mr York came
to see us.
Mr York looked at us carefully.
'Is there anything you want to mention about
them, Mr Manly?' he said.
'I don't believe there's a better pair of
horses in the country,' said John, 'but they're
not alike.
The black one has the most perfect temper
I've ever known.
The other was badly treated before she came
to us, but has grown better- tempered in the
last three years.
We've never used a bearing rein with either
of them.'
'They'll wear one here,' said York.
'Lady Gray follows the fashion, and if her
horses are not reined up tight, she doesn't
like it.'
'I'm sorry to hear that,' said John.
He came to pat each of us for the last time.
I held my face close to him, which was all
I could do to say goodbye.
And then he was gone, and I have never seen
him since.
Lord Gray came to look at us the next day
and seemed pleased.
He heard what John had said about us.
'Keep an eye on the mare,' he said to York.
'Don't make the bearing rein too tight at
first, and I'll mention it to my wife.'
In the afternoon, we were harnessed to the
carriage and Lady Gray came out and looked
at us.
She was a tall, proud-looking woman and did
not look pleased, but she said nothing and
got into the carriage.
The bearing rein annoyed me but did not pull
my head any higher than I was used to carrying
it.
I was worried about Ginger, but she seemed
quite happy.
But the next afternoon when Lady Gray came
down the steps, she said, 'York, you must
put those horses' heads higher; they don't
look nice.'
'I'm sorry, my Lady,' said York, 'but they
have not been reined up for three years.
But if it pleases you, I can take them up
a little more.'
'Do that,' she said.
That day we had to pull the carriage up a
steep hill.
I wanted to put my head forward to make the
work easier, but I couldn't.
'Now you can see what it's like,' said Ginger,
when we came back.
'If it doesn't get any worse, I shall say
nothing.
But I won't have the rein pulled up tight!'
Each day the bearing reins were shortened
a little more; then one day Lady Gray came
out later than usual and said, 'York, when
will you get those horses' heads up.
Pull them up at once, and let's have no arguing.'
York came to me first and made the rein very
tight.
Then he went to Ginger.
But the moment he took off the rein in order
to shorten it, she stood up on her back legs.
York and the groom could not control her.
She kicked herself out of the carriage and
fell down, kicking me on the leg as she went.
York sat on her head to keep her still and
shouted, 'Let the black horse out!
Undo the carriage!
Cut the harness!'
The groom cut me out of the harness and hurried
me back to my box, then ran back to York.
I was angry and my leg hurt, and I felt that
I wanted to kick the first person who came
near me.
Soon after, Ginger was led in by two grooms.
York was with her and came to look at me.
'I knew those bearing reins would cause trouble,'
he said to himself.
He saw where I had been kicked and washed
the place gently with hot water to help the
pain.
Lord Gray was angry when he heard what had
happened.
He blamed York for taking orders from the
mistress, and York said that he would take
orders only from Lord Gray himself from now
on.
But things went on the same as before, except
that Ginger was never put into the carriage
again.
I pulled it with a horse called Max who was
used to the tight rein.
But those four months pulling Lady Gray's
carriage were terrible.
The sharp bit cut into my tongue and mouth,
the rein hurt my neck and made it difficult
to breathe, and I felt tired and very miserable.
In the spring, Lord Gray and some of his family
went up to London and took York with them.
Two daughters remained at the Hall.
Lady Harriet never went out in the carriage,
and Lady Anne preferred riding on horseback
with her brother or cousins.
She chose me for her horse and I enjoyed these
rides, sometimes with Ginger, sometimes with
Lizzie, a horse liked by the young gentlemen.
There was a gentleman called Blantyre staying
at the Hall, who always rode Lizzie and was
so pleased with her that Lady Anne wanted
to try her.
'I don't advise it,' said Blantyre.
'She's too easily frightened for a lady to
ride.'
'My dear cousin,' said Lady Anne, laughing,
'I've been riding horses since I was a baby
and have followed the hounds many times.
Now, help me up.'
So Blantyre helped her into the saddle, then
climbed on me.
Just as we were moving off, Lady Harriet asked
for a message to be taken to Dr Ashley in
the village.
The village was about two kilometres away,
and the doctor's house was the last one in
it.
Blantyre got off to open the gate for Lady
Anne but she said, 'I'll wait here for you.'
He went off and we waited.
There was a field with an open gate on the
opposite side of the road, and at that moment,
some young horses came trotting out.
They were wild and excited, and there was
a boy behind them, waving a large whip.
Suddenly, one of the young horses ran across
the road, and banged into Lizzie's back legs.
She gave a violent kick, nearly unseating
Lady Anne, and immediately galloped away at
full speed.
I gave a loud neigh for help and made a noise
with my feet until Mr Blantyre came running
out of the doctor's house.
He saw Lizzie and Lady Anne, now far away
down the road, and quickly jumped into the
saddle, and we raced after them.
For about two kilometres, the road was straight,
then it turned to the right before becoming
two roads.
Long before we came to the bend, Lady Anne
was out of sight.
Which way had she gone?
A woman was in her garden, looking up the
road.
'Which way?'
shouted Blantyre.
'To the right!'
cried the woman.
Away we went, up the right-hand road.
We saw her for a moment, then she was gone
again round another bend.
Several times, we saw her, but lost her again.
Then we came to some rough land, very uneven
and full of holes in the ground - the worst
possible place for galloping.
On this open ground, we could now see Lady
Anne clearly, her long hair flying out behind
her in the wind, and slowly we began to catch
up.
There was a wide ditch ahead and I was sure
it would stop them, but without a pause, Lizzie
jumped it - and fell.
I cleared the ditch and landed safely.
Lady Anne was lying on the ground, not moving.
Blantyre jumped down beside her and called
her name, but there was no reply.
Her face was white and her eyes were closed.
'Annie, dear Annie, do speak!' he cried.
There were two men cutting grass close by
and they saw Lizzie galloping away without
a rider and came across.
'Can you ride?'
Blantyre asked one of them.
'I'm not a good horseman, sir,' he said.
'But I'll do my best.'
'Ride this horse to the doctor's and ask him
to come immediately, then go on to the Hall,'
said Blantyre.
'Tell them all you know and ask them to send
a carriage.'
The man climbed into my saddle and we galloped
off.
I tried not to shake him about too much, and
he soon discovered that he needed no whip.
There was a lot of excitement at the Hall
when they heard what happened.
I was put into my box, the saddle and bridle
were taken off and a cloth was thrown over
me.
Two days later, Blantyre came and patted me.
'You did well,' he said.
'I'm sure you knew Annie was in danger.
She must ride only you from now on.'
From this, I knew that my young mistress was
out of danger and would soon be able to ride
again.
CHAPTER NINE
The accident and new masters
A man called Reuben Smith looked after us
while York was in London.
He was gentle and clever with horses, and
an excellent driver.
But he had one fault - he sometimes drank
too much.
For weeks or months, he was all right, but
then without warning he would begin to drink
heavily and behave badly.
But he was a useful man so York had kept quiet
about Smith's drinking, saying nothing to
Lord Gray.
Then one night Smith drove some ladies and
gentlemen home from a party and was so drunk
that he could not hold the reins.
York could not hide this and Lord Gray told
Smith to leave.
However, sometime later, York spoke again
to Lord Gray, who was very kind-hearted, and
he took Reuben Smith back.
Smith promised never to get drunk again and
kept his promise, and because of this, he
was told to look after the stables while York
was away.
One day the carriage needed some repairs so
it was arranged that Smith would take it to
town, leave it at the carriage-maker's, and
then ride me back again.
Mr Blantyre wanted to go to the station, so
he went with us.
At the station, Mr Blantyre gave Smith some
money and said, 'Take care of Lady Anne, Reuben,
and don't let anyone else except her ride
Black Beauty.'
We left the carriage at the maker's, and Smith
rode me to the White Lion hotel.
He told the stableman to give me some food
and have me ready for four o'clock.
One of my front shoes was loose but the stableman
did not see it until four o'clock.
Smith came back at five and said he would
now leave at six because he'd met some old
friends.
The stableman told him about the loose shoe.
'It'll be all right until we get home,' said
Smith.
He finally came back at nine o'clock, shouting
loudly and in a very bad temper.
We left and almost immediately, he began to
gallop, often giving me sharp cuts with the
whip, although I was going at full speed.
Before we were out of the town my shoe came
off, but Smith was too drunk to notice.
It was very dark, and on the rough road at
that speed, my foot was soon cut and bleeding
from the sharp stones.
I could not go on; the pain was too great,
and I fell violently on both my knees.
Smith was thrown off.
He tried to get up but couldn't, then he lay
still.
I could do nothing but wait.
It was nearly midnight when I heard a horse's
feet and the wheels of a carriage.
I neighed loudly, and was very happy to hear
an answering neigh from Ginger, and men's
voices.
Then the carriage came out of the darkness
and stopped.
Two men jumped down beside Smith.
'It's Reuben,' said one, 'and he's not moving,
Robert.'
'He's dead,' said Robert, touching Smith.
'His hands are cold and his head is covered
with blood.'
They looked at me and saw my cut knees.
'The horse has been down and thrown him!'
said Robert.
He tried to lead me forward but I almost fell
again.
'He's bad in the foot, too.
No wonder he went down, riding over these
stones without a shoe!
Reuben was drunk, Ned.
He would never ride a horse without a shoe
unless he was drunk.'
Ned took Smith's body back in the carriage,
and Robert tied his handkerchief round my
foot and led me slowly home.
No one blamed me for the accident.
The owner of the White Lion hotel said that
Reuben Smith was drunk when he left.
But I had to leave Earlshall, and so did Ginger.
For a month or two, I was allowed to live
out in a field, and one day Ginger was brought
in to join me.
She had been ruined by the hard riding of
Lord Gray's son, and after twelve months'
rest she was going to be sold.
And although my knees got better, they looked
very ugly and so I was no longer suitable
for a fashionable family.
It was very pleasant being in the field with
Ginger, but one day Robert came in and took
me away.
We were both very sad to say goodbye to each
other, Ginger and I.
I was sold to a man in Bath who kept many
horses and different kinds of carriages for
hire.
I was a 'job horse' and all kinds of people
hired me.
Some were good drivers, others were very bad.
Then one man persuaded my master to sell me
to a friend of his who wanted a safe, pleasant
horse for riding.
And so that summer I was sold to Mr Barry.
Mr Barry knew very little about horses but
he hired a comfortable stable for me, and
a man called Filcher to look after me.
He ordered the best oats, and plenty of other
good food for me to eat, too.
For a while, all went well, but then there
seemed to be fewer oats and more grass in
my meals.
The grass food, though very good, was not
enough to keep me strong and healthy.
However, I could not say anything and it went
on for about two months.
Then one afternoon my master rode into the
country to see a friend - a gentleman farmer
who knew about horses, and who looked very
closely at me.
'Your horse doesn't look as well as he did
when you first had him, Barry,' he said, feeling
my neck and shoulders.
'See how wet and warm he is - after just a
gentle ride!'
'My groom says that horses are never in good
condition in the autumn,' said my master.
'But this is only August!' said the farmer.
'With your light work and the good food, he
shouldn't be like this.
I don't know who eats your oats, my friend,'
he went on, 'but I doubt that your horse gets
any of them.
I advise you to watch your groom more closely.'
Oh, how I wanted to speak!
I wanted to tell my master where his oats
went to.
My groom came every morning at six o'clock,
bringing his little boy with him.
The boy carried a basket and went into the
room where the oats were kept.
I would see them filling a bag with oats and
putting the bag into the basket.
Five or six mornings after the visit to the
farmer, the boy left the stable with his basket
of oats, but came back soon after, looking
frightened, with two policemen holding his
arms.
'Show me where your father keeps the food
for his chickens,' one policeman said to the
boy.
The boy began to cry but there was no escape.
Moments later, the policemen found another
empty bag like the one in the boy's basket,
and they took Filcher away with them.
That was the last I ever saw of him.
Another groom was employed, but he was very
lazy about cleaning and I became thin and
unhealthy from standing in a wet, dirty stable.
After all this trouble with grooms, Mr Barry
decided to stop keeping a horse and I was
sent to a horse fair - a place where hundreds
of horses were bought and sold, and more lies
were told, I think, than in any other place
in the country.
That day I was lucky.
I was bought for twenty-five pounds by a man
called Jeremiah Barker, but everyone called
him Jerry and I shall do the same.
CHAPTER TEN
A London cab horse
Jerry Barker was a small man, but well-made
and quick in all his movements.
He lived in London and was a cab driver.
Jerry's wife, Polly, was a little woman with
smooth dark hair and dark eyes.
His son, Harry, was nearly twelve years old,
and was a tall, good-tempered boy.
His daughter, Dolly, was eight, and she looked
just like her mother.
Jerry had his own cab and two horses, which
he drove and groomed himself.
His other horse was a tall, white animal called
Captain.
The next morning, Polly and Dolly came to
see me.
Harry had helped his father since early that
morning and had already decided that I would
be a good horse.
Polly brought me a piece of apple and Dolly
brought me some bread.
'We'll call him Jack, after the old one,'
said Jerry.
'Shall we, Polly?'
'Yes,' she said.
'I like to keep a good name going.'
Captain went out in the cab all morning and
I went out in the afternoon.
Jerry took a lot of care to make sure that
my collar and bridle were comfortable - and
there was no bearing rein!
We went to the cabstand where the other cabs
were waiting for passengers, and took our
place at the back of the last cab.
Several of the other drivers came to look
at me.
'Too handsome,' said one.
'You'll find something wrong with him one
morning.'
Then a man in a grey coat and grey hat came
up.
His name was Grant, and he looked a happy,
sensible kind of man.
He had been longer on the cabstand than any
of the other men, so they let him through
to have a look at me, and waited for his opinion.
He looked me all over very carefully, then
said:
'He's the right kind for you, Jerry.
I don't care what you paid for him, he'll
be worth it.'
My first week as a cab horse was very hard.
I was not used to London - the noise, the
hurry, the crowds of horses, carts and carriages.
But Jerry was a good driver and soon discovered
that I was willing to work and do my best.
He never used the whip on me, and we soon
understood each other as well as a horse and
man can do.
Jerry kept his horses clean and gave us plenty
of food and fresh water, and on Sundays, we
rested.
I never knew a better man than my new master.
He was kind and good-tempered, like John Manly.
Harry was clever at stable work and always
wanted to do what he could.
Polly and Dolly came in the morning to brush
out the cab, and to wash the glass, while
Jerry gave Captain and me a grooming.
There was a lot of laughing and fun between
them, which all helped to keep Captain and
me happy.
The family came early in the morning because
Jerry did not like lateness.
It always made him angry when people wanted
him to drive hard because of their own lateness.
One day, two wild-looking young men called
to him.
'Cabby!
Hurry up, we're late for our train at Victoria.
Get us there in time for the one o'clock train
and we'll pay you double!'
'I will take you at the usual speed, gentlemen,'
said Jerry.
'Extra money doesn't pay for extra speed.'
Larry's cab was standing next to ours.
He opened the door and said, 'I'm your man,
gentlemen!
My horse will get you there all right.'
And as he shut them in, with a smile at Jerry,
he said, 'He always refuses to go faster than
a trot!'
Then, whipping his horse hard, he went off
as fast as he could.
Jerry patted me on the neck.
'Extra money won't pay for that kind of thing,
will it, Jack?' he said.
Although he was against hard driving to please
careless people, he always went at a fair
speed and was not against going faster if
there was a good reason.
I remember one morning we were on the stand
waiting for a passenger when a young man carrying
a large suitcase went by.
He stepped on a piece of apple, which lay
in the road, and fell down heavily.
Jerry ran across the road and helped him up,
then took him into a shop to sit him down.
Sometime later, the young man, looking white
and ill, came out again and called Jerry,
so we went across the road.
'Can you take me to the South-Eastern Railway?'
he said.
'My fall has made me late, and it's very important
that I don't miss the twelve o'clock train.
I'll pay you extra if you can get me there
in time.'
'We'll do our best, sir,' said Jerry, and
helped him into the cab.
It was always difficult to drive fast in the
city in the middle of the day, when the streets
were full of traffic, but Jerry and I were
used to it, and no one was faster at getting
through the carriages and carts, all moving
at different speeds, going this way and that
way.
In and out, in and out we went, as fast as
a horse can do it.
And we got to the station just as the big
clock showed eight minutes to twelve.
'We're in time!' said the young man, happily.
'Thank you, my friend, and your good horse,
too.
Take this extra money -'
'No, sir,' said Jerry.
'Thank you, but it isn't necessary.
I'm glad we were in time - now hurry and catch
your train.'
When we got back to the cabstand, the other
men were laughing because Jerry had driven
hard to the train.
'How much extra did he pay you, Jerry?' said
one driver.
'Nothing,' said Jerry.
'He offered me extra but I didn't take it.
If Jack and I choose to have a quick run now
and then, that's our business and not yours.'
'You'll never be a rich man then,' said Larry.
'Perhaps not,' said Jerry, 'but I'll be a
happy one!'
'And you, Larry,' added Mr Grant, 'will die
poor, because you spend too much money on
new whips, beating your poor horse until it's
exhausted - and then you have to buy another
one.'
'Well, I've never had good luck with my horses,'
said Larry.
'And you never will,' said Mr Grant.
'Good Luck is very careful who she travels
with, and mostly chooses those who are kind
and sensible.
That's my experience, anyway.'
He turned round again to his newspaper, and
the other men went back to their cabs.
Winter came early, with snow, rain or strong
winds almost every day for weeks.
Jerry sometimes went to a coffee shop near
the cabstand, and sometimes Dolly came with
some hot soup that Polly had made for him.
One cold windy day, Dolly was waiting for
Jerry to finish his soup when a gentleman
came towards us.
Jerry started to give the soup bowl back to
Dolly and was just going to take off my warm
cloth when the man said, 'No, no, finish your
soup, my friend.
I can wait in the cab until you've finished.'
Jerry thanked him, then came back to Dolly.
'That's a real gentleman, Dolly,' he said.
'He has time and thought for the comfort of
a poor cab driver.'
Jerry finished his soup, then we took the
man to Clapham.
After that, he took our cab several times,
and often came to pat me.
It was very unusual for anyone to notice a
cab horse, and I was grateful.
Another day, the gentleman saw a cart with
two horses standing in the street.
The driver was not with them and I don't know
how long they had been standing there.
However, they decided to move on a few steps.
Suddenly, the cart driver ran out of a building
and caught them.
He seemed very angry and began to whip the
horses hard, even beating them around the
head.
Our gentleman saw him and walked quickly across.
'Stop that at once or I'll call the police!'
he said.
The driver was drunk and he began to shout,
but he stopped whipping the horses.
Meanwhile, our gentleman wrote down the name
and address that was on the side of the cart.
'Why do you want that?'
shouted the driver.
Our gentleman didn't answer.
He came back to the cab.
'Many people have thanked me for telling them
how their horses have been used,' he told
Jerry.
'I wish there were more gentlemen like you,
sir,' said Jerry.
'They're needed in this city.'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Goodbye to old friends
One day we were waiting outside one of the
London parks when a dirty old cab drove up
beside ours.
The horse was brown, with bones that showed
through her coat.
I was eating some hay and the wind took a
little of it her way.
The poor animal put out her long thin neck
and picked it up, then turned and looked for
more.
There was a hopeless look in her dull eye
and I wondered where I'd seen her before.
Then she looked straight at me.
'Black Beauty, is that you?'
she said.
It was Ginger!
But how different she looked!
Her face, which was once so full of life,
was now miserable and full of pain, and her
breathing was very bad.
I moved closer to her so that we could have
a quiet talk, and it was a sad story that
she told me.
After twelve months' rest at Earlshall, she
was considered to be ready to work again,
and was sold to a gentleman.
She got on well for a little while, but after
a long gallop one day, she became ill again.
She was rested, was seen by a horse-doctor,
then sold.
In this way, she went from owner to owner
several times, each one poorer than the one
before.
'So at last I was bought by a man who keeps
a number of cabs and horses, and hires them
out,' said Ginger.
'You look happy and comfortable with life
as a cab horse, and I'm glad, but it's different
for me.
They whip me and work me seven days a week.
They say that they paid more for me than I
was worth, and now they're trying to get their
money back by working me until I drop.'
'You used to stand up and fight when people
were cruel to you,' I said.
'Yes, I did once,' said Ginger.
'But men are stronger than we are, and if
they're cruel and have no feelings, then there's
nothing we can do about it.
Oh, I wish the end would come.
I wish I was dead.'
I was very sad.
I put my nose against hers but could find
nothing to say that would cheer her up.
I think she was pleased to see me, because
she said, 'You're the only friend I ever had.'
A few weeks after this, a cart with a dead
horse in it passed by our cabstand.
It was a brown horse with a long thin neck,
and I believe it was Ginger.
I hoped it was, because then her troubles
would be over.
There was one day when we were very busy.
First, a fat gentleman with a large bag wanted
to go to Bishopsgate Station; then we were
called by a lady who wanted to be taken to
Regent's Park; then a man jumped into the
cab and called out, 'Bow Street Police Station,
quick!'
After another journey or two, we came back
to the cabstand and Jerry gave me some food,
saying, 'We must eat when we can on days like
this, Jack.'
And he took out the meat and bread Polly had
given him.
But neither of us had eaten many mouthfuls
before a poor young woman came along the street.
She was carrying a child and she looked lost
and worried.
'Can you tell me the way to St Thomas's Hospital,
please?'
she asked.
'I have to take my little boy there, and I'm
a stranger in London.'
The little boy was crying as she spoke.
'He's in great pain and can't walk, but the
doctor says that if I can get him to the hospital,
then perhaps he'll get well again.'
'You can't carry him through the crowds,'
said Jerry.
'It's five kilometres, and that child is heavy.'
'I'm strong,' said the woman.
'I think I can manage, if I know the way.'
'You can't do it.
Just get into this cab and I'll drive you
there.
Don't you see that it's beginning to rain?'
'No, sir, I can't do that,' she said.
'I've only just enough money to get me home
again.'
'Listen,' said Jerry.
'I've got a wife and children at home, and
I'd be ashamed of myself if I let a woman
and a sick child put themselves in danger.
Get in the cab and I'll take you for nothing.'
'Oh, how kind you are!' said the woman, and
began to cry.
Jerry opened the door but two men ran up,
calling out, 'Cab!'
'It's taken,' said Jerry, but one man pushed
past the woman and jumped in, followed by
the other.
'This cab is already taken, gentlemen,' Jerry
said again, 'by this lady.'
'Lady!' said one of the men unpleasantly,
looking at the woman's poor clothes.
'She can wait.
Our business is very important, and anyway,
we were in first, and we'll stay in.'
A smile came over Jerry's face as he shut
the cab door.
'Stay in as long as you like, gentlemen.
I can wait while you rest yourselves.'
He walked over to the young woman who was
standing nearby.
'They'll soon be gone, don't worry,' he said,
laughing.
And he was right.
When the two men realized that they were going
to have a very long wait, they got out, calling
Jerry all kinds of bad names.
After this, we were soon on our way to the
hospital.
'Thank you a thousand times,' said the young
woman, as Jerry helped her out of the cab.
'I hope your child will soon be better,' said
Jerry.
He watched her go in, then patted my neck.
It was something he always did when he was
pleased.
The rain was now coming down fast and, just
as we were leaving the hospital, a lady came
down the steps calling, 'Cab!'
Jerry seemed to know her at once.
'Jerry Barker, is it you?' said the woman.
'I'm very glad to find you here.
It's difficult to get a cab in this part of
London today.'
'I'll be proud to take you,' said Jerry.
'Where do you want to go?'
'Paddington Station,' said the woman.
We got to the station and went in under cover.
The lady stood beside the cab talking to Jerry
for some time, and I discovered that she was
once Polly's mistress.
'How do you like cab work in the winter?'
she asked Jerry.
'Polly was worried about your cough last year.'
'She worries because I work all hours and
in all kinds of weather,' said Jerry.
'But I get on all right, and I would be lost
without horses to look after.'
'It would be wrong to harm your health in
this work when you have a wife and two children,'
said the lady.
'There are many places where good drivers
or grooms are wanted.
If you ever decide to give up cab work, let
me know.'
She put something into his hand.
'There's some money for the children.'
Jerry thanked her and, after leaving the station,
we went home.
Christmas and the New Year are no holidays
for cab drivers and their horses.
People go to parties and dances, and the work
is often late.
Sometimes driver and horse have to wait for
hours, shaking with cold.
We had a lot of late work during Christmas
week and Jerry's cough was bad.
On New Year's Eve we took two gentlemen to
a house in the West End, and were told to
come for them at eleven o'clock.
'You may have to wait a few minutes, but don't
be late,' one of them said.
Jerry arrived at the right time and we waited.
The wind was very cold and it was snowing.
Jerry pulled one of my cloths higher over
my neck, then walked up and down, trying to
keep warm.
At half-past twelve, Jerry rang the doorbell
and asked if the gentlemen still wanted the
cab.
The man at the door said, 'Oh, yes, you'll
be wanted.'
At one o'clock, the door opened and two men
came out.
They got in the cab without a word, and told
Jerry where to drive.
It was three kilometres away, and when the
men got out they didn't say they were sorry
for the long wait, but they were angry when
Jerry made them pay for the extra waiting
time.
But it was money hard-earned.
When we got home, Jerry could not speak, and
his cough was terrible, but he groomed me
and made sure that I was warm and comfortable.
It was late the next morning before anyone
came, and then it was only Harry.
He cleaned us and gave us our food but was
very quiet.
Later that morning he came again, and this
time Dolly came with him.
She was crying, and I discovered from their
conversation that Jerry was dangerously ill.
Two days passed, and only Harry and Dolly
came to the stable.
On the third day, Mr Grant from the cabstand
arrived when Harry was in the stable.
'I won't go to the house, boy, but how is
your father?' he said.
'He's very bad,' said Harry.
'I'm sorry to hear that,' said Mr Grant.
'He's the best man I know.'
But when he came the next day, Harry was able
to tell him, 'Father is better today.
Mother hopes he will get over it soon.'
'Thank God!' said Mr Grant.
He was a kind man, and did a lot to help the
family during this time, because while Jerry
was ill, he was earning no money, and we all
had to eat.
Jerry got slowly better, but the doctor said
he must never do cab work again.
The children talked a lot about what their
mother and father would do, but a few days
later Dolly ran into the stable to find Harry.
'There's a letter from Mrs Fowler, mother's
old mistress!' said Dolly.
'She wants father to be her carriage driver,
and we're going to live in a cottage in the
country - with chickens, and apple trees,
and everything!'
This was bad news for me.
I was not young now, and could not hope for
a better master than Jerry, although Mr Grant
promised to find a comfortable place for me.
I never saw Jerry again and was very sorry
to leave.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Hard times
I was sold to a baker who Jerry knew, but
the baker's cart driver was a man called Jakes,
who drove with the bearing rein up.
This made it difficult for me to pull a heavy
cart, and I found the work very hard.
One day, after three or four months of this,
I was pulling the cart, which was much heavier
than usual, up a steep hill.
I had to stop several times to rest, which
didn't please Jakes.
'Move on, you lazy horse, or I'll make you!'
he shouted, and he hit me with his whip.
After a few more metres, I had to stop again.
The whip came down across my back once more
and the pain was sharp.
I was doing my best but the driver was still
punishing me cruelly, which seemed very unfair.
Jakes was whipping me a third time when a
woman hurried over and said, 'Oh, please don't
whip your horse like that.
I think I can help, if you'll let me.'
Jakes laughed.
'Oh?'
'He can't use all his strength when his head
is held back with that bearing rein,' the
woman went on.
'If you take it off, I'm sure he'll do better.'
'Anything to please a lady,' said Jakes, smiling.
The rein was taken off and I moved my head
up and down several times to help my aching
neck.
'Poor boy is that what you wanted?' said the
woman, patting me.
She turned to Jakes.
'If you speak to him kindly and lead him on,
I believe he'll do better.'
Jakes took the rein, and I put down my head
and moved on.
I pulled the cart up the hill, then stopped
to take a breath.
'Well, that helped,' said Jakes, 'but if I
went without a bearing rein all the time,
the other cart drivers would laugh at me.
It's fashionable, you see.'
'It's better to start a good fashion than
to follow a bad one,' said the woman.
'Many gentlemen don't use bearing reins now.'
She gave me another pat on the neck and walked
on.
After that, Jakes always took off my bearing
rein when I was going up a hill, and that
made my life easier.
But pulling heavy carts day after day slowly
began to exhaust me and a younger horse was
brought in to do my work.
I was sold to another cab owner whose name
was Nicholas Skinner.
He was hard on his drivers, and they were
hard on the horses.
We worked long hours, had no Sunday rest,
and it was a hot summer.
My driver was just as hard as his master,
and he had a cruel whip with something sharp
at the end which often cut me and made me
bleed.
It was a terrible life, and sometimes, like
poor Ginger, I wished I was dead.
One day I nearly got my wish.
We were at the railway station when a family
of four people hired us.
There was a noisy man with a lady, a little
boy, a young girl, and a lot of heavy luggage.
'Father,' said the young girl, 'this poor
horse can't take us and all our luggage.
He's too tired.'
'Oh, he's all right, miss!' said my driver.
He put a heavy box on the cab with the other
luggage.
'Father, please take a second cab,' said the
girl.
'I'm sure this is very cruel.'
'Grace, get in at once, and don't be stupid,'
said her father.
'The driver knows his own business.'
My gentle friend had to obey, and box after
box was lifted up and put on the top of the
cab, or next to the driver.
Then the driver hit me with his whip and we
moved out of the station.
The cab was very heavy and I had not eaten
or rested since early that morning.
I did my best and got along quite well until
we came to Ludgate Hill.
By then I was exhausted, and the heavy cab
was too much for me.
My feet went from under me and I fell heavily,
knocking all the breath out of me.
I lay quite still because I could not move.
Indeed, I expected to die.
There were angry voices above me and luggage
was taken off the cab, but it was all like
a dream.
I thought I heard the girl's voice saying,
'Oh, that poor horse!
It's all our fault!'
Someone loosened my bridle and collar, and
another voice said, 'He's dead, he'll never
get up again.'
I heard a policeman giving orders but I did
not open my eyes.
Cold water was thrown over my head, some medicine
was put into my mouth, and I was covered with
a cloth.
I don't know how long I was there, but a man
with a kind voice persuaded me to try to get
up - and I managed it.
Then I was gently led to some stables close
by.
That evening, I was taken back to Skinner's
stables, and the next morning the horse-doctor
came to see me.
'He's been worked too hard,' said the doctor.
'There's no strength left in him.'
'Then he must go for dog food,' said Skinner.
'I have no fields for sick horses.
It doesn't suit my business.
I work them for as long as they'll go, then
I sell them for what I can get.'
'There's a horse fair in ten days' time,'
said the doctor.
'If you rest him and give him food, he may
get better, and then you may get more than
his skin's worth.'
Luckily, for me, Skinner took the doctor's
advice and, after rest and food, I began to
feel better.
Ten days later, I was taken to the horse fair,
a few miles outside London.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
My last home
I was sold to a farmer at the horse fair,
but it was his young grandson who persuaded
him to buy me.
The two of them walked past me and, seeing
kindness in the farmer's face, I lifted my
head, put my ears forward and tried to look
my best.
The farmer stopped and looked at me.
'There's a horse, Willie, that has known better
days,' he said.
'Poor thing!' said the boy.
'Do you think he was ever a carriage horse,
grandfather?'
'Oh, yes,' said the farmer.
'Look at his fine head and the shape of his
neck and shoulder.'
He reached out a hand and patted me on the
neck.
I put out my nose in answer to his kindness,
and the boy gently put his hand against my
face.
'Look how well he understands kindness,' said
the boy.
'Won't you buy him, and make him young and
strong again?'
The man who was selling me said, 'The boy
can recognize a good horse, sir.
This one isn't old, just tired and thin from
too much work.
In six months, he'll be fine.'
Five pounds changed hands and, soon after,
I was taken to my new home.
The farmer gave orders for me to have hay
and oats every night and morning, and I was
let out into a large field in the daytime.
Willie, the young boy, was responsible for
me, and he came to see me every day, bringing
carrots or apples.
During that winter, the rest, the good food,
the soft grass and gentle running and trotting
all helped to make me feel quite young again.
When the spring came, the farmer tried me
with a carriage, and I did the work quite
easily.
'He's growing young, Willie,' he said.
'We'll give him some gentle work and look
for a good home for him.'
One day during this summer, the groom cleaned
and dressed me with special care, and Willie
seemed half-worried and half-excited as he
got into the carriage with his grandfather.
'I hope the ladies like him,' said the farmer.
A kilometer or two beyond the village, we
came to a pretty house, and Willie went to
knock on the door.
He asked if Miss Blomefield and Miss Ellen
were at home.
They were, and Willie stayed with me while
the farmer went into the house.
He came back about ten minutes later with
three ladies.
They seemed to like me, but one of them, worried
by my knees, wondered if I was safe.
'It's true his knees were broken once,' said
the farmer, 'but we don't know why he fell.
It was probably a careless driver and not
the horse's fault at all.
He seems very safe to me.
If you like him, you can try him for a few
weeks,' he went on.
'Then your driver will see what he thinks
of him.'
One of the three ladies - a tall, white-faced
lady, who held the arm of a younger woman
- said, 'You have always given us good advice
about our horses, so we accept your offer
to try him.'
The next morning, a young man came for me.
He looked pleased until he saw my knees, then
he said, 'I'm surprised you suggested this
horse to my ladies.'
'You're only taking him to try him,' said
the farmer.
'If he's not as safe as any horse you ever
drove, send him back, young man.'
I was taken to a comfortable stable, given
some food, then left to myself.
The next day, the groom was cleaning my face
when he said, 'That's just like the star that
Black Beauty had on his forehead.
I wonder where he is now.'
He looked more closely at me.
'White star on the forehead, one white foot
- and a little white place on his back!
It must be Black Beauty!
Beauty!
Do you know me?
I'm little Joe Green, who almost killed you!'
And he began patting me all over my back.
I could not say I remembered him, as he was
now a fine young man with a black moustache
and a deep voice.
But I was sure he knew me, and that he was
Joe Green, and I was very glad.
I put my nose up to him and tried to say that
we were friends.
I never saw a man so pleased.
That afternoon, I was harnessed to a carriage
for Miss Ellen to try me.
Joe Green went with her and told her that
he was sure I was Mr Gordon's old Black Beauty.
'I shall write to Mrs Gordon and tell her
that her favourite horse has come to us,'
said Miss Ellen.
'How pleased she will be!'
I have now lived in this happy place a whole
year.
Joe is the best and kindest of grooms.
My work is easy and pleasant, and I feel my
strength coming back again.
The ladies have promised that they will never
sell me, and so I have nothing to fear; and
here my story ends.
My troubles are all over, and I am at home;
and often, before I am quite awake, I dream
I am still in the field at Birtwick, standing
with my old friends under the apple trees.
- THE END -