PART ONE
John 'Jack' Sheppard - Housebreaker and escape
artist
CHAPTER ONE
A Life of Crime
John Sheppard was a thief and highwayman,
but he became a very popular figure in his
lifetime because of his extraordinary courage.
At least two plays were written about him,
and society was fascinated by his life and
adventures.
John Sheppard's father was a carpenter in
a poor part of London called Spitalfields.
He had two sons, John, who was born in 1702,
and Thomas.
John was always known as Jack.
The two brothers both became famous robbers.
Jack was the first of the two brothers to
begin a life of crime.
He worked for a carpenter in London, but he
soon began to spend a lot of time at the Black
Lion pub in Drury Lane.
It was here that he met a woman called Elizabeth
Lyon, but more commonly known among her friends
as Edgeworth Bess.
Jack fell under her influence and they formed
a partnership.
'I can make you rich,' she told him.
'How?' he asked her.
'Listen,' she said.
'You're a carpenter.
You work in rich people's houses.
That gives you the perfect opportunity to
steal valuable objects.'
At first Jack was very successful and no one
suspected him of the robberies that were taking
place in the houses where he worked.
He stole valuable items for Edgeworth Bess
and she sold them for him.
Jack also had another woman friend named Maggot,
and she persuaded him to rob a local merchant,
Mr Bains, who was a trader in valuable cloth.
First Jack went to Mr Bains' house and bought
some cloth in order to see what the house
was like inside.
He went home and put the piece of cloth in
his trunk.
The same night he returned secretly to the
house.
He broke in and stole money and other property,
which he then took to Maggot.
Jack did not go back to his master's home
that night, or the next, and his master began
to be suspicious of the young man's activities.
He decided to open Jack's trunk to see what
was inside.
He found the piece of cloth that Jack had
bought from Mr Bains.
When Jack finally returned home, he realised
that his master now had evidence that connected
him with Mr Bains.
So Jack stole the piece of cloth back from
his employer and hid it.
When Jack's master heard about the robbery
at Mr Bains' house, he was sure that Jack
was involved.
He contacted Mr Bains and described the piece
of cloth that he had seen in Jack's trunk.
Mr Bains knew immediately that Jack was the
young man who had bought the cloth, and he
too guessed that the purchase of the cloth
was a trick to enter his house.
When Jack heard that he was suspected, he
pretended to get very angry.
'I haven't stolen anything,' he shouted.
'My mother gave me that piece of cloth!'
'Did she?'
Mr Bains said.
'And where did she get it from?'
'Ask her yourself,' Jack said.
'I think I will,' his master replied.
Jack's master sent for the boy's mother and
asked her about the cloth.
'My son's telling the truth,' she said.
'I bought the cloth at a market in Spitalfields.'
'Where exactly in the market did you buy it?'
the master asked.
'I don't remember,' Jack's mother said.
Jack's master and Mr Bains did not believe
what Jack and his mother told them, but they
had no direct evidence against Jack for the
robbery.
Despite his suspicions of him, Jack's master
decided to let the boy continue to work for
him as an apprentice.
Jack became more and more involved in crime,
and he finally became part of a gang led by
Jonathan Wild, another famous criminal.
He now worked for himself as a carpenter and
this meant that he continued to have easy
entrance to rich people's houses.
In one case he was repairing a house belonging
to an elderly gentleman in a rich area of
London.
He robbed the gentleman of money, jewellery
and expensive clothes.
Shortly after this robbery Edgeworth Bess
was arrested and sent to a local prison.
Jack went to the prison and demanded to see
his friend.
When the prison officer refused him permission,
Jack attacked him and went in.
'You're coming with me,' he told Edgeworth
Bess.
'What do you mean?'
she asked him.
'I'm a prisoner here.
I can't come with you!'
'Yes, you can!'
Jack told her with a laugh.
'I knocked the officer out - he won't give
us any trouble now!'
He picked up Bess and carried her out of the
prison.
This episode made him very popular with the
criminal world in London, especially with
the women.
The brothers, Tom and Jack, worked together,
robbing houses and selling the items that
they had stolen.
They also continued to work with Edgeworth
Bess.
They broke into the house of a merchant, Mrs
Cook, and stole some valuable items.
Tom tried to sell them but he was arrested
and taken to Newgate prison, where some of
London's most notorious criminals were kept.
He offered to give evidence against his brother
Jack and Edgeworth Bess in order to receive
a lighter punishment.
The authorities looked everywhere for Jack
and Edgeworth Bess, but they could not find
them.
One day Jack met a friend of his in the street,
a man called James Sykes.
Sykes knew that the authorities were looking
for Jack, and he made a plan.
He hoped to get a lot of money for capturing
Jack.
He took Jack into a pub and bought him a lot
of beer.
While Jack was happily drinking, Sykes sent
for a constable.
The constable arrested Jack and took him to
prison.
Jack waited until the middle of the night
and then made a hole in the roof of the prison
and escaped.
Jack's freedom did not last long.
He was soon arrested again, and this time
he and Edgeworth Bess were taken to another
prison.
The authorities thought that Jack and Bess
were husband and wife, and they allowed them
to live together in a room in the prison called
Newgate Ward.
A few days after their arrival at the prison,
Jack managed to cut off his iron chains.
He then made a hole in the prison wall, and
removed one of the iron bars from the window.
He looked down and saw that it was too far
to jump to the ground.
So he tied some sheets together, and tied
one end around a bar in the window.
Then he helped Edgeworth Bess to climb down
to the ground, and he quickly followed her.
They were now in front of a high prison wall,
but they managed to climb over it and escape
into the city.
The criminal class of London enjoyed hearing
about Jack's adventures and he became a hero
to them.
One criminal, Charles Grace, asked if he could
work with Jack, and Jack agreed.
Charles and Jack made friends with a young
man called Anthony Lamb, who worked for a
maker of mathematical instruments.
They planned to rob a wealthy gentleman who
lived in the instrument maker's house.
Late one night Lamb opened the door of the
house and let Jack and Charles in and they
stole a lot of money.
When the robbery was discovered the next morning,
Anthony Lamb was very frightened.
His master sent for him and asked what had
happened.
'I don't know, sir,' Lamb replied.
His master looked at him suspiciously.
He saw that the young man's hands were shaking.
'I don't believe you,' he said angrily.
'I think you stole the money, and you'll be
hanged for it!'
In the end Lamb confessed his involvement
in the crime.
He was sent to Newgate prison, tried, and
then transported.
Thomas Sheppard was also tried for the robbery
of Mrs Cook and he was transported as well.
Jack Sheppard then started working with another
famous criminal, a man called Blueskin.
They sometimes sold the items that they had
stolen to a man called William Field.
Meanwhile, they hired a stable in which they
kept what they had stolen before selling it.
Among the other stolen items in the stable
was a length of cloth that had been taken
from a certain Mr Kneebone.
It was stealing this piece of cloth that led
to Jack's next arrest.
One day Jack and Blueskin asked William Field
to go to their stable and look at the items
they had, so that he could find buyers for
them.
Field, who was a coward but an imaginative
criminal, did more than that.
He broke into the stable and stole everything.
Then he went to Jonathan Wild, knowing his
influence in the criminal world, and told
him that Jack was working with Blueskin.
Jack and Blueskin were arrested soon after
and sent to Newgate prison, where they were
tried for their robberies, and Jack was sentenced
to death for the theft of the cloth belonging
to Mr Kneebone.
CHAPTER TWO
Great Escapes
An order for the execution of Jack Sheppard
arrived at Newgate prison on Monday 30 August
1724.
Once again Jack showed his extraordinary courage.
There was a place in the prison where friends
could come to talk to the prisoners.
The visitors and the prisoners were separated
by a hole in the wall that had bars in it.
Jack loosened one of the bars.
When some women friends came to visit him,
he broke the bar off the wall completely and
the women pulled him through the hole.
He was a free man once again.
Jack went to see a friend of his called Page,
and they went into the country for a week.
On their return to London they passed a watchmaker's
shop.
They were surprised to see that the shop was
open, but that there was only a boy guarding
it.
Jack immediately broke the shop window and
pulled out some valuable watches.
Jack's friends now knew that he was back in
London, and they warned him that the authorities
were looking everywhere for him.
They eventually found where he was hiding
and took him back to Newgate prison.
This time they were determined to stop him
escaping.
'You've been very lucky in the past,' one
of the officers told him, 'but you're not
going to escape from us again.
We'll make sure it's impossible!'
They put iron chains on his legs and handcuffs
on his wrists.
The chains on his legs were attached to a
ring in the floor of his prison cell.
His adventures had by now made Jack famous
with all social classes, and many important
people came to visit him.
Some of his visitors gave him money.
'Who knows if he'll try to escape again,'
they thought.
Sheppard found a nail in the room, which he
used to open the lock that attached his chain
to the ring in the floor.
Then he used the same nail to open his handcuffs.
He could not remove the chains, but he pulled
them as high up his legs as he could.
His next move was to climb the chimney in
the room, but his way was blocked by an iron
bar.
He then worked with his hands to free the
iron bar.
He climbed back up the chimney and made his
way into the room above.
No one had used this room for many years and
the door was locked, but it did not take Sheppard
long to break it.
He then went into the prison chapel and climbed
onto the roof of the prison.
He looked down, and saw that the nearest building
was a long way below him.
If he jumped, it would be very dangerous.
He went back to his original cell and took
the blanket from the bed.
Then he went back onto the roof.
He tied one end of the blanket to the roof
of the prison, and then climbed down to the
neighbouring house.
It was midnight by now, and Sheppard was exhausted
after his escape.
He walked to the edge of the city and found
a stable where he slept for some hours.
It was raining when he woke up and he was
cold and hungry.
He bought some food from a little shop nearby
and returned to the stable.
Next he tried to remove the chains from his
legs by hitting them with a stone.
Two long, miserable days passed.
Finally, a shoemaker passed by the stable
and Sheppard asked him to help remove the
chains, offering to pay the man twenty shillings.
The shoemaker agreed, and by five o'clock
that afternoon Sheppard was able to walk freely.
He tore his clothes to make himself look like
a beggar and walked back to London.
He stayed in a poor tavern in the city and
talked to the landlady about the adventures
of Jack Sheppard.
'I hope he escapes again,' the woman said.
'He's a brave young man!'
'So do I,' Jack replied.
'He might do it, too!'
Jack then walked around the streets, where
he heard two ballad singers singing about
his adventures.
A few nights later he broke into a shop in
Drury Lane and stole some fine clothes, a
sword, rings, watches and other items.
He put on the stolen clothes and went to find
his old friends.
He ate in taverns with his friends, and he
even visited his mother to tell her that he
was free once more.
He celebrated his new freedom by drinking
a lot of wine and brandy.
At midnight, the boy who worked in the tavern
where Jack Sheppard was entertaining his friends
recognised who he was.
The boy called the authorities and they arrested
Sheppard and took him back to Newgate.
Up until the end Jack Sheppard hoped to escape
his death at Tyburn.
He hid a sharp knife in his pocket on the
journey to the place of execution, but an
officer discovered it and took it away from
him.
He had another plan for survival.
'After they hang me,' he told his friends,
'you must put me into a warm bed and open
a vein in my arm.
I'm sure this will help me recover from the
hanging.'
He behaved with courage and dignity at the
execution, and confessed his crimes.
He was executed on 21 November 1724.
PART TWO
John Gow-Captain of famous gang of pirates
CHAPTER ONE
The Life of a Pirate
John Gow, the man who became known as the
'Orkney Pirate', was born in 1698 and grew
up in the North of Scotland, on one of the
Orkney Islands, where he became a sailor.
He was very good at his profession and soon
became third-in-command of a ship sailing
for Santa Cruz.
The crew of the ship were very unhappy with
their conditions on board, and complained
particularly about the food.
The captain did not take their complaints
seriously at first, but he soon changed his
mind.
He realised that the crew were preparing to
take over control of the ship, and called
the chief mate.
'I think we may have some trouble with the
men,' the captain explained.
'I want you to put some pistols in the cabin.'
'Yes, sir,' the chief mate replied.
Two members of the crew heard the conversation
and they told John Gow about the captain s
preparations.
Gow, who had always wanted to become a pirate,
thought about what to do.
'If you take control of the ship, I'll help
you,' Gow told the men.
But I want to be the new captain!'
Gow was excited.
It looked as if his secret desire to be a
pirate was really going to happen!
That night a group of rebel sailors attacked
the senior officers of the ship, murdering
the doctor, the chief mate and then the captain.
They elected John Gow the new captain of the
ship.
Not all of the crew had been involved in the
mutiny, and the innocent men were now hiding,
frightened that they might be killed too.
'Nothing will happen to you if you continue
to obey orders as you did before the mutiny,
but now I'll give the orders!'
John Gow told the men.
The sailors agreed.
The rebels decided to change the name of the
ship from the George Galley to the Revenge.
They left for Spain and Portugal, where they
hoped to steal a large quantity of wine.
During the journey they discovered a British
fishing ship, which they decided to attack
and capture.
They sailed very close to the ship and Gow
shouted his commands to the other captain.
'We're pirates and we're going to capture
your ship,' he shouted.
'It's useless to resist us.
If you try, we'll kill all of you!'
'We won't fight,' the other captain shouted
back.
'Come and take what you want.'
They had no use for the cargo or the ship,
so they sank the ship and kept its captain
and four of his men on the Revenge.
They then attacked a Scottish fishing ship.
Once again they sank the ship and took the
men onto the Revenge.
By now they did not have much drinking water,
so they decided to go to the Portuguese island
of Madeira.
They anchored some distance away from the
harbour and made a plan.
Seven men left for the harbour in a small
boat.
Their instructions were to capture a ship
and bring it out of the harbour.
If they could not do this, they had to steal
wine and water and bring it back to the Revenge.
This attempt failed, however, and they decided
to leave Madeira.
They sailed about ten miles along the coast
until they reached a small town, Port Santa.
Gow sent some men to the town with a present
of fish for the governor.
The governor treated them very politely and
visited the Revenge as a guest.
Gow and the rebels entertained the governor
and his friends very well at first.
Later, however, when the boat they had sent
to the island for food and drink came back
without any, Gow threatened the governor and
his friends.
'We want food and wine,' he told the governor
and his friends.
'If you don't get it for us immediately, we'll
kill you!'
The governor was very surprised and frightened.
'I'll make sure you get food and wine,' he
said.
'There's no need to kill anyone.'
The pirates then left for the coast of Spain,
where they found a British ship carrying slaves.
They captured the ship and put on board all
the men they had taken from other captured
ships.
Then they took all the food and drink from
the ship and allowed it to continue on its
way.
They next captured a French ship, which had
a cargo of wine, oil and fruit.
The pirates stole the goods and gave this
ship to the Scottish captain whose fishing
ship they had sunk, and he took his men on
board with him.
Gow was delighted with his crew.
'Well done, men!' he cried.
'If we go on like this, we'll all be rich
men!'
The pirates cheered their captain.
Soon they saw another French ship approaching.
It was a large ship and had thirty-two guns,
so Gow called his crew together to discuss
tactics.
He told them it was too dangerous to risk
attacking a ship with so many guns.
All the crew agreed with him except lieutenant
Williams, who was a violent, dangerous man.
'You're not brave enough to be in command
of a pirate ship,' Williams told him.
'We should attack this ship, capture it, and
throw all its men into the sea!'
Gow looked angrily at the lieutenant.
'I say that it's too dangerous to attack that
ship,' he replied.
'And I won't throw prisoners into the sea
- there's been too much violence already.'
Williams took out his pistol and pointed it
at Gow, but it did not fire.
Two pirates immediately shot Williams, injuring
him seriously.
Williams jumped into the hold and threatened
to blow the ship up, but some of the pirates
fought him and tied him up, then put him with
the French prisoners.
Their next capture was another British ship.
Again they stole all the food and drink from
the ship and then put their prisoners on board
the captured ship.
They also put Williams on board, and instructed
the captain of the ship to hand Williams over
to the British authorities.
Williams knew that if he was taken back to
England, he would be executed.
'Don't send me back to England,' he asked
Gow very humbly, 'you know what will happen
to me there.
Throw me into the sea if you like, but don't
send me back to England!'
Gow did not say a word to Williams but some
of the pirates began to laugh cruelly at him.
'They'll hang you,' they told him.
'Have a good voyage to the gallows.'
CHAPTER TWO
Captured
The pirates' next problem was where to go.
'North America, that's the place for us,'
some of them suggested.
'We'll be safe there, and we can find all
the things we want.'
Gow, however, was against this.
He wanted to go back home.
'We'll go to the Orkney Islands,' he told
the crew.
'I know the place well, and we can easily
sell what we've captured and live comfortably
off the profits.
Anyway,' he continued, 'we need to repair
the ship as well.
We can only do that in a northern port.
Eventually the crew accepted his decision,
and the ship sailed for the Orkney Islands.
When they arrived at one of the islands, Gow
told his crew how to behave when they went
ashore.
'You must say that we were sailing from Cadiz
to Stockholm but that bad winds drove the
ship too far north.
You must also tell the local people that you
want to repair the ship, and that if they
help you, you'll pay them very well.'
But Gow's luck began to go against him; the
sailors on board the ship who had not wanted
to join the mutiny saw their opportunity.
When one of the ship's boats went to the island,
a sailor escaped from the pirates and went
in search of the local sheriff.
'The Revenge is really a pirate ship,' he
explained.
'I had to stay on board because they threatened
to kill me.'
'You did the right thing to come here and
tell me,' the sheriff replied.
Then the sheriff ordered his men to make preparations
to capture the ship.
Another ten sailors who had been forced to
join the mutiny stole the ship's boat and
sailed to the mainland of Scotland.
They were arrested when they arrived in Edinburgh
and put in prison because the authorities
thought they were pirates.
Despite the loss of these members of his crew,
Gow did not move the ship.
He decided to stay in the bay and to rob the
gentlemen and ladies who lived on the island.
When they had finished, they sailed to a neighbouring
island called Calf Sound.
Gow wanted to rob the house of a gentleman
who lived there, a man called Fea, who Gow
had been at school with.
Gow brought the Revenge too close to the rocks
when he anchored the ship, and he sent a letter
to Mr Fea asking for a boat so that he could
pull his ship away from the rocks.
Mr Fea was suspicious of the sailors, because
he knew they had robbed a lady on one of the
small islands nearby.
He ordered his servants to sink his own boat
so that Gow and his men could not use it.
That evening five of Gow's men went to Mr
Fea's house.
They were carrying weapons, and they threatened
to kill Mr Fea if he did not help them.
'Our captain, John Gow, says you must give
us a boat to leave the island, or we'll kill
you this instant!' said one of the men.
'If you want me to help you, you'll have to
be nicer than that,' said Mr Fea.
'Let's go to the tavern for a drink, and we
can discuss things.'
Before they left for the tavern, Mr Fea secretly
instructed his servants to sink the boats
they had come in.
'These men are very dangerous.
They're pirates, and I'm going to arrest them
if I can.
I want you to sink their boats, then come
back to me immediately.'
After a while one of his servants arrived
at the tavern and asked to speak to him for
a moment outside.
The servant explained that they had followed
his orders about the pirates' boats.
Mr Fea ordered six servants to hide behind
some trees with their weapons.
He said that he would walk back that way either
with the ship's officer alone, or with all
five pirates.
His men must be prepared to attack the pirates
and capture them.
Mr Fea went back into the tavern and asked
the officer to come with him to inspect his
boat.
The officer agreed, and they left the tavern
together.
When they passed the hedge where Mr Fea's
men were hiding, they ran out and captured
the pirate.
They tied him up and left one of the six servants
in charge of him.
Then Mr Fea and his five remaining servants
went back to the tavern.
They ran through the two doors, showing their
weapons.
'Surrender!'
they shouted.
The pirates had no choice, and they too became
prisoners.
The next day the wind blew the Revenge onto
the rocks of the island.
Gow sent a message to Mr Fea, telling him
that he was offering 1,000 pounds for help
in getting the ship away from the island.
He also sent a sailor to the island with a
present of a bottle of brandy for Mr Fea.
Mr Fea, however, was determined to capture
all the pirates and send them to prison.
'I'll give you a boat,' Mr Fea offered, 'but
you'll have to send the ship's carpenter with
two or three men to repair it.'
Gow sent the men, and Mr Fea immediately captured
them.
Then he sent Gow a message saying that all
the pirates had to come and take the boat,
as his men were working on it and getting
it ready for the pirates' escape.
Once again John Gow instructed his crew to
go to the island, and this time he came with
them.
Mr Fea's men were able to capture them all.
All twenty-eight pirates were sent to Edinburgh,
and then to Marshalsea prison in London, where
they found their former partner, the cruel
lieutenant Williams.
Twelve of them were condemned to death, including
John Gow, but five of them were found not
guilty because they had been forced to join
the rebellion.
John Gow's days as a pirate were finally over.
He was sent to Newgate prison and tried at
the Old Bailey.
A strange thing happened during John Gow's
execution on 11 August 1729.
The officials tied the rope around his neck
and pushed him off the cart.
He hung in the air for a moment, struggling
terribly.
Then suddenly the rope broke and he fell to
the ground.
He was in agony.
The officials took hold of him and tied the
rope around his neck again.
Then they put him back on the cart and pushed
him off once more.
This time the rope did not break and in a
few moments the famous pirate was dead.
His body was hung in chains by the River Thames
as a warning to other pirates.
PART THREE
Jonatan Wild - Criminal genius
CHAPTER ONE
Crime Pays
Jonathan Wild was the eighteenth century's
most famous criminal.
He was born in Staffordshire in the North
of England in 1682, and when he was fifteen
his father sent him to work for a buckle maker
in Birmingham; He worked there for seven years,
and then moved to Wolverhampton where he married
and set up a business on his own.
He and his wife had a son, and for two years
they seemed to live fairly happily together.
Wild, however, found his life in Wolverhampton
too boring, and he decided to move to London,
leaving his wife and son behind.
Things did not go well for him in the big
city, however, and he soon fell into debt.
As he was unable to pay his debts, he was
arrested and sent to prison.
He remained a prisoner for more than four
years.
Later, when he wrote about his criminal life,
he said that it was the experience of mixing
with criminals in Wood Street prison that
made him choose crime as a career.
While he was in prison Wild made many friends
among the other prisoners, and formed a relationship
with a woman called Mary Milliner.
When they were released from prison, Wild
and Milliner lived together as husband and
wife, and they used her money or their money
from illegal practices to open a tavern in
Cock Alley.
It played an important part in Wild's criminal
career, and became a legendary place in the
history of crime.
The usual customers of the tavern were criminals,
and they soon found that Wild was a sympathetic
and interested listener.
They told him about the robberies they had
recently committed, and they revealed their
plans for future crimes.
This gave Wild enormous power over them: if
Wild told the authorities about the crimes,
they might arrest them.
Instead of doing this, however, Wild helped
the criminals by hiding stolen property in
his house and selling it for them.
It was not difficult for Wild to sell the
stolen articles because at the time it was
not a crime to receive or sell stolen property.
Parliament soon changed the law, however,
and a new crime of receiving stolen property
came into existence.
The punishment for this offence was transportation
for fifteen years.
Wild was determined to continue his profitable
business with the criminals, but the new law
worried him: he did not want to be arrested
for receiving stolen property.
So he invited the criminals to a meeting in
his tavern.
'I can't take the goods you steal anymore,'
he explained.
'It's too dangerous.
But I have a suggestion that will make us
all rich.'
The criminals were very excited.
'You won't make much money if you try to sell
the goods to other receivers of stolen property.
Bring everything to me,' he continued, 'and
I'll arrange to return all the goods to their
owners in exchange for some money.'
The criminals were pleased with Wild's plan
and they decided to do as he suggested.
Wild found several places around London to
keep the stolen goods that the criminals gave
him.
The new plan worked very well.
When a criminal came to him with an item that
he had stolen, Wild went to the person who
had been robbed.
He explained that he had a friend, an honest
trader, who had bought the item and wanted
to return it because he guessed that it had
been stolen.
Wild suggested that the owner should pay the
honest trader a fee for the goods.
Many people were so pleased to have the chance
of getting their property back that they willingly
paid half the value of the property as the
fee to Wild's trader friend.
This fee, of course, was then divided between
Wild and the criminal.
Wild did not receive any money directly from
the owners of the stolen property, who only
paid the fee to his non-existent trader.
There was no law against this type of business,
and for a considerable time Wild was very
successful and became very rich.
He even opened an office where people who
had been robbed could come and ask his help
in getting their property back.
Wild charged everyone who came to the office
a small fee for his advice.
He then asked for a full description of the
goods that had been taken, and how much the
owners were prepared to pay to recover the
goods.
'All you have to do is describe the stolen
goods and tell me how much you're willing
to pay for their recovery, and I'll make investigations
into your case,' Wild told the client.
'I'll do the rest.'
The client then returned to Wild's office
to find out how the investigation was proceeding.
'Unfortunately, on this occasion I haven't
been able to recover your property,' Wild
began.
'I've heard through a contact that the thieves
are determined to sell the property for more
money than you've offered to recover the object.
However, if you wanted to offer more money,
maybe they'd reconsider.'
This tactic was so successful that most of
the owners increased their offer for the return
of their goods.
Wild's interviews with the victims of crime
allowed him to find out how truthful the thieves
were with him.
The thieves were frightened of Wild's power
over them, and most of them told him the truth
about their crimes.
Wild's imagination was now so involved in
the planning of crimes that he even invented
some new forms of crime.
He realised that there were a lot of articles
that had no real value, except to the owners
themselves.
'The things I want you to steal are books
of accounts, watches and rings,' he told his
thieves.
'All of these are personal items that are
important to their owners, and I'm sure they'll
pay very high fees in order to recover them.'
CHAPTER TWO
The Thief-taker
Wild's reputation with the thieves was by
now firmly established.
Nearly all of them were afraid of him and
so they obeyed him.
He always paid them what he had promised,
and they knew that he would always help them
if they were arrested.
There were some thieves, however, who resented
his power in the criminal world and they refused
to work for him.
In these cases he used to send for the thief
concerned, with a message guaranteeing the
thief's safety.
He then tried to persuade the thief to change
his attitude and to work for him.
If the man refused, he ended the interview
with a sinister threat.
'Remember what I told you: you can come here
perfectly safely, and leave here perfectly
safely, and I'll keep my promise.
But the next time you see me, you'll see your
worst enemy!'
One of the ways that Wild helped his criminal
friends who were unlucky enough to be arrested
was very clever.
He visited them in prison and suggested that
they could escape punishment if they offered
'evidence'.
A criminal who told the court about more important
crimes committed by other people could be
given his freedom as a reward for helping
the justice system.
The 'evidence' that Wild gave his friends
always concerned criminals who had refused
to work for him.
He also helped his colleagues when they went
to prison by making sure that witnesses against
them did not appear in court on the day of
the trial.
He did this by threatening the witnesses so
that they were too frightened to come to court.
If there were no witnesses against the criminals,
the judge had to let them go because there
was no evidence.
Jonathan Wild was often asked how it was possible
for him to recover so much stolen property
if he was not really working with the thieves
themselves.
His reply to this question was always the
same.
'I know many thieves, and when I hear about
a particular crime, I make enquiries about
it.
I leave a message for the criminals, telling
them that they'll receive the reward if they
leave the goods in a certain place.
I also promise them that no questions about
the crime will be asked.
I don't commit a crime myself, because I don't
talk to the thieves personally, and I don't
receive the stolen property myself.'
Wild was a very dangerous enemy to the criminals
who refused to work for him, as the following
story shows.
One evening in March 1716, a young gentleman
called Knap and his mother were walking back
from the opera together.
They were attacked by five men.
His mother shouted out for help, but one of
the five men shot her dead.
An account of the terrible murder appeared
in the newspapers and a substantial reward
was offered for the discovery of the murderer.
Wild read the descriptions of the men in the
paper, and when he recognised who they were,
he decided to find them and give them up to
the authorities.
He hoped to be rewarded as a thief-catcher.
Wild heard that some of the gang were drinking
in a tavern.
He went to there with his servant Abraham
and found one of the gang members, and took
him to prison.
Wild then heard that another enemy, a man
called Aires, was at a tavern in Smithfield.
Once again Wild and Abraham went to get him.
The man who had been described as Aires was
really Thomas Thurland, a member of the gang
that had killed Knap's mother.
Thurland had two pistols but as he was surprised
by the appearance of Abraham and Wild, he
had no chance to use them.
They took Thurland into custody as well, along
with another member of the gang, a certain
Edward Darvel, who was captured the following
night.
Soon afterwards the authorities were looking
for yet another criminal, Isaac Rag, for a
burglary.
Wild and his men found Rag and delivered him
over to the authorities.
Rag tried to save himself by giving 'evidence'
of other crimes and criminals.
He told the magistrate about twenty-two other
accomplices and a vast number of crimes.
The court accepted him as a witness for the
crown.
The other gang members were tried at the Old
Bailey.
The charges included the attack on Mr Knap
and the murder of Mrs Knap.
They were found guilty and all three were
executed at Tyburn on 8 June 1716.
Wild, however, was still determined to find
the remaining member of the gang, Timothy
Dun.
Dun was hiding with his wife at home, but
he became bored and decided to send her to
ask Jonathan Wild if he was now safe from
the authorities.
Dun's wife came to Wild's office to talk to
him, but she did not trust him completely.
Afterwards she went home a long, complicated
way to avoid being followed by one of Wild's
men.
But this is exactly what happened: she was
followed.
After finding out where he lived, Wild, Abraham
and two other men went to the house.
Dun tried to escape through a window and Abraham
fired a shot that hit Dun in the arm.
He fell out of the window, then another of
Wild's men shot him in the face.
He was captured and taken to Newgate and executed
at Tyburn soon after.
In this way Jonathan Wild succeeded in capturing
all the members of the gang involved in the
murder of Mrs Knap, and removed his enemies
without committing a single murder.
CHAPTER THREE
Stolen Property
Wild by now had so much stolen property in
London that he decided to sell some of it.
He bought a ship and transported the goods
to Bruges, Ghent and Brussels.
Here they were sold in exchange for wine,
brandy and other items that were then smuggled
secretly into England.
This scheme was Very successful for about
two years until the captain of the boat Johnson,
and his assistant had an argument.
The assistant told the authorities about Johnson's
illegal activities, and the ship was captured
and the captain was arrested in a tavern.
Johnson immediately sent for Jonathan Wild.
When he arrived Wild realised that he had
to do something quickly if he wanted to save
his friend.
He poured a glass of beer over a large man
who was sitting with some friends.
This made the man very angry.
'What did you do that for?' he shouted at
Wild.
'You and your friends are cowards!'
Wild shouted back.
'Come outside and fight me - all of you!'
The man and his friends stood up.
One of them threw a chair at Wild but it missed
him, and hit another group of men who were
sitting at a table.
They stood up as well and everyone began fighting.
'Now's your chance,' Wild whispered urgently
to Johnson.
'Get out now!'
Johnson took Wild's advice and ran out of
the tavern as fast as he could.
The officers reacted too slowly.
They saw their prisoner escape, but they could
not do anything about it.
They knew, however, that Jonathan Wild was
responsible for the riot and they wanted their
revenge for what he had done.
The authorities began searching for Jonathan
Wild, and a number of charges were prepared
against him.
His good luck was about to come to an end.
Mr Jones, the high constable of Holborn, issued
a warrant for the arrest of Wild.
When the authorities discovered where he was,
they arrested him and took him to Newgate
prison.
Mr Jones produced a long list of crimes that
he said Jonathan Wild had committed, including
two crimes which were punishable by death.
On 15 May 1725 Wild was tried for the theft
of fifty yards of lace from the house of Mrs
Streatham.
During the trial it emerged that Jonathan
Wild had organised the theft of the lace,
but that he had not gone into the house himself:
he had sent his men into the house to steal
the lace.
They had delivered it to him in the street
outside the house.
Wild's defence lawyer argued that Wild was
not guilty of the offence.
'The charge explicitly states that my client
stole the lace in the house,' the lawyer argued.
'But the evidence shows that Mr Wild didn't
steal the lace in the house because he was
outside in the street.
Therefore my client isn't guilty of the crime.'
'You're right,' the judge agreed.
'The charge against your client isn't accurate.'
The jury listened to the judge's words carefully
and they found Jonathan Wild not guilty of
the crime.
Parliament now passed a new law.
The new law said that if people had secret
dealings with criminals, and took money for
recovering stolen property from their criminal
contacts, they should be treated as if they
had committed the crimes themselves.
The second charge brought against Jonathan
Wild was based on this new law.
It concerned the same crime as before, the
theft of the lace from Mrs Streatham.
She gave evidence that after the lace was
stolen, she went to Wild's office to ask for
his help in recovering it.
He told her that he would investigate the
crime for her.
She said that she would be prepared to pay
twenty-five guineas for the recovery of her
property.
Shortly afterwards Jonathan Wild was arrested
and imprisoned in Newgate.
Mrs Streatham said that Wild wrote to her
from prison.
'Bring me ten guineas, and your property will
be returned to you,' he wrote.
She went to the prison to see Wild and found
another man with him.
Wild told her to give the other man the ten
guineas.
She gave him the money and he left.
He returned soon afterwards with a box containing
the stolen lace.
The judge decided that the new law applied
to Jonathan Wild.
He said that it was clear that Wild had secret
dealings with thieves and that he took money
for returning stolen property to its owners.
The jury found Jonathan Wild guilty of the
crime, and he was condemned to death.
Wild tried to escape the consequences of his
crimes by arguing that he had done society
a service by returning stolen property to
the people from whom it had been taken.
He wanted some of the important and influential
people who had paid him for his services to
organise a royal pardon for him.
These hopes, however, were in vain; it was
clear that there was no hope for Wild.
He became desperate and tried to poison himself
before the day of the execution, but he did
not succeed.
Jonathan Wild was taken to Tyburn to be executed
on 24 May 1725.
His notoriety as a criminal was so great that
people threw stones at him on his last journey.
The executioner told him that he could have
a reasonable period to prepare himself for
the execution.
Jonathan Wild sat in the prison cart for a
considerable time.
This made the crowd frustrated and angry.
'Hang him!'
they shouted at the executioner.
'Hang him now, or we'll hang you!'
The executioner was afraid and performed his
duty immediately, and the career of one of
the most successful eighteenth-century criminals
came to an end.
PART FOUR
Richard 'Dick' Turpin - Gentleman, Highwayman
and horse thief
CHAPTER ONE
The Essex Gang
Richard Turpin, more commonly known as Dick
Turpin, was the son of an Essex farmer.
He was brutal and cruel even as a young man,
and he seemed destined for a life of crime.
Turpin eventually became a butcher, and he
married soon afterwards.
He began stealing his neighbours' farm animals,
which he used to sell in his shop.
His crimes were discovered and an order for
his arrest was prepared, but he ran away before
the authorities came to his house and joined
a gang of smugglers in another part of Essex.
The gang then moved to London, where they
robbed people's houses.
Their strategy worked like this.
One of the gang used to knock on the door
of a house, and when someone opened it, the
rest of the gang ran in and stole what they
could find.
Their first victim was an old man who had
a shop.
They robbed him but they were not violent
with him.
They carried out a series of such robberies,
and Dick Turpin was increasingly cruel to
his victims.
He held one old woman over a fire until she
told the gang where her money was hidden.
On 11 January 1735 the gang robbed a rich
farmer, Mr Saunders, in Kent.
They rushed into his house, where they found
Mr Saunders with his wife and friends playing
cards.
'Everybody stay very quiet!'
Turpin ordered.
'If you do what we tell you, no one will be
hurt.'
Mr Saunders and the rest of the people in
the house quickly gave the gang their money
and valuable possessions.
Their house robberies continued in this way
for a considerable time.
Then, on 4 February 1735, they decided to
rob a certain Mr Lawrence, who lived in Edgware.
The gang arrived at the house just as Mr Lawrence
was going in.
They took hold of him and told him to instruct
the servant boy to open the front door of
the house.
The boy was so frightened that he did nothing.
Another servant opened the door, imagining
that nothing was wrong, and the gang rushed
in with their prisoner, Mr Lawrence.
They looked through the house for items of
value, but were not satisfied with what they
found.
They said they would murder Mr Lawrence if
he did not tell them where his valuable possessions
were hidden.
Finally, one of the gang treated a female
servant very cruelly, and they left the house,
leaving everyone there tied up.
The authorities offered a reward of 50 pounds
for information about the gang, but this produced
no results.
They continued as before, entering houses
and threatening and robbing the owners.
One day they robbed another farmer, Mr Francis.
They found two of Mr Francis' servants working
outside the house.
They captured them and tied them up.
When they went to the house and discovered
that Mr Francis was just about to go in himself,
they captured him as well and tied him up
together with his two servants.
Then they rushed into the house where they
found Mrs Francis, her daughter, and a female
servant.
They attacked the three women very violently
before leaving the house with all the valuables
they could find.
The authorities now increased the reward to
100 pounds for information about the members
of the gang.
As a result of this, two gang members were
arrested and hanged, and the remaining members
decided that it was now too dangerous to continue
working together.
Dick Turpin realised that it was too dangerous
to remain in the area and he escaped to the
country.
It was time to change his career; he had decided
to become a highwayman.
CHAPTER TWO
King and Horses
One day Turpin was riding towards Cambridge
when he saw another traveller ahead of him
on the road.
He seemed like a rich man, and Turpin decided
to rob him.
He rode up to him and took out two pistols,
pointed them at him and demanded his money.
The other traveller was himself a highwayman,
King, who recognised Turpin immediately.
King laughed at Turpin's demand for money.
'What,' he asked him, 'dog eat dog?
I know who you are, Richard Turpin.'
Turpin smiled.
He wanted to know what King was going to say
next.
'We should work together,' King told him.
'We could be partners.
What do you think?'
'All right,' Turpin agreed.
'Maybe a partnership isn't such a bad idea.
Let's try it.'
The two men began a series of highway robberies,
and they became known in and outside London
for their exploits.
On one occasion, they robbed a gentleman on
the road and then allowed him to buy back
the watch they had just taken.
Turpin was also known to be a gentleman to
the ladies he and King robbed, and if they
were young and beautiful, he complimented
them on their beauty when he took their possessions,
saying:
'It's a pity to take things from such beautiful
ladies.'
King and Turpin made a hiding-place for themselves
in Epping Forest, where they could sleep and
keep their horses.
One day disaster struck for Turpin.
A certain Mr Thompson, who worked in Epping
Forest, had seen the hiding-place, and he
guessed who the two mysterious men were.
When he heard that the authorities were offering
a reward of 100 pounds for information about
Turpin and King, he decided to arrest them.
Mr Thompson approached their hiding-place
with a friend.
Turpin saw them coming and went out to meet
them.
He thought they were poachers.
'There aren't any rabbits near here,' he told
them.
'That's true,' Mr Thompson's friend replied,
'but there's a Turpin.'
He pointed his gun at Turpin and told him
to surrender.
'Very well, gentlemen,' Turpin replied in
a friendly way.
'There's no chance for me.
I surrender.'
As he was talking, however, Turpin began to
walk backwards very slowly.
Then he quickly reached down, picked up his
own gun and shot Mr Thompson's friend.
Mr Thompson ran away into the forest.
He told the authorities about the murder,
and they issued a reward of 200 pounds for
the arrest of Richard Turpin.
Turpin and King now decided to work separately.
Turpin decided that Epping Forest was a dangerous
place, and he left the area.
He sent a message to his wife to meet him
in a tavern.
When he arrived at the tavern he saw a butcher
there.
This man knew who he was, and he remembered
that Dick Turpin owed him five pounds.
'Now, Dick,' he said, 'I know you've got a
lot of money these days.
Give me the five pounds you owe me.'
'My wife is in the next room,' Turpin told
the butcher 'She'll give you the money.'
The butcher now began telling the other people
in the tavern who Dick Turpin was.
He said that they should arrest him Turpin
escaped through a window and rode away.
Turpin and King joined up again, and they
took a third partner into their business,
a man called Potter.
One day, riding towards London, Turpin's horse
was tired and when he saw another traveller
on the road, he decided to take his horse.
The owner of the horse was called Mr Major,
and the theft took place in Epping Forest
near a tavern called The Green Man.
Mr Major immediately told the landlord of
The Green Man about the theft of his horse.
He also advertised for information about the
thieves and his horse.
The landlord of The Green Man soon received
information that a horse very similar to the
one that had been stolen could be found at
the Red Lion tavern in Whitechapel, London.
The landlord of The Green Man went to the
tavern and waited to see if someone arrived
to collect the horse.
When King's brother arrived at the tavern
he was immediately arrested.
At first he said that the horse belonged to
him, but it was soon proved that he was lying,
as the whip he carried in his hand had the
name 'Major' written on it.
The landlord then told King's brother that
he would only be freed if he told them where
his employers were.
He said that a man was waiting for the horse
in Red Lion Street.
The landlord of The Green Man and his friends
went there and saw the man that had been described
to them.
The man, who was Turpin's partner, King, saw
the crowd of people coming towards him and
took out his pistol.
He tried to fire at the crowd but his pistol
did not work.
He called out desperately to Turpin.
'Fire, Dick, fire or they'll take us!'
Turpin fired his pistol but the bullet hit
King.
'You've killed me, Dick,' King cried out to
him.
Turpin rode away as fast as he could from
the scene.
King lived for a week after being shot by
Turpin, and he gave the authorities information
about where they might be able to find Turpin
himself.
Turpin knew now that the authorities were
looking for him everywhere, and he rode from
one place to another.
First he went to the east, to Lincolnshire,
where he stole some horses.
He was caught and arrested but managed to
escape.
Next he went further north to Yorkshire, where
he used another name.
He pretended to be a gentleman, and frequently
went hunting with the upper classes.
He supported himself by stealing horses in
Lincolnshire and selling them in Yorkshire.
Turpin then made a very small mistake that
cost him his life.
When he was out hunting with his friends one
day, he shot a cockerel that belonged to his
landlord.
One of the huntsmen, Mr Hall, told him that
he had made a mistake to shoot the cockerel.
'If you stay here,' Turpin replied coldly,
'I'll shoot you as well.'
Mr Hall was very angry at Turpin's behaviour.
He told the landlord what Turpin had done,
and the authorities arrested him.
The magistrates began to collect information
about this mysterious man who had appeared
among them.
They learned that he travelled frequently
to Lincolnshire and always came back with
money and horses.
They began to suspect that he was a highwayman.
Turpin insisted that his real name was Palmer,
and that he had been a butcher in Lincolnshire.
He said that he had lost his business and
had decided to come and live in Yorkshire.
The magistrates made enquiries and discovered
that there had been a butcher in Lincolnshire
called Palmer.
This man was a sheep thief who had escaped
from the authorities there, who were looking
for him.
When he had been in prison in York Castle
for about four months, Turpin wrote a letter
to his brother in Essex.
He signed the letter 'John Palmer'.
He asked his brother to help him, but his
brother did not read the letter.
He did not want to pay the postage for receiving
it.
The letter was then sent back to the post
office in Essex.
By chance, the schoolmaster in Essex who had
taught Dick Turpin saw the letter in the post
office.
He recognised his old pupil's writing immediately.
He took the letter to the magistrate and explained
that the writer of the letter was not John
Palmer but Richard Turpin.
Turpin was now tried and sentenced to death
for his crimes.
He behaved very cheerfully after receiving
his sentence and joked about the execution
ahead of him.
He bought some fine clothes shortly before
the day of the execution.
He also paid five poor men to be his mourners
and to follow the cart taking him to the execution.
He behaved with great courage on the day of
the execution, 10 April 1739.
He waved at the crowd who had come to see
him die and he spoke for half an hour with
the executioner before throwing himself down
from the execution ladder.
The career of the famous highwayman had come
to an end at last.
- THE END -