Women often knit gifts for their families.
Wives knit socks or scarves for their husbands;
grandmothers knit little jackets for their
children's babies.
Buying a gift is quick and easy, but making
a gift with your own hands takes longer.
And if, like Leonard's wife, your hands are
old and stiff and crooked with arthritis,
perhaps knitting is not the best thing to
do...
I'll knit him a scarf.
Yes.
I'll knit him a scarf the same colour as his
eyes.
I wait until my niece takes me shopping.
'I want to buy some wool,' I tell her.
'I want to knit Leonard a scarf.'
'But you don't knit,' she says.
She looks at my crooked hands and quickly
looks away again.
'And Leonard doesn't go out any more.'
But Petra takes me to the wool shop anyway.
'I want to buy some blue wool,' I say to the
woman in the shop.
'The colour of my husband's eyes.'
I touch a ball of blue wool that feels as
soft as a bird's feathers.
'Isn't this a little too fine?' asks the woman
in the shop.
'No, it's just right.'
Later, tired after my shopping, I lie back
in my armchair and have a little sleep.
When the car stops outside, I am still half-asleep,
and in my mind, I see a younger Leonard standing
at the door.
His back is as straight as a piece of wood,
and his blue eyes smile.
'Is anyone home?'
Dan calls.
I wake with a jump.
'Here we are, Mr Phipps,' Dan says to Leonard.
Holding Leonard's arm, Dan walks him into
the house.
'Thank you, Dan.'
I take off Leonard's coat and push some hair
away from his eyes.
We eat dinner in a silence that aches.
I drink red wine and Leonard eats with a spoon.
Then, after I've washed him and put him to
bed, I sit down to knit.
The needles are silver.
The needles are cold.
I take the paper cover off the wool, find
one end of it, and try again and again to
make the first stitch.
I am listening to music by Beethoven, and
it is nearly halfway through before I have
finished the first row of stitches.
My fingers hurt, and they won't do what I
tell them.
But I have begun.
Leonard and I met at a concert in Auckland.
He was tall, with blond hair then.
I can still see him walking towards my seat.
He took off the soft blue scarf that was the
same colour as his eyes, and my heart gave
a little jump.
We talked over supper, and I found out where
he lived and what he did.
'I'm an eye doctor,' he said, 'just beginning.
No money, but I never miss concerts.'
I made our first date while we were walking
out of the concert building.
In those days, men always did the asking,
not girls.
I don't know if Leonard was surprised at my
asking him or not.
He never said anything.
On the days when Leonard goes to the day-care
centre, I knit.
I plan to finish the scarf for our fifty-third
wedding anniversary.
The scarf is almost finished, and when I hold
it to the light, diamonds shine through.
I shake the wool, drop a stitch, try to find
it again.
Was I more in love with Leonard than he was
with me?
I have so many questions... and I cannot ask
any of them now.
'It's finished,' I tell my niece, putting
the scarf round my neck.
'It looks good,' she said, 'if you don't look
too closely.
Is it a gift?'
'Yes.
My last.'
On the morning of our anniversary, I kiss
Leonard and give him the scarf.
I know he will not speak, but while I am putting
the scarf round his neck, I find that I am
still hoping.
The scarf is as crooked as my fingers.
It's full of holes - long thin holes, little
round holes.
Leonard puts his hand up and touches the wool,
and for one short moment, his eyes come alive
again.
'Yes,' he wants to tell me.
'Yes,' he wants to say.
'The scarf is soft.
The scarf is blue.
The scarf is us.'
- THE END -