CHAPTER ONE
Down the Rabbit-hole
Alice and her big sister sat under a tree
one sunny day. Alice's sister had a book,
but Alice had nothing with her. She looked
at her sisters book. There were no pictures
or conversations in it.
'Why is she reading a book without pictures
or conversations?' she thought. 'I'm bored.
I know! I'll look for some Bowers.' Then she
thought, 'No, it's too hot for that and I
feel sleepy.'
Suddenly, a white rabbit ran past her. It
took a watch from its jacket and looked at
it. 'Oh! Oh! I'm going to be late!' it said.
'That's strange! A rabbit with a watch!' said
Alice.
She jumped up and ran after the animal. It
ran down a large rabbit-hole, so Alice went
down the hole too. She didn't stop and ask,
'How am I going to get out again?'
Alice fell down and down. But she fell very
slowly and didn't feel afraid. 'What's going
to happen next?' she wondered.
She looked round. There were cupboards in
the walls of the rabbit-hole. Some of the
cupboards were open, and there were books
in them. Sometimes she saw pictures. She looked
down, but she couldn't see any light.
Down, down, down. 'When will the hole end?'
she wondered. 'Perhaps I'm going to come out
in Australia! I'll have to ask the name of
the country. 'Please, madam, is this Australia
or New Zealand?' No, I can't do that. They'll
think I'm stupid.'
She thought about her cat, Dinah. 'What's
Dinah doing? Will they remember her milk tonight?
Oh, Dinah! Why aren't you here with me? Perhaps
there's a mouse here and you can eat it!'
Suddenly, Alice was at the bottom of the hole.
'That didn't hurt,' she said and sat up quickly.
She could see the White Rabbit and she ran
after him again. They were in a different
rabbit-hole now.
'Oh, my ears and nose!' the White Rabbit cried.
'It's getting very late!'
He ran faster and vanished through another
hole. Alice followed him through the hole.
Now she was in a very long room. She looked
round for the White Rabbit, but she couldn't
see him anywhere.
There were four doors in the room, but Alice
couldn't open them. Also, she couldn't see
the hole anywhere. 'How am I going to get
out?' she wondered.
Then she saw a little table. It had a very
small key on it.
'Perhaps it will open one of the doors,' she
thought. She took the key and tried to open
each door with it. But it was no good. The
key was too small.
'This key has to open something,' she thought.
Then she saw a very small door about 40 centimeters
high. The little key opened it. She put her
head down and looked through the door into
a beautiful garden. She tried to walk through
it, but she was too big. Sadly, she shut the
door again and put the key back on the table.
'Why can't I get smaller?' thought Alice.
'This is a very strange place - so perhaps
I can.'
She looked at the table. There was a little
bottle on it.
'That bottle was not on the table before,'
thought Alice.
The bottle had 'DRINK ME' on it in large letters.
Alice looked at it carefully.
'Is it all right to drink?' she wondered.
'I'll drink a little,' she thought. She had
some and it was very nice. So she had some
more.
'This feels strange,' said Alice. 'I'm getting
smaller and smaller!' After a short time,
she was only 25 centimetres high.
'Now I can go through that door,' she thought.
She went to the door, but could not open it.
The key was on the table. She went back to
the table. But Alice was too short and she
couldn't get the key. She tried to climb the
table legs, but it was too difficult. The
little girl sat down and cried.
'Alice! Alice!' she said after some minutes.
'Don't cry. It isn't going to help you. Stop
now!'
Then she saw a little box under the table.
She opened it. There was a cake inside. On
it, she saw the words, 'EAT ME'.
'Yes, I will eat it,' Alice said. 'Perhaps
I'll get bigger and then I can get the key.
Or perhaps I'll get smaller. Then I can get
under the door into the garden.'
She ate some cake.
'Will I go up or down?' she wondered. She
felt the top of her head with her hand. But
nothing happened - she stayed the same size.
So she finished the cake.
CHAPTER TWO
Alice's Tears
'Oh! What's happening?' cried Alice. 'I'm
getting taller and taller!' She looked down.
'Goodbye, feet! Who will put your shoes on
for you now? I can't do it! I'll give you
some new shoes for Christmas. I'll have to
send them to you!'
In a short time, Alice was more than three
meters high.
'I want to go into that garden!' she thought.
She took the little key from the table. Then
she went to the door and opened it. But she
was too big and couldn't go through it.
She sat down and began to cry again. Because
she was very big, her tears were very big
too.
'Alice, stop it this minute! Don't cry!' she
said.
But she couldn't stop the big tears and after
a time there was water everywhere.
She heard the sound of small feet. She looked
down and there was the White Rabbit again.
He had his best clothes on, and in one hand
he had a white hat.
'Oh, the Duchess, the Duchess!' he said. 'She'll
be angry with me because I'm late!'
Alice wanted to ask him for help. 'Please,
Sir-' she said very politely.
The White Rabbit jumped. He ran out of the
room and his hat fell from his hands. Alice
took the hat.
'Am I different?' she wondered. I was Alice
yesterday, but everything is different today.
Perhaps I'm not me now. So who am I? That's
the question.'
She began to think about her friends. 'Perhaps
I'm one of them,' she thought. 'I'm not Ada
because her hair is different to mine. I don't
want to be my friend Mabel, because she doesn't
know very much. I know more than she does.'
Then she thought, 'Do I know more? Let me
see. What's four and four? Eight. Eight and
eight is sixteen. Sixteen and sixteen is...
Oh! I can't remember! And she started to cry
again.
But this time her tears were small tears - she
was small again!
'Why?' she wondered. Then she understood.
She had the White Rabbit's hat in her hand.
'I'm smaller because I've got the hat in my
hand!' she thought.
She put the hat on. It was the right size
for her head.
'Am I smaller than the table now?' she wondered.
She went to the table and stood next to it.
She was smaller than the table. 'I'm getting
smaller all the time!' she cried. 'I'm going
to vanish!' She quickly took the hat off.
'Now I can go into the garden!' thought Alice,
and she started to run to the little door.
But before she got there, she fell into some
water. She tried to put her feet on the ground
but she couldn't. She had to swim.
'I'm in the sea!' she thought. But it wasn't
the sea. The water was her tears.
Something was in the water - Alice could hear
it. 'Perhaps it's a big fish or sea animal,'
she thought. She looked round. There, very
near her, was a mouse.
'I'll speak to it,' thought Alice. 'Everything
is strange here. Perhaps it can speak and
understand me.'
'Oh Mouse,' she said. 'Do you know the way
out of this room?' The Mouse didn't answer.
'Perhaps it doesn't understand English. Perhaps
it's a French mouse,' Alice thought. She remembered
some words from her schoolbook, so she spoke
to the mouse in French.
'Where is my cat?' she asked.
The Mouse moved quickly away from her.
'Oh, I'm sorry,' said Alice. 'I forgot. You're
a mouse, so you don't like cats.'
'Don't like cats!' cried the mouse. 'I'm a
mouse. Of course I don't like cats!'
'No,' Alice said. 'No. But I think you will
like Dinah. She is a nice, dear thing. She's
very quiet and good. She catches a mouse every
day - Oh! You're angry again! We won't talk
about Dinah any more-'
'We!' cried the Mouse. 'I never speak about
cats! Our family hates cats! I don't want
to hear any more about them.'
'No, no,' said Alice quickly. 'Perhaps - perhaps
you like dogs? There's a very nice little
dog near our house. It likes playing with
children but it works too. It kills all them
- Oh! I'm sorry!'
The Mouse looked angrily at her and swam quickly
away.
'Dear Mouse!' said Alice softly. 'Come back
again and we won't talk about cats or dogs.'
When the Mouse heard this, it turned round.
It swam slowly back. 'All right,' it said.
'I'll talk to you, but let's get out of the
water.'
They climbed out and Alice looked round. There
were a lot of animals and birds in the water.
When they saw her, they got out of the water
too.
CHAPTER THREE
A Race
Alice and the birds and animals felt cold
and wet. The largest bird spoke to Alice.
'Good afternoon,' it said loudly. 'I am the
Dodo.'
'What is a Dodo?' thought Alice, but she smiled
politely. 'Hello, Dodo. I'm Alice,' she said.
'I have an idea,' said the Dodo.' We all want
to get warm. So let's have a race - a Caucus
race.'
'What is a Caucus race?' Alice asked.
'I can tell you,' said the Dodo,' but I won't.
I'll show you! That will be easier.'
He put the animals and birds in different
places in the room. In a race, somebody usually
says,' One, two, three, go!' But the Dodo
didn't do that. Everybody started to run at
different times and stopped at different times
too. After half an hour, the Dodo cried, 'Everybody
stop! All the birds and animals stopped. Then
they all came to the Dodo and stood round
it.' Who was first? Who was first?' they shouted.
The Dodo had to think about it. He sat
for a long time with his finger in his mouth.
Then he said, 'Everybody was first. So everybody
can have a chocolate.'
'But who will give us the chocolates?' the
Mouse asked.
'She will,' the Dodo said and looked at Alice.
The birds and animals came and stood round
Alice.
'Chocolates, chocolates!' they cried.
'What am I going to do?' thought Alice. I
haven't got any chocolates.' But then she
saw a box of chocolates near her feet.
'Here we are,' she said, and opened the box.
There was one chocolate for each bird and
animal.
'But Alice has to have something, you know,'
said the Mouse.
'Of course,' the Dodo answered. He turned
to Alice. 'What can you have?' he asked.
'I can have the box,' said Alice sadly.
'Give it to me,' said the Dodo and Alice gave
it to him.
They all stood round Alice again, and the
Dodo gave her the box.
'Please take this beautiful box,' he said.
'This is very stupid,' thought Alice and she
wanted to laugh. But she didn't. She took
the box and smiled politely.
The animals and birds ate their chocolates
noisily. Some of them cried. The big animals
and birds wanted more. But the chocolates
were too big for the small birds, and they
had to eat them very slowly. When they finished
their chocolates, they sat and looked at Alice.
'Oh, where is Dinah?' said Alice. 'I want
her with me.'
'And who is Dinah?' the Dodo asked.
Alice loved to talk about her cat. 'Dinah's
our cat. She's very nice. And very clever
and fast. She can catch a mouse in the morning
for her breakfast and a little bird in the
evening for her dinner - Oh! I'm sorry!'
It was too late. The birds and animals started
leaving.
One old bird said, 'I really have to go home.
It gets so cold at night!'
Another bird called to her children, 'Come
away, my dears! It's time for bed!'
They all spoke politely to Alice and left
the room.
'Oh, why did I talk about Dinah?' cried Alice.
'Nobody likes Dinah down here, but she's the
best cat in the world. Perhaps I'll never
see her again!'
She sat down and started to cry again. After
a time, she heard the sound of small feet
and looked up.
'Perhaps it's the Mouse,' she thought.
CHAPTER FOUR
The White Rabbit's House
It was not the Mouse. It was the White Rabbit.
He came slowly into the room.
'Oh, my ears and nose!' he said quietly. 'The
Duchess! The Duchess! She'll be angry! They'll
cut off my head, I know! Oh, where is it?
Where did it fall?'
'He's looking for his hat,' thought Alice.
She wanted to help him, but she couldn't see
the hat anywhere. She looked round. Everything
was different now. She wasn't in the long
room anymore, and there was no table or water.
She was outside again, in the country.
The White Rabbit saw her. 'What are you doing
out here, Mary Ann?' he asked angrily. 'Run
home this minute and bring me a hat. Quick,
now!'
Alice didn't say, 'I'm not Mary Ann.' She
felt too afraid. She ran fast and after a
short time, she came to a pretty little house.
Above the door were the words 'W. RABBIT'.
She went in and ran up the stairs.
'This is very strange,' she thought. 'I hope
I don't meet Mary Ann. Why am I bringing a
rabbit his hat? Perhaps when I get home, I'll
do things for Dinah. Perhaps I'll watch mouse-holes
for her!'
She went into a small room. There, on a table,
was a hat and a little bottle. Alice took
the hat and looked at the bottle. It didn't
have the words 'DRINK ME' on it, but she drank
from it.
'I know something interesting will happen,'
she thought. 'When I eat or drink something
here, it always does. I hope I get bigger
this time. I don't like being small.'
She drank half the bottle. 'Oh, I'm getting
much taller!' she cried. 'Oh!' Her head hit
the top of the house and she put the bottle
down quickly.
'Oh no!' she thought. 'I hope I don't get
taller!'
She sat down. But after a very short time
she was too big for the room. She had to put
one arm out of the window and one foot in
the fireplace.
'I can't do any more,' she thought. 'What
will happen to me?' She waited for some time,
but she didn't get bigger. 'Well, that's good,'
she thought. But then she tried to move and
couldn't. She didn't feel well and she was
very unhappy.
'I'm never going to get out of here,' she
thought. 'It was much nicer at home. First
I get larger, then I get smaller, then larger...
Oh, why did I go down the rabbit-hole? But
it is interesting here. Perhaps somebody will
write a book about this place - and about
me! Perhaps I will, when I'm bigger.' Then
she remembered. 'But I'm bigger now!'
She heard somebody outside. 'Mary Ann, Mary
Ann! Where are you? Bring me my hat!' The
words came from the garden, outside the window.
It was the White Rabbit.
He came inside and ran up the stairs to the
room. He tried to open the door. But he couldn't
because Alice's back was next to it.
'I'll climb in through the window,' the Rabbit
said.
'Oh no, you won't,' thought Alice. She waited
and listened. One of her arms was outside
the window. When she could hear the Rabbit
outside the window, she moved her arm up and
down. There was a little cry.
'Pat, Pat, where are you? Come here!' shouted
the Rabbit.
'Coming, Sir,' somebody - or something - answered.
'What's that in the window?' asked the Rabbit.
'It's an arm, Sir,' Pat answered.
'Don't be stupid! How can it be an arm? It's
too big!'
'It is very big, but it is an arm, sir.'
'Well, what's it doing up there? Take it away!'
said the Rabbit angrily.
Alice moved her arm again. Now there were
two little cries. Everything was quiet for
a short time, then something hard hit her
arm.
'That hurt!' said Alice.
Something came through the window and fell
on the floor. Alice looked down. It was a
little cake.
'A cake? Why did they throw a cake?' she wondered.
Then she thought, 'I'll eat it and perhaps
I'll get smaller again. I can't get bigger!'
So she ate the cake and two or three minutes
later she was small again. She ran out of
the house as quickly as she could.
The White Rabbit saw her. He ran after her
but Alice ran too fast for him. After some
time, she came to a wood. She was tired because
she was very small now.
'I have to get bigger again,' said Alice.
'But how? I have to eat or drink something,
but the question is - what?'
That was the question. She looked all round
her, but she couldn't see anything with 'EAT
ME' or 'DRINK ME' on it. There were some mushrooms
near her. Some were white and some were brown.
'I eat mushrooms for dinner,' she thought.
'I'll eat some mushrooms and perhaps I'll
get bigger again.'
One white mushroom was as big as Alice. She
stood up tall and looked over the top. There,
on top of the mushroom, was a large green
caterpillar.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Caterpillar
The Caterpillar looked at Alice for some time
before it spoke. Then it said slowly, 'Who
are you?'
It was a difficult question. 'I... I don't
really know, Sir,' Alice said. 'I was Alice
when I got up this morning. But then I changed
- and then I changed again - and again.'
'What do you mean?' the Caterpillar asked.
'I don't know,' Alice answered. 'You see,
I'm not me now.'
'I don't understand,' said the Caterpillar.
'I'll try and tell you,' said Alice. 'You
see, I change all the time. It's very difficult
for me.'
'Why? I can change very easily.'
'Well, perhaps it's not difficult for you,
but it is for me,' said Alice.
'For you? Who are you?' said the Caterpillar
and laughed. Alice felt angry. 'It asked me
that question before,' she thought. She stood
very tall and said, 'I will tell you, but
first, you tell me. Who are you?'
'Why do I have to tell you?' asked the Caterpillar.
This was another difficult question and Alice
could not answer it.
'This caterpillar isn't very friendly,' she
thought. So she walked away.
'Come back!' the Caterpillar called. 'I want
to tell you something important.' Alice turned
and came back again.
'Don't get angry,' said the Caterpillar.
'Is that all?' Alice asked. She felt very
angry with the Caterpillar.
'No,' said the Caterpillar.
It did not speak for some minutes, then it
said, 'So you're different, are you?'
'Yes, I am, Sir,' said Alice. 'I can't remember
things, and my size changes all the time.
Sometimes I get bigger and then I get smaller
again.'
'So you can't remember things,' said the Caterpillar.
'Try this. Repeat, "You are old, Father William."'
Alice put her hands behind her back and repeated:
'You are old, Father William,' the young man
said,
'And your hair is now very white;
So why do you often stand on your head -
Do you think at your age it is right?'
'You are old, Father William,' the young man
said,
'You are old and really quite fat;
But you jump up and down and turn round and
round,
Now what is the answer to that?'
'That is not right,' said the Caterpillar.
'I know. Some of the words are different,'
said Alice.
'It's wrong from beginning to end,' said the
Caterpillar. It was quiet for a time. Then
it asked, 'What size would you like to be?'
'I'd like to be taller,' said Alice. 'Seven
centimetres is too small.'
'Seven centimetres is a very good size,' said
the Caterpillar angrily. It stood up very
tall.
'It's a good size for you, but not for me,'
said Alice. And she thought, 'Why does it
get angry all the time?'
The Caterpillar was quiet for some minutes.
Then it climbed down the mushroom. 'Eat from
my mushroom and you'll get bigger. Eat from
that brown mushroom there and you'll get smaller,'
it said. It started to move away a minute
later, it vanished behind a flower and Alice
never saw it again.
Alice looked at the two mushrooms and thought
for a minute. Then she went to the Caterpillars
mushroom and broke off some of it with her
right hand. She went to the brown mushroom
and did the same with her left hand.
She ate some of the brown mushroom. Suddenly,
her head hit her foot.
'Oh!' she cried. 'I'm really small!'
She quickly ate a little from the white mushroom
in her left hand. She started to get bigger.
She ate some more, and got very tall. Then
she ate some from one hand and some from the
other. In a short time, she was her right
size again.
She felt quite strange. 'What shall I do now?'
she wondered. 'I know! I'll look for that
beautiful garden.'
She began to walk through the wood. After
some time, she came to a little house. It
was about one meter high.
'I can't go inside, I'm too big,' Alice thought.
'The people in the house will be afraid of
me. I know! I'll eat some of the brown mushroom.'
When she was 18 centimetres high, she walked
to the house. She opened the door and went
in.
CHAPTER SIX
The Duchess and the Cheshire Cat
Inside, a large, ugly woman sat with a baby
in her arms. There was a cook by the fire
and there was food on the table. Near the
fire, there was a large cat with a big smile.
This smile went from ear to ear on its face.
'I think that woman is the Duchess,' thought
Alice. 'Can girls speak to Duchesses?' she
wondered.
But the Duchess did not say anything to her,
so Alice asked, 'Please, why is your cat smiling?'
'Because it's a Cheshire Cat, that's why,'
said the Duchess.
'So Cheshire Cats can smile. I didn't know
that,' said Alice.
'You don't know much,' said the Duchess.
'That's not very polite,' thought Alice.
She started to say something. Suddenly, the
cook threw a plate at the Duchess. The Duchess
didn't move. The cook threw more things - plates,
cups, spoons. Some of them hit the Duchess
and the baby. The Duchess did nothing, but
the baby started to cry. 'Oh, don't throw
things at the baby!' cried Alice. 'You'll
hit its pretty nose!'
'You be quiet, it isn't your baby!' the Duchess
shouted. She began to sing to it. These were
the words of the song:
Be angry with your little boy,
And hit him when he cries:
He has to know that he's a child,
He's really not your size!
The cook sang the song too. When they finished,
they sang it again. The Duchess started to
throw the baby up and down. At the end of
the song, she threw the baby to Alice.
'Here, you can have it now,' site said. 'I
have to get ready. I'm going to see the Queen.'
The cook threw another plate at the Duchess.
It didn't hit her, but she left the room quickly.
Alice looked at the baby. It was a strange
little thing and not very pretty. She took
it outside. 'I'll have to take this child
away from here, or they'll kill it!' she thought.
The baby made a strange little sound and she
looked at it again.
'Its nose is changing!' she cried. She looked
at it very carefully. 'Its face is changing,
everything is changing! Oh! It's not a baby
any more, it's a pig!'
It was very strange, but the baby was now
a pig.
'What am I going to do with it?' Alice thought.
The pig made another, louder sound. Alice
put the little animal down and it ran happily
away into the wood.
'It wasn't a pretty baby, but it's quite a
pretty pig,' thought Alice.
She looked round her and jumped. The Cheshire
Cat was up in one of the trees. The Cat smiled
at Alice.
'It looks kind, but perhaps it will get angry.
They all get angry in this place,' thought
Alice. So she spoke to it very politely. 'Cheshire
Cat, dear,' she said.
The Cat's smile got bigger.
'Please, can you help me? I want to go somewhere
new,' said Alice.
'Where do you want to go?' asked the Cat.
'Somewhere different,' Alice said.
'Somewhere different,' repeated the Cat. It
thought for a minute or two. Then it said,
'Walk that way and you'll come to a house.
A man lives there. He makes hats and he's
very strange. We call him the "Mad Hatter".'
'But I don't want to meet a strange man,'
said Alice.
The cat didn't answer her. It said, 'Walk
this way and you'll find the March Hare. He's
strange too.'
'But I told you, I don't want to meet strange
animals.'
'Oh, you can't help that,' said the cat. 'We're
all strange here. I'm strange. You're strange.'
'How do you know I'm strange?' asked Alice.
'Of course you are,' the Cat said. 'Everybody's
strange here. I'm very strange. I laugh when
I'm sad, and I cry when I'm happy. That's
strange. Are you going to see the Queen today?
She's quite strange too?'
'I'd like to see the Queen,' Alice said, 'but
I haven't got an invitation?'
'You'll see me in the Queen's garden?' said
the Cheshire Cat, and vanished.
'That's strange, but not very strange,' thought
Alice. She waited for two minutes, and the
Cat came back again.
'What happened to the baby?' it asked.
'It changed into a pig? Alice said.
'I knew it!' said the Cat and vanished again.
Alice stayed under the tree for a short time.
'Perhaps it will come back again?' she thought.
'But it didn't.'
'I think I'll go and visit the March Hare?'
said Alice. She started to walk to his home.
After some minutes, she heard a sound. She
looked up, and there was the Cheshire Cat
in a tree - a different tree.
'Did you say "pig"?' asked the Cat.
'Yes?' Alice answered. Then she said, 'Cheshire
Cat, one minute you vanish and the next minute
you're there again. I don't like it?'
'I know?' said the cat. And this time it vanished
quite slowly. First its body went, then its
legs. Then all of it vanished, and there was
only its smile.
'There are a lot of cats without a smile,
but a smile without a cat! Now that's very
strange!' Alice said.
Slowly, the Cheshire Cat's smile vanished
too, and Alice began to walk again. She saw
the March Hare's house through the trees.
It was bigger than the Duchess's house.
Alice ate some of the white mushrooms. She
got bigger again. In a short time she was
about 60 centimetres high. She felt afraid,
but walked to the house.
'I hope the March Hare isn't too strange,'
she thought.
CHAPTER SEVEN
A Tea Party
There was a tree in front of the house. Under
the tree was a big table with a lot of chairs
round it. But there were only three at the
table: the Mad Hatter, the March Hare and
a large brown mouse. The Mouse sat between
the Mad Hatter and the March Hare. It was
asleep, so they talked over its head.
When they saw Alice, they cried, 'No, no,
you can't sit here! There isn't a place for
you!'
'There are a lot of places,' Alice said. She
sat down in a chair at one end of the table.
'Have some wine,' the Mad Hatter said politely.
Alice looked round the table but there was
only tea.
'I don't see any wine,' she answered.
'There isn't any,' said the March Hare.
'Then why did you say, "Have some wine"? It
wasn't very polite of you,' Alice said angrily.
'We didn't invite you to tea, but you came.
That wasn't very polite of you,' said the
March Hare.
'No, it wasn't. Cut your hair!' said the Mad
Hatter.
'Oh, be quiet,' said Alice.
The Mad Hatter opened his eyes very wide,
but he said nothing. Then he took out his
watch and looked at it. 'What day is it?'
he asked.
Alice thought for a little. 'Wednesday, I
think,' she said.
'My watch says Monday,' the Mad Hatter said.
'You see, I was right. Butter isn't good for
a watch.' He looked angrily at the March Hare.
'But it was the best butter,' answered the
March Hare.
'Yes, but you put it in with the bread knife.
Perhaps some bread got in.'
The March Hare took the watch from the Mad
Hatter and looked at it sadly. Then he put
it in his tea. He took it out and looked at
it again.' It was the best butter, you know,'
he repeated.
Alice looked at the watch. 'It's a strange
watch!' she said. 'It tells you the day, but
it doesn't tell you the time.'
'So? Does your watch tell you the year?' asked
the Mad Hatter.
'No,' Alice answered, 'but it's the same year
for a very long time.'
'And my watch doesn't tell the time because
it's always tea-time.'
Alice thought about that. 'I don't really
understand you,' she said politely. She looked
round the table. There were a lot of teacups
on the table.
'We move from place to place,' said the Mad
Hatter.
'Don't you wash the cups?' asked Alice.
'No, we don't have time,' said the Mad Hatter.
'Why not?' asked Alice.
'It's a long story,' said the Mad Hatter.
'Time was my friend, you see. But he and I
aren't friends now. So he doesn't do anything
for me. And I don't have time for anything.'
'I see,' said Alice and smiled politely. But
she didn't really understand.
'Oh, look! The Mouse is asleep again,' said
the Mad Hatter. He took his teacup and put
a little hot tea on the Mouse's nose. It woke
up and started to sing.
'Be quiet!' the Mad Hatter said very loudly,
and the Mouse stopped singing.
'Have some more tea,' the March Hare said
to Alice.
'Thank you, but I haven't got any tea. So
how can I have some more?'
'You can have more,' the Mad Hatter said.
'You can have more than nothing.'
'I don't think-' Alice began.
'Then don't speak,' the Mad Hatter said.
Alice got up angrily and walked away from
the table into the woods.
'Perhaps they'll call me back,' she thought.
'And then they'll be nice to me and give me
some tea and bread-and-butter.'
But they didn't say anything.
When she looked back, the Mouse was asleep
with its head on its plate.
"I'll never go there again,' Alice said. 'That
was a stupid tea party!'
She looked round and saw a door in one of
the trees. 'A door in a tree? That's strange!'
she thought. And she opened the door and went
inside.
'Oh, good!' she cried. She was back in the
long room, near the little table! 'I'm small
now. I can get through the little door into
the garden.'
The key was on the table. She took it and
opened the little door. Then she ate some
of the brown mushroom. She started to get
smaller. When she was about 30 centimeters
high, she walked through the door into the
garden.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Inside the Garden
Near Alice was a small tree with flowers on
it. There were three gardeners by the tree.
'Be careful, Five!' one of them said.
'I'm always careful, Seven,' answered Five.
Alice went to them. 'What are you doing?'
she asked.
'We're making the flowers red,' one of the
gardeners said.
'That's strange!' thought Alice. 'Why?' she
asked.
The three men looked unhappy.
'You tell her, Seven,' Five said.
'No,' said Seven,' You tell her, Two.'
'Well, Miss, the Queen wanted trees with red
flowers on them. But this tree's got white
flowers! We don't want the Queen to see it.
She'll be very angry and cut off our heads.
So we're making the flowers red before she
sees them.'
'Oh no!' Five shouted suddenly.' The Queen!
The Queen!'
The three gardeners fell to the ground, with
their faces down. Alice heard the sound of
many feet and turned round.
'Oh good!' she thought. 'Now I'll see the
Queen.'
First, ten men with clubs in their hands came
into the garden. Next came the King's men.
There were ten of them, and they had red diamonds
on their clothes. The children of the King
and Queen came next, all with red hearts.
After them there were a lot more people. Most
of them were Kings and Queens. The White Rabbit
was there, but he didn't see Alice. The Knave
of Hearts came next. Last of all were the
King and Queen of Hearts.
When these people saw Alice, they all stopped.
The Queen said to the Knave of Hearts, 'Who
is this?'
The Knave of Hearts didn't know. So he smiled
and said nothing.
'Stupid man!' shouted the Queen. She turned
to Alice and said, 'What's your name, child?'
'My name is Alice, Madam,' Alice answered.
She didn't feel very afraid of the Queen.
'They're only cards,' she thought.
The Queen looked at the gardeners. They were
on the ground and she couldn't see their faces.
Who are these men?' she asked.
'Don't ask me! I don't know,' answered Alice,
not very politely.
The Queen's face got redder and redder. She
looked at Alice and shouted, 'Cut off her
head! Cut-'
'Oh, be quiet!' said Alice.
The Queen stopped shouting. The King put his
hand on her arm. He said quietly, 'Don't be
angry, my dear. She's only a child.'
The Queen turned away from him angrily. 'Turn
those men over!' she said to the Knave of
Hearts. The Knave did this very carefully,
with one foot.
'Get up!' the Queen shouted.
The three gardeners jumped up. The Queen turned
to the little tree and looked at it carefully.
'What's wrong with these flowers?' she asked
the gardeners.
'Well, you see, M - M - Madam,' said Two.
'They were white, and - and-'
The Queen looked from the flowers to the men.
'I see,' she said. 'Cut off their heads!'
Everybody started walking again. The gardeners
ran to Alice. 'Help us!' they cried. Alice
put them behind some trees.
'Don't be afraid,' she said. 'They're not
going to cut off your heads.'
The Kings men looked for the gardeners but
couldn't find them. 'Are their heads off?'
shouted the Queen.
'Yes, Madam,' shouted the King's men.
'Good!' shouted the Queen.
Everybody started walking again and Alice
walked with them.
'It's a very fine day,' somebody said. Alice
turned round and there was the White Rabbit
next to her.
'Very,' said Alice. 'Where's the Duchess?'
'Quiet!' said the Rabbit and looked all round
him. Then he put his mouth near to Alice's
ear. 'They're going to cut off her head!'
he said.
'Why?' asked Alice.
'Did you say, "Oh no!"?' asked the White Rabbit.
'No, I didn't. I said, "Why?"'
'She hit the Queen,' the Rabbit said. Alice
started to laugh.
'Quiet!' said the Rabbit again. 'The Queen
will hear you, she hears everything. You see,
the Duchess came late. When she arrived, the
Queen said-'
Suddenly, the Queen shouted very loudly, 'Cut
off their heads!'
'Who's going to lose their head now?' Alice
wondered. She began to feel afraid. 'The Queen
isn't angry with me now,' she thought. 'But
it will happen. I would like to speak to somebody
about it.'
She looked round. The White Rabbit wasn't
there. She looked up. There was something
above her head.
'What is it?' she wondered. She watched for
a minute or two. It was a smile! 'It's the
Cheshire Cat,' she thought. 'Now I can talk
to somebody.'
'How are you?' the Cheshire Cat asked.
Alice waited. She thought, 'I won't speak
to it before it has its ears - or perhaps
one ear.'
In another minute, she could see its ears
and eyes.
'Do you like the Queen?' the Cat asked.
'I don't,' said Alice. But then she saw the
Queen. She was very near Alice. 'She's wonderful,'
said Alice. The Queen smiled and moved away.
But the King saw the Cat's head and came to
Alice.
'Who are you talking to?' he asked.
'It's a friend - a Cheshire Cat,' answered
Alice.
The King looked carefully at the Cat. 'I don't
like it,' said the King.
'Well, I don't like you,' said the Cat.
'That's not polite,' said the King and got
behind Alice.
Alice said, 'A cat can look at a King. I read
that in a book, I think.'
'Well, this cat has to go,' said the King.
He called to the Queen, 'My dear, I don't
like this cat.'
The Queen had only one answer to problems.
'Cut off its head!' she shouted loudly. She
didn't look at the Cat. The King smiled happily.
After a short time, there were a lot of people
round the Cat. There was the King and Queen,
and a man with a very long knife in his hand.
'How can I cut off its head?' asked the man
with the knife. 'I can't do it and I'm not
going to.'
'Oh yes you are,' said the King. 'It's got
a head, so you can cut it off.'
'Do something now, or I'll cut off everybody's
head!' said the Queen angrily.
'What do you think?' the King asked Alice.
Alice thought for a minute. Then she said,
'It's the Duchess's Cat. Ask her about it.'
'Bring the Duchess here,' the Queen said.
Then the Cheshire Cat's head started to vanish.
Somebody came back with the Duchess. But now
there was nothing above Alices head - not
an eye or an ear or a smile. The King looked
for the Cat for some time, but he couldn't
find it anywhere.
'Come for a walk, you dear thing,' the Duchess
said to Alice. She put her arm through Alice's
and they walked through the garden.
'She's very friendly to me,' thought Alice.
'Perhaps when the cook isn't there, she's
nice. When I'm a Duchess, I'm going to be
kind to my children.'
'Are you thinking?' asked the Duchess. 'You
have to talk to me, you know.'
'All right,' said Alice. She could hear the
Queen at the other end of the garden. 'Cut
off her head! Cut off his head!' she shouted,
every two or three minutes.
'Will they cut off your head?' Alice asked
the Duchess.
'Oh no, they never cut off anybody's head.
The Queen likes saying it, but she never does
it.'
Alice wanted to ask more questions but they
heard a cry: "The trial is beginning!"
'What trial is it?' Alice asked. The Duchess
didn't answer and started to run. Her arm
was in Alice's, so Alice ran too.
CHAPTER NINE
Who Took the Tarts?
Alice and the Duchess followed everybody into
a house with one very large room. The King
and Queen were there. They sat on big chairs
above all the animals and birds. All the cards
were there too. Near the King was the White
Rabbit. He had a paper in his hand and looked
very important. The Knave of Hearts stood
in front of the King and Queen. He stood between
two men and his head was down. It was his
trial. In the middle of the room was a table
with a large plate of tarts on it.
Alice found a place and sat down. She looked
round.
'I know a lot of the animals and birds here,'
she thought. She looked hungrily at the tarts.
'I hope they finish the trial quickly,' she
thought. 'Then we can eat the tarts.'
Suddenly, the White Rabbit cried, 'Quiet please!'
The King looked round the room. 'Read the
paper!' he said. The White Rabbit stood up
and read from a very long paper:
The Queen of Hearts, she made some tarts,
One lovely sunny day;
The Knave of Hearts, he took those tarts,
He took them all away.
'Cut off his head!' cried the Queen.
'No, no,' said the Rabbit. 'We have to call
people into the room, and ask them questions.'
'All right then. Call the Mad Hatter!' said
the King.
The Mad Hatter came into the room. He had
a teacup in one hand, and some bread-and-butter
in the other hand.
'Why did you call me? I wanted to finish my
tea,' he said.
'When did you begin your tea?' asked the King.
The Mad Hatter thought for a minute. The March
Hare and the Mouse were quite near him and
he looked at them for ideas. Then he said,
'March the fourteenth - I think.'
'Fifteenth,' said the March Hare.
'Sixteenth,' said the Mouse.
'Write that down,' said the King to the White
Rabbit. Then he said to the Mad Hatter, 'Take
off your hat.'
'It isn't mine,' said the Mad Hatter.
'Oh, so you took it from somebody, you bad
man,' said the King.
'No, no! I sell hats. I'm a Hatter,' answered
the Mad Hatter. He looked very afraid.
'Don't be afraid or I'll cut off your head!'
said the King.
'I'm not a bad man!' the Mad Hatter cried.
'But the March Hare told me-'
'I didn't!' the March Hare said quickly.
'Well, the Mouse said...' The Mad Hatter stopped
and looked at the Mouse. But the Mouse didn't
say anything, because he was asleep.
'After that,' said the Mad Hatter, 'I cut
some more bread-and-butter.'
'But what did the Mouse say?' asked the King.
'I can't remember,' the Mad Hatter said.
'You have to remember,' the King said, 'or
I'll cut off your head.'
'I'm a good man, Sir...' the unhappy Mad Hatter
began. But the King wasn't interested now.
'You can go,' he said to the Mad Hatter.
The Mad Hatter ran out of the room.
'Take his head off outside!' shouted the Queen.
Two men ran after him. But the Mad Hatter
ran very fast and they could not catch him.
Alice did not feel very well. 'What's wrong
with me?' she wondered. And then she understood.
'I'm getting bigger again,' she thought.
She was between the Duchess and the Mouse.
'You're hurting me,' the Duchess said.
'I can't do anything,' said Alice. 'I'm getting
bigger.'
'You can't get bigger here,' said the Mouse.
'Yes, I can,' said Alice. 'You're getting
bigger too.'
'Yes, but not as fast as you,' said the Mouse.
He got up and sat in a different place.
'Call the next person!' said the King.
The next person came in. It was the Duchess's
cook.
The King looked at her. 'What do you know
about these tarts?' he asked. The cook didn't
answer.
'Speak!' said the King.
'No!' said the cook.
'Ask her some questions,' the White Rabbit
said to the King.
'All right, all right,' said the King. 'What
was in those tarts?'
'Fish,' said the cook.
'Don't be stupid,' said the King. 'Call the
next person!'
Alice looked round. 'Who can it be?' she wondered.
The White Rabbit looked at his paper and read
the next name: 'Alice!'
CHAPTER TEN
The End of the Trial
'Here!' cried Alice and stood up quickly.
But she was tall now, and chairs, tables and
people fell here, there and everywhere.
'Put everything and everybody back!' said
the King loudly. Alice put them all back in
their places. Then the King asked, 'What do
you know about these tarts?'
'Nothing,' answered Alice.
'That's very important,' said the King.
'You mean, unimportant, Sir,' said the White
Rabbit. 'Unimportant - of course,' said the
King. 'Important - unimportant - important
- unimportant,' he repeated.
He looked at Alice carefully. He took a book
and read from it. 'Alice is more than a kilometer
high. So she has to leave the room!' he said.
'I'm not more than a kilometer high - Alice
began.
'You are,' said the King.
'More than two kilometers high,' said the
Queen.
'Well, I'm not leaving this room,' said Alice.
The King's face went white.
'Cut off her head!' shouted the Queen. Nobody
moved.
'You stupid woman,' said Alice. She was very
large now and she wasn't afraid of anybody.
'Cut off her head!' shouted the Queen.
'Don't be stupid!' Alice said. 'Who's afraid
of you? I'm not. You're only cards!'
The cards - all fifty-two of them - came down
on top of Alice. She felt afraid and angry
and started to fight them. Then she opened
her eyes...
She saw a tree, a big old tree. She was under
it, next to her sister. Her sister's hand
was on her hair.
'Wake up, Alice dear,' her sister said. 'You
slept for a long time!'
'Oh!' said Alice, and then she understood.
She sat up and told her sister about the White
Rabbit and the rabbit-hole. When she finished
her story, her sister laughed.
'Let's go home to tea,' she said. 'It's getting
late.'
'Oh yes! I'd like some tea!' cried Alice.
And she got up and ran home.
- THE END -