CHAPTER ONE
A Visitor
My name's Samuel. Lenny
Samuel. You can call me Len.
I'm a private eye. A private eye is a
private detective - a detective who will
work for anyone who will pay him. I'm not a
policeman. I work on my own as a private eye.
My office is on the west side of Los Angeles,
on the fourth floor of a high building.
There are only two rooms in my office - the
outer room and the inner room. The outer
room is the waiting-room. There are four chairs
in the waiting-room, although there are never
four people waiting to see me. In fact, there
is usually no one at all waiting to see me.
In the inner room, there's a cheap wooden desk.
There's a big wooden chair for me to sit on and,
on the opposite side of the desk, there's
a low metal chair for my visitors.
The rest of the furniture in my office
consists of a large, empty metal cupboard,
and a low bed in one corner. When there is a
lot of work, I sometimes sleep in the office.
The notice outside my door says: "L. Samuel.
Private Detective." That's me. I'm quite tall,
nearly two metres, and I weigh eighty
kilos. A lot of men say that I'm ugly,
but women seem to find me attractive. I've got
brown eyes, brown hair and very nice teeth.
I had a good nose, too, until someone
broke it in a fight last year.
Recently, I haven't been very busy.
In fact, I've had very little to do.
However, I did have some work last month.
It all started late one afternoon, when I
was sitting in my office. I had just finished
cutting my nails and I was about to clean them.
Suddenly, I heard someone
walk into the outer room.
I always leave the door of the outer room open,
in case anyone wants to come in and see me.
When I heard the footsteps in the
outer room, I wasn't very surprised.
I thought that someone had made a
mistake and come into the wrong office.
It was probably someone looking
for the doctor next door.
But a moment later, there was a very
quiet knock on the door of the inner room.
'Come in,' I shouted and put away the
scissors I had been cutting my nails with.
The door opened and in walked one
of the most beautiful women I had
ever seen. She was about eighteen years
old, with blue eyes and long blonde hair.
She was wearing a smart green coat and
had a big brown handbag over her shoulder.
'Excuse me,' said the girl.
'I'm looking for Mr Samuel.'
'I'm Samuel,' I said, with a quick
smile. 'Come in and sit down.'
The girl didn't smile back at me.
'No, I won't sit down,' she said.
'Well, if you won't sit down, at least
come in and close the door,' I replied.
The girl came in, walked over
and put her handbag on my desk.
'Now,' I said, 'what can I do for you?'
'I need help,' said the girl slowly.
'But I don't know if you will be able to
help me. Are you a real private detective?'
'Of course I am,' I replied angrily. 'Didn't
you see the notice on the office door?
It says "L. Samuel. Private Detective."
I'm Samuel. I'm a private eye.'
'All right, Mr Samuel,' the girl said
coldly. 'There's no need to get angry.
I have a little job for you.'
'Right,' I said quickly.
'What do you want me to do?'
'It's very simple really,' the girl replied.
'I want you to find my sister.
She has disappeared.'
CHAPTER TWO
Please Find My Sister
'I see,' I said. 'Your sister has disappeared.
Have you reported her
disappearance to the police?'
The blonde girl shook her head. She looked
very nervous and was starting to cry.
'No, I haven't told the police,' she said.
'I don't want any trouble with the police.
I just want you to help find my sister.' She
took a small, pink handkerchief out
of her handbag and dried her eyes.
'All right,' I said. 'Tell
me all about your sister.'
'Her name is Elaine Garfield,' said the girl.
'And what's your name?' I interrupted.
'Helen. Helen Garfield,' she replied.
'My sister disappeared a week ago.
We had arranged to have dinner together
last Monday night, but she didn't come.'
'Perhaps your sister didn't come because she
doesn't like the food you cook,' I suggested.
'Don't try to be funny. I flew all the
way from New York to see her last Monday,'
she said angrily.
'Oh, so you don't live in
Los Angeles, then,' I said.
'No,' she replied quickly, 'I live in New York.
I flew right across America to see my sister,
but, when I got here, I discovered
that she had disappeared.'
'How do you know she has disappeared?' I asked.
'Perhaps your sister just
forgot about the dinner.'
The blonde girl took a deep breath.
'Look,' she said, 'Let me finish my story. If you
don't stop asking questions, I'll
find myself another detective.'
'Right,' I said, 'I'm listening.'
'I waited for my sister last Monday evening, in
my hotel,' said the girl. 'But she didn't come.
I telephoned her, but there was no answer. So
the next morning, I went to the office where
she worked. At her office, they said that she
had been to work the day before, on the Monday.
They also told me that she'd left
suddenly, in the middle of the afternoon,
without telling anyone. After that I went
round to her flat, but there was no one there.'
The girl stopped for a minute, and then continued.
'Mr Samuel,' she said, 'I'm very worried
about my sister. It's not usual for her to
disappear suddenly like this. I'm sure that
she's in danger and I want you to find her.'
'All right,' I said. 'It may
be easy or it may be difficult,
but I'll find her. But first, tell me why
you've waited six days before coming to me.'
'That's none of your business,' the girl said.
'OK,' I replied. 'Your sister's name is
Elaine Garfield. What does she look like?'
'Oh, that's easy,' Helen Garfield
replied, 'she looks like me. We're twins.
Now, Mr Samuel, how much money do you charge?
'Fifty dollars a day,' I said.
'Very well, Mr Samuel,' said the girl,
'but fifty dollars a day is a lot of money.
I hope that you will work hard for it.'
'Oh yes,' I replied, with a smile, 'I'll work
very hard. Now give me the address of your
sister's flat, and the name of the office
where she works. I'll start work at once.'
The blonde girl wrote the addresses on
a piece of paper and gave me the paper.
'One more thing,' I said. 'Can
you give me your address, too?'
'That won't be necessary,' she
replied, as she picked up her handbag.
'I'll come and see you again tomorrow afternoon,
at five o'clock. Goodbye, Mr Samuel.'
Without waiting for an answer, the girl
turned around and walked out of the office.
As I watched her walk out of
my office, I smiled to myself.
'This is better than cleaning my nails,'
I thought. Then I began my work.
CHAPTER THREE
The Manson Building
After the blonde girl had left my office,
I looked at the two addresses which she had
written on the piece of paper. The first was:
Elaine Garfield,
Apartment 716,
Manson Building,
Sunset Place.
The second address was:
Myer and Myer,
Attorneys,
Title-Insurance Building
Putting the paper in my pocket, I
got up and walked towards the door.
Then I stopped and went back to my desk. I opened
the top left-hand drawer and took out my gun,
a .38 Smith and Wesson. Then I
put the gun back in the drawer.
I decided that it was safer to leave it behind.
It's easy to get shot, if you're carrying a gun.
I ran down the stairs, all four
floors, and out into the street.
My old grey Chrysler was outside, so I jumped
in and drove off fast, towards Sunset Place.
The Manson Building was a tall,
ugly block of apartments. I parked
the Chrysler outside and walked
towards the big glass front doors.
'Hey, mister!' a voice said.
I continued walking.
'Hey, mister!' said the voice again.
'You can't leave your car there.'
I stopped and turned around. A man in a
grey uniform was standing by the Chrysler.
'Hey, mister!' the man repeated,
'you can't park your car here.'
'Why not?' I asked.
'Because only people who live in the
Manson Building can park here,' he replied.
'So,' I said, 'How do you know that
I don't live in the Manson Building?'
'Because I'm the porter,' the man
replied. 'I work in the entrance of
the building and let people in and out
of the door. I know everybody here.'
'Right,' I said, 'then please let me in.'
The porter and I walked up to the big
glass front doors and he let me in.
'Who do you want to see?' the porter asked.
'Miss Elaine Garfield,' I said.
'She lives in Apartment 716.'
'I'm sorry,' the porter
replied, 'Miss Garfield is out.'
'When did she go out?' I asked,
trying not to look interested.
'Mind your own business,' said the
porter. 'I'm not going to tell you.
And I'm not going to let you go up to Miss
Garfield's apartment, when she's not there.'
'Why don't you go for a
walk?' I said to the porter
and put five dollars in his hand. I gave
the porter the money to make him go away.
The porter shook his head.
'No,' he said.
I gave the porter five dollars more.
'Now go for a long walk,' I said.
The porter went out into the street
and I went up to Apartment 716,
Miss Elaine Garfield's apartment.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Very Tidy Apartment
I rang the bell beside the door
of Apartment 716 and waited.
There was no answer. I rang again, but there
was still no answer. Then I took a small,
square piece of plastic out of my pocket. I
looked around. I was alone. I pushed the piece
of plastic into the space between the door and
the door frame and moved the plastic up and down.
In a minute, the door opened
and I went into the flat.
I stood still and listened. There was silence.
I switched on the light and looked
around. It was a modern apartment.
I was standing in the living-room. Through an
open door on my left, I could see the bedroom
which was very neat and tidy. I looked
in the wardrobe - it was almost empty.
'That's funny,' I thought. 'People who disappear
don't usually take most of their clothes with
them. They only take their clothes if they've been
planning their disappearance for a long time.'
I walked back into the living-room
and searched it carefully.
But I found nothing to explain
Elaine Garfield's disappearance.
Then I went into the kitchen. The kitchen was
also very clean and tidy. There were no dirty
plates or cups. There was no old milk in the
refrigerator. Everything was in its place.
'Well,' I thought, 'there's only
the bathroom left to search now.'
The bathroom, too, was empty and clean. I walked
quickly around the flat, making sure that I hadn't
forgotten anything. I wiped everything I had
touched with my handkerchief, because I didn't
want to leave any fingerprints. Then I switched
off the lights and opened the door to leave.
But I didn't leave. There were two men standing
outside the door. One of them was short and had
red hair and a nasty smile. The other was
quite tall and was wearing a hat pulled
down over his face. The one with the hat was
holding a gun and the gun was pointing at me.
I tried to close the door, but the red-haired
man put his foot out to stop the door closing.
I let go of the door. The door
opened and both the men came
in. The one with the hat was in front
and he was still carrying the gun.
'Hold your hands up in the
air,' said the man with the gun.
Then he turned to the red-haired man.
'See if he's got a gun on him, Jo.'
Jo, the red-haired man, came over towards me. I
waited. When Jo was between me and the man with
the gun, I jumped. I jumped forward and caught
Jo around the neck. I held him in front of me.
The man with the gun couldn't shoot
because he would hit his friend.
'Right,' I said to the man with
the gun. 'Get out of the way.
I'm leaving now and I'm
taking your friend with me.'
Holding Jo in front of me, I walked
slowly towards the man with the gun.
Then something went wrong with my plan.
The man with the gun started to laugh. He put
the gun back in his pocket and stood laughing.
'Why are you laughing?' I asked.
'I'm laughing because you're so stupid,' the
man with the gun said and walked up to me.
'Stop,' I said, 'or else I'll...'
'What will you do?' asked the man with the gun.
'You can't do anything. I'm the one with the gun.'
As he said this, the man leant forward. He
pulled Jo out of my hands and hit me in the face.
I must say that I wasn't
expecting to be hit in the face.
It hurt. It hurt even more when he hit me again
and I fell on the floor. I lay still on the floor,
hoping that the two men would go away. But
they didn't go away. Instead, they picked me
up and hit me hard on the head. Everything went
black. I lay on the floor - I was unconscious.
CHAPTER FIVE
Myer and Myer
I woke up with a terrible pain in my head.
I was lying on the floor outside the front door of
Miss Elaine Garfield's apartment. I looked around.
The man with the gun and his red-haired friend had
left. I was alone and I had a terrible headache.
I got up slowly and felt my head gently, to see
if there was any blood. There wasn't any blood,
but my head was still very painful. I decided
to go back to the office and go to bed.
There was no sign of the porter at
the entrance to the Manson Building.
I walked out of the door and across to the old
grey Chrysler. I drove slowly back to the office.
The telephone was ringing when I arrived at
the office. I went in quickly and answered it.
'Samuel speaking.'
'Listen, Samuel,' replied a
voice. 'Forget about Elaine
Garfield. We hurt you a little in her apartment.
If you don't forget all about Elaine
Garfield, we'll hurt you a lot more.'
'Who are you?' I asked.
But there was no answer. The
man had put down the telephone.
I decided to do what the man had told me. I would
forget all about Elaine Garfield - for ten hours.
After a good night's sleep, I would look for
Elaine Garfield. I would also try to find the
man with the gun and his friend, Jo. I lay down
on the hard, low bed and went straight to sleep.
I woke up the next morning at eight
o'clock. I felt my head carefully,
but it did not hurt so much now.
I left the office and went across the street
to the cafe where I usually had breakfast.
I drank a glass of orange juice, ate some
fresh toast and drank several cups of coffee.
I read the morning newspapers. There was a lot
of news, but nothing about Miss Elaine Garfield.
I looked at my watch, left the cafe
and walked over to the Chrysler.
By nine o'clock, I was outside
the Title Insurance Building.
At three minutes past nine, I was standing outside
the door of Myer and Myer, Attorneys. At twenty
past nine, I was still standing outside the door.
Nobody had arrived yet to work. At nine thirty,
the first secretary arrived and, at eighteen
minutes to ten, I was sitting in Mr Myer's office.
'Well, Mr Myer,' I said, 'my name's
Samuel and I'm a private detective.'
'I'm pleased to meet you,' Mr Myer said politely.
He was about fifty-five years old, with
a grey suit, grey hair and a grey face.
'Does Miss Elaine Garfield work here?' I asked.
'Yes, she does,' Mr Myer said,
'But she hasn't been to work since last
Monday. Why do you want to see Elaine?'
'Her sister has asked me to
help find her,' I replied.
'Can you think of anything Elaine said or
did which could explain her disappearance?'
Mr Myer scratched his head.
'No,' he said, 'I'm afraid I can't help you.'
'Who did Elaine work with?' I asked.
Mr Myer looked at me.
'Why do you say, "Who did Elaine work
with?" and not "Who does Elaine work with?"
Elaine's not dead, is she?' he asked.
I looked straight back at Mr Myer.
'I don't know if Elaine is dead or not,' I
said. 'Would you be very sad if she was dead?'
'Yes, of course I would be
sad!' Mr Myer replied angrily.
'Are you trying to suggest
that I know where Elaine is?'
I smiled.
'Now don't get excited, Mr Myer,' I said.
'Can you tell me the name of anyone who
works with Elaine - anyone who shares a
desk with her or works in the same room?'
'Yes,' Mr Myer said, 'that's easy.
Elaine shares a room with Suzy Graham.'
I got up.
'Thank you very much, Mr Myer,' I said.
'Where is Suzy Graham's office, please?'
'It's along the corridor,' said Mr
Myer 'the third door on the left.'
I thanked Mr Myer again and walked to the door.
'Oh, Mr Samuel,' Mr Myer said,
'I'm sorry that I got angry,
but you understand that I don't want...'
'Yes, I understand,' I interrupted. 'You don't
want dirty private detectives
in your nice, clean office.'
I walked out of Mr Myer's office
and banged the door behind me.
I walked slowly down the corridor and
knocked on the third door on the left.
'Come in,' said a voice.
So I went into the room.
'Are you Suzy Graham?' I asked.
'Yes,' said the girl sitting
at the desk. 'I'm Suzy.'
I smiled at her. Suzy, was the
kind of girl everyone smiled at.
She was small and slim and had
a pair of beautiful, brown eyes.
'What can I do to help you?' Suzy asked.
I smiled again.
'I'd like to ask you some questions, Miss Graham.'
'Don't call me Miss Graham,' the
girl said, 'you can call me Suzy.'
'Well, Suzy,' I said, 'I would like to ask
you some questions about a friend of yours.
Her name is Elaine Garfield.'
Suzy stopped smiling.
'Yes, all right,' she said. 'But I don't want
to talk about Elaine here in the office.'
'Right,' I replied, 'I'll tell you what
we'll do. We'll go out and find a cafe.
I'll buy you a cup of coffee and you
can tell me about Elaine. All right?'
Suzy cheered up and looked much happier.
'I'd like to have a cup of coffee,' she said, 'but
Mr Myer might get angry if I leave the office.'
'Don't worry about Mr Myer,' I said, with a
big smile. 'Mr Myer and I are great friends.'
CHAPTER SIX
Suzy
Suzy put on her coat and we
left the office together.
We found a little cafe, just opposite
the Title-Insurance Building.
In the cafe, I told Suzy why I was
asking questions about Elaine Garfield.
'Elaine's twin sister, Helen, thinks that
Elaine has disappeared, and she has asked
me to find Elaine,' I said. 'Helen told me that
she came to Myer and Myer last Tuesday. She was
told that Elaine had left work suddenly,
last Monday afternoon. Is that right?'
Suzy nodded.
'At least, part of it's right,' she said.
'Elaine was at work last Monday, and she
hurried off in the middle of the afternoon.'
Suzy stopped for a minute, and then she continued.
'But I don't remember seeing Elaine's sister,
Helen, on Tuesday. In fact, I didn't
even know that Elaine had a sister.'
'Elaine's sister lives in New York,' I explained.
'Now, can you remember last Monday afternoon?
Did Elaine give any reason for leaving suddenly?'
'Oh, yes,' Suzy said, 'Elaine said that she
wasn't feeling well and was going to lie down.'
'Did Elaine receive any visitors or phone
calls last Monday afternoon?' I asked.
'No, I don't think so,' said Suzy.
'No wait a minute, I think ... yes, Elaine did
receive a phone call, just before she left.'
I smiled.
'I don't suppose that, by chance, you might
have heard any of the telephone conversation?'
'Certainly not,' Suzy replied, 'I don't
listen to other people's phone calls.'
'Can you think of any reason why
Elaine disappeared?' I asked.
'No,' Suzy replied, 'Elaine was
always very friendly with everyone
and she didn't seem to have any troubles.'
'Did Elaine have any special friends, any men
or women she talked about a lot?' I asked.
'No, not really,' Suzy replied. 'Elaine and
I used to be quite friendly and we went out
dancing together a lot. But recently
we haven't been out together at all'
'I understand,' I said, though I really
didn't understand anything at all.
'Can you remember the last time you went out
together? Can you remember the place you went to?'
'Oh, that's easy,' Suzy said quickly, 'we went
to the Las Cabanas Club. We always went there.
It was about a month ago. We had an argument
there and we haven't gone out together since.'
'What was the argument about?' I asked.
'It was after midnight,' Suzy explained, 'and I
wanted to go home. But Elaine said she wanted to
stay a bit longer. She said that she had met a
wonderful man and didn't want to leave. I said
I was going home and I left Elaine in the club.
After that evening, one thing led to another.'
'What do you mean,' I asked,
"...one thing led to another"?'
Suzy smiled.
'I often spoke to Elaine
about the man she had met.
Elaine thought he was wonderful. I
told her that he was no good at all.'
'What did Elaine say when you told
her that?' I asked, with interest.
'She became very angry,' replied Suzy. 'We
haven't been out dancing together since then.'
I paid for the coffee.
'You've been very helpful, Suzy,'
I said, 'and I've only got one more
question. Can you remember the name of the
man Elaine Garfield met at Las Cabanas?'
'Benny Greep,' Suzy said,
'that's his name. Benny Greep.'
'Thank you very much indeed, Suzy,' I said,
with a smile. 'You've been a great help.'
'Not at all,' Suzy said and looked at
me with her beautiful, big, brown eyes.
'If there's anything else I
can do for you, just ask.'
I looked straight into her eyes.
'What are you doing tonight?' I asked.
'I'll be at home watching television,'
Suzy replied. 'My boyfriend's a boxer and he's
fighting in a match on television tonight.'
'Goodbye, Suzy,' I said and watched her as
she walked back across the street to the
Tide-Insurance Building. Her boyfriend
was a boxer! That was just my luck.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Benny Greep
I looked at my watch. It was nearly eleven
o'clock. I went back into the cafe and asked if I
could look at the telephone book. I turned to "L"
and ran my finger down the outside of the page.
Soon, I found the name I was looking for: "Las
Cabanas". I looked more closely. The address was:
Las Cabanas, 232 Golden Drive. Telephone: 323.0313
I left the cafe and walked over to
where I had parked the Chrysler.
It wasn't time for lunch yet, so I decided
to go and see what Las Cabanas was like.
It took me nearly twenty minutes to drive there
and another ten minutes to find somewhere to park.
Have you ever seen a night club in the
daytime? It's a very depressing sight.
At night, a nightclub seems wonderful.
However, at a quarter to twelve in the morning,
it looks old, empty and dirty. The man I met at
Las Cabanas looked old, empty and dirty, too.
I rang the bell for five minutes
before he answered the door.
Even then, he didn't open the door itself.
Instead, he opened a small window in the door.
'What do you want?' he asked. 'The club
doesn't open until ten o'clock tonight.'
'I'm looking for someone,' I said,
'someone called Benny Greep.'
'I don't know anyone called Benny Greep,' the
man replied and started to shut the window.
'Wait a minute,' I said and pushed
five dollars through the window.
'That's better,' the man said.
And he opened the door and let me in.
I followed him across the dance
floor. The man was a cleaner.
He picked up a brush and began to clean the floor.
'Do you know where I can find Benny
Greep?' I asked the man again.
'If you come back tonight at ten
o'clock, you'll find Benny Greep here,'
the man said. 'Benny plays the drums in the band.'
I gave the man another five dollars.
'Where can I find Benny now?' I asked.
The man picked up a piece of paper from
the floor and wrote an address on it.
I took the paper and left immediately.
As I drove the grey Chrysler
away from Las Cabanas,
I looked at the address the cleaner had written:
5314 ARVIEDA STREET
WEST LOS ANGELES
5314 Arvieda Street was an
old block of apartments.
I gave the porter a couple of dollars and he
told me which was Benny Greep's apartment. I
walked up the narrow, dark stairs until I came to
the fifth floor. I was looking for Apartment 507.
I knocked on the door of Apartment
507 and waited. There was no answer,
so I rang the bell. No answer. I knocked
again, hard. There was still no answer.
I pushed against the door and it opened easily.
I waited. There was no sound from the apartment,
so I went in. The light was on and the curtains
were drawn. The apartment was very small. There
was one main room, which was used as the
living-room, dining-room and bedroom.
The room had two doors. One of the doors led
into the kitchen and the other into the bathroom.
The main room was very untidy. The table
was covered with dirty plates and glasses
and there was a full ashtray lying on the
floor. There was a strange smell in the room.
I looked into the kitchen. The
kitchen was also dirty and untidy.
I walked across to the
bathroom and opened the door.
Benny Greep was in the bath. His left hand was
hanging over the side of the bath. The hand had
neatly cut nails, and there was a gold ring on one
finger. The wrist was covered by a shirt-sleeve,
which was rather dirty. I couldn't see the rest
of the arm, because it was under the water.
Benny Greep's head was just out of the water. He
had a handsome face and quite long, black hair.
His eyes were wide open. The only other parts
of his body out of the water were his feet.
But I couldn't see his toes because he still had
his shoes and socks on. The bath water was red.
I pulled out the plug in the bath, to let
the water out. When the bath was empty,
I looked at the dead man more closely. He had been
dead for several hours. He had been shot in the
chest and then pushed into the bath. I looked on
the floor by the bath. There was blood there, too,
and I was standing in it. I moved back and
cleaned the blood off my shoes with some water.
Then I quickly looked round the main
room again. The dead man's coat was
lying on a chair and I felt in the
pockets. I found a few dollars and
a driving licence. The driving licence
had a photograph of the dead man on it.
The licence belonged to Benny Greep,
and the address in the licence was 5314
Arvieda Street, West Los Angeles. The dead
man in the bath was definitely Benny Greep.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Arrested for Murder
I moved around the room and carefully cleaned
everything I had touched. I didn't want to
leave any fingerprints. There was nothing in the
room to connect Benny Greep with Elaine Garfield.
I picked up the telephone
and asked for the police.
'I'm speaking from Apartment 507, 5314 Arivieda
Street,' I said. 'There's a dead man in the bath.'
'Right,' said the policeman at the other
end of the telephone. 'What's your name?'
I told him.
'Don't touch anything,' the policeman said,
'and stay where you are. A police
car will he there in a few minutes.'
I put down the phone and sat down to wait. Three
minutes later, I heard the police car coming.
The car stopped outside the building and I
could hear heavy feet running up the stairs.
Two policemen walked into the apartment.
They were both wearing ordinary clothes
and looked hot and tired. One was about
twenty-five years old, the other about forty.
The older policeman came up to me
and showed me his police papers.
'Where's the body?' he asked.
I pointed to the bathroom. Both
policemen went into the bathroom
to have a look. The younger one
came back first, shaking his head.
'All right,' said the younger
policeman, 'why did you do it?'
'Do what?' I asked in surprise.
'Why did you kill your friend in
the bath?' said the young policeman.
'He wasn't my friend,' I replied.
'I don't care if he was your friend or not,' said
the policeman. 'Tell me why you killed, him.'
'I didn't kill him,' I said calmly.
'Then what are you doing here?' asked the
older policeman, coming in from the bathroom.
'My name's Lenny Samuel,' I explained. 'I'm
a private detective and I came here to talk
to Benny Greep. The door was open and so I
came in. I looked in the bathroom and I found
the dead man in the bath, so I telephoned
the police. The dead man is Benny Greep.'
'Why did you want to talk to Benny
Greep?' the younger policeman asked.
'I'm sorry, I can't answer that,' I replied.
'Who are you working for?'
asked the older policeman.
'I'm sorry, I can't answer that
either,' I said. 'As far as I know,
Benny Greep's death doesn't have anything
to do with the person I'm working for.'
'Tell me who you are working for,'
shouted the younger policeman angrily.
'Take it easy,' said the older policeman to
the younger one. 'You stay here until the
other police arrive. I'm going to take
Mr Samuel down to the police station.'
I kept quiet and followed the older policeman
out of the room and down the stairs.
Outside the building, we got into my
old Chrysler. The policeman drove.
We were soon at the police station, where
the policeman locked me in a small room.
I sat down on a hard, wooden chair in
the locked room and tried to sleep.
It was no use getting angry or
upset at being arrested for murder.
That is something you have to get used to, if you
are a private detective. It happens all the time.
But I could not sleep. I was thinking about
all the things which had happened since I had
met Helen Garfield the day before. I couldn't
sleep, because several things were worrying me.
But I couldn't remember what those things were.
CHAPTER NINE
Sergeant Murphy
While I was in the police station, I remembered
one of the things which was worrying me.
How had Jo and his tall friend known that
I was in Elaine Garfield's apartment?
The porter at the Manson Building
must have told the two men.
I decided that I would go and talk to the
porter when I left the police station.
I sat back in the chair and looked at my
watch. The time was nearly four o'clock.
Then I remembered that Helen Garfield was coming
to my office at five o'clock. I
would not be there to meet her.
But there was something else that was
worrying me. It wasn't anything important.
It was quite a small thing. But
I couldn't remember what it was.
Suddenly, the door opened and a policeman came in.
'Stand up,' shouted the policeman. 'Follow me.'
I stood up and followed the policeman
out of the room and along a corridor.
The policeman stopped, knocked
on a door and opened it.
'Are you ready to see the private
detective?' asked the policeman,
as he put his head around the door.
Without waiting for an answer, the policeman
opened the door wide and pushed me into the room.
The policeman came into the room
and closed the door behind him.
In the room, there was a man sitting behind a
desk. He was completely bald - he had no hair
at all. He was about fifty-five years
old and his name was Sergeant Murphy.
Sergeant Murphy had spent all his life in the
police and he didn't like private detectives.
Sergeant Murphy sat looking at me. He looked at me
for about five minutes, without saying anything.
I was standing in front of his
desk, looking straight back at him.
The silence didn't worry me.
In fact, I quite liked it.
The silence was much nicer than questions about
what I'd been doing in Benny Greep's apartment.
'What were you doing in Benny Greep's
apartment?' asked Sergeant Murphy suddenly.
'I wanted to talk to him,' I replied.
'Why did you kill Benny Greep?'
shouted Sergeant Murphy suddenly.
'I didn't kill him,' I replied,
and I told Sergeant Murphy the same story that I
had told the policemen in Benny Greep's apartment.
'I don't believe a word of what you've told me,'
said the sergeant. 'Who are you working for?'
'I'm sorry,' I replied, 'I can't
tell you who I'm working for.
As far as I know, Benny Greep's death has nothing
to do with me or with the person I'm working for.'
I stopped and looked at the sergeant. I
knew that what I had just said wasn't true.
In fact, I thought Benny Greep's death was
connected with Elaine Garfield's disappearance.
But I couldn't tell the police. Helen Garfield had
said that she didn't want the police to
know about her sister's disappearance.
Sergeant Murphy looked me straight in the eyes.
'I hate all private detectives,' he said slowly,
'and you are the private detective that I hate
the most. I don't think you are telling me the
truth. I think you are hiding things from me.
I think you know more about Benny
Greep's death than you say you do.
And you are going to tell me all you know - now.'
'I've already told you all
I know,' I replied quietly.
Sergeant Murphy's face went red. The red colour
went up until it covered all of his bald head.
'Don't try to play, games with
me,' he shouted. 'Now get out.'
'Can I go home now?' I asked.
'No,' said Sergeant Murphy.
The sergeant told the policeman at the door to
take me back to the small
room and lock me up again.
I went with the policemen and didn't
argue. I don't like arguing with policemen.
When I was alone in the room again, I sat down.
I tried to remember the other thing that had been
worrying me earlier. Someone had said something
important, but I could not remember what it was.
CHAPTER TEN
The Yellow Car
I looked at my watch. It was half past five.
I was still at the police station. I'd seen
Sergeant Murphy once more, during the afternoon.
It hadn't been a pleasant meeting. I hadn't told
the sergeant who I was working for. And I hadn't
told him why I'd wanted to talk to Benny Greep.
Half past five. I wondered if Helen
Garfield was waiting for me at my office.
Suddenly, the door of the room
opened and Sergeant Murphy came in.
'Get out,' he said, 'I've decided to let
you go. Now go before I change my mind.'
I went before Sergeant Murphy changed his mind.
As I got my car out of the police garage, I
wondered why Sergeant Murphy had let me go.
As I drove away from the police station,
I noticed a small yellow car behind me.
A minute later, I looked in the mirror again.
The small yellow car was still behind me.
I drove a little faster and
then suddenly turned right
up a narrow street. At the end of the narrow
street, I turned left and then left again.
Soon, I was back on the main road. I looked in the
mirror. The yellow car was still right behind me.
So that was why Sergeant Murphy had let me go. The
sergeant had ordered some policemen to follow me.
They were going to watch what I did and who I met.
I drove straight back to the
office. As I parked the car outside,
I noticed the yellow car had stopped across
the road. I ran up the stairs and into my
office. The door to the outer room was
open, as usual, but the room was empty.
Helen Garfield wasn't, there. But
there was a letter on the table,
on top of the magazines. I picked
the letter up and read it.
Dear Mr. Samuel,
I came here at five o'clock
and waited but you didn't
come. I must see you urgently. Meet
me at has Cabanas at 11.30 tonight.
Helen Garfield.
I put the letter in my pocket and looked
at my watch. It was just after six o'clock.
I had five and a half hours before
the meeting with Helen Garfield.
There was plenty of time to go to the
Mansion Building and talk to the porter.
I got into the Chrysler and drove
off towards the Mansion Building.
The small yellow car was still following me. As
I drove, I thought about Helen Garfield's letter.
'Why does she want to meet me
at Las Cabanas?' I asked myself.
'In fact, how does she know about Las Cabanas
at all? She says that she lives in New York.'
I would have to ask Miss Helen Garfield
a few questions, the next time I saw her.
But the most important thing now was to get away
from the yellow car, which was still following me.
I was going to the building where Elaine Garfield
lived and I didn't want the police to know.
There were two men in the yellow car. I
turned right and the yellow car followed.
I stopped and the yellow car stopped. I turned the
Chrysler around and the yellow car turned around.
I tried to drive faster than the yellow car,
but the Chrysler was too old and too slow.
I slowed down and waited until I was near the
next traffic lights. Then, just as the lights
were changing from green to red, I drove
across them. The yellow car was too late.
The lights were now red. But that didn't stop
the car. It drove straight past the red light.
Then, as I looked angrily in my mirror,
something happened which made me laugh.
A policeman on a motorbike
drove after the yellow car.
The policeman made the driver stop,
because he had driven past the red light.
I drove away as fast as possible. In my mirror, I
could see the driver inside the car arguing with
the policeman on the motorbike. It was the
funniest sight I had seen for a long time.
I drove on towards the Manson
Building, happy to have escaped.
I may even have sung a little,
because I was feeling so good.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
A Short Visit to the Manson Building
As I was driving happily towards the
Manson Building, I had a surprise.
I looked in the mirror. The yellow
car was coming up fast behind me.
I drove as fast as I could, but the
yellow car got closer and closer.
Just then, a dog ran across the
road, in front of the Chrysler.
I braked hard and the tyres screamed as the
Chrysler stopped suddenly to avoid the dog.
Then there was the scream of more tyres as
the driver of the yellow car tried to stop.
There was a loud crash and a bang, as the small
yellow car ran right into the back of my big,
old, grey Chrysler. The two men
in the yellow car weren't hurt,
but their car was badly damaged at the front.
Oil and water were running out onto the road.
The old Chrysler was not damaged at all. I
got out and walked back to the yellow car.
'You ought to be more careful,' I said to the
driver. 'You were driving very dangerously.
It's lucky for you that my
car isn't badly damaged.'
'But...but...,' the driver began to
say, but I did not wait to listen.
I ran back to the Chrysler, jumped
in and drove on. The last I saw
of the yellow car was the two men
pushing it to the side of the road.
I was soon at the Manson Building and I
went into the hall, to look for the porter.
I couldn't see him anywhere. Then I noticed
a door with a sign on it saying "Porter".
I knocked quietly, but there was no answer. I
opened the door slowly and looked into the room.
The porter was sitting at his desk, asleep.
His feet were on the desk and he was lying
back in his chair. I walked quickly and
quietly into the room and closed the door.
I went up to the desk and noticed a
piece of paper lying by the telephone.
There was a telephone number
written on the paper - 3230313.
'Las Cabanas,' I said to myself. 'That's
the telephone number of the nightclub.'
Without waking the porter, I left the room.
I had found out what I wanted to know.
The two men who had hit me on the head
had probably come from Las Cabanas.
The porter must have telephoned them
when I went up to Elaine Garfield's flat.
I was now very interested in Las Cabanas. Elaine
Garfield used to go dancing there with Suzy.
Benny Greep worked there before
he was killed. Helen Garfield
wanted to meet me there at half
past eleven. And now the porter
and the two men who had hit me on the
head were connected with Las Cabanas.
I went home, washed, changed and had a meal.
At eleven o'clock, I went out
again. I was going to Las Cabanas.
There were lots of cars parked outside and I had
to leave the Chrysler quite a long way away from
the nightclub. As I walked up to the entrance
of Las Cabanas, it started to rain heavily.
I knocked on the door and the little window
in the door opened. A face looked at me for a
minute. Then the door opened and I went in.
The club no longer looked empty and dirty.
Soft lights and sweet music had changed
the appearance of the club completely.
I stood and looked around. There was a small
dance floor, on which a few people were dancing.
The band was small and not very good. There
was a new drummer instead of Benny Greep.
Around the dance floor, several groups
of people were sitting round low tables.
To the right of the dance floor, there
were more tables where people were eating.
There were two doors behind the
tables, which led into the kitchen.
I sat down at a table by the dance floor, in
the darkest part of the room, and waited.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Las Cabanas
Exactly at eleven thirty, Helen Garfield came
into the nightclub. She was looking as beautiful
as ever, but seemed to be a little worried. Her
blue eyes looked around the room until she saw me.
Then, with a little smile, she
walked up and sat down at the table.
She sat next to me, with
her back to the dance floor.
She was carrying a bag, which she put on the floor
beside her. The smile disappeared from her face.
'Where were you this afternoon, Mr Samuel?' she
said sharply. 'I'm paying you fifty dollars a day.
In return for that money, I
want you to do what I tell you.
Now why weren't you at your office
this afternoon at five o'clock?'
I took a deep breath.
'Well, Miss Garfield,'
I said, 'it's a long story. Let's have
a drink and I'll tell you all about it.'
A waiter came over and I ordered some drinks.
When the waiter had gone, the beautiful, blonde
girl said, 'Come on, Mr Samuel, tell me.'
'OK,' I said, 'but stop calling me Mr Samuel.
Call me Len - all my friends call me Len.'
'I'm not a friend of yours, Mr Samuel,'
the blonde girl said, in a voice like ice.
'I'm paying you a lot of money to work for me.'
'Fifty dollars a day doesn't allow you
to be rude to me,' I replied quietly.
'In the last twenty four hours, I've been
hit on the head and suspected of murder.'
'What do you mean?' the girl said,
and leant towards me. 'Murder?'
Just then, the waiter brought the drinks
and we sat in silence until he had gone.
Then I told Helen Garfield about my visit to
her sister's apartment in the Manson Building.
I told her about the two men who had caught
me there. Helen Garfield listened in silence.
'Do you like the band, Miss Garfield?' I asked.
'I didn't come here to talk about the
band,' the blonde girl said angrily.
'The band has got a new drummer tonight,' I said,
'because I found the old drummer
dead in his bath this morning.'
The blonde girl turned around
quickly to look at the band.
She said something to herself
which I didn't hear. She lifted
her right hand and started stroking her
hair. She looked sad and very worried.
'What...what was the drummer ...the
dead man's name?' Helen Garfield asked.
'Greep,' I said, 'Benny Greep. I don't
suppose that you know Benny Greep, do you?'
Helen Garfield shook her head.
'No,' she said.
I told her what had happened
at the police station.
Then I told her about the policemen
who had followed me in a yellow car.
'Do you think they're still
following you?' the blonde
girl asked quickly and looked around the club.
I told her how I had got away from the yellow car.
'Now, Miss Garfield,' I continued, 'it's time
for me to ask you a few questions. There are
some things about your sister's disappearance
which worry me. I want to ask you about them.'
'All right,' she said, 'but I don't
think I can help you. I don't know much
about Elaine's life here. I don't know
very much about Los Angeles, either.'
I sat back in my chair and
looked at her. This beautiful,
blonde girl was paying me fifty
dollars a day to find her sister.
I liked what I saw. Then, very quietly, I
began to ask Helen Garfield some questions.
'You don't know Los Angeles very well?' I began.
'That's right,' the girl replied.
'But you were able to find out
where Elaine worked,' I continued.
'And you went to Myer and Myer last Tuesday,
to ask if they knew anything about Elaine.'
'Yes,' the girl said, looking at me closely.
'Who did you speak to at Myer
and Myer?' I asked. 'Suzy?'
'No,' the girl said, 'I spoke to Mr Myer.'
'I want to ask you something else,' I
said. 'When I went to Elaine's flat,
I noticed something unusual. There were
very few clothes in the wardrobe. It seems
your sister planned her disappearance quite
carefully. She had taken her clothes with her.'
'I see,' the girl said and
looked around the nightclub.
I waited until she looked back at me.
'Do you like it here?' I asked.
'Yes,' she said.
'I like it, too,' I said, 'But there's
something else which is worrying me.
Do you mind if I ask you one more question?'
'Not at all,' the girl said.
'Well,' I began, 'I've been wondering why you
asked me to meet you here, at Las Cabanas.'
Helen Garfield pushed back her chair and stood up.
'Would you please excuse
me for a minute?' she said.
She picked her bag up from the floor and
walked over towards the ladies' toilet,
which was near the entrance.
'Would you like another
drink?' I shouted after her.
'Yes, please,' she shouted back, over
her shoulder. I ordered two more drinks
and sat back in my chair. I looked around
the nightclub. It was almost midnight.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Helen Garfield Leaves
I sat by the dance floor in Las Cabanas, waiting
for Helen Garfield to come back from the toilet.
I was waiting for her to answer my
question. I wanted to know why she
had asked me to meet her here. I looked
around at the people who were dancing.
On the other side of the dance floor,
I could see people sitting eating at
the tables. Waiters were carrying food in and
out of the two doors leading to the kitchen.
I looked at my watch again.
It was five past twelve.
Helen Garfield was taking a long time. I
finished my drink and ordered another one.
At ten past twelve, I got up and
walked over towards the entrance.
There was a man standing by the front door of
the nightclub. I asked him if he had seen Helen.
'The beautiful blonde with
blue eyes?' the man asked.
'Yes,' I said.
'She left nearly a quarter of
an hour ago,' said the man.
'Are you sure?' I asked.
'Yes,' the man replied. 'She
asked me to get her a taxi.'
'Did you hear her give the taxi
driver an address?' I asked quickly.
The man shook his head.
'No,' he said, 'I'm sorry.'
I thanked the man and walked back to my seat.
Why did Helen Garfield leave
without telling me? I asked myself.
Perhaps some of the questions
that I asked made her angry.
Just then, I looked up and saw a man
walking across the dance floor towards me.
I recognised the man. He was short, with red
hair. He was looking at me and smiling in a
rather unfriendly way. It was Jo - one of the men
who had found me in Elaine Garfield's apartment.
I decided to leave. I stood up and started to
walk towards the door. I didn't want to meet
Jo again. As I walked towards the door,
I thought that I heard someone shouting.
'Excuse me, sir,' said a voice.
I didn't stop or look around.
Then I heard the voice again.
'Excuse me, sir. You haven't paid your bill.'
I had forgotten to pay for the
drinks. The waiter came running
up to me and I quickly took out ten
dollars and gave them to the waiter.
'You can keep the change,' I
said as I gave him the money.ну
Without waiting for a reply, I
turned and hurried towards the door.
Then I heard the waiter's voice again.
'Excuse me, sir, excuse me, sir,' he said.
I stopped and turned around.
The waiter came up to me.
'Excuse me, sir, ten dollars is not enough,'
he said, 'The price of your
drinks is twelve dollars.'
'Las Cabanas is very expensive,' I said,
as I gave the waiter another five
dollars. 'Now, you can keep the change.'
Then I stopped thinking about money.
Jo was walking quickly towards me.
I turned around and ran towards
the door as fast as I could.
I got to the door and was just about to leave
Las Cabanas. I was happy because I had escaped.
Then I got a surprise. There,
standing by the door of the nightclub,
was Jo's tall friend. It was the same man who had
hit me on the head in Miss Garfield's apartment.
The tall man had seen me coming and had moved
in front of the door. Now, I couldn't get out.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
The Fight
I stopped and looked behind me. Jo was closer now
and the smile on his face looked very unfriendly.
I was caught. I could not go out of
the door and Jo was right behind me.
I turned around quickly and ran towards
Jo. Before he knew what I was doing,
I put my arms around him and started dancing. He
was very surprised and tried to pull away from me.
But he couldn't fight properly. He was
afraid that the other people would notice.
I looked over my shoulder and saw the tall man
standing helplessly on the
side of the dance floor.
I pushed Jo into the middle of the dance floor,
where there were lots of other people dancing.
Then I felt something sharp touching my back. It
was a knife. 'Stop trying to be funny, Samuel,'
said Jo angrily. 'Stop dancing and go over to
the door or else I'll push this knife into you.'
We were right in the middle of the dance
floor and a long way from the tall man.
Jo was holding a knife against my back. Some of
the other people around us had stopped dancing.
They were staring in surprise at the
sight of two men dancing together.
I lifted my foot and kicked
Jo's leg as hard as I could.
He gave a cry of pain and fell to the floor.
I looked around to see where I could run to.
Jo's tall friend was coming
through the dancers towards me.
I turned around and ran off the
dance floor. I looked back over
my shoulder and saw that both Jo
and his friend were following me.
I ran between the tables where people were
eating. The floor was slippery and I fell over.
As I fell, I knocked over a table and the
plates of food and glasses fell on top of me.
I got up quickly and ran out through
one of the doors into the kitchen.
Then I stopped and counted to five.
As Jo and his tall friend
were coming towards the door,
I pushed the door closed as hard as I could. There
was a loud bang as the men ran into the door.
I smiled and turned round. But
I did not smile for very long.
Three cooks were coming towards me
with big kitchen knives in their hands.
I looked at the cooks and at
the knives they were holding.
I thought about running towards
them and trying to fight them.
I decided that it would be a stupid idea
to try and fight three big men with knives.
To my left, there was a very big saucepan
full of boiling soup on the stove. I picked
it up and threw it at the cooks. There were loud
cries of pain as the hot soup hit the three men.
Just then, the door opened behind me.
Jo and his tall friend stood in the
doorway, and the tall man was holding a gun.
There was a loud bang as the gun went off.
The bang was followed by a scream of pain
from one of the cooks, because the tall
man had shot him in the foot by mistake.
I quickly picked up a large pile of dirty plates
and threw them at Jo. He saw the plates coming and
he tried to move away. As he moved, he slipped on
the floor and fell onto a pile of broken plates.
Without waiting, I ran to a door at the
back of the kitchen. The door was locked
and I banged against the door with my shoulder.
The lock broke easily and I pushed the door open.
As I ran out into the dark street, I could still
hear the shouts and cries coming from the Club.
I came to the Chrysler and
bent over to open the door.
Just then, there was a noise behind me. I
turned around and saw a man with his arm raised.
Then I felt a terrible pain in my head. Everything
went black. I fell to the ground, unconscious.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
The Police Station
'Feeling better now?' asked a voice.
I opened my eyes and looked around
me. I didn't know where I was.
I was lying on something hard and
there was a bright light on my eyes.
'Where am I?' I asked.
Then I realised where I was.
I recognised the grey walls,
the hard furniture and the bright electric
lights. I was in the police station again.
'Feeling better now?' the voice repeated.
I looked at the policeman who was talking to me.
'Yes,' I said very slowly, 'but my head
feels as if it is breaking in half.'
'You're lucky to be alive,' said
the policeman. 'A police car found
you lying in the middle of the road on
Golden Drive. You would have been hit
by passing cars - and probably killed,
if the police car hadn't found you.'
I thought for a moment. I wasn't
sure how much the police knew.
I didn't want to tell the police
anything they did not already know.
'Yes, I was lucky,' I said. 'By the way,
what was a police car doing on Golden Drive?'
'Oh,' said the policeman, 'there was a big
fight at a nightclub called Las Cabanas.
We had a telephone call to say that
there was a madman in the club.
The madman was breaking up all the furniture.
A police car was sent to the nightclub,
but the madman escaped before the police arrived.
The police car was returning when it found you
lying in the middle of the road. You were very
lucky. The car nearly ran right over you.'
I smiled.
'I don't feel very lucky,' I
replied. 'In fact, I feel terrible.'
'Never mind,' said the policeman. 'Can you walk?'
I stood up and walked a few steps. My
head hurt, but otherwise I felt all right.
'Yes,' I said, 'I can walk.'
'Good,' the policeman said, 'let's
walk along the corridor, then,
and have a talk with a friend of yours.'
We went along the corridor. The
policeman stopped at a door and
knocked. There was a shout from inside the
room and the policeman opened the door.
I walked into the room and the policeman followed.
He shut the door and stood in front of it.
There was only one desk in the
room and behind the desk was a man.
He was bald. It was my 'old
friend', Sergeant Murphy.
'Hello, Sergeant Murphy,' I said, trying
to smile. 'How are you feeling tonight?'
Sergeant Murphy didn't smile back at me.
'Are you trying to be funny?' he asked.
'It isn't night, it's morning.
You've been unconscious all night.'
'Oh,' I said.
'Now,' said Sergeant Murphy, 'let's begin. I want
you to tell me why you were lying, unconscious,
in the middle of Golden Drive at half past twelve
last night. You were a danger to the traffic.'
'I thought that the traffic was a danger to me,'
I replied. But the sergeant didn't even smile.
'I'm waiting for you to tell me
what happened,' said the sergeant.
'Nothing much happened,' I began, 'I spent
part of the evening at Las Cabanas and left
just before midnight. I walked back to my
car. Just as I was about to get into the car,
someone hit me over the head.
That's the last I remember.
'This policeman,' and I pointed
to the one standing by the door,
'told me that I had been found in the middle
of the road. Someone must have put me there.'
Sergeant Murphy smiled.
'Yes,' he said, 'someone who wanted to
kill you put you in the middle of the road.
Someone was hoping that a car
would hit you and kill you.'
I smiled back at the sergeant.
'Can you think of anyone who would want
to kill you?' the sergeant asked me.
'Oh, yes,' I replied, 'hundreds of people would
like to kill me, including a few policemen.'
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Tell Me the Truth
Did you leave Las Cabanas before
midnight?' asked Sergeant Murphy.
'That's right,' I replied, 'I left
the nightclub just before twelve.'
'So you weren't at Las Cabanas when the big fight
started, just after twelve?' asked the sergeant.
'Big fight?' I said, trying to sound surprised.
'Don't sound so surprised,' said Sergeant
Murphy angrily. 'We received a telephone
call from the owner of Las Cabanas. He
said that just after midnight last night,
a tall man with brown hair and brown eyes, called
Lenny Samuel, attacked two of the people at the
club. The owner of the club said that you
'then attacked and injured three cooks. Then
you broke over one hundred plates and a table,
and ruined food worth several hundred dollars.'
I didn't say anything. I could
not think of anything to say.
'Did you really do all that?'
Sergeant Murphy asked, in a different voice.
The Sergeant sounded both surprised and pleased.
'Did you really do all that on your
own, or did you have men to help you?'
'I did it all on my own,' I said,
beginning to feel a little proud of myself.
'Do you know that you could go to prison
for six months for what you did last night?'
the sergeant asked. He was laughing as he said it.
I wasn't laughing. I couldn't see
anything funny about six months in prison.
'Look,' Sergeant Murphy said, 'I'm not stupid.'
I agreed with the sergeant that he was not stupid.
'I'm not stupid,' Sergeant Murphy repeated, 'and
I know why you were at Las Cabanas last night.
Benny Greep used to work there and
you went to find out about his death.'
I agreed with the sergeant again.
It seemed the best thing to do.
'Now,' Sergeant Murphy said slowly,
'I'm interested in Las Cabanas.
The club is owned by people who are criminals.
But we can't prove that they have broken the law.
I'm also interested in Benny Creep's murder. Now,
what I suggest is this. Tell me all you know about
Las Cabanas and Benny Greep and I will let you
go. If you tell me all you know, you won't go to
prison for the fight at the nightclub. But I want
the truth, not the lies you told me yesterday.'
I took a deep breath and started
to tell the sergeant what I knew.
I told him about everything
except Elaine Garfield.
I wasn't sure how closely Elaine Garfield
was connected with Benny Creep's death. So,
I told the sergeant that Helen Garfield, from New
York, had asked me to find out about Las Cabanas.
Sergeant Murphy asked me for Helen Garfield's
address in New York and I said I didn't know it.
Then the sergeant asked me where Helen Garfield
was staying in Los Angeles. I said I didn't know.
I told Sergeant Murphy all
that I knew about Benny Greep,
except that the drummer had known Elaine Garfield.
Then I asked him about the two men in the yellow
car, who had followed me. The sergeant smiled
and said that the two men were policemen.
Finally, I told him about
the fight at Las Cabanas.
Sergeant Murphy listened to everything.
When I had finished my story,
he looked at me in silence for a few moments.
'Right, Samuel, I hope that
you've told me the truth,
and all the truth. If you've been telling
me more lies, I'll make sure that you go
to prison for six months, because of the
fight at Las Cabanas. Now, you can go.'
I stood up.
'Thank you,' I said, with a smile.
Sit down, he said, 'and listen. You
can go. But you must promise to tell
me anything you find out about Las
Cabanas and about Benny Greep.'
'I promise,' I said quickly and stood up.
Wait a minute, said Sergeant Murphy. 'I've one
more thing to tell you. I'm going to telephone
the New York police. I'm going to ask them to
find out all they can about Helen Garfield.
If the police in New York discover that
you've told me lies about Helen Garfield,
you will be in very serious trouble.'
I told the sergeant not to
worry and thanked him very much.
I left the police station feeling very
happy because Sergeant Murphy had let me go.
I called a taxi and went out to
Golden Drive to get the Chrysler.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Telephone Calls
I drove the Chrysler back to the
office and walked up the stairs.
The office looked just the same.
There were no letters for me.
I went down to the cafe and had a
late breakfast. As I drank my coffee,
I thought about some of the things Helen Garfield
had told me at Las Cabanas before the fight.
I decided to check one of the things
immediately and walked over to the telephone.
I opened the telephone book and looked under
'M' until I found the telephone number of
Myer and Myer. I picked up the
telephone and dialled the number.
'Myer and Myer, good morning,' said a
voice which I recognised. 'Can I help you?'
'Hello, Suzy,' I said, 'this is
Len Samuel. Do you remember me?'
'Of course I remember you,' said Suzy.
'Did your boyfriend win his boxing
match on television?' I asked.
'No,' Suzy replied, 'and anyway,
he's not my boyfriend any more.'
'Really,' I said happily, thinking that perhaps
I could ask Suzy to go for a drink with me.
'Yes,' Suzy said, 'the boxer had a fight with
my new boyfriend outside my house last night.'
'And who won?' I asked.
'My new boyfriend,' replied Suzy.
'Oh,' I said sadly, 'and what
does your new boyfriend do?'
'My new boyfriend's a weight lifter.' Suzy
replied. 'He lifts big weights in competitions.'
I was about to say goodbye. Then I remembered
that I had not telephoned to speak to,
Suzy. I wanted to speak to her boss, Mr Myer.
'Can I speak to Mr Myer please, Suzy?' I asked.
'Right,' Suzy said, 'I'll put
you through to Mr Myer. Goodbye.'
There was a pause and then
I heard Mr Myer's voice.
'Hello, Myer speaking.'
'Good morning Mr Myer,' I said, in a
deep voice. I had put my handkerchief
over the telephone, so that Mr
Myer would not know my voice.
'This is the police,' I said,
'Sergeant Murphy speaking.'
I pretended to be Sergeant Murphy so
that Mr Myer would answer my questions.
'Good morning,' said Mr Myer.
'What do you want to ask me about?'
'It's about a girl who works for you,' I said.
'Her name is Elaine Garfield. She has disappeared
and we are trying to find her. Elaine's sister,
Helen, came to see you last Tuesday, didn't she?'
'No,' said Mr Myer, 'Elaine's sister didn't come
to see me last Tuesday. I didn't know that Elaine
had a sister, until a private detective told me.
He said that Elaine's sister was called Helen.'
The telephone line was very bad and it was
difficult for me to hear what Mr Myer was saying.
'What did you say?' I asked.
'I said that Elaine's sister was called Helen,'
replied Mr Myer. 'The names
are very similar, aren't they?'
Thank you very much, Mr Myer,' I
said and put the telephone down.
Mr Myer was right. The names Helen
and Elaine were very similar. Elaine
Garfield had disappeared. And so far, I was
the only person who had met Helen Garfield.
I left the cafe and walked back up to my office.
As I climbed the stairs, I
could hear my telephone ringing.
I didn't hurry. I walked slowly along the corridor
into my office, and answered the telephone.
'Is that Samuel?' a voice said. I
recognised the voice at once. It was Jo.
'Yes,' I said, 'this is Len Samuel.'
'Listen, Samuel,' Jo said, 'we want Elaine
Garfield and we think you know where she
is. We are coming to your office to
see you. Wait for us. Don't go out.'
'But I ...' I started, but it was too
late. Jo had put the telephone down.
I sat down at my desk sadly.
'Now what's going to happen?' I thought.
'Jo and his friend will come to see me. They'll
ask me if I know where Elaine Garfield is.
But I don't know where she is. I wonder
if they will believe me when I tell them.'
The telephone rang again. I picked it up.
'Hello,' I said.
'Hello, Samuel,' said a familiar voice.
'Hello, Sergeant Murphy,' I
replied, trying to sound pleased.
'We've just telephoned New
York,' the sergeant said angrily,
'and the New York police were very helpful. The
New York police told us that there is no such
person as Helen Garfield. Helen Garfield does
not exist. There is no one living in New York
called Helen Garfield. You were lying when you
told me that you were working for Helen Garfield.'
'But...' I started.
'Now, listen,' the sergeant interrupted,
'I am sending a police car round to your
office. I want to see you. Wait
for the police car. Don't go out.'
The sergeant put down the telephone and I sat back
in my chair. I was worried. What would happen now?
Jo was coming to see me and so was a policeman. I
tried to think of what I would say to them both.
I hoped that the policeman and Jo
would not arrive at the same time.
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
I Find Elaine Garfield
The telephone rang again. I was afraid to answer
it. The telephone continued ringing. Finally,
I did answer it.
'Hello,' I said.
'Is that Mr Samuel?' asked a voice. It was
Helen Garfield. 'Yes, Miss Garfield,' I replied,
'this is Len Samuel speaking.' 'I
must see you,' said Helen Garfield.
'Well, I would like to talk
to you, too, Miss Garfield,'
I said slowly. 'I think there are a lot
of things you and I must talk about.'
'Right,' the girl said, 'meet me at the
"Seventh Mann" cafe in five minutes.
Do you know where the cafe is? It's
about half a mile from your office.'
'I know the "Seventh Man", 'I replied,
'but I can't meet you in five minutes,
because I'm expecting visitors.'
'You must come at once, Mr Samuel,' she said.
'But...' I began.
It was too late. Helen Garfield had put her
telephone down. I got up from the chair and
walked to the door. I decided to go and meet Helen
Garfield. Both Jo and Sergeant Murphy had told me
not to go out. But I decided I would rather
talk to Helen Garfield than to the policeman
or to Jo. If Jo and the policeman came when
I was out, they could talk to each other.
I left the building and drove the
Chrysler down the road. I was very lucky,
because I was able to park right outside
the "Seventh Mann". I walked into the cafe.
Helen Garfield was sitting at a table in the
comer. I walked over and sat down beside her.
I asked the waiter for a cup of coffee. I
drank the coffee without saying anything.
Then I put the cup down and looked at the
beautiful, blonde girl sitting beside me.
'Miss Garfield,' I said, you are a very beautiful
girl, but I think you are a liar. I think that
everything you've said to me has been lies.
I don't think you've ever told me the truth.'
The blonde girl's face slowly became
red. She looked straight at me.
'Mr Samuel,' she said, 'I'm paying
you a lot of money to work for me.
I asked you to find my sister. I
didn't ask you to call me a liar.'
'Well, Miss Garfield, I think
I have found Elaine Garfield.
Would you like me to tell you where she is?'
'Yes,' the blonde girl said, 'where is Elaine?'
'She's here in this cafe,' I said.
'Elaine Garfield is sitting next to me.
You are Elaine Garfield.
Helen Garfield doesn't exist.
You pretended to be Helen Garfield, but
there really never was any such person.
'The police in New York say that Helen Garfield
doesn't exist,' I went on. 'Helen Garfield and
Elaine Garfield are the same person. You are
Elaine Garfield and you pretended to be Helen.'
The blonde girl stood up angrily.
'How much money do you want, Mr Samuel? You
are no longer working for me,' she shouted.
'Sit down,' I said quietly.
The blonde girl did not sit down,
so I pulled her down beside me.
'Now listen, Miss Garfield,' I
said firmly. 'You are going to
tell me all about yourself
and why you came to see me.
I want to know all about Benny Creep and Las
Cabanas. I want to know why you disappeared.'
'I won't tell you anything,' she said.
'Oh, yes, you will tell me everything,' I
replied, 'you'll tell me everything or else
I'll take you straight to the police. You see,
the police are looking for me at this moment.
'The police think that I may have killed
Benny Greep,' I continued. 'The police
know that I had a fight at Las Cabanas
last night. A red haired man and his
tall friend are also chasing me. They are the
two men who started the fight at Las Cabanas.
They will try to kill me if I don't tell them
where you are. So you see, Miss Garfield,
I think you had better tell me everything.
I'm the only person who can help you.'
The blonde girl sat in silence for
a minute. Then she began to cry.
'All right,' she said, 'I'll tell you
everything. I am Elaine Garfield.'
CHAPTER NINETEEN
Everything Is Explained
I looked at the blonde girl.
'So you agree that you're really Elaine
Garfield and not Helen,' I said quietly.
'Now tell me about Benny Greep.'
The girl took a deep breath.
'Suzy Graham and I used to go out dancing
together a lot,' said Elaine. 'We often
went to Las Cabanas. One night when we were
there, I met a wonderful man called Benny.
Benny was the drummer in the
band. I liked him very much and
went to the nightclub very often, to
see Benny. We became very good friends.'
The girl stopped again and
took out her handkerchief.
'Go on,' I said quietly.
'I used to go to Las Cabanas to
see Benny nearly every night,
but it was difficult for us to talk
to each other,' the girl continued.
'Why was it difficult for you and
Benny to talk to each other?' I asked.
'Because Benny was the drummer
in the band, of course,'
Elaine Garfield replied. 'We couldn't
talk to each other very much,
because he was playing with
the band most of the evening.'
'I understand,' I said and
ordered two more coffees.
'So I spent a lot of time in Las
Cabanas, watching Benny play the drums,'
the girl said. 'And I also watched everything
else which happened in the nightclub.'
'What did you see?' I asked.
'I didn't notice anything unusual at first,'
the girl replied. 'But, after a few nights,
I noticed that the same people always
came to the club, at the same time.'
'Which people?' I asked.
'There was a red-haired man,
a tall man who never took off his hat, and
one or two others,' said Elaine Garfield.
'Yes,' I said, 'I think I have met two of them.
They were the men who hit me on
the head in the Manson Building.'
'Anyway,' the girl continued, 'one night, I asked
Benny why these men came to the club every night.
Benny told me not to ask questions. So I watched
the men more carefully afterwards and noticed
that they always arrived with bags. But when
the men left, they weren't carrying bags.'
'What did you do then?' I asked.
'I asked Benny about the men again,' she
said. 'Benny said that there were a lot
of strange things happening at Las Cabanas,
and that it was dangerous to ask questions.'
The waiter brought the coffees and
Elaine waited until he had gone.
'One night,' she continued, 'one of the
men was sitting at the table next to me.
He was talking to some other men and
he opened the bag that he was carrying.
I was sitting quite close and I could see into the
bag. The bag was full of diamonds and jewellery.'
'Really?' I said and drank my coffee.
'I told Benny about the bag of jewellery,
later on in the evening,' continued Elaine.
'Benny was very excited at the news.
He told me that he had known for a long
time that criminals used Las Cabanas.
They used the club as a place
to buy and sell stolen things.
Benny and I talked all evening about the bag
of jewellery. Benny said that the jewellery
was stolen. The men who were selling it were
criminals and they had stolen the jewellery.
'Well,' Elaine continued, 'Benny
wanted to steal one of the bags.
He said that the jewellery was stolen, so it
didn't matter if we stole it from the criminals.
I agreed to help him. We hoped to sell the
bag and to use the money to go away together.'
'I see,' I said, 'and did you help
Benny to steal the bag of jewellery?'
'Yes, we waited for nearly a week,' Elaine
replied. 'Then, last Sunday, I had a chance
to steal the bag. It was at the end of the
evening, and nearly everyone had left the club.
I had found out where they hid the bag and
I was able to take it and give it to Benny.
Benny had big bags in which he carried
his drums. It was easy for him to hide
the bag of jewellery in the drum
bag. We left the club together,
with the bag of jewellery. We decided to hide the
jewellery in my apartment and then sell it later.
'The next day was Monday,' Elaine continued,
'and I went to work. In the afternoon,
I had a telephone call from Benny. Benny
said that the red-haired man knew that the
bag of jewellery had been stolen. He was very
angry. Benny told me to stop work and go home.
He told me to stay at home, to make sure that no
one came to take the jewels. Benny was going to
continue working at Las Cabanas. Then no one
would think that he had stolen the jewels.'
'And did you stay at home?' I asked.
'Yes, I stayed at home for three days,' Elaine
replied. 'But I was afraid that the red-haired
man would find out where I was living. Then
he would come to get the bag of jewellery.'
'So what did you do?' I asked.
'That was easy,' she said, with a smile.
'I moved into a hotel in the centre
of the town and then came to see you.'
'But why did you come to see me?' I asked.
'To make sure that I was safe,' said
Elaine. 'I pretended to be my sister
and said that I had disappeared. I asked you
to find me. Then I knew that I was safe.'
'Why?' I asked.
'Because you were looking for me,'
Elaine continued. 'If the men from
Las Cabanas found me or took me away,
you would find out and chase them.'
'Thank you very much for thinking
that I am such a good detective,'
I said. 'But why didn't you tell me the truth?'
'That's easy,' said Elaine. 'I didn't
want to tell you about the jewels.'
CHAPTER TWENTY
I'm Sorry, Mr Samuel
'Go on with your story,' I said.
'The evening I came to see you at your office,'
said Elaine, 'I telephoned Benny at Las Cabanas.
I told Benny what I had done. Benny
told me that the red-haired man knew
that we had stolen the jewellery.
Benny told me that there would be
no trouble if I brought the jewels
back to Las Cabanas the next night.'
'You were stupid to trust
the red-haired man,' I said.
'I know,' the girl said. 'I was afraid. So I
asked you to meet me at Las Cabanas at midnight'
'So you didn't know that Benny was dead
until I told you at Las Cabanas,' I said.
'No,' Elaine said. 'That is why I
ran away before midnight. I decided
not to give them the jewellery,
because they had killed Benny.'
'You've still got the jewels, then?' I
asked, in surprise. 'Where are they?'
'Here,' Elaine said, and pointed
to a small bag under the table.
I reached under the table, picked up the hag
and opened it. The bag was full of diamonds
and jewellery. Just then I heard a voice
and, at the same time, Elaine screamed.
'Give it to me!' said the voice.
I looked up quickly and saw Jo standing beside
me. His tall friend was right behind him.
'Give me the bag!' said Jo, once again.
'How did you know I was here?' I asked.
'You parked your car right outside,' said
Jo, with a laugh. 'Now, give me the bag.'
I passed him the bag. As I gave him the bag, I
jumped to my feet and hit Jo hard in the face.
He tripped and fell heavily onto the
floor. I moved towards the tall man,
who was still standing a few feet away. I was
about to run at him, but then I stopped. The
tall man had taken a gun from his pocket
and the gun was pointing straight at me.
'Right,' said the tall man. 'Don't
move or else I'll shoot you.'
Jo got up from the floor. He still
had the bag of jewellery in his hand.
Together, Jo and his friend with
the gun walked towards the door.
They walked backwards, to make sure that
Elaine and I did not try to get the bag back.
As the two men reached the
door, I started to laugh.
'What are you laughing at?'
shouted the man with the gun.
'Look behind you,' I said.
Both men turned around and looked. In the
doorway of the cafe stood Sergeant Murphy,
with two other policemen. Sergeant Murphy jumped
on the tall man with the gun and Jo ran back into
the cafe. I stepped forward to stop Jo and
he ran straight into me. We both fell on the
floor and the two policemen ran up. One of the
policemen held Jo. The other policeman held me.
'They are the criminals,' I shouted,
pointing at Jo and his friend, 'not me.'
'You are all coming down to the police station,'
Sergeant Murphy said and looked over to
Elaine Garfield. 'You must come, too.'
It took a long time to tell Sergeant
Murphy the whole story. In the end,
he believed what Elaine and I told him. The
sergeant warned me not to tell him lies again,
and agreed to let me go free. Elaine told
Sergeant Murphy all she knew about Las Cabanas.
The sergeant was very pleased to catch
Jo and his friend with the jewels.
Sergeant Murphy agreed to let Elaine go
free, because she helped catch the criminals.
As we were leaving the police station,
I asked Sergeant Murphy how he had
found us in the "Seventh Man" cafe.
'It was very lucky, really,' said the
sergeant. 'We went to your office to see you,
but you weren't there. As we were leaving, we
saw the red-haired man and his friend entering.
We waited and when they left,
we followed them to the cafe.'
'Thank you very much, Sergeant,' said
Elaine. 'And thank you very much, Mr Samuel.'
'That's all right,' I said, 'you
are paying me fifty dollars a day.'
'I'm sorry, Mr Samuel,' Elaine said,
'I'm afraid I can't pay you. Now that I've given
the jewels to the police, I don't have any money.'
I smiled and got into the old grey Chrysler and
drove back to the office. I didn't say goodbye.
When I got back to the office, I sat down in my
chair. It's not much fun being a private eye.
You get hit on the head, nearly killed, and chased
by the police. And you don't always get paid.
- THE END -