Progress
Government offices are much the same everywhere.
Sometimes the officials in them are good people,
helpful and kind; sometimes they are not.
And if you need something badly, sometimes
it is necessary to give little 'presents',
maybe some money, which then disappears into
a back pocket.
These are the ways of the world.
People have been giving and taking bribes
forever.
Marina Salcedo, Senior Clerk, second grade,
hurried to her desk to open her pay envelope.
It was the fifteenth of July, and tomorrow
she was leaving for Manila, to get the promotion
that she had been promised for five years.
She had worked in the Ministry for twenty
years, and in the last five years the cost
of living had risen greatly.
Without the extra money from her promotion,
her youngest son would not be able to go to
college.
Also, three years ago they had borrowed money
on their house when her husband had had to
go to hospital.
She checked her pay carefully.
Two hundred and sixty pesos; this is what
she would take to Manila.
She walked down to the far end of the hall
to the Chief's office.
The girls there were not talking.
That meant the Chief was in.
His secretary told her to go straight in.
The Chief was reading a dirty copy of Playboy,
a magazine for men full of photos of women.
He did not put the magazine away, and Marina
stood in front of him, waiting for him to
look up.
He was about fifty, and going bald.
'So you are leaving tomorrow, Marina,' he
said.
'Yes, sir...'
'Well, you can have the afternoon off, to
get ready.
You will only have three working days in Manila.
Do you think that will be enough?'
'I would like to have three more days, sir,
if possible.'
'No problem, Marina,' the Chief said.
'Oh, and when you are there, will you please
buy me the latest gabardine material for a
pair of pants?
I will pay when you get back.'
'Yes, sir.
Thank you.'
Gabardine material - it must cost at least
sixty pesos.
Last time, the Chief wanted a pair of Levi
jeans; they had cost a hundred and twenty
pesos.
When she returned, they had played this little
game: he saying he must pay, she refusing
to take the money.
After all, he was not a bad boss - three days
off with pay, for example.
And he did not try to touch her in the way
he did with the other women clerks.
The bus left at six in the morning, driving
along the valley through the newly planted
rice fields, the water shining in the early
morning sun.
The roads were good, with strong new bridges,
making the journey to Manila only ten hours.
It used to take a full day.
This was progress, the kind that people could
see and enjoy.
Marina knew there were problems in the mountain
villages and other places, but in her province
things were calm.
Her own life was not so bad.
She and her husband had finally built a house.
Three children, one married and soon to leave
for the United States; another soon to finish
college; and the youngest nearly finished
high school.
But the cost of living had gone up.
They had to cook on wood fires, and could
not afford to buy toilet paper.
Five years ago she had asked for promotion.
She had gone to Manila twice about it, and
finally she had received a notice saying it
would happen.
The bus arrived in Manila as it was getting
dark.
Marina walked to the street where her second
cousin lived.
They had been college students together.
She would probably sleep on a hard sofa in
their living room, but that was better than
spending thirty pesos on a cheap, dirty room
somewhere.
They were having dinner when she arrived and,
like a good relation, she had brought meat,
fish, and rice from her province.
They seemed pleased to see her, but Marina
noticed that her cousin soon asked, 'When
will you leave?'
'I won't be here more than a week,' she said,
'and I won't eat here.
I'll spend every day at the Ministry, following
up my papers.'
She was up at six the next day.
Her cousin's children, aged thirteen and fourteen,
were getting ready for school.
They had kept her awake playing rock music
in the night.
When she arrived at the Ministry, she went
straight to Personnel.
The people that she worked with years ago
in that office had all left, and there was
nobody she knew.
She asked for the person who worked on the
papers of staff promotion, and was sent to
the other end of the office, to a fat woman
in her early thirties, with bad teeth, thin
hair, and a uniform that was too small for
her large body.
The woman brought out a list and read through
it carefully.
Then she moved some papers around on her desk,
and looked up with a fat little smile.
'I am sorry, Mrs Salcedo, but your name is
not here.
Maybe the forms got lost...'
'But it cannot be,' Marina said.
Her voice got louder.
'I have the official letter from you.'
She quickly pulled it out of her handbag.
'Here... and the file number.'
The woman shook her head, and her fixed little
smile did not change.
'Mrs Salcedo,' she said sweetly, 'I will have
to look through the files, hundreds and hundreds
of them.
I will have to ask one of the boys.'
She opened the drawer in her desk that was
closest to Marina.
'Why don't you drop a twenty-peso bill in
here for him...?'
For a moment Marina Salcedo could not believe
this was happening to her.
She worked in the same Ministry as these people.
Then she remembered that Anita Botong in her
office in the province did the same thing.
It had gone on for a long time - too long
to be easy to stop.
She took a twenty-peso bill from her handbag,
and dropped it in the drawer.
'Will I come back this afternoon then?'
she asked.
'Oh, Mrs Salcedo,' the woman said, still smiling.
'You know how difficult it will be.
Why don't you come back early tomorrow?'
'I am from the province...'
'Yes, I know.
I will do all I can to help you...'
She had nothing more to do.
She left the Ministry and took a jeepney to
the market in Quiapo.
What was the best kind of gabardine, she asked,
and what did it cost?
In the end she bought the material in one
of the big department stores for thirty-four
pesos.
Then she looked round the rest of the market,
and found that food prices were higher than
at home.
So, prices in the province were not so bad
then!
She spent five pesos on a bowl of noodles
with chicken for lunch, then walked around
the city.
She had not been to Manila for some time,
and it had changed a lot.
In Makati, a very rich area, there were tall,
glass-sided buildings, and the streets were
clean.
It was like America.
She thought of her son, who would soon be
in America.
One day in the future she and her husband
hoped to join him there.
But the future was here, in Makati.
And if this was the future, was it necessary
to leave the country?
The next morning, back at the Ministry, the
fat woman had found her papers, but there
was a new form to complete.
Marina would have to fetch Form D22a from
another office in the building, fill it in,
and then take it to Personnel, who would sign
it and send it back to the first office.
This office was on the fifth floor, and the
lift was not working.
The man in the Form D22a office was very sorry.
'Oh, please come back tomorrow afternoon.
We have no forms here at the moment - we have
to get some more.'
Marina recognized the old game at once, and
was annoyed.
The top drawer in the man's desk was open,
and Marina dropped a five-peso bill into it.
She must remember to carry two-peso bills,
she thought.
'Please, I am really in a hurry,' she said.
'Do try and find one.
There must be one lying around...'
The man closed his desk drawer with a smile,
then went to an old filing cabinet behind
his desk.
It didn't take him a minute to find the form.
The form had a lot of questions, about dates
of this and that, school and college, travel
abroad...
That made Marina laugh.
How many government clerks have ever traveled
abroad?
She hadn't even traveled around her own country.
Looking back over her past, she began to think
about what she wanted from life.
She had never wanted to climb to the top of
the tree, to become a minister.
Both she and her husband were happy enough
with things as they were.
After all these years, they had their own
home, a piece of land, and they could sleep
deeply at night, not worried by the kind of
bad dreams that important ministers must have.
She took her completed form to the Chief in
the office, who was said to be an honest man.
Now was the moment when she would find out
if that was true.
She waited and waited, and was at last called
over to the glass-topped desk where Chief
Bermudez was sitting.
'Well, what is your problem?'
'My promotion, sir,' Marina said.
'I've been waiting a long time for it.'
She put her papers on the desk in front of
him.
Chief Bermudez read them all carefully.
'Well, Mrs Salcedo, everything here seems
all right.
You know what to do next.
After I sign the forms, you go to Finance
to find out if there are funds to pay you.
If there are, the Minister will sign the papers
- and you will have your hundred pesos a month.
And I think your pay rise should start at
the beginning of this year, to give you those
extra months.
I will make sure that happens.'
He began to sign the papers.
'I know you have worked for the Ministry for
a long time.
Things happen too slowly sometimes - I should
not tell you this really - but we must be
patient.
We must push, and push, and push... but only
gently.'
He smiled.
'Good luck with Finance.'
They were now alone in the room.
'Is that all, sir?' said Marina.
'Why, is there something that I have forgotten?'
In her surprise, Mrs Salcedo forgot to thank
him.
At the door she decided that Chief Bermudez
was a good man.
Perhaps she should buy him some gabardine
material too.
After all, he had added several extra months
to her pay rise.
After a quick lunch, just some bananas and
a drink, she went to Finance.
The girls in the office were sitting talking,
or reading newspapers, or doing nothing.
The Finance Chief, she was told, was out and
would not be in until tomorrow.
Marina left, and decided to go and see a movie.
The next morning she was back in Finance before
eight o'clock.
She noticed that the office had several pretty
girls, and they seemed to do nothing.
At eight-thirty the Finance Chief arrived,
Julio Lobo, one of the top men in the Ministry.
He was wearing a brown gabardine suit - she
recognized the material at once.
She went into his office.
Chief Lobo was reading some files and adding
up some figures on a calculator.
He looked up at her.
There were heavy bags under his eyes, and
his thick lips smiled.
'Yes?'
Mrs Salcedo explained her story, telling him
she was from the province.
'You can leave your papers here,' he said,
still smiling.
'I am in a hurry.
I have a meeting in another town today and
will not be back until five.
You can come and see me then.'
Marina now had to wait all day, and this endless
battle to get her promotion was giving her
a headache.
But it could be worse in other ministries.
She knew a teacher who had to pay a thousand
pesos just to move to another town.
It was raining outside so she decided to stay
in the building and visit the Education office,
where she had friends.
At three o'clock she went back to wait outside
Chief Lobo's office, and tried to read a novel,
but it did not hold her interest.
The pretty girls in the office were all talking
about the disco they were going to that evening.
At five Chief Lobo arrived, and some of the
girls went in and out with papers.
When they had left, Marina went in.
'Ah, Mrs Salcedo - yes, your papers are still
here.
I will work on them tomorrow, Saturday.
Did you know I work even on Saturday?'
'No, sir.'
'Well, I do.
' He smiled, showing teeth yellow from cigarette
smoke.
He looked at his desk diary, then at her papers
again.
'Mmm... a hundred pesos a month.
Why, that's one thousand two hundred pesos
a year.
Surely, you can afford to buy me a forty-peso
dinner!'
'Yes, of course, sir,' she said.
'Well, then, my favorite Japanese restaurant
is in Ermita.
It's easy to find.
I'll be there on Sunday evening, at seven.
I will have your papers - all finished.
I see no problem, really.'
'Thank you, sir,' Mrs Salcedo said.
Forty pesos!
If she did not eat, she could afford the meal.
She would still just have enough to buy her
bus ticket.
During Saturday and Sunday morning Marina
did not leave her cousin's apartment.
Going out meant spending money.
So she made rice cakes, cleaned her cousin's
kitchen, and washed the floor and the walls
in the living room.
When the family came home Saturday evening,
the place was shining clean, and her cousin
was very pleased.
On Sunday afternoon she went out to find the
Japanese restaurant.
It was mostly foreigners eating there, and
it looked very expensive.
She would have to give the waiters something
too.
She must be honest with Chief Lobo, tell him
that she did not have the money, that she
would give him a present later, when she had
got her pay rise.
From there she went to the Manila Hotel, where
in 1955 she had danced with her boyfriend,
later her husband, when they finished their
university studies.
It was pleasant to remember those days.
But the hotel had changed - it was all new
inside, with thick carpets and fine wooden
furniture.
She saw the coffee shop, but she could not
afford even one cup of coffee, so she sat
on one of the deep soft sofas, watching the
beautiful people walking past.
So, there was progress under the government's
grand new plan, as this fine hotel showed.
At six-thirty she walked back to the Japanese
restaurant.
Chief Lobo was there, his fat stomach too
big for his blue jeans, and his T-shirt smelly
from his unwashed body.
They sat down, and all around them were the
delicious smells of fresh food cooking.
Marina found it hard to speak.
'Sir, you know I am just a poor clerk in the
province.
I have only a hundred pesos-'
Chief Lobo's hand came down heavily onto her
knee, and stayed there.
'My dear woman,' he said.
'We are not going to spend all that.
I will just have tea, and... some fish.
Too much food is bad for me.
But making love is not bad for me.
So, after this, we go to a motel.
That will be no more than forty pesos...'
Marina did not want to believe what she had
heard.
Then she remembered office talk about the
Finance Chief - how he behaved towards women,
what he asked for...
'I have three children, sir,' she said miserably.
'My oldest is married, I have a grandson,
the first.'
'That's wonderful,' said Chief Lobo.
'But you know, you don't look like a grandmother.'
He looked at her body hungrily, and Marina
felt her face turning red.
'You have a good body, very nice...'
'Surely, sir, with all those pretty girls
in your office...'
Chief Lobo laughed.
'Ha!
You noticed,' he said.
'But they are young, they need teaching.
I don't want to be a teacher all the time.
I enjoy beautiful, older women - like you.'
His hand moved higher up her leg.
'I am forty-five,' said Marina.
'But you don't look thirty-five!' he said.
She followed him to his car outside in the
street.
Her mouth was dry with fear.
She must be good to him.
The future was in his hands.
She tried again and again to talk him out
of it, but he did not listen.
Alone with him in the motel room at last,
she begged him one more time.
'Sir, please.
I will give you half the money I get from
my promotion.
I promise!'
Chief Lobo looked at her in surprise.
'Stupid girl,' he said angrily 'It's not money
I need.'
He began to take off his shoes.
When she did not move, he shouted at her.
'Take off your clothes!'
'My poor husband, my poor children,' Marina
cried softly as he began to touch her.
She was back at the apartment at nine.
She took a long shower, hating Chief Lobo,
hating herself, hating the world.
How would it be tomorrow when she saw him
again?
He had not even brought her papers as he had
promised.
She did not sleep much that night.
When morning came, she knew she must go on,
finish the job.
After that terrible evening, there was no
battle that she could not fight - nothing
could stop her now.
Chief Lobo's thick lips smiled at her when
she came in.
'We will go up to the Minister's office now,'
he said, standing up and picking up her papers.
The Minister's office was very big, with a
carpet, paintings on the walls, and tall green
plants in the corners.
Minister Guzman was also wearing a brown gabardine
suit, but Marina, looking at it closely, realized
it was a finer, more expensive material.
She had heard that the Minister had a drinking
problem.
He certainly seemed strange this morning - either
sleepy or drunk.
Chief Lobo put Marina's papers on the desk,
and the Minister looked through them.
'Ah, Mrs Salcedo... your promotion...
I am very happy to sign these.'
To Chief Lobo.
'Are there funds for this?'
'Yes, sir,' Lobo said.
After the Minister had signed the papers,
he turned to her again.
'Mrs Salcedo, how is it in your province?
What are your problems?
It's good to see someone from your province
here.
You know, your province is very important
in our New Society plan.'
Mrs Salcedo looked at him.
Was the Minister serious?
How could he be so drunk so early in the morning?
She shook her head.
'We have no problems, sir.'
'Come now,' the Minister said.
'Be honest.
We need the truth, the facts.
Only that way can we make progress.'
Marina shook her head again.
'Everything is fine in our province, sir,'
she said.
'All right then,' the Minister said.
'But you must work hard.
All of you.
You must remember we are building a New Society,
progress for the people, a country to be proud
of.'
He seemed to be talking to everyone in the
office.
'Yes, sir,' Marina said.
'We must all work together.
Progress.
Promotions are wonderful, but we must work
for them.
Progress...'
After Marina had bought her bus ticket, she
had two pesos left.
She had made three meat sandwiches at her
cousin's, and that would have to be enough
until she got home.
When the bus arrived in her town, it was past
six and already dark.
To save money, she decided to walk home from
the bus station.
She only had a handbag, a small bag of clothes,
the gabardine material, and two apples.
Away from the town centre, the road was unlit
and rough.
She and her family lived on the edge of the
town, where they could grow vegetables and
keep chickens.
She had just turned a corner when a man jumped
out of the shadows and grabbed her handbag.
She held on to it as hard as she could, but
the man pushed her and she fell, hurting her
face on the ground.
He took the bag, and as he ran, she shouted
after him.
'There's no money in there - just my papers.
My papers!'
But he was gone too fast and did not hear
her.
She stood up slowly, feeling weak and strange.
She still had a long way to walk, and her
legs did not want to move.
It started to rain, but her umbrella was in
the handbag that was stolen.
She did not mind the rain; it was losing her
papers that felt like a heavy stone lying
on her heart.
Without the papers, there would be no pay
rise.
She knew, only too well, that nothing could
make Manila send copies of her papers.
She would have to return to the capital, and
the thought of that filled her heart with
fear and misery.
At last she reached her house, with the trees
all around it.
When she pushed the door open, her family
were eating supper and they ran from the table
to greet her.
They saw the dirt on her clothes, her pale
face, her wet untidy hair.
To their questions she gave no answers, and
Marina Salcedo fell to her knees, the anger
and misery coming from her in violent sobbing.
No words of kindness, of love, no friendly
touch could stop the river of her tears.
- THE END -