CHAPTER ONE
Thunder Road - Bruce Spingsteen
I can remember listening to this song and
loving it in 1975; I can remember listening
to this song and loving it almost as much
quite recently, a few months ago.
(And, yes, I was in a car, although I probably
wasn't driving, and I certainly wasn't driving
down any turnpike or highway or freeway, and
the wind wasn't blowing through my hair, because
I possess neither a convertible nor hair.
It's not that version of Springsteen.)
So I've loved this song for a quarter of a
century now, and I've heard it more than anything
else, with the possible exception of...
Who am I kidding?
There are no other contenders.
See, what I was going to do there was soften
the blow, slip in something black and... or
cool possibly 'Let's Get It On', which I think
is the best pop record ever made, and which
would easily make it into my top 20 most-played
songs list, but not at number 2.
Number 2 - and I'm trying to be honest here
- would probably be something like '(White
Man) In Hammersmith Palais' by The Clash,
but it would be way, way behind.
Let's say I've played 'Thunder Road' 1,500
times (just over once a week for twenty-five
years, which sounds about right, if one takes
into account the repeat plays in the first
couple of years); '(White Man)... would have
clocked up something like 500 plays.
In other words, there's no real competition.
It's weird to me how 'Thunder Road' has survived
when so many other, arguably better songs
- 'Maggie May', 'Hey Jude', 'God Save The
Queen', 'Stir It Up', 'So Tired of Being Alone',
'You're A Big Girl Now' - have become less
compelling as I've got older.
It's not as if I can't see the flaws: 'Thunder
Road' is overwrought, both lyrically (as Prefab
Sprout pointed out, there's more to life than
cars and girls, and surely the word 'redemption'
is to be avoided like the plague when you're
writing songs about redemption) and musically
- after all, this four and three-quarter minutes
provided Jim Steinman and Meatloaf with a
whole career.
It's also po-faced, in a way that Springsteen
himself isn't, and if the doomed romanticism
wasn't corny in 1975, then it certainly is
now.
But sometimes, very occasionally, songs and
books and films and pictures express who you
are, perfectly.
And they don't do this in words or images,
necessarily; the connection is a lot less
direct and more complicated than that.
When I was first beginning to write seriously,
I read Anne Tyler's Dinner at the Homesick
Restaurant, and suddenly knew what I was,
and what I wanted to be, for better or for
worse.
It's a process something like falling in love.
You don't necessarily choose the best person,
or the wisest, or the most beautiful; there's
something else going on.
There was a part of me that would rather have
fallen for Updike, or Kerouac, or DeLillo
- for someone masculine, at least, maybe somebody
a little more opaque, and certainly someone
who uses more swear-words - and, though I
have admired those writers, at various stages
in my life, admiration is a very different
thing from the kind of transference I'm talking
about.
I'm talking about understanding - or at least
feeling like I understand - every artistic
decision, every impulse, the soul of both
the work and its creator.
'This is me,' I wanted to say when I read
Tyler's rich, sad, lovely novel.
'I'm not a character, I'm nothing like the
author, I haven't had the experiences she
writes about.
But even so, this is what I feel like, inside.
This is what I would sound like, if ever I
were to find a voice.'
And I did find a voice, eventually, and it
was mine, not hers; but nevertheless, so powerful
was the process of identification that I still
don't feel as though I've expressed myself
as well, as completely, as Tyler did on my
behalf then.
So, even though I'm not American, no longer
young, hate cars, and can recognize why so
many people find Springsteen bombastic and
histrionic (but not why they find him macho
or jingoistic or dumb - that kind of ignorant
judgment has plagued Springsteen for a huge
part of his career, and is made by smart people
who are actually a lot dumber than he has
ever been), 'Thunder Road' somehow manages
to speak for me.
This is partly - and perhaps shamingly - because
a lot of Springsteen's songs from this period
are about becoming famous, or at least achieving
some kind of public validation through his
art: what else are we supposed to think when
the last line of the song is 'I'm pulling
out of here to win', other than that he has
won, simply by virtue of playing the song,
night after night after night, to an ever-increasing
crowd of people?
(And what else are we supposed to think when
in 'Rosalita' he sings, with a touching, funny
and innocent glee, 'Cos the record company,
Rosie, just gave me a big advance', other
than that the record company has just given
him a big advance?)
It's never objectionable or obnoxious, this
dream of fame, because it derives from a restless
and uncontrollable artistic urge - he knows
he has talent to burn, and the proper reward
for this, he seems to suggest, would be the
financial wherewithal to fulfil it - rather
than an interest in celebrity for its own
sake.
Hosting a TV quiz show, or assassinating a
president, wouldn't scratch the itch at all.
And, of course - don't let anyone tell you
otherwise - if you have dreams of becoming
a writer, then there are murky, mucky visions
of fame attached to these dreams too; 'Thunder
Road' was my answer to every rejection letter
I received, and every doubt expressed by friends
or relatives.
They lived in towns for losers, I told myself,
and I, like Bruce, was pulling out of there
to win.
(These towns, incidentally, were Cambridge
- full of loser doctors and lawyers and academics
- and London - full of loser successes of
every description - but never mind.
This was the material I had to work with,
and work with it I did.)
It helped a great deal that, as time went
by, and there was no sign of me pulling out
of anywhere to do anything very much, and
certainly not with the speed implied in the
song, 'Thunder Road' made reference to age,
thus accommodating this lack of forward momentum.
'So you're scared and you're thinking that
maybe we ain't that young any more', Bruce
sang, and that line worked for me even when
I had begun to doubt whether there was any
magic in the night: I continued thinking I
wasn't that young any more for a long, long
time - decades, in fact - and even today I
choose to interpret it as a wistful observation
of middle age, rather than the sharp fear
that comes on in late youth.
It also helped that, sometime in the early
to mid-eighties, I came across another version
of the song, a bootleg studio recording of
Springsteen alone with an acoustic guitar
(it's on War And Roses, the Born To Run outtakes
bootleg); he reimagines 'Thunder Road' as
a haunting, exhausted hymn to the past, to
lost love and missed opportunities and self-delusion
and bad luck and failure, and that worked
pretty well for me, too.
In fact, when I try to hear that last line
of the song in my head, it's the acoustic
version that comes first.
It's slow, and mournful, and utterly convincing:
an artist who can persuade you of the truth
of what he is singing with either version
is an artist who is capable of an awful lot.
There are other bootleg versions that I play
and love.
One of the great things about the song as
it appears on Born To Run is that those first
few bars, on wheezy harmonica and achingly
pretty piano, actually sound like they refer
to something that has already happened before
the beginning of the record, something momentous
and sad but not destructive of all hope; as
Thunder Road' is the first track on side one
of Born To Run, the album begins, in effect,
with its own closing credits.
In performance at the end of the seventies,
during the Darkness on the Edge of Town tour,
Springsteen maximized this effect by seguing
into 'Thunder Road' out of one of his bleakest,
most desperate songs, 'Racing In The Street',
and the harmonica that marks the transformation
of one song into the other feels like a sudden
and glorious hint of spring after a long,
withering winter.
On the bootlegs of those seventies shows,
Thunder Road' can finally provide the salvation
that its position on Born To Run denied it.
Maybe the reason Thunder Road' has sustained
for me is that, despite its energy and volume
and fast cars and hair, it somehow manages
to sound elegiac, and the older I get the
more I can hear that.
When it comes down to it, I suppose that I
too believe that life is momentous and sad
but not destructive of all hope, and maybe
that makes me a self-dramatizing depressive,
or maybe it makes me a happy idiot, but either
way 'Thunder Road' knows how I feel and who
I am, and that, in the end, is one of the
consolations of art.
Postscript
A few years ago, I started to sell a lot of
books, at first only in the UK, and then later
in other countries too, and to my intense
bewilderment found that I had somehow become
part of the literary and cultural mainstream.
It wasn't something I had expected, or was
prepared for.
Although I could see no reason why anyone
would feel excluded from my work - it wasn't
like it was difficult, or experimental - my
books still seemed to me to be quirky and
small- scale.
But suddenly all sorts of people, people I
didn't know or like or respect, had opinions
about me and my work, which overnight seemed
to go from being fresh and original to cliched
and ubiquitous, without a word of it having
changed.
And I was shown this horrible reflection of
myself and what I did, a funfair hall-of-mirrors
reflection, all squished-up and distorted
- me, but not me.
It wasn't like I was given a particularly
hard time, and certainly other people, some
of whom I know, have experienced much worse.
But even so, it becomes in those circumstances
very hard to hang on to the idea of what you
want to do.
And yet Springsteen somehow managed to find
a way through.
His name is still taken in vain frequently
(a year or so ago I read a newspaper piece
attacking Tony Blair for his love of Bruce,
an indication, apparently, of the Prime Minister's
incorrigible philistinism), and for some,
the hall-of-mirrors reflection is the only
Springsteen they can see.
He went from being rock 'n' roll future to
a lumpy, flag-waving, stadium-rocking meathead
in the space of a few months, again with nothing
much having changed, beyond the level of his
popularity.
Anyway, his strength of purpose, and the way
he has survived the assault on his sense of
self, seem to me exemplary; sometimes it's
hard to remember that a lot of people liking
what you do doesn't necessarily mean that
what you do is of no value whatsoever.
Indeed, sometimes it might even suggest the
opposite.
CHAPTER TWO
I'm Like a Bird - Nelly Furtado
Oh, of course I can understand people dismissing
pop music.
I know that a lot of it, nearly all of it,
is trashy, unimaginative, poorly written,
slickly produced, inane, repetitive and juvenile
(although at least four of these adjectives
could be used to describe the incessant attacks
on pop that you can still find in posh magazines
and newspapers); I know too, believe me, that
Cole Porter was 'better' than Madonna or Travis,
that most pop songs are aimed cynically at
a target audience three decades younger than
I am, that in any case the golden age was
thirty-five years ago and there has been very
little of value since.
It's just that there's this song I heard on
the radio, and I bought the CD, and now I
have to hear it ten or fifteen times a day...
That's the thing that puzzles me about those
who feel that contemporary pop (and I use
the word to encompass soul, reggae, country,
rock - anything and everything that might
be regarded as trashy) is beneath them, or
behind them, or beyond them - some preposition
denoting distance, anyway: does this mean
that you never hear, or at least never enjoy,
new songs, that everything you whistle or
hum was written years, decades, centuries
ago?
Do you really deny yourselves the pleasure
of mastering a tune (a pleasure, incidentally,
that your generation is perhaps the first
in the history of mankind to forgo) because
you are afraid it might make you look as if
you don't know who Harold Bloom is?
Wow, I'll bet you're fun at parties.
The song that has been driving me pleasurably
potty recently is 'I'm Like a Bird' by Nelly
Furtado.
Only history will judge whether Ms Furtado
turns out to be any kind of artist, and though
I have my suspicions that she will not change
the way we look at the world, I can't say
that I'm very bothered: I will always be grateful
to her for creating in me the narcotic need
to hear her song again and again.
It is, after all, a harmless need, easily
satisfied, and there are few enough of those
in the world.
I don't even want to make a case for this
song, as opposed to any other - although I
happen to think that it's a very good pop
song, with a dreamy languor and a bruised
optimism that immediately distinguishes it
from its anemic and stunted peers.
The point is that a few months ago it didn't
exist, at least as far as we are concerned,
and now here it is, and that, in itself, is
a small miracle.
Dave Eggers has a theory that we play songs
over and over, those of us who do, because
we have to 'solve' them, and it's true that
in our early relationship with, and courtship
of, a new song, there is a stage which is
akin to a sort of emotional puzzlement.
There's a little bit in 'I'm Like a Bird',
for example, about halfway through, where
the voice is double-tracked on a phrase, and
the effect - especially on someone who is
not a musician, someone who loves and appreciates
music but is baffled and seduced by even the
simplest musical tricks - is rich and fresh
and addictive.
Sure, it will seem thin and stale soon enough.
Before very long I will have 'solved' 'I'm
Like a Bird', and I won't want to hear it
very much anymore - a three-minute pop song
can only withhold its mysteries for so long,
after all.
So, yes, it's disposable, as if that makes
any difference to anyone's perceptions of
the value of pop music.
But then, shouldn't we be sick of 'Moonlight'
Sonata by now?
Or Christina's World?
Or The Importance of Being Earnest?
They're empty!
Nothing left!
We sucked 'em dry!
That's what gets me: the very people who are
snotty about the disposability of pop will
go over and over again to see Lady Bracknell
say 'A handbag?'
in a funny voice.
They don't think that joke's exhausted itself?
Maybe disposability is a sign of pop music's
maturity, a recognition of its own limitations,
rather than the converse.
And anyway, I was sitting in a doctor's waiting-room
the other day, and four little Afro- Caribbean
girls, patiently sitting out their mother's
appointment, suddenly launched into Nelly
Furtado's song.
They were word perfect, and they had a couple
of dance moves, and they sang with enormous
appetite and glee, and I liked it that we
had something in common, temporarily; I felt
as though we all lived in the same world,
and that doesn't happen so often.
A couple of times a year I make myself a tape
to play in the car, a tape full of all the
new songs I've loved over the previous few
months, and every time I finish one I can't
believe that there'll be another.
Yet there always is, and I can't wait for
the next one; you need only a few hundred
more things like that, and you've got a life
worth living.
CHAPTER THREE
Samba Pa Ti - Santana
'Samba Pa Ti' is an instrumental, rather than
a song, but for a crucial period in my mid-teens,
when I first came across it, it spoke to me
as eloquently as anything that contained lyrics:
I was convinced that it described sex.
More specifically, 'Samba Pa Ti' was what
I was going to hear when I lost my virginity
- if not on the stereo, then in my head.
It starts off slow and mysterious and beautiful,
and then it gets more urgent, and then - well,
then it fades out.
(The track lasts four minutes and forty-seven
seconds, incidentally; but before I am accused
of showing off, I had anticipated that we'd
be doing other things - kissing, getting undressed,
possibly waiting for a bus home from the cinema
- during the slow bit, so I was confident
that I could make it through to the fade.)
I hadn't, at that time, heard anything that
would serve as a better soundtrack; indeed,
I'm not entirely sure that I've heard anything
to beat it since.
All sorts of pieces of music are constantly
being described as 'sexy', but that doesn't
necessarily mean that you'd want them to accompany
love-making.
Most of them, in fact, are sexual substitutes,
rather than sexual accompaniments - music
for people who aren't getting any (or won't
be until they get home) rather than people
who are.
Would it be possible to fuck to the tune of
'Let's Get It On' without laughing?
(Not that there's anything wrong with laughing
during sex, but laughter was not, I suspect,
the sound that Marvin intended to provoke.
If you want to laugh, then why not enhance
your amorous pleasure with 'I Have a Pony',
by Steven Wright, or 'Disco Duck', by Rick
Dees?)
And even if you did manage to get through
it without a giggling fit, could you man-age
the same during 'If I Should Die Tonight',
the third track on the album?
Granted, you may have finished by then, but
there's every chance that you won't have turned
the music off, which means that you'll be
lying there with your girlfriend, or boyfriend,
or someone you don't know very well, while
Marvin is telling you that the sex you have
just had is unlikely to be bettered during
the remainder of your lifetimes - indeed,
that you may as well shuffle off this mortal
coil now, so anticlimactic is any subsequent
experience likely to be.
This is an intolerable burden to place on
any couple, and certainly inhibits the usual
post-coital activities (sleep, the hunt for
socks or the TV remote, exchanges of false
email addresses, etc.).
Prince's 'Do Me, Baby', from the Controversy
album, is one of the most sexually explicit,
and genuinely erotic, records ever made, but
it's every bit as problematic as 'Let's Get
It On'.
For a start, there's a bit after the climax
(crashing piano chords, moans, sighs, and
so on) when he goes all weird, and starts
saying he's 'soooo cold', which might well
prove to be something of a distraction unless
you too have an inappropriately under togged
duvet.
And though the next song on the album, 'Private
Joy', is hardly what you want to hear at an
intimate moment, at least it brings the first
side of Controversy to a close if you have
the album on vinyl; if you have the CD, however,
you may find yourself in the unhappy position
of trying to give and receive carnal pleasure
while Prince sings 'Ronnie Talk To Russia'
- a sentiment that no longer even contains
the virtue, arguable in a sexual context anyway,
of urgency.
What, one wonders, was he thinking of when
he sequenced the tracks?
Presumably something along the lines of, 'Give
them five minutes to get their breath back,
and then they'll be wanting to think about
impending Armageddon.'
Inevitably, I did not lose my virginity to
'Samba Pa Ti'.
Instead, my unfortunate girlfriend and I were
listening to the second side of Rod Stewart's
Smiler, my favourite record at the time; side
two, I notice now, features 'Hard Road', 'I've
Grown Accustomed To Her Face' and 'Dixie Toot'.
In a perfect world, obviously, that wouldn't
have happened.
CAN YOU PLEASE CRAWL OUT YOUR WINDOW?
BOB DYLAN
CHAPTER FOUR
Rain - The Beatles
By expressing no preference between a Rod
Stewart version of a Bob Dylan song and the
Dylan original, I have, I know, exposed myself:
I'm not a big Dylan fan.
I've got Blonde On Blonde and Highway 61 Revisited,
obviously.
And Bringing It All Back Home and Blood On
the Tracks.
Anyone who likes music owns those four.
And I'm interested enough to have bought The
Bootleg Series Volumes 7-3, and that live
album we now know wasn't recorded at the Royal
Albert Hall.
The reviews of Time Out Of Mind and Love And
Theft convinced me to shell out for these
two, as well, although I can't say I listen
to them very often.
I once asked for Biograph as a birthday present,
so with that and The Bootleg Series I've got
two Dylan boxed sets.
I also, now I look, seem to own copies of
World Gone Wrong, The Basement Tapes and Good
As I Been To You, although this, I suspect,
is due more to my respect for Greil Marcus,
who has written so persuasively and brilliantly
about Dylan's folk and blues roots, than to
my Dylanphilia.
And I have somehow picked up along the way
Street Legal, Desire, and John Wesley Harding.
Oh, and I bought Oh Mercy because it contains
the lovely 'Most of the Time', which is on
the High Fidelity soundtrack.
There are, therefore, around twenty separate
Bob Dylan CDs on my shelf; in fact I own more
recordings by Dylan than by any other artist.
Some people - my mother, say, who may not
own twenty CDs in total - would say that I
am a Dylan fanatic, but I know Dylan fanatics,
and they would not recognize me as one of
them.
(I have a friend who stays logged on to the
Dylan website Expecting Rain most of the day
at work - as if the website were CNN and Dylan's
career were the Middle East - and who owns
130 Dylan albums, including a fourteen-CD
box of every single thing Dylan recorded during
1965 apart from - get this - Highway 67 Revisited,
the only thing he recorded during 1965 that
sane people would want to own.
He's pretty keen.)
I can't quote whole songs - just the odd line
here and there.
I do not regard Dylan as any more important,
or any more talented, than Elvis Presley,
or Marvin Gaye, or Bob Marley, or several
other major artists.
I have no opinion as to whether he was a poet,
and especially not as to whether he was a
better poet than another poet, I don't own
any bootlegs, I have no desire to see him
play live again (I saw him twice, and that
was more than enough), I have no theories
about any single song...
I just like some of the tunes, and that, I
have been led to believe, is Not Good Enough.
There is a very clever English artist called
Emma Kay who has done a series of artworks
which consist entirely of her (verbal) memories
of Shakespeare plays.
If I were to do the same for the life of Bob
Dylan, it would consist of the following list:
Zimmerman
Hibbing, Minnesota
New York coffee houses
Joan Baez (But what about her?
I'm not sure.)
The Band, formerly The Hawks.
Electricity.
'Judas!'
Motorbike crash.
Never as good afterwards.
(Is that true?
I fear I may be getting the crash confused
with Elvis's spell in the army.)
Sara (Sara who?
Don't know).
Divorce.
Eye-liner Christianity Farm Aid Lots of tours
This, it seems to me, is way too much knowledge.
(Why on earth am I able to name his home town?
And why should I recall that he fell off his
bloody motorbike?)
I will not attempt a similar list pertaining
to the life of William Shakespeare, because
it would be far too shaming, but suffice to
say that it would not extend much beyond Stratford-upon-Avon,
Anne Hathaway and her cottage, the Globe and
the Dark Lady.
Jane Austen: Bath; unmarried; once went to
my sister's house, apparently, although some
time before my sister moved there.
(That must be right, mustn't it, dates-wise?)
Obviously I have no one but myself to blame
for my ignorance of our major literary figures.
I'm not responsible for my intimacy with the
Life of Bob, however.
That's the fault of all sorts of other people:
friends, music writers, university professors,
editors at my publishing house.
He's hard to avoid - mostly because his status
as a major poet allows one to like him without
inducing the feelings of intellectual insecurity
that usually accompany devotion to a pop star.
I suppose I re-sent that.
In my book, you're either in or you're out,
and if you're in, then get in properly, and
find as big a place in your heart for the
stupid stuff - 'Mmmm Bop' and 'Judy Is a Punk'
- as for the stuff that you can pass off as
poetry.
Obviously I wouldn't ask you to find as big
a place in your head for 'Mmmm Bop', but then,
that's partly the trouble: the best music
connects to the soul, not the brain, and I
worry that all this Dylan-devotion is somehow
anti-music - that it tells us the heart doesn't
count, and only the head matters.
Elsewhere in this book you will find fanciful
comparisons be-tween literature and music,
specifically novels and songs, but you sure
can exhaust a great song much more quickly
than you can clean out a great novel, and
- partly, I suspect, because I am not interested
in Dylan as poet - I've exhausted Bob, or
at least the bits of Bob that I'm interested
in.
I wish I hadn't; there's a density and a gravity
to a Dylan song that you can't find anywhere
else.
But even more than I regret mining the seam
for all it's worth (or all it's worth to me),
I regret never having heard any of the songs
at the right age, in the right year.
What must it have been like, to listen to
'Like A Rolling Stone' in 1966, aged nineteen
or twenty?
I heard 'White Riot' and 'Anarchy In The UK'
in 1976, aged nineteen, but the enormous power
those records had then has mostly been lost
now.
Much of the shock came from their volume and
speed and brevity, and records consequently
became louder and faster and shorter; listening
to them a quarter of a century later is like
watching old film of Jesse Owens running.
You can see that he won his races, but all
sense of pace has been wiped away by Maurice
Greene.
'Like A Rolling Stone', however, still sounds
perfect.
It just doesn't sound fresh anymore.
In Victorian London they used to burn phosphorus
at seances in an attempt to see ghosts, and
I suspect that the pop-music equivalent is
our obsession with B-sides and alternative
versions and unreleased material.
If you can hear Dylan and The Beatles being
unmistakably themselves at their peak - but
unmistakably themselves in a way we haven't
heard a thousand, a million times before - then
suddenly you get a small but thrilling flash
of their spirit, and it's as close as we'll
ever get, those of us born in the wrong time,
to knowing what it must have been like to
have those great records burst out of the
radio at you when you weren't expecting them,
or anything like them.
'Can You Please Crawl Out Your Window?' is,
I accept, a minor Dylan track, one of his
snarly (and less than poetic) put-downs, but
it is from my favourite period (electric,
with that crisp, clean organ sound), and I
haven't heard it a million times before, so
it sneaks its way on to car tapes now.
And 'Rain' is a great Beatles song from a
great year in their career, the year that
Oasis have been trying to live in for the
last ten years, and it's wonderful to listen
to a Lennon/McCartney song that hasn't quite
had all the pulp sucked from it.
I'll get sick of both these songs in the end,
of course - they just don't last long enough
to keep their mystery and magic forever.
But they'll do for now.
CHAPTER FIVE
A Minor Incident - Badly Drawn Boy
'You must be excited about the film coming
out,' a friendly and well-meaning acquaintance
remarked at the end of 2001, a few months
before the movie version of About A Boy was
released.
(Those weren't her actual words.
Her actual words were, 'You must be excited
about About A Boy coming out.'
I changed them because, prose stylist that
I am, I wanted to avoid that double 'about'.
I'm sick of it.
My advice to young writers: never begin a
title with a preposition, because you will
find that it is impossible to utter or to
write any sentence pertaining to your creation
without sounding as if you have an especially
pitiable stutter.
'He wanted to talk to me about About A Boy.'
'What about About A Boy?'
The thing about About A Boy...'
'Are you excited about About A Boy?'
And so on.
I wonder if Steinbeck and his publishers got
sick of it?
'What do you think of Of Mice and Men?'
'I've just finished the first half of Of Mice
and Men.'
'What's the publication date of Of Mice and
Men?'...
Still, it seemed like a good idea at the time.)
I smiled politely, but the supposition mystified
me.
Why on earth would I get excited?
There had been interesting, sometimes even
enjoyable bits along the way - selling the
rights to the book for an unfeasibly large
sum of money, for example, meeting the people
responsible for the film version, seeing the
end product, which I liked a lot.
I'd be very suspicious, however, of any writer
who was actually excited by any of this process,
which can be on occasion distasteful (About
A Boy ate up a director and got spat out by
another film company even before it was made)
and stupefying prolonged; indeed, the time
before, during and after a film's release
is positively unpleasant.
You get reviewed all over again; you discover
that half your friends never read the book
in the first place; the bits of the film people
like the most turn out to be nothing to do
with you.
But the first time I heard the soundtrack
to the film really was exciting, in the proper,
tingly sense of the word.
Seeing one's words converted into Hollywood
cash is gratifying in all sorts of ways, but
it really cannot compare to the experience
of hearing them converted into music: for
someone who has to write books because he
cannot write songs, the idea that a book might
somehow produce a song is embarrassingly thrilling.
Like a lot of people, I spent a large chunk
of 2000 listening to and loving Badly Drawn
Boy's The Hour of the Bewilder beast album.
It's one of the very few English records of
recent years I've had any time for; it's thoughtful,
quirky without being inept (despite my earlier
presumption that the name of the artist was
somehow indicative of the ramshackle nature
of the music, a presumption that stopped me
from listening to him for a while), it's melodic,
it borrows lightly and judiciously from all
sorts of folky, rocky things I like (Damon
Gough is an early-Springsteen devotee), it
doesn't show off, it is un-English in the
sense that it wouldn't be much use to Ibiza
clubbers or boozed-up football hooligans,
it has soul.
It also sounds cinematic, with its little
snatches of orchestration (it begins with
a brass-band instrumental that would not have
sounded out of place in a gentle sixties comedy)
and its range of moods.
It seemed to me that Damon could write a wonderful
film score, and I would have suggested him
for About A Boy had I not known that writers
have less chance of influencing film adaptations
of their books than they do of changing the
weather.
And then, the first time we met, Chris and
Paul Weitz, the co-directors, told me that
they had already asked Damon to provide all
the music for the film.
This struck me as being troublingly neat - could
it really be possible that the music in my
head was the same as the music in theirs?
- but anyway, here I am, in my office, listening
to a whole lot of new Badly Drawn Boy songs
and music cues that very few people in the
world have heard yet, and feeling lucky.
I began writing About A Boy in 1996, the year
my son Danny was finally diagnosed as autistic.
There were lots of things to think (or panic,
or despair, or lose sleep) about, and money
was only one of them, but I suddenly went
from feeling reasonably wealthy - I was in
my fourth year of earning a decent whack from
writing, and for the first time in my life
I had some savings - to financially vulnerable:
I was going to have to find enough to make
sure that my son was secure, not just for
the duration of my life, but for the duration
of his, and that extra thirty or forty years
was hard to contemplate, in more or less any
direction.
And then, no sooner had these worries begun
to take hold and chafe a little bit than this
Hollywood money arrived.
Until the movie was made, this was the only
connection I had forged between the book and
Danny.
The character of Marcus was nothing to do
with him (Marcus is twelve, and brightly voluble,
if odd; Danny was three, and five years later
is still unable to speak), and I don't think
that Danny would recognize the parenting that
Marcus experiences.
It's possible that, if I had been child-less,
I would have been attracted to a different
kind of story, but that's the only way that
About A Boy is about Danny.
'A Minor Incident', a sweet, heartfelt, acoustic
strummer with a wheezy Dylanesque harmonica
solo, refers directly to a major incident
in the book and the movie: Marcus comes home
from a day out to discover his mother, Fiona,
lying comatose on the sofa after an attempt
to kill herself, her vomit on the floor beside
her.
The song is her suicide note to her son.
I wrote one for her too, but it wasn't in
the form of a song lyric, and Damon's words
capture Fiona's dippy, depressive insouciance
perfectly.
But here's the thing: once I'd listened to
'A Minor Incident' a couple of times, it started
to make me think of Danny in ways that I hadn't
done when I was writing the book.
'You always were the one to make us stand
out in a crowd I Though every once in a while
your head was in a cloud I There's nothing
you could never do to ever let me down', sings
Damon as Fiona, and the lines brought me up
short.
Autistic children are by their nature the
dreamiest of kids, and Danny's ways of making
us stand out in a crowd can include attempts
to steal strangers' crisps and to get undressed
on the top of a number 19 bus.
But that peculiar negative in the last line...
How did Badly Drawn Boy know that it's the
things that Danny will never do (talk, read,
play football, all sorts of stuff) that make
those who love him feel the most fiercely
proud and protective of him?
And, suddenly, five years on, I find a mournful
undertow of identification in the lyric to
the song, because the money from the sale
of the film rights has forced me to contemplate
my own mortality; like Fiona, I'm thinking
of a time when I won't be around for Danny
- for different reasons, but the end result
is the same.
So there we go.
That's where the excitement lies: in the magical
coincidences and transferences of creativity.
I write a book that isn't about my kid, and
then someone writes a beautiful song based
on an episode in my book that turns out to
mean something much more personal to me than
my book ever did.
And I won't say that this sort of thing is
worth more than all the Hollywood money in
the world, because I'm a pragmatist, and that
Hollywood money has given Danny a trust fund
which will hopefully see him through those
terrifying thirty or forty years.
But it's worth an awful lot, something money
can't buy, and it makes me want to keep writing
and collaborating, in the hope that something
I write will strike this kind of dazzling,
serendipitous spark off someone again.
CHAPTER SIX
Caravan - Van Morrison
The magnificent version of 'Caravan' on It's
Too Late to Stop Now (Van Morrison's most
enjoyable album, unarguably, so don't even
think about arguing) sounds to me like it
could be played over the closing credits of
the best film you've ever seen; and if something
sounds like that to you, then surely by extension
it means that it could also be played at your
own funeral.
I don't think this is over-dramatizing the
importance of one's own life.
Not all films have to be like Lawrence of
Arabia or Apocalypse Now, and you'd have to
have been pretty unlucky, at least in our
part of the world (and if you walked into
a bookshop and bought this book, you live
in the part I'm talking about), not to have
experienced a few moments of joy or pure hope
or clenched-fist triumph or simple contentment
amongst all the drudgery and heartbreak and
pain.
To me, 'Cara-van' recognizes and synthesizes
all of it, and the fact that what it produces
from the whole extraordinary mess is something
that sounds cheerful doesn't mean that the
song is trite.
'Caravan' isn't a song about life or death,
as far as I can tell: it's a song about merry
gypsies and campfires and turning up your
radio and stuff.
But in its long, vamped passage right before
the cli-max, when the sax weaves gently in
and out of the cute, witty, neochamber strings,
while the piano sprinkles bluesy high notes
over the top, Morrison's band seems to isolate
a moment somewhere between life and its aftermath,
a big, baroque entrance hall of a place where
you can stop and think about everything that
has gone before.
(Gosh.
A sudden panic: can you hear any of that,
those of you who already own the album or
who are interested enough in this description
to check it out?
Possibly not.
But - panic over - this book isn't predicated
on you and me sharing the ability to hear
exactly the same things; in other words, it
isn't music criticism.
All I'm hoping here is that you have equivalents
that you spend a lot of time listening to
music and seeing faces in its fire.)
And, though it won't be me doing the thinking,
as far as we know, is it arrogant to expect
a little reflection from friends and family?
It's my funeral, after all.
And they don't have to think only about me;
they can think about all sorts of things,
as long as they're worthy of the occasion
and the music, and don't involve foodstuffs,
emails, footwear, etc.
The only thing that worries me about having
'Caravan' played at my funeral is that string
section.
Will people think I'm making some concession
to classical music when they hear it?
Will they say to themselves, 'What a shame
he lost the courage of his convictions right
at the end there, just like everybody else'?
I wouldn't want them to think that.
Unless something unimaginable happens to me
over the next couple of decades, I will have
gone through an entire life listening more
or less only to popular music in one or other
of its forms.
(I have a few classical CDs, and sometimes
I play them, too; but I never respond to Mozart
or Haydn as music, merely as something that
makes the room smell temporarily different,
like a scented candle, and I don't like treating
art in that way, with disrespect.)
And I'm unrepentant, too.
'I'd see him banged up for having anything
to do with the inanity that is pop, full stop,'
said a famously sour writer and newspaper
columnist recently, while attempting to defend
a well-known music-business mogul who had
just been imprisoned, but you've heard this
stuff before.
I have no idea whether his use of the word
'pop' is the same as mine, whether he thinks
that all of it, Dylan and Marvin Gaye and
Neil Young, is inane.
I suspect he does.
It's not a complaint I've ever understood,
because music, like colour, or a cloud, is
neither intelligent nor unintelligent - it
just is.
The chord, the simplest building-block for
even the tri test, silliest chart song, is
a beautiful, perfect, mysterious thing, and
when an ill-read, uneducated, uncultured,
emotionally illiterate boor puts a couple
of them together, he has every chance of creating
something wonderful and powerful.
I don't want to read inane books, but books
are built from words, our only instruments
of thought; all I ask of music is that it
sounds good.
Despite its crudity and simplicity, 'Twist
and Shout' sounds good - in fact, any attempt
to sophisticate it would make it sound much
worse - and I fundamentally, profoundly disagree
with anyone who equates musical complication
and intelligence with superiority.
It doesn't work like that, which is maybe
why these people despise pop music, because
it's one of the very few things that doesn't.
(They often hate sports, too.)
I don't dislike classical music because of
its cultivation - I'm not an inverted snob.
I dislike it (or at least, I'm unaffected
by it) because it sounds churchy, and because,
to my ears at least, it can't deal with the
smaller feelings that constitute a day and
a week and a life, and because there are no
backing vocals or basslines or guitar solos,
and because a lot of people who profess to
like it actually don't really like any music
(or any culture) at all, and because I grew
up listening to something else, and because
it does not possess the ability to make me
feel, and because I don't need my music to
sound any 'better' than it does already - a
great, farting, squelching, quick-witted sax
solo does the job for me.
So 'Caravan' will be played at my funeral.
The problem with the extended passage that
I mentioned earlier, the bit that I hope will
make the mourners think and reflect is that...
Well, OK, here's the thing: it's the bit where
Van Morrison introduces the band.
'Terry Adams on cello...
Nancy Ellis on viola...
Bill Elwin on trumpet...
David Hayes on bass...'
Is that too weird?
Can people really file out of my funeral listening
to a list of names of people they (and I)
don't know?
I've started to think of this passage as a
sort of metaphorical dramatis personae now:
granted, I don't know David Hayes or Nancy
Ellis, but, you know... I probably knew someone
like them.
That's the best I can come up with, and it'll
have to do, because I'm not changing my mind,
so there.
- THE END -