Childhood is a time of innocence, when life is
simple and uncomplicated. Children, watching the
comings and goings of adults, often see things
that they don't understand until years later,
when they are adults themselves
and know the ways of the world.
And the ways of the world
are sometimes rather sad...
There is still talk about her in
the village, all these years later.
She did not come back after she went
away so suddenly that morning ...
no one really cared to find out what happened to
her. But they did not forget her. Even recently
an old man in the village said her name,
Missiya, with sadness in his voice.
And the village never again knew anyone quite like
her. They remembered her not so much for her good
looks as for her boldness. She was good-looking,
though. But in those days there was no way a
good-looking girl could escape from village
life and make an exciting future for herself.
What could Missiya do, except sell
her good looks while she was young?
Selling them for so little - almost nothing.
Every time I go back home to the
village I see Missiya in my mind.
She had brown skin which shone with good
health, and a beautiful, strong body.
She moved beautifully too. She used to carry
a full pot of water on her hip and use her
other hand to pick a fruit or a branch off
a tree for firewood. She was full of fun.
She ran when there was no need to run,
smiled all the time and laughed often.
The women envied her, and felt jealous
of the way men watched her lovely body.
Missiya never married. She never wanted to be
like other village girls, who spent time getting
to know boys, walking in the fields, talking of
love, and making careful plans for the future.
Missiya's house was usually full of men,
and her parents did not mind her free and
easy ways with the young men - and older
ones - who crowded into that little house.
No surprise, then, that before she was
sixteen, people were already talking about her!
As a child I couldn't take my eyes off her. She
had a pair of eyes which seemed enormous to me.
Her smiling lips were full and red with betel
juice. She used to laugh at the way I watched her,
wide-eyed. Under her breath and still smiling,
she used to whisper something which I knew was
not meant for my child's ears. But there was no
harm in her - it was her nature, her love of life!
But there were things I did not understand about
her. Sometimes she was my friend. On some days
when I saw her, she used to greet me cheerfully,
take my hand in hers and take me into the woods
to pick fruit, show me the animals and birds
and a thousand secrets that lay hidden there.
But there were days when she pretended not to see
me and looked away, as she hurried into the woods.
That always made me sad and I felt a warm tear
roll down my face. At those times I used to
look away too, pretending to look at a wild
flower or watch some insects on the ground.
I knew she did not want me around, and I
wanted her to think that it did not matter.
But it did. It did.
I did not understand the way my
mother felt about her, either.
As I grew a year or two older, she told
me not to go into the woods with Missiya.
Suddenly one hot afternoon mother called me from
the garden and said, very firmly, 'You must not
see Missiya again. You're not a child any longer
- you must stop bothering her to play with you.'
I couldn't understand why. I didn't say anything.
I stood by my mother and looked
out of that sun-filled room.
In the garden I saw the purple bougainvillea
and the bright yellow hibiscus flowers.
I wanted to be out there playing with Missiya.
There was no one to play with except Missiya.
And now my mother was telling
me I must not play with her!
'Then who will make me a mud house when
it rains?' I asked my mother, confused.
Mother knew me. She heard the
anxiety in my voice and said quietly,
without even lifting her eyes from
the book she was reading, 'I will.'
Missiya did not miss me. She did not care at
all that she had ended a handful of my dreams.
She continued to laugh her way through the days,
the months. She became more beautiful as the years
passed and her lovely body became more rounded.
There was a bolder look in her eyes and a wildness
in her movements that drove the men crazy.
There were violent arguments in
the village. Like the night when
old Appuhamy's wife went to search for him
and found him inside Missiya's house, drunk.
The whole village gathered to watch and cheer,
although it was well past midnight. All the women
cursed Missiya, and the men watched her with a new
interest. Missiya did not show the least concern.
She spat an enormous mouthful of betel juice
towards them and disappeared into the night.
They said that she was a witch. But by now I
was old enough to know that she was no witch.
She was human and soon enough I knew what she
was. I began to understand what those trips
into the woods meant. I knew the meaning of
those violent arguments. I knew why some women
hated her and cursed her. I began to understand
why women like my mother wanted to protect their
daughters from her influence and
their sons from her clever tricks.
But Missiya herself was one of the world's
lucky ones. She didn't care what anyone said.
She didn't care what happened to anyone. She cared
only about one person in the whole world and that
was herself. Perhaps, in a way, that did make
her a witch. At least she was not quite human.
That thoughtless confidence of hers couldn't
last, however. Almost ten years later,
she came to live in a dark little hut that
stood just beyond the end of our garden.
By then she had begun to lose the freshness
of her young beauty and her carefree ways.
At twenty-five she was an adult woman, a
good-looking woman, and an inviting one.
She lived alone because her parents had
died, but nothing else had changed with her.
The village still hated her and loved
her. The men still came to her by night.
During the day she worked, making baskets.
Day or night, she appeared not to care how
the next meal came to her, what happened to
her, or what she would do when she grew old.
When I met her for the first
time after many years away,
I was shy. She smiled at me as
I walked past her little house.
'Well, well, how you've grown!'
she said with her usual bold smile.
I said something in reply and hurried away. In the
rapid look I gave her, I saw the heaviness of her
body, and wondered if she was getting fat. There
was something about her that seemed different.
I looked back and saw her watching me. She had a
look of catlike happiness on her face that day.
'Has she met some man and married him?' I
wondered as I walked towards my parents' home.
But soon enough I knew she was not married.
The village now felt sorry for her - she
was a woman growing old before her time.
The men did not come to her for
their pleasures as much as before.
The village was moving into the modern world
- just two miles away there was now a cinema,
and after the late-night showing there were women
available there too. So Missiya was finding it
hard to earn enough money even for food. The
village talked and laughed unkindly about her:
how poor she was, how little she had. Her
clothes were unwashed, her habits dirty.
It seemed that the world's oldest
profession did not pay very well.
The morning it happened started like any other.
The sun shone and the raindrops danced on the wet
grass. I walked down to the edge of the garden,
reliving the pleasures of my childhood.
These trips back to the village filled me
with confused thoughts - a wish for past days,
past magic, when the world and I were young...
The old tree where I had sat in the shade,
and cried desperate tears over some
young sadness or other, was still there.
So was the dead tree trunk where my friends and I
had sat on so many golden evenings and watched the
sun go down. The voices from the past whispered
in my ear, some long gone from my life...
The cool air was still so
well-known and dear to me.
And the morning sun gave a silver touch
to the rice field spread out at my feet.
I stopped with a start when
I saw the two policemen.
They looked towards our house and then looked
away. I took a step backwards and watched them.
They spoke to each other and entered the
large shed in which the hay was stored.
It was early morning. There
was no one else around.
And quietly the village began to wake up.
First, the old businessman, the Mudalali,
clearing his throat and walking to the
corner to get his morning newspaper.
He was followed by the young man who worked
in the tea shop. Then the women appeared,
wanting to know what was happening. Suddenly
there was a crowd, and excitement in the air.
And then the policemen brought out the
terrible bundle from inside the building.
I shut my eyes and turned away.
It was such a tiny bundle, a helpless little
thing, killed by its own mother and hidden in the
hay. It had no father who would accept it as his
child. So it had to die. A fatherless baby in that
little village was a terrible thing, and women
like its mother were cursed, perhaps even killed.
In that lovely little village,
with its sunny green fields and blue
hills, there was no room for that child.
And then they brought out the mother. She didn't
hide her head guiltily, as they wanted her to.
She still held her head high,
and looked straight at all of us.
I hid behind a tree and watched her -
I still couldn't take my eyes off her.
She looked at the silent crowd and then she
noticed me. She smiled at me, bold and direct,
as always. I shut my eyes. She didn't care that
I gave her no answering smile. She turned to
the crowd with the same bold smile, and spat an
enormous mouthful of betel juice towards them.
And then she went away with the policemen.
- THE END -