Marrying a man who already has children makes
you a stepmother, a difficult part to play
in a family. And stepmothers in stories are
often mean and unkind to their stepchildren.
Lakshman, who is nine, knows this very
well. He never wanted a stepmother. Why
ever did his father marry her? Maybe if he
is horrible to her, she will go away again...
Lakshman ran his hand over the surface of the
cupboard and breathed in the pleasant smell of
newly cut wood. An almirah, with four doors, two
above and two below, and a shiny key in each one -
what use was an almirah to a baby! Nobody
ever made almirahs with four doors!
Carefully he turned the keys
to look inside. In one half,
there was a place to hang clothes - small clothes.
The other half had narrow shelves. Underneath,
there were two long, wide shelves. Somebody - she,
he supposed - had already put some toys there,
baby things, plastic cups that fit into each
other, little wooden bricks, and coloured balls.
Angrily he banged the doors
shut. What a complete waste!
In his bare feet he walked down the
stairs to the back of the house,
to the kitchen area. The old Amme was squatting
on the floor, cutting up vegetables for the meal.
A row of pots and pans stood on the floor, and
Kandy, the Alsatian dog, was sleeping peacefully
beside them, his tail occasionally waving away
the flies. Both Lakshman and the Amme knew this
was against the rules - the rules the new woman
had made after she took control of the house.
But they understood each other, the old cook
and the boy. He squatted down opposite her,
watching her. Although he was nine
he was small for his age - small,
but strong. He wore an old shirt and a
too-small pair of washed-out blue trousers.
For some time he watched the Amme in silence.
Then, in his rather high little-boy's voice,
he asked, 'Where is the bloody woman?'
The Amme did not stop her cutting. She said
calmly, 'She's getting dressed to go out.
She wants you to change and go with
her. To buy new shoes for school.'
The boy sighed. He picked up a piece
of sugarcane and began to suck it
noisily. That was really too bad! Did
she really think he'd go out with her,
walk in the street where all his friends would
see him? True, his father had said she would help
him and look after him. But that did not mean
she could give him orders, or that he had to do
what she wanted. Why, he wouldn't go with her for
anything - not even if she offered him a bicycle.
Lakshman had been saving for a bicycle for
some time. His weekly money from his father,
gifts from aunts and uncles and grandparents,
all this was carefully saved. In fact
Lakshman lived for the day when there would
be enough for that bicycle. But dislike of
his stepmother was so great that he could not even
imagine himself accepting a bicycle from her. He
bit off a piece of sugarcane and said crossly, 'I
am not going out with her to buy a pair of shoes.'
It was hot in the kitchen. The Amme
lifted a corner of the cotton cloth she
was wearing wrapped round her like a skirt,
and wiped the sweat from her face and neck.
At that moment Lakshman's stepmother appeared
in the doorway. Her eyes took in the scene
and narrowed angrily. She raised her voice
and said, 'Amme, I have told you again
and again not to cut vegetables on the
floor,' and then to Lakshman, 'Lakshman,
go and change your clothes. I want to
take you out to buy a pair of shoes.'
Neither Amme nor the child moved. The Amme began
to cut vegetables again, with great concentration.
Lakshman looked quickly at his stepmother. The
she-devil. Whatever had made his father marry her?
He said, 'Amme doesn't understand English. And I
don't want to go out. You buy the shoes for me.'
The woman straightened her back and looked down
at him. 'If Amme doesn't understand English,
why don't you tell her in Singhalese? And
you say you won't come out with me... Well,
I can't buy a pair of shoes unless you try
them on. So please get ready. Quickly now.'
He turned to the Amme and said in Singhalese,
'That bloody woman says not to
cut vegetables on the floor.'
Very slowly and heavily the Amme
got up from where she was squatting.
She picked up the vegetables and
threw them on the kitchen table.
Then she said to the child, 'Tell her I can't work
for her. Also I am not well. I have to go home.'
Lakshman repeated in English
exactly what the old cook
had said. The tall one looked from the
child to the old woman a little helplessly,
then shrugged her shoulders.
'If she is not feeling well,
she must go home and get better.
Meanwhile, you get ready. I am waiting.'
He stepped right in front of his stepmother;
he had to bend his head far back in order to see
her face. He collected the spit in his mouth,
then walked slowly and deliberately to the corner
of the kitchen where there was a space for washing
vegetables, and spat. Spitting was the best
way to drive away evil things. Then he said:
'But I told you. I am not coming.'
She took a deep breath. 'All right. If you
are not coming, I am not buying the shoes.'
She turned and walked towards the front door.
Lakshman ran after her and shouted
so that it echoed down the road,
'If you don't buy those shoes, I'll - I'll tell
all the neighbours and relations what a mean,
hateful, horrible stepmother you are...'
She didn't even turn her head. All she said
was, 'You tell them whatever you like, Lakshman.
But if you want a pair of shoes, you've got
to come and try them on. Or else, no shoes.'
He watched her drive off. He was very angry,
not because he needed the shoes so badly,
but because he felt she had won this particular
argument. He could hear the men servants talking
and laughing loudly in the kitchen with the
Amme, who was packing her things. They were
talking about his stepmother. And
suddenly a cold fury rose in him.
Why had she come here and upset things,
when everything was running so smoothly
before! And now the Amme was leaving...
Upstairs the baby began to cry.
That was another thing - her baby.
All that fuss and bother about him... you
would think nobody had ever had a baby before.
And all that nonsense about keeping him clean
and not touching him with dirty fingers!
And almirahs! Almirahs were bought
for brides when they got married,
to take to their new husband's house,
to keep their saris and jewellery safe.
And then he had an idea.
Thoughtfully he climbed back up the stairs. There
stood the almirah, with its smell of new wood.
Without hesitating he opened the two bottom doors,
which he could easily reach because they were at
his height. He took hold of one door and forced
it back further and further until the wood broke
and the door fell to the ground with a loud crash.
The second door soon followed the first. To reach
the upper two doors, he got a chair and climbed
on it. It was more difficult this time, but he
pushed as hard as he could, until the third door
landed on the ground with an even bigger crash.
He waited for a moment to see whether
anyone would come to investigate,
but he wasn't really worried. They
- the servants - couldn't stop him.
Wasn't he the young master? Anyway,
they wouldn't want to stop him.
Not at all. They'd be delighted with the trouble
he was causing the new woman. He smiled nastily.
Wouldn't she be wild! He imagined her
return. This time she'd really get mad. She'd
hit him and scream at him, and then his
father would get rid of her, once and for all.
With this happy thought he turned back to the
almirah, and finally managed to break the fourth
door off. Carefully he replaced the chair, and
left the broken doors where they had fallen. Then
he decided to play a game in his room. There would
be enough time to hide when he heard the car.
She was coming up the stairs. Lakshman
was lying flat on the floor of his room,
looking through the narrow space under his door.
He could hear the changing sound of her footsteps
as she came higher and higher, and he
held his breath when she finally stopped.
She stopped for quite some time. Then
she called - not him, but the servant.
She asked, 'Who has done this, Somapala?'
Somapala, who had not seen the broken almirah
before, gasped and said, 'I don't know.' There
was another pause, and she said something Lakshman
couldn't hear. Then she went into her bedroom.
That was too much for Lakshman. After all
his hard work... He jumped up from the floor,
ran through the doors, and burst into her room
without knocking. She was standing by the mirror
examining her face, and his
eyes met hers in the mirror.
He screamed, 'You want to know who did it.
Well, I did, I did it...' His face was
red under the brown skin, and his eyes
very black, shining with the light of battle. His
arms hung by his sides, his hands tightly closed.
She turned slowly. 'You did it, Lakshman? You?'
She looked down at him from her great height.
Her fingers were playing with the household
keys she was holding. 'That's really too bad,
Lakshman. Breaking the baby's cupboard.
We had to pay a lot of money for it.'
He almost laughed. The stupid woman! What
was the point in breaking something cheap?
He waited for her fury to break,
preparing himself for the punishment,
looking forward to it almost with pleasure.
But it didn't come. She just stood
there and looked at him calmly.
Then she said, 'That's really too bad, Lakshman,
I thought you were a sensible sort of boy.' She
sighed. 'So now we have to ask the workman to
repair the damage. Quite an unnecessary bother
and cost.' She walked towards the baby's room.
Lakshman had a terrible feeling of disappointment,
worse than he had ever experienced before.
Wildly he ran after her and asked urgently,
'But aren't you going to punish me?'
'Punish you?' She appeared
surprised. 'Punish you? Oh, no.
There's no point in that. Because
that's what you want, isn't it?'
She looked him straight in the eye. 'No,
Lakshman. I am not going to punish you.
Only...' She hesitated for a moment. 'About the
repairs. You are going to pay for them, Lakshman.
Out of your bicycle money.
That's fair, don't you think?'
She opened the door of the baby's room,
walked through, and firmly shut it behind her.
Lakshman stared at the closed door. The sun was
shining outside and little gold bits of dust were
dancing in the sunlight. The blood had left his
face, and he stood there, wide-eyed and silent.
Then he walked out of her room, past the
four broken almirah doors on the floor,
and down the stairs. His head
was bent as he went slowly down,
his old shirt hanging out over
the too-small blue trousers.
He heard the door of the baby's room opening.
The woman was looking down at him from the top
of the stairs, but he pretended not to see,
and continued going down without stopping.
She said, 'Lakshman?' Pause. 'Lakshman
- we can come to an arrangement.'
He did not look up. But there was no
longer any sharpness in her voice;
instead, there was a warm note in it
that the child did not fail to notice.
She said, 'You help the workman repair the
cupboard, and I'll pay half the cost. Agreed?'
His eyes were hot with tears.
'The bloody woman,' he whispered to
himself. 'The bloody, bloody woman...'
But he slowed down, and as he reached the bottom
of the stairs, she heard him begin to whistle.
'Agreed,' he shouted, and ran
quickly out of sight.
-
THE END -