CHAPTER ONE
Sir Walter Elliot
Sir Walter Elliot of Kellynch Hall in Somerset,
south-west England, never read anything except
the Baronetage. He particularly liked to read
the pages about his own family:
Walter Elliot, baronet, born 1 March 1760,
married Elizabeth Stevenson 15 July 1784.
Three daughters: Elizabeth (born 1 June 1785),
Anne (born 9 August 1787), and Mary (born
20 November 1791, married Charles Musgrove
16 December 1810). A still-born son (5 November
1789). Lady Elliot died in 1800. Heir presumptive:
William Walter Elliot, the great grandson
of the second Sir Walter.
This introduction was followed by the history
of the Elliot family: three hundred years
of respectability. Reading it gave Sir Walter
great satisfaction. Vanity was his principal
characteristic: he was vain about his noble
family and his good looks. At fifty-four he
was still a handsome man. His friends had
been surprised that he had never married again.
He could have asked Lady Russell to marry
him. She was a widow who lived nearby and
had been Lady Elliot's closest friend. However,
thirteen years had passed since Lady Elliot's
death, and Sir Walter and Lady Russell were
still just good friends and neighbours.
Sir Walter's favourite daughter was Elizabeth.
She was twenty-nine, but she was still very
good-looking. Anne was twenty-six and had
been pretty a few years before, but now she
was pale and thin. Mary had grown fat since
her marriage. Lady Russell had deep lines
around her eyes. Sir Walter took great pleasure
in thinking that of all the people he knew
only he and Elizabeth were still as good-looking
as ever. Elizabeth will marry a great nobleman,
he thought, and he did not notice that he
had been thinking it for the past thirteen
years.
When Elizabeth was sixteen, she had planned
to marry her father's heir William Walter
Elliot. That was the only way she could keep
her father's property. When she met the young
man, she liked him. He was invited to Kellynch
Hall, but he never came. A year later, he
married a rich woman from a middle-class family.
Elizabeth was angry and upset. Her life went
on rather emptily. She went to elegant parties
and visited friends. She tried to fill the
time, but it was difficult, since she had
no talents or interests.
Recently she had been worried about her father:
he was in debt. Neither Elizabeth nor her
father could imagine how to pay these debts.
Both felt that their extravagant lifestyle
was essential to the dignity of a noble family.
Lady Russell and Anne spent hours trying to
find a way to save money and pay the debts,
but every plan for economy they proposed was
rejected by Sir Walter. Finally he accepted
the radical plan of moving to the town of
Bath. There he could live for less money without
losing his dignity. Meanwhile, Kellynch Hall
was rented to a gentleman called Admiral Croft.
When Sir Walter's lawyer Mr Shepherd had completed
the business arrangements with Admiral Croft,
he came to Kellynch to report to Sir Walter.
'Admiral Croft is very nice,' said Mr Shepherd.
'His wife's brother lived in the nearby village
of Monkford a few years ago. Perhaps you know
the gentleman. Now, what was his name?' Mr
Shepherd searched his memory but couldn't
remember the name of Mrs Croft's brother.
'He lived in the grey stone house...'
After a moment, Anne said, 'I suppose you
mean Mr Wentworth.'
'Ah!' said Sir Walter. 'The curate of Monkford.
When you said "gentleman" I thought you meant
a man of property, somebody of the nobility.
Mr Wentworth was nobody.'
Anne left the room quietly and went out into
the garden. As she walked between the tall
trees, she thought, 'In a few months, perhaps
he will be here!'
She was thinking of the curate's brother - Captain
Frederick Wentworth of the Royal Navy - who
had spent the year 1806 in Monkford. At that
time, he was a handsome, clever, charming
young man, and Anne was a pretty, gentle,
sensitive girl. They fell in love and were
happy for a short period, but, when Frederick
asked Sir Walter if he could marry Anne, Sir
Walter was not pleased. He thought that Frederick's
family was not good enough. Even Lady Russell,
who was much more sensible than Sir Walter,
disapproved. Anne was Lady Russell's favourite
of the Elliot sisters; only Anne had the gentleness,
good sense and modesty that Lady Russell had
loved so much in her old friend Lady Elliot.
Lady Russell thought that it was foolish for
Anne to marry a young man with no money. 'When
your father dies,' she had said, 'he'll leave
you very little money and no property. You
need to marry someone rich and so does Captain
Wentworth. If you marry each other, you'll
have no money at all, and you'll both be miserable
as a result.'
Anne was too gentle to argue against this.
She broke off her engagement to Frederick,
convinced that it was the best thing for him.
Frederick was angry and hurt. 'I'm sure that
I'll earn money and promotion in the Navy,'
he said, but Anne continued to resist him,
and finally he went to sea. That was eight
years ago, when Anne was nineteen. Very few
people knew about the relationship between
them: his sister Mrs Croft had been abroad
with her husband at the time, and Anne's sister
Mary had been away at school. Captain Wentworth
had never returned to Monkford, because his
brother had moved away.
In the eight years since Captain Wentworth
had left, Anne had never fallen in love with
anyone else. Mr Charles Musgrove had asked
her to marry him, but she had refused, and
he had married her sister Mary instead. Anne
read about Captain Wentworth's career in the
newspapers. He had been right: his Navy career
was a great success. By now he must be quite
rich, thought Anne sadly. He had never married.
Thinking about it now, Lady Russell's advice
seemed too cautious: Anne thought she was
being prudent, but instead she had ruined
her life.
***
Mary lived at Uppercross, three miles from
Kellynch Hall. One day she said to her sister
Elizabeth, 'When you go to Bath, please leave
Anne with me. I'm not well, and I need Anne's
help.'
'All right,' said Elizabeth. 'No one will
miss her in Bath!'
Elizabeth's friend Mrs Clay - a young widow
- was going to Bath with them. Elizabeth was
perfectly happy with the thought of her father
and her friend as her only companions.
Anne was also happy with the arrangement and
gladly accepted Mary's invitation. She did
not like Bath. She much preferred to stay
in the country close to Lady Russell, who
appreciated her. She and Mary did not enjoy
each other's company, but at least Mary valued
her help, and this way she did not have to
go to Bath.
There was only one problem with the plan:
the idea of Mrs Clay staying for months with
Elizabeth and Sir Walter at their house in
Bath made Anne worried. Mrs Clay was not a
pretty woman, but she was intelligent and
friendly. Anne thought it imprudent to let
a pleasant young single woman stay in the
house with Sir Walter for so long a period.
She told Elizabeth this, but Elizabeth replied,
'Nonsense! Father doesn't find Mrs Clay attractive.
Besides, she isn't from a noble family. There's
no danger.'
So Sir Walter, Elizabeth and Mrs Clay left
for Bath, and Anne moved into Mary's house.
Mary lived in the Cottage, the smaller of
two houses on a large property owned by her
husband's parents. Mr and Mrs Musgrove Senior
lived in the Great House. Anne and Mary spent
a lot of time with Mr and Mrs Musgrove and
their daughters Henrietta and Louisa. They
were rather pretty, lively, fashionable girls,
who were very popular in the neighbourhood.
They seemed to enjoy life a lot, but the only
thing Anne was envious of was their friendly
feeling towards each other - this was very
different from Anne's relationship with either
of her sisters.
CHAPTER TWO
Captain Wentworth
When Admiral Croft and his wife arrived at
Kellynch Hall, Mary and Charles invited them
to the Cottage. Mr and Mrs Musgrove and their
daughters were also invited.
'Dear Mrs Croft,' said Mrs Musgrove, as soon
as the introductions were over, 'did you know
that my son Dick served in the Navy under
your brother Captain Frederick Wentworth?'
'Really?' asked Mrs Croft. 'And what does
your son do now?'
'The poor boy died at sea!' cried Mrs Musgrove,
with tears in her eyes.
'Oh, I'm so sorry to hear that,' said Mrs
Croft.
'But in one of his letters to me, he wrote,
"Captain Wentworth is a fine, courageous young
gentleman." Yes, he admired your brother very
much, Mrs Croft!'
In fact, Dick Musgrove had been a stupid,
lazy, difficult young man, so his parents
had sent him to sea. He was as difficult in
the Navy as he had been at home. When he had
died two years before, at the age of twenty,
no one except his mother really felt sorry.
Mrs Croft, who was a sensible, confident,
straightforward lady, tried to comfort Mrs
Musgrove.
'My brother will be very glad to meet you,
Mrs Musgrove,' said Mrs Croft. 'His career
in the Navy has been a great success. Now
that the war is over he's back in England.
He's coming to stay with us at Kellynch Hall
next week.'
Anne, who was standing nearby, heard this,
and her heart beat fast in agitation.
***
The following week, Henrietta and Louisa came
to visit Anne and Mary at the Cottage.
'We've met Captain Wentworth!' cried Henrietta.
'He's very handsome and charming! Father invited
him to dinner this evening.'
'Yes,' cried Louisa. 'You must all come to
meet him!'
'I'm afraid we can't,' said Mary. 'My little
boy has a cold. We must stay with him this
evening.'
'Well, I can go, can't I?' Charles asked Mary.
'If you want!' replied Mary, clearly offended
that her husband did not want to stay with
her.
'You can both go,' said Anne. 'I'll stay here
with little Charles.'
'What a good idea!' cried Mary, suddenly happy
again.
Charles and Mary went to the Great House and
Anne remained at the Cottage. All evening
she thought about the dinner at the Great
House. There, Frederick Wentworth was smiling
and talking to other people. How does he feel,
she wondered, about meeting me again? Sooner
or later we will have to meet. Perhaps he
feels indifferent. Or perhaps he'll be embarrassed.
In all these years, he has never tried to
contact me.
Charles and Mary came home late, full of enthusiasm
for Captain Wentworth. 'Such a friendly young
man!' said Mary. 'Charles has invited him
to go shooting tomorrow after breakfast. He
invited him to come to breakfast, but Captain
Wentworth was afraid of disturbing little
Charles.'
Anne understood it. He did not want to see
her.
'But Anne!' continued Mary. 'He says he knows
you. He says he met you eight years ago, but
I don't remember him at all!'
'No, you were at school then,' said Anne quietly.
The next morning, Henrietta and Louisa walked
down to the Cottage with Captain Wentworth.
When Anne saw Captain Wentworth walking towards
the Cottage, she blushed and she could hardly
breathe from nervousness.
'Ah!' said Mary. 'Henrietta and Louisa have
come too. They probably want to walk and watch
the shooting. If you can stay with little
Charles, Anne, I think I'll go with them.'
'Certainly,' said Anne, in a trembling voice.
And suddenly he was there - in the drawing
room. He bowed to her. She curtsied to him.
Her eyes met his briefly then looked away
again. She heard his voice. He made polite
conversation with Mary for a few minutes.
And then he was gone - with the Musgrove sisters,
Charles and Mary - and Anne was left alone
in the drawing room, thinking, 'Thank God
that's over!'
***
'Captain Wentworth wasn't very polite to you,
Anne!' said Mary, when she returned. 'As we
left the house, Henrietta asked what he thought
of you, and he said, "She's changed so much
that hardly recognised her."'
Mary - being rather insensitive - had no idea
how much pain her words caused her sister.
It must be true! thought Anne. But he hasn't
changed. He's just as good-looking as ever.
His comment hurt her, but it also made her
calm. If I have changed so much, she thought,
there is no hope that he will love me as he
did before. So be calm, she told herself.
If you can be calm, you will be content.
Surprised by Henrietta's question, Frederick
Wentworth had told the truth, but he had not
expected anyone to repeat his comment to Anne.
He had not forgiven Anne Elliot. She had abandoned
him, and, in doing so, she had shown weakness
of character: she had allowed herself to be
persuaded by others. He had loved her, and
he had never felt that way again about any
other woman. He had never met another woman
he considered to be equal to her. When he
came to Kellynch, he had been curious to meet
her again, but he thought her power over him
was completely gone.
Now that he was rich and the war was over,
he wanted to settle down with some attractive
young woman. Either of the Musgrove sisters
could win his heart if she wanted to. In fact,
any attractive young lady could do so - except
Anne Elliot. When his sister asked him about
his intentions, he said with a laugh, I'm
here, Sophia, to find a wife. Any young lady
can capture me with a little beauty, a few
smiles, and a few compliments about the Navy.'
But, later, he gave his sister a serious description
of the kind of wife he wanted: 'The woman
marry must have a strong mind and a sweet
manner.' He had not entirely forgotten Anne.
***
From then on, Anne was often in Frederick
Wentworth's company, though never alone with
him. It was strange to spend hours in the
same room with him, listening to his voice,
yet never looking at him closely or talking
to him intimately. Once they had been everything
to each other, but now they were just acquaintances.
'Tell us about your adventures at sea, Captain
Wentworth,' cried Louisa one evening. 'You
said that your first ship was called the Asp.
Did you have any adventures on the Asp?'
'Oh, certainly I did,' replied the captain.
'It was 1806. That year I had a strong desire
to go to sea, and the Navy gave me the Asp.
It was an old ship, but a fine one. That autumn,
we captured a French ship and brought it into
Plymouth harbour. As we approached Plymouth,
a terrible storm hit us and continued for
four days. The Asp was already damaged from
our battles with the French. I thought that
was the end for me and the Asp! I said to
myself, "We'll probably go down to the bottom
of the sea together this time!" But, as I
said, she was a fine old ship, and we finally
got to the port alive and well.'
Henrietta and Louisa cried out in pity and
horror, while Anne silently shivered at the
terrible thought of him going down to the
bottom of the sea.
'Your next ship was the Laconia, wasn't it?'
said Mrs Musgrove. 'How lucky for us, sir!'
Frederick looked confused until Henrietta
whispered to him. 'She's thinking of my brother
Dick.'
'Ah!' said Frederick. There was something
in his face at that moment that suggested
to Anne that his memories of Dick were not
happy ones. No one else noticed that look:
only someone who knew him very well could
have noticed it. He crossed the room, sat
on the sofa beside Mrs Musgrove, and spoke
to her quietly and seriously about her son.
Anne, meanwhile, sat on the other side of
Mrs Musgrove, thinking, We're on the same
sofa!
However, when he got up to leave, he bowed
to Anne with cold politeness, like someone
who hardly knew her, and said, 'Good evening.'
CHAPTER THREE
Henrietta or Louisa?
The Musgroves were cousins of the Hayters
of Winthrop. Winthrop was a large farm two
miles from Uppercross, and the Hayter family
were, for the most part, plain ignorant people.
For this reason, Mary was very unhappy that
they were connected to the Musgrove family.
She spoke to them as little as possible and
never went to Winthrop.
Charles Hayter, the eldest son, was better
educated and more gentlemanly than his father
and his brothers. He was a curate and, over
the past year or so, he and Henrietta had
seemed to be in love with each other.
He was away on business at the time Captain
Wentworth came to Kellynch. When he returned,
after two weeks, he found that everything
had changed. Henrietta did not look at him
with loving eyes anymore or listen attentively
when he spoke. Both she and Louisa gave all
their attention to Captain Wentworth.
Everyone at Uppercross seemed to be charmed
by the captain, but Charles Hayter did not
find him charming at all.
***
One evening, when they were alone in their
room, Mary said to her husband Charles, 'Captain
Wentworth seems to like your sisters very
much. He spends a lot of time with them. Do
you think he'll marry one of them?'
'Maybe,' said Charles. 'I think perhaps he'll
marry Louisa.'
'Well, Louisa is the livelier of the two,
but Henrietta is prettier,' said Mary.
'True,' her husband replied, 'but I think
Henrietta is already in love - with her cousin
Charles Hayter.'
'Oh dear, I hope not!' cried Mary. 'That Hayter
family is so common! We really don't want
to be any more closely connected to them than
we already are.'
'But Charles is in a good position,' said
her husband. 'He's the eldest son, so he will
inherit Winthrop. And he's a curate. He'll
probably become curate of the church of Uppercross
when the old vicar retires.'
'Well, I hope that Henrietta will marry Captain
Wentworth instead,' said Mary. 'He's a fine
young man, and I hear that he made twenty-five
thousand pounds during the war. That's a splendid
fortune.'
***
The next day, Louisa, Henrietta, Captain Wentworth,
Mary, Charles and Anne went for a long walk
together. Mary got tired very early in the
walk and began to complain. They climbed a
hill to see the view. There, below them, was
Winthrop, without beauty and without dignity.
'I had no idea that we were walking towards
Winthrop!' cried Mary. 'Let's go back now.
I'm tired.'
Henrietta had known the direction of their
walk; in fact, she and Louisa had chosen to
walk towards Winthrop in the hope of seeing
their cousin Charles Hayter. He had not been
to visit them at Uppercross for days, and
Henrietta had begun to feel sorry about paying
so much attention to Captain Wentworth and
so little attention to her cousin. She looked
down at Winthrop sadly, and, not seeing her
cousin, she replied to Mary, 'All right,'
and turned to walk back to Uppercross.
'No!' cried Charles and Louisa. Louisa whispered
something in her sister's ear, then Charles
said, 'Henrietta and I shall go down and say
hello to the Hayters. You can wait for us
here. We won't be long.'
Captain Wentworth and Louisa went for a walk.
Anne found a place for Mary to sit down and
rest, but Mary refused and went off to find
herself a more comfortable seat. Anne was
very tired too, so she sat down and waited
quietly for the others to return. After a
while, she heard Louisa's voice on the other
side of the hedge.
'And so, I made Henrietta go. I knew that
she wanted to go to Winthrop to see her cousin,
but she's so weak - she always lets herself
be persuaded by other people. When Mary said
we should go home, she agreed! Even though
she wanted to see her cousin! I never let
myself be persuaded by other people. Once
I have decided what I want to do, no one can
persuade me to do something else!'
Then Frederick spoke: 'She's very fortunate
to have you to help her!' he said. 'If your
sister and Mr Hayter are in love, they must
be strong; they can't let other people influence
them. Your sister's very nice, but I see now
that you have the stronger character!'
Anne sat very still, afraid of being seen
by the two people on the other side of the
hedge.
'Well, I never let Mary tell me what to do!'
Louisa replied. 'She's so proud and snobbish.
I wish Anne was Charles's wife instead. Do
you know that Charles wanted to marry Anne?'
After a moment's pause, Frederick said, 'Did
she refuse him?'
'Yes. Mother and Father think that her friend
Lady Russell persuaded her to refuse. She
thought that Charles wasn't good enough for
Anne because he doesn't read poetry...'
Their voices became quieter as they walked
further away. Anne sat still, hardly breathing.
Now she knew what Captain Wentworth thought
of her: everything he had said about strength
of character and weakness, about allowing
yourself to be persuaded by others, made that
perfectly clear. He had also shown a curiosity
about her which made her heart beat fast.
Charles and Henrietta returned from Winthrop,
bringing Charles Hayter with them. Henrietta
and her cousin looked very happy. Clearly
their misunderstanding was over. They began
the long walk home: Louisa and Captain Wentworth
walked in front, Henrietta and her cousin
behind them, and Charles Musgrove was at the
back with Anne and Mary. Just then, Mr and
Mrs Croft drove up in their carriage.
'Does anyone want a lift to Uppercross?' asked
Mrs Croft. 'I'm afraid we only have space
for one person.'
Everyone refused. Henrietta and Louisa were
not tired, and Mary felt offended at not being
asked before the others.
'Nobody? Well, enjoy your walk,' said Mrs
Croft, but then Captain Wentworth went up
to the carriage and whispered something to
his sister.
'Miss Elliot!' cried Mrs Croft. 'You look
tired. Please come with us.'
Anne really was tired. At first she refused,
but the Admiral and Mrs Croft insisted, and
soon she was in the carriage, knowing that
Frederick had worried about her. He had seen
that she was tired. She understood him: he
could not forgive her for the past, and he
was now thinking of marrying another woman,
but even so, he could not see her suffer without
wanting to help her.
CHAPTER FOUR
Lyme Regis
A week later, Captain Wentworth went to Lyme
Regis to see his friend Captain Harville.
When he returned, he described the beauties
of the town and surrounding countryside to
his friends at Uppercross. They all decided
to go to Lyme for two days and stay at an
inn - Charles, Mary, Anne, Henrietta, Louisa
and Captain Wentworth.
When they arrived they went to the inn, and
then Captain Wentworth took them to Captain
Harville's house. Captain Harville was a tall
dark man who had been seriously injured in
battle two years before. His face was kind
and friendly, but his injuries had aged him,
and he looked much older than Captain Wentworth,
although they were in fact the same age. He
lived with his wife, his children and his
friend Captain Benwick, who had been an officer
on the Laconia when Frederick was captain.
Captain Benwick had been engaged to Harville's
sister Fanny, but she had died while Captain
Benwick was at sea. Ever since, he had lived
with the Harvilles as a member of the family.
After Fanny's death, Captain Wentworth had
spent an entire week with Captain Benwick,
trying to comfort his friend. Anne saw that
the friendships between these three men were
very strong and sincere, and she thought sadly,
'If I had married him, these people would
now be my friends too!'
When they left the Harvilles' house, Louisa
said to Captain Wentworth, 'What splendid
friends you have! What kind honest people!
I think the men in the Navy must be the finest
men in England!'
They went for a walk by the sea, then returned
to the inn for dinner. Anne was looking very
pretty: the cold wind had made her cheeks
pink and her eyes shine. As they entered the
inn, a gentleman dressed in black was going
out. He looked at Anne with great admiration,
and then stepped to the side politely to let
her pass. He was not a handsome man, but Anne
thought that his face was that of a pleasant
sensible man. Captain Wentworth noticed the
gentleman looking at Anne and asked the waiter
who he was.
'That's Mr William Walter Elliot, sir,' the
man replied. 'He has just left us to return
to London.'
'What a coincidence!' said Mary. 'My father's
heir was here - in the same inn!'
***
The next morning they went for a walk by the
sea. It was too windy for the ladies to walk
on the top of the sea wall, so they went down
the steps to a path more protected from the
wind. Mary, Anne and Henrietta went down the
steps slowly and carefully, but Louisa asked
Frederick to hold her hands while she jumped
from the top step to the path below.
'It's too dangerous,' said Frederick.
'Oh, please,' Louisa insisted. 'I want to
jump. Just hold my hands, and I'll jump down.'
'I really don't think it's a good idea,' said
Frederick. 'You might fall.'
'You can't persuade me!' cried Louisa. 'When
I want to do something, I do it!'
So Frederick held her hands and she jumped,
but when she landed on the lower path, she
slipped on the wet stone, and she fell and
hit her head. She lay unconscious on the path.
Her face went very white and she did not seem
to be breathing.
'She's dead! She's dead!' cried Mary.
Henrietta fainted from the shock. Poor Charles
was trying to comfort his wife and hold Henrietta
up at the same time. Frederick, on his knees
by Louisa's side, cried out, 'Will someone
help me?'
Anne came up to Charles, put her arms around
Henrietta and Mary and said, 'Charles! Go
and help the captain! Quickly! I can take
care of Mary and Henrietta.'
Frederick looked up at Charles and said, 'What
shall we do?'
'Go and get a doctor!' cried Anne.
'You're right,' said Frederick. 'You go and
find a doctor, Charles. I'll wait for you
here.'
'Shouldn't we take her to the inn and wait
for the doctor there?' asked Anne.
'Good idea!' said Frederick, 'or - wait! - Harville's
house is closer. I'll take her there. Charles,
bring the doctor to Harville's house!'
Charles ran off to find a doctor, Frederick
carried Louisa to his friend's house and Anne
- with the help of some local people - followed
with Mary and Henrietta. Half an hour later,
the doctor told them that Louisa's injuries
were not serious.
'Someone must go and tell her parents what
has happened,' said Frederick.
'Please, will you go, Captain,' said Charles.
'I want to stay with my sister.'
'Certainly,' replied Frederick. 'I will take
the other ladies home, but I think Anne should
stay here with you. There's no one more capable
than Anne.'
'Nonsense!' said Mary. 'I should stay with
my husband and his sister! Anne can go home
with you.'
And so it was decided: Mary and Charles stayed
at the Harvilles' house with Louisa, while
Anne, Henrietta and Frederick took the inn's
carriage to Uppercross. In the carriage, Frederick
spoke mostly to Henrietta. Anne sat quietly
beside him and listened. At one point he said,
'I should have stopped her! I should have
insisted! But dear sweet Louisa has such a
strong character: she won't be persuaded by
anyone!'
Anne wondered whether he now questioned the
opinions he had expressed so confidently behind
the hedge. Perhaps now he realised that, like
other qualities of the mind, strength of character
should have its proportions and limits.
As they approached Uppercross, Henrietta fell
asleep. Frederick then said to Anne in a low
voice, 'I've been thinking about what we should
do when we get there. I think it will upset
Henrietta too much to be present when I tell
her parents. Do you think it's a good idea
for you to stay with her in the carriage until
I've told them?'
'Yes, I do,' whispered Anne. She was very
glad that he had asked for her opinion, very
glad that he valued her, thought her capable
and treated her as a friend. It was a great
pleasure to her.
When they got to the Great House, Frederick
went in and told Mr and Mrs Musgrove what
had happened. Then he came back to the carriage
and helped Henrietta into the house. Finally,
he took the carriage back to Lyme, leaving
Anne with the Musgroves.
***
The next day, Anne received a letter from
Lady Russell, saying that she was now home
in Kellynch and inviting Anne to come and
stay with her. Anne wrote back and told Lady
Russell about the accident at Lyme: 'I'm so
glad that you're home. As soon as Mary and
Charles get back from Lyme, I'll pack my bags
and come to your house.'
She was glad. She had missed her friend. But
at the same time she was worried. What will
Lady Russell think of me spending all that
time in Captain Wentworth's company?
Two days later, she was at her friend's house.
'How pretty you look, my dear!' cried Lady
Russell when Anne walked in. 'I haven't seen
you look so well for years!'
Anne was pleased. She remembered the look
of admiration that William Walter Elliot,
her father's heir, had given her at the inn
while he was leaving. 'Perhaps I really am
pretty again!' she thought.
Lady Russell sat down beside Anne and said,
'I hear you've been spending a lot of time
with Captain Wentworth.' She sat waiting for
an answer.
'Yes,' replied Anne, trying not to seem agitated.
'He came to see the Musgroves almost every
day, so of course I saw him often. I think
he is in love with Louisa.'
'Really?' said Lady Russell, and she thought,
with angry pleasure, 'How can a man who once
appreciated the value of Anne Elliot, now,
eight years later, possibly be charmed by
Louisa Musgrove?'
'Well,' Lady Russell continued, 'Admiral and
Mrs Croft have gone to visit friends in the
north, so he probably won't come back to this
neighbourhood. I think Mrs Croft said he was
going to stay with his brother in Shropshire.'
'Oh!' said Anne.
CHAPTER FIVE
Bath
Anne stayed at Lady Russell's house in Kellynch
for a month, then they both went to Bath.
Lady Russell had rented a house for herself
there. Anne wished she could stay with her
friend, but she had to stay at her father's
house with Elizabeth and Mrs Clay. When they
arrived, Sir Walter, Elizabeth and Mrs Clay
seemed to be in good spirits and welcomed
Anne more warmly than she had expected. Elizabeth
told them that William Walter Elliot had been
visiting them often over the past two weeks.
He was in Bath, staying with his friend Colonel
Wallis and his wife and new baby.
'It's surprising that he visits you so often!'
said Lady Russell. 'I've never liked the man
because he showed no respect for the family.
He never came to see you while his wife was
alive. I suppose, now that she is dead, he
is beginning to value his family.'
Anne was slightly confused. When she had seen
him in Lyme, she had thought that Mr Elliot
seemed a sensible man. Why, Anne asked herself,
is he so interested in making friends with
the family now, after all these years? She
thought perhaps it was for Elizabeth. Certainly
Elizabeth herself and Mrs Clay thought so.
That evening, Mr William Walter Elliot came
to visit. When he saw Anne, his face showed
surprise and pleasure. 'My dear cousin!' he
said. 'I saw you just a few weeks ago at Lyme,
but I had no idea that it was you!'
He sat between Anne and Lady Russell. His
manners were very pleasant. He asked Anne
why she had been in Lyme, and when she mentioned
the accident he was interested and sympathetic
- he wanted to know every detail. Then he
spoke to Lady Russell about the years in which
there had been no communication between himself
and Sir Walter. 'It was all a misunderstanding,'
he said. 'I thought I had offended him, that
he didn't want to see me anymore. But now
I realise that was a mistake. I'm so sorry
that I missed all those years of his company!'
After he left, Lady Russell cried, 'What a
nice man! Is this really the same Mr Elliot?
I used to dislike him, but now he seems completely
admirable: he's intelligent, sophisticated,
polite and friendly. He has the right opinions
and strong family feelings.'
Anne went to bed that night with a smile on
her face: her first evening in Bath had been
surprisingly pleasant.
***
The only thing that disturbed Anne's first
few days in Bath was her fear that her father
was falling in love with Mrs Clay.
When Mrs Clay was in the room with him, he
talked to her a lot, and when she was out
of the room he referred to her often: 'Mrs
Clay thinks' this and 'Mrs Clay says' that.
One evening, when Mr William Walter Elliot
and Lady Russell were visiting them, Sir Walter
and Elizabeth spoke with great enthusiasm
about Sir Walter's cousin Lady Dalrymple.
'She has come to Bath and has rented a beautiful
house in Laura Place, which is of course the
best street in town,' said Sir Walter. 'Since
we are cousins, I called on her immediately
and she invited us to tea.'
'Yes,' said Elizabeth, 'She's a really charming
lady, and her carriage is the most splendid
one in Bath!'
Anne was embarrassed. She had never seen her
father and sister in contact with nobility
before, and she felt ashamed of them. Usually
she considered them too proud - too conscious
of their own position in society and snobbish
towards anyone they considered inferior. But
now, for the first time, she wished they had
more pride. She wished they did not show so
openly how important it was to them for Lady
Dalrymple to recognise them and treat them
as equals. Lady Dalrymple was pleasant enough,
but she was nothing special. She was not intelligent
or cultured. Certainly she smiled at everyone,
but the only reason Elizabeth called her 'charming'
was because she was a wealthy aristocrat.
Mr Elliot turned to Anne and said in a low
voice, 'I'm so glad that Sir Walter has found
good company in Bath.'
Anne smiled and replied, 'My idea of good
company, Mr Elliot, is the company of clever
well-educated people who can make interesting
conversation.'
'You're mistaken,' he said gently. 'That is
not good company; that is the best. To be
good company, you need only to be from a respectable
family and have nice manners.'
'Well,' said Anne, 'I'm proud of my family,
and I don't like to see them trying so hard
to be friendly with Lady Dalrymple simply
because she's an aristocrat.'
'We agree on one thing, at least,' replied
Mr Elliot. 'I too am proud of my family, and
I would rather see Sir Walter being friendly
with Lady Dalrymple than with others who are
below him.' He glanced at Mrs Clay.
Although Anne was sure that Mr Elliot's pride
was different from hers, she was glad that
he did not like Mrs Clay.
***
The following week, they were all invited
to Lady Dalrymple's house. Anne said that
she could not go, because she had already
made plans to visit a friend of hers - Mrs
Smith. They had been at school together years
ago, but now Mrs Smith was a poor widow. Her
husband, Mr Smith, had been wealthy but had
lost all his money. Now Mrs Smith had very
little money to live on, and she was in bad
health. Sir Walter thought that Anne was foolish
to waste her time with such a person.
The next day, Lady Russell told Anne all about
their evening at Lady Dalrymple's house. 'My
dear, Mr Elliot was very sorry that you weren't
there, but he said he admired you for wanting
to visit your old friend. He thinks that you're
an extraordinary young woman; a model of female
excellence! We discussed your virtues for
half an hour!'
Hearing this gave Anne great pleasure, just
as Lady Russell had planned.
Lady Russell had now decided that Mr Elliot
was an excellent gentleman. She was sure that
he wanted to marry Anne. She told Anne her
thoughts on the subject. After a moment, Anne
replied, 'Mr Elliot is a nice man, but we
are not compatible.'
'Just think,' said Lady Russell. 'If you marry
Mr Elliot, you will have your dear mother's
name, her position and your old home!'
This vision affected Anne very deeply. Yes,
she would love to be Lady Elliot of Kellynch
Hall! But she did not want to marry Mr Elliot.
There was only one man she had ever wanted
to marry, and besides, she had doubts about
Mr Elliot's sincerity. He was clever, friendly,
interesting and polite, but he was not open.
He had suggested to her that he disliked Mrs
Clay, yet he was just as charming to Mrs Clay
as to everyone else. He never expressed anger
or pleasure at the good or evil of others.
She preferred people who occasionally made
mistakes but were warm-hearted and sincere.
CHAPTER SIX
A Surprise
In February, the Crofts came to Bath. When
they arrived, Mrs Croft sent a note to Anne,
inviting her to visit them. The same day,
Anne received a letter from Mary.
Dear Anne,
I am sorry not to have written for so long,
but now I really must write to tell you some
interesting news. Last Tuesday Louisa came
home from Lyme to the Great House here at
Uppercross. Mr and Mrs Harville and Captain
Benwick came with her. As soon as they arrived,
Captain Benwick asked to speak with Mr Musgrove
in private. What do you think? He asked Mr
Musgrove if he could marry Louisa! Mr Musgrove
agreed, and now they are engaged! What a surprise!
We thought that Louisa was going to marry
Captain Wentworth...
When she read this, Anne's heart beat fast,
and she blushed at the thought that Captain
Wentworth was now free. She was full of joy!
She left the house, with the idea of going
to visit the Crofts, but on the way she met
Admiral Croft.
'Ah, Miss Elliot! What a pleasure to see you!'
said the Admiral. 'Do you have time to take
a little walk with me? I have some news for
you.'
'Certainly,' said Anne. 'I'm so glad that
you and Mrs Croft have come to Bath. What
is the news?'
'It's Miss Louisa Musgrove,' he said. 'I thought
that Sophia's brother Frederick was going
to marry her, but now it seems she's going
to marry James Benwick!'
'Really?' said Anne. 'I hope that this hasn't
caused problems between Captain Wentworth
and Captain Benwick. They are such good friends.'
'I don't think so,' said the Admiral. 'Frederick
wrote and told us all about it. He didn't
seem angry or disappointed. Perhaps we were
all mistaken in thinking he was in love with
her. After her accident, you know, we thought
he would stay in Lyme until she was better,
but after two weeks he went off to stay with
his brother in Shropshire. If he was thinking
of marrying her, he'll have to start all over
again with somebody else! I think we should
invite him to stay with us in Bath.'
***
In fact, while Anne was taking her walk with
Admiral Croft, Captain Wentworth was already
on his way to Bath, and, the next time Anne
went out, she saw him. She was walking with
Mr Elliot, Elizabeth and Mrs Clay, when suddenly
she saw Captain Wentworth walking towards
them with some of his Navy friends and their
wives. She felt confused, lost and embarrassed
about her own feelings, which were somewhere
between delight and misery.
Captain Wentworth saw her and immediately
went red in the face. He seemed even more
confused and agitated by the sight of her
than she was by the sight of him. They stopped
and spoke to each other like polite acquaintances.
Anne noticed that Elizabeth turned away, as
if she did not know him.
When Anne and her companions were gone, one
of the ladies in Captain Wentworth's group
said, 'It's clear that Mr Elliot likes his
cousin!'
'Yes,' replied another lady, 'He's always
with them, and he always walks with his cousin
Anne. What a good-looking man he is!'
'And Anne Elliot is very pretty, if you look
at her closely,' said the first lady. 'Most
people think her sister is prettier, but I
don't.'
Captain Wentworth listened to them in silence
as he walked. He had recognised Mr Elliot
immediately from the one time he had seen
him in Lyme.
***
Days passed and Anne had no opportunity of
seeing Captain Wentworth. He moved in a different
social circle: his friends went to concerts
and the theatre; her friends spent their time
in the elegant stupidity of private parties.
But at last there was an opportunity; a special
concert that Lady Dalrymple had promised to
attend. Sir Walter, Elizabeth, Mrs Clay, Mr
Elliot, Lady Russell and Anne were all going
with her. Sir Walter, his two daughters and
Mrs Clay were the first to arrive at the concert
hall. They stood by the fire in the large
entrance room, waiting for the others.
Captain Wentworth walked in alone. He was
simply going to bow and move on, but Anne
stepped forward and said 'Hello.' He stopped
and made polite conversation with her. Sir
Walter made a slight bow to Captain Wentworth
and Elizabeth curtsied. Captain Wentworth
bowed to them. When they had discussed the
weather, Bath and the concert, there was a
pause in the conversation. Then Captain Wentworth
said, 'Have you heard? Louisa's accident in
Lyme did produce one good result: she's engaged
to be married to Benwick.'
'Yes, I heard,' said Anne.
'I hope they will be very happy,' said the
Captain. 'They have no difficulties at home:
Mr and Mrs Musgrove are behaving very honourably
and kindly. They don't oppose the marriage,
even though Louisa could have found a richer
man.'
He stopped speaking suddenly when he noticed
that Anne was blushing and looking at the
ground. Then he realised that his words might
seem to refer to their own past. 'I was surprised
by their engagement,' he continued, a little
nervously. 'They are so different. Louisa
is a very sweet, friendly girl, and she's
not stupid, but Benwick is something more.
He's a really intelligent man; he reads a
lot and thinks deeply. Fanny Harville was
like him in that way. She was an extraordinary
woman and his love for her was real. A man
doesn't get over the loss of a woman like
that! I'm surprised that he's able to love
someone else at all especially so soon after
Fanny's death.'
Anne was breathing very quickly and feeling
a hundred things at the same time. But they
were in a public place, surrounded by other
people. She tried to bring their conversation
back to everyday things. 'I would like to
go to Lyme again,' she said.
'But you had such a terrible experience there;
I'm surprised you want to go back.'
'My memories of Lyme are not all bad,' said
Anne.
Just then, Lady Dalrymple and the others came
in and Anne had to leave the Captain. When
they took their seats in the concert hall,
Anne looked around, hoping to see him. Mr
Elliot sat beside her and began talking to
her in a low voice.
'I'm so glad I can sit beside you this evening,'
he said. 'On Thursday I'm going to visit some
friends in Thornberry and I won't be back
until Friday evening. I'll miss the pleasure
of your company.'
The concert opened with some Italian love
songs and the texts were included in the concert
programme. Mr Elliot asked Anne to translate
them for him, and she did so. 'You are so
clever!' he said.
'Oh,' replied Anne, 'not really. My Italian
isn't very good.'
'And modest - too modest,' said Mr Elliot.
'You've only known me a few weeks,' said Anne.
'You don't know my character well yet.'
'Perhaps I know more about you than you think,'
he replied. 'I heard about your character
long before I came to Bath.'
'Really?' said Anne, in great surprise. 'Who
spoke about me to you?'
'I'll tell you some other time, not now,'
said Mr Elliot. 'For now, all I'll say is
that the name Anne Elliot has, for many years,
been an interesting one for me. I hope that
name will never change.'
Anne looked away from him in embarrassment.
She did not want to talk to him anymore. She
wished he wasn't sitting next to her.
Just then, she heard Lady Dalrymple say to
her father, 'A very fine young man! Who is
he?'
'Captain Wentworth,' Sir Walter replied. 'I
know him only slightly...'
Anne looked in the direction in which they
were looking and saw him. He was looking at
her. Just as her eyes met his, he looked away.
'Mr Elliot!' said Lady Dalrymple during the
interval. 'Come and sit beside me. I want
to ask you something.'
To Anne's relief, Mr Elliot moved away. The
seat beside her was now empty, and, after
a few minutes, Captain Wentworth came over
to talk to her. He looked unhappy. Something
must have happened since they had spoken in
the entrance room. Anne thought that perhaps
Lady Russell or her father had glanced at
him in an unpleasant way.
'Do you like the concert?' she asked.
'No. The music isn't very good,' he replied.
I think I'll leave now.'
'The next song is beautiful. It's worth waiting
for,' said Anne.
'No,' he said, in a voice full of emotion.
'There's no reason for me to stay!'
And he left.
He's jealous of Mr Elliot! thought Anne. For
a moment this thought gave her great pleasure.
But then she felt hopeless and depressed.
How could she tell him the truth? How could
she let him know that she did not care for
Mr Elliot at all?
CHAPTER SEVEN
Mrs Smith Tells All
The next day, Anne went to visit Mrs Smith.
She was glad to get out of the house. She
did not want to see Mr Elliot and he was sure
to visit Sir Walter.
'My friend tells me that Mr Elliot is often
at your house,' said Mrs Smith, when they
were sitting in her small room, drinking tea.
'Who is your friend?' asked Anne.
'Mrs Rooke. She's a nurse and she works for
Colonel Wallis. You know his wife has just
had a baby.'
'Yes, and Colonel Wallis is Mr Elliot's friend.
Do you know Mr Elliot?'
'I used to know him very well,' said Mrs Smith,'but
I haven't seen him for three years now.'
'Did you ever talk about me to him?' asked
Anne.
'Yes, I did. I often spoke about your fine
character, your modesty and intelligence.
It was at the time when he met your father
and sister, before his marriage. Speaking
of marriage, Mrs Rooke tells me that Mrs Wallis
thinks you will marry Mr Elliot.'
'Well,' said Anne, 'Mrs Wallis is mistaken.
Mr Elliot hasn't asked me to marry him, and,
if he did, I would refuse him.'
'I'm glad to hear you're not engaged to him.
You don't know his real character.'
'Please tell me about it. I've often wondered
what he was like when he was young.'
Mrs Smith looked at Anne with a serious expression
on her face. 'Mr Elliot is a man without heart
or conscience,' she said angrily. 'He thinks
only of himself. My husband was his close
friend before we were married, and, after
our marriage, I became his friend too. I thought
he was a fine young gentleman then. I remember
when he met your father and sister, and they
invited him to Kellynch. He spent the evening
with us afterwards and told us the whole story.
He laughed at your father and said he knew
that Sir Walter wanted him to marry his daughter.
But he had no money, and he wanted to marry
a rich woman. He knew that he would get Kellynch
Hall and the title anyway, even if he didn't
marry Elizabeth. At that time, he didn't care
at all about the honour of his family. He
once said that if titles could be sold, he
would sell his for fifty pounds!'
Anne was shocked and angry. 'But why has he
been so friendly to us since he came to Bath?'
she asked.
'Ah, well, people change, you see. That was
years ago, when he was a young man. Now he
cares a lot about the family honour and the
title. Colonel Wallis told him that Mrs Clay
was staying with your sister and that she
was trying to make Sir Walter fall in love
with her.'
'How do you know? You said you haven't spoken
to him for three years.'
'Mrs Rooke again,' replied Mrs Smith. 'You
see, Colonel Wallis tells his wife everything,
and Mrs Wallis tells her nurse everything,
and Mrs Rooke very kindly told me. She said
that when Mr Elliot heard about Mrs Clay,
he decided to make friends with Sir Walter
and separate him from Mrs Clay. He has spoken
to Mrs Clay in private and warned her not
to try to win Sir Walter's affections. Mrs
Clay is afraid of him and doesn't want to
spend a lot of time with Sir Walter while
Mr Elliot is present. And so he spends as
much time as possible with Sir Walter. You
see, Mr Elliot is afraid that Sir Walter might
marry her and have a son. Then he wouldn't
inherit Kellynch Hall.'
'This is terrible!' said Anne.
'Yes,' said Mrs Smith. 'As I said, he's a
heartless man, but for me the clearest example
of it is the way he treated my poor husband
and the way he has treated me since my husband
died. After his marriage, Mr Elliot was very
rich. My husband was never good at managing
money, and he was getting into serious financial
difficulties. Mr Elliot did nothing to help
him. Before my husband died, he had made Mr
Elliot the executor of his will. If Mr Elliot
had tried a bit harder and invested a little
of his own money, my husband's property in
the West Indies would now be mine. But he
did nothing, and now the bank owns the property.
So you see, it's Mr Elliot's fault that I'm
so poor. I've written him several letters
asking him for help, but he always refuses.
Here are some of the letters I've received
from him.'
Mrs Smith handed Anne a packet of letters.
As she read them, Anne felt more and more
angry: each letter showed coldness and hard-hearted
indifference.
As she walked home, Anne thought about her
conversation with Mrs Smith. She wanted to
tell her family immediately, but she knew
that they would not listen to her. She decided
that she would tell Lady Russell and ask her
advice.
The idea of Mr Elliot's interest in her now
filled her with disgust. At least he was going
to be away at Thornberry for two days, and
she would not have to talk to him. She shivered
at the thought that Lady Russell might have
persuaded her to marry him. Then she would
have discovered his true character when it
was too late!
***
When she got home, she found Charles and Mary
there. They had come to Bath for a few days
with Captain Harville, Henrietta and Mrs Musgrove.
They were all staying at the White Hart Inn.
Anne was surprised and really glad to see
them. Before she left, Mary turned to Anne
and said, 'You must come and spend the day
with us at the inn tomorrow. We have so much
to talk about, and Mrs Musgrove and Henrietta
want to tell you all about the wedding plans.'
The next morning, Anne went to the White Hart.
Captain Wentworth was there visiting his friend
Captain Harville. Anne tried to be calm. If
he still loves me and I still love him (which
I certainly do), she thought, surely we'll
understand each other before long.
'Anne!' cried Mary, who was standing by the
window. 'Come and look! There's Mrs Clay and
Mr Elliot!'
'It can't be,' said Anne, going to the window.
'He's in Thornberry until tomorrow evening.'
Captain Wentworth was looking at her, and
she felt sorry that she had spoken. She turned
and looked out of the window, it really was
Mr Elliot. In order to correct any wrong impression
her words might have given Captain Wentworth,
she said, 'Oh! It is him. I must have been
mistaken. I wasn't listening very closely
when he spoke about his plans.'
Charles went up to Mrs Musgrove and said,
'Mother, I have a surprise for you. I have
taken a box at the theatre for tomorrow night.
I know you love the theatre. There's space
for nine people. Captain Wentworth says he'll
come, and I know Anne likes the theatre. We
all do.'
'Charles!' cried Mary. 'You've forgotten that
my father is giving a party tomorrow night,
and we're all invited. Lady Dalrymple will
be there and Mr Elliot, my father's heir.
Surely you want to meet him?'
'Why should I?' said Charles. 'Mr Elliot is
nothing to me.'
Captain Wentworth had been listening intently
to this conversation. At this last remark,
Captain Wentworth's eyes moved from Charles
to Anne.
Then Mrs Musgrove said to Charles, 'You'd
better go back to the theatre and change the
box to Tuesday night. If there's a party at
her father's house, Anne will have to go to
it, and we don't want to go to the theatre
without Anne.'
'I'd much prefer to go to the theatre than
stay home for my father's party,' said Anne.
'But perhaps it would be best to go on Tuesday
instead.'
Captain Wentworth came over and sat by Anne.
'Don't you like parties?' he asked.
'No,' she replied.
'I remember you didn't use to like them, but
people change over time.'
'I haven't changed much,' said Anne, hoping
to suggest to him that her love was unchanged.
But then she realised he might think she meant
the opposite: that she would still refuse
to marry him. She fell silent and blushed
in confusion.
'Eight and a half years is a very long time,'
he said.
Just then the door opened and Sir Walter,
Elizabeth and Mrs Clay came in.
'We've come with invitations to our party,'
said Elizabeth and she handed an invitation
to everyone there, including Captain Wentworth.
Captain Wentworth thanked her but did not
say whether he would come to the party. After
they had left, he stood staring at the invitation
in confusion. Anne understood him. He could
not accept the invitation as an apology for
all their insulting behaviour in the past.
That evening, at home, she thought about these
things a lot. Would Captain Wentworth come
to the party? She had no idea.
Turning to Mrs Clay, she said, 'I saw you
talking to Mr Elliot in the street today.
I had thought he was in Thornberry.'
'Oh, yes! I forgot to tell you,' said Mrs
Clay. 'I was surprised to see him too. He
told me why he hadn't yet left for Thornberry,
but I forget what he said - I wasn't really
listening. I remember he said that he would
definitely be back in time for the party tomorrow.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
A Conversation with Captain Harville
Anne spent the next day with her friends at
the White Hart Inn. Captain Wentworth was
there too. He asked if he could write a letter.
Mrs Musgrove showed him the writing table
and brought him pen and paper.
Captain Harville, who was standing by the
window not far away from Captain Wentworth's
table, smiled at Anne. She went and stood
by him. He was holding a small painting, and
he showed it to her. 'Do you know who that
is?' he asked.
'Certainly. It's Captain Benwick.'
'Yes. And he's giving it to Miss Louisa Musgrove,
but it wasn't painted for her. He had it done
for my poor sister, and now he has asked me
to bring it to Bath - he wants to have it
framed so that he can give it to another woman!
Captain Wentworth is writing to him now to
tell him when it will be ready. I'm glad that
Benwick has found someone else, but poor Fanny!'
he said with strong emotion. 'She wouldn't
have forgotten him so quickly!'
'No,' said Anne. 'I don't think any woman
who has truly loved can forget. We don't forget
you as soon as you forget us. We live at home,
quietly, with nothing to distract us from
our feelings. You always have business of
some sort to take you back into the world
immediately. Your lives are filled with activity,
and so it's easier for you to forget.'
'But Benwick has not been busy out in the
world,' said Captain Harville. 'He's been
living very quietly with us.'
'True,' said Anne. 'Well, if it isn't the
result of the differences between men's and
women's lives, it must be the differences
between their natures.'
'No, no. I don't think it's more in man's
nature than in woman's to forget about love.
I believe the opposite. Our bodies are stronger
than yours and so are our feelings.'
'Your feelings may be stronger,' said Anne,
'but ours are more tender. I too will make
a comparison between the mind and the body:
man is more robust than woman, but he doesn't
live longer.'
They were interrupted by the sound of Captain
Wentworth's pen falling to the floor. Captain
Harville turned to him and asked, 'Have you
finished your letter?'
'I'll be five minutes, then we can go,' was
the reply.
Then Captain Harville turned back to Anne
and said, 'All literature is against you,
you know. Poetry and novels all talk of woman's
inconstancy, but perhaps you'll say they were
all written by men.'
'Perhaps I will!' said Anne with a smile.
'It's easier for men to tell their own story.
They're much better educated than we are.
No - books prove nothing. We can only speak
from our own experience.'
'Well, in my experience men suffer a great
deal in love. When a sailor goes to sea, leaving
his wife and children behind, wondering if
he'll ever see them again, he suffers greatly.
Then he thinks of them every day until he
returns!'
'Oh!' cried Anne. 'I'm sure that's true! I
didn't mean to suggest that only women are
capable of true love and loyalty. I only meant
to say that men forget more easily when the
object of their love has gone, but women go
on loving even when there is no hope.' She
stopped speaking because she felt too much
emotion to continue.
Captain Wentworth stood up and said to his
friend, 'I've finished. We can go now.'
Captain Harville said goodbye to Anne and
went off to say goodbye to Mrs Musgrove. Captain
Wentworth looked at her with strong emotion
in his eyes. There were two letters in his
hand. He gave her one of them quickly, so
that no one else would see. Then he was gone.
Anne looked down at the letter. Her name was
written on the envelope. Her heart beat fast.
Her whole happiness depended on the contents
of that letter. She sat down at the writing
desk, opened the letter with a trembling hand,
and read the following words:
I cannot listen in silence anymore. Listening
to you, I feel both pain and hope. Tell me
that I am not too late! I offer myself to
you again. I love you even more than I did
eight and a half years ago, when you broke
my heart. Please do not believe that man forgets
about love sooner than woman. I have loved
no one else. I was angry with you, and I could
not forgive you, but I was never inconstant.
I came to Bath because you were here. I think
about nothing but you. Have you not noticed?
Do you not see that I love you? I did not
tell you my feelings earlier because I was
afraid you did not love me anymore. Please
believe that I have always loved you and I
always will. I have to go now, but I will
come back as soon as possible. A word, a look
from you will be enough to tell me whether
I enter your father's house this evening or
never.
F. W.
Anne put the letter down with tears in her
eyes. She had to get out of this room, out
of the inn, and away from other people. She
went to Mrs Musgrove and said, 'I'm afraid
I must go home now.'
'Are you ill? You look very pale.'
Then Charles came up to Mrs Musgrove and said
he had to go out. 'I have an appointment.
It won't take long. I'll be back in half an
hour.'
'All right,' said Mrs Musgrove, 'but Charles,
will you please" take Anne home first? She's
feeling ill.'
'Certainly,' said Charles, and they left.
CHAPTER NINE
Union Street
Anne could not feel angry with Charles or
Mrs Musgrove - they were both so kind - but
she felt frustrated. She wanted to be alone.
She wanted, above all, to find Captain Wentworth
and talk to him. When they were walking up
Union Street, Captain Wentworth saw them and
crossed the street to walk with them. He looked
at Anne nervously. She blushed and looked
at him with an expression she hoped would
show her true feelings.
'Ah! Captain Wentworth!' said Charles. 'Are
you going towards Anne's house? She's not
feeling well and must go home. I have an appointment
in five minutes, could you please walk her
home?'
'Of course,' said Captain Wentworth. Charles
said goodbye and left them. Anne and Frederick
walked on together slowly. They were surrounded
by people on the busy street, but they did
not notice them. Soon they had expressed again
all those feelings of love which, eight and
a half years earlier, had made their future
seem so secure. Now they were older, wiser
and stronger than they had been then, and
their love was based on a fuller knowledge
of each other's character.
'I never loved Louisa Musgrove,' he said.
'I tried to like her, and was thinking of
marrying her, because I wanted to marry. I
wanted to have children and a home, and I
was too angry and proud to ask you again.
I had thought for years that you were too
weak - too easily persuaded by other people.
But in Lyme I saw the dangers of the opposite
- a character that would not be persuaded
at all. I began to realise your true excellence
when Louisa had her accident. You were so
strong, so capable, so fine! I realised then
that your character is the perfect balance
of strength and gentleness. But, by that point,
people thought that Louisa and I would get
married. Perhaps even she thought so. I felt
that the only honourable thing to do would
be to marry her, if she wanted me. In the
hope that she would forget me, I went to stay
with my brother in Shropshire, feeling lost
and depressed. Then Harville wrote to me and
told me that Louisa was engaged to Benwick!
I came immediately to Bath to find you, but
then I saw you with Mr Elliot. Everyone in
Bath was sure that you would marry him, and
I was afraid that Lady Russell would persuade
you to do so.'
They had reached her house. They said goodbye,
and Anne ran up to her room, feeling happier
than she had ever felt before.
***
The evening came and the guests arrived. Anne's
happiness made her cheeks pink and her eyes
bright. She looked lovely as she moved through
the rooms, talking to the guests. Lady Dalrymple
and Mr Elliot were there, but she did not
care - no one could affect her happiness.
She did not mind the snobbish, irritating
things her father and Elizabeth said. She
did not mind Mrs Clay standing by her father's
side. She talked to Mrs Musgrove and the Crofts
and Captain Harville. She tried to talk to
Lady Russell but found it impossible. Sometimes
Captain Wentworth came and talked to her.
Sometimes she saw him across the room talking
to someone else but looking at her. At one
point, they stood side by side, pretending
to admire the plants.
'I've been thinking about the past,' said
Anne, 'and trying to decide if I was right
or wrong to follow my friend's advice. I think
I was right. I don't mean that I think her
advice was good: she was too prudent, and
I would never give such advice to a young
person now. But I think I was right to do
as she advised. She said that, if we married,
we would be poor and we would both be miserable.
If I had married you then, I would have felt
guilty - I would have felt that I was the
cause of any financial worries you might have
in the years ahead. Now I have nothing to
feel guilty about. I hope one day you will
be able to forgive Lady Russell and to like
her more than you do now.'
Captain Wentworth looked across the room at
Lady Russell. 'Maybe, one day,' he said. 'I
too have been thinking, and I've decided that
one person was more my enemy than Lady Russell
- and that person was myself. Tell me, if
I had come to you two years later, in 1808,
with a few thousand pounds, would you have
married me then?'
'Oh, yes!'
'Good God!' he cried. 'I was such a fool!
I wanted to do it, but I was too proud to
ask you again. I didn't understand you. I
shut my eyes and refused to understand you.
I ought to forgive everyone before I forgive
myself. This realisation is a new pain for
me. I've always thought of myself as a man
who works hard and gets what he deserves.
Now I'll have to get used to being happier
than I deserve to be.'
***
Who can be in doubt about what followed? If
two young people decide to marry, they'll
probably do so, even if they have no money,
have no common sense, and are completely incompatible.
This may be a bad moral with which to end
my story, but I believe it to be true. And,
if couples like that succeed, can you doubt
that Captain Wentworth and Anne Elliot - with
the advantages of maturity, intelligence,
and twenty-five thousand pounds - succeeded
too? Sir Walter and Elizabeth were not enthusiastic,
but they did not oppose the marriage. Now
that Captain Wentworth was at the top of his
profession and had earned a fine fortune in
the war, Sir Walter could not say that he
was nobody. He was now good enough to marry
the daughter of a foolish, spendthrift baronet.
Anne's only real worry was for Lady Russell.
She had told her friend everything that Mrs
Smith had told her about Mr Elliot's true
character. Anne knew that Lady Russell must
be suffering from the knowledge that she had
been wrong about both Mr Elliot and Captain
Wentworth. She had mistaken manners for character
in both cases. Anne, though so much younger
than Lady Russell, was a much better judge
of character. But Lady Russell was a good
woman, and her greatest concern was Anne's
happiness. Very soon she began to feel affection
for the man who had made Anne happy.
Mary was very pleased about the marriage.
Captain Wentworth was much richer and better
looking than either Charles Hayter or Captain
Benwick, so she felt that her own sister had
done better than her husband's sisters, and
this gave her great pleasure.
Soon after Anne and Frederick announced their
engagement, Mr Elliot left Bath. Elizabeth
had always believed that he was there for
her, so she felt humiliated by his departure.
Mr Elliot was shocked and upset by the news
of Anne's engagement. He had hoped to marry
her, so that he could watch Sir Walter more
closely and make sure he did not marry again.
But, since that plan had not worked, he made
a new plan for his own comfort and pleasure.
He left Bath and Mrs Clay left soon afterwards.
She moved into a house in London and Mr Elliot
paid the rent. He was often seen at her house,
and people said that, though he had stopped
Mrs Clay from becoming the wife of Sir Walter,
she might one day convince him to make her
the wife of Sir William.
When Frederick heard Mrs Smith's story and
how she had helped Anne to understand what
kind of man Mr Elliot really was, he felt
very friendly and grateful towards her. He
became as good a friend to her as Anne was.
She was their first guest when they were settled
in their new home. Frederick wrote letters
to the West Indies and worked hard to help
Mrs Smith to get her West Indian property
back, so that Mrs Smith finally had enough
money to live a quiet, contented life.
Anne and Frederick were very happy together.
Anne's only worry was that a future war might
take him away from her, but she was very proud
to be a sailor's wife: she felt that the men
of the Navy were the finest men in England.
- THE END -