CHAPTER ONE
The Dance
Edward Henry Machin first saw daylight on
the 27th of May, 1867, in Brougham Street
in Bursley, the oldest of the Five Towns.
Brougham Street goes down a hill to the canal,
and contains a number of potbanks or pottery
factories as well as some small houses. The
rent for one of these houses was not high
- only about twenty-three pence a week.
Edward Henry's mother (his father was dead)
lived by making and washing clothes for fine
ladies. She did not often laugh, and if you
tried to argue with her, you never got very
far. She was a woman of few words, and saved
time every day by calling her son Denry, instead
of Edward Henry.
Denry did not work hard at school, and boys
who were lazy and not very clever usually
just found jobs in the potbanks. Luckily,
at the age of twelve, he won a place at the
best school in Bursley. It happened like this.
On the second day of the examination, Denry
arrived a little early. As he walked around
the examination room, he came to the teacher's
desk, where he saw a list of names with the
marks for the first day of the examination.
The highest possible mark was thirty, but
next to his name he saw the number 7. The
numbers were written in pencil, and the pencil
was on the desk. He picked it up, looked around
the empty room, and at the door, and then
wrote a 2 in front of the 7. Of course, this
was not honest, but how many truly honest
schoolboys are there? Denry was no worse than
most of them.
Denry did not do well at his new school, but
he did not do badly either - and he was usually
very pleased with himself. As he grew older,
he continued to think well of himself. He
knew that he was made for better things than
a job in the potbanks, working with his hands.
***
When Denry was sixteen, his mother made a
very fine dress for Mr Duncalf's sister. Mr
Duncalf was the most important lawyer in Bursley.
His sister was grateful to Mrs Machin, and
so Denry got a job in Mr Duncalf's office.
For several years Denry was happy. Then he
met the Countess.
The Countess of Chell was a very grand lady.
Her husband was one of the richest men in
the Five Towns and was the new Mayor of Bursley.
The mayor and his wife had decided to have
a ball and to invite all the most important
people in the town. There were thirty-five
thousand people in Bursley, and at least two
thousand of these thought that they were important.
But only two hundred could dance in the Town
Hall.
Three weeks and three days before the ball,
Denry was sitting, alone, in Mr Duncalf's
office when a tall and pretty young woman
walked in. Before Denry could hide the newspaper
he was reading, she said 'Good morning' in
a very friendly way.
'Good morning, madam,' answered Denry.
'Is Mr Duncalf in?'
'No, madam. He's at the Town Hall.'
'Well, just tell him I called.'
'Of course, madam. Nothing I can do?'
She was already turning away, but she turned
back and gave him a smile. 'Could you give
him this list? The other lists are coming
to him as well. The invitations must go out
by Wednesday.'
She was gone. It was the first time Denry
had seen the Countess, and she was even more
beautiful than her photographs. And so easy
to talk to! He started looking at her list
of names, and he had a fantastic idea. He
could go to the ball himself. The Countess
had made a list of people to invite, but she
had asked four or five other people for lists
as well. She wanted Mr Duncalf to put the
lists together and send the invitations. Of
course the work was given to Denry, so it
was easy to add E. H. Machin to the list.
On Wednesday Denry received his invitation,
and on Thursday he accepted it.
***
Denry had never been to a ball. He couldn't
dance and he didn't have an evening suit.
All the rich young men of Bursley bought their
suits at Shillitoe's, so two days later Denry
stepped into Shillitoe's shop. 'I want you
to make me an evening suit,' he said to young
Shillitoe.
Shillitoe knew Denry and he also knew that
Denry did not have enough money to pay for
a suit. He replied that he was too busy. 'So
you're going to the ball, are you?' he asked,
surprised.
'Yes,' said Denry; 'are you?'
Shillitoe shook his head. 'I've no time for
balls.'
Denry looked around the shop, and at the door,
and then said, 'I can get you an invitation
if you like.'
Denry got his suit, and two years to pay for
it.
One of the best dancing teachers in Bursley
was Miss Ruth Earp. Denry learned to dance
quickly, but he paid nothing for his lessons.
Miss Earp also got an invitation to the ball.
Miss Earp was not beautiful, but she was young
and a very good dancer, and at his last lesson
Denry asked, 'Will you give me the first dance
at the ball?'
Ruth Earp thought for a minute, and then said
yes.
***
It took Denry two hours to get ready for the
ball, and he arrived a little late. He walked
up the beautiful double staircase into the
ballroom and looked for Ruth. When he found
her, he asked, 'What about that first dance?'
'It's nearly finished,' she answered, coldly.
'I'm awfully sorry. Can we finish it?'
'No!' she said, and walked away.
She was angry with him, and Denry did not
know what to say. But she was only at the
ball, he thought, because he had got her invitation
for her!
He joined a group of young men who were watching
the dancing. Harold Etches, who was one of
the richest young men in the Five Towns, was
there, with two or three of the Swetnam boys,
and Shillitoe. At first Denry did not say
anything. They all knew, of course, that he
was Mr Duncalf's office worker and the son
of a washer-woman, but all young men - rich
or poor - look the same in evening suits.
The conversation in the group was about the
Countess. All the important older men in the
town were standing around her, but she was
not dancing. Perhaps she didn't want to, but
perhaps they were all afraid to ask.
'Why doesn't someone ask her to dance?' asked
Denry suddenly.
'Why don't you?' said Shillitoe. 'It's a free
country.'
'Perhaps I will,' Denry said.
Harold Etches looked at Denry for a moment.'
You won't ask her,' he said. Then he smiled,
not very pleasantly. 'I'll give you five pounds
if you do.'
'All right,' said Denry, and quickly walked
away.
'She can't eat me! She can't eat me!' he said
to himself as he walked towards the Countess.
The men were still around her and one of them,
Denry saw, was Mr Duncalf. Denry was sorry
about this because Mr Duncalf didn't know,
of course, that Denry was coming to the ball.
Suddenly he found himself standing in front
of the Countess, and immediately he forgot
all the fine, polite words that Ruth Earp
had taught him.
'Could I have this dance with you?' he said
quickly, but smiling and showing his teeth.
('I've won that fiver, Mr Etches!' he said
to himself.)
The Countess had to accept. She could see
that everyone else was afraid to ask - and
she did want to dance! So they danced together,
and all the men of Bursley watched with open
mouths. Denry managed to dance well most of
the time, although once they nearly hit two
other dancers. When the music stopped, the
Countess looked at Denry and saw that he was
really just a boy.
'You dance well!' she said, smiling almost
like an aunt.
'Do I?' he smiled back. 'It's the first time
I've ever danced, except in a lesson.'
'Really? You pick things up easily, I suppose.'
'Yes,' he said. 'Do you?'
Something in Denry's question amused the Countess
very much. She put her head back and laughed,
and everybody in the room could see that Denry
had made the Countess laugh. She was still
laughing, and so was he, when he thanked her
for the dance.
As she turned away, Denry saw that she had
dropped her fan. Quickly, he picked it up
and put it in his pocket. Then he walked back
to the group of young men.
'Here you are!' said Harold Etches, giving
Denry a five-pound note.
Denry just smiled, and put the note in his
pocket. He could see in the faces of the young
men around him that he was suddenly famous.
He was no longer just the son of a washer-woman;
he was the man who had first danced with the
Countess.
'Just the same as dancing with any other woman,'
he said, when Shillitoe asked him what it
was like.
'What was she laughing at?' someone asked.
'Ah!' said Denry. 'I can't tell you that.'
This was not the last time he was asked that
question, but he always refused to answer.
Many young ladies wanted to dance with him
now, after his success with the Countess.
Later, he saw Ruth Earp again and danced with
her, and with her young friend, Nellie. But
he said nothing at all about the Countess's
fan in his pocket.
At the end of the ball, just as the Countess
was leaving, Denry pushed through the crowd
and held out her fan.
'I've just picked it up,' he said to the Countess.
'Oh! Thank you so much!' she said. Then she
smiled. 'You do pick things up easily, don't
you?'
And both Denry and the Countess laughed and
laughed, but nobody in Bursley knew why.
Denry walked home that night in a dream, thinking
about the Countess, Ruth Earp and Nellie,
and about the five-pound note in his pocket
- more than he got for a month's work in Mr
Duncalf's office.
He was a happy man. But trouble was waiting
for him.
CHAPTER TWO
The Rent Collector and the Widow Hullins
The ball made a new man of Denry. He had danced
with the Countess - the first man to dance
with her. Bursley thought he was a wonderful
fellow, and so did Denry himself. He had always
been a hopeful, cheerful kind of person. Now
he was filled with happiness all the time,
and when he got out of bed in the morning,
he felt like singing and dancing. Something
good was going to happen, he knew; he just
had to wait. He didn't have to wait very long.
A few days after the ball, Mrs Codleyn came
to see Mr Duncalf. Mrs Codleyn was a widow,
a woman of nearly sixty. She owned about seventy
small houses in Bursley, and Mr Duncalf collected
the rents for her. (Denry, of course, actually
went to the houses to get the money.) Although
the rent from all these houses was about twelve
pounds a week, Mrs Codleyn always said that
it was not enough. And the taxes! Every year
the taxes on those houses got higher and higher,
and Mrs Codleyn hated paying her taxes.
Mr Duncalf was an important man at the Town
Hall. Because of this, Mrs Codleyn thought
that he should make the taxes lower on her
houses. Mrs Codleyn had chosen Mr Duncalf
to collect her rents because she thought he
was an honest man - but an honest man would
never try to change the taxes specially for
one person. What strange ideas people have
sometimes!
Mrs Codleyn had just heard that her taxes
were going up again, but she did not stay
long in Mr Duncalf's office. The conversation
(which Denry listened to through the wall)
was short, loud, and not very polite. When
Mrs Codleyn left, Mr Duncalf called Denry
into his office.
'Write this letter to Mrs Codleyn,' he said
angrily. 'Madam, I understand from our conversation
this morning that you prefer to find another
lawyer...'
Denry wrote down the letter. As he was leaving
the room, Mr Duncalf spoke again.
'Machin!'
Denry knew what was coming. He had known it
was coming ever since the ball.
'Who invited you to the ball?'
There it was. A very difficult question.
'I did, sir.' Denry just could not think of
a lie.
'Why?'
'I thought perhaps you'd forgotten to, sir.'
'I suppose you think you're a really fine
fellow after your dance with the Countess?'
Mr Duncalf said unpleasantly.
'Yes,' said Denry. 'Do you?'
He had not meant to say it. The same little
question had amused the Countess greatly,
but it was true to say that it was not amusing
his employer now. Mr Duncalf's own dance with
the Countess had come to a very quick ending,
because he had stepped heavily on her skirt.
'You will leave my office at the end of the
week,' said Mr Duncalf, coldly.
'Oh, very well,' said Denry. And he said to
himself: 'Something good must happen now.'
He had no idea what he would do next, but
he was still cheerful. And he still had Harold
Etches' five pounds.
The next morning both Mrs Codleyn and Denry
were late for church. Mrs Codleyn was late
by accident and also because she was fat.
Denry was late because he had planned it that
way. The two met at the church door.
'Well, you're nice people, I must say!' Mrs
Codleyn said to Denry. She meant Duncalf and
all his office workers.
'Nothing to do with me, you know!' said Denry.
'I wish I could find someone else to collect
my rents.'
'I can still collect them for you, if you
like,' said Denry.
'You?'
'I've told Duncalf I'm leaving him,' Denry
said. 'The fact is, he and I don't agree on
a lot of things.'
Mrs Codleyn looked at him and thought about
it. He was just a young office worker, and
his mother was a washer-woman. His suit was
clean, but old and unfashionable.
'And what's more,' Denry went on, 'I'll do
the work for less money. You pay Duncalf ninety
pence a week - well, I'll do it for sixty
pence a week. And I'll collect them better
than him. Give me a month and you'll see the
difference!'
At the end of the week a notice appeared on
the front door of Denry's mother's house,
which said:
E. H. MACHIN
Rent Collector
In a few weeks, Denry was doing very well.
He was working for himself, and in two days
he earned more money than in a week with Mr
Duncalf. He walked around the town, smiling,
looking important, talking to other young
men, and thinking of new ways of making money.
***
One Monday morning he went to Mrs Hullins'
house to collect the rent. It was a very small
house, not much more than one room downstairs
and one room upstairs. The rent was fifteen
pence a week, and the Widow Hullins had not
paid any rent at all for some weeks. She had
lived there all her life, and after two husbands
and eleven children, she now lived alone.
She had seen a lot of life, and was old and
tired.
'I've nothing for you,' she said when Denry
came in.
'That's not good enough, I'm afraid,' said
Denry cheerfully. 'I'm not leaving until I
get ten pence.'
'It'll be a long wait. I'll have nothing until
Saturday, when my son Jack starts a new job.'
'I'm sorry,' said Denry kindly, 'but if you
don't pay, you'll have to go. Mrs Codleyn
will put you out in the street, you know.
Why don't you go and live with one of your
children?'
After some more conversation, Denry left the
house, still smiling cheerfully. And then,
two minutes later, he put his head round the
door again.
'Look here, mother,' he said, 'I'll lend you
ten pence if you like. But you must pay me
a penny a week for it. You must pay me back
next week and give me eleven pence.'
And he wrote down 'Ten pence, paid' in her
rent book.
'Eh, you're a funny fellow, Mr Machin,' said
Mrs Hullins.
The next Monday, all the neighbours knew that
Denry could be very helpful about problems
with the rent. And Denry, with his cheerful,
smiling face, saved many families from a life
in the street. Of course, it was good business
for him, too. If someone borrowed ten pence
for four weeks, when they paid Denry back,
they had to give him fourteen pence. If it
was for six months, they had to pay him back
thirty-six pence. Money made like this just
grows and grows.
Denry began to think that he was different
from other men. He had invited himself to
the ball, danced with the Countess, left his
job with Duncalf, taken Duncalf's rent-collecting,
and then introduced the idea of collecting
rents and lending money at the same time.
He was becoming well-known in Bursley as an
unusual and amusing fellow - in other words,
a card.
But then the day came when Mrs Codleyn decided
to sell some of her smaller houses. This was
very bad news for Denry because these houses
were the most important part of his business.
Denry talked to her, and tried to show her
that it was not a sensible idea, but it was
no good. Finally, Denry said wildly that he
would buy some of the houses himself.
'I'll buy the Widow Hullins' house,' he said.
'I'll give you forty-five pounds for it.'
It was all the money he had.
Mrs Codleyn agreed. And selling this one house,
for the moment, seemed to be enough for her.
***
Denry was now a property owner. And he had
also joined the Sports Club - the club for
the rich, the fashionable, and the successful
men of Bursley. It was a great thing for the
son of a washer-woman to join a club like
this.
On Denry's second visit to the club, he saw
that some of the most important men in Bursley
were there. A group of them were arguing in
a corner of the comfortable bar.
'Some of the poor people in this town live
in the most terrible old houses,' said Charles
Fearns, a lawyer. 'And the town just doesn't
care about them. There's an old woman - Hullins
is her name - who's lived in the same awful
old house for fifty years. She pays fifteen
pence a week rent for this place, and now
she's going to be put out into the street
because she can't pay.'
'Who's the hard-hearted owner?' someone asked.
'Mrs Codleyn,' said Fearns.
'Mrs Codleyn isn't the owner,' called Denry,
who was sitting at the next table, smiling.
'I am.'
'Oh, I'm sorry,' said Fearns, 'I had no idea-'
'Not at all!' said Denry. 'But what can I
do? She can't pay, or doesn't want to pay.
Do I let her live in the house for no rent
because she's seventy? Come on, tell me. What
do I do?'
'Fearns would make her a present of the house!'
a voice said laughing, and everybody else
laughed too.
'Well, that's what I'll do,' said Denry. 'I'll
give her the house. That's the kind of hard-hearted
owner I am.'
The room was silent for a moment.
'I mean it!' said Denry, and picked up his
glass. 'She can have the house! Good health
to the Widow Hullins.'
And the next morning, everybody in Bursley
was talking about it. 'I say, have you heard
Machin's latest?'
He was now not just a card; he was the card.
CHAPTER THREE
The Dancing Teacher and the Furniture Van
One day in July Denry knocked at the door
of a house at the top of Brougham Street.
The dancing teacher, Miss Ruth Earp, lived
there, in a house owned by Mr Calvert, and
Denry now collected Mr Calvert's rents for
him.
'Good morning, Miss Earp,' said Denry, when
she opened the door. 'I've come about the
rent.'
'The rent?' said Ruth, surprised. She gave
him a look which seemed to say, 'Why does
a little boy like you ask about my rent?'
'Yes. I collect rents for Mr Calvert now,'
Denry said. He did not like the 'little boy'
look on her face, and added, 'You haven't
paid any rent for more than a year.'
Ruth Earp gave a hard little laugh. 'I see,'
she said. 'So Mr Herbert Calvert is paying
you to do his dirty work now. I must tell
you, Mr Machin, that not long ago Mr Calvert
was more interested in me than in my rent.
But when I decided that I could not return
his interest, he said things which hurt me
very much - very much indeed.'
'Oh,' said Denry. He told himself that he
was here on business.
'But if you can't pay your rent, Miss Earp,
I'm afraid you'll have to leave.'
Ruth looked at him, and then gave a slow,
sad smile. 'Of course I can pay it,' she said
gently. 'I just wanted to punish Mr Calvert
a little. I can't pay you just at this moment,
I'm afraid. The bank is closed. Can you come
back tomorrow? Come at four o'clock, and I'll
give you a cup of tea.'
The next day Denry returned. It was the first
time he had taken tea with a young lady, and
so he had put on his best summer suit. He
noticed that Ruth was wearing a very pretty
dress - something white with bits of pink
in it.
Ruth had introduced Denry to dancing, and
now she introduced him to taking tea. It was
all very beautifully done - tea in very small
cups, little squares of bread-and-butter,
and interesting conversation. Ruth seemed
much more friendly today, and Denry found
it all very pleasant.
Then suddenly Ruth stopped speaking, and lay
back in her chair with her eyes closed.
'Is something the matter?' asked Denry.
'I'm afraid I've got an awful headache,' she
answered.
'I'm sorry,' said Denry. 'Is there anything
I can do? Perhaps you should lie down. Would
you like me to go?'
'But I must pay you the rent first.' She put
her hand to her head. 'The money's in that
desk. Could you get it for me?'
She gave Denry a key. He went over to the
desk, put the key in the lock, and tried to
turn it. Nothing happened, and then the key
turned and turned. 'I can't open it,' he said.
Ruth stood up, holding her head. She came
over to the desk, and tried the key. 'Oh dear.
I'm afraid you've broken the lock. I'll have
to get someone to mend it tomorrow morning,
and then I'll bring the money round to you.'
'Don't worry,' said Denry. 'I can easily call
back for it tomorrow. And I'm very sorry about
the lock.'
***
Late that night Denry came home from an evening
at the Sports Club and just as he reached
his mother's house, he saw something strange
at the top end of Brougham Street. A large
furniture van was moving down the street all
on its own; there were no horses. Clearly,
the owner had left it there and forgotten
to put on the brakes. It was moving slowly
now, but Denry could see that when it reached
the bottom of Brougham Street, it could be
very dangerous.
Denry was always at his finest at difficult
or dangerous moments. As the van passed him,
moving at about five or six kilometres an
hour, he jumped on, losing his hat, and tried
to put the brakes on. For a second or two
the van seemed to slow down, but then Denry
realized that the brakes were not working
and the van was moving faster and faster down
the hill. At the bottom of the street was
the canal, and clearly nothing was going to
stop the van now. It was too late to jump
off, so Denry closed his eyes and held on
hard.
When the van went in, Denry was under water
for a moment, but then he managed to climb
further up on the front of the van. Everything
was still and dark, except for a little starlight
on the water. Only Denry had seen the van's
strange journey down the hill.
'Well, well!' he said aloud to himself.
And a voice answered from inside the van:
'Who's there?'
Denry's heart seemed to stop beating. 'It's
me!' he said.
'Not Mr Machin?' said the voice.
'Yes,' said he. 'I jumped on as it came down
the street - and here we are!'
'Oh!' cried the voice. 'I wish you could get
round to me.'
It was Ruth Earp's voice. Denry understood
immediately. Ruth had played with him! She
had planned to take her furniture and run
away in the night. She had no rent money locked
in her desk at all. But he was not angry with
her, just amused. Ruth was really very clever
- in fact, very like Denry himself.
He had to climb over the roof of the van to
get to the back. The van was black inside,
and the floor was under fifty centimetres
of water.
'Where are you?'
'I'm here. I'm on a table. It's the only thing
the men put in the van before they went to
have their supper.'
Denry felt around until he touched her wet
dress.
'You're a bad girl, you know,' he said.
Ruth started to cry. 'I know,' she said miserably.
'But I had no money. What could I do?'
Denry climbed on to the table next to her.
'What can we do now?' she whispered.
'Wait until it gets light,' said he.
So they waited. On a hot July night it is
not unpleasant to sit in the dark with your
feet in water. Ruth told Denry all about her
life and her money problems.
When it started to get light, Denry saw that
the back of the van was only a metre from
the edge of the canal, so they jumped. In
the grey early light they looked at one another.
Ruth had a black eye, and Denry had lost his
hat.
'Go home by the back streets, not up Brougham
Street,' said Denry. 'I'll come and see you
in the morning.'
It was four o'clock in the morning when Denry
went quietly up his mother's stairs. He had
seen nobody.
***
Only two people in Bursley ever knew exactly
what had happened that night. Everybody knew
that Denry had tried to save the town from
a dangerous runaway van and had ended in the
canal. But as well as this one fact, there
were a great many stories about the accident,
and in these stories the names of Denry and
Ruth were always appearing.
One morning Denry went to see Mr Herbert Calvert
and gave him ten pounds which he said came
from Ruth Earp.
Calvert gave Denry a strange look. 'What's
going on?' he asked. 'Is it true that she
was trying to leave without paying?'
'I don't think so. It's all very extraordinary.
I think the van was at the wrong house.'
'Are you engaged to her?' asked Calvert.
Denry waited for a moment. 'Yes,' he said.
'Are you?'
And Denry thought to himself that few engagements
had begun as strangely as theirs.
CHAPTER FOUR
Saved by a Storm
When newly engaged people like Denry and Ruth
want to go away on a summer holiday, there
are many things to think about. A businessman,
for example, who lives by collecting rents
every week cannot go away easily for two.
And a young woman who lives alone must always
be careful about what other people think,
so Ruth asked her friend Nellie Cotterill
to go with her.
Ruth and Nellie took a room together at 26
St Asaph's Road, Llandudno. Denry took a room
at number 28 St Asaph's Road. Who could want
more?
Denry had never seen the sea before. As he
walked along the beach in his best clothes,
with the girls on either side of him, he thought
it was all wonderful. He also saw fantastic
possibilities for making money, because here
were fifty thousand people, all on holiday,
all wanting to do interesting things, and
all with money to spend.
Denry thought about this a lot because he
felt he was now a serious person. He had something
to live for. He was very pleased and happy
to be engaged to Ruth, although still a little
surprised. What could this fine young lady
see in him?
They had not discussed money at all, although
Denry wanted to. It was clear that Ruth thought
he was a rich man, and Denry was spending
a lot of money. In fact, he could not move
without paying for something. The pier, swimming,
ice cream, chairs, fruit, boat trips, photographs,
teas, coffees - even a short walk with Ruth
was expensive.
Ruth had very little money, but it didn't
worry her. She didn't know what money was,
and she spent Denry's like water. The gentle,
silent Nellie often asked to pay for something
herself, but of course Denry couldn't let
her. He liked Nellie Cotterill. She thought
that he and Ruth were wonderful, and although
she was a very quiet person, she was also
very sensible.
At the end of the first week Denry was getting
more and more worried about money. On the
Monday morning he went back to Bursley to
collect rents, and returned to Llandudno on
Tuesday evening with his pockets full of rent
money. Something had to happen, he thought.
He didn't know what it was, but three months
of engagement with Ruth Earp was going to
leave him penniless.
***
He was saved by a storm at sea. They woke
up on Wednesday morning to find the rain and
wind crashing against the windows. The three
walked down into the town, where they learnt
that the town's lifeboat had gone out to a
ship further along the coast. A second lifeboat
(an old one, now owned by a fisherman) had
gone out to a Norwegian ship, the Hjalmar,
which was in difficulties just off Llandudno
itself. Everyone in the town was watching
the lifeboat save the sailors while the ship
went down. Denry and the girls went onto the
pier, and Denry even got his feet wet helping
one or two of the Norwegian sailors from the
lifeboat onto the pier. After that, he talked
for a time to Cregeen, the owner of the lifeboat.
It was a very exciting day, and it gave Denry
an idea.
'I'll write a report about all this for the
Signal,' he said. This was the Five Towns
daily newspaper.
'Oh yes!' said Nellie. 'What a good idea!'
The next morning Denry was up early to send
the report off by train. Then he and the girls
walked into town - and spent more money. Everybody
in the town was talking about the storm, the
wreck of the Hjalmar and the wonderful rescue
of all the Norwegian sailors by the lifeboat.
After a few minutes, Ruth turned to Denry.
'I had the bill for our room this morning,'
she said.
'Oh!' he said. 'Did you pay it?'
'Yes. But now I've almost no money left. We
spent so much money while you were away in
Bursley. You don't know how quickly money
goes!' She waited a moment, then said, 'I
suppose we'll have to go home.'
'What a pity!' said Denry, sadly.
Of course, Ruth wanted Denry to say that he
could pay for her to stay. But all he said
was, 'What a pity!'
'I think I'll go home this afternoon.'
'I'm sorry,' said Denry.
At that moment a hand touched his arm. It
was Cregeen.
'Mr Machin. It's now or never. It's twenty-five
pounds if you can pay today.'
'Right!' said Denry. 'I'll see you this evening.'
Ruth pretended not to be interested in any
of this.
***
Poor Nellie. She knew something was wrong,
but she didn't know what it was. All she knew
was that her holiday was coming to a sudden
end. In the evening, the three of them walked
to the station.
'Where's your luggage?' Ruth asked Denry.
'I'm not going. I've got business here.'
There was a bookshop in the station. Denry
bought the Signal, which had just come in,
and there was his report: 'Terrible Storm
in North Wales - a report by Mr E. H. Machin
of Bursley'. Denry was ready to explode with
happiness, but he gave the newspaper calmly
to Ruth.
She did not look at it. 'We'll read it on
the train,' she said.
The bookshop also had a lot of souvenirs of
Llandudno. Ruth wanted a glass plate with
a picture of Great Orme Head on it, but the
man in the shop said that they had sold out.
'Couldn't you get one and send it to me?'
said Ruth.
'Oh yes,' said the man, taking out a book.
'What name?'
Ruth looked at Denry, in the way that a woman
always looks at a man when she wants him to
pay.
'Rothschild,' said Denry. 'The millionaire.'
These words ended their engagement. The next
day Denry received by post a ring in a box,
with a short letter.
'I only said "Rothschild"!' said Denry to
himself. But secretly, he was pleased.
***
An hour later Denry met Cregeen, and was soon
the owner of the old Llandudno lifeboat. He
then went to find Simeon, an old sailor with
a white beard. He had been in the lifeboat
when they rescued the men on the Hjalmar.
'I've got the boat,' said Denry. 'I'll give
you two pounds for the week.'
'All right,' said the old man. 'And I've seen
three of those Norwegians. They don't speak
English, but they understand about the money.'
'Good,' said Denry. 'I'll see you tomorrow
morning.'
At five o'clock the next morning a boat left
Llandudno. There were six men rowing, three
of them Norwegians. There was also a man with
a white beard, and Denry. In twenty minutes
they were at the wreck of the Hjalmar and
Denry was feeling very ill. Twenty minutes
more and he was happy to be back on land.
At ten o'clock that morning two Norwegian
sailors were walking around the town giving
little notices to everyone they met.
THE WRECK OF THE HJALMAR
FAMOUS RESCUE AT LLANDUDNO
Every day at 11, 12, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 o'clock
the famous lifeboat which rescued the Norwegian
sailors will visit the wreck of the Hjalmar.
The lifeboat's captain is Simeon Edwards,
one of the rescuers, and the lifeboat is rowed
by three of the rescued Norwegians.
Return trip, 12 pence
On the first day, Denry made twelve pounds.
That evening he received a packet in the post.
It was from Nellie. There was a box of chocolates
and a note which said: Thank you very much
for the holiday. I hope you will like these.
Nellie. Denry was very pleased by this. Ruth's
young friend, he thought, was much more grateful
than Ruth herself.
The boat trips out to the wreck became more
and more popular. In the afternoons, Denry
had to ask 25 pence - it was the only way
to stop the big crowds that were waiting on
the beach. Soon, he was making a hundred pounds
a week. He was sorry the wreck had happened
in August and not July. He was sorry there
were not two or even forty Hjalmars.
One day in September when business was beginning
to slow down (he was down to fifty pounds
a week), Denry had a very pleasant surprise.
He met Nellie on the beach, and it was a fact
that seeing her gave him a great feeling of
happiness. She was with her father, Councillor
Cotterill, and her mother. The Councillor
was a builder who had become rich building
cheap houses for the people of the Five Towns.
'Well, young man!' said Councillor Cotterill.
He continued to call Denry 'young man' in
a way that made Denry cross. 'I've made more
money this summer than you have in a year,'
he said silently to the Councillor's back.
'You must have dinner with me one evening,'
Denry said finally. 'At the Majestic.' The
Majestic was the finest, and most expensive,
hotel in Llandudno. Some of the waiters were
French!
They agreed to go the next day. Then Mrs Cotterill
remembered that Ruth was coming to stay with
them for a few days.
'Bring her along too!' said Denry.
The dinner was a great success. Denry had
never arranged a dinner before, but it was
easy. You just walked into the hotel in the
morning and said what you wanted. The hotel
arranged everything! And it was easy to meet
a woman who had just broken off her engagement
to you. You just said, 'Good afternoon, how
are you?' and she said the same. Then you
shook hands. And there you were, still alive.
After the meal, Denry walked back with the
others to their hotel. Councillor Cotterill
had stopped calling Denry 'young man'; he
now called him 'my boy'.
'That lifeboat. It was just an idea, my boy,
just an idea.'
'Yes,' said Denry, 'but I thought of it.'
'The question is,' said the Councillor, 'can
you think of any more ideas as good?'
'Well,' said Denry, 'can you?'
When they reached the Cotterills' hotel, Ruth
waited a moment while the others went in,
and then turned to Denry:
'I don't feel like sleeping at all. I suppose
you wouldn't like to go for a walk?'
'Well...'
'I suppose you're very tired.'
'No,' he replied. 'It's this moonlight I'm
afraid of.'
A few days later the Cotterills and Ruth Earp
went home, and Denry went with them. He had
now sold the lifeboat and brought all his
business in Llandudno to an end. He had very
little luggage, but he did have a new hat-box.
It was very heavy.
When Denry got home, he was pleased to see
his mother again. She had often collected
his rents for him during the summer, and had
done it very well. He gave the hat-box to
her, and she immediately dropped it.
'I don't want any of your games, young man,'
she said crossly. 'What's in it?'
'Some pretty stones from the beach.'
She picked up the hat-box, opened it, and
screamed. It fell to the floor with a crash
and Mrs Machin was standing up to her ankles
in money. She could see coins running all
over the floor. At last they stopped moving,
and then it was silent. Denry could hear his
heart beating. For once in her life his mother
could not find a word to say.
For several days afterwards Mrs Machin was
still picking up coins. The story of the money
in the hat-box quickly went round the town.
It was Denry's 'latest' and people talked
about it for weeks afterwards.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Rescue of the Countess
Denry's rent-collecting business grew and
grew. He had come back from the Llandudno
adventure with a thousand pounds. Two years
later he had two thousand pounds, and his
bank manager spoke to him with great politeness.
Denry now rented a small office, and employed
an office-boy.
He also bought a mule and cart. He said he
needed them for his work. He could, of course,
collect rents on a bicycle, and a bicycle
doesn't eat much, or run away. But Denry wanted
a mule. It was a good advertisement for his
business.
Denry was happy that people talked about the
mule as his 'latest', and he was happy to
be making money. But he wanted more than money.
He was always looking for new ideas, exciting
things to do - things which would make sure
that he was always the greatest 'card' in
the Five Towns.
One day, a new notice appeared on Denry's
door:
FIVE TOWNS SAVINGS CLUB
Secretary and Manager - E. H. Machin
Many shops in the Five Towns had savings clubs.
Every week customers paid a few pence into
the club. At Christmas the customers could
spend all the money they had paid in. Denry's
idea was for a savings club for every shop
in the Five Towns. It was a fantastic idea.
A poor person could pay just a little money
every week, and to make it easier, Denry could
come to the house and collect the money. Denry's
savings club was special in one very important
way. After paying a pound to Denry, someone
could spend two pounds in the shops immediately
- although they must then, of course, continue
to pay into the club every week.
Denry needed to make a profit, of course,
and his profit would come from the shops.
For every six pence spent in a shop, the shop
had to pay him one penny. He started by going
to Bostocks, the biggest clothes shop in the
Five Towns. With Bostocks' name on the list
it was easier to find other shops. In two
weeks he had nearly a hundred.
Now he needed something to give the club a
good start. For twenty-five pounds Denry could
put an advertisement on the front page of
the Signal, but he preferred free advertisements.
Then he had an idea. He could ask the Countess
of Chell to be the patron of his club. Hers
was the best possible name to have at the
top of his letter paper. She was the richest
woman in the Five Towns. Some people loved
her and some people hated her, but everybody
knew her.
'I'll ask her. I'll have her as a patron,'
he said to himself. 'I'll go to Sneyd Hall.
She can't eat me.'
So one morning he arrived, without his mule,
at the home of the Countess of Chell. He had
been to Sneyd Hall before; the gardens were
open to the people of the Five Towns, and
there were often hundreds of people there
on Sunday afternoons in summer. But today
the gardens were empty.
It was a long walk between the trees up to
the house, and a long walk up the steps. Denry
rang, and the door opened.
'Well?' said a lady. She was dressed in black.
'Can I see the Countess?' he asked, giving
her his card.
'I will ask,' she answered. She disappeared
into the house, leaving Denry in the hall.
A few moments later he heard the Countess's
voice:
'Oh, no! I'm terribly busy. I'm leaving in
a few minutes.'
Still Denry waited. Nobody came to see him.
Minutes passed and still nothing. Had they
forgotten him? Then, through an open door
in the back of the house he saw a man. It
was Jock, the son of a friend of his mother.
Jock worked at Sneyd Hall, where he drove
the Countess's carriage.
Denry did not want to shout through the house,
so he walked towards him. 'Jock!' he called,
softly.
Jock didn't hear, and disappeared through
another door. Denry followed, through door
after door, until suddenly he found himself
in a long ballroom, full of mirrors, paintings
and rich furniture, with high windows to one
side and big doors on the other. Jock had
disappeared. Denry tried the big doors, but
they were all locked. He went back to the
door he had used to come into the room. But
strangely, that was now locked as well. Then
he heard horses outside, and running to a
window, he saw the Countess's carriage driving
away.
Denry tried knocking on all the doors, first
politely, then noisily. He tried calling out,
then shouting as loudly as he could. Nothing.
At last he realized that there was nobody
to hear him. He was a prisoner in an empty
house.
He looked around the room. The only possible
escape was to break a window, so Denry preferred
to wait until night. He spent a long afternoon
in the great ballroom of Sneyd Hall, looking
at pictures and furniture. When night fell,
he broke one of the big windows and went home.
The Five Towns Savings Club began life without
the Countess.
The next morning, Denry opened the Signal
and suddenly felt very ill.
ROBBERY AT SNEYD HALL
Yesterday, thieves broke into the great ballroom
at Sneyd, home of the Countess of Chell. The
police say that nothing seems to be missing.
The Countess (who is away in Italy) will pay
twenty pounds for any information about the
thieves.
Denry was lucky. The robbery was the talk
of the town for a few days, but nobody, it
seemed, had remembered his visit to Sneyd
Hall, or found his visiting card. And because
nothing was stolen, the police were not very
interested. Indeed, a week or two later, Denry
saw a chance to make something out of his
adventure. All that long afternoon he had
been in the great ballroom, and he had used
his eyes well. He remembered everything. Soon,
a report appeared in the Signal under Denry's
name. It began:
The recent robbery at Sneyd Hall gives us
a reason to remember the beautiful paintings
and furniture which it contains and which,
happily, were not stolen. Only friends of
the family, of course, ever see the great
ballroom, but perhaps readers of the Signal
will be interested to read a description of
this fine room...
Everybody read the report of course, and everybody
understood that Denry, who had already danced
with the Countess, was now a good friend of
the family.
***
The Savings Club was a great success; in fact,
it became too successful. The reason was this.
When customers had paid in two pounds, they
were allowed to spend four pounds in the shops.
They did spend four pounds in the shops. And
Denry had to pay the shops. Customers were
still paying in their five pence and their
ten pence - but that wasn't enough to help
Denry. His two thousand pounds in the bank
was going very quickly. And then a whisper
began to go round that Denry's famous Savings
Club was not healthy, that it was going to
fail, and that everyone would lose their money.
Denry knew that he had to do something - and
do it very quickly. He thought of the Countess.
The Countess was very good at opening things.
She opened hospitals and schools all over
the Five Towns, and Denry read in the Signal
that she was going to open a new Police Club
in Hanbridge in a week's time. There are a
number of facts about what happened on the
day of the opening, and during the week before
it. Some people may have ideas to explain
some of these facts.
The facts are these. First: Denry called one
day at the house of Mrs Kemp in Brougham Street.
Mrs Kemp was the mother of Jock, Denry's old
friend and carriage-driver to the Countess.
Second: a day or two later, Jock came to visit
his mother, and Denry also came to visit.
Denry and Jock went for a short walk together.
Third: on the afternoon of the opening of
the Police Club, the Countess's carriage broke
a wheel between Sneyd Hall and Hanbridge,
about five kilometres from Hanbridge. Fourth:
about five minutes later, Denry drove past
in his mule cart, wearing his best clothes.
Fifth: as Denry drove past, Jock called out,
'Excuse me, sir!' and Denry stopped. These
are the facts.
'Good afternoon, Countess,' said Denry, lifting
his hat.
'Oh, it's you, is it?' said the Countess.
'Good afternoon.'
'I see you've had an accident,' said Denry.
'Are you going somewhere important?'
'Yes, I am going somewhere important! I've
got to be at the Police Club by three. And
I shan't be. I'm late now.'
'I can get you there by three o'clock,' said
Denry.
It was five kilometres to Hanbridge, and they
were there in seventeen minutes. The mule
was moving as fast as he could, but when they
came into the main square, he stopped suddenly.
There were several hundred policemen outside
the Police Club, waiting for the Countess.
'Oh dear!' said Denry. 'He hates policemen.'
'I'll walk,' said the Countess.
'Oh no,' said Denry. 'It's all right.' He
hit the mule over the head with his whip.
The mule dashed off, but away from the Police
Club. They hit another cart, full of vegetables,
and turned it over. They dashed down a hill,
fast. Then the Countess noticed that Denry
was not using his right arm.
'I think I broke it when we hit the cart,'
he said. 'Don't worry. I'll go up this hill
- that'll stop him.'
Denry managed to turn the mule into Birches
Street, which went up a hill. The mule slowed
down, then stopped.
'Shall I drive him to the Club?' asked the
Countess. She could see that Denry's arm was
very painful.
And so the Countess arrived at the Police
Club in Denry's mule cart. And she invited
Denry to the Club opening, where she told
the five mayors and all the important people
of the Five Towns how Denry had rescued her.
After the opening, Denry left the Club with
the Countess, to help her find her carriage.
But it still had not arrived.
'I can take you home in my cart,' offered
Denry.
'I think I'll wait,' said the Countess.
'Well, let's go and have a cup of tea while
we're waiting,' said Denry. 'There's a good
tea-shop near here.'
The Countess loved tea, and they were soon
sitting in a corner of the tea-shop. The Countess
looked hard at Denry.
'How did you get all that information about
the rooms at Sneyd Hall?' she asked.
After this, the conversation became exciting.
That evening a notice appeared in the Signal
which said that the Countess was now Patron
of the Five Towns Savings Club. In a few days
a thousand more people had joined the Club.
Denry had no more worries about money.
CHAPTER SIX
The Battle with Denry's Mother
Late one winter's evening a few years later,
Denry opened the door of his mother's house
in Brougham Street.
'Is that you, Denry?' came a tired voice.
'Yes,' he said, walking into the living room.
His mother was sitting very near the fire,
which was burning brightly. She looked cold
and ill.
'You must see a doctor, mother.'
'A doctor! What for? I've just got a bit of
a cold, that's all.'
'You've been ill a lot this winter,' said
Denry. 'It's this awful old house we live
in.'
'It's a very good house. It was good enough
for your father and it's good enough for me.'
'Mother, I'm earning two thousand pounds a
year! And here we are, living in an old house
at a rent of twenty-three pence a week!'
Actually, Denry was making nearly four thousand
a year, but he was afraid to tell his mother
that. These days he was a great man in the
Five Towns, but his greatness was nothing
in Brougham Street.
'You can go and live in a fine, grand house
if you like, Denry,' said his mother. 'But
I'm staying here.'
And so the battle went on. Denry wanted to
move, but his mother refused to leave Brougham
Street. And Denry wouldn't move to a new house
without her.
One morning a few weeks later, there was a
letter for Mrs Machin from the man who owned
her house. He had sold the house, he wrote,
to a man in London, a Mr Wilbraham. From next
month Mrs Machin must pay her rent to him.
The next day Denry came home with some news.
'I've met Mr Wilbraham, the man who bought
our house. He came down from London. He wants
me to collect the rents for him.'
'What did you tell him?'
'I said yes. Why not? It's easier for you.
And he's an interesting man. He's building
a new house up at Bleakridge. It's going to
be a really modern house; a house where you
can live comfortably without servants.'
'He's certainly a sensible man,' answered
Mrs Machin. She hated servants and said so
about once a week.
The house at Bleakridge started to grow. Mr
Wilbraham stayed in London. The builder was
Mr Cotterill (Denry had been friendly with
the family since Llandudno), but Denry also
kept an eye on things. The house was nearly
finished when Mrs Machin got a second letter
from Mr Wilbraham.
'He says we have to leave,' she cried. 'He
wants us out immediately. Oh Denry, what shall
we do!'
'We'll go and see him,' said Denry. 'He's
coming to his new house tonight!'
So they put on their best clothes and went
up to Bleakridge. Half an hour later they
were standing outside Mr Wilbraham's house.
Denry rang the bell, and they waited.
'Dirty doorstep,' said Mrs Machin, looking
down at it. In Brougham Street it was important
to have a clean doorstep, even if your rent
was only twenty-three pence a week.
'Easy to clean,' said Denry. 'Watch!' He turned
a tap next to the doorstep, and water ran
over the step, washing it.
'Is that hot water?' asked Mrs Machin.
'Of course,' said Denry. He could see his
mother liked the tap. 'Wilbraham's fixed a
lot of things like that in his house.'
He rang again but there was no answer. 'Perhaps
his train's late. I've got a key. We'll go
in and wait for him.' He opened the door and
turned on the electric light. Mrs Machin had
never seen electric light before. She thought
it was wonderful.
'It's very warm in here,' she said.
'Central heating,' said Denry. 'No fires to
light, no wood to carry, no fireplaces to
clean-'
The doorbell rang.
'There he is!' said Denry, moving to the door.
Three people stood on the washed doorstep
- Mr and Mrs Cotterill, and Nellie. Mr Wilbraham
had invited them, said Mr Cotterill.
'Oh, come in, come in!' said Denry. 'He's
not here. Perhaps he's missed his train. But
the house is all ready for him. Come on, I'll
show you round.'
He and Nellie ran upstairs and the others
followed. Upstairs the house was as wonderful
as downstairs. So easy to clean. No work at
all. 'Why,' said Mrs Cotterill, 'I could live
here without any servants and still have it
clean and tidy by ten o'clock in the morning.'
Mrs Machin agreed.
Downstairs they found a fine cold supper ready
to eat.
'Come on,' said Denry. 'Let's eat. I'm sure
he'd like us to.'
Mrs Machin didn't want to. 'It's very strange
that he isn't here,' she said.
'He's a strange man,' said Denry. 'I think
he's a little mad.'
'I don't think he can be mad,' said Mrs Machin.
'The house is much too sensible for a madman.'
Finally, they all sat down to supper, and
after some food and three bottles of wine
they started to enjoy themselves. Soon Denry
was searching the house for a fourth bottle
of wine. He found one, opened it, drank some,
and, with a cry, dropped the glass on the
floor, where it broke.
It was not wine. It was a bottle of cleaning
liquid. And the word POISON was written on
it in large letters. Nellie didn't seem to
realize how serious it was, and began to laugh.
Mrs Machin took Denry's arm. 'Come out to
the kitchen,' she said. 'You must have some
salt water, to make you sick.'
'Oh no!' said Denry. 'I'll be all right.'
But his mother wouldn't listen to him, and
pulled him out of the room. Nellie had her
hand over her mouth, trying very hard not
to laugh, but not succeeding.
Ten minutes later they returned. Denry looked
very white, and very cross. 'There's no danger
now,' said Mrs Machin.
So the party came to an end. The Cotterills
stood up to leave, and asked Denry how he
was feeling.
'I feel much too ill to walk home,' he said.
'I'll sleep here. The bedrooms are all ready.
My mother can stay too.'
The Cotterills left and Denry went to bed.
After an hour his mother went to bed, too,
but she slept very badly.
The next morning she was up before Denry and
went out. Half an hour later she was back,
waking Denry up.
'Oh, Denry! I've just been back home. They're
pulling the house down. The roof's gone and
the furniture...'
Denry sat up.
'I'll tell you something now,' he said. 'Wilbraham's
dead.'
'Dead!'
'Dead. Well, he was never really alive, of
course.'
And Mrs Machin understood. This was all Denry's
plan to move her out of Brougham Street and
up to Bleakridge. Soon all Bursley knew that
Denry had won the battle with his mother.
And they loved it.
But at least Mrs Machin had won with the salt
water.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Mayor, the Wife and the Football Club
Soon after the move to Bleakridge, Bursley
made Denry a Town Councillor. He was the youngest
Councillor in the town, and one of the richest
men in the Five Towns, but Councillor Cotterill
still called him 'young man'.
Denry did not like Councillor Cotterill, but
he was very friendly with Nellie and her mother.
So when he bought one of the first cars in
the Five Towns, he decided to invite them
to go for a drive. When he got there, Nellie
came to the door.
'Come in,' she said. 'I've got a surprise
for you.'
In the sitting room, next to Mrs Cotterill,
Denry saw a wonderful woman, beautifully dressed
in black. When she turned to look at him,
Denry suddenly recognized her. It was Ruth.
Then he remembered that Ruth had married a
rich man, a Mr Capron-Smith, who had recently
died.
'Well, Denry,' she said, softly.
'Well, Ruth.'
Conversation was not difficult. Ruth was talking
about a holiday in Switzerland. Denry listened
with interest.
After a few minutes, the front door opened,
and Mr Cotterill was heard in the hall. He
did not come into the sitting room, so Mrs
Cotterill went out to speak to him. When she
came back, she was crying.
'It's the bank!' she cried. 'After all these
years, and now, suddenly... all his money...'
Nellie and Ruth ran to her, and Denry decided
it was probably better to leave. But as he
walked into the hall, he met Councillor Cotterill.
He was looking very worried.
'Ah, Denry,' he said. 'You're a friend of
the family. We've no secrets from you. I'm
afraid things are looking bad. The fact is,
the bank wants its money and I can't pay.'
'What are you going to do?' asked Denry.
'We'll all go to Canada. My brother lives
there - he's in the building business. He'll
give me a job. It's stupid really. I only
need two thousand pounds, for a month or two,
until I sell the houses I'm building. I say,'
he continued, 'you don't have a thousand or
two, do you, young man? There'll be an excellent
profit in two or three months. You and I have
been friends for ten years.'
'And I suppose I've come to visit you once
a fortnight,' answered Denry. 'Perhaps two
hundred and fifty times in ten years. That's
eight pounds a visit, Cotterill. That's more
expensive than the most fashionable doctor
in England!'
This conversation does not make Denry look
very kind. But Councillor Cotterill had called
him 'young man' too many times.
Several weeks later the Cotterills left Bursley
and took the train to Liverpool, where they
would take the ship to Canada. On the day
they left the Five Towns, Denry happened to
meet Ruth in the street.
'Did you know they have the cheapest tickets
for the ship?' she said. 'It's terrible! And
it's too late to change them now.'
'No, it isn't,' said Denry. 'I could go to
Liverpool and arrange it. The ship doesn't
leave until tomorrow.'
'Let's both go!' she said. 'And we'll pay
half each for their new tickets.'
They had a very pleasant train journey. Ruth
was warm and friendly to Denry, and as the
train pulled into Liverpool, he had a very
strange thought. 'I could still marry her!
She's a fine woman, and now she's rich herself...'
They found the Cotterills, and paid for them
to travel in a more comfortable part of the
ship. Mr Cotterill said he would repay them,
Mrs Cotterill cried, and Nellie said nothing
at all. The ship's bell rang for the second
time. Denry and Ruth said their goodbyes and
started to leave.
Then Denry looked back and saw Nellie's sad
little face. He felt as he had never felt
before in his life. He wondered what was happening
to his legs. He turned and ran back to Nellie.
'Look here,' he whispered. 'Come with me for
a moment. There's something I want to give
you. I left it in the taxi.'
Ruth was already lost in the crowds of people
leaving the ship.
'But there's not time. The bell-'
'It'll only take a minute. Quick.' Without
waiting to argue, he took her hand, pulled
her off the ship, and towards a taxi.
'Which taxi is yours?' asked Nellie.
'Any one. It doesn't matter. Jump in.' He
pushed her in.
'I'll miss the boat.'
'I know you will. I don't want you to go to
Canada.'
'What are you going to do with me?' whispered
Nellie.
'Well, what do you think?' shouted Denry.
'I'm going to marry you, of course!'
***
One evening Councillor Denry Machin sat down
to tea with his wife, Nellie, in the house
in Bleakridge. He opened the newspaper and
read aloud: Sudden Death of Councillor Bloor.
'Poor man!' said Nellie. 'And he was going
to be mayor in November, wasn't he?'
'So he was,' said Denry.
'Who'll be mayor now?'
'Barlow, I suppose,' said Denry.
'Barlow! He's an awful man! Nobody likes Barlow.
Why don't they make you mayor?'
'Would you like to be mayoress?'
'I don't know. Why not?'
'I probably will be mayor after Barlow. But
I want to be the youngest mayor, which means
I'll have to do it this year, while I'm still
thirty-three.'
'Who decides?'
'The Council, of course. But you're right.
Nobody likes Barlow. And he's having a lot
of problems with the Football Club. He's the
chairman, you know.'
Bursley Football Club was having a very bad
year. In fact it had had several very bad
years. It lost most of its games, and because
not many people wanted to see Bursley lose,
few people went to watch the games.
A few days after Denry's conversation with
Nellie there was a crowded meeting at the
Town Hall to discuss the club's future. Barlow,
the chairman, got up to speak.
'I've been chairman of this club for thirteen
years. In that time I've put two thousand
pounds of my own money into the club. I can't
put in any more. But what have you, the people
of Bursley, done for your club? You don't
come and watch. If we lose a game you stay
at home the next week. We lose fifty or sixty
pounds every time we play, and we can't go
on like this.'
Several other people stood up to speak. Most
of them had nothing kind to say about Councillor
Barlow. All of them said that the club needed
new players.
'New players!' said Barlow. 'Where's the money
for new players? Has anybody got a thousand
pounds?'
Nobody offered money. But more speakers stood
up to ask for new players. Finally a man at
the back of the hall stood up and walked up
to the front.
'It's Machin!' said somebody. 'Good old Machin!'
Denry turned and looked at the sea of faces.
'I don't know a lot about football,' he said,
'although I enjoy a good game. But I do want
to say something about new players. Isn't
it true that one of the best players in England
comes from Bursley?'
'Yes!' shouted the crowd. 'Callear! He's the
best player in England!'
'That's right. Callear. He left Bursley when
he was nineteen to play for Liverpool. He
scored a lot of goals there in three years.
Then he went to York, didn't he? And York
have some money problems now, I hear, and
want to sell some of their players. Gentlemen,
Callear must come back home to Bursley.'
The crowd in the hall were now very noisy
and excited. Barlow jumped angrily to his
feet.
'And how are we going to get Callear? Councillor
Machin says he doesn't know much about football,
and it's true! Aston Villa have already offered
700 pounds for Callear. Blackburn have offered
750 pounds. Has anybody here got 800 pounds?'
'Have you finished?' asked Denry, who was
still standing.
The hall exploded with laughter.
'Now,' called Denry, 'Mr Callear, will you
please come up to the front of the hall?'
The hall was suddenly silent. A tall young
man walked nervously down to the front of
the hall.
'That's him!' said somebody. 'It's Callear.
Good old Callear! Good old Machin!'
'Well?' asked Denry, turning to Barlow. 'Do
you want him?'
'Yes. But what about the money?'
'That's my problem. I've just come back from
York. If you want him, you can have him.'
Two days later a letter appeared in the Signal.
It said that Denry should be the next mayor.
Other letters followed, saying the same thing,
and that Bursley needed a young and popular
mayor. And when the Council met, it agreed.
That evening Denry told Nellie: 'You'll be
the mayoress to the youngest mayor. And it's
cost me, with hotels and travel, about eight
hundred and eleven pounds!'
After the meeting a group of councillors were
talking about Denry.
'What a card!' said one, laughing.
'There's never been a man like him in all
the Five Towns!' said another.
'But he's never done a day's work in his life,'
said Barlow. 'What's he done for the town?'
'What's he done? He's made us all laugh! That's
what he's done.'
- THE END -