The Gift of the Magi
One dollar and eighty-seven cents. That was all.
Della counted it three times. She was very careful
with money and bought only the cheapest food. But
she only had one dollar and eighty-seven
cents. And the next day was Christmas.
There was nothing to do so she sat down and
cried. Della lived in New York City in a poor,
little apartment. The rent was $8 a week. The
name on the front door of their flat was "Mr
James Dillingham Young". In the past he earned
$30 a week, but now he earned only $20 a week.
When he came home after work Della always
hugged him. And this was very good.
Della stopped crying and dried her face.
She stood by the window and looked
at a gray cat on the gray street.
"Tomorrow will be Christmas Day and I have
only one dollar and eighty-seven cents
to buy Jim a Christmas present," she thought. She
wanted to buy him something fine and beautiful.
She wanted to show him that she loved him a lot.
There was a small mirror on the
wall and Della stood in front of it.
Her eyes were bright. She pulled down her
beautiful long hair. It went below her knees.
Now, the James Dillingham Youngs
had two very special things.
One was Jim's gold pocket watch. It
belonged to his father and before that,
to his grandfather. The other
special thing was Della's hair.
She put up her hair again. A tear or two
fell on the old red carpet. Then she put
on her old brown coat and her old brown hat and
quickly went out with her eyes still shining.
She stopped in front of a door with a sign:
Madame Sofronie, Hair Goods. Della
opened the door and saw a big woman.
"Will you buy my hair?" asked Della.
"I buy hair," said Madame Sofronie. "Take
your hat off and show me your hair."
Della's beautiful brown hair fell down.
"Twenty dollars," said Madame Sofronie and she
touched the long hair with her expert hand.
"Cut it off, quickly! And give
me the money," said Della.
During the next two hours Della went to
many stores and looked for Jim's present.
She found it at last. It was
perfect for Jim: a simple gold
chain for his pocket watch. He was proud
of his pocket watch but it had no chain.
The gold chain cost twenty-one dollars,
and Della hurried home happily with it
and the eighty-seven cents. When she got home
she looked at her very short hair in the mirror.
"Oh dear, what can I do
with my hair?" she thought.
She was very busy with her hair for the next
forty minutes. Then she looked in the mirror
again. She looked like a schoolboy
with tiny curls all over her head.
What's Jim going to say when he sees me?"
she thought. "But what could I do with
one dollar and eighty-seven cents?"
At seven o'clock the coffee was ready
and the frying pan was on the stove.
Jim was never late. Della had
the gold chain in her hand
and she waited for him near the door.
Then she heard his footsteps on the stairs
and she was afraid for a moment. "I hope
Jim still thinks I'm pretty," she thought.
The door opened and Jim came in. He was
thin and serious. He needed a new overcoat
and he had no gloves. Poor fellow, he was only
twenty-two years old and he already had a family.
His eyes were fixed on Della. She could not
understand the look on his face. He was not
angry or surprised. He simply looked at her with a
strange expression on his face. Della ran to him.
"Jim, darling," she cried. "Don't
look at me that way. I sold my hair
because I wanted to give you a present. My hair
will be long again, it grows quickly. Oh, Jim,
say 'Merry Christmas' and let's be
happy! I have a beautiful gift for you."
"Did you cut off your hair?" asked Jim slowly.
"Yes, I cut it off and sold it," said Della.
"Don't you like me anymore? I'm still Della!"
Jim looked around the room.
"You cut your hair?" Jim
said again, almost stupidly.
"Yes, I sold it because I love you so
much, Jim. Shall I get dinner ready now?"
Jim put his arms around Della. Then he
took a package from his overcoat pocket
and threw it on the table.
"Don't worry about me, Della," he said. "I
will always love you. It doesn't matter if
your hair is short or long. But if you open the
package, you'll see why I was strange before."
Della was excited and she
quickly opened the package.
She gave a little scream of happiness,
but then she started crying.
There were The Combs-two beautiful,
tortoise-shell combs with little jewels.
They were the perfect color for
her hair. When Della saw them
the first time in a store window
on Broadway, she wanted them.
She knew they were expensive combs and now they
were hers. But she did not have long hair anymore!
Della held The Combs in her
hand and looked at them.
She smiled lovingly at Jim and said,
"My hair grows very fast, Jim!"
Then Della jumped up like
a cat and cried, "Oh, oh!"
She showed Jim his beautiful gift.
"Isn't it splendid, Jim? I looked everywhere
to find it. Now you'll look at your watch a
hundred times a day. Give me your watch!
Let's see how it looks on the new chain."
Jim sat down and put his hands
behind his head and smiled.
"Della," he said, "Let's put
our Christmas presents away and
keep them a while. They're too nice to use now.
I sold my watch to get the money to buy you
The Combs. And now, let's have dinner."
- THE END -