CHAPTER ONE
As long ago as 1860 it was the proper thing
to be born at home. At present, so I am told,
the high gods of medicine have decreed that
the first cries of the young shall be uttered
upon the anaesthetic air of a hospital, preferably
a fashionable one. So young Mr. and Mrs. Roger
Button were fifty years ahead of style when
they decided, one day in the summer of 1860,
that their first baby should be born in a
hospital. Whether this anachronism had any
bearing upon the astonishing history I am
about to set down will never be known.
I shall tell you what occurred, and let you
judge for yourself.
The Roger Buttons held an enviable position,
both social and financial, in ante - bellum
Baltimore. They were related to the This Family
and the That Family, which, as every Southerner
knew, entitled them to membership in that
enormous peerage which largely populated the
Confederacy. This was their first experience
with the charming old custom of having babies
- Mr. Button was naturally nervous. He hoped
it would be a boy so that he could be sent
to Yale College in Connecticut, at which institution
Mr. Button himself had been known for four
years by the somewhat obvious nickname of
"Cuff."
On the September morning consecrated to the
enormous event he arose nervously at six o'clock
dressed himself, adjusted an impeccable stock,
and hurried forth through the streets of Baltimore
to the hospital, to determine whether the
darkness of the night had borne in new life
upon its bosom.
When he was approximately a hundred yards
from the Maryland Private Hospital for Ladies
and Gentlemen he saw Doctor Keene, the family
physician, descending the front steps, rubbing
his hands together with a washing movement
- as all doctors are required to do by the
unwritten ethics of their profession.
Mr. Roger Button, the president of Roger Button
& Co., Wholesale Hardware, began to run toward
Doctor Keene with much less dignity than was
expected from a Southern gentleman of that
picturesque period.
"Doctor Keene!" he called. "Oh, Doctor Keene!"
The doctor heard him, faced around, and stood
waiting, a curious expression settling on
his harsh, medicinal face as Mr. Button drew
near.
"What happened?" demanded Mr. Button, as he
came up in a gasping rush. "What was it? How
is she" A boy? Who is it? What -"
"Talk sense!" said Doctor Keene sharply, He
appeared somewhat irritated.
"Is the child born?" begged Mr. Button.
Doctor Keene frowned. "Why, yes, I suppose
so - after a fashion." Again he threw a curious
glance at Mr. Button.
"Is my wife all right?"
"Yes."
"Is it a boy or a girl?"
"Here now!" cried Doctor Keene in a perfect
passion of irritation, "I'll ask you to go
and see for yourself. Outrageous!" He snapped
the last word out in almost one syllable,
then he turned away muttering: "Do you imagine
a case like this will help my professional
reputation? One more would ruin me - ruin
anybody."
"What's the matter?" demanded Mr. Button appalled.
"Triplets?"
"No, not triplets!" answered the doctor cuttingly.
"What's more, you can go and see for yourself.
And get another doctor. I brought you into
the world, young man, and I've been physician
to your family for forty years, but I'm through
with you! I don't want to see you or any of
your relatives ever again! Good - bye!"
Then he turned sharply, and without another
word climbed into his phaeton, which was waiting
at the curbstone, and drove severely away.
Mr. Button stood there upon the sidewalk,
stupefied and trembling from head to foot.
What horrible mishap had occurred? He had
suddenly lost all desire to go into the Maryland
Private Hospital for Ladies and Gentlemen
- it was with the greatest difficulty that,
a moment later, he forced himself to mount
the steps and enter the front door.
A nurse was sitting behind a desk in the opaque
gloom of the hall. Swallowing his shame, Mr.
Button approached her.
"Good - morning," she remarked, looking up
at him pleasantly.
"Good - morning. I - I am Mr. Button."
At this a look of utter terror spread itself
over girl's face. She rose to her feet and
seemed about to fly from the hall, restraining
herself only with the most apparent difficulty.
"I want to see my child," said Mr. Button.
The nurse gave a little scream. "Oh - of course!"
she cried hysterically. "Upstairs. Right upstairs.
Go - up!"
She pointed the direction, and Mr. Button,
bathed in cool perspiration, turned falteringly,
and began to mount to the second floor. In
the upper hall he addressed another nurse
who approached him, basin in hand. "I'm Mr.
Button," he managed to articulate. "I want
to see my -"
Clank! The basin clattered to the floor and
rolled in the direction of the stairs. Clank!
Clank! I began a methodical decent as if sharing
in the general terror which this gentleman
provoked.
"I want to see my child!" Mr. Button almost
shrieked. He was on the verge of collapse.
Clank! The basin reached the first floor.
The nurse regained control of herself, and
threw Mr. Button a look of hearty contempt.
"All right, Mr. Button," she agreed in a hushed
voice. "Very well! But if you knew what a
state it's put us all in this morning! It's
perfectly outrageous! The hospital will never
have a ghost of a reputation after -"
"Hurry!" he cried hoarsely. "I can't stand
this!"
"Come this way, then, Mr. Button."
He dragged himself after her. At the end of
a long hall they reached a room from which
proceeded a variety of howls - indeed, a room
which, in later parlance, would have been
known as the "crying - room." They entered.
Ranged around the walls were half a dozen
white - enameled rolling cribs, each with
a tag tied at the head.
"Well," gasped Mr. Button, "which is mine?"
"There!" said the nurse.
Mr. Button's eyes followed her pointing finger,
and this is what he saw. Wrapped in a voluminous
white blanket, and partly crammed into one
of the cribs, there sat an old man apparently
about seventy years of age. His sparse hair
was almost white, and from his chin dripped
a long smoke - coloured beard, which waved
absurdly back and forth, fanned by the breeze
coming in at the window. He looked up at Mr.
Button with dim, faded eyes in which lurked
a puzzled question.
"Am I mad?" thundered Mr. Button, his terror
resolving into rage. "Is this some ghastly
hospital joke?
"It doesn't seem like a joke to us," replied
the nurse severely. "And I don't know whether
you're mad or not - but that is most certainly
your child."
The cool perspiration redoubled on Mr. Button's
forehead. He closed his eyes, and then, opening
them, looked again. There was no mistake - he
was gazing at a man of threescore and ten
- a baby of threescore and ten, a baby whose
feet hung over the sides of the crib in which
it was reposing.
The old man looked placidly from one to the
other for a moment, and then suddenly spoke
in a cracked and ancient voice. "Are you my
father?" he demanded.
Mr. Button and the nurse started violently.
"Because if you are," went on the old man
querulously, "I wish you'd get me out of this
place - or, at least, get them to put a comfortable
rocker in here,"
"Where in God's name did you come from? Who
are you?" burst out Mr. Button frantically.
"I can't tell you exactly who I am," replied
the querulous whine, "because I've only been
born a few hours - but my last name is certainly
Button."
"You lie! You're an impostor!"
The old man turned wearily to the nurse. "Nice
way to welcome a new - born child," he complained
in a weak voice. "Tell him he's wrong, why
don't you?"
"You're wrong. Mr. Button," said the nurse
severely. "This is your child, and you'll
have to make the best of it. We're going to
ask you to take him home with you as soon
as possible - some time to - day."
"Home?" repeated Mr. Button incredulously.
"Yes, we can't have him here. We really can't,
you know?"
"I'm right glad of it," whined the old man.
"This is a fine place to keep a youngster
of quiet tastes. With all this yelling and
howling, I haven't been able to get a wink
of sleep. I asked for something to eat" - here
his voice rose to a shrill note of protest
- "and they brought me a bottle of milk!"
Mr. Button sank down upon a chair near his
son and concealed his face in his hands. "My
heavens!" he murmured, in an ecstasy of horror.
"What will people say? What must I do?"
"You'll have to take him home," insisted the
nurse - "immediately!"
A grotesque picture formed itself with dreadful
clarity before the eyes of the tortured man
- a picture of himself walking through the
crowded streets of the city with this appalling
apparition stalking by his side. "I can't.
I can't," he moaned.
People would stop to speak to him, and what
was he going to say? He would have to introduce
this - this septuagenarian: "This is my son,
born early this morning." And then the old
man would gather his blanket around him and
they would plod on, past the bustling stores,
the slave market - for a dark instant Mr.
Button wished passionately that his son was
black - past the luxurious houses of the residential
district, past the home for the aged...
"Come! Pull yourself together," commanded
the nurse.
"See here," the old man announced suddenly,
"if you think I'm going to walk home in this
blanket, you're entirely mistaken."
"Babies always have blankets."
With a malicious crackle the old man held
up a small white swaddling garment. "Look!"
he quavered. "This is what they had ready
for me."
"Babies always wear those," said the nurse
primly.
"Well," said the old man, "this baby's not
going to wear anything in about two minutes.
This blanket itches. They might at least have
given me a sheet."
"Keep it on! Keep it on!" said Mr. Button
hurriedly. He turned to the nurse. "What'll
I do?"
"Go down town and buy your son some clothes."
Mr. Button's son's voice followed him down
into the: hall: "And a cane, father. I want
to have a cane."
Mr. Button banged the outer door savagely...
CHAPTER TWO
"Good - morning," Mr. Button said nervously,
to the clerk in the Chesapeake Dry Goods Company.
"I want to buy some clothes for my child."
"How old is your child, sir?"
"About six hours," answered Mr. Button, without
due consideration.
"Babies' supply department in the rear."
"Why, I don't think - I'm not sure that's
what I want. It's - he's an unusually large
- size child. Exceptionally - ah large."
"They have the largest child's sizes."
"Where is the boys' department?" inquired
Mr. Button, shifting his ground desperately.
He felt that the clerk must surely scent his
shameful secret.
"Right here."
"Well -" He hesitated. The notion of dressing
his son in men's clothes was repugnant to
him. If, say, he could only find a very large
boy's suit, he might cut off that long and
awful beard, dye the white hair brown, and
thus manage to conceal the worst, and to retain
something of his own self - respect - not
to mention his position in Baltimore society.
But a frantic inspection of the boys' department
revealed no suits to fit the new - born Button.
He blamed the store, of course - in such cases
it is the thing to blame the store.
"How old did you say that boy of yours was?"
demanded the clerk curiously.
"He's - sixteen."
"Oh, I beg your pardon. I thought you said
six hours. You'll find the youths' department
in the next aisle."
Mr. Button turned miserably away. Then he
stopped, brightened, and pointed his finger
toward a dressed dummy in the window display.
"There!" he exclaimed. "I'll take that suit,
out there on the dummy."
The clerk stared. "Why," he protested, "that's
not a child's suit. At least it is, but it's
for fancy dress. You could wear it yourself!"
"Wrap it up," insisted his customer nervously.
"That's what I want."
The astonished clerk obeyed.
Back at the hospital Mr. Button entered the
nursery and almost threw the package at his
son. "Here's your clothes," he snapped out.
The old man untied the package and viewed
the contents with a quizzical eye.
"They look sort of funny to me," he complained,
"I don't want to be made a monkey of -"
"You've made a monkey of me!" retorted Mr.
Button fiercely. "Never you mind how funny
you look. Put them on - or I'll - or I'll
spank you." He swallowed uneasily at the penultimate
word, feeling nevertheless that it was the
proper thing to say.
"All right, father" - this with a grotesque
simulation of filial respect - "you've lived
longer; you know best. Just as you say."
As before, the sound of the word "father"
caused Mr. Button to start violently.
"And hurry."
"I'm hurrying, father."
When his son was dressed Mr. Button regarded
him with depression. The costume consisted
of dotted socks, pink pants, and a belted
blouse with a wide white collar. Over the
latter waved the long whitish beard, drooping
almost to the waist. The effect was not good.
"Wait!"
Mr. Button seized a hospital shears and with
three quick snaps amputated a large section
of the beard. But even with this improvement
the ensemble fell far short of perfection.
The remaining brush of scraggly hair, the
watery eyes, the ancient teeth, seemed oddly
out of tone with the gaiety of the costume.
Mr. Button, however, was obdurate - he held
out his hand. "Come along!" he said sternly.
His son took the hand trustingly. "What are
you going to call me, dad?" he quavered as
they walked from the nursery - "just 'baby'
for a while? till you think of a better name?"
Mr. Button grunted. "I don't know," he answered
harshly. "I think we'll call you Methuselah."
CHAPTER THREE
Even after the new addition to the Button
family had had his hair cut short and then
dyed to a sparse unnatural black, had had
his face shaved so dose that it glistened,
and had been attired in small - boy clothes
made to order by a flabbergasted tailor, it
was impossible for Button to ignore the fact
that his son was a excuse for a first family
baby. Despite his aged stoop, Benjamin Button
- for it was by this name they called him
instead of by the appropriate but invidious
Methuselah - was five feet eight inches tall.
His clothes did not conceal this, nor did
the clipping and dyeing of his eyebrows disguise
the fact that the eyes under - were faded
and watery and tired. In fact, the baby - nurse
who had been engaged in advance left the house
after one look, in a state of considerable
indignation.
But Mr. Button persisted in his unwavering
purpose. Benjamin was a baby, and a baby he
should remain. At first he declared that if
Benjamin didn't like warm milk he could go
without food altogether, but he was finally
prevailed upon to allow his son bread and
butter, and even oatmeal by way of a compromise.
One day he brought home a rattle and, giving
it to Benjamin, insisted in no uncertain terms
that he should "play with it," whereupon the
old man took it with - a weary expression
and could be heard jingling it obediently
at intervals throughout the day.
There can be no doubt, though, that the rattle
bored him, and that he found other and more
soothing amusements when he was left alone.
For instance, Mr. Button discovered one day
that during the preceding week be had smoked
more cigars than ever before - a phenomenon,
which was explained a few days later when,
entering the nursery unexpectedly, he found
the room full of faint blue haze and Benjamin,
with a guilty expression on his face, trying
to conceal the butt of a dark Havana.This,
of course, called for a severe spanking, but
Mr. Button found that he could not bring himself
to administer it. He merely warned his son
that he would "stunt his growth."
Nevertheless he persisted in his attitude.
He brought home lead soldiers, he brought
toy trains, he brought large pleasant animals
made of cotton, and, to perfect the illusion
which he was creating - for himself at least
- he passionately demanded of the clerk in
the toy - store whether "the paint would come
oft the pink duck if the baby put it in his
mouth." But, despite all his father's efforts,
Benjamin refused to be interested. He would
steal down the back stairs and return to the
nursery with a volume of the Encyclopedia
Britannica, over which he would pore through
an afternoon, while his cotton cows and his
Noah's ark were left neglected on the floor.
Against such a stubbornness Mr. Button's efforts
were of little avail.
The sensation created in Baltimore was, at
first, prodigious. What the mishap would have
cost the Buttons and their kinsfolk socially
cannot be determined, for the outbreak of
the Civil War drew the city's attention to
other things. A few people who were unfailingly
polite racked their brains for compliments
to give to the parents - and finally hit upon
the ingenious device of declaring that the
baby resembled his grandfather, a fact which,
due to the standard state of decay common
to all men of seventy, could not be denied.
Mr. and Mrs. Roger Button were not pleased,
and Benjamin's grandfather was furiously insulted.
Benjamin, once he left the hospital, took
life as he found it. Several small boys were
brought to see him, and he spent a stiff - jointed
afternoon trying to work up an interest in
tops and marbles - he even managed, quite
accidentally, to break a kitchen window with
a stone from a sling shot, a feat which secretly
delighted his father.
Thereafter Benjamin contrived to break something
every day, but he did these things only because
they were expected of him, and because he
was by nature obliging.
When his grandfather's initial antagonism
wore off, Benjamin and that gentleman took
enormous pleasure in one another's company.
They would sit for hours, these two, so far
apart in age and experience, and, like old
cronies, discuss with tireless monotony the
slow events of the day. Benjamin felt more
at ease in his grandfather's presence than
in his parents' - they seemed always somewhat
in awe of him and, despite the dictatorial
authority they exercised over him, frequently
addressed him as "Mr."
He was as puzzled as any one else at the apparently
advanced age of his mind and body at birth.
He read up on it in the medical journal, but
found that no such case had been previously
recorded. At his father's urging he made an
honest attempt to play with other boys, and
frequently he joined in the milder games - football
shook him up too much, and he feared that
in case of a fracture his ancient bones would
refuse to knit.
When he was five he was sent to kindergarten,
where he initiated into the art of pasting
green paper on orange paper, of weaving coloured
maps and manufacturing eternal cardboard necklaces.
He was inclined to drowse off to sleep in
the middle of these tasks, a habit which both
irritated and frightened his young teacher.
To his relief she complained to his parents,
and he was removed from the school. The Roger
Buttons told their friends that they felt
he was too young.
By the time he was twelve years old his parents
had grown used to him. Indeed, so strong is
the force of custom that they no longer felt
that he was different from any other child
- except when some curious anomaly reminded
them of the fact. But one day a few weeks
after his twelfth birthday, while looking
in the mirror, Benjamin made, or thought he
made, an astonishing discovery. Did his eyes
deceive him, or had his hair turned in the
dozen years of his life from white to iron
- gray under its concealing dye? Was the network
of wrinkles on his face becoming less pronounced?
Was his skin healthier and firmer, with even
a touch of ruddy winter colour? He could not
tell. He knew that he no longer stooped, and
that his physical condition had improved since
the early days of his life.
"Can it be - ?" he thought to himself, or,
rather, scarcely dared to think.
He went to his father. "I am grown," he announced
determinedly. "I want to put on long trousers."
His father hesitated. "Well," he said finally,
"I don't know. Fourteen is the age for putting
on long trousers - and you are only twelve."
"But you'll have to admit," protested Benjamin,
"that I'm big for my age."
His father looked at him with illusory speculation.
"Oh, I'm not so sure of that," he said. "I
was as big as you when I was twelve."
This was not true - it was all part of Roger
Button's silent agreement with himself to
believe in his son's normality.
Finally a compromise was reached. Benjamin
was to continue to dye his hair. He was to
make a better attempt to play with boys of
his own age. He was not to wear his spectacles
or carry a cane in the street. In return for
these concessions he was allowed his first
suit of long trousers...
CHAPTER FOUR
Of the life of Benjamin Button between his
twelfth and twenty - first year I intend to
say little. Suffice to record that they were
years of normal ungrowth. When Benjamin was
eighteen he was erect as a man of fifty; he
had more hair and it was of a dark gray; his
step was firm, his voice had lost its cracked
quaver and descended to a healthy baritone.
So his father sent him up to Connecticut to
take examinations for entrance to Yale College.
Benjamin passed his examination and became
a member of the freshman class.
On the third day following his matriculation
he received a notification from Mr. Hart,
the college registrar, to call at his office
and arrange his schedule. Benjamin, glancing
in the mirror, decided that his hair needed
a new application of its brown dye, but an
anxious inspection of his bureau drawer disclosed
that the dye bottle was not there. Then he
remembered - he had emptied it the day before
and thrown it away.
He was in a dilemma. He was due at the registrar's
in five minutes. There seemed to be no help
for it - he must go as he was. He did.
"Good - morning," said the registrar politely.
"You've come to inquire about your son."
"Why, as a matter of fact, my name's Button
-" began Benjamin, but Mr. Hart cut him off.
"I'm very glad to meet you, Mr. Button. I'm
expecting your son here any minute."
"That's me!" burst out Benjamin. "I'm a freshman."
"What!"
"I'm a freshman."
"Surely you're joking."
"Not at all."
The registrar frowned and glanced at a card
before him. "Why, I have Mr. Benjamin Button's
age down here as eighteen."
"That's my age," asserted Benjamin, flushing
slightly.
The registrar eyed him wearily. "Now surely,
Mr. Button, you don't expect me to believe
that."
Benjamin smiled wearily. "I am eighteen,"
he repeated.
The registrar pointed sternly to the door.
"Get out," he said. "Get out of college and
get out of town. You are a dangerous lunatic."
"I am eighteen."
Mr. Hart opened the door. "The idea!" he shouted.
"A man of your age trying to enter here as
a freshman. Eighteen years old, are you? Well,
I'll give you eighteen minutes to get out
of town."
Benjamin Button walked with dignity from the
room, and half a dozen undergraduates, who
were waiting in the hall, followed him curiously
with their eyes. When he had gone a little
way he turned around, faced the infuriated
registrar, who was still standing in the door
- way, and repeated in a firm voice: "I am
eighteen years old."
To a chorus of titters which went up from
the group of undergraduates, Benjamin walked
away.
But he was not fated to escape so easily.
On his melancholy walk to the railroad station
he found that he was being followed by a group,
then by a swarm, and finally by a dense mass
of undergraduates. The word had gone around
that a lunatic had passed the entrance examinations
for Yale and attempted to palm himself off
as a youth of eighteen. A fever of excitement
permeated the college. Men ran hatless out
of classes, the football team abandoned its
practice and joined the mob, professors' wives
with bonnets awry and bustles out of position,
ran shouting after the procession, from which
proceeded a continual succession of remarks
aimed at the tender sensibilities of Benjamin
Button.
"He must be the Wandering Jew!"
"He ought to go to prep school at his age!"
"Look at the infant prodigy!"
"He thought this was the old men's home."
"Go up to Harvard!"
Benjamin increased his gait, and soon he was
running. He would show them! He would go to
Harvard, and then they would regret these
ill - considered taunts!
Safely on board the train for Baltimore, he
put his head from the window. "You'll regret
this!" he shouted.
"Ha - ha!" the undergraduates laughed. "Ha
- ha - ha!" It was the biggest mistake that
Yale College had ever made...
CHAPTER FIVE
In 1880 Benjamin Button was twenty years old,
and he signalised his birthday by going to
work for his father in Roger Button & Co.,
Wholesale Hardware. It was in that same year
that he began "going out socially" - that
is, his father insisted on taking him to several
fashionable dances. Roger Button was now fifty,
and he and his son were more and more companionable
- in fact, since Benjamin had ceased to dye
his hair (which was still grayish) they appeared
about the same age, and could have passed
for brothers.
One night in August they got into the phaeton
attired in their full - dress suits and drove
out to a dance at the Shevlins' country house,
situated just outside of Baltimore. It was
a gorgeous evening. A full moon drenched the
road to the lustreless colour of platinum,
and late - blooming harvest flowers breathed
into the motionless air aromas that were like
low, half - heard laughter. The open country,
carpeted for rods around with bright wheat,
was translucent as in the day. It was almost
impossible not to be affected by the sheer
beauty of the sky - almost.
"There's a great future in the dry - goods
business," Roger Button was saying. He was
not a spiritual man - his aesthetic sense
was rudimentary.
"Old fellows like me can't learn new tricks,"
he observed profoundly. "It's you youngsters
with energy and vitality that have the great
future before you."
Far up the road the lights of the Shevlins'
country house drifted into view, and presently
there was a sighing sound that crept persistently
toward them - it might have been the fine
plaint of violins or the rustle of the silver
wheat under the moon.
They pulled up behind a handsome brougham
whose passengers were disembarking at the
door. A lady got out, then an elderly gentleman,
then another young lady, beautiful as sin.
Benjamin started; an almost chemical change
seemed to dissolve and recompose the very
elements of his body. A rigour passed over
him, blood rose into his cheeks, his forehead,
and there was a steady thumping in his ears.
It was first love.
The girl was slender and frail, with hair
that was ashen under the moon and honey - coloured
under the sputtering gas - lamps of the porch.
Over her shoulders was thrown a Spanish mantilla
of softest yellow, butterflied in black; her
feet were glittering buttons at the hem of
her bustled dress.
Roger Button leaned over to his son. "That,"
he said, "is young Hildegarde Moncrief, the
daughter of General Moncrief."
Benjamin nodded coldly. "Pretty little thing,"
he said indifferently. But when the negro
boy had led the buggy away, he added: "Dad,
you might introduce me to her."
They approached a group, of which Miss Moncrief
was the centre. Reared in the old tradition,
she curtsied low before Benjamin. Yes, he
might have a dance. He thanked her and walked
away - staggered away.
The interval until the time for his turn should
arrive dragged itself out interminably. He
stood close to the wall, silent, inscrutable,
watching with murderous eyes the young bloods
of Baltimore as they eddied around Hildegarde
Moncrief, passionate admiration in their faces.
How obnoxious they seemed to Benjamin; how
intolerably rosy! Their curling brown whiskers
aroused in him a feeling equivalent to indigestion.
But when his own time came, and he drifted
with her out upon the changing floor to the
music of the latest waltz from Paris, his
jealousies and anxieties melted from him like
a mantle of snow. Blind with enchantment,
he felt that life was just beginning.
"You and your brother got here just as we
did, didn't you?" asked Hildegarde, looking
up at him with eyes that were like bright
blue enamel.
Benjamin hesitated. If she took him for his
father's brother, would it be best to enlighten
her? He remembered his experience at Yale,
so he decided against it. It would be rude
to contradict a lady; it would be criminal
to mar this exquisite occasion with the grotesque
story of his origin. Later, perhaps. So he
nodded, smiled, listened, was happy.
"I like men of your age," Hildegarde told
him. "Young boys are so idiotic. They tell
me how much champagne they drink at college,
and how much money they lose playing cards.
Men of your age know how to appreciate women."
Benjamin felt himself on the verge of a proposal
- with an effort he choked back the impulse.
"You're just the romantic age," she continued
- "fifty. Twenty - five is too wordly - wise;
thirty is apt to be pale from overwork; forty
is the age of long stories that take a whole
cigar to tell; sixty is - oh, sixty is too
near seventy; but fifty is the mellow age.
I love fifty."
Fifty seemed to Benjamin a glorious age. He
longed passionately to be fifty.
"I've always said," went on Hildegarde, "that
I'd rather marry a man of fifty and be taken
care of than many a man of thirty and take
care of him."
For Benjamin the rest of the evening was bathed
in a honey - coloured mist. Hildegarde gave
him two more dances, and they discovered that
they were marvellously in accord on all the
questions of the day. She was to go driving
with him on the following Sunday, and then
they would discuss all these questions further.
Going home in the phaeton just before the
crack of dawn, when the first bees were humming
and the fading moon glimmered in the cool
dew, Benjamin knew vaguely that his father
was discussing wholesale hardware.
"... And what do you think should merit our
biggest attention after hammers and nails?"
the elder Button was saying.
"Love," replied Benjamin absent - mindedly.
"Lugs?" exclaimed Roger Button, "Why, I've
just covered the question of lugs."
Benjamin regarded him with dazed eyes just
as the eastern sky was suddenly cracked with
light, and an oriole yawned piercingly in
the quickening trees...
CHAPTER SIX
When, six months later, the engagement of
Miss Hildegarde Moncrief to Mr. Benjamin Button
was made known (I say "made known," for General
Moncrief declared he would rather fall upon
his sword than announce it), the excitement
in Baltimore society reached a feverish pitch.
The almost forgotten story of Benjamin's birth
was remembered and sent out upon the winds
of scandal in picaresque and incredible forms.
It was said that Benjamin was really the father
of Roger Button, that he was his brother who
had been in prison for forty years, that he
was John Wilkes Booth in disguise - and, finally,
that he had two small conical horns sprouting
from his head.
The Sunday supplements of the New York papers
played up the case with fascinating sketches
which showed the head of Benjamin Button attached
to a fish, to a snake, and, finally, to a
body of solid brass. He became known, journalistically,
as the Mystery Man of Maryland. But the true
story, as is usually the case, had a very
small circulation.
However, every one agreed with General Moncrief
that it was "criminal" for a lovely girl who
could have married any beau in Baltimore to
throw herself into the arms of a man who was
assuredly fifty. In vain Mr. Roger Button
published Us son's birth certificate in large
type in the Baltimore Blaze. No one believed
it. You had only to look at Benjamin and see.
On the part of the two people most concerned
there was no wavering. So many of the stories
about her fiance were false that Hildegarde
refused stubbornly to believe even the true
one. In vain General Moncrief pointed out
to her the high mortality among men of fifty
- or, at least, among men who looked fifty;
in vain he told her of the instability of
the wholesale hardware business. Hildegarde
had chosen to marry for mellowness, and marry
she did...
CHAPTER SEVEN
In one particular, at least, the friends of
Hildegarde Moncrief were mistaken. The wholesale
hardware business prospered amazingly. In
the fifteen years between Benjamin Button's
marriage in 1880 and his father's retirement
in 1895, the family fortune was doubled - and
this was due largely to the younger member
of the firm.
Needless to say, Baltimore eventually received
the couple to its bosom. Even old General
Moncrief became reconciled to his son - in
- law when Benjamin gave him the money to
bring out his History of the Civil War in
twenty volumes, which had been refused by
nine prominent publishers.
In Benjamin himself fifteen years had wrought
many changes. It seemed to him that the blood
flowed with new vigour through his veins.
It began to be a pleasure to rise in the morning,
to walk with an active step along the busy,
sunny street, to work untiringly with his
shipments of hammers and his cargoes of nails.
It was in 1890 that he executed his famous
business coup: he brought up the suggestion
that all nails used in nailing up the boxes
in which nails are shipped are the property
of the shippee, a proposal which became a
statute, was approved by Chief Justice Fossile,
and saved Roger Button and Company, Wholesale
Hardware, more than six hundred nails every
year.
In addition, Benjamin discovered that he was
becoming more and more attracted by the gay
side of life. It was typical of his growing
enthusiasm for pleasure that he was the first
man in the city of Baltimore to own and run
an automobile. Meeting him on the street,
his contemporaries would stare enviously at
the picture he made of health and vitality.
"He seems to grow younger every year," they
would remark. And if old Roger Button, now
sixty - five years old, had failed at first
to give a proper welcome to his son he atoned
at last by bestowing on him what amounted
to adulation.
And here we come to an unpleasant subject
which it will be well to pass over as quickly
as possible. There was only one thing that
worried Benjamin Button; his wife had ceased
to attract him.
At that time Hildegarde was a woman of thirty
- five, with a son, Roscoe, fourteen years
old. In the early days of their marriage Benjamin
had worshipped her. But, as the years passed,
her honey - coloured hair became an unexciting
brown, the blue enamel of her eyes assumed
the aspect of cheap crockery - moreover, and,
most of all, she had become too settled in
her ways, too placid, too content, too anaemic
in her excitements, and too sober in her taste.
As a bride it been she who had "dragged" Benjamin
to dances and dinners - now conditions were
reversed. She went out socially with him,
but without enthusiasm, devoured already by
that eternal inertia which comes to live with
each of us one day and stays with us to the
end.
Benjamin's discontent waxed stronger. At the
outbreak of the Spanish - American War in
1898 his home had for him so little charm
that he decided to join the army. With his
business influence he obtained a commission
as captain, and proved so adaptable to the
work that he was made a major, and finally
a lieutenant - colonel just in time to participate
in the celebrated charge up San Juan Hill.
He was slightly wounded, and received a medal.
Benjamin had become so attached to the activity
and excitement of array life that he regretted
to give it up, but his business required attention,
so he resigned his commission and came home.
He was met at the station by a brass band
and escorted to his house.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Hildegarde, waving a large silk flag, greeted
him on the porch, and even as he kissed her
he felt with a sinking of the heart that these
three years had taken their toll. She was
a woman of forty now, with a faint skirmish
line of gray hairs in her head. The sight
depressed him.
Up in his room he saw his reflection in the
familiar mirror - he went closer and examined
his own face with anxiety, comparing it after
a moment with a photograph of himself in uniform
taken just before the war.
"Good Lord!" he said aloud. The process was
continuing. There was no doubt of it - he
looked now like a man of thirty. Instead of
being delighted, he was uneasy - he was growing
younger. He had hitherto hoped that once he
reached a bodily age equivalent to his age
in years, the grotesque phenomenon which had
marked his birth would cease to function.
He shuddered. His destiny seemed to him awful,
incredible.
When he came downstairs Hildegarde was waiting
for him. She appeared annoyed, and he wondered
if she had at last discovered that there was
something amiss. It was with an effort to
relieve the tension between them that he broached
the matter at dinner in what he considered
a delicate way.
"Well," he remarked lightly, "everybody says
I look younger than ever."
Hildegarde regarded him with scorn. She sniffed.
"Do you think it's anything to boast about?"
"I'm not boasting," he asserted uncomfortably.
She sniffed again. "The idea," she said, and
after a moment: "I should think you'd have
enough pride to stop it."
"How can I?" he demanded.
"I'm not going to argue with you," she retorted.
"But there's a right way of doing things and
a wrong way. If you've made up your mind to
be different from everybody else, I don't
suppose I can stop you, but I really don't
think it's very considerate."
"But, Hildegarde, I can't help it."
"You can too. You're simply stubborn. You
think you don't want to be like any one else.
You always have been that way, and you always
will be. But just think how it would be if
every one else looked at things as you do
- what would the world be like?"
As this was an inane and unanswerable argument
Benjamin made no reply, and from that time
on a chasm began to widen between them. He
wondered what possible fascination she had
ever exercised over him.
To add to the breach, he found, as the new
century gathered headway, that his thirst
for gaiety grew stronger. Never a party of
any kind in the city of Baltimore but he was
there, dancing with the prettiest of the young
married women, chatting with the most popular
of the debutantes, and finding their company
charming, while his wife, a dowager of evil
omen, sat among the chaperons, now in haughty
disapproval, and now following him with solemn,
puzzled, and reproachful eyes.
"Look!" people would remark. "What a pity!
A young fellow that age tied to a woman of
forty - five. He must be twenty years younger
than his wife." They had forgotten - as people
inevitably forget - that back in 1880 their
mammas and papas had also remarked about this
same ill - matched pair.
Benjamin's growing unhappiness at home was
compensated for by his many new interests.
He took up golf and made a great success of
it. He went in for dancing: in 1906 he was
an expert at "The Boston," and in 1908 he
was considered proficient at the "Maxine,"
while in 1909 his "Castle Walk" was the envy
of every young man in town.
His social activities, of course, interfered
to some extent with his business, but then
he had worked hard at wholesale hardware for
twenty - five years and felt that he could
soon hand it on to his son, Roscoe, who had
recently graduated from Harvard.
He and his son were, in fact, often mistaken
for each other. This pleased Benjamin - he
soon forgot the insidious fear which had come
over him on his return from the Spanish - American
War, and grew to take a naive pleasure in
his appearance. There was only one fly in
the delicious ointment - he hated to appear
in public with his wife. Hildegarde was almost
fifty, and the sight of her made him feel
absurd...
CHAPTER NINE
One September day in 1910 - a few years after
Roger Button & Co., Wholesale Hardware, had
been handed over to young Roscoe Button - a
man, apparently about twenty years old, entered
himself as a freshman at Harvard University
in Cambridge. He did not make the mistake
of announcing that he would never see fifty
again, nor did he mention the fact that his
son had been graduated from the same institution
ten years before.
He was admitted, and almost immediately attained
a prominent position in the class, partly
because he seemed a little older than the
other freshmen, whose average age was about
eighteen.
But his success was largely due to the fact
that in the football game with Yale he played
so brilliantly, with so much dash and with
such a cold, remorseless anger that he scored
seven touchdowns and fourteen field goals
for Harvard, and caused one entire eleven
of Yale men to be carried singly from the
field, unconscious. He was the most celebrated
man in college.
Strange to say, in his third or junior year
he was scarcely able to "make" the team. The
coaches said that he had lost weight, and
it seemed to the more observant among them
that he was not quite as tall as before. He
made no touchdowns - indeed, he was retained
on the team chiefly in hope that his enormous
reputation would bring terror and disorganisation
to the Yale team.
In his senior year he did not make the team
at all. He had grown so slight and frail that
one day he was taken by some sophomores for
a freshman, an incident which humiliated him
terribly. He became known as something of
a prodigy - a senior who was surely no more
than sixteen - and he was often shocked at
the worldliness of some of his classmates.
His studies seemed harder to him - he felt
that they were too advanced. He had heard
his classmates speak of St. Midas's, the famous
preparatory school, at which so many of them
had prepared for college, and he determined
after his graduation to enter himself at St.
Midas's, where the sheltered life among boys
his own size would be more congenial to him.
Upon his graduation in 1914 he went home to
Baltimore with his Harvard diploma in his
pocket. Hildegarde was now residing in Italy,
so Benjamin went to live with his son, Roscoe.
But though he was welcomed in a general way
there was obviously no heartiness in Roscoe's
feeling toward him - there was even perceptible
a tendency on his son's part to think that
Benjamin, as he moped about the house in adolescent
mooniness, was somewhat in the way. Roscoe
was married now and prominent in Baltimore
life, and he wanted no scandal to creep out
in connection with his family.
Benjamin, no longer persona grata with the
debutantes and younger college set, found
himself left much done, except for the companionship
of three or four fifteen - year - old boys
in the neighbourhood. His idea of going to
St. Midas's school recurred to him.
"Say," he said to Roscoe one day, "I've told
you over and over that I want to go to prep,
school."
"Well, go, then," replied Roscoe shortly.
The matter was distasteful to him, and he
wished to avoid a discussion.
"I can't go alone," said Benjamin helplessly.
"You'll have to enter me and take me up there."
"I haven't got time," declared Roscoe abruptly.
His eyes narrowed and he looked uneasily at
his father. "As a matter of fact," he added,
"you'd better not go on with this business
much longer. You better pull up short. You
better - you better" - he paused and his face
crimsoned as he sought for words - "you better
turn right around and start back the other
way. This has gone too far to be a joke. It
isn't funny any longer. You - you behave yourself!"
Benjamin looked at him, on the verge of tears.
"And another thing," continued Roscoe, "when
visitors are in the house I want you to call
me 'Uncle' - not 'Roscoe,' but 'Uncle,' do
you understand? It looks absurd for a boy
of fifteen to call me by my first name. Perhaps
you'd better call me 'Uncle' all the time,
so you'll get used to it."
With a harsh look at his father, Roscoe turned
away...
CHAPTER TEN
At the termination of this interview, Benjamin
wandered dismally upstairs and stared at himself
in the mirror. He had not shaved for three
months, but he could find nothing on his face
but a faint white down with which it seemed
unnecessary to meddle. When he had first come
home from Harvard, Roscoe had approached him
with the proposition that he should wear eye
- glasses and imitation whiskers glued to
his cheeks, and it had seemed for a moment
that the farce of his early years was to be
repeated. But whiskers had itched and made
him ashamed. He wept and Roscoe had reluctantly
relented.
Benjamin opened a book of boys' stories, The
Boy Scouts in Bimini Bay, and began to read.
But he found himself thinking persistently
about the war. America had joined the Allied
cause during the preceding month, and Benjamin
wanted to enlist, but, alas, sixteen was the
minimum age, and he did not look that old.
His true age, which was fifty - seven, would
have disqualified him, anyway.
There was a knock at his door, and the butler
appeared with a letter bearing a large official
legend in the corner and addressed to Mr.
Benjamin Button. Benjamin tore it open eagerly,
and read the enclosure with delight. It informed
him that many reserve officers who had served
in the Spanish - American War were being called
back into service with a higher rank, and
it enclosed his commission as brigadier - general
in the United States army with orders to report
immediately.
Benjamin jumped to his feet fairly quivering
with enthusiasm. This was what he had wanted.
He seized his cap, and ten minutes later he
had entered a large tailoring establishment
on Charles Street, and asked in his uncertain
treble to be measured for a uniform.
"Want to play soldier, sonny?" demanded a
clerk casually.
Benjamin flushed. "Say! Never mind what I
want!" he retorted angrily. "My name's Button
and I live on Mt. Vernon Place, so you know
I'm good for it."
"Well," admitted the clerk hesitantly, "if
you're not, I guess your daddy is, all right."
Benjamin was measured, and a week later his
uniform was completed. He had difficulty in
obtaining the proper general's insignia because
the dealer kept insisting to Benjamin that
a nice Y.M.C.A. badge would look just as well
and be much more fun to play with.
Saying nothing to Roscoe, he left the house
one night and proceeded by train to Camp Mosby,
in South Carolina, where he was to command
an infantry brigade. On a sultry April day
he approached the entrance to the camp, paid
off the taxicab which had brought him from
the station, and turned to the sentry on guard.
"Get some one to handle my luggage!" he said
briskly.
The sentry eyed him reproachfully. "Say,"
he remarked, "where you goin' with the general's
duds, sonny?"
Benjamin, veteran of the Spanish - American
War, whirled upon him with fire in his eye,
but with, alas, a changing treble voice.
"Come to attention!" he tried to thunder;
he paused for breath - then suddenly he saw
the sentry snap his heels together and bring
his rifle to the present. Benjamin concealed
a smile of gratification, but when he glanced
around his smile faded. It was not he who
had inspired obedience, but an imposing artillery
colonel who was approaching on horseback.
"Colonel!" called Benjamin shrilly.
The colonel came up, drew rein, and looked
coolly down at him with a twinkle in his eyes.
"Whose little boy are you?" he demanded kindly.
"I'll soon darn well show you whose little
boy I am!" retorted Benjamin in a ferocious
voice. "Get down off that horse!"
The colonel roared with laughter.
"You want him, eh, general?"
"Here!" cried Benjamin desperately. "Read
this." And he thrust his commission toward
the colonel.
The colonel read it, his eyes popping from
their sockets.
"Where'd you get this?" he demanded, slipping
the document into his own pocket.
"I got it from the Government, as you'll soon
find out!"
"You come along with me," said the colonel
with a peculiar look. "We'll go up to headquarters
and talk this over. Come along."
The colonel turned and began walking his horse
in the direction of headquarters. There was
nothing for Benjamin to do but follow with
as much dignity as possible - meanwhile promising
himself a stern revenge.
But this revenge did not materialise. Two
days later, however, his son Roscoe materialised
from Baltimore, hot and cross from a hasty
trip, and escorted the weeping general, sans
uniform, back to his home.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
In 1920 Roscoe Button's first child was born.
During the attendant festivities, however,
no one thought it "the thing" to mention,
that the little grubby boy, apparently about
ten years of age who played around the house
with lead soldiers and a miniature circus,
was the new baby's own grandfather.
No one disliked the little boy whose fresh,
cheerful face was crossed with just a hint
of sadness, but to Roscoe Button his presence
was a source of torment. In the idiom of his
generation Roscoe did not consider the matter
"efficient." It seemed to him that his father,
in refusing to look sixty, had not behaved
like a "red-blooded he-man" - this was Roscoe's
favourite expression - but in a curious and
perverse manner. Indeed, to think about the
matter for as much as a half an hour drove
him to the edge of insanity. Roscoe believed
that "live wires" should keep young, but carrying
it out on such a scale was - was - was inefficient.
And there Roscoe rested.
Five years later Roscoe's little boy had grown
old enough to play childish games with little
Benjamin under the supervision of the same
nurse. Roscoe took them both to kindergarten
on the same day, and Benjamin found that playing
with little strips of coloured paper, making
mats and chains and curious and beautiful
designs, was the most fascinating game in
the world. Once he was bad and had to stand
in the corner - then he cried - but for the
most part there were gay hours in the cheerful
room, with the sunlight coming in the windows
and Miss Bailey's kind hand resting for a
moment now and then in his tousled hair.
Roscoe's son moved up into the first grade
after a year, but Benjamin stayed on in the
kindergarten. He was very happy. Sometimes
when other tots talked about what they would
do when they grew up a shadow would cross
his little face as if in a dim, childish way
he realised that those were things in which
he was never to share.
The days flowed on in monotonous content.
He went back a third year to the kindergarten,
but he was too little now to understand what
the bright shining strips of paper were for.
He cried because the other boys were bigger
than he, and he was afraid of them. The teacher
talked to him, but though he tried to understand
he could not understand at all.
He was taken from the kindergarten. His nurse,
Nana, in her starched gingham dress, became
the centre of his tiny world. On bright days
they walked in the park; Nana would point
at a great gray monster and say "elephant,"
and Benjamin would say it after her, and when
he was being undressed for bed that night
he would say it over and over aloud to her:
"Elyphant, elyphant, elyphant." Sometimes
Nana let him jump on the bed, which was fun,
because if you sat down exactly right it would
bounce you up on your feet again, and if you
said "Ah" for a long time while you jumped
you got a very pleasing broken vocal effect.
He loved to take a big cane from the hat - rack
and go around hitting chairs and tables with
it and saying: "Fight, fight, fight." When
there were people there the old ladies would
cluck at him, which interested him, and the
young ladies would try to kiss him, which
he submitted to with mild boredom. And when
the long day was done at five o'clock he would
go upstairs with Nana and be fed on oatmeal
and nice soft mushy foods with a spoon.
There were no troublesome memories in his
childish sleep; no token came to him of his
brave days at college, of the glittering years
when he flustered the hearts of many girls.
There were only the white, safe walls of his
crib and Nana and a man who came to see him
sometimes, and a great big orange ball that
Nana pointed at just before his twilight bed
hour and called "sun." When the sun went his
eyes were sleepy - there were no dreams, no
dreams to haunt him.
The past - the wild charge at the head of
his men up San Juan Hill; the first years
of his marriage when he worked late into the
summer dusk down in the busy city for young
Hildegarde whom he loved; the days before
that when he sat smoking far into the night
in the gloomy old Button house on Monroe Street
with his grandfather - all these had faded
like unsubstantial dreams from his mind as
though they had never been. He did not remember.
He did not remember clearly whether the milk
was warm or cool at his last feeding or how
the days passed - there was only his crib
and Nana's familiar presence. And then he
remembered nothing. When he was hungry he
cried - that was all. Through the noons and
nights he breathed and over him there were
soft mumblings and murmurings that he scarcely
heard, and faintly differentiated smells,
and light and darkness.
Then it was all dark, and his white crib and
the dim faces that moved above him, and the
warm sweet aroma of the milk, faded out altogether
from his mind.
- THE END -