Pauline Attenborough was seventy-two
years old, but she looked much younger.
When a soft light shone on her, she could look as
young as thirty. She had a lovely figure and face,
and her nose was a very good shape. Only
her big grey eyes made her look older.
Pauline had left her husband, Ronald, many
years ago. Pauline and Ronald had had two sons,
Henry and Robert. Henry, the older
son, had died when Robert was only ten.
Now Robert was thirty-two. He lived with
his mother and worked as a lawyer in London.
Robert Attenborough did not earn very much money,
but this was not a problem.
His mother was a rich woman.
Pauline's niece, Ciss, also lived in the house.
Her father, Ronald Attenborough's brother,
had died five years ago. Ciss
had no money or home of her own.
She needed a place to live. So
she depended on her Aunt Pauline.
Ciss was a big young woman, with
dark hair and eyes. She was very shy.
She was in love with her cousin, Robert,
but she had never told him this. Robert was
also very shy. He had no confidence in himself.
Pauline, Robert and Ciss lived
together quietly, in a lovely house
about twenty-five miles from London. The
house was surrounded by pleasant gardens.
It was the perfect house and the perfect life for
Pauline. Every day, Robert went to work in London.
Then when he came home, the three of them -
Pauline, Robert and Ciss - ate dinner together.
During dinner, there were always candles
on the table. Pauline liked candles because
the soft candlelight made her look
young and beautiful. The soft light
shone on the skin of her bare arms and the
soft material of her dress. Pauline shone
with happiness. She looked like a beautiful
woman of only thirty-two or thirty-three.
After dinner, they had coffee
in the warm drawing room.
The room was full of lovely furniture. For
many years, Pauline had collected furniture
and beautiful, unusual pictures
from many different countries.
She had sold these things to museums for a
lot of money. This had made her a rich woman.
Pauline, Robert and Ciss chatted together
pleasantly. Their conversation was always
simple and bright. Then at half-past eight, Ciss
carried the tray of coffee things out of the room.
Robert always stayed and
continued chatting to his mother.
He always listened to everything that she said.
At the side of the house, there was a large
courtyard. Ciss had a flat just across the
courtyard, above the old coach house and
stables. Several years ago, a carriage
and horses had been kept in these buildings.
Now Robert kept his car in the coach-house.
Ciss did not always go to her flat after dinner.
In summer, she sometimes sat outside in the
large garden. She listened to Pauline's
laughter coming from the drawing room.
In winter, Ciss put on a thick coat and walked
through the garden and down to the little
bridge over the stream. She liked to hear the
water running under the bridge. She would look
back at the lighted windows of the drawing room,
where Pauline and Robert were so happy together.
Ciss loved Robert. 'I believe that Pauline
wants Robert to marry me when she dies,'
she thought. 'But Robert is very shy. Perhaps his
mother won't die for many years. By that time,
it will be too late. Robert will be just
an empty man who never enjoyed his life.'
Sometimes Ciss stayed in the dark garden until
about ten o'clock, when she saw the light go on
in Pauline's bedroom. Robert usually stayed in the
drawing room for another hour, then he would go to
bed too. Ciss, standing in the garden, wanted to
go to him. She wanted to say, 'Oh, Robert! This is
all wrong!' But she could not do this because Aunt
Pauline would hear. So she went to her own rooms.
In the mornings, Robert went to
London at about nine o'clock.
Pauline rested in bed. She
came downstairs at lunchtime.
Sometimes she did not leave her bedroom until
teatime. But she always looked fresh and young.
Pauline always had a rest in the afternoons. When
the sun shone, she liked to lie outside and bathe
in the warm sun. Behind the stables,
there was a second, smaller courtyard,
which was surrounded by trees. The sun
shone right down into this little courtyard,
so it was a perfect place for sunbathing. Here,
Ciss put a chair for Pauline to lie on, a large
umbrella and blankets. If the sun became too hot,
Pauline could lie in the shade of the umbrella.
One afternoon, Ciss decided to sunbathe
too. She found a ladder and climbed up
onto the flat roof of the stables. Then she lay
down on a blanket in one corner of the roof.
The sun shone brightly here and it was
very hot. Ciss was above Aunt Pauline,
who lay in the little courtyard below. But Pauline
did not know that Ciss was on the roof above her.
It was lovely, lying in the warm sun and air.
The warmth of the sun on her legs
and arms made Ciss feel comfortable
and relaxed. Suddenly she heard a voice speaking
softly and her heart jumped with fear and shock.
'No, Henry dear!' said the voice. 'It was not my
fault that you died instead of marrying Claudia.'
The voice did not sound human. Where was it coming
from? There must be someone on the roof! Ciss
lifted her head and looked around. But
there was nobody on the roof with her.
Suddenly she heard the soft voice again.
'No, darling! I said that you would be tired of
her in six months! I warned you, and it was true.
I couldn't do anything more. And you
died without ever knowing me again.'
The voice was silent. Ciss lay on her blanket.
It was a beautiful summer afternoon. Did the
voice belong to a ghost? Ciss hated
the idea of ghosts, spirits and magic.
Then she heard a deep sigh and
the strange voice spoke again.
'Ah, well, a heart must feel pain!
But it wasn't my fault, dear.
It is better for a heart to feel pain,
rather than break from sorrow. And Robert
could marry poor, boring Ciss tomorrow, if
he wanted to. But he doesn't care about her.'
Ciss sat up quickly. She was very surprised. It
was Aunt Pauline talking! It must be Aunt Pauline!
Where was she? And how was Ciss hearing her
strange whispers? Aunt Pauline must be lying
right below her. And she must be using a trick
to make her voice sound strange. Aunt Pauline
was trying to frighten her! Ciss was still
afraid, but she was now thinking more clearly.
Ciss lay down again. She knew the story of Henry,
Robert's older brother. Henry had been in love
with Claudia, a beautiful young actress. But his
mother had been against Claudia and had laughed
at Henry. Henry had become ill with a brain
disease and died at the age of twenty two.
'I think that I should get up
now,' the voice was saying.
'I've had enough sun. A woman might live forever
if she has enough sun, love and good food.
I truly believe a good life
will make me live forever.'
'That is certainly Aunt Pauline's
voice,' Ciss said to herself.
'How horrible! I'm hearing
Aunt Pauline's thoughts.'
Ciss turned and looked down in front of her.
She was staring at a hole in the corner of
the roof. The lead gutter, the pipe for taking
away the rainwater, went down into this hole.
The water then came out of the
rain pipe, near the ground.
Suddenly a sigh and a
whisper came out of the hole.
'Ah well, Pauline! Get up.
You've had enough sun today.'
Now Ciss understood. Aunt Pauline was
lying below her and the rain pipe was
carrying her voice up to the roof! Aunt
Pauline was speaking her thoughts aloud.
She did not know that the sound of
her voice was going up to the roof.
So Aunt Pauline was feeling
guilty about Henry's death.
He had died and she thought that it was her fault.
Ciss believed that Pauline had loved her big,
handsome son Henry, more than she
loved Robert. Henry's death had been
a terrible shock for Pauline. She only
loved Robert because Henry was dead.
Ciss put on her clothes, picked up her
blanket, and carefully climbed down the ladder.
As she went down, she heard her aunt calling,
'All right, Ciss!' The lovely lady had finished
sunbathing. She was returning to the house.
Ciss went into the small courtyard. She
picked up Pauline's blankets and the chair
and put them in the house. Then she
looked for the opening of the rain pipe.
She found it in the corner of
two walls of the stable building.
The mouth of the rain pipe was almost
hidden by the leaves of a plant on the wall.
When Pauline sat in her chair and turned her
face to the wall, her mouth would be near to
the rain pipe. Ciss had heard her aunt's voice.
No ghosts, spirits, or magic had made the voice.
That evening, after they had drunk
their coffee, Pauline stood up.
'The sun has made me so sleepy today,' she said.
'I shall go to bed now. You two sit and chat.'
When Pauline had gone to bed,
Ciss turned towards Robert.
'Do you remember your brother,
Henry?' she asked him.
Robert looked at her in surprise.
'Yes, very well,' he said.
'What was he like?' asked Ciss.
'Tall and handsome, with
soft brown hair like mother,'
Robert said. 'Women liked him.
Henry was very happy and clever.'
'Did he love your mother?'
'Very much,' Robert said. 'She loved
him too - more than she loves me.'
'Robert,' Ciss said. 'Do you like me?'
Ciss saw Robert's face become pale.
'Yes,' Robert said. 'I like you very much.'
'Will you kiss me? Nobody
ever kisses me,' Ciss said.
Robert looked at his cousin with
fear in his eyes. Then he stood up
and kissed her gently on the cheek. Ciss held
Robert's hand and pressed it against her breast.
'Come and sit with me in the garden,' she said.
'But what about mother?' he
said. He was nervous and shy.
Ciss smiled a little and looked into his
eyes. Suddenly Robert's face became red.
A few minutes later, she left
him and went to her flat.
The sunny weather continued. It was now
July. Every afternoon, Pauline sunbathed
in the small courtyard. And Ciss lay on
the roof above the stables, listening.
But the sound of Pauline's voice
did not come up the pipe again.
After dinner in the evenings,
Ciss waited in the garden.
She saw the light go on in her aunt's bedroom.
She saw the lights go out in the drawing room.
She waited, but Robert did not come
into the garden. Then one night,
he came out and walked towards her. Ciss stood
up and walked softly over the grass to him.
'Don't speak,' Robert whispered.
They stood together, looking up
at the stars in the dark sky.
'How can I ask you to love me?'
he said. 'And how can I marry?
I haven't made much money. And I
can't ask my mother for money.'
'Then don't worry about marrying yet,'
Ciss said. 'But do love me a little.'
Robert gave a short laugh.
'It's hard to begin,' he said.
They sat down and he held her hand. At last,
she said goodnight, stood up, and went indoors.
The next day, Ciss lay on the roof, sunbathing.
Suddenly she heard her aunt's voice
from the hole in the lead gutter.
First Pauline spoke in Italian,
then she spoke in English.
'No, Robert dear,' said Pauline's voice. 'You
will never be the same kind of man as your
father. But you look like him. Mauro was a
wonderful lover. Mauro! Mauro! How you loved me!'
The voice stopped speaking. Ciss realized
that her aunt had a secret. Pauline's husband,
Ronald, had not been Robert's father! Robert's
father had been an Italian man called Mauro.
'I'm disappointed with you, Robert,'
continued Pauline's voice. 'Your father was a
priest, but he was the best lover in the world.
You are like a cold fish. And Ciss is
like a cat who is trying to catch you.'
Ciss suddenly put her mouth near the hole
in the rain pipe and spoke. 'Leave Robert
alone!' she said in a deep
voice. 'Don't kill him too.'
There was a silence. The hot afternoon
sun shone on the flat roof of the stables.
Ciss listened, with her heart beating quickly.
At last, she heard her aunt Pauline
whisper the words, 'Did someone speak?'
Ciss spoke again into the hole of the lead gutter.
'You killed me,' she said in a deep,
terrible voice. 'Don't kill Robert too!'
'Ah!' said Pauline, giving a
little cry. 'Who's speaking?'
'Henry!' said Ciss in the same, deep voice.
There was silence again.
'I didn't kill you, Henry,' said Pauline.
'No! No! Henry, it wasn't my fault. I loved
you, my dearest boy. I only wanted to help you.'
'You killed me!' Ciss said in the deep voice.
Now, let Robert live. Let him go! Let him marry!'
'Henry!' said Pauline. Are you a ghost?
Have you come to punish me for your death?'
'YES! I HAVE COME TO PUNISH YOU!' said
Ciss in a terrible, frightening voice.
She was very angry with Pauline. She felt that
her anger was going down the rain pipe to her
aunt. At the same time, she almost laughed.
This was a very funny conversation!
Ciss lay and listened. No sound came from the
rain pipe. The afternoon had become cooler.
Yellow and grey clouds had covered the sun.
There was a roar of thunder. A storm was coming.
Ciss dressed quickly, went down the ladder,
and ran to the corner of the stables.
'Aunt Pauline!' she called.
'Did you hear thunder?'
'Y-yes! I am going indoors,' her aunt
replied in a weak voice. 'Don't wait for me.'
Ciss watched her aunt go inside the house.
The sky was growing darker. Ciss took the
blankets and the chair and hurried inside.
Then the storm began. Pauline did not come
downstairs to tea because she did not like
thunder. Robert did not arrive home until after
tea. By this time, the rain was pouring down.
Ciss went to her flat and got ready for dinner.
She put on a pretty white dress and fastened some
white flowers at her breast. When she went
into the drawing room, Robert was waiting.
He was standing by the drawing-room
window and listening to the rain falling.
He now had a different look
on his face as he watched her.
The drawing room was lit by the soft light of a
table lamp. Ciss walked towards the bookshelves
near the door. When she heard the door opening
softly, Ciss suddenly turned on the switch of
the ceiling light. Her aunt, wearing a black
dress, stood in the doorway. The strong, hard
light showed her face clearly. Pauline was wearing
make-up, but her face looked old and full of hate.
'Oh, aunt!' cried Ciss.
'Mother, you look like a little old
lady!' said Robert in a shocked voice.
'Aren't we going to eat
dinner?' asked Pauline angrily.
Pauline sat at the table, getting angrier and
angrier. She looked very, very old and very ugly.
Ciss and Robert watched each other. He was very
shocked by his mother's face. Pauline ate her
dinner quickly, like a hungry dog. As soon as they
had finished eating, she ran towards the stairs.
Robert and Ciss followed her from the room.
'You pour the coffee. I hate it,' said the old
woman quickly. 'I'm going to bed! Goodnight!'
There was silence.
At last, Robert said, 'I'm afraid that
mother isn't well. She must see a doctor.'
'Yes,' said Ciss.
The rest of the evening passed in silence.
Robert and Ciss stayed in the drawing room. A
fire was lit. Outside, cold rain was falling.
At about ten o'clock, the door opened
and Pauline came into the room.
She shut the door and came to the fire. Then she
looked at Robert and Ciss with hate in her eyes.
'You two should get married quickly,' she said
in an ugly voice. 'You are so much in love.'
Robert looked up at his mother. 'You
believed that cousins should not marry,
Mother,' he said quietly.
'You told me that often.'
'I do believe that cousins shouldn't marry,'
replied Pauline. 'But you're not cousins.
Your father was an Italian priest, Robert.
He was a great man. And he was too
great to have a weak son like you.'
With a terrible look on her
face, Pauline left the room.
Pauline had gone mad. Her madness continued
for a week. The doctor came and told her that
she must sleep. He gave her drugs to help her.
But she did not take the medicine. She walked
about her room, looking ugly and full of hate.
She would not look at either Robert or Ciss.
At first, Ciss was frightened by what she
had done. She realized that her trick had
made her aunt mad. Ciss almost felt sorry
for the terrible thing that she had done.
Then she thought, 'This woman is the real
Pauline. We never saw her true character before.'
But Pauline was not going to live
long. She stayed in her room, and did
not see anyone. She had her mirrors taken
away. She did not want to look at herself.
Robert and Ciss spent a lot of time together.
But Ciss could not tell Robert
what she had done. She was afraid.
'Do you think that your mother ever loved
anybody?' Ciss asked him one evening.
'Mother only loved herself!'
Robert said. 'And she loved power.
She got her power by controlling other people's
lives. She was beautiful, and she grew strong
by controlling everyone and everything. She
destroyed Henry and she was destroying me.'
'And don't you forgive her?' asked Ciss.
'No, I don't. She took other people's
hopes and happiness and destroyed them.'
Two days later, Pauline died.
Ciss found her dead, in her bed. Pauline's
heart had become weak, and the drugs that she
took were too strong for her. But after her death,
Pauline got her revenge on her son and her niece.
Pauline Attenborough was a very rich woman, but
she left Robert only one thousand pounds. And
she left Ciss only one hundred pounds.
The rest of her money went to a museum.
She had built a museum and given it her own
name - the Pauline Attenborough Museum.
- THE END -