CHAPTER ONE
Exiled from London
Dear Will, do you remember me?
I am Frank Osbaldistone and I want to narrate
the adventurous story of my early life.
It was the year 1714 and I was about twenty.
My father ordered me to come back from Bordeaux,
France, where I worked and to return to London.
My father was the founder of the business
house Osbaldistone & Tresham, with offices
in Crane Alley, London.
He was a tall man, full of energy, with dark,
penetrating eyes.
He had a fiery spirit, full of initiative
and acute powers of analysis.
He never used a word in vain, and he never
got really angry, but when he was displeased,
he spoke in a brusque manner.
My father wanted me to become his successor
in the family business, but I preferred to
study literature and write poems.
He tried everything to convince me to change
my mind and eventually threatened, "I have
a brother in Northumberland and he too has
children, Frank.
I will ask one of your cousins to take your
place in the business, if you do not obey
me."
Showing little respect for his wishes, I replied,
"You can do as you please - the business is
yours!
I will never sell my liberty for gold!"
As I was very obstinate, in the end my father
decided to send me to his brother at Osbaldistone
Hall in the north of England.
The following morning I took the road to York,
mounted on a good horse and with sixty guineas
in my pocket.
I was sad, but I did not want to go back to
London.
I wanted to show my father that I was adult
enough to decide for myself and that I was
truly convinced of my decision.
The journey was monotonous, but sometimes
I had the opportunity to speak to different
travellers - parsons, farmers, officers.
We spoke of many different matters - taxes,
markets, wars and outlaws.
One man that I met, a Mr Morris, was particularly
afraid of outlaws.
He had a heavy portmanteau which he never
abandoned for a moment.
He never mentioned his destination, he trusted
nobody and he was afraid of me, too.
In those days travellers used to break their
journey on Sundays.
They rested their horses and had dinner together
at the local inn, where the innkeeper offered
them a meal.
On this particular Sunday I stopped at Darlington,
at the "Black Bear", with my new companion,
the strange Mr Morris.
A Scotsman, Mr Campbell, joined us for dinner.
It was the first time I had met a Scotsman
and I looked at him with curiosity because
I had many prejudices against the inhabitants
of Scotland.
When I was a child my nurse told me terrible
stories about them, of blood and revenge.
I considered the Scottish people dishonest,
avaricious and hostile to Englishmen.
Mr Campbell was a tall, athletic man who spoke
to other people with superiority.
Strangely, my timorous companion Mr Morris
asked if he could travel north with him, but
Mr Campbell refused.
"Your companion talks too much," he said.
"It is unsafe to say where you are going in
these troubled times."
CHAPTER TWO
The Osbaldistones
The following morning, I left the company
to go westward where my uncle lived in Osbaldistone
Hall.
The landscape was romantic and picturesque
and appealed to my love of nature.
I went past rivers and little solitary valleys
until I arrived at Osbaldistone Hall.
The house was in a glen between two mountains,
surrounded by a large wood of oaks.
I was on a hill above Osbaldistone Hall when
I heard the sound of dogs and horses - it
was a fox hunt.
I saw some men, dressed in green and red uniforms,
riding after the fox and I thought: 'Here
are my cousins.'
Suddenly I had a vision - a beautiful young
lady appeared in front of me.
Her face was uncommonly fine and animated
by the hunt.
She had long, black hair down to her shoulders.
She was wearing riding clothes, like a man,
and rode a splendid black horse.
Just then the sound of a horn announced the
end of the chase.
A young man came triumphantly towards us.
He was carrying the fox's tail in his hand.
The young woman spoke to him, then she turned
to me and said, "Excuse me, did you meet a
young man on the road, a Mr Osbaldistone?"
"I am Francis Osbaldistone," I answered.
"Ah...
I'm pleased to meet you, Mr Osbaldistone.
This young man is Thorncliff Osbaldistone,
your cousin, and I am Diana Vernon," she continued.
Diana accompanied me to Osbaldistone Hall,
where my uncle, Sir Hildebrand Osbaldistone,
welcomed me.
He was a man of about sixty, dressed in hunting
clothes.
Once he had been a soldier and a knight under
King James II.
Alter the king's deposition, he retired to
his lands in the countryside where he was
lord.
"These are your cousins, Francis," he told
me.
"Percie, Thornie, John, Dick, Wilfred and
Rashleigh.
The girl you met earlier is Die Vernon, Diana,
my dead wife's niece.
She lives here too.
Now, shall we have dinner together?"
My cousins were all tall, well-built and good-humoured,
with the exception of Rashleigh.
He was different from the others - short,
thin, lame, and his expression was cruel.
However, these disadvantages were partly compensated
for by his very soft, sweet voice and his
great ability in putting words together.
Diana Vernon was sitting next to me at dinner
and gave me some information about my cousins.
"Rashleigh," she said, "wanted to become a
priest in the Roman Catholic Church, but his
deformity prevented him from entering the
seminary."
She also revealed that my father had chosen
Rashleigh to take my place in his company.
After dinner my cousins started to drink and
laugh immoderately.
As my foreign education had given me a dislike
for intemperance, I preferred to be alone
and decided to go for a walk in the garden.
On one of the little paths I met a gardener.
He touched his Scottish bonnet with an air
of respect.
"Good evening, my Lord!" he said.
"I am Andrew Fairservice.
For twenty-four years I have served the Osbaldistones."
He was very talkative.
He told me that he was a Presbyterian and
when he heard that I was an English dissenter,
he took out a tobacco box and offered me a
little.
I asked him about Die Vernon.
"Oh, the young mistress?
The lassie Vernon?" he answered.
"She is a Catholic and, what is worse, she
is a Jacobite!"
CHAPTER THREE
Accused of Robbery!
I went to bed that night, thinking about the
strange Osbaldistone family, my father, Rashleigh
and Die Vernon.
When I woke up, I heard the horn announcing
that the fox hunt was beginning again.
In the courtyard, where men, dogs and horses
were in full preparation, I met Die Vernon.
We left with the rest of the hunting party,
but after a few miles we were alone.
Die guided me to the top of a hill, and stopped
her horse under some trees.
She indicated some mountains on the far horizon.
She said that they were in Scotland and that
if necessary my horse could take me there
in two hours.
I was surprised.
I had no desire to go to Scotland.
"What should I do in Scotland?"
I asked.
"Provide for your safety..." she replied.
"Didn't you travel here with a man, a Mr Morris?"
the girl asked me then.
"Well... yes.
I travelled with a strange little man who
was always worried about his portmanteau,"
I answered, slowly.
"Someone stole that bag, Frank!"
explained Die.
"You do not think I am a thief!"
I replied, angrily.
"Mr Morris is an agent for the London government,"
she continued.
"He was carrying important documents and money
for the English soldiers in the north.
You are accused of robbery and of treason,
Frank Osbaldistone!"
"So, I am a traitor, too!"
I exclaimed angrily.
She saw I was angry and tried to console me.
"Around here many important people are in
favour of James II and against the Hanoverians,"
she said.
"Your crime is considered the crime of a gentleman
- and a kings man."
"But I want to refute this terrible accusation!
Who is examining my case?"
I demanded.
"Judge Ingle wood.
He told my uncle to show you the road to Scotland,"
replied Die.
"Then I must see him and tell him the truth!"
Diana insisted on accompanying me.
When we arrived, we were surprised to meet
Rashleigh coming out of Judge Ingle wood's
house.
The Judge was having lunch when we entered.
Another man was with him at the table - it
was Mr Morris, my timorous travelling companion.
He said that one of the robbers had mentioned
the name of Osbaldistone.
"But that is not a good reason to accuse me!"
I replied.
At that moment, the servant announced the
arrival of another gentleman and I was surprised
to see Mr Campbell, the other man I had met
on my journey north.
He explained to Judge Inglewood that he had
been with Mr Morris when the bandits attacked
him.
"Why didn't you help Mr Morris, then?" asked
the Judge.
"Mr Morris is strong enough to defend himself,"
he replied coldly.
"I am a man of peace.
I do not want to have trouble with the Law.
But of one thing I am sure - Mr Osbaldistone
was not one of the bandits who stole the bag."
At that point, Mr Morris retracted his accusations
against me and the Judge declared I was innocent.
Soon after, Mr Morris left the house with
Campbell.
Die Vernon and I rode back to Osbaldistone
Hall.
The girl started to tell me something of her
life.
She had many troubles, she said.
I tried to learn more but she replied mysteriously,
"I cannot reveal my secrets."
At Osbaldistone Hall, Die ordered dinner for
us in the library.
The ancient, dark library was full of books,
very untidy and neglected.
On one wall was a portrait of Die's grandfather,
Lord Vernon, with the Vernon motto above it.
He had been loyal to the Kings of the Stuart
dynasty, she said, and had shared the misfortunes
of Charles I.
The Vernon family, once important, was now
ruined.
During our meal, Rashleigh entered.
"I must thank you for calling Mr Campbell.
His defence saved me," I said.
I was curious and wanted to learn more about
the connection between Rashleigh and Campbell,
so we continued to talk until Diana went to
bed.
CHAPTER FOUR
New Troubles
The following day was Sunday, a dull day at
Osbaldistone Hall.
We all attended the formal religious service
in the morning and, when it was over, Sir
Hildebrand congratulated me.
"Ha ha!
So you did not go to prison after all, my
lad!
You were lucky this time - but do not tempt
Fate again!"
His words embarrassed and irritated me.
"On my honour, sir!"
I replied.
"I am innocent.
I was not involved in that detestable crime!"
I was saved from more embarrassment by the
arrival of Rashleigh.
He was leaving soon for London and wanted
to know more about my father, his relations
with me and about the business.
I, however, was more curious to find out about
Die Vernon.
"We were close friends once and I was her
tutor," he said.
"Then my studies took me far from her.
She must now decide between life in a convent
or a convenient marriage.
She is engaged to Thorncliff, my brother.
But I am convinced that I am better qualified
for her."
These words hurt me and that evening, when
I met Die, I was cold and rude to her.
At dinner I drank too much and so I talked
too much, quarrelled and laughed immoderately.
Rapidly I lost all control.
It seemed to me that Rashleigh was making
insinuations about my feelings for Die, and,
furious with him, I slapped his face.
My cousins took me by force to my room and
locked the door.
I slept badly and the next morning I knew
I must apologise for my behaviour.
My cousins accepted my excuses - only Rashleigh
showed his resentment.
I also apologized to Diana for my discourtesy
to her.
She insisted on knowing what had provoked
my bad humour and, embarrassed, I told her.
She answered that I had to be careful when
speaking to Rashleigh.
I decided then that I had to inform my father
about my cousin's true character and wrote
him a letter.
It was after this that I realized how much
Miss Vernon and the secrets around her occupied
my thoughts - I was falling in love!
Rashleigh left the Hall for London and after
his departure I started to help Die with her
studies.
I discovered that while she had had an extremely
good education, she was totally ignorant of
real life beyond the Hall and knew nothing
of accepted feminine behaviour.
One day Andrew Fairservice, the gardener,
informed me that news of the robbery incriminating
me was circulating in London.
I was anxious and decided to send another
letter to my father to explain and rode into
town to post it.
At the post office I found a letter from Owen,
my father's clerk, waiting for me.
He said that he was worried because he had
had no recent news from me.
He did not mention my previous message concerning
Rashleigh, and so I became suspicious.
"Does someone intercept my letters at Osbaldistone
Hall?"
I wondered.
That evening, when I was in the garden, I
saw a light at the library window.
This was not unusual because Diana often read
there alone, but I was surprised when I observed
the shadows of two people inside.
After that I became jealous and started to
watch Miss Vernon's looks and actions.
I was desperate to know who visited her in
the library.
The next time I saw the light there again,
I ran into the library but I found Diana alone.
However, there was a man's glove on the table.
Diana refused to give me any explanation.
With an air of authority she told me I should
spend my time in a better way, instead of
spying on her.
Then she gave me a letter which had arrived
for me.
"Gracious heaven!"
I cried.
"My folly and disobedience have ruined my
father!
This letter says that Rashleigh has gone to
Scotland.
During my father's absence in Holland, Rashleigh
left London taking documents and large sums
of money from the company.
Mr Owen is now in Scotland too, in Glasgow,
trying to discover where Rashleigh is hiding."
I decided I had to go to Scotland immediately
to help my father's clerk.
Before I left, Diana gave me a sealed packet
without an address, and ordered me to open
it only in an emergency.
CHAPTER FIVE
Reunion with a Friend
I asked Andrew Fairservice to accompany me
into Scotland because I did not know the country.
We met at three in the morning because we
didn't want to wake the Osbaldistone family.
On a Saturday evening, after a long ride,
we arrived in Glasgow, the principal town
in the west of Scotland.
The next morning all the bells of the city
announced the sanctity of the day, Sunday.
I wanted to start looking for Owen immediately,
but Andrew said, "You cannot do anything until
the church service is over."
So I decided to go to the cathedral of Glasgow,
a solid and massive example of Gothic architecture.
While all the people were silent and listening
to the sermon, a voice from behind me whispered
distinctly in my ear: "You are in danger in
this city!
Meet me tonight at the Brigg at twelve precisely."
I turned round, but there was no one there.
I spent the rest of the day at the inn reflecting
on what I should do.
In the end I decided to go to the appointment
on the bridge.
I waited on the bridge in the dark.
I was very apprehensive.
What was going to happen.
Then the clock struck midnight, and suddenly
a stranger appeared near me and said, "Mr
Osbaldistone, follow me!"
I hesitated and replied, "Can't you give me
your information here?"
"You must receive it from your eyes, not from
my tongue," he said.
"You must follow me, or remain in ignorance."
So I obeyed and was surprised when the man
led me to...
Glasgow prison!
The prison guard, a Highlander called Dougal,
seemed happy to see my companion.
He took us upstairs to a cell where a prisoner
was sitting dejected in the corner: it was
Mr Owen!
He recognized me and exclaimed, "What!
You are here too?
Oh!
Mr Frank, your company is ruined and now you
are in a Scottish prison!
God help us!"
I assured him that I was not a prisoner and
asked him to explain what had happened.
What was he doing in Glasgow prison?
He told me that my father had two correspondents
for his business in Scotland, the house of
MacVittie-MacFin & Co. and the Bailie, Mr
Nicol Jarvie.
They transacted a great deal of business for
the London firm and Owen had gone to see them
when he arrived in the city.
"I immediately contacted MacVittie and MacFin,"
said Owen.
"They had always professed themselves obliged
and devoted to Mr Osbaldistone, so I openly
revealed the present difficulties of the house
caused by the absence of your father and the
disappearance of Rashleigh.
I asked for counsel and financial assistance
regarding the next payments, but when they
discovered they had large credits with Osbaldistone
& Tresham, they refused to help me.
They had me arrested and sent to prison as
a debtor instead!"
Just then we were interrupted by a loud knocking
on the prison door.
A few minutes later, Bailie Jarvie himself
came in and spoke to Owen, asking to see his
papers.
He examined them with great attention, then
said, "You owe money to several people in
Glasgow.
But you cannot pay your debts if you are in
prison.
I will act as your guarantor and they will
let you go free."
Bailie Jarvie took the lamp and scrutinized
the other people in the room.
"Ah!
Eh!
Oh!
My conscience!
It's impossible and yet...
no!
You robber, you devil that you are!
Can this be you, Robin?"
exclaimed the Bailie.
"That is so," was my guide's laconic answer.
Mr Jarvie also wanted to know who I was and
then asked me, "Young man, how will you find
the five thousand pounds to pay your father's
bills in three days?"
I didn't know what to say, then suddenly I
remembered Diana's packet.
I opened the seal and a letter dropped onto
the floor at Mr Jarvie's feet.
After examining the name on the envelope,
he gave it to Robin.
I realized then that my mysterious guide was
in fact Mr Campbell himself!
I recognized his deep voice, his severe face,
and his Scottish accent.
Mr Campbell read the letter, then instructed
Owen to remain in Glasgow.
He told me Bailie Jarvie and I should go to
his Highland home in the glens.
The next day I went to the Bailie's home for
lunch and found Owen there.
The honest man was depressed after his stay
in the prison but Mr Jarvie's kind and friendly
interest in my fathers affairs consoled him.
I asked the Bailie to tell me something about
Robert Campbell.
"He is a distant cousin of mine.
Many people have been cruel to him.
He is a Highland cattle merchant that wears
the tartan when he is in the hills and trousers
when he is in Glasgow!"
explained the magistrate.
Then he started to examine some business documents
with Owen.
As I could not help them, Mr Jarvie suggested
going out for a walk.
I could return later for lunch.
CHAPTER SIX
An Unexpected Encounter
After Mr Jarvie's house, I directed my steps
to the college grounds.
While I was walking, my attention was attracted
by three men who appeared at the end of the
garden.
I looked again and recognized Rashleigh with
Mr Morris and Mr MacVittie!
I did not want to be seen, so I hid behind
some trees and came out only when the men
separated.
I followed Rashleigh and took his arm to stop
him.
I was determined to demand reparation for
the wrongs done to my father.
"I am glad to meet you at last!" were my first
words.
"Oh, I am easily found by my friends and more
easily still by my enemies," replied Rashleigh
coolly.
"Which of the two are you, Mr Francis?"
"I will be an enemy, if you do not immediately
render justice to your benefactor, my father,"
I said.
"Why should I justify my actions to a young
gentleman who has no inclination for business
matters?
Go, young man, and amuse yourself in the world
of your poetical imagination!"
replied my cousin insolently.
"This is no answer for the wrongs done to
my father!
You must come with me to the magistrate and
give me full satisfaction!"
I exclaimed, angrily.
"You insulted me once before, remember!"
hissed Rashleigh.
"Your insolence merits personal punishment.
Now, follow me to a place where we cannot
be interrupted!"
I followed him, watching him attentively because
I knew that he was treacherous.
In fact I had no time to take off my cloak
and take out my sword before he was on me.
He attacked me without warning and I only
saved my life by springing back.
Rashleigh fought furiously.
After the first impulse of passion, I reflected
that Rashleigh was my cousin, the son of my
uncle, and decided to try and disarm him only.
But I soon realized that I had met my match
- the combat seemed destined to have a tragic
end.
I slipped, Rashleigh's sword passed through
my waistcoat, grazed my ribs and ran through
my coat behind.
I thought that I was fatally wounded and assaulted
my opponent, ready now to kill him.
At that moment a man stepped between us and
separated us, exclaiming, "What?
The sons of two brothers doing this!
I will break your heads if you continue!"
I looked up in surprise.
The speaker was Mr Campbell.
"Are you hurt, lad?" he asked me.
Then, turning to Rashleigh: "Do you think
men will trust their lives and fortunes to
one who goes around quarrelling like a drunk
man?"
After a few more quiet words he sent Rashleigh
away and again invited me to be prudent and
to stay at home.
Then he disappeared and left me to reflect
upon the singular events of the morning.
I tried to adjust my dress and to hide the
blood which was flowing down my right side.
On the way to Mr Jarvie's house I stopped
at a little shop, an apothecary's, where a
lively, elderly man treated my wound and laughed
at the excuse which I gave him for it.
"Ah!
Young blood!
Young blood!" he repeated.
"What made you so late?" asked Mr Jarvie when
I returned.
I made my apologies but did not tell him what
had happened.
Soon we were seated at table where the Bailie
entertained me with great hospitality and
good humour.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Journey Begins
We ended the meal with some brandy-punch.
"The limes," Mr Jarvie assured us proudly,
"come from my little farm overseas.
I made the liquor myself!"
This led to a conversation between Mr Owen
and our host about the possibility, which
the government had recently given to Scottish
towns, to trade with the British colonies
in America and the West Indies.
I was silent and, when the Bailie questioned
me, I related the events of the morning and
anxiously asked him, "What should I do to
help my father and satisfy my own honour?"
"I think that Robin will help you, if he can.
He is a good-hearted man," replied the Bailie.
"Can I consider Mr Campbell an honest man?"
I continued.
"Can I go to the appointment in the glens
safely, and believe in a man who fears justice?"
Mr Jarvie explained that in the Highlands
there was no law and no magistrates.
The country was savage and poor, and people
often became bandits.
Robin Campbell, once an honest and active
man of noble lineage, became an outlaw, known
as Rob Roy, when his creditors took everything
he had.
Here Mr Jarvie's face became very sad.
"Rob was away on business," he said, "and
when he came home, he found desolation where
he had left plenty; he looked east, west,
south, north and he saw no hope, no shelter!"
The Bailies voice showed his affection and
sympathy for Campbell's misfortunes.
"Robin put on his bonnet, took his big sword
and collected a band of blue bonnets.
He and his men started to protect the lands
and cattle of the southern farmers from robbers,
in exchange for money."
"Oh, a very singular contract of insurance!
The robbers who threaten the southern farmers
are those same Highlanders!"
exclaimed Owen at this point.
This form of blackmail was against the law,
and Rob risked capture and death if he was
found in Glasgow.
"He is a sort of Robin Hood!"
concluded the Bailie.
"I am convinced that he robbed Morris with
the help of Rashleigh to accelerate the Jacobite
rebellion against King George.
He was certainly an agent between our Highland,
chiefs and the gentlemen in the north of England."
The conversation went on, and gradually we
came to the opinion that I should leave at
once for the glens and meet Rob Roy there.
The next morning at five o'clock we started
our journey.
Mr Owen remained in Glasgow and Andrew came
with us.
We travelled all day, going north-east from
Glasgow - first across a marshy barren land,
then through a wild and desolate area with
dark blue mountains visible in the distance.
I began to appreciate Mr Jarvie.
He had an observant mind and he knew the ancient
history of the area.
He was a good Scotsman that loved the traditions
of his land, but he also understood the importance
of the union with England for the future prosperity
of his town and country.
We had lunch at noon at a most miserable alehouse,
and then continued our journey quickly because
we wanted to reach the clachan of Aberfoil
before night fell.
During the last three miles Mr Jarvie began
to give Andrew his instructions.
"Keep your tongue in your mouth, and don't
say a word, good or bad, to anyone in the
clacham!" he told him sharply.
"And... remember, no blasting about your master's
name - or mine!"
"I have many things of more importance to
speak about!"
was Andrew's indignant reply.
CHAPTER EIGHT
In the Highlands
At last we arrived at the inn at Aberfoil.
There was a willow-branch across the half-opened
door, blocking our entrance.
Mr Jarvie told me that this meant there were
some Highland chiefs inside who did not want
to be disturbed.
After some discussion with the landlady we
were allowed to enter.
Inside the inn was a large, bare room full
of smoke, with a big fire blazing merrily
in the centre.
Three men were sitting at an old, scratched
oak table near the fire.
Two looked like Highlanders, judging by their
clothes.
The third was in the Lowlands dress and looked
like a soldier.
Another Highlander, all covered up by a plaid,
was sleeping on the floor.
It seemed that they did not pay any attention
to us but when I ordered some food, one of
them said to me in very good English,
"You think you are at home here, I see!"
His tone was offensive and a dispute started.
In a few moments we were fighting - three
against three I thought, but then I noticed
that Andrew had vanished.
The Bailie started well but he was corpulent
and soon exhausted his energy.
He was almost at die mercy of his antagonist,
when suddenly the sleeping Highlander jumped
up from his place on the floor and, placing
himself between the two men, exclaimed, "This
is Bailie Jarvie!
I will defend him!"
At these words, with the cry "Hold your hands,
hold your hands!", the fight stopped and we
all sat down together and drank in friendship.
Supper was nearly ready so I went to look
for Andrew.
The landlady offered to guide me to the stable
with a light and, when we were outside, she
gave me a piece of paper.
It was a message from Robin Campbell.
He said that he could not come to the meeting,
and advised me not to mix with the people
at the inn because they were dangerous.
After looking for him everywhere finally discovered
Andrew in the stable, hiding in a corner.
He was frightened and continued repeating:
"I am an honest lad, sir!
I am!
I am!"
I requested an explanation and eventually
he told me that he thought I was putting myself
in extreme danger.
"Take care of yourself, sir!
Don't go near Rob Roy!" he said with sincere
alarm.
We went back into the inn and found that Bailie
Jarvie was now quarrelling with the tall Highlander.
Then we heard the measured steps of soldiers,
some orders were shouted outside, and an officer
wearing a red coat came into the room.
He looked severe.
He addressed the three men.
"I am Captain Thornton.
You are, I suppose, the Major and the Highland
gentlemen I had to meet in this place?"
They nodded in agreement.
Then, pointing to us, he continued, "Are these
gentlemen with your group?
I have orders to arrest an old person and
a young one - as traitors!"
He looked hard at Mr Jarvie and me.
"You two!
What are your names?"
Mr Jarvie told him and when the officer heard
the name Osbaldistone he ordered his soldiers
to disarm and search me.
They found the note from Mr Campbell, and
decided that we had to be Rob Roy's spies.
The officer decided to send us to the garrison
with an escort.
We spent the rest of the night at the inn.
I did not sleep well.
I heard the soldiers going out many times
on patrol, but apparently they did not find
out the information the English officer wanted
because he became more nervous each time they
returned!
CHAPTER NINE
A Memorable Woman
Early the next morning some soldiers ran into
the inn.
They were dragging a Highlander triumphantly.
I immediately recognized him - it was the
prison guardian, Dougal, the very man who
had defended Mr Jarvie!
The Bailie recognized him too and exclaimed,
"Mercy on us!
They have taken that poor creature, Dougal!
Captain, I will give you money for his liberty!"
The officer, however, paid no attention to
the Bailie's request.
Instead he started to question Dougal.
He forced the Highlander to admit, with great
reluctance and after many contradictions,
that he knew Rob Roy MacGregor Campbell and
that he had seen him only an hour before.
"And now, my friend," said the officer, "you
will please tell me how many men your master
has with him at present."
Dougal looked away and replied slowly that
he did not know.
"Look at me, you Highland dog!"
the officer threatened showing him a rope.
"I'll hang you from the nearest tree if you
do not take us to Rob Roy's hiding place!"
The soldiers got ready to move and we left
the inn.
I was glad to be outside in the refreshing
fragrance of the morning air.
I liked the woods around me, the mountain
lake in the distance, the romantic solitude
of the place where a man alone seemed to be
in a state of inferiority.
At one point the roadwe were following suddenly
emerged from the forest and started to follow
the shore of the lake.
It gradually became narrow and steep, the
ideal place for an ambush.
Suddenly a woman appeared on the summit of
a rock above us.
"Stop!"
she cried in a commanding tone.
"What are you doing in MacGregor's country?"
She was an imposing woman of about fifty.
Her face, once beautiful, was expressive but
now full of lines.
She wore a plaid wrapped around her body,
as Highland soldiers do, and a man's bonnet
with a feather.
She was also carrying a sword in her hand,
and had a pair of pistols in her belt.
"We are looking for Rob Roy MacGregor Campbell!"
replied the officer.
"Let us pass!
We don't want to fight against a woman, we
offer you civil treatment!"
"Ah!" shouted the woman.
"I know your civil treatment!
You have left me and mine no house and no
bed, no cattle and no clothes!
And now you come for our lives!"
"That's Helen Campbell, Robs wife!"
whispered the Bailie to me.
Suddenly the officer gave the order for the
soldiers to charge.
Guns flashed from various parts of the pass
and three red-coats were killed.
The captain prepared a second attack against
the Highlanders, and Dougal, no longer under
escort, escaped from his captors and began
to ascend the mountainside with incredible
agility.
I followed his example while the fire and
the grenades exploded and hissed behind me,
and I continued climbing until I was out of
breath.
Then I stopped and looked down.
I saw the Bailie hanging in mid-air from the
branch of a thorn tree.
Andrew was on the top of a rock, exposed to
all dangers, and was crying for mercy alternately
in Gaelic and English.
In spite of the danger the scene was very
comical!
After a few minutes the guns stopped.
Some of the soldiers were lying lifeless on
the ground, the rest were in the hands of
the Highlanders.
I realized then for sure that Dougal was not
a traitor.
He had given false information to the officer
to guide the soldiers into the ambush because
he wanted to protect Mr Campbell, alias Robert
MacGregor, alias Rob Roy!
CHAPTER TEN
Captured!
The Bailie and Andrew were soon treed from
their uncomfortable position, and I joined
them.
Dougal came to our help, and took us to Rob
Roy's wife.
Helen MacGregor Campbell had not personally
taken part in the fight, but her aspect was
menacing: her hands and arms were naked, her
face and sword were stained with blood, her
hair was in a disorderly state, her eyes were
inflamed by the triumph of victory.
She looked like a biblical heroine.
"I am very happy to have this joyful opportunity,"
said the Bailie.
"Do you remember me, Mrs MacGregor Campbell.
I am your cousin, Nicol Jarvie, son of Deacon
Jarvie."
He explained the connection between their
two families, and talked of the times when
Rob Roy had still been an honest cattle merchant.
We were interrupted by the melancholy sound
of bagpipes.
Rob Roy's two sons arrived and I looked at
them with interest.
The two boys were young - hardly twenty.
The elder, Hamish, or James in English, was
tall, fair and handsome, with blue eyes and
a profusion of blond hair under his blue bonnet.
The younger, Robert, or Oig in the language
of the Highlanders, had dark hair and a dark
complexion.
He was a stout, strong boy, a real Highlander.
They brought bad news, however - their father
had been captured and was now a prisoner of
the English troops!
But Helen MacGregor did not weep at their
news.
Instead she shouted at them furiously:
"Your father taken?
A prisoner?
And you, you are still alive!
Better that you had died protecting him!"
Rob Roys sons stood in front of their mother
and listened to her reproaching words silently.
Their faces showed pain and shame.
She asked what had happened and Hamish told
her how his father had fallen into a trap.
He spoke in a low tone of voice and he spoke
in English, probably because he did not want
his followers to understand, but I was very
near them and I could hear his story.
A man had brought Rob Roy a message from a
person whose name I could not hear.
Rob Roy had left with three men but only one
of them had come back.
"The man that brought the message is our hostage
now," Hamish continued.
"We can try to exchange him for our father."
Helen asked to see him mid they brought forward
a man half dead with terror.
Imagine my great surprise-when I recognized
him - he was my old acquaintance, Mr Morris.
He fell on the ground before Helen MacGregor
and implored her to spare his life.
"I was totally ignorant of any design on the
person of Rob Roy, a man I honour and love.
I was sent by Rashleigh with a message for
MacGregor, but I did not know of the plot
against him."
But the woman was not moved by his words.
"Life is a heavy burden for me, for you it
is enjoyment.
This enjoyment must end.
You shall die, miserable dog!"
she said, and gave a brief command to her
attendants.
Two Highlanders came and dragged Morris to
a cliff over the lake.
He struggled and shouted while they tied a
rock around his neck and took off some of
his clothes.
His cries were terrible, I still remember
them.
He looked at me and begged for my help, and
I tried to speak on his behalf, but my words
were vain.
They threw him into the cold, deep water.
We were horrified.
Bailie Jarvie protested, "That was a cruel,
unnecessary murder!" he declared.
Helen MacGregor pretended not to hear, but
turned to me and asked, "Are you Rashleigh
Osbaldistone?
I heard Morris call you Osbaldistone."
"No, my name is Francis Osbaldistone," I replied.
"Do you know this Rashleigh? is he a relative
of yours?"
she continued.
I answered that I knew him.
"Then you will go to the garrison with a message,"
she told me.
"If they don't free Rob Roy MacGregor in twelve
hours, we will send back all our prisoners
cut into pieces."
A few minutes later I left for the garrison.
The commanding officer read the letter I gave
him and gave me his reply: "Rob Roy must die."
He showed no interest whatsoever in the prisoners'
lives and ordered the cavalry troops to prepare
to leave, escorting Rob Roy and the English
prisoner - that is to say, me.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Where Is Rob Roy?
We travelled surrounded by armed soldiers.
Rob Roy was on a horse tied with a horse-belt
to a very big, strong Scotsman called Ewan.
When we were near the river, Rob Roy whispered
to Ewan, "It is sad to see a Scotsman who
considers an English captains orders more
important than a friend's life."
In the middle of the river I heard a splash
and immediately understood - Rob Roy's words
had convinced Ewan to free him and give him
the chance to live.
He had jumped off the horse into the water!
The captain also heard the sound and guessed
what had happened.
"You dogs!" he cried.
"Where is the prisoner?
Go and look for him!
I promise a hundred guineas as a reward!"
There was great confusion.
Some soldiers tried to follow the fugitive
into the water, but the force of the current
carried them away.
Others, who were more cautious, galloped along
the riverbanks, shooting and shouting.
Escape for Rob Roy was not difficult - he
was an expert swimmer.
At first he was confused under the water but
then he freed himself from his plaid, swam
away under the surface and was soon out of
view.
The soldiers saw the plaid in the water and
tried to catch it but they soon gave up.
In many places the river was inaccessible
because of the thick vegetation and besides,
it was getting dark, so it was not easy to
see anything in the water.
Most of them believed that Rob would not be
able to survive the current and the freezing
water.
At last the sound of a trumpet announced the
retreat.
Up to that moment, I had been a spectator
- like someone watching a hunting scene at
Osbaldistone Hall.
But suddenly I heard a voice call out "Where
is the Englishman.
He gave Rob Roy the knife to cut the belt.
We must kill him!"
And I realized then the danger of my situation.
I jumped from my horse and ran into a wood
where the darkness of the night protected
my escape.
I decided I had to try somehow to return to
Aberfoil.
Eventually I found my way back to the road.
While I was walking, lost in my thoughts,
a horseman approached me and asked me if the
road was safe.
I replied that it was not and then noticed
his companion.
Both of them were wrapped in travelling cloaks
and the hood of the man's cloak hid his face,
but his companion was not wearing a hood,
only a small hat, and in the dark her figure
seemed familiar.
She addressed me in a familiar voice, saying
my name.
My blood froze in surprise: it was Diana Vernon's
voice!
But the man with her prevented any further
conversation saying in a commanding tone,
"Give him his property!"
Diana gave me a small case and said, "Rashleigh
had to abandon your father's papers.
Here they are.
Now, we must part forever.
Farewell, dear Frank."
Then she galloped away with the unknown man.
I was deeply sad, but I continued on my way.
After a while another voice addressed me.
"Good night, Mr Osbaldistone."
There was no doubt: it was Rob Roy.
He had escaped his enemies and had acquired
a musket and other Highland weapons since
his escape at the river.
I welcomed him, and he asked me about the
events of the preceding day.
I told him about the ambush at the lake and
the meeting with Diana Vernon.
I was jealous and wanted to know the name
of the man accompanying her.
Did he know?
Rob called him ''His Excellency", but he was
so vague that I continued to ask myself, is
he Diana's husband?"
Suddenly three Highlanders appeared in front
of us on the road and commanded us to stop.
Rob said the word Gregaragh, his name in Gaelic,
and they cheered us.
They were relieved to see that their chief
was safe.
We arrived at Aberfoil together where we met
Jarvie, who was waiting for us.
The following day Rob Roy MacGregor accompanied
us to Loch Lomond, where we could take a boat
to Glasgow.
As we rode he told me, "We Highlanders are
rude and ignorant, we are also violent and
passionate, but we are not cruel.
We are a persecuted generation.
We do not want to go against the laws of the
country, but people do not permit us to live
in peace - so, we must fight."
He then explained that Rashleigh had been
obliged to give back my father's papers.
He had gone to Stirling and informed the authorities
that the Highlanders were preparing a rebellion
against King George.
While he was speaking, Helen and his two sons
arrived.
"You are welcome," she said, looking at me
and at the Bailie.
"Excuse my previous rudeness.
We live in bad times!"
and she gave me a ring.
It was one of Dianas rings - a farewell present,
Helen said.
A boat was waiting for us.
We parted from Rob Roy with many manifestations
of affection while the bagpipes sounded their
melancholy notes.
He remained watching us for some time, standing
on a rock at the side of the loch with his
long gun, his tartan and the single feather
in his cap.
Then he vanished.
CHAPTER TWELVE
The Tables Are Turned
That same night we reached Glasgow.
I returned to my inn, where Andrew himself
came to open the door.
Owen appeared behind him with another man
- it was my father!
"My dear, dear son!" he said, embracing me.
We were overjoyed to see one another.
He told me that he had come to Scotland to
capture Rashleigh and to put his affairs in
order.
My father asked Bailie Jarvie to be his firm's
correspondent in Glasgow and we decided to
return to London.
On the morning of our departure, Andrew Fairservice
came to my room like a mad man, jumping up
and down with excitement and told me that
the long-awaited rebellion of the Highlanders
in favour of the Old Pretender, King James,
was beginning.
Rob Roy and his men were on their way to Glasgow!
In the troubled times that followed my Osbaldistone
cousins fought for the Jacobite cause and,
one after the other, all perished.
My uncle, Sir Hildebrand, passed away in a
Hanoverian prison.
They say he died of sorrow.
After his death I learned from Judge Inglewood
that Sir Hildebrand had left all his property
to me in the event of his sons' deaths.
He had cancelled Rashleigh from his will because
of his support of the Hanoverians, whom my
uncle hated.
I was now the heir to Osbaldistone Hall - I
had inherited everything!
The judge also revealed to me that the man
they called "His Excellency" was really Diana's
father, Sir Frederick Vernon.
He had lived in secret at Osbaldistone Hall
for many years and only Sir Hildebrand, Diana
and Rashleigh knew his secret.
I was shocked to hear this information but
at the same time I was pleased.
The strange man Diana often met in the library
was her father, not her husband - she wasn't
married after all!
The next morning I set out for Osbaldistone
Hall with Andrew.
When we arrived, the house had a very different
aspect from the last time I had seen it.
It was silent and solitary, the doors and
windows were closed, the grass in the courtyards
was long, the gardens neglected - a sharp
contrast to the lively, bustling atmosphere
of some months ago.
Andrew knocked at every door of the building
and finally my uncle's ancient major-domo,
appeared.
He seemed very agitated and, when I asked
him to light a fire in the library, he was
reluctant.
I soon understood why!
As I waited there, I heard a deep sigh behind
me and turned to see Diana Vernon standing
there with her father.
"We beg you to help us, Mr Osbaldistone,"
Sir Frederick said.
"To give us refuge.
I am a convinced Catholic, I took part in
the rebellion in favour of King James, but
I was obliged to flee.
I am hiding here at Osbaldistone Hall with
my daughter, waiting for a boat to take us
to the Continent."
I invited them to remain for as long as they
needed but I was very agitated.
That night there was a violent knocking at
the gate - there were soldiers outside.
They demanded to enter.
They had orders to arrest Sir Vernon on a
charge of treason.
Diana appeared beside me.
She whispered "Danger is familiar to us, Frank.
Don't be afraid.
We will escape into the garden and then into
the wood.
Dear, dear Frank, farewell!"
I heard Andrew shouting.
With the soldiers there was a magistrate with
a legal mandate accompanied by - Rashleigh!
They went at once to the library but it was
already empty - Diana and her father had fled.
They ran into the gardens and caught the fugitives
at the gate.
It seemed all was lost but then, as the escort
party was leaving with their prisoners, they
found a barricade at the Hall gates.
A group of Highlanders barred the way with
their cattle.
Rashleigh's men were trying to drive the cattle
away, when suddenly the leader of the Highlanders
cried "Claymore!"
It was an ambush prepared by Rob Roy!
There was a desperate fight.
The soldiers fled and Rashleigh was badly
wounded.
"Ask pardon for your treason in the name of
God, King James and our old friendship," cried
Rob Roy, his sword at Rashleigh's throat.
"Never!"
replied Rashleigh, firmly.
"Then, traitor, die for your treason!"
cried Rob and passed his sword through his
enemy's body.
He was still breathing when we brought him
to the Hall.
His last words were for me: "The pangs of
death do not alter my feelings towards you,
Frank Osbaldistone - I hate you with an immense
hatred!"
And then he died.
Diana and her father escaped and took the
boat to France.
I returned to London to work in my fathers
company.
After some time, my anxiety to learn the fate
of Miss Vernon became acute and I embarked
for France.
There, after many adventures, I found her
and married her.
We have lived happily together since that
day.
- THE END -