CHAPTER ONE
A Beautiful Wife
I cannot remember how, when or where I met
Ligeia.
It was a long time ago and my memory is not
good.
But I think I met her first in a large, old
city near the Rhine in Germany.
She told me that she came from an ancient
family.
But I never knew the family name of the woman
who was my friend, my partner in my studies
and finally my wife.
Why did I never discover her family name?
Perhaps because she did not want me to find
out, but I cannot remember.
I remember one thing very well: Ligeia was
tall and slim.
Later, at the end, she became very thin.
How can I describe her quiet, aristocratic
movements, or the strange softness of her
footsteps?
If she came into my office, I only knew she
was there when I heard her voice, or when
she put her white hand on my shoulder.
She had a beautiful face, but it was not a
classical kind of beauty.
There was something strange about it.
I have often tried to understand it: was it
her pure white skin or her thick, black hair?
I looked at her long, delicate nose many times.
It was perfect!
I looked at her sweet mouth.
How soft and red it was!
And when she smiled, her teeth were white.
Then I looked into her eyes.
They were much bigger than normal eyes.
Sometimes, when she was excited, they looked
like a deer's eyes.
They were black, with long black eyelashes
and black eyebrows.
But as I looked into them, I realised that
they had a strange expression.
I thought about it for many hours, sometimes
all night.
What was the expression in those eyes?
I wanted to know.
Many times I thought I almost had the answer,
but then it was gone.
Ligeia was very determined.
She was always calm and quiet, but her determination
showed in her eyes.
It shone like a terrible energy, and sometimes
it frightened me.
Ligeia was very clever.
She was excellent at Latin and Greek, and
she knew many other languages perfectly; she
never made a mistake.
She was also a student of science and mathematics.
When we were first married I often asked her
for help with my studies, and we worked together.
But after she died I was alone.
Without her I was like a child in the dark.
When she first became ill, she did not come
to help me as often as before.
She lost weight and her skin became pale and
transparent.
When I saw that she was dying, I felt desperate.
Ligeia resisted death with all her energy
- she was determined to live.
I watched in agony as she fought for life.
I knew she loved me, but I only understood
how much she loved me now that she was dying.
She held my hands and said that she was devoted
to me.
I cannot talk about it now, but let me say
that her love for me was part of her determination
to live.
On the night she died she suddenly got out
of bed and cried, 'Oh God, must I die?
Must I lose my fight with death?
No, I can't die like this!'
But my dear Ligeia died.
I was so sad I could not stay in the old city
by the Rhine.
For a few months I travelled around, then
I bought an old abbey in an isolated part
of England.
This dark, sad place expressed my feelings
of loneliness.
But I decorated it with beautifully coloured
curtains, carpets and ornaments.
I said to myself, 'Perhaps the bright colours
will make me feel happier.'
Unfortunately they did not.
I began to drink too much.
But I do not want to speak about that time
of my life.
I will only say that one day I married Lady
Rowena Trevanion of Tremaine.
My new wife had blonde hair and blue eyes.
She was very different from my first wife,
but how could I ever forget Ligeia?
CHAPTER TWO
A Fight with Death
I took Lady Rowena back to a room high up
in the tower of the abbey, where we lived
for the first month of our marriage.
The room was very large, with an enormous
window made of glass from Venice.
The ceiling was high, like a church, and in
the center there was a big gold chandelier.
There were sofas from the East, and an Indian
bed.
On the walls were long tapestries, like carpets,
with designs made of gold.
The tapestries moved every time the wind blew.
My wife was afraid of me because I was often
sad and depressed.
She did not love me much and stayed away from
me, but I preferred this.
I always thought about Ligeia - my beautiful,
Ligeia, dead in the tomb.
Sometimes in my dreams I called to her in
the night.
I imagined that perhaps my love for her could
bring her back to me.
At the beginning of the second month Lady
Rowena became ill.
She did not sleep very well, and told me she
could hear sounds and movements in the tower.
'You have a fever,' I said.
'You're imagining things.'
She got better, but then she went back to
bed with a second illness, worse than the
first.
The doctors could not understand it.
Again Rowena began to hear little sounds and
movements in the bedroom, and they frightened
her.
One night at the end of September she woke
up suddenly.
I was sitting on a sofa by her bed.
She whispered to me that she could hear sounds
and see movements, and there was a frightened
expression on her thin face.
But I saw and heard nothing.
'It's the wind,' I explained.
'You can see the tapestries moving in the
wind.'
But her face was white with fear, and she
nearly fainted.
I remembered that there was some wine on the
table on the other side of the room.
As I walked under the light of the chandelier,
a strange thing happened.
I felt something invisible pass me, and on
the carpet I saw a shadow, almost the shadow
of a shadow.
I decided to say nothing to Rowena.
I poured out a glass of wine and gave it to
her.
Then I sat on the sofa and watched her.
After some moments I heard very quiet footsteps
on the carpet, coming towards the bed.
A second later, as Rowena was about to drink
the wine, I saw - or perhaps I dreamed that
I saw - three or four large drops of a bright
red liquid fall into the glass.
Rowena did not see it; she drank the wine,
and I said nothing because I thought it was
only my imagination.
After this, Rowena's health got much worse,
and on the third night she died.
Her servants prepared her for the tomb, then
covered her with a sheet.
The next night I sat alone with her body in
the bedroom.
Strange forms and shadows moved around me.
I looked nervously into the dark corners,
at the moving tapestries, and I felt frightened.
Then I looked at the carpet under the chandelier.
There was no shadow there, and I felt better.
When I looked at Rowena on the bed, sad memories
of Ligeia - the only woman I ever loved - came
back to me.
It was perhaps around midnight when I heard
a sound.
It was quiet but clear, and it woke me from
my dreams.
I thought it came from the bed.
I listened in terror, but I did not hear it
again.
I looked carefully at Rowena for any sign
of life.
She was not moving, but I continued to look
at her.
Minutes passed.
Then I noticed a little colour in Rowena's
face.
My heart stopped in horror; I could not move.
When I understood that Rowena was not dead,
I tried to revive her.
But soon the colour disappeared from her cheeks,
her face looked like marble again and her
lips were thin with the horrible expression
of death.
When her body was cold and rigid, I fell on
to the sofa and dreamed about Ligeia.
An hour later I heard the same sound as before.
I listened; yes, there it was again - a sigh
from the bed!
I ran over and saw clearly that her lips were
trembling.
Then they opened, showing her bright teeth.
I thought I was going mad.
There was a pink colour on her cheeks and
neck, her body was getting warm again and
her heart was beating a little.
Lady Rowena was alive!
I did everything I could to revive her.
Then suddenly her colour disappeared, her
heart stopped and her body became cold and
rigid.
I sat down and began to think about Ligeia
again.
Then again for the third time there was a
sound from the bed.
But why must I describe the horrors of that
night?
Again I tried to revive Rowena, and then a
fourth time.
Each time she seemed to fight with an invisible
force; and each time her body changed.
I cannot say how, but she looked different.
It was nearly dawn I when she moved again.
I was sitting on the sofa, exhausted, but
Rowena's body moved with more energy than
before.
Her colour returned, signs of life changed
her face.
Her eyes were closed, but she looked alive.
Then she suddenly got out of bed and walked
slowly to the centre of the room, like she
was walking in her sleep.
I did not tremble; I did not move.
I was as cold and still as stone, paralysed
by what I saw.
As I looked at her, my head filled with wild
thoughts.
Was Rowena really alive?
Could I really see her blonde hair and blue
eyes?
Why wasn't I certain?
I could not see her mouth very well, but her
cheeks were like pink roses.
Weren't they Rowena's cheeks?
But wasn't she taller than before?
I was filled with a kind of madness.
I ran to her, but she moved away.
Then I saw her long hair moving in the wind
- it was blacker than the black of midnight!
And now slowly her eyes opened.
I shouted like a madman, 'These are the black
eyes of my lost love - the eyes of Ligeia!'
- THE END -