CHAPTER ONE
Let's Do It!
Jack Griggs stands on his boat. The wind is
strong and his boat moves quickly over the sea.
A big, white bird goes past and
makes a noise. 'Keyaaaa', it cries.
Jack smiles and says: 'Hello,
bird. How are you, today?'
Jack's friends laugh and
give some fish to the bird.
'Ah,' says Jack. 'Hungry, I see.' Jack's friends
are Max and Sasha, and his wife's name is Tonya.
'I am hungry, too,' says Jack. 'Sandwiches
and drinks everybody? Tonya. Can you steer?'
Half an hour later they are eating.
'What are we going to do now?' asks Jack.
'Oh, I am going to read my book.
Then I'm going to sleep,' says Tonya.
'No - what about tomorrow...?
Next month...? Next year?'
Jack looks at everyone. 'We have lots
of money from our old business, but...'
'We can start another business,' says Max.
'A sailing business?' says Sasha.
'I don't want to work any more,'
says Tonya. 'We don't need to work.'
'OK, listen to me,' says Jack. 'I am
thinking about sailing around the world.'
Max, Tonya and Sasha look at Jack.
'What? From here to Australia?' says Tonya.
'Of course,' says Jack. He is getting very
excited now. 'Max, what do you think?'
'I think we must talk about it,' says Max.
They talk for hours. It is night when Max, Sasha
and Tonya say excitedly: 'OK. Let's do it!'
They have to do a lot before they leave.
Jack talks to a man who knows about sailing around
the world. He tells Jack that it is hard work.
'Does the sea frighten you?
Your boat is very small.
Do you know your friends well? Are
they good at sailing?' he asks.
'We know each other well. They are the
best people in the world,' says Jack.
The four friends look at lots of maps. Sasha
wants to see a whale. Max wants to see Africa.
'I want to sit in the sun and
catch fish to eat,' laughs Tonya.
It is exciting for all of them.
And at first everything is easy.
The big day arrives - they are leaving. Some
of their friends and family come to watch.
Their friends stand by the water and say goodbye.
'Good luck,' one of them says.
'Don't forget us!' says Sasha's sister.
'Write to me every day,' says Tonya's
friend. 'Give the letters to a bird.'
Sasha begins to cry. 'What are we
doing? Do I really want to go?'
she thinks. Max takes her hand. All of them
are quiet, excited, and a little unhappy.
'Bye,' says Jack quietly.
CHAPTER TWO
Sailing South
The wind is strong and the
boat moves faster and faster.
Jack, Max, Sasha and Tonya are
happy at sea. There is a lot to do
on the boat. The wind is behind them and soon
they cannot see England. They are not unhappy now.
They are sailing south. In France they
stop at L'Orient and Biarritz. In Spain,
they visit La Coruna, and in Portugal they stop
in Lisbon. The sun gets hotter and they feel good.
Sasha catches a big fish and they eat it for tea.
Soon, they are sailing past Africa.
Here, everything is different.
They stop in Gambia and people look at them.
Small children bring beads and shells and cloth.
Tonya buys a green hat. There is a lot
of colour and noise and excitement.
They sail for weeks and weeks past Africa. They
stop at many small towns and villages by the sea.
'Africa is so interesting, so big,'
says Sasha. 'It goes on and on.
I look at it on the map, but...'
'This is why we are here,' says
Jack. 'Talking to different people,
seeing different things. The boat, the sea,
the wind. Nothing is better than this, is it?'
Some days later they see a big
fishing boat. It is moving very fast.
'Hello!' they shout at the boat. The
men on the boat look at them angrily.
Max looks carefully at the
boat through his binoculars.
'There is something wrong with their fishing
net,' he says. Max moves the binoculars
and sees something in the sea.
'I can see some net over there.'
He points to their left. 'Why are
they leaving it? Let's have a look.'
They get nearer to the net and Tonya takes
the binoculars. 'What in the world...' says
Tonya. 'What's that? There is something
in the net. It's alive, but what is it?'
Very slowly they move nearer to the net. The thing
in the net is big and it is making a lot of noise.
'I can see it now,' says Tonya. 'It's an
orca - a killer whale - and it's hurt.
There is blood in the water. What
can we do? How can we help it?'
'I can see it too. It is a baby
but we must be careful,' says Max.
Jack is in the water. He is carrying
a long paddle. 'I am going to help it.
I can get the net off its fin,' he says.
'Where's its mother?' asks Sasha. She looks
at the sea. 'I can't see any other whales,
but they are near here, I
think. Be careful, Jack.'
Jack gets the net off the baby killer whale.
There is a big cut on its fin, but it swims away.
Suddenly there are other
killer whales near the boat.
'Jack!' Tonya shouts. 'Get in quickly.'
Jack swims to the boat as fast as a fish.
'That baby killer whale... I am
going to call it Lucky,' he says.
CHAPTER THREE
The Big Wave
It begins to rain as they move away
from the killer whales. Suddenly
it is raining very hard and there
is a lot of wind. The sky is black.
Jack says: 'This is bad. We must get away from
the wind. I can see a town over there. Let's go.'
'I'm frightened,' says Tonya. It is
difficult to hear her because of the wind.
'We're all frightened,' says
Jack. 'But everything is OK.'
The town gets nearer but the
waves get bigger and bigger.
Suddenly a very big wave hits the
boat. There is water everywhere.
'Is everyone OK,' shouts Jack. 'Max?'
'Yes,' says Max.
'Sasha?'
'My arm hurts but I'm OK,' says Sasha.
'Tonya...? Tonya...? Where's Tonya?' shouts Jack.
'She's not in the boat,' says Sasha.
'She's in the water. But where?'
They look in the cold, dark water for hours.
'Tonya! Say something, Tonya.
Where are you?' shouts Max.
The wind gets stronger and the boat is full
of water. Another big wave hits the boat.
Sasha's arm hurts a lot now.
'Jack, we must stop. Do you want us all to
die?' says Max. He puts his arm around Jack.
'We can't do any more. Tonya is wearing
a lifejacket and she can swim very well.
Let's sail to the town.'
Jack puts his head in his hands. 'This
can't happen. It can't!' he says.
Max begins to steer the boat.
But the wind is too strong.
Some time later the boat hits a beach. The
three friends get out. They are very tired.
They stop there. Max and Sasha sleep on
the beach, but Jack sits near the water.
He looks at the sea, thinking about Tonya.
CHAPTER FOUR
Tonya
Tonya is five hundred metres away
out in the sea. She begins to swim,
but the waves are too big
and the water is too cold.
She finds some wood and puts her arms around it.
Tonya is thinking: 'I must be
strong. I am not going to die.
I want to see the sun again.
Jack is going to find me.'
Tonya sees a boat far away. She calls
to it. 'Help! Help me! I'm over here!'
She moves her arms and shouts, but nobody hears
her. The wind moves her away from the boat.
'Oh, Jack. I'm sorry,' she says.
Her head goes down on to the wood.
In the arms of the sea, she sleeps.
Suddenly Tonya is not sleeping. There
is no wind and she can see the sun.
She looks everywhere. There is a beach in
front of her - but she cannot swim to it.
'I am too cold and too tired,' she
thinks. 'I must see a boat soon.'
She looks at the sea. There are no
boats, no people, but some birds.
'Can the birds help me?' she thinks sleepily.
Tonya listens to the sea. She likes the
noise. Then she hears something different.
'Is it a baby crying?' she thinks and looks up.
Ten metres in front of her is a big fin... a
very big fin. Under the fin is a killer whale.
The whale is making the noise. But it
is not a baby - it is five metres long.
Behind it is another whale.
And another. And another.
'Killer whales eat people. I
am going to die,' thinks Tonya.
The killer whales come nearer and
nearer. Tonya can't feel her legs.
'It's OK, they are cold. That's all,' she thinks.
She starts to swim away from the big fins.
'Help me!' she shouts. 'Help, help, help!'
The killer whales are all around her. She
closes her eyes and waits. But she does not die.
The biggest killer whale is under
her. Suddenly she is on his back.
'What is happening? Perhaps they
are not hungry.' Tonya thinks.
The killer whale moves slowly to the
shore. He is taking Tonya to the beach.
Tonya puts her hands on the fin in front of her.
'This is a very big fish - too
big for my tea!' she thinks.
She smiles and puts her head on his big
back. Soon, she is sleeping again.
CHAPTER FIVE
'Tonya? Is That You?'
Jack sits on the beach. The sun is in
the sky. Behind him, Max and Sasha sleep.
'I must do something,' he thinks. 'I can't
take my boat but I must look for Tonya.'
He begins to walk along the
beach. 'There is a town near here.
I can get a new boat, then I can look for Tonya.'
Just then Jack sees something on the
beach. He walks nearer. It is a woman.
Jack runs to the woman on the beach.
'Tonya?' he shouts. 'Tonya! Is that you?'
Tonya moves her head slowly.
'Jack! Oh, Jack. You're OK!'
Jack puts his arms around Tonya. He kisses her
face and cries. He can't speak - he is too happy.
Tonya says: 'What about Max
and Sasha? Are they OK, too?'
'Everyone is OK,' answers Jack.
They sit on the beach and look at the sea.
Jack says: 'We are very, very lucky.'
Tonya sits up and sees a small fin
in the water. It has a cut on it.
The fin waves slowly and moves out to
sea. It is waving goodbye, thinks Tonya.
'Lucky. Yes, Lucky,' she
says quietly to Jack.
- THE END -