CHAPTER ONE
The Ingalls family goes West
A
long time ago, Pa and Ma and Mary and Laura
and Baby Carrie left their little house in
Wisconsin.
They drove away and left it lonely and empty
among the big trees, and they never saw that
little house again.
They were going to Indian country.
Pa said there were too many people in Wisconsin
now.
Wild animals did not stay in a country where
there were so many people, so Pa didn't want
to stay.
He liked a country where the animals lived
without fear.
He liked to see them looking at him in the
forest and eating fruit from the trees.
In the long winter evenings Pa talked to Ma
about the Western country.
'Let's go see the West,' he said.
'The land is flat and the grass grows thick
and high.
Animals run freely and there are no settlers.
Only Indians live there.'
'Oh, Charles, must we go now?'
Ma said.
'The weather's so cold and our warm house
is so comfortable.'
'If we are going this year, we must go now,'
said Pa.
'We can't cross the Mississippi River after
the ice breaks.'
So Pa sold the little house in Wisconsin.
With Ma's help, he made a canvas cover for
their wagon.
They put everything into the wagon except
their beds and tables and chairs.
Pa could make new ones out West.
The next morning when it was still dark, Ma
gently shook Mary and Laura until they got
up.
By the light of the fire she helped them dress
warmly.
They put on warm dresses and heavy coats.
Grandmother, Grandfather, aunts, and uncles
were all there to say good-bye to them.
Pa put his gun inside the wagon where he could
reach it quickly.
He put his fiddle between two blankets in
order to keep it safe.
Their dog Jack went under the wagon, and they
drove away.
'When we get to the West,' Pa said to Laura,
'you'll see a papoose.'
'What's a papoose?'
she asked.
'A papoose is a little brown Indian baby,'
Pa explained.
It was a long, long way to Indian country.
Almost every day the horses travelled as far
as they could; almost every night Pa and Ma
stopped in a new place.
They rode across the wide Mississippi River
before the ice broke, and crossed many other
rivers and creeks.
One day Pa sold the tired brown horses and
got two small young black horses with soft
gentle eyes and long tails.
'They're western horses,' Pa said.
'Very strong but very gentle.'
When Laura asked what their names were, Pa
said that she and Mary could choose names
for the horses.
So they called one 'Pet' and the other 'Patty'.
They had travelled across Wisconsin, Minnesota,
Iowa, and Missouri.
All that long way, their little dog Jack had
walked along under the wagon.
Pa sat up front, holding the reins.
Ma sat next to him, straight and quiet.
Baby Carrie slept in soft blankets in the
back.
Now they were crossing Kansas, an endless
flat land covered with tall grass.
Day after day they saw nothing but grass and
a big sky.
There was nothing new to do and nothing new
to look at.
'Ma, can't we get out and run behind the wagon?'
Laura said.
'My legs are so tired.'
'No, Laura,' Ma said.
'I'm hungry.
I want to camp now!'
Then Ma said, 'Laura.'
That was all she said, but Laura understood
that she should stay quiet.
'We're coming to a creek or river,' Pa said.
'Girls, can you see those trees?
That's where we'll camp tonight.'
Suddenly the road went down and they arrived
at the creek.
Pet and Patty stopped to drink.
The sound of fast-running water tilled the
still air.
The river was silver and blue and the water
ran quickly in the middle.
'The creek's really high,' Pa said.
'But I guess we can cross It.'
Pa looked at Ma.
'What do you say, Caroline?'
'Yes, Charles,' Ma answered.
'I think we can.'
So the wagon went forward.
Soon the wheels were in deep water.
'The horses may have to swim out there in
the middle,' Pa said.
'But we'll get across all right, Caroline.'
Laura thought of Jack and said, 'I wish Jack
could ride in the wagon, Pa.'
Pa did not answer.
He was busy with the horses, pulling their
reins.
Ma said, 'Jack can swim, Laura.
He'll be fine.'
Then suddenly the wagon lifted and rocked,
and Laura knew they were in the creek.
Mary hid under the blankets.
She was afraid of the water.
But Laura was excited.
Ma said loudly, 'Lie down, girls!
Don't move!'
Mary and Laura dropped flat on the bed.
When Ma spoke like that, they obeyed her.
Ma's arm pulled a blanket over them, heads
and all.
Laura felt the wagon turning.
The water made so much noise.
Then Pa's voice frightened Laura.
'Take the horses, Caroline!' he said.
Suddenly Pa was gone.
Ma sat alone, holding the reins with both
hands.
Mary hid her face in the blankets again, but
Laura sat up and looked out.
She couldn't see anything but water everywhere
and three heads in the water - Pet's head,
Patty's head, and Pa's small wet head.
Pa's hand was holding Pet's head and he was
talking calmly to the horses.
Ma's face was white and frightened.
Mary was crying and Laura felt cold and sick.
She closed her eyes, but she could still see
the terrible water with Pa in it.
For a long time the wagon rocked in the water.
Finally the front wheels hit the ground and
Pa shouted.
Laura saw the wet horses climbing out of the
water.
Pa was running beside them, shouting 'Get
up!
Get up!
Good girls!'
And then the horses and the wagon stood still,
safely out of that creek.
Pa was wet and tired.
'Oh, Charles!'
Ma cried.
'Calm down, Caroline,' said Pa.
'We're all safe.
All's well that ends well.'
But Laura was still frightened.
She knew they were lucky to be alive.
Suddenly she shouted, 'Oh, where's Jack?'
They had forgotten Jack and could not see
him anywhere.
Pa walked up and down the creek looking everywhere
for him.
But Jack was gone.
There was nothing to do but go on.
Laura tried not to cry.
She looked back all the way but she saw nothing
except hills and trees.
Soon Pa stopped the horses.
He was ready to camp.
Mary and Laura climbed to the ground, too.
Pa seemed sad.
He did not sing while he worked as he usually
did.
'I don't know what we'll do in a wild country
without a good dog,' he said.
Pa made a fire and brought water from the
creek.
Mary and Laura helped Ma make a supper of
salted pork, cornbread, and coffee.
As they ate, purple shadows closed around
the campfire.
The wide prairie was dark and still.
Then Laura heard a long, frightening cry from
the dark prairie.
'Wolves,' Pa said.
'I wish Jack was still with us.'
Laura felt like crying, but she knew she must
be strong.
Suddenly she jumped up.
She had seen something.
Two green lights were shining, deep in the
dark.
They were eyes.
'Look, Pa, look!'
Laura said.
A wolf!'
Pa moved quickly.
He took his gun from the wagon and was ready
to shoot at those green eyes.
Pa threw some wood at the animal.
The green eyes went close to the ground.
Pa held the gun ready.
The animal did not move.
'Don't shoot, Charles,' Ma said.
But Pa walked slowly toward those eyes.
And slowly along the ground the eyes moved
toward him.
And then Laura saw a little brown animal.
She screamed and Pa shouted.
The next thing she knew, a happy, jumping
Jack was on top of her.
Her face and hands were wet from his warm
wet tongue.
He jumped from Pa to Ma and back to her again.
Then he lay down close to Laura and slept.
When Laura went to bed that night, she looked
at the large, shining stars in the sky.
Pa could reach them, she thought.
Suddenly she was very surprised.
The largest star smiled at her!
Then she was waking up the next morning.
CHAPTER TWO
Pa builds the little house
It was still dark, and Pa was packing everything
into the wagon.
Mary and Laura ate their breakfast in a hurry.
When the sun came up, they were driving across
the prairie again.
There was no road now.
So Pet and Patty walked through the tall grass.
Before noon, Pa stopped the wagon.
'Here we are, Caroline!' he said.
'We'll build our house right here.'
Laura and Mary jumped out.
There was nothing around them but grass that
reached to the edge of the sky.
Nearby was a creek.
It lay below the prairie, but they could see
the dark green tree-tops.
Far away another line of different greens
lay across the prairie.
'That's the Verdigris River,' Pa said to Ma.
Then Pa and Ma took everything out of the
wagon and put it on the ground.
They took the canvas off the wagon and covered
all their things.
Then Pa took his axe and drove away.
'Where's Pa going?'
Laura asked.
'To get logs from the creek for our house,'
Ma said.
It was strange and frightening to be without
the wagon on the High Prairie.
The land and the sky seemed too large, and
Laura felt small.
She wanted to hide in the tall grass like
a prairie chicken.
But she didn't.
First she helped Ma make the beds under the
canvas cover.
Then she went for a walk.
She found a mysterious little path in the
grass, and she followed it slowly.
But suddenly she felt afraid and hurried back
to Ma.
When Pa returned with the logs, Laura told
him about the path.
'I saw it earlier,' he said.
'It's an old trail, I guess.'
'When will I see a papoose?'
she asked.
'I don't know, Laura,' Pa replied.
'You only see Indians when they want you to
see them.'
Day after day Pa drove to the creek.
When he had enough logs, he measured the shape
of the house on the ground by walking from
side to side and front to back.
He dug shallow trenches along two sides and
rolled two big logs into them.
Then he put two strong logs across the first
two to make a square.
With his axe he made a deep wide cut near
the end of each log.
The four logs fit together at these cuts.
These four strong logs could hold up the new
house.
All by himself Pa built the house three logs
high.
Then Ma helped him.
Log by log, they built the walls higher while
Laura played in the tall grass.
One day she heard Pa shout, 'Caroline, be
careful!
Get out of the way!'
A big log was falling towards Ma.
Pa couldn't stop it.
It crashed down, and Ma fell to the ground.
Laura and Pa ran to Ma.
The log was on her foot.
Pa lifted it and Ma pulled out her foot.
Pa felt her leg; nothing was broken.
'Can you move your arms?' he asked.
'Can you turn your head?'
Ma moved her arms and turned her head.
'I'm all right,' she whispered.
'Thank God,' Pa said.
'Nothing's broken.
It's only a bad sprain.'
Ma's face was gray but she said bravely, 'Well,
a sprain will soon get better.
Don't worry, Charles.'
But Ma's foot didn't get better for some time.
'The house must wait,' said Pa.
Then one afternoon, Pa came up the creek road
singing.
'Good news!' he shouted.
'We have a neighbour only three kilometers
away on the other side of the creek.
I met him while I was hunting.
He's going to help me finish our house, and
then I'll go over and help him with his house.'
Early the next morning Mr Edwards arrived.
He was tall and wore old clothes, but he was
very polite to Ma.
And he was a fast worker.
In one day he and Pa finished the walls.
They laughed and sang while they worked, and
their axes made the wood fly.
They cut holes for a door and two windows,
and soon the house was finished except for
the roof and floor.
Laura ran inside the new house.
It smelled sweetly of cut wood and prairie
grass.
The sun shone through the window holes and
fell across Laura's hands and her arms and
her feet.
The walls were thick and the house felt large
and strong.
Ma had cooked a good supper and she and Pa
invited Mr Edwards to stay.
There was rabbit and hot cornbread with pork
and even coffee with real sugar.
Then Pa took out his fiddle.
Mr Edwards lay on the ground near the fire
to listen as Pa played Laura and Mary's favourite
song, 'I am a Gypsy King'.
Pa's voice was deeper than an old frog's.
Laura could not stop laughing.
Then Mr Edwards jumped up and began to dance
wildly in the moonlight.
Pa played song after song while Mr Edwards
danced.
Laura's and Mary's hands were clapping and
their feet were moving with the music, too.
And Baby Carrie, who had woken up, was sitting
in Ma's arms, clapping her little hands and
laughing.
When it was time for Mr Edwards to go, he
took his gun and said good night.
Pa played one last song as Mr Edwards walked
away into the darkness, singing happily.
When the song ended, the prairie was silent.
Only the wind whispered in the tall grass.
'The walls are up,' Pa said to Ma the next
morning.
'Let's move in.
I heard wolves everywhere around us last night.
We should have strong thick walls around us.
I'll make the floor and roof later because
I must build a stable for Pet and Patty as
fast as I can.
They should be safe inside walls, too.'
'Why haven't we seen any Indians?'
Ma asked.
'I don't know,' Pa replied.
'I've seen the places where they camp.
They're away hunting for food now, I guess.'
After breakfast Pa got on top of the walls
to put the canvas wagon cover over the house.
The canvas blew wildly in the wind, and so
did Pa's hair.
Once he almost flew away into the air like
a big bird.
But he finally tied the canvas down.
By dinner time, the house was ready.
The beds were made on the floor.
Short logs had become chairs.
Pa's gun was up in its place over the door.
It was a pleasant house.
'Before winter comes I'll make a wood floor
and a solid roof,' Pa said.
'But that must wait until I finish helping
Mr Edwards and building a stable.
We're going to do well here, Caroline.
We'll be happy here for the rest of our lives.'
Laura liked this place, too.
She liked the great big sky, the winds, and
the wide land.
Everything was so clean and big and wonderful.
Inside the thick walls of their new home they
felt warm and safe.
Pa put up a quilt over the door hole.
As she fell asleep that night, Laura heard
a wolf's cry from somewhere far away on the
prairie.
She did not feel so frightened.
CHAPTER THREE
Wolves frighten the family
Pa and Mr Edwards built the stable for Pet
and Patty in one day.
By the time they put the roof on, it was dark.
'Now!' said Pa.
'Let those wolves howl!
I'll sleep tonight.'
In the morning when Laura went into the stable,
she found a surprise waiting for her.
A little colt with long ears stood beside
Pet!
When Laura ran toward it, gentle Pet put back
her ears and showed her teeth.
'Stay back, Laura!'
Pa shouted.
'She could bite you.'
Then he said to Pet, 'You know we won't hurt
your baby, Pet.'
Pet let Pa touch the baby, but she didn't
let Laura or Mary go near her.
Early that afternoon, Pa rode Patty across
the prairie to see what he could see.
There was plenty of meat in the house, so
he did not take his gun.
By late afternoon, he still had not come home.
Ma and Laura began to get supper ready outside
by the fire.
Mary was in the house, taking care of the
baby, and Laura asked Ma, 'What's the matter
with Jack?'
Jack was walking up and down and around the
house, looking worried.
His hair stood up on his neck.
Then Pet started running around in circles.
Ma looked around at the wide prairie and the
sky but didn't see anything unusual.
'It's probably nothing at all, Laura,' Ma
said.
She made the coffee.
The prairie chicken that was cooking on the
fire began to smell good.
But all the time Ma went on looking around.
Suddenly Patty came running fast across the
prairie.
Pa was almost flat, holding onto her neck.
Patty ran past the stable before Pa could
stop her.
She was trembling, and her black coat was
hot and wet.
Pa was hot and tired, too.
'What's the matter, Charles?'
Ma asked him.
Pa's eyes were looking toward the creek, so
Ma and Laura looked at it, too.
But they only saw grass and trees.
'What is it?'
Ma asked again.
'Why were you riding Patty so fast?'
'I was afraid the wolves had come here.'
'Wolves!'
Ma cried.
'What wolves?'
'Everything's fine now, Caroline,' said Pa.
'Let me rest a minute.'
Then he said, 'We saw fifty of them, Caroline.
They were the biggest wolves I've ever seen.
It was terrible.'
Supper was ready.
Mary and Laura stayed close to the fire and
kept Baby Carrie with them.
They could feel the darkness everywhere, and
they didn't stop looking around.
Shadows moved on the prairie.
Jack did not growl, but his ears were lifted,
listening to the darkness.
The girls ate their chicken as they listened
to Pa telling Ma about the wolves.
He had found some more neighbours.
Settlers were coming in and building houses
along both sides of the creek.
Not far away, a man and his wife were building
a house.
Their name was Scott, and Pa said they were
nice people.
As he was riding home across the prairie,
a pack of wolves came out of nowhere.
They were all around Pa in a moment.
'It was a big pack,' Pa said.
'There were fifty wolves, and the biggest
wolves I ever saw in my life.
Their leader was a meter tall.
I tell you, my hair stood straight up.'
'And you didn't have your gun,' said Ma.
'I know.
But to be honest, I didn't miss it.
You can't fight fifty wolves with one gun.'
'What did you do?'
Ma asked.
'Nothing,' said Pa.
'Patty tried to run, but I pulled the reins
hard and made her walk.
Wolves will chase and hurt a running horse.'
'How awful, Charles!'
Ma said quietly.
'Yes, it was,' said Pa.
'Those wolves just walked along with us, like
a pack of dogs going along with a horse.
They were all around us, jumping and playing
with each other, just like dogs.
We were lucky they weren't hungry.'
Laura's mouth and eyes were wide open.
Her heart was beating fast.
'Patty was trembling all over,' Pa said.
'She was so scared.
I was, too.
But I made her walk.
When we got near the creek, the leader turned
down toward the creek, and the rest of the
pack followed him.
That's when I let Patty go.
I was scared the whole way home.
I thought the wolves might come this way.
I knew you could keep the wolves out of the
house with the gun.
But Pet and her colt were outside.'
'I guess I could save our horses, Charles,'
Ma said.
'I know,' said Pa.
'I wasn't thinking straight.
But the wolves are far from here by now, and
all's well that ends well.'
Jack was walking around the campfire.
When he stopped to smell the air, the hair
lifted on his neck.
'It's time for bed, girls!'
Ma said.
She took them all into the house.
But it took Laura a long time to fall asleep.
Suddenly she was sitting straight up in bed.
She had been asleep.
Light from the moon was coming through the
window and the cracks in the wall.
Pa was standing there with his gun.
Suddenly, a wolf howled right in Laura's ear.
She pulled away from the wall.
The wolf was just on the other side of it.
Laura was too scared to speak.
Then many wolves started howling all around
the house, and Laura got out of bed.
Pa turned his head and saw her standing there.
'Do you want to see them, Laura?' he asked,
softly.
Without saying anything, Laura walked over
to Pa.
He put down his gun and lifted her up to the
window.
There in the light of the moon sat a half
circle of wolves.
They looked at Laura, and she looked at them.
The biggest one was taller than Laura.
His coat was gray and his eyes were shining
and green.
Laura looked and looked at that wolf.
'He's awfully big,' Laura said into Pa's ear.
'Yes, and see how his coat shines,' Pa said
into her hair.
'They're in a circle around the house.'
Laura went with him to the other window.
There she saw the other half of the circle
of wolves.
The big wolf lifted his nose to the sky and
howled.
All the other wolves answered him.
The noise filled the wide prairie.
'Now go back to bed, Laura,' Pa said.
'Go to sleep.
Jack and I will take care of you all.'
So Laura went back to bed.
She heard the wolves howling and trying to
smell them through the cracks in the walls
of the house.
It was a long time before she fell asleep.
CHAPTER FOUR
Pa finishes the house
When Laura woke up the next morning, the warm
sun was on her face.
She ran outdoors.
Mary was talking to Ma by the fire.
There were no wolves anywhere.
Pa came up the creek road with his gun in
hand.
He had made sure that the wolves were gone.
They all sat by the fire and ate their breakfast.
'I'll make a door today,' Pa said.
'I want more than a quilt between us and the
wolves next time.'
After breakfast, Pa took the horses and his
axe and went to get wood for the door.
Mary watched, but Laura helped Pa to make
the door.
She gave him his saw, which he used to cut
the logs at the ends.
With his axe he made nice straight boards
from the logs.
He laid the long boards on the ground and
fastened some shorter boards across them.
That made the door.
Then Pa made a door frame and put hinges on
the door to make it open and close.
While he put the door in place, Laura stood
against it to hold it up, and Pa fastened
the hinges to the frame.
When the door was finished, it was beautiful
and strong.
'Now we're all safe!' said Pa.
'And I had a fine little helper!'
He put his hand gently on Laura's head.
The sun was going down, the wind was cooler,
and supper was cooking on the fire.
It was salt pork, which made the best supper
smells that Laura had ever smelled.
That night Pa said to Ma, 'Now, Caroline,
I'm going to build you a fireplace.
Then you can do your cooking inside the house.
I've never seen such a sunny place as this,
but I suppose that one of these days the rains
will come.'
'Yes, Charles,' Ma said.
'Good weather always comes to an end, sooner
or later.'
And so Pa was soon cutting away the grass
just outside the wall of the house where he
was going to build the fireplace.
Then he climbed into the wagon.
He looked down at Laura; she was looking up
at him.
'Do you want to go along, Laura?
You and Mary?'
Ma said that they could.
The girls climbed up and sat on the high seat
beside Pa.
Pet and Patty started with a little jump and
pulled the wagon down the new road that Pa's
wagon wheels had begun to make.
They rode through dry valleys and over low,
round hills.
Forests covered some of these hills, but some
of them were open and grassy.
Deer were lying under the trees or standing
and eating grass in the sun.
They lifted their heads and watched the wagon
with their large, soft eyes.
Birds sang and rabbits jumped out of the way
of the wagon.
When they arrived at the creek, Pa said, 'You
girls can play, but don't go too far into
the water.'
So Laura and Mary played by the creek while
Pa dug the big rocks that he needed for the
fireplace.
When the wagon was full, they rode home to
the High Prairie, where the wind was blowing
and the grass was singing.
Laura decided she liked the High Prairie best.
It was so wide and sweet and clean.
That afternoon, the family watched Pa build
the fireplace.
First, he had cleared grass in a square outside
the house wall.
Now he put a row of rocks around the square.
Next he mixed earth and water to a beautiful,
thick mud.
He put some mud over the rocks.
In the mud he put another row of rocks.
With rocks and mud and more rocks and more
mud, Pa built the fireplace and chimney as
high as the house wall.
Then he used wood and mud to finish the top
of the chimney.
Finally he went into the house, and with his
axe and saw he cut a hole in the wall.
And there was the fireplace!
The whole family stood and admired it.
Ma carefully built a little fire in the new
fireplace and cooked a prairie chicken for
supper.
And that evening they ate in their house.
The chicken tasted so good in Laura's mouth.
Her hands and face were washed and her hair
was brushed.
She sat up straight on her log chair and used
her knife and fork nicely, as Ma had taught
her.
She did not say anything, because children
must not speak at the table until they are
spoken to, but she looked at Pa and Ma and
Mary and Baby Carrie, and she felt happy.
It was nice to be in a house again.
All day long, every day, Laura and Mary were
busy.
When the dishes were washed and the beds were
made, there was always plenty to do and to
see.
In the tall grass, they looked for birds and
watched baby prairie chickens running to their
mothers.
They watched snakes lying still in the sun
or moving fast through the prairie.
All the time, of course, either Laura or Mary
was taking care of Baby Carrie.
Sometimes Laura forgot to be quiet when Baby
Carrie was sleeping.
She ran around and shouted until Ma came to
the door and said, 'Laura, dear, must you
shout like an Indian?
In fact, you girls are getting as brown as
Indians in the sun!
Why can't you learn to keep your hats on?'
'Pa, when are we going to see a papoose?'
Laura asked.
Pa was up on the house wall, beginning to
put on the roof.
'Why do you want to see an Indian baby?'
Ma said, surprised.
'Put on your hat and forget your crazy ideas.'
But Laura did not forget the papoose.
This was Indian country and she wanted to
see Indians.
She knew that she would see them sometime,
but she was tired of waiting.
Pa had taken the canvas off the top of the
house.
For days he had been carrying logs from the
creeks and cutting them into long, thin boards.
The boards were lying all around the house.
Now Pa reached down and pulled up a board.
He put it across the rafters.
Then he began to nail the board to the rafters.
Pa pulled up and nailed down more boards,
all the way to the top of the rafters.
The roof was done.
Rain would never get in.
Then Pa made a floor with beautiful hard wood.
'You've done a wonderful job, Charles,' Ma
said.
They were all happy that night.
The sky was full of stars.
Pa sat for a long time by the open door and
played his fiddle and sang to his family in
the house, and to the stars outside.
Later Pa dug a well with Mr Scott's help and
they didn't need to fetch muddy water from
the creek any more.
And after that he went to town to get glass
to put in the windows, and then the house
was truly finished.
CHAPTER FIVE
Indians
Early one morning Pa took his gun and went
hunting.
Jack wanted to go.
too, but Pa tied him to the stable.
'No, Jack,' Pa said.
'You must stay here and take care of the family.'
Then he said to Mary and Laura, 'Don't untie
him, girls.'
Poor Jack lay down.
Mary and Laura stayed by the stable all morning
and tried to play with him, but he was miserable.
Jack's head was on Laura's leg and she was
talking to him when he suddenly stood up and
growled.
The hair on his neck stood straight up and
his eyes stared, red and angry.
Laura was afraid.
Jack had never growled at her before.
Then she looked over her shoulder, where Jack
was looking, and she saw two wild men, one
behind the other coming closer on the Indian
trail.
'Mary!
Look!'
she shouted.
Mary looked and saw them, too.
They were tall, thin, fierce-looking men.
Their skin was reddish-brown.
Their eyes were black and shining.
There were feathers on their heads.
'Indians!'
Mary whispered.
Laura suddenly felt cold.
Her legs trembled.
Jack growled angrily.
The Indians came closer and closer.
Then Mary and Laura watched them walk right
into the house!
Jack was growling, jumping, and trying to
break free.
'Jack's here,' Laura whispered to Mary.
'We'll be safe if we stay close to him.'
'But they're in the house,' Mary whispered.
'They're in the house with Ma and Carrie!'
Then Laura began to shake all over.
She knew she must do something.
What were the Indians doing to Ma and Baby
Carrie?
There was no sound from the house.
'Oh, what are they doing to Ma?'
Laura screamed, in a whisper.
'Oh, I don't know!'
Mary whispered.
'I'm going to untie Jack,' Laura whispered
loudly.
'He'll kill them.'
'Pa told us not to do that,' Mary answered.
'He didn't know Indians would come,' Laura
said.
'He said not to untie Jack,' Mary was almost
crying.
Laura thought of little Baby Carrie and Ma,
there in the house with those Indians.
'I'm going in to help Ma!' she said.
She ran two steps and then turned and flew
back to Jack.
She hid her face against his neck.
'We mustn't leave Ma in there alone,' Mary
whispered.
She stood still and trembled.
Laura made herself leave Jack.
She shut her eyes and ran towards the house
as fast as she could.
She fell down and her eyes opened.
She got up again and started running.
Mary was right behind her.
They came to the door.
It was open, and they entered the house without
a sound.
The naked wild men stood by the fireplace.
Ma was cooking something over the fire while
Baby Carrie hid her face in Ma's dress.
Laura ran towards Ma, but as she reached the
Indians, she smelled something awful.
She looked up at the Indians and ran to hide
behind the table.
With one eye, she looked out at the wild men.
First, she saw the moccasins on their feet.
Then their thin, red-brown legs, all the way
up.
Around their waists each Indian wore the skin
of a small animal.
The skin was black and white, and now Laura
knew what had made that smell.
The skins were made from fresh skunks.
There was a knife and a small axe in each
skin.
Their faces were very calm and very fierce.
These wild men had no hair around their ears,
where hair usually grows.
There was hair only at the very top of their
heads, and they had put feathers in it.
When Laura looked out from behind the table,
both Indians were looking straight at her.
Her heart jumped.
The Indians did not move.
Only their eyes shone.
Laura did not move, either.
Then the Indians made short sounds like 'Hah!'
Laura hid again behind the table.
She heard them sitting down on the floor.
She heard Ma giving them cornbread and she
heard them eating it.
When Laura looked again, she saw they had
eaten every bit of the cornbread.
Then the Indians got up.
They looked at Ma, made deep noises in their
throats, and walked out the door.
Their feet made no sound at all.
Ma sat down on the bed.
She looked sick.
She put her arms around Laura and Mary.
'Do you feel sick, Ma?'
Mary asked her.
'No.' said Ma.
'I'm just thankful they're gone.'
Soon Pa arrived home with a big rabbit and
two prairie chickens.
He put his gun up in its place over the door.
Laura and Mary threw their arms around him,
both talking at the same time.
'What's all this?' he said.
'Indians?
So you've seen Indians at last, have you,
Laura?
I noticed they have a camp in a valley west
of here.
Did Indians come into the house, Caroline?'
'Yes, Charles, two of them,' Ma said.
'I'm sorry, but they took all your tobacco
and ate a lot of cornbread.
I just gave them what they wanted.
Oh, Charles!
I was afraid!'
'You did the right thing,' Pa told her.
'We don't want to make enemies of the Indians.'
Then he said, 'What a smell!'
'They wore fresh skunk skins around their
waists,' said Ma.
'And that was all they wore.'
Later, when Laura and Mary were helping Pa
clean the prairie chickens, Laura said, 'I
wanted to untie Jack to eat those Indians.'
Pa laid down his knife and asked in a terrible
voice, 'Did you girls even think of untying
Jack?'
Laura dropped her head and whispered, 'Yes,
Pa.'
'After I told you not to?'
Pa said, in a more terrible voice.
'Yes, Pa,' Mary whispered, almost crying.
For a moment Pa was silent.
'After this,' he then said in his angry voice,
'you girls must do as I say.
You must always obey me.
Do you hear?'
'Yes, Pa,' Laura and Mary whispered.
'If the Indians come again and Jack is untied,
he'll bite them.
And then there will be trouble.
Bad trouble.
Do you understand?'
'Yes, Pa,' the girls said.
But they did not understand.
'Do as you're told,' said Pa, 'and you'll
be safe.'
One day Pa said that the Indians had left
their little camp on the prairie.
'Do you want to see it?' he asked Laura and
Mary.
When the girls jumped up and down with excitement,
Pa said, 'Come on then, let's go.'
The ground was hot under their feet.
They went farther and farther into the big
prairie.
At last they went down into the little valley
where the Indians had camped.
Laura and Mary looked around.
There were small animals, flowers, and trees.
It was a beautiful secret place.
'Pa, are there other Indian camps on the prairie?'
Laura asked.
'Yes, Laura,' he answered.
'Are there Indians in them?' she whispered.
'I don't know,' said Pa.
'Perhaps.'
She held one of his hands and Mary held the
other, and together they looked at the Indians'
camp.
There were old campfires.
They could see where Indian horses had eaten
the grass, where big and small moccasins had
walked, and where Indians had cooked and eaten.
Suddenly Laura shouted, 'Look!
Look!'
Something bright blue was shining on the ground.
She picked it up.
It was a beautiful blue bead.
Laura shouted with excitement.
Then Mary saw a red bead, and Laura saw a
green one, and they forgot everything except
beads.
They found white beads and brown beads, and
more and more red and blue beads.
All that afternoon they looked for beads.
When they had finished, the sun was going
down.
Laura had a handful of beads, and so did Mary.
Pa put them carefully in his pockets, and
they all went home together.
Supper was cooking on the fire when they arrived,
and Baby Carrie was playing on the floor.
'Sorry we're late!' said Pa, and then he took
the beads out of his pockets and showed them
to Ma.
'But look what the girls found,' he said.
'Oh, they're beautiful!'
Ma said with a smile.
Laura thought the beads looked even prettier
than before.
She touched her beads with her finger and
watched them shine.
'These are mine,' she said.
Then Mary said, 'Carrie can have mine.'
Ma waited for Laura to speak.
But Laura didn't want to say anything.
She felt all hot inside and wished that Mary
wasn't always such a good girl.
But she couldn't let Mary be better than she
was.
So she said, slowly, 'Carrie can have mine,
too.'
'You're good little girls,' Ma said.
She put Mary's beads into Mary's hands, and
Laura's into Laura's hands, and she said,
'You can make a pretty necklace for Carrie
to wear around her neck.'
Mary and Laura sat side by side on their bed
and made Carrie's necklace.
They didn't say anything.
Perhaps Mary felt sweet and good inside, but
Laura didn't.
When she looked at Mary she wanted to hit
her.
So she didn't look at her again.
The beads made a beautiful necklace.
Carrie laughed when she saw it.
Then Ma tied it around Carrie's little neck
and Laura felt a little bit better.
It looked so pretty on her.
But when Carrie felt the beads on her neck,
she tried to break the necklace.
So Ma untied it and put it away.
'Carrie can wear it when she's older,' Ma
said.
Laura still wanted those pretty beads for
herself.
But she knew it had been a wonderful day.
She knew she was never going to forget the
Indian camp.
CHAPTER SIX
Summertime on the prairie
Summer had come to the prairie, and the air
was still and warm.
One evening Laura and Pa were sitting outside
under a big moon while Pa played his fiddle.
Everything was so beautiful.
Laura wanted it to stay that way forever.
Suddenly she heard a strange, low sound far
away.
'What's that?'
she asked.
Pa listened.
'Cattle!' he said.
'It must be the cattle herds going north.'
They listened together and Laura thought she
could hear a song.
'Is that singing, Pa?' she asked.
'Yes,' Pa said.
'The cowboys are singing to their cattle.
It's time for them to sleep, and you too!'
The next morning when Laura ran out of the
house, two strange men were sitting on horses
by the stable.
They were talking to Pa.
They were as red-brown as Indians, and they
wore big, wide hats and cowboy boots.
Handkerchiefs were tied around their necks,
and guns were at their sides.
They said goodbye to Pa and rode away across
the hot prairie.
'What a piece of luck!'
Pa said to Ma.
'Those men are cowboys.
They want me to help them to move the cattle
across the creek.
They'll pay me with beef.
How would you like a good piece of beef?'
'Oh, Charles!'
Ma said, and her eyes shone.
Pa tied his biggest handkerchief around his
neck.
He showed Laura how a cowboy pulls it up over
his mouth and nose to keep the dust out.
Then Pa rode Patty down the Indian trail.
All day the sun shone hot and the sound of
cattle herds came nearer.
Laura and Mary could see the dust that they
made.
Pa came riding home as the sun was going down,
covered with dust.
There was dust in his hair and around his
eyes, and dust fell from his clothes.
He was going to work again the next day because
the cattle were not across the creek yet.
The cattle moved slowly, eating grass as they
went.
Pa fell asleep soon after supper that night.
Laura lay awake and listened to the sounds
of the cattle on the prairie and the high,
lonely songs of the cowboys.
The songs sounded like the crying of wolves
under the moon, and they made Laura feel sad.
All the next day, Laura and Mary watched the
prairie.
Suddenly out of the dusty grass, not far from
the stable, cattle came running.
They ran fast, their feet beating the ground.
A cowboy on a black-and-white horse rode faster
to get in front of them.
He waved his big hat and shouted at the cattle
as he moved them along.
They all went over a low hill and disappeared.
Laura ran around outside, waving her hat and
shouting wildly.
'Laura,' Ma said.
'Stop that!
A young lady shouldn't shout like that.'
'I wish I could be a cowboy, Ma,' Laura said.
Late that afternoon, Laura saw Pa riding home
with two cowboys, a cow, and a little black-and-white
calf.
Pa tied the cow to the stable and said goodbye
to the cowboys.
Ma's eyes opened wide when she saw their new
animals.
'They gave me the cow because she was too
thin to sell,' Pa said when he came in the
house.
'And the calf is too small to travel.
They gave me the beef, too.'
Then Pa went out to the stable to get some
milk from the cow for Baby Carrie.
They watched her drink all that good milk.
Baby Carrie's little red tongue cleaned her
milky lips and she laughed.
Ma cooked the beef and everyone felt happy.
Nothing had ever tasted as good as that thick,
red meat.
The cattle were far away now, and the girls
couldn't hear the songs of the cowboys any
more.
A little later in the year, there were blackberries,
and in the hot afternoons, Laura went with
Ma to pick them in the bushes by the creek.
There were mosquitoes everywhere in the blackberry
bushes, and they liked to bite Laura and Ma.
Laura's fingers and her mouth got purple-black
from eating the big blackberries.
Her face, hands, and feet were covered with
mosquito bites.
But every day they brought home buckets full
of berries, and Ma laid them out in the sun
to dry.
In the day there were only a few mosquitoes
in the house.
But at night, if the wind wasn't blowing hard,
there were lots of them.
On still nights Pa burned wet grass around
the house to keep the mosquitoes away, but
they came just the same.
Pa could not play his fiddle in the evenings
because so many mosquitoes bit him.
Mr Edwards did not visit after supper, because
there were too many mosquitoes in the creek.
And every morning Laura's face was full of
red mosquito bites.
'It'll get colder soon,' Pa said, 'and then
they'll go.'
Laura did not feel very well.
One day she felt cold even in the hot sun,
and she could not get warm by the fire.
'Why don't you and Mary go out to play?'
Ma asked Laura.
'I don't want to play,' answered Laura.
'I'm tired and I ache.'
Ma stopped her work.
'Where do you ache?'
'I don't know,' said Laura.
'I just ache.
My legs ache.'
'I ache, too,' Mary said.
Ma put her hand against Laura's face.
'You're as hot as fire,' she said.
Laura felt like crying, but of course she
didn't.
Only little babies cried.
'I'm cold now,' she said.
'And my back aches.'
'Charles,' Ma called.
'Look at the girls.
I think they're sick.'
Pa and Ma put them to bed in the middle of
the day.
Laura did not really go to sleep, but she
did not really wake up again for a long, long
time.
Strange things seemed to be happening.
She heard voices, but no words.
Sometimes she felt as cold as ice, and then
she was burning.
Days and nights passed like this.
She heard Pa say, 'Go to bed, Caroline.'
Ma said, 'You're sicker than I am, Charles.'
Then one day Laura opened her eyes and saw
the bright light of the sun.
Mary was beside her crying, 'I want a drink
of water!
I want a drink of water!'
Jack was walking between the big bed and her
little bed.
Pa was lying on the floor by the big bed.
Jack took Pa's shirt in his teeth and shook
it.
Pa's head lifted up a little, and he said,
'I must get up, I must.
Caroline and the girls.'
Then his head fell back and he lay still.
Jack howled.
Laura tried to get up, but she was too tired.
Then she saw Ma's red face looking from the
big bed.
Mary was still crying for water.
Ma looked at Mary and then she looked at Laura,
and she whispered, 'Laura, can you get up?'
'Yes, Ma.'
Laura said.
This time she got out of bed, but when she
tried to stand up, she fell down again.
She felt Jack's tongue on her face and she
held onto him and sat up.
She knew she must get water for Mary, and
she did.
She crawled all the way across the floor to
the water bucket and then crawled all the
way back to Mary with the water.
Mary's eyes did not open, but her mouth drank
all the water.
Then she stopped crying.
Laura crawled back into bed.
It was a long time before she began to get
warm again.
Sometimes she heard Jack howling and she thought
he was a wolf.
She lay in bed burning and hearing him howl.
She heard the voices talking again, and she
opened her eyes and saw a big, black face
close to hers.
Its eyes were black and soft.
This face smiled, and a deep voice said softly,
'Drink this, little girl.'
Laura opened her mouth but the drink was bitter
and she turned her head away.
The deep voice said again, 'Drink it.
It will make you well.'
So she drank the bitter medicine.
When Laura woke again a fat woman was by the
fire.
She brought Laura water and a cup of something
hot that tasted good, like chicken.
'Drink it all up, like a good child,' she
said.
Laura looked at Mary asleep beside her; she
looked at Pa and Ma asleep in the big bed.
Jack lay half asleep on the floor.
Laura looked again at the fat woman and asked,
'Who are you?'
'I'm Mrs Scott,' she said, smiling.
'I'm here to take care of everything until
you're all well.
Now go to sleep.'
The next morning Laura felt so much better
that she wanted to get up, but Mrs Scott said
she must stay in bed until the doctor came.
Laura was surprised when she saw him.
He was the black man!
Laura had never seen a black man before, and
she could not take her eyes off Dr Tan.
He talked with Pa and Ma and laughed his big
laugh before he hurried away.
Mrs Scott said that all the settlers along
the creek were sick.
She had been going from house to house, working
day and night.
'You're lucky to be alive,' she said.
'It's because Dr Tan found you when he did.'
Dr Tan was a doctor with the Indians.
He was on his way to the town of Independence
when he passed Pa's house.
Strangely Jack, who usually hated strangers,
had run after Dr Tan and made him come in.
'And here you all were, more dead than alive,'
Mrs Scott said.
'All of you sick at the same time.
Dr Tan stayed with you a day and a night before
I came.
Now he's taking care of all the sick settlers.'
The next day Pa and Laura were out of bed.
The next day, Ma got up, and then Mary.
They were all thin and shaky, but they could
take care of themselves.
So Mrs Scott went home.
'How can we ever thank you?'
Ma said.
'It's nothing,' Mrs Scott said.
'Neighbours are there to help each other.'
Pa was thinner and walked slowly, and Ma often
sat down.
Mary and Laura didn't feel like playing.
But every day they got a little bit stronger.
Pa couldn't work outside, so he sat in the
house and made a beautiful chair for Ma.
He played his fiddle, and Mary and Laura were
happy.
No one knew, in those days, that the illness
was malaria, and that it came from the mosquitoes.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Mr Edwards meets Santa Claus
The prairie had changed.
Now the days were short and cold and the wind
howled.
Day after day the cold rain fell.
Mary and Laura played close to the fire and
listened to the wet sound of rain.
The nights were cold, but it never snowed.
Every morning they saw only sad, wet grass.
They wished they could see snow.
Laura was worried because Christmas was near,
and Santa Claus could not travel without snow.
Mary thought that, with or without snow, perhaps
Santa Claus couldn't find them, so far away
in Indian Territory.
'What day is it?'
the girls asked Ma.
'How many more days until Christmas?'
And they counted the days until there was
only one more day to go.
Rain was still falling that morning.
'Perhaps there won't be a Christmas this year,'
Laura said.
Still she went on hoping.
But when Ma opened the door to let in some
air and Laura heard the noise of the creek,
she knew there was not going to be a Christmas
that year.
The creek was full and roaring with water.
Santa Claus could not possibly cross it.
Pa came in, bringing a big fat turkey.
'How's that for a Christmas dinner?' he asked.
'Pa, is the water in the creek going down?'
Mary asked.
'No, Mary, the water is moving fast.
It'll be too dangerous for Mr Edwards to try
to cross it now,' Pa replied.
Mr Edwards was invited to eat Christmas dinner
with them, but now it looked impossible.
'No,' Pa said.
'I don't think Edwards will be here tomorrow.'
'Then Santa Claus can't come either,' said
Mary.
'It's too bad,' Ma said.
'But I know he hasn't forgotten you girls.
He'll come next year, I'm sure.'
Still.
Laura and Mary were not happy.
It did not seem at all like Christmas.
Even Pa did not want to play his fiddle.
After a long while, Ma suddenly stood up.
'I'm going to put up your stockings, girls,'
she said.
'Perhaps something will happen.'
Laura's heart jumped.
But then she remembered the roaring creek
and felt sad.
She and Mary watched Ma put their stockings
over the fireplace.
'Now go to sleep,' Ma said, kissing them as
they lay in their beds.
'Morning will come quicker if you're asleep.'
Then Laura heard Jack growl and someone crying,
'Ingalls!
Ingalls!'
When Pa opened the door, Laura saw that it
was morning.
'Edwards!
Come in, man!
What's happened?
Come sit by the fire!'
Pa said.
Mr Edwards was shaking with cold.
'I swam across the creek,' he said.
'I carried my clothes on my head.
But I'll be all right as soon as I get warm.'
'It was too dangerous, Edwards,' Pa said.
'We're happy you're here, but it was too dangerous
for a Christmas dinner.'
'Your little ones needed a Christmas,' Mr
Edwards replied.
'I had their presents from Independence, so
no creek could stop me.'
Laura sat straight up in bed.
'Did you see Santa Claus in Independence?'
she shouted.
'I sure did.'
Mr Edwards said.
'Where?
When?
What did he look like?
Did he really give you something for us?'
Mary and Laura cried.
'Wait, wait a minute!'
Mr Edwards laughed.
'I'll put Santa's presents in your stockings,
girls,' said Ma, 'like Santa usually does.
You mustn't look.'
They tried not to look at Ma as Mr Edwards
answered all their questions.
When he saw the creek was so full, he said,
he knew Santa Claus could not get across it.
'But you did,' said Laura.
'Yes, but I'm young.
Santa Claus is too old and fat.
I knew that Santa could only get as far south
as Independence.
So I walked to Independence and met Santa
coming up the street, and the first thing
he said to me was "Hello Edwards".'
'How did he know you?' asked Laura.
'Santa Claus knows everybody,' said Mr Edwards.
And he said he knew two good little girls
named Mary and Laura who lived by the Verdigris
River.
He asked me to bring your presents for him
this year because with the water so high,
he couldn't cross the creek himself.
So here I am, sent by Santa Claus.'
Laura and Mary were silent a minute, thinking
about that.
Then Ma said.
'You may look now.
girls.'
Something was shining bright in the top of
Laura's stocking.
She jumped out of bed.
So did Mary, but Laura beat her to the fireplace.
And the shining thing was a bright new tin
cup.
Mary had one just like it.
These new tin cups were their very own.
Now they each had a cup to drink from.
Laura jumped up and down and shouted and laughed,
but Mary stood still and looked with bright
eyes at her own tin cup.
Then they reached into the stockings again.
And they pulled out two long sticks of red
and white candy.
They looked and looked at that beautiful candy.
Laura put her tongue on her candy, just to
taste it, but Mary only looked at hers.
Those stockings were not empty yet.
They each pulled out a little cake shaped
like a heart.
They had white sugar - like snow - on top
and were too pretty to eat.
Laura and Mary just sat there, but then Ma
said.
Are you sure the stockings are empty?'
The girls put their arms down inside them
again.
And in the toe of each stocking was a shiny
bright new penny!
They could not speak.
There had never been such a Christmas.
'Aren't you going to thank Mr Edwards?'
Ma said gently.
'Oh, thank you, Mr Edwards!
Thank you!'
they said, and they meant it with all their
hearts.
Pa shook Mr Edwards' hand, and Pa and Ma and
Mr Edwards looked like they were almost crying.
Laura didn't know why.
Then Ma's eyes opened wide.
Mr Edwards was taking sweet potatoes from
his pockets.
They were for Christmas dinner.
Mr Edwards had brought them all the way from
town, too.
'It's too much, Edwards,' Pa said.
'We can never thank you enough.'
For Christmas dinner there was the big, tasty
turkey.
There was bread that Ma had made, and there
were the sweet potatoes.
And after all that, they ate dried blackberries
and little cakes.
Then Pa and Ma and Mr Edwards sat by the fire
and talked about Christmas times back in Wisconsin.
Mary and Laura looked at their beautiful cakes
and played with their pennies.
Little by little, they ate their sticks of
candy.
That was a happy Christmas.
CHAPTER EIGHT
More and more Indians
The nights were still cold on the High Prairie,
and the days were short and grey.
Indians came riding on the path that passed
so close to the house.
They sat up straight on their naked horses
and did not look right or left.
But their black eyes shone.
Mary and Laura sat against the house and looked
up at them.
'I'm sorry I built the house so close to the
Indian trail,' Pa said.
'But I thought they didn't use it anymore.'
'Yes, there are so many Indians around here,'
Ma said.
'I can't look up without seeing one.'
As she spoke she looked up, and there stood
an Indian.
He was in the doorway and they had not heard
a sound.
'Oh, dear!'
Ma whispered, frightened.
Jack jumped at the Indian.
Pa caught him just in time.
'How!'
the Indian said to Pa.
Pa held onto Jack and replied, 'How!'
He pulled Jack over to the bed and tied him
there.
The Indian came in and sat down by the fire,
and Pa sat down next to him.
They sat there, friendly but not talking,
while Ma finished cooking dinner.
Laura and Mary were quiet on their bed in
the corner.
They couldn't take their eyes from that Indian.
He was so still that the beautiful eagle feathers
in his hair did not move.
He wore trousers made of animal skins, and
his moccasins were covered with beads.
Pa and the Indian ate silently.
Then Pa gave the Indian some tobacco for his
pipe.
They filled their pipes, lighted them, and
silently smoked until the pipes were empty.
All this time nobody had said anything.
But now the Indian said something to Pa.
Pa shook his head and said.
'No speak.'
They all sat silent a while longer.
Then the tall Indian got up and went away
without a sound.
'Oh, dear!'
Ma said again.
Pa said the Indian was an important man.
'He wore eagle feathers in his hair.
I think he was an Osage Indian.
I'm sure that was French he was speaking.
I wish I spoke some French.'
'I think Indians should stay together with
other Indians,' Ma said, 'and we'll do the
same.'
'Don't worry, Caroline,' Pa said.
'That Indian was very friendly.
And their camps down along the creek are quiet
enough.
If we're polite to them and watch Jack, we
won't have any trouble.'
The very next morning when Pa opened the door,
Laura saw Jack standing on the Indian trail,
showing all his teeth.
Right in front of him was the tall Indian,
sitting very still on his horse.
Jack looked ready to jump at them.
When the Indian saw Pa, he lifted his gun
and pointed it straight at Jack.
Pa ran to the trail and pulled Jack out of
the way, and the Indian rode on.
'We were lucky that time!'
Pa said.
'Well, it's his path.
It was an Indian trail long before we came.'
After that, Jack was always tied up.
He got crosser and crosser, but there was
nothing Pa could do about it.
'If Jack hurts an Indian,' he said, 'there
will be bad trouble.'
Wild animals were wearing their thick winter
fur, and Pa went hunting every day.
He caught small animals and shot large ones
for their fur.
He carefully put the skins outside the house
to dry in the sun.
In the evenings he pulled the dry skins between
his hands to make them soft, and every day
the bundle of furs on the floor grew bigger.
Laura loved to feel the soft fur in her fingers.
Pa was saving all these furs to trade next
spring in Independence.
One day when Pa was hunting, two Indians walked
right into the house.
They were dirty and cross.
One of them looked at all the things in Ma's
cupboard and took all the cornbread.
The other took Pa's tobacco.
Then one of them picked up the bundle of furs.
Ma held Baby Carrie in her arms, and Mary
and Laura stood close to her.
They looked at that Indian taking all Pa's
furs but they couldn't do anything to stop
him.
The Indian carried the furs as far as the
door.
Then the other Indian said something to him
in an angry voice, and he dropped the bundle.
They finally went away.
Ma sat down and pulled Mary and Laura close
to her, and Laura felt Ma's heart beating.
'Well,' said Ma, smiling, 'I'm thankful they
didn't take the plough and seeds.'
Laura was surprised.
She asked, 'What plough?'
'Your Pa is going to trade that bundle of
furs for a plough and lots of different seeds
in the spring.'
Ma said.
When Pa came home they told him about those
Indians, and he looked serious.
'But all's well that ends well,' he said.
'And soon all the Indians here will move west.'
'Why do they go west?'
Laura asked.
'When white settlers arrive in a place, the
Indians have to move away from there.'
'But why?'
'The government makes them.
Laura.'
Pa said.
'That's why we're here.
Lots of white people are going to come and
live here.
We came first to choose the best land.
Now do you understand?'
'Yes.
Pa,' Laura said.
'But.
Pa, I thought this was Indian Territory.
Won't the Indians be angry if they have to-'
'No more questions, Laura,' Pa said.
'It's time for bed.'
Winter ended at last.
The wind was softer, and the terrible cold
was gone.
One day Pa said it was time to take his furs
to Independence.
Ma said.
'But the Indians are so near!'
'They're very friendly.'
Pa said.
'I often meet them when I'm hunting in the
forest.
You needn't be afraid of them.'
'No,' Ma said.
But Laura knew that Ma was afraid of Indians.
'You must go, Charles,' she said.
'We must have a plough and seeds.
And you'll be back soon.'
The next morning before the sun came up, Pa
got the horses ready, put the furs into the
wagon, and drove away.
Laura and Mary counted the long, empty days.
One, two, three, four, and still Pa had not
come home.
Ma said it was taking him a long time to trade
his furs in town.
In the afternoon of the fifth day, Laura and
Mary were playing a game outside.
The weather was wild and sweet.
The wind smelled like spring, and birds were
flying north in the wide blue sky.
Suddenly Mary stopped and said, 'What's that?'
Laura had already heard the strange noise.
'It's the Indians,' she said.
Mary stood still.
She was frightened.
Laura was not really afraid, but that noise
made her feel strange.
It was the sound of many Indian voices, something
like an axe cutting wood or like a dog barking.
It was wild, but it didn't seem angry.
Ma came outdoors and listened for a minute.
Then she locked the animals in the stable.
She told Laura and Mary to bring wood into
the house.
The sound was getting louder, now, and faster.
It made Laura's heart beat fast.
'Come inside the house, now,' Ma said.
She took Jack inside, too, and locked the
door.
The sun went down and the sky turned bright
pink.
Ma was busy getting supper ready, but Laura
and Mary watched from the window silently.
All that time the sound from the creek got
louder and louder, faster and faster.
And Laura's heart beat faster and louder.
Then she heard Pa's wagon!
Laura and Mary ran to the door and jumped
on Pa, who had his arms full.
Pa laughed his big laugh.
'What do you think I am,' he laughed, 'a tree
to climb?'
He dropped his bundles on the table and put
his big arms around them.
'Listen to the Indians.
Pa,' Laura said.
'Why are they making that strange noise?'
'Oh, they're having some kind of jamboree.
I heard them when I crossed the creek.'
Then he went to put the horses and the new
plough in the stable.
When he came back, they opened the bundles.
He had bought brown sugar, coffee, cornmeal,
salt, and all the seeds that they needed.
Then Pa gave Ma a packet.
He watched her open it with his big smile.
There was pretty cotton cloth in it for her
to make herself a dress.
'Oh, Charles, you shouldn't!
It's too much!'
she cried.
But her face shone with happiness.
Mary watched Pa quietly, but Laura climbed
onto his leg and began beating him with her
hands.
'Where is it?
Where's my present?'
she said, beating him.
Pa laughed his big laugh, like great bells
ringing, and he pulled a packet out of his
shirt pocket.
'You first, Mary,' he said, 'because you're
waiting so quietly.'
And he gave Mary a comb to wear in her hair.
'And here you are, Laura!
This is for you,' he said.
The combs were just alike.
They both had a bright star on the top.
Mary's star was blue and Laura's was red.
Ma put the combs in their hair.
They laughed with excitement.
They had never had anything so pretty.
Ma said, 'But Charles, you didn't get yourself
a thing!'
'Oh, I got myself a plough,' said Pa.
'The weather will soon be warm enough to start
using it.'
That was the happiest supper they had had
in a long time.
The salt pork that Pa had brought was very
good.
And Pa told them all about the seeds.
He had got tobacco seeds and corn seeds, and
the seeds of many different kinds of vegetables
like carrots and potatoes.
'I tell you, Caroline, when these seeds grow
in this rich land of ours, we'll be living
like kings!'
Pa said.
They had almost forgotten the wild noise from
the Indian camps.
But then Pa said something to Ma that made
Laura sit very still and listen carefully.
'People in Independence say the government
is going to move the white settlers out of
Indian Territory.'
'Oh.
no!'
Ma said.
'Not when we have done so much.'
'Well, I don't believe what I heard,' Pa said.
'The government has always let settlers keep
the land.
I think they'll make the Indians move west
again.'
Laura lay awake in bed a long time that night.
She could still hear the noise of the wild
jamboree in the Indian camp.
Their fierce cries were carried on the screaming
wind.
They made her heart beat faster and faster
and faster.
CHAPTER NINE
Prairie fire
Spring had come.
The warm winds smelled exciting, and the outdoors
was large and bright and sweet.
Big white clouds were high up in the sky,
and you could see their shadows over the prairie.
Pa was working hard, getting ready to plant
potatoes.
Pet and Patty were working hard, too, pulling
the heavy plough.
The plough was breaking up the grassy earth,
and turning it over.
Pa liked the land because it was so rich,
and there wasn't a tree or stone in it.
Now many Indians came riding along the Indian
trail.
Indians were everywhere.
Laura could hear their guns in the creeks
when they were hunting.
Indians often came to the house.
Some of them were friendly, and some were
not.
All of them wanted food and tobacco, and Ma
gave them what they wanted.
But most of the food in the house was hidden.
Jack was miserable all the time.
He was always tied up, and all the time he
lay and hated the Indians.
Laura and Mary were not surprised to see Indians
anymore.
But they always felt safer near Pa or Jack.
One day they were helping Ma to get dinner
ready.
Baby Carrie was playing on the floor in the
sun, and suddenly the light was gone.
'I think it's going to rain,' Ma said, looking
out the window.
Laura looked, too, and saw great black clouds
in the south across the sun.
Pet and Patty came running from the field
pulling the plough behind them and with Pa
running after them.
'Prairie fire!' he shouted.
'Fill the tub with water!
Put sacks in it!
Hurry!'
Ma ran to the well, and Laura pulled the tub
to it.
Pa put the cows in the barn.
Ma started pulling up water as fast as she
could.
Laura ran to get the sacks from the stable.
The sky was black now in the south, almost
as dark as night.
Pet and Patty were still pulling the plough,
with Pa running behind them.
Pa was making a long trench all the way around
three sides of the house.
He was shouting at the horses to make them
hurry.
Frightened rabbits came running across the
prairie past Pa.
When the trench around the house was finished,
Pa tied the horses to the house.
The tub was full of water.
Laura and Ma pushed the sacks into the water
and made them very wet.
'Hurry, Caroline,' Pa shouted.
'The fire's coming faster than a horse can
run.'
A big rabbit jumped right over the tub while
Pa and Ma were lifting it.
Ma told Laura to stay at the house.
Pa and Ma carried the heavy tub all the way
to the trench.
Laura stayed close to the house.
She could see the red fire coming under the
big black cloud of smoke.
Jack was trembling and crying and staying
close to Laura.
The wind was blowing harder and screaming
wildly.
More and more rabbits came running.
Birds screamed in the screaming wind.
All the wild things on the prairie ran or
jumped or flew as fast as they could go down
to the creek.
Pa was going along the trench, making a small
fire in the grass on the other side of it.
Ma followed him with a wet sack, beating violently
at the small fire when it crossed to her side
of the trench.
Soon Pa's small fire was burning along the
other side of the trench all around the house.
He and Ma fought it when it crossed the trench
to their side.
They beat it with the wet sacks, and did not
let it come toward the house.
The big prairie fire was roaring now, roaring
louder and louder in the screaming wind.
Great flames turned and climbed high into
the sky.
Mary and Laura stood against the house and
held hands and trembled.
Baby Carrie was in the house.
Laura wanted to do something, but inside her
head it was roaring like the fire.
Her body shook.
The smoke burned her nose, and her red eyes
couldn't stop crying.
Jack howled.
The orange and yellow flames were coming faster
than horses can run, and their terrible light
danced over everything.
Pa's small fire burned slowly, moving away
from the house.
Slowly it went to meet the big wall of fire.
And suddenly the big fire ate the little fire.
The wind screamed louder and the flames climbed
all the way to the sky.
Fire was all around the house.
Then suddenly it was all over.
The fire roared past the house and was gone.
Pa and Ma were beating little fires that burned
here and there around the house.
When those fires were out, Ma came to the
house to wash.
Her skin was black with smoke, and she was
trembling.
'Don't worry, girls,' she said.
'Pa's little fire saved us.
And all's well that ends well.'
The air smelled of burned grass.
Smoke was blowing in the wind.
The wide prairie was black all the way to
the line where the sky began.
Everything felt different and miserable.
But Pa and Ma were happy because the house
was safe.
The animals came out of the creek.
The birds came flying, the rabbits jumped
slowly and looked, and the prairie chickens
came out walking.
That night Mr Edwards and Mr Scott came to
see Pa.
They were worried.
'Maybe the Indians started the fire to frighten
us.
Maybe they want all the white settlers to
leave,' Mr Scott said.
'I don't believe it,' said Pa.
'The Indians have always burned the prairie
to make the green grass grow more quickly.
And it's easier for them to ride their horses
in shorter grass.'
While they were talking, they could hear the
drums that were beating in the camps, and
the shouts of the Indians.
Laura sat quietly listening to the talk and
to the Indians.
'There are too many Indians in those camps,'
said Mr Edwards.
'I don't like it.'
'The only good Indian is a dead Indian,' Mr
Scott said.
'I don't know,' Pa said.
'I think the Indians are as good as anyone,
if they are left alone.
But the government has moved them west so
many times.
Naturally, they hate white settlers, but they're
afraid of the white soldiers at Fort Dodge
and Fort Gibson.
I don't think they'll make any trouble.'
'Why are so many of them in the camps?' asked
Mr Scott.
'They're just getting ready to hunt buffalo.'
Pa said.
'Well,' Mr Scott said slowly, 'I hope you're
right, Ingalls.
I really hope you're right.'
CHAPTER TEN
Indian war-cry
The next day Pa worked in the field, getting
it ready to plant the seeds.
He came in at noon, black from the burned
prairie, but he was pleased.
He didn't have to worry about the tall grass
anymore.
But he began to worry about the Indians.
More and more of them were camping near the
creek.
Mary and Laura saw the smoke from their fires
by day, and at night they heard fierce shouts.
When shadows began to fall on the prairie
and the wind was quiet, the noises from the
Indian camps grew louder and wilder.
Pa shut the horses and cows in the stable
and brought Jack into the house.
No one could go outdoors until morning.
In her sleep Laura heard the wild noises and
beating drums.
One night Pa sat by the fireplace making bullets.
Laura and Mary lay awake and watched him.
'Why are you doing that, Pa?'
Mary asked.
'Oh, I have nothing better to do,' Pa said.
But Laura knew he was tired from working in
the field and wanted to sleep.
No more Indians came to the house.
Mary did not want to go out of the house anymore,
so Laura had to play outside by herself.
But she felt strange there.
The prairie didn't feel safe anymore.
Mr Scott and Mr Edwards, with their guns,
came and talked to Pa in the field one day.
At dinner, Pa told Ma that some of the settlers
were talking about building a stockade.
'I told Scott and Edwards that it wasn't a
good idea.
If we need one, we'll need it before we can
build it.
And the worst thing is to show that we're
afraid.'
Laura wondered why Pa was talking this way.
Pa was never afraid.
But she was.
Every night the Indian drums beat faster and
faster, and their cries got wilder and wilder.
In the middle of the night.
Laura sat straight up in bed and screamed.
A terrible sound had woken her.
Ma came quickly and said in her gentle way,
'Be quiet, Laura.
You mustn't frighten Carrie.'
The house was dark, but Ma was still wearing
her dress.
She had not gone to bed.
Pa stood by the window, looking out.
He had his gun.
Then that terrible sound came again.
'What is it?'
Laura screamed.
'What is it?
Oh, Pa, what is it?'
Pa said, 'It's the Indian war-cry, Laura.'
Ma made a soft sound, and he said to her,
'They need to know, Caroline.'
He explained that the Indians were dancing
around their fires and talking about war.
'But I'm here and Jack's here,' Pa said, 'and
there are soldiers at Fort Dodge.
So don't be afraid, Mary and Laura.'
'No, Pa,' Laura said.
But she was terribly afraid.
The drums seemed to beat inside her head.
The wild howls were worse than wolves.
Then they heard the sound of a running horse.
It came nearer and nearer.
In the light of the moon, Laura saw a little
black horse with an Indian on its back.
The Indian had a blanket around him, feathers
on his head, and a gun at his side.
He rode by as fast as the wind, and then he
was gone.
'That was the tall Osage Indian who came to
the house once and talked French to me!'
Pa said.
'What's he doing out at this hour, riding
so fast?'
Nobody answered because nobody knew.
The next day they could not go out of the
house.
There was not one sound from the Indian camps.
The whole wide prairie was still.
But that night the noise in the camps was
worse than the night before.
The war-cries were terrible.
Pa watched at the window with his gun, Laura
and Mary stayed close to Ma, and poor little
Carrie cried.
Jack growled all night long, and he howled
when the war-cries came.
Night after night, the Indians shouted and
danced and beat their drums.
All up and down the creek, war-cries answered
war-cries.
The sound filled the prairie.
There was no rest.
Laura ached all over.
The silent days were worse than the nights.
The animals stayed in the stable.
Mary and Laura could not go out of the house.
And Pa watched and listened all the time.
He didn't eat much.
One day his head fell onto the table and he
slept a little.
He was so tired.
But in a minute he woke up with a jump and
said, crossly, to Ma, 'Don't let me do that
again!'
That night was the worst night of all.
The drums beat faster and the war cries made
their blood run cold.
At the window Pa said, 'Caroline, they're
quarrelling among themselves.
Maybe they'll fight each other.'
'Oh, Charles, I hope so!'
Ma said.
All night long there was not a minute's rest.
Just before the sun came up, the last war-cry
ended and Laura fell asleep in Ma's arms.
She woke up in bed.
The door was open, and the sun was high in
the sky.
It was already noon.
Ma was cooking dinner and Pa was sitting outside
on the step.
He said to Ma, 'There's another big group,
going off to the south.'
Laura went to the door and saw a long line
of Indians far away.
Pa told her that two long lines of Indians
had gone west that morning.
Now this one was going south.
It meant that the Indians had argued among
themselves and were not going to hunt buffalo
together.
'Tonight we'll sleep!'
Pa said, and they did.
They did not even dream.
In the morning Pa took his gun and went down
the creek road.
Laura and Mary and Ma stayed in the house
and waited the whole long day.
When Pa came back in the late afternoon, he
said everything was all right.
He had gone up and down the creek and seen
many empty Indian camps.
All the Indian tribes had left, except the
Osages.
He had met an Osage in the forest who could
speak English.
He told Pa that all the tribes except the
Osages wanted to kill the settlers.
The tall Indian had ridden so far and so fast
that night because he did not want them to
kill the white people.
He was an Osage chief, and his name was Great
Soldier.
'He went on arguing with them day and night,'
Pa said, 'until the other Osages agreed with
him.
Then he told the other tribes that the Osages
were ready to fight them to save the white
settlers.'
That was why there had been so much noise
in the camps.
The Indian tribes were howling at each other.
In the end, the other tribes did not want
to fight Great Soldier and the Osages.
So they went away.
'That's one good Indian!'
Pa said.
There was another long night of sleep.
In the morning Pa opened the door to let in
the warm spring air.
He stood on the step, looking east, and he
said, 'Come here, Caroline.
And you, Mary and Laura.'
Laura ran out first, and she was surprised.
The Indians were coming.
First came the tall Indian chief who had saved
their lives.
His black horse was very near now, and Laura's
heart beat fast.
She looked at the Indian's moccasins, at his
colourful blanket, at his naked brown-red
arms that carried the long gun.
His face was still and tierce.
Only the long eagle feathers in his hair moved
in the wind.
'Great Soldier himself,' Pa said softly.
He lifted his hand to say hello.
But the horse and the Indian chief went by
without looking at Pa or Ma or Mary or Laura
or the house.
Then other horses and Indians with eagle feathers
in their hair went by.
Brown face after brown face went by.
Bright beads shone in the sun, and horses'
tails and eagle feathers blew in the wind.
The women and children came riding behind
the Indian men.
Little naked brown Indians, no bigger than
Mary and Laura, went riding by.
They did not have to wear clothes.
All their skin was out in the air.
Their straight black hair blew in the wind
and their black eyes shone with happiness.
Laura looked and looked at the Indian children,
and they looked at her.
She had a sudden wish to be a little Indian
girl, to ride naked in the wind and the sun.
Then Indian mothers came riding by with babies
in baskets at the sides of their horses.
Laura looked straight into the bright eyes
of one little baby.
Its eyes were black as a night when no stars
shine.
'Pa,' she said, 'get me that little Indian
baby!'
Be quiet, Laura!
Pa said.
The baby's head turned and its eyes looked
into Laura's eyes.
'Oh, I want it!
I want it!'
Laura cried.
'It wants to stay with me.
Please, Pa, please!'
'Quiet, Laura,' Pa said.
'The Indian woman wants to keep her baby.'
Then Laura began to cry.
The little papoose was gone.
She was never going to see it again.
'I've never heard of such a thing,' Ma said.
'Why do you want an Indian baby, of all things?'
'Its eyes are so black,' Laura cried.
She could not say what she meant.
No one was hungry for dinner.
Pa and Ma and Mary and Laura stayed by the
door and looked at the long line of Indians
until nothing was left but silence and emptiness.
All the world seemed very quiet and lonely.
One morning the whole prairie was green.
Pa hurried into the field with the horses
and his plough, and Mary and Laura helped
Ma plant the seeds for the vegetables.
They were all so happy because spring had
come.
'Soon we'll have vegetables to eat and we'll
live like kings!'
Pa said.
One day Mary and Laura were washing dishes
in the house when they heard Pa's voice, loud
and angry.
They looked out and saw Mr Edwards and Mr
Scott in the field with Pa.
'No, Scott!' said Pa.
'I won't stay here until the soldiers take
me away like a criminal.
The government in Washington told us it was
all right to build our houses here.
But if now they want us to go, we'll go.
We won't wait for the soldiers to make us
leave.
We're going now!'
'What's the matter, Charles?
Where are we going?'
Ma asked.
'I don't know, Caroline!
But we're going.
We're leaving here,' Pa said.
'Scott and Edwards say the government is sending
soldiers to make the settlers leave Indian
Territory.'
His face was very red and his eyes were like
blue fire.
Laura was frightened; she had never seen Pa
look like that.
'I'm going, too,' said Mr Edwards.
'Take the cow and the calf,' Pa said to Mr
Scott.
'You've been a good neighbour, and I'm sorry
to leave you.
But we're going in the morning.'
After Mr Scott left with the animals, Mr Edwards
and Pa shook hands and said goodbye.
Then he shook hands with Ma and said.
'Goodbye, Mrs Ingalls.
I'll never forget how kind you were to me.'
Mary said politely, 'Goodbye, Mr Edwards.'
But Laura forgot to be polite.
She said, 'Oh, Mr Edwards, please don't go
away!
Oh, Mr Edwards, thank you, thank you for going
all the way to Independence to find Santa
Claus for us.'
Mr Edwards eyes shone very bright, and he
went away without saying another word.
Pa began to put the canvas cover on the wagon
and Laura and Mary knew it was true; they
really were going away.
Everyone was quiet that night.
Ma looked sad and said gently, 'A year gone.
Charles.'
But Pa answered with a smile, 'What's a year?
We have all the time in the world.'
The next morning, Pa and Ma packed the wagon.
First Ma laid two beds across the back of
the wagon.
Then she and Pa packed the clothes, the food,
and the dishes.
The only thing they could not take was the
plough.
Laura and Mary climbed into the wagon and
sat on the bed in the back.
Ma put Baby Carrie between them.
Ma climbed to her place on the seat.
Then suddenly Laura wanted to see the house
again.
So Pa opened the back of the wagon cover,
and Mary and Laura looked out at their little
log house.
Pa climbed to his place beside Ma and took
the reins in his hands.
Jack went under the wagon, and Pet and Patty
walked away from the little house on the prairie.
As far as they could see, to the east and
to the south and to the west, nothing was
moving.
Only the green grass was waving in the wind.
'It's a great country, Caroline,' Pa said.
'But there will be wild Indians and wolves
here for many years.'
Pa and Ma were still and silent, and Mary
and Laura were quiet, too.
But Laura felt all excited inside.
You never know what will happen next, nor
where you will be tomorrow, when you are travelling
in a covered wagon.
- THE END -