The Call of Cthulhu
by H. P. Lovecraft
Written Summer 1926
Published February 1928 in Weird
Tales, Vol. 11, No. 2, p. 159-78, 287.
Of such great powers or beings there may
be conceivably a survival… a survival of
a hugely remote period when… consciousness
was manifested, perhaps, in shapes and forms
long since withdrawn before the tide of advancing
humanity… forms of which poetry and legend alone
have caught a flying memory and called them gods,
monsters, mythical beings of all sorts and kinds…
- Algernon Blackwood
I. The Horror In Clay
The most merciful thing in the world, I think,
is the inability of the human mind to correlate
all its contents. We live on a placid island of
ignorance in the midst of black seas of infinity,
and it was not meant that we should voyage far.
The sciences, each straining in its own direction,
have hitherto harmed us little; but some day the
piecing together of dissociated knowledge will
open up such terrifying vistas of reality, and
of our frightful position therein, that we shall
either go mad from the revelation or flee from the
light into the peace and safety of a new dark age.
Theosophists have guessed at the awesome grandeur
of the cosmic cycle wherein our world and human
race form transient incidents. They have hinted
at strange survivals in terms which would freeze
the blood if not masked by a bland optimism. But
it is not from them that there came the single
glimpse of forbidden eons which chills me when
I think of it and maddens me when I dream of it.
That glimpse, like all dread glimpses
of truth, flashed out from an accidental
piecing together of separated things
- in this case an old newspaper item
and the notes of a dead professor. I hope that
no one else will accomplish this piecing out;
certainly, if I live, I shall never knowingly
supply a link in so hideous a chain.
I think that the professor, too intented
to keep silent regarding the part he knew,
and that he would have destroyed his
notes had not sudden death seized him.
My knowledge of the thing began in the winter
of 1926-27 with the death of my great-uncle,
George Gammell Angell, Professor Emeritus
of Semitic Languages in Brown University,
Providence, Rhode Island. Professor
Angell was widely known as an authority on
ancient inscriptions, and had frequently been
resorted to by the heads of prominent museums;
so that his passing at the age of
ninety-two may be recalled by many.
Locally, interest was intensified by
the obscurity of the cause of death.
The professor had been stricken whilst returning
from the Newport boat; falling suddenly;
as witnesses said, after having been jostled by
a nautical-looking negro who had come from one of
the queer dark courts on the precipitous hillside
which formed a short cut from the waterfront to
the deceased’s home in Williams Street. Physicians
were unable to find any visible disorder,
but concluded after perplexed debate that some
obscure lesion of the heart, induced by the brisk
ascent of so steep a hill by so elderly a man,
was responsible for the end. At the time I saw no
reason to dissent from this dictum, but latterly
I am inclined to wonder - and more than wonder.
As my great-uncle’s heir and executor, for he died
a childless widower, I was expected to go over
his papers with some thoroughness; and for that
purpose moved his entire set of files and boxes
to my quarters in Boston. Much of the material
which I correlated will be later published by
the American Archaeological Society, but there
was one box which I found exceedingly puzzling,
and which I felt much averse from showing to other
eyes. It had been locked and I did not find the
key till it occurred to me to examine the personal
ring which the professor carried in his pocket.
Then, indeed, I succeeded in opening it, but when
I did so seemed only to be confronted by a greater
and more closely locked barrier. For what could
be the meaning of the queer clay bas-relief and
the disjointed jottings, ramblings, and cuttings
which I found? Had my uncle, in his latter years
become credulous of the most superficial
impostures? I resolved to search out the
eccentric sculptor responsible for this apparent
disturbance of an old man’s peace of mind.
The bas-relief was a rough rectangle less than an
inch thick and about five by six inches in area;
obviously of modern origin. Its designs,
however, were far from modern in atmosphere
and suggestion; for, although the vagaries
of cubism and futurism are many and wild,
they do not often reproduce that cryptic
regularity which lurks in prehistoric writing.
And writing of some kind the bulk of
these designs seemed certainly to be;
though my memory, despite much the papers
and collections of my uncle, failed in any
way to identify this particular species,
or even hint at its remotest affiliations.
Above these apparent hieroglyphics was a
figure of evident pictorial intent, though its
impressionistic execution forbade a very clear
idea of its nature. It seemed to be a sort of
monster, or symbol representing a monster, of a
form which only a diseased fancy could conceive.
If I say that my somewhat extravagant imagination
yielded simultaneous pictures of an octopus,
a dragon, and a human caricature, I shall not be
unfaithful to the spirit of the thing. A pulpy,
tentacled head surmounted a grotesque and
scaly body with rudimentary wings; but
it was the general outline of the whole
which made it most shockingly frightful.
Behind the figure was a vague suggestions
of a Cyclopean architectural background.
The writing accompanying this oddity was,
aside from a stack of press cuttings,
in Professor Angell’s most recent hand;
and made no pretense to literary style.
What seemed to be the main document was headed
“CTHULHU CULT” in characters painstakingly
printed to avoid the erroneous reading of a word
so unheard-of. This manuscript was divided into
two sections, the first of which was headed
“1925 - Dream and Dream Work of H.A. Wilcox,
7 Thomas St., Providence, R. I.”, and the
second, “Narrative of Inspector John R. Legrasse,
121 Bienville St., New Orleans, La., at 1908 A.
A. S. Mtg. - Notes on Same, & Prof. Webb’s Acct.”
The other manuscript papers were brief notes, some
of them accounts of the queer dreams of different
persons, some of them citations from theosophical
books and magazines (notably W. Scott-Elliot’s
Atlantis and the Lost Lemuria ), and the rest
comments on long-surviving secret societies and
hidden cults, with references to passages in such
mythological and anthropological source-books as
Frazer’s Golden Bough and Miss Murray’s Witch-Cult
in Western Europe. The cuttings largely alluded
to outr mental illness and outbreaks of
group folly or mania in the spring of 1925.
The first half of the principal manuscript told
a very particular tale. It appears that on March
1st, 1925, a thin, dark young man of neurotic and
excited aspect had called upon Professor Angell
bearing the singular clay bas-relief, which was
then exceedingly damp and fresh. His card bore
the name of Henry Anthony Wilcox, and my uncle
had recognized him as the youngest son of an
excellent family slightly known to him, who
had latterly been studying sculpture at the
Rhode Island School of Design and living alone at
the Fleur-de-Lys Building near that institution.
Wilcox was a precocious youth of known genius
but great eccentricity, and had from chidhood
excited attention through the strange stories
and odd dreams he was in the habit of relating.
He called himself “psychically hypersensitive”,
but the staid folk of the ancient commercial city
dismissed him as merely “queer.” Never mingling
much with his kind, he had dropped gradually
from social visibility, and was now known only
to a small group of esthetes from other towns.
Even the Providence Art Club, anxious to preserve
its conservatism, had found him quite hopeless.
On the ocassion of the visit, ran the professor’s
manuscript, the sculptor abruptly asked for the
benefit of his host’s archeological knowledge in
identifying the hieroglyphics of the bas-relief.
He spoke in a dreamy, stilted manner which
suggested pose and alienated sympathy;
and my uncle showed some sharpness in replying,
for the conspicuous freshness of the tablet
implied kinship with anything but archeology.
Young Wilcox’s rejoinder, which impressed my uncle
enough to make him recall and record it verbatim,
was of a fantastically poetic cast which must have
typified his whole conversation, and which I
have since found highly characteristic of him.
He said, “It is new, indeed, for I made it
last night in a dream of strange cities;
and dreams are older than brooding Tyre, or the
contemplative Sphinx, or garden-girdled Babylon.”
It was then that he began that rambling tale which
suddenly played upon a sleeping memory and won
the fevered interest of my uncle. There had been
a slight earthquake tremor the night before,
the most considerable felt in New England for some
years; and Wilcox’s imagination had been keenly
affected. Upon retiring, he had had an
unprecedented dream of great Cyclopean cities of
Titan blocks and sky-flung monoliths, all dripping
with green ooze and sinister with latent horror.
Hieroglyphics had covered the walls and pillars,
and from some undetermined point below had come a
voice that was not a voice; a chaotic sensation
which only fancy could transmute into sound,
but which he attempted to render
by the almost unpronounceable
jumble of letters: “Cthulhu fhtagn.”
This verbal jumble was the key to the recollection
which excited and disturbed Professor Angell.
He questioned the sculptor
with scientific minuteness;
and studied with frantic intensity the bas-relief
on which the youth had found himself working,
chilled and clad only in his night clothes,
when waking had stolen bewilderingly over him.
My uncle blamed his old age, Wilcox afterwards
said, for his slowness in recognizing both
hieroglyphics and pictorial design. Many of
his questions seemed highly out of place to his
visitor, especially those which tried to connect
the latter with strange cults or societies;
and Wilcox could not understand the repeated
promises of silence which he was offered in
exchange for an admission of membership in some
widespread mystical or paganly religious body.
When Professor Angell became convinced that the
sculptor was indeed ignorant of any cult or system
of cryptic lore, he besieged his visitor with
demands for future reports of dreams. This bore
regular fruit, for after the first interview the
manuscript records daily calls of the young man,
during which he related startling fragments
of nocturnal imaginery whose burden was always
some terrible Cyclopean vista of dark and
dripping stone, with a subterrene voice or
intelligence shouting monotonously in enigmatical
sense-impacts uninscribable save as gibberish.
The two sounds frequently repeated are those
rendered by the letters “Cthulhu” and “R’lyeh.”
On March 23, the manuscript continued, Wilcox
failed to appear; and inquiries at his quarters
revealed that he had been stricken with an obscure
sort of fever and taken to the home of his family
in Waterman Street. He had cried out in the night,
arousing several other artists in the building,
and had manifested since then only
alternations of unconsciousness and delirium.
My uncle at once telephoned the family, and from
that time forward kept close watch of the case;
calling often at the Thayer Street office of
Dr. Tobey, whom he learned to be in charge.
The youth’s febrile mind, apparently, was dwelling
on strange things; and the doctor shuddered now
and then as he spoke of them. They included not
only a repetition of what he had formerly dreamed,
but touched wildly on a gigantic thing
“miles high” which walked or lumbered about.
He at no time fully described this
object but occasional frantic words,
as repeated by Dr. Tobey, convinced the
professor that it must be identical with
the nameless monstrosity he had sought to depict
in his dream-sculpture. Reference to this object,
the doctor added, was invariably a prelude
to the young man’s subsidence into lethargy.
His temperature, oddly enough,
was not greatly above normal;
but the whole condition was otherwise such as to
suggest true fever rather than mental disorder.
On April 2 at about 3 P.M. every trace
of Wilcox’s malady suddenly ceased.
He sat upright in bed, astonished to find himself
at home and completely ignorant of what had
happened in dream or reality since the night
of March 22. Pronounced well by his physician,
he returned to his quarters in three days; but to
Professor Angell he was of no further assistance.
All traces of strange dreaming had vanished with
his recovery, and my uncle kept no record of
his night-thoughts after a week of pointless and
irrelevant accounts of thoroughly usual visions.
Here the first part of the manuscript ended,
but references to certain of the scattered
notes gave me much material for thought - so much,
in fact, that only the ingrained skepticism then
forming my philosophy can account for
my continued distrust of the artist.
The notes in question were those descriptive
of the dreams of various persons covering the
same period as that in which young Wilcox had had
his strange visitations. My uncle, it seems, had
quickly instituted a prodigiously far-flung body
of inquires amongst nearly all the friends whom he
could question without impertinence, asking for
nightly reports of their dreams, and the dates
of any notable visions for some time past. The
reception of his request seems to have varied;
but he must, at the very least, have received
more responses than any ordinary man could
have handled without a secretary. This original
correspondence was not preserved, but his notes
formed a thorough and really significant digest.
Average people in society and business - New
England’s traditional “salt of the earth” -
gave an almost completely negative result,
though scattered cases of uneasy but formless
nocturnal impressions appear here and there,
always between March 23 and and April 2
- the period of young Wilcox’s delirium.
Scientific men were little more affected, though
four cases of vague description suggest fugitive
glimpses of strange landscapes, and in one case
there is mentioned a dread of something abnormal.
It was from the artists and poets
that the pertinent answers came,
and I know that panic would have broken
loose had they been able to compare notes.
As it was, lacking their original letters, I
half suspected the compiler of having asked
leading questions, or of having edited the
correspondence in corroboration of what
he had latently resolved to see. That is why I
continued to feel that Wilcox, somehow cognizant
of the old data which my uncle had possessed,
had been imposing on the veteran scientist.
These responses from esthetes told disturbing
tale. From February 28 to April 2 a large
proportion of them had dreamed very bizarre
things, the intensity of the dreams being
immeasurably the stronger during the period of the
sculptor’s delirium. Over a fourth of those who
reported anything, reported scenes and half-sounds
not unlike those which Wilcox had described; and
some of the dreamers confessed acute fear of the
gigantic nameless thing visible toward the last.
One case, which the note describes with
emphasis, was very sad. The subject,
a widely known architect with leanings toward
theosophy and occultism, went violently insane
on the date of young Wilcox’s seizure, and expired
several months later after incessant screamings to
be saved from some escaped denizen of hell. Had my
uncle referred to these cases by name instead of
merely by number, I should have attempted some
corroboration and personal investigation; but
as it was, I succeeded in tracing down only a
few. All of these, however, bore out the notes
in full. I have often wondered if all the the
objects of the professor’s questioning felt
as puzzled as did this fraction. It is well
that no explanation shall ever reach them.
The press cuttings, as I have
intimated, touched on cases of panic,
mania, and eccentricity during the given period.
Professor Angell must have employed a cutting
bureau, for the number of extracts was tremendous,
and the sources scattered throughout the globe.
Here was a nocturnal suicide in London, where
a lone sleeper had leaped from a window after
a shocking cry. Here likewise a rambling letter
to the editor of a paper in South America, where
a fanatic deduces a dire future from visions he
has seen. A dispatch from California describes a
theosophist colony as donning white robes en masse
for some “glorious fulfiment” which never arrives,
whilst items from India speak guardedly of serious
native unrest toward the end of March 22-23.
The west of Ireland, too, is full of wild
rumour and legendry, and a fantastic painter
named Ardois-Bonnot hangs a blasphemous Dream
Landscape in the Paris spring salon of 1926.
And so numerous are the recorded troubles in
insane asylums that only a miracle can have
stopped the medical fraternity from noting strange
parallelisms and drawing mystified conclusions.
A weird bunch of cuttings, all told;
and I can at this date scarcely envisage
the callous rationalism with which I set
them aside. But I was then convinced that
young Wilcox had known of the older
matters mentioned by the professor.
II. The Tale of Inspector Legrasse.
The older matters which had made the sculptor’s
dream and bas-relief so significant to my uncle
formed the subject of the second half
of his long manuscript. Once before,
it appears, Professor Angell had seen the
hellish outlines of the nameless monstrosity,
puzzled over the unknown hieroglyphics,
and heard the ominous syllables which
can be rendered only as “Cthulhu” ; and all
this in so stirring and horrible a connexion
that it is small wonder he pursued young
Wilcox with queries and demands for data.
This earlier experience had come
in 1908, seventeen years before,
when the American Archaeological Society held its
annual meeting in St. Louis. Professor Angell,
as befitted one of his authority and attainments,
had had a prominent part in all the deliberations;
and was one of the first to be approached by
the several outsiders who took advantage of
the convocation to offer questions for correct
answering and problems for expert solution.
The chief of these outsiders, and in a short time
the focus of interest for the entire meeting,
was a commonplace-looking middle-aged man who had
travelled all the way from New Orleans for certain
special information unobtainable from any local
source. His name was John Raymond Legrasse, and
he was by profession an Inspector of Police. With
him he bore the subject of his visit, a grotesque,
repulsive, and apparently very ancient stone
statuette whose origin he was at a loss to
determine. It must not be fancied that Inspector
Legrasse had the least interest in archaeology.
On the contrary, his wish for enlightenment was
prompted by purely professional considerations.
The statuette, idol, fetish, or whatever it
was, had been captured some months before in
the wooded swamps south of New Orleans during
a raid on a supposed voodoo meeting; and so
singular and hideous were the rites connected
with it, that the police could not but realise
that they had stumbled on a dark cult totally
unknown to them, and infinitely more diabolic
than even the blackest of the African voodoo
circles. Of its origin, apart from the erratic
and unbelievable tales extorted from the captured
members, absolutely nothing was to be discovered;
hence the anxiety of the police for any
antiquarian lore which might help them
to place the frightful symbol, and through
it track down the cult to its fountain-head.
Inspector Legrasse was scarcely prepared for the
sensation which his offering created. One sight of
the thing had been enough to throw the assembled
men of science into a state of tense excitement,
and they lost no time in crowding around him
to gaze at the diminutive figure whose utter
strangeness and air of genuinely abysmal antiquity
hinted so potently at unopened and archaic vistas.
No recognised school of sculpture had animated
this terrible object, yet centuries and even
thousands of years seemed recorded in its dim
and greenish surface of unplaceable stone.
The figure, which was finally passed slowly
from man to man for close and careful study,
was between seven and eight inches in height,
and of exquisitely artistic workmanship.
It represented a monster of vaguely anthropoid
outline, but with an octopus-like head whose face
was a mass of feelers, a scaly, rubbery-looking
body, prodigious claws on hind and fore feet,
and long, narrow wings behind. This thing,
which seemed instinct with a fearsome and
unnatural malignancy, was of a somewhat bloated
corpulence, and squatted evilly on a rectangular
block or pedestal covered with undecipherable
characters. The tips of the wings touched the back
edge of the block, the seat occupied the centre,
whilst the long, curved claws of the doubled-up,
crouching hind legs gripped the front edge and
extended a quarter of the way down toward the
bottom of the pedestal. The cephalopod head was
bent forward, so that the ends of the facial
feelers brushed the backs of huge fore paws
which clasped the croucher’s elevated knees.
The aspect of the whole was abnormally life-like,
and the more subtly fearful because its source
was so totally unknown. Its vast, awesome,
and incalculable age was unmistakable; yet
not one link did it shew with any known type of
art belonging to civilisation’s youth - or indeed
to any other time. Totally separate and apart,
its very material was a mystery; for the soapy,
greenish-black stone with its golden or iridescent
flecks and striations resembled nothing familiar
to geology or mineralogy. The characters along the
base were equally baffling; and no member present,
despite a representation of half the world’s
expert learning in this field, could form the
least notion of even their remotest linguistic
kinship. They, like the subject and material,
belonged to something horribly remote and distinct
from mankind as we know it. something frightfully
suggestive of old and unhallowed cycles of life in
which our world and our conceptions have no part.
And yet, as the members severally shook
their heads and confessed defeat at the
Inspector’s problem, there was one man
in that gathering who suspected a touch
of bizarre familiarity in the monstrous shape
and writing, and who presently told with some
diffidence of the odd trifle he knew. This
person was the late William Channing Webb,
Professor of Anthropology in Princeton University,
and an explorer of no slight note. Professor Webb
had been engaged, forty-eight years before, in a
tour of Greenland and Iceland in search of some
Runic inscriptions which he failed to unearth;
and whilst high up on the West Greenland coast
had encountered a singular tribe or cult of
degenerate Esquimaux whose religion, a curious
form of devil-worship, chilled him with its
deliberate bloodthirstiness and repulsiveness. It
was a faith of which other Esquimaux knew little,
and which they mentioned only with shudders,
saying that it had come down from horribly
ancient aeons before ever the world was made.
Besides nameless rites and human sacrifices there
were certain queer hereditary rituals addressed
to a supreme elder devil or tornasuk; and of this
Professor Webb had taken a careful phonetic copy
from an aged angekok or wizard-priest, expressing
the sounds in Roman letters as best he knew how.
But just now of prime significance was
the fetish which this cult had cherished,
and around which they danced when the
aurora leaped high over the ice cliffs.
It was, the professor stated, a
very crude bas-relief of stone,
comprising a hideous picture and some
cryptic writing. And so far as he could tell,
it was a rough parallel in all essential features
of the bestial thing now lying before the meeting.
This data, received with suspense and astonishment
by the assembled members, proved doubly exciting
to Inspector Legrasse; and he began at
once to ply his informant with questions.
Having noted and copied an oral ritual among
the swamp cult-worshippers his men had arrested,
he besought the professor to remember as best
he might the syllables taken down amongst the
diabolist Esquimaux. There then followed an
exhaustive comparison of details, and a moment
of really awed silence when both detective
and scientist agreed on the virtual identity
of the phrase common to two hellish rituals
so many worlds of distance apart. What,
in substance, both the Esquimaux wizards and
the Louisiana swamp-priests had chanted to
their kindred idols was something very
like this: the word-divisions being
guessed at from traditional breaks
in the phrase as chanted aloud:
“Ph’nglui mglw’nafh Cthulhu
R’lyeh wgah’nagl fhtagn.”
Legrasse had one point in advance
of Professor Webb, for several among
his mongrel prisoners had repeated to him what
older celebrants had told them the words meant.
This text, as given, ran something like this:
“In his house at R’lyeh dead
Cthulhu waits dreaming.”
And now, in response to a
general and urgent demand,
Inspector Legrasse related as fully as possible
his experience with the swamp worshippers;
telling a story to which I could see my
uncle attached profound significance. It
savoured of the wildest dreams of myth-maker and
theosophist, and disclosed an astonishing degree
of cosmic imagination among such half-castes and
pariahs as might be least expected to possess it.
On November 1st, 1907, there had come to the
New Orleans police a frantic summons from
the swamp and lagoon country to the south. The
squatters there, mostly primitive but good-natured
descendants of Lafitte’s men, were in the grip
of stark terror from an unknown thing which had
stolen upon them in the night. It was voodoo,
apparently, but voodoo of a more terrible sort
than they had ever known; and some of their women
and children had disappeared since the malevolent
tom-tom had begun its incessant beating far within
the black haunted woods where no dweller ventured.
There were insane shouts and harrowing screams,
soul-chilling chants and dancing devil-flames;
and, the frightened messenger added,
the people could stand it no more.
So a body of twenty police, filling two carriages
and an automobile, had set out in the late
afternoon with the shivering squatter as a guide.
At the end of the passable road they alighted,
and for miles splashed on in silence through
the terrible cypress woods where day never came.
Ugly roots and malignant hanging nooses of Spanish
moss beset them, and now and then a pile of dank
stones or fragment of a rotting wall intensified
by its hint of morbid habitation a depression
which every malformed tree and every fungous
islet combined to create. At length the squatter
settlement, a miserable huddle of huts, hove in
sight; and hysterical dwellers ran out to cluster
around the group of bobbing lanterns. The muffled
beat of tom-toms was now faintly audible far, far
ahead; and a curdling shriek came at infrequent
intervals when the wind shifted. A reddish glare,
too, seemed to filter through pale undergrowth
beyond the endless avenues of forest night.
Reluctant even to be left alone again, each one of
the cowed squatters refused point-blank to advance
another inch toward the scene of unholy worship,
so Inspector Legrasse and his nineteen colleagues
plunged on unguided into black arcades of
horror that none of them had ever trod before.
The region now entered by the police was one of
traditionally evil repute, substantially unknown
and untraversed by white men. There were legends
of a hidden lake unglimpsed by mortal sight,
in which dwelt a huge, formless white polypous
thing with luminous eyes; and squatters whispered
that bat-winged devils flew up out of caverns
in inner earth to worship it at midnight.
They said it had been there before d’Iberville,
before La Salle, before the Indians, and before
even the wholesome beasts and birds of the woods.
It was nightmare itself, and to see it was to die.
But it made men dream, and so they knew enough to
keep away. The present voodoo orgy was, indeed, on
the merest fringe of this abhorred area, but that
location was bad enough; hence perhaps the very
place of the worship had terrified the squatters
more than the shocking sounds and incidents.
Only poetry or madness could do justice
to the noises heard by Legrasse’s men
as they ploughed on through the black morass
toward the red glare and muffled tom-toms.
There are vocal qualities peculiar to men,
and vocal qualities peculiar to beasts;
and it is terrible to hear the one when the source
should yield the other. Animal fury and orgiastic
license here whipped themselves to daemoniac
heights by howls and squawking ecstacies that
tore and reverberated through those nighted woods
like pestilential tempests from the gulfs of hell.
Now and then the less organized
ululation would cease, and from what
seemed a well-drilled chorus of hoarse voices
would rise in sing-song chant that hideous
phrase or ritual:
“Ph’nglui mglw’nafh Cthulhu
R’lyeh wgah’nagl fhtagn.”
Then the men, having reached a spot where
the trees were thinner, came suddenly in
sight of the spectacle itself. Four of them
reeled, one fainted, and two were shaken into
a frantic cry which the mad cacophony of the orgy
fortunately deadened. Legrasse dashed swamp water
on the face of the fainting man, and all stood
trembling and nearly hypnotised with horror.
In a natural glade of the swamp stood a
grassy island of perhaps an acre’s extent,
clear of trees and tolerably dry. On
this now leaped and twisted a more
indescribable horde of human abnormality than
any but a Sime or an Angarola could paint.
Void of clothing, this hybrid spawn were braying,
bellowing, and writhing about a monstrous
ring-shaped bonfire; in the centre of which,
revealed by occasional rifts in the curtain of
flame, stood a great granite monolith some eight
feet in height; on top of which, incongruous in
its diminutiveness, rested the noxious carven
statuette. From a wide circle of ten scaffolds
set up at regular intervals with the flame-girt
monolith as a centre hung, head downward,
the oddly marred bodies of the helpless squatters
who had disappeared. It was inside this circle
that the ring of worshippers jumped and roared,
the general direction of the mass motion being
from left to right in endless Bacchanal between
the ring of bodies and the ring of fire.
It may have been only imagination and it may have
been only echoes which induced one of the men,
an excitable Spaniard, to fancy he heard
antiphonal responses to the ritual from some
far and unillumined spot deeper within the wood of
ancient legendry and horror. This man, Joseph D.
Galvez, I later met and questioned; and he proved
distractingly imaginative. He indeed went so far
as to hint of the faint beating of great wings,
and of a glimpse of shining eyes and a mountainous
white bulk beyond the remotest trees but I suppose
he had been hearing too much native superstition.
Actually, the horrified pause of the
men was of comparatively brief duration.
Duty came first; and although there must have been
nearly a hundred mongrel celebrants in the throng,
the police relied on their firearms and
plunged determinedly into the nauseous
rout. For five minutes the resultant din
and chaos were beyond description. Wild
blows were struck, shots were
fired, and escapes were made;
but in the end Legrasse was able to count some
forty-seven sullen prisoners, whom he forced to
dress in haste and fall into line between two rows
of policemen. Five of the worshippers lay dead,
and two severely wounded ones were carried away on
improvised stretchers by their fellow-prisoners.
The image on the monolith, of course, was
carefully removed and carried back by Legrasse.
Examined at headquarters after a trip of intense
strain and weariness, the prisoners all proved
to be men of a very low, mixed-blooded, and
mentally aberrant type. Most were seamen,
and a sprinkling of Negroes and mulattoes, largely
West Indians or Brava Portuguese from the Cape
Verde Islands, gave a colouring of
voodooism to the heterogeneous cult.
But before many questions were asked,
it became manifest that something
far deeper and older than Negro fetishism was
involved. Degraded and ignorant as they were,
the creatures held with surprising consistency
to the central idea of their loathsome faith.
They worshipped, so they said, the Great Old
Ones who lived ages before there were any men,
and who came to the young world out of the sky.
Those Old Ones were gone now, inside the earth
and under the sea; but their dead bodies had
told their secrets in dreams to the first men,
who formed a cult which had never died. This
was that cult, and the prisoners said it had
always existed and always would exist, hidden in
distant wastes and dark places all over the world
until the time when the great priest Cthulhu,
from his dark house in the mighty city of R’lyeh
under the waters, should rise and bring the earth
again beneath his sway. Some day he would call,
when the stars were ready, and the secret
cult would always be waiting to liberate him.
Meanwhile no more must be told. There was a
secret which even torture could not extract.
Mankind was not absolutely alone
among the conscious things of earth,
for shapes came out of the dark to visit the
faithful few. But these were not the Great
Old Ones. No man had ever seen the Old Ones. The
carven idol was great Cthulhu, but none might say
whether or not the others were precisely like him.
No one could read the old writing now, but things
were told by word of mouth. The chanted ritual
was not the secret - that was never spoken aloud,
only whispered. The chant meant only this: “In
his house at R’lyeh dead Cthulhu waits dreaming.”
Only two of the prisoners were found sane enough
to be hanged, and the rest were committed to
various institutions. All denied a part in the
ritual murders, and averred that the killing had
been done by Black Winged Ones which had come to
them from their immemorial meeting-place in the
haunted wood. But of those mysterious allies no
coherent account could ever be gained. What the
police did extract, came mainly from the immensely
aged mestizo named Castro, who claimed to have
sailed to strange ports and talked with undying
leaders of the cult in the mountains of China.
Old Castro remembered bits of hideous legend
that paled the speculations of theosophists and
made man and the world seem recent and transient
indeed. There had been aeons when other Things
ruled on the earth, and They had had great cities.
Remains of Them, he said the deathless Chinamen
had told him, were still be found as Cyclopean
stones on islands in the Pacific. They all died
vast epochs of time before men came, but
there were arts which could revive Them
when the stars had come round again to the
right positions in the cycle of eternity.
They had, indeed, come themselves from the
stars, and brought Their images with Them.
These Great Old Ones, Castro continued, were
not composed altogether of flesh and blood. They
had shape - for did not this star-fashioned image
prove it? - but that shape was not made of matter.
When the stars were right, They could plunge from
world to world through the sky; but when the stars
were wrong, They could not live. But although They
no longer lived, They would never really die. They
all lay in stone houses in Their great city of
R’lyeh, preserved by the spells of mighty Cthulhu
for a glorious surrection when the stars and
the earth might once more be ready for Them.
But at that time some force from outside
must serve to liberate Their bodies.
The spells that preserved them intact likewise
prevented Them from making an initial move,
and They could only lie awake in the dark
and think whilst uncounted millions of years
rolled by. They knew all that
was occurring in the universe,
for Their mode of speech was transmitted thought.
Even now They talked in Their tombs. When,
after infinities of chaos, the first men came,
the Great Old Ones spoke to the sensitive among
them by moulding their dreams; for only thus could
Their language reach the fleshly minds of mammals.
Then, whispered Castro, those first men
formed the cult around tall idols which
the Great Ones shewed them; idols brought in dim
eras from dark stars. That cult would never die
till the stars came right again, and the secret
priests would take great Cthulhu from His tomb
to revive His subjects and resume His rule
of earth. The time would be easy to know,
for then mankind would have become as the Great
Old Ones; free and wild and beyond good and evil,
with laws and morals thrown aside and all men
shouting and killing and revelling in joy.
Then the liberated Old Ones would teach them
new ways to shout and kill and revel and enjoy
themselves, and all the earth would flame
with a holocaust of ecstasy and freedom.
Meanwhile the cult, by appropriate rites,
must keep alive the memory of those ancient ways
and shadow forth the prophecy of their return.
In the elder time chosen men had talked
with the entombed Old Ones in dreams,
but then something happened. The great
stone city R’lyeh, with its monoliths
and sepulchres, had sunk beneath the waves;
and the deep waters, full of the one primal
mystery through which not even thought can
pass, had cut off the spectral intercourse.
But memory never died, and the high-priests
said that the city would rise again when
the stars were right. Then came out of
the earth the black spirits of earth,
mouldy and shadowy, and full of dim rumours picked
up in caverns beneath forgotten sea-bottoms.
But of them old Castro dared not speak
much. He cut himself off hurriedly,
and no amount of persuasion or subtlety
could elicit more in this direction.
The size of the Old Ones, too, he
curiously declined to mention. Of the cult,
he said that he thought the centre lay amid
the pathless desert of Arabia, where Irem,
the City of Pillars, dreams hidden and untouched.
It was not allied to the European witch-cult,
and was virtually unknown beyond its members.
No book had ever really hinted of it, though
the deathless Chinamen said that there were double
meanings in the Necronomicon of the mad Arab Abdul
Alhazred which the initiated might read as they
chose, especially the much-discussed couplet:
That is not dead which can eternal lie,
And with strange aeons even death may die.
Legrasse, deeply impressed and not a little
bewildered, had inquired in vain concerning
the historic affiliations of the cult. Castro,
apparently, had told the truth when he said that
it was wholly secret. The authorities at Tulane
University could shed no light upon either cult
or image, and now the detective had come
to the highest authorities in the country
and met with no more than the
Greenland tale of Professor Webb.
The feverish interest aroused at the meeting by
Legrasse’s tale, corroborated as it was by the
statuette, is echoed in the subsequent
correspondence of those who attended;
although scant mention occurs in the
formal publications of the society.
Caution is the first care of those accustomed
to face occasional charlatanry and imposture.
Legrasse for some time lent the image to
Professor Webb, but at the latter’s death
it was returned to him and remains in his
possession, where I viewed it not long ago.
It is truly a terrible thing, and unmistakably
akin to the dream-sculpture of young Wilcox.
That my uncle was excited by the tale of the
sculptor I did not wonder, for what thoughts
must arise upon hearing, after a knowledge
of what Legrasse had learned of the cult,
of a sensitive young man who had dreamed not
only the figure and exact hieroglyphics of the
swamp-found image and the Greenland devil tablet,
but had come in his dreams upon at least three
of the precise words of the formula uttered alike
by Esquimaux diabolists and mongrel Louisianans?.
Professor Angell’s instant start on an
investigation of the utmost thoroughness was
eminently natural; though privately I suspected
young Wilcox of having heard of the cult in some
indirect way, and of having invented a series
of dreams to heighten and continue the mystery
at my uncle’s expense. The dream-narratives
and cuttings collected by the professor were,
of course, strong corroboration; but the
rationalism of my mind and the extravagance
of the whole subject led me to adopt what I
thought the most sensible conclusions. So,
after thoroughly studying the manuscript again and
correlating the theosophical and anthropological
notes with the cult narrative of Legrasse, I
made a trip to Providence to see the sculptor
and give him the rebuke I thought proper for
so boldly imposing upon a learned and aged man.
Wilcox still lived alone in the
Fleur-de-Lys Building in Thomas Street,
a hideous Victorian imitation of seventeenth
century Breton Architecture which flaunts its
stuccoed front amidst the lovely colonial houses
on the ancient hill, and under the very shadow
of the finest Georgian steeple in America, I
found him at work in his rooms, and at once
conceded from the specimens scattered about that
his genius is indeed profound and authentic. He
will, I believe, some time be heard from as one
of the great decadents; for he has crystallised
in clay and will one day mirror in marble those
nightmares and phantasies which Arthur Machen
evokes in prose, and Clark Ashton Smith
makes visible in verse and in painting.
Dark, frail, and somewhat unkempt in aspect,
he turned languidly at my knock and
asked me my business without rising.
Then I told him who I was, he displayed
some interest; for my uncle had excited
his curiosity in probing his strange dreams, yet
had never explained the reason for the study.
I did not enlarge his knowledge in this regard,
but sought with some subtlety to draw him out.
In a short time I became convinced ofhis absolute
sincerity, for he spoke of the dreams in a manner
none could mistake. They and their subconscious
residuum had influenced his art profoundly,
and he shewed me a morbid statue whose contours
almost made me shake with the potency of its black
suggestion. He could not recall having seen the
original of this thing except in his own dream
bas-relief, but the outlines had formed themselves
insensibly under his hands. It was, no doubt,
the giant shape he had raved of in delirium.
That he really knew nothing of the hidden cult,
save from what my uncle’s relentless catechism
had let fall, he soon made clear; and again I
strove to think of some way in which he could
possibly have received the weird impressions.
He talked of his dreams in a strangely poetic
fashion; making me see with terrible vividness
the damp Cyclopean city of slimy green stone
- whose geometry, he oddly said, was all
wrong - and hear with frightened expectancy the
ceaseless, half-mental calling from underground:
“Cthulhu fhtagn”, “Cthulhu fhtagn.”
These words had formed part of that dread
ritual which told of dead Cthulhu’s dream-vigil
in his stone vault at R’lyeh, and I felt
deeply moved despite my rational beliefs.
Wilcox, I was sure, had heard of the cult in
some casual way, and had soon forgotten it
amidst the mass of his equally
weird reading and imagining.
Later, by virtue of its sheer impressiveness,
it had found subconscious expression in dreams,
in the bas-relief, and in the terrible statue I
now beheld; so that his imposture upon my uncle
had been a very innocent one. The youth was of
a type, at once slightly affected and slightly
ill-mannered, which I could never like, but I
was willing enough now to admit both his genius
and his honesty. I took leave of him amicably,
and wish him all the success his talent promises.
The matter of the cult still remained to fascinate
me, and at times I had visions of personal fame
from researches into its origin and connexions.
I visited New Orleans, talked with Legrasse and
others of that old-time raiding-party, saw the
frightful image, and even questioned such of the
mongrel prisoners as still survived. Old Castro,
unfortunately, had been dead for some years.
What I now heard so graphically at first-hand,
though it was really no more than a detailed
confirmation of what my uncle had written,
excited me afresh; for I felt sure that I was
on the track of a very real, very secret, and very
ancient religion whose discovery would make me an
anthropologist of note. My attitude was still one
of absolute materialism, as I wish it still were,
and I discounted with almost
inexplicable perversity
the coincidence of the dream notes and odd
cuttings collected by Professor Angell.
One thing I began to suspect,
and which I now fear I know,
is that my uncle’s death was far from natural. He
fell on a narrow hill street leading up from an
ancient waterfront swarming with foreign mongrels,
after a careless push from a Negro sailor.
I did not forget the mixed blood and marine
pursuits of the cult-members in Louisiana, and
would not be surprised to learn of secret methods
and rites and beliefs. Legrasse and his men, it is
true, have been let alone; but in Norway a certain
seaman who saw things is dead. Might not the
deeper inquiries of my uncle after encountering
the sculptor’s data have come to sinister ears?.
I think Professor Angell died because he knew too
much, or because he was likely to learn too much.
Whether I shall go as he did remains to
be seen, for I have learned much now.
III. The Madness from the Sea
If heaven ever wishes to grant me a boon, it
will be a total effacing of the results of a
mere chance which fixed my eye on a certain stray
piece of shelf-paper. It was nothing on which I
would naturally have stumbled in the course of
my daily round, for it was an old number of an
Australian journal, the Sydney Bulletin for April
18, 1925. It had escaped even the cutting bureau
which had at the time of its issuance been avidly
collecting material for my uncle’s research.
I had largely given over my inquiries into what
Professor Angell called the “Cthulhu Cult”,
and was visiting a learned friend in Paterson,
New Jersey; the curator of a local museum and
a mineralogist of note. Examining one day the
reserve specimens roughly set on the storage
shelves in a rear room of the museum, my eye was
caught by an odd picture in one of the old papers
spread beneath the stones. It was the Sydney
Bulletin I have mentioned, for my friend had
wide affiliations in all conceivable foreign
parts; and the picture was a half-tone cut of
a hideous stone image almost identical with
that which Legrasse had found in the swamp.
Eagerly clearing the sheet of its precious
contents, I scanned the item in detail;
and was disappointed to find
it of only moderate length.
What it suggested, however, was of
portentous significance to my flagging quest;
and I carefully tore it out for
immediate action. It read as follows:
MYSTERY DERELICT FOUND AT SEA
Vigilant Arrives With Helpless
Armed New Zealand Yacht in Tow.
One Survivor and Dead Man Found Aboard. Tale of
Desperate Battle and Deaths at Sea. Rescued Seaman
Refuses Particulars of Strange Experience. Odd
Idol Found in His Possession. Inquiry to Follow.
The Morrison Co.‘s freighter
Vigilant, bound from Valparaiso,
arrived this morning at its wharf in Darling
Harbour, having in tow the battled and
disabled but heavily armed steam yacht Alert
of Dunedin, N.Z., which was sighted April 12th
in S. Latitude 34 21’, W. Longitude 152 17’,
with one living and one dead man aboard.
The Vigilant left Valparaiso March 25th, and on
April 2nd was driven considerably south of her
course by exceptionally heavy storms and monster
waves. On April 12th the derelict was sighted;
and though apparently deserted, was found
upon boarding to contain one survivor in a
half-delirious condition and one man who had
evidently been dead for more than a week.
The living man was clutching a horrible stone
idol of unknown origin, about foot in height,
regarding whose nature authorities at
Sydney University, the Royal Society,
and the Museum in College Street all profess
complete bafflement, and which the survivor
says he found in the cabin of the yacht,
in a small carved shrine of common pattern.
This man, after recovering his senses, told an
exceedingly strange story of piracy and slaughter.
He is Gustaf Johansen, a Norwegian of some
intelligence, and had been second mate of
the two-masted schooner Emma of Auckland, which
sailed for Callao February 20th with a complement
of eleven men. The Emma, he says, was delayed
and thrown widely south of her course by the
great storm of March 1st, and on March 22nd,
in S. Latitude 49 51’ W. Longitude 128 34’,
encountered the Alert, manned by a queer and
evil-looking crew of Kanakas and half-castes.
Being ordered peremptorily to turn back, Capt.
Collins refused; whereupon the strange crew began
to fire savagely and without warning upon the
schooner with a peculiarly heavy battery of brass
cannon forming part of the yacht’s equipment.
The Emma ‘s men shewed fight, says the survivor,
and though the schooner began to sink from shots
beneath the water-line they managed to heave
alongside their enemy and board her, grappling
with the savage crew on the yacht’s deck,
and being forced to kill them all,
the number being slightly superior,
because of their particularly abhorrent and
desperate though rather clumsy mode of fighting.
Three of the Emma’s men, including Capt.
Collins and First Mate Green, were killed;
and the remaining eight under Second Mate
Johansen proceeded to navigate the captured yacht,
going ahead in their original direction to see if
any reason for their ordering back had existed.
The next day, it appears, they raised and landed
on a small island, although none is known to exist
in that part of the ocean; and six of the men
somehow died ashore, though Johansen is queerly
reticent about this part of his story, and speaks
only of their falling into a rock chasm. Later,
it seems, he and one companion boarded the yacht
and tried to manage her, but were beaten about
by the storm of April 2nd, From that time till
his rescue on the 12th the man remembers little,
and he does not even recall when
William Briden, his companion, died.
Briden’s death reveals no apparent cause, and
was probably due to excitement or exposure.
Cable advices from Dunedin report that the
Alert was well known there as an island trader,
and bore an evil reputation along the waterfront,
It was owned by a curious group of half-castes
whose frequent meetings and night trips to
the woods attracted no little curiosity;
and it had set sail in great haste just after
the storm and earth tremors of March 1st.
Our Auckland correspondent gives the Emma
and her crew an excellent reputation,
and Johansen is described
as a sober and worthy man.
The admiralty will institute an inquiry on the
whole matter beginning tomorrow, at which every
effort will be made to induce Johansen to
speak more freely than he has done hitherto.
This was all, together with the
picture of the hellish image; but
what a train of ideas it started in my mind! Here
were new treasuries of data on the Cthulhu Cult,
and evidence that it had strange
interests at sea as well as on land.
What motive prompted the hybrid crew to order
back the Emma as they sailed about with their
hideous idol? What was the unknown island
on which six of the Emma ‘s crew had died,
and about which the mate Johansen was so
secretive? What had the vice-admiralty’s
investigation brought out, and what was known of
the noxious cult in Dunedin? And most marvellous
of all, what deep and more than natural linkage
of dates was this which gave a malign and now
undeniable significance to the various turns
of events so carefully noted by my uncle?
March 1st - or February 28th according to the
International Date Line - the earthquake and storm
had come. From Dunedin the Alert and her noisome
crew had darted eagerly forth as if imperiously
summoned, and on the other side of the earth
poets and artists had begun to dream of a strange,
dank Cyclopean city whilst a young sculptor had
moulded in his sleep the form of the dreaded
Cthulhu. March 23rd the crew of the Emma landed
on an unknown island and left six men dead; and
on that date the dreams of sensitive men assumed
a heightened vividness and darkened with dread
of a giant monster’s malign pursuit, whilst an
architect had gone mad and a sculptor had lapsed
suddenly into delirium! And what of this storm of
April 2nd - the date on which all dreams of the
dank city ceased, and Wilcox emerged unharmed from
the bondage of strange fever? What of all this -
and of those hints of old Castro about the sunken,
star-born Old Ones and their coming reign; their
faithful cult and their mastery of dreams? Was I
tottering on the brink of cosmic horrors beyond
man’s power to bear? If so, they must be horrors
of the mind alone, for in some way the second
of April had put a stop to whatever monstrous
menace had begun its siege of mankind’s soul.
That evening, after a day of hurried cabling and
arranging, I bade my host adieu and took a train
for San Francisco. In less than a month I was
in Dunedin; where, however, I found that little
was known of the strange cult-members who had
lingered in the old sea-taverns. Waterfront scum
was far too common for special mention; though
there was vague talk about one inland trip these
mongrels had made, during which faint drumming
and red flame were noted on the distant hills.
In Auckland I learned that Johansen
had returned with yellow hair
turned white after a perfunctory and
inconclusive questioning at Sydney,
and had thereafter sold his cottage in West Street
and sailed with his wife to his old home in Oslo.
Of his stirring experience he would
tell his friends no more than he had
told the admiralty officials, and all they
could do was to give me his Oslo address.
After that I went to Sydney and talked
profitlessly with seamen and members
of the vice-admiralty court. I saw the
Alert, now sold and in commercial use,
at Circular Quay in Sydney Cove, but
gained nothing from its non-committal bulk.
The crouching image with its cuttlefish head,
dragon body, scaly wings, and hieroglyphed
pedestal, was preserved in the Museum at Hyde
Park; and I studied it long and well, finding
it a thing of balefully exquisite workmanship, and
with the same utter mystery, terrible antiquity,
and unearthly strangeness of material which I had
noted in Legrasse’s smaller specimen. Geologists,
the curator told me, had found it a monstrous
puzzle; for they vowed that the world held no rock
like it. Then I thought with a shudder of what
Old Castro had told Legrasse about the Old Ones;
“They had come from the stars, and
had brought Their images with Them.”
Shaken with such a mental revolution as I had
never before known, I now resolved to visit Mate
Johansen in Oslo. Sailing for London, I reembarked
at once for the Norwegian capital; and one autumn
day landed at the trim wharves in the shadow of
the Egeberg. Johansen’s address, I discovered,
lay in the Old Town of King Harold Haardrada,
which kept alive the name of Oslo during all the
centuries that the greater city masqueraded as
“Christiana.” I made the brief trip by taxicab,
and knocked with palpitant heart at the door of
a neat and ancient building with plastered front.
A sad-faced woman in black answered
my summons, and I was stung with
disappointment when she told me in halting
English that Gustaf Johansen was no more.
He had not long survived
his return, said his wife,
for the doings sea in 1925 had broken him. He
had told her no more than he told the public,
but had left a long manuscript - of “technical
matters” as he said - written in English,
evidently in order to guard her
from the peril of casual perusal.
During a walk through a narrow lane near the
Gothenburg dock, a bundle of papers falling
from an attic window had knocked him down. Two
Lascar sailors at once helped him to his feet, but
before the ambulance could reach him he was
dead. Physicians found no adequate cause the end,
and laid it to heart trouble and a weakened
constitution. I now felt gnawing at my vitals that
dark terror which will never leave me till I,
too, am at rest; “accidentally” or otherwise.
Persuading the widow that my connexion with her
husband’s “technical matters” was sufficient to
entitle me to his manuscript, I bore the document
away and began to read it on the London boat.
It was a simple, rambling thing - a naive sailor’s
effort at a post-facto diary - and strove to
recall day by day that last awful voyage. I
cannot attempt to transcribe it verbatim in
all its cloudiness and redundance, but I will tell
its gist enough to shew why the sound the water
against the vessel’s sides became so unendurable
to me that I stopped my ears with cotton.
Johansen, thank God, did not know quite all,
even though he saw the city and the Thing,
but I shall never sleep calmly again when I think
of the horrors that lurk ceaselessly behind life
in time and in space, and of those unhallowed
blasphemies from elder stars which dream beneath
the sea, known and favoured by a nightmare cult
ready and eager to loose them upon the world
whenever another earthquake shall heave their
monstrous stone city again to the sun and air.
Johansen’s voyage had begun just as
he told it to the vice-admiralty.
The Emma, in ballast, had cleared Auckland on
February 20th, and had felt the full force of
that earthquake-born tempest which must have
heaved up from the sea-bottom the horrors that
filled men’s dreams. Once more under control,
the ship was making good progress when held
up by the Alert on March 22nd,
and I could feel the mate’s regret
as he wrote of her bombardment and
sinking. Of the swarthy cult-fiends
on the Alert he speaks with significant horror.
There was some peculiarly abominable quality about
them which made their destruction seem almost a
duty, and Johansen shews ingenuous wonder at the
charge of ruthlessness brought against his party
during the proceedings of the court of inquiry.
Then, driven ahead by curiosity in their captured
yacht under Johansen’s command, the men sight
a great stone pillar sticking out of the sea,
and in S. Latitude 47 9’, W. Longitude l23 43’,
come upon a coastline of mingled mud, ooze, and
weedy Cyclopean masonry which can be nothing less
than the tangible substance of earth’s supreme
terror - the nightmare corpse-city of R’lyeh,
that was built in measureless aeons behind
history by the vast, loathsome shapes that
seeped down from the dark stars. There lay
great Cthulhu and his hordes, hidden in green
slimy vaults and sending out at last, after cycles
incalculable, the thoughts that spread fear to the
dreams of the sensitive and called imperiously
to the faithfull to come on a pilgrimage of
liberation and restoration. All this Johansen did
not suspect, but God knows he soon saw enough!
I suppose that only a single mountain-top,
the hideous monolith-crowned citadel
whereon great Cthulhu was buried, actually
emerged from the waters. When I think of
the extent of all that may be brooding down
there I almost wish to kill myself forthwith.
Johansen and his men were awed by the cosmic
majesty of this dripping Babylon of elder daemons,
and must have guessed without guidance that it was
nothing of this or of any sane planet. Awe at the
unbelievable size of the greenish stone blocks, at
the dizzying height of the great carven monolith,
and at the stupefying identity of the colossal
statues and bas-reliefs with the queer image found
in the shrine on the Alert, is poignantly visible
in every line of the mates frightened description.
Without knowing what futurism is like,
Johansen achieved something very close
to it when he spoke of the city; for instead of
describing any definite structure or building,
he dwells only on broad impressions of vast angles
and stone surfaces - surfaces too great to belong
to anything right or proper for this earth, and
impious with horrible images and hieroglyphs.
I mention his talk about angles because it
suggests something Wilcox had told me of his
awful dreams. He said that the geometry
of the dream-place he saw was abnormal,
non-Euclidean, and loathsomely redolent
of spheres and dimensions apart from ours.
Now an unlettered seaman felt the same
thing whilst gazing at the terrible reality.
Johansen and his men landed at a sloping
mud-bank on this monstrous Acropolis,
and clambered slipperily up over titan oozy blocks
which could have been no mortal staircase. The
very sun of heaven seemed distorted when viewed
through the polarising miasma welling out from
this sea-soaked perversion, and twisted menace and
suspense lurked leeringly in those crazily elusive
angles of carven rock where a second glance
shewed concavity after the first shewed convexity.
Something very like fright had come over all the
explorers before anything more definite
than rock and ooze and weed was seen.
Each would have fled had he not feared the scorn
of the others, and it was only half-heartedly
that they searched - vainly, as it proved
- for some portable souvenir to bear away.
It was Rodriguez the Portuguese who climbed
up the foot of the monolith and shouted of
what he had found. The rest followed him, and
looked curiously at the immense carved door
with the now familiar squid-dragon bas-relief.
It was, Johansen said, like a great barn-door;
and they all felt that it was a door because of
the ornate lintel, threshold, and jambs around it,
though they could not decide whether it lay
flat like a trap-door or slantwise like an
outside cellar-door. As Wilcox would have
said, the geometry of the place was all wrong.
One could not be sure that the sea
and the ground were horizontal,
hence the relative position of everything
else seemed phantasmally variable.
Briden pushed at the stone in
several places without result.
Then Donovan felt over it delicately around the
edge, pressing each point separately as he went.
He climbed interminably along the
grotesque stone moulding - that is,
one would call it climbing if the thing
was not after all horizontal - and the men
wondered how any door in the universe could
be so vast. Then, very softly and slowly,
the acre-great lintel began to give inward at
the top; and they saw that it was balanced.
Donovan slid or somehow propelled himself down
or along the jamb and rejoined his fellows,
and everyone watched the queer recession
of the monstrously carven portal.
In this phantasy of prismatic distortion
it moved anomalously in a diagonal way,
so that all the rules of matter
and perspective seemed upset.
The aperture was black with a darkness almost
material. That tenebrousness was indeed a
positive quality ; for it obscured such parts of
the inner walls as ought to have been revealed,
and actually burst forth like smoke from its
aeon-long imprisonment, visibly darkening the sun
as it slunk away into the shrunken and gibbous sky
on flapping membraneous wings. The odour rising
from the newly opened depths was intolerable,
and at length the quick-eared Hawkins thought
he heard a nasty, slopping sound down there.
Everyone listened, and everyone was listening
still when It lumbered slobberingly into sight and
gropingly squeezed Its gelatinous green immensity
through the black doorway into the tainted
outside air of that poison city of madness.
Poor Johansen’s handwriting almost gave out
when he wrote of this. Of the six men who never
reached the ship, he thinks two perished
of pure fright in that accursed instant.
The Thing cannot be described - there is no
language for such abysms of shrieking and
immemorial lunacy, such eldritch contradictions
of all matter, force, and cosmic order. A mountain
walked or stumbled. God! What wonder that across
the earth a great architect went mad, and poor
Wilcox raved with fever in that telepathic
instant? The Thing of the idols, the green,
sticky spawn of the stars, had awaked to
claim his own. The stars were right again,
and what an age-old cult had failed to do by
design, a band of innocent sailors had done
by accident. After vigintillions of years great
Cthulhu was loose again, and ravening for delight.
Three men were swept up by the flabby
claws before anybody turned. God rest them,
if there be any rest in the universe. They were
Donovan, Guerrera, and Angstrom. Parker slipped
as the other three were plunging frenziedly over
endless vistas of green-crusted rock to the boat,
and Johansen swears he was swallowed up by an
angle of masonry which shouldn’t have been there;
an angle which was acute, but behaved as if
it were obtuse. So only Briden and Johansen
reached the boat, and pulled desperately for
the Alert as the mountainous monstrosity flopped
down the slimy stones and hesitated,
floundering at the edge of the water.
Steam had not been suffered to go down entirely,
despite the departure of all hands for the shore;
and it was the work of only a few moments of
feverish rushing up and down between wheel and
engines to get the Alert under way. Slowly, amidst
the distorted horrors of that indescribable scene,
she began to churn the lethal waters; whilst
on the masonry of that charnel shore that
was not of earth the titan Thing from the
stars slavered and gibbered like Polypheme
cursing the fleeing ship of Odysseus. Then, bolder
than the storied Cyclops, great Cthulhu slid
greasily into the water and began to pursue with
vast wave-raising strokes of cosmic potency.
Briden looked back and went mad, laughing
shrilly as he kept on laughing at intervals
till death found him one night in the cabin
whilst Johansen was wandering deliriously.
But Johansen had not given out yet. Knowing that
the Thing could surely overtake the Alert until
steam was fully up, he resolved on a desperate
chance; and, setting the engine for full speed,
ran lightning-like on deck and reversed the wheel.
There was a mighty eddying and foaming in the
noisome brine, and as the steam mounted higher and
higher the brave Norwegian drove his vessel head
on against the pursuing jelly which rose above the
unclean froth like the stern of a daemon galleon.
The awful squid-head with writhing feelers came
nearly up to the bowsprit of the sturdy yacht,
but johansen drove on relentlessly. There was
a bursting as of an exploding bladder, a slushy
nastiness as of a cloven sunfish, a stench as of
a thousand opened graves, and a sound that the
chronicler could not put on paper. For an instant
the ship was befouled by an acrid and blinding
green cloud, and then there was only a venomous
seething astern; where - God in heaven! - the
scattered plasticity of that nameless sky-spawn
was nebulously recombining in its hateful original
form, whilst its distance widened every second as
the Alert gained impetus from its mounting steam.
That was all. After that Johansen only brooded
over the idol in the cabin and attended to a
few matters of food for himself and the
laughing maniac by his side. He did not
try to navigate after the first bold flight, for
the reaction had taken something out of his soul.
Then came the storm of April 2nd, and a
gathering of the clouds about his consciousness.
There is a sense of spectral whirling
through liquid gulfs of infinity,
of dizzying rides through reeling universes
on a comets tail, and of hysterical plunges
from the pit to the moon and from the moon back
again to the pit, all livened by a cachinnating
chorus of the distorted, hilarious elder gods and
the green, bat-winged mocking imps of Tartarus.
Out of that dream came rescue-the
Vigilant, the vice-admiralty court,
the streets of Dunedin, and the long voyage
back home to the old house by the Egeberg.
He could not tell - they would think him mad. He
would write of what he knew before death came,
but his wife must not guess. Death would be a
boon if only it could blot out the memories.
That was the document I read, and now I have
placed it in the tin box beside the bas-relief and
the papers of Professor Angell. With it shall go
this record of mine - this test of my own sanity,
wherein is pieced together that which I hope may
never be pieced together again. I have looked upon
all that the universe has to hold of horror, and
even the skies of spring and the flowers of summer
must ever afterward be poison to me. But I do
not think my life will be long. As my uncle went,
as poor Johansen went, so I shall go. I
know too much, and the cult still lives.
Cthulhu still lives, too, I suppose, again in
that chasm of stone which has shielded him since
the sun was young. His accursed city is sunken
once more, for the Vigilant sailed over the spot
after the April storm; but his ministers
on earth still bellow and prance and slay
around idol-capped monoliths in lonely places.
He must have been trapped by the sinking whilst
within his black abyss, or else the world would
by now be screaming with fright and frenzy.
Who knows the end? What has risen
may sink, and what has sunk may rise.
Loathsomeness waits and dreams in the deep, and
decay spreads over the tottering cities of men.
A time will come - but I must not and cannot
think! Let me pray that, if I do not survive this
manuscript, my executors may put caution before
audacity and see that it meets no other eye.
-THE END-