CHAPTER ONE
Blood Feuds
No one who has not felt it can understand
the pain of an exile.
Living in a country that is not your own,
among people who are not your people.
Always a foreigner, an outsider, someone who
does not belong.
Two families, living in Zimbabwe, but the
country they call home is Malawi, a country
they have not seen for nearly thirty years,
a sad, troubled country...
Of course my father and Uncle Phala had their
little disagreements.
But they were the usual ones among friends.
Then there were all those moments of loneliness,
of no hope at all, that everyone in exile
feels.
But they always survived, because they missed
home so much.
They never doubted they would return one day.
That was all my father and Uncle Phala dreamed
about: the return to their own country.
They talked about home all the time.
How they grew up.
The games they used to play.
The schools they went to, the fight for freedom.
'You young ones have no idea what we had to
do to get rid of the British,' Uncle Phala
used to tell us whenever he could.
He was proud of the injury to his leg, which
he said he got in a street battle against
the government in the 1950s.
And then my father, of course, felt he had
to show us the marks on his back, which he
got from beatings in prison.
'I was in prison for a week,' he would say
proudly, 'not like others who only got injured
in a fight.'
Over the years his time in prison became a
month, six weeks, then a year.
'Don't listen to him,' Uncle Phala would answer.
'He fell out of a tree.
That's how he got those marks!'
And he would break into a great, deep laugh.
'Now I'll tell you how he really got his injury!'
my father would say, also laughing.
And they would go on like this.
It wasn't just that they liked each other
- it was much more than that.
They called each other brother.
It was twelve years or more before I learned
that Uncle Phala was, in fact, not my real
uncle.
He and my father had met in the mining village
in Zimbabwe where I was born and grew up.
Their two families lived together in a flat
as big as a matchbox, and my brothers and
sisters and I grew up and went to school with
Uncle Phala's children.
When we finished school, I and most of my
brothers became miners and lived in the mining
village.
All through their years in Zimbabwe my father
and Uncle Phala were involved in exile politics.
It began with the mining village's Home Burial
Society.
This helped workers from our home country
in times of trouble, particularly burials.
Years later my father and Uncle Phala joined
the National Redemption Movement.
This was an organization of exiles who were
against the government back home.
When I was a young boy, I sometimes went with
my father and Uncle Phala to the beer hall
where the Movement held its meetings.
They were both good organizers and fine speakers.
Whenever one of them rose to speak, the hall
became silent and people listened to every
word.
After they finished speaking, everybody would
clap, and I felt so proud of them.
When they stopped working as miners at the
age of fifty, they began working full-time
for the Movement, which grew quickly, thanks
to a large exile community.
Over the years the news from home got worse.
We heard of arrests, violence, and worse.
It was not the government that my father and
Uncle Phala had fought for when the British
left in the 1960s and our country finally
became independent.
'In the beginning,' my father remembered,
'we loved them.
We loved the government.
We thought it was ours.'
I remember Uncle Phala telling us when we
were small about the day of independence.
'Everything seemed so beautiful that day.
The sunshine felt a little gentler, the skies
were bluer, the plants were greener, and the
air smelled fresher.
Just before midnight the British flag was
taken down, and our flag was raised as thousands
clapped.
We loved every word our leader spoke.
We called him "the savior" - we thought he
would save us.'
Like so many other people, my father and Uncle
Phala spent all the money they had to go to
the capital for the independence ceremony
- a great day for our country.
At that time my father worked on a farm.
Soon afterwards he lost his job when the farm
was sold to one of the new government officers
who preferred to employ workers from his own
part of the country.
Uncle Phala lost his job because he was the
leader of a workers' organization at his factory.
The new government did not allow workers'
organizations any more, saying that the workers
had no enemies now that independence had been
won.
So Uncle Phala and my father left the country
a couple of years later, as so many others
had done before them, to look for jobs in
the mines of Zimbabwe.
The exiles in Zimbabwe learned to live with
the bad news that came from home.
They would discuss it and pass it on, but
it was something they did not actually experience.
Although exile was painful, they could hide
behind it and dream, and avoid being responsible
for their own lives.
I did not think of myself as one of them.
Of course, I considered where my parents came
from as my homeland too, although I had never
been there.
But I also felt strong ties to Zimbabwe, the
place of my birth.
At home we spoke my parents' language; elsewhere
we used one of the local languages.
I never really had to think much about my
real home until I was an adult.
It didn't matter when I was a child.
Of course, the other children would sometimes
call us by rude names - whatever word was
fashionable for 'foreigners' at the time - but
it never mattered to me.
Not so in later years.
It was partly age, I suppose.
As you grow older, things seem to hurt a little
deeper.
The situation in Zimbabwe was also changing.
People began to think of themselves less as
Africans and more as Zimbabweans.
We became 'foreigners', even those of us who
were born in Zimbabwe, when it came to giving
out jobs and to finding someone to blame for
the nation's problems.
That is when I became more involved in the
National Redemption Movement.
Slowly, our community turned inward, and as
far as possible we kept together, helped one
another, and married among ourselves.
I married Uncle Phala's eldest daughter, Mwali,
which pleased both our parents greatly.
'We are now real brothers!'
the two men told everyone at the wedding ceremony.
I began to miss my homeland as much as my
father and Uncle Phala did.
I wanted to know more about it.
So I asked questions; I searched for information
in books, newspapers, and magazines.
I dreamed of the shining lake with its golden
sand beaches, the rivers, hills, and mountains,
and the cool green highlands.
A land, as my father and Uncle Phala remembered
it, of tidy villages, handsome cities, safe
streets, and smiling faces.
Not this dry, empty land that was only good
for exiles.
We hoped and dreamed.
In the meantime I grew older.
I had three children.
My father and Uncle Phala began to look like
the grandfathers they were.
They continued to be involved in the Movement,
but the situation in our homeland stayed the
same.
None of us thought it would change soon, although
we did not doubt that change would come in
the end.
Nobody imagined how quickly the thirty-year-old
regime would fall a few years later.
People had been unhappy for years, of course,
but it was the church leaders who brought
it into the open.
One Easter Sunday the priests read out a letter
in churches throughout the country.
The letter did not ask for anything unusual,
just simple things like respect for the law,
freedom for political prisoners, food for
the hungry...
But the letter hit the country like a bomb.
No one had ever demanded these things openly
before.
Some church leaders were arrested and terrible
warnings were given.
But it was too late.
The students, young and impatient, joined
the fight.
'Give us free elections!'
they demanded.
'Let political prisoners go free!'
The universities and colleges were closed
and the students were sent home.
That only made things worse, because the students
took the message back to their home towns.
Then the workers joined the battle.
They stopped work, demanding better pay.
The police tried to break up one protest march,
but they only succeeded in shooting hundreds
of workers and starting angry protests all
over the country.
Even foreign governments and banks began to
talk about sending no more money to a regime
that had lost control.
I had never seen my father and Uncle Phala
so excited.
They had the radio and television on all the
time, following the news from home.
For some reason I was not as excited as I
had expected.
I had become so used to hoping and dreaming
that the possibility of return frightened
me.
Exile had always been my life.
It was all I knew.
Other things made me uneasy too.
Our community of exiles began to break into
two groups: those who wanted to return, and
those who were not so enthusiastic.
The same disagreements were seen in families,
and before long in the Movement itself.
At our yearly meeting there were so many arguments
that by the end the Movement had broken into
three separate groups.
It was sad to watch.
Nothing prepared me for what was waiting for
us in our dear homeland.
It was certainly beautiful, but that was all.
We went first to my father's village.
I was disappointed.
It was nothing more than a group of rough
mud houses.
I met some of my uncles and aunts for the
first time.
They all looked much older than my father,
although they were younger than he was.
They were nice and friendly, but that was
all they could offer us.
It was the same at my mother's village, which
was a few miles away.
I felt like a stranger.
Our relations called us machona, meaning the
long lost people.
As machona, we were expected to bring endless
presents, far more than the workers who returned
every two years or so, carrying huge suitcases
full of gifts for their relations - clothes,
blankets, radios, watches, sunglasses...
For a couple of months they would live like
chiefs.
Then, when all their money had gone, they
would leave for Zimbabwe once again.
But we disappointed our relations.
I suspected that this was one of the reasons
that my father had not returned for so long.
I also began to understand that my own people
were no different from the people of Zimbabwe,
who had many arguments and fights between
their different ethnic groups.
We were proud that our community of exiles
in the mining village had no silly ethnic
arguments of that kind, although we had people
who came from different places and ethnic
groups in the homeland.
My father, for example, was from the south,
and Uncle Phala from the north.
But back in our own country I heard the same
sad, silly arguments.
In fact, it was more serious than that.
All our politicians, old and new, seemed to
want to make trouble between the different
ethnic groups.
Perhaps this was because no political party
had any real ideas or plans for our country's
future.
My father, of course, soon got involved in
politics.
At first he was busy trying to start a business
with the money he had brought back from Zimbabwe.
Then someone asked him to be a leader of one
of the local parties.
He said no at first, but I think that was
only because he did not want to seem too enthusiastic.
'Well, I have to do what is best for my people,'
he said in the end.
'They need a man of my experience for leadership.'
It was good for his business.
Many of the local businesses here in the south
were owned by northerners, and people were
beginning to dislike this more and more.
A few weeks later I went north with my family
to visit Uncle Phala.
We were well received.
Uncle Phala proudly introduced me to his relations.
I liked his village better than my father's.
The place and the people seemed less miserable.
Mwali and I decided to make our home there
and start a business.
I bought two lorries to take fish from the
lake to the capital.
It would make me a lot of money.
My father was not pleased with my plan when
I returned for a visit.
He said I was turning my back on my people.
'But Father,' I protested, 'we're living with
Uncle Phala.
He's your "brother", remember?'
'Uncle Phala is all right.
It's his people who aren't.'
'I can't believe you, of all people, saying
that.'
I did not tell Uncle Phala about my father's
opinions.
He was pleased that we had decided to stay.
'You're my favourite son.
You've been good to my daughter.'
Uncle Phala did not have a son.
All of his eight children were girls.
Like my father, he had also started a business,
which was doing quite well.
Before long he, too, was asked to join a leading
local political party.
And like his 'brother', he waited for a while
before he agreed.
And so the two most important men in my life
became caught in the new politics.
Each party tried to organize bigger meetings,
bigger marches than the others; no one discussed
plans for government.
Political prisoners, locked up in prison,
were almost forgotten, except by their mothers.
And no party called for national discussions
on how to bring good government to our poor,
weak, unhappy country.
It was difficult not to be part of the noisy
business of politics, but I tried to stay
out of it.
I missed the quieter politics of exile.
Here there was no hoping, no dreaming - it
was all rough and real.
Too rough, in fact.
A couple of months before the elections were
held for a new government, violence broke
out.
It was not clear who started it.
Northerners accused southerners, and southerners
accused northerners.
Both sides chased the 'foreigners', the outsiders,
living among them.
Church leaders and others blamed the government
for making the troubles worse.
The government, of course, said that they
were not responsible.
Our "savior", now a very sick old man, said
the violence proved he was right.
It showed that party politics and elections
were as foreign to the country as winter.
One morning we were woken by a noise like
a bomb exploding.
We looked out of the window.
My lorries were on fire.
We all knew why, but we blamed thieves for
it.
It was less painful that way.
We were trying to keep the hopes and dreams
of exile alive, but we could not hide from
the real world any longer.
That evening Uncle Phala spoke what was on
our minds.
'You're not safe here.
Maybe you should go home.'
'I thought I was home,' I said, more in sadness
than in anger.
'So did I.
This isn't the country your father and I left
thirty years ago.
They've changed it into something else, something
terrible, that will eat us alive if we aren't
careful.'
For the first time he looked very old.
'We'll be out of here as soon as we can.'
'No, you'll go alone.
Mwali and the children will be as unsafe in
your home as you are here.'
'But I can't leave my family behind.'
'It's for their own good, and for your own
good too,' he said sadly.
'Believe me.'
'It's not right,' I said softly.
'It's just not right.'
He did not look at Mwali or me, but I could
see that he agreed.
Mwali and I spent a sleepless night discussing
the matter.
We decided that we would either stay together
or leave together.
Nothing would separate us.
But we did not have time to tell Uncle Phala
what we had decided, because early the next
morning we heard a large crowd shouting excitedly
outside.
'We want the southerner!'
they screamed.
'We want the southerner!
Give us the southerner!'
'Hide under the bed quick,' Mwali whispered.
The shouting came closer, and some people
started banging on the door.
Then the noise stopped, and we heard Uncle
Phala's voice.
'He ran away last night!'
'No!'
the crowd shouted with disappointment.
'We want the southerner!'
'You know how these southerners are!'
Uncle Phala shouted.
'They don't know what "brave" means.
They may be good with books and take all the
jobs for teachers and clerks, but that's all
they can do.
They can't fight.
That boy may have balls, but he's no braver
than a woman.'
The crowd laughed.
'Leave the house alone.'
Suddenly he called out Mwali's name.
'Come and tell these brave sons of the north
where your useless husband is.'
I could not believe what he was saying.
Had he gone crazy?
'What should I do?'
she asked me desperately.
'I don't know.
What's wrong with your father?
I thought he loved me.
He told me so himself.'
'Mwali!
Please come out and tell these men where your
good-for-nothing husband went.'
I felt suddenly angry.
'Go.
He's your father.'
I pushed her and she started crying.
'Go, I said!'
'Don't scream.
They'll hear you.'
She tried to get herself under control.
'Please stay where you are.
Don't move,' she said as she went unwillingly
to the door.
'See, she's crying,' Uncle Phala said when
she came out.
'I told her not to marry a southerner!'
The crowd began to go away, still shouting
about southerners.
Moments later Mwali returned, looking both
shaken and thankful.
I stayed indoors the whole day.
Later Uncle Phala came to me.
I could see the unhappiness on his face.
'I'm sorry I had to say all those things.'
'So you didn't mean it,' I said coldly.
'Of course not.'
He was trying not to cry.
'That was the only way I could save you, by
talking their kind of language.
You'll always be my favourite son, no matter
what.'
I do not know how long we sat there, staring
at the walls.
We all wished to be back in the old days of
exile.
I escaped that night, and my people were thankful
to see me safe.
'I always told you that northerners are cruel
and wild,' my father said.
I could not remember him ever saying that.
But I did not feel like arguing with him.
I just wanted to sleep and dream of the simpler
days of exile.
The elections were held on time.
The old governing party just managed to win,
but the other political parties refused to
accept the results and did not recognize the
government.
While this argument went on, the army appeared
on the streets, and the frightened country
became calm.
It seemed safe enough for me to ask Mwali
and the children to come.
Uncle Phala came with them.
When the two old men met, they put their arms
round each other.
For a while it seemed like the old days, except
that they both looked so much older now.
They were both much thinner.
Uncle Phala walked even more painfully, and
my father could not see or hear very well.
But it was not the old days.
They had little to talk about.
It was painful to watch.
The friendliness and the laughter had all
gone.
The days of exile now seemed so far away and
unreal.
And yet we had been back for about a year.
Uncle Phala only stayed a couple of days.
He left early in the morning.
We all went with him to the bus station, except
for my mother who was not feeling well.
My father and Uncle Phala stood in silence
with their arms round each other for what
seemed like a long time.
From the steps of the bus Uncle Phala waved
to us with his stick.
waved in return.
Then he climbed painfully onto the bus and
never looked back.
- THE END -