CHAPTER ONE
Tug is Taken Away
DAY ONE - SUNDAY 7TH AUGUST
Tug was running. His legs ached, his feet hurt,
all his body was screaming at him to stop running.
But he didn't want to stop. He wanted today's
run to be better and faster than ever before.
Now he was nearly at the end of his run, and
his legs were burning, but he still went on
running. As he came round the last street corner,
he saw his own front door, a hundred metres away.
I mustn't stop now! he thought. I promised
myself I'd do eight kilometres, and I will!
The church bells were ringing, and
the blood was beating in his ears.
Suddenly it all seemed easy, and his legs felt
strong. I can do it! he said happily to himself.
He reached the front door, and looked at
his watch. 36 minutes 20 seconds. At last!
Eight kilometres in less than 37 minutes!
I've been trying to do that for weeks!
He put his key in the door. Now he could have
a hot bath. His mother would get home later.
She had promised to cook him a
special meal - chicken and chips,
and a chocolate cake. He smiled
as he pushed open the door.
Strange! The house was dark, too dark. And
there was something more... But he was too
tired to think. Suddenly there was an arm
round his neck and a hand over his face.
He fell, and everything went black.
DAY TWO - MONDAY 8TH AUGUST
Fifteen hours later and
two hundred kilometres away in Derbyshire,
Jinny Slattery came out of the farmhouse.
In the moonlight she could see the ridge
of mountains called Ashdale Great Edge.
It stood, black and frightening, against the
sky, with the Castle Rock at its southern end.
Jinny walked away from the farmhouse, and took
the narrow road up the hill. It was two o'clock in
the morning, and very quiet. When she reached some
trees, her father stepped out and touched her arm.
'Oh!' she cried in surprise, and felt angry
with herself. He had told her to be quiet.
'Follow me,' Joe said, and went on up
the road. He walked quickly and silently,
his dog just behind him.
I must remember what he told
me to do, Jinny thought.
I don't want to make a mistake!
Now they were high up on the moors.
Further along was an old cottage,
which Mrs Hollins used to rent to
summer visitors. It was almost hidden
by trees. On the right was a gate into a
field, the field which they had chosen.
Jinny felt sick. She knew what would happen next.
Joe had already filled every hole in the hedges
round the field, so the gate was the only way
out. Now he was putting a net over the gate.
Just then they heard a car driving up the road.
'Where is it going?' asked Jinny. 'This road
only goes to the moors and Mrs Hollins' cottage.'
'Visitors,' said Joe softly,
'probably renting the cottage.
Keep quiet, they won't see us in the dark.'
The car drove slowly past them and
stopped in front of the cottage.
Jinny could hear the voices of a man
and a woman, and then a strange noise.
Were they pulling something heavy into the
house? She couldn't see what was happening.
When it was quiet again, Joe
said softly, 'Remember, Jinny.
Remember everything I told you,' and went
silently into the field, followed by his dog.
Jinny was shaking now, not from cold but from
fear and excitement. She knew that Joe and the
dog were moving slowly through the field. She
thought of the hare, lying asleep in the grass.
It would try to escape through the gate.
Then she must do what Joe had told her.
I can't! she thought. But she had
to do it. 'If you want to eat meat,
you must be able to kill an animal,' Joe had
said. 'Why should other people do it for you?'
But in the end it almost seemed easy. The hare
tried to jump through the gate and was caught
in the net. Automatically Jinny hit its neck hard,
and the hare's warm dead body fell at her feet. As
she was looking at it, Joe arrived. 'Good girl,'
he said, and started taking the net off the gate.
Just then a loud noise broke the silence.
It was the sound of hammering,
and it came from the cottage.
'What's that?' Jinny cried. But Joe didn't stop
what he was doing. 'Nothing to do with us,'
he replied. That was what he always said.
For him the Slattery family was much
more important than the outside world.
'But if someone hears,' said Jinny,
'they'll come up here to see,
and then the police will catch us...
stealing hares that don't belong to us!'
'Don't worry,' said Joe calmly. 'From the village
you can't hear anything that happens up here.
We'll make sure that we get home
with the hare before anyone comes.'
They walked down the road to the farmhouse.
I'm not like Joe, thought Jinny. I always
want to know why things happen. And I want
to know what's happening in that cottage!
10.00 A.M.
Seven hours later,
Tug woke up in the cottage. The room was
full of sunshine and very loud music.
Above him was a high window, with strong
bars across it, and blue sky outside.
It must be a dream. He wanted to wake up,
and find himself in his own bedroom.
But the dream did not go away.
Suddenly he noticed a woman at the door. She
was about thirty, and very thin, with long legs,
long brown hair and long fingers. But her eyes
were the most interesting thing about her.
They were large and yellow-brown, almost golden.
She said something, but he couldn't
hear her because of the music.
'Sorry, I didn't hear that,' he said.
'I said how are you feeling?' she shouted angrily.
Tug tried to sit up. When he moved his
head, he felt sick. 'What happened?'
he asked. 'I don't remember this place.'
He was sure he had never been there before.
The woman sounded careless, unworried.
'You fell... hit your head ...
we had to carry you upstairs...'
It was important, but he couldn't
hear because the music was so loud.
'It's too noisy! We can't talk!' he shouted.
She didn't answer, but opened the
bedroom door and shouted to someone.
The music was louder through the open door. Tug
couldn't think, and his head was still hurting.
A man came into the room, with slow, unhurried
steps. He had a strangely white face,
with cold blue eyes and thick black hair. The
woman spoke quietly to him. Tug couldn't hear.
'Look,' said Tug. He wanted to sound as polite as
possible. 'I don't remember anything. Where am I?
And how did I get here? And who are you?
Please will you tell me what's happening?'
'Don't worry,' said the man
coldly. 'You hit your head
and you've forgotten a few things.
That's all. You'll be fine after a rest.'
He turned to go, but Tug reached
out for his arm. 'Please!'
he cried wildly. 'You must tell me something!
'We're in the cottage that we've rented
for our holiday, in the north of England.
You remember? Now try and sleep.'
'But who are you?' shouted Tug. They
were both leaving the room. The man
said something that Tug didn't hear, ...
mirror...' and closed the door behind him.
Tug jumped out of bed and ran
to the door, but it was locked.
Suddenly he felt very cold. The music still filled
his head, but it didn't stop him thinking now. He
had hoped this was all a mistake, that they would
answer his questions and explain everything,
or take him home. But now he realized that they
wanted to keep him a prisoner in that room.
It was a small room just under the roof, with
only a bed and a cupboard in it. He looked up at
the window above his head. They had hammered the
bars on to it very recently. He couldn't escape
that way. He sat on the bed and put his head in
his hands. He had never felt so miserable and
frightened before. Just then he thought of his
mother. He knew what she would say to him now.
Why do you always feel sorry for yourself? Get up
and do something! He felt better when he thought
of her small angry face. Cheer up, Tug! he told
himself, and got up to look in the cupboard.
He was very pleased to find his clothes there, all
ready for him to wear. But as he reached for them,
he noticed something. On the inside
of the door was a long mirror.
What had the man said? Something about a
mirror. Slowly Tug turned to look at himself.
And for a second he was in a bad dream.
Because the face in the mirror was not his.
Then he realized what was different - his hair. It
was black, not fair. His face seemed very white,
and his blue eyes looked coldly back at him. He
looked at himself in the mirror for a long time.
With the black hair, white
face and cold blue eyes,
he looked just like the man.
He could almost be his son.
12.45 P.M.
Jinny ran into the village.
Her father had asked her to post something, so
she wanted to get to the post office before it
closed for lunch. Outside the post office
she saw Rachel Hollins sitting on a wall.
Rachel's father was the village policeman, and her
mother worked in the post office. Rachel was very
pretty, and always wore beautiful clothes. 'Hello
Jinny!' she cried. 'Do you like my new dress?'
'Very nice,' replied Jinny crossly. 'But I
couldn't wear that for working on the farm.'
'Oh, I forgot!' said Rachel. She smiled sweetly -
too sweetly, and Jinny wanted to hit her. 'I'm so
sorry! Poor Jinny! You have to work so hard and
you never have any new clothes and... She stopped
as she saw someone behind Jinny 'I must go in and
have lunch,' she said quickly, and ran inside.
Jinny turned to see who was
behind her. It was a woman,
with the strangest, loveliest eyes she had ever
seen - big, yellow-brown eyes, almost golden.
Hares eyes, thought Jinny. The woman looked
like a hare, with her long legs and thin face.
'I can see that girl only thinks about clothes,'
said the Hare-woman to Jinny,
and walked into the post office.
Jinny watched her go. What an interesting woman!
she thought. And she understands about Rachel!
Inside the post office the one
o'clock news was on the radio.
The Hare-woman, Mrs Hollins,
and Jinny all listened.
Terrorists are holding
thirteen-year-old Liam Shakespeare,
Harriet Shakespeare's son, at the family
home in London. Police are trying to...
'How terrible!' said Mrs Hollins. 'That poor boy!'
'Who's Harriet Shakespeare?' asked Jinny.
'You haven't heard of her?' asked the Hare-woman
in surprise. 'She's a television reporter,
always looking for other people's
secrets. Thinks herself very important.'
Mrs Hollins pretended to feel sorry for
Jinny. 'Poor girl, she doesn't have any
newspapers or radio or television in her house,'
she explained. 'Her family grow their own food,
make their own clothes. They
never buy anything new!'
Mrs Hollins always laughs at us Slatterys,
thought Jinny. 'We prefer to do everything
for ourselves,' she said. She really
wanted the stranger to understand.
But Mrs Hollins had started talking about the
news again. 'That poor Harriet Shakespeare!
She must be very worried. A mother always
worries about her children. Have you any
children?' she asked the Hare-woman. 'Ye-es,
yes, I have. A son, Philip, almost fourteen.'
'Well, well! My daughter Rachel and Jinny here are
both nearly fourteen. Are you staying near here?'
The Hare-woman laughed. 'Well, yes, we're staying
in your cottage. We arrived late last night.'
'Oh, you're Mrs Doyle!' Mrs Hollins
said, and shook the stranger's hand
warmly. So the Hare-woman was one of the
visitors to the cottage thought Jinny.
'In fact, I hope we didn't wake
everyone in the village up last night,'
said the Hare-woman. 'Philip fell
over and crashed into some furniture.
There was a terrible noise. He hit his
head, so he'll be in bed for a while.'
Jinny said nothing, but she knew that wasn't true.
'We were very tired,' continued the
Hare-woman, 'so we took Philip upstairs
and went to bed immediately.'
Another lie! thought Jinny. You
didn't go to bed immediately.
You hammered and hammered. Why are you lying?
Suddenly the Hare-woman
seemed to remember something.
She stopped talking, bought
some food and hurried out.
Jinny walked slowly back to the farm.
At first she had liked the stranger,
with her beautiful honest eyes.
But why was she lying?
CHAPTER TWO
WHAT'S HAPPENING AT THE COTTAGE?
DAY THREE - TUESDAY 9TH AUGUST
8.00 A.M.
Tug was lying on the bed. He hadn't slept since
the Man and the Woman walked out after their
first visit, hours ago. The music had a strong
beat which hammered at the inside of his head,
and it hadn't stopped all
night. He was very tired,
and hungry and thirsty. But he was
watching the door and waiting for Them.
When the door opened, the music was louder for
a moment as the Man entered. He looked at Tug.
'Did you sleep well?' he asked, after a moment.
'No,' said Tug. 'I - I'm thirsty.'
'Have some water,' answered the Man. 'I've brought
some.' And he offered Tug a glass of water.
I'm not taking anything from you, Tug wanted
to say, before you tell me what's happening.
But he was so thirsty! He took
the glass and drank all the water.
Then he turned to the Man and said, 'Tell me-'
'Sit down on the bed,' ordered the Man.
Something in the Man's face told Tug
that it was not a good idea to refuse.
He sat down. The Man opened the door and, while
watching Tug carefully, put his arm outside.
And suddenly the music stopped.
Tug fell back on the bed, free from the terrible
noise at last. The room was beautifully silent.
Then he heard someone climbing the stairs.
The Woman walked in. She was carrying a tray.
'Breakfast,' she said. 'Look.' It was a
dream breakfast. A big plate of fried eggs,
tomatoes and bread, with a cup of hot, strong tea.
Tug could not stop looking at the tray. But the
Woman did not move. She stayed near the door.
'Well?' he said at last. 'Isn't it for me?'
'Oh yes,' she replied. 'It's for
you. But what do you say first?'
I'm not a child! thought Tug angrily. She's
teaching me to be polite! But he was very hungry.
'Thank you,' he said.
'Thank you - what?' she asked.
'I don't understand,' said Tug. Is this a game?
'You usually call her something,' said the Man.
Tug began to see what they
wanted. Were they serious?
He pretended that he still didn't understand.
'What do you mean? What do I usually call her?'
It was the Woman who answered. 'You usually call
me Ma. And your breakfast will be cold soon.'
But Tug wasn't ready to do what they wanted yet.
He turned to the Man. 'And
I suppose I call you Dad!'
'No,' smiled the Man calmly. 'You could,
but you don't. You call me Doyle.'
Doyle... Ma... Tug looked from one to the other.
It almost seemed true. Suddenly he shouted,
'You're crazy! All that's rubbish! Why
don't you explain what's happening...'
The door banged shut. The Woman had walked
out and taken his breakfast with her.
'That was stupid of you,' said
Doyle. 'She's angry with you.
Mothers are like that sometimes, aren't they?'
'But -' said Tug, and stopped. He could
hear her climbing up the stairs again.
'Now be careful this time,' said Doyle quietly.
The Woman entered again, with the tray. Tug
could smell the hot food. It looked wonderful.
'Breakfast,' said the Woman, for the second time.
What does it matter? thought Tug. Ma isn't
what I call my mother. I call her Hank.
'Thank you - Ma,' he said. The Woman gave him the
tray, and left the room. As Doyle followed her,
he turned and smiled slowly at Tug.
'Have a good breakfast - Philip.'
'I'm not Philip!' Tug shouted. 'And you're not
my parents!' But the door had already closed.
And then the music started. With
that terrible beat in his head,
he wasn't sure of anything any more.
10.00 A.M.
Jinny was digging in the garden.
While she was working, she was talking angrily to
herself. Forget it! Its nothing to do with you!
But she couldn't stop herself thinking of
the Hare-woman. Why had she lied about the
noises in the night? And why had there
been so much hammering at the cottage?
Suddenly she had an idea. She
could go up to the cottage now.
She knew that she should go on with her
work - there were always lots of jobs to
do on the Slatterys' small farm - but she
really wanted to understand the mystery.
Perhaps the Hare-woman had a good reason for lying
and perhaps she would tell Jinny all about it...
Soon she was walking up the narrow road to the
moors. The cottage was on the left, but she didn't
go up to it. She climbed up the small hill behind
the house, and hid in the trees halfway up the
hill. She couldn't see anybody in the cottage,
but she could hear a radio playing loud music.
Something was different about the
cottage... Jinny went a few steps nearer,
to look more closely at the window in the roof...
Suddenly a voice spoke from below. 'Hallo.'
'Oh!' cried Jinny in surprise, and
the branch that she was holding broke.
She fell, and slid all the way down
the hill to the cottage garden.
'Well, well!' said the voice.
Jinny looked up. It was a man with black
hair and cold blue eyes. He looked angry.
Jinny thought fast.
'I - I'm sorry, I didn't mean to - You see, I was
looking for - for - mushrooms.' Would he believe
her? She continued quickly, 'They're very good
to eat, er, fried in butter, for breakfast -'
'Yes.' The cold voice stopped her. 'But perhaps
you'd like to find a different place to look for
mushrooms. We're here on holiday, you see, and we
don't want people crashing in through the kitchen
window.' He was holding her by the arm as he
spoke, and pulling her away from the cottage.
Jinny was frightened.
Just then she heard a single wild shout from
inside the cottage, followed immediately
by a crashing sound. The loud music went on
playing. The man shouted towards the house,
'Oh, be quiet, Philip!' He's pretending
to be a father who's angry with his son,
thought Jinny, but I don't believe him! Why is he
so cold and unfriendly? Is he hiding something?
But she was shaking a little after her
fall, and she was still afraid of the man.
So she pulled her arm away, and
said quickly, 'I - I must go home.'
She knew that he was watching her as
she hurried away from the cottage.
10.30 A.M.
The music was still playing in the bedroom.
Tug had just finished his breakfast when
he heard the noise of Jinny's fall outside.
He jumped on to the bed and looked out of the
window. He could only see the sky and the tops of
trees, but he heard a girl saying, 'They're very
good to eat, fried in butter, for breakfast -' Who
was she? Could he send her a message? Would it
be dangerous? Then he heard feet running up the
stairs. It was now or never. He pushed open the
window and shouted as loudly as possible, 'Help!'
The next moment the Woman had crashed into him.
He fell on to the floor, and she held him
down with one strong hand over his mouth.
She only let him get up when she heard
the Man come back into the house.
'Right!' she said. 'Now you learn to obey
orders!' She hit him hard across the face,
on one side and then the other. She went
on hitting him, in time to the beat of
the music. Tug began to think that she would
never stop. He was trying hard not to scream,
because when he started, he would go on and on,
like her... Then suddenly Doyle was there. He put
a finger on the Woman's arm. Just one finger.
And no words. But it was enough. She stopped.
'Stupid woman,' said Doyle calmly. 'Stupid to hit
his face. Get some water.' She went downstairs.
'She hit me,' said Tug. 'Just because I -'
'You have to understand,' Doyle said
quietly. 'We'll kill you if we have to.'
The room seemed very quiet, although the music
was still playing. I've never been really afraid
before, thought Tug. He was full of a deep, cold
fear. For the first time in his life, he realized
that he could die. Not in a hundred years, or
when he was very old, but now. Today or tomorrow.
But the moment passed. Soon Doyle and the Woman
were washing Tug's face, like careful parents.
When the Woman left the
room, Doyle sat by the door.
Now he had a gun with him, which he was cleaning.
Tug could not take his eyes off the cold grey gun.
Perhaps he's going to kill me
now... to shoot me with the gun...
At last Doyle put the gun down. Suddenly
angry, Tug shouted, 'How can you two pretend
to be my parents? Look what that woman
did to my face! She can't be my mother!'
'Most murders happen in the family, you know. Your
family are the people who can give you most pain.
They know how to hurt you. Parents are the worst.'
'Then why are you trying to hurt me?' asked Tug.
'Trying to hurt you? No, Philip,
we're doing our best for you.
But we're prisoners of the family
ourselves. Like the rest of the world.'
And he smiled as he picked up his gun again.
11.00 A.M.
Jinny was still
running when she reached the village. I must
tell Keith what's happening at the cottage!
I know he'll listen to me! Keith
was Rachel Hollins' brother,
and Jinny's best friend in the village,
although he was five years older than her.
She found him in the Hollins' sitting-room, with
a lot of different newspapers in front of him.
'Keith!' she cried. 'I've got to tell you! It was
so awful! I didn't do anything wrong but he -'
She began to cry as she started speaking.
But Keith always took care of
her. He gave her his cup of tea.
'Now, drink that, Jinny,' he told her.
'You'll feel better in a moment.
Then tell me all about it.'
She told him about the people at the cottage,
and explained how the Hare-woman had told lies
in Mrs Hollins' shop. 'So I went to
the cottage to see,' she continued.
'And I slid down the hill behind the
house - and there was an awful man
who told me to go away. But the really
important thing is what I heard!'
'Tell me quickly, or I'll die of excitement.'
Keith was laughing quietly to himself.
'Listen,' she said angrily. 'It's serious.
I heard someone shouting "Help!" And the
person who shouted meant it.
Now what do you think, Keith?'
'Well,' said Keith, after thinking for a moment.
'Perhaps someone was just playing a game.'
'A game! No! There was hammering - and she told
lies - and I heard the shout! These are facts!'
'These newspapers have all got facts in,' said
Keith. 'But they make different stories out of
the same facts. That's my school work for the
summer - to take a story and follow it in all
the newspapers for a week, to see how different
the stories are, although the facts are the same.
Can you think of a story that I could follow?'
Jinny remembered the Hare-woman in the shop,
listening to the radio. 'You could do the story
of Harriet Shakespeare's son, you know, held by
terrorists. But Keith, you're forgetting my story!
What about the voice that
shouted "Help!"? What can I do?'
'I agree it is a bit strange. But
there's probably a good reason for it.
If you find some more facts, I'll
ask my father to investigate it.
But now I really must start reading
these newspapers. Sorry I can't help.'
I'll investigate it myself,
thought Jinny crossly.
DAY FOUR - WEDNESDAY 10TH AUGUST
11.00 A.M.
Tug felt terrible. The music had given
him a headache. He was alone for a moment,
while Doyle and the Woman were downstairs. He
looked tiredly round the room, at the cupboard,
the walls, the wallpaper ... An idea suddenly
came to him. I'll tear a piece of paper off
the wall behind the cupboard, nobody will
notice... He pulled at a corner of the paper.
Hurry, hurry! One of Them will be back soon.
Now he had a large piece of paper in his hand.
With the pencil that he always kept in his
pocket, he wrote a few words quickly on the paper.
Then, with his hands shaking, he folded
the paper into the shape of a dart.
Hurry, hurry! He jumped on to the bed, pushed his
arm through the bars, and threw the dart as far
as possible out of the open window. That's your
only chance to get a message to the outside world,
he told himself. I hope that
someone finds it soon!
CHAPTER THREE
FREE PEOPLE
DAY FIVE - THURSDAY 11TH AUGUST
6.30 A.M.
As Jinny did her work on the farm, she could not
stop thinking about the mystery of the Hare-woman
and her son. She was hoping to go back to the
cottage today. But at breakfast her father said,
'You'll have to make the butter today, Jinny,
because your mother is making the bread.
Oz,' he said to Jinny's young brother,
'you're coming to help me mend the walls
round the south field. And Jinny, you'll
have to plant the vegetables as well.
I think you'll have time. There's a
lot to do before harvest next week.'
Thanks a lot! Jinny thought angrily. Don't I
get any time for myself? It's always the same!
Later she talked to her mother, Bella, about it.
'Mum, why do I have to spend all my time
working on the farm? It's the summer holidays
now. My school friends all get up late
and go riding. Or shopping, like Rachel.'
'Jinny, you know why we decided
to leave London and buy this farm.
Joe was working much too hard in London. His
work was making him ill. We wanted a healthier,
freer life. I agree that it's hard
work, but we chose this life.'
'You two chose it, you mean. No one asked me.'
'All children get the life
that their parents have chosen.
You can choose your own life
when you're old enough.'
'But I want some time now!
I'm - I'm so angry with Dad!
He gives me too much work to do.
Sometimes I - I almost want to kill him!'
Her mother did not reply immediately. Then she
said quietly, 'It's because you love him that
you want to kill him. But it's the wrong answer.
If you kill the people who you love, or run away
from them, you only destroy yourself in the end.
You have to accept them, or change yourself.'
Suddenly Jinny realized that it was
true. Accepting what other people wanted,
and working together - that was family
life. She smiled at her mother.
5.30 P.M.
Doyle looked at his watch.
'Time to go downstairs.'
'What?' said Tug. He had been there for almost
five days now. Was it possible to leave the room?
Doyle pushed him towards the door, and they
went down the stairs. At the same moment
Doyle turned off the music. For the last
two days it had not stopped for a second.
Now, the house was suddenly
silent, and Tug felt frightened.
They were in a big sitting-room, full of old heavy
furniture. The Woman was sitting in an armchair.
'Sit down,' she said to Tug. 'We're going to have
a nice family evening in front of the television.'
Clearly, Tug's visit downstairs was planned.
The television news was just starting.
Of course! thought Tug. I'll be in the news!
'Good evening. The terrorists who
are holding thirteen-year-old Liam
Shakespeare at his home in London have
said that they belong to "Free People".
That is the revolutionary group
which wants to end family life.
They say that they want all children and adults
to live free from the prison of the family.'
What's happening? thought Tug. Am I
crazy? How can I be here and in London?
'Our reporter spoke to Liam's mother, Harriet
Shakespeare, at a friend's house today.'
There was Hank. Her small face looked tired, and
Tug could see that she was trying not to cry.
Hank, Hank, come and save me from these people!
'Mrs Shakespeare, have you spoken
to your son?' asked the reporter.
'No,' replied Hank. 'But we can see him moving
around in the house, so we know he's still alive.'
'Why do you think this group has taken your son?'
'Well, I suppose that it's because I've
investigated Free People in the past.
It's my job to investigate revolutionary groups.'
'You have always said that nobody should
give terrorist groups what they want.
Do you still think that, now
that your own son is in danger?'
'Yes, I do. But we - we don't know yet what
the group wants. We'll have to wait and see.'
That's a lie! Tug thought. He always knew
when Hank was lying. But she seemed to
believe that he was held by terrorists in
London. And the reporters believed it too.
Doyle and the Woman were watching him carefully.
'It's interesting to hear about your
friend Liam, isn't it?' Doyle said slowly.
'He isn't my friend-' began Tug. Then
he stopped. He remembered Hank saying,
We can see him moving around. Suddenly he
felt very tired. Who am I? Where's home?
In the bedroom, with the music,
he would feel better. He stood up.
'I want to go back upstairs.'
Doyle put an arm round Tug, and led
him upstairs like a small child.
8.00 P.M.
Keith was very excited about
the Liam Shakespeare story.
'Don't you think it's strange?' he asked Jinny.
'What do you mean?' she answered. She was
very tired after a long day on the farm.
'Well, I've just shown you all the newspapers
and the video of the six o'clock news. There's
Harriet Shakespeare, a brave, loving mother,
worried about her son. A picture of mother-love
and happy families. But it's the wrong picture,
isn't it? The terrorists have made a bad mistake.'
Jinny was too tired to think clearly.
'What do they care? They just want
money or something, don't they?'
'Don't you understand? Terrorists aren't strong
enough to change the world by themselves.
So they try to make pictures that will change
people's ideas. The Free People group want
publicity. And in this Shakespeare story, they're
making a picture that says Mothers are wonderful.
But they don't want to say that. They want to
say Destroy family life, because it's bad for
you. Their message to the world here' - he picked
up one of the papers - 'is that everybody - women,
men, and children - should escape from the prison
of the family. So why are they giving us the
wrong message? Yes, it's a very interesting
story, Jinny! What's going to happen?'
DAY SIX - FRIDAY 12TH AUGUST
2.00 A.M.
Tug woke up suddenly from a bad
dream. The room was very dark,
and a large shadow was standing over his
bed. Tug screamed. A hand covered his mouth.
'Quiet,' said a voice, very softly.
'Daddy's going to tell you a bedtime story.
When I was a small boy, I used
to wake up in the night and cry.
Because I was afraid of the dark, you
see. Like you. Crying in the dark.'
Tug wanted to say, I wasn't crying.
But he was too frightened to speak.
Doyle went on. 'And when I started crying, my
Daddy used to come. And he always used to hit me.
So I learnt never, never to cry in the
dark, because my Daddy didn't like it.
And you know, I've inherited that from my
father. I don't like my son crying in the dark.'
Tug was suddenly very angry. 'But I
haven't inherited anything from you!
You're not my father!'
Doyle did not seem to hear. 'That's the worst
thing about families. Because my father hit me,
I'll hit you, and you'll hit your
children. This will go on and on -'
'No! No!' shouted Tug. 'You're not my father!'
Suddenly the light went on, and the Woman stood at
the door. 'What's happening?' she asked angrily.
'I'm just telling him a little story
about family life.' Doyle smiled slowly.
The Woman looked at Tug's white, frightened
face. 'Come downstairs with me,' she said.
'I'll make you a hot drink.'
In the kitchen Tug said, his voice shaking,
'I didn't - didn't know Doyle was like that.'
The Woman laughed. 'Doyle doesn't often get
angry, like me. But he's a very dangerous man.'
For a moment she put her warm hands round
Tug's, and he felt like a small child again.
The fear began to disappear.
'Ma, what's going on? I just don't understand.'
She put a gentle hand on his head.
'I know it's difficult, but it'll be all
right in the end. Come on now, back to bed.'
When he was in bed again, Tug suddenly
realized a terrible thing. I called her
Ma. And it was worse than that. In the kitchen he
had actually felt that she was kind and loving,
and could be his mother. Was he Philip? Or
Liam? And hadn't anyone found his message?
6.30 P.M.
Jinny and her brother
Oz were sitting in the Hollins' sitting- room.
On the table in front of them was the dart that
Tug had thrown out of the window. Keith and Mr
Hollins were listening to Jinny's excited story.
'You see, Mr Hollins, Oz and I were picking
mushrooms up on the moors near the cottage.
We were - well, we were interested in the visitors
there, so we hid in the trees near their garden.
We couldn't see anything, so we were just leaving
when Oz found this piece of paper on the grass!
Look! It says, HELP I AM A PRISONER HERE.'
'I can read, Jinny,' said Mr Hollins, smiling.
'Well, what do you want me to do about it?'
'She wants you to go and investigate,
Dad,' said Keith. 'There's something
very strange about those visitors.'
'All right then,' said the policeman. 'You
come with me, Jinny. We'll take the police car,
drive to the cottage and just ask a few
questions. Oz and Keith can stay here.'
When they arrived at the cottage,
the Hare-woman opened the door.
She did not seem surprised at all.
'Good evening, Mrs Doyle,' said Mr
Hollins. 'Could we come in for a moment?'
'Of course.' They went straight into the
sitting-room. There were books, maps and a
camera on the table. A family on holiday, thought
Jinny. There was the man with the cold blue eyes,
and sitting next to him, a boy with black
hair and very serious ice-blue eyes.
'This is my husband,' said the Hare-woman, 'and
my son Philip.' They look so alike! thought Jinny.
Mr Hollins was talking about a lost dog.
'We think that perhaps it came
up here on the moors,' he said.
'There's no dog here,' smiled the man.
'But would you like to look round
the house while you're here?'
'Good idea,' said Mr Hollins. 'Thank you.'
'I'll come with you,' said the
Hare-woman. They went upstairs.
Jinny looked at the boy. He was staring
at her, and his face was very white.
'Talk to the girl, Philip,' said his father.
The boy's voice sounded strangely polite. He
was not smiling. 'Where do you live?' he asked.
'Outside the village, on a small farm...' Jinny
was talking quickly, although the boy did not
seem interested. And then it happened. As Mr
Hollins and the Hare-woman came downstairs,
the man's eyes looked away from Jinny and the
boy for a moment. In that second, while Jinny
was talking, the boy stared straight at her and
made the shape of a word with his mouth. Help.
'We must go, Jinny,' said Mr Hollins. 'Thank
you, Mrs Doyle. Sorry to take up your time.'
In the car, as they drove back to the village,
he explained kindly to Jinny, 'Of course you
couldn't know, but the boy's a bit strange. He's
nearly fourteen, but he's like a five-year-old
child really. His mother told me all about it,
so you see, there's nothing to investigate.'
7.15 P.M.
Tug watched the police car drive away.
He hadn't been brave enough to scream for
help, because of the gun in Doyle's pocket.
And what had the girl and the policeman seen?
The Doyle family. But I am Tug, he said
angrily to himself. I'm not Philip Doyle.
'Well, we are a happy
family,' said Doyle, smiling.
'No!' cried Tug. 'It's a lie!'
'Of course it's a lie,' agreed the Woman.
'The idea of the happy family is a lie.
The family is a prison. We
want people to escape from it.'
'I didn't mean that rubbish!'
cried Tug. 'I meant -'
'Oh Tug!' she said. 'Don't you understand?'
Tug had been afraid of Doyle's gun, but he was
much more afraid now. 'What did you call me?'
'What? Oh, I called you Tug. Don't you remember?
It's the name that I called
you when you were a baby.'
'No,' said Tug in a low, frightened voice. It
had been his secret. It was what Hank called him.
'Look.' The Woman suddenly opened her large
handbag and brought out an old photo. The
photo was of her when she was much younger.
In her arms she was holding a small baby.
'You, six weeks old,' she said, watching Tug.
'No!' said Tug. It can't be
true! Suddenly he took the photo,
tore it into two pieces, and
threw them wildly on the floor.
He looked up and saw that he had really
hurt the Woman. Her face was very white.
That night Tug could not sleep.
Help me, Hank, he cried to himself.
But now he could not remember
Hank's face or voice. The only
face he could see was long and thin,
with large golden eyes. Ma's face.
CHAPTER FOUR
A MESSAGE FOR HARRIET
DAY EIGHT - SUNDAY 14TH AUGUST
10.00 A.M.
Jinny could not forget the white,
staring face of the boy at the cottage.
She was busy all day on Saturday, but on Sunday,
when her mother was cooking the hare for lunch,
she walked down to the village to see Keith.
'Jinny, the terrorists who're holding Liam
Shakespeare have said what they want!'
he said excitedly.
'Who? Oh, him! But I want to talk to you about-'
'No, listen, this is important. They want
special children's homes all over the country,
where all children under sixteen
can live away from their families.'
'That's crazy,' said Jinny. 'The
Government will never agree to that.'
'No, of course not. But it's giving Free
People some publicity for their ideas,
isn't it? And they say that they'll shoot
Liam if the Government don't agree by Friday.'
'Poor Harriet Shakespeare! If the terrorists
are asking for something impossible,
there's nothing she can do to help
Liam. She must be so frightened!'
'That's the strange thing! She isn't! Last
night, when I watched her on the news,
she looked very calm! And guess what? She
said, "I'm sure I can get Liam out by Friday!"
She really did sound sure about
it. Here she is on the video.'
On the television Jinny saw Harriet
Shakespeare's small white face
and very serious ice-blue eyes... ice-blue eyes...
'Show me the video again!' Jinny said quickly.
'Why?' asked Keith, but Jinny did not answer.
They watched the video again. It must be him!
thought Jinny. But what will happen if I'm right?
'Have you got a photo of Liam, from a newspaper?'
she asked. It's impossible, she was thinking.
The photo that Keith held out to her showed
the face of the boy who was in the cottage.
But in the photo his hair was fair, not black.
She picked up a pencil, and carefully
changed the colour of his hair to black.
'What are you doing?' asked Keith at last.
Jinny showed him the photo, her
hands shaking with excitement.
'Liam Shakespeare isn't in that London house.
He's here in Derbyshire, in your Mum's cottage!'
10.45 A.M.
Tug's room was quiet now, because the music
had stopped. He was alone with the questions in
his head, the questions that he could not answer.
Doyle, the Woman, the television reporters, Hank,
the girl, the policeman, and his own face in the
mirror all told him that he was Philip Doyle, and
that Liam Shakespeare was in a house in London.
So did he really believe that they
were all wrong and he was right?
Was the rest of the world crazy? Or was he crazy?
Just then he heard the church bells from the
village, and realized that it must be Sunday.
Last time he had heard them
was when he was running...
Yes! Last Sunday I went for a run. Hank
was going to cook me a special meal...
No! Last Sunday Doyle and Ma
drove me here. We're on holiday...
How could he be sure which really happened? If I
can remember things about myself which are true,
I can build up a picture of the real
me. He liked running. He hated bananas.
He could make a cake. He could mend
bicycles. He could speak some French...
An hour later, he was still remembering things,
when the Woman came to say that
lunch was ready downstairs.
When they arrived in the sitting-room, Tug
was surprised to see that they were going to
have a family Sunday lunch. On the big table
there were knives, forks, plates and glasses,
and in the centre there was a large roast
chicken with a lot of different vegetables.
But Doyle did not sit down. 'Oh, very nice!'
he said, with a cold smile.
'What a lovely family meal!'
The Woman stared at him angrily. 'Don't be
stupid! What does it matter? It's only a meal!'
'Nothing is only itself. Everything means
something. And Sunday lunch means family life.
We're against that, remember?' He turned to Tug.
'Don't look surprised, Philip. Families often
argue during Sunday lunch. My parents used to
argue all Sunday afternoon, and then Dad
used to hit us children, again and again.'
'We don't want to hear about
your past,' said the Woman.
Doyle looked coldly at her. 'It's better than
hearing about your past, about a mother and baby.'
The Woman hit Doyle hard in the mouth.
But before Doyle could do or say anything,
Tug said quickly, 'Ma, I'm hungry.'
Doyle looked at Tug almost sadly. 'Children
don't like it when their parents argue,' he said.
The Woman laughed and sat down. 'Come on,
let's eat the chicken. After
that we're having baked bananas.'
'Oh Ma!' cried Tug without thinking.
'You know I hate bananas. I'll be sick!'
'Of course I haven't forgotten,' she
replied. 'There's an apple for you.'
1.00 P.M.
'Mr Hollins, please believe me!' cried Jinny.
'I'm sorry, Jinny,' said the policeman kindly.
'Everybody knows that Liam Shakespeare's
in London. How can he be in our cottage?
Now I'm going to have my lunch, so
you go home and forget about it.'
Jinny and Keith walked out of the Hollins' house.
'We must do something!' said Jinny miserably.
'I'm really sure that it's Liam
Shakespeare in the cottage.'
'And Harriet Shakespeare sounded strange on
the television news, didn't she?' said Keith.
'Why was she so sure that Liam would be safe on
Friday? Perhaps she knows that he's not in London.
Listen, I've got an idea. We
could send a message to her.
It says in the newspaper that she's
staying with a friend, Lucy Mallory.
Well, if we can find Lucy Mallory's
phone number, we can phone her.'
'How can we find her number?'
'Well, they've got a London street map
and a London phone book at the library.
I'll go there tomorrow and find the phone
number. Can you meet me tomorrow evening?
We'll phone Lucy Mallory together,
from the village phone box.'
'All right. Shall we say - about 10 o'clock?'
DAY NINE - MONDAY 15TH AUGUST
4.00 P.M.
This time the Woman was sitting
at the door of Tug's room.
She kept her own gun by the side of her chair.
'Why was Doyle so angry yesterday, Ma?' Tug asked.
'Oh, you know what he's like. He wants people
to understand. For years he hated his father.
He believed that he was bad,
because his father hated him.
Then one day he understood. It was
the happiest moment of his life.'
Did Doyle ever have happy moments? Impossible!
thought Tug. 'What had he understood?' he asked.
'That it isn't natural for people to
stay in families for years and years.
People stop loving and start hating. That's
what happened to me. That's why I -' She stopped
suddenly, then started again. 'Governments and
big business want people to live in families,
because if you've got a family, you've got
something to lose. You don't want to fight
against the government. We've got to show people
how to be free! Free to live and free to fight!'
She looked wonderfully tall and strong and
brave, as she stood in the centre of the room
and waved her arms. Tug wanted to jump up and join
her. But a small voice inside his head was saying,
If a speaker excites you, be very
careful. Forget the excitement,
and think hard about the ideas. It was
Hank's voice. Hank was right, of course.
Then something terrible happened. He thought,
Is Hank real? He knew that Harriet Shakespeare
was real because he had seen her on television.
But was she really his mother? Perhaps Hank was
only an idea, a wish - the kind of mother
that he would like to have, instead of Ma.
Perhaps he was living in a
dream world. Crazy Philip Doyle.
He was shaking and could not speak. The Woman
noticed, and came over to put her arms round him.
'What's the matter, Tug? Everything'll
be all right. After tomorrow.'
Just then Doyle entered the room,
with a tray. 'What's happening?'
he asked the Woman coldly. 'What a
wonderful picture of motherly love!'
'I was just being a little bit kind...'
'And what about the gun? It's on
the bed, where Philip can reach it.'
He picked it up. 'That's dangerous.' He stared
at the Woman - a long, cold, hard stare.
After a minute she turned
away, and went out of the room.
Doyle gave the tray to Tug. 'Here's your supper.'
'Thanks,' Tug said. He took the tray
with hands that were still shaking.
'Thanks - what?'
'Oh.' He had forgotten. 'Thanks, Doyle.'
9.50 P.M.
Jinny hurried down the road to the village,
and saw Keith waiting by the phone box.
'Come on,' he said excitedly.
'I've got the number.'
The phone rang and rang. At last a voice
answered. 'What number do you want? Who
do you want to speak to? What is your
name? What number are you calling from?'
Jinny answered all these questions. Then
she asked Keith, 'What's happening?'
'The police are checking all phone calls to
Mrs Shakespeare or her friends, I think.'
Then another voice. 'Lucy Mallory here.'
'Please,' said Jinny hurriedly, 'I want to
speak to Harriet Shakespeare. It's important.
It's about Liam.'
'Wait a moment.' The woman did not sound friendly.
Then another voice spoke,
the deep voice that Jinny and Keith had
heard on the television news. 'Yes?'
'You - you're Harriet Shakespeare?' asked Jinny,
not sure what to say. 'I - I know where Liam is.'
'Everyone knows where Liam
is.' The voice was hard.
'But he's not in your house. He's a prisoner,
in my village. I've seen him. He's...'
'Listen!' Harriet Shakespeare said angrily.
'You're the fourteenth person who's phoned me
at Lucy's to tell me crazy stories about Liam!'
'But you must believe me! The police up here
won't believe me, and we thought, when we saw
you on television, that you knew something,
something that you weren't telling anybody -'
'Oh yes? And what do I know?' Suddenly
her voice was very quiet, and worried.
'That the terrorists are only
pretending to hold Liam in your house.
That really he's in a different place.'
'Oh.' She sounded almost thankful, Jinny thought.
Then the voice became angry again. 'Well,
you're wrong about that. Now please just forget
it, and don't ring me again.' The phone went dead.
'Well,' said Jinny unhappily, 'we
were wrong. She didn't know anything.
She didn't believe me. And she was awful'
'Never mind, Jinny,' said Keith slowly. 'I
agree, we were wrong about what she knew.
But I'm sure that she was hiding
something. What could it be?'
CHAPTER FIVE
ON THE EDGE
DAY TEN - TUESDAY 16TH AUGUST
2.55 A.M.
'Tug!' The Woman was trying to wake him. 'Tug!'
'Ma? What time is it? What's the matter?'
She spoke quietly into his ear.
'Don't speak so loudly, or you'll wake
Doyle. The news is on in a moment.'
'In the middle of the night?' But Tug took the
small radio from her and put it near his ear.
'Good morning. This is the news. Police have
arrested the terrorists who said that they were
holding Liam Shakespeare at his home in London.
But when the police entered the house just before
midnight, Liam himself was not there. One of
the group is a boy of fifteen, with fair hair,
who looks like Liam. It is not known why the
terrorists were pretending to hold Liam prisoner.
The police are continuing
to investigate the matter.'
'I don't understand,' said Tug, still half asleep.
She held his hand. 'You're all right. We just
have to wait, wait until the end of today.'
Today. Tuesday. 'Aren't you going to tell me -'
'No! Go to sleep now!'
But he could not sleep. He had
so many things to think about.
Liam Shakespeare had disappeared. So who was Tug?
He tried to remember the facts that he knew about
himself. He liked running. He hated bananas...
6.45 A.M.
Jinny was getting breakfast ready. She
hadn't slept all night. She knew that she
was right about the boy in the cottage. But today
I won't have time to worry about it! she thought,
because it's our harvest day, the busiest day of
the year. All the neighbours were coming to help.
Just then she noticed a car coming up the narrow
road to the farm. A visitor! On harvest day!
It was a woman, dressed in an expensive suit, and
wearing sunglasses. Jinny went out to meet her.
'You're Jinny Slattery,' the woman said.
Jinny recognized the deep voice that
she had heard on the phone last night.
'You gave your name and the number of the village
phone box, luckily. That's how I found you. I've
driven all the way from London, and the girl in
the post office told me where your farm was.'
'But why have you come?' asked Jinny.
'You didn't believe me last night!'
'Haven't you heard the news? Liam isn't
at our home in London. I came to find you
because you're the only person who seems to know
where he is. You're my only hope! Where is he?
How can I get him out?' She sounded desperate.
'Look, I can show you the house where he is, but-'
'We must hurry! There isn't much time! We've
got to get him out by 2 o'clock today!'
7.15 A.M.
Tug knew that today was different from other days.
At breakfast, both Doyle and the Woman kept
their guns on the table by their hands,
ready for - what? Tug felt afraid.
Doyle stared coldly at Tug. 'Suppose
that this is the last day of your life.
What would you like to do most?'
'Doyle!' said the Woman angrily,
and put her hand on Tug's arm.
Doyle continued. 'If you don't know what you'd
choose to do on the last day of your life,
you don't know what's really important to you.
Forget about parents and other people. Only
free people know the answer to that question.'
'It's not easy to know what
you want,' agreed the Woman.
'Because you need to know who you really are.
Nothing to do with your family. Just you.'
'You think you're Liam Shakespeare,' Doyle went
on. 'We say you're Philip Doyle. Without one of
those names, you're nobody. And you can't answer
my question, can you? You don't know who you are!'
They were both staring at him, with their wild,
crazy eyes. Why should I play their games?
thought Tug. I'm Tug, I like
running. I hate bananas...
'Yes, I do know who I am,' he said.
Doyle seemed surprised. 'Well?'
he said. 'If you're so sure, what would
you do on the last day of your life?'
Tug thought for a moment. He stared out of
the window at the great rocky ridge which
stood high against the sky. It looked black
and frightening in the early morning light.
'What's that long hill called?' he asked.
Doyle smiled. He thought that Tug
could not answer his question.
'That's Ashdale Great Edge. And the rock
at the end is called the Castle Rock.'
'I can tell you what I'd do on the last
day of my life,' Tug said calmly. 'I'd run,
all the way along Ashdale Great
Edge, from this end to Castle Rock.'
'That's a stupid thing to do!' said Doyle.
But I know that's what I want, and
nobody can take that away from me,
thought Tug. Then he noticed the Woman looking
very sadly at him. He had to ask her the question.
'So - is this going to be
the last day of my life?'
'I think perhaps - not,' Doyle answered.
'It will be the last day of someone's
life, but not yours, I think.'
7.35 A.M.
Around the
breakfast table sat Jinny, Oz, their parents,
Harriet, and Keith, who had just arrived.
'So, Mrs Shakespeare,' said Joe Slattery, 'you
think that your son is staying in the cottage
with people who are probably terrorists. You
don't want to go to the police because it'll
take too much time. And you want us to think of
a plan to save your son before two o'clock today.
On harvest day, the most
important day of the year for us.'
Harriet stared desperately
at Joe. 'Yes,' she said.
Joe thought for a moment. 'Well, Keith here says
that one of the Doyles goes to the post office to
get a newspaper every day. That'll give us about
twenty minutes. We can send Jinny to the cottage.
She goes inside, with some excuse or other.
Then I'll come up with some of the neighbours,
we'll knock on the door, and pull out the person
who comes to the door. That way, neither of the
Doyles will get a chance to use a gun, and
we can get both Liam and Jinny out safely.'
Nobody spoke for a second. Then Harriet said,
'Yes, it's a good plan. All
right, shall we go?' and got up.
'Wait,' said Joe suddenly. 'Now I have a question.
Why? You want me to forget about my harvest and
put my daughter in danger. But why today?
The television reporters are saying that the
terrorists won't hurt Liam until Friday. That's
what Keith says. So we don't need to hurry.'
'I've told you, if the terrorists don't
get what they want by two o'clock today,
Liam will die.' Harriet stared angrily at Joe.
Keith suddenly said, 'I don't think they're really
interested in those special homes for children.
I think they want something more important.'
'You're right,' said Harriet tiredly. 'They've got
publicity for their ideas now, of course. But - I
see that I'll have to tell you what they really
want. They want to do something that people will
remember for a long time. They want to destroy,
to bomb the most famous family in the country.'
'You mean -' said Bella
Slattery. 'But that's impossible.
The royal family always have police and
detectives around them, don't they?'
'You only need one terrorist with a bomb,
in the right crowd at the right time. At two
o'clock this afternoon,' replied Harriet.
'I was investigating Free People, you see.
And when I discovered their plan, they
took Liam, to stop me warning the police.
It's difficult for me, isn't it? If
I warn the police, Free People will
kill Liam - and say that he died because his
mother, his family, chose not to save him.
But if I don't warn the police, there will be
several deaths in another, more famous family.
And Free People will say that they died because
of my love for my son, my family. Either way,
Free People win the game, because the
idea of the family gets bad publicity.'
She put her head in her hands and sat very still.
Joe stood up. 'I understand now. We'll help you.'
'But -' said Keith miserably, 'shouldn't we
tell the police about the bomb before we start?'
'Yes,' said Harriet. She was
finding it difficult to speak.
'I decided yesterday to warn the
police. So the royal family are
safe. But Liam will be dead after two
o'clock, if we don't get him out.'
11.00 A.M.
Doyle had gone out and Tug was washing
the breakfast dishes when there was a knock on the
door. The Woman hid the guns and opened the door.
It was the girl who had come with the policeman.
'Hallo, Mrs Doyle,' the girl said politely.
'We just wanted to invite you to our harvest
party this evening. It's very good fun -' She
saw Tug in the kitchen and ran through the
sitting-room to him. 'Do come, Philip.'
Just then they heard Doyle's car coming very fast
up the road. Tug saw sudden fear in the girl's
face. The car door banged, and Doyle hurried
into the house, shouting orders at the Woman.
'Come on! We've got to leave!
Harriet Shakespeare's in the village!
I met that stupid little girl from
the post office just down the road,
and she told me! Bring the boy! And
that girl! And the guns and the radio!'
In a few moments they were all in the car,
driving fast down the road away from the cottage.
'So what's your plan, Doyle?' asked the Woman. She
had her gun in her hand, and was ready to shoot.
'You'll see. We're going somewhere safe
for the next two or three hours - Oh no!'
There were four men walking along the road towards
them. Doyle drove faster, straight at them,
and at the last moment the men jumped to one
side, shouting and banging on the roof of the car.
The next minute the car turned away
from the village, and up to the moors.
The car finally stopped high up above
the valley. 'Get out!' ordered Doyle.
'Start walking!' They walked up the long ridge
that Tug had seen from the kitchen window.
The wind was strong and cold, and they could
see a long way on both sides of the ridge.
'Stop here!' shouted Doyle. Now we wait for
visitors!' They did not have to wait long.
Two cars drove fast up the hill and
stopped a few hundred metres away.
Tug saw the men who had been on the road,
with a boy who was older than him, and - Hank.
'Stay there!' shouted Doyle to them.
He was holding the girl by her hair,
and slowly he put his gun to her head. 'If you
come any nearer, I'll shoot!' Then he smiled at
Tug and the Woman. 'Sit down, everyone,' he said.
'We're going to wait and listen to the news.'
Why not? thought Tug. It all seemed like a dream.
He sat on the grass, staring at the radio.
2.25 P.M.
This is probably the last wind
that I'll ever feel, thought Jinny. When they hear
the news, they'll know that their plan has failed.
And then they'll shoot us. She could
see the blue uniforms of policemen
in the little group of people waiting by the
cars. Some policemen had guns. But Doyle and
the Hare-woman were very careful to keep the
boy and Jinny in front of their own bodies.
'Right,' said Doyle. 'Now let's listen to the
two-thirty news. We're waiting to hear of some
important deaths. If those people haven't died,
you'll know that Harriet Shakespeare chose to
save their lives, not her son's. Because
he's less important to her than they are.'
The boy's face went white. It's not true, Jinny
wanted to say, she loves you! I've seen that!
They listened silently to the news. At the end,
Doyle turned off the radio
and said, 'Now, let's talk.'
'What about?' asked the boy in a high, frightened
voice. 'You're going to kill me, aren't you?'
'Oh, yes,' said Doyle. 'We're going to kill
you. But you can choose something first.
Harriet Shakespeare can't be sure that you're Liam
because she's too far away to see you clearly.
And if she's not sure, you can't be sure, can
you? So I'm going to call her over here. She's
going to walk slowly towards us. Then we can see
her face when she decides if you are Liam or not.'
'Then you'll shoot me, I suppose ?' said the boy.
'No, I won't. Your mother will.'
Jinny did not understand why the boy
turned to stare at the Hare-woman.
'Ma - would you really shoot me?' he said.
Doyle laughed. 'You don't know her very well, do
you? She killed her own baby twelve years ago.'
Nobody spoke for a moment.
'So,' continued Doyle, 'you can wait for
Harriet Shakespeare to decide who you are,
to put you in a box with a name on
it. Or you can choose for yourself,
and spend your last moments of life how you want.'
'We're giving you the chance to
choose,' added the Hare- woman,
almost gently, ' - to choose who
you really are, inside yourself.'
Tug tried to think clearly. Oh Hank! What would
you choose? Suddenly, he could hear her voice
in his head. Do I have to decide everything
for you? Decide for yourself! He smiled. Of
course she was his mother! He knew it now,
without question. Now it was easy to decide.
He stood up. 'I'm ready,' he said,
and began to run away from Hank, along
the ridge towards the Castle Rock.
Jinny stared. Why was he running that way?
she thought. But the Hare-woman was now lifting
the gun in her hands, ready to shoot the boy.
'You're crazy!' screamed
Jinny. 'Don't shoot him-!'
Doyle's hand suddenly
covered her mouth. 'Hurry up,
you stupid cow,' he said to the
Hare-woman, 'or it'll be too late.'
And Jinny could see that the police, the farmers
and Harriet were beginning to come nearer.
Jinny stared at the Hare-woman. Her face looked
desperate, like... who was it? Like Harriet
Shakespeare, when she arrived at the farmhouse,
worried about her son, because she loved him.
Suddenly Jinny bit Doyle's hand hard, and pulled
her mouth away. She shouted at the Hare-woman,
using the words that her
own mother had used to her.
'It's because you love him
that you want to kill him!
But if you kill him, you'll
only destroy yourself!'
The Hare-woman looked round, surprised.
At that moment, there was a bang and she
put her hand to her side. A policeman had shot
her. Doyle ran to take her gun before she fell,
but before he could take it, she threw it high up
in the air. It fell over the side of the ridge.
'Run, Tug, run! You're free!'
she called into the wind.
And Harriet Shakespeare, running towards them,
cried at the same moment, 'Tug,
it's all right! You're safe!'
Tug heard the sound of the gun, and then the
two shouts behind him. But he did not stop,
because the only thing that mattered was the
running. His legs ached, and his feet hurt, but
in front of him was the Castle Rock and he knew
that he could reach it. And as he ran, he sang
in his head, This is me. Here I am, Hank. Here
I am, Ma. This is me. This is who I am.
- THE END -