Chapter one
Nonstop
Henry Stankey hated flying.
Actually, "hate" was perhaps the wrong word.
Hatred implied anger, active resistance; hatred
was a type of control.
Airplane flight filled Stankey with the kind
of helpless despair he sometimes imagined
must have poisoned the air of Belsen and Treblinka;
he only felt anger when he looked around the
boarding area at his complacent fellow passengers,
slumped in identical airport chairs like an
exhibition of soft sculptures, their faces
bored, uncaring, flattened into shadowlessness
by the fluorescent lights.
As he stared, he could feel moisture again
between his hand and the chair's plastic arm.
He ground his palm on the knees of his corduroys
and was miserable.
Why hadn't Diana come?
Stankey hated himself for needing his wife
this way - not for herself, but as a handholder,
a nursemaid.
When she had told him that her boss was out
sick with strep throat, that they couldn't
do without her at the office and that he would
have to go to Dallas by himself, he had wanted
to reach out and shake her.
She knew he couldn't cancel out this late;
he'd already paid good money to ship his artwork
to the hotel.
He'd also used his scant funds to pay convention
fees.
He had to go.
Diana knew how much he hated flying, dreaded
it, yet she had chosen to stay and help out
her boss Muriel rather than him.
The night she told him, he had not slept well.
He had dreamed of cattle herded up a ramp-eye-rolling,
idiot cattle bumping against each other as
they were prodded into a dark boxcar.
The Thursday afternoon flight out of San Francisco
was terrible.
He almost took a couple of the Valium hidden
deep in his pocket in a twist of Saran Wrap.
Only the compelling thought that the plane
might catch fire on the runway, that the panicking
crew and passengers might leave him behind
in drugged sleep, prevented him from taking
the tranquilizers.
Instead, as he always did, he clutched the
lucky talisman hidden beneath his shirt-he
was ashamed of it, really: a hide bolo tie
Diana had brought back from New Mexico, where
her aged parents lived in a trailer camp-clutched
it and willed the aircraft down the run-way.
Sweaty hand clasped on chest, he forced the
plane up off the tarmac through sheer force
of mind, dragging it aloft as the other passengers
stared unconcernedly out the small windows,
or read gaudy paperbacks, or slept (slept!).
Once the jet was in the air, he began his
terrified drill: smoothing the turbulence,
wishing away dangerous crosswinds, tensing
his legs so as to put the minimum amount of
weight down on the cabin floor and avoid the
laboring vibrations of the plane's underpowered,
overtaxed engines.
Fortunately, the passenger by the window-Henry
always got an aisle seat-was one of those
nerveless clods who dozed through flights,
and did not have his window blind open.
Stankey was spared the additional stress of
watching the plane's wings dipping and bucking
crazily, straining to break free from the
fuselage.
No one who did not feel as he did about flying
realized what a strenuous job it was: three
hours in the air, head flung back and eyes
closed, white-knuckled hand wrapped around
the hidden bolo-charm, forcing his mind through
an endless circle of airy, buoyant thoughts-helium,
swans down, drifting dandelion puffs.
At every bump or shudder his heart began to
speed even more swiftly; he had to redouble
his efforts to smooth interference away, to
guide the plane back once more to the path
of least resistance.
The landing was the worst part.
As the captains (infuriatingly bland) voice
announced the beginning of descent, and the
plane nosed downward at a sickening angle,
Henry Stankey pulled back on his seat arms
until his wrists ached.
The pitched whine of the engines mounted to
a panicky scream, and he felt himself gradually
lifting from the chairseat, gravity in temporary
abeyance like that time - the one and only
time - he had ridden the old roller coaster
at Playland-by-the-Sea.
His heart climbed into his chest, his stomach
pressed against the bottom of his lungs - but
the man across from him was reading a newspaper!
Calmly extinguishing a cigarette!
Henry closed his eyes again.
The seemingly endless fall ended at last.
There was a momentary sensation of leveling
out; the wheels touched, lifted, then hit
the ground once more with the full weight
of the plane upon them.
At once, an even more terrible squalling started
up as the pilot desperately tried to stop
the hurtling plane before it skidded off the
end of the runway into the terminal, to explode
in sun-hot flames.
It didn't explode this time, but rather rolled
down the Texas tarmac to a final stop.
The distorted voice of a woman on the PA system
gabbled something at the unheeding customers,
who were already up and shouldering their
luggage down from the overhead compartments,
laughing and chattering and pushing up the
aisle.
Back.
Stankey hung limply in his chair.
His shirtfront was creased and sweat-stained
where he had clutched his lucky bolo - but
it had worked!
Again, somehow beyond all hope he had gotten
through, kept the plane up, then lowered it
once more to the stable earth.
As the panic began to recede, he sensed the
high-water mark of his fear; although he had
struggled to hold it back, the terror seemed
to have crept higher than ever before.
He felt as though he had been beaten up and
left lying on a downtown sidewalk.
Damn Diana for deserting him!
Damn her!
After getting into his hotel room and showering
the sour odor of perspiration from his body,
he slept for an hour - a dark, heavy sleep
that nevertheless smoothed some of the cramping
from his limbs and back.
By the time he got to the conference room
where the art show would be, ascertained that
his paintings had indeed arrived and began
to set them up in his assigned corner, a feeling
of mild elation began to well inside him.
He had made it by himself, without Diana,
and now could look forward to tonight, Friday,
and Saturday before he would need to begin
thinking about the flight back.
A tiny smile worked at the corners of his
mouth as he tacked his paintings into their
frames and fussed with the arrangement; it
was good to feel good again.
These conventions were important to him (of
course they must be, he went through Hell
to get to them); they were a priceless opportunity
to have his artwork noticed, to touch base
with people who could steer jobs his way and
help him to break through.
He had been just getting by for too long - that
was the worst thing about free-lancing: the
never-knowing, the waiting...
waiting for an offer on a cover-bid, waiting
for calls back, waiting to see if a project
would hold together long enough to get him
a guarantee, a kill-fee...
He was grateful for the lightening of spirit
he was suddenly feeling; it was hard enough
to make a living without scaring people away
on top of it.
It turned out to be a fairly good convention.
Several people praised his work; he sold two
small paintings, a large pen and ink, and
a few smallish sketches.
Roger Norrisert of Lemuria Press dropped some
large hints about an upcoming cover-and-illos
possibility for a projected special printing
of a Manly Wade Wellman book.
Thursday and Friday passed quickly in a blurry
montage of handshakes and nametag squinting
and several cheerfully tipsy conversations
in the hotel lounge.
Both nights he slept deeply, dreamless interludes
that did much to restore his normally affable
outlook.
Eating breakfast at a table splashed with
Saturday morning sunlight, he remembered that
there were indeed things he liked about conventions.
That night Stankey went with Norrisert and
a couple of writers to a Cajun restaurant
downtown where they sat up late, swapping
stories and drinking beer.
Henry got pretty tight, and did not wake until
late Sunday morning.
It had not been a pleasant night.
He had tossed and twitched, pulling the sheets
loose from the mattress.
Waking sometime after four in the morning
from a dream of choking (faulty oxygen mask,
hole in the hose, smoke everywhere), he had
found his lucky New Mexico string tie twisted
tightly around his neck, bruising his throat.
After worrying it, loose with sleep-clumsy
fingers he had pushed it into the pocket of
his jacket, which hung on a chair beside his
rumpled bed.
Later, after dawdling around the hotel for
a couple of bleak hours watching the Cowboys
and the New Orleans Saints play an endless
game of exchanged turnovers, and after laboriously
packing and labeling his flats, he found himself
with nothing to do for an hour and a half
until the shuttle bus, like Charons ferry,
would whisk him away to the airport.
To the waiting airport.
The hotel bar was almost empty, the last knots
of conventioneers clumped around small tables,
luggage at their feet.
Stankey saw no one that he recognized; he
could think of no excuse to introduce himself,
to join a conversation and enlist support
in his battle against reflection.
The prospect of the flight home had risen
from its temporary grave and was groping for
attention with clammy fingers.
Against his better judgment- needle-sharp,
reflexes were vital in combating the treacherous,
gravity-embracing tendencies of airplanes
- Henry ordered a vodka tonic and nursed it
as he sat in a corner seat trying to read
a Ramsey Campbell book.
The drink was a good idea.
It soothed the ragged edges of his thoughts;
he felt it working like aftershave lotion
on a just-shaved face, stripping away the
heat, quieting scratchy nerves - well, after
all, aftershave was alcohol, too.
He thought, a little cavalierly, of just ordering
another drink, but he knew that was the lulling
effect of the first one at work.
He could not afford to be that relaxed: he
was needed, even if the other passengers never
realized it.
Still, the one drink had been a good idea.
The Campbell novel had not.
The dank, depressing Liverpool setting and
the hopelessly phobic thoughts of the characters
made Stankey feel a little sick.
He put the book down after thirty pages or
so and stared out the window at the hotel
parking lot, toying with the slowly melting
ice in his glass.
The bus came.
It took him, tightlipped and silent, to the
airport, and left him there.
On the walkway outside the terminal he could
already feel the acid gnawing at his stomach,
the placating effects of the vodka-tonic evaporated
by harsh lights and disembodied, inflectionless
voices, by the chill, echoing vastness of
the place.
He carried his hand luggage to the boarding
area - no massive suitcase in the hold for
him: why make the plane any heavier than it
had to be?
- and stood in line between a Mexican woman
with a screaming child and a boy in a baseball
cap who, except for his drooping, morons mouth,
could have been a Norman Rockwell character.
Some of the other passengers were talking
about something he could not quite catch-the
flight?
- But he would not be distracted.
At last, he reached the front of the line,
put his ticket on the counter, and was told
by the female mannequin in the royal blue
vest that the plane was delayed: it would
be an hour and twenty-five minutes late taking
off.
She might as well have hit him with a hammer.
His defenses were keyed up, he was wound tight
as a mountain climber's rope- and now this!
He wanted to shout, to screech at this in
comprehending woman with her twinkly Rose
Parade smile.
Turning hurriedly, he lurched to the high
window where he leaned against a pillar and
willed his heart to slow down.
He-would-be-calm.
When he felt a little more in control, he
went to the payphone to call Diana, to tell
her he would be late.
No one answered at home.
It was hard not to feel betrayed.
So he sat, staring out at the now-darkening
sky, trying not to watch the technicians scurrying
like parasites beneath the bodies of the big
jets.
This was the last time, he vowed to himself.
Never again.
Other artists and writers got by without having
to leave home.
He could take the train if he really needed
to go anywhere, even though it took days.
It was ridiculous to scourge himself this
way.
Nothing in life was worth this kind of sick
fear.
An announcement about his flight crackled
over the PA system.
The message was hard to make out, but he was
positive he had heard the words "mechanical
difficulties."
When he demanded to know what had been said,
the woman at the counter-looking a little
amused - confirmed that he had indeed heard
that numbing phrase, that such in fact was
the reason the jet had been delayed in Atlanta.
But, she told him, it was in the air now and
would arrive soon.
Under sharp questioning about the nature of
the "difficulties", she professed ignorance,
but assured him that everything was being
taken care of.
This time he went back to his window even
more slowly, like a man mounting thirteen
steps to the gibbet.
The counterwoman favored his retreat with
a condescending smile.
Damn the bitch.
And damn Diana too, for good measure.
At last, the plane arrived.
Stankey, squinting suspiciously through the
high boarding area windows, could see nothing
overtly wrong - but that, of course, meant
nothing.
He would never see the loose bolts that would
vibrate free and drop the engine like a stone,
never detect the fault in the landing gear
that would snap the wheel off on contact and
send the jet sliding to flaming oblivion.
He boarded, a stale taste in his mouth, and
found his way to seat 21, near the back of
the plane.
After stowing his shoulder bag, he sat down
and promptly fastened his seat belt, then
reached his hand up to his breastbone to feel
for the lucky bolo tie hanging beneath his
shirt.
It wasn't there.
He checked the pockets of his jacket, which
disgorged keys, wallet, ticket folder, receipts,
and matchbooks... but no good-luck talisman.
In a growing panic, he unbuckled his lap belt
and sprang up, nearly knocking over the crew-cutted
businessman seating himself across the aisle.
Stankey jerked open the overhead compartment
and levered out his bag, opening it across
his lap to rummage through the carefully folded
shirts and socks.
The Mexican woman in the seat before his shifted
her wet-mouthed baby to look over her shoulder
at him as he cursed to himself, emptying the
bag with trembling hands.
The bolo tie was nowhere inside.
Henry could dimly remember taking it off in
the night and putting it in the pocket of
his jacket - but he was wearing that jacket
now.
He searched the pockets again, fruitlessly.
As he sat in the wreckage of his meticulous
packing, a pert- faced stewardess leaned over
to ask if he needed any help.
Unable to speak, he shook his head and began
to stow the clothing back into the bag, dislodging
a stack of convention giveaway magazines,
which slithered to the floor.
He excoriated himself and his disability as
he crouched on the cabin floor picking them
up.
A middle-aged woman in a parka waited impatiently
for him to finish so she could get past to
the window seat.
As she slid by, he forced the repacked bag
into the compartment, then slumped back into
his chair.
What could he do?
The damned bolo must have fallen out on the
hotel floor, must even now be in the pocket
of some maid, or lying unnoticed behind the
bed.
He knew how much he needed it.
It had gotten him through every miserable
one of the dozen or so flights he had taken
in the last five years - even the one to Wisconsin
where the turbulence had been so bad the seatbelt
sign never went off.
It had gotten him through Thursday's flight,
the first one he had ever taken without Diana.
Now he had neither his wife nor his lucky
talisman.
He thought seriously for a moment of simply
getting up and walking off the plane, but
he knew that was a foolish idea.
He would still have to get back to San Francisco
somehow, the expensive airline ticket would
be wasted, and he would miss the Monday afternoon
meeting with Janicos from Beltane Books...
No, he would have to stay on the flight.
Again, he cursed his poverty, his childish
fears, his treacherous wife.
The final passengers had boarded, and the
doors were being shut.
The compact thump of the vacuum seal sounded
like the coffin lid of the Premature Burial.
He could see the stewardesses walking down
the aisle, checking to make sure the compartment
doors were closed - trim, blue-skirted death
angels, hair shining in the cabin lights.
Henry unbuckled his belt again and scrambled
out into the aisle, moving quickly to the
lavatory.
In the narrow room, scarcely even a closet,
he felt the surge of claustrophobia.
Why had he come back here?
His face in the small mirror looked pale,
haunted; he turned back toward the door.
It all felt like a terrible dream, a grinding
nightmare which he could not shut off.
He remembered the Valium in his pocket.
Maybe I can take one of these, he thought....
No, better yet, take two, take three or four,
sleep through the whole damned flight.
If it catches fire on takeoff, so what?
I'll never know.
But how would the plane stay aloft?
He knew, somewhere in his fevered thinking,
that planes traveled every day without him
on board - lifted off, flew, and landed without
Henry Stankey's straining intercession.
It could fly while he slept, just this once...
couldn't it?
Yes, planes did that, but he hadn't been on
one that had.
He had always worked like a dray-horse to
keep them aloft, pulled them along through
the turbulent winds that sought to batter
them to the ground like badminton birds.
Could he relinquish that control?
He had to.
Otherwise, he would never make it - he knew
that as a certainty.
Without Diana, it had been nearly impossible;
without either wife or talisman, it was flatly
inconceivable.
And if he couldn't manage the strain, wouldn't
it be better not to see the last moments coming?
To sleep a narcotized sleep through the screeching
final seconds?
He was disgusted by his own spinelessness,
by his desertion of his fellow passengers
who (although they didn't know it) would be
deprived his valuable assistance in keeping
the plane safe and themselves ignorant and
happy... but there was no alternative he could
see.
None.
Hands moist with fear-sweat, he unpeeled the
plastic-wrapped pills and plucked two out
of the jumble.
After a moment's consideration, he took up
another pair, then downed them all with a
swallow of water from the tiny sink.
Wrapping the remainder, he stumbled back to
his seat.
The plane was beginning to roll, heading toward
the takeoff site.
As he wedged himself into place and cinched
the belt tightly across his lap, he wondered
if the pills would take long to kick in.
He knew he would have to get through at least
the beginning without help.
The jet gathered speed down the runway, engines
howling like late-night-movie Indians bent
on massacre, and Stankey's hand rose reflexively
to his chest.
There was, of course, no charmed bolo tie
to grasp.
He clutched his lapel instead, crushing the
material into a wet, wrinkled knot.
Straining, heaving, the plane forced its way
upward.
By some miracle, it broke from the ground's
cruel pull and mounted up at a fierce angle
to the waiting sky.
Henry Stankey, tendons stretched like violin
strings, waited for either the sickening lurch
of lost altitude or the now desperately- awaited
onset of drowsiness.
Drowsiness won.
By the time, the aircraft had leveled out
six miles or so above the earth's hidden surface,
he could feel languor beginning to creep over
him, as though a warm, wooly blanket was settling
over his body.
His muscles unknotted.
His breathing slowed.
The woman sitting by the window a seat away
looked at him sharply, questioningly.
Henry, growing groggier by the moment, was
even able to muster a thin smile.
The woman turned away.
The drone of the airplane made him feel as
though he rode the night in a great, glowing
beehive...
It seemed that he had to claw his way up from
sleep.
The tarbaby grip of the Valium held him back,
but a part of his mind knew that he was urgently
needed: even as he clambered up from unconsciousness
he could feel the plane lurching and rocking,
the cabin rattling like a toy in a child's
fist.
He opened his eyes, fighting for wakefulness...
and knew he had been right.
All his fears were now confirmed - he should
never have taken those pills, never have relinquished
control!
He moaned, straining to dislodge the tendrils
of sleep.
The faces of his fellow passengers told all.
This time no one was reading unconcernedly
or chatting with neighbors.
Like Stankey, they gripped their seat arms
and stared straight ahead as the plane bucked
and swerved.
Eyes stared darkly from pale faces.
The Mexican woman clutched her sobbing baby;
Henry could hear her voice moving in the urgent,
rhythmic cadences of prayer.
A sudden lurch and the plane plummeted, a
drop that seemed to last minutes, like the
freefall of an amusement park ride.
One woman's voice rose in a brief, muffled
shriek.
The plane bottomed out, climbed a moment,
stabilized.
There was none of the usual nervous laughter;
the heaving and the battering side-to-side
swaying continued.
Above the tense muttering of the passengers,
Stankey heard the voice of the captain on
the intercom.
Even as he spoke, the stewardesses hurried
down the aisle to the back of the plane.
There was another sickening plunge, and a
meal tray tumbled out of a passenger's grip
to carom down the aisle, scattering food everywhere.
The flight attendants did not even look down
as they made their way back to their own seats
to strap in.
To Henry, this was the grimmest proof of all.
Was it too late?
He strained outward with his mind, murky thoughts
wrestling with the shivering plane and its
staggering attempts to defy gravity.
For a moment, he thought he could do it.
The lights blinked on and off, the captain's
voice gargled through the cabin... fasten
seat belts, stay calm... turbulence...
Henry concentrated his will, fighting treacherous
sleepiness; the plane seemed to settle a bit,
its passage momentarily smoothed.
The shuddering became less.
Almost without knowing Stankey relaxed - just
a little, the most minute's concession to
the downward drag of the medication - and
lost it.
The plane heaved like a gutshot dinosaur and
rolled to one side.
Several of the overhead compartments burst
open, vomiting luggage on the shouting passengers.
Suitcases somersaulted down the aisle in slow
motion; a blind man's cane, folded in segments,
accordioned out from his seat to fly end over
end through the cabin like a bizarre albino
insect.
The airplane hung for a moment on its side:
Stankey felt himself dangling across his seat
arm, sliding toward the gap-mouthed face of
the woman by the window.
The glass behind her looked out on black,
formless emptiness.
The plane nosed down so steeply that it seemed
to Henry the passengers near the front of
the cabin had fallen down a hole, a hole from
which he was being dragged by some fierce
power, pulled back against his seat, chest
and lungs crushed in a giant's grip.
The cabin was suddenly a lively Hell of flailing
arms and flying objects.
A woman's faint voice screamed: heads down
heads down heads down...!
The turbine shriek of the wind buried all
other sounds; the mouths that gaped and worked
without words joined their last cries to the
panicked roar of the plummeting airplane.
Sound cutting through his head like a jigsaw,
Stankey screamed too - screamed out his despair
and terror, screeched out wordless curses
at what fate, his wife, his own fear had done
to him.
He struggled to force himself up against the
shocking, smashing pressure of pitched descent.
It wasn't fair!
He had tried everything!
He had to take the pills, couldn't have kept
the plane up this time!
Why?!
Whywhywhywhywhywhywhy...
Impact
Time... is... stopping.
Henry feels himself standing at last... a
man at last... on his feet.
He is thrown forward - his flight as inexorable
but unhurried as the slide of a black-ice
glacier (time now creeping as slowly as eroding
stone)-forward like a stop-motion film of
a plant growing, unfolding, hurtling forward
but barely moving...
The passengers around him are a frozen flash
photograph, eyes bulging...
suitcases hang in the air like corpuscles
in the clear ichor of a god's arteries.
The walls of the plane wrinkle, contract around
him, surge toward the nose; the seats fold
forward like a row of dominoes, the passengers
folding with them - slowly, slowly, like a
child's pop-up book being carefully closed.
Stankey, unfettered, is passing through them
all now, flowing remorselessly forward, sliding
through the dividing substance of passengers
and objects like a bullet tumbling through
a sand castle.
The way opens before him, a kaleidoscopic
mandala of blood and bone and fabric and torn
metal - a succession of slow-blooming, intricate
flowers through which he tumbles like a bee
in melting amber.
His journey to the crystalline heart of the
petals takes millennia.
Slower now, slower... matter bunching up,
molecule on static molecule...
Dense.
Denser.
Densest...
...Until Time itself falls behind his ultimate
slowness, until only the remembrance remains,
the memory of the light years of waiting before
the next tick of atomic decay and then he
is through...
The morgue attendant slides the drawer back
in.
The widow is led out by friends; her shoulders
heave.
When she is gone, he pulls the drawer out
again and stares at the body.
He twitches the sheet aside to look at the
bruised pelvis, the mottled black and yellow
bars where the victim broke the seatbelt across
his own body struggling to rise from his seat.
The airline says that the victim had slept
through the whole flight until the last descent,
when he began to shout and writhe in his sleep,
in the depths of an unbreathable dream.
Unwaking, he had struggled with the seat.
With gravity, with the belt itself until he
snapped it loose - the heavy canvas torn by
a near-incomprehensible strength - and had
stood shouting in the aisle, eyes shut.
When the wheels touched the runway, the airline
representative said, the man had screamed
once and fallen forward, dead.
The attendant looks the body up and down and
shakes his head.
He slides it back inside on near-silent rollers.
A heart attack, they say.
Extreme shock and terror, they say.
So, the attendant wonders, why is the corpse
smiling?
...he has come through - and Henry Stankey
is no more.
He is a mote of light passing through a radiant
universe, speeding through unending brightness.
And flying is a joy.
- THE END -