CHAPTER ONE
'Let's go to the cinema!'
Today it is possible to buy or hire a video
and watch a film at home, but millions of
people all over the world still prefer to
go to their town or city cinema for a 'night
out'. And before television arrived in people's
homes, a visit to the cinema was something
really special to look forward to.
The 'golden age' of film-making - and going
to the cinema - was between about 1930 and
1950. Film stars seemed like kings and queens.
Cinemas were 'picture palaces' where, for
the price of a ticket, you could enter into
a magical world where anything and everything
was possible.
In 1946, 1,650,000,000 cinema tickets were
sold in Great Britain. That's thirty-three
tickets for every man, woman and child in
the country.
And in the year 1939 - the year when audiences
first saw Cone With The Wind - 30,000 people
were employed by the big film studios in Hollywood.
They made 400 films every year. Americans
called the moving pictures, 'the movies',
and fifty million of them went to the cinema
every week. They wanted to see the magic of
the movies!
But how did it all begin...?
CHAPTER TWO
In the beginning
The first moving pictures were simple 'shadow
shows' or 'shadow plays'.
Then came the magic lanterns which projected
painted glass slides on to a screen. These
became very popular in Europe in the 18th
century, and lantern showmen travelled from
village to village.
But in the 1820s, Nicephore Niepce invented
photography, and soon photographs were used
instead of the much more expensive glass slides.
But these were not movies. The pictures did
not move. To make moving pictures it is necessary
to take a large number of photographs very
quickly, one after the other. Then, when the
photographs are projected, the person or animal
in the picture appears to move.
In 1878, the British photographer, Eadweard
Muybridge, who was living in California, fixed
twelve cameras beside a racetrack and took
pictures of a racehorse - very quickly, one
after the other. The American inventor, Thomas
Edison, watched the work of Muybridge with
great interest. (Edison had invented the phonograph
- an early 'record player' - in 1877.) By
1890, William K. L. Dickson, who was working
with Edison, had managed to take 'moving pictures'
with something called the Kinetograph.
In 1893 the world's first film studio was
built by Edison in West Orange, New Jersey.
Actors from Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show,
and Barnum and Bailey's Circus were filmed
there. The films were shown in Kinetoscope
machines. These machines did not project the
film on to a screen, they had 'peep-holes'
that one person at a time could look through.
It was the Lumiere brothers, in France, who
invented a camera and projector in one - the
Cinematographe. Now large audiences could
watch projected pictures on a screen. And
because films were longer, people were happy
to pay more to see them.
The Lumiere brothers gave the first performance
of their Cinematographe in Paris in 1895,
in a room under the Grand Cafe, 14 boulevard
des Capucines on 28th December. They borrowed
a hundred chairs from the cafe, but only thirty-five
seats were sold at one franc each. But it
was the world's first 'film show'.
Then Edison introduced the Vitascope projector
in New York on April 23, 1896. And by the
end of that year, films were flickering on
screens all over Europe and America. (Films
were often called 'flickers' or 'flicks'.)
At first, people did not mind what they watched,
it was exciting enough just to be able to
see real moving photographs of people and
animals.
But slowly films with stories began to appear,
and the Frenchman, Georges Melies, began to
use clever photography to make strange things
happen. These were some of the first 'special
effects'.
Film fact
There was a bad accident in May 1897. A Cinematographe
show was part of the great Charity Bazaar
in Paris. But the projectionist was careless
and the film caught fire. This started an
even bigger fire, and 140 people died. Many
of them were very rich and important people.
CHAPTER THREE
The cinema comes to Hollywood
How did Hollywood begin? A Kansas couple,
Harvey and Daidia Wilcox, came to Los Angeles
in 1883, when there were just orange and lemon
farms in the area. Three years later, they
owned fifty hectares of land which they called
Hollywood.
The Wilcoxes sold the land, bit by bit, and
the first Hollywood studio was built in 1911
by the Nestor Company. The American filmmakers
came to California because the weather was
good, and because the Californian workers
were cheap to employ. In 1913, Cecil B. DeMille
came to Hollywood and started what became
known as Paramount Studios. Universal Studios
started about the same time, the Fox Company
two years later (joining with 20th Century
Pictures in 1935), United Artists in 1919
and Warner Brothers, MGM, and Columbia in
the early 1920s. If you wanted to 'get into
the movies', Hollywood was the place to go!
The first films were silent. The words of
the actors appeared on cards which were shown
every twenty seconds or so. Suitable music
was played during the film by an orchestra,
or by one person on a piano.
Edwin S. Porter was the filmmaker who introduced
film 'editing' - cutting the film and putting
it back together again with the shots in a
different order. This made the films more
exciting to watch. His film, The Great Train
Robbery (1903), is a good example of this.
Until 1910, audiences did not know the names
of their favourite actors and actresses. Actresses
were given names like 'The Biograph Girl'
or 'The Vitagraph Girl' or were not named
at all. Carl Laemmle, chief of Independent
Motion Pictures (which later became Universal
Studios) was the first to name a star, when
he employed Florence Lawrence. By 1913, every
studio was naming its actors and actresses.
CHAPTER FOUR
Famous faces
Although the first films were silent, during
the years after 1910, going to the cinema
was becoming more and more popular.
Charlie Chaplin and Buster Keaton were busy
making audiences laugh.
Rudolph Valentino, an Italian actor, became
the 'great lover' of the silent screen, and
millions of women sent him love letters after
films like The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse
and The Sheik (both 1921). Sadly, he died
in 1926 when he was only thirty-one.
Douglas Fairbanks was the star of some of
the best adventure films... and audiences
loved the beautiful Clara Bow.
One very famous silent film was The Birth
of a Nation, directed by D. W. Griffith. It
was first shown in 1915 and was almost three
hours long. It was about the American Civil
War, and a lot of people who had never been
inside a cinema before came to see this film.
The first 'serial' - a film shown a bit at
a time, usually one bit (or 'episode') each
week - arrived in 1912. Audiences rushed back
each week to see the next episode. A favourite
serial was The Perils of Pauline (1914) starring
Pearl White. Pearl had to fight Indians in
one episode, was pushed off the Rocky Mountains
in another, and was blown up at sea in another.
But she always seemed to escape for another
exciting day.
Film fact
By 1916, Mary Pickford and Charlie Chaplin
were each earning $10,000 a year. By 1918,
both had contracts for more than $1 million
a year.
CHAPTER FIVE
The golden age
The golden age of the cinema began with the
talkies - when the actors on film were able
to talk for the first time. In 1927, at New
York's Warner Theatre, Al Jolson, the Russian-born
Hollywood actor and singer, spoke, and sang
six songs in the Warner Brothers film, The
Jazz Singer. The first words that he spoke
in the film were: 'You ain't seen nothing
yet!' The audiences loved him.
At first there were many problems with talking
pictures. Microphones picked up the noises
in the studio, directors had to stop shouting
orders to the actors, and the actors had to
learn all their words.
Some stars of the silent screen could not
make the change to 'talkies'; audiences laughed
at their funny voices. But the deep, mysterious
voice of silent star Greta Garbo was a great
success when she appeared in Anna Christie.
The film magazines said: 'Garbo talks!' (She
also made it fashionable for women of the
time to wear berets!) Garbo's career ended
in 1942 when she left Hollywood, saying that
she would never act again.
By 1930, all films were 'talkies', and many
actors and directors moved from the theatre
into the cinema. Actors like Edward G. Robinson,
Spencer Tracey, Humphrey Bogart, Clark Gable
and Bette Davis began to appear on the screen.
Musical films began to be popular in the 1930s.
Fred Astaire and Ginger Rogers starred in
Flying Down to Rio (1933). This was the first
of nine films which they made together.
And then there were the fast-moving crime
films of James Cagney, Humphrey Bogart and
Edward G. Robinson. One of the best was The
Roaring Twenties.
The 1930s also introduced 'singing cowboys'
like Roy Rogers and Gene Autry. But it was
the film Stagecoach, directed by John Ford
in 1939, which made a star of one of Hollywood's
most famous cowboys - John Wayne.
The year 1939 was when audiences first saw
what is now sometimes described as the greatest
film ever made: Gone With The Wind, starring
Clark Gable and Vivien Leigh. The book appeared
in 1936 and sold a million in the first six
months. The film has earned more than $300
million, and won eight Oscars (with the first
one ever given to a black actress, Hattie
McDaniel, who played the part of 'Mammy').
Film fact
Alfred Hitchcock made the first British talking
picture in 1929. It was called Blackmail,
and was first written as a silent film. Hitchcock
quickly added words and sound when he saw
how popular talking pictures were becoming.
CHAPTER SIX
The 'star system'
In 1932, Technicolor introduced a camera which
could produce 'natural' colours for the films
that were shown in the cinemas. Filming in
Technicolor was expensive, but soon every
kind of movie could be seen for the first
time 'In Glorious Technicolor.'
The golden age of the cinema continued through
most of the 1940s. Audiences filled the 'picture
palaces' in their towns, enjoying exciting
films like Citizen Kane, Casablanca and Double
Indemnity, and musicals like Meet Me in St
Louis and Easter Parade.
During the Second World War, many people went
to the cinema for another reason as well.
They could see the main film, but they could
also see newsreels - films of the week's news
- with all the latest film and information
about the war.
At this time, actors worked for just one company.
This was known as the 'star system'. MGM Studios
told everyone that it had 'more stars than
there are in heaven' working for them; stars
like Judy Garland, Mickey Rooney, Jean Harlow,
Spencer Tracy, Clark Gable and Joan Crawford.
Studios often chose or wrote stories especially
for their big stars.
And sometimes a director would be brought
in from another studio to do a film because
that star liked him, or worked well with him.
Or a cameraman would be brought in because
he knew how to make the star look his or her
best on screen.
The Academy Awards are given every year by
the US Academy of Motion Picture Arts and
Sciences. They are called 'Oscars', and they
are supposed to have got their name because
they looked like the Uncle Oscar of Margaret
Herrick, a lady who worked in the Academy
film library. The first Awards were given
in May, 1929, and the Oscars were awarded
for silent films only. In 1930, the award-giving
was broadcast on the radio, and today it is
seen on TV by millions of people all over
the world.
Film fact
One star, Marlon Brando, was paid $2.25 million
for ten days work on Superman (1978). He appears
on the screen for about ten minutes in the
film.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Bigger and better!
In the 1950s, people stopped going to the
cinema two or three times a week, and stayed
at home to watch TV instead. The cinema queues
got shorter, and the film companies realized
that they had to fight back. They tried to
do this by making films that looked as different
as possible from TV.
TV in the 1950s was in black-and- white, and
the pictures were shown on very small screens.
So the cinema produced Cinemascope, which
made it possible to show films on a much wider
screen than ever before, and, of course, in
colour. And 'big screens' meant 'big' films
that looked good on a wide screen. Films like
The Robe (1953) and Ben Hur (1959).
Then came 3-D, where the pictures seemed to
jump off the screen at the audience.
Warner Brothers had a success with House of
Wax in 1953, and there were nearly twenty
more 3-D films shown in cinemas that year.
Alfred Hitchcock's Dial M for Murder (1954)
was popular. But the people in the audience
had to wear special coloured glasses to see
the effects of 3-D, and they soon became bored
with having to do this. And so the studios
stopped making 3-D films.
Cinerama films were popular for a short time,
but it needed three projectors and a bigger
screen again to show them. People had to move
their heads from side to side to see what
was happening at both ends of the screen!
But Cinerama films were very expensive to
make, and it was difficult to put the very
big screens into most cinemas.
The studios continued their fight with TV,
but television was becoming more and more
popular. Then, in 1955, RKO studios needed
money quickly to stay alive, and they sold
their films to television. Other studios soon
began to do the same and old films became
popular on TV.
But although the 'golden age' of the cinema
was finished, films continued to be made.
And there were some big successes - like the
James Bond films From Russia with Love (1963),
and Goldfinger (1964). There were popular
family films starring Julie Andrews - Mary
Poppins (1965) and The Sound of Music (1965).
Then the 1970s brought The Godfather (1972),
Jaws (1975), Star Wars (1977) and Superman
(1979). In the 1980s, young people hurried
to see E.T. The Extra- Terrestrial (1982),
Ghosthusters (1984), Back to the Future (1985)
and Batman (1989).
And in the 1990s came Stephen Spielberg's
Jurassic Park (1993) with its wonderful special
effects and exciting story. You can see the
video of Jurassic Park at home on your own
television. But the special effects are much
more frightening on a big screen in a dark
cinema.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Animation
Mickey Mouse, Tom and Jerry, Popeye, Rugs
Bunny. All these famous cartoon characters
began their lives as simple pictures on paper.
Cartoon characters are painted on to sheets
of clear film, called 'cels', so that the
painted 'background' can be seen through the
unpainted parts of the cel. Then they are
photographed. Each cel will have one picture,
and each picture will be a little different,
to make the characters appear to move when
they are projected at twenty-four pictures
every second.
The characters must look and sound the same
in every film.
Everybody recognizes the voice of Bugs Bunny
('Eeh, what's up, Doc?'), spoken by Mel Blanc.
Blanc also gave the character the name 'Bugs'.
The most famous producer of animated films
was Walt Disney. He introduced Mickey Mouse
to audiences in 1928 in a black-and- white
cartoon, Plane Crazy. At first the mouse was
called Mortimer, but then the name was changed
to Mickey.
Disney also produced the first Walt Disney
colour cartoon, Flowers and Trees (1932),
and the first animated feature film, Snow
White and the Seven Dwarfs. More followed:
Pinocchio, Fantasia, Dumbo, Bambi, Cinderella,
The Sleeping Beauty, 101 Dalmatians, The Jungle
Book, Aladdin, The Lion King, Pocahontas and
The Hunchback of Notre Dame.
Walt Disney studied at the Kansas City Art
Institute. He made animated cartoons for the
Kansas City Film Ad Company before going off
to Hollywood and starting a company with his
brother Roy in 1923.
In the film Who Framed Roger Rabbit? (1988),
cartoon characters and real actors appear
together.
Today, more and more animators are using computers,
instead of employing people to do all the
painting.
Some animators use marquettes (models) instead
of pictures, and bend the model's arms and
legs, or change its face, to make the character
'move'. Creature Comforts, produced by Aardman
Animations, who use models in all their films,
won an Oscar for best animation.
CHAPTER NINE
Behind the camera
A lot of people are needed to make a film,
as well as the actors and actresses. They
are all the other people whose names appear
at the beginning or end of a film. Some of
them have strange-sounding jobs like 'Best
Boy' or 'Key Grip'. Let's look at just some
of them.
Producer - the person who chooses which film
to make, who gets the money needed to make
it, and who takes care of all the business
problems.
Director - the person who decides how to 'shoot'
(or film) each scene, and who controls all
the actors and other people who are helping
to make the film. The director is the one
who shouts 'Action!' when he or she is ready.
One piece of film which is filmed without
stopping the camera is called a 'take'.
Screenwriter - the person who writes the screenplay
or script of a film. Sometimes many screenwriters
are employed before a director is happy with
a screenplay. And when a book is made into
a film, it is not usually the writer of the
book who writes the screenplay. A screenwriter
is usually given this job.
Editor - the person who 'cuts' and then puts
together the film after the filming has finished,
and makes it into the final movie.
Set Designer - the person who arranges the
furniture and scenery needed in the film.
The designer often plans by making models
of the scenery before working on the final
set.
Wardrobe Designer - the person who designs
or chooses the clothes that the actors wear
in the film. These are often got from special
companies who keep every kind of film and
theatre clothes that you can think of.
Gaffer - the lights and lighting chief in
the studio.
Best Boy - the Gaffer's assistant.
Key Grip - the person who moves the camera
around.
Boom Operator - the person who moves the microphone
above the heads of the actors when they are
speaking.
Film facts
In the film, Cleopatra, made in 1963, 26,000
costumes were used. But 32,000 were used to
make the film Quo Vadis in 1951.
Warner Brothers paid $5 million to American
writer, Tom Wolfe, to make the film of his
book, Bonfire of the Vanities (1990), starring
Tom Hanks, Melanie Griffith and Bruce Willis.
CHAPTER TEN
Inside or outside?
In the very early years of the cinema, almost
all filming was done outside. Today, filming
is done 'on location' when it is impossible
to build a real city, or a mountain or something,
inside the studio. Also, some directors prefer
to film on location. It is then that the cameras
go out into the real world.
All of some films are shot on location, but
others have only short outside scenes to join
with the scenes that are shot in the studio.
As an example, suppose it is important to
show a policeman arriving at an office on
Fifth Avenue, in New York, and meeting a businesswoman
inside the building. A location film crew
will 'shoot' the policeman getting out of
a taxi on Fifth Avenue and walking into the
office building. But the scene where he meets
the businesswoman in the office will be filmed
inside a studio, perhaps days or weeks later.
All studios have large 'stages' where the
sets are built. One of the biggest in the
world is at the British studios of Pinewood
in Buckinghamshire, where one of the stages
is 102 metres long.
Sets are sometimes used for more than one
film, and this was very true for cowboy films
that were made in the 1920s and 1930s. Then,
a Hollywood studio often made thirty or forty
of them in a year, and the street where the
cowboys had their final gunfight often appeared
in film after film, with only small changes.
Film facts
The largest number of locations used in a
Hollywood film was 140, for Around the World
in 80 Days (1956).
The largest number of cameras used for a single
scene was forty-eight for the sea battle in
the 1925 film of Ben Hur.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Special effects
Special effects are used when it is too difficult,
too dangerous, or too expensive to do something
in the usual way. They are used to make the
audience think that they are seeing something
which they really are not.
For example, small models of towns or buildings
are very useful. In films, when you see a
house catch fire, a plane crash, or a bomb
blow up a ship, you are probably watching
a model house, plane and ship. But you do
not realize this when you see it on the film.
The big dinosaurs in the film Jurassic Park
(1993) were not real, of course! Lots of models
were made of each of them.
Today, computers are used more and more in
special effects, making the impossible seem
possible.
The first 'special effect' happened in the
film The Execution of Mary, Queen of Scots,
which was made in the Edison studios in 1895.
The audience appear to see Queen Mary's head
being cut off, but the director stopped the
camera and changed the actress for a dummy,
whose head was cut off in the next shot.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Stunts and make-up
Stuntmen and stuntwomen are used when something
is too difficult or too dangerous for the
actor to do. Every stunt is carefully planned
before filming, and must be as safe as possible.
They wear the same clothes and make-up as
the star, and are usually filmed so that their
faces are not seen clearly.
They wear special clothes that will not catch
fire if they are to be filmed in a 'burning'
building (although often there is more smoke
than fire, and the fire is carefully controlled).
Stuntmen often wear padding under their clothes
so that they do not hurt themselves when they
fall from something like a horse or a moving
car.
Guns are not real guns, and knives are usually
made of rubber so that they will bend when
somebody is hit. Stuntmen who fall from buildings
will fall onto something soft (which you won't
see in the final film, of course!). The important
thing is that it looks real.
Some stars do their own stunts, although film
companies would prefer that they didn't. The
director doesn't want his star to get hurt
- it's too expensive for the film! Mel Gibson
did all his own stunts in Mad Max Beyond the
Thunderdrome (1985).
The make-up artist can change a nice-looking
actor into something very frightening... or
a beautiful young actress into an old woman.
It took eight-and-a half hours each day to
change the actress Francesca Annis into a
100-year-old woman in the 1982 film Krull.
Rubber masks are made for the actor to wear
when it is necessary to make very big changes
to their face. Wigs, beards, moustaches, false
eyelashes - all these things help to make
a 'character'.
It is even possible to make a man look like
a woman!
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Picture palaces
The greatest of all the 'picture palaces'
built in the 1920s and 1930s was the Roxy
Cinema in New York. It cost $12 million to
build and had 6214 seats. Three hundred people
worked at the cinema, with sixteen projectionists
and 110 musicians. It also had a hundred singers,
and a group of dancers to keep the audience
happy - and its own hospital! The Roxy opened
in March 1927 and closed in March 1960.
Most of the cinemas in the big cities seemed
like palaces to the film-goer. Inside were
comfortable seats, thick carpets and coloured
lights.
There was often a restaurant, and sometimes
a dance floor, too. Some American cinemas
had creches where mothers could leave their
babies while they went to watch the film.
A man or woman played a cinema organ while
audiences waited for the film to begin. The
organ came up out of the floor as the music
started.
Film fact
The drive-in cinema became popular in the
early 1950s in America - very popular with
young people! More than 4000 drive-ins opened
between 1948 and 1956.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
What happens next?
Today, cinema audiences are much smaller (and
usually younger) than the audiences of the
'golden age'. Many of the 'picture palaces'
are now 'multi-screen' cinemas with four or
five small cinemas inside one building.
Today's films appear on video, and then on
TV, after they have been seen by cinema audiences.
But some old films don't look so good on TV.
Cowboy films are an example of this. The wonderful
scenery in films like How the West Was Won
needs a large screen to show it at its best.
Television can't do it. For many people, the
cinema is still the only place to watch a
film.
One of the cinema's newest ideas is IMAX projection.
A screen 19 metres high and 15 metres wide,
and excellent sound, makes an audience feel
that they are 'really there'.
IMAX DOME theatres have a big, 30 metre screen
which puts the audience right in the centre
of everything that is happening in the film.
And with IMAX 3D, people find themselves reaching
out to try and touch what they can see, it
is so real!
There are nearly 150 IMAX theatres in different
countries all over the world, and more are
being built every year.
So this is cinema today.
And as Al Jolson said in The Jazz Singer,
'You ain't seen nothing yet!'
- THE END -