CHAPTER ONE
Robots and Japan
IF IN THE FUTURE YOU BUY A HOUSEHOLD ROBOT,
THE CHANCES ARE IT WILL BE JAPANESE
Japan is famous for its long tradition of
automatons, or machines that look and act
like humans.
In the 18th and 19th centuries, realistic
human models, known as Karakuri ningyo, or
"dolls that trick," were seen in homes, theaters,
and religious ceremonies.
The most common example was a small model
of a woman in a kimono that served cups of
tea to guests.
These sophisticated dolls became highly popular.
Interestingly, the great engineer Tanaka Hisashige,
founder of the company that would eventually
become TOSHIBA, actually started his career
in the early 19th century as a maker of Karakuri
dolls.
But Japan did not invent automatons.
In fact, they have been with us for thousands
of years.
The word automaton comes from the Greek "it
moves itself."
The 1st-century Greek inventor Hero was famous
for his automated machines, which included
moving dancers and fountains.
There are also many stories from ancient China
of wooden automatons that sang, danced, or
served drinks.
Later, in the 12th century, the Islamic scholar
Al-Jazari wrote a whole book on mechanisms
and automatons, which included clocks, animals,
a waitress, and even a programmable musical
band complete with flute-player and drummer!
The English word robot comes from the Czech
language and means "to serve."
It was first used in the 1920s in a play by
the Czech writer Karel Capek, titled R.U.R.
(Rossum's Universal Robots).
The play showed a futuristic world where human-like
machines did all the work.
In Capek's play these machines could think
and feel, and eventually they rebelled against
their human rulers.
By the 1920s in Japan robots were starting
to appear in department stores.
At first, however, they were not much more
than complicated Karakuri.
The first Japanese humanoid robot was created
in 1928 and was called Gakutensoku, or "Learning
from the Laws of Nature."
It was a Buddha-like model that used air to
move its head and hands.
Its creator, the biologist Makoto Nishimura,
believed these machines were part of nature.
He is quoted as saying, "If one considers
humans as the children of nature, artificial
humans created by the hand of man are thus
nature's grandchildren."
His robot became a huge success and toured
Asia and Europe.
Nishimura's opinions highlight the Japanese
attitude to machines and technology and the
fascination they have with robots.
This may be linked to Japan's Shinto religion,
whose followers regard all things as having
spirits.
Tools and all objects made with tools possess
their own special qualities, almost as if
they were individuals.
Certainly the Japanese view of robots is very
different from the views traditionally held
in Western cultures, which are often suspicious
of robots.
The Japanese look upon robots as things of
interest and beauty, designed to help humans
and make our lives better.
This view was most famously expressed in the
1951 Manga comic, Tetsuwan Atomu.
Atomu, or Astro Boy, as he was later known
in the West, was the first major robot character
to show robots as friendly and helpful.
The Japanese love of comic book robot characters,
together with the country's fast increasing
electronics industry, meant that by the 1980s
Japan had become a world leader in robot research
and production.
Today, more than a third of the world's industrial
robots work in factories in Japan.
As well as the typical industrial robots,
many robots are designed simply as toys or
for entertainment.
Animal robots, dancing robots, car-driving
robots, even piano- playing robots are all
made and sold in Japan.
And as technology improves, the differences
between humans and machines may become increasingly
blurred.
CHAPTER TWO
Robot and Recreation
FOR THE JAPANESE, ROBOTS ARE A GREAT SOURCE
OF ENTERTAINMENT.
Technically, a robot is any kind of autonomous
self-controlled or remote-controlled machine,
often used in factories for dangerous or precision
work.
But when we think of a robot, we often imagine
a machine with a recognizably human face and
figure.
These robots are called androids (from the
Greek for man, andr-) and are specifically
designed to have characteristics that make
them more attractive to humans.
Japan has a keen interest in humanoid models.
Karakuri dolls, for example, were seen as
more than models; they were respected as an
art form.
The Japanese fascination with robots meant
that in the late 20th century, when huge improvements
were being made in motors and computing, many
electronics companies began to design humanoid
robots that could interact with people on
a social level.
The first entertainment robot with commercial
success was not a humanoid, however, but a
robot dog.
Designed as a toy pet and launched in 1999,
Sony's AIBO quickly became popular worldwide.
The AIBO (Japanese for "companion") could
walk, could see using cameras, and had special
software that allowed it to develop from puppy
to adult, learning to play and understand
up to 100 voice commands.
Furthermore, special programmable software
allowed owners to change their AIBO's personality
and behavior.
Teams of AIBOs have even played at the annual
RoboCup, a soccer tournament where all the
competitors must be autonomous robots.
Humanoid robots have proved more difficult
to make.
However, in 2000 Honda finally introduced
its first real humanoid robot, ASIMO.
ASIMO was able to help disabled people move
around more easily.
The robot could recognize and respond to human
movements and commands, and was aware of its
environment.
It has made many public appearances, talking,
dancing, and even conducting an orchestra.
Its little brother, the QRIO made by Sony,
could run and interact to such an extent that
it was also capable of playing in the RoboCup.
Although the QRIO was too expensive to be
produced commercially, there are now many
different humanoid robots available on the
market.
They are generally simpler, more like expensive
remote-controlled toys, but they are all humanoid
and have some degree of autonomy.
The lack of easily available or reasonably-priced
humanoid robots hasn't stopped Japan's robot
enthusiasts.
DIY robotics has become increasingly popular
in recent years, to such an extent that a
robot championship, Robo-One, was started
in 2002.
The championship consists of a series of tasks
that the homemade robots must perform.
Tasks include falling from a standing position,
getting up, walking, jumping, and even competing
against other robots in a one-on-one boxing
match.
There has also been a Robo-One soccer match.
The robots in Robo-One are designed and built
at home by individual designers, but may use
commercial parts.
Many robots are made from aluminum and powered
by small electric motors.
One problem with two-legged robots is how
to make them walk like us.
Robots look awkward when they walk because
they constantly bend their knees.
However, in 2011 the Nagoya Institute of Technology
produced the first robot legs modeled on human
biomechanics.
So naturally moving humanoids may soon be
a common sight.
CHAPTER THREE
Robots and Money
JAPAN IS THE THIRD LARGEST ECONOMY IN THE
WORLD AND HAS THE LARGEST ELECTRONICS INDUSTRY,
IN WHICH IT IS CONSIDERED A LEADING INNOVATOR.
The Japanese have traditionally been noted
for the high quality of their craftsmanship.
European travelers arriving in Japan in the
16th and 17th century were amazed at its architecture,
metalwork, and technology.
After the Second World War, the Japanese emphasis
on quality and precision helped to create
strong, dynamic industries, innovating in
many areas.
Japanese cars and electronics became synonymous
with quality, reliability, and affordability.
This led to continuous economic growth for
over 30 years, which leveled off in the late
20th century.
As Japan enters the 21st century, the main
problem its economy faces is a shortage of
workers, a result of an aging population and
a falling birth rate.
These changes mean that, among other things,
there are fewer workers to earn money or care
for the elderly.
Many people in Japan believe that the Japanese
robotics industry may be the answer to Japan's
challenges, both economically (in 2010, the
worldwide industry was worth $5.6 billion),
but also as a technology that can produce
workers and caregivers for the country's aging
population.
CHAPTER FOUR
Robots and Work
WILL TOMORROW'S ROBOTS BE ABLE TO FULFILL
A SOCIAL ROLE?
What can Japan do to solve the problem of
the reduction in its workforce?
Traditionally suspicious of foreigners, the
country seems reluctant to relax its strict
immigration policy, looking instead to the
robotics industry to provide its workers.
What would seem a strange solution in many
other countries seems perfectly normal to
the electronics-obsessed Japanese.
Robots in Japanese society already carry out
many different roles.
Here are a few ways that robots are becoming
a part of everyday life in Japan.
Healthcare
One of the main shortages in workers in Japan
at the moment is in healthcare, especially
for the elderly.
Although there are many trained nurses available
from other parts of Asia, Japan allows very
few immigrants into the country.
Consequently, many robotics firms are looking
at the possibility of robot nurses.
Toyota launched four robot nursing models
in 2013.
These machines aren't humanoid, but resemble
motorized chairs, designed to help patients
move around and get in and out of bed.
A highly innovative use of a robot in healthcare
can be found in Tokyo's Cyberdyne gym.
Here, users can exercise wearing robotic legs
that recognize impulses made by the brain
when the person wants to walk.
With practice, people who have problems with
their legs can walk around and do exercises.
Security
Several Japanese companies have built security
robots.
There are robots to guard houses and offices,
a robot that collects cash from banks, and
a robot that can stop criminals.
The Tmsuk Company's T-34 is a small, four-wheeled
robot that can be controlled by mobile phone.
It can catch thieves by firing a net over
them.
Other robots have been used to direct traffic
in Tokyo.
And Fujitsu has produced a guide robot for
offices and malls.
It recognizes faces and has a touch screen
that people can press for information.
Actroids
An astounding example of Japanese robot philosophy
can be seen in their development of actroids.
A combination of the words actor and android,
these robots are specifically designed to
look as believably human as possible.
Robot directing traffic in Japan
The first actroid, presented at the 2003 International
Robot Convention by the University of Osaka,
was modeled on the looks of an average Japanese
woman.
It had realistic silicone skin and could blink,
speak, and breathe, using air to move its
features.
Later models are even more realistic.
Professor Ishiguro of Osaka University believes
that human acceptance of robots depends on
them having a familiar appearance.
In the future, he hopes that these human copies
could be used to represent people in business
meetings and in other events.
So far, the closest any of the actroids has
come was when HRP-4C starred as a model in
the 2009 Tokyo Fashion Week.
CHAPTER FIVE
Robots and Life
JAPAN'S RELIGIOUS TRADITIONS HELP ITS PEOPLE
APPRECIATE ROBOTS.
Mindless metal boxes, coldly following their
programming to the end, robots are not to
be trusted.
This, at least, is the impression you might
get from many Hollywood movies.
Traditionally, robots in Hollywood have generally
played the bad guy, an unforgiving, unstoppable
creature of incredible power, usually only
defeated because of its lack of flexibility
and imagination.
From movies like Blade Runner and Terminator
to The Matrix, we are often shown a world
where, given the opportunity, robots and computers
will enslave humans and try to take over.
This view reflects a deep mistrust of machines
in Western culture, a sense of separation
from the things we create.
However, it is a view not necessarily shared
by other cultures.
In Japan, many fictional accounts of robots
are positive.
Robots are seen as a force for good, as creators
of a more pleasant society.
These different points of view carry over
into everyday life.
An American may see robots as a threat to
his or her job, as an unnecessary complication,
or simply as a useless toy.
In Japan the same robot would be seen as a
way to make work easier and more efficient,
and as an interesting companion, as something
fun.
This probably explains why there are hundreds
of humanoid robots being developed in Japan,
while in the USA there are currently just
two.
So why is there such a difference between
these two points of view?
Many people have written about the subject,
both in Japan and abroad.
It seems mainly to be a question of whether
and how much something is seen to be alive.
In this respect, Japan's Shinto and Buddhist
heritage plays an important role.
Japan's Religious Tradition
While Buddhism and Shinto are officially separate,
in reality most people practice them together.
Buddhism, with its belief in the oneness or
unity of all things, was imported from China.
Shinto is a set of religious beliefs and practices
native to Japan and was first recorded in
the 8th century.
Shinto involves the worship of Kami, which
roughly translates as "spirits."
These spirits can be a natural experience,
such as wind or rain, or the spirit of a natural
place, such as a forest or river, or even
rocks.
This recognition of spiritual life in all
things and actions is known as animism.
Although Kami can also be the spirits of ancestors
or people, they are not gods in the Western
sense of the word.
Shinto's main aim is to keep in harmony with
the surrounding world by showing respect for
the kami that inhabit it.
In the same way, the tools you use or works
you create possess their own spirit or identity,
something worthy of respect.
It is not surprising that such a belief would
give rise to a culture of exceptional craftsmen.
A Sense of Connection
This sense of connection with the things an
artist or designer creates is very different
from Western ideas, which sharply divide living,
thinking beings from lifeless machines.
Japanese craftsmen's natural respect for and
appreciation of the machines they create becomes
even stronger when applied to a responsive
robot.
In Japan, robots are not seen only as tools
that exist to make human life easier.
As one writer has put it, it is no longer
a question of robots doing things for people,
but of doing things with them.
This is a philosophy that looks into a future
where man and machine live in harmony.
CHAPTER SIX
What Do You Think?
HOW WILL OUR LIVES CHANGE IN THE FUTURE BECAUSE
OF ROBOTS?
Every year, technological advances mean newer,
faster computers, newer communication devices,
and more sophisticated, more capable robots.
In Japan, this is viewed with excitement.
Perhaps, due to their philosophical history,
the Japanese are more capable of "understanding"
and working with robots.
Do you think robots will become as popular
in other parts of the world?
Will they be as accepted in other countries
or will they be objects of fear?
Robots will probably soon play a more important
role in our lives.
They will be able to move around better and
perform simple jobs around the house, such
as painting, cleaning, and other household
tasks.
But will they be able to communicate with
humans, have decision-making abilities, and
generally live alongside us on the planet?
The robot brain is based on computers and
their increasing ability to carry out billions
of instructions very quickly.
But will robot brains ever have the same kind
of intelligence as humans do?
Will the computer-based artificial brain allow
robots to become like intelligent human beings?
Some predictions say "Yes!"
Already computers can "understand" humans
to some extent by recognizing our speech.
Can you imagine having a robot as a friend?
Will children go to school with robot friends
who help them with their homework?
How will people behave socially with robots
in the future?
Will they be treated as machines?
Or will they act so like us that we treat
them as equals?
Will we have to change our laws to include
the fair treatment of robots?
We might even have groups fighting for "robot
rights."
For example, should robots be paid for the
work they do?
And if so, how?
What do you think will happen?
And will it happen in your lifetime?
- THE END -