CHAPTER ONE
Mr Lockwood visits Wuthering Heights
I have just returned from a visit to my
landlord, Mr Heathcliff. I am delighted
with the house I am renting from him. Thrushcross
Grange is miles away from any town or village.
That suits me perfectly. And the scenery
here in Yorkshire is so beautiful!
Mr Heathcliff, in fact, is my only neighbour,
and I think his character is similar to
mine. He does not like people either.
'My name is Lockwood,' I said, when
I met him at the gate to his house.
'I'm renting Thrushcross Grange from you. I
just wanted to come and introduce myself.'
He said nothing, but frowned, and
did not encourage me to enter.
After a while, however, he
decided to invite me in.
'Joseph, take Mr Lockwood's horse!' he called.
'And bring up some wine from the cellar!'
Joseph was a very old servant,
with a sour expression on his face.
He looked crossly up at me as he took my horse.
'God help us! A visitor!' he muttered to himself.
Perhaps there were no other servants, I thought.
And it seemed that Mr Heathcliff
hardly ever received guests.
His house is called Wuthering Heights. The
name means 'a windswept house on a hill',
and it is a very good description. The
trees around the house do not grow straight,
but are bent by the north wind, which
blows over the moors every day of the year.
Fortunately, the house is strongly built, and
is not damaged even by the worst winter storms.
The name 'Earnshaw' is cut into
a stone over the front door.
Mr Heathcliff and I entered the huge main room. It
could have been any Yorkshire farmhouse kitchen,
except that there was no sign of cooking,
and no farmer sitting at the table.
Mr Heathcliff certainly does not look like
a farmer. His hair and skin are dark, like a
gipsy's, but he has the manners of a gentleman. He
could perhaps take more care with his appearance,
but he is handsome. I think
he is proud, and also unhappy.
We sat down by the fire, in silence.
'Joseph!' shouted Mr Heathcliff. No answer
came from the cellar, so he dived down there,
leaving me alone with several
rather fierce-looking dogs.
Suddenly one of them jumped angrily up at me, and
in a moment all the others were attacking me. From
every shadowy corner in the great room appeared
a growling animal, ready to kill me, it seemed.
'Help! Mr Heathcliff! Help!' I shouted, trying to
keep the dogs back. My landlord and his servant
were in no hurry to help, and could not have
climbed the cellar steps more slowly, but luckily
a woman, who I supposed was the housekeeper,
rushed into the room to calm the dogs.
'What the devil is the matter?' Mr Heathcliff
asked me rudely, when he finally entered the room.
'Your dogs, sir!' I replied. 'You shouldn't
leave a stranger with them. They're dangerous.'
'Come, come, Mr Lockwood. Have some wine.
We don't often have strangers here, and I'm afraid
neither I nor my dogs are used to receiving them.'
I could not feel offended after this, and
accepted the wine. We sat drinking and talking
together for a while. I suggested visiting him
tomorrow. He did not seem eager to see me again,
but I shall go anyway. I am interested in
him, even if he isn't interested in me.
Two days later Yesterday afternoon
was misty and bitterly cold,
but I walked the four miles to Wuthering Heights
and arrived just as it was beginning to snow.
I banged on the front door for ten
minutes, getting colder and colder.
Finally Joseph's head appeared at a
window of one of the farm buildings.
'What do you want?' he growled.
'Could you let me in?' I asked desperately.
He shook his head. 'There's only Mrs Heathcliff
indoors, and she won't open the door to you.'
Just then a young man appeared and called me to
follow him. We went through the back door and
into the big room where I had been before. I was
delighted to see a warm fire and a table full of
food. And this time there was a woman sitting by
the fire. She must be Mrs Heathcliff, I thought.
I had not imagined my landlord was married. She
looked at me coldly without saying anything.
'Terrible weather!' I remarked. There was silence.
'What a beautiful animal!' I tried again,
pointing to one of the dogs that had attacked me.
She still said nothing, but got up to make
the tea. She was only about seventeen, with
the most beautiful little face I had ever seen.
Her golden wavy hair fell around her shoulders.
'Have you been invited to
tea?' she asked me crossly.
'No, but you are the proper
person to invite me,' I smiled.
For some reason this really annoyed her. She
stopped making the tea, and threw herself
angrily back in her chair. Meanwhile the
young man was staring aggressively at me.
He looked like a farm worker, but
seemed to be part of the family.
I did not feel at all comfortable.
At last Heathcliff came in.
'Here I am, sir, as I
promised!' I said cheerfully.
'You shouldn't have come,' he answered,
shaking the snow off his clothes.
'You'll never find your way back in the dark.'
'Perhaps you could lend me a servant to
guide me back to the Grange?' I asked.
'No, I couldn't. There aren't any servants
here except Joseph and the housekeeper. Get
the tea ready, will you?' he added fiercely to the
young woman. I was shocked by his unpleasantness.
We sat down to eat. I tried to make conversation
with the three silent people round the table.
'How happy you must be, Mr Heathcliff,' I began,
'in this quiet place, with your wife and-'
'My wife! My wife's ghost, you mean?'
I suddenly realized I had made a
serious mistake. So his wife was dead!
Of course he was too old to be married to that
young girl. She must be married to the young
man next to me, who was drinking his tea out of
a bowl and eating his bread with unwashed hands.
Perhaps the poor girl had found no one better to
marry in this uninhabited area. I
turned politely to the young man.
'Ah, so you are this lady's husband!' This was
worse than before. His face went red, and he
seemed only just able to stop himself hitting
me. He muttered something I could not hear.
'Wrong again, Mr Lockwood,' said Mr
Heathcliff. 'No, her husband, my son,
is dead. This, 'he added', looking scornfully
at the young man, 'is certainly not my son.'
'My name is Hareton Earnshaw,'
growled the young man.
We finished our meal in silence,
and when I looked out of the window,
all I could see was darkness and snow.
'I don't think I can get home without a
guide,' I said politely. No one answered me.
I turned to the woman.
'Mrs Heathcliff,' I begged,
'What can I do? Please help me!'
'Take the road you came on,'
she replied without interest,
opening a book. 'That's the
best advice I can give.'
'Mr Heathcliff, I'll have to stay
here for the night!' I told him.
'I hope that will teach you not to
walk over the moors in bad weather,'
he answered. 'I don't keep guest bedrooms.
You can share a bed with Hareton or Joseph.'
I was so angry with them all that I could not stay
there a moment longer, and rushed out into the
darkness. I saw Joseph by the back door, caught
hold of the lamp he was carrying, and ran with
it to the gate. But the dogs chased after me and
attacked me, and I was soon knocked to the ground.
Heathcliff and Hareton
stood at the door, laughing,
as I shouted at the dogs and tried to get up. In
the end I was again rescued by the housekeeper,
Zillah, who ordered away the
dogs and helped me to my feet.
I was so bruised and exhausted that I
did not feel strong enough to walk home,
and although I did not want to, I had
to spend the night at Wuthering Heights.
Nobody wished me goodnight, as Zillah
took me upstairs to find a bed for me.
CHAPTER TWO
Catherine Earnshaw's room
'Quietly, sir!' whispered the housekeeper,
as we climbed up the dark stairs.
'My master will be angry if he discovers
which bedroom you're sleeping in.
For some reason he doesn't
want anyone to sleep there,
I don't know why. They're strange people in
this house, you know. Here's the room, sir.'
But I was too tired to listen.
'Thank you, Zillah,' I said, and, taking the
candle, I entered the room and closed the door.
The only piece of furniture in the large, dusty
bedroom was a bed, placed next to the window.
There were heavy curtains which could be pulled
around it, to hide the sleeper from anyone else
in the room. Looking inside the curtains I saw a
little shelf full of books, just under the window.
I put my candle down on the shelf, and dropped
thankfully on to the bed. I closed the curtains
around the bed, and felt safe from Heathcliff
and everyone else at Wuthering Heights.
I noticed that there were names written on the
wall in childish handwriting - Catherine Earnshaw,
Catherine Heathcliff and Catherine Linton.
Then I fell asleep, but I was woken very suddenly
by a smell of burning. My candle had fallen on to
a Bible on the shelf and was burning it. When
I opened the Bible to see if it was damaged,
I found that wherever there was an empty page,
or half a page, someone had written on it,
and on the first page was written
'Catherine Earnshaw's diary, 1776'.
Who was the girl who had slept in this
bed, written her name on the wall,
and then written her diary in the Bible,
twenty-five years ago? I read it with interest.
'How I hate my brother Hindley!' it
began. 'He is so cruel to poor Heathcliff.
If only my father hadn't died! While he
was alive, Heathcliff was like a brother
to Hindley and me. But now Hindley and his wife
Frances have inherited the house and the money,
and they hate Heathcliff. That horrible old
servant Joseph is always angry with Heathcliff
and me because we don't pray or study the Bible,
and when he tells his master, Hindley always
punishes us. I can't stop crying. Poor Heathcliff!
Hindley says he is wicked, and can't
play with me or eat with me anymore.'
My eyes were beginning to
close again and I fell asleep.
Never before had I passed such a terrible
night, disturbed by the most frightening dreams.
Suddenly I was woken by a gentle knocking on
the window. It must be the branch of a tree, I
thought, and tried to sleep again. Outside I could
hear the wind driving the snow against the window.
But I could not sleep. The knocking annoyed
me so much that I tried to open the window.
When it did not open, I broke the glass angrily
and stretched out my hand towards the branch.
But instead, my fingers closed around a small,
ice-cold hand! It held my hand tightly, and
a voice cried sadly, 'Let me in! Let me in!'
'Who are you?' I asked,
trying to pull my hand away.
'Catherine Linton,' it replied.
'I've come home. I lost my way!'
There seemed to be a child's
face looking in at the window.
Terror made me cruel. I rubbed
the creature's tiny wrist
against the broken glass so that
blood poured down on to the bed.
As soon as the cold fingers let go for a moment,
I pulled my hand quickly back, put a pile of
books in front of the broken window, and tried
not to listen to the desperate cries outside.
'Go away!' I called. 'I'll never let you in,
not if you go on crying for twenty years!'
'It is almost twenty years!'
replied the sad little voice.
'I've been out here in the dark for nearly
twenty years!' The hand started pushing through
the window at the pile of books, and I knew
it would find me and catch hold of me again.
Unable to move, I stared in horror at
the shape behind the glass, and screamed.
There were rapid footsteps
outside my bedroom door,
and then I saw the light of a candle in the room.
'Is anyone here?' whispered Heathcliff. He
could not see me behind the curtains, and
clearly did not expect an answer. I knew I could
not hide from him, so I opened the curtains wide.
I was surprised by the effect of my action.
Heathcliff dropped his candle and stood
without moving, his face as white as the wall
behind him. He did not seem to recognize me.
'It's only your guest, Lockwood,' I said.
'I'm sorry, I must have had a bad
dream and screamed in my sleep.'
'To the devil with you, Mr Lockwood!'
growled my landlord. 'Who allowed you
to steep in this room? Who was it?'
'It was your housekeeper, Mr Heathcliff,'
I said, quickly putting my clothes on.
'And I'm angry with her myself! No one
can sleep in a room full of ghosts!'
'What do you mean?' asked Heathcliff, looking
suddenly very interested. 'Ghosts, you say?'
'That little girl, Catherine Linton, or Earnshaw,
or whatever her name was, must have been wicked!
She told me she had been a
ghost for nearly twenty years.
It was probably a punishment for her wickedness!'
'How dare you speak of her to
me?' cried Heathcliff wildly.
But as I described my dream, he became calmer,
and sat down on the bed, trembling
as he tried to control his feelings.
'Mr Lockwood,' he said finally,
brushing a tear from his eye,
'you can go into my bedroom to sleep for the
rest of the night. I'll stay here for a while.'
'No more sleep for me tonight,' I replied.
'I'll wait in the kitchen until it's daylight,
and then I'll leave. You needn't worry about
my visiting you again either. I've
had enough company for a long time.'
But as I turned to go downstairs, my landlord,
thinking he was alone, threw himself on the bed,
pushed open the window and
called into the darkness.
'Come in! Come in!' he cried,
tears rolling down his face.
'Catherine, do come! My
darling, hear me this time!'
But only the snow and wind blew into the room.
How could my dream have produced such madness?
I could not watch his suffering
any more, and went downstairs.
I waited in the kitchen until it was light enough
outside for me to find my way through the deep
snow back to Thrushcross Grange. The housekeeper
there, Ellen Dean, rushed out to welcome me home.
She thought I must have died in
the previous night's snowstorm.
With a warm fire, and a hot meal, I began
to recover from my unpleasant experiences.
After my stay at Wuthering Heights,
I thought I would never want to speak
to any human being again, but by the end of
the next day I was beginning to feel lonely.
I decided to ask Mrs Dean
to sit with me after supper.
'How long have you lived in
this house?' I asked her.
'Eighteen years, sir. I came here early in 1783
when my mistress was married, to look after her.
And when she died, I stayed here as housekeeper.'
'Who was your mistress?' I asked.
'Her name was Catherine Earnshaw,' she replied.
'Ah, my ghostly Catherine,'
I muttered quietly to myself.
'She married Mr Edgar Linton, a neighbour,'
added Mrs Dean, 'and they had a daughter,
Cathy, who married Mr Heathcliffs son.'
'Ah, so that must be the widow, young
Mrs Heathcliff at Wuthering Heights!'
'That's right, sir. Did you see her? I
looked after her as a baby, you know.
How is she? I do want to know.'
'She looked very well, and very
beautiful. But I don't think she's happy.'
'Oh, poor thing! And what did
you think of Mr Heathcliff?'
'He's a rough, hard man, Mrs Dean. But I'm very
interested in him. Tell me more about him.'
'Well, he's very rich, of course,
and mean at the same time.
He could live here at Thrushcross Grange, which
is a finer house than Wuthering Heights, but he
would rather receive rent than live comfortably.
But I'll tell you the whole story of his life,
as much as I know, that is, and
then you can judge for yourself.'
CHAPTER THREE
Ellen Dean's story - Catherine
and Heathcliff as children
When I was a child, I was always at Wuthering
Heights, because my mother was a servant with
the Earnshaw family. They are a very old family
who have lived in that house for centuries,
as you can see from their name on the
stone over the front door. I grew up
with Catherine and Hindley Earnshaw, and
we three played together as children.
One day, their father Mr Earnshaw came
back from a long journey. He had travelled
sixty miles to Liverpool and back
on business, and was very tired.
'Look what I've brought you!' he told us all,
unwrapping something he was holding carefully
in his arms. Catherine and Hindley were expecting
presents, and they rushed eagerly to see what it
was. They were very disappointed to see
only a dirty, black-haired gipsy child.
'I found him all alone in the
busy streets of Liverpool,'
Mr Earnshaw explained to them, and I couldn't
leave him to die. He can sleep in your room.'
But Hindley and Catherine were angry
because they had not received any presents,
and refused to let the strange child share
their room. However Mr Earnshaw insisted,
and little by little the boy became
accepted by the family. He was called
Heathcliff, as a first and last name. No one
ever discovered who his parents had been.
Catherine and he became great friends, but
Hindley hated him, and was often cruel to him.
Old Mr Earnshaw was strangely fond of this
gipsy child, and frequently punished his son for
behaving badly to Heathcliff. Hindley began to be
jealous of his father's feelings for Heathcliff,
and saw them both as enemies.
This situation could not last.
As Mr Earnshaw grew old and ill,
Heathcliff became even more his favourite,
and Hindley often quarrelled with his father.
When Hindley was sent away to study, I hoped
that we would have peace in the house. But then
it was that old servant Joseph who caused
trouble. He tried to persuade his master
to be stricter with the children, and was
always complaining that Heathcliff and Catherine
did not spend enough time studying the
Bible or attending church services.
Catherine was a wild, wicked girl in those days.
We had to watch her every moment of the day, to
stop her playing her tricks on us. She was proud,
and liked giving orders. But she had the prettiest
face and the sweetest smile you've ever seen.
I could forgive her anything when
she came to say she was sorry.
She was much too fond of Heathcliff, and the
worst punishment we could invent was to keep
her separate from him. Her father could
no longer understand her or her behaviour,
and Catherine did not realize that his
illness made him less patient with her.
At last Mr Earnshaw found peace. He died quietly
in his chair by the fire one October evening in
1775. The night was wild and stormy, and we
were all sitting together in the big kitchen.
Joseph was reading his Bible at the table, while
Catherine had her head on her father's knee.
He was pleased to see her so gentle for
once, and she was singing him to sleep.
I was glad the old gentleman was sleeping so well.
But when it was time to go to bed, Catherine put
her arms round her father's neck to say goodnight,
and immediately screamed, 'Oh,
he's dead, Heathcliff! He's dead!'
Heathcliff and I started
crying loudly and bitterly too.
Joseph told me to fetch the doctor, so I ran to
the village, although I knew it was too late.
When I came back, I went to the children's room,
to see if they needed me, and I listened for
a moment at their door. They were imagining
the dead man in a beautiful distant place,
far from the troubles of this world.
And as I listened, crying silently, I could not
help wishing we were all there safe together.
CHAPTER FOUR
Catherine Earnshaw gets to know the Lintons
1775 Hindley came home for his father's burial.
What was more surprising was that he brought a
wife with him. She was called Frances, a thin,
pale woman with a frequent cough. Now
that Hindley was the master of the house,
he ordered Joseph and me to spend our evenings in
the small back-kitchen, as we were only servants,
while he, his wife and Catherine sat in the
main room. Catherine and Heathcliff were
treated very differently. Catherine received
presents, and could continue her lessons,
but Heathcliff was made to work on the farm with
the men, and, as a farm worker, was only allowed
to eat with us in the back-kitchen. They grew up
like two wild animals. Hindley did not care what
they did, as long as they kept out of his way, and
they did not care even if he punished them. They
often ran away on to the moors in the morning and
stayed out all day, just to make Hindley angry.
I was the only one who cared what happened to the
two poor creatures, and I was afraid for them.
One Sunday evening they were missing at bedtime,
and Hindley ordered me angrily to lock the front
door. But I did not want them to stay out in the
cold all night, so I kept my window open to look
out for them. In a while I saw Heathcliff walking
through the gate. I was shocked to see him alone.
'Where's Catherine?' I cried sharply.
'At Thrushcross Grange, with our neighbor's the
Lintons,' he replied. Let me in, Ellen, and I'll
explain what happened.' I went down to unlock
the door, and we came upstairs very quietly.
'Don't wake the master up!'
I whispered. 'Now tell me!'
'Well, Catherine and I thought we'd just
walk to the Lintons' house. We wanted to
see if Isabella and Edgar Linton are punished
all the time by their parents, as we are.'
'Probably not,' I answered. 'I expect they are
good children and don't need to be punished.'
'Nonsense, Ellen! Guess what we saw when we looked
in at their sitting-room window? A very pretty
room, with soft carpets and white walls. Catherine
and I would love to have a room like that!
But in the middle of this beautiful room, Isabella
and Edgar Linton were screaming and fighting
over a little dog! How stupid they are, Ellen!
If Catherine wanted something, I would give it
to her, and she would do the same for me. I would
rather be here at Wuthering Heights with her, even
if I'm punished by Joseph and that wicked Hindley,
than at Thrushcross Grange with those two fools!'
'Not so loud, Heathcliff! But you still
haven't told me why Catherine isn't with you?'
'Well, as we were looking in, we started laughing
at them so loudly that they heard us, and sent the
dogs after us. We were about to run away, when
a great fierce dog caught Catherine's leg in its
teeth. I attacked it, and made it let go of
her leg, but the Lintons' servants appeared
and caught hold of me. They must have thought we
were robbers. Catherine was carried unconscious
into the house, and they pulled me inside too.
All the time I was shouting and swearing at them.
"What a wicked pair of thieves!" said
old Mr Linton. "The boy must be a gipsy,
he's as dark as the devil!"
Mrs Linton raised her hands in
horror at the sight of me. Catherine opened
her eyes, and Edgar looked closely at her.
"Mother," he whispered, "the young lady is Miss
Earnshaw, of Wuthering Heights. I've seen her in
church occasionally. And look what our dog
has done to her leg! It's bleeding badly!"
"Miss Earnshaw with a gipsy!" cried Mrs Linton.
"Surely not! But I think you must be right, Edgar.
This girl is wearing black, and Mr
Earnshaw died recently. It must be her.
I'd better put a bandage on her leg at once."
"Why does her brother Hindley let her run around
with such a companion?" wondered Mr Linton. "I
remember now, he's the gipsy child Mr Earnshaw
brought home from Liverpool a few years ago."
"He's a wicked boy, you can
see that," said Mrs Linton.
"And did you hear the bad language he used just
now? I'm shocked that my children heard it."
I was pushed out into the garden, but I stayed to
watch through the window. They put Catherine on a
comfortable sofa, cleaned her wound and fed her
with cakes and wine. I only left the house when
I was sure she was well taken care of. She's a
breath of fresh air for those stupid Lintons.
'I'm not surprised they like her. Everybody who
sees her must love her, mustn't they, Ellen?'
'I'm afraid you'll be punished for
this, Heathcliff,' I said sadly.
And I was right. Hindley warned
Heathcliff that he must never
speak to Catherine again, or he would
be sent away from Wuthering Heights,
and it was decided that Catherine would
be taught to behave like a young lady.
She stayed with the Linton family at Thrushcross
Grange for five weeks, until Christmas. By that
time her leg was fine, and her manners were much
better than before. Frances Earnshaw visited her
often, bringing her pretty dresses to wear, and
persuading her to take care of her appearance,
so that when she finally came home after her long
absence, she almost seemed a different person.
Instead of a wild, hatless girl, we saw a
beautiful, carefully dressed young lady.
When she had greeted all of
us, she asked for Heathcliff.
'Come forward, Heathcliff!' called Hindley.
You may welcome Miss Catherine
home, like the other servants.'
Heathcliff was used to being outside all day, and
had not bothered to wash or change his clothes.
His face and hands were black with dirt.
In spite of this, Catherine was very glad to see
him and rushed up to kiss him. Then she laughed.
'How funny and black and cross you look! But
that's because I'm used to Edgar and Isabella,
who are always so clean and tidy. Well,
Heathcliff, have you forgotten me?'
But, ashamed and proud, the boy said nothing,
until suddenly his feelings were too much for him.
'I won't stay to be laughed at!' he cried,
and was about to run away, when
Catherine caught hold of his hand.
'Why are you angry, Heathcliff? You... you just
look a bit strange, that's all. You're so dirty!'
She looked worriedly at her
hands, and her new dress.
'You needn't have touched me!' he said,
pulling away his hand. 'I like being
dirty, and I'm going to be dirty!'
As he ran miserably out of the room,
Hindley and his wife laughed loudly,
delighted that their plan to separate the
two young people seemed to be succeeding.
The next day was Christmas Day. Edgar and
Isabella Linton had been invited to lunch,
and their mother had agreed, on condition that
her darlings were kept carefully apart from that
wicked boy. I felt sorry for poor Heathcliff,
and while the Earnshaws were at church, I
helped him wash and dress in clean clothes.
'You're too proud,' I scolded him as I
brushed his black hair. You should think
how sad Catherine is when you can't be
together. And don't be jealous of Edgar Linton!'
'I wish I had blue eyes and fair hair like him!
I wish I behaved well, and was
going to inherit a fortune!'
'He has none of your intelligence or character!
And if you have a good heart,
you'll have a handsome face.
Who knows who your parents were? Perhaps a king
and queen, far more important than the Lintons!'
In this way I encouraged Heathcliff to have more
confidence in himself. But when the Earnshaws
and the Lintons arrived back from church, the
first thing Hindley did was shout at Heathcliff.
'Get out of my sight, until we've finished eating!
I'll pull that long hair of yours
if you don't obey me at once!'
'It is long,' said Edgar. I'm surprised he can
see anything.' This was too much for Heathcliff.
He looked desperately around for a weapon, picked
up a bowl of hot soup and threw it at Edgar,
who started screaming. Hindley immediately took
hold of Heathcliff and pushed him upstairs.
'I'm sure Hindley's going to hit him!'
cried Catherine. 'I hate it when Heathcliff
is punished! It's your fault, Edgar, you
annoyed him! Why did you speak to him?'
'I didn't,' replied Edgar, tears in his eyes. 'I
promised Mother I wouldn't. I
spoke about him, not to him.'
'Well, don't cry,' said Catherine with scorn.
'You've made enough trouble
already. Here comes my brother.'
Hindley returned, hot and breathless.
'That'll teach him!' he said.
'And now let's have lunch!'
The others seemed to forget Heathcliff,
but I noticed Catherine could not eat much,
and I knew she was sorry for her friend. In the
evening there was music from a travelling band,
and dancing in the main room. Catherine
said the music sounded sweeter from high up,
and so she went to sit in the dark on the stairs.
When I went to find her, however, I discovered
she had gone right to the top of the house to talk
to Heathcliff through his locked bedroom door,
and had then climbed out on to the roof and
in through his window. I persuaded them both
to come out of the room the same way, as I had
no key to the door, and took Heathcliff down
into the warm servants' kitchen with me, while
Catherine returned to her guests and the dancing.
'You must be hungry, Heathcliff,' I said.
'You haven't eaten all day.
Have some Christmas cake, do.'
'I can't eat anything,' he growled,
putting his head in his hands.
'I've got to think how I can have my revenge
on Hindley. I only hope he doesn't die first!
He'll be sorry he's treated
me like this, Ellen!'
CHAPTER FIVE
Catherine and Edgar
1778 In the summer of this year Hindley's
wife Frances had her first, and last,
baby. They called the boy Hareton. But the
poor woman had been ill for a long time,
although we had not realized it, and
died soon after Hareton was born.
Hindley only had room in his heart for two
people, himself and his wife, so when she died,
he was in despair. He neither cried nor
prayed. Instead he swore at God and man, and
drank himself to sleep every night. The servants
all left him, except for Joseph and me. Joseph
enjoyed being able to scold his wicked
employer, with warnings from the Bible,
and I could not leave Miss Catherine. After
all, I had grown up with her and Hindley.
But the master's behaviour was a bad example
for Catherine and Heathcliff. At fifteen,
Catherine was the most beautiful girl for miles
around, but she was proud and quick-tempered.
She led what was almost a double life. At
Wuthering Heights, under Heathcliffs influence,
she annoyed Hindley, laughed at Joseph, and
was rude to me. But at Thrushcross Grange,
which she often visited, she showed a different,
calmer side of her character, and was polite,
intelligent and amusing. The Lintons all liked
her, and poor Edgar had fallen in love with her.
Heathcliff was sixteen at this time. He did
not have time to study any more, and the long
hours of work on the farm made him tired and dull.
There was always an angry expression on his face,
and he did not even try to keep himself clean and
tidy. He seemed to want people to dislike him.
Catherine and he still spent time together, when
he was not working in the fields, but he no longer
expressed his fondness for her in words, and
he looked angry if she touched or kissed him.
One afternoon, when Hindley had gone into town,
Heathcliff came into the main room after lunch.
I was helping Catherine to arrange her hair,
as she had invited Edgar Linton to
visit her while Hindley was absent.
'Catherine, are you going
anywhere this afternoon?'
asked Heathcliff. 'Why have you got that silk
dress on? Nobody's visiting you, I hope.'
'No-o, I don't think so,' replied Catherine,
looking quickly at me. 'But you
should be at work by now, Heathcliff.'
'That devil Hindley isn't away very often. I'm
taking a holiday. I won't work anymore today.
I'm staying with you this
afternoon. He'll never know.'
Catherine thought for a moment. 'Somehow she had
to prepare him for Edgar's visit. Isabella and
Edgar said they might call here this afternoon.
If they come, you'll be scolded for not working.'
'Tell Ellen to say you're busy and can't
see them,' he said. Those friends of yours
take up all your time. You spend most of
your evenings with them, not with me.'
'Well, why should I always spend my
time with you?' she asked crossly.
'What can you talk about? How can you amuse me?'
'You never told me before that you didn't
like my company, Catherine!' cried Heathcliff.
Just then we heard a horse outside, and there was
a light knock on the door. Edgar Linton entered,
his handsome face full of delight at
receiving Catherine's unexpected invitation.
I wondered if Catherine was comparing her two
friends, as Edgar came in and Heathcliff ran out.
'I haven't come too soon,
have I?' asked Edgar politely.
'No,' answered Catherine. 'Leave us alone, Ellen.'
'I'm just doing my work, miss,' I
replied, pretending to dust the furniture.
'Hindley had told me to be present if
Edgar Linton came to visit Catherine.'
She came up to me, and whispered crossly,
'Go away, Ellen!' Keeping her back to
Edgar, she cruelly scratched my arm.
'Oh!' I screamed, to show Edgar what had happened.
'What a wicked thing to do, miss!
You have no right to hurt me!'
'I didn't touch you, you lying creature!'
she cried angrily, and, unable to
control herself, hit me hard on the face.
'Catherine, love! Catherine!'
cried Edgar, shocked.
The baby, Hareton, who followed me everywhere,
immediately started sobbing and
saying, 'Wicked aunt Catherine!'
She picked him up and shook the poor child
until he screamed. Edgar rushed up to her
and tried to stop her. At once she turned and
hit him over the ear as hard as she could.
The young man looked very pale
and went straight to the door.
'Where are you going, Edgar Linton?' she asked.
'Don't leave me! I shall be miserable all night!'
'Can I stay after you have hit me?'
he replied. 'You've made me afraid and
ashamed of you. I won't come here again!'
'Well, go then, if you want to!' she
cried. 'I'm going to cry until I'm ill!'
and she dropped on to the floor, her shoulders
shaking and the tears rolling down her face.
Edgar managed to get as far as the door.
But here he hesitated, and I called
out to him to encourage him to leave.
'Miss is just a selfish child, sir!
You'd better ride home and forget her!'
But as he could not stop looking at her, I knew
there was no hope for him. Nothing would keep
him away from her now. And sure enough, he came
back into the room and shut the door. This time
I left them alone, and stayed in the kitchen with
little Hareton, but when I came to warn them that
Hindley had returned, I realized that their
quarrel had only brought them closer together.
CHAPTER SIX
Heathcliff disappears
1778-9 Hindley came into the kitchen, swearing
terribly, just as I was about to hide little
Hareton in a cupboard. I was always afraid
that Hindley would hurt his small son, either
by accident or on purpose, when he was drunk,
so I tried to keep Hareton out of the way.
But this time Hindley discovered my plan.
'Ah, you keep my son in a cupboard, do you!' he
cried angrily, picking up a sharp kitchen knife.
'With the devil's help I'll make you swallow this,
Ellen!' And he pushed the knife between my teeth.
I was never afraid he would hurt me, and
calmly took the knife out of my mouth.
'But that can't be my son, can
it?' he continued aggressively,
staring at the frightened little boy. 'If it
is, he should be punished for not running to
greet his father. Perhaps I'll cut his ears
off!' And then suddenly his manner changed.
'No, Hareton, darling, don't
cry! Kiss me, kiss your father!
What? You won't? Then I'll break your neck!'
Poor Hareton, screaming wildly,
was carried upstairs by his father.
Suddenly Hindley stopped on the stairs to
listen, almost forgetting what he was holding.
Heathcliff had come into the house and stood
at the bottom of the stairs, looking up.
Just then the child jumped out
of Hindley's arms and fell.
I only had time to gasp in horror, before
I saw that Heathcliff had caught him.
Heathcliff stared down at
the child he was holding.
He must have felt sorry he had
saved the life of his enemy's son.
I rushed to take the poor little boy in my
arms, and Hindley came slowly downstairs.
'Look what you've done, Mr Hindley!' I
cried. 'You nearly killed your own son!
What would his mother say if she were alive?'
'Take him away, Ellen. And you, Heathcliff, go
away too. I won't murder you tonight, unless
perhaps I set the house on fire. But that depends
how I feel.' And he poured himself a drink.
'Don't drink any more, Mr Hindley!' I begged.
'What difference does it make?' he growled.
'Get out, both of you! To the devil with you!'
We left him swearing at us,
and went back into the kitchen.
'It's a pity he can't kill himself with drink,'
muttered Heathcliff. Dr Kenneth says he'll
live longer than any of us, he's so strong.'
He walked out of the door and, I thought, into
the fields. In fact I discovered later that he
was sitting just under the window, and could
hear everything that was said in the kitchen.
I was singing little Hareton to
sleep when Catherine came in.
'Are you alone, Ellen?' she
whispered. 'Where's Heathcliff?'
'He's out on the farm,' I answered.
She looked sad and worried, and I
even saw a tear or two on her face.
But I had not forgotten how she had lied, and
behaved so badly to me as well as to Edgar Linton,
so I did not feel sorry for
her, or encourage her to talk.
'Ellen, will you keep a secret for me?' she
asked in the end, giving me her sweetest smile.
'I must tell you! I need your advice.
Today Edgar Linton has asked me to
marry him, and I gave him an answer.
Now, before I tell you if it was yes or
no, you tell me which I should have said.'
'Really, Miss Catherine, how can I know?
Perhaps you should have refused him. He must
be a fool to ask you, after you were
so rude and violent this afternoon.'
'Well, I accepted him, Ellen!' she said crossly.
But should I have done so?
Should I? What do you think?'
'First, do you love him?' I asked.
'Of course I do,' she replied.
'Why do you love him, Miss Catherine?'
'Well, I do, that's enough. Well, because
he's handsome, and a pleasant companion.'
'Oh, that's bad,' I said, shaking my head.
'And because he loves me.'
'That's worse.'
'And because he'll be rich, and I shall be
the most important woman for miles around.'
'Worst of all. But there are several other
handsome, rich young men in the world.
Why don't you marry one of them?'
'I don't know any of them. I only know Edgar.'
'Well, I don't know why you're unhappy, Miss
Catherine. Your brother will be pleased,
and Mr Edgar's parents will, too. You love
Edgar, and Edgar loves you. What's the problem?'
'Here! And here! replied Catherine, beating
her head and her chest. 'In my heart and soul
I know I'm wrong! Ellen, I can't live apart
from Heathcliff! He is more myself than I am.
Our souls are the same! I have nothing in common
with Edgar. But I can't marry Heathcliff now!
Hindley has made him become a poor, dull farm
worker. He'll never know how I love him.'
I suddenly heard a movement outside the window,
and saw Heathcliff stand up and walk away.
I realized he had been listening until he
heard Catherine say she could not marry him.
Then he stayed to hear no more.
'Quiet, Miss Catherine!' I said. Just
imagine how hard it will be for Heathcliff
when you marry Mr Edgar! He'll have
no friends at all when you leave him.'
'Leave him? Why should we be separated?'
she asked angrily. 'Who will separate us?
Nobody will dare! Edgar must
learn to accept him as my friend.
Didn't you ever think, Ellen,
that if Heathcliff and I married,
we would be very poor? But if I marry Edgar, I
can help Heathcliff with my husband's money.'
'That's the worst reason you've given so far
for marrying Mr Edgar,' I replied, shocked.
'It isn't! Heathcliff is more
important to me than myself.
My love for Edgar is like the leaves on
the trees. I'm sure time will change it.
But my love for Heathcliff is like the
rocks in the ground - not beautiful,
but necessary and unchanging.
He's always, always in my heart-'
Just then Joseph entered the kitchen.
I whispered to Catherine that I was sure
Heathcliff had heard some of what she said.
She jumped up, frightened, and rushed outside. But
although we all looked everywhere for Heathcliff,
there was no sign of him that night,
or for many nights in the future.
At about midnight, while we were still waiting for
him to come home, we noticed the wind was getting
stronger. We could hear it whistling down the
chimney, and howling all around the house.
Suddenly there was a terrible crash of thunder,
and the branch of a tree fell on to the roof.
We were not hurt, but Joseph immediately
dropped on to his knees to pray.
The rain was beating down on the windows,
but Catherine stayed outside, although by
now her hair and clothes were completely wet.
In the end we all went to bed. I managed
to persuade Catherine to come in,
but she insisted on sleeping in the kitchen,
in case Heathcliff returned during the night.
In the morning we discovered that she had caught
a fever, as a result of getting wet. She became
seriously ill, and it was several weeks
before Dr Kenneth would allow her out of bed.
When she recovered, she was invited to stay for
a while at Thrushcross Grange. Unfortunately
old Mr and Mrs Linton caught the fever too, and
died within a few days of each other. Catherine
returned to us, prouder and quicker-tempered
than ever, but not as strong as before.
'If she gets ill again, it could be fatal,'
Dr Kenneth warned us. 'My advice to you
is to do whatever she wants, and don't
make her angry!' So we had to obey
all her orders, and Joseph and I were
not allowed to scold her any more.
Edgar Linton was still in love with her, and
thought himself the happiest man on earth when he
married her three years after his parents' death.
She insisted on having me with her, so we moved
together to Thrushcross Grange, although I was
very sad to leave little Hareton with his father.
It's very late, Mr Lockwood.
I think you should go to bed,
or you'll be ill tomorrow. I can tell
you the rest of the story another time.
Four weeks later in fact I was ill the next day,
and have been ill since then. The terrible night
I spent at Wuthering Heights was the cause of
my illness, and I blame Mr Heathcliff for it.
Dr Kenneth has warned me I won't
be able to go out until the spring.
All I can do is lie in bed, listening to the
howling wind and staring at the grey northern sky.
So I've decided to ask Mrs Dean to come
upstairs and finish telling me her story.
She tells me she's happy to continue.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Heathcliff returns
1783 Well, sir, when Miss Catherine became Mrs
Linton, and we went to live at Thrushcross Grange,
I must say I was surprised
and pleased by her behaviour.
She showed great fondness for her
husband, and for his sister, Isabella.
He, of course, was very anxious that no one
should disobey her, or make her angry. If
she was depressed for a time, he blamed it on
the illness she had had, and was sympathetic.
But for most of the time, I believe they
shared a deep and growing love for each other.
Unfortunately this happiness did not last.
One evening I was bringing in a basket of
apples from the garden, when a voice
behind me said, 'Ellen, is that you?'
It was a deep, rather unusual voice.
I turned, to see a tall, dark man
in the shadow near the kitchen door.
'Don't you know me?' he asked.
'Look, I'm not a stranger!'
'What!' I cried in surprise,
for it had been four years since he
disappeared. 'Heathcliff! Is it really you?'
'Yes,' he replied, looking up
at the windows of the house.
'Are they at home? Where is she?
Tell me, Ellen! I must speak to her!'
'I'm not sure if you should see her,' I
hesitated. 'Will the shock be too much for her?'
'Go and tell her I'm here, Ellen!' he said
impatiently. 'Don't make me suffer like this!'
I left him at the door, and went upstairs to
find Mr and Mrs Linton. They were sitting quietly
together, looking out over the peaceful valley.
The room, and the view, and the two people,
seemed so calm that I did not want to disturb
them. But I had to deliver my message.
'A man wants to see you, madam,' I muttered.
'I'll go downstairs and see
him then,' replied Catherine.
'Bring the tea up, Ellen, while
I'm away.' She left the room.
'Who is it, Ellen?' asked Mr Edgar.
'It's that Heathcliff, sir. You remember,
he used to live at Wuthering Heights.'
'What! The gipsy, who worked
on the farm?' he cried.
'Mrs Linton would be angry if she heard
you talking about him like that, sir.
She was very upset when he ran away.
She's very fond of him, you know.'
'Mr Edgar put his head out of the
window and called to his wife,
Don't stand there in the cold, love! Bring
the person in, if it's anyone special.'
Catherine rushed upstairs and into the room,
wild and breathless. She threw
her arms round her husband's neck.
'Oh Edgar darling! Heathcliffs come back!'
'Well, well,' said Mr Edgar crossly,
'there's no need to get excited.'
'I know you didn't like him,' she said, 'but
please, I beg you to be friends with him now.
Shall I ask him to come up?'
'You're suggesting inviting him up here,
into our sitting room? Don't you think
the kitchen is more suitable for him?'
Catherine looked at her husband,
half angry and half laughing. 'No,'
she said, 'I can't sit in the kitchen. Ellen,
bring two tables, one for your master and Miss
Isabella, the other for Heathcliff and myself.
We'll sit apart from them, as we're of a lower
class! Will that please you, Edgar darling?
Decide quickly! I must have him near me!'
'Ellen, you go and bring him up,' said Mr Edgar.
'And Catherine, try not to behave
foolishly. Remember, he's only a servant!'
When Heathcliff entered the sitting-room, I
was surprised to see how much he had changed.
He wore a confident, intelligent expression on
his face, and his manner was no longer rough.
Although I recognized the same black fire in
his eyes, the farm boy had become a gentleman.
Mr Edgar was as surprised as I was, but
welcomed Heathcliff as politely as he could.
However, he grew more and more annoyed
as he watched his wife's delighted face.
She could not take her eyes off Heathcliff.
'Tomorrow I won't be able to believe that
I've seen and touched you, Heathcliff!'
she cried, catching hold of his hands.
But how cruel of you to run away and keep
silent for four years, and never think of me!'
'I've thought of you more than you've thought of
me,' he replied quietly. 'I heard you had married,
Catherine, and I came, just to see you once, and
then take my revenge on your brother Hindley.
Your welcome may change my plans. You
know, I've had a bitter, hard life
since I last heard your voice, and if
I've survived, it's all because of you!'
'Catherine,' said Mr Edgar, trying to remain
polite, 'please pour out the tea, or it will
be cold. Mr Heathcliff will have a long walk to
wherever he's staying tonight, and I'm thirsty.'
But Catherine was too excited, and
Mr Edgar too angry, to drink any tea.
After a while their guest left. We discovered that
he had been invited to stay at Wuthering Heights,
by Hindley. I could not understand why
Hindley, who hated him, would want his company,
and I felt sure it would have been better for
all of us if Heathcliff had never come back.
Catherine could not keep her happiness to herself.
In the middle of the night she
woke me to talk about Heathcliff.
'I just can't sleep, Ellen!' she said.
And Edgar won't listen when I tell
him how happy I am! He's so selfish!'
'He never liked Heathcliff,' I replied, 'and
he'll be angry if you go on talking about him.
You think he's weak, but he could be as determined
as you, about something he thinks is important.'
'No!' she laughed. 'I have such confidence in
Edgar's love that I think I could kill him,
and he wouldn't blame me for it. He will have
to learn to accept Heathcliff as my friend.'
'Do you know why Heathcliff is
staying at Wuthering Heights?'
'Oh, yes. He explained that
he went there to look for me.
Hindley asked him to play cards, and when
he discovered Heathcliff had a lot of money,
invited him to stay there. You know how greedy
my brother is. He'll make Heathcliff pay rent,
and hope to win money from him at cards.
Heathcliff wants to stay there to be near me.
I'm so happy, Ellen! And I want
everyone around me to be happy too!'
Catherine behaved so sweetly to her husband in
the next few days that Thrushcross Grange seemed
full of sunshine, and in spite of his doubts, Mr
Edgar allowed Heathcliff to visit her regularly.
However, Heathcliffs visits produced a
result which none of us had expected.
Isabella, Mr Edgar's sister, a pretty girl of
eighteen, suddenly declared that she was in love
with Heathcliff. Mr Edgar, who loved her dearly,
was shocked. He knew that if he and Catherine had
no sons, Isabella would inherit the considerable
Linton fortune. He did not like the idea
of the fortune passing to Heathcliff, as
Isabella's husband. But more importantly,
he suspected that Heathcliff was hiding his true
wickedness under his gentlemanly appearance.
Catherine tried hard to persuade Isabella
that Heathcliff was not worth loving,
but poor Isabella was jealous of
Catherine's relationship with Heathcliff
and would not listen. Finally, Catherine
told Heathcliff himself that Isabella
was in love with him. She thought
she knew what his answer would be.
'How could I ever love that stupid girl?' he
asked. 'She has a miserable pale face, and weak
blue eyes, just like your husband! But... she will
inherit the family wealth from him, won't she?'
'That's true,' replied Catherine. 'But
don't think about that, Heathcliff.
I hope Edgar and I will have several
sons, and then they will inherit it.'
Catherine did not speak of this matter again,
but I am sure Heathcliff often thought about it.
I watched him carefully in the next few days.
I hoped he would do nothing to hurt Mr Edgar,
who was a kind master to me. I was worried, too,
about what was happening at Wuthering Heights.
Hindley and his son Hareton
seemed like lost sheep to me,
and I knew there was a wicked wolf just
waiting for the chance to attack them.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Catherine is ill
1783 The next time Heathcliff
came to Thrushcross Grange,
he met Isabella by chance in front of the
house. I was watching from the kitchen window,
as he went up to her, and, supposing that
no one else could see him, kissed her.
'Look, madam!' I cried to Catherine,
who was passing through the kitchen.
That devil Heathcliff told you he could never
love Miss Isabella! And now he's kissing her!'
So when Heathcliff entered the house,
Catherine was ready to scold him.
'Leave Isabella alone, Heathcliff!'
she ordered. 'You'll make Edgar angry!'
'You think I'm afraid of
that weak little creature?'
he growled. 'Anyway, what
difference does it make to you?
I can kiss her if she likes it. I'm not
your husband, you needn't be jealous of me!'
'I'm not jealous of you!' replied Catherine.
'If you like Isabella, you can
marry her. But do you like her?'
'It's you I want to talk about, Catherine.
You know you've treated me badly.
And I'm going to have my revenge!
Thank you for telling me Isabella's
secret. I swear I'll make good use of it!'
At this point I went to look for my master,
and told him that Catherine and Heathcliff
were quarrelling in the kitchen.
'How can my wife call that man a friend?'
he cried angrily. I've been too weak with
her. 'I can't allow him to visit her anymore.'
'Call two servants, Ellen.'
He went to the kitchen. I followed him,
telling the servants to wait in the hall.
'Catherine!' said Mr Edgar
to his wife as he entered.
'Do you think it's right to
listen to this wicked man's talk?'
'Have you been listening at the door, Edgar?'
asked Catherine coldly. Heathcliff
laughed, which made Mr Edgar even angrier.
'You, sir,' he said to Heathcliff, are poisoning
our family life. I should never have accepted you
as Catherine's friend. I must inform you that you
will never be allowed to enter this house again,
and that if you don't leave within
three minutes, you will be thrown out.'
'Well, well!' replied Heathcliff, looking
scornfully at Mr Edgar's small figure.
'So, you're going to throw
me out yourself, are you?'
My master looked towards the door. I realized he
wanted to call the servants, as he knew he was
not strong enough to fight Heathcliff alone.
But Catherine must have guessed his plan.
She hurried to the door and locked it.
Mr Edgar looked at her in angry surprise.
'You must fight him like a gentleman,
without anyone to help you!' she told her
husband. 'That'll teach you to scold me!'
Mr Edgar tried to get hold of the key,
but she threw it quickly into the hottest
part of the fire. He went very pale, and
could not stop his whole body trembling.
'Oh Edgar!' cried his wife. 'You've lost the
fight already! You aren't a man, you're a mouse!'
'So that,' said Heathcliff, pointing at Mr Edgar,
'is the thing you preferred to me, Catherine.
Is he crying, or is he going to die of fear?'
He went up to look more closely at Mr Edgar,
who suddenly recovered and hit Heathcliff
hard on the neck. While Heathcliff
was getting his breath back, Mr Edgar walked
out of the other kitchen door into the garden.
'Now you'll never be able to come here again,'
said Catherine to Heathcliff. 'Go away
quickly! He'll return with men and guns.'
Heathcliff was sensible enough to take her advice.
He broke down the locked door and escaped,
just as the master and his men returned.
Catherine, who was over-excited,
ordered me to go upstairs with her.
I hoped she would not discover that I had told
Mr Edgar about her quarrel with Heathcliff.
'I'm wild with anger, Ellen!' she said, when we
reached the sitting-room. 'All this trouble is
because of Isabella! Tell Edgar I'm in danger
of becoming seriously ill. I hope it's true,
I want to frighten him. He's upset me badly.
Why did he listen to us talking in the kitchen?
Heathcliff says wicked things,
but I know I can control him.
Well, if I can't have Heathcliff as my friend,
if Edgar is going to be mean and jealous,
I'll try to break both their hearts by breaking
my own. You must remind Edgar how quick tempered
I am, and what Dr Kenneth said about my
health. Edgar must let me do what I want!'
I did not feel sympathetic towards Catherine, and
certainly did not want to frighten my poor master
by telling him she was ill. As I was
leaving the room, however, he entered.
'Catherine,' he said, 'you must tell me
one thing. You must choose between me
and Heathcliff. Which do you intend to have?'
'Leave me alone!' she cried wildly.
'I'm ill, can't you see, I can't
even stand! Edgar, leave me!'
She fell, stiff and pale, on to the
floor. Mr Edgar looked very frightened.
'Don't worry, sir,'
I whispered to him. 'She told me she would try
to make you afraid by pretending to be ill.'
Unfortunately she heard me. She jumped
up, her hair loose and her eyes staring,
and rushed to her bedroom. We
heard the key turn in the lock.
For the next few days she refused to speak to
anyone, even me. I took her food up to her room,
but she would not eat. Mr Edgar spent his time
in the library, and did not ask about his wife.
He hoped, I suppose, that she would
come and ask him to forgive her.
But I knew she was too proud to do that.
On the third day she unlocked her door
and called me. She ate and drank eagerly,
then lay down again.
'Oh, why don't I die, since no one cares about
me!' she muttered. 'Edgar doesn't love me at all!
What is he doing all this time, Ellen?'
'He's reading books in the
library, madam,' I answered.
'Reading books!' she cried,
shocked. 'And I'm dying up here!
My God! Does he know how I've changed, how ill I
am? Can't you tell him I'm seriously ill, Ellen?'
'You forget, Mrs Linton, that you've
eaten tonight. I'm sure you'll feel
better tomorrow morning.' I still wanted to
make her realize how selfish she was being,
although I was a little worried
by her pale, almost ghostly face.
'I begin to see that you don't like me, Ellen.
How strange! I always thought everybody loved me!
Now they are all my enemies - Isabella and Edgar
and you! I'll die with cold faces around me!
I've had terrible dreams these past few nights,
you know. Open the window, Ellen! I'm so hot!'
I refused, as it was the middle
of winter. She was feverish.
'Who is that over there?' she asked, staring at
her own face in a mirror opposite her bed. I could
not make her understand it was herself, and I
began to be afraid that her illness was real.
'Stay with me, Ellen,' she cried, holding
my hand. 'I'm frightened of that face!
I'm frightened of being alone! I wish I were
in my bed at Wuthering Heights, with the wind
howling through the trees. Do let me feel a
breath of air from the moors, just one breath!'
I opened the window for a moment, then
closed it. The cold air seemed to calm her.
'I wish I were a young girl again, wild
and free, out on the moors with Heathcliff!
Open the window again, wider
this time! Why won't you?'
'Because I don't want you
to die of cold,' I replied.
'But it's my only chance of life!' she cried,
jumping out of bed and going to the window.
I tried to force her back to bed, but
her fever made her surprisingly strong.
We looked out together into the icy
darkness. There was no moon, and no
lights were visible anywhere. But Catherine
was sure she could see Wuthering Heights.
'Look!' she said. 'There's my old
home, and the churchyard near it.
I won't lie there alone, Heathcliff! I won't
rest until you're in the grave with me!'
I was still holding her back from the window, and
wondering what to do next, when Mr Edgar entered.
'Please help, sir,' I called, 'Mrs Linton is ill.'
'Catherine's ill?' he gasped. 'Shut
the window, Ellen! Catherine! Why-'
When he saw his wife's face, he was so shocked
that he stopped speaking and stared at her in
horror. She was almost unconscious
and did not recognize him at first.
'Ah,
it's you, is it, Edgar Linton?' she said after a
few moments. 'You don't come when you're wanted,
and now you come when you're not wanted!
But whatever you say, nothing can keep me
from my home, my place of rest, out there in
the open air, with a gravestone at my head!'
'She's feverish, sir, and
doesn't know what she's saying,'
I whispered. 'If she has food
and rest, she'll recover.'
'I want no further advice from you, Ellen Dean,'
said Mr Edgar coldly. You knew how
ill she was, and you didn't tell me!'
I ran downstairs and out of the
kitchen door to fetch the doctor.
I thought I heard the sound
of horses in the distance,
which seemed strange at two o'clock in the
morning. And when I found Dr Kenneth, he told me
someone had seen Isabella and Heathcliff meeting
secretly in the garden earlier that evening.
That night none of us slept. We all sat together
and waited, while the doctor stayed with his
patient. He told us he hoped that Catherine
would recover, if we kept her very quiet.
In the morning we discovered that Isabella's room
was empty. She had run away with Heathcliff! When
Mr Edgar heard the news, he just said, 'She chose
to go with him. Don't speak to me of her again.
I no longer think of her as my sister.'
CHAPTER NINE
Isabella's story
1784 For two months we heard
nothing of Isabella or Heathcliff.
During that time Catherine was dangerously
ill with brain fever, and Dr Kenneth warned us
that even if she recovered, her brain would
never return to normal. However she did seem
to get better, and no one could have been happier
than my master, when he saw her sitting up in bed
for the first time, and beginning to take an
interest in the people and things around her.
He loved her so much, and took such good care
of her, that I really thought she would recover.
There was another reason for her
to live. She was expecting a baby,
and we all hoped she would have a son,
who would inherit the Linton fortune.
Then Mr Edgar received a letter from Isabella,
telling him that she and Heathcliff were married.
With it was a long letter for me, which said:
Wuthering Heights
Dear Ellen,
I arrived here last night and
heard that Catherine is ill.
My brother refuses to write to me, so
you are the only one I can write to.
Tell Edgar I still love him and Catherine, and
want to return to Thrushcross Grange, but I can't!
The rest of this letter is for you alone, Ellen.
Two questions - how did you manage to get on
with the people in this house? They don't seem
human! And (this interests me very much) what is
Mr Heathcliff? A man? A madman? A devil? When
you come to visit me, you must explain to me
what sort of creature I've married. And you
must come very soon, with a message from Edgar.
Heathcliff brought me here last night.
This house is going to be my home, he says.
He disappeared as soon as we arrived, so I entered
the kitchen alone. What a miserable, depressing
place it is now, Ellen! By the fire stood a dirty
child. I realized he must be Catherine's nephew,
Hareton, and tried to shake his hand. But he
greeted me by swearing at me, so I went into
the hall to find somebody else. When I knocked at
another door, it was opened by a tall, thin man,
with long, dirty hair hanging down to his
shoulders. I knew this must be Hindley Earnshaw,
Catherine's brother and Hareton's father. His
eyes, and Hareton's, reminded me of Catherine.
'What do you want?' he asked roughly.
'My name was Isabella Linton,' I replied.
'Now I'm married to Mr Heathcliff.'
'Ah, so that devil has
returned! Good!' he growled.
You can imagine, Ellen, how unhappy I felt in
that unpleasant house. I knew that only four
miles away was my real home, Thrushcross Grange,
containing the only people I loved in the world.
But those four miles were like an
ocean, which I could not cross!
Don't tell Edgar or Catherine this, but I had
hoped to find a friend at Wuthering Heights,
someone to support me against Heathcliff. Now
I realized that no one here would help me.
After a long silence I said, 'Please ask a maid to
show me my bedroom. I'm tired after my journey.'
'We have no maids here,' he answered. 'Joseph
will show you Heathcliffs room, if you like.
And - and - you'd better lock
the bedroom door tonight!'
Why, Mr Earnshaw?' I asked. I did not
want to lock myself in with Heathcliff.
He brought out a gun, which
had a knife attached to it.
'Look at this,' he said. Every night
I try to open his bedroom door.
Up to now he's locked it. But one night
he'll forget, and then I'll kill him!'
'Why do you hate him so much?' I asked.
'Because he's taken everything from me!'
he shouted angrily. 'There's nothing
left for Hareton to inherit! But I'm going
to get it all back and his money too,
and then his blood. Then the
devil can have his soul!'
He seemed mad to me, Ellen. I left him,
and went to find the old servant, Joseph.
It seemed that Heathcliffs room was
locked, and there were no guest bedrooms,
so in the end I slept on a chair in the
child's room. What a welcome to my new home!
I know Heathcliff blames Edgar for Catherine's
illness. He has warned me he'll make me suffer
for it. Oh, I do hate him - I'm so miserable
- I've been such a fool! Don't tell anyone at
Thrushcross Grange about this, Ellen.
Come quickly - don't disappoint me!
Isabella
As soon as I had read this, I asked Mr Edgar if
I could take a message from him to his sister.
'You may visit her this afternoon, Ellen, if
you like. Tell her I'm not angry, just sorry
to have lost her. I can't imagine she will ever be
happy. I shall never visit her or write to her.'
When I arrived at Wuthering Heights that
afternoon, I was shocked to see how much worse
the house looked than when I used to live there. I
realized that Hindley did not care what conditions
he lived in, and Joseph clearly spent more time
praying than cleaning. Heathcliff and Isabella
were both in the main room. Heathcliff looked
more like a gentleman than I had ever seen him,
but his wife had not bothered to brush her hair
or change her dress. I had to explain to poor
Isabella that Mr Edgar had refused to write to
her. She cried a little when she heard that.
Then Heathcliff asked me question after
question about Catherine's illness.
'If you really love her,' I told him, 'you'll keep
away from her now. She mustn't be over-excited.
Her health will always be weak. And her
loving husband is a very good nurse to her!'
'Her loving husband!' repeated
Heathcliff scornfully.
'Don't compare my feeling for her with his!
No, Ellen, before you leave this house,
I'll make you promise to arrange a meeting
for me with Catherine. I must see her!'
'I'll never agree to that,' I said. 'She's just
beginning to recover. She's almost forgotten you,
and now you want to upset her again!'
'Ellen, you know as well as I do that she
can never forget me! If she thinks once
of Edgar Linton, she thinks a thousand
times of me! He can't love her as I can!
And Catherine has a heart as deep as mine!'
'Catherine and Edgar are very fond of each other!'
said Isabella suddenly. 'Don't
speak of my brother like that!'
'Your dear brother doesn't care enough about
you to write to you,' replied
Heathcliff, smiling sourly.
'That's because he doesn't know how much
I've suffered,' she answered quietly,
turning away to hide the tears on her face.
'Sir,' I said, 'it seems to me that Miss
Isabella, Mrs Heathcliff, I should say,
is unhappy. You must treat her kindly. Try to
look after her. Let her have a maid, for example.'
'I'm not going to be soft with
her,' he replied with a laugh.
'She was stupid enough to run away
with me. I never pretended to love her.
Now I think she's beginning to realize that
I scorn her. She's an even weaker fool than
her brother, but she's going to be useful
to me. That's why I'm keeping her with me.'
'Ellen, he says he married me
to have his revenge on Edgar!
But I won't let him carry out his plan, whatever
it is. I'll die, or I'll see him dead first!'
'You're getting violent, Isabella!'
said Heathcliff. Go upstairs now.
I want to speak to Ellen Dean in private. Go
on!' And he pushed her roughly out of the door.
'Don't you feel pity for her?' I asked,
when we were alone. 'Have you ever
felt pity for anybody in your life?'
'Why should I? She's just like an insect under
my foot. The more she cries, the more I enjoy
hurting her. Now, Ellen, listen. I'll wait every
day and every evening in the Grange garden,
until I find a chance to see Catherine. If I meet
Edgar Linton or his servants, I'll shoot them.
But don't you think it'd
be better to avoid a fight?
You could tell me when she'll be
alone. Then there'll be no violence.'
I argued and complained, and refused fifty
times, but in the end he forced me to agree.
I promised to let him know when Edgar Linton was
away from home. I suppose it was wrong of me,
but I hoped it would be Heathcliffs
last meeting with Catherine.
CHAPTER TEN
Heathcliff visits Catherine for the last time
1784 Heathcliff had given
me a letter for Catherine,
but I decided not to show it to her
until Mr Edgar was out of the house.
My chance came four days after my visit
to Wuthering Heights. As it was a Sunday,
Mr Edgar and all the servants went to church,
leaving me alone to look after Catherine.
She was sitting downstairs, by an open window,
enjoying the spring sunshine. Her appearance
had changed since her illness, but there
was a strange beauty in her pale face.
She did not read or sew any more, but used to
sit there silently, staring into the distance.
Her eyes seemed fixed on something far
away, something beyond normal sight.
I showed her the letter, but she looked confused
and could not seem to understand
it, so I had to explain.
'It's from Mr Heathcliff,' I said gently.
'He's in the garden, and wants to see you.
What shall I tell him?'
She said nothing, but bent
forward in her chair to listen.
We both heard someone coming through the hall.
Heathcliff had realized the house was almost
empty, and had found an open door. Catherine
looked eagerly towards the entrance to the room.
He appeared, and in two steps was by her side.
For five whole minutes he held her in his arms
and kissed her again and again. It gave
him great pain to look at her face.
He could see, as I could, that she would
never recover, that she was certain to die.
'Oh, Catherine! Oh, my life!
How can I bear it!' he cried.
'You and Edgar have broken my heart,' said
Catherine. 'And you both want me to pity you!
How strong you are, Heathcliff!
You'll live for years after my death!
Will you forget me, and be happy
with others, when I'm in my grave?'
'It's wicked of you to say that, Catherine. You
know your words will burn forever in my memory
after you've left me. You know
I could never forget you!'
'I don't want you to suffer
more than I do, Heathcliff.
I only want us to be together, always.'
Heathcliff turned away, his shoulders shaking.
'That isn't my Heathcliff,' Catherine said
to me. 'I'll always love my Heathcliff,
and take him with me. He's in my soul, you see.
Oh, Ellen, I do want to escape from this prison.
There's a beautiful world waiting for me out
there. You feel sorry for me now because I'm ill.
Well, very soon I'll feel sorry for
you, because I'll be beyond you all!'
Heathcliff turned towards her, his fierce eyes
wet. For a moment they looked at each other,
and then they were in each other's arms
again. No one could have separated them.
'How cruel you've been to me,
Catherine!' he cried wildly.
'You loved me, so why did you marry Edgar Linton?
It's all your fault! I haven't broken your heart,
you've broken it! And you've broken mine too!
Do you think I want to live after you are dead?'
'If I've done wrong, I'm dying
for it!' sobbed Catherine.
It's your fault too, Heathcliff! You left me,
remember? But I forgive you. Now forgive me!'
'It's hard to forgive, when I look at
your sad eyes, and feel your thin hands.
Kiss me again, Catherine! I forgive you for making
me suffer, but how can I forgive you for dying?'
Catherine sobbed quietly,
hiding her face in his shoulder,
and tears rolled down Heathcliffs dark face.
Suddenly I noticed, through the window,
the servants coming back from church.
I was afraid Mr Edgar would
find Heathcliff with Catherine.
'My master will be here in
a moment,' I warned them.
'I must go, Catherine,' said Heathcliff.
'No, no!' she screamed. 'Don't go! It's the
last time! Edgar won't hurt us! Heathcliff,
I'll die if you go!'
'All right, my darling, I'll stay. If
he shot me in your arms, I'd die happy.'
At that moment my master appeared
at the door. When he saw Heathcliff
holding his wife, he went pale with anger.
'Here, take care of her first,' said Heathcliff,
putting Catherine in her husband's arms,
'then speak to me later if you
wish.' He walked out of the house.
Catherine seemed to be unconscious, and Mr Edgar
was so worried about her that he
forgot about Heathcliff for the moment.
She recovered a little, but did not recognize
any of us, and was clearly very ill.
We put her to bed immediately, and at twelve
o'clock that night her daughter, Cathy, was born,
two months early. That's the young lady
you saw at Wuthering Heights, Mr Lockwood.
Two hours later, Catherine died, without
calling for Heathcliff, or recognizing Edgar.
My poor master was in the depths of despair.
I thought it was very unfortunate that
Catherine had only given him a daughter,
not a son. Now the Linton fortune would pass to
Isabella and her husband after Mr Edgar's death.
'Catherine's dead body lay peacefully on her bed.
In death she looked more beautiful than in
life. I wondered if she was now beyond us all',
as she had said, and hoped that
her soul had found a home with God.
In the morning I went to look for Heathcliff.
I found him in the Grange garden, where
he had been waiting for news all night.
'She's dead, I know!' he called to me as I came
closer. 'Don't cry, she doesn't need your tears!
Tell me - tell me, how did-?' He tried
to say her name, but could not manage it.
How did she die?' he said at last,
staring fiercely at me. Don't be
sorry for me, I don't want your pity!'
'Poor creature!' I thought. You have a heart just
like other men, but you are too proud to show it!'
Aloud I said, 'She died quietly, in her
sleep. Her life finished in a gentle dream.
I hope she wakes as calmly in the other world!'
'Where are you, Catherine?' he cried in despair.
'Don't leave me here, where I can't find you!
I pray that you will never rest while I'm
alive. You said I killed you - haunt me then!
Murdered people do haunt their murderers,
I believe. Come back as a ghost - drive me
mad - I don't care! Oh, God! I can't bear
it! I cannot live without you, my soul!'
He howled like a wild animal, and hit his
forehead several times against a tree,
until the wood was covered in blood. I knew
I could no longer help him, so I left him.
Catherine was buried the following Friday. Her
brother Hindley, although invited, did not come,
and Isabella was not invited, so it was only Mr
Edgar and the servants who attended the ceremony.
To our surprise, she was not buried
in the church with the Lintons,
nor with the Earnshaws. She lies in
an open corner of the churchyard,
where she can breathe the air from the
moors. Her husband's grave is next to hers.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Isabella escapes
1784 That Friday evening the wind changed,
and brought first rain, then snow.
Next morning the spring flowers were all hidden
under deep snow. Mr Edgar stayed in his room.
I was in the sitting-room with the baby, when I
was surprised to hear a girl's voice behind me.
I turned round, and saw it was Isabella
Heathcliff. I was quite shocked by her appearance.
Her hair was loose, and wet with snow and rain.
She wore a light silk dress and thin shoes,
which did not seem at all suitable
for a long walk in the snow.
Under her ear was a deep wound, which was
bleeding. Her face was scratched and bruised,
and she looked very tired. I could
see that she was expecting a baby.
'I've run all the way here from Wuthering
Heights,' she said, gasping for breath.
'I couldn't count how many times I've fallen
down! Ellen, please ask a maid to find some
dry clothes for me, and then I'll go on
to the village. I'm not staying here.'
'First, my dear young lady,' I told her,
'you'll get warm and dry, and I'll put a bandage
on that wound. Then we'll have some tea.'
She was so exhausted that she let
me help her without protesting,
and finally we sat down together
near the fire with our cups of tea.
'Oh, Ellen,' she said, 'I cried bitterly
when I heard of Catherine's death, you know.
And Heathcliff is desperately sad!
But I can't feel sorry for him.
This is the last thing of his I've got,' and
she took off her gold wedding-ring and threw
it in the fire. I'll never go back to him. But
I can't stay here, in case he comes to find me.
And anyway I don't want to beg for Edgar's help,
or make trouble for him. To escape from Heathcliff
I must go a long way away. How could
Catherine have liked him, Ellen?
I wish he would die, and then
I could forget him completely!'
'Don't say that,' I protested, he's a human
being. There are worse men than him in the world!'
'He isn't human,' she replied. 'I gave
him my heart, and he destroyed it,
so I can't feel pity for him. But I
must tell you how I managed to escape.
Hindley Earnshaw should have been at Catherine's
burial yesterday, but he had been drinking so
much that he couldn't go. Last night he and I were
sitting silently in the kitchen at about midnight,
when Heathcliff came home. Hindley decided to lock
the doors so that Heathcliff could not get in.
He told me his plan was to murder his hated guest
that night, with the weapon he had shown me.
I hate Heathcliff too, but I could not
agree to murder, so I called out a warning
from the kitchen window. Heathcliff swore
horribly at me and broke one of the windows.
Hindley put his right arm out through the hole,
with the gun in it, and aimed it at his enemy.
But before he could fire, Heathcliff
caught hold of the gun and pulled it
away from Hindley. The knife cut into
Hindley's wrist, and blood poured out.
Heathcliff jumped into the
kitchen through the window,
and started kicking and hitting Hindley, who
was lying unconscious on the kitchen floor.
I ran off to find Joseph. When we
came back, Heathcliff was putting
a bandage on Hindley's wrist. Joseph
was shocked at the sight of his master,
and would have gone to the police, if Heathcliff
hadn't forced me to describe what happened.
I had to agree that Hindley had
certainly attacked Heathcliff first.
The next day, I decided to have my revenge on
Heathcliff, by telling Hindley that 'that devil'
had hit and kicked him when he was unconscious.
And I told Heathcliff to his face that he could
never have made Catherine happy, if she had been
his wife. This made him so angry that he threw
a knife at me, which cut my neck, and then he
rushed towards me, swearing violently. I knew
I had to get away quickly, and as I ran out of the
kitchen, I saw Hindley attack Heathcliff. Both of
them were rolling on the floor, fighting. I came
over the moors through the snow to the Grange.
At last I'm free! And I shall never, never
spend another night at Wuthering Heights.'
After drinking her tea, Isabella
left the Grange. From our village
she travelled by coach to the
south, where she made her new home
near London. There, a few months later,
she had a son. She called him Linton.
Heathcliff must have discovered
this from the servants.
One day when I saw him in the village, he said,
'I hear I've got a son, Ellen, whose name's
Linton! I suppose Isabella wants me to hate him!
She can keep him for the moment. But tell Edgar
Linton I'll have the boy one day! He's mine!'
After Catherine's death my poor master, Mr Edgar,
was a changed man. He no longer went to church,
or saw any friends. He occasionally went for
lonely walks on the moors, and regularly visited
his wife's grave. But fortunately Catherine had
left him something of herself, her daughter Cathy.
This tiny child soon won his heart.
It's strange, Mr Lockwood, to compare Hindley
and Edgar. They both lost their wives, and were
left with a child. Hindley did not believe in
God, and showed no interest in his son Hareton.
But Edgar believed, and loved
his daughter Cathy deeply.
Hindley himself died six months
after his sister Catherine.
We never discovered exactly what happened, but
Heathcliff said he had drunk himself to death.
It appeared that Heathcliff had won Hindley's
house, land and money from him when playing cards,
so he was now the master of Wuthering Heights.
Hareton inherited nothing from his father,
and could only stay on at
Wuthering Heights as a servant,
working for the man who had
been his father's enemy.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Bringing up Cathy
1797 During the next twelve years I was
happier than I had ever been before.
All my time was spent looking after little
Cathy, who brought sunshine into our lives.
She was a real beauty, with the Earnshaws'
dark eyes and the Lintons' fair skin.
She wasn't as proud and quick-tempered as her
mother, but she was used to getting what she
wanted. Her father loved her so much that he
gave her everything, and never scolded her.
Until she was thirteen she had
never been outside the Grange garden
alone. She knew nothing of Wuthering
Heights or Heathcliff. She often asked me
about the hills in the distance, beyond the
moors, and wanted to ride her pony there. I
knew the master would not let her leave
the safety of the Grange to go so far,
especially as the road to the hills passed
close to Wuthering Heights. So I always told
her she would be able to go there when she was
older. I did not know what she was planning.
Mr Edgar received a letter
from his sister Isabella.
She wrote that she was dying of a fever, and asked
him to visit her for the first and last time.
She also wanted him to take care
of her son Linton after her death.
Although my master hated travelling, he did
not hesitate to do as she requested. He told me
to look after Cathy carefully, and left at once.
He was away for three weeks. Cathy
did not cause me any trouble at first.
She spent her days walking her dogs and
riding her pony in the large garden.
But one day she asked if she
could stay out the whole day,
and away she went on her little pony,
with her two dogs running behind.
There was no sign of her at tea-time,
and I began to be seriously worried.
I went outside to look for her. At the gate I
found a workman, who had seen her jump the low
wall separating the garden from the road, and then
ride on towards the hills and Wuthering Heights.
I was very frightened now. She
could be lost on the moors!
She could have tried to
climb the hills, and fallen!
I walked across the moors as fast as I could,
and arrived breathless at Wuthering Heights.
How glad I was to see one of her dogs lying
outside the kitchen door! I knocked loudly,
and Zillah let me in. I knew she had been
the housekeeper there since Hindley's death.
'Ah,' she said, 'you've come for your little
mistress! She's here, quite safe! The master,
Mr Heathcliff, isn't here. He
won't be back for a while.'
Cathy was sitting comfortably in the kitchen,
talking eagerly to Hareton. He was now
a big, strong young man of eighteen,
who was staring rather stupidly at her.
I was delighted to find her again, but
I pretended to be angry to punish her.
'Well, miss! You are wicked,
going such a long way all alone!
I've been all over the moors looking
for you! Your father will be angry!'
'What have I done?' she sobbed,
suddenly frightened. 'Father
didn't forbid me to leave the Grange garden! He
won't scold me, Ellen. He's never cross, like you!
And I've been to the hills, Ellen! This - man
- showed me, because I didn't know the way.'
I made her put on her hat and prepare to leave.
'Whose house is this?' she asked suddenly.
'It's your father's, isn't it?'
she added, turning to Hareton.
'No,' he replied, looking
down. His face went very red.
'Whose then - your master's?' she asked.
He swore, and turned away.
'Ellen, he didn't say "miss" to me. Servants
should always say "miss", shouldn't they?'
Hareton frowned and looked
very angry, but said nothing.
'You, get my horse,' she ordered him. 'Hurry!'
'What the devil do you mean? I'm
not your servant!' he growled.
'You see, Miss Cathy? Nice words
to be used to a young lady!
Now come along, let's fetch
the pony and leave,' I said.
'But Ellen,' she cried, staring horrified at him,
'how dare he speak to me like
that! He must do as I tell him!'
'He's not your servant, miss,' said Zillah,
who had been listening to the
conversation. 'He's your cousin.'
'He can't be my cousin!' cried Cathy, with a
scornful laugh. 'Father has gone to fetch my
cousin from London. He's a gentleman's
son, not - not a farm worker like him!'
She pointed at poor Hareton,
whose clothes were old and dirty.
I was very annoyed with her and Zillah. Now
Heathcliff would hear about his son's arrival,
which we had hoped to keep secret from him. And
Cathy would certainly ask her father whether she
had a cousin at Wuthering Heights. On our way home
I explained to her that if her father discovered
she had visited Wuthering Heights, he would
perhaps be so angry with me that he would send
me away. She could not bear to think of that, so
she promised to keep her visit a secret from him.
We heard from Mr Edgar that his sister had died,
and that he was returning soon with his
young nephew. Cathy was wild with excitement.
She would see her dear father again, and
have a cousin of the same age to play with.
But when the coach arrived, young Linton had to be
carried into the house. He was a pale, thin boy,
who looked very like Mr Edgar. He seemed so weak
that I wondered how long he would live. I thought
he would have no chance of life if his father
Heathcliff took him to live at Wuthering Heights.
In fact Linton only stayed one night with
us. Later that evening Heathcliffs servant
Joseph arrived and asked to speak
to the master. Although it was late
and Mr Edgar was tired after his journey, Joseph
insisted, so I took him to the master's room.
'Heathcliff has sent me for his son, and
I can't go back without him,' he said.
Mr Edgar was silent for a moment. On his
face was an expression of deep sadness. He
had hoped to keep Linton with him, as Isabella had
wished. But he could not refuse the boy's father.
'Tell Mr Heathcliff,' he said calmly, that
Ellen will take his son to Wuthering Heights
tomorrow. He's asleep at the
moment, and I won't disturb him.'
'No!' said Joseph, banging the table with
his hand. 'I must take him back now!'
'Not tonight!' answered Mr Edgar. 'Leave the
house now, and tell your master what I said!'
'Very well!' shouted Joseph, as he walked out.
'If he doesn't arrive early in the
morning, Heathcliff will come for him!'
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Heathcliffs son at Wuthering Heights
1797 Linton was very surprised to be
woken so early, and told that he had
another journey to make, before breakfast. As
we rode the four miles to Wuthering Heights,
he kept asking me questions about his new
home, and the father he had never seen.
When we arrived, Heathcliff, Hareton, and Joseph
all came out of the house to inspect the child.
'Master, that's not a boy,' said Joseph after a
while. 'Look at that white skin and fair hair!
Mr Edgar's sent you his daughter instead!'
'God! What a beautiful creature!'
laughed Heathcliff scornfully.
'That's worse than I expected!'
I helped the trembling child off the horse
and into the house. Heathcliff
took him roughly by the arm.
'I hope you'll be kind to him, Mr Heathcliff,'
I said. He's weak, and ill. And
he's all the family you've got!'
'Don't worry, Ellen,' replied Heathcliff with a
smile. As Isabella's son he'll inherit Thrushcross
Grange one day, and I don't want him to die
before that. He'll be educated as a gentleman.
But I'm bitterly disappointed at having
such a weak, crying baby for a son!'
So poor Linton was left in his father's
care. At first Cathy was miserable,
because she would not now have anyone
to play with, but she soon forgot him.
Whenever I met Zillah, the housekeeper, in
the village, I used to ask her about Linton.
'He's often ill,' she told me. 'And so
selfish! He has to have a fire even in summer!
He calls for cakes and hot drinks all the time.
He only ever thinks of himself. Mr Heathcliff
can't bear being in the same room as him!'
Several years passed without any more news of
Linton. In 1800 Cathy reached the age of sixteen.
We never celebrated her birthday,
because it was also the day her
mother died. On this particular day she
came downstairs, dressed for going out,
and suggested a walk on the moors
with me. Her father gave permission.
It was a lovely spring morning, and I
was very happy walking in the sunshine,
watching Cathy running ahead of me. But
we had walked further than I had realized,
and I called to her to come back.
She did not seem to hear me.
We were on the moors, close to Wuthering Heights,
when I caught sight of two men talking to her.
I recognized Heathcliff and Hareton at
once. I hurried to catch up with her.
'Miss Cathy,' I said breathlessly, 'we must
go home. Your father will be getting worried.'
'No, he won't, Ellen. This gentleman wants
me to go to his house and meet his son.
He says we've already met, but I don't
remember, do you? Let's go, Ellen!'
Although I protested, she and Hareton
were already halfway to Wuthering Heights.
Heathcliff and I followed behind.
'It's very bad of you, Mr Heathcliff,'
I scolded him. 'Mr Edgar will blame
me for letting her go to your house.'
'I want her to see Linton, Ellen,'
he replied. 'Listen to my plan.
It's really a very generous one. I
want the two cousins to fall in love
and marry. You know Cathy won't inherit
anything from her father. My son Linton
will inherit all the Linton fortune when Edgar
dies. If she marries Linton, she'll be wealthy.
Of course, if Linton dies, then the money
comes to me, as his only other relation.'
I was still angry with Heathcliff, but it was too
late to stop Cathy entering Wuthering Heights.
She was delighted to rediscover her cousin
Linton, who was keeping warm by the fire.
'If he is my cousin, and you are his father,'
she said to Heathcliff, smiling, then
you must be my uncle! Why don't
you ever visit us at the Grange?'
'I visited it once or twice too
often before you were born,' he said.
'I must tell you that I quarrelled
violently with your father once.
He hates me, and if you tell him you
want to come here, he'll forbid it.'
'Well, if I can't come here, Linton can come to
visit me at the Grange,' suggested Cathy happily.
'It'll be too far for me,' said her cousin
weakly. 'It would kill me to walk four miles.'
Heathcliff looked scornfully at his son.
'I don't think my plan will ever succeed, Ellen!'
he whispered to me. 'Who would fall in love with a
selfish baby like that?' He went to the kitchen
door and called, Hareton! Come and take Miss
Cathy round the farm.' Cathy was eager to see
the animals, and she and Hareton went out.
As we watched them through the kitchen window,
Heathcliff seemed to be thinking aloud.
'I've taken my revenge on his father, by
making Hareton work for me. I treat him badly,
as they used to do to me, and he suffers,
as I used to. He's intelligent, and strong,
and handsome, but I've taught him to scorn those
qualities. So now he's just an uneducated farm
worker, and knows nothing of the world. That's
how he'll always be. And my son? He's stupid,
and weak, and ill. But he's a gentleman,
and he'll marry Cathy, and he'll be rich!'
Meanwhile Linton had got up from his armchair
and gone out to join Cathy and Hareton.
Through the open window I
could hear the two younger ones
laughing at Hareton's coarse way of speaking.
I began to dislike Linton rather than pity him.
When we arrived back at the Grange,
Cathy told her father about the visit.
He did not want to frighten her, and, in my
opinion, did not explain clearly enough why
she should never communicate with Linton again. At
the time she seemed to accept her father's wish.
During the next few weeks, however,
I noticed Cathy's behaviour change.
She was always writing on little pieces of paper,
which she kept in a locked drawer in her room,
and every morning she got up surprisingly early
to go down to the kitchen. I suspected something,
and one day I decided to break open her drawer.
In it I was horrified to find a whole pile of
love letters from Linton. The two cousins had been
writing to each other in secret for several weeks,
and Cathy had used the milkman as a messenger.
I told her at once that I knew her secret, and
made her promise not to send or receive any more
letters. We burnt Linton's letters together.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Secret visits
1800 The months passed, and soon it was autumn. Mr
Edgar caught a bad cold, which seemed to get worse
and worse. He stayed indoors the whole winter,
so Cathy only had me as a companion on her walks.
She had become very quiet and sad since
her relationship with Linton had ended,
and was very worried about her father's illness.
One day when we were walking in the
Grange garden, I noticed her crying.
'Cathy, what's the matter, love?' I asked.
'Oh, Ellen,' she sobbed, what shall I do if
Father dies? And if you die? I'll be left alone!'
'I hope he and I have years more of life ahead
of us. All you need do is look after your father;
and let him see you're cheerful.
But I think he would be really ill
if he thought you loved Linton, whose
father would like to see Mr Edgar dead.'
'I'll never, never do anything to
worry or annoy Father,' she promised.
I only want him to recover. I love him more than
anyone else in the world, more than myself!'
Just then
we reached the gate, and I saw a gentleman on
a horse looking over it. It was Heathcliff.
'Miss Linton!' he called. 'There's
something I must tell you!'
'I won't listen,' answered Cathy. Father
and Ellen both say you're a wicked man.'
'But this is about my son Linton, not
me. What a trick you played on him!
You wrote him all those love letters, and then I
suppose you got tired of it, and stopped! Well,
you've broken poor Linton's heart.
I swear, he's dying of love for you,
and he'll be in the grave by next summer unless
you help him! Be generous, come and visit him.
I'll be away all next week, so your
father won't be angry if you come.'
He rode away. Although I tried to persuade Cathy
that Heathcliff could not be telling the truth,
my young mistress was very upset, and
determined to discover how Linton was.
The next morning we rode to Wuthering Heights.
We found Linton alone, lying on a sofa. He
looked feverish and ill, and had a bad cough.
'Will you shut the door?' he
said crossly, as we entered.
'It's so cold! No, Cathy, I can't
breathe if you kiss me! I want a drink.'
Cathy poured him a glass of water.
'And are you glad to see me,
Linton?' she asked hopefully.
'Yes, I am,' he replied. 'But you should
have come before! My father swore at me,
and said it was my fault you didn't
come. Will you come and visit me again?'
'Yes, Linton,' Cathy said gently, holding
his hand. If Father agreed, I'd spend half
my time with you. I wish you were my brother,
then we could spend all our time together!'
'But my father says you would love me best if
you were my wife, so that would be better.'
'I'd never love anybody more than Father,' she
replied seriously. 'Sometimes men hate their
wives, like your father. He hated your mother,
my aunt Isabella. That's why she left him.'
'That's not true!' cried the boy. 'Anyway, your
mother hated your father! And she loved mine!'
'You're lying! I hate you!' she shouted
angrily, and gave the sofa a violent push.
He fell back, and started coughing so
badly that even I was frightened. At last
he recovered. Cathy was crying in a corner,
afraid that she had really hurt him.
'How do you feel now, Linton?' she asked after
a while. I'm sorry, I didn't mean to hurt you.'
'I wish you felt as ill as I do, you cruel
thing! And I was better today, before you came!'
His voice was full of pity for himself.
'We must go,' I said. 'You can see, Miss Cathy,
that he isn't dying of love for you! It's
not your fault that he's ill. Come along!'
But I could not stop Cathy whispering something
in Linton's ear, before we left the room.
On the way home I told her I would
not allow her to visit him again.
'He's a selfish child, Miss Cathy, and I
don't think he'll live till he's twenty.
I'm glad you're not going to marry him.'
'Cathy looked sad. I'm sure he'd recover
if I looked after him. And I don't think
we'd quarrel if we knew each other better.'
'Well, miss, if you try to go there again,
with or without me, I'll tell your father.'
But the next day I fell ill, and had to
stay in bed for three weeks, which was
very unusual for me. My little mistress
went from her father's bedroom to mine,
and back again, and looked after us both with
the greatest care. But I never wondered what
she did in the evenings, when Mr Edgar had
gone to bed, and I no longer needed her.
I only discovered the truth on the first day
I was able to get up. In the evening I asked
her to read to me, and was surprised how sleepy
she seemed. She went to bed early. I felt rather
worried about her health, and went to her room
an hour later to see if she needed anything.
Her bedroom was empty. I sat there in
the dark, waiting for her to return.
When she arrived, shaking the snow off her
shoes, she was shocked to find me there.
I guessed where she had been, but
I made her tell me the whole story.
Every night since I had been ill, she had
ridden to Wuthering Heights and spent the
evening with her cousin. Sometimes she was
happy with Linton, when he was cheerful and
less selfish, but most of the time she
was miserable. However, she insisted
that the visits should continue, because
Linton needed her, and she wanted to see him.
Although she begged me to
say nothing to her father,
I went straight to the master and told him. He
forbade her to visit Wuthering Heights again.
She had to obey her father,
although it made her very sad.
Well, Mr Lockwood, all this happened only about
a year ago. I never thought I would be telling
a stranger this story! But who knows how long
you'll be a stranger? You're too young to live
alone for long, and no one could see Cathy and
not love her. Anyway, I'll continue my story.'
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
A Trap
A Few days after the master had forbidden Cathy
to visit Linton, he asked my opinion of the boy.
'Tell me honestly, Ellen, what
do you think of his character?'
'Well, sir, I don't think
he's wicked, like his father.
But you'll have plenty of time to get to
know him, sir. He's too young to marry yet.'
Mr Edgar walked to the window and looked out.
It was a misty February evening,
but the churchyard was just visible.
'I've often prayed for death, Ellen. I've
been very happy with my little Cathy.
But I've been just as happy lying, through
the long June evenings, on her mother's grave,
and looking forward to the moment
when I can join Catherine there!
I haven't got much time left, Ellen. What can I do
for Cathy before I die? Should she marry Linton? I
wouldn't mind him being Heathcliffs son, if only
he loved her and could be a good husband to her.'
'God will show us what to do, sir,' I replied.
In the spring Mr Edgar was still ill, and
he continued to worry about Cathy's future.
One day he wrote to Linton
inviting him to visit the Grange.
Linton wrote a long letter back, explaining
that his father would not allow him to do that.
He begged his uncle to let him meet Cathy
for a walk or a ride on the moors between
the Grange and Wuthering Heights, as
they could not meet in either house.
Mr Edgar refused at first, and
Linton sent him several more letters.
I am sure they had all been carefully checked
by Heathcliff before they were posted.
Finally Mr Edgar agreed. He hoped
that, if Cathy married Linton,
who would inherit the Linton fortune, she would
at least be able to remain in her family home.
He had no idea that Linton was seriously ill.
Neither did I. I never imagined that a father
could treat a dying child as cruelly and wickedly
as we later discovered Heathcliff had done.
It was a hot, sunny day in summer when Cathy
and I rode out to meet her cousin. We were both
shocked to discover that he could neither
ride nor walk, and was lying on the grass,
waiting for us. He looked even paler and
weaker than the last time I had seen him.
During our meeting he did not seem interested in
Cathy or her news. Cathy noticed this immediately.
'Well, Linton,' she said after a while, you don't
want to talk to me, so I think I'll go home.'
'No, no!' he cried, getting quite excited.
'Not yet! Stay - at least another half-hour!
My father will be angry
with me if you leave early!'
'I suppose we can stay a few
minutes longer,' said Cathy.
We waited, talking to each other quietly
while Linton slept a little.
Sometimes he cried out in pain.
'Do you think his health is better
now than before?' whispered Cathy.
'I'm sorry, Miss Cathy, I think
it's much worse,' I answered.
Cathy called her pony, and
the sound woke Linton up.
'If you see my father,' he said, hesitating,
'could you tell him I've been cheerful?
He'll be here soon!' And
he looked round in terror.
'I'll be here next Thursday!' cried Cathy,
as she jumped on her pony. Come on, Ellen!'
In the week that followed, Mr
Edgar's illness grew worse every day.
Cathy could not avoid realizing how serious
it was, and sat by his bedside day and night,
looking sad and pale. Her father's
room had become her whole world.
On Thursday I thought a ride in the fresh air
would be good for her, and Mr Edgar gladly gave
her permission to see Linton. He was hoping that
she would not be left alone after his death.
I did not want to worry him in his last moments,
so I did not tell him that Linton was also dying.
We rode on to the moors and found Linton
lying in the same place as before.
He was looking very frightened.
'I thought you weren't going to come!' he said.
'Why won't you be honest?' cried Cathy at
once. 'Why have you brought me here again,
if you don't want to see me? My father's
very ill and I should be with him.'
Tears rolled down Linton's
face. He seemed terrified.
'Oh, I can't bear it!' he sobbed. Cathy, I daren't
explain! But if you leave me, he'll kill me!
Dear Cathy, my life is in your hands!
Kind, sweet Cathy, perhaps you will agree,
and then he won't hurt me!'
Cathy was no longer impatient. 'Agree
to what, Linton?' she asked gently.
'Tell me everything! You wouldn't do anything to
hurt me, would you, Linton? I'm your best friend.'
'I daren't tell you! My father-' the boy gasped.
Just then Heathcliff appeared. He did not look
at Cathy and Linton, who continued talking
to each other, but he spoke quietly to me.
'Ellen, how is Edgar? Is he
dying, as the villagers say?'
'It's true, the master is dying,' I answered.
'That boy over there is dying too. I only hope
Edgar dies before him. If Linton dies first,
my plan will fail.' He shouted angrily to his son,
Get up, Linton!' and then said politely to Cathy,
'Miss Cathy, would you help him back
to the house. He can't walk far alone.'
'Father has forbidden me to
enter your house,' said Cathy.
'Well, come along, Linton. I'll have to
take you home then,' said Heathcliff.
'No! No! No! Please, Cathy! You must
come with me!' screamed Linton wildly.
He held desperately on to her arm.
Cathy could not refuse the boy, who
seemed almost mad with fear. So we all
walked the few steps to Wuthering Heights.
When we had entered the house, however,
I was horrified to see Heathcliff lock
the front door. The key was in his hand.
'Hareton, Joseph and Zillah are all out of the
house,' he said calmly, so we are quite alone.'
'Give me that key!' cried Cathy
angrily. 'I'm not afraid of you!'
She took hold of his closed hand and bit
it. He hit her violently several times, on
both sides of the head, and she fell into a chair,
trembling. I rushed at him, but he pushed me away.
'Cry as much as you like, Miss Cathy,' he
said. 'In a few days I'll be your father,
and I'll punish you just like
that, as often as necessary!'
When Heathcliff went out to look for our horses,
Cathy and I hurried round the
kitchen looking for a way to escape.
But all the doors and windows were locked. Linton
was sitting calmly in a chair near the fire,
happy that he was not being punished this time. We
persuaded him to explain his father's plan to us.
'Father is afraid I'll die soon, you see, so
he wants us to be married tomorrow morning.
You'll have to stay here all night, Cathy. Then
perhaps he'll let you go home in the morning.'
'You marry this beautiful, healthy young lady?'
I cried. You must be mad! And wicked too! You and
your father have tricked us into coming here!'
And I shook him until he started coughing.
'I must go home now. Father will
be worried already,' said Cathy.
I love Father better than you, Linton!'
Heathcliff returned and sent
his son upstairs to bed.
'Mr Heathcliff,' begged Cathy, 'Father
will be miserable if I don't go home.
Please let me go. I promise to marry Linton.
Father would like it, and I love him.
Why do you force me to do something I want to do?'
'He can't force you!' I cried.
'I'll go to the police!'
'To the devil with you, Ellen! Miss
Cathy, I'm delighted that your father
will be miserable. In that case you will
certainly stay here for twenty-four hours.
You won't leave here until you've
kept your promise to marry Linton.'
'Please send Ellen to let Father know
I'm safe!' sobbed Cathy bitterly.
'Poor Father! He'll think we're lost!'
'Your father must have hated
you when you came into the world
(I did, at least), and he'll hate you as he
leaves it. Go on crying. That's what you'll
be doing when you're Linton's wife. He'll
make a cruel, selfish husband, I think.'
Heathcliff took us upstairs to Zillah's room,
where we spent the night, locked in. Neither of
us could sleep. At seven the following morning
he came to fetch Cathy, and took her away. From
that moment I saw nobody except Hareton, who
brought me food, for four whole days and nights.
On the fifth morning Zillah came into the
room. She was surprised and pleased to see me,
and told me the villagers all thought
Cathy and I had got lost on the moors,
and died, four days ago. I ran
out of the room to look for Cathy.
The big kitchen was full of sunshine, and the door
was open, but the only person there was Linton.
'Where is she? Where is
Miss Cathy?' I cried wildly.
'Upstairs, in a locked room,' he
replied calmly, eating a piece of sugar.
'We won't let her go yet. Father says I shouldn't
be soft with Cathy. We've had the wedding
ceremony, so she's my wife now, and must stay
with me. I don't care if she cries, or is ill!'
'Have you forgotten her kindness to you last
winter, when you wrote that you loved her,
and she used to come through wind and snow to see
you? Now you believe your father's lies about her!
And you leave her alone, ill and crying
in a strange house! You pity yourself,
but you won't pity her! What a
heartless, selfish boy you are!'
'I can't stay with her! She cries so much I can't
bear it! I can't sleep with all that noise. She
promised that if I gave her the key to our room,
she'd give me all her nice books, and her pony,
but I told her she had nothing to give. They're
all mine, or they'll belong to me very soon.
And then she cried, and took a little gold case
from around her neck. Inside were two pictures,
one of her mother and one of her father. I wanted
to take them both from her, but she wouldn't let
me, so I screamed for help. My father came, and
ordered her to give him the pictures and the case.
When she refused, he - he hit her
on the face and knocked her down,
and broke the gold case under his foot.
He took away the picture of her mother.'
'And were you pleased to see
Miss Cathy hurt?' I asked.
'My father was right to punish her. But I
didn't like seeing her mouth full of blood.
She can't speak because of the pain. Now
you've made me tired with all this talking!
You won't find the key to the room! Go away!'
As there seemed to be no chance of
persuading him to help her escape,
I decided to go back to the Grange as
quickly as possible, and rescue her later.
What a welcome I received from the servants
at the Grange, who thought I was dead! But
I did not have time to tell them my story. I went
straight to my master's room. He was lying in bed,
very weak and close to death. I told
him how Heathcliff had trapped us,
and that Cathy was probably married to Linton
by now. Mr Edgar realized that his enemy
wanted to get hold of the Linton
fortune, through his son. He asked me
to send for his lawyer, to make arrangements so
that Cathy would not lose all her inheritance.
I did as he asked, but the lawyer sent a message,
saying that he could not come until the next day.
I also sent four strong men with
weapons to Wuthering Heights,
to demand my young lady's freedom. I was
very angry when they returned without her,
because Heathcliff had sent them away.
But I needn't have worried. In the middle of the
night, as I was taking some water to the master,
I heard a knock on the front door, and
went to open it. It was my little mistress!
'Ellen, Ellen!' she sobbed.
'Is Father still alive?'
'Yes,' I cried, 'and thank God
you're safe with us again!'
'I managed to make Linton help me escape
from the room! Now I must see Father!'
'I could not bear to be present at their
meeting. I waited outside the bedroom door.
But they were both calm. Cathy's despair was
as silent as her father's happiness. He died
in perfect peace, Mr Lockwood.
Kissing her, he whispered,
I'm going to join her, and you, dear child,
will join us!' He did not move or speak again.
Cathy did not cry, but sat silently by
his dead body all morning. At lunch-time
the lawyer arrived, too late to help Cathy.
Heathcliff had bribed him to stay away.
He gave us Heathcliffs orders. All
the servants except me had to leave.
Cathy, Mrs Heathcliff now, was only allowed to
stay at the Grange until her father was buried.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Cathy becomes a widow
1800-1 On the evening after the
burial, Heathcliff came to fetch Cathy.
'Why not let her stay here with me?' I begged.
'I'm looking for someone to
rent the Grange from me,'
he answered. 'You'll stay on
here as housekeeper, Ellen,
but Cathy must come to Wuthering Heights.
From now on she'll have to work for her food.'
'I shall work,' replied Cathy. And I'll look after
Linton. He's all I've got to love in the world.
I'm just sorry for you, Mr Heathcliff.
You have nobody to love you! You are as
lonely and miserable as the devil! Nobody will
cry for you when you die! I'm glad I'm not you!'
'Go and get your clothes, you wicked girl,'
he said. 'We'll be leaving in a few minutes.'
When she had gone, he walked across the room
to look at the picture of Cathy's mother,
Catherine, which was hanging on the wall.
'Do you know what I did yesterday, Ellen?' he
said, turning quickly away from the picture.
'I went to the churchyard, and asked the man
who was digging Edgar's grave to open the lid
of Catherine's coffin for me. Her face looked
just the same! I could not stop looking at her.
When the man closed the lid, I broke open one side
of her coffin, the side away from Edgar's grave,
and covered it up with earth. And I bribed the
man to bury me there when I die, next to her,
and to take the side of my coffin away too, so
that I shall have her in my arms, not Edgar!'
'You were very wicked, Mr
Heathcliff, to disturb the dead!'
'I disturbed nobody, Ellen, and I feel much
happier now. She is the one who has disturbed me.
For eighteen years she has haunted me. You know I
was wild, almost mad, after she died. For days I
prayed for her ghost to return to me. On the day
of her burial, I went to her grave in the evening.
There was a bitter wind, and snow on the ground. I
wanted so much to have her in my arms again! So I
dug down through the loose earth to her coffin,
and was about to pull the lid off, when I felt
a warm breath on my face. She seemed to be with
me, not in the earth, but close to me. I was
so happy that she was with me again! I filled in
the grave, and ran eagerly home to the Heights.
I looked impatiently round for her. I
could feel her but I could not see her!
And since then, she has played
plenty of tricks on me like that.
When I sleep in her bedroom, I can hear her
outside the window, or entering the room,
or even breathing close to me, but when I
open my eyes, I'm always disappointed. Slowly,
slowly, she's killing me, with the ghost
of a hope that's lasted eighteen years!'
He was talking almost to himself,
so I did not answer. When Cathy
came in, he stood up, ready to go.
'Goodbye, Ellen!' whispered my dear
little mistress. 'Come and visit me!'
As she kissed me, her face felt as cold as ice.
'Oh, no you won't, Ellen!'
said Heathcliff. I'll send for you if I want
you!' and together they left the Grange.
I haven't seen Cathy since then. Once I went
to the Heights to visit her, but I was not
allowed to see her. About six weeks ago I had a
long conversation with Zillah, the housekeeper,
who gave me news of Cathy. It appeared that, when
she arrived at the Heights, she did her best to
look after her sick husband. He was obviously
dying, although Heathcliff refused to call the
doctor. Only a few weeks after her arrival, Linton
died in the night, with only Cathy by his bedside.
Heathcliff inherited all of Linton's, and what had
been Cathy's, fortune, so Cathy is now very poor.
She must be very miserable, and very
lonely, in that dark, unpleasant house.
Heathcliff hates her, and Joseph and Zillah don't
speak to her, because they think she's too proud.
Poor Hareton would like to be friendly with
her, but she scorns him because he's uneducated.
I would like to leave my job here, rent a little
cottage and ask Cathy to come and live with me,
but Mr Heathcliff will never permit that.
Of course, if she married again, she could
leave that house, but I can't arrange that.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Mr Lockwood visits Wuthering Heights again
1802 After hearing the end of Mrs Dean's
story, I made my plans for the future.
I decided I did not want to spend another
winter at the Grange, and told her I would
ride to the Heights to inform my landlord. She
handed me a letter to give to Cathy Heathcliff.
When I arrived at the gate, Hareton met me
and took me into the house. Cathy was there,
preparing vegetables for lunch.
She did not bother to greet me.
'She may be beautiful,' I thought,
'but she's not very polite.'
I passed by her chair, and cleverly
dropped Mrs Dean's note in front of her,
so that Hareton wouldn't see it. She,
however, just said aloud, 'What's that?'
'A letter from the housekeeper at the
Grange,' I said, annoyed with her.
She gasped, and tried to pick it
up, but Hareton got there first.
'Mr Heathcliff will want to look at
this,' he said, putting it in his pocket.
But when Cathy pretended to cry,
Hareton could not bear to make her sad,
and he threw the letter down on the table.
She eagerly read every word, and asked me
several questions about the people at the Grange.
'Mrs Dean will want an answer
to her letter,' I reminded her.
'You must tell her that I have
no paper or pens to write with.
I haven't even any books!' she answered sadly.
'No books!' I cried. 'How can you manage
without them in this lonely place?'
'I always used to read so much that Mr
Heathcliff decided to take away my only pleasure
and destroy my books. I've looked
all over the house for them.
Joseph only reads the Bible, but some
of my books are in Hareton's room!
Why did you take them, Hareton? Just because you
enjoy stealing? They can't be any use to you!'
'I think Mr Hareton wants to learn,' I said,
hoping to prevent a quarrel between them.
'No doubt he took them away to study them.'
'Yes,' replied Cathy, laughing. 'I hear
him trying to read to himself sometimes
and it's extremely funny! He
makes some terrible mistakes!'
After a moment's shocked silence Hareton left
the room. He returned almost immediately with
his arms full of books, and threw
them angrily down at Cathy's feet.
'Take them!' he shouted. 'I
never want to see them again!'
'I won't have them now,' she said. 'I'll hate
them because they'll make me think of you.'
Hareton picked up the books and threw them on
the fire, then walked quickly out of the house.
Mr Heathcliff came in as Hareton went out. He
had a restless, anxious expression on his face.
'Mr Heathcliff,' I said, 'I must tell
you I'm leaving for London next week,
for six months, and I shan't want to
rent the Grange any more after October.'
'So, Mr Lockwood, you've got tired of the
moors already, have you? Well, have your lunch
with Hareton and me, anyway. Cathy, take your
lunch in the kitchen with Joseph and Zillah.'
I did not enjoy lunch with
my two silent companions,
and left the Heights straight afterwards.
'What a pity,' I thought, 'that Cathy
Heathcliff and I didn't fall in love,
as Mrs Dean would have liked! Then I could have
taken her away from this miserable place forever!'
Several months later, in September, I was
travelling to visit friends in Yorkshire.
I found myself near Thrushcross Grange,
and decided to spend a night there.
After all, I was still paying rent for it.
When I arrived, I was surprised to find a
different housekeeper, who told me Mrs Dean had
become housekeeper at the Heights. I wanted to
have a walk after travelling all day, so I
left orders for the woman to cook my supper
and prepare a bedroom for me, and I walked
the four miles to Wuthering Heights.
As I came close to the old house, I noticed
that there were flowers in the garden,
and the doors and windows stood open. I could see
two people inside, and I stopped for a moment,
curious to hear a little of their conversation.
'Read it again, stupid!' said a
voice as sweet as a silver bell.
'Read it correctly this time,
or I'll pull your hair!'
'You must kiss me if I get it
right,' answered a deep voice.
The man was sitting at a table, reading from
a book. His handsome face shone with pleasure,
and his eyes often left the book to look at
the small white hand that lay on his shoulder.
The girl stood behind him, bending over to help
him. Her face - it was fortunate he could not
see her face, or he would never have been able
to concentrate on his studies. I could see it,
and I was bitterly sorry that I had thrown away my
chance of seeing that beauty every day of my life.
I did not want to disturb their happiness,
so I went round to the back door, where
I discovered my old friend Ellen Dean.
'Oh, Mr Lockwood, welcome back!' she cried.
'Are you staying at the Grange again?'
'Yes, Mrs Dean, just for one night.
But tell me, why are you housekeeper
here now and not at the Grange?'
'Zillah left, you see, and Mr
Heathcliff wanted me here.'
'I have a little business
with him, about the rent.'
'Oh! Mr Heathcliff is dead,
sir. He died three months ago.
I manage all Mrs Heathcliffs business for her.
She hasn't learnt to do it herself yet, you see.'
'Heathcliff is dead!' I repeated, surprised.
'Well! Tell me how it happened, Mrs Dean!'
'Sit down, sir, and drink some beer. I'll gladly
tell you. His life ended very strangely.'
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
Heathcliffs end
1801-2 I was delighted to come back to the
Heights, and hoped I could make Cathy's life more
comfortable. But she was restless, and complained
of loneliness. At first she continued to annoy
Hareton, by laughing at him, but after a while
she decided she really wanted him as a friend.
She apologized for being rude to him, and
offered to teach him everything she knew.
From that moment on, the two cousins
have always been together, studying.
Hareton has a lot to learn, and Cathy is not the
most patient of teachers. But what they have in
common is their love for each other. You see, Mr
Lockwood, it was easy enough to win Cathy's heart.
But now I'm glad you didn't try. I'll be the
happiest woman in England when those two marry!
Heathcliff noticed little of
what was happening around him,
and would never have been aware of the cousins'
feelings, if it hadn't been for Joseph. In the
middle of our lunch one day, the old man
rushed into the room, shaking with anger.
'I'll have to leave! I wanted to die here,
where I've been a servant for sixty years!
But now she's taken my garden from me! She's
stolen the boy's soul, master! I can't bear it!'
'Is the fool drunk?' asked Heathcliff.
Can you explain this, Hareton?'
'I've pulled up two or three of his fruit-trees,'
confessed Hareton, but I'll put them back again.'
'It was my fault,' added Cathy
bravely. I asked him to do it.
We wanted to plant some flowers there.'
'Who the devil gave you
permission?' growled Heathcliff.
'You should let me have a bit of garden, as
you've taken all my land!' replied Cathy sharply.
And you've taken Hareton's land too! He and
I are friends now! I'll tell him about you!'
The master stood up, staring at her fiercely.
'Out of the room, wicked girl!' he
shouted. I'll kill you if I get near you!'
'If you hit me, Hareton will hit
you. He won't obey you anymore,
and soon he'll hate you as much as I do!'
'You'd better leave, Cathy,' whispered Hareton
urgently. 'I won't quarrel with Mr Heathcliff.'
But it was too late. I was sure Heathcliff
was going to hit her. He took hold of her,
one strong hand in her hair and the other raised
over her head. But when he looked into her face,
his anger suddenly disappeared, and he
let his arm fall to his side. He sat
heavily down in his chair and put his hand over
his eyes for a moment. We all stared at him.
You must learn not to make me angry,'
he said, trying to be calm. Go away,
all of you! Leave me alone!' A little later he
went out, saying he would return in the evening.
As darkness fell, Cathy and Hareton were
busy at their studies in the kitchen.
I was sitting with them, happy to
see them helping each other so well.
I feel they're almost my children, Mr
Lockwood, and I'm very proud of them. As
the master entered the house, he had a full view
of us three. They lifted their eyes to meet his.
Perhaps you haven't noticed it, but their eyes
are very similar, and they are exactly like those
of Catherine Earnshaw. Mr Heathcliff stopped
and stared, then looked away. At a sign from me,
Cathy and Hareton went quietly out into the
garden, leaving me alone with Mr Heathcliff.
'It's silly, isn't it, Ellen,' he muttered,
'that I have worked all my life to destroy
these two families, the Earnshaws and the
Lintons. I've got their money and their land.
Now I can take my final revenge on the last
Earnshaw and the last Linton, I no longer want to!
There's a strange change coming in my life. I'm
in its shadow. I'm so little interested in daily
events that I even forget to eat and drink.
I don't want to see those two, that's why I
don't care if they spend time together. She only
makes me angry. And he looks so like Catherine!
But everything reminds me of Catherine! In
every cloud, in every tree I see her face!
The whole world reminds me that she
was here once, and I have lost her!'
'You don't feel ill, sir, do
you? Are you afraid of death?'
I'm not ill, Ellen, and I'm not afraid
to die. But I can't continue like this!
I have to remind myself to breathe
- almost to remind my heart to beat!
I have a single wish, for something
my whole body and heart and brain
have wanted for so long! Oh God! It's
a long fight! I wish it were finished!'
For some days after that, Mr Heathcliff
avoided meeting us at meals. He ate less
and less. Late one night I heard him leave the
house. He did not return until the morning.
When he came in, I noticed
a change in his expression.
There was a strange, wild happiness in his
face, although he was pale and trembling.
'Will you have some breakfast, sir?' I asked.
'No, I'm not hungry,' he answered.
'I don't think you should stay outside at
night, sir. You'll catch a bad cold or a fever!'
'Leave me alone, Ellen,' he replied.
I began to worry about him. He was strong and
healthy, but a man must eat in order to live.
For the next three days he ate nothing. At every
meal the food lay untouched on the plate in front
of him. He did not look at the food, or at us.
He seemed to be looking at something quite close
to him, something we could not see. His fierce
black eyes followed it with such eager interest
that he sometimes stopped breathing
for as much as half a minute.
He did not sleep either. For three days he had
spent the night in Catherine Earnshaw's old
bedroom, and I could hear him walking up and
down, and talking, calling, crying all night.
One morning I managed to speak to him,
and make him listen to me. Mr Heathcliff,
you must have some food and sleep. Look at
yourself in the mirror! You look ill and tired.'
'It's not my fault that I can't eat or
rest. You wouldn't tell a drowning man to
rest when he can see the shore! I'm close
to what I've wanted for eighteen years,
very close! But my soul's
happiness is killing my body!'
'It's a strange kind of happiness,
master. Take my advice, and pray to God
to forgive you for what you've done wrong in
the past, if you think you're going to die.'
'Thank you, Ellen, you've reminded me of
something. It's the way I want to be buried.
My coffin will be carried to the churchyard in
the evening. You and Hareton will be present,
nobody else. And make sure my orders
about the two coffins are obeyed!
I want no ceremony, or words from the
Bible - I don't believe in any of that.'
He spent the next night, and the next day, in
Catherine's room, muttering and sobbing all
the time. I sent for Dr Kenneth, but the door
was locked, so the doctor could not see him.
The following night was
very wet, and in the morning
as I walked in the garden, I noticed
that the bedroom window was wide open.
'He must be very wet if he's in bed,'
I thought, the bed is so close to the
window. I'll go and look.' I found another key
which fitted the lock, and opened the door.
Mr Heathcliff was there in bed, lying on his back.
His eyes were staring at me, so eagerly
and fiercely, and he seemed to be smiling!
His face and clothes were wet from the rain,
and he did not move. I realized he was dead!
I closed the window. I combed his
long, black hair from his forehead.
I tried to close his eyes, but they would not
shut. Suddenly frightened, I called for Joseph.
The old servant came at once,
but refused to touch the body.
'Ah, the devil's taken his soul! I
warned him that would happen!' he cried.
'You see how wicked he is, smiling at death! But
thank God Hareton Earnshaw will have the house and
land now, that he should have inherited from his
father!' And he went down on his knees to pray.
Hareton was, in fact, the only one who was sad at
Heathcliffs death. He and I were present at the
burial. Heathcliff was buried next to Catherine's
grave, as he had wished. As we were not sure
of his age or anything else about him, there is
only one word on his gravestone - Heathcliff. The
villagers are very frightened of his ghost. They
say he often haunts the churchyard and the moors.
Hareton and Cathy will be married on New
Year's Day, and they'll move to the Grange.
I'll be their housekeeper. Joseph
will take care of Wuthering Heights,
but most of the rooms here won't be used again.
You'll pass the churchyard, Mr Lockwood, on
your way back to the Grange, and you'll see
the three gravestones close to the moor.
Catherine's, the middle one, is old now,
and half buried in plants which have grown
over it. On one side is Edgar Linton's,
and on the other is Heathcliffs new one. If
you stay there a moment, and watch the insects
flying in the warm summer air, and listen to
the soft wind breathing through the grass,
you'll understand how quietly they rest,
the sleepers in that quiet earth.
- THE END -