I
Patrol Cruiser "IP-T 247" circling out toward
Pluto on leisurely inspection tour to visit
the outpost miners there, was in no hurry
at all as she loafed along.
Her six-man crew was taking it very easy,
and easy meant two-man watches, and low speed,
to watch for the instrument panel and attend
ship into the bargain.
She was about thirty million miles off Pluto,
just beginning to get in touch with some of
the larger mining stations out there, when
Buck Kendall's turn at the controls came along.
Buck Kendall was one of life's little jokes.
When Nature made him, she was absentminded.
Buck stood six feet two in his stocking feet,
with his usual slight stoop in operation.
When he forgot, and stood up straight, he
loomed about two inches higher.
He had the body and muscles of a dock navvy,
which Nature started out to make.
Then she forgot and added something of the
same stuff she put in Sir Francis Drake.
Maybe that made Old Nature nervous, and she
started adding different things.
At any rate, Kendall, as finally turned out,
had a brain that put him in the first rank
of scientists—when he felt like it—the
general constitution of an ostrich and a flair
for gambling.
The present position was due to such a gamble.
An IP man, a friend of his, had made the mistake
of betting him a thousand dollars he wouldn't
get beyond a Captain's bars in the Patrol.
Kendall had liked the idea anyway, and adding
a bit of a bet to it made it irresistible.
So, being a very particular kind of a fool,
the glorious kind which old Nature turns out
now and then, he left a five million dollar
estate on Long Island, Terra, that same evening,
and joined up in the Patrol.
The Sir Francis Drake strain had immediately
come forth—and Kendall was having the time
of his life.
In a six-man cruiser, his real work in the
Interplanetary Patrol had started.
He was still in it—but it was his command
now, and a blue circle on his left sleeve
gave his lieutenant's rank.
Buck Kendall had immediately proceeded to
enlist in his command the IP man who had made
the mistaken bet, and Rad Cole was on duty
with him now.
Cole was the technician of the T-247.
His rank as Technical Engineer was practically
equivalent to Kendall's circle-rank, which
made the two more comfortable together.
Cole was listening carefully to the signals
coming through from Pluto.
"That," he decided, "sounds like Tad Nichols'
fist.
You can recognize that broken-down truck-horse
trot of his on the key as far away as you
can hear it."
"Is that what it is?"
sighed Buck.
"I thought it was static mushing him at first.
What's he like?"
"Like all the other damn fools who come out
two billion miles to scratch rock, as if there
weren't enough already on the inner planets.
He's got a rich platinum property.
Sells ninety percent of his output to buy
his power, and the other eleven percent for
his clothes and food."
"He must be an efficient miner," suggested
Kendall, "to maintain 101% production like
that."
"No, but his bank account is.
He's figured out that's the most economic
level of production.
If he produces less, he won't be able to pay
for his heating power, and if he produces
more, his operation power will burn up his
bank account too fast."
"Hmmm—sensible way to figure.
A man after my own heart.
How does he plan to restock his bank account?"
"By mining on Mercury.
He does it regularly—sort of a commuter.
Out here his power bills eat it up.
On Mercury he goes in for potassium, and sells
the power he collects in cooling his dome,
of course.
He's a good miner, and the old fool can make
money down there."
Like any really skilled operator, Cole had
been sending Morse messages while he talked.
Now he sat quiet waiting for the reply, glancing
at the chronometer.
"I take it he's not after money—just after
fun," suggested Buck.
"Oh, no.
He's after money," replied Cole gravely.
"You ask him—he's going to make his eternal
fortune yet by striking a real bed of jovium,
and then he'll retire."
"Oh, one of that kind."
"They all are," Cole laughed.
"Eternal hope, and the rest of it."
He listened a moment and went on.
"But old Nichols is a first-grade engineer.
He wouldn't be able to remake that bankroll
every time if he wasn't.
You'll see his Dome out there on Pluto—it's
always the best on the planet.
Tip-top shape.
And he's a bit of an experimenter too.
Ah—he's with us."
Nichols' ragged signals were coming through—or
pounding through.
They were worse than usual, and at first Kendall
and Cole couldn't make them out.
Then finally they got them in bursts.
The man was excited, and his bad key-work
made it worse.
"—Randing stopped.
They got him I think.
He said—th—ship as big—a—nsport.
Said it wa—eaded my—ay.
Neutrons—on instruments—he's coming over
the horizon—it's huge—war ship I think—register—instru—neutrons—."
Abruptly the signals were blanked out completely.
Cole and Kendall sat frozen and stiff.
Each looked at the other abruptly, then Kendall
moved.
From the receiver, he ripped out the recording
coil, and instantly jammed it into the analyzer.
He started it through once, then again, then
again, at different tone settings, till he
found a very shrill whine that seemed to clear
up most of Nichols' bad key-work.
"T-247—T-247—Emergency.
Emergency.
Randing reports the—over his horizon.
Huge—ip—reign manufacture.
Almost spherical.
Randing's stopped.
They got him I think.
He said the ship was as big as a transport.
Said it was headed my way.
Neutrons—ont—gister—instruments.
I think—is h—he's coming over the horizon.
It's huge, and a war ship I think—register—instruments—neutrons."
Kendall's finger stabbed out at a button.
Instantly the noise of the other men, wakened
abruptly by the mild shocks, came from behind.
Kendall swung to the controls, and Cole raced
back to the engine room.
The hundred-foot ship shot suddenly forward
under the thrust of her tail ion-rockets.
A blue-red cloud formed slowly behind her
and expanded.
Talbot appeared, and silently took her over
from Kendall.
"Stations, men," snapped Kendall.
"Emergency call from a miner of Pluto reporting
a large armed vessel which attacked them."
Kendall swung back, and eased himself against
the thrusting acceleration of the over-powered
little ship, toward the engine room.
Cole was bending over his apparatus, making
careful check-ups, closing weapon-circuits.
No window gave view of space here; on the
left was the tiny tender's pocket, on the
right, above and below the great water tanks
that fed the ion-rockets, behind the rockets
themselves.
The tungsten metal walls were cold and gray
under the ship lights; the hunched bulks of
the apparatus crowded the tiny room.
Gigantic racked accumulators huddled in the
corners.
Martin and Garnet swung into position in the
fighting-tanks just ahead of the power rooms;
Canning slid rapidly through the engine room,
oozed through a tiny door, and took up his
position in the stern-chamber, seated half-over
the great ion-rocket sheath.
"Ready in positions, Captain Kendall," called
the war-pilot as the little green lights appeared
on his board.
"Test discharges on maximum," ordered Kendall.
He turned to Cole.
"You start the automatic key?"
"Right, Captain."
"All shipshape?"
"Right as can be.
Accumulators at thirty-seven per cent, thanks
to the loaf out here.
They ought to pick up our signal back on Jupiter,
he's nearest now.
The station on Europa will get it."
"Talbot—we are only to investigate if the
ship is as reported.
Have you seen any signs of her?"
"No sir, and the signals are blank."
"I'll work from here."
Kendall took his position at the commanding
control.
Cole made way for him, and moved to the power
board.
One by one he tested the automatic doors,
the pressure bulkheads.
Kendall watched the instruments as one after
another of the weapons were tested on momentary
full discharge—titanic flames of five million
volt protons.
Then the ship thudded to the chatter of the
Garnell rifles.
Tensely the men watched the planet ahead,
white, yet barely visible in the weak sunlight
so far out.
It was swimming slowly nearer as the tiny
ship gathered speed.
Kendall cast a glance over his detector-instruments.
The radio network was undisturbed, the magnetic
and electric fields recognized only the slight
disturbances occasioned by the planet itself.
There was nothing, noth—
Five hundred miles away, a gigantic ship came
into instantaneous being.
Simultaneously, and instantaneously, the various
detector systems howled their warnings.
Kendall gasped as the thing appeared on his
view screen, with the scale-lines below.
The scale must be cock-eyed.
They said the ship was fifteen hundred feet
in diameter, and two thousand long!
"Retreat," ordered Kendall, "at maximum acceleration."
Talbot was already acting.
The gyroscopes hummed in their castings, and
the motors creaked.
The T-247 spun on her axis, and abruptly the
acceleration built up as the ion-rockets began
to shudder.
A faint smell of "heat" began to creep out
of the converter.
Immense "weight" built up, and pressed the
men into their specially designed seats—
The gigantic ship across the way turned slowly,
and seemed to stare at the T-247.
Then it darted toward them at incredible speed
till the poor little T-247 seemed to be standing
still, as sailors say.
The stranger was so gigantic now, the screens
could not show all of him.
"God, Buck—he's going to take us!"
Simultaneously, the T-247 rolled, and from
her broke every possible stream of destruction.
The ion-rocket flames swirled abruptly toward
her, the proton-guns whined their song of
death in their housings, and the heavy pounding
shudder of the Garnell guns racked the ship.
Strangely, Kendall suddenly noticed, there
was a stillness in the ship.
The guns and the rays were still going—but
the little human sounds seemed abruptly gone.
"Talbot—Garnet—" Only silence answered
him.
Cole looked across at him in sudden white-faced
amazement.
"They're gone—" gasped Cole.
Kendall stood paralyzed for thirty seconds.
Then suddenly he seemed to come to life.
"Neutrons!
Neutrons—and water tanks!
Old Nichols was right—" He turned to his
friend.
"Cole—the tender—quick."
He darted a glance at the screen.
The giant ship still lay alongside.
A wash of ions was curling around her, splitting,
and passing on.
The pinprick explosions of the Garnell shells
dotted space around her—but never on her.
Cole was already racing for the tender lock.
In an instant Kendall piled in after him.
The tiny ship, scarcely ten feet long, was
powered for flights of only two hours acceleration,
and had oxygen for but twenty-four hours for
six men, seventy-two hours for two men—maybe.
The heavy door was slammed shut behind them,
as Cole seated himself at the panel.
He depressed a lever, and a sudden smooth
push shot them away from the T-247.
"DON'T!" called Kendall sharply as Cole reached
for the ion-rocket control.
"Douse those lights!"
The ship was dark in dark space.
The lighted hull of the T-247 drifted away
from the little tender—further and further
till the giant ship on the far side became
visible.
"Not a light—not a sign of fields in operation."
Kendall said, unconsciously speaking softly.
"This thing is so tiny, that it may escape
their observation in the fields of the T-247
and Pluto down there.
It's our only hope."
"What happened?
How in the name of the planets did they kill
those men without a sound, without a flash,
and without even warning us, or injuring us?"
"Neutrons—don't you see?"
"Frankly, I don't.
I'm no scientist—merely a technician.
Neutrons aren't used in any process I've run
across."
"Well, remember they're uncharged, tiny things.
Small as protons, but without electric field.
The result is they pass right through an ordinary
atom without being stopped unless they make
a direct hit.
Tungsten, while it has a beautifully high
melting point, is mostly open space, and a
neutron just sails right through it, or any
heavy atom.
Light atoms stop neutrons better—there's
less open space in 'em.
Hydrogen is best.
Well—a man is made up mostly of light elements,
and a man stops those neutrons—it isn't
surprising it killed those other fellows invisibly,
and without a sound."
"You mean they bathed that ship in neutrons?"
"Shot it full of 'em.
Just like our proton guns, only sending neutrons."
"Well, why weren't we killed too?"
"'Water stops neutrons,' I said.
Figure it out."
"The rocket-water tanks—all around us!
Great masses of water—" gasped Cole.
"That saved us?"
"Right.
I wonder if they've spotted us."
The stranger ship was moving slowly in relation
to the T-247.
Suddenly the motion changed, the stranger
spun—and a giant lock appeared in her side,
opened.
The T-247 began to move, floated more and
more rapidly straight for the lock.
Her various weapons had stopped operating
now, the hoppers of the Garnell guns exhausted,
the charge of the accumulators aboard the
ship down so low the proton guns had died
out.
"Lord—they're taking the whole ship!"
"Say—Cole, is that any ship you ever heard
of before?
I don't think that's just a pirate!"
"Not a pirate—what then?"
"How'd he get inside our detector screens
so fast?
Watch—he'll either leave, or come after
us—" The T-247 had settled inside the lock
now, and the great metal door closed after
it.
The whole patrol ship had been swallowed by
a giant.
Kendall was sketching swiftly on a notebook,
watching the vast ship closely, putting down
a record of its lines, and formation.
He glanced up at it, and then down for a few
more lines, and up at it—
The stranger ship abruptly dwindled.
It dwindled with incredible speed, rushing
off along the line of sight at an impossible
velocity, and abruptly clicking out of sight,
like an image on a movie-film that has been
cut, and repaired after the scene that showed
the final disappearance.
"Cole—Cole—did you get that?
Did you see—do you understand what happened?"
Kendall was excitedly shouting now.
"He missed us," Cole sighed.
"It's a wonder—hanging out here in space,
with the protector of the T-247's fields gone."
"No, no, you asteroid—that's not it.
He went off faster than light itself!"
"Eh—what?
Faster than light?
That can't be done—"
"He did it, I know he did.
That's how he got inside our screens.
He came inside faster than the warning message
could relay back the information.
Didn't you see him accelerate to an impossible
speed in an impossible time?
Didn't you see how he just vanished as he
exceeded the speed of light, and stopped reflecting
it?
That ship was no ship of this solar system!"
"Where did he come from then?"
"God only knows, but it's a long, long way
off."
II
The IP-M-122 picked them up.
The M-122 got out there two days later, in
response to the calls the T-247 had sent out.
As soon as she got within ten million miles
of the little tender, she began getting Cole's
signals, and within twelve hours had reached
the tiny thing, located it, and picked it
up.
Captain Jim Warren was in command, one of
the old school commanders of the IP.
He listened to Kendall's report, listened
to Cole's tale—and radioed back a report
of his own.
Space pirates in a large ship had attacked
the T-247, he said, and carried it away.
He advised a close watch.
On Pluto, his investigations disclosed nothing
more than the fact that three mines had been
raided, all platinum supplies taken, and the
records and machinery removed.
The M-122 was a fifty-man patrol cruiser,
and Warren felt sure he could handle the menace
alone, and hung around for over two weeks
looking for it.
He saw nothing, and no further reports came
of attack.
Again and again, Kendall tried to convince
him this ship he was hunting was no mere space
pirate, and again and again Warren grunted,
and went on his way.
He would not send in any report Kendall made
out, because to do so would add his endorsement
to that report.
He would not take Kendall back, though that
was well within his authority.
In fact, it was a full month before Kendall
again set foot on any of the Minor Planets,
and then it was Mars, the base of the M-122.
Kendall and Cole took passage immediately
on an IP supply ship, and landed in New York
six days later.
At once, Kendall headed for Commander McLaurin's
office.
Buck Kendall, lieutenant of the IP, found
he would have to make regular application
to see McLaurin through a dozen intermediate
officers.
By this time, Kendall was savagely determined
to see McLaurin himself, and see him in the
least possible time.
Cole, too, was beginning to believe in Kendall's
assertion of the stranger ship's extra-systemic
origin.
As yet neither could understand the strange
actions of the machine, its attack on the
Pluto mines, and the capture and theft of
a patrol ship.
"There is," said Kendall angrily, "just one
way to see McLaurin and see him quick.
And, by God, I'm going to.
Will you resign with me, Cole?
I'll see him within a week then, I'll bet."
For a minute, Cole hesitated.
Then he shook hands with his friends.
"Today!"
And that day it was.
They resigned, together.
Immediately, Buck Kendall got the machinery
in motion for an interview, working now from
the outside, pulling the strings with the
weight of a hundred million dollar fortune.
Even the IP officers had to pay a bit of attention
when Bernard Kendall, multi-millionaire began
talking and demanding things.
Within a week, Kendall did see McLaurin.
At that time, McLaurin was fifty-three years
old, his crisp hair still black as space,
with scarcely a touch of the gray that appears
in his more recent photographs.
He stood six feet tall, a broad-shouldered,
powerful man, his face grave with lines of
intelligence and character.
There was also a permanent narrowing of the
eyes, from years under the blazing sun of
space.
But most of all, while those years in space
had narrowed and set his eyes, they had not
narrowed and set his mind.
An infinitely finer character than old Jim
Warren, his experience in space had taught
him always to expect the unexpected, to understand
the incomprehensible as being part of the
unknown and incalculable properties of space
and the worlds that swam in it.
Besides the fine technical education he had
started with, he had acquired a liberal education
in mankind.
When Buck Kendall, straight and powerful,
came into his office with Cole, he recognized
in him a character that would drive steadily
and straight for its goal.
Also, he recognized behind the millionaire
that had succeeded in pulling wires enough
to see him, the scientist who had had more
than one paper published "in an amateur way."
"Dr. Bernard Kendall?"
he asked, rising.
"Yes, sir.
Late Buck Kendall, lieutenant of the IP.
I quit and got Cole here to quit with me,
so we could see you."
"Unusual tactics.
I've had several men join up to get an interview
with me."
McLaurin smiled.
"Yes, I can imagine that, but we had to see
you in a hurry.
A hidebound old rapscallion by the name of
Jim Warren picked us up out by Pluto, floating
around in a six-man tender.
We made some reports to him, but he wouldn't
believe, and he wouldn't send them through—so
we had to send ourselves through.
Sir, this system is about to be attacked by
some extra-systemic race.
The IP-T-247 was so attacked, her crew killed
off, and the ship itself carried away."
"I got the report Captain Jim Warren sent
through, stating it was a gang of space pirates.
Now what makes you believe otherwise?"
"That ship that attacked us, attacked with
a neutron gun, a gun that shot neutrons through
the hull of our ship as easily as protons
pass through open space.
Those neutrons killed off four of the crew,
and spared us only because we happened to
be behind the water tanks.
Masses of hydrogen will stop neutrons, so
we lived, and escaped in the tender.
The little tender, lightless, escaped their
observation, and we were picked up.
Now, when the 247 had been picked up, and
locked into their ship, that ship started
accelerating.
It accelerated so fast along my line of sight
that it just dwindled, and—vanished.
It didn't vanish in distance, it vanished
because it exceeded the speed of light."
"Isn't that impossible?"
"Not at all.
It can be done—if you can find some way
of escaping from this space to do it.
Now if you could cut across through a higher
dimension, your projection in this dimension
might easily exceed the speed of light.
For instance, if I could cut directly through
the Earth, at a speed of one thousand miles
an hour, my projection on the surface would
go twelve thousand miles while I was going
eight.
Similar, if you could cut through the four
dimensional space instead of following its
surface, you'd attain a speed greater than
light."
"Might it not still be a space pirate?
That's a lot easier to believe, even allowing
your statement that he exceeded the speed
of light."
"If you invented a neutron gun which could
kill through tungsten walls without injuring
anything within, a system of accelerating
a ship that didn't affect the inhabitants
of that ship, and a means of exceeding the
speed of light, all within a few months of
each other, would you become a pirate?
I wouldn't, and I don't think any one else
would.
A pirate is a man who seeks adventure and
relief from work.
Given a means of exceeding the speed of light,
I'd get all the adventure I wanted investigating
other planets.
If I didn't have a cent before, I'd have relief
from work by selling it for a few hundred
millions—and I'd sell it mighty easily too,
for an invention like that is worth an incalculable
sum.
Tie to that the value of compensated acceleration,
and no man's going to turn pirate.
He can make more millions selling his inventions
than he can make thousands turning pirate
with them.
So who'd turn pirate?"
"Right."
McLaurin nodded.
"I see your point.
Now before I'd accept your statements in re
the 'speed of light' thing, I'd want opinions
from some IP physicists."
"Then let's have a conference, because something's
got to be done soon.
I don't know why we haven't heard further
from that fellow."
"Privately—we have," McLaurin said in a
slightly worried tone.
"He was detected by the instruments of every
IP observatory I suspect.
We got the reports but didn't know what to
make of them.
They indicated so many funny things, they
were sent in as accidental misreadings of
the instruments.
But since all the observatories reported them,
similar misreadings, at about the same times,
that is with variations of only a few hours,
we thought something must have been up.
The only thing was the phenomena were reported
progressively from Pluto to Neptune, clear
across the solar system, in a definite progression,
but at a velocity of crossing that didn't
tie in with any conceivable force.
They crossed faster than the velocity of light.
That ship must have spent about half an hour
off each planet before passing on to the next.
And, accepting your faster-than-light explanation,
we can understand it."
"Then I think you have proof."
"If we have, what would you do about it?"
"Get to work on those 'misreadings' of the
instruments for one thing, and for a second,
and more important, line every IP ship with
paraffin blocks six inches thick."
"Paraffin—why?"
"The easiest form of hydrogen to get.
You can't use solid hydrogen, because that
melts too easily.
Water can be turned into steam too easily,
and requires more work.
Paraffin is a solid that's largely hydrogen.
That's what they've always used on neutrons
since they discovered them.
Confine your paraffin between tungsten walls,
and you'll stop the secondary protons as well
as the neutrons."
"Hmmm—I suppose so.
How about seeing those physicists?"
"I'd like to see them today, sir.
The sooner you get started on this work, the
better it will be for the IP."
"Having seen me, will you join up in the IP
again?" asked McLaurin.
"No, sir, I don't think I will.
I have another field you know, in which I
may be more useful.
Cole here's a better technician than fighter—and
a darned good fighter, too—and I think that
an inexperienced space-captain is a lot less
useful than a second-rate physicist at work
in a laboratory.
If we hope to get anywhere, or for that matter,
I suspect, stay anywhere, we'll have to do
a lot of research pretty promptly."
"What's your explanation of that ship?"
"One of two things: an inventor of some other
system trying out his latest toy, or an expedition
sent out by a planetary government for exploration.
I favor the latter for two reasons: that ship
was big.
No inventor would build a thing that size,
requiring a crew of several hundred men to
try out his invention.
A government would build just about that if
they wanted to send out an expedition.
If it were an inventor, he'd be interested
in meeting other people, to see what they
had in the way of science, and probably he'd
want to do it in a peaceable way.
That fellow wasn't interested in peace, by
any means.
So I think it's a government ship, and an
unfriendly government.
They sent that ship out either for scientific
research, for trade research and exploration,
or for acquisitive exploration.
If they were out for scientific research,
they'd proceed as would the inventor, to establish
friendly communication.
If they were out for trade, the same would
apply.
If they were out for acquisitive exploration,
they'd investigate the planets, the sun, the
people, only to the extent of learning how
best to overcome them.
They'd want to get a sample of our people,
and a sample of our weapons.
They'd want samples of our machinery, our
literature and our technology.
That's exactly what that ship got.
"Somebody, somewhere out there in space, either
doesn't like their home, or wants more home.
They've been out looking for one.
I'll bet they sent out hundreds of expeditions
to thousands of nearby stars, gradually going
further and further, seeking a planetary system.
This is probably the one and only one they
found.
It's a good one too.
It has planets at all temperatures, of all
sizes.
It is a fairly compact one, it has a stable
sun that will last far longer than any race
can hope to."
"Hmm—how can there be good and bad planetary
systems?" asked McLaurin.
"I'd never thought of that."
Kendall laughed.
"Mighty easy.
How'd you like to live on a planet of a Cepheid
Variable?
Pleasant situation, with the radiation flaring
up and down.
How'd you like to live on a planet of Antares?
That blasted sun is so big, to have a comfortable
planet you'd have to be at least ten billion
miles out.
Then if you had an interplanetary commerce,
you'd have to struggle with orbits tens of
billions of miles across instead of mere millions.
Further, you'd have a sun so blasted big,
it would take an impossible amount of energy
to lift the ship up from one planet to another.
If your trip was, say, twenty billions of
miles to the next planet, you'd be fighting
a gravity as bad as the solar gravity at Earth
here all the way—no decline with a little
distance like that."
"H-m-m-m—quite true.
Then I should say that Mira would take the
prize.
It's a red giant, and it's an irregular variable.
The sunlight there would be as unstable as
the weather in New England.
It's almost as big as Antares, and it won't
hold still.
Now that would make a bad planetary system."
"It would!"
Kendall laughed.
But as we know—he laughed too soon, and
he shouldn't have used
the conditional.
He should have said, "It does!"
III
Gresth Gkae, Commander of Expeditionary Force
93, of the Planet Sthor, was returning homeward
with joyful mind.
In the lock of his great ship, lay the T-247.
In her cargo holds lay various items of machinery,
mining supplies, foods, and records.
And in her log books lay the records of many
readings on the nine larger planets of a highly
satisfactory planetary system.
Gresth Gkae had spent no less than three ultra-wearing
years going from one sun to another in a definitely
mapped out section of space.
He had investigated only eleven stars in that
time, eleven stars, progressively further
from the titanic red-flaming sun he knew as
"the" sun.
He knew it as "the" sun, and had several other
appellations for it.
Mira was so-named by Earthmen because it was
indeed a "wonder" star, in Latin, mirare means
"to wonder."
Irregularly, and for no apparent reason it
would change its rate of radiation.
So far as those inhabitants of Sthor and her
sister world Asthor knew, there was no reason.
It just did it.
Perhaps with malicious intent to be annoying.
If so, it was exceptionally successful.
Sthor and Asthor experienced, periodically,
a young ice age.
When Mira decided to take a rest, Sthor and
Asthor froze up, from the poles most of the
way to the equators.
Then Mira would stretch herself a little,
move about restlessly and Sthor and Asthor
would become uninhabitably hot, anywhere within
twenty degrees of the equator.
Those Sthorian people had evolved in a way
that made the conditions endurable for savage
or uncivilized people, but when a scientific
civilization with a well-ordered mode of existence
tried to establish itself, Mira was all sorts
of a nuisance.
Gresth Gkae was a peculiar individual to human
ways of thinking.
He stood some seven feet tall, on his strange,
double-kneed legs and his four toed feet.
His body was covered with little, short feather-like
things that moved now with a volition of their
own.
They were moving very slowly and regularly.
The space-ship was heated to a comfortable
temperature, and the little fans were helping
to cool Gresth Gkae.
Had it been cold, every little feather would
have lain down close against its neighbors,
forming an admirable, wind-proof and cold-proof
blanket.
Nature, on Sthor, had original ideas of arrangement
too.
Sthorians possessed two eyes—one directly
above the other, in the center of their faces.
The face was so long, and narrow, it resembled
a blunt hatchet, with the two eyes on the
edge.
To counter-balance this vertical arrangement
of the eyes, the nostrils had been separated
some four inches, with one on each of the
sloping cheeks.
His ears were little pink-flesh cups on short,
muscular stems.
His mouth was narrow, and small, but armed
with quite solid teeth adapted to his diet,
a diet consisting of almost anything any creature
had ever considered edible.
Like most successful forms of intelligent
life, Gresth Gkae was omnivorous.
An intelligent form of life is necessarily
adaptable, and adaptation meant being able
to eat what was at hand.
One of his eyes, the upper one, was fully
twice the size of the lower one.
This was his telescopic eye.
The lower, or microscopic eye was adapted
to work for which a human being would have
required a low power microscope, the upper
eye possessed a more normal power of vision,
plus considerable telescopic powers.
Gresth Gkae was using it now to look ahead
in the blank of space to where gigantic Mira
appeared.
On his screens now, Mira appeared deep violet,
for he was approaching at a speed greater
than that of light, and even this projected
light of Mira was badly distorted.
"The distance is half a light-year now, sir,"
reported the navigation officer.
"Reduce the speed, then, to normal velocity
for these ranges.
What reserve of fuel have we?"
"Less than one thousand pounds.
We will barely be able to stop.
We were too free in the use of our weapons,
I fear," replied the Chief Technician.
"Well, what would you?
We needed those things in our reports.
Besides, we could extract fuel from that ore
we took on at Planet Nine of Phahlo.
It is merely that I wish speed in the return."
"As we all do.
How soon do you believe the Council will proceed
against the new system?"
"It will be fully a year, I fear.
They must gather the expeditions together,
and re-equip the ships.
It will be a long time before all will have
come in."
"Could they not send fast ships after them
to recall them?"
"Could they have traced us as we wove our
way from Thart to Karst to Raloork to Phahlo?
It would be impossible."
Steadily the great ship had been boring on
her way.
Mira had been a disc for nearly two days,
gigantic, two-hundred-and-fifty-million-mile
Mira took a great deal of dwarfing by distance
to lose her disc.
Even at the Twin Planets, eight thousand two
hundred and fifty millions of miles out, Mira
covered half the sky, it seemed, red and angry.
Sometimes, though, to the disgust of the Sthorians
it was just red-faced and lazy.
Then Sthor froze.
"Grih is in a descendant stage," said the
navigation officer presently.
"Sthor will be cold when we arrive."
"It will warm quickly enough with our news!"
Gresth laughed.
"A system—a delightful system—discovered.
A system of many close-grouped planets.
Why think—from one side of that system to
the other is less of a distance than from
Ansthat, our first planet's orbit, to Insthor's
orbit!
That sun, as we know, is steady and warm.
All will be well, when we have eliminated
that rather peculiar race.
Odd, that they should, in some ways, be so
nearly like us!
Nearly Sthorian in build.
I would not have expected it.
Though they did have some amazing peculiarities!
Imagine—two eyes just alike, and in a horizontal
row.
And that flat face.
They looked as though they had suffered some
accident that smashed the front of the face
in.
And also the peculiar beak-like projection.
Why should a race ever develop so amazing
a projection in so peculiar and exposed a
position?
It sticks out inviting attack and injury.
Right in the middle of the face.
And to make it worse, there is the air-channel,
and the only air channel.
Why, one minor injury to the throat would
be certain to damage that passage beyond repair,
and bring death.
Yet such relatively unimportant things as
ears, and eyes are doubled.
Surely you would expect that so important
a member as the air-passage would be doubled
for safety.
"Those strange, awkward arms and legs were
what puzzled me.
I have been attempting to manipulate myself
as they must be forced to, and I cannot see
how delicate or accurate manual manipulation
would be possible with those rigid, inflexible
arms.
In some ways I feel they must have had clever
minds to overcome so great a handicap to constructive
work.
But I suppose single joints in the arms become
as natural to them as our own more mobile
two.
"I wonder if life in any intelligent form
wouldn't develop somewhat similar formations,
though.
Think, in all parts of Sthor, before men became
civilized and developed communication, even
so much as twenty thousand years ago, our
records show that seats and chairs were much
as they are today, and much as they are, in
all places among all groups.
Then too, the eye has developed in many different
species, and always reached much the same
structure.
When a thing is intended and developed to
serve a given purpose, no matter who develops
it, or where or how, is it not apt to have
similar shapes and parts?
A chair must have legs, and a seat and arm-rests
and a back.
You may vary their nature and their shape,
but not widely, and they must be there.
An eye must, anywhere, have a sensitive retina,
an adjustable lens, and an adjustable device
for controlling the entrance of light.
Similarly there are certain functions that
the body of an intelligent creature must serve
which naturally tend to make intelligent creatures
similar.
He must have a tool—the hand—"
"Yes, yes—I see your point.
It must be so, for surely these creatures
out there are strange enough in other ways."
"But tell me, have you calculated when we
shall land?"
"In twelve hours, thirty-three minutes, sir."
Eleven hours later, the expedition ship had
slowed to a normal space-speed.
On her left hung the giant globe of Asthor,
rotating slowly, moving slowly in her orbit.
Directly ahead, Sthor loomed even greater.
Tiny Teelan, the thousand-mile diameter moon
of the Insthor system shone dull red in the
reflected light of gigantic Mira.
Mira herself was gigantic, red and menacing
across eight and a quarter billions of miles
of space.
One hundred thousand miles apart, the twin
worlds Sthor and Asthor rotated about their
common center of gravity, eternally facing
each other.
Ten million miles from their common center
of gravity, Teelan rotated in a vast orbit.
Sthor and Asthor were capped at each pole
now by gigantic white icecaps.
Mira was sulking, and as a consequence the
planets were freezing.
The expedition ship sank slowly toward Sthor.
A swarm of smaller craft had flown up at its
approach to meet it.
A gaily-colored small ship marked the official
greeting-ship.
Gresth had withheld his news purposely.
Now suddenly he began broadcasting it from
the powerful transmitter on his ship.
As the words came through on a thousand sets,
all the little ships began to whirl, dance
and break out into glowing, sparkling lights.
On Sthor and Asthor even commotions began
to be visible.
A new planetary system had been found— They
could move!
Their overflowing populations could be spread
out!
The whole Insthor system went mad with delight
as the great Expeditionary Ship settled downward.
IV
There was a glint of humor in Buck Kendall's
eyes as he passed the sheet over to McLaurin.
Commander McLaurin looked down the columns
with twinkling eyes.
"'Petition to establish the Lunar Mining Bank,'"
he read.
"What a bank!
Officers: President, General James Logan,
late of the IP; Vice-president, Colonel Warren
Gerardhi, also late of the IP; Staff, consists
of 90% ex-IP men, and a few scattered accountants.
Designed by the well-known designer of IP
stations, Colonel Richard Murray."
Commander McLaurin looked up at Kendall with
a broad grin.
"And you actually got Interplanetary Life
to give you a mortgage on the structure?"
"Why not?
It'll cut cost fifty-eight millions, with
its twelve-foot tungsten-beryllium walls and
the heavy defense weapons against those terrible
pirates.
You know we must defend our property."
"With the thing you're setting up out there
on Luna, you could more readily wipe out the
IP than anything else I know of.
Any new defense ideas?"
"Plenty.
Did you get any further appropriations from
the IP Appropriations Board?"
McLaurin looked sour.
"No.
The dear taxpayers might object, and those
thickheaded, clogged rockets on the Board
can't see your data on the Stranger.
They gave me just ten millions, and that only
because you demonstrated you could shoot every
living thing out of the latest IP cruiser
with that neutron gun of yours.
By the way, they may kick when I don't install
more than a few of those."
"Let 'em.
You can stall for a few months.
You'll need that money more for other purposes.
You've installed that paraffin lining?"
"Yes—I got a report on that of 'finished'
last week.
How have you made out?"
Buck Kendall's face fell.
"Not so hot.
Devin's been the biggest help—he did most
of the work on that neutron gun really—"
"After," McLaurin interrupted, "you told him
how."
"—but we're pretty well stuck now, it seems.
You'll be off duty tomorrow evening, can't
you drop around to the lab?
We're going to try out a new system for releasing
atomic energy."
"Isn't that a pretty faint hope?
We've been trying to get it for three centuries
now, and haven't yet.
What chance at it within a year or so?—which
is the time you allow yourself before the
Stranger returns."
"It is, I'll admit that.
But there's another factor, not to be forgotten.
The data we got from correlating those 'misreadings'
from the various IP posts mean a lot.
We are working on an entirely different trail
now.
You come on out, and you can see our new apparatus.
They are working on tremendous voltages, and
hoping to smash the thing by a brutal bombardment
of terrific voltage.
We're trying, thanks to the results of those
instruments, to get results with small, terrifically
intense fields."
"How do you know that's their general system?"
"They left traces on the records of the post
instruments.
These records show such intensities as we
never got.
They have atomic energy, necessarily, and
they might have had material energy, actual
destruction of matter, but apparently, from
the field readings it's the former.
To be able to make those tremendous hops,
light-years in length, they needed a real
store of energy.
They have accumulators, of course, but I don't
think they could store enough power by the
system they use to do it."
"Well, how's your trick 'bank' out on Luna,
despite its twelve-foot walls, going to stand
an atomic explosion?"
"More protective devices to come is our only
hope.
I'm working on three trails: atomic energy,
some type of magnetic shield that will stop
any moving material particle, and their faster-than-light
thing.
Also, that fortress—I mean, of course, bank—is
going to have a lot of lead-lined rooms."
"I wish I could use the remaining money the
Board gave me to lead-line a lot of those
IP ships," said McLaurin wistfully.
"Can't you make a gamma-ray bomb of some sort?"
"Not without their atomic energy release.
With it, of course, it's easy to flood a region
with rays.
It'll be a million times worse than radium
'C,' which is bad enough."
"Well, I'll send through this petition for
armaments.
They'll pass it all right, I think.
They may get some kicks from old Jacob Ezra
Stubbs.
Jacob Ezra doesn't believe in anything war-like.
I wish they'd find some way to keep him off
of the Arms Petition Board.
He might just as well stay home and let 'em
vote his ticket uniformly 'nay.'"
Buck Kendall left with a laugh.
Buck Kendall had his troubles though.
When he had reached Earth again, he found
that his properties totaled one hundred and
three million dollars, roughly.
One doesn't sell properties of that magnitude,
one borrows against them.
But to all intents and purposes, Buck Kendall
owned two half-completed ship's hulls in the
Baldwin Spaceship Yards, a great deal of massive
metal work on its way to Luna, and contracts
for some very extensive work on a "bank."
Beyond that, about eleven million was left.
A large portion of the money had been invested
in a laboratory, the like of which the world
had never seen.
It was devoted exclusively to physics, and
principally the physics of destruction.
Dr. Paul Devin was the Director, Cole was
in charge of the technical work, and Buck
Kendall was free to do all the work he thought
needed doing.
Returned to his laboratory, he looked sourly
at the bench on which seven mechanicians were
working.
The ninth successive experiment on the release
of atomic energy had failed.
The tenth was in process of construction.
A heavy pure tungsten dome, three feet in
diameter, three inches thick, was being lowered
over a clear insulum dome, a foot smaller.
Inside, the real apparatus was arranged around
the little pool of mercury.
From it, two massive tungsten-copper alloy
conductors led through the insulum housing,
and outside.
These, so Kendall had hoped, would surge with
the power of broken atoms, but he was beginning
to believe rather bitterly, they would never
do so.
Buck went on to his offices, and the main
calculator room.
There were ten calculator tables here, two
of them in operation now.
"Hello, Devin.
Getting on?"
"No," said Devin bitterly, "I'm getting off.
Look at these results."
He brought over a sheaf of graphs, with explanatory
tables attached.
Rapidly Buck ran through them with him.
Most of them were graphs of functions of light,
considered as a wave in these experiments.
"H-m-m-m—not very encouraging.
Looks like you've got the field—but it just
snaps shut on itself and won't work.
The lack of volume makes it break down, if
you establish it, and makes it impossible
to establish in the first place without the
energy of matter.
Not so hot.
That's certainly cock-eyed somewhere."
"I'm not.
The math may be."
"Well"—Kendall grinned—"it amounts to
the same thing.
The point is, light doesn't.
Let's run over that theory again.
Light is not only magnetic; but electric.
Somehow it transforms electric fields cyclically
into magnetic fields and back again.
Now what we want to do is to transform an
electric into a magnetic field and have it
stay there.
That's the first step.
The second thing, is to have the lines of
magnetic force you develop, lie down like
a sheath around the ship, instead of standing
out like the hairs on an angry cat, the way
they want to.
That means turning them ninety degrees, and
turning an electric into a magnetic field
means turning the space-strain ninety degrees.
Light evidently forms a magnetic field whose
lines of force reach along its direction of
motion, so that's your starting point."
"Yes, and that," growled Devin, "seems to
be the finishing point.
Quite definitely and clearly, the graph looped
down to zero.
In other words, the field closed in on itself,
and destroyed itself."
"Light doesn't vanish."
"I'll make you all the lights you want."
"I simply mean there must be something that
will stop it."
"Certainly.
Transform it back to electric field before
it gets a chance to close in, then repeat
the process—the way light does."
"That wouldn't make such a good magnetic shield.
Every time that field started pulsing out
through the walls of the ship it would generate
heat.
We want a permanent field that will stay on
the job out there.
I wonder if you couldn't make a conductor
device that would open that field out—some
special type of oscillating field that would
keep it open."
"H-m-m-m—that's an angle I might try.
Any suggestions?"
Kendall had suggestions, and rapidly he outlined
a development that appeared from some of the
earlier mathematics on light, and might be
what they wanted.
Kendall, however, had problems of his own
to work on.
The question of atomic energy he was leaving
alone, till the present experiment either
succeeded, or, as he rather suspected, failed
as had its predecessors.
His present problem was to develop more fully
some interesting lines of research he had
run across in investigating mathematically
the trick of turning electric to magnetic
fields and then turning them back again.
It might be that along this line he would
find the answer to the speed greater than
that of light.
At any rate, he was interested.
He worked the rest of that day, and most of
the next on that line—till he ran it into
the ground with a pair of equations that ended
with the expression: dx.dv=h/(4πm).
Then Kendall looked at them for a long moment,
then he sighed gently and threw them into
a file cabinet.
Heisenberg's Uncertainty.
He'd reduced the thing to a form that simply
told him it was beyond the limits of certainty
and he ran it into the normal, natural uncertainty
inevitable in Nature.
Anyway he had real work to do now.
The machine was about ready for his attention.
The mechanicians had finished putting it in
shape for demonstration and trial.
He himself would have to test it over the
rest of the afternoon and arrange for power
and so forth.
By evening, when Commander McLaurin called
around with some of the other investors in
Kendall's "bank" on Luna, the thing was already
started, warming up.
The fields were being fed and the various
scientists of the group were watching with
interest.
Power was flowing in already at a rate of
nearly one hundred thousand horsepower per
minute, thanks to a special line given them
by New York Power (a Kendall property).
At ten o'clock they were beginning to expect
the reaction to start.
By this time the fields weren't gaining in
intensity very rapidly, a maximum intensity
had been reached that should, they felt, break
the atoms soon.
At eleven-thirty, through the little view
window, Buck Kendall saw something that made
him cry out in amazement.
The mercury metal in the receiver, behind
its layers of screening was beginning to glow,
with a dull reddish light, and little solidifications
were appearing in it!
Eagerly the men looked, as the solidifications
spread slowly, like crystals growing in an
evaporating solution.
Twelve o'clock came and went, and one o'clock
and two o'clock.
Still the slow crystallization went on.
Buck Kendall was casting furtive glances at
the kilowatt-hour meter.
It stood at a figure that represented twenty-seven
thousand dollars' worth of power.
Long since the power rate had been increased
to the maximum available, as the power plant's
normal load reduced as the morning hours came.
Surely, this time something would start, but
Buck had two worries.
If all the enormous amount of energy they
had poured in there decided to release itself
at once—
And at any rate, Buck saw they'd never dare
to let a generator stop, once it was started!
The men were a tense group around the machine
at three-fifteen a.m.
There remained only a tiny, dancing globule
of silvery mercury skittering around on the
sharp, needle-like crystals of the dull red
metal that had resulted.
Slowly that skittering drop was shrinking—
Three twenty-two and a half a.m. saw the last
fraction of it vanish.
Tensely the men stared into the machine—backing
off slowly—watching the meters on the board.
At nearly eighty thousand volts the power
had been fed into it.
The power continued to flow, and a growing
halo of intense violet light appeared suddenly
on those red, needle-like crystals, a swiftly
expanding halo—
Without a sound, without the slightest disturbance,
the halo vanished, and softly, gently, the
needle-like crystals relapsed, melted away,
and a dull pool of metallic mercury rested
in the receiver.
At eighty thousand volts, power was flowing
in—
And it didn't even sparkle.
V
The apparatus of the magnetic shield had been
completed two days later, and set up in Buck's
own laboratory.
On the bench was the powerful, but small,
little projector of the straight magnetic
field, simply a specially designed accumulator,
a super-condenser, and the peculiar apparatus
Devin had designed to distort the electric
field through ninety degrees to a magnetic
field.
Behind this was a curious, paraboloid projector
made up of hundreds of tiny, carefully orientated
coils.
This was Buck's own contribution.
They were ready for the tests.
"I would invite McLaurin in to see this,"
said Kendall looking at them, and then across
the room bitterly toward the alleged atomic
power apparatus on the opposite bench.
"I think it will work.
But after that—" He stared, glaring, at
the heavy tungsten dome with its heavy tungsten
contacts, across which the flame of released
atomic energy was supposed to have leapt.
"That was probably the flattest flop any experiment
ever flopped."
"Well—it didn't blow up.
That's one comfort," suggested Devin.
"I wish it had.
Then at least it would have shown some response.
The only response shown, actually, was shown
on the power meter.
It damn near wore out the bearings turning
so fast."
"Personally, I prefer the lack of action."
Devin laughed.
"Have you got that circuit hooked up?"
"Right," sighed Kendall, turning back to the
work in hand.
"Is Douglass in on this?"
"Yes—in the next room.
He'll let us know when he's ready.
He's setting up those instruments."
Douglass, a young junior physicist, late of
the IP Physics Department, stuck his head
in the door and announced his instruments
were all set up.
"Keep an eye on them.
They'll move somehow, at any rate.
This thing couldn't go as flat as that atom-buster
of mine."
Carefully Kendall made a few last-minute adjustments
on the limiting relays, and took up his position
at the power board.
Devin took his place near the apparatus, with
another series of instruments, similar to
those Douglass was now watching in the next
room, some thirty feet away, through the two-inch
metal wall.
"Ready," called Kendall.
The switch shot home.
Instantly Kendall, Devin, and all the men
in the building jumped some six feet from
their former positions.
A monstrous roar of sound crashed out in that
laboratory that thundered from one wall to
the other, and bellowed in a Titan's fury.
It thundered and growled, it bellowed and
howled, the walls shook with the march and
counter-march of crashing waves of sound.
And a ten-foot wavering flame of blue-white,
bellying electric fire shuddered up to the
ceiling from the contact points of the alleged
atomic generator.
The heat, pouring out from the flashing, roaring
arc sent prickles of aching burns over Kendall's
skin.
For ten seconds he stood in utter, paralyzed
surprise as his flop of flops bellowed its
anger at his disdain.
Then he leapt to the power board and shut
off the roaring thing, by cutting the switch
that had started it.
"Spirits of Space!
Did that come to life!"
"Atomic Energy!"
Devin cried.
"Atomic energy, hell.
That's my thirty thousand dollars' worth of
power breaking loose again," chortled Kendall.
"We missed the atomic energy, but, sweet boy,
what an accumulator we stubbed our toes on!
I wondered where in blazes all that power
went to.
That's the answer.
I'll bet I can tell you right now what happened.
We built that mercury up to a new level, and
that transitional stage was the red, crystalline
metal.
When it reached the higher stage, it was temporarily
stable—but that projector over there that
we designed for the purpose of holding open
electric and magnetic fields just opened the
door and let all that power right out again."
"But why isn't it atomic energy?
How do you know that no more than your power
that you put in is coming out?"
demanded Devin.
"The arc, man, the arc.
That was a high-current, and low-voltage arc.
Couldn't you tell by the sound that no great
voltage—as atomic voltages go—was smashing
across there?
If we were getting atomic voltage—and power—there'd
have been a different tone to it, high and
shriller.
"Now, did you take any readings?"
"What do you think, man?
I'm human.
Do you think I got any readings with that
thing bellowing and shrieking in my ears,
and burning my skin with ultra-violet?
It itches now."
Kendall laughed.
"You know what to do for an itch.
Now, I'm going to make a bet.
We had those points separated for a half-million
volts discharge, but there was a dust-cover
thrown over them just now.
That, you notice, is missing.
I'll bet that served as a starter lead for
the main arc.
Now I'm going to start that projector thing
again, and move the points there through about
six inches, and that thing probably won't
start itself."
Most of the laboratory staff had collected
at the doorway, looking in at the white-hot
tungsten discharge points, and the now silent
"atomic engine."
Kendall turned to them and said: "The flop
picked itself up.
You go on back, we seem to be all in one piece
yet.
Douglass, you didn't get any readings, did
you?"
Sheepishly, Douglass grinned at him.
"Eh—er—no—but I tore my pants.
The magnetic field grabbed me and I jumped.
They had some steel buttons, and a lot of
steel keys—they're kinda' hard to keep on
now."
The laboratory staff broke into a roar of
laughter, as Douglass, holding up his trousers
with both hands was beheld.
"I guess the field worked," he said.
"I guess maybe it did," adjudged Kendall solemnly.
"We have some rope here if you need it—"
Douglass returned to his post.
Swiftly, Kendall altered the atomic distortion
storage apparatus, and returned to the power-board.
"Ready?"
"Check."
Kendall shoved home the switch.
The storage device was silent.
Only a slight feeling of strain made itself
felt, and the sudden noisy hum of a small
transformer nearby.
"She works, Buck!"
Devin called.
"The readings check almost exactly."
"All good then.
Now I want to get to that atomic thing.
We can let that slide for a little bit—I'll
answer it."
The telephone had rung noisily.
"Kendall Labs—Kendall speaking."
"This is Superintendent Foster, of the New
York Power, Mr. Kendall.
We have some trouble just now that we think
your operations may be responsible for.
The sub-station at North Beaumont blew all
the fuses, and threw the breakers at the main
station.
The men out there said the transformers began
howling—"
"Right you are—I'm afraid I did do that.
I had no idea that it would reach so far.
How far is that from my place here?"
"It's about a thousand yards, according to
the survey maps."
"Thanks—and I'll be careful about it.
Any damage, I am responsible for?
All okay?"
"Yes, sir, Mr. Kendall."
Kendall hung up.
"We stirred up a lot more dust than we expected,
Devin.
Now let's start seeing if we can keep track
of it.
Douglass, how did your readings show?"
"I took them at the ten stations, and here
they are.
The stations are two feet apart."
"H-m-m—.5—.55—.6—.7—20—198—5950—6010—6012—5920.
Very, very nice—only the darned thing's
got an arm as long as the law.
Your readings were about .2, Devin?"
"That's right."
"Then these little readings are just leakage.
What's our normal intensity here?"
"About .19.
Just a very small fraction less than the readings."
"Perfect—we have what amounts to a hollow
shell of magnetic force—we can move inside,
and you can move outside—far enough.
But you can't get a conductor or a magnetic
field through it."
He put the readings on the bench, and looked
at the apparatus across the room.
"Now I want to start right on that other.
Douglass, you move that magnetostat apparatus
out of the way, and leave just the 'can-opener'
of ours—the projector.
I'm pretty sure that's what does the deed.
Devin, see if you can hunt up some electrostatic
voltmeters with a range in the neighborhood
of—I think it'll be about eighty thousand."
Rapidly, Douglass was dismounting the apparatus,
as Devin started for the stock room.
Kendall started making some new connections,
reconnecting the apparatus they had intended
using on the "atomic engine," largely high-capacity
resistances.
He seemed to perform this work mechanically,
his mind definitely on something else.
Suddenly he stopped, and looked carefully
into the receiver of the machine.
The metal in it was silvery, liquid, and here
and there a floating crystal of the dull red
metal.
Slowly a smile spread across his face.
He turned to Douglass.
"Douglass—ah, you're through.
Get on the trail of MacBride, and get him
and his crew to work making half a dozen smaller
things like this.
Tell 'em they can leave off the tungsten shield.
I want different metals in the receiver of
each.
Use—hmmm—sodium—copper—magnesium—aluminium,
iron and chromium.
Got it?"
"Yes, sir."
He left, just as Devin returned with a large
electrostatic voltmeter.
"I'd like," said he, "to know how you know
the voltage will range around eighty thousand."
"K-ring excitation potential for mercury.
I'm willing to bet that thing simply shoved
the whole electron system of the mercury out
a notch—that it simply hasn't any K-ring
of electrons now.
I'm trying some other metals.
Douglass is going to have MacBride make up
half a dozen more machines.
Machines—they need a name.
This—ah—this is an 'atostor.'
MacBride's going to make up half a dozen of
'em, and try half a dozen metals.
I'm almost certain that's not mercury in there
now, at all.
It's probably element 99 or something like
it."
"It looks like mercury—"
"Certainly.
So would 99.
Following the periodic table, 99 would probably
have an even lower melting point than mercury,
be silvery, dense and heavy—and perhaps
slightly radioactive.
The series under the B family of Group II
is Magnesium, Zinc, Cadmium, Mercury—and
99.
The melting point is going down all the way,
and they're all silvery metals.
I'm going to try copper, and I fully expect
it to turn silvery—in fact, to become silver."
"Then let's see."
Swiftly they hooked up the apparatus, realigned
the projector, and again Kendall took his
place at the power-board.
As he closed the switch, on no-load, the electrostatic
voltmeter flopped over instantly, and steadied
at just over 80,000 volts.
"I hate to say 'I told you so,'" said Kendall.
"But let's hook in a load.
Try it on about 100 amps first."
Devin began cutting in load.
The resistors began heating up swiftly as
more and more current flowed through them.
By not so much as by a vibration of the voltmeter
needle, did the apparatus betray any strain
as the load mounted swiftly.
100—200—500—1000 amperes.
Still, that needle held steady.
Finally, with a drain of ten thousand amperes,
all the equipment available could handle,
the needle was steady as a rock, though the
tremendous load of 800,000,000 watts was cut
in and out.
That, to atoms, atoms by the nonillions, was
no appreciable load at all.
There was no internal resistance whatever.
The perfect accumulator had certainly been
discovered.
"I'll have to call McLaurin—" Kendall hurried
away with a broad, broad smile.
VI
"Hello, Tom?"
The
telephone rattled in a peeved sort of way.
"Yes, it is.
What now?
And when am I going to see you in a social
sort of way again?"
"Not for a long, long time; I'm busy.
I'm busy right now as a matter of fact.
I'm calling up the vice-president of Faragaut
Interplanetary Lines, and I want to place
an order."
"Why bother me?
We have clerks, you know, for that sort of
thing," suggested Faragaut in a pained voice.
"Tom, do you know how much I'm worth now?"
"Not much," replied Faragaut promptly.
"What of it?
I hear, as a matter of fact that you're worth
even less in a business way.
They're talking quite a lot down this way
about an alleged bank you're setting up on
Luna.
I hear it's got more protective devices, and
armor than any IP station in the System, that
you even had it designed by an IP designer,
and have a gang of Colonels and Generals in
charge.
I also hear that you've succeeded in getting
rid of money at about one million dollars
a day—just slightly shy of that."
"You overestimate me, my friend.
Much of that is merely contracted for.
Actually it'll take me nearly nine months
to get rid of it.
And by that time I'll have more.
Anyway, I think I have something like ten
million left.
And remember that way back in the twentieth
century some old fellow beat my record.
Armour, I think it was, lost a million dollars
a day for a couple of months running.
"Anyway, what I called you up for was to say
I'd like to order five hundred thousand tons
of mercury, for delivery as soon as possible."
"What!
Oh, say, I thought you were going in for business."
Faragaut gave a slight laugh of relief.
"Tom, I am.
I mean exactly what I say.
I want five—hundred—thousand—tons of
metallic mercury, and just as soon as you
can get it."
"Man, there isn't that much in the system."
"I know it.
Get all there is on the market for me, and
contract to take all the 'Jupiter Heavy-Metals'
can turn out.
You send those orders through, and clean out
the market completely.
Somebody's about to pay for the work I've
been doing, and boy, they're going to pay
through the nose.
After you've got that order launched, and
don't make a christening party of the launching
either, why just drop out here, and I'll show
you why the value of mercury is going so high
you won't be able to follow it in a space
ship."
"The cost of that," said Faragaut, seriously
now, "will be about—fifty-three million
at the market price.
You'd have to put up twenty-six cash, and
I don't believe you've got it."
Buck laughed.
"Tom, loan me a dozen million, will you?
You send that order through, and then come
see what I've got.
I've got a break, too!
Mercury's the best metal for this use—and
it'll stop gamma rays too!"
"So it will—but for the love of the system,
what of it?"
"Come and see—tonight.
Will you send that order through?"
"I will, Buck.
I hope you're right.
Cash is tight now, and I'll probably have
to put up nearer twenty million, when all
that buying goes through.
How long will it be tied up in that deal,
do you think?"
"Not over three weeks.
And I'll guarantee you three hundred percent—if
you'll stay in with me after you start.
Otherwise—I don't think making this money
would be fair just now."
"I'll be out to see you in about two hours,
Buck.
Where are you?
At the estate?" asked Faragaut seriously.
"In my lab out there.
Thanks, Tom."
McLaurin was there when Tom Faragaut arrived.
And General Logan, and Colonel Gerardhi.
There was a restrained air of gratefulness
about all of them that Tom Faragaut couldn't
quite understand.
He had been looking up Buck Kendall's famous
bank, and more and more he had begun to wonder
just what was up.
The list of stockholders had read like a list
of IP heroes and executives.
The staff had been a list of IP men with a
slender sprinkling of accountants.
And the sixty-million dollar structure was
to be a bank without advertising of any sort!
Usually such a venture is planned and published
months in advance.
This had sprung up suddenly, with a strange
quietness.
Almost silently, Buck Kendall led the way
to the laboratory.
A small metal tank was supported in a peculiar
piece of apparatus, and from it led a small
platinum pipe to a domed apparatus made largely
of insulum.
A little pool of mercury, with small red crystals
floating in it rested in a shallow hollow
surrounded by heavy conductors.
"That's it, Tom.
I wanted to show you first what we have, and
why I wanted all that mercury.
Within three weeks, every man, woman and child
in the system will be clamoring for mercury
metal.
That's the perfect accumulator."
Quickly he demonstrated the machine, charging
it, and then discharging it.
It was better than 99.95% efficient on the
charge, and was 100% efficient on the discharge.
"Physically, any metal will do.
Technically, mercury is best for a number
of reasons.
It's a liquid.
I can, and do it in this, charge a certain
quantity, and then move it up to the storage
tank.
Charge another pool, and move it up.
In discharge, I can let a stream flow in continuously
if I required a steady, terrific drain of
power without interruption.
If I wanted it for more normal service, I'd
discharge a pool, drain it, refill the receiver,
and discharge a second pool.
Thus, mercury is the metal to use.
"Do you see why I wanted all that metal?"
"I do, Buck—Lord, I do," gasped Faragaut.
"That is the perfect power supply."
"No, confound it, it isn't.
It's a secondary source.
It isn't primary.
We're just as limited in the supply of power
as ever—only we have increased our distribution
of power.
Lord knows, we're going to need a power supply
badly enough before long—" Buck relapsed
into moody silence.
"What," asked Faragaut, looking around him,
"does that mean?"
It was McLaurin who told him of the stranger
ship, and Kendall's interpretation of its
meaning.
Slowly Faragaut grasped the meaning behind
Buck's strange actions of the past months.
"The Lunar Bank," he said slowly, half to
himself.
"Staffed by trained IP men, experts in expert
destruction.
Buck, you said something about the profits
of this venture.
What did you mean?"
Buck smiled.
"We're going to stick up IP to the extent
necessary to pay for that fort—er—bank—on
Luna.
We'll also boost the price so that we'll make
enough to pay for those ships I'm having made.
The public will pay for that."
"I see.
And we aren't to stick the price too high,
and just make money?"
"That's the general idea."
"The IP Appropriations Board won't give you
what you need, Commander, for real improvements
on the IP ships?"
"They won't believe Kendall.
Therefore they won't."
"What did you mean about gamma rays, Buck?"
"Mercury will stop them and the Commander
here intends to have the refitted ships built
so that the engine room and control room are
one, and completely surrounded by the mercury
tanks.
The men will be protected against the gamma
rays."
"Won't the rays affect the power stored in
the mercury—perhaps release it?"
"We tried it out, of course, and while we
can't get the intensities we expect, and can't
really make any measurements of the gamma-ray
energy impinging on the mercury—it seems
to absorb, and store that energy!"
"What's next on the program, Buck?"
"Finish those ships I have building.
And I want to do some more development work.
The Stranger will return within six months
now, I believe.
It will take all that time, and more for real
refitting of the IP ships."
"How about more forts—or banks, whichever
you want to call them.
Mars isn't protected."
"Mars is abandoned," replied General Logan
seriously.
"We haven't any too much to protect old Earth,
and she must come first.
Mars will, of course, be protected as best
the IP ships can.
But—we're expecting defeat.
This isn't a case of glorious victory.
It will be a case of hard won survival.
We don't know anything about the enemy—except
that they are capable of interstellar flights,
and have atomic energy.
They are evidently far ahead of us.
Our battle is to survive till we learn how
to conquer.
For a time, at least, the Strangers will have
possession of most of the planets of the system.
We do not think they will be able to reach
Earth, because Commander McLaurin here will
withdraw his ships to Earth to protect the
planet—and the great 'Lunar Bank' will display
its true character."
VII
Faragaut looked unsympathetically at Buck
Kendall, as he stood glaring perplexedly at
the apparatus he had been working on.
"What's the matter, Buck, won't she perk?"
"No, damn it, and it should."
"That," pointed out Faragaut, "is just what
you think.
Nature thinks otherwise.
We generally have to abide by her opinions.
What is it—or what is it meant to be?"
"Perfect reflector."
"Make a nice mirror.
What else, and how come?"
"A mirror is just what I want.
I want something that will reflect all the
radiation that falls on it.
No metal will, even in its range of maximum
reflectivity.
Aluminum goes pretty high, silver, on some
ranges, a bit higher.
But none of them reaches 99%.
I want a perfect reflector that I can put
behind a source of wild, radiant energy so
I can focus it, and put it where it will do
the most good."
"Ninety-nine percent.
Sounds pretty good.
That's better efficiency than most anything
else we have, isn't it?"
"No, it isn't.
The accumulator is 100% efficient on the discharge,
and a good transformer, even before that,
ran as high as 99.8 sometimes.
They had to.
If you have a transformer handling 1,000,000
horsepower, and it's even 1% inefficient,
you have a heat loss of nearly 10,000 horsepower
to handle.
I want to use this as a destructive weapon,
and if I hand the other fellow energy in distressing
amounts, it's even worse at my end, because
no matter how perfect a beam I work out, there
will still be some spread.
I can make it mighty tight though, if I make
my surface a perfect parabola.
But if I send a million horse, I have to handle
it, and a ship can't stand several hundred
thousand horsepower roaming around loose as
heat, let alone the weapon itself.
The thing will be worse to me than to him.
"I figured there was something worth investigating
in those fields we developed on our magnetic
shield work.
They had to do, you know, with light, and
radiant energy.
There must be some reason why a metal reflects.
Further, though we can't get down to the basic
root of matter, the atom, yet, we can play
around just about as we please with molecules
and molecular forces.
But it is molecular force that determines
whether light and radiant energy of that caliber
shall be reflected or transmitted.
Take aluminum as an example.
In the metallic molecule state, the metal
will reflect pretty well.
But volatilize it, and it becomes transparent.
All gases are transparent, all metals reflective.
Then the secret of perfect reflection lies
at a molecular level in the organization of
matter, and is within our reach.
Well—this thing was supposed to make that
piece of silver reflective.
I missed it that time."
He sighed.
"I suppose I'll have to try again."
"I should think you'd use tungsten for that.
If you do have a slight leak, that would handle
the heat."
"No, it would hold it.
Silver is a better conductor of heat.
But the darned thing won't work."
"Your other scheme has."
Faragaut laughed.
"I came out principally for some signatures.
IP wants one hundred thousand tons of mercury.
I've sold most of mine already in the open
market.
You want to sell?"
"Certainly.
And I told you my price."
"I know," sighed Faragaut.
"It seems a shame though.
Those IP board men would pay higher.
And they're so damn tight it seems a crime
not to make 'em pay up when they have to."
"The IP will need the money worse elsewhere.
Where do I—oh, here?"
"Right.
I'll be out again this evening.
The regular group will be here?"
Kendall nodded as he signed in triplicate.
That evening, Buck had found the trouble in
his apparatus, for as he well knew, the theory
was right, only the practical apparatus needed
changing.
Before the group composed of Faragaut, McLaurin
and the members of Kendall's "bank," he demonstrated
it.
It was merely a small, model apparatus, with
a mirror of space-strained silver that was
an absolutely perfect reflector.
The mirror had been ground out of a block
of silver one foot deep, by four inches square,
carefully annealed, and the work had all been
done in a cooling bath.
The result was a mirror that was so nearly
a perfect paraboloid that the beam held sharp
and absolutely tight for the half-mile range
they tested it on.
At the projector it was three and one-half
inches in diameter.
At the target, it was three and fifty-two
one hundredths inches in diameter.
"Well, you've got the mirror, what are you
going to reflect with it now?" asked McLaurin.
"The greatest problem is getting a radiant
source, isn't it?
You can't get a temperature above about ten
thousand degrees, and maintain it very long,
can you?"
"Why not?"
Kendall smiled.
"It'll volatilize and leave the scene of action,
won't it?"
"What if it's a gaseous source already?"
"What?
Just a gas-flame?
That won't give you the point source you need.
You're using just a spotlight here, with a
Moregan Point-light.
That won't give you energy, and if you use
a gas-flame, the spread will be so great,
that no matter how perfectly you figure your
mirror, it won't beam."
"The answer is easy.
Not an ordinary gas-flame—a very extra-special
kind of gas-flame.
Know anything about Renwright's ionization-work?"
"Renwright—he's an IP man isn't he?"
"Right.
He's developed a system, which, thanks to
the power we can get in that atostor, will
sextuply ionize oxygen gas.
Now: what does that mean?"
"Spirits of space!
Concentrated essence of energy!"
"Right.
And in preparation, Cole here had one made
up for me.
That—and something else.
We'll just hook it up—"
With Devin's aid, Kendall attached the second
apparatus, a larger device into which the
silver block with its mirror surface fitted.
With the uttermost care, the two physicists
lined it up.
Two projectors pointed toward each other at
an angle, the base angles of a triangle, whose
apex was the center of the mirror.
On very low power, a soft, glowing violet
light filtered out through the opening of
the one, and a slight green light came from
the other.
But where the two streams met, an intense,
violet glare built up.
The center of action was not at the focus,
and slowly this was lined up, till a sharp,
violet beam of light reached out across the
open yard to the target set up.
Buck Kendall cut off the power, and slowly
got into position.
"Now.
Keep out from in front of that thing.
Put on these glasses—and watch out."
Heavy, thick-lensed orange-brown goggles were
passed out, and Kendall took his place.
Before him, a thick window of the same glass
had been arranged, so that he might see uninterruptedly
the controls at hand, and yet watch unblinded,
the action of the beam.
Dully the mirror-force relay clicked.
A hazy glow ran over the silver block, and
died.
Then—simultaneously the power was thrown
from two small, compact atostors into the
twin projectors.
Instantly—a titanic eruption of light almost
invisibly violet, spurted out in a solid,
compact stream.
With a roar and crash, it battered its way
through the thick air, and crashed into the
heavy target plate.
A stream of flame and scintillating sparks
erupted from the armor plate—and died as
Kendall cut the beam.
A white-hot area a foot across leaked down
the face of the metal.
"That," said Faragaut gently, removing his
goggles.
"That's not a spotlight, and it's not exactly
a gas-flame.
But I still don't know what that blue-hot
needle of destruction is.
Just what do you call that tame stellar furnace
of yours?"
"Not so far off, Tom," said Kendall happily,
"except that even S Doradus is cold compared
to that.
That sends almost pure ultra-violet light—which,
by the way, it is almost impossible to reflect
successfully, and represents a temperature
to be expressed not in thousands of degrees,
nor yet in tens of thousands.
I calculated the temperature would be about
750,000 degrees.
What is happening is that a stream of low-voltage
electrons—cathode rays—in great quantity
are meeting great quantities of sextuply ionized
oxygen.
That means that a nucleus used to having two
electrons in the K-ring, and six in the next,
has had that outer six knocked off, and then
has been hurled violently into free air.
"All by themselves, those sextuply ionized
oxygen atoms would have a good bit to say,
but they don't really begin to talk till they
start roaring for those electrons I'm feeding
them.
At the meeting point, they grab up all they
can get—probably about five—before the
competition and the fierce release of energy
drives them out, part-satisfied.
I lose a little energy there, but not a real
fraction.
It's the howl they put up for the first four
that counts.
The electron-feed is necessary, because otherwise
they'd smash on and ruin that mirror.
They work practically in a perfect vacuum.
That beam smashes the air out of the way.
Of course, in space it would work better."
"How could it?" asked Faragaut, faintly.
"Kendall," asked McLaurin, "can we install
that in the IP ships?"
"You can start."
Kendall shrugged.
"There isn't a lot of apparatus.
I'm going to install them in my ships, and
in the—bank.
I suspect—we haven't a lot of time left."
"How near ready are those ships?"
"About.
That's all I can say.
They've been torn up a bit for installation
of the atostor apparatus.
Now they'll have to be changed again."
"Anything more coming?"
Buck smiled slowly.
He turned directly to McLaurin and replied:
"Yes—the Strangers.
As to developments—I can't tell, naturally.
But if they do, it will be something entirely
unexpected now.
You see, given one new discovery, a half-dozen
will follow immediately from it.
When we announced that atostor, look what
happened.
Renwright must have thought it was God's gift
to suffering physicists.
He stuck some oxygen in the thing, added some
of his own stuff—and behold.
The magnetic apparatus gave us directly the
shield, and indirectly this mirror.
Now, I seem to have reached the end for the
time.
I'm still trying to get that space-release
for high speed—speed greater than light,
that is.
So far," he added bitterly, "all I've gotten
as an answer is a single expression that simply
means practical zero—Heisenberg's Uncertainty
Expression."
"I'm uncertain as to your meaning"—McLaurin
smiled—"but I take it that's nothing new."
"No.
Nearly four centuries old—twentieth century
physics.
I'll have to try some other line of attack,
I guess, but that did seem so darned right.
It just sounded right.
Something ought to happen—and it just keeps
saying 'nothing more except the natural uncertainty
of nature.'"
"Try it out, your math might be wrong somewhere."
Kendall laughed.
"If it was—I'd hate to try it out.
If it wasn't I'd have no reason to.
And there's plenty of other work to do.
For one thing, getting that apparatus in production.
The IP board won't like me."
Kendall smiled.
"They don't," replied McLaurin.
"They're getting more and more and more worried—but
they've got to keep the IP fleet in such condition
that it can at least catch an up-to-date freighter."
Gresth Gkae looked back at Sthor rapidly dropping
behind, and across at her sister world, Asthor,
circling a bare 100,000 miles away.
Behind his great interstellar cruiser came
a long line of similar ships.
Each was loaded now not with instruments and
pure scientists, but with weapons, fuel and
warriors.
Colonists too, came in the last ships.
One hundred and fifty giant ships.
All the wealth of Sthor and Asthor had been
concentrated in producing those great machines.
Every one represented nearly the equivalent
of thirty million Earth-dollars.
Four and a half billions of dollars for mere
materials.
Gresth Gkae had the honor of lead position,
for he had discovered the planets and their
stable, though tiny, sun.
Still, Gresth Gkae knew his own giant Mira
was a super-giant sun—and a curse and a
menace to any rational society.
Our yellow-white sun (to his eyes, an almost
invisible color, similar to our blue) was
small, but stable, and warm enough.
In half an hour, all the ships were in space,
and at a given signal, at ten-second intervals,
they sprang into the superspeed, faster than
light.
For an instant, giant Mira ran and seemed
distorted, as though seen through a porthole
covered with running water, then steadied,
curiously distorted.
Faster than light they raced across the galaxy.
Even in their super-fast ships, nearly three
and a half weeks passed before the sun they
sought, singled itself from the star-field
as an extra bright point.
Two days more, and the sun was within planetary
distance.
They came at an angle to the plane of the
ecliptic, but they leveled down to it now,
and slanted toward giant Jupiter and Jovian
worlds.
Ten worlds, in one sweep, it was—four habitable
The nine satellites would be converted into
forts at once, nine space-sweeping forts guarding
the approaches to the planet.
Gresth Gkae had made a fairly good search
of the worlds, and knew that Earth was the
main home of civilization in this system.
Mars was second, and Venus third.
But Jupiter offered the greatest possibilities
for quick settlement, a base from which they
could more easily operate, a base for fuels,
for the heavy elements they would need—
Fifteen million miles from Jupiter they slowed
below the speed of light—and the IP stations
observed them.
Instantly, according to instructions issued
by Commander McLaurin, a fleet of ten of the
tiniest, fastest scouts darted out.
As soon as possible, a group of three heavy
cruisers, armed with all the inventions that
had been discovered, the atostor power system,
perfectly conducting power leads, the terrible
UV ray, started out.
The scouts got there first.
Cameras were grinding steadily, with long
range telescopic lenses, delicate instruments
probed and felt and caught their fingers in
the fields of the giant fleet.
At ten-second intervals, giant ships popped
into being, and glided smoothly toward Jupiter.
Then the cruisers arrived.
They halted at a respectful distance, and
waited.
The Miran ships plowed on undisturbed.
Simultaneously, from the three leaders, terrific
neutron rays shot out.
The paraffin block walls stopped those—and
the cruisers started to explain their feelings
on the subject.
They were the IP-J-37, 39, and 42.
The 37 turned up the full power of the UV
ray.
The terrific beam of ultra-violet energy struck
the second Miran ship, and the spot it touched
exploded into incandescence, burned white-hot—and
puffed out abruptly as the air pressure within
blew the molten metal away.
The Mirans were startled.
This was not the type of thing Gresth Gkae
had warned them of.
Gresth Gkae himself frowned as the sudden
roar of the machines of his ship rose in the
metal walls.
A stream of ten-inch atomic bombs shrieked
out of their tubes, fully glowing green things
floated out more slowly, and immediately waxed
brilliant.
Gamma ray bombs—but they could be guarded
against—
The three Solarian cruisers were washed in
such frightful flame as they had never imagined.
Streams of atomic bombs were exploding soundlessly,
ineffectively in space, not thirty feet from
them as they felt the sudden resistance of
the magnetic shields.
Hopefully, the 39 probed with her neutron
gun.
Nothing happened save that several gamma ray
bombs went off explosively, and all the atomic
bombs in its path exploded at once.
Gresth Gkae knew what that meant.
Neutron beam guns.
Then this race was more intelligent than he
had believed.
They had not had them before.
Had he perhaps given them too much warning
and information?
There was a sudden, deeper note in the thrumming
roar of the great ship.
Eagerly Gresth Gkae watched—and sighed in
relief.
The nearer of the three enemy ships was crumbling
to dust.
Now the other two were beginning to become
blurred of outline.
They were fleeing—but oh, so slowly.
Easily the greater ship chased them down,
till only floating dust, and a few small pieces
of—
Gresth Gkae shrieked in pain, and horror.
The destroyed ships had fought in dying.
All space seemed to blossom out with a terrible
light, a light that wrapped around them, and
burned into him, and through him.
His eyes were dark and burning lumps in his
head, his flesh seemed crawling, stinging—he
was being flayed alive—in shrieking agony
he crumpled to the floor.
Hospital attachés came to him, and injected
drugs.
Slowly torturing consciousness left him.
The doctors began working over his horribly
burned body, shuddering inwardly as the protective,
feather-like covering of his skin loosened,
and dropped from his body.
Tenderly they lowered him into a bath of chemicals—
"The terrible light which caused so much damage
to our men," reported a physicist, "was analyzed,
and found to have some extraordinary lines.
It was largely mercury-vapor spectrum, but
the spectrum of mercury-atoms in an impossibly
strained condition.
I would suggest that great care be used hereafter,
and all men be equipped with protective masks
when observations are needed.
This sun is very rich in the infra-X-rays
and ultra-visible light.
The explosion of light, we witnessed, was
dangerous in its consisting almost wholly
of very short and hard infra-X-rays."
The physicist had a special term for what
we know as ultra-violet light.
To him, blue was ultra-violet, and exceedingly
dangerous to red-sensitive eyes.
To him, our ultra-violet was a long X-ray,
and was designated by a special term.
And to him—the explosion of the atostor
reservoirs was a terrible and mystifying calamity.
To the men in the five tiny scout-ships, it
was also a surprise, and a painful one.
Even space-hardened humans were burned by
the terrifically hard ultra-violet from the
explosion.
But they got some hint of what it had meant
to the Mirans from the confusion that resulted
in the fleet.
Several of the nearer ships spun, twisted,
and went erratically off their courses.
All seemed uncontrolled momentarily.
The five scouts, following orders, darted
instantly toward the Lunar Bank.
Why, they did not know.
But those were orders.
They were to land there.
The reason was that, faster than any Solarian
ship, radio signals had reached McLaurin,
and he, and most of the staff of the IP service
had been moved to the Lunar Bank.
Buck Kendall had extended an invitation in
this "unexpected emergency."
It so happened that Buck Kendall's invitation
got there before any description of the Strangers,
or their actions had arrived.
The staff was somewhat puzzled as to how this
happened—
And now for the satellites of great Jupiter.
One hundred and fifty giant interstellar cruisers
advanced on Callisto.
They didn't pause to investigate the mines
and scattered farms of the satellite, but
ten great ships settled, and a horde of warriors
began pouring out.
One hundred and forty ships reached Ganymede.
One hundred and thirty sailed on.
One hundred and thirty ships reached Europa—and
they sailed on hurriedly, one hundred and
twenty-nine of them.
Gresth Gkae did not know it then, but the
fleet had lost its first ship.
The IP station on Europa had spoken back.
They sailed in, a mighty armada, and the first
dropped through Europa's thin, frozen atmosphere.
They spotted the dome of the station, and
a neutron ray lashed out at it.
On the other, undefended worlds, this had
been effective.
Here—it was answered by ten five-foot UV
rays.
Further, these men had learned something from
the destruction of the cruisers, and ten torpedoes
had been unloaded, reloaded with atostor mercury,
and sent out bravely.
Easily the Mirans wiped out the first torpedo—
Shrieking, the Miran pilots clawed their way
from the controls as the fearful flood of
ultra-violet light struck their unaccustomed
skins.
Others too felt that burning flood.
The second torpedo they caught and deflected
on a beam of alternating-current magnetism
that repelled it.
It did not come nearer than half a mile to
the ship.
The third they turned their deflecting beam
on—and something went strangely wrong with
the beam.
It pulled that torpedo toward the ship with
a sickening acceleration—and the torpedo
exploded in that frightful violet flame.
Five-foot diameter UV beams are nothing to
play with.
The Mirans were dodging these now as they
loosed atomic bombs, only to see them exploded
harmlessly by neutron guns, or caught in the
magnetic screen.
Gamma ray bombs were as useless.
Again the beam of disintegrating force was
turned on—
The present opponent was not a ship.
It was an IP defense station, equipped with
everything Solarian science knew, and the
dome was an eight-foot wall of tungsten-beryllium.
The eight feet of solid, ultra-resistant alloy
drank up that crumbling beam, and liked it.
The wall did not fail.
The men inside the fort jerked and quivered
as the strange beam, a small, small fraction
of it, penetrated the eight feet of outer
wall, the six feet or so of intervening walls,
and the mercury atostor reserves.
"Concentrate all those UV beams on one spot,
and see if you can blast a hole in him before
he shakes it loose," ordered the ray technician.
"He'll wiggle if you start off with the beam.
Train your sights on the nose of that first
ship—when you're ready, call out."
"Ready—ready—" Ten men replied.
"Fire!"
roared the technician.
Ten titanic swords of pure ultra-violet energy,
energy that practically no unconditioned metal
will reflect to more than fifty per cent,
emerged.
There was a single spot of intense incandescence
for a single hundredth of a second—and then
the energy was burning its way through the
inner, thinner skins with such rapidity that
they sputtered and flickered like a broken
televisor.
One hundred and twenty-nine ships retreated
hastily for conference, leaving a gutted,
wrecked hull, broken by its fall, on Europa.
Triumphantly, the Europa IP station hurled
out its radio message of the first encounter
between a fort and the Miran forces.
Most important of all, it sent a great deal
of badly wanted information regarding the
Miran weapons.
Particularly interesting was the fact that
it had withstood the impact of that disintegrating
ray.
VIII
Grimly Buck Kendall looked at the reports.
McLaurin stood beside him, Devin sat across
the table from him.
"What do you make of it, Buck?" asked the
Commander.
"That we have just one island of resistance
left on the Jovian worlds.
And that will, I fear, vanish.
They haven't finished with their arsenal by
any means."
"But what was it, man, what was it that ruined
those ships?"
"Vibration.
Somehow—Lord only knows how it's done—they
can project electric fields.
These projected fields are oscillated, and
they are tuned in with some parts of the ship.
I suspect they are crystals of the metals.
If they can start a vibration in the crystals
of the metal—that's fatigue, metal fatigue
enormously speeded.
You know how a quartz crystal oscillator in
a radio-control apparatus will break, if you
work it on a very heavy load at the peak?
They simply smash the crystals of metal in
the same way.
Only they project their field."
"Then our toughest metals are useless?
Can't something tough, rather than hard, like
copper or even silver for instance, stand
it?"
"Calcium metal's the toughest going—and
even that would break under the beating those
ships give it.
The only way to withstand it is to have such
a mass of metal that the oscillations are
damped out.
But—"
The set tuned in on the IP station on Europa
was speaking again.
"The ships are returning.
There are one hundred and twenty-nine by accurate
count.
Jorgsen reports that telescopic observation
of the dead on the fallen cruiser show them
to be a completely un-human race!
They are of mottled coloring, predominately
grayish brown.
The ships are returning.
They have divided into ten groups, nine groups
of two each, and a main body of the rest of
the fleet.
The group of eighteen is descending within
range, and we are focusing our beams on them—"
Out by Europa, ten great UV beams were stabbing
angrily toward ten great interstellar ships.
The metal of the hulls glowed brilliant, and
distorted slowly as the thick walls softened
under the heat, and the air behind pressed
against it.
Grimly the ten ships came on.
Torpedoes were being launched, and exploded,
and now they had no effect, for the Mirans
within were protected.
The eighteen grouped ships separated, and
arranged themselves in a circle around the
fort.
Suddenly one staggered as a great puff of
gas shot out through the thin atmosphere of
Europa to flare brilliantly in the lash of
the stabbing UV beam.
Instantly the ship righted itself, and labored
upward.
Another dropped to take its place—
And the great walls of the IP fort suddenly
groaned and started in their welded joints.
The faint, whispering rustle of the crumbling
beam was murmuring through the station.
Engineers shouted suddenly as meters leapt
the length of their scales, and the needles
clicked softly on the stop pins.
A thin rustle came from the atostors grouped
in the great power room.
"Spirits of Space—a revolving magnetic field!"
roared the Chief Technician.
"They're making this whole blasted station
a squirrel cage!"
The mighty walls of eight-foot metal shuddered
and trembled.
The UV beams lashed out from the fort in quivering
arcs now, they did not hold their aim steady,
and the magnetic shield that protected them
from atomic bombs was working and straining
wildly.
Eighteen great ships quivered and tugged outside
there now, straining with all their power
to remain in the same spot, as they passed
on from one to another the magnetic impulses
that were now creating a titanic magnetic
vortex about the fort.
"The atostors will be exhausted in another
fifteen minutes," the Chief Technician roared
into his transmitter.
"Can the signals get through those fields,
Commander?"
"No, Mac.
They've been stopped, Sparks tells me.
We're here—and let's hope we stay.
What's happening?"
"They've got a revolving magnetic field out
there that would spin a minor planet.
The whole blasted fort is acting like the
squirrel cage in an induction motor!
They've made us the armature in a five hundred
million horsepower electric motor."
"They can't tear this place loose, can they?"
"I don't know—it was never—" The Chief
stopped.
Outside a terrific roar and crash had built
up.
White darts of flame leapt a thousand feet
into the air, hurling terrific masses of shattered
rock and soil.
"I was going to say," the Chief went on, "this
place wasn't designed for that sort of a strain.
Our own magnetic field is supporting us now,
preventing their magnetic field from getting
its teeth on metal.
When the strain comes—well, they're cutting
loose our foundation with atomic bombs!"
Five UV beams were combined on one interstellar
ship.
Instantly the great machine retreated, and
another dropped in to take its place while
the magnetic field spun on, uninterruptedly.
"Can they keep that up long?"
"God knows—but they have a hundred and more
ships to send in when the power of one gives
out, remember."
"What's our reserve now?"
The Chief paused a moment to look at the meters.
"Half what it was ten minutes ago!"
Commander Wallace sent some other orders.
Every torpedo tube of the station suddenly
belched forth deadly, fifteen-foot torpedoes,
most of them mud-torpedoes, torpedoes loaded
with high explosive in the nose, a delayed
fuse, and a load of soft clinging mud in the
rear.
The mud would flow down over the nose and
offer a resistance foot-hold for the explosive
which empty space would not.
Four hundred and three torpedoes, equipped
with anti-magnetic apparatus darted out.
One hundred and four passed the struggling
fields.
One found lodgement on a Miran ship, and crushed
in a metal wall, to be stopped by a bulkhead.
The Chief engineer watched his power declining.
All ten UV beams were united in one now, driving
a terrible sword of energy that made the attacked
ship skip for safety instantly, yet the beams
were all but useless.
For the Miran reserves filled the gap, and
the magnetic tornado continued.
For seventeen long minutes the station resisted
the attack.
Then the last of the strained mercury flowed
into the receivers, and the vast power of
the atostors was exhausted.
Slowly the magnetic fields declined.
The great walls of the station felt the clutching
lines of force—they began to heat and to
strain.
A low, harsh grinding became audible over
the roar of the atomic bombs.
The whole structure trembled, and jumped slightly.
The roar of bombs ceased suddenly, as the
station jerked again, more violently.
Then it turned a bit, rolled clumsily.
Abruptly it began to spin violently, more
and more rapidly.
It started rolling clumsily across the plateau—
A rain of atomic bombs struck the unprotected
metal, and the eighth breached the walls.
The twentieth was the last.
There was no longer an IP station on Europa.
"The difference," said Buck Kendall slowly,
when the reports came in from scout-ships
in space that had witnessed the last struggle,
"between an atomic generator and an atomic
power-store, or accumulator, is clearly shown.
We haven't an adequate source of power."
McLaurin sighed slowly, and rose to his feet.
"What can we do?"
"Thank our lucky stars that Faragaut here,
and I, bought up all the mercury in the system,
and had it brought to Earth.
We at least have a supply of materials for
the atostors."
"They don't seem to do much good."
"They're the best we've got.
All the photocells on Earth and Venus and
Mercury are at present busy storing the sun's
power in atostors.
I have two thousand tons of charged mercury
in our tanks here in the 'Lunar Bank.'"
"Much good that will do—they can just pull
and pull and pull till it's all gone.
A starfish isn't strong, but he can open the
strongest oyster just because he can pull
from now on.
You may have a lot of power—but."
"But—we also have those new fifteen-foot
UV beams.
And one fifteen-foot UV beam is worth, theoretically,
nine five-foot beams, and practically, a dozen.
We have a dozen of them.
Remember, this place was designed not only
to protect itself, but Earth, too."
"They can still pull, can't they?"
"They'll stop pulling when they get their
fingers burned.
In the meantime, why not use some of those
IP ships to bring in a few more cargoes of
charged mercury?"
"They aren't good for much else, are they?
I wonder if those fellows have anything more
we don't know?"
"Oh, probably.
I'm going to work on that crumbler thing.
That's the first consideration now."
"Why?"
"So we can move a ship.
As it is, even those two we built aren't any
good."
"Would they be anyway?"
"Well—I think I might disturb those gentlemen
slightly.
Remember, they each have a nose-beam eighteen
feet across.
Exceedingly unpleasant customers."
"Score: Strangers; magnetic field, atomic
bombs, atomic power, crumbler ray.
Home team; UV beams."
Kendall grinned.
"I'd heard you were a pessimistic cuss when
battle started—"
"Pessimistic, hell, I'm merely counting things
up."
"McClellan had all the odds on Lee back in
the Civil War of the States—but Lee sent
him home faster than he came."
"But Lee lost in the end."
"Why bring that up?
I've got work to do."
Still smiling, Kendall went to the laboratory
he had built up in the "Lunar Bank."
Devin was already there, calculating.
He looked unhappy.
"We can't do anything, as far as I can see.
They're using an electric field all right,
and projecting it.
I can't see how we can do that."
"Neither can I," agreed Kendall, "so we can't
use that weapon.
I really didn't want to anyway.
Like the neutron gun which I told Commander
McLaurin would be useless as a weapon, they'd
be prepared for it, you can be sure.
All I want to do is fight it, and make their
projection useless."
"Well, we have to know how they project it
before we can break up the projection, don't
we?"
"Not at all.
They're using an electric field of very high
frequency, but variable frequency.
As far as I can see, all we need is a similar
variable electric field of a slightly different
frequency to heterodyne theirs into something
quite harmless."
"Oh," said Devin.
"We could, couldn't we?
But how are you going to do that?"
"We'll have to learn, that's all."
Buck Kendall started trying to learn.
In the meantime, the Mirans were taking over
Jupiter.
There were three IP stations on the planet
itself, but they were vastly hindered by the
thick, almost ultra-violet-proof atmosphere
of Jupiter.
Their rays were weak.
And the magnetic fields of the Mirans were
unaffected.
Only their atomic bombs were hindered by the
heavier gravity that pulled the rocks back
in place faster than the bombs could throw
them out.
Still—a few hours of work, and the IP stations
on Jupiter had rolled wildly across the flat
plains of the planet like dented cans, to
end in utter destruction.
The Mirans had paid no attention to the fleeing
passenger and freighter ships that left the
planet, loaded to the utmost with human cargo,
and absolutely no freight.
The IP fleet had to go to their rescue with
oxygen tanks to take care of the extra humans,
but nearly three-quarters of the population
of Jupiter, a newly established population,
and hence a readily mobile one, was saved.
The others, the Mirans did not bother with
particularly except when they happened to
be near where the Mirans wanted to work.
Then they were instantly destroyed by atomic
bombing, or gamma rays.
The Mirans settled almost at once, and began
their work of finding on Jupiter the badly
needed atomic fuels.
Machines were set up, and work begun, Mirans
laboring under the gravity of the heavy planet.
Then, fifty ships swam up again, reloaded
with fuel, and with crews consisting solely
of uninjured warriors, and started for Mars.
Mars was half way between her near conjunction
and her maximum elongation with respect to
Jupiter at that time.
The Mirans knew their business though, for
they started in on the IP station on Phobos.
They were practiced by this time, and this
IP station had only seven five-foot beams.
In half an hour that station fell, and its
sister station on Deimos followed.
Three wounded ships returned to Jupiter, and
ten new ships came out.
The attack on Mars itself was started.
Mars was a different proposition.
There were thirty-two IP stations here, one
of them nearly as powerful as the Lunar Bank
station.
It was equipped with four of the huge fifteen-foot
beams.
And it had fifteen tons of mercury, more than
seven-eighths charged.
The Mars Center Station was located a short
ten miles from the Mars Center City, and under
the immediate orders of the IP heads, Mars
Center City had been vacated.
For two days the Mirans hung off Mars, solidifying
their positions on Phobos and Deimos.
Then, with sixty-two ships, they attacked.
They had made some very astute observations,
and they started on the smaller stations just
beyond the range of the Mars Center Station.
Naturally, near so powerful a center, these
stations had never been strong.
They fell rapidly.
But they had been counted on by Mars Center
as auxiliary supports.
McLaurin had sent very definite orders to
Mars Center forbidding any action on their
part, save gathering of power-supplies.
At last the direct attack on Mars Center was
launched.
For the first time, the Mirans saw one of
the fifteen-foot beams.
Mars' atmosphere is thin, and there is little
ozone.
The ultra-violet beams were nearly as effective
as in empty space.
When the Mirans dropped their ships, a full
thirty of them, into the circle formation,
Mars Center answered at once.
All four beams started.
Those fifteen-foot beams, connected directly
to huge atostor release apparatus, delivered
a maximum power of two and three-quarter billion
horsepower, each.
The first Miran ship struck, sparkled magnificently,
and a terrific cascade of white-hot metal
rolled down from its nose.
The great ship nosed down and to the left
abruptly, accelerated swiftly—and crashed
with tremendous energy on the plain outside
of Mars Center City.
White, unwavering flames licked up suddenly,
and made a column five hundred feet high against
the dark sky.
Then the wreck exploded with a violence that
left a crater half a mile across.
Three other ships had been struck, and were
rapidly retreating.
Another try was made for the ring formation,
and four more ships were wounded, and replaced.
The ring did not retreat, but the great magnetic
field started.
Atomic and gamma ray bombs started now, flashing
sometimes dangerously close to the station
as its magnetic field battled the rotating
field of the ships.
The four greater beams, and many smaller ones
were in swift and angry action.
Not more than a ten-second exposure could
be endured by any one ship, before it must
retreat.
For five minutes the Mirans hung doggedly
at their task.
Then, wisely, they retreated.
Of the fleet, not more than seven ships remained
untouched.
Mars Center Station had held—at what cost
only they knew.
Five hundred tons of their mercury had been
exhausted in that brief five minutes.
One hundred tons a minute had flowed into
and out of the atostor apparatus.
Mars Center radioed for help, when the fleet
lifted.
There was one other station on Mars that stood
a good chance of survival, Deenmor Station,
with three of the big beams installed, and
apparatus for their fourth was in the station,
and being rapidly worked over.
McLaurin did a wise and courageous thing,
at which every man on Mars cursed.
He ordered that all IP stations save these
two be deserted, and all mercury fuel reserves
be moved to Deenmor and Mars Center.
The Mirans could not land on the North Western
section of Mars, nor in the South Central
region.
Therefore Mars was not exactly habitable to
Miran ships, because the great beams had been
so perfectly figured that they were effective
at a range of nearly twelve hundred miles.
Deenmor station was attacked—but it was
a half-hearted attack, for Mirans were becoming
distinctly skittish about fifteen-foot UV
beams.
Two badly blistered ships—and the Mirans
retreated to Jupiter.
But Mira held Phobos and Deimos.
In two weeks, they had set up cannon there,
and proved themselves accurate long-range
gunners.
Against the feeble attraction of Deimos, and
with Mars' gravity to help them, they began
bombarding the two stations, and anything
that attempted to approach them, with gamma
and atomic explosive bombs.
Meanwhile they amused themselves occasionally
by planting a gamma-ray bomb in each of Mars'
major cities.
They made Mars uninhabitable for Solarians
as well as for Mirans, at least until the
deadly slow-action atomic explosives wore
off, or were removed.
Then the Mirans, after a lapse of three weeks
while they dug in their toes on Jupiter, prepared
to leap.
Earth was the next goal.
Miran scout-ships had been sent out before
this—and severely handled by the concentrated
fleets of the IP that hung grimly off Earth
and Luna now.
But the scouts had learned one thing.
Mirans could never hope to attain a firm grasp
on Earth while terribly armed Luna hung like
a Sword of Damocles over their heads.
Further, attack on Earth directly would be
next to impossible, for, thanks to Faragaut's
Interplanetary Company, nearly all the mercury
metal in the system was safely lodged on Earth,
and saturated with power.
Every major city had been equipped with great
UV apparatus.
And neutron guns in plenty waited on small
ships just outside the atmosphere to explode
harmlessly any atomic or gamma bombs Miran
ships might attempt to deposit.
An attack on Luna was the first step.
But that terrible, gigantic fort on Luna worried
them.
Yet while that fort existed, Earth ships were
free to come and go, for Mirans could not
afford to stand near.
At a distance of twenty thousand miles, small
Miran ships had felt the touch of those great
UV beams.
Finally, a brief test-attack was made, with
an entire fleet of one hundred ships.
They drew almost into position, faster than
light, faster than the signaling warnings
could send their messages.
In position, all those great ships strained
and heaved at the mighty magnetic vortex that
twisted at the field of the fort.
Instantly, twelve of the fifteen-foot UV beams
replied.
And—two great UV beams of a size the Mirans
had never seen before, beams from the two
ships, "S Doradus" and "Cepheid."
The test-attack dissolved as suddenly as it
had come.
The Mirans returned to Jupiter, and to the
outer planets where they had further established
themselves.
Most of the Solar system was theirs.
But the Solarians still held the choicest
planets—and kept the Mirans from using the
mild-temperatured Mars.
IX
"They can't take this, at least," sighed McLaurin
as they retreated from Luna.
"I didn't think they could—right away.
I'm wondering though if they haven't something
we haven't seen yet.
Besides which—give them time, give them
time."
"Well, give us time, too," snapped McLaurin.
"How are you coming?"
Buck smiled.
"I'm sure I don't know.
I have a machine but I haven't the slightest
idea of whether or not it's any good."
"Why not?"
"I can destroy—I hope—but I can't build
up their ray.
I can't test the machine because I haven't
their ray to test it against."
"What can we do to test it?"
"The only thing I can see is to call for volunteers—and
send out a six-man cruiser.
If the ship's too small, they may not destroy
it with the big crumbler rays.
If it's too large—and the machine didn't
work—we'd lose too much."
Twelve hours later, the IP men at the Lunar
Bank fort were lined up.
McLaurin stepped up on the platform, and addressed
the men briefly, told them what was needed.
Six volunteers were selected by a process
of elimination, those who were married, had
dependents, officers, and others were refused.
Finally, six men of the IP were chosen, neither
rookies nor veterans, six average men.
And one average six-man cruiser, one hundred
and eleven feet long, twenty-two in diameter.
It was the T-208, a sister ship of the T-247,
the first ship to be destroyed.
The T-208 started out from Luna, and with
full acceleration, sped out toward Phobos.
Slowly she circled the satellite, while distant
scouts kept her under view.
Lazily, the Miran patrol on Phobos watched
the T-208, indifferent to her.
The T-208 dove suddenly, after five fruitless
circles of the tiny world, and with her four-foot
UV beam flaming, stabbed angrily at a flight
of Miran scouts berthed in the very shadow
of a great battle cruiser, one of the interstellar
ships stationed here on Phobos.
Four of the little ships slumped in incandescence.
Angrily the terrific sword of energy slashed
at the frail little scouts.
Angrily the Miran interstellar ship shot herself
abruptly into action against this insolent
cruiser.
The cruiser launched a flight of the mercury-torpedoes.
Flashing, burning, ultra-violet energy flooded
the great ship, harmlessly, for the men were,
as usual, protected.
The Miran answered with the neutron beam,
atomic and gamma bombs—and the crumbler
ray.
Gently, softly a halo of shimmering-violet
luminescence built up about the T-208.
The UV beam continued to flare, wavering slightly
in its aim—then fell way off to one side.
The T-208 staggered suddenly, wandered from
her course—whole, but uncontrolled.
For the men within the ship were dead.
Majestically the Miran swung along beside
the dead ship, a great magnetic tow-cable
shot out toward it, to shy off at first, then
slowly to be adjusted, and take hold in the
magnetic shield of the T-208.
The pilots of the watching scout-ships turned
away.
They knew what would happen.
It did.
Five—ten—twenty seconds passed.
Then the "dead-man" took over the ship—and
the stored power in the atostor tanks blasted
in a terrible flame that shattered the metal
hull to molecular fragments.
The interstellar cruiser shuddered, and rolled
half over at the blasting pressure.
Leaking seams appeared in her plates.
The scouts raced back to Luna as the Miran
settled heavily, and a trifle clumsily to
Phobos.
Miran radio-beams were forcing their way out
toward the Miran station on Europa, to be
relayed to the headquarters on Jupiter, just
as Solarian radio beams were thrusting through
space toward Luna. Said the Miran messages:
"Their ships no longer crumble."
Said the Solarian messages: "The ships no
longer crumble—but the men die."
His deep eyes burning tensely, Buck Kendall
heard the messages coming in, and rose slowly
from his seat to pace the floor.
"I think I know why," he said at last.
"I should have thought.
For that too can be prevented."
"Why—what in the name of the Planets?"
asked McLaurin.
"It didn't kill the men in the forts—why
does it kill the men in the ships, when the
ships are protected?"
"The protection kills them."
"But—but they had the protective oscillations
on all the way out!"
protested the Commander.
"Think how it works though.
Think, man.
The enemy's field is an electric-field oscillation.
We combat it by setting up a similar oscillating
field in the metal of the hull ourselves.
Because the metal conducts the strains, they
meet, and oppose.
It is not a shield—a shield is impossible,
as I have said, because of energy concentration
factors.
If their beam carried a hundred thousand horsepower
in a ten-foot square beam, in every ten square
feet of our shield, we'd have to have one
hundred thousand horsepower.
In other words, hundreds of times as much
energy would be needed in the shield, as they
used in their beam.
We can't afford that.
We had to let the beams oppose our oscillations
in the metal, where, because the metal conducts,
they meet on an equal basis.
But—when two oscillations of slightly different
frequency meet, what is the result?"
"In this case, a heterodyne frequency of a
lower, and harmless frequency."
"So I thought.
I was partly right.
It does not harm the metal.
But it kills the men.
It is super-sonic.
The terrible, shrill sounds destroy the cells
of the men's bodies.
Then, when their dead hands release the controls,
the automatic switches blow up the ship."
"God!
We stop one menace—and it is like the Hydra.
For every head we lop off, two spring up."
"Ah—but they are lesser heads.
Look, what is the fundamental difference between
sound and light?"
"One is a vibration of matter and the—ah—eliminate
the material contact!"
"Exactly!
All we need to do is to let the ships operate
airless, the men in space suits.
Then the air cannot carry the sounds to them.
And by putting special damping materials in
their suits, we can stop the vibrations that
would reach them through their feet and hands.
Another six-man ship must go out—but this
ship will come back!"
And with the order for another experimental
ship, went the orders for commercial supplies
of this new apparatus.
Every IP ship must be equipped to resist it.
Buck Kendall sailed on the six-man scout that
went out this time.
Again they swooped once at Phobos, again Miran
scout-ships crumbled under the attack of the
vicious UV beams.
The Mirans were not waiting contemptuously
this time.
In an instant the great interstellar ship
rose from its berth, its weapons working angrily.
The crumbler ray snapped out at the T-253.
Kendall stared into the periscope visor intently.
Clumsily his padded hands worked at the specially
adapted controls.
The soft hiss of the oxygen release into his
suit disturbed him slightly.
The radio-phones in his helmet carried all
the conversations in the ship to him with
equal clarity.
He watched as the great ship angled angrily
up—
His vision was momentarily obscured by a violet
glow that built up and reached out gently
from every point of metal in the ship.
The instant Kendall saw that, the T-253 was
fleeing under his hands.
The test had been made.
Now all he desired was safety again.
The ion-rockets flared recklessly as, crushed
under an acceleration of four Earth-gravities,
he sank heavily into his seat.
Grimly the Miran ship was pursuing them, easily
keeping up with the fleeing midget.
The crumbler became more intense, the violet
glow more vivid.
The UV beam was reaching out directly behind
now.
The—
With a cry of agony, Kendall ripped the radio-phone
connection out of his suit.
A soft hiss of leaking air warned him of too
great violence only minutes later.
For his ears had been deafened by the sudden
shriek of a tremendous signal from outside!
Instantly Kendall knew what that meant.
And he could not communicate with his men!
There was no metal in these special suits,
even the oxygen tanks were made of synthetic
plastics of tremendous strength.
No scrap of vibrating metal was permissible.
The padded gloves and boots protected him—but
there was a new and different type of crackle
and haze from the metal points now.
It was almost invisible in the practically
airless ship, but Kendall saw it.
Presently he felt it, as he desperately increased
his acceleration.
Slow creeping heat was attacking him.
The heat was increasing rapidly now.
Desperately he was working at the crumbler-protection
controls—but immediately set them back as
they were.
He had to have the crumbler protection as
well—!
Grimly the great Miran ship hung right beside
them.
Angrily the two four-foot UV beams flashed
back—seeking some weak spot.
There were none.
At her absolute maximum of acceleration the
little ship plunged on.
Gamma and atomic bombs were washing her in
flame.
The heavy blocks of paraffin between her walls
were long since melted, retained only by the
presence of the metal walls.
Smoke was beginning to filter out now, and
Kendall recognized a new, and deadlier menace!
Heat—quantities of heat were being poured
into the little ship, and the neutron guns
were doing their best to add to it.
The paraffin was confined in there—and like
any substance, it could be volatilized, and
as a vapor, develop pressure—explosive pressure!
The Miran seemed satisfied in his tactics
so far—and changed them.
Forty-seven million miles from Earth, the
Miran simply accelerated a bit more, and crowded
the Solarian ship a bit.
White-faced, Buck Kendall was forced to turn
a bit aside.
The Miran turned also.
Kendall turned a bit more—
Flashing across his range of vision at an
incredible speed, a tiny thing, no more than
twenty feet long and five in diameter, a scout-ship
appeared.
Its tiny nose ultra-violet beam was blasting
a solid cylinder of violet incandescence a
foot across in the hull of the Miran—and,
to the Miran, angling swiftly across his range
of vision.
Its magnetic field clashed for a thousandth
of a second with the T-253, instantly meeting,
and absorbing the fringing edges.
Then—it swept through the Miran's magnetic
shield as easily.
The delicate instruments of the scout instantaneously
adjusted its own magnetic field as much as
possible.
There was resistance, enormous resistance—the
ship crumpled in on itself, the tail vanished
in dust as a sweeping crumbler beam caught
it at last—and the remaining portion of
the ship plowed into the nose of the Miran.
The Miran's force-control-room was wrecked.
For perhaps a minute and a half, the ship
was without control, then the control was
re-established—and in vain the telescopes
and instruments searched for the T-253.
Lightless, her rockets out now, her fields
damped down to extinction, the T-253 was lost
in the pulsing, gyrating fields of half a
dozen scout-ships.
Kendall looked grimly at the crushed spot
on the nose of the Miran.
His ship was drifting slowly away from the
greater ship.
Presently, however, the Miran put on speed
in the direction of Earth, and the T-253 fell
far behind.
The Miran was not seriously injured.
But that scout pilot, in sacrificing life,
had thrown dust in their eyes for just those
few moments Kendall had needed to lose a lightless
ship in lightless space—lightless—for
the Mirans at any rate.
The IP ships had been covered with a black
paint, and in no time at all, Kendall had
gotten his ship into a position where the
energy radiations of the sun made him undetectable
from the Miran's position, since the radiation
of his own ship, even in the heat range, was
mingled with the direct radiation of the sun.
The sun was in the Miran's "eyes," both actual
and instrumental.
An hour later the Miran returned, passed the
still-lightless ship at a distance of five
million miles, and settled to Phobos for the
slight repairs needed.
Twelve hours later, the T-253 settled to Luna,
for the many rearrangements she would need.
"I rather knew it was coming," Kendall admitted
sadly, "but danged if I didn't forget all
about it.
And—cost the life of one of the finest men
in the system.
Jehnson's family get a permanent pension just
twice his salary, McLaurin.
In the meantime—"
"What was it?
Pure heat, but how?"
"Pure radio.
Nothing but short-wave radio directed at us.
They probably had the apparatus, knew how
to make it, but that's not a good type of
heat ray, because a radio tube is generally
less than eighty percent efficient, which
is a whale of a loss when you're working in
a battle, and a whale of an inconvenience.
We were heated only four times as much as
the Miran.
He had to pump that heat into a heat-reservoir—a
water tank probably—to protect himself.
Highly inefficient and ineffective against
a large ship.
Also, he had to hold his beam on us nearly
ten minutes before it would have become unbearable.
He was again, trying to kill the men, and
not the ship.
The men are the weakest point, obviously."
"Can you overcome that?"
"Obviously, no.
The thing works on pure energy.
I'd have to match his energy to neutralize
it.
You knew it's an old proposition, that if
you could take a beam of pure, monochromatic
light and divide it exactly in half, and then
recombine it in perfect interference, you'd
have annihilation of energy.
Cancellation to extinction.
The trouble is, you never do get that.
You can't get monochromatic light, because
light can't be monochromatic.
That's due to the Heisenberg Uncertainty—my
pet bug-bear.
The atom that radiates the light, must be
moving.
If it isn't, the emission of the light itself
gives it a kick that moves it.
Now, no matter what the quantum might have
been, it loses energy in kicking the atom.
That changes the situation instantly, and
incidentally the 'color' of the light.
Then, since all the radiating atoms won't
be moving alike, etc., the mass of light can't
be monochromatic.
Therefore perfect interference is impossible.
"The way that relates to the problem in hand,
is that we can't possibly destroy his energy.
We can, as we do in the crumbler stunt, change
it.
He can't, I suspect, put too much power behind
his crumbler, or he'd have crumbling going
on at home.
We get a slight heating from it, anyway.
Into the bargain, his radio was after us,
and his neutrons naturally carried energy.
Now, no matter what we do, we've got that
to handle.
When we fight his crumbler, we actually add
heat-energy to it, ourselves, and make the
heating effect just twice as bad.
If we try to heterodyne his radio—presto—it
has twice the heat energy anyway, though we
might reduce it to a frequency that penetrated
the ship instead of all staying in it.
But by the proposition, we have to use as
much energy, and in fact, remember the 80%
rule.
We've got to take it and like it."
"But," objected McLaurin, "we don't like it."
"Then build ships as big as his, and he'll
quit trying to roast you.
Particularly if the inner walls are synthetic
plastics.
Did you know I used them in the 'S Doradus'
and 'Cepheid'?"
"Yes.
Were you thinking of that?"
"No—just luck—and the fact that they're
light, strong as steel almost, and can be
manufactured in forms much more quickly.
Only the outer hull is tungsten-beryllium.
The advantage in this will be that nearly
all the energy will be absorbed outside, and
we'll radiate pretty fast, particularly as
that tungsten-beryllium has a high radiation-factor
in the long heat range."
"What does that mean?"
"Well, ordinary polished silver is a mighty
poor radiator.
Homely example: Try waiting for your coffee
to cool if it's in a polished silver pot.
Then try it in a tungsten-beryllium pot.
No matter how you polish that tungsten-beryllium,
the stuff WILL radiate heat.
That's why an IP ship is always so blamed
cold.
You know the passenger ships use polished
aluminum outer walls.
The big help is, that the tungsten-beryllium
will throw off the energy pretty fast, and
in a big ship, with a whale of a lot of matter
to heat, the Strangers will simply give up
the idea."
"Yes, but only two ships in the system compare
with them in size."
"Sorry—but I didn't build the IP fleet,
and there are lots of tungsten and beryllium
on Earth.
Enough anyway."
"Will they use that beam on the fort?
And can't we use the thing on them?"
"They won't and we won't—though we could.
A bank of those new million watt tubes—perhaps
a hundred of them—and we'd have a pretty
effective heater—but an awful waste of power.
I've got something better."
"New?"
"Somewhat.
I've found out how to make the mirror field
in a plate of metal, instead of a block.
Come on to the lab, and I'll show you."
"What's the advantage?
Oh—weight saved, and silver metal saved."
"A lot more than that, Mac.
Watch."
At the laboratory, the new apparatus looked
immensely lighter and simpler than the old.
The atostor, the ionizer, and the twin ion-projectors
were as before, great, rigid, metal structures
that would maintain the meeting point of the
ions with inflexible exactitude under any
acceleration strains.
But now, instead of the heavy silver block
in which a mirror was figured, the mirror
consisted of a polished silver plate, parabolic
to be sure, but little more than a half-inch
in thickness.
It was mounted in a framework of complex,
stout metal braces.
Kendall started the ion-flame at low intensity,
so the UV beam was little more than a spotlight.
"You missed the point, Mac.
Now—watch that tungsten-beryllium plate.
I'll hold the power steady.
It's an eighteen-inch beam—and now the energy
is just sufficient to heat that tungsten plate
to bright red.
But—"
Kendall turned over a small rheostat control—and
abruptly the eighteen-inch diameter spot on
the tungsten-beryllium plate began contracting;
it contracted till it was a blazing, sparkling
spot of molten incandescence less than an
inch across!
"That's the advantage of focus.
At this distance of a few hundred feet with
a small beam I can do that.
With a twenty-foot beam, I can get a two-foot
spot at a distance of nearly ten miles!
That means that the receiving end will have
the pleasure of handling one hundred times
the energy concentration.
That would punch a hole through most anything.
All you have to do is focus it.
The trouble being, if it's out of focus the
advantage is more than lost.
So if there's any question about getting the
focus, we'll get along without it."
"A real help, if you do.
That would punch a hole before the Stranger
ship could turn away as they do now."
Kendall nodded.
"That's what I was after.
It is mainly for the forts, though.
We'll have to signal the dope to the Mars
Center and Deenmor stations.
They can fix it up, themselves.
In the meantime—all we can do is hold on
and hunt, and let's hope better than the Strangers
do."
X
Sadly the convalescent Gresth Gkae listened
to the reports of his lieutenants.
More and more disgraced he felt as he realized
how badly he had blundered in reporting the
people of this system unable to cope with
the attackers' weapons.
Gresth Gkae looked up at his old friend and
physician, Merth Skahl.
He shook his head slowly.
"I'm afraid, Merth Skahl.
I am afraid.
We have, perhaps, made a mistake.
The better and the stronger alone should rule.
Aye, but is the stronger always the better?
I am afraid we have mistaken the Truth in
assuming this.
If we have—then may Jarth, Lord of Truth
and Wisdom punish us.
Mighty Jarth, if I have mistaken in following
my judgments, it is not from disobedience,
it is lack of Thy knowledge.
The strongest—they are not always the better,
are they?"
Merth Skahl bent sharply over his friend.
"Quiet thyself, Gresth Gkae.
You know, and I know, you have done only your
best, and surely Jarth himself can ask no
better of any one.
You must rest, for only by rest can those
terrible burns be healed.
All your stheen over half the body-area was
burned off.
You have been delirious for many days."
"But Merth Skahl, think—have we disobeyed
Jarth's will?
It is, we know, his will that only the best
and the strongest shall rule—but are the
best always the strongest?
An imbecile adult could destroy the life of
a genius-grade child.
The strongest wins, but not the best.
Such would not be the will of Jarth.
If we be the stronger, and the best, then
it is right and just that these strange creatures
should be destroyed that we may have a stable
world of stable light and heat.
But look and see, with what terrible swiftness
these strange creatures have learned!
May it not be they are the better race—that
it is we who are the weaker and the poorer?
Can it be that Jarth has brought us together
that these people might learn—and destroy
us?
If they be the stronger, and the better—then
may Jarth's will be done.
But we must test our strength to the utmost.
I must rise, and go to my laboratory soon.
They have set it up?"
"Aye, they have, Gresth Gkae.
But remember, the weak and the sick make faults
the strong and the well do not.
Better that you rest yourself.
There is little you can do while your body
seeks to recover from these terrible burns."
"You are wrong, my friend, wrong.
Don't you see that my mind is clear—that
it is the mind which must fight in these battles,
for surely the man is weak against such things
as this infra-X-radiation?
Why, I am better able to fight now than are
you, for I am a trained fighter of the mind,
while you are a trained healer of the body.
These strange beings with their stiff arms
and legs, their tender skins, and—and their
swift minds have fought us all too well.
If we must test, let it be a test.
I have heard how they so quickly solved the
riddle of the crumbling field.
That took us longer, and we designed it.
The Counsel of Worlds put me in command, let
me up, Skahl, I must work."
Concerned, the physician looked down at him.
Finally he spoke again.
"No, I will not permit you to leave the hospital-ship.
You must stay here, but if, as you have said,
the mind is what must fight, then surely you
can fight well from here, for your mind is
here."
"No, I cannot, and you well know it.
I may shorten my life, but what matter.
'Death is the end toward which the chemical
reaction, Life, tends,'" quoted the scientist.
"You know I have left my children—my immortality
is assured through them.
I can afford to die in peace, if it assures
their welfare.
Time is precious, and while my mind might
work from here, it must have data on which
to work.
For that, I must go to the laboratories.
Help me, Merth Skahl."
Reluctantly the physician granted the request,
but begged of Gresth Gkae a promise of at
least six hours rest in every fifteen, and
a good sleep of at least twenty-seven hours
every "night."
Gresth Gkae agreed, and from a wheelchair,
conducted his work, began a new line of experimentation
he hoped would yield them the weapon they
needed.
Under him, the staff of scientists worked,
aiding and advising and suggesting.
The apparatus was built, tested, and found
wanting.
Time and again as the days passed, they watched
Gresth Gkae, gaining strength very, very slowly,
taken away despondent at the end of his forty
hours of work.
A dozen expeditions were sent to Jupiter's
poles to watch and measure and study the tremendous
auroral displays there, where Jupiter's vast
magnetic field sucked in countless quintillions
of the flying electrons from the sun, and
brought them circling in, in a vast, magnificent
display of auroral ionization.
Expeditions went to the great Southern Plateau,
the Plateau of Storms, where the titanic air
currents resulted in an everlasting display
of terrific lightnings, great burning balls
of electric force floating dangerous and deadly
across the frozen, ultra-cold plain.
And the expeditions brought back data.
Yet still Gresth Gkae could not sleep, his
thoughts intruding constantly.
Hours Merth Skahl spent with him, calming
him to sleep.
"But what is this constant search?
It is little enough I know of science, but
why do you send our men to these spots of
wonderfully beautiful, but useless natural
forces.
Can we somehow, do you think, turn them against
the people of these worlds?"
Softly the old Miran smiled.
"Yes, you might say so.
For look, it is the strange balls of electric
force I want to know about.
Sthor had few, but occasionally we saw them.
Never were they properly investigated.
I want to know their secret, for I am sure
they are balls of electric forces not vastly
dissimilar from the nucleus of the atom.
Always we have known that no system of purely
electrical forces could remain stable.
Yet these strange balls of energy do.
How is it?
I am sure it will be of vast importance.
But the direct secret I hope to learn is in
this: What can be done with electric fields
can nearly always be duplicated, or paralleled
in magnetic fields.
If I can learn how to make these electric
balls of energy, can I not hope to make similar
magnetic balls of energy?"
"Yes, I see—that would seem true.
But what benefit would you derive from that?
You have magnetic beams now, and yet they
are useless because you can get nowhere near
the forts.
How then would these benefit you?"
"We can do nothing to those forts, because
of that magnetic shield.
Could we once break it down, then the fort
is helpless, and one or two small atomic bombs
destroy it.
But—we cannot stay near, for the terrible
infra-X-rays of theirs burn holes in our ships,
and—in our men.
"But look you, I can drop many atomic bombs
from a distance where their beams are ineffective.
Suppose I do make a magnetic ball of energy,
a magnetic bomb.
Then—I can drop it from a distance!
We have learned that the power supply of these
forts is very great—but not endless, as
is ours now, thanks to the vast supplies of
power metal on this heavy planet.
Then all we need do is stay at a distance
where they cannot reach us—and drop magnetic
bombs.
Ah, they will be stopped, and their energy
absorbed.
But we can keep it up, day after day, and
slowly drain out their power.
Then—then our atomic bombs can destroy those
forts, and we can move on!"
But suddenly the animation and strength left
his voice.
He turned a sad, downcast face to his friend.
"But Merth Skahl, we can't do it," he complained.
"Ah—now I can see why you so want to continue
this wearing and worrying work.
You need time, Gresth Gkae, only time for
success.
Tomorrow it may be that you will see the first
hint that will lead you to success."
"Ah—I only hope it, Merth Skahl, I only
hope it."
But it was the next day that they saw the
first glimpse of the secret, and saw the path
that might lead to hope and success.
In a week they were sending electric bombs
across the laboratory.
And in three days more, a magnetic bomb streaked
dully across the laboratory to a magnetic
shield they had set up, and buried itself
in it, to explode in brilliant light and heat.
From that day Gresth Gkae began to mend.
In the three weeks that were needed to build
the apparatus into ships, he regained strength
so that when the first flight of five interstellar
ships rose from Jupiter, he was on the flagship.
To Phobos they went first, to the little inner
satellite of Mars, scarcely eight miles in
diameter, a tiny bit of broken metal and rock,
utterly airless, but scarcely more than 3700
miles from the surface of Mars below.
The Mars Center and Deenmor forts were wasting
no power raying a ship at that distance.
They could, of course, have damaged it, but
not severely enough to make up for the loss
of their strictly limited power.
The photocells had been working overtime,
every minute of available light had been used,
and still scarcely 2100 tons of charged mercury
remained in the tanks of Mars Center and 1950
in the tanks at Deenmor.
The flight of five ships settled comfortably
upon Phobos, while the three relieved of duty
started back to Jupiter.
Immediately work was begun on the attack.
The ships were first landed on the near side,
while the apparatus of the projectors was
unloaded, then the great ships moved around
to the far side.
Phobos of course rotated with one face fixed
irrevocably toward Mars itself, the other
always to the cold of space.
Great power leads trailed beneath the ships,
and to the dark side.
Then there were huge water lines for cooling.
On this almost weightless world, where the
great ships weighing hundreds of thousands
of tons on a planet, weighed so little they
were frequently moved about by a single man,
the laying of five miles of water conduit
was no impossibility.
Then they were ready.
Mars Center came first.
Automatic devices kept the aim exact, as the
first of the magnetic bombs started down.
At five-second intervals they were projected
outward, invisible globes of concentrated
magnetic energy, undetectable in space.
Seven seconds passed before the first became
dimly visible in the thin air of Mars.
It floated down, it would miss the fort it
seemed—so far to one side— Abruptly it
turned, and darted with tremendously accelerating
speed for the great magnetic field of the
fort.
With a vast blast of light, it exploded.
Five seconds later a second exploded.
And a third.
Mars Center signaled scoffingly that the bombs
were all being stopped dead in the magnetic
atmosphere, after the bombardment had been
witnessed from Earth and Luna.
An hour later they gave a report that they
were concentrated magnetic fields of energy
that would be rather dangerous—if it weren't
that they couldn't even stand into the magnetic
atmosphere.
Three hours later Mars Center reported that
they contained considerably more energy than
had at first been thought.
Further, which they had not carefully considered
at first, they were taking energy with them!
They were taking away about an equal amount
of energy as each blew up.
It was only a half-hour after that that the
men at Mars Center realized perfectly what
it meant.
Their power was being drained just a little
bit better than twice as fast as they generated
during the day—and since Phobos spun so
swiftly across the sky.
Deenmor got the attack just about the time
Mars Center was released.
Deenmor immediately began seeking for the
source of it.
Somewhere on Phobos—but where?
The Mirans were experts at camouflage.
Deenmor Station, realizing the menace, immediately
rayed the "projector."
They tore up a great deal of harmless rock
with their huge UV rays.
But the bomb device continued to throw one
bomb each five seconds.
When Deenmor operated from Phobos' position,
Mars Center was exposed to the deadly, constant
drain.
A day or two later, the bombs were coming
one each second and a half, for more ships
had joined in the work on Phobos.
Gresth Gkae saw the work was going nicely.
He knew that now it was only a question of
time before those magnetic shields would fail—and
then the whole fort would be powerless.
Maybe—it might be a good idea, when the
forts were powerless to investigate instead
of blowing them up.
There might be many interesting and worthwhile
pieces
of apparatus—particularly the UV beam's
apparatus.
XI
Buck Kendall entered the Communications room
rather furtively.
He hated the place.
Cole was there, and McLaurin.
Mac was looking tired and drawn, Cole not
so tired, but equally drawn.
The signals were coming through fairly well,
because most of the disturbance was rising
where the signals rose, and all the disturbance,
practically, was magnetic rather than electric.
"Deenmor is sending, Buck," McLaurin said
as he entered.
"They're down to the last fifty-five tons.
They'll have more time now—a rest while
Phobos sinks.
Mars Center has another 250 tons, but—it's
just a question of time.
Have you any hope to offer?"
"No," said Kendall in a strained voice.
"But, Mac, I don't think men like those are
afraid to die.
It's dying uselessly they fear.
Tell 'em—tell 'em they've defended not alone
Mars, but all the system, in holding up the
Strangers on Mars.
We here on Luna have been safer because of
them.
And tell—Mac, tell them that in the meantime,
while they defended us, and gave us time to
work, we have begun to see the trail that
will lead to victory."
"You have!"
gasped McLaurin.
"No—but they will never know!"
Kendall left hastily.
He went and stood moodily looking at the calculator
machines—the calculator machines that refused
to give the answers he sought.
No matter how he might modify that original
idea of his, no matter what different line
of attack he might try in solving the problems
of Space and Matter, while he used the system
he knew was right—the answer came down to
that deadly, hope-blasting expression that
meant only "uncertain."
Even Buck was beginning to feel uncertain
under that constant crushing of hope.
Uncertainty—uncertainty was eating into
him, and destroying—
From the Communications room came the hum
and drive of the great sender flashing its
message across seventy-two millions of miles
of nothing.
"B-u-c-k K-e-n-d-a-l-l s-a-y-s h-e h-a-s l-e-a-r-n-e-d
s-o-m-e-t-h-i-n-g t-h-a-t w-i-l-l l-e-a-d
t-o v-i-c-t-o-r-y w-h-i-l-e y-o-u h-e-l-d
b-a-c-k t-h-e—"
Kendall switched on a noisy, humming fan viciously.
The too-intelligible signals were drowned
in its sound.
"And—tell them to—destroy the apparatus
before the last of the power is gone," McLaurin
ordered softly.
The men in Deenmor station did slightly better
than that.
Gradually they cut down their magnetic shield,
and some of the magnetic bombs tore and twisted
viciously at the heavy metal walls.
The thin atmosphere of Mars leaked in.
Grimly the men waited.
Atomic bombs—or ships to investigate?
It did not matter much to them personally—
Gresth Gkae smiled with his old vigor as he
ordered one of the great interstellar ships
to land beside the powerless station, approaching
from such an angle that the still-active Mars
Center station could not attack.
One of the fleet of Phobos rose, and circled
about the planet, and settled gracefully beside
the station.
For half an hour it lay there quietly, waiting
and watching.
Then a crew of two dozen Mirans started across
the dry, crumbly powder of Mars' sands, toward
the fort.
Simultaneously almost, three things happened.
A three-foot UV beam wiped out the advancing
party.
A pair of fifteen-foot beams cut a great gaping
hole in the wall of the interstellar ship,
as it darted up, like a startled quail, its
weapons roaring defiance, only to fall back,
severely wounded.
And the radio messages pounded out to Earth
the first description of the Miran people.
Methodically the men in Deenmor station used
all but one ton of their power to completely
and forever wreck and destroy the interstellar
cripple that floundered for a few moments
on the sands a bare mile away.
Presently, before Deenmor was through with
it, the atomic bombs stopped coming, and the
atomic shells.
The magnetic shield that had been re-established
for the few minutes of this last, dying sting,
fell.
Deenmor station vanished in a sudden, colossal
tongue of blue-green light as the ton of atomically
distorted mercury was exploded by a projector
beam turned on the tank.
It was long gone, when the first atomic bombs
and magnetic bombs dropped from Phobos reached
the spot, and only hot rock and broken metal
remained.
Mars Center failed in fact the next time Phobos
rode high over it.
The apparatus here had been carefully destroyed
by technicians with a view of making it indecipherable,
but the Mirans made it even more certain,
for no ship settled here to investigate, but
a stream of atomic bombs that lasted for over
an hour, and churned the rock to dust, and
the dust to molten lava, in which pools of
fused tungsten-beryllium alloy bubbled slowly
and sank.
"Ah, Jarth—they are a brave race, whatever
we may say of their queer shape," sighed Gresth
Gkae as the last of Mars Center sank in bubbling
lava.
"They stung as they died."
For some minutes he was silent.
"We must move on," he said at length.
"I have been thinking, and it seems best that
a few ships land here, and establish a fort,
while some twenty move on to the satellite
of the third planet and destroy the fort there.
We cannot operate against the planet while
that hangs above us."
Seven ships settled to Mars, while the fleet
came up from Jupiter to join with Gresth Gkae's
flight of ships on its way to Luna.
An automatically controlled ship was sent
ahead, and began the bombardment.
It approached slowly, and was not destroyed
by the UV beams till it had come to within
40,000 miles of the fort.
At 60,000 Gresth Gkae stationed his fleet—and
returned to 150,000 immediately as the titanic
UV beams of the Lunar Fort stretched out to
their maximum range.
The focus made a difference.
One ship started limping back to Jupiter,
in tow of a second, while the rest began the
slow, methodical work of wearing down the
defenses of the Lunar Fort.
Kendall looked out at the magnificent display
of clashing, warring energies, the great,
whirling spheres and discs of opalescent flame,
and turned away sadly.
"The men at Deenmor must have watched that
for days.
And at Mars Center."
"How long can we hold out?" asked McLaurin.
"Three weeks or so, at the present rate.
That's a long time, really.
And we can escape if we want to.
The UV beams here have a greater range than
any weapon the Strangers have, and with Earth
so near—oh, we could escape.
Little good."
"What are you going to do?"
"I," said Buck Kendall, suddenly savage, "am
going to consign all the math machines in
the universe to eternal damnation—and go
ahead and build a machine anyway.
I know that thing ought to be right.
The math's wrong."
"There is no other thing to try?"
"A billion others.
I don't know how many others.
We ought to get atomic energy somehow.
But that thing infuriates me.
A hundred things that math has predicted,
that I have checked by experiment, simple
little things.
But—when I carry it through to the point
where I can get something useful—it wriggles
off into—uncertainty."
Kendall stalked off to the laboratory.
Devin was there working over the calculus
machines, and Kendall called him angrily.
Then more apologetic, he explained it was
anger at himself.
"Devin, I'm going to make that thing, if it
blows up and kills me.
I'm going to make that thing if this whole
fort blows up and kills me.
That math has blown up in my face for four
solid months, and half killed me, so I'm going
to kill it.
Come on, we'll make that damned junk."
Angrily, furiously, Kendall drove his helpers
to the task.
He had worked out the apparatus in plan a
dozen times, and now he had the plans turned
into patterns, the patterns into metal.
Saucily, the "S Doradus" made the trip to
and from Earth with patterns, and with metal,
with supplies and with apparatus.
But she had to dodge and fight every inch
of the way as the Miran ships swooped down
angrily at her.
A fighting craft could get through when the
Miran fleet was withdrawn to some distance,
but the Mirans were careful that no heavy-loaded
freighter bearing power supply should get
through.
And Gresth Gkae waited off Luna in his great
ship, and watched the steady streams of magnetic
bombs exploding on the magnetic shield of
the Lunar Fort.
Presently more ships came up, and added their
power to the attack, for here, the photo-cell
banks could gather tremendous energy, and
Gresth Gkae knew he would need to overcome
this, and drain the accumulated power.
Gresth Gkae felt certain if he could once
crack this nut, break down Earth, he would
have the system.
This was the home planet.
If this fell, then the two others would follow
easily, despite the fact that the few forts
on the innermost planet, Mercury, could gather
energy from the sun at a rate greater than
their ships could generate.
It took Kendall two weeks and three days to
set up his preliminary apparatus.
They had power for perhaps four days more,
thanks to the fact that the long Lunar day
had begun shortly after Gresth Gkae's impatient
attack had started.
Also, the "S Doradus" had brought in several
hundred tons of charged mercury on each trip,
though this was no great quantity individually,
it had mounted up in the ten trips she had
made.
The "Cepheid," her sister ship, had gone along
on seven of the trips, and added to the total.
But at length the apparatus was set up.
It was peculiar looking, and it employed a
great deal of power, nearly as much as a UV
beam in fact.
McLaurin looked at it sceptically toward the
last, and asked Buck: "What do you expect
it to do?"
"I am," said Kendall sourly, "uncertain.
The result will be uncertainty itself."
Which, considering things, was a surprisingly
accurate statement.
Kendall gave the exact answer.
He meant to give an ironic comment.
For the mathematics had been perfectly correct,
only Buck Kendall misinterpreted the answer.
"I've followed the math with mechanism all
the way through," he explained, "and I'm putting
power into it.
That's all I know.
Somewhere, by the laws of cause and effect,
this power must show itself again—despite
what the damn math says."
And in that, of course, Kendall was wrong.
Because the laws of cause and effect didn't
hold in what he was doing now.
"Do you want to watch?" he asked at length.
"I'm all set to try it."
"I suppose I may as well."
McLaurin smiled.
"In our close-knit little community the fate
of one is of interest to all.
If it's going to blow up, I might as well
be here, and if it isn't, I want to be."
Kendall smiled appreciatively and replied:
"Let it be on thy own head.
Here she goes."
He walked over to the power board, and took
command.
Devin, and a squad of other scientists were
seated about the room with every conceivable
type and combination of apparatus.
Kendall wanted to see what this was doing.
"Tubes," he called.
"Circuits A and D. Tie-ins."
He stopped, the preliminary switches in.
"Main circuit coming."
With a jerk he threw over the last contact.
A heavy relay thudded solidly.
The hum of a straining atostor.
Then—
An electric motor, humming smoothly stopped
with a jerk.
"This," it remarked in a deep throaty voice,
"is probably the last stand of humanity."
The galvanometer before which Devin was seated
apparently agreed.
In a rather high pitched voice it pointed
out that: "If the Lunar Fort falls, the Earth—"
It stopped abruptly, and an electroscope beside
Douglass took up the thread in a high, shrill
voice, rather slurred, "—will be directly
attacked."
"This," resumed the motor in a hoarse voice,
"will certainly mean the end of humanity."
The motor gave up the discourse and hummed
violently into action—in reverse!
"My God!"
Kendall pulled the switch open with a sagging
jaw and staring eyes.
The men in the room burst into sudden startled
exclamations.
Kendall didn't give them time.
His jaw snapped shut, and a blazing light
of wondrous joy shone in his eyes.
He instantly threw the switch in again.
Again the humming atostor, the strain—
Slowly Devin lifted from his seat.
With thrashing arms and startled, staring
eyes, he drifted gently across the room.
Abruptly he fell to the floor, unhurt by the
light Lunar gravity.
"I advise," said the motor in its grumbling
voice, "an immediate exodus."
It stopped speaking, and practiced what it
preached.
It was a fifty-horse motor-generator, on a
five-ton tungsten-beryllium base, but it rose
abruptly, spun rapidly about an axis at right
angles to the axis of its armature, and stopped
as suddenly.
In mid air it continued its interrupted lecture.
"Mercury therefore is the destination I would
advise.
There power is sufficient for—all machines."
Gently it inverted itself and settled to the
middle of the floor.
Kendall instantly cut the switch.
The relay did not chunk open.
It refused to obey.
Settled in the middle of the floor now, torn
loose from its power leads, the motor-generator
began turning.
It turned faster and faster.
It was shrilling in a thin scream of terrific
speed, a speed that should have torn its windings
to fragments under the lash of centrifugal
force.
Contentedly it said throatily.
"Settled."
The galvanometer spoke again in its peculiar
harsh voice.
"Therefore, move."
Abruptly, without apparent reason, the stubborn
relay clicked open.
The shrilly screaming motor stopped dead instantly,
as though it had had no real momentum, or
had been inertialess.
Startled, white-faced men looked at Kendall.
Buck's eyes were shining with an unholy glee.
"Uncertainty!"
he shouted.
"Uncertainty—uncertainty—uncertainty,
you fools!
Don't you see it?
All the math—it said uncertainty—man,
man—we've got just that—uncertainty!"
"You're crazy," gasped McLaurin.
"I'm crazy, everything's gone crazy."
Kendall roared with sudden, joyous laughter.
"Absolutely.
Everything goes crazy—the laws of nature
break down!
Heisenberg's principle showed that the law
of cause and effect weren't absolute.
We've made them absolutely uncertain!"
"But—but motors talking, instruments giving
lectures—"
"Certainly—or rather uncertainly—anything,
absolutely anything.
The destruction of the laws of gravity, freedom
from inertia—why, merely picking up a radio
lecture is nothing!"
Suddenly, abruptly, a thousand questions poured
in on him.
Jubilantly he answered what he could, told
what he thought—and then brought order.
"The battle's still on, men—we've still
got to find out how to use this, now we've
got it.
I have an idea—that there's a lot more.
I know what I'll get this time.
Now help me remake this apparatus so we don't
broadcast the thing."
At once, ten times the former pace, work was
done.
On the radio, news was sent out that Kendall
was on the right track after all.
In two hours the apparatus had been vastly
altered, it was in the final stage, and an
entirely different sort of field set up.
Again they watched as Buck applied the power.
The atostor hummed—but no strange tricks
of matter happened this time.
The more concentrated, altered field was,
as Buck was to find out later, "Uncertainty
of the Second Degree."
It was molecular uncertainty.
In a field a foot and a half in diameter,
Buck saw the thing created—and suddenly
a brilliant green-blue flame shot up, and
a great dark cloud of terrible, red-brown
deadly vapor.
Then an instant later, Kendall had opened
the relay.
Gasping, the men ran from the laboratory,
shutting the deadly fumes in.
"N2O4" gasped Morton, the chemist, as they
reached safety.
"It's exothermic—but it formed there!"
In that instant, Kendall grasped the meaning
the choking fumes carried.
"Molecular uncertainty!" he decided.
"We're going back—we're getting there—"
He altered the apparatus again, added another
atostor in series, reduced the size of his
sphere of forces—of strange chaos of uncertainty.
Within—little was certain.
Without—the laws of nature applied as ever.
Again the apparatus was started, cautiously
this time.
Only a strange jumbled ionization appeared
this time, then a slow, rising blue flame
began to creep up, and burn hot and blue.
Buck looked at it for a moment, then his face
grew tense and thoughtful.
"Devin—give me a half-dollar."
Blankly, Devin reached in his pocket, and
handed over the metal disc.
Cautiously Buck Kendall tossed it toward the
sphere of force.
Instantly there was a flash of flame, soundless
and soft-colored.
Then the silver disc was outlined in light,
and swiftly, inevitably crumbling into dust
so fine only a blue haze appeared.
In less than two seconds, the metal was gone.
Only the dense blue fog remained.
Then this began to go, and the leaping blue
flame grew taller, and stronger.
"We're on the track—I'm going to stop here,
and calculate.
Bring the data—"
Kendall shut off the machine, and went to
the calculation room.
Swiftly he selected already prepared graphs,
graphs of the math he had worked on.
Devin came soon, and others.
They assembled the data and with tables and
arithmetical machines turned it into graphs.
Then all these graphs were fed into the machine.
There were curves, and sine-curves, abrupt
breaking lines—but the answer that came
when all were compounded was a perfect diagram
of a flight of four steps, descending in unequal
treads to zero.
Kendall looked at it for long minutes.
"That," he said at length, "is what I expected.
There are four degrees of uncertainty, we
generated 'Uncertainty of the First Degree,'
'Mass Uncertainty,' when we started.
That, as here shown, takes little energy concentration.
Then we increased the energy concentration
and got 'Uncertainty of the Second Degree,'
'Molecular Uncertainty.'
Then I added more power, and reduced the field,
and got 'Uncertainty of the Third Degree'—'Atomic
Uncertainty.'
There is 'Uncertainty of the Fourth Degree.'
It is barely attainable with our atostors.
It is—utter uncertainty.
"In the First Degree, the laws of mass action
fail, the great broad-reaching laws.
In the Second Degree, the laws of the molecules,
a finer organization, break down, and anything
can happen in chemistry.
In the Third Degree, the laws of atomic physics
break down slowly.
The atom is tough.
It is very compact, and we just barely attained
the concentration needed with that apparatus.
But—in the Third Degree, when the Atomic
Laws break down into utter uncertainty, the
atoms break, and only hydrogen can exist.
That was the blue flame.
"But the Fourth Degree—there is no law whatsoever,
nothing in all the Universe can exist.
It means—the utter destruction and release
of the energy of matter!"
Kendall paused for a moment.
"We have won, with this.
We need only make up this apparatus—and
maybe make it into a weapon.
You know, in the Fourth Degree, nothing in
all the Universe could resist, deflect, or
control it, if launched freely, and self-maintaining.
I think that might be done.
You see, no law affects it, for it breaks
down the law.
Magnetism cannot attract or repel it because
magnetic fields cannot exist; there is no
law of magnetic force, where this field is.
"And you know, Devin, how I have analyzed
and duplicated their magnetic ball-fields.
This should be capable of formation into a
ball-field.
"We need only make it up now.
We will install it in the 'S Doradus' and
the 'Cepheid' as a weapon.
We need only install it as an energy source
here.
Let us start."
XII
Buck Kendall with a slow smile, looked out
of the port in the thick metal wall.
The magnetic shield of the Lunar Fort was
washed constantly with the fires of exploding
magnetic bombs.
The smile spread broader.
"My friends," he said softly, "you can pull
from now till doomsday as far as I'm concerned,
and you won't even disturb us now."
He looked back over his shoulder into the
power room.
A hunched bulk, beautifully designed and carefully
finished, the apparatus that created 'Uncertainty
of the Fourth Degree' was destroying matter,
and creating by its destruction terrific electric
fields.
These fields were feeding the magnetic shield
now.
Under the present drain, the machine was not
noticeably working.
In fact, Kendall was a bit annoyed.
He had tested out the energy generating properties
of this machine, trying to find a limit.
He had found there was no limit.
The great copper conductors, charged with
the same atostor force that was used in the
mercury fuel, were perfect conductors, they
had not heated.
But the eleven thousand tons of discharged
mercury metal had been completely charged
in just a bit better than eleven minutes.
The pumps wouldn't force it through the charging
apparatus any faster than that.
Two weeks more had passed, while the "S Doradus"
and the "Cepheid" were fitted out with the
new apparatus Buck had designed.
They were almost ready to start now.
McLaurin came down the corridor, and stopped
near Kendall.
He too smiled at the Miran's attempts.
"They've got a long way to go, Buck."
"They're going a long way.
Clear back home—and we'll be right along.
I don't think they can outdistance us."
"I still don't see why you couldn't use one
of those Uncertainty conditions—the First
Degree perhaps, and annihilate our inertia."
"You can't control Uncertainty.
By its essential character it's beyond control."
"What's that Fourth Degree machine of yours—the
material energy—if it isn't controlled and
utilized Uncertainty?"
"It's utter and utterly uncontrolled Uncertainty.
The matter within that field breaks down to
absolutely nothing.
Within, no law whatsoever applies, but fortunately,
outside the old laws of physics apply—and
we can gather and use the energy which is
released outside, though nothing can be done
inside.
Why, think, man, if I could control that Uncertainty,
I could do anything at all, absolutely anything.
It would be a world as unreasonable as a bad
dream.
Think how unreasonable those manifestations
we first got were!"
"But can't you get any control at all?"
"Very little.
Anyway, if I could get inertialess conditions
at will, I'd be afraid of them.
They'd make chemical reactions impossible
in all probability—and life is chemical.
Two atoms must come into more or less violent
contact before a union takes place, and cannot
if they have neither momentum nor inertia.
"Anyway—why worry.
I can't do it, because I can't control this
thing.
And we have the extra-space drive."
"How does that darned thing work?
Can't you drop the math and tell me about
it?"
Kendall smiled.
"Not too readily.
Remember first, as to the driving system,
that it works on the fabric of space.
Space is, in the physical sense, a fabric
woven of the threads of lines of force from
every body in the universe, made up of fields
and forces.
It is elastic, and can transmit strains.
But anything that can transmit strains, can
be strained against.
With the tremendous field intensities available
by the material engines, I can get such fields
as will 'dig their toes' into space and push.
"That's the drive itself.
It is accelerationless, because it enfolds
us, and acts equally on every atom of us.
By maintaining in addition a slight artificial
gravity—thanks also to the intensity of
those material engine fields—we can be comfortable,
while we accelerate at tremendous rates.
"That is, I think, at least allied to the
Stranger's system.
For the high-speed drive, I do in fact use
the Uncertainty.
I can control it in a certain sense by determining
its powers, and the limits of uncertainty,
whether First, Second, Third or Fourth Degree.
It advances in jumps—but on a finer plotting
of the curve, you can see that each jump represents
a vast series of smaller jumps.
That is, there is Class A, B, C, D, and so
forth Uncertainty of the First Degree.
Now Class A First Degree Uncertainty involves
only the deepest, broadest principles.
Only they break down.
One of these is the law of the speed of light.
"I'm sure that isn't the system the Strangers
use, but I'm also sure there's no limit to
the speed we can get."
"Doesn't that wreck your drive system?"
"No, because gravity and the fields I use
in driving are First Degree Uncertainties
of the higher classes.
"But at any rate, it will work.
And—I suspect you came to say you were ready
to go."
"I did."
McLaurin nodded.
"Still stick to your original plan?"
"I think it's best.
You follow those fellows back to their system
in the 'S Doradus' and I'll stay here in the
'Cepheid' to protect the system.
They may need some time to get out of the
place here.
And remember, we ought to be as decent as
they were.
They didn't bother the transports leaving
Jupiter when they came in, only attacked the
warships.
We're bound to do the same, but we'll have
to keep a watch on them, nonetheless.
So you go on ahead."
They started down the corridor, and came presently
to the huge locks where the "S Doradus" and
the "Cepheid" were berthed.
The super-ships lay cold and gray now, men
swarming in and out with last-minute supplies.
Air, water, spare parts, bedding and personal
equipment.
Douglass, Cole, and most of the laboratory
staff would go with Kendall when he followed
the Strangers home.
Devin and a few of the most advanced physicists
would stay with McLaurin in case of need.
An hour later the "S Doradus" rose gently,
soundlessly from her berth, and floated out
of the open lock-door.
The "Cepheid" followed her in five seconds.
Still under the great screen of the fort,
the lashing, coruscating colors of the magnetic
bombs and the magnetic screen flashed and
was iridescent.
The "S Doradus" poked her great nose gently
through the screen, and an instant later her
titanically powerful, material-engine effortlessly
discharged a great magnetic bomb, sent with
the combined power of five atomic-powered
interstellar ships.
The two ships separated now, the "Cepheid"
under McLaurin flashing ahead with sudden,
terrific acceleration toward Mars, whispering
through space at a speed that made it undetectable,
faster than light.
The "S Doradus" journeyed out leisurely toward
the fleet of forty-seven Miran ships.
Gresth Gkae saw the "S Doradus" and as he
watched the steady progress, felt sudden fear
at his heart.
The ship seemed so certain—
At a distance of thirty thousand miles, Kendall
stopped.
Magnetic bombs were washing his screen continuously
now, seeking to exhaust the ship as all the
great ships beyond poured their energy against
it.
A slow smile spread over Kendall's mouth as
he heard the gentle hum of the barely working
material-engine.
Carefully he aligned the nose UV beam of the
"S Doradus" on the nearest of the Miran ships.
Then he depressed a switch.
There was no ion-release before the force-mirror
now.
Just a jet of gas whirling into a half-inch
field of "Uncertainty of the Fourth Degree."
The matter vanished instantly in released
energy so stupendous that the greatest previous
UV beams had been harmless things by comparison.
Material energy maintained the mirror forces.
Material energy gave the power that was released.
And only material energy could have stood
up before it.
Thirty thousand miles away, a Miran ship flamed
instantaneously into inconceivable incandescence,
vanishing almost in blue-violet light of terrific
intensity.
The ship reeled away, a half-molten wreck.
The beam spotted two more ships before it
winked out.
Then Kendall began sending bombs.
He moved up to within 2000 miles that his
aim might be accurate.
They were bombs of "Uncertainty of the Third
Degree," the Uncertainty of atomic law in
bomb form.
One hit the nose of the nearest ship, and
a sphere five feet in diameter glowed mistily
blue for a moment.
Then very easily, the matter that formed the
wall of the cruiser began to run and change,
and presently there was only a hole, and an
expanding cloud of gas.
Three more flowed toward it—and the hole
enlarged, and another hole appeared in a bulkhead
behind.
Kendall made a change.
For the first time there came the staccato
bark of the material engine under strain,
as it fashioned the terrific fields of "Uncertainty
of the Ultimate Degree."
Abruptly they leapt out, invisible till they
entered a magnetic screen, then run over with
opalescent light as the energy of the field
was sucked into them and released.
It struck the nose of a ship—a field no
larger than an apple—
A titanic gout of energy burst out that was
soundless in space.
The ship suddenly opened back, opened like
the peel of a banana, till a little nub remained
at the further end, and the metal flaps dropped
back across and behind it dejectedly.
A second ship was struck, and it was struck
on one side, so that it was shattered like
a spent firecracker.
Then the Miran fleet vanished in speed.
Kendall followed them.
"I think," he said with a grin, "they tried
to use their radio beam, but it spread too
much to do anything at that distance.
And they used their rotating magnetic field,
which we couldn't feel.
And their crumbler ray too, of course.
I wonder—are they headed only for Jupiter?
No—no, they've passed it!"
Faster than light, faster than energy could
follow through space, or Uncertainty Bombs
pursue, the Mirans were fleeing for home.
They knew now that only in speed lay safety.
Already they knew that a similar ship had
appeared off Jupiter, and, after wiping out
the Phobos and Mars stations with one bomb
each, had cleared the Jovian Satellites with
equal terrible efficiency.
In one of the fleeing ships was a broken,
tired old man, and his staff.
Gresth Gkae looked back at the blank, distorted
space behind them, at the swiftly dwindling
sun, and spoke.
"I was at fault, my friends.
Jarth has spoken.
They are the stronger and the wiser race.
Farth Skalt has shown you—they use space
fields of intensity 100.
That means the energy of the ultimate destruction.
Jarth used us as his instrument of testing,
only to drive and stimulate that race.
I do not—nay.
There is no doubt now, for look."
Plainly visible, rapidly overtaking them,
the "S Doradus" appeared sharp, and luminous
on the jet of distorted space.
"We cannot escape, my friends.
Shall we return to Sthor or remain in space,
lost?"
"Let us deflect our course—at least he may
not know our destination."
The interstellar ship turned very slightly
in her course.
Plainly they saw the "S Doradus" flash on,
in a straight line, headed for distant, red-glowing
Mira.
Gresth Gkae watched, and shrugged.
Silently he put the ship back on its course,
at its utmost speed.
Parallel with them, near to them, the "S Doradus"
flashed on.
Day after day, the two hurled through space
faster than light.
Gradually Mira brightened, and at last became
a disc.
Gresth Gkae slowed his ships, and Kendall,
watching, slowed to match his speed.
Five billion miles from Sthor, they had reached
normal space speeds.
Viciously the Miran fleet attacked the lone
ship from Earth.
Their rays, their bombs, their every weapon
was flaming.
Great interstellar ships flashed suddenly
into speeds greater than that of light, seeking
to ram and destroy the smaller ship.
The "S Doradus" flashed into equal or greater
speed, and eluded them.
Kendall had determined now, which was the
leader's ship.
Gresth Gkae watched dully as his ships attempted
to destroy the single, small ship.
He sighed in resignation, and turned to walk
back to the chapel aboard the ship.
One last prayer to Jarth—
Gresth Gkae stopped abruptly.
The great ship was lurching strangely.
Men shouted sudden, frightened cries.
The clanking and thud of relays sounded, the
shrill of alarms.
Then the alarms stopped, and suddenly the
whole great ship vibrated to an infinitely
deep voice speaking in perfect Sthorian.
The voice remarked solemnly, in great, vibrant
tones, that they would certainly receive news
presently from the Expeditions.
It went on for some seconds to discuss the
conditions as reported in the new system.
Then it stopped abruptly.
An electric motor just above Gresth Gkae's
head suddenly hummed into action without reason
or power connection.
Almost simultaneously he heard the shouts
of startled men as the great lock doors began
to open into space of their own accord, bulkhead
doors slipped shut as the roar of escaping
air echoed in the ship.
Then it was all over.
Gresth Gkae ran to the control room.
The Mirans there looked up at him with drawn
faces.
"The instruments—Gresth Gkae—the instruments.
The instruments read impossible things, the
motors worked without reason, the fields fluctuated—the
atomic engines stopped and the magnetic shield
broke down and gripped part of the ship instead!"
reported the bewildered pilot.
"I do not know—some strange weapon of—"
began the old scientist.
Something luminous and huge twisted suddenly
through space toward them, a bomb of "Uncertainty
of the First Degree."
It wrapped the ship silently—and again strange
things happened.
Abruptly the ship started whirling violently,
yet without centrifugal force.
The heavens wheeled crazily, and turned about
three axes simultaneously.
There was no gyroscopic effect to hold them!
Gradually the thing died out.
Then a great field seemed to catch the ship,
and hurl it away from its companions.
Abruptly the pilot applied all his power to
pull free.
In vain.
Gresth Gkae shook his head slowly, and raised
the pilot's hands from the board.
"Let them do as they will.
I think they mean us no real harm, Thart Kralt.
They can, we know, destroy us in an instant.
Perhaps he wants us to go somewhere with him"—Gresth
Gkae smiled sadly—"and anyway, we can do
nothing."
For nearly a billion miles the great ship
was hurled through space at tremendous normal-space
velocity.
Then abruptly it was halted, without a sign
of strain or hurt.
The great twenty-foot UV beam on the nose
of the "S Doradus" broke into glowing gentle
red light.
It flashed twice.
There was a pause.
Then it flashed four times.
A long wait.
Then three times, a pause and nine times.
A wait.
Four times, a pause, sixteen times.
Then it stopped.
A slow smile of ineffable joy spread over
Gresth Gkae's face.
"Jarth Be Praised.
He can destroy, but does not wish to.
Ah, Thart Kralt, turn your spotlight toward
him, and flash it twenty-five times, for he
is trying to start communications with us.
Jarth is wise beyond all understanding.
They were the weaker race, and they are the
stronger.
But also they are the better, for they could
destroy, and they do not, but seek only
to communicate."
- THE END -