THE
ADVENTURES OF BUSTER BEAR
CHAPTER I
BUSTER BEAR GOES FISHING
Buster Bear yawned as he lay on his comfortable
bed of leaves and watched the first early
morning sunbeams creeping through the Green
Forest to chase out the Black Shadows.
Once more he yawned, and slowly got to his
feet and shook himself.
Then he walked over to a big pine-tree, stood
up on his hind legs, reached as high up on
the trunk of the tree as he could, and scratched
the bark with his great claws.
After that he yawned until it seemed as if
his jaws would crack, and then sat down to
think what he wanted for breakfast.
While he sat there, trying to make up his
mind what would taste best, he was listening
to the sounds that told of the waking of all
the little people who live in the Green Forest.
He heard Sammy Jay way off in the distance
screaming,
"Thief!
Thief!" and grinned.
"I wonder," thought Buster, "if some one has
stolen Sammy's breakfast, or if he has stolen
the breakfast of some one else.
Probably he is the thief himself."
He heard Chatterer the Red Squirrel scolding
as fast as he could make his tongue go and
working himself into a terrible rage.
"Must be that Chatterer got out of bed the
wrong way this morning," thought he.
He heard Blacky the Crow cawing at the top
of his lungs, and he knew by the sound that
Blacky was getting into mischief of some kind.
He heard the sweet voices of happy little
singers, and they were good to hear.
But most of all he listened to a merry, low,
silvery laugh that never stopped but went
on and on, until he just felt as if he must
laugh too.
It was the voice of the Laughing Brook.
And as Buster listened it suddenly came to
him just what he wanted for breakfast.
"I'm going fishing," said he in his deep grumbly-rumbly
voice to no one in particular.
"Yes, Sir, I'm going fishing.
I want some fat trout for my breakfast."
He shuffled along over to the Laughing Brook,
and straight to a little pool of which he
knew, and as he drew near he took the greatest
care not to make the teeniest, weeniest bit
of noise.
Now it just happened that early as he was,
some one was before Buster Bear.
When he came in sight of the little pool,
who should
he see but another fisherman there, who had
already caught a fine fat trout.
Who was it?
Why, Little Joe Otter to be sure.
He was just climbing up the bank with the
fat trout in his mouth.
Buster Bear's own mouth watered as he saw
it.
Little Joe sat down on the bank and prepared
to enjoy his breakfast.
He hadn't seen Buster Bear, and he didn't
know that he or any one else was anywhere
near.
Buster Bear tiptoed up very softly until he
was right behind Little Joe Otter.
"Woof, woof!" said he in his deepest, most
grumbly-rumbly voice.
"That's a very fine looking trout.
I wouldn't mind if I had it myself."
Little Joe Otter gave a frightened squeal
and without even turning to see who was speaking
dropped his fish and dived headfirst into
the Laughing Brook.
Buster Bear sprang forward and with one of
his big paws caught the fat trout just as
it was slipping back into the water.
"Here's your trout, Mr. Otter," said he, as
Little Joe put his head out of water to see
who had frightened him so.
"Come and get it."
Illus Here's your trout, Mr. Otter, said he
Here's your trout, Mr. Otter, said he.
Page 5.
But Little Joe wouldn't.
The fact is, he was afraid to.
He snarled at Buster Bear and called him a
thief and everything bad he could think of.
Buster didn't seem to mind.
He chuckled as if he thought it all a great
joke and repeated his invitation to Little
Joe to come and get his fish.
But Little Joe just turned his back and went
off down the Laughing Brook in a great rage.
"It's too bad to waste such a fine fish,"
said Buster thoughtfully.
"I wonder what I'd better do with it."
And while he was wondering, he ate it all
up.
Then he started down the Laughing Brook to
try to catch some for himself.
CHAPTER II
LITTLE JOE OTTER GETS EVEN WITH BUSTER BEAR
Little Joe Otter was in a terrible rage.
It was a bad beginning for a beautiful day
and Little Joe knew it.
But who wouldn't be in a rage if his breakfast
was taken from him just as he was about to
eat it?
Anyway, that is what Little Joe told Billy
Mink.
Perhaps he didn't tell it quite exactly as
it was, but you know he was very badly frightened
at the time.
"I was sitting on the bank of the Laughing
Brook beside one of the little pools,"
he told Billy Mink, "and was just going to
eat a fat trout I had caught, when who should
come along but that great big bully, Buster
Bear.
He took that fat trout away from me and ate
it just as if it belonged to him!
I hate him!
If I live long enough I'm going to get even
with him!"
Of course that wasn't nice talk and anything
but a nice spirit, but Little Joe Otter's
temper is sometimes pretty short, especially
when he is hungry, and this time he had had
no breakfast, you know.
Buster Bear hadn't actually taken the fish
away from Little Joe.
But looking at the matter as Little Joe did,
it amounted to the same thing.
You see, Buster knew perfectly well when he
invited Little Joe to come back and get it
that Little Joe wouldn't dare do anything
of the kind.
"Where is he now?" asked Billy Mink.
"He's somewhere up the Laughing Brook.
I wish he'd fall in and get drowned!"
snapped Little Joe.
Billy Mink just had to laugh.
The idea of great big Buster Bear getting
drowned in the Laughing Brook was too funny.
There wasn't water enough in it anywhere except
down in the Smiling Pool, and that was on
the Green Meadows, where Buster had never
been known to go.
"Let's go see what he is doing," said Billy
Mink.
At first Little Joe didn't want to, but at
last his curiosity got the better of his fear,
and he agreed.
So the two little brown-coated scamps turned
down the Laughing Brook, taking the greatest
care to keep out of sight themselves.
They had gone only a little way when Billy
Mink whispered: "Sh-h!
There he is."
Sure enough, there was Buster Bear sitting
close beside a little pool and looking into
it very intently.
"What's he doing?" asked Little Joe Otter,
as Buster Bear sat for the longest time without
moving.
Just then one of Buster's big paws went into
the water as quick as a flash and scooped
out a trout that had ventured too near.
"He's fishing!"
exclaimed Billy Mink.
And that is just what Buster Bear was doing,
and it was very plain to see that he was having
great fun.
When he had eaten the trout he had caught,
he moved along to the next little pool.
"They are our fish!" said Little Joe fiercely.
"He has no business catching our fish!"
"I don't see how we are going to stop him,"
said Billy Mink.
"I do!"
cried Little Joe, into whose head an idea
had just popped.
"I'm going to drive all the fish out of the
little pools and muddy the water all up.
Then we'll see how many fish he will get!
Just you watch me get even with Buster Bear."
Little Joe slipped swiftly into the water
and swam straight to the little pool that
Buster Bear would try next.
He frightened the fish so that they fled in
every direction.
Then he stirred up the mud until the water
was so dirty that Buster couldn't have seen
a fish right under his nose.
He did the same thing in the next pool and
the next.
Buster Bear's fishing was spoiled for that
day.
CHAPTER III
BUSTER BEAR IS GREATLY PUZZLED
Buster Bear hadn't enjoyed himself so much
since he came to the Green Forest to live.
His fun began when he surprised Little Joe
Otter on the bank of a little pool in the
Laughing Brook and Little Joe was so frightened
that he dropped a fat trout he had just caught.
It had seemed like a great joke to Buster
Bear, and he had chuckled over it all the
time he was eating the fat trout.
When he had finished it, he started on to
do some fishing himself.
Presently he came to another little pool.
He stole up to it very, very softly, so as
not to frighten the fish.
Then he sat down close to the edge of it and
didn't move.
Buster learned a long time ago that a fisherman
must be patient unless, like Little Joe Otter,
he is just as much at home in the water as
the fish themselves, and can swim fast enough
to catch them by chasing them.
So he didn't move so much as an eye lash.
He was so still that he looked almost like
the stump of an old tree.
Perhaps that is what the fish thought he was,
for pretty soon, two or three swam right in
close to where he was sitting.
Now Buster Bear may be big and clumsy looking,
but there isn't anything that can move much
quicker than one of those big paws of his
when he wants it to.
One of them moved now, and quicker than a
wink had scooped one of those foolish fish
out on to the bank.
Buster's little eyes twinkled, and he smacked
his lips as he moved on to the next little
pool, for he knew that it was of no use to
stay longer at the first one.
The fish were so frightened that they wouldn't
come back for a long, long time.
At the next little pool the same thing happened.
By this time Buster Bear was in fine spirits.
It was fun to catch the fish, and it was still
more fun to eat them.
What finer breakfast could any one have than
fresh-caught trout?
No wonder he felt good!
But it takes more than three trout to fill
Buster Bear's stomach, so he kept on to the
next little pool.
But this little pool, instead of being beautiful
and clear so that Buster could see right to
the bottom of it and so tell if there were
any fish there, was so muddy that he couldn't
see into it at all.
It looked as if some one had just stirred
up all the mud at the bottom.
"Huh!" said Buster Bear.
"It's of no use to try to fish here.
I would just waste my time.
I'll try the next pool."
So he went on to the next little pool.
He found this just as muddy as the other.
Then he went on to another, and this was no
better.
Buster sat down and scratched his head.
It was puzzling.
Yes, Sir, it was puzzling.
He looked this way and he looked that way
suspiciously, but there was no one to be seen.
Everything was still save for the laughter
of the Laughing Brook.
Somehow, it seemed to Buster as if the Brook
were laughing at him.
"It's very curious," muttered Buster, "very
curious indeed.
It looks as if my fishing is spoiled for to-day.
I don't understand it at all.
It's lucky I caught what I did.
It looks as if somebody is trying to—ha!"
A sudden thought had popped into his head.
Then he began to chuckle and finally to laugh.
"I do believe that scamp Joe Otter is trying
to get even with me for eating that fat trout!"
And then, because Buster Bear always enjoys
a good joke even when it is on himself, he
laughed until he had to hold his sides, which
is a whole lot better than going off in a
rage as Little Joe Otter had done.
"You're pretty smart, Mr.
Otter!
You're pretty smart, but there are other people
who are smart too," said Buster Bear, and
still chuckling, he went off to think up a
plan to get the best of Little Joe Otter.
CHAPTER IV
LITTLE JOE OTTER SUPPLIES BUSTER
BEAR WITH A BREAKFAST
Getting even just for spite
Doesn't always pay.
Fact is, it is very apt
To work the other way.
That is just how it came about that Little
Joe Otter furnished Buster Bear with the best
breakfast he had had for a long time.
He didn't mean to do it.
Oh, my, no!
The truth is, he thought all the time that
he was preventing Buster Bear from getting
a breakfast.
You see he wasn't well enough acquainted with
Buster to know that Buster is quite as smart
as he is, and perhaps a little bit smarter.
Spite and selfishness were at the bottom of
it.
You see Little Joe and Billy Mink had had
all the fishing in the Laughing Brook to themselves
so long that they thought no one else had
any right to fish there.
To be sure Bobby Coon caught a few little
fish there, but they didn't mind Bobby.
Farmer Brown's boy fished there too, sometimes,
and this always made Little Joe and Billy
Mink very angry, but they were so afraid of
him that they didn't dare do anything about
it.
But when they discovered that Buster Bear
was a fisherman, they made up their minds
that something had got to be done.
At least, Little Joe did.
"He'll try it again to-morrow morning," said
Little Joe.
"I'll keep watch, and as soon as I see him
coming, I'll drive out all the fish, just
as I did to-day.
I guess that'll teach him to let our fish
alone."
So the next morning Little Joe hid before
daylight close by the little pool where Buster
Bear had given him such a fright.
Sure enough, just as the Jolly Sunbeams began
to creep through the Green Forest, he saw
Buster Bear coming straight over to the little
pool.
Little Joe slipped into the water and chased
all the fish out of the little pool, and stirred
up the mud on the bottom so that the water
was so muddy that the bottom couldn't be seen
at all.
Then he hurried down to the next little pool
and did the same thing.
Now Buster Bear is very smart.
You know he had guessed the day before who
had spoiled his fishing.
So this morning he only went far enough to
make sure that if Little Joe were watching
for him, as he was sure he would be, he would
see him coming.
Then, instead of keeping on to the little
pool, he hurried to a place way down the Laughing
Brook, where the water was very shallow, hardly
over his feet, and there he sat chuckling
to himself.
Things happened just as he had expected.
The frightened fish Little Joe chased out
of the little pools up above swam down the
Laughing Brook, because, you know, Little
Joe was behind them, and there was nowhere
else for them to go.
When they came to the place where Buster was
waiting, all he had to do was to scoop them
out on to the bank.
It was great fun.
It didn't take Buster long to catch all the
fish he could eat.
Then he saved a nice fat trout and waited.
By and by along came Little Joe Otter, chuckling
to think how he had spoiled Buster Bear's
fishing.
He was so intent on looking behind him to
see if Buster was coming that he didn't see
Buster waiting there until he spoke.
"I'm much obliged for the fine breakfast you
have given me," said Buster in his deepest,
most grumbly-rumbly voice.
"I've saved a fat trout for you to make up
for the one I ate yesterday.
I hope we'll go fishing together often."
Then he went off laughing fit to kill himself.
Little Joe couldn't find a word to say.
He was so surprised and angry that he went
off by himself and sulked.
And Billy Mink, who had been watching, ate
the fat trout.
CHAPTER V
GRANDFATHER FROG'S COMMON-SENSE
There is nothing quite like common sense to
smooth out troubles.
People who have plenty of just plain common
sense are often thought to be very wise.
Their neighbors look up to them and are forever
running to them for advice, and they are very
much respected.
That is the way with Grandfather Frog.
He is very old and very wise.
Anyway, that is what his neighbors think.
The truth is, he simply has a lot of common
sense, which after all is the very best kind
of wisdom.
Now when Little Joe Otter found that Buster
Bear had been too smart for him and that instead
of spoiling Buster's fishing in the Laughing
Brook he had really made it easier for Buster
to catch all the fish he wanted, Little Joe
went off down to the Smiling Pool in a great
rage.
Billy Mink stopped long enough to eat the
fat fish Buster had left on the bank and then
he too went down to the Smiling Pool.
When Little Joe Otter and Billy Mink reached
the Smiling Pool, they climbed up on the Big
Rock, and there Little Joe sulked and sulked,
until finally Grandfather Frog asked what
the matter was.
Little Joe wouldn't tell, but Billy Mink told
the whole story.
When he told how Buster had been too smart
for Little Joe, it tickled him so that Billy
had to laugh in spite of himself.
So did Grandfather Frog.
So did Jerry Muskrat, who had been listening.
Of course this made Little Joe angrier than
ever.
He said a lot of unkind things about Buster
Bear and about Billy Mink and Grandfather
Frog and Jerry Muskrat, because they had laughed
at the smartness of Buster.
"He's nothing but a great big bully and thief!"
declared Little Joe.
"Chug-a-rum!
He may be a bully, because great big people
are very apt to be bullies, and though I haven't
seen him, I guess Buster Bear is big enough
from all I have heard, but I don't see how
he is a thief," said Grandfather Frog.
"Didn't he catch my fish and eat them?" snapped
Little Joe.
"Doesn't that make him a thief?"
"They were no more your fish than mine," protested
Billy Mink.
"Well, our fish, then!
He stole our fish, if you like that any better.
That makes him just as much a thief, doesn't
it?"
growled Little Joe.
Grandfather Frog looked up at jolly, round,
bright Mr. Sun and slowly winked one of his
great, goggly eyes.
"There comes a foolish green fly," said he.
"Who does he belong to?"
"Nobody!"
snapped Little Joe.
"What have foolish green flies got to do with
my
—I mean our fish?"
"Nothing, nothing at all," replied Grandfather
Frog mildly.
"I was just hoping that he would come near
enough for me to snap him up; then he would
belong to me.
As long as he doesn't, he doesn't belong to
any one.
I suppose that if Buster Bear should happen
along and catch him, he would be stealing
from me, according to Little Joe."
"Of course not!
What a silly idea!
You're getting foolish in your old age,"
retorted Little Joe.
"Can you tell me the difference between the
fish that you haven't caught and the foolish
green flies that I haven't caught?" asked
Grandfather Frog.
Little Joe couldn't find a word to say.
"You take my advice, Little Joe Otter," continued
Grandfather Frog, "and always make friends
with those who are bigger and stronger and
smarter than you are.
You'll find it pays."
Illus You take my advice, Little Joe Otter,
continued Grandfather Frog.
You take my advice, Little Joe Otter, continued
Grandfather Frog.
Page 26.
CHAPTER VI
LITTLE JOE OTTER TAKES GRANDFATHER
FROG'S ADVICE
Who makes an enemy a friend,
To fear and worry puts an end.
Little Joe Otter found that out when he took
Grandfather Frog's advice.
He wouldn't have admitted that he was afraid
of Buster Bear.
No one ever likes to admit being afraid, least
of all Little Joe Otter.
And really Little Joe has a great deal of
courage.
Very few of the little people of the Green
Forest or the Green Meadows would willingly
quarrel with him, for Little Joe is a great
fighter when he has to fight.
As for all those who live in or along the
Laughing Brook or in the Smiling Pool, they
let Little Joe have his own way in everything.
Now having one's own way too much is a bad
thing.
It is apt to make one selfish and thoughtless
of other people and very hard to get along
with.
Little Joe Otter had his way too much.
Grandfather Frog knew it and shook his head
very soberly when Little Joe had been disrespectful
to him.
"Too bad.
Too bad!
Chug-a-rum!
It is too bad that such a fine young fellow
as Little Joe should spoil a good disposition
by such selfish heedlessness.
Too bad," said he.
So, though he didn't let on that it was so,
Grandfather Frog really was delighted when
he heard how Buster Bear had been too smart
for Little Joe Otter.
It tickled him so that he had hard work to
keep a straight face.
But he did and was as grave and solemn as
you please as he advised Little Joe always
to make friends with any one who was bigger
and stronger and smarter than he.
That was good common sense advice, but Little
Joe just sniffed and went off declaring that
he would get even with Buster Bear yet.
Now Little Joe is good-natured and full of
fun as a rule, and after he had reached home
and his temper had cooled off a little, he
began to see the joke on himself,—how when
he had worked so hard to frighten the fish
in the little pools of the Laughing Brook
so that Buster Bear should not catch any,
he had all the time been driving them right
into Buster's paws.
By and by he grinned.
It was a little sheepish grin at first, but
at last it
grew into a laugh.
"I believe," said Little Joe as he wiped tears
of laughter from his eyes, "that Grandfather
Frog is right, and that the best thing I can
do is to make friends with Buster Bear.
I'll try it to-morrow morning."
So very early the next morning Little Joe
Otter went to the best fishing pool he knew
of in the Laughing Brook, and there he caught
the biggest trout he could find.
It was so big and fat that it made Little
Joe's mouth water, for you know fat trout
are his favorite food.
But he didn't take so much as one bite.
Instead he carefully laid it on an old log
where Buster Bear would be sure to see it
if he should come along that way.
Then he hid near by, where he could watch.
Buster was late that morning.
It seemed to Little Joe that he never would
come.
Once he nearly lost the fish.
He had turned his head for just a minute,
and when he looked back again, the trout was
nowhere to be seen.
Buster couldn't have stolen up and taken it,
because such a big fellow couldn't possibly
have gotten out of sight again.
Little Joe darted over to the log and looked
on the other side.
There was the fat trout, and there also was
Little Joe's smallest cousin, Shadow the Weasel,
who is a great thief and altogether bad.
Little Joe sprang at him angrily, but Shadow
was too quick and darted away.
Little Joe put the fish back on the log and
waited.
This time he didn't take his eyes off it.
At last, when he was almost ready to give
up, he saw Buster Bear shuffling along towards
the Laughing Brook.
Suddenly Buster stopped and sniffed.
One of the Merry Little Breezes had carried
the scent of that fat trout over to him.
Then he came straight over to where the fish
lay, his nose wrinkling, and his eyes twinkling
with pleasure.
"Now I wonder who was so thoughtful as to
leave this fine breakfast ready for me," said
he out loud.
"Me," said Little Joe in a rather faint voice.
"I caught it especially for you."
"Thank you," replied Buster, and his eyes
twinkled more than ever.
"I think we are going to be friends."
"I—I hope so," replied Little Joe.
CHAPTER VII
FARMER BROWN'S BOY HAS NO LUCK
AT ALL
Farmer Brown's boy tramped through the Green
Forest, whistling merrily.
He always whistles when he feels light-hearted,
and he always feels light-hearted when he
goes fishing.
You see, he is just as fond of fishing as
is Little Joe Otter or Billy Mink or Buster
Bear.
And now he was making his way through the
Green Forest to the Laughing Brook, sure that
by the time he had followed it down to the
Smiling Pool he would have a fine lot of trout
to take home.
He knew every pool in the Laughing Brook where
the trout love to hide, did Farmer Brown's
boy, and it was just the kind of a morning
when the trout should be hungry.
So he whistled as he tramped along, and his
whistle was good to hear.
When he reached the first little pool he baited
his hook very carefully and then, taking the
greatest care to keep out of sight of any
trout that might be in the little pool, he
began to fish.
Now Farmer Brown's boy learned a long time
ago that to be a successful fisherman one
must have a great deal of patience, so though
he didn't get a bite right away as he had
expected to, he wasn't the least bit discouraged.
He kept very quiet and fished and fished,
patiently waiting for a foolish trout to take
his hook.
But he didn't get so much as a nibble.
"Either the trout have lost their appetite
or they have grown very wise," muttered Farmer
Brown's boy, as after a long time he moved
on to the next little pool.
There the same thing happened.
He was very patient, very, very patient, but
his patience brought no reward, not so much
as the faintest kind of a nibble.
Farmer Brown's boy trudged on to the next
pool, and there was a puzzled frown on his
freckled face.
Such a thing never had happened before.
He didn't know what to make of it.
All the night before he had dreamed about
the delicious dinner of fried trout he would
have the next day, and now—well, if he didn't
catch some trout pretty soon, that splendid
dinner would never be anything but a dream.
"If I didn't know that nobody else comes fishing
here, I should think that somebody had been
here this very morning and caught all the
fish or else frightened them so that they
are all in hiding," said he, as he trudged
on to the next little pool.
"I never had such bad luck in all my life
before.
Hello!
What's
this?"
There, on the bank beside the little pool,
were the heads of three trout.
Farmer Brown's boy scowled down at them more
puzzled than ever.
"Somebody has been fishing here, and they
have had better luck than I have," thought
he.
He looked up the Laughing Brook and down the
Laughing Brook and this way and that way,
but no one was to be seen.
Then he picked up one of the little heads
and looked at it sharply.
"It wasn't cut off with a knife; it was bitten
off!" he exclaimed.
"I wonder now if Billy Mink is the scamp who
has spoiled my fun."
Thereafter he kept a sharp lookout for signs
of Billy Mink, but though he found two or
three more trout heads, he saw no other signs
and he caught no fish.
This puzzled him more than ever.
It didn't seem possible that such a little
fellow as Billy Mink could have caught or
frightened all the fish or have eaten so many.
Besides, he didn't remember ever having known
Billy to leave heads around that way.
Billy sometimes catches more fish than he
can eat, but then he usually hides them.
The farther he went down the Laughing Brook,
the more puzzled Farmer Brown's boy grew.
It made him feel very queer.
He would have felt still more queer if he
had known that all the time two other fishermen
who had been before him were watching him
and chuckling to themselves.
They were Little Joe Otter and Buster Bear.
CHAPTER VIII
FARMER BROWN'S BOY FEELS HIS
HAIR RISE
'Twas just a sudden odd surprise
Made Farmer Brown's boy's hair to rise.
That's a funny thing for hair to do—rise
up all of a sudden—isn't it?
But that is just what the hair on Farmer Brown's
boy's head did the day he went fishing in
the Laughing Brook and had no luck at all.
There are just two things that make hair rise—anger
and fear.
Anger sometimes makes the hair on the back
and neck of Bowser the Hound and of some other
little people bristle and stand up, and you
know the hair on the tail of Black Pussy stands
on end until her tail looks twice as big as
it really is.
Both anger and fear make it do that.
But there is only one thing that can make
the hair on the head of Farmer Brown's boy
rise, and as it isn't anger, of course it
must be fear.
It never had happened before.
You see, there isn't much of anything that
Farmer Brown's boy is really afraid of.
Perhaps he wouldn't have been afraid this
time if it hadn't been for the surprise of
what he found.
You see when he had found the heads of those
trout on the bank he knew right away that
some one else had been fishing, and that was
why he couldn't catch any; but it didn't seem
possible that little Billy Mink could have
eaten all those trout, and Farmer Brown's
boy didn't once think of Little Joe Otter,
and so he was very, very much puzzled.
He was turning it all over in his mind and
studying what it could mean, when he came
to a little muddy place on the bank of the
Laughing Brook, and there he saw something
that made his eyes look as if they would pop
right out of his head, and it was right then
that he felt his hair rise.
Anyway, that is what he said when he told
about it afterward.
What was it he saw?
What do you think?
Why, it was a footprint in the soft mud.
Yes, Sir, that's what it was, and all it was.
But it was the biggest footprint Farmer Brown's
boy ever had seen, and it looked as if it
had been made only a few minutes before.
It was the footprint of Buster Bear.
Now Farmer Brown's boy didn't know that Buster
Bear had come down to the Green Forest to
live.
He never had heard of a Bear being in the
Green Forest.
And so he was so surprised that he had hard
work to believe his own eyes, and he had a
queer feeling all over,—a little chilly
feeling, although it was a warm day.
Somehow, he didn't feel like meeting Buster
Bear.
If he had had his terrible gun with him, it
might have been different.
But he didn't, and so he suddenly made up
his mind that he didn't want to fish any more
that day.
He had a funny feeling, too, that he was being
watched, although he couldn't see any one.
He was being watched.
Little Joe Otter and Buster Bear were watching
him and taking the greatest care to keep out
of his sight.
All the way home through the Green Forest,
Farmer Brown's boy kept looking behind him,
and he didn't draw a long breath until he
reached the edge of the Green Forest.
He hadn't run, but he had wanted to.
"Huh!" said Buster Bear to Little Joe Otter,
"I believe he was afraid!"
And Buster Bear was just exactly right.
CHAPTER IX
LITTLE JOE OTTER HAS GREAT NEWS
TO TELL
Little Joe Otter was fairly bursting with
excitement.
He could hardly contain himself.
He felt that he had the greatest news to tell
since Peter Rabbit had first found the tracks
of Buster Bear in the Green Forest.
He couldn't keep it to himself a minute longer
than he had to.
So he hurried to the Smiling Pool, where he
was sure he would find Billy Mink and Jerry
Muskrat and Grandfather Frog and Spotty the
Turtle, and he hoped that perhaps some of
the little people who live in the Green Forest
might be there too.
Sure enough, Peter Rabbit was there on one
side of the Smiling Pool, making faces at
Reddy Fox, who was on the other side, which,
of course, was not at all nice of Peter.
Mr. and Mrs. Redwing were there, and Blacky
the Crow was sitting in the Big Hickory-tree.
Little Joe Otter swam straight to the Big
Rock and climbed up to the very highest part.
He looked so excited, and his eyes sparkled
so, that every one knew right away that something
had happened.
"Hi!" cried Billy Mink.
"Look at Little Joe Otter!
It must be that for once he has been smarter
than Buster Bear."
Little Joe made a good-natured face at Billy
Mink and shook his head.
"No, Billy," said he, "you are wrong, altogether
wrong.
I don't believe anybody can be smarter than
Buster Bear."
Illus Reddy glared across the Smiling Pool
at Peter.
Reddy Fox rolled his lips back in an unpleasant
grin.
"Don't be too sure of that!"
he snapped.
"I'm not through with him yet."
"Boaster!
Boaster!"
cried Peter Rabbit.
Reddy glared across the Smiling Pool at Peter.
"I'm not through with you either, Peter Rabbit!"
he snarled.
"You'll find it out one of these fine days!"
"Reddy, Reddy, smart and sly,
Couldn't catch a buzzing fly!"
taunted Peter.
"Chug-a-rum!" said Grandfather Frog in his
deepest, gruffest voice.
"We know all about that.
What we want to know is what Little Joe Otter
has got on his mind."
"It's news—great news!"
cried Little Joe.
"We can tell better how great it is when we
hear what it is," replied Grandfather Frog
testily.
"What is it?"
Little Joe Otter looked around at all the
eager faces watching him, and then in the
slowest, most provoking way, he drawled: "Farmer
Brown's boy is afraid of Buster Bear."
For a minute no one said a word.
Then Blacky the Crow leaned down from his
perch in the Big Hickory-tree and looked very
hard at Little Joe as he said:
"I don't believe it.
I don't believe a word of it.
Farmer Brown's boy isn't afraid of any one
who lives in the Green Forest or on the Green
Meadows or in the Smiling Pool, and you know
it.
We are all afraid of him."
Little Joe glared back at Blacky.
"I don't care whether you believe it or not;
it's true," he retorted.
Then he told how early that very morning he
and Buster Bear had been fishing together
in the Laughing Brook, and how Farmer Brown's
boy had been fishing there too, and hadn't
caught a single trout because they had all
been caught or frightened before he got there.
Then he told how Farmer Brown's boy had found
a footprint of Buster Bear in the soft mud,
and how he had stopped fishing right away
and started for home, looking behind him with
fear in his eyes all the way.
"Now tell me that he isn't afraid!"
concluded Little Joe.
"For once he knows just how we feel when he
comes prowling around where we are.
Isn't that great news?
Now we'll get even with him!"
"I'll believe it when I see it for myself!"
snapped Blacky the Crow.
CHAPTER X
BUSTER BEAR BECOMES A HERO
The news that Little Joe Otter told at the
Smiling Pool,—how Farmer Brown's boy had
run away from Buster Bear without even seeing
him,—soon spread all over the Green Meadows
and through the Green Forest, until every
one who lives there knew about it.
Of course, Peter Rabbit helped spread it.
Trust Peter for that!
But everybody else helped too.
You see, they had all been afraid of Farmer
Brown's boy for so long that they were tickled
almost to pieces at the very thought of having
some one in the Green Forest who could make
Farmer Brown's boy feel fear as they had felt
it.
And so it was that Buster Bear became a hero
right away to most of them.
A few doubted Little Joe's story.
One of them was Blacky the Crow.
Another was Reddy Fox.
Blacky doubted because he knew Farmer Brown's
boy so well that he couldn't imagine him afraid.
Reddy doubted because he didn't want to believe.
You see, he was jealous of Buster Bear, and
at the same time he was afraid of him.
So Reddy pretended not to believe a word of
what Little Joe Otter had said, and he agreed
with Blacky that only by seeing Farmer Brown's
boy afraid could he ever be made to believe
it.
But nearly everybody else believed it, and
there was great rejoicing.
Most of them were afraid of Buster, very much
afraid of him, because he was so big and strong.
But they were still more afraid of Farmer
Brown's boy, because they didn't know him
or understand him, and because in the past
he had tried to catch some of them in traps
and had hunted some of them with his terrible
gun.
So now they were very proud to think that
one of their own number actually had frightened
him, and they began to look on Buster Bear
as a real hero.
They tried in ever so many ways to show him
how friendly they felt and went quite out
of their way to do him favors.
Whenever they met one another, all they could
talk about was the smartness and the greatness
of Buster Bear.
"Now I guess Farmer Brown's boy will keep
away from the Green Forest, and we won't have
to be all the time watching out for him,"
said Bobby Coon, as he washed his dinner in
the Laughing Brook, for you know he is very
neat and particular.
"And he won't dare set any more traps for
me," gloated Billy Mink.
"Ah wish Brer Bear would go up to Farmer Brown's
henhouse and scare Farmer Brown's boy so that
he would keep away from there.
It would be a favor to me which Ah cert'nly
would appreciate," said Unc' Billy Possum
when he heard the news.
"Let's all go together and tell Buster Bear
how much obliged we are for what he has done,"
proposed Jerry Muskrat.
"That's a splendid idea!"
cried Little Joe Otter.
"We'll do it right away."
"Caw, caw caw!"
broke in Blacky the Crow.
"I say, let's wait and see for ourselves if
it is all true."
"Of course it's true!"
snapped Little Joe Otter.
"Don't you believe I'm telling the truth?"
"Certainly, certainly.
Of course no one doubts your word," replied
Blacky, with the utmost politeness.
"But you say yourself that Farmer Brown's
boy didn't see Buster Bear, but only his footprint.
Perhaps he didn't know whose it was, and if
he had he wouldn't have been afraid.
Now I've got a plan by which we can see for
ourselves if he really is afraid of Buster
Bear."
"What is it?" asked Sammy Jay eagerly.
Blacky the Crow shook his head and winked.
"That's telling," said he.
"I want to think it over.
If you meet me at the Big Hickory-tree at
sun-up to-morrow morning, and get everybody
else to come that you can, perhaps I will
tell you."
CHAPTER XI
BLACKY THE CROW TELLS HIS PLAN
Blacky is a dreamer!
Blacky is a schemer!
His voice is strong;
When things go wrong
Blacky is a screamer!
It's a fact.
Blacky the Crow is forever dreaming and scheming
and almost always it is of mischief.
He is one of the smartest and cleverest of
all the little people of the Green Meadows
and the Green Forest, and all the others know
it.
Blacky likes excitement.
He wants something going on.
The more exciting it is, the better he likes
it.
Then he has a chance to use that harsh voice
of his, and how he does use it!
So now, as he sat in the top of the Big Hickory-tree
beside the Smiling Pool and looked down on
all the little people gathered there, he was
very happy.
In the first place he felt very important,
and you know Blacky dearly loves to feel important.
They had all come at his invitation to listen
to a plan for seeing for themselves if it
were really true that Farmer Brown's boy was
afraid of Buster Bear.
On the Big Rock in the Smiling Pool sat Little
Joe Otter, Billy Mink, and Jerry Muskrat.
On his big, green lily-pad sat Grandfather
Frog.
On another lily-pad sat Spotty the Turtle.
On the bank on one side of the Smiling Pool
were Peter Rabbit, Jumper the Hare, Danny
Meadow Mouse, Johnny Chuck, Jimmy Skunk, Unc'
Billy Possum, Striped Chipmunk and Old Mr.
Toad.
On the other side of the Smiling Pool were
Reddy Fox, Digger the Badger, and Bobby Coon.
In the Big Hickory-tree were Chatterer the
Red Squirrel, Happy Jack the Gray Squirrel,
and Sammy Jay.
Blacky waited until he was sure that no one
else was coming.
Then he cleared his throat very loudly and
began to speak.
"Friends," said he.
Everybody grinned, for Blacky has played so
many sharp tricks that no one is really his
friend unless it is that other mischief-maker,
Sammy Jay, who, you
know, is Blacky's cousin.
But no one said anything, and Blacky went
on.
"Little Joe Otter has told us how he saw Farmer
Brown's boy hurry home when he found the footprint
of Buster Bear on the edge of the Laughing
Brook, and how all the way he kept looking
behind him, as if he were afraid.
Perhaps he was, and then again perhaps he
wasn't.
Perhaps he had something else on his mind.
You have made a hero of Buster Bear, because
you believe Little Joe's story.
Now I don't say that I don't believe it, but
I do say that I will be a lot more sure that
Farmer Brown's boy is afraid of Buster when
I see him run away myself.
Now here is my plan:
"To-morrow morning, very early, Sammy Jay
and I will make a great fuss near the edge
of the Green Forest.
Farmer Brown's boy has a lot of curiosity,
and he will be sure to come over to see what
it is all about.
Then we will lead him to where Buster Bear
is.
If he runs away, I will be the first to admit
that Buster Bear is as great a hero as some
of you seem to think he is.
It is a very simple plan, and if you will
all hide where you can watch, you will be
able to see for yourselves if Little Joe Otter
is right.
Now what do you say?"
Right away everybody began to talk at the
same time.
It was such a simple plan that everybody agreed
to it.
And it promised to be so exciting that everybody
promised to be there, that is, everybody but
Grandfather Frog and Spotty the Turtle, who
didn't care to go so far away from the Smiling
Pool.
So it was agreed that Blacky should try his
plan the very next morning.
CHAPTER XII
FARMER BROWN'S BOY AND BUSTER
BEAR GROW CURIOUS
Ever since it was light enough to see at all,
Blacky the Crow had been sitting in the top
of the tallest tree on the edge of the Green
Forest nearest to Farmer Brown's house, and
never for an instant had he taken his eyes
from Farmer Brown's back door.
What was he watching for?
Why, for Farmer Brown's boy to come out on
his way to milk the cows.
Meanwhile, Sammy Jay was slipping silently
through the Green Forest, looking for Buster
Bear, so that when the time came he could
let his cousin, Blacky the Crow, know just
where Buster was.
By and by the back door of Farmer Brown's
house opened, and out stepped Farmer Brown's
boy.
In each hand he carried a milk pail.
Right away Blacky began to scream at the top
of his lungs.
"Caw, caw, caw!"
shouted Blacky.
And all the time he flew about among the trees
near the edge of the Green Forest as if so
excited that he couldn't keep still.
Farmer Brown's boy looked over there as if
he wondered what all that fuss was about,
as indeed he did, but he didn't start to go
over and see.
No, Sir, he started straight for the barn.
Blacky didn't know what to make of it.
You see, smart as he is and shrewd as he is,
Blacky doesn't know anything about the meaning
of duty, for he never has to work excepting
to get enough to eat.
So, when Farmer Brown's boy started for the
barn instead of for the Green Forest, Blacky
didn't know what to make of it.
He screamed harder and louder than ever, until
his voice grew so hoarse he couldn't scream
any more, but Farmer Brown's boy kept right
on to the barn.
"I'd like to know what you're making such
a fuss about, Mr. Crow, but I've got to feed
the cows and milk them first," said he.
Now all this time the other little people
of the Green Forest and the Green Meadows
had been hiding where they could see all that
went on.
When Farmer Brown's boy disappeared in the
barn, Chatterer the Red Squirrel snickered
right out loud.
"Ha, ha, ha!
This is a great plan of yours, Blacky!
Ha, ha, ha!" he shouted.
Blacky couldn't find a word to say.
He just hung his head, which is something
Blacky seldom does.
"Perhaps if we wait until he comes out again,
he will come over here," said Sammy Jay, who
had joined Blacky.
So it was decided to wait.
It seemed as if Farmer Brown's boy never would
come out, but at last he did.
Blacky and Sammy Jay at once began to scream
and make all the fuss they could.
Farmer Brown's boy took the two pails of milk
into the house, then out he came and started
straight for the Green Forest.
He was so curious to know what it all meant
that he couldn't wait another minute.
Now there was some one else with a great deal
of curiosity also.
He had heard the screaming of Blacky the Crow
and Sammy Jay, and he had listened until he
couldn't stand it another minute.
He just had to know what it was all about.
So at the same time Farmer Brown's boy started
for the Green Forest, this other listener
started towards the place where Blacky and
Sammy were making such a racket.
He walked very softly so as not to make a
sound.
It was Buster Bear.
CHAPTER XIII
FARMER BROWN'S BOY AND BUSTER
BEAR MEET
If you should meet with Buster Bear
While walking through the wood,
What would you do?
Now tell me true,
I'd run the best I could.
That is what Farmer Brown's boy did when he
met Buster Bear, and a lot of the little people
of the Green Forest and some from the Green
Meadows saw him.
When Farmer Brown's boy came hurrying home
from the Laughing Brook without any fish one
day and told about the great footprint he
had seen in a muddy place on the bank deep
in the Green Forest, and had said his was
sure that it was the footprint of a Bear,
he had been laughed at.
Farmer Brown had laughed and laughed.
"Why," said he, "there hasn't been a Bear
in the Green Forest for years and years and
years, not since my own grandfather was a
little boy, and that, you know, was a long,
long, long time ago.
If you want to find Mr. Bear, you will have
to go to the Great Woods.
I don't know who made that footprint, but
it certainly couldn't have been a Bear.
I think you must have imagined it."
Then he had laughed some more, all of which
goes to show how easy it is to be mistaken,
and how foolish it is to laugh at things you
really don't know about.
Buster Bear had come to live in the Green
Forest, and Farmer Brown's boy had seen his
footprint.
But Farmer Brown laughed so much and made
fun of him so much, that at last his boy began
to think that he must have been mistaken after
all.
So when he heard Blacky the Crow and Sammy
Jay making a great fuss near the edge of the
Green Forest, he never once thought of Buster
Bear, as he started over to see what was going
on.
When Blacky and Sammy saw him coming, they
moved a little farther in to the Green Forest,
still screaming in the most excited way.
They felt sure that Farmer Brown's boy would
follow them, and they meant to lead him to
where Sammy had seen Buster Bear that morning.
Then they would find out for sure if what
Little Joe Otter had said was true,—that
Farmer Brown's boy really was afraid of Buster
Bear.
Now all around, behind trees and stumps, and
under thick branches, and even in tree tops,
were other little people watching with round,
wide-open eyes to see what would happen.
It was very exciting, the most exciting thing
they could remember.
You see, they had come to believe that Farmer
Brown's boy wasn't afraid of anybody or anything,
and as most of them were very much afraid
of him, they had hard work to believe that
he would really be afraid of even such a great,
big, strong fellow as Buster Bear.
Every one was so busy watching Farmer Brown's
boy that no one saw Buster coming from the
other direction.
You see, Buster walked very softly.
Big as he is, he can walk without making the
teeniest, weeniest sound.
And that is how it happened that no one saw
him or heard him until just as Farmer Brown's
boy stepped out from behind one side of a
thick little hemlock-tree, Buster Bear stepped
out from behind the other side of that same
little tree, and there they were face to face!
Then everybody held their breath, even Blacky
the Crow and Sammy Jay.
For just a little minute it was so still there
in the Green Forest that not the least little
sound could be heard.
What was going to happen?
CHAPTER XIV
A SURPRISING THING HAPPENS
Blacky the Crow and Sammy Jay, looking down
from the top of a tall tree, held their breath.
Happy Jack the Gray Squirrel and his cousin,
Chatterer the Red Squirrel, looking down from
another tree, held their breath.
Unc' Billy Possum, sticking his head out from
a hollow tree, held his breath.
Bobby Coon, looking through a hole in a hollow
stump in which he was hiding, held his breath.
Reddy Fox, lying flat down behind a heap of
brush, held his breath.
Peter Rabbit, sitting bolt upright under a
thick hemlock branch, with eyes and ears wide
open, held his breath.
And all the other little people who happened
to be where they could see did the same thing.
You see, it was the most exciting moment ever
was in the Green Forest.
Farmer Brown's boy had just stepped out from
behind one side of a little hemlock-tree and
Buster Bear had just stepped out from behind
the opposite side of the little hemlock-tree
and neither had known that the other was anywhere
near.
For a whole minute they stood there face to
face, gazing into each other's eyes, while
everybody watched and waited, and it seemed
as if the whole Green Forest was holding its
breath.
Then something happened.
Yes, Sir, something happened.
Farmer Brown's boy opened his mouth and yelled!
It was such a sudden yell and such a loud
yell that it startled Chatterer so that he
nearly fell from his place in the tree, and
it made Reddy Fox jump to his feet ready to
run.
And that yell was a yell of fright.
There was no doubt about it, for with the
yell Farmer Brown's boy turned and ran for
home, as no one ever had seen him run before.
He ran just as Peter Rabbit runs when he has
got to reach the dear Old Briar-patch before
Reddy Fox can catch him, which, you know,
is as fast as he can run.
Once he stumbled and fell, but he scrambled
to his feet in a twinkling, and away he went
without once turning his head to see if Buster
Bear was after him.
There wasn't any doubt that he was afraid,
very much afraid.
Everybody leaned forward to watch him.
"What did I tell you?
Didn't I say that he was afraid of Buster
Bear?"
cried Little Joe Otter, dancing about with
excitement.
"You were right, Little Joe!
I'm sorry that I doubted it.
See him go!
Caw, caw, caw!"
shrieked Blacky the Crow.
For a minute or two everybody forgot about
Buster Bear.
Then there was a great crash which made everybody
turn to look the other way.
What do you think they saw?
Why, Buster Bear was running away too, and
he was running twice as fast as Farmer Brown's
boy!
He bumped into trees and crashed through bushes
and jumped over logs, and in almost no time
at all he was out of sight.
Altogether it was the most surprising thing
that the little people of the Green Forest
ever had seen.
Illus Buster Bear was running away, too
Sammy Jay looked at Blacky the Crow, and Blacky
looked at Chatterer, and Chatterer looked
at Happy Jack, and Happy Jack looked at Peter
Rabbit, and Peter looked at Unc' Billy Possum,
and Unc' Billy looked at Bobby Coon, and Bobby
looked at Johnny Chuck, and Johnny looked
at Reddy Fox, and Reddy looked at Jimmy Skunk,
and Jimmy looked at Billy Mink, and Billy
looked at Little Joe Otter, and for a minute
nobody could say a word.
Then Little Joe gave a funny little gasp.
"Why, why-e-e!" said he, "I believe Buster
Bear is afraid too!"
Unc' Billy Possum chuckled.
"Ah believe yo' are right again, Brer Otter,"
said he.
"It cert'nly does look so.
If Brer Bear isn't scared, he must have remembered
something impo'tant and has gone to attend
to it in a powerful hurry."
Then everybody began to laugh.
CHAPTER XV
BUSTER BEAR IS A FALLEN HERO
A fallen hero is some one to whom every one
has looked up as very brave and then proves
to be less brave than he was supposed to be.
That was the way with Buster Bear.
When Little Joe Otter had told how Farmer
Brown's boy had been afraid at the mere sight
of one of Buster Bear's big footprints, they
had at once made a hero of Buster.
At least some of them had.
As this was the first time, the very first
time, that they had ever known any one who
lives in the Green Forest to make Farmer Brown's
boy run away, they looked on Buster Bear with
a great deal of respect and were very proud
of him.
But now they had seen Buster Bear and Farmer
Brown's boy meet face to face; and while it
was true that Farmer Brown's boy had run away
as fast as ever he could, it was also true
that Buster Bear had done the same thing.
He had run even faster than Farmer Brown's
boy, and had hidden in the most lonely place
he could find in the very deepest part of
the Green Forest.
It was hard to believe, but it was true.
And right away everybody lost a great deal
of the respect for Buster which they had felt.
It is always that way.
They began to say unkind things about him.
They said them among themselves, and some
of them even said them to Buster when they
met him, or said them so that he would hear
them.
Of course Blacky the Crow and Sammy Jay, who,
because they can fly, have nothing to fear
from Buster, and who always delight in making
other people uncomfortable, never let a chance
go by to tell Buster and everybody else within
hearing what they thought of him.
They delighted in flying about through the
Green Forest until they had found Buster Bear
and then from the safety of the tree tops
screaming at him.
"Buster Bear is big and strong;
His teeth are big; his claws are long;
In spite of these he runs away
And hides himself the livelong day!"
A dozen times a day Buster would hear them
screaming this.
He would grind his teeth and glare up at them,
but that was all he could do.
He couldn't get at them.
He just had to stand it and do nothing.
But when impudent little Chatterer the Red
Squirrel shouted the same thing from a place
just out of reach in a big pine-tree, Buster
could stand it no longer.
He gave a deep, angry growl that made little
shivers run over Chatterer, and then suddenly
he started up that tree after Chatterer.
With a frightened little shriek Chatterer
scampered to the top of the tree.
He hadn't known that Buster could climb.
But Buster is a splendid climber, especially
when the tree is big and stout as this one
was, and now he went up after Chatterer, growling
angrily.
How Chatterer did wish that he had kept his
tongue still!
He ran to the very top of the tree, so frightened
that his teeth chattered, and when he looked
down and saw Buster's great mouth coming nearer
and nearer, he nearly tumbled down with terror.
The worst of it was there wasn't another tree
near enough for him to jump to.
He was in trouble this time, was Chatterer,
sure enough!
And there was no one to help him.
CHAPTER XVI
CHATTERER THE RED SQUIRREL JUMPS
FOR HIS LIFE
It isn't very often that Chatterer the Red
Squirrel knows fear.
That is one reason that he is so often impudent
and saucy.
But once in a while a great fear takes possession
of him, as when he knows that Shadow the Weasel
is looking for him.
You see, he knows that Shadow can go wherever
he can go.
There are very few of the little people of
the Green Forest and the Green Meadows who
do not know fear at some time or other, but
it comes to Chatterer as seldom as to any
one, because he is very sure of himself and
his ability to hide or run away from danger.
But now as he clung to a little branch near
the top of a tall pine-tree in the Green Forest
and looked down at the big sharp teeth of
Buster Bear drawing nearer and nearer, and
listened to the deep, angry growls that made
his hair stand on end, Chatterer was too frightened
to think.
If only he had kept his tongue still instead
of saying hateful things to Buster Bear!
If only he had known that Buster could climb
a tree!
If only he had chosen a tree near enough to
other trees for him to jump across!
But he had said hateful things, he had chosen
to sit in a tree which stood quite by itself,
and Buster Bear could climb!
Chatterer was in the worst kind of trouble,
and there was no one to blame but himself.
That is usually the case with those who get
into trouble.
Nearer and nearer came Buster Bear, and deeper
and angrier sounded his voice.
Chatterer gave a little frightened gasp and
looked this way and looked that way.
What should he do?
What could he do!
The ground seemed a terrible distance below.
If only he had wings like Sammy Jay!
But he hadn't.
"Gr-r-r-r!"
growled Buster Bear.
"I'll teach you manners!
I'll teach you to treat your betters with
respect!
I'll swallow you whole, that's what I'll do.
Gr-r-r-r!"
"Oh!" cried Chatterer.
"Gr-r-r-r!
I'll eat you all up to the last hair on your
tail!"
growled Buster, scrambling a little nearer.
"Oh!
Oh!" cried Chatterer, and ran out to the very
tip of the little branch to which he had been
clinging.
Now if Chatterer had only known it, Buster
Bear couldn't reach him way up there, because
the tree was too small at the top for such
a big fellow as Buster.
But Chatterer didn't think of that.
He gave one more frightened look down at those
big teeth, then he shut his eyes and jumped—
jumped straight out for the far-away ground.
It was a long, long, long way down to the
ground, and it certainly looked as if such
a little fellow as Chatterer must be killed.
But Chatterer had learned from Old Mother
Nature that she had given him certain things
to help him at just such times, and one of
them is the power to spread himself very flat.
He did it now.
He spread his arms and legs out just as far
as he could, and that kept him from falling
as fast and as hard as he otherwise would
have done, because being spread out so flat
that way, the air held him up a little.
And then there was his tail, that funny little
tail he is so fond of jerking when he scolds.
This helped him too.
It helped him keep his balance and keep from
turning over and over.
Down, down, down he sailed and landed on his
feet.
Of course, he hit the ground pretty hard,
and for just a second he quite lost his breath.
But it was only for a second, and then he
was scurrying off as fast as a frightened
Squirrel could.
Buster Bear watched him and grinned.
"I didn't catch him that time," he growled,
"but I guess I gave him a good fright and
taught him
a lesson."
CHAPTER XVII
BUSTER BEAR GOES BERRYING
Buster Bear is a great hand to talk to himself
when he thinks no one is around to overhear.
It's a habit.
However, it isn't a bad habit unless it is
carried too far.
Any habit becomes bad, if it is carried too
far.
Suppose you had a secret, a real secret, something
that nobody else knew and that you didn't
want anybody else to know.
And suppose you had the habit of talking to
yourself.
You might, without thinking, you know, tell
that secret out loud to yourself, and some
one might, just might happen to overhear!
Then there wouldn't be any secret.
That is the way that a habit which isn't bad
in itself can become bad when it is carried
too far.
Now Buster Bear had lived by himself in the
Great Woods so long that this habit of talking
to himself had grown and grown.
He did it just to keep from being lonesome.
Of course, when he came down to the Green
Forest to live, he brought all his habits
with him.
That is one thing about habits,—you always
take them with you wherever you go.
So Buster brought this habit of talking to
himself down to the Green Forest, where he
had many more neighbors than he had in the
Great Woods.
"Let me see, let me see, what is there to
tempt my appetite?" said Buster in his deep,
grumbly-rumbly voice.
"I find my appetite isn't what it ought to
be.
I need a change.
Yes, Sir, I need a change.
There is something I ought to have at this
time of year, and I haven't got it.
There is something that I used to have and
don't have now.
Ha!
I know!
I need some fresh fruit.
That's it—fresh fruit!
It must be about berry time now, and I'd forgotten
all about it.
My, my, my, how good some berries would taste!
Now if I were back up there in the Great Woods
I could have all I could eat.
Um-m-m-m!
Makes my mouth water just to think of it.
There ought to be some up in the Old Pasture.
There ought to be a lot of 'em up there.
If I wasn't afraid that some one would see
me, I'd go up there."
Buster sighed.
Then he sighed again.
The more he thought about those berries he
felt sure were growing in the Old Pasture,
the more he wanted some.
It seemed to him that never in all his life
had he wanted berries as he did now.
He wandered about uneasily.
He was hungry—hungry for berries and nothing
else.
By and by he began talking to himself again.
"If I wasn't afraid of being seen, I'd go
up to the Old Pasture this very minute.
Seems as if I could taste those berries."
He licked his lips hungrily as he spoke.
Then his face brightened.
"I know what I'll do!
I'll go up there at the very first peep of
day to-morrow.
I can eat all I want and get back to the Green
Forest before there is any danger that Farmer
Brown's boy or any one else I'm afraid of
will see me.
That's just what I'll do.
My, I wish to-morrow morning would hurry up
and come."
Now though Buster didn't know it, some one
had been listening, and that some one was
none other than Sammy Jay.
When at last Buster lay down for a nap, Sammy
flew away, chuckling to himself.
"I believe I'll visit the Old Pasture to-morrow
morning myself," thought he.
"I have an idea that something interesting
may happen if Buster doesn't change his mind."
Sammy was on the lookout very early the next
morning.
The first Jolly Little Sunbeams had only reached
the Green Meadows and had not started to creep
into the Green Forest, when he saw a big,
dark form steal out of the Green Forest where
it joins the Old Pasture.
It moved very swiftly and silently, as if
in a great hurry.
Sammy knew who it was: it was Buster Bear,
and he was going berrying.
Sammy waited a little until he could see better.
Then he too started for the Old Pasture.
CHAPTER XVIII
SOMEBODY ELSE GOES BERRYING
Isn't it funny how two people will often think
of the same thing at the same time, and neither
one know that the other is thinking of it?
That is just what happened the day that Buster
Bear first thought of going berrying.
While he was walking around in the Green Forest,
talking to himself about how hungry he was
for some berries and how sure he was that
there must be some up in the Old Pasture,
some one else was thinking about berries and
about the Old Pasture too.
"Will you make me a berry pie if I will get
the berries to-morrow?"
asked Farmer Brown's boy of his mother.
Of course Mrs. Brown promised that she would,
and so that night Farmer Brown's boy went
to bed very early that he might get up early
in the morning, and all night long he dreamed
of berries and berry pies.
He was awake even before jolly, round, red
Mr. Sun thought it was time to get up, and
he was all ready to start for the Old Pasture
when the first Jolly Little Sunbeams came
dancing across the Green Meadows.
He carried a big tin pail, and in the bottom
of it, wrapped up in a piece of paper, was
a lunch, for he meant to stay until he filled
that pail, if it took all day.
Now the Old Pasture is very large.
It lies at the foot of the Big Mountain, and
even extends a little way up on the Big Mountain.
There is room in it for many people to pick
berries all day without even seeing each other,
unless they roam about a great deal.
You see, the bushes grow very thick there,
and you cannot see very far in any direction.
Jolly, round, red Mr. Sun had climbed a little
way up in the sky by the time Farmer Brown's
boy reached the Old Pasture, and was smiling
down on all the Great World, and all the Great
World seemed to be smiling back.
Farmer Brown's boy started to whistle, and
then he stopped.
"If I whistle," thought he, "everybody will
know just where I am, and will keep out of
sight, and I never can get acquainted with
folks if they keep out of sight."
You see, Farmer Brown's boy was just beginning
to understand something that Peter Rabbit
and the other little people of the Green Meadows
and the Green Forest learned almost as soon
as they learned to walk,—that if you don't
want to
be seen, you mustn't be heard.
So he didn't whistle as he felt like doing,
and he tried not to make a bit of noise as
he followed an old cow-path towards a place
where he knew the berries grew thick and oh,
so big, and all the time he kept his eyes
wide open, and he kept his ears open too.
That is how he happened to hear a little cry,
a very faint little cry.
If he had been whistling, he wouldn't have
heard it at all.
He stopped to listen.
He never had heard a cry just like it before.
At first he couldn't make out just what it
was or where it came from.
But one thing he was sure of, and that was
that it was a cry of fright.
He stood perfectly still and listened with
all his might.
There it was again—"Help!
Help!
Help"—and it was very faint and sounded
terribly frightened.
He waited a minute or two, but heard nothing
more.
Then he put down his pail and began a hurried
look here, there, and everywhere.
He was sure that it had come from somewhere
on the ground, so he peered behind bushes
and peeped behind logs and stones, and then
just as he had about given up hope of finding
where it came from, he went around a little
turn in the old cow-path, and there right
in front of him was little Mr. Gartersnake,
and what do you think he was doing?
Well, I don't like to tell you, but he was
trying to swallow one of the children of Stickytoes
the Tree Toad.
Of course Farmer Brown's Boy didn't let him.
He made little Mr. Gartersnake set Master
Stickytoes free and held Mr.
Gartersnake until Master Stickytoes was safely
out of reach.
CHAPTER XIX
BUSTER BEAR HAS A FINE TIME
Buster Bear was having the finest time he
had had since he came down from the Great
Woods to live in the Green Forest.
To be sure, he wasn't in the Green Forest
now, but he wasn't far from it.
He was in the Old Pasture, one edge of which
touches one edge of the Green Forest.
And where do you think he was, in the Old
Pasture?
Why, right in the middle of the biggest patch
of the biggest blueberries he ever had seen
in all his life!
Now if there is any one thing that Buster
Bear had rather have above another, it is
all the berries he can eat, unless it be honey.
Nothing can quite equal honey in Buster's
mind.
But next to honey give him berries.
He isn't particular what kind of berries.
Raspberries, blackberries, or blueberries,
either kind, will make him perfectly happy.
"Um-m-m, my, my, but these are good!" he mumbled
in his deep grumbly-rumbly voice, as he sat
on his haunches stripping off the berries
greedily.
His little eyes twinkled with enjoyment, and
he didn't mind at all if now and then he got
leaves, and some green berries in his mouth
with the big ripe berries.
He didn't try to get them out.
Oh, my, no!
He just chomped them all up together and patted
his stomach from sheer delight.
Now Buster had reached the Old Pasture just
as jolly, round, red Mr. Sun had crept out
of bed, and he had fully made up his mind
that he would be back in the Green Forest
before Mr. Sun had climbed very far up in
the blue, blue sky.
You see, big as he is and strong as he is,
Buster Bear is very shy and bashful, and he
has no desire to meet Farmer Brown, or Farmer
Brown's boy, or any other of those two-legged
creatures called men.
It seems funny but he actually is afraid of
them.
And he had a feeling that he was a great deal
more likely to meet one of them in the Old
Pasture than deep in the Green Forest.
So when he started to look for berries, he
made up his mind that he would eat what he
could in a great hurry and get back to the
Green Forest before Farmer Brown's boy was
more than out of bed.
But when he found those berries he was so
hungry that he forgot his fears and everything
else.
They tasted so good that he just had to eat
and eat and eat.
Now you know that Buster is a very big fellow,
and it takes a lot to fill him up.
He kept eating and eating and eating, and
the
more he ate the more he wanted.
You know how it is.
So he wandered from one patch of berries to
another in the Old Pasture, and never once
thought of the time.
Somehow, time is the hardest thing in the
world to remember, when you are having a good
time.
Jolly, round, red Mr. Sun climbed higher and
higher in the blue, blue sky.
He looked down on all the Great World and
saw all that was going on.
He saw Buster Bear in the Old Pasture, and
smiled as he saw what a perfectly glorious
time Buster was having.
And he saw something else in the Old Pasture
that made his smile still broader.
He saw Farmer Brown's boy filling a great
tin pail with blueberries, and he knew that
Farmer Brown's boy didn't know that Buster
Bear was anywhere about, and he knew that
Buster Bear didn't know that Farmer Brown's
boy was anywhere about, and somehow he felt
very sure that he would see something funny
happen if they should chance to meet.
"Um-m-m, um-m-m," mumbled Buster Bear with
his mouth full, as he moved along to another
patch of berries.
And then he gave a little gasp of surprise
and delight.
Right in front of him was a shiny thing just
full of the finest, biggest, bluest berries!
There were no leaves or green ones there.
Buster blinked his greedy little eyes rapidly
and looked again.
No, he wasn't dreaming.
They were real berries, and all he had got
to do was to help himself.
Buster looked sharply at the shiny thing that
held the berries.
It seemed perfectly harmless.
He reached out a big paw and pushed it gently.
It tipped over and spilled out a lot of the
berries.
Yes, it was perfectly harmless.
Buster gave a little sigh of pure happiness.
He would eat those berries to the last one,
and then he would go home to the Green Forest.
CHAPTER XX
BUSTER BEAR CARRIES OFF THE PAIL
OF FARMER BROWN'S BOY
The question is, did Buster Bear steal Farmer
Brown's boy's pail?
To steal is to take something which belongs
to some one else.
There is no doubt that he stole the berries
that were in the pail when he found it, for
he deliberately ate them.
He knew well enough that some one must have
picked them—for whoever heard of blueberries
growing in tin pails?
So there is no doubt that when Buster took
them, he stole them.
But with the pail it was different.
He took the pail, but he didn't mean to take
it.
In fact, he didn't want that pail at all.
You see it was this way: When Buster found
that big tin pail brimming full of delicious
berries in the shade of that big bush in the
Old Pasture, he didn't stop to think whether
or not he had a right to them.
Buster is so fond of berries that from the
very second that his greedy little eyes saw
that pailful, he forgot everything but the
feast that was waiting for him right under
his very nose.
He didn't think anything about the right or
wrong of helping himself.
There before him were more berries than he
had ever seen together at one time in all
his life, and all he had to do was to eat
and eat and eat.
And that is just what he did do.
Of course he upset the pail, but he didn't
mind a little thing like that.
When he had gobbled up all the berries that
rolled out, he thrust his nose into the pail
to get all that were left in it.
Just then he heard a little noise, as if some
one were coming.
He threw up his head to listen, and somehow,
he never did know just how, the handle of
the pail slipped back over his ears and caught
there.
This was bad enough, but to make matters worse,
just at that very minute he heard a shrill,
angry voice shout, "Hi, there!
Get out of there!"
He didn't need to be told whose voice that
was.
It was the voice of Farmer Brown's boy.
Right then and there Buster Bear nearly had
a fit.
There was that awful pail fast over his head
so that he couldn't see a thing.
Of course, that meant that he couldn't run
away, which was the thing of all things he
most wanted to do, for big as he is and strong
as he is, Buster is very shy and bashful when
human beings are around.
He growled and whined and squealed.
He tried to back out of the pail and couldn't.
He tried to shake it off and couldn't.
He tried to pull it off, but somehow
he couldn't get hold of it.
Then there was another yell.
If Buster hadn't been so frightened himself,
he might have recognized that second yell
as one of fright, for that is what it was.
You see Farmer Brown's boy had just discovered
Buster Bear.
When he had yelled the first time, he had
supposed that it was one of the young cattle
who live in the Old Pasture all summer, but
when he saw Buster, he was just as badly frightened
as Buster himself.
In fact, he was too surprised and frightened
even to run.
After that second yell he just stood still
and stared.
Buster clawed at that awful thing on his head
more frantically than ever.
Suddenly it slipped off, so that he could
see.
He gave one frightened look at Farmer Brown's
boy, and then with a mighty "Woof!" he started
for the Green Forest as fast as his legs could
take him, and this was very fast indeed, let
me tell you.
He didn't stop to pick out a path, but just
crashed through the bushes as if they were
nothing at all, just nothing at all.
But the funniest thing of all is this—
he took that pail with him!
Yes, Sir, Buster Bear ran away with the big
tin pail of Farmer Brown's boy!
You see when it slipped off his head, the
handle was still around his neck, and there
he was running away with a pail hanging from
his neck!
He didn't want it.
He would have given anything to get rid of
it.
But he took it because he couldn't help it.
And that brings us back to the question, did
Buster steal Farmer Brown's boy's pail?
What do you think?
CHAPTER XXI
SAMMY JAY MAKES THINGS WORSE
FOR BUSTER BEAR
"Thief, thief, thief!
Thief, thief, thief!"
Sammy Jay was screaming at the top of his
lungs, as he followed Buster Bear across the
Old Pasture towards the Green Forest.
Never had he screamed so loud, and never had
his voice sounded so excited.
The little people of the Green Forest, the
Green Meadows, and the Smiling Pool are so
used to hearing Sammy cry thief that usually
they think very little about it.
But every blessed one who heard Sammy this
morning stopped whatever he was doing and
pricked up his ears to listen.
Sammy's cousin, Blacky the Crow, just happened
to be flying along the edge of the Old Pasture,
and the minute he heard Sammy's voice, he
turned and flew over to see what it was all
about.
Just as soon as he caught sight of Buster
Bear running for the Green Forest as hard
as ever he could, he understood what had excited
Sammy so.
He was so surprised that he almost forgot
to keep his wings moving.
Buster Bear had what looked to Blacky very
much like a tin pail hanging from his neck!
No wonder Sammy was excited.
Blacky beat his wings fiercely and started
after Sammy.
And so they reached the edge of the Green
Forest, Buster Bear running as hard as ever
he could, Sammy Jay flying just behind him
and screaming, "Thief, thief, thief!"
at the top of his lungs, and behind him Blacky
the Crow, trying to catch up and yelling as
loud as he could, "Caw, caw, caw!
Come on, everybody!
Come on!
Come on!"
Poor Buster!
It was bad enough to be frightened almost
to death as he had been up in the Old Pasture
when the pail had caught over his head just
as Farmer Brown's boy had yelled at him.
Then to have the handle of the pail slip down
around his neck so that he couldn't get rid
of the pail but had to take it with him as
he ran, was making a bad matter worse.
Now to have all his neighbors of the Green
Forest see him in such a fix and make fun
of him, was more than he could stand.
He felt humiliated.
That is just another way of saying shamed.
Yes, Sir, Buster felt that he was shamed in
the eyes of his neighbors, and he wanted nothing
so much as to get away by himself, where no
one could see him, and try
to get rid of that dreadful pail.
But Buster is so big that it is not easy for
him to find a hiding place.
So, when he reached the Green Forest, he kept
right on to the deepest, darkest, most lonesome
part and crept under the thickest hemlock-tree
he could find.
But it was of no use.
The sharp eyes of Sammy Jay and Blacky the
Crow saw him.
They actually flew into the very tree under
which he was hiding, and how they did scream!
Pretty soon Ol' Mistah Buzzard came dropping
down out of the blue, blue sky and took a
seat on a convenient dead tree, where he could
see all that went on.
Ol' Mistah Buzzard began to grin as soon as
he saw that tin pail on Buster's neck.
Then came others,—Redtail the Hawk, Scrapper
the Kingbird, Redwing the Blackbird, Drummer
the Woodpecker, Welcome Robin, Tommy Tit the
Chickadee, Jenny Wren, Redeye the Vireo, and
ever so many more.
They came from the Old Orchard, the Green
Meadows, and even down by the Smiling Pool,
for the voices of Sammy Jay and Blacky the
Crow carried far, and at the sound of them
everybody hurried over, sure that something
exciting was going on.
Presently Buster heard light footsteps, and
peeping out, he saw Billy Mink and Peter Rabbit
and Jumper the Hare and Prickly Porky and
Reddy Fox and Jimmy Skunk.
Even timid little Whitefoot the Wood Mouse
was where he could peer out and see without
being seen.
Of course, Chatterer the Red Squirrel and
Happy Jack the Gray Squirrel were there.
There they all sat in a great circle around
him, each where he felt safe, but where he
could see, and every one of them laughing
and making fun of Buster.
"Thief, thief, thief!"
screamed Sammy until his throat was sore.
The worst of it was Buster knew that everybody
knew that it was true.
That awful pail was proof of it.
"I wish I never had thought of berries," growled
Buster to himself.
CHAPTER XXII
BUSTER BEAR HAS A FIT OF TEMPER
A temper is a bad, bad thing
When once it gets away.
There's nothing quite at all like it
To spoil a pleasant day.
Buster Bear was in a terrible temper.
Yes, Sir, Buster Bear was having the worst
fit of temper ever seen in the Green Forest.
And the worst part of it all was that all
his neighbors of the Green Forest and a whole
lot from the Green Meadows and the Smiling
Pool were also there to see it.
It is bad enough to give way to temper when
you are all alone, and there is no one to
watch you, but when you let temper get the
best of you right where others see you, oh,
dear, dear, it certainly is a sorry sight.
Now ordinarily Buster is one of the most good-natured
persons in the world.
It takes a great deal to rouse his temper.
He isn't one tenth so quick tempered as Chatterer
the Red Squirrel, or Sammy Jay, or Reddy Fox.
But when his temper is aroused and gets away
from him, then watch out!
It seemed to Buster that he had had all that
he could stand that day and a little more.
First had come the fright back there in the
Old Pasture.
Then the pail had slipped down behind his
ears and held fast, so he had run all the
way to the Green Forest with it hanging about
his neck.
This was bad enough, for he knew just how
funny he must look, and besides, it was very
uncomfortable.
But to have Sammy Jay call everybody within
hearing to come and see him was more than
he could stand.
It seemed to Buster as if everybody who lives
in the Green Forest, on the Green Meadows,
or around the Smiling Brook, was sitting around
his hiding place, laughing and making fun
of him.
It was more than any self-respecting Bear
could stand.
With a roar of anger Buster Bear charged out
of his hiding place.
He rushed this way and that way!
He roared with all his might!
He was very terrible to see.
Those who could fly, flew.
Those who could climb, climbed.
And those who were swift of foot, ran.
A few who could neither fly nor climb nor
run fast, hid and lay shaking and trembling
for fear that Buster would find them.
In less time than it takes to tell about it,
Buster was alone.
At least, he couldn't see any one.
Illus Those who could fly, flew.
Those who could climb, climbed.
Then he vented his temper on the tin pail.
He cuffed at it and pulled at it, all the
time growling angrily.
He lay down and clawed at it with his hind
feet.
At last the handle broke, and he was free!
He shook himself.
Then he jumped on the helpless pail.
With a blow of a big paw he sent it clattering
against a tree.
He tried to bite it.
Then he once more fell to knocking it this
way and that way, until it was pounded flat,
and no one would ever have guessed that it
had once been a pail.
Then, and not till then, did Buster recover
his usual good nature.
Little by little, as he thought it all over,
a look of shame crept into his face.
"I—I guess it wasn't the fault of that thing.
I ought to have known enough to keep my head
out of it,"
he said slowly and thoughtfully.
"You got no more than you deserve for stealing
Farmer Brown's boy's berries,"
said Sammy Jay, who had come back and was
looking on from the top of a tree.
"You ought to know by this time that no good
comes of stealing."
Buster Bear looked up and grinned, and there
was a twinkle in his eyes.
"You ought to know, Sammy Jay," said he.
"I hope you'll always remember it."
"Thief, thief, thief!"
screamed Sammy, and flew away.
CHAPTER XXIII
FARMER BROWN'S BOY LUNCHES ON
BERRIES
When things go wrong in spite of you
To smile's the best thing you can do—
To smile and say, "I'm mighty glad
They are no worse; they're not so bad!"
That is what Farmer Brown's boy said when
he found that Buster Bear had stolen the berries
he had worked so hard to pick and then had
run off with the pail.
You see, Farmer Brown's boy is learning to
be something of a philosopher, one of those
people who accept bad things cheerfully and
right away see how they are better than they
might have been.
When he had first heard some one in the bushes
where he had hidden his pail of berries, he
had been very sure that it was one of the
cows or young cattle who live in the Old Pasture
during the summer.
He had been afraid that they might stupidly
kick over the pail and spill the berries,
and he had hurried to drive whoever it was
away.
It hadn't entered his head that it could be
anybody who would eat those berries.
When he had yelled and Buster Bear had suddenly
appeared, struggling to get off the pail which
had caught over his head, Farmer Brown's boy
had been too frightened to even move.
Then he had seen Buster tear away through
the brush even more frightened than he was,
and right away his courage had begun to come
back.
"If he is so afraid of me, I guess I needn't
be afraid of him," said he.
"I've lost my berries, but it is worth it
to find out that he is afraid of me.
There are plenty more on the bushes, and all
I've got to do is to pick them.
It might be worse."
He walked over to the place where the pail
had been, and then he remembered that when
Buster ran away he had carried the pail with
him, hanging about his neck.
He whistled.
It was a comical little whistle of chagrin
as he realized that he had nothing in which
to put more berries, even if he picked them.
"It's worse than I thought," cried he.
"That bear has cheated me out of that berry
pie my mother promised me."
Then he began to laugh, as he thought of how
funny
Buster Bear had looked with the pail about
his neck, and then because, you know he is
learning to be a philosopher, he once more
repeated, "It might have been worse.
Yes, indeed, it might have been worse.
That bear might have tried to eat me instead
of the berries.
I guess I'll go eat that lunch I left back
by the spring, and then I'll go home.
I can pick berries some other day."
Chuckling happily over Buster Bear's great
fright, Farmer Brown's boy tramped back to
the spring where he had left two thick sandwiches
on a flat stone when he started to save his
pail of berries.
"My, but those sandwiches will taste good,"
thought he.
"I'm glad they are big and thick.
I never was hungrier in my life.
Hello!"
This he exclaimed right out loud, for he had
just come in sight of the flat stone where
the sandwiches should have been, and they
were not there.
No, Sir, there wasn't so much as a crumb left
of those two thick sandwiches.
You see, Old Man Coyote had found them and
gobbled them up while Farmer Brown's boy was
away.
But Farmer Brown's boy didn't know anything
about Old Man Coyote.
He rubbed his eyes and stared everywhere,
even up in the trees, as if he thought those
sandwiches might be hanging up there.
They had disappeared as completely as if they
never had been, and Old Man Coyote had taken
care to leave no trace of his visit.
Farmer Brown's boy gaped foolishly this way
and that way.
Then, instead of growing angry, a slow smile
stole over his freckled face.
"I guess some one else was hungry too," he
muttered.
"Wonder who it was?
Guess this Old Pasture is no place for me
to-day.
I'll fill up on berries and then I'll go home."
So Farmer Brown's boy made his lunch on blueberries
and then rather sheepishly he started for
home to tell of all the strange things that
had happened to him in the Old Pasture.
Two or three times, as he trudged along, he
stopped to scratch his head thoughtfully.
"I guess," said he at last, "that I'm not
so smart as I thought I was, and I've got
a lot to learn yet."
This is the end of the adventures of Buster
Bear in this book because—guess why.
Because Old Mr. Toad insists that I must write
a book about his adventures, and Old Mr. Toad
is such a good friend of all of us that I
am going to do it.
- THE END -