CHAPTER ONE
The Bet
Professor Augustus S. F. X. Van Dusen's appearance
was as strange as his name. He was thin with
the thin shoulders of a student and his face
was extremely pale. His eyes were the eyes
of a man who studies little things. They were
always half-closed in concentration. Although
he wore thick glasses you could see that his
eyes were blue. But his strangest feature
was his abnormally large forehead, on top
of which sat a crown of yellow hair. Together
all these things gave him a bizarre, almost
grotesque personality.
Professor Van Dusen's family came from Germany.
Many of his ancestors had been famous scientists;
he was the logical result, the mastermind.
And logic was his passion. He believed that
two and two always equal four, except in unusual
cases, when they may equal three or Five.
He believed that all things that start must
go somewhere, and he was able to concentrate
all the mental force of his ancestors to solve
any problem.
The public knew Van Dusen as The Thinking
Machine and perhaps this phrase described
him best of all. He spent all his time in
his small laboratory where he invented brilliant
theories that shocked scientists and had a
profound effect on the world.
The Thinking Machine didn't have many visitors.
When people did come to see him they were
usually scientists. Two of these men, Dr Charles
Ransome and Alfred Fielding visited him one
evening to discuss some theory (what it was
exactly is of no importance).
"That is impossible," said Dr Ransome.
"Nothing is impossible," said The Thinking
Machine. "The mind is master of all things.
When science understands this, it will be
a great day."
"What about the airship?" asked Dr Ransome.
"That's not impossible at all," said The Thinking
Machine. "It will be invented soon. I would
do it myself, but unfortunately I'm too busy."
Dr Ransome laughed.
"I've heard you say things like that before,"
he said. "But they mean nothing. The mind
may be master of the material world, but there
are some problems that cannot be solved by
thought alone."
"Give me an example," demanded The Thinking
Machine.
Dr Ransome thought for a moment as he smoked.
"Well, what about the walls of a prison?"
he replied. "No man can escape from a cell
just by thinking about it. If he could, there
would be no prisoners." He continued. "Let's
imagine a case. A cell for prisoners who are
condemned to death. These men will do anything
to try to escape. Imagine you were in that
cell. Could you escape?"
"Certainly," said The Thinking Machine.
"Of course," said Mr Fielding, "you could
destroy the cell with an explosive, but if
you are a prisoner inside the cell you can't
have that."
"I don't need an explosive," said The Thinking
Machine. "I would be just like any other prisoner
and I would still be able to leave the cell."
"You could escape only if you entered it with
tools," said Dr Ransome.
The Thinking Machine was visibly irritated.
"Lock me in any cell in any prison anywhere
at any time, wearing only normal clothes,
and I'll escape in a week," he declared. Dr
Ransome was interested. Mr. Fielding lit a
new cigar.
"You're saying that you could escape from
the cell just by thinking about it?" Ransome
asked.
"I could get out."
"Are you serious?"
"Certainly, I'm serious."
Dr Ransome and Mr Fielding were silent for
a long time.
"Would you like to try it?" asked Mr Fielding
finally.
"Certainly," said Professor Van Dusen and
added ironically, "I have done more ridiculous
things than that to convince men of less important
facts."
Of course it was an absurd thing but they
decided it at that moment.
"To begin now." said Dr Ransome.
"I'd prefer tomorrow," said The Thinking Machine,
"because..."
"No, now!" said Mr Fielding. "You will be
locked in a cell with no chance to communicate
with friends. You will receive exactly the
same attention as a real prisoner, a man condemned
to death. Do you still agree to do it?"
"All right. Now, if you want," said The Thinking
Machine, and he stood up. "The death-cell
in Chisholm Prison?"
"Fine."
"And what will you wear?"
"Very little," said The Thinking Machine.
"Shoes, long socks, trousers and a shirt."
"The guards will search you, of course."
"They must treat me like any other prisoner,"
said The Thinking Machine.
And so they made the arrangements. They had
to obtain permission for the experiment but
all three of them wore important men and everything
was finalized with a few telephone calls.
The prison governors could not understand
why Professor Van Dusen wanted to do it. But
one thing was certain. They had never had
such an important prisoner.
The Thinking Machine dressed himself in the
clothes that he was going to wear in prison,
and called his housekeeper.
"Martha," he said, "it is now twenty-seven
minutes past nine. I am going away. One week
from tonight at half-past nine, these gentlemen
and one or two others will have dinner with
me here. Remember Dr Ransome likes carrots."
A driver took the three men to Chisholm Prison.
The warden was waiting for them. He understood
only that Professor Van Dusen was going to
be his prisoner for one week. He was not a
criminal, but he must be treated just like
any other prisoner.
"Search him," said Dr Ransome.
The guards searched The Thinking Machine but
they didn't find anything. The pockets of
his trousers were empty and his shirt didn't
have any pockets. They took off his shoes
and socks and looked inside them. Nothing.
Dr Ransome regarded Van Dusen's weak body
and his colorless face. He was suddenly sorry
about his idea.
"Are you sure you want to do this?" he asked.
"Would you believe me if I didn't do it?"
The Thinking Machine replied.
"No."
"All right, I'll do it."
Ransome didn't like the arrogance in Van Dusen's
voice. His sympathy for the man disappeared.
He decided that the experiment was a good
thing. It would teach The Thinking Machine
a lesson.
"Will it be possible for him to communicate
with anyone outside the prison?" he asked.
"No. It will be absolutely impossible," said
the warden. "He will not have anything to
write with."
"And the guards, will they send messages for
him?"
"Not one word," said the warden. "They will
tell me anything he says and they will give
me anything he gives them."
"Good," said Mr Fielding.
"Of course if he does not escape in a week,"
said Dr Ransome, "and asks to leave, you will
let him go?"
"I understand," said the warden.
Then The Thinking Machine spoke.
"I have three requests," he said, "I would
like some toothpaste and also one five-dollar
and two ten- dollar bills"
"Could he bribe your guards for twenty-five
dollars?"
Not even for twenty-five hundred dollars."
"In that case, give him the money," said Mr
Fielding.
"And what is the third request?" asked Dr
Ransome.
"Could somebody clean my shoes?"
The three men looked very surprised. This
last request seemed completely absurd, but
they agreed to it anyway. After this, they
took The Thinking Machine to his cell. They
walked down a long corridor and stopped at
the third steel door.
"Here is Cell 13," said the warden. "This
is where condemned killers are kept. No one
can leave it without my permission. No one
in it can communicate with anyone outside.
It is very near my office and I can hear any
noise that comes from it."
"Is this cell all right, gentlemen?" asked
The Thinking Machine.
"Yes, it's perfect," replied Fielding and
Ransome together.
The guard opened the door and The Thinking
Machine walked into the dark room. No sooner
was he inside than the warden closed the door
and locked it with a double lock. Ransome
heard a noise from inside the cell.
"What is that noise?" he asked through the
bars.
"Rats - the cell is full of rats," replied
The Thinking Machine.
The three men said goodnight and were turning
to go when The Thinking Machine called:
"What time is it exactly, warden?"
"Seventeen minutes past eleven."
"Thanks. I will see you all in your office
at half-past eight one week from this evening,"
said The Thinking Machine.
"And if you do not?"
"There is no possibility of that."
CHAPTER TWO
Chisholm Prison
Chisholm prison was a large building. It was
four floors high and stood in the centre of
a large open space. The wall around it was
six metres high and impossible to climb. Even
if a man managed to escape from his cell,
he could not pass over the wall.
The yard around the building was eight metres
wide on all sides. This was the distance from
the prison building to the wall. During the
day, prisoners used the yard to do exercises.
But it was not for those prisoners in Cell
13.
There were always four armed guards in the
yard, one for each side of the building.
At night strong lights illuminated the yard
and the wall. The wires that carried electricity
to these lights ran up the walls of the building.
The Thinking Machine saw and understood all
these things. He had to stand on his bed to
see out of the small barred window. It was
the morning after his incarceration. He soon
realised that somewhere on the other side
of the wall there was a river because he could
hear the sound of a boat and saw a river bird
in the sky. From the same direction he heard
the sound of children playing baseball, so
he knew that there was a children's playground
between the prison wall and the river.
No man had ever escaped from Chisholm Prison
and it was easy to see why. The walls of the
cell were perfectly solid and the bars on
the window were new. And in any case the window
itself was too small to escape through.
But this didn't discourage The Thinking Machine.
He looked up at the light and saw how the
wire went from it to the wall of the prison
building. He realised that the wire passed
near the window of his cell. That could be
useful.
Cell 13 was on the same floor as the prison
offices. The Thinking Machine couldn't see
the ground through the window of his cell.
However, there were only four steps up to
the office floor. Therefore the cell must
be near the ground. Good.
The Thinking Machine remembered how he had
come to the cell. First there was the outside
guard's room which formed part of the wall,
next to the prison gates. There was always
one guard at these gates who let people come
into the prison and then let them out again
when the warden told him to. The warden's
office was in the prison building. From the
yard you had to pass through a solid steel
door to get to it. The door had only one small
hole in it to see who was there. Then between
the office and Cell 13 there was a heavy wooden
door and two steel doors in the corridors
of the prison. Then, of course, there was
the door of Cell 13.
"There are seven doors between Cell 13 and
freedom," thought The Thinking Machine. "It
will not be easy. But there are advantages.
I am alone here. Nobody looks at what I am
doing.
There is one guard who brings my food three
times a day, at six o'clock in the morning,
at noon, then again at six in the afternoon.
And then there is the inspection at nine o'clock.
But that is all."
There was nothing, absolutely nothing in his
cell except a bed that was strongly made and
impossible to dismantle. There was no chair,
no table, no cup or fork or spoon. Nothing.
The guard watched him while he ate and took
away his plate and spoon as soon as he had
finished.
The Thinking Machine considered all these
facts very carefully. Then he began an examination
of his cell. He examined the stones in the
walls and roof and the cement between them.
He walked over the floor many times but it
was solid cement. After the examination he
sat on his bed and thought for a long time.
Because Professor Augustus S.F.X. Van Dusen
had something to think about.
Suddenly, he was disturbed by a rat which
ran across his foot and disappeared into a
dark corner of the cell. The Thinking Machine
looked hard into the corner. After some time
he saw several pairs of yellow eyes looking
back at him.
Then for the first time The Thinking Machine
noticed the bottom of his cell door. There
was a space of about five centimeters between
the steel bar and the floor. The Thinking
Machine walked into the corner where the rats
were, but he continued to look at the door.
The rats were afraid and tried to escape.
There was the sound of running feet and several
squeaks and then silence.
None of the rats had gone out the door, yet
the cell was now empty. Therefore there must
be another way out of the cell, even if it
was very small. He got down on his hands and
knees and began to look for the opening. Finally
he found it. It was a small circular hole
in the floor about four centimeters in diameter.
"So this is how the rats escaped. Interesting."
He put his hand in the hole. It seemed to
be an old drainpipe.
The Thinking Machine sat on the bed and thought
for an hour. Then he looked once more outside
his cell window. One of the outside guards
stood directly opposite, beside the wall.
He was looking at the window of Cell 13 when
The Thinking Machine's large head appeared.
But the Professor didn't see the guard.
At twelve o'clock the Cell 13 guard brought
The Thinking Machine his food. It was horrible
but The Thinking Machine didn't mind. He wasn't
interested in food. He spoke to the guard,
who watched him as he ate.
"Have they made any modifications here in
the last few years?" asked The Thinking Machine.
"Not really," said the guard. "They built
the new wall four years ago."
"Have they done anything to the prison building?"
"Well, they painted the outside. And then
seven years ago they had a new plumbing system
installed."
"Ah, I see," said the prisoner. "How far is
the river over there?"
"About a hundred metres. The boys have a baseball
ground between the wall and the river."
The Thinking Machine had nothing more to say,
but when the guard was ready to go he asked
for some water.
"I get very thirsty here," he explained. "Could
I have some water in a cup please?"
"I'll ask the warden," replied the guard,
and he went away.
Half an hour later he returned with a small
cup.
"The warden says you may keep this cup," he
told the prisoner. "But you must show it to
me when I ask for it. If you break it, I won't
give you another one."
"Thank you," said The Thinking Machine. "I
won't break it."
Two hours later the same guard was passing
the door of Cell 13. He heard a noise and
stopped. The Thinking Machine was on his hands
and knees in a corner of the cell. There was
the sound of several squeaks. The guard watched
him.
"Ah, I've got you," he heard the prisoner
say.
"What have you got?" said the guard.
"One of these rats," he replied. "See?" The
guard saw a rat in The Thinking Machine's
hands. The prisoner carried it towards the
light. "It's a water rat," he said.
"Haven't you got anything better to do than
catch rats?" asked the guard.
"It's terrible that there are rats in this
prison," said The Thinking Machine. "Take
this one away and kill it. There are many
more where it came from."
The guard took the rat and killed it. Later
he told the warden about the incident, but
the warden only smiled.
Later that afternoon the armed guard in the
yard outside Cell 13 saw the prisoner look
out and put a hand through the bars of the
window. Something white fell slowly to the
ground. It was a roll of linen from a shirt,
and wrapped around it was a five-dollar bill.
The guard looked up at the window again but
the face was no longer there.
With a smile he took the cloth and the five-dollar
bill to the warden's office. There was something
written on the outside of the cloth in strange
ink. It said:
"Please deliver to Dr Charles Ransome."
"Ha!" said the warden, "His first plan of
escape has failed. But why did he address
it to Dr Ransome?"
"And where did he get the pen and ink to write
with?" added the guard.
The warden looked at the guard and the guard
looked at the warden. There was no easy solution
to the mystery. The warden studied the writing
carefully.
"Well, let's see what he wanted to say to
Dr Ransome," he said. He unrolled the second
piece of linen.
"Well, if that - what - what do you think
of that?" he asked, extremely confused.
The guard took the piece of linen
and read:
"Epa cseot d'net niiy awe htto n'si sih. T."
CHAPTER THREE
A Message from Cell 13
The warden spent an hour trying to discover
what the message was. Why did his prisoner
want to talk to Dr Ransome? And where had
he got the materials to write? He examined
the linen again. It was a part of a white
shirt. But what had he written with? The warden
knew that the prisoner didn't have a pen or
a pencil. So what had he used? The warden
decided to investigate. The Thinking Machine
was his prisoner. "If this man is trying to
escape by sending coded messages," he thought,
"I will stop him."
The warden returned to Cell 13. He found The
Thinking Machine on his hands and knees. He
was catching rats. The prisoner heard the
warden and turned to him quickly.
"It's terrible," he said. "These rats. There
are hundreds of them."
"Other men can live with them," said the warden.
"Give me your shirt. Here is another one."
"Why?" demanded The Thinking Machine.
"You have attempted to communicate with Dr
Ransome," said the warden, angrily. "As the
warden of this prison, I must stop you." The
Thinking Machine was silent for a moment.
"All right," he said, finally. "Here. Take
it."
The warden smiled. The prisoner stood up and
took off his shirt. He gave it to the warden.
In exchange, the warden gave him a blue prison
shirt. The warden looked at The Thinking Machine's
white shirt. He compared the pieces of linen
he had with the shirt. It was torn in two
places. The Thinking Machine watched him.
"Did the guard give you those?" he asked.
"Yes, he did," said the warden. "And that
is the end of your first attempt to escape."
The Thinking Machine watched the warden as
he looked at the shirt. He saw that there
were only two pieces missing from it. He smiled.
"What did you write this message with?" asked
the warden.
"I'm afraid you must discover that!" The Thinking
Machine said.
The warden became angry but he didn't say
anything more. He made a very careful inspection
of the cell and the prisoner, but he found
nothing. Nothing that The Thinking Machine
could use as a pen. And the liquid that he
had used to write the message was also a mystery.
Finally the warden went out of the cell. He
took The Thinking Machine's shirt with him.
"Well, he won't escape by writing messages
on a shirt," the warden thought.
On the third day of his incarceration The
Thinking Machine tried to bribe the guard
so that he could escape. The guard brought
his food and waited outside the cell door.
"The drainpipes of the prison go to the river,
don't they?" The Thinking Machine asked.
"Yes," said the guard.
"I imagine they are very small?"
"Yes. They are too small to escape through."
There was silence. The Thinking Machine finished
his food. Then he said:
"You know I'm not a criminal, don't you?"
"Yes."
"And I can leave the prison if I want to?"
"Well, when I came here I believed I could
escape," said the prisoner. "Will you help
me if I give you some money?"
The guard was an honest man.
"No," he said.
"Five hundred dollars," said The Thinking
Machine. "I am not a criminal."
"No," said the guard.
"A thousand?"
"No. If you gave me ten thousand dollars,
I couldn't get you out. To get out you have
to pass through seven doors and I only have
the keys to two."
The guard ran to the warden's office and told
him about the prisoner's offer.
"Plan number two fails," said the warden and
smiled. "First a message and then a bribe."
At six o'clock, the guard went to Cell 13
again to bring food to The Thinking Machine.
He stopped in the corridor. There was a noise
coming from inside the cell. The guard walked
very quietly to the cell door. Through the
bars he saw The Thinking Machine at the window.
He was trying to cut through the iron bars
of the window with a file.
The guard went back to the office and told
the warden. The two men went back to Cell
13, walking very quietly. The warden looked
into the cell and saw The Thinking Machine
still at the window. He entered the cell.
The Thinking Machine turned round and jumped
onto the floor. He tried to hide the file
in his hand.
"Give it to me," said the warden.
"No," said the prisoner. There was anger in
his voice.
"Come on. Give it to me."
"No," repeated The Thinking Machine.
"Very well. Search him," said the warden to
the guard.
The guard searched The Thinking Machine. After
some minutes he found a piece of steel about
five centimeters long in the prisoner's trousers.
A few minutes later he found another piece.
The guard gave the pieces of steel to the
warden. The warden looked at them.
"You couldn't cut through the bars on the
window with these," he said.
"Yes I could," said The Thinking Machine.
"In six months perhaps," said the warden,
smiling.
"Just wait, you'll see," said The Thinking
Machine.
Once more the guard searched the cell. But
once more they found nothing. The warden stood
on the bed and looked at the bars of the window.
He took the bars in his hand and tried to
move them. They were immovable. He smiled
and then got down from the bed.
"Forget it, Professor, you will never escape
from here," he said.
The Thinking Machine said nothing. He just
sat on the bed with his head in his hands.
The warden and the guard went out of the cell
and closed the door.
"He is mad to try and escape," said the warden,
"but he is very clever. I would like to know
what he used to write that coded message."
It was four o'clock the next morning when
a terrible scream resounded through the prison.
It came from a cell near the centre of the
building, a sound full of horror and great
fear. The warden heard it and ran with three
of his men into the long corridor that went
to Cell 13.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Strange Voice
As they ran they heard the scream again. The
white faces of prisoners appeared at cell
doors. They were afraid.
"It's that crazy man in Cell 13." the warden
said.
He stopped and looked into the cell. "That
crazy man in Cell 13" was sleeping comfortably
in his bed. They heard the scream again. It
was coming from somewhere above. The warden
and the guards went upstairs. There they found
a man in Cell 43, directly above Cell 13.
He was sitting in the corner of his cell like
a child.
"What's wrong?" demanded the warden.
"Thank God you've come!' said the prisoner.
"What is it?" demanded the warden again.
He opened the door and went into Cell 43.
The prisoner's face was white with terror.
"Take me out of this cell, please take me
out," he said.
"What is it?" asked the warden.
"I heard something - something."
"What did you hear?"
"I can't tell you," said the prisoner. "Please
take me out of this cell - put me anywhere
- but take me out of here."
"Who is this man?" the warden asked the guard.
"His name is Joseph Ballard," the guard replied.
"And what is his crime?"
"They say he killed a woman with acid."
"But they can't prove it," said the prisoner.
"They can't prove it!" The warden was silent
for a minute.
"Listen to me, Ballard," he said, finally.
"If you heard something, I want to know what
it was. Now tell me."
"I can't tell you." Ballard was crying now.
"Where did it come from?"
"I don't know. Everywhere - nowhere. I don't
know."
"Was it a voice?"
"I can't tell you," said the prisoner. "You
must tell me," said the warden, angrily.
"It was a voice - but - but - it wasn't human,"
said the prisoner.
"A voice, but not human?" repeated the warden.
He was confused.
"It was strange and very far away, like a
ghost."
"Did it come from inside or outside the prison?"
"It didn't come from anywhere. It was here,
there, everywhere. I heard it. I heard it!"
For an hour the warden tried to get the story,
but Ballard became silent and didn't say anything
more. Finally the warden went away. He was
very confused. Ballard sat at his cell door
until morning, his white face staring through
the bars.
It was the fourth day of The Thinking Machine's
incarceration. He stood at his cell window
and threw another piece of linen to the guard
outside. And once more the guard took it to
the warden. The warden read the message on
it. It said:
"Only three days more."
The warden was not surprised by the message.
He knew The Thinking Machine meant that there
were only three days more before he escaped.
"But how did he write it?" the warden thought.
"Where did he find another piece of linen?
Where? How?" He looked at the linen. It was
white, like the material from a shirt. He
took The Thinking Machine's shirt and put
the two original pieces of linen on the torn
places. The third piece was completely superfluous.
But it was the same material. "Where did he
get it? And where - where does he get anything
to write with?"
Later on the fourth day The Thinking Machine
spoke to the guard outside his window.
"What day of the month is it?" he asked.
"The fifteenth."
The Thinking Machine made a mental astronomical
calculation. "Good," he thought. "Tonight
the moon will not rise before nine o'clock."
Then he asked another question.
"Who looks after the big lights on the roof?"
"An electrician from the company."
"You have no electricians in the building?"
"No."
At the end of the afternoon, just before he
finished work, the outside guard saw The Thinking
Machine's head again at the window. He had
something in his hand which he threw to the
ground. It was a five-dollar bill.
"That's for you," said the prisoner.
Once again, the guard took it to the warden.
"He said it was for me."
"I imagine it's a present from him. I think
you can accept it," said the warden. Then
suddenly he stopped. "Wait a minute. When
the professor went into the cell he had one
five-dollar bill and two ten-dollar bills.
There was a five-dollar bill with the first
message. I have it here. But now he has given
you another five- dollar bill. It's impossible.
He has only two ten-dollar bills."
"Perhaps somebody changed a ten-dollar bill
for him," said the guard.
"Perhaps. But tonight we are going to search
Cell 13 again. We are going to search it as
no cell has ever been searched before."
So that night at three o'clock in the morning
the warden and his guards searched The Thinking
Machine's cell again. The warden found the
hole in the floor. He put his hand into it.
There was something there. He pulled it out.
A dead rat. He threw it to the floor in disgust.
But he continued the search. Once more he
examined the bars on the window but found
them to be solid. He then examined The Thinking
Machine's clothes. In his trousers he found
some money.
"Five one-dollar bills!" said the warden.
He was very surprised.
"That's right," said the prisoner.
"But the... you had two tens and a five...
how do you do it?"
"That's my business," said The Thinking Machine.
"Did any of my men change this money for you?"
"No."
"Well, do you make it?" asked the warden.
"That's my business," said the prisoner again.
The warden was very angry. He left the cell
and went back to bed.
About an hour later he heard the scream again.
He got up and ran immediately to Cell 43,
where he saw Ballard, his face pressed against
the bars of the door.
"Take me out, take me out," he screamed. "I
did it. I did it. I killed her. Take me out
of here."
"Was it the voice again?" asked the warden.
"Yes," said Ballard.
"What did it say?"
"Acid - acid - acid!" said the prisoner. "It
knew. I threw the acid in the woman's face
and killed her. Oh!"
"Acid?" repeated the warden, more confused
than ever.
CHAPTER FIVE
Countdown to Freedom
On the fifth day of The Thinking Machine's
incarceration, the warden looked tired. He
wanted this thing to finish. He wanted his
confusion to end. But that day The Thinking
Machine threw another piece of linen to the
guard. It said "Only two days more". This
time there was a silver half-dollar with it.
Now the warden knew - he knew that the man
in Cell 13 didn't have any half-dollars - he
couldn't have any half-dollars. Just as he
couldn't have pen and ink and linen. But he
did have them. It was a fact, not a theory.
And that is why the warden looked so tired.
Then there was the voice that Ballard had
heard. The word acid. It didn't mean anything,
of course. Ballard was obviously mad. But
there were so many things that "didn't mean
anything" now that The Thinking Machine was
in the prison.
On the sixth day, the warden received a letter
from Dr Ransome. It said:
Dear Sir.
Mr Fielding and I will meet you in your office
tomorrow evening. If Professor Van Dasen has
not escaped - and we believe he has not because
we have not received a letter from him - we
will meet him there too.
Yours, Dr Ransome.
That day The Thinking Machine had three more
messages for the warden. They were written
on the same linen and referred to the meeting
with Dr Ransome and Mr Fielding.
On the afternoon of the seventh day the warden
passed Cell 13 and looked in. The Thinking
Machine was sleeping on his bed. Everything
in the cell was completely normal. "He cannot
escape between now and half-past eight this
evening," the warden thought.
That evening after six o'clock he saw the
guard. "Is everything all right in Cell 13?"
he asked. "Yes sir," replied the guard. "But
he didn't eat much today." The warden was
feeling happy when he met Dr Ransome and Mr
Fielding that evening, at seven o'clock. He
wanted to show them The Thinking Machine's
messages. He wanted to tell them about the
events of the week. But before he could speak,
the guard from the river side of the prison
yard came into the office.
"The light on my side of the yard is broken,"
the guard said. Oh no. Another problem," said
the warden. The guard returned to his post
in the dark. The warden called the electric
light company.
"Hello. This is Chisholm Prison," he said
into the phone. "One of our lights is broken.
Could you send four men here to repair it?
Thank you. Goodbye." The warden went out into
the yard. While Dr Ransome and Mr Fielding
were waiting, the guard from the prison gate
came into the office. In his hand was a letter.
Dr Ransome looked at the letter.
"Incredible!" he said. "What is it?" asked
Mr Fielding. The doctor gave him the letter.
Fielding looked at it. "It's a coincidence.
It must be," he said. It was almost eight
o'clock when the warden returned to his office.
"The electricians have arrived," he said.
"They are working on the light now."
The warden telephoned the guard at the prison
gate. "How many electricians came in?" he
asked. "Four," was the reply.
"All right. You must be certain that only
four men go out of the prison," said the warden.
He put down the phone and took the letter.
"My God! It's not possible," he said, shocked.
"What is it?" asked Mr Fielding.
"It's a letter from Cell 13," said the warden.
"An invitation to dinner!"
"What?" said Ransome.
The three men were silent for a long time.
Finally the warden called a guard.
"Go down to Cell 13 immediately," he said,
"and see if the Professor is still there."
The guard ran down the corridor. Dr Ransome
and Mr Fielding examined the letter.
"It's Van Dusen's handwriting; there's no
doubt about that," said Dr Ransome. "I've
seen too much of it."
At that moment the telephone rang again. It
was the guard at the prison gate. There were
two newspaper reporters and they wanted to
see the warden. The warden told the guard
to let them come in.
"It's impossible," he said. "Professor Van
Dusen must be in Cell 13."
Then the guard returned.
"He's still in his cell, sir," he said. "I
saw him. He's sleeping."
"There. I told you." said the warden. "But
if he is still in his cell how did he send
the letter?"
There was a knock at the door.
"It's the reporters," said the warden. "Come
in."
The door opened and the two men entered.
"Good evening, gentlemen," said one. It was
Hutchinson Hatch. The warden knew him well.
Then the second man came in.
"Well, I'm here," he said. It was The Thinking
Machine.
The warden sat with his mouth open. He was
paralyzed.
"How - how - how did you do it?" asked the
warden, finally.
"Let's go back to the cell," said The Thinking
Machine.
The men walked down the corridor to the door
of Cell 13.
"Look inside," said The Thinking Machine.
The warden looked inside. Everything looked
normal and there - there on the bed was the
figure of The Thinking Machine. Certainly!
There was his yellow hair! The warden looked
again at the man beside him. "I must be mad,"
he thought.
Then he unlocked the cell door and The Thinking
Machine went inside.
"Look here," he said.
He put his foot on the steel bars at the bottom
of the cell door and three of them fell out.
"And here, too," The Thinking Machine stood
on his bed and put his hand to the bars on
the window. All of them came out.
"So what's this in the bed?" asked the warden.
"It's a wig," The Thinking Machine replied.
"Take the cover off."
The warden did this. Under it was a coil of
strong rope about ten metres long, a knife,
three files, three metres of electric wire,
a pair of steel pliers, a hammer and a pistol
"How did you do it?" asked the warden. "You
gentlemen have an invitation to dinner with
me at half-past nine," said The Thinking Machine.
"Come on, or we shall be late."
"But how did you do it?" the warden insisted.
"You cannot hold a man in prison who can use
his brain," replied The Thinking Machine.
"Come on, or we shall be late."
CHAPTER SIX
How Did He Do It?
When dinner was finished The Thinking Machine
turned to Dr Ransome.
"Well, do you believe me now?" he asked.
"Yes I do," replied Dr Ransome.
There was a long silence. Like all the other
guests, Ransome was waiting for the explanation.
"So, tell us how you did it," said Fielding,
finally.
The Thinking Machine began the story.
"The agreement was to go into a cell in Chisholm
Prison with nothing but the necessary clothes
and to leave that cell within seven days.
I didn't know Chisholm Prison. When I went
into the cell I asked for three things: toothpaste,
two ten-dollar bills and one five-dollar bill
and to have my shoes blacked. You agreed to
these things.
"I knew that there was nothing useful in the
cell, so I had to use these three innocent
things to help me escape. But anything is
dangerous in the hands of a man like me.
"The first night I did two things. I slept
and I ran after rats. You gentlemen thought
I wanted time to organize an escape with assistance
from outside the prison. But this was not
true. I knew I could communicate with anyone
I wanted to at any time."
The warden looked at him for a moment. The
Thinking Machine continued.
"The guard woke me up at six o'clock the next
morning. He brought me my breakfast. He told
me lunch was at twelve o'clock and dinner
was at six. I knew that between these times
I was alone. So after breakfast I examined
the outside area from my cell window. I saw
that it was impossible to get over the wall.
But I knew that on the other side of the wall
there was a river and also a playground. The
guard confirmed it. So I knew one important
thing. A person could come near the prison
on that side without attracting the attention
of the guards.
"But there was something even more important.
I saw a wire which went to the light on the
prison roof. It was very near my cell window.
I knew then that if it was necessary I could
cut off that light.
"Then I thought about escaping through the
prison building. I remembered the way to my
cell. I knew that was the only way out. There
were seven doors between my cell and the outside.
It was too difficult."
The Thinking Machine stopped for a moment.
Dr Ransome lit a new cigar. For several minutes
there was silence. Then The Thinking Machine
continued.
"When I was thinking about these things a
rat ran across my foot. It gave me a new idea.
I saw there were at least six rats in the
cell. But they didn't come from under the
door. I ran after them and they disappeared.
But they didn't go out of the door. So I knew
there was another way out.
"I looked for this other way and found it.
It was a hole in the floor. It went to an
old drainpipe. Obviously the rats came this
way. But where did they come from? Drainpipes
normally go outside the prison. This one probably
went to the river or near it. So the rats
came from that direction.
"When the guard came with my lunch he told
me two important things. One was that there
was a new plumbing system in the prison. The
other was that the river was only a hundred
metres away. So I knew that the pipe in my
cell was part of an old system. And I knew
it went to the river. The other end of the
pipe was outside the prison walls.
"But before I could start work, I knew I had
to distract the warden. I wanted him to think
that I was trying to communicate with you,
Dr Ransome. So I took two pieces of linen
from my shirt and wrote a message on them.
Do you have the message, warden?"
"Yes." The warden looked at the codec message.
"But what does it mean?" he asked. "Read it
from right to left, beginning with the T"
said The Thinking Machine. "Don't consider
the division into words."
The warden read the message.
"T-h-i-s," he began, "is not the way I intend
to escape." The warden smiled. "But what did
you write it with?"
"This," said The Thinking Machine. He put
his foot on the table. On it was the shoe
that he wore in prison. But the polish was
gone.
"The shoe polish, mixed with some water, was
my ink," said The Thinking Machine, "and the
metal end of the shoe lace was a good pen."
The warden laughed. "Continue," he said.
"After the message the warden wanted to search
my cell. This was good. I wanted him to search
my cell very often. I thought, 'He won't find
anything so he will stop and leave me alone.'
"The warden took my shirt away and gave me
a prison shirt.
Without my white shirt I couldn't write any
more messages. But I had another piece of
the same shirt in my mouth."
"Where did it come from?" asked the warden.
"I saw that there were only two pieces cut
from the shirt. And I had both of them."
"You forget that shirts like mine have three
layers of linen," The Thinking Machine replied.
"I took out the inside one. You didn't notice
it.
"Now that the warden was busy, I started to
work on my real escape plan. I knew that the
pipe from my cell went to the playground outside
the prison. It is a place where boys play
baseball. I knew many of the boys there. I
knew that the rats came into my cell from
out there. Perhaps it was possible for me
to communicate with someone outside. I could
use the rats.
"The first thing I needed was a long thread.
So I used the thread from my socks." He pulled
up his trouser-legs. The strong thread at
the top of his long socks was not there.
"Then on one half of my last piece of linen
I wrote a message for Hutchinson Hatch. He
is a friend and often helps me. I knew he
would help me this time. It was a great story
for his newspaper. I tied a ten-dollar bill
to the letter to attract attention. People
always find money. I wrote on the linen: 'If
you find this message give it to Hutchinson
Hatch. He will give you another ten dollars
for the information.' Then I wrote instructions
for Hatch.
"I had to get this note outside the prison.
There were two ways but the best way was the
rats. I took one of them. I tied the linen
and the money to one of its legs and tied
my thread to another. Then I put it in the
pipe.
"From the moment the rat disappeared into
that dirty pipe I was nervous. The thread
could break. Anything could happen. I waited.
I was holding the thread and I saw that it
became gradually shorter. Finally there was
only about one metre of thread in my hand.
I knew that the rat was outside the prison.
But would Hatch receive the message?
"I had to wait. I decided to try some other
man oeuvres. This was to confuse the warden
more. I tried to bribe the guard. I tried
to cut through the bars on my cell window.
The warden became very angry. He took the
bars in his hands to see if they were solid.
They were - then.
"That night I didn't sleep. The thread was
tied to my hand. I waited for the signal from
outside. I thought. 'If Hatch has received
the message, and if he finds the drainpipe,
he will pull the thread.' At half-past three
in the morning I felt something pull the thread."
The Thinking Machine turned to Hutchinson
Hatch.
"Now you can explain what you did," he said.
"A small boy brought the linen message to
me. I gave the boy another ten dollars. I
got some string and then some wire. I went
with the boy to the playground. I looked for
the end of the drainpipe for an hour. Then
finally I found it. It was about thirty centimeters
in diameter. I took the end of the thread
and pulled it three times. The Professor pulled
twice to reply. Quickly I tied my string to
the Professor's thread. Then I tied the wire
to the string. Professor Van Dusen began to
pull it all into his cell. The wire was the
most important because it could not break.
The thread was too weak. It could break easily.
With the wire I could transport things to
the cell."
"Yes," continued The Thinking Machine. "I
was very happy when the wire arrived in the
cell. Then we tried another experiment. I
spoke to Mr Hatch through the pipe. He heard
me but it was not easy for him to understand
me. I wanted some nitric- acid and I had to
repeat the word 'acid' several times. Then
I heard a scream from the cell above me.
"With the wire it was easy to transport things
to my cell. And it was also easy to hide them.
I could put them into the pipe. You, Mr Warden,
found the pipe but you could not find the
wire. Your hands are too big. My fingers are
longer and thinner so it was easy for me.
In addition I put a dead rat in the pipe.
You pulled it out."
"I remember," said the warden.
"The rat was there to stop you investigating
the pipe," said The Thinking Machine.
"That night Mr Hatch could not send me anything
useful. But he did send me change for ten
dollars as a test. The next clay I continued
to work on my plan.
"For this it was necessary that the guard
outside saw me often at my cell window. To
attract his attention I threw messages to
him. I stood at my cell window for hours.
Sometimes I spoke to him. He told me that
there were no electricians inside the prison.
If there was a problem with the lights they
had to call the light company.
"This was perfect for my escape plan. There
was only one more thing to do before I escaped.
Once again I spoke to Mr Hatch through the
pipe. It was the fourth night of my incarceration.
Again Mr Hatch could not understand me. Again
I repeated the word 'acid' three times. It
was this that made the prisoner above me confess
to murder. The guard told me the next day.
The prisoner heard strange voices through
the pipe. He thought it was a ghost.
"With nitric acid it was very easy to cut
the bars of the window. But it was a long
process. The outside guard saw me standing
at my window. He didn't know what I was doing.
As he watched me I cut the bars with a piece
of wire covered with acid. On the night of
my escape I used the same acid to cut the
electric wire that went to the lights. The
yard outside my window was completely dark.
It was easy to escape.
"I also had a wig from Mr Hatch. It was the
same color as my hair. Yellow. I put it in
the bed with some other things that Hatch
sent me. When the guard passed the door he
thought I was sleeping."
"But how did you get outside the prison gate,"
asked the warden.
"It was simple," The Thinking Machine replied.
"As I said. I cut the wire to the lights before
the guards turned on the current. When they
turned on the current, the light on my side
of the yard didn't work. The outside guard
went to your office to tell you and I escaped
through my cell window. I stayed in the shadows
until the four electricians arrived. Mr Hatch
was one of them.
"When I saw him he gave me some workman's
clothes to put on. You, Mr Warden, were standing
only three metres away. Then Mr Hatch called
me - as a workman - and together we went out
of the gate to get something from the van.
The guard at the gate knew that there were
four workers in the yard. He saw that we were
workers so he let us go out of the prison.
Then we changed clothes and came back in.
We went to your office and asked to see you.
That's all."
"And the letter of invitation?" asked Ransome.
"I wrote it in my cell with Mr Hatch's pen,"
said The Thinking Machine. "Then I sent it
through the pipe and Mr Hatch posted it."
There was silence for several minutes. Dr
Ransome was the first to speak.
"Incredible!" he said. "Absolutely brilliant!"
But Mr Fielding had two more questions.
"And what was the toothpaste for?" he asked.
"For brushing my teeth."
"Why did Mr Hatch come with the electricians?"
"His father is the manager of the company,"
said The Thinking Machine.
"But what if there was no Mr Hatch outside
to help you?"
"Every prisoner has at least one friend who
will help him if he can."
"What if there was no old drainpipe in your
cell," asked the warden.
"There were another two ways to escape," said
The Thinking Machine.
Ten minutes later the telephone rang. It was
for the warden.
"Is the light working now?" asked the warden
through the phone. "Good. The wire was cut
beside Cell 13? Yes I know. What's that? There
are too many electricians. Two went out of
the prison and there are three still inside.
But only four men came from the light company."
The warden turned to the others, confused.
"The guard says that he saw four electricians
come into the prison. Two went out again.
But there are still three men inside," he
said.
"Don't you remember? I was the extra man,"
said The Thinking Machine.
"Oh," said the warden. "I see." He turned
back to the phone. "You can let the fifth
man go. He's all right."
- THE END -