127 HOURS
PROLOGUE
You are going to die.
I hear the voice in my head.
I call it my first voice.
It always comes after I've made some kind
of mistake.
Its words never help, they just make me feel
bad.
So I wait for the second voice.
Its words are calm and sensible and nearly
always help me.
I wait, but tonight the second voice doesn't
come.
There is only silence, darkness and cold.
In the first days, the second voice always
came.
It stopped me feeling sad, angry, or afraid.
It gave me ideas.
It showed me things.
It brought me hope.
I believed I could be free again.
But, slowly, that voice disappeared.
My belief disappeared with it.
Now there is only the first voice.
It says the same thing over and over again.
Finally, I must accept the truth: I am going
to die.
CHAPTER ONE
'The most beautiful place on Earth'
It is Saturday, April the 26th, 2003.
My name is Aron Ralston.
I'm biking and hiking in Canyonlands National
Park in southeast Utah, USA.
Edward Abbey, one of my favourite writers,
described it as 'the most beautiful place
on Earth'.
Right now, with the sun on my back and the
wind in my hair, I agree.
Today is the third day of an activity holiday.
It started on Thursday when I went climbing
and skiing on Mount Soplis with my friend,
Brad.
Yesterday, I biked the Slick Rock Trail, alone.
It's not very long - only a little over nineteen
kilometres - but it's one of the most difficult
bike trails in the US.
Today, my plan is to hike through Blue John
and Horseshoe Canyons after biking to the
trail.
I'll leave my bike at the end of the trail
and hike back to the carpark.
I'll drive over in the truck and collect the
bike later.
After that, I'll drive to Goblin Valley, about
eighty kilometres north of here.
My friends are having a party there.
I hope I get some sleep because tomorrow I
want to hike the most popular trail in southern
Utah - Little White Horse.
I plan to spend the whole of Monday biking
along the White Rim Trail.
The trail forms a rough circle of 175 kilometres.
It's not difficult and I should be able to
finish in about eighteen hours.
By Monday evening, I'll be back in Aspen,
Colorado.
Aspen is famous for its mountains and the
countryside around it.
It's a popular place for skiing.
I live there and I work for Ute Mountaineer,
a sports equipment shop.
Leona, one of the people I live and work with,
is having a goodbye party on Monday night.
Now that winter is over, she's going to another
town in Colorado to work as a gardener for
the summer.
Her party will be a cool way to end my trip.
00 hrs
8.45 am I arrive at the Horseshoe Canyon carpark
early in the morning, pull my bike from the
truck and lock the door.
Then I check the time: eight forty-five in
the morning.
As I start cycling, I wonder how quickly I
can get to the start of the trail.
I can now see the sign pointing to this end
of the trail.
That means I've cycled thirteen kilometres
in less than two hours.
That's good.
It will give me more time to finish my hike
back to the truck.
I lock my bike to a tree and start walking.
As I walk, I think about the history of the
people who were here before me.
One of them, Butch Cassidy, was very famous.
He and his men stole horses and hid from the
law during the last years of the nineteenth
century.
Since that time, the area has been called
Robbers Roost country.
My climbing bag is heavy with the weight of
my equipment.
I think about my plan for the day.
Blue John Canyon will be the most difficult
part of the hike.
Three kilometres along the trail is the Big
Drop Rappel.
Here, the canyon suddenly drops eighteen metres.
The hardest part is 180 metres before this.
The walls there are very narrow and the trail
goes up and down, sharply.
There are also a lot of very large rocks called
boulders, stuck between the canyon walls.
If these boulders move or fall, they can be
dangerous.
But I'm not thinking of danger at the moment.
I am excited.
Today, I will finally see the Great Gallery.
The Gallery is part of Horseshoe Canyon, and
it's famous for the huge rock paintings which
cover its walls.
Some of them are more than five thousand years
old.
I should reach my truck by late afternoon.
So far, things are going well.
I arrived here earlier than I thought.
This gives me a little more time to finish
my trip.
I always get very excited when I'm about to
leave on a trip.
This means I sometimes forget things.
Before starting this trip, I forgot to leave
a message telling anyone exactly where I was
going.
This is one of the things my mother taught
me.
But this time, I just called a quick goodbye
to my housemates - Brian, Joe, and Leona.
Leona asked where I was going.
I told her I was going to Utah and promised
to be back for her party.
Then I got in my truck and drove away.
I can't wait for adventure.
It makes me feel happier than anything.
It's part of who I am.
I'm on a high rock, looking down at the trail.
I've stopped because I can hear voices.
This surprises me.
I had expected to be alone.
Two young women suddenly appear below me.
I feel pleased.
I've spent the last eighteen hours alone.
It will be good to have company for a while.
'Hi,' I call as I climb down the rock.
The girls hadn't noticed me.
They turn, looking a little nervous.
I guess they are about twenty-five years old.
I smile and hold out my hand, 'My name's Aron.'
They smile back.
'I'm Megan,' says the darker girl, 'and this
is Kristi.'
We shake hands and continue along the trail.
As we go, we talk about our interests.
We all love hiking, biking and adventures.
For all of us, this is more important than
earning a lot of money.
They work in the same business, too.
They work for Outward Bound, a sports equipment
shop in Moab, Utah.
Both Aspen and Moab are important tourist
centres for hikers.
We are on the trail together for about five
kilometres.
At that point, there is a smaller canyon to
the west.
The west canyon goes back in a half-circle.
The girls left their bikes at the end of it.
We will say goodbye there and I'll continue
on alone to the Big Drop Rappel.
We arrive just before 2.00 pm.
I don't feel like saying goodbye.
In the hour and a half we've been together,
we've already become friends.
Megan feels the same.
'Why don't you come with us?'
she asks.
'We can finish the west canyon trail, go back
to our truck and have a few beers.'
I like the idea, but following my plan is
more important.
I ask them to come with me.
'How far is it back to your truck?'
Megan asks.
'Around thirteen kilometres.'
'That's too far.
You won't get back before dark,' she says.
'Maybe not, but I really want to do the Big
Drop Rappel.
And I can't miss the paintings in the Great
Gallery.
I'll meet you after for a drink.'
We agree on a plan to meet and go to the party
together.
Then I turn and wave goodbye.
The movement is so easy I don't think about
it.
But there is something I don't know.
It is the last time I will wave goodbye with
my right hand.
CHAPTER TWO
The accident
The girls disappear into the west canyon.
I am alone again.
I continue walking towards the Big Drop Rappel.
It seems strangely quiet without Kristi and
Megan.
I turn on my CD player and listen to a soft,
slow song by Phish, one of my favourite bands.
The music is perfect for the way I feel: lucky,
free and happy.
The weather is perfect, too.
It's warm and sunny with just a few white
clouds in the sky.
Suddenly, my feet hit a pile of loose stones
and I nearly fall to the ground.
Careful, Aron.
I listen to the voice in my head and look
up the canyon.
I can see that the trail ahead becomes more
difficult.
The Big Drop Rappel is now just under a kilometre
away.
Twenty minutes later, I arrive at the most
difficult part of the trail.
Here, the canyon walls are a lot narrower.
The trail rises and falls and is full of sharp
rocks.
I will have to be careful.
I look up and see part of a tree stuck between
the canyon walls.
It was carried along the canyon after heavy
rain.
This is one of the dangers of hiking in canyon
country.
After a sudden storm, canyons can quickly
fill with water.
In seconds, the water can throw you against
the canyon walls and kill you.
That's why it's always very important to check
the weather before canyoning.
Just below the tree is the first drop in the
trail.
It's only about three metres, so I won't need
any equipment.
There are plenty of holes in the rock for
my hands and feet so I climb down easily.
A metre from the bottom I let go and land
on the ground.
Soft sand covers the tops of my boots.
From here, it would be difficult to climb
back up.
One thing is immediately clear: I can't go
back.
The canyon walls become even narrower.
Stuck between them, as far as I can see, are
boulders of different sizes.
It's an unusual sight.
I stop and take a few pictures with my camera.
The Big Drop Rappel is now only about 160
metres away.
Climbing down will be no problem.
I have all the equipment I need in my backpack.
For food, I have two burritos.
I also have a full water bottle and an extra
two litres in a CamelBak.
The boulders are both good and bad news.
The good news is that I should be able to
climb over many of them.
This will be quicker than dropping on to the
trail and climbing back up again.
The bad news is that the boulders could move.
I will have to be careful.
I manage the first few boulders without any
problems and reach another drop.
This one is about four metres down.
About three metres from the edge of the drop
is a boulder.
It's about the same size as the wheel of a
bus.
If I climb onto it, the drop from there will
be shorter.
I chimney to the boulder quite easily.
As I stand on it, I feel something move.
The movement stops almost immediately.
It seems there's nothing to worry about.
I lie down, put my hands in two holes on the
far edge of the boulder and push my legs over
the opposite side to jump down.
As most of my weight pushes on one side of
the boulder, it makes a strange sound.
Immediately I know this is trouble but it's
too late to go back.
From this point, everything seems to happen
very slowly.
I let go of the boulder and drop towards the
ground.
As I fall, I look up and see the boulder crashing
towards my head.
If I don't get out of the way, I'm dead.
I try to push against the boulder with both
hands.
It hits my left hand hard against the canyon
wall.
I pull it back with a scream of pain.
The boulder then hits my right arm and traps
my hand against the right side of the canyon.
6 hrs
2.45 pm All this happens in a couple of seconds.
I don't even notice landing on the canyon
floor.
I am so shocked I feel no pain.
I just stand there, looking at my trapped
hand in disbelief.
Stupid, Aron, stupid!
When you first stood on the rock, it moved.
That was a clear message to stay away!
But you were in such a hurry to finish the
hike you didn't stop and check.
The voice in my head doesn't help.
It just makes things worse.
A terrible pain travels up my arm.
I scream and pull hard to try and free myself.
Nothing happens.
I try again.
This time I push against the boulder with
my knees at the same time.
It's no good.
The boulder is a lot heavier than I am.
I am stuck and there's no way out.
CHAPTER THREE
Three plans
Stop thinking about how bad the problem is,
Aron.
You need to be sensible.
The voice in my head is right.
I must be sensible.
This has to be my rule from now on.
The first thing I need is a drink.
Without stopping to think, I take the water
bottle from my bag and drink a third of it
in five seconds.
I suddenly realise what I'm doing and pull
the bottle out of my mouth.
Already, I have broken my rule to be sensible.
I have no idea how long I will be here.
This means that the most important thing of
all is to save water.
Damn it, Aron!
Stupid!
6 hrs 43 mins
3.28 pm It's almost forty-five minutes since
my accident.
I am calmer than before.
For the last half hour, I've been thinking
of my best chance of escape.
I said I would meet Kristi and Megan after
the hike.
If I don't appear, will they go to my truck
to find me?
I won't be there.
But will they realise that something is wrong
and go for help?
The answer is probably 'no'.
Kristi and Megan don't know me very well.
They'll just think that I decided not to meet
them.
What about other hikers?
Will they find me by chance?
Again, the answer is probably 'no'.
Very few people travel to the Great Gallery
from this end of the trail.
My friends won't worry, either.
They weren't completely sure I was going to
the party.
Even on Monday evening, my housemates will
just think I'm late getting back.
No one will miss me until Tuesday morning.
When I don't arrive for work, Brion After,
my boss, will know that something is wrong.
I am never late for work.
He will probably call my family and they will
tell the police that I am missing.
But I didn't tell anyone exactly where I was
going, so it will take the police days to
find me.
If I don't escape before then, I will die.
All of this means that I will have to get
out of here alone.
But how?
I can think of three possible plans.
The first plan is to use the large knife on
the multi-tool to chip at the boulder.
This might take away enough of the rock to
free my hand.
The second plan is to try and lift the boulder
using some of my equipment.
The third plan is the worst.
I could amputate my arm using the multi-tool.
It's too soon to think of that idea.
I try plan one.
I take the multi-tool from my climbing bag.
It has two knives.
One is longer than the other.
I use the longest one, which is not so sharp.
To free my hand, I must remove a piece of
rock over fifteen centimetres wide and seven
centimetres deep.
That's a lot of rock.
10 hrs 15 mins
7.0 pm I've been chipping at the rock for
almost three and a half hours.
I stop for a drink of water.
I lay the multi-tool on the boulder and reach
for the water bottle.
This time I am more careful and take only
a sip.
I wonder how long I'll be able to survive
with the water I have left, only two-thirds
of a litre.
Until Monday night, maybe?
Tuesday morning at the latest.
CHAPTER FOUR
Night and day
After Kristi and Megan left Aron, they got
lost in the west canyon and arrived late at
the meeting place.
He wasn't there.
'He's probably left already,' said Megan,
'but he can't be far away.
Let's drive around and see if we can find
him.'
But there was no sign of Aron or his bike.
'It doesn't really matter,' said Megan.
'We'll see him at the party.'
Again, she was wrong.
By the time they reached Goblin Valley, the
car park was full and there was nowhere to
stay for the night.
The girls now felt very tired and decided
not to go to the party.
'We'll drive to Little Wild Horse Canyon tomorrow
morning,' said Megan.
'We'll probably find Aron there.'
Kristi agreed and they parked by the side
of the road for the night.
The next morning, there was no sign of Aron
at Little Wild Horse Canyon.
All they found was a truck from Colorado with
a bike inside and skis on the roof.
'That's probably Aron's truck,' said Megan.
'He must be in the canyon already.
We've missed him again.'
She wrote their email addresses on a piece
of paper and left it on the truck window.
'Why didn't we just get his phone number?'
Megan asked as they drove back to Moab.
15 hrs 15 mins
12.00 am My headlamp is on and I'm chipping
at the boulder.
I've managed to chip a space above and below
an area of pink rock.
Perhaps I can remove this large piece before
I stop for the night.
I will need to hit it hard.
I don't want to break the knife, so I use
a different part of the multi-tool.
I hit the boulder as hard as I can and the
piece of rock falls onto my trapped arm.
I can now see some softer rock below.
I chip at the rock for another hour and remove
as much as the piece that came off before.
More success, but my left arm hurts and I
have to stop.
I take a sip of water.
I have decided to do this every ninety minutes.
I look up at the sky.
It's a clear night and it's very cold.
Now that I've stopped chipping I feel cold.
The wind is the worst.
Every few minutes, it blows down the canyon
and makes my body shake.
I decide to use my climbing bag as a jacket
to keep warm.
I lay everything inside it on top of the boulder.
Then I put the bag back on.
I'm a little warmer but I need something soft
to put my legs on.
I take my rope, form it into a circle, and
lay it on a rock below me.
Now I can rest my knees instead of standing
up all the time.
After a while, I begin to feel uncomfortable
again.
The problem is the weight on my legs.
I decide to try and build some kind of seat.
I put on my harness and rope.
Then I tie carabiners to one end of the rope
and make a kind of ball.
The idea is to throw the rope over one of
the boulders above my head.
If I do it right, the ball will stick in the
space between the boulder and the canyon wall.
It takes twenty-five throws before it lands
in the right place.
Now, will it hold my weight?
I sit in the harness.
It holds.
Success!
I feel very happy.
But I'm not comfortable for long.
I soon need to move again.
I stand and chip for twenty minutes, then
sit and rest for twenty minutes.
This becomes my routine.
As morning comes, I'm not feeling too unhappy.
This first night was not as bad as I thought.
I've done quite well, but one thought still
worries me: I haven't chipped much rock from
the boulder.
At this speed, it will take me 150 hours to
free my trapped arm.
Chipping is not enough.
I will have to think of something else.
CHAPTER FIVE
A sad message
23 hrs 30 mins
8.15 am I am feeling optimistic.
The sun is shining into the canyon and a raven
has just flown across the blue sky above my
head.
The sight and sound of the bird fills me with
hope.
I hold my leg in the sunlight.
It feels warm against my skin.
But I need to do something.
It's time for plan two.
I will use my ropes, webbing and carabiners
to try and lift the boulder and free my hand.
I look up.
There's a sharp piece of rock above my head.
If I can throw the rope around this, it might
hold everything in the right position.
After many tries, I finally succeed.
I tie the other end of the rope around the
boulder.
But when I pull, nothing happens.
Everything holds, but the boulder doesn't
move.
I put more weight on the rope, but it still
doesn't work.
The rope is not tight enough.
28 hrs 15 mins
1.00 pm I've spent four hours trying to lift
the boulder, but nothing has worked.
Suddenly, I hear voices.
'Help!
Help!'
I shout.
I stop and listen.
At first, there's nothing.
But then I hear a sound from above and realise
my mistake.
It's just a small animal moving in the rock.
I'd imagined it was people.
The sound of my voice shouting for help frightened
me.
It made me feel lost and alone.
I make a promise that I won't do it again.
The optimistic feelings of earlier in the
day have disappeared.
No one is going to save me.
That leaves only the third, and worst, plan:
I will have to amputate my right arm.
What will I need for the job?
The knife, that's certain, but also a tourniquet
to stop the blood.
The plastic pipe from the CamelBak seems best
for that.
I take it off and use a carabiner to make
it tight.
It works well and I feel a bit better.
As soon as I put the knife against the skin
of my arm, I feel ill.
I can't do it.
It would be like killing myself.
I drop the knife and lay my head on the boulder.
None of my plans have worked.
I can't free my hand.
I can't lift the boulder.
I can't amputate my arm.
My only hope is rescue, but I'll die before
help arrives.
I feel angry with the boulder, but it's not
the boulder's fault - it's mine.
Everything about this stupid adventure was
a mistake.
I didn't tell anyone where I was going, I
didn't go with Kristi and Megan to the west
canyon, and I didn't get off the boulder when
it moved.
30 hrs
2.45 pm It's exactly twenty-four hours since
the accident.
I decide it's time to film a message for my
family and friends.
I place my camcorder on the boulder, turn
it on and start speaking.
'My name is Aron Ralston.
It's just after three o'clock on Sunday, April
the 27th, 2003.
I have been trapped in Blue John Canyon for
the last twenty-four hours.
My parents are Donna and Larry Ralston of
Eaglewood, Colorado.
If anyone finds this, please give it to them.
Thank you.'
I describe all that has happened in the last
two days.
As I reach the end of my story, I feel very
sad.
I know this could be a final goodbye to my
parents and sister, Sonja.
After telling them how much I love them, there
is only one more thing to say.
'Mum, Dad, Sonja - I'm sorry.'
I turn off the machine.
All I can do now is wait for someone to find
me.
CHAPTER SIX
Waiting
33 hrs 15 mins
6.00 pm My second night in the canyon is moving
closer.
Beyond that, I see no future.
Escape has been impossible and I will die
before anyone finds me.
I feel strong enough to survive the fear of
death, but not my body's need for water.
This terrible, growing thirst will drive me
crazy.
I now have only a quarter of a litre of water
left.
I have to make this last as long as possible.
I drank at 3.15 pm, just after I finished
filming.
Then I missed the next drink and decided to
save it for later.
I'll drink at nine, midnight, three and six
in the morning, but I'll take even smaller
sips.
The mosquitoes have found me.
There are several at my feet and some drinking
the blood on the canyon wall.
I kill five or six as they circle around my
head.
Can I eat them, I wonder?
Even if I could, it wouldn't be enough to
keep me alive.
I go back to waiting.
It seems colder than the night before.
I start chipping at the boulder just to keep
warm.
36 hrs 15 mins
9.00 pm Night has fallen.
The mosquitoes have gone.
The sky above is beautiful: clear with bright
stars.
But clear skies mean lower temperatures.
I must do something to cover more of my body.
I tie the camera bag around my left arm.
Then I tie webbing around my right arm and
put rope around each of my legs.
I do the same for my right arm, using webbing.
I put rope round each leg.
It looks funny and I can't help smiling.
I begin my routine of standing and sitting.
Most of my body feels warmer, but I'm still
shaking because my head and neck are cold.
I decide to put the plastic rope bag over
my head.
I keep the far end open to let fresh air in.
I lay my head against the boulder.
I still can't sleep but at least I'm warmer.
The long, boring hours of the night pass slowly
by.
Finally, the sky grows lighter.
Today, it's a dirty white colour.
I wonder if this is cloud.
Clouds at night are good because they trap
the day's heat in the canyon, but clouds during
the day are bad because the sun doesn't warm
the air.
There's also the chance of a storm.
Slowly the pale sky turns bright blue.
It's going to be hot again.
As always, the light and warm air make me
want to do something.
I try and lift the boulder again by pushing
down on the rope with my feet.
This doesn't work either and I feel suddenly
hopeless.
What more can I do?
No voice inside my head suggests anything
useful.
All I see in my mind are pictures of the food
and drink left on the floor of my truck.
I think again about amputating my arm.
I didn't try hard enough the last time.
I need to be brave and try again.
I put on the tourniquet and make it tight.
When everything is ready, I try to cut through
the skin of my arm with the longer knife.
I push hard but the skin doesn't break.
Then, over the same area, I use the shorter,
sharper knife.
But even that doesn't work.
It's still not sharp enough to do the job.
All I have for the time I've spent on this
is a long red line across my right arm.
I take off the tourniquet and go back to waiting.
47 hrs 30 mins
8.15 am The raven appears.
I check my watch.
It has arrived at exactly the same time as
yesterday.
For the first time in two days, I need to
urinate.
I open my shorts and watch the yellow urine
disappear into the sand.
I spend most of the day chipping, resting,
and counting the minutes before my next drink
of water.
54 hrs
2.45 pm It's the middle of the afternoon and
time to film again.
Filming has now become a part of my daily
routine.
I turn on the camcorder.
'Hi, everyone.
It's Monday, April the 28th.
I'm still trapped.
I've been here for exactly forty-eight hours.
That's two whole days with no sleep and very
little water.
I now have only about one-eighth of a litre
left.'
I continue with a message to my sister, Sonja.
She is getting married in the autumn.
I tell her how proud I am of her and send
her my love and best wishes.
I finish filming at 3.35 pm.
It's strange but I feel the need to urinate
again.
This time, my second voice tells me not to
urinate on the ground.
Save it, Aron.
It will soon be all you have to drink.
It's good advice.
I urinate into the CamelBak.
The urine is now a dark orange colour.
The other urine was clearer.
Why didn't I save it?
57 hrs 15 mins
6.00 pm It's early evening.
Sunlight shines off the bottom of thin clouds
high above me.
I hope they will stay and keep the heat in
the canyon.
But as time passes, it seems to grow colder.
My water won't last much longer.
Soon, I will have to start drinking urine.
Like the raven, the mosquitoes seem to arrive
on time.
I kill a few more.
Mosquitoes mean there must be water quite
close - probably at the Big Drop Rappel.
Forget it, Aron.
You'll never see water again.
The first voice is back.
I try not to listen.
CHAPTER SEVEN
'Where's Aron?'
Back in Aspen, Aron's housemates were preparing
for the party.
Elliot, another friend of his, was moving
into the house after Leona had gone.
At eight-thirty, he asked, 'Has anyone seen
Aron?'
'No,' said Brian.
'He's probably still on his trip.'
'Does he know about the party?'
Elliot asked.
'Of course,' said Leona.
'He said he'd be here for sure.
He'd better come.
It's my goodbye party.
I'll be upset if he doesn't come.'
The party ended at around two o'clock the
next morning, but there was still no sign
of Aron.
The first person to think something might
be wrong was Aron's boss, Brion.
Early Tuesday morning, he called the house
and spoke to Leona.
'He didn't come to the party last night,'
Leona told him.
'I thought he'd driven straight to work.'
'No, he's not here, and Aron's never late.
I think something might be wrong.
Could you call me right away if he gets back?'
'Yes, sure,' said Leona, feeling a little
worried.
She called Brion later that afternoon to ask
if Aron had arrived.
'No,' said Brion.
'Did he say where he was going?'
'He didn't say much to any of us.
Only that he was going climbing and biking.
He also said he might hike in Utah.
Somewhere in Canyonlands.
He didn't say where, exactly.'
'Mmm, that's a big area,' said Brion.
'I'll wait until nine o'clock tomorrow morning.
If he's not back by then, I'll call his parents.'
Aron's housemates decided not to wait any
longer.
At six-thirty that evening, they called the
police.
The officer on the desk asked for Aron's information:
full name, age, height and weight.
He also wanted to know the model of his truck
and the license-plate number.
But there was something the officer didn't
tell them: a person has to be missing for
at least forty-eight hours before the police
will start a search and rescue operation.
This meant that they wouldn't do anything
until late the following day.
63 Mrs 15 mins
12.00 am It's my third night here and I've
decided to take my first sip of urine.
There's still half a cup of water left, but
I want to save it.
The urine tastes bad, but not quite as bad
as I thought.
I decide not to drink any more until the water
is finished.
I've changed my drinking routine because the
night is colder.
I can now only sit for a few minutes so I
take smaller sips every hour.
66 hrs 15 mins
3.00 am It's now sixty hours since my accident.
That's sixty hours of pain, no sleep, and
very little water.
Two hours later, it's time for my next sip
of water.
I put the bottle between my legs and turn
the top.
When it's open, I try and lift it towards
my mouth.
But it hits my harness and falls back onto
my legs.
I am too tired to catch it.
Some of the valuable water falls onto my shorts.
'Damn!
Damn!
Damn!'
I shout.
Now look what you've done!
Says the first voice.
I know exactly what I've done.
I've just lost half of the rest of my life.
70 hrs
6.45 am As morning arrives once more, I feel
a little hope.
At least I've survived another night.
It's now Tuesday, April the 29th: my fourth
day trapped in the canyon.
I decide to film earlier today.
I put the camcorder on the boulder, then turn
the screen the other way.
I don't want to look at myself as I speak.
'Hi.
It's Tuesday morning.
I guess everyone missed me when I didn't arrive
for Leona's party last night.
Most people will probably think I'm still
travelling.
Except for Brion.
When I don't arrive for work, he'll think
something is wrong.
He might call the police and report me missing.
They'll wait forty-eight hours before searching.
If I'm lucky, they'll start some time on Wednesday.
If I'm very lucky, they might search the Robbers
Roost area first.
Even then, the earliest they'll reach me is
Thursday.
I'll try to stay alive as long as I can, but
I can't imagine living longer than one more
day.
This means help will arrive too late.
By Thursday, I'll be dead.
And this video will be history.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
The raven
70 hrs 45 mins
7.30 am That last video recording was the
most pessimistic so far.
It's strange, but the feeling of hopelessness
doesn't last.
As the sky grows brighter, I think of the
raven.
The bird is a sign of hope.
Just thinking about it makes me want to do
something.
I try lifting the boulder once more.
I make the rope even shorter, but when I step
on it, nothing happens.
I do everything I can to make it work.
I push, jump and shout as I put all my weight
onto the rope.
It's still no good.
The boulder doesn't move a millimetre.
I step down and lay my head on the boulder.
I feel like crying but I can't.
There's not enough water in my body to produce
any tears.
But there's still the knife.
It's lying open on top of the boulder.
Suddenly, I know what I'm going to do.
Quickly, I put the tourniquet around my arm
and tighten it.
Then I pick up the multi-tool, open the shorter
knife and push it hard into my arm.
This time, the knife goes all the way in.
I pull out the knife and look at the deep
hole I've made in my right arm.
I can't believe I've done this.
It didn't even hurt and there's very little
blood.
I can see the bones in my arm through the
hole.
I will never be able to cut through them with
only a small knife.
It's time for a drink.
I pick up the bottle and feel the last of
the water disappear down my throat.
I check the time.
It's exactly 8.00 am and all I have to drink
now is urine.
71 hrs 45 mins
8.30 am The raven appears.
It's fifteen minutes late but I'm happy.
I was beginning to think it wouldn't come.
I feel happy and start thinking of all the
wonderful times I've spent with friends and
family.
I remember a trip to Washington D.C. with
my sister, and another to Gettysburg with
my dad.
I also think of all the adventures I've had
with different friends.
The time passes quickly Midday arrives without
me realising.
I urinate into the CamelBak.
Then I pour the clearer half of the urine
into my water bottle.
I throw the rest away.
I have no idea how long anyone can survive
on urine alone.
At least drinking it wasn't as bad as I expected.
It is now the warmest part of the day.
This is the time I am most comfortable.
I have found the best way to sit and feel
calmer in the warm air.
Perhaps help will arrive in time.
If so, I will soon be as free as the raven.
Three hours later, I have reached the end
of my third day trapped in the canyon.
None of my plans of escape have worked.
All I can do is stay strong for another night
and hope for rescue.
I eat the last burrito.
It is too dry to get down my throat so I take
a mouthful of urine.
The urine tastes better at night because it's
colder, but it's still going to be a long,
hard night.
On Wednesday morning, Brion After was at work
in the shop.
At nine-fifteen, he called Leona to check
if he had arrived, but he hadn't.
Brion had waited long enough.
He picked up the phone.
Aron's mother answered on the first ring.
'Mrs Ralston?'
'Yes?'
'This is Brion After - Aron's boss at Ute
Mountaineer.
I'm afraid I'm rather worried about him.
He hasn't returned from a trip he took last
week.
Do you know where he went?
No one here has seen him since last Wednesday.'
'Oh dear,' said Aron's mother.
'I have no idea where he is.
I called him last week and left a message,
but he didn't call back.
Did he tell any of his housemates where he
was going?'
'No, just that he might hike somewhere in
the Canyonlands area of Utah,' explained Brion
'I think you should call the Aspen police.'
'Yes, I'll do that right now.
I'll let you know what happens.'
'Thank you, Brion.'
Mrs Ralston's hand was shaking as she put
down the phone.
She suddenly had an idea.
Perhaps Aron had sent an email to one of his
friends saying where he was going?
She went to the computer.
Aron had an email address - but what was it?
She found his name, but had to answer a secret
question to read his emails.
None of the answers she gave worked but she
kept trying.
In the end, she guessed the correct answer
and sent the information to Brion.
After Brion had called the Aspen police, the
head officer, Adam Crider, started the rescue
operation.
He called Mrs Ralston for the license-plate
number of her son's truck.
Mrs Ralston had written it down on a piece
of paper.
When she read it to Officer Crider, she didn't
realise it was wrong.
Aron had given it to her in a hurry and made
a mistake.
Officer Crider called back and told Mrs Ralston
there was no record of that license plate.
This left her with another problem.
How could she find the correct license-plate
number?
Brion After was having better luck.
He had found a list of email addresses for
Aron's climbing friends.
Perhaps they knew where he was.
He wanted to check immediately, but he had
to leave for Australia that day.
He called Aron's housemate Elliot and asked
him to manage the store and rescue operation
until he returned.
Elliot agreed.
When Elliot reached the store, he received
a call from Mrs Ralston.
She wanted to check the license-plate number
she had given Brion.
It was on his desk.
Elliot checked as she read out the number.
'Wait.
Did you say 886, Mrs Ralston?'
'Yes.'
'Brion made a mistake.
He wrote down 888.
I'll call Officer Crider and give him the
correct number.'
By early afternoon, Elliot had received an
email from Steve Pratchett, the most important
of Aron's climbing friends.
Steve had climbed for many years.
He often led rescue operations to find climbers
lost in the mountains.
Another friend, Jason, had sent Steve a list
of all the canyons Aron said he wanted to
hike in Canyonlands.
Steve called the Utah police for the area
and spoke to one the main officers, Kyle Ekker.
Officer Ekker was very helpful.
Steve gave him the latest license-plate number
for Aron's truck and Officer Ekker sent his
men out to look for it.
They returned as night fell.
There was no sign of the truck.
Officer Ekker checked the number with the
national license office.
There was no vehicle on record.
Once again, the number was wrong.
The bad news reached Aron's mother.
Then she remembered that Aron was living in
Albuquerque, New Mexico, when he bought the
truck.
The vehicle license office for the area was
in Santa Fe.
She called and an officer searched the records
and found Aron's name.
The records showed his license-plate number
as NM 846-MMY.
Finally, they had the correct number.
The information was given to Officer Ekker.
It was too late to continue searching that
night.
It would have to wait until the morning.
'Wait for us, Aron,' Mrs Ralston said as she
went to bed.
'We're coming.'
89 hrs 15 mins
2.00 am The darkness seems unreal.
In fact, I don't know what is real and what
isn't anymore.
I start to have visions.
Friends suddenly appear in the canyon like
silent ghosts and wave me towards them.
I follow and find myself in some place I know
from the past.
They smile at me in a kind way, but they never
speak.
Because of their kindness, I am not afraid.
I know they are protecting me.
I am happy while the visions last.
To me, they are real.
It is only when they disappear and the cold
and pain return that I know they are not.
Then, shaking hard, I continue chipping at
the boulder.
After that, I sit again and it's not long
before the visions return.
During the second half of the night, I have
visions of myself as a child.
Sometimes I'm playing cards with my grandfather.
Other times I am running across bright green
fields with my friends.
Something about the visions tells me that
I have not given the people I care about enough
attention.
I'm always thinking of the things I want to
achieve and not noticing other people.
Now I realise that my love for friends and
family is the main reason I want to escape.
The thought of seeing them again is keeping
me alive.
I promise myself that if I can escape from
here back to the people, I will be kinder
towards them.
The visions always include some kind of drink.
It is usually something cold and sweet like
apple juice or ice tea.
Just as I am about to drink, the vision disappears
and I wake up.
Then I feel the cold and the pain of the rope
against my legs.
I stand up and begin my routine all over again.
However, the visions tell me something: I
am not ready to die.
As morning comes on the fifth day, I feel
sure I can still last a few more days.
I don't know if this is true, but I'm still
alive when the sun rises.
The raven appears on time.
The sound of its wings and the light in the
canyon are beautiful.
I watch its smooth flight, following the line
of the canyon.
I take out my camera and film as it disappears
from view.
CHAPTER NINE
'It's his truck'
97 hrs 45 mins
10.30 am I don't want to look at my watch.
When I did this last night, the time seemed
to pass more slowly.
I have a new idea.
It came to me, as I was looking at all the
rocks around me.
Why not find a hard rock and use it to break
the boulder?
There's one in a hole in the canyon wall above
me.
It is round and black.
I reach up and pull it out.
It's perfect - just the right size and weight.
I hit the rock hard against the boulder.
Little bits of stone fly into the air.
It's working.
I continue, but soon have to stop because
of the pain in my left hand.
I decide to rest for a while.
Early afternoon is usually the warmest time
of day.
But today it's only thirteen degrees, the
coldest day so far.
It also means that tonight will be the coldest
night.
Realising this makes me want to do something
while it's still light.
The problem with using the black rock was
that it hurt my left hand.
But what if I tie a sock around my hand to
protect it?
I do this and it works.
By 6.00 pm, I have taken off more of the boulder
in three hours than I did in four days.
But it's still not enough.
And even with the sock there is too much pain
in my left hand to continue.
I put down the rock.
I feel sure I won't survive another night
in the canyon.
I finally accept this.
There is nothing else I can do to save myself.
110 hrs 15 mins
11.00 pm The canyon feels as cold as ice.
I have been awake for over a hundred hours.
Another night of the sitting - standing routine
will kill me.
I haven't had any clean water since eight
o'clock yesterday morning, only urine.
How much longer can I survive?
Death could come at any moment.
I am so certain of this that I take the knife
and write the dates of my life on the canyon
wall.
When I have finished I read them by the light
of my headlamp: ARON OCT 75 - APR 03.
Around midnight, I have another vision.
I am walking alone through the canyon wall.
On the other side is a living room.
I step inside and look around.
A little boy in a red shirt comes into the
room.
I guess he must be about three.
Suddenly, I know who he is.
He is my future son and the room is in my
future home.
The little boy runs across the wooden floor,
laughing.
I pick him up with my left arm.
My right arm has no hand.
Then I put him onto my shoulder and he laughs
even more.
He holds my arms in his little hands and together
we dance around the room.
The sun is shining and I feel free, happy,
and alive.
The vision disappears.
I am back in the canyon again, but now I don't
feel the same as before.
Seeing the boy has changed everything.
Now, even with the cold, pain, tiredness and
thirst, I am sure I will survive.
On Thursday, May the 1st, Kyle Ekker was looking
at a map of the Canyonlands area on his office
wall.
The clock above read 9.07 am.
Already that morning, his men had searched
the top and centre of the area and found nothing.
What about the Robbers Roost canyons in the
south?
The only roads down there were made of rocks
and sand.
It might take longer to search.
He called Glen Sherrill, the head officer
for the area.
When Glen answered the phone, Kyle described
Aron's truck.
'It's a red Toyota.
License number NM 846-MMY.'
'I think I've seen a truck like that,' Glen
replied.
'I'll radio one of my men and ask them to
check.'
Kyle thanked him and put down the phone.
Twenty minutes later, Glen called back.
'Officer Kyle?'
'Speaking.'
'Glen Sherrill here.
We've found the truck you're looking for.
It's in the Horseshoe Canyon carpark.'
By 10.00 am, the good news had reached Elliot,
Steve, and Mrs Ralston.
Steve immediately arranged for a rescue team
to join the police and help in the search.
Half an hour later, they were on their way.
Things were now moving fast.
CHAPTER TEN
Escape
120 hrs
8.45 am It's Thursday, May the 1st.
120 hours without sleep.
Two days without water.
I can't believe I'm still alive.
I didn't think I'd survive beyond Wednesday.
Perhaps the vision of the little boy kept
me alive last night.
But now, with no sign of a rescue, my hopes
are disappearing fast.
I am also upset because the raven hasn't appeared.
It's never been this late before.
I try and forget about the bird and pick up
the camcorder.
I am certain that this will be my last message
to my family.
I am calm as I leave necessary instructions
for my parents.
I tell them to give most of my things to Sonja.
Then I tell them what to do with my dead body.
The video ends with three simple words: 'I
love you.'
I'm crying as I close the camcorder for the
last time.
But there are no tears - my body is too dry
for tears.
Now I can only wait.
I can't accept this.
I've discovered that nothing I can do will
help me escape.
But it's better to be doing something than
nothing.
I pick up the black rock and hit it as hard
as I can against the boulder.
I continue, trying to forget the pain in my
left hand.
In the end, I can't.
I try to drop the rock, but the fingers of
my hand won't open.
What have you done now? asks the first voice.
Stay calm, says the second.
Slowly, my fingers loosen and the stone falls
out of my hand.
I look at my other arm.
It's covered with bits of rock.
As I'm removing these with the knife I push
too hard and the blade goes through the skin
near my wrist.
I don't feel anything.
That part of my arm must be dead.
My right hand died long ago.
It's now a dark blue colour.
I push the knife through the skin of my thumb.
There's a sound as some gas escapes, followed
by a bad smell.
The arm is poisoned and the poison will kill
me.
I don't want the arm to be a part of me anymore.
I throw myself against the boulder.
When I look at my arm, I see that it's in
a strange position.
That moment is like the sun coming out.
I realise what it means.
I can break my arm by using my own weight.
That means I won't have to cut through bone
anymore.
I throw the whole weight of my body below
the boulder.
There is a loud noise.
I keep going.
There is a second loud noise.
I've done it!
I've broken both bones in my arm.
I tie the tourniquet, take the knife and begin
cutting.
The only thing on my mind is escape, but the
pain is terrible.
I scream as I push down with the knife.
For almost one hour the pain, screams, and
cutting continue.
122 hrs 47 mins
11.32 am Finally, I feel the knife hit rock
on the other side of my arm.
I fall back with a single thought screaming
through my head.
You've done it, Aron!
You're FREE!
FREE!
There's no time to lose.
Blood is coming out of the end of my arm and
it's a long walk back to my truck.
I tighten the tourniquet.
Then I tie my climbing bag on my arm to hold
it.
I tighten it around my neck and put my things
inside.
Before I leave, I take two pictures of the
part of my arm still trapped by the boulder.
Now I am ready to go.
I can't walk straight.
My body crashes from one side of the canyon
wall to the other.
I stop.
My heart is going much too fast.
I could still die at any moment.
I make myself stay calm.
What I need most of all is water.
There might be some at the Big Drop Rappel,
but first I need to get there.
It takes me twenty minutes.
I stand at the edge and look down.
It is just over eighteen metres to the canyon
floor.
There are metal rings in the rock for climbers.
I tie my rope to them and rappel down.
With only one arm, this is not easy.
For once, I am careful as I go down the rope.
I reach the bottom and turn.
On the ground in front of me is a pool of
brown water.
It's full of dead mosquitoes but I don't care.
I fill my bottle and drink one litre in a
few seconds.
I drink another and don't want to move.
I just want to stay there for the rest of
my life.
That won't be long if you don't start walking.
There are still twelve kilometres to go.
The voice is right.
I drink one more litre, slowly this time.
Then I fill my bottle and the CamelBak and
begin walking.
Blood is coming out faster from my arm now.
I wonder if I can get back to the truck in
time.
Things start to go wrong.
I get lost up a side canyon and have to turn
round.
Then I notice that water is coming out of
my CamelBak.
There's a hole in it.
Quickly, I drink the rest of the water.
Now I only have the water in the water bottle.
This has to last all the way back to the truck
and the temperature is rising.
I am so weak and tired I can't imagine surviving
that long.
I take a sip and keep the water in my mouth
as I walk.
That seems to help.
I still wonder if I can get back to my truck.
I can't walk straight, I can't think for more
than a few seconds, and I'm losing blood,
fast.
125 hrs 10 mins
1.55 pm I've arrived at the Great Gallery.
The paintings are amazing but all I can think
of is water.
There is more here.
I stop to fill the water bottle.
It has taken me two and a half hours to travel
six kilometres.
For someone close to death I have done well.
But my problems are getting worse every minute.
Blood is now coming from my arm really fast
and I'm in terrible pain from the amputation.
I want to stop and rest, but I can't.
I must go on.
I walk as fast as I can.
By two-thirty, I have covered nearly ten kilometres.
Only three more kilometres to my truck, but
I'm feeling weaker every minute.
125 hrs 45 mins
2.30 pm I've come to another huge canyon.
The walls must be over thirty metres high.
Ahead of me is a steep hill.
This is bad news.
I'll never be able to climb it - I'm too weak.
Something makes me look again.
I shake my head, unable to believe what I
see.
About seventy metres ahead of me are a family
of three people - a man, a woman and a young
boy.
They are walking away from me.
'HELP!
HELP!
PLEASE!
I NEED HELP!'
They turn and come running towards me.
When they reach me, I begin telling my story:
'My name is Aron Ralston.
I was trapped by a boulder in the canyon for
five days.
This morning, I had to amputate my arm to
escape.
I need a doctor.
I'm losing blood, fast...'
Unable to continue, I fall to the ground.
The man gives me a bottle of water.
'The police at the carpark told us about you,'
he says.
His name is Eric.
His wife is Monique and his son is called
Andy.
They are tourists from the Netherlands.
Eric gives me more water while Monique and
Andy run back to get the police.
After about ten minutes, Eric helps me up
and we continue walking slowly.
The steep trail is ahead.
Even with Eric's help, I know I won't be able
to climb it.
'How will I ever get out of here?'
I ask myself.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
127 hours
126 hrs 18 mins
3.03 pm A noise somewhere above me answers
the question.
It's a helicopter!
A helicopter to take me to hospital.
I can't believe it!
It doesn't seem real.
I sit down and wait as a man jumps to the
ground and walks towards me.
'Are you Aron Ralston?'
he asks.
'Yes.'
A second man gets out of the helicopter and
they help me inside.
I ask one of the men to get my climbing bag.
Eric gives it to him.
'Thank you, Eric,' I say.
'Thanks for everything.'
I wave goodbye as the helicopter rises into
the air.
I sit behind the pilot and watch blood pour
slowly down my arm.
Be strong, Aron.
You're almost safe.
'Keep him talking,' the pilot says to his
partner.
'Where are we going?'
I ask the second man.
'We're taking you to the hospital in Moab,'
he replies.
'How long will that take?'
'It's about twelve minutes from here.'
He asks me what happened in the canyon and
I begin telling my story.
By the time I finish, we are circling around
Moab.
I look down and see an area of green grass
below.
This gets bigger as we move down towards it.
I realise we are landing in front of the hospital.
A man who looks like a policeman is standing
with two nurses in white coats on the hospital
steps.
The helicopter lands and the nurses carry
me into the building.
They put me in an empty room.
The man walks in and introduces himself.
'Hi, Aron.
I'm Steve, and I'm a Park Ranger.'
As the nurses take off my shoes, I ask Steve
to let my mother know that I'm OK and to arrange
for someone to collect all the things I left
at Horseshoe Canyon.
'I'll do that when we've finished here,' Steve
replies.
He wants to know what happened in the canyon.
Once again, I tell my story.
It's the third time I've done this in two
hours.
When I finish, I can see that Steve wants
to ask me a lot of questions.
He doesn't get the chance.
A doctor comes back into the room with a large
needle.
'Wait!'
I say as she goes to put it into my skin.
'I have a problem with needles.
I sometimes go into shock.
I fell out of a chair once.'
The doctor looks surprised.
'You mean you're not in shock already?'
'I don't know,' I reply.
'Look, do you want this for the pain or not?'
'Damn it, yes!'
I say.
I continue talking to Steve as the needle
goes into my arm.
127 hrs
3.45 pm I suddenly hear another man's voice.
He sounds like a doctor.
He pulls at the things over my right arm and
asks Steve what they are.
'There are a couple of tourniquets under there,'
Steve replies.
'No, just one,' I whisper.
I look at the clock on the wall.
It's 3.45 pm on Thursday, May the 1st.
I realise that my nightmare has lasted for
exactly 127 hours.
It's my last thought before falling into a
long, deep sleep.
EPILOGUE
My rescue was only the first part of a long,
difficult fight back to health.
In that first month, I had five operations.
I was also taking eighteen different medicines
a day.
Most were for the pain and to fight the poison
in my blood.
While I was taking them, I couldn't do anything
well.
I couldn't sleep and my thoughts were unclear.
After ten days in hospital, I went home.
A week later, I was back in hospital in Denver
for my fifth and most difficult operation.
The time I woke up after the operation was
the lowest point after my escape.
I felt terrible.
I couldn't eat, I couldn't sleep and I was
still in pain.
Later, I discovered that I nearly died.
However by May the 25th, I was home to stay.
The following weeks were difficult for my
family.
I was like a child again, unable to do anything
for myself.
Slowly, however, things got better.
I was soon eating normal food and by the end
of the summer, I was the same weight as before
the accident.
By this time, I had a prosthetic arm.
I learnt to use it quite well.
I felt pleased.
It wouldn't be long before I would be able
to go climbing again.
Of course, I didn't tell my mother that.
On August the 31st, four months after the
accident, I spoke at Sonja's wedding.
Four days later, I climbed Mount Moran in
Wyoming with eight of my friends.
On October the 25th - two days before my twenty-eighth
birthday - I returned to Blue John Canyon.
Some friends, including Kristi Moore, were
with me.
We filmed the place where the accident happened.
Then, as the others made their way back to
their vehicles, I stayed behind for a few
minutes.
Just before I left, I looked at the dates
of my life on the canyon wall.
I was wrong.
My life didn't end in the canyon.
Thoughts of the people I love had kept me
alive.
If I wanted to see them again, I had to survive.
That's what I told myself.
And that's what I did.
My accident changed my life.
I know that even if I could travel back in
time, I wouldn't change anything.
I would still say goodbye to Megan and Kristi
and continue alone.
I've learned a lot from that choice.
I believe we are on Earth to do the things
we love, even if that means making a hard
choice.
Sometimes, that means cutting out something
and leaving it in the past.
Saying goodbye to things from our past is
also a new beginning.
- THE END -