CHAPTER ONE
Veney, Switzerland
Vevey is a beautiful little town on the shore of
a very blue lake in Switzerland. Tourism is the
business of the place, and there are many hotels.
American tourists particularly like the hotel
called the Trois Couronnes. Two years ago, a
young American named Frederick Winterbourne
spent a few days there. He had come from Geneva to
see his aunt, Mrs Costello, who was staying at the
Trois Couronnes. The morning after Winterbourne
arrived in Vevey, his aunt had a headache,
so he was free to sit in the garden of the hotel
and enjoy its beauties. He sat by the wall,
looking out at the Castle of Chillon,
which stood on a small island in the lake.
Winterbourne was twenty-seven years old
and had lived in Geneva for a long time.
He had been at school and university there.
When his friends spoke of him, they usually said
that he was at Geneva 'studying'. When certain
other people spoke of him they said that he
spent so much time in Geneva because he was
very attached to a lady who lived there - a
European lady - a person older than himself. None
of his American friends had ever met this lady.
As Winterbourne was drinking his coffee
in the garden of the Trois Couronnes,
a small boy came up to him and said,
'Can you give me a lump of sugar?'
Winterbourne noticed that the boy spoke with an
American accent. He pointed to the bowl of sugar
and said, 'Take one, but I don't
think sugar is good for little boys.'
The boy took three lumps of sugar. He put
two in his pocket and one in his mouth. 'I
eat sugar lumps,' he said, 'because I can't get
any candy here. American candy is the best.'
'And are American boys the
best?' asked Winterbourne.
'I don't know,' said the child. 'I am an
American boy. Are you an American man?'
'Yes.'
'American men are the best!' said the boy. Then,
looking round, he added, 'Here comes my sister!'
Winterbourne looked up and saw a
beautiful young lady coming towards them.
'American girls are the best!' he
said cheerfully to his companion.
'My sister isn't the best,' said the
boy. 'She's always criticising me.'
'That's probably your fault, not hers,' said
Winterbourne. The young lady was dressed very
elegantly in white. 'How pretty they are!'
thought Winterbourne, preparing to get up.
The young lady stopped in front of him.
She looked out over the blue lake.
'Randolph!' she said. 'What are you doing?'
'I'm talking to this man,' said
Randolph. 'He's an American.'
Winterbourne stood up and said, 'Your
brother and I have been discussing America.'
He felt a little embarrassed: in Geneva, a
gentleman could not speak to a young lady without
being formally introduced. The young lady looked
at him quickly then looked back at the lake.
'We've been talking about
American candy,' said the boy.
'I don't want to go to Italy.
I want to go home to America!'
'Are you going to Italy?' asked Winterbourne.
'Yes,' replied the young lady.
'Italy is a beautiful place.'
'But can you get any candy there?' asked Randolph.
'I think you've had enough candy,' said
his sister, 'and Mother thinks so too.'
'Isn't this a splendid lake?' said Winterbourne.
He no longer felt embarrassed, because he realised
that the young lady did not feel embarrassed. When
she looked at him, her eyes were honest and fresh.
They were very pretty eyes. In fact, she was
the prettiest girl he had seen for a long time.
Her face was delicate but perhaps a little
vulgar; it was bright, sweet, and superficial.
He thought that she might be a flirt,
but her expression was too innocent.
Before long, she was speaking to him freely. She
told him that she was going to Rome for the winter
with her mother and Randolph. She told
him that she was from New York State.
'Her name's Daisy Miller,' said Randolph. 'But
that isn't her real name. Her real name is
Annie P. Miller. And my father's name is
Ezra B. Miller. He's back in New York State.
He's got a big business. My father's rich.'
Miss Miller sat down and talked to Winterbourne
while Randolph ran round the garden. She talked
a lot - about her family, about her travels
in Europe, about the hotels and the trains.
Sometimes she looked at Winterbourne,
and sometimes she looked out at the lake.
'The hotels are very good,' said Miss Daisy
Miller. 'And I think Europe is perfectly
sweet. I'm not disappointed - not at all. I
knew a lot about Europe before I came here.
I have lots of friends at home
who have travelled in Europe,
and they told me all about it. And back
home I have lots of dresses from Paris...'
Winterbourne enjoyed this
conversation. It was many years
since he had heard a young girl talk so much.
'The only thing I don't like about Europe is
the society,' said Miss Miller. 'I like society.
Last winter seventeen dinners were given in my
honour, three of them by gentlemen.' She looked at
him with her slightly monotonous smile and said,
'I've always had a lot of gentlemen friends.'
Winterbourne was amused, perplexed, and charmed.
He felt that he had lived too long in Geneva
and therefore could no longer understand young
American girls. He had never met a girl like
this before. Was she simply a pretty girl from
New York - were they all like that? Or was she
an immoral young woman? She looked extremely
innocent. Winterbourne decided that she was
just a pretty American flirt. He was happy to have
found a formula to describe Miss Daisy Miller.
'Have you been to that old castle?' asked Miss
Miller, pointing to the Castle of Chillon.
'Yes.'
'I want to go there, but
Randolph doesn't want to go.'
'You could ask someone to stay
with Randolph at the hotel.'
'Will you stay with him?'
'Can't I come to the Castle of Chillon with you?'
asked Winterbourne. He was afraid that he had
offended her, but she did not blush. 'And your
mother, of course,' he said very respectfully.
'Oh, Mother won't come,' said Miss Daisy
Miller. 'She'll stay with Randolph,
and Eugenio will stay too - he's our
courier - so we can go to the castle.'
Winterbourne thought, '"We" can only mean
Miss Miller and I, it's too good to be true!'
At that moment Eugenio came up to
them. He looked at Winterbourne
with suspicion then said,
'Lunch is ready, mademoiselle.'
'Oh, Eugenio!' Daisy Miller replied,
'I'm going to that old castle anyway.'
'Really?' said Eugenio. He looked
at Winterbourne disrespectfully.
Miss Miller blushed a little. 'We are
going, aren't we?' she asked Winterbourne.
'I won't be happy until we go!' he said.
'And you are staying at this hotel?' she
continued. 'And you really are an American?'
'I'll introduce you to my aunt, Mrs
Costello. She can tell you all about me.'
'Oh, well,' said Daisy
Miller, 'we'll go some day.'
She smiled at Winterbourne and walked
back to the hotel with Eugenio.
CHAPTER TWO
Mrs Costello
The next day, Winterbourne went
to see his aunt in her room.
'I hope you're feeling better,' he said.
'A little,' replied Mrs Costello. She was a rich
widow and an important figure of New York society.
She had a long pale face and a lot of white hair.
She had two married sons in New York and a third
son who was travelling in Europe but had not
come to see her. Winterbourne had come to Vevey
just to see his aunt. She often told him that he
paid more attention to her than her own sons did.
'Have you noticed an American
family here at the hotel?'
asked Winterbourne. 'A family called Miller?'
'A mother, a daughter, a little boy,
and a courier? Oh, yes! I've noticed
them!' said Mrs Costello. 'I confess I'm very
exclusive, but in New York you have to be.
There are so many vulgar people in society these
days. That Miller family is a perfect example.'
'The young girl is very
pretty,' said Winterbourne.
'Of course she's pretty, but she's very
vulgar. She's too friendly with the courier.
Her mother is just as bad. They treat
the courier like a family friend.
He probably eats dinner with them. I'm sure
they've never seen a man with such good manners,
such fine clothes, so like a gentleman! He sits
with them in the garden and smokes cigars.'
'I see what you mean, of
course,' said the young man,
'but I met the young lady in the garden.
I'd like to introduce her to you.'
'I'm afraid I can't meet her! Why
do you want to introduce her to me?'
'To guarantee my respectability.'
'But who'll guarantee hers?'
'Ah, you're cruel!' said the young man. 'She's
a very nice girl and completely unsophisticated.
I'm going to take her to the Castle of Chillon.'
'Really? And how long had you known her when this
plan was formed?' asked Mrs Costello in surprise.
'Half an hour!' said Winterbourne, smiling.
'Oh, what a terrible girl!' cried
Mrs Costello. 'My dear Frederick,
you've been away from America too long. You're
too innocent. You'll make some great mistake.'
'I'm not so innocent!'
'You're too guilty, then!'
Winterbourne sat in silence for a while then
said, 'So I can't introduce her to you?'
'No. I can't accept a girl who
talks to strangers in hotels.'
'But don't all the young girls in
America do that sort of thing?'
'My grand-daughters don't do that
sort of thing!' said Mrs Costello.
Winterbourne had heard his pretty
cousins in New York described as
'terrible flirts'. If Miss Daisy Miller
did things that his cousins did not do,
she must be very unconventional indeed.
Winterbourne was impatient to see her again.
That evening, he met Miss Daisy Miller walking in
the garden. She seemed very pleased to see him.
'Have you been walking here all alone?' he asked.
'No,' she replied. 'I've been walking
with Mother, but she's gone to find
Randolph. She wants him to go to bed. He
doesn't like to go to bed before eleven.'
Winterbourne and Daisy walked
in the garden together.
'I hear that your aunt is very exclusive,' said
Daisy. 'I want to meet her. I know I'll like her.'
Winterbourne was embarrassed. 'I'm
afraid she often has headaches,' he said.
Daisy looked at him for a moment then said,
'She doesn't want to meet me! Why don't you
just say so? You needn't be afraid. I'm not
afraid!' She gave a little nervous laugh.
Winterbourne wanted to comfort her. He
wanted to tell her that his aunt was a snob
and that her opinion was
not important. But just then
a lady came into the garden and stood at a
distance from them, looking out at the lake.
'Oh. There's Mother,' said Daisy Miller.
Mrs Miller was a small nervous-looking
person, very elegantly dressed,
with enormous diamonds in her ears.
'I should go,' said Winterbourne.
'No, no,' replied Daisy.
'I want to introduce you to Mother. I always
introduce my gentlemen friends to Mother.'
'She doesn't seem to want to be
introduced to me,' said Winterbourne,
since Mrs Miller still had not looked at him.
'She's very shy,' Daisy explained, then she
took Winterbourne over to meet her mother.
'Mother, this is Mr Winterbourne,' said Daisy
very prettily. Yes, Miss Daisy Miller was vulgar,
as Mrs Costello had said, but Winterbourne thought
she also had an unusual and delicate grace.
'Did you convince Randolph
to go to bed?' asked Daisy.
'No,' replied Mrs Miller. 'He won't go.'
'He won't do what he's told,' said Daisy.
'He won't go to that castle either,
so I'm going with Mr Winterbourne.'
'It's a beautiful castle, Mrs Miller,' said
Winterbourne. 'Don't you want to see it?'
'No, thank you,' said Mrs
Miller. 'Daisy will go, though.'
Winterbourne thought how
very different Mrs Miller was
from the vigilant mothers of Geneva. They never
let their daughters go anywhere unprotected.
'Mr Winterbourne,' said Daisy suddenly.
'Will you take me out in a boat?'
'Now?'
'Yes, now.'
'Well, Annie Miller!' cried her mother.
'I'm sure that Mr Winterbourne wants to take
me out in a boat!' said Daisy, laughing.
'But what time is it? I'm sure it's
time to go to bed!' said Mrs Miller.
'It's eleven o'clock, madam,'
said a voice from the darkness.
'Oh, Eugenio,' said Daisy.
'I'm going out in a boat!'
'At eleven o'clock, mademoiselle?'
'Please tell her she can't go,'
said Mrs Miller to the courier. 'Does
mademoiselle want to go alone?' asked Eugenio.
'No,' Mrs Miller replied. 'She wants to go with
this gentleman!' Eugenio looked at Winterbourne,
then he said, 'As mademoiselle pleases.'
'Why don't you say no?' said Daisy to the courier.
'I don't want to go now.' She
turned to Winterbourne, smiled,
and said, 'Good night. I hope you're
disgusted or disappointed or something.'
'I'm confused,' said Winterbourne. He stood
and watched the two ladies and their courier
as they walked back into the hotel.
CHAPTER THREE
The Castle of Chillon
Two days later, Winterbourne and Miss Miller
went to the Castle of Chillon. They met by
the main door of the hotel. Daisy ran down
the stairs, with a bright smile on her face.
She was simply but elegantly dressed. All the
couriers, servants, and foreign tourists in the
main hall stared at her. To Winterbourne their
trip to the castle seemed romantic: he thought
of it as an adventure, and he hoped that she did
too, but in this respect he was disappointed.
She seemed happy but not excited. She did not
blush when she looked at him or when she saw that
other people were looking at her. Winterbourne
wanted to go to the castle in a carriage,
over the wooden bridge that connected
the island to the shore, but Daisy
said that she preferred to go in the little
steamboat. She liked the breeze on the lake.
The steamboat was very crowded, and
the people stared at Miss Daisy Miller.
Winterbourne thought, 'Will she embarrass me by
talking too loudly or laughing too much?' But soon
he forgot those anxieties. He stood smiling at her
and listening to her conversation. He had agreed
with his aunt when she had said that Miss Daisy
Miller was vulgar, but now he felt uncertain. 'Is
she really vulgar?' he asked himself, watching her
pretty face. Winterbourne did not feel embarrassed
by her at all. In fact, he felt rather proud to
be with such a beautiful and elegant young lady.
She talked a lot, and most of her conversation
was about the things she had seen and done.
She asked him many questions about his life
and opinions, and she told him about herself
and her family. At one point, she turned
to him and said, 'Why are you so serious?'
'Serious?' asked the young man in surprise.
'I thought I was grinning from ear to ear!'
'You look as if you were taking me to a funeral.
If that's a grin, your ears
are very close together!'
'I'm having the time of my
life,' said Winterbourne quietly.
She looked at him for a moment then laughed:
'I like to make you say those
things! You're a strange mixture!'
It was a beautiful sunny day. At the castle,
they walked around alone except for the guide.
Winterbourne asked the guide not to hurry,
to let them pause wherever they pleased.
He gave the guide a generous tip as he said this.
The guide thought he was being paid
to leave them in peace, and he did so.
Daisy ran up the stairs and looked out of
the little windows with great enthusiasm,
but Winterbourne could see that she was
not really interested in the old castle.
She asked him about the history of the
place, and when he had explained it,
she said, 'You certainly know a lot. Do you want
to come travelling with us and teach Randolph?'
'I'm afraid I can't,' Winterbourne replied.
'Why not? You don't work. You're not in
business. Why can't you do what you want?'
'There are things I must do in Geneva.
In fact, I must go back there tomorrow.'
'I don't believe it!' cried Miss Daisy Miller.
'I'm afraid it's true.'
'Well, Mr Winterbourne, I think you're
horrible!' For the next ten minutes she
kept repeating that he was horrible.
Poor Winterbourne was confused. No
young lady had ever done him the honour
of being so agitated by his departure.
'I suppose you must be going to
see a lady there!' said Daisy.
'No, I'm not!' protested Winterbourne, but he
thought, 'How does she know about the lady?'
He was surprised by her insight and by the honest
way she confronted him about the lady in Geneva.
Miss Daisy Miller seemed to him an extraordinary
mixture of innocence and vulgarity.
'Does she never allow you out
for more than three days?'
asked Daisy sarcastically. 'Doesn't
she give you a vacation in the summer?
But never mind. I'll forgive you if you
promise to come to Rome in the winter.'
'Certainly I'll come,' said
Winterbourne. 'My aunt has a
house in Rome, and I've promised
to visit her there this winter.'
'I don't want you to come for your aunt,' said
Miss Daisy Miller. 'I want you to come for me.'
After this, Daisy lost all interest in the
castle and the lake. Winterbourne found
a carriage to take them back to the hotel.
On the journey back, she was very quiet.
CHAPTER FOUR
Meeting in rome
The next day, Winterbourne returned to Geneva,
but in January he went to Rome, as promised.
On his first evening there, his aunt
said to him, 'That Miller family is here.
The girl goes out alone with Italian
men - well-known Roman fortune-hunters.
And she takes them to respectable people's houses!
It's a great scandal. When she comes to a party,
she brings with her a gentleman with
elegant manners and a splendid moustache.'
'And where's her mother?' asked Winterbourne.
'I've no idea,' Mrs Costello replied. 'They're
terrible people.' Winterbourne thought for a
moment. 'They're just very ignorant and innocent.
I really don't believe that they're bad people.'
'They're very vulgar,' said his aunt. 'You may
say that being vulgar is different from being bad,
but I don't see the difference.' Winterbourne
had imagined Miss Daisy Miller looking out of her
window in a Roman hotel rather sadly, waiting for
him to arrive. This new picture of her surrounded
by Roman fortune-hunters did not please him, so he
did not go to visit her on his first day in Rome.
Instead he went to the house of Mrs Walker, an
American lady he knew from Geneva, where her
children were at school. She lived in the Via
Gregoriana. Winterbourne found her in a little
red drawing-room full of afternoon sunshine. As he
was talking to Mrs Walker, the servant came in and
announced, 'Mrs Miller!'. Then Randolph entered
the room, followed by Daisy and her mother.
'Well!' said Daisy in surprise. 'I didn't know
you were in Rome! Why didn't you come to see me?'
'I only arrived yesterday,' replied Winterbourne.
Randolph looked around the room and said,
'We've got a bigger place than this.
The walls are all gold.'
'Oh, Randolph!' said Mrs Miller nervously.
'Are you enjoying Rome?' Winterbourne asked her.
'Well, I'm rather disappointed,' she replied.
'We'd heard so much about it, but we've
seen other places I like much better.'
'Really? Which places?'
'For example, Zurich,' said Mrs
Miller. 'I think Zurich is lovely,
and we hadn't heard much about it.'
'The best place we've been is the
City of Richmond,' said Randolph.
'He means the ship that brought us to Europe,'
Mrs Miller explained. 'Randolph
enjoyed the City of Richmond.'
'It's the best place I've seen,' said
Randolph, 'but it was going the wrong way.'
'I hope Miss Miller is enjoying
Rome,' said Winterbourne.
'Oh, yes,' replied Mrs Miller. 'Daisy
loves Rome. The society is splendid.
She's invited to many people's houses. She
goes out much more frequently than I do.
And she knows a lot of gentlemen
here. Yes, she loves Rome.
Of course, young ladies are always happier in
a place if they know a lot of gentlemen there.'
Daisy had been talking to Mrs Walker, but
now she turned to Winterbourne and said,
'I've been telling Mrs Walker how
horrible you were to me in Vevey.'
Winterbourne was rather irritated. She did
not seem to appreciate the fact that he had
travelled from Geneva without stopping
at Bologna or Florence, simply because
he was impatient to see her. He remembered an
American friend of his who had told him that
American women - the pretty ones - were the most
demanding and least grateful women in the world.
'My dear young lady!' cried Winterbourne.
'Have I come all the way to Rome
just to hear you criticise me?'
But Daisy ignored him. She turned
back to Mrs Walker and said,
'Thank you for inviting us to your
party. We gladly accept the invitation.'
'I'm delighted to hear it,' replied Mrs Walker.
'I've got a lovely dress.'
'I'm very sure of that.'
'But I want to ask you a favour:
can I please bring a friend?'
'Certainly,' said Mrs Walker, smiling at Mrs
Miller. 'Any friend of yours is welcome.'
'Oh, they're not my friends,' said Mrs Miller
with a nervous smile. 'I've never met them!'
'He's a very close friend of
mine,' said Daisy. 'Mr Giovanelli.'
Mrs Walker was silent for a moment.
She looked quickly at Winterbourne
then said, 'Mr Giovanelli is
welcome to come to the party.'
'He's an Italian,' continued Daisy serenely.
'He's the most handsome man in the world,
except for Mr Winterbourne. He knows lots of
Italians, but he wants to meet some Americans.
He's very clever and perfectly lovely!'
'Daisy,' said Mrs Miller. 'It's
time to go back to the hotel.'
'You go,' Daisy replied with a smile.
'I'm going to the Pincio for a walk.'
'She's going to walk with Mr
Giovanelli,' said Randolph.
'Alone, my dear?' asked Mrs Walker. 'And
at this hour? I don't think it's safe.'
'Neither do I,' said Mrs
Miller. 'You'll get the fever!'
'I'm not going alone,' said Daisy to Mrs Walker.
'I'm going with the beautiful Mr Giovanelli.'
'My dear young friend,' said Mrs Walker.
'Don't go to the Pincio at this
hour to meet a beautiful Italian.'
'Oh!' said Daisy. 'I don't
want to do anything improper.
Perhaps Mr Winterbourne will walk to the
Pincio with me. That'll solve the problem.'
Winterbourne agreed, and they walked together
down the stairs and past Mrs Miller's carriage,
in which Eugenio was waiting.
'Goodbye, Eugenio,' cried Daisy.
'I'm going for a walk.'
CHAPTER FIVE
Introducing Mr Giovanelli
As they walked, Daisy told Winterbourne
all about her experiences in Rome.
'We have very beautiful rooms at the hotel,'
she said. 'We'll stay here all winter,
unless we die of the fever, and in
that case we'll stay even longer!
I'm enjoying Rome very much. I know lots of
charming people here...' She talked like this
for some time, then she turned to him and
asked, 'Why didn't you come to visit me?'
'I've already told you,' Winterbourne
replied. 'I've only just got off the train.'
'You must have stayed on the train
a long time after it stopped!'
said Daisy, with a little laugh. 'Anyway,
you've had time to go and visit Mrs Walker.'
'I know Mrs Walker from Geneva-'
'I know. She told me. Well,
you know me from Vevey.
That's just as good. So you
ought to have come to visit me.'
When they reached the Pincio,
Daisy saw Mr Giovanelli.
He was standing by a tree, looking
at the women in their carriages.
He was a handsome little man, very elegantly
dressed, with a flower in his buttonhole.
'Are you going to speak to
that man?' asked Winterbourne.
'Of course!' said Daisy.
'Then I'm staying with you.'
Daisy stopped and looked at him for a
moment in silence, but the expression
on her face was still serene. 'I don't like
the way you say that,' she said with a smile,
'I never allow gentlemen to tell me what to do.'
'I think you've made a
mistake,' Winterbourne replied.
'You should sometimes listen to
a gentleman - the right one.'
She looked at him again, more seriously this time,
with her pretty eyes, then she laughed and said,
'I do nothing but listen to gentlemen!
Is Mr Giovanelli the right one?'
Just then, Giovanelli saw
them and walked up to them.
He had a brilliant smile and intelligent eyes.
'No, he isn't the right one,' said Winterbourne.
Daisy introduced Giovanelli to Winterbourne, and
they walked along, one gentleman on each side of
Daisy. Mr Giovanelli spoke English very well.
He made pleasant conversation with Winterbourne
and Daisy. He was disappointed that Daisy
had not come alone, but he did not show his
disappointment. 'He's not a gentleman,' thought
Winterbourne. 'He's a good imitation of one,
but a nice girl ought to know the difference!' But
was Miss Daisy Miller a nice girl? That was the
question. She had no delicacy, and yet she did not
seem impatient for Winterbourne to go: she did not
seem to want to be alone with her lover. She was
a strange combination of audacity and innocence.
Fifteen minutes later, Winterbourne noticed Mrs
Walker sitting in her carriage at the side of the
road. She waved to him. He left Miss Miller
with Mr Giovanelli and went to Mrs Walker,
who looked agitated. 'This is terrible!' said Mrs
Walker. 'That girl mustn't do this kind of thing.
She mustn't walk here with you two
men. Fifty people have noticed her!'
'Is it really that important?' asked
Winterbourne. 'She's very innocent.'
'She's very crazy!' cried Mrs Walker.
'And her mother is an absolute
fool! When you left, I thought that,
since her mother won't warn her, I should,
so I came here to find her. Tell
her I want to speak to her.'
'I don't think it's a good idea,'
said Winterbourne, 'but you can try.'
When Winterbourne gave Daisy this message,
the young lady walked serenely to Mrs Walker's
carriage with Mr Giovanelli at her side.
'Mrs Walker, this is Mr
Giovanelli,' said Daisy prettily.
Mrs Walker nodded to the Italian
then turned to Daisy and said,
'Will you get in the carriage and drive with me?'
'No, thank you,' said Daisy. 'I'm perfectly happy
as I am.' And she smiled at her two gentlemen.
'You may be perfectly happy, dear child,
but it isn't the custom here for a young
lady to walk alone with gentlemen.'
'Well, it ought to be!' said
Daisy. 'I love walking!'
'You should walk with your
mother, dear,' said Mrs Walker.
'My mother never goes for a walk.
And I'm not five years old!'
'You're old enough to be more
reasonable,' said Mrs Walker.
'You're old enough, my dear Miss
Miller, to cause a scandal.'
'What do you mean?' asked
Daisy, smiling intensely.
'Come into my carriage, and I'll
explain it to you,' Mrs Walker replied.
Daisy looked at Giovanelli then at Winterbourne.
'I don't think I want to know what you mean!'
She blushed, and Winterbourne thought she was
extremely pretty. She looked at Winterbourne
and said, 'Do you think that - to save my
reputation - I should get into the carriage?'
Winterbourne blushed a little and hesitated. It
seemed so strange to hear her talk that way of her
'reputation'. He wanted to give the
reply that was best for Daisy herself.
He felt that it was in Daisy's best interest
to hear the truth, and the truth, Winterbourne
thought, was that she should do what Mrs Walker
had asked her to do. He looked at her exquisite
prettiness and then said, very gently, 'I
think you should get into the carriage'.
Daisy gave a violent laugh. 'How ridiculous! If
this is improper, Mrs Walker, then I am improper.
Goodbye!' Then she turned and
walked away with Mr Giovanelli.
Mrs Walker watched her go with tears in her eyes.
'Get in the carriage,' she said to Winterbourne.
'I think I should accompany Miss Miller.'
'If you don't get into this carriage, I'll
never speak to you again!' cried Mrs Walker.
Winterbourne said goodbye to Daisy and Giovanelli
and got into the carriage. 'That
wasn't very clever of you,' he said.
'I'm not trying to be clever;
I'm trying to be honest,' replied Mrs
Walker. 'She's causing a great scandal.
Italian men come to see her at her hotel late at
night, when her mother has already gone to bed.'
'She's just unsophisticated,'
said Winterbourne impatiently.
'She has no natural delicacy,' replied
Mrs Walker. 'You must stop seeing her,
stop flirting with her: leave her alone!'
'I can't do that. I like her very much.'
'Then you should want to protect her
from scandal.' Winterbourne got out of
the carriage and said goodbye to Mrs Walker. He
saw Daisy and Giovanelli standing by the wall,
looking at the beautiful Villa Borghese.
Giovanelli took Daisy's parasol and
opened it. He rested the parasol on her shoulder
so that both their heads were hidden behind it.
Winterbourne hesitated a moment, then he turned
and walked away, towards his aunt's house.
CHAPTER SIX
Mrs Walker's party
Mrs Walker's party was a few days later. Mrs
Miller came alone. The poor lady was very
nervous. 'I've never been to a party alone before,
especially in this country!' she told Mrs Walker,
'I wanted to bring Randolph or Eugenio,
but Daisy told me to go alone!'
'Is your daughter going to favour us
with her company?' asked Mrs Walker,
but Mrs Miller did not notice her sarcasm.
'Well, she's dressed for the party. She
got dressed before dinner. But her friend
is there - the Italian gentleman. Daisy's
playing the piano and Mr Giovanelli's singing.
He sings splendidly. But I think they'll
come soon,' said Mrs Miller hopefully.
Mrs Walker turned to Winterbourne and said,
'This is horrible! Miss Miller is trying to
punish me for criticising her in the Pincio the
other day. When she comes, I won't speak to her!'
Daisy came after eleven o'clock. 'I'm sorry
I'm late,' she said to Mrs Walker with a
smile. 'Mr Giovanelli and I were practicing
his songs so that he can sing for your guests.
He has such a beautiful voice.' Daisy looked
very lovely as she said this in her sweet, bright
voice. 'Is there anyone here I know?' she asked,
looking around with interest at the other guests.
'I think everyone knows who you are!'
said Mrs Walker coldly. Mr Giovanelli
sang his songs very well, although no one had
asked him to do so. Daisy talked as he sang.
'I'd love to dance,' she said to
Winterbourne, 'but these rooms are too small.'
'I don't want to dance,' Winterbourne
replied. 'I can't dance.'
'Of course you can't dance; you're too stiff.'
said Miss Daisy. 'I hope you enjoyed
your ride in Mrs Walker's carriage.'
'No, I didn't enjoy it. I
preferred walking with you.'
'You went with your friend, and I
went with mine. That was much better.
But really, Mrs Walker has such strange ideas!'
continued Daisy. 'How could I get into her
carriage and leave poor Mr Giovanelli?'
'Mr Giovanelli was wrong to
ask you to walk with him.
No young Italian lady walks
with gentlemen in the streets.'
'In the streets?' cried Daisy. 'The Pincio
is not "the streets"! And fortunately I'm
not a young Italian lady! It seems
to me they have a miserable time!'
'People here think you're
a flirt,' said Winterbourne
seriously. 'Of course I am!'
said Daisy with a smile.
'All nice girls are flirts! But I suppose
you'll say that I'm not a nice girl.'
'You're a very nice girl,' said Winterbourne,
'but I want you to flirt with me and nobody else.'
'Thank you!' replied Daisy. 'But I don't
want to flirt with you: you're too stiff!'
'Well, at least stop flirting with Giovanelli.
They don't understand that sort of thing here.'
'I thought they understood
nothing else!' said Daisy.
'Not in young unmarried women.'
'It seems to me much more proper
in young unmarried women than in
old married ones,' cried Daisy.
'Well,' said Winterbourne, 'you
must obey the customs of the place.
Flirting is a purely American custom;
it doesn't exist here. So when you
go out in public with Mr Giovanelli and
without your mother, people are shocked.'
'Poor Mother!' said Daisy.
'You are flirting, but Mr Giovanelli
isn't: he's quite serious.'
'At least he doesn't tell me what
to do!' cried Daisy. 'Anyway,
I'm not flirting with Mr Giovanelli. We're
good friends, very intimate friends.'
'Ah,' replied Winterbourne, 'it's different
if you're in love with each other.'
To Winterbourne's surprise,
Daisy blushed and stood up
angrily. 'At least Mr Giovanelli never
says such horrible things!' she cried.
Daisy spent the rest of the evening sitting with
Mr Giovanelli in a quiet corner of the room.
When she came back to say goodbye to Mrs
Walker, the lady ignored her. Daisy went pale
and looked anxiously at her mother.
Winterbourne felt very sorry for her.
'That was very cruel,' he said to
Mrs Walker, after Daisy had left.
'I'll never invite her here
again!' Mrs Walker replied.
In the weeks that followed, Winterbourne
often went to visit Daisy at her hotel.
Giovanelli was always there, but Daisy did
not seem disturbed by Winterbourne's presence.
It seemed that she could talk as
happily with one gentleman or two.
One Sunday afternoon, Winterbourne went to St
Peter's with his aunt. When he saw Daisy and
Giovanelli walking together in the great church,
he said to his aunt, 'There's Miss Miller!'
Mrs Costello looked at Daisy for a moment
then said, 'Is that what makes
you so distracted these days?'
'I'm not distracted,' replied Winterbourne.
'You seem very preoccupied:
you're thinking of something.'
'And what do you think I'm thinking of?'
'Of Miss Miller's intimacy
with that ridiculous Italian,'
said Mrs Costello, indicating Giovanelli.
'I don't think it's an "intimacy"
in the sense you mean.'
'Everyone else does. He's very handsome, and she's
very vulgar. She thinks he's the most elegant
gentleman in the world. He's even better than the
courier! The courier probably introduced them,
and when they're married this man will give the
courier a lot of money. Yes, I see how it is.'
'I don't believe she's thinking of
marrying him,' said Winterbourne,
'and I don't think he hopes to marry her.'
'She's so vulgar that she probably doesn't think
at all,' said Mrs Costello. 'But believe me,
very soon she'll tell you that she's engaged.'
'I don't think so,' Winterbourne replied.
'I've asked some questions about him.
He's a perfectly respectable little man,
but he's not from the best Italian society.
He has no money and no title - he's not a
count or a marchese - so he knows that he cannot
hope to marry her. He probably doesn't realise
that Daisy and her mother aren't sophisticated
enough to want to catch a count or a marchese.'
'He thinks he can win her with his
handsome face,' said Mrs Costello.
'No,' replied Winterbourne. 'He knows
that he has nothing but his handsome
face, and he knows that Mr Miller,
in the mysterious land of dollars, will want his
daughter to marry someone with more than that.'
Some of Mrs Costello's American friends joined
them then, and Winterbourne heard a lot of talk
about the scandalous Miss Daisy Miller. He
felt sorry for her. He was sorry to hear them
talking about her like that: to him she seemed
just pretty and unprotected and natural.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Innocent or Immoral?
A few days later, Winterbourne went
to see Mrs Miller at her hotel,
hoping to persuade her to take
better care of her daughter.
'I'm sorry, Daisy isn't here,' said Mrs Miller.
'She's gone somewhere with Mr Giovanelli. She's
always going somewhere with Mr Giovanelli.'
'I've noticed that they're very
intimate,' said Winterbourne.
'Oh! It seems as if they couldn't live
without each other!' said Mrs Miller. 'Well,
at least he's a real gentleman. I keep
telling Daisy that she's engaged!'
'And what does Daisy say?'
'Oh, she says she isn't engaged, but she acts
as if she is! I asked Mr Giovanelli to tell me
if they get engaged, so that I
can write and tell Mr Miller.'
Winterbourne had never heard a parent speak
of a daughter's behaviour in such a distant
way. He found Mrs Miller's attitude so strange and
confusing that he gave up the idea of warning her.
After that, Winterbourne noticed that Daisy was
no longer invited to people's houses. Society
had decided that Miss Daisy Miller had gone too
far. How did she feel about that? Sometimes he
thought she did not care: she was too childish and
superficial to notice what people thought of her.
At other moments he thought she knew
perfectly well the impression she produced,
but she refused to change because
she knew that she was innocent.
But then he thought perhaps she refused to
change because she was irresponsible. It
was becoming more and more difficult
for him to believe in her innocence.
He was angry with himself because he
could not decide what kind of young lady
Miss Daisy Miller was. He had no idea whether
her eccentricities were personal or national.
By not inviting her to their parties,
the other American residents in Rome
were sending a clear message to their Italian
friends, who were all aristocrats. They were
telling the Italians that, though Miss
Daisy Miller was an American young lady,
she was not typical. So perhaps Daisy's
eccentricities were purely personal.
But was she innocent or immoral? Did she
understand the consequences of her actions,
or was she ignorant of them? Was she simply
a child, or was she a rebellious young woman?
One day, he met her in the Palace of the Caesars.
She was walking through the flowers in the
beautiful deserted gardens with Mr Giovanelli.
'Aren't you lonely?' asked Daisy.
'Lonely?'
'Yes. You're always walking around alone.
Can't you find anyone to walk with you?'
'I'm not as fortunate as your
companion,' replied Winterbourne.
From the first, Giovanelli had treated
Winterbourne with great courtesy and respect.
He had listened to Winterbourne s conversation
and laughed whenever Winterbourne said something
amusing. He gave the impression that he
considered Winterbourne a superior young man.
He did not act like a jealous lover. Obviously,
Giovanelli was very diplomatic. He did not mind
showing a little humility
in front of the American.
At times, it even seemed to Winterbourne that
Giovanelli wanted to talk to him privately - to
explain that of course he, Giovanelli, knew
that this young lady was too good for him. On
this occasion, he walked away from his companions
and went to pick some flowers for his buttonhole.
'I know why you say that,' said Daisy. 'You
think I spend too much time with Mr Giovanelli.'
'Everyone thinks so.'
'They don't really care what I do,' Daisy replied.
'Oh yes, they do, and they'll be very unpleasant
to you. They're already being unpleasant to you.
Haven't you noticed?'
'I've noticed you,'
said Daisy. 'But I noticed that you were very
stiff and conventional the first time I saw you!'
'I'm not as stiff as some of the
others,' said Winterbourne, smiling.
'Haven't you noticed that they don't
invite you to their houses anymore?'
'Why do you let people be so unkind?' cried Daisy.
'What can I do?' replied Winterbourne.
'You could say something to them.'
'I do say something. I say that
your mother thinks you're engaged.'
'Well, she does,' said Daisy very simply.
'And does Randolph believe it?'
asked Winterbourne, laughing.
'I don't know. I don't
think he believes anything,'
she replied, 'and since you've
mentioned it, I am engaged.'
Winterbourne stopped laughing and looked at her
in surprise. 'You don't believe it!' cried Daisy.
He was silent a moment and
then said, 'Yes, I believe it.'
'Oh no, you don't!' she replied.
'Well, then - I'm not!'
CHAPTER EIGHT
A night at the Golosseum
A week later, Winterbourne was walking home alone
at eleven o'clock at night after dinner with
friends. He decided to go into the Colosseum.
Outside, he noticed a carriage was waiting.
He walked into the silent arena in the moonlight.
One half of the gigantic circus was in the shadow.
The place had never seemed more splendid,
and he remembered Byron's famous lines.
But then he thought, 'The poets
love the Colosseum by night,
but the doctors say it's dangerous because of
the risk of getting malaria. I should go soon.'
As he walked towards the great
cross in the centre of the arena,
he saw that two people were on the steps at
its base. One, a woman, was sitting on a step;
her companion was standing beside her.
Then Winterbourne heard the woman's voice:
'He looks at us as one of those old lions
must have looked at the Christians!'
It was the voice of Miss Daisy Miller.
'Let's hope he's not very hungry,'
Giovanelli replied with a laugh.
Winterbourne stopped. He felt a combination
of horror and relief. Now at last he knew
what to think of Miss Daisy Miller: she was not a
respectable young lady. He felt angry with himself
for having spent so much time trying to decide
what to think of her. He turned to walk out of
the Colosseum, but then she spoke again: 'It's Mr
Winterbourne! He saw me, and he didn't say hello!'
How cleverly she played the part of the
innocent! But he could not just ignore
her. As he walked towards the great cross,
Daisy stood up and Giovanelli raised his hat.
Winterbourne now began to think how crazy
she was to be there. A delicate young girl
should not spend the evening in the Colosseum: she
might get Roman fever. 'It's now clear,' thought
Winterbourne, 'that she's an immoral young woman,
but even so I don't want her to die of malaria.'
'How long have you been here?' he asked angrily.
Daisy, lovely in the moonlight,
looked at him for a moment
then said gently, 'We've been here
all evening. Isn't it pretty?'
'You could get malaria! You won't think that's
pretty!' cried Winterbourne. Then, turning to
Giovanelli, he's said, 'You're a Roman. You know
about Roman fever. Why did you bring her here?'
'Ah,' said the handsome Roman, 'I'm
not afraid of getting malaria myself.'
'But what about this young lady?'
'I told the Signorina that it was
dangerous, but she's never cautious.'
'I've never been ill a day
in my life!' said Daisy.
'I wanted to see the Colosseum by moonlight,
and we've had a lovely time. When I get home,
Eugenio will give me some of his medicine
against malaria. He has some splendid pills.'
'Well, go home now and take
one!' cried Winterbourne.
Giovanelli went out to find the carriage.
Daisy followed with Winterbourne.
She did not seem at all embarrassed.
She talked about the beauty of the place
and how glad she was to seen it by moonlight.
Then she noticed that Winterbourne was silent.
'Why are you so quiet?' she asked.
Winterbourne did not reply but began to laugh.
'Did you believe that I was
engaged the other day?' she asked.
'It doesn't matter what I believed the other
day?' replied Winterbourne, still laughing. 'Now
I believe it makes very little difference
whether you're engaged or not!'
Daisy looked at him, but in the
darkness he could not see her face.
Then Giovanelli came to say
that the carriage was ready.
'Don't forget to take Eugenio's
pills!' said Winterbourne.
Daisy replied in a trembling voice, 'I don't
care whether I get Roman fever or not!'
Then she got into the
carriage, and it drove off.
CHAPTER NINE
Daisy becomes ill
Winterbourne told no one that he had met Miss
Miller at eleven o'clock in the Colosseum with
a gentleman. Nevertheless, two days later, all
the American residents in Rome knew about it
and were talking about 'the little
American flirt'. Winterbourne found
that he no longer cared that people were
saying unkind things about Daisy Miller.
Then he heard that Daisy was very ill.
He went to the hotel to ask how she was.
There he met three other visitors who
said that Daisy was dangerously ill:
she had a terrible case of
malaria. He did not see Mrs Miller:
finally that lady was where she should
always have been - at her daughter's side.
Winterbourne went to the hotel often to ask
for news of Daisy. One time he saw Mrs Miller.
'Daisy spoke of you the other day,' said Daisy's
mother. 'Half the time she's delirious from the
fever and she doesn't know what she's
saying, but that time I think she did.
She told me to tell you that she was never engaged
to that handsome Italian. I was very glad to hear
that: Mr Giovanelli hasn't been to see us since
she got ill. A lady told me that he's afraid
that I'm angry with him for taking Daisy out at
night. Well, I am angry with him, but I'm a lady:
even when I'm angry I can be polite to guests.
Anyway, Daisy said she's not engaged. I don't
know why she wanted you to know. She told me three
times. "Be sure to tell Mr Winterbourne" she said.
And then she told me to ask if you remember the
time you went to that castle in Switzerland.'
A week later, the poor girl died. Daisy's
grave was in the little Protestant cemetery
by the wall of imperial Rome, beneath
the cypress trees and the spring flowers.
Winterbourne was surprised by the number of people
present at the funeral. Many people who had been
unkind to her when she was alive came to pay their
last respects now that she was dead. Giovanelli
stood near Winterbourne. He was very pale. On
this occasion he had no flower in his buttonhole.
When the funeral was over, Giovanelli
turned to Winterbourne and said,
'She was the most beautiful young lady I ever saw,
and the nicest.' He was silent for a moment,
then he said, 'And she was the most innocent.'
Winterbourne looked at him then repeated
his words, 'And the most innocent?'
'The most innocent!'
Winterbourne felt very angry. 'Why the devil,'
he asked, 'did you take her to that fatal place?'
Mr Giovanelli was silent for a moment,
then he said, 'I had no fear for
myself, and she wanted to go.'
'That's no reason!' cried Winterbourne.
Giovanelli was silent again, and then he said,
'She didn't want to marry me. For a while I
hoped, but now I'm sure that she didn't want to.'
Winterbourne listened to him. He looked down
at the new grave surrounded by April flowers.
When he looked up again, Mr Giovanelli had gone.
Winterbourne left Rome soon afterwards.
In the months that followed,
he often thought about Daisy Miller and her
mysterious manners. The following summer,
he went to see his aunt Mrs Costello in
Vevey. One day he spoke to her about Daisy.
'I think I treated her unfairly,' he said.
'She sent me a message before her death
which I didn't understand at the time.
But I have thought about it since, and now
I understand. She wanted me to respect her.'
'Is that a modest way of saying she wanted
you to love her?' asked Mrs Costello.
Winterbourne did not reply to this question. After
a short silence, he continued: 'What you said last
summer was true: I did make a great mistake.
I've lived too long in foreign countries.'
Nevertheless, he went back to Geneva. His
friends say that he is 'studying' there.
Other people say that he is interested
in a very clever foreign lady.
-
THE END -