THE ADVENTURES OF TOM SAWYER
A Few Words to Begin
Most of the ADVENTURES in this book really
happened.
One or two were my own experiences.
The others were experiences of boys in my
school.
Huck Finn really lived.
Tom Sawyer is made of three real boys.
My book is for boys and girls, but I hope
that men and women also will read it.
I hope that it will help them to remember
pleasantly the days when they were boys and
girls, and how they felt and thought and talked,
what they believed, and what strange things
they sometimes did.
MARK TWAIN
in the State of Connecticut,
Hartford 1876
Aunt Polly Decides Her Duty
“Tom!”
No answer.
“TOM!”
The old lady looked around the room.
“When I find you, I—”
She did not finish.
With her head down, she was looking under
the bed.
Only the cat came out.
She went to the open door and looked toward
the garden.
No Tom was there.
She shouted:
“You, Tom!”
There was a little noise behind her.
She turned and caught a small boy, stopping
him before he could escape.
“What were you doing in that corner?”
“Nothing.”
“Nothing!
What is that on your hands and face?”
“I do not know, Aunt Polly.”
“I know.
You have been eating sweets.
I have told you a hundred times not to eat
those sweets.”
Her hand was raised in the air—it started
down—it was very near—
“Oh!
Look behind you, Aunt!”
The old lady turned.
The boy ran.
In a moment he was up on the high board fence.
Then he was on the far side of it.
His Aunt Polly was surprised.
Then she laughed a little.
“That boy!
I never know what he will do next.
And he knows that I do not want to hit him.
But I should.
And if he does not go to school this afternoon,
I must make him work tomorrow.
He does not like work.
Especially on Saturday, when there is no school,
he does not like work.
All the other boys will be playing.
But I must try to make him a good boy.
He is my dead sister’s son, and it is my
duty.
I must do my duty.”
Tom did not go to school and he had a very
happy afternoon.
He came home late.
He hurried to do his share of the evening
work.
His brother Sid had already finished his share.
Sid was a quiet boy, who had no adventures
and also no troubles.
While Tom sat eating, his Aunt Polly asked
questions.
She hoped to learn about his afternoon.
“Tom, was it warm in school?”
“Yes, Aunt Polly.”
“Did you wish to go swimming, Tom?”
Tom began to feel afraid.
What did she know about his afternoon?
“No, Aunt Polly.
Not very much.”
She touched his shirt.
It was dry.
But Tom knew what she would touch next.
He said quickly, “Some of us put water on
our heads because we were hot.
My hair is not dry yet.”
He watched her face.
Yes, she believed him.
He was safe.
And Aunt Polly was glad to believe that he
had been good.
The summer evenings were long.
Tom walked along the street, whistling like
a bird.
Then he stopped whistling.
He had met a stranger, a boy a little larger
than he was.
The boy’s clothes were new and good, and
he was wearing shoes.
Tom would wear shoes and good clothes like
these only to church on Sunday.
Tom looked and looked.
The boy’s clothes seemed to become better
and better, and his own clothes seemed to
grow poorer.
Neither boy spoke.
If one moved, then the other moved.
But they moved only to the side, in a circle.
They remained face to face and eye to eye.
Then Tom said:
“I can beat you!”
“Try.”
“I can.”
“No, you can’t.”
“Yes, I can.”
“I can.”
“You can’t.”
“Can!”
“Can’t!”
A moment of quiet.
Then Tom said:
“I could beat you with one hand.”
“Do it.
You say you can do it.”
“That hat!”
“Hit it off my head if you can.”
“I will.”
“You are afraid.”
“I am not afraid.”
“You are.”
“I am not.”
More moving in a circle.
Now they were shoulder to shoulder, each trying
to make the other fall back.
And then suddenly they were both rolling in
the dust.
Each pulled at the other’s hair, and each
hit the other’s nose.
And now through the dust Tom appeared, sitting
on the new boy, beating him with hard, closed
hands.
“Have you had enough?” said he.
The boy tried to get free.
He was weeping with anger.
“Have you had enough?”
Then the new boy said, “Enough!”
Tom let him stand up and walk away.
But as soon as Tom turned, the new boy threw
a stone, hitting Tom’s back.
Therefore, Tom followed him home, and waited.
The boy did not come out again.
His mother came and said that Tom was a bad
child.
She told him to go home.
It was late when Tom got there.
Very quietly and carefully, he entered through
a window.
But his aunt was waiting for him.
She had learned from Sid about Tom’s afternoon.
Now she saw his clothes and she knew that
he had been fighting.
She knew what she must do.
Tom would work all day on Saturday.
Strong Desire — Wise Action
Saturday morning came.
All the summer world was bright and fresh
and full of life.
Tom appeared in front of the house with paint
and a big brush.
He looked at the fence, and all joy left him.
A deep sadness settled upon his heart.
The fence was long and high.
He wet the brush and moved it along the top
board.
He did it again, and did it again.
He looked at what he had done.
The painted part was very, very small.
The whole fence was very large.
He sat down.
He felt that he could not continue.
Jim, a boy who worked for the family, came
through the gate.
He was going to get water, and he was singing
happily.
Tom said, “Jim, I will get the water, if
you will paint.”
Jim said, “No.
I must get the water.”
“Are you afraid of Aunt Polly?
She won’t hurt you.
She talks about it, but talk never hurts.
It never hurts except when she weeps, also.
You should not be afraid of her.
Jim, I will give you one of my playthings.
And I will show you my foot.
I will show you where I hurt it.”
Jim was only human.
He took the plaything and he put his head
down to look at the foot.
In another moment he was running down the
street.
Tom was painting as fast as possible.
And Aunt Polly was returning to the house.
But Tom began to think of the pleasure planned
for this day.
His hands moved more slowly.
Soon the other boys would come and laugh at
him for working.
From his pocket he took everything that he
owned.
He looked at it.
There was nothing of real value.
It was not enough to buy another boy’s help.
At this dark moment, a wonderful idea came
to him.
It was like a great, bright light.
He took his brush and went quietly to work.
Ben Rogers appeared soon.
Tom had been especially afraid of Ben’s
laugh.
Ben was eating an apple.
Also as he walked, he was making noises like
those of a big riverboat.
He would shout loudly.
Then he would say, “Ding-dong-dong,” like
a bell.
Then he would shout again, and say, “Ding-dong-dong,”
again, and make other strange noises.
He was the boat, and he was the captain of
the boat, and the boat bell.
“Turn her!” he shouted.
“Slow her!
Stop!”
He made a slow, careful turn, came close beside
Tom, and stopped.
Tom continued his painting.
He did not look at the boat.
Ben said, “Hello!
You are in trouble.”
No answer.
Tom moved his brush gently, and looked at
the result.
Ben came nearer.
Tom wished for the apple, but he did not turn
from his work.
Ben said:
“Hello, you must work, must you?”
Tom turned suddenly.
“Oh, Ben, is it you?
I did not see you.”
“I am going swimming, I am.
Do you wish you could go with me?
Or would you rather work?”
Tom said, “What do you mean?
Work?”
“That is work.”
Tom returned to his painting.
“It may be work and it may not be.
But it is fine for Tom Sawyer.”
“Do you mean that you enjoy it?”
“Enjoy it?
Does a boy have a chance to paint a fence
every day?”
Here was a new idea.
Ben stopped eating his apple.
Tom moved his brush—stepped away to look
at the result—added a little paint here
and there—stepped away again.
Ben watched.
He was more and more interested.
Then he said:
“Tom, let me paint a little.”
Tom thought.
Then he said, “No, Ben.
Aunt Polly wants this fence to be perfect.
If it was the fence behind the house, you
could help.
But this fence, beside the street, must be
done very carefully.
There is not one boy in a thousand who can
do it well.”
“Oh, Tom, let me try.
Only a little.
I will be careful.
Tom, I will give you part of my apple.”
“No, Ben.
I am afraid—”
“I will give you all of it!”
Tom gave the brush to Ben slowly, but with
joy in his heart.
And, while the boy who a few moments before
had been a riverboat worker and became hot
in the sun, Tom sat under the tree, eating
the apple and planning how to get more help.
There were enough boys.
They came along the street, stopped to laugh,
but remained to paint.
After Ben, Bill Fisher painted.
Then Johnny Miller came.
Each one paid to be allowed to work.
In the middle of the afternoon, Tom was very
rich.
He had many playthings, a small cat with one
eye, a piece of broken blue glass, and much
more.
And he had not worked, and the whole fence
had been painted three times.
There was no more paint.
With more paint, Tom would soon have owned
everything belonging to the other boys.
And the other boys in the village would have
owned nothing.
Tom had discovered a great law of human action.
A man or a boy will desire something if it
is not easy to get.
Tom as an Army Officer — Delightful Sadness
Tom went to report to Aunt Polly.
She was sitting beside an open window.
She was half asleep, and she was holding the
sleeping cat.
She was surprised to see Tom.
She thought that he had run away from his
work long ago.
Tom said, “May I go and play now, Aunt?”
“Already?
How much have you done?”
“It is all done, Aunt.”
“Tom, is that true?
It makes me sad if you do not tell the truth.”
“It is true, Aunt; it is all done.”
She went to see, and her surprise was very
great.
“You can work when you want to, Tom.
But you do not often want to.
Go and play.
But remember to come home again.”
And she gave him a large apple.
She did not see him take a piece of cake as
he passed through the kitchen.
Tom hurried to the center of the village.
There two armies of boys had met for a battle.
Tom was the leader, the General, of one army,
and his good friend, Joe Harper, was the General
of the other.
Tom and Joe did not fight.
They sat together and sent their orders to
the armies.
When the battle was finished, they agreed
to have another battle on another day.
Then the armies marched away, and Tom started
to go home alone.
As he passed Jeff Thatcher’s house, he saw
a new girl in the garden.
She had blue eyes and yellow hair.
She was beautiful.
Tom had loved a girl named Amy Lawrence.
A week ago she had said that she loved him.
He had been happy and proud.
But now in a moment she was gone from his
heart.
He watched the new girl until she discovered
him.
Then he looked at other places, as if he had
not seen her.
And he began to jump, and dance, and walk
on his hands, so that she would continue to
watch him.
She walked toward the house, and Tom’s heart
was sad.
But she threw a flower over the fence.
Then she was gone.
Tom looked around.
There was no person to see him.
Slowly he picked up the flower.
He put it under his shirt, near his heart.
And he stayed near the fence until darkness
came.
Then he went home to eat.
He was full of joy.
His aunt wondered why.
Later that evening his brother Sid was a bad
boy.
He took some sweets.
But his aunt did not believe that Sid could
be bad.
She gave Tom the blow that she should have
given to Sid.
She learned the truth later, and was sorry.
But she said nothing to Tom.
Therefore, Tom was very sorry for himself.
He began to wish that he would die.
She would feel sorry then.
He could see himself being carried home from
the river, dead, his hair wet, his troubles
past.
He went out into the darkness, and went to
the river.
It would be good to drown—if he could drown
without pain.
He thought of his flower, and took it from
inside his shirt.
Would the new girl be sad if he died?
Would she put her arms around him?
Or would she turn coldly away?
This picture brought him much delightful suffering.
He kept it a long time in his mind.
Then he started home.
He stopped near the Thatcher house.
There was a light in one window.
Was that the new girl’s room?
He lay down on the ground below the window,
with her flower in his hands.
He would lie there and die in the cold.
In the morning, she would look out the window,
and see him.
The window opened suddenly.
He heard the voice of a woman who worked for
the Thatchers.
She threw water out of the window, and it
fell on him.
Tom jumped up and ran.
Sid opened his eyes and saw Tom, ready for
bed, looking at his wet clothes.
Tom’s wild eyes made Sid afraid.
He did not dare to speak.
But he would remember and tell his aunt.
Going to Sunday School
The sun rose upon a quiet world and looked
warmly down upon the peaceful village.
The family began the day by praying together.
Then Tom did his Sunday studying.
He was trying to learn some words from the
Bible.
Sid had already finished his studying, but
Tom was slow.
His mind was busy with other things.
Tom was learning five verses.
Some verses are long and some are short.
Tom had found five short verses.
Aunt Polly’s daughter, Mary, helped him,
and after a time, he could say the verses
without looking at the book.
Mary gave him a knife for studying so well.
It was not a good knife, but it was a knife.
Tom was deeply delighted.
Then Mary helped him to dress in his Sunday
clothes.
He hoped that she would forget his shoes.
But she did not.
When they were ready, the three children went
to Sunday school.
With his whole heart, Tom wished not to go.
Mary and Sid enjoyed going.
At the church door Tom stopped to speak to
a friend.
“Billy, do you have a yellow ticket?”
“Yes.”
“Will you sell it to me?”
“What will you pay for it?”
Tom offered enough, and received the ticket.
Then Tom stopped other boys, and bought more
tickets, some red and some blue.
He was busy with this buying for about ten
minutes.
Then he went into the church.
These tickets were given for learning the
Bible verses.
A blue ticket was given for two verses.
A red ticket was equal to ten blue tickets.
A yellow ticket was equal to ten red tickets.
And for ten yellow tickets, for learning two
thousand verses, the Sunday school teacher
gave the student a Bible.
It was a wonderful day when a boy or a girl
received one of these Bibles.
Perhaps Tom did not want the Bible.
But he did want the wonderful experience of
receiving it.
“Now, children,” the teacher said, “sit
up as straight as possible, and listen.
That is what good little boys and girls should
do.”
While the teacher was talking, three gentlemen
and a lady entered the church.
The lady was leading a child.
When Tom saw this small girl, waves of happiness
went over him.
He began hitting other boys, pulling their
hair, doing everything to force the new girl
to look at him and smile.
He was quickly forgetting the water the woman
threw from her window the night before.
The gentlemen and the lady went to the front
of the church and sat down there.
Then the teacher told who they were.
One gentleman was Mr. Thatcher, who lived
in the village.
All knew him.
But one was his brother, the great Judge Thatcher.
He had traveled, he had seen the world, he
came from a large town twelve miles away.
The teacher wished that on this day he could
give some boy or girl a Bible.
He would have been proud to do that.
The famous Judge Thatcher would know, then,
that this was a fine Sunday school.
But no child had enough yellow tickets.
At this moment, when hope was dead, Tom Sawyer
came forward.
He had nine yellow tickets, nine red tickets,
and ten blue tickets.
It was like a storm coming from a clear sky.
The teacher had not expected Tom to gather
so many tickets in ten years, but here were
the tickets.
It was the surprise of the year.
The teacher knew that it was strange.
He could not understand how it had happened.
He did not believe that Tom had learned two
thousand verses.
He did not believe that Tom had learned twelve
verses.
The other boys watched Tom.
All wished that they, too, had enough tickets
for a Bible.
Some boys suffered more deeply, because they
had sold Tom their tickets.
They were able to understand what had happened.
Tom had become rich by letting other boys
whitewash the fence.
He had been rich enough to buy their tickets.
And now anger filled them.
They saw clearly what fools they had been.
Tom stood in a place of honor beside the Judge.
The Judge put his hand on Tom’s head and
called him a fine little man.
Tom could not speak.
His breath would not come.
His heart was shaking.
This was partly because the Judge was a great
man, but it was chiefly because the Judge
was her father.
The Judge asked his name.
“Tom.”
“Is that all of it?”
“Thomas.”
“But you have more, perhaps?
Another name?”
“Tell the gentleman your other name, Thomas,”
said the teacher.
“Thomas Sawyer.”
“That is a good boy.
You are a fine, manly little fellow.
Two thousand verses is a very, very great
many.
And you never can be sorry that you learned
them.
Learning makes great men and good men.
You will be a great man and a good man some
day, Thomas.
Then you will remember this day.
Then you will be glad that you went to Sunday
school.
Now, Thomas, tell me and this lady some of
what you have learned in your Bible verses.
We are proud of little boys who learn.
Now, you know the names of the twelve great
followers of Jesus Christ.
Tell us the names of the first two.”
Tom’s face became red and he looked down
at his feet.
The teacher knew that Tom could not answer.
But he felt that he must speak.
He said: “Answer the gentleman, Thomas.
Do not be afraid.”
Tom said nothing.
“Surely you will tell me,” said the lady.
“The names of the first two followers of
Jesus Christ were—”
Tom remembered two names from the Bible.
He did not remember who the people were, or
what they had done.
But the two names were always together.
He shouted them now:
“DAVID AND GOLIATH!”
But David and Goliath had not been among the
twelve great followers of Jesus Christ.
Their story was in a different part of the
Bible.
David was a boy and Goliath was a man of very
great size and strength.
They were enemies.
And David had killed Goliath.
Let us be kind enough to look away from the
rest of this scene of Tom Sawyer in Sunday
school.
In Church
The bell of the small church began to ring.
The people began to gather to hear Mr. Sprague
speak to them.
Mr. Sprague spoke to them in church every
Sunday, and prayed with them.
The Sunday-school children now sat with their
fathers and mothers, who would try to keep
them quiet.
Aunt Polly came, and Tom and Sid and Mary
sat with her.
Tom was placed as far as possible from the
open window and the interesting summer scenes
outside.
Other people came in and went to their seats.
There were the old and poor.
There were the middle-aged.
There were the pretty girls in bright summer
clothes, and the young men, with their eyes
following the girls.
There was Mrs. Douglas, whose husband died.
She was rich and good-hearted, and she lived
in the big house on Cardiff Hill.
There was Mufferson, the “Good Boy” of
the village.
He came to church with his mother.
All the other mothers talked of his goodness.
All the other boys did not like him.
Now the bell was heard again, and then the
church became very quiet.
They were ready to begin.
They began with a song.
After the song, Mr. Sprague read a very long
list of meetings to come in the following
week.
Then he prayed.
He prayed for many things and for many people.
He prayed for the church, and for the little
children of the church, and for the other
churches of the village, and for the village,
and then for the whole country, and for the
Government, and then for people of far countries.
Tom did not enjoy hearing Mr. Sprague pray,
but he knew he must remain quiet.
While Mr. Sprague prayed, a flying bug stopped
on the back of the seat in front of Tom.
It moved its front legs together, one over
the other.
It put them around its head, and seemed to
pull until Tom thought that the head would
separate from the body.
It used its back legs to clean its wings.
And it did all this slowly, as if knowing
that it was safe.
And indeed it was safe.
Tom did not dare to reach for it.
He believed that his soul would be destroyed
suddenly if he did such a thing while Mr.
Sprague was praying.
But with the last words, his hand began to
move forward.
When the last word came, the bug was in his
hand.
But his aunt saw this.
She told him to let the bug fly away.
Then Mr. Sprague began a longer talk.
He read the words he was saying and Tom counted
the pages as he turned them.
After church, Tom always knew how many pages
there had been.
He did not often know what had been said.
But this morning Tom was interested for a
little while.
Mr. Sprague talked about future peace in the
world.
The strong and powerful nations, he said,
would be friends of the weak.
The strong, he said, would be like a strong,
wild animal of the forest.
The weak would be like a weak animal of the
farm.
But the strong animal would not hurt the weak
animal.
They would lie down beside each other, in
peace.
They would be so gentle and friendly that
a little child could lead them.
Tom wished to be that child.
Then there was no more talk about animals.
Again Tom began to suffer.
He remembered a valuable object that he carried,
and he took it from his pocket.
It was a large black bug in a small box.
The bug quickly took a painful hold on Tom’s
finger.
The next moment, the bug was on the floor,
on its back, and Tom’s finger was in his
mouth.
The bug lay there, moving its legs, but it
could not get on its feet again.
Tom could not reach it.
It was too far away.
But he watched it.
Other people, also not interested in Mr. Sprague’s
words, found pleasure in watching the bug.
Then a dog entered the church.
He was sad at heart.
He wanted some new, different thing to do.
He saw the large black bug, and his tail lifted
and moved a little, happily.
He looked at the bug carefully; walked around
it; put his nose nearer; lay down with the
bug between his front feet; and began to sleep.
His head moved down, it touched the bug, and
the bug took a painful hold on his nose.
The dog cried loudly, shaking his head.
And the bug fell again on the floor, on its
back.
People sitting near were laughing gently,
with their faces covered.
Tom was completely happy.
The dog seemed like a fool, and perhaps felt
like a fool.
There was anger in his heart, also.
He went near the bug again and began jumping
at it.
Moving in a circle, he jumped again and again.
Then he had had enough of jumping.
He found a smaller bug and followed it for
a while.
Then he had had enough of the smaller bug.
Forgetting the large black bug, he sat down
on it.
With a wild cry of pain, he went running around
the church.
The bug kept its hold.
The dog ran across the front of the church,
and across the back.
His cries grew louder and louder.
Then he jumped into his owner’s arms.
His owner threw him out a low window.
Then slowly the sound of his voice grew softer
and was gone as he ran quickly away.
Now all the people in the church had red faces
and were trying not to laugh.
Mr. Sprague had stopped speaking.
He began again, but it was not easy for him
to continue.
Here and there a laugh could be heard.
All were glad when it was time to go home.
Tom Sawyer went home quite happy.
Church was a pleasure when something different
happened.
There was only one thing that he did not like.
He was glad to let the dog play with his bug.
But the dog should not have carried it away.
A Talk of Devils — Happy Hours
The next morning Tom was very sad.
This was the beginning of another week of
slow suffering in school.
He usually began this day wishing that there
had been no Saturday and no Sunday.
Because of them, school seemed more painful
to him.
He lay in bed, thinking.
If he were sick, he could stay home.
He thought carefully about all parts of his
body, but he could discover no sickness.
Then he looked at his foot.
His foot had been hurt.
He had an idea.
He began to cry as if with pain.
But Sid, in his bed across the room, continued
to sleep.
Tom’s voice grew louder.
Now he seemed to feel real pain in his foot.
No result from Sid.
Tom said, “Sid, Sid!” and tried shaking
him.
This time the result was good.
When Tom cried again, Sid sat up and looked
at him.
He said, “Tom!
What is wrong?”
No answer.
Now Sid tried shaking Tom.
Tom said, “Oh, do not do that, Sid.
It hurts me.”
“I must call Aunt Polly.”
“No.
Do not call her.”
He cried loudly again.
Then he said, “I will forget everything
bad that you have done to me, Sid.
When I am dead—”
“Oh, Tom, are you dying?”
“Give my cat with one eye to that new girl,
and tell her—”
But Sid was gone.
He ran to his aunt.
“Oh, Aunt Polly!
Tom is dying!”
“Dying!
I can’t believe it!”
But she ran.
Her face was white with fear.
At the bedside she cried, “Tom!
Tom, what is wrong?”
“It is my foot, Aunt.
Where I hurt it.
The doctor must cut it off.”
The old lady sat down in a chair and laughed
a little, then wept a little, then did both
together.
Feeling better, she said, “Tom, you stop
that, and get out of bed.”
Tom stopped crying and the pain stopped, too.
As he walked to school, he met Huckleberry
Finn.
Huckleberry’s father was always drunk.
None of the mothers in the village liked Huckleberry.
But all the children liked him.
They wished that they dared to be like him.
Tom also wished that he could be like Huckleberry.
He had been ordered never to play with him.
Therefore, he played with Huckleberry every
time that it was possible.
Huckleberry was always dressed in old clothes.
The clothes were always too big for him.
His hat was full of holes.
The bottom of his coat touched the ground.
He came and went as he wished.
He did not sleep in a bed; he did not sleep
in a house.
He did not go to school or to church.
He could go swimming or fishing when and where
he might choose.
He was the first boy to wear no shoes in the
early summer.
He was the last boy to wear shoes in the early
winter.
He never washed.
He had everything that any boy could desire.
Tom said, “Hello, Huckleberry.”
“Hello yourself.”
“What is that?”
“Dead cat.”
“Let me see him, Huck.
Where did you get him?”
“From a boy.”
“Why do you want him, Huck?”
“To take off these warts.”
Huckleberry showed Tom the small spots of
thick, hard skin on his hands.
“I take them off with a bean, Huck.”
“Yes.
Bean is good.
I have done that.”
“How did you do it?”
“You take the bean and break it in two pieces.
Then you cut the wart and get some blood.
Then you put the blood on half the bean.
You make a hole in the ground.
You put that half of the bean in the hole,
and cover it with earth.
You must do this in the middle of the night
where two roads cross and when the moon is
dark.
Then you burn the other half of the bean.
The piece of bean with blood on it will try
to pull the other half to it.
And that helps the blood to pull the wart,
and it is gone from your hand.”
“Yes, that is right, Huck.
Although when you put the bean in the ground,
you should say, ‘Down, bean; off, wart;
appear no more.’
But how do you take off warts with a dead
cat?”
“You wait until the dead body of some bad
person has been put in the ground.
Then you take your cat and you go to that
place before the middle of the night.
At the middle of the night a devil will come
to carry the dead man away.
Perhaps two or three devils will come.
You can’t see them.
You can only hear a sound like the wind.
Or perhaps you can hear them talk.
And when they take the body away, you throw
the cat after them.
You say, ‘Devil follow body, cat follow
devil, warts follow cat.’
That will take off any wart.”
“Did you ever try it?”
“Not yet.”
“Huck, when are you going to do it?”
“Tonight.
I think that they will come to get old Hoss
Williams tonight.”
“But they put him in the ground Saturday.
The devils would take him Saturday night.”
“The devils can’t come until twelve.
At twelve on Saturday night, it is Sunday.
Devils can’t come on Sunday.”
“I never thought of that.
Let me go with you?”
“If you won’t be afraid.”
“Afraid!
Will you come to my house and call to me?
Make a noise like a cat.”
“Yes.But you answer Another night I came
to your house,saying, ‘Meow, meow,’ like
a cat.
But you never answered.
And your neighbor threw stones at me.”
“Aunt Polly was watching me.
But I will ‘meow’ this time.”
Tom continued walking to school.
He went in quickly, and sat in his seat.
The teacher looked at him.
“Thomas Sawyer!”
Tom knew that trouble was coming when his
whole name was used.
“Why are you late again?”
Tom looked around the room.
He saw the new girl.
No girl sat in the seat beside her.
And girls sat in all the other seats on the
girls’ side of the room.
He said, “I stopped to talk with Huckleberry
Finn.”
All the children looked at Tom.
It was very foolish to say that to a teacher.
“Thomas Sawyer, I never heard more surprising
words.
Take off your coat.”
The teacher had a supply of thin branches
cut from a tree.
He used and broke several of these while beating
Tom’s back.
Then he ordered, “Go and sit with the girls!”
The new girl turned her back toward Tom.
Then, after a short time, she turned toward
him, and she saw an apple on the table in
front of her.
She moved it away.
Tom gently moved it toward her.
She moved it away again.
Tom returned it.
Then she let it remain where he had placed
it.
Now Tom began to make a picture on a piece
of paper.
He held one hand over it while he worked and
she could not see it.
She tried to see.
He seemed not to notice her interest.
Then she said, “Let me see.”
He showed her.
It was a picture of a house.
It was not good, but she thought that it was.
“It is nice.
Now make a man.”
The man was bigger than the house.
“It is beautiful.
Now make me.”
He made a picture of another person.
“That is very nice.
I wish that I could make pictures.”
“I will teach you.
At noon.
Do you go home to eat?”
“I will stay if you stay.”
“Good.
What is your name?”
“Becky Thatcher.
What is yours?
Oh, I know.
It is Thomas Sawyer.”
“That is my name when they beat me.
I am Tom when I am good.
You call me Tom, will you?”
“Yes.”
Now Tom began writing something, hiding it
with his hand.
She asked to see.
“Oh, it is nothing.
You do not want to see it.”
“Yes, I do.”
“You will tell what it is.”
“I promise never to tell.”
“Oh, you do not want to see!”
“I will see.”
She put her small hand on his, and then Tom
let her pull the writing away.
She read these words: “I love you.”
“Oh, you bad thing!”
And she hit his hand.
But her face showed pleasure.
At this moment the boy felt a hand on his
ear, and a pull lifting him from the seat.
He was returned to his usual seat.
The whole school laughed.
But although Tom’s ear hurt, his heart was
joyful.
An Agreement Is Made
At noon Tom ran to Becky and said softly in
her ear:
“Start to go home with the others, and then
return here.
I will do the same.”
Soon both had returned.
Now they were alone in the school.
They sat together, and Tom put his hand on
Becky’s, guiding it.
They made a picture of another house.
Then they talked.
Tom was filled with happiness.
He said, “Becky, were you ever engaged?”
“What does that mean?”
“Did you ever promise to marry any boy?”
“No.”
“Would you like to be engaged?”
“What do you do?”
“You tell a boy that you will marry him.
Then you kiss.
That is all.
It is easy.”
“Why do you kiss?”
“They always do that.
Do you remember what I was writing?”
“Yes.”
“What was it?
Shall I tell you?”
“Yes—but not now.
Tomorrow.”
“No.
Now.
I will say it quietly, Becky.
Close to your ear.”
He put his arm around her and said the words
quietly.
“Now you tell me.”
She made him turn his face away.
Then she came near.
Her breath moved his hair as she said, “I—love—you!”
Then she jumped away from him and ran around
the seats, with Tom running after her.
He caught her in a corner, with her hands
over her face.
But her hands dropped.
Tom kissed her and said, “Now it is all
finished, Becky.
And always after this you can’t love any
boy except me or marry any boy except me.”
“And you can’t marry any girl but me.”
“Certainly.
That is part of it.
And we will walk to school together.
Because we are engaged.”
“It is nice.
I never heard of it before.”
“Oh, it is fine.
Me and Amy Lawrence—”
The big eyes told him that he had said the
wrong thing.
“Oh, Tom!
I am not the first that you were engaged to!”
She began to weep.
“I do not love her now.
I do not love any girl except you.”
More weeping.
Tom took from his pocket the thing he valued
most.
It was a ball-shaped object, of no worth,
but as bright as gold.
“Becky, take this.”
She hit it from his hand to the floor.
Then, filled with anger, Tom marched out of
the school and over the hills and far away.
He would return no more that day.
Becky had not really wanted him to go, and
when he did not return within a few moments,
she called, “Tom!
Come back!”
Then she wept again.
Tom Decides What to Do
Half an hour later Tom was beyond Mrs. Douglas’
house on Cardiff Hill.
He entered a thick forest, went to the center
of it, and sat down under a tree.
He was very sad.
He wished that he could die—for a short
time.
But soon he began to think again of living.
He would go far away, to countries across
the sea.
How would Becky feel then?
He would be a soldier, and return famous,
after many wars.
No, he would join the Indians, and hunt and
fight with them in the Far West.
But no, there was something better.
He would sail across the seas in a long, fast
black ship.
He would follow other ships, take the gold
and silver they carried, then send them to
the bottom of the sea.
That was it!
He would be a pirate, famous in the whole
world.
Tom Sawyer the Pirate!
Yes, it was decided.
He would start his journey the next morning.
At this moment he heard a call from far away
in the forest.
He went to a place, very near, where he kept
some of his things.
From this place he took a long knife made
of wood.
He tied it to his side.
He was not Tom Sawyer now.
He dreamed he had become a famous leader named
Robin Hood who had lived with his men hundreds
of years before, in another forest.
He advanced slowly, moving carefully from
behind one tree to another.
Believing for the moment that he really was
Robin Hood, he said:
“Stay where you are, my men.
Do not move until I call.”
Now Joe Harper appeared.
He, too, had a long wooden knife.
Tom called, “Stop!
Who comes here into Sherwood Forest?
No person enters my forest until I say that
he may!”
“I am Guy of Guisborne,” said Joe Harper,
continuing the game.
“I go where I wish.
Who are you?”
“I!
I am Robin Hood, as you shall soon know when
you lie dead there on the ground.”
“Are you indeed that famous man?
Gladly will I fight with you.”
They took their two long knives, and began
a slow, careful fight.Then Tom said, “Now
fight faster.”
They were soon hot from their efforts.
“Fall!”
Tom said.
“You must fall!”
“You fall!
I am fighting better than you.”
“But the story of Robin Hood says that I
kill you.
Turn and let me hit you in the back.”
Joe turned, received the blow, and fell.
“Now,” Joe said, rising, “you must let
me kill you.”
“I can’t do that.
It is not in the story.”
“It should be.”
“Joe, you can be Robin Hood for a while.
I will be Robin’s enemy, and you can kill
me.”
This was agreeable, and more fighting followed.
Then Tom became Robin Hood again, and he was
hurt, and all his blood ran from his body.
And Joe, who had now become all of Robin Hood’s
men, watched with tears in his eyes as Robin
Hood died.
Then the boys went home.
They were sad because Robin Hood had lived
so long ago.
They would have liked living with him in Sherwood
Forest better than being President of the
United States.
Indian Joe Explains
At nine that night Tom and Sid were sent to
bed as usual.
They prayed, and Sid was soon asleep.
Tom was waiting.
Time passed very slowly.
Little noises came out of the darkness.
The cry of a far off dog was heard in the
night air, and was answered by another dog.
By that time Tom was asleep.
Then there came, among his dreams, the call
of a cat.
A neighbor opened a window.
Tom heard this, and a minute later he was
through his window.
He “meowed” as he went.
Then he jumped.
Huckleberry Finn was there with his dead cat.
In half an hour the boys were in the graveyard.
The graveyard was on a hill, a mile and a
half from the village.
There was an old board fence around it.
A light wind sounded in the trees, and Tom
was afraid that the sound came from the spirits
of the dead.
The boys talked little.
The time and the place and the quiet were
heavy on their hearts.
They found the new grave and sat down under
the branches of three big trees near it.
They waited a long time.
After a while, Tom felt that he must talk.
“Huck, do you believe that the dead people
are pleased to have us here?”
“I wish I knew.”
“Huck, do you think Hoss Williams hears
us talking?”
“His spirit hears us.”
“I wish I had said Mr. Williams.
But all the people said Hoss.”
“You must be careful how you talk about
dead people, Tom.”
There was no more talk for a while.
Then Tom touched Huck’s arm.
“Did you hear it?
There it is again!
Now you hear it.”
The two held each other with fast-beating
hearts.
“Tom, they are coming!
What shall we do?”
“I do not know.
Will they see us?”
“Tom, they can see in the dark, like cats.
I wish I had not come.”
“Oh, do not be afraid.
We are doing nothing.
If we are completely quiet, perhaps they won’t
see us.”
“I will try, Tom.
But I am shaking.”
“Listen!”
The sound of voices came from the far end
of the graveyard.
“Look!
See there!” said Tom.
“What is it?”
“It is devil-fire.
Oh, Tom, this is very bad.”
Some dark shapes came near, carrying a light.
Huckleberry said, shaking more, “It is the
devils.
Three of them.
Tom, we are in great trouble.
Can you pray?”
“I will try.”
Tom began to pray.
“Tom!
They are human!
That is old Muff Potter’s voice.
He is drunk, as usual.
He won’t see us.”
“Huck, I know another voice.
It is Indian Joe.”
“Devils would be better than that half-Indian.
What do they want here?”
Then the boys were quiet, because the three
men had arrived at the new grave.
“Here it is,” said the third voice.
In the light the boys saw the face of young
Doctor Robinson.
He was so near that the boys could have touched
him.
“Hurry, men!” he said.
“The moon may appear from behind the clouds.”
The other two men began opening the grave.
For a while no sound was heard except the
sound of their work.
Then they came to the box which contained
the body.
They opened it and lifted the body out of
the box.
The moon appeared and the dead man’s face
could be seen.
Potter held up a knife.
“Now, Doctor, the thing is ready.
And here it stays unless you pay us five dollars
more.”
“You have your money,” the doctor said.
“You and your father once sent me to jail,”
Indian Joe said.
“Five years ago.
Do you think I would forget?
Now you pay!”
The doctor hit him suddenly, and Indian Joe
fell.
Potter dropped his knife.
“You hit my friend!” he said.
He jumped at the doctor and the two began
fighting.
Now Indian Joe was on his feet again.
He picked up Potter’s knife, and began moving
like a cat, around and around the fighters.
He was watching for a chance to strike the
doctor.
Suddenly the doctor was free.
He picked up a board and used it to strike
Potter, who fell quickly to the ground.
At the same moment Indian Joe saw his chance.
The whole length of his knife went into the
doctor’s body.
The doctor fell, partly on Potter, covering
Potter with his blood.
Clouds covered the moon, and the two boys
ran into the darkness.
When the moon appeared again, Indian Joe was
looking down at the two men lying on the ground.
The doctor made some sounds that were not
possible to understand, and then, after a
long breath, he was quiet.
The Indian said, “Now that is finished!”
He put the knife in Potter’s right hand.
Then he sat down and waited.
Soon Potter began to move.
His hand closed on the knife.
He looked at it and let it fall.
Then he sat up and looked at the doctor’s
body.
“What happened, Joe?” he said.
“It is a bad business,” said Joe.
“Why did you do it?”
“I!
I never did it!”
Potter was shaking.
“I was drunk.
I do not remember what happened.
Did I do it, Joe?
I never wanted to do it.”
“He hit you and then you did it.
But you have always been good to me, Muff
Potter.
I won’t tell.”
“Oh, Joe, I will bless you for that as long
as I live.”
And Potter began to weep.
“This is no time for weeping.
You go that way and I will go this way.
Move, now.”
Potter started running.
Joe stood watching him.
“He forgets his knife because he is drunk.
When he remembers, he will be afraid to return
for it.”
Two or three minutes later the dead doctor,
the body from the grave, the opened box, were
alone under the moon.
The quiet was complete again.
The Promise — The Result of Fear
The two boys ran toward the village.
They looked behind them often, afraid that
they were being followed.
After a while, they came to the edge of the
village.
There stood an old building which was not
used.
They ran through the open door and fell to
the ground.
“Huckleberry, what do you think will happen
now?”
“If the doctor dies, they will hang Indian
Joe.”
Tom spoke.
“Who will tell about it?
You and I?”
“If we did, and if Indian Joe did not hang,
he would kill us.”
“I was thinking that, Huck.”
“Let Muff Potter tell if he is fool enough.
He is usually drunk enough.”
Tom continued to think.
Then he said, “Huck, Muff Potter does not
know what happened.
The doctor had hit him with that board.
Huck, are you sure that you won’t tell?”
“Tom, we can’t tell.
You know that.
Indian Joe would drown us like two cats if
we told.
Tom, we must promise never to tell.
It must be a strong promise.
With writing.
And blood.”
Tom agreed with all his heart.
This idea was what must be done.
It was deep and dark and fearful.
This was the hour and the place to do it.
He found a clean broad piece of wood.
In his pocket he found something to write
with.
The moon was his light.
Painfully he formed the words:
Huck Finn and Tom Sawyer promise they will
never tell about this, and they wish they
may die in their footsteps if they ever tell.
Then each boy cut a finger and signed in blood
TS and HF.
Tom helped Huck to write his H and F.
Then they made a hole in the ground near the
wall of the building.
They placed the piece of wood in the hole
and covered it with earth.
Now they were certain.
Their mouths would never speak about what
their eyes had seen.
When Tom entered his house through his bedroom
window, the night was almost gone.
He took off his clothes very quietly and lay
down.
He believed, happily, that his aunt would
never know that he had been away.
But Sid was not asleep.
The next morning his aunt gave him some food.
Then she wept, and she asked him why he hurt
her old heart.
She wished to help him to be good.
She tried and tried, but she could try no
more.
A thousand beatings would have been easier
for Tom.
He wept.
He promised to be good.
But he felt that she did not believe his promises.
He went to school, and there the teacher beat
him and Joe Harper, because they had run away
from school the day before.
Then he went to his seat.
A hard object, covered in paper, was waiting
for him there.
He opened the paper.
Inside was the bright, shining ball that looked
like gold that he had given to Becky Thatcher.
This was too much.
Now his heart was broken.
Tom’s Troubled Mind
At noon the whole village suddenly knew the
fearful news.
The story traveled quickly from man to man,
group to group, house to house.
The schoolteacher closed the school.
The knife had been found.
It was known to be Potter’s knife.
And Potter had been seen washing himself in
a small stream, in the very early morning.
When seen, he had run away.
All this was very strange, especially because
Potter almost never washed.
All the people in the town were slowly going
toward the graveyard.
Tom joined them.
He did not wish to go, but something seemed
to force him.
He arrived at the fearful place, and saw the
scene again.
It seemed a hundred years since he had seen
it before.
A hand touched his arm.
He turned.
His eyes met Huckleberry’s.
Both looked away.
Were they being watched?
Now Tom began to shake, because he saw Indian
Joe.
Then Muff Potter appeared.
A few people saw him.
They shouted.
The crowd separated and Potter walked through.
A village law officer was holding his arm.
Potter’s eyes showed his fear.
When he stood beside the dead doctor, he put
his face in his hands and began to weep.
“I did not do it, friends,” he said.
“I did not do it.”
“Who said that you did?”
a voice shouted.
Potter lifted his face and looked around without
hope.
He saw Indian Joe, and said, “Oh, Indian
Joe, you promised me that you would never—”
“Is this your knife?”
It was held by the law officer for him to
see.
Potter began to fall.
Men caught him and let him go slowly down
to the ground.
Then he said, “I thought that I should come
and get—” He stopped, shaking.
Then he said, “Tell them, Joe.
Tell them.”
Indian Joe told his story.
Huckleberry and Tom stood, not able to speak,
and with eyes wide with fear.
They expected the skies to open with a sudden
storm, to strike down Indian Joe.
But he finished his story and stood there,
living and whole.
They wished to tell the truth, but they did
not dare.
During a week after this, Tom could not sleep
well.
One morning Sid said, “Tom, you talk in
your sleep so much that I can’t sleep half
the night.”
Tom’s face became white and he looked away.
“This is bad,” said Aunt Polly.
“There is something in your mind, Tom.
What is it?”
“Nothing.”
But Tom’s hand was shaking.
He could not lift his cup.
“And you say fearful things!”
Sid said.
“Last night you said, ‘It is blood, it
is blood!’
You said that again and again.
Then you said, ‘Do not hurt me.
I will tell!’
Tell what?”
Aunt Polly said, “I understand.
It is that killing.
I dream about it also.”
Mary said that she also dreamed about it,
and then Sid stopped talking.
Slowly Tom’s mind grew quieter and his sleep
was easier.
Almost every day, during this bad time, Tom
went to the jail window and gave Potter some
small gift.
Then he felt happier.
The village people wanted to put Indian Joe
in jail also.
Like Muff Potter, he had been helping the
doctor to carry away that dead body from its
grave.
But the people did nothing.
All were afraid of Indian Joe.
Tom Shows His Kindness
Tom had a new and great trouble.
Becky Thatcher was ill.
He was afraid that she might die.
The joy of life was gone.
He played no games.
He was not interested in anything.
His aunt did not know what was wrong.
She tried to find some help for him.
She was always reading about health.
She read about how to go to bed, and how to
get up from bed, what to eat, and what to
drink, and what clothes to wear for good health,
and how to think for good health.
She believed all that she read.
When she read something new, she wanted to
try it.
She took Tom outside in the early morning
and poured cold water over him.
Then she covered him with a wet cloth and
put him to bed, with heavy covers over him.
When he was so hot that water formed on his
skin, she was happy.
She thought that this would help him.
But Tom became sadder and sadder.
She tried pouring hot water over him instead
of cold.
She tried less food.
Soon Tom stopped fighting against what she
did.
And then she was sure that he was very ill
indeed.
Next, she heard of something new named Painkiller.
She put some in her own mouth, to taste it.
It was like a mouthful of fire.
She gave some to Tom and watched him.
This Painkiller had a strong result.
The boy was wildly interested.
He acted as if she had built a fire under
him.
She knew that she had found the right thing.
And Tom knew that it was time for him to act.
He thought of several plans.
He decided to say that he liked Painkiller.
He asked for it so often that his aunt gave
the whole container to him.
Now he could have Painkiller at any time.
She did not know that everyday he put some
in a hole in the floor.
One day as he was doing this, the cat came
in and seemed to want some of the Painkiller.
“You do not want it, Peter.”
But Peter continued to seem to ask for it.
“Are you sure?”
Peter was sure.
“You have asked for it, and I will give
it to you.
I am a kind boy.
But if you do not like it, remember that you
asked.”
He opened the cat’s mouth and put in some
Painkiller.
Peter jumped high into the air and cried a
wild cry.
Then he started going around and around the
room, running against chairs and tables.
Next he stood on his back feet and danced,
with cries of joy.
Then he went faster around the room again.
Aunt Polly arrived.
He rolled over and over, gave one last great
cry, and jumped through the open window.
Tom was on the floor, weak from laughing.
“Tom, what is wrong with the cat?”
“Cats always do that to show their joy.”
But Aunt Polly saw the Painkiller.
She knew what had happened.
She caught Tom’s ear and pulled him up,
then hit him with her hand.
“Why did you do that to the cat?”
“Because I am sorry that he has no aunt
to care for him.”
“Has no aunt!
Why do you say that?”
“Because if he had an aunt she would give
him a drink that burned his mouth and not
think of his feelings.
She would say, if the drink was good for a
human, it would be good for a cat.”
Aunt Polly thought.
If it hurt a cat, it might hurt a boy, also.
She put her hand on Tom’s head.
“I was trying to help you.”
“And I was trying to help Peter.
And it helped him.
I never saw him move so fast.”
He was smiling at her now.
“Oh, Tom!
I will not give you any more Painkiller.
Go to school.
And try to be a good boy.”
Tom was early at school.
He was often early now.
Today, as he often did, he waited at the gate.
He did not play.
He was sick, he said.
And he seemed sick.
Jeff Thatcher came down the road, and Tom’s
face was brighter.
But quickly it was dark again.
Jeff was alone.
When Tom saw a girl’s dress far away, he
watched and watched.
But the girl was never the right one.
He entered the school and sat down to suffer.
Then one more dress came through the gate.
Tom’s heart jumped.
The next moment he was outside again, shouting,
laughing, running after other boys, jumping
over the fence, standing on his head.
He was doing all this to make Becky Thatcher
watch him.
She never looked at him.
Was it possible that she did not see him?
He came running and shouting.
He threw a boy’s hat over the schoolhouse.
He ran through a group of boys, and then he
fell at her feet.
She turned away with her nose raised high
in the air.
“Some people always want other people to
look at them!”
His face became red.
He stood straight and walked quietly away.
The Young Pirates
Tom had decided now.
He was sad and without hope.
He was a boy with no friends.
No person loved him.
He had tried to do what was right, but they
would not let him.
Yes, they were forcing him into a bad life.
He could now choose nothing else.
He had come far from the village.
He heard the distant school bell, and he knew
that he would never, never hear it again.
Tears fell from his eyes.
Here he met his best friend, Joe Harper.
Joe’s eyes were filled with anger, and it
was easy to see that there was a great and
sad purpose in his heart.
Tom said that he was going to travel around
the world, never to return to the village.
He hoped that Joe would not forget him.
And Joe had come to say the same to Tom.
They were two souls with only one thought.
Joe’s mother had beaten him.
But he had done nothing.
She plainly wished him to go away.
Therefore, he was going.
He hoped that she would be happy now.
He hoped that she would never be sorry about
sending her boy into the cold world to suffer
and die.
The two boys walked together.
They agreed to be like brothers.
They would never separate until they died.
They began to plan.
They decided to be pirates.
Three miles south of the village, there was
an island in the river.
The Mississippi River was a mile wide there.
The island was long and not very wide, and
it was covered with trees.
No people lived on it, and few people lived
on the river’s shore near the island.
It would be a good place for pirates.
Then they met Huckleberry Finn, and he joined
them.
They talked, and then they separated.
They would meet again beside the river two
miles north of the village at twelve that
night.
Tom knew where they would find a small boat.
They would take it.
Each boy would bring food and other useful
things, if possible.
Tom arrived with meat and a few other things.
He stopped among the trees on a hill above
the meeting place.
There were many stars, and it was very quiet.
The great river lay like an ocean at rest.
Tom listened a moment, but the quiet was broken
by no sound.
Then he whistled gently.
The whistle was answered from below.
Tom whistled two more times and was answered
again.
Then a voice said:
“Who goes there?”
“Tom Sawyer the Black Pirate.
Name your names.”
“Huck Finn the Red-Handed and Joe Harper
the Destroyer of the Seas.”
Tom had taken these names from his best-loved
books.
“Speak the word.”
Two voices spoke together: “BLOOD!”
Tom went down the hill to join them.
The Destroyer of the Seas had also brought
meat, and Finn the Red-Handed had some tobacco.
The Black Pirate said that they must also
have fire.
They went to a large riverboat that was near,
and they took some of the fire burning there.
They knew that there were no men on the boat.
The boatmen were all in the village.
But the boys moved very quietly and carefully.
Pirates must be pirates.
With Tom as captain of their ship, they left
the shore and went into the middle of the
river.
From here they let the moving river carry
them along.
They passed the distant village.
Two or three lights showed where it was, peacefully
sleeping.
The Black Pirate stood in the boat looking
for the last time at the scene of his early
joys and later sufferings.
He wished that his aunt could see him now,
facing the fearful future with a smile on
his lips.
After two hours their boat touched the island.
There was an old sail in the boat.
They spread this over their supplies, under
the trees.
They would sleep in the open air, as pirates
should.
They built a fire and cooked some meat.
It seemed wonderful to be eating in that wild,
free manner in the forest, far from other
people.
They said that they would never return to
a village or town again.
After eating, they lay on the ground, talking.
The fire lighted their faces and the trees
near them with a red light.
Huck prepared to smoke some of his tobacco.
Soon he was blowing out a cloud of smoke,
and the other pirates were wishing that they
could do the same.
Huck said, “What do pirates do?”
Tom said, “Oh, they enjoy life.
They follow other ships and catch them and
burn them.
They take the money from those ships and put
it in a deep hole in the ground on their island.
And they kill the people on the ships.”
“They carry the women to the island,”
said Joe.
“They do not kill the women.”
“No,” Tom agreed.
“Pirates are good.
They do not kill the women.
And the women are always beautiful.”
“And their clothes are covered with gold
and silver,” said Joe.
“Whose clothes?” said Huck.
“The pirates’.”
Huck looked down at his clothes.
“I am not dressed right for a pirate,”
he said.
“But these are my only clothes.”
The other boys told him that the fine clothes
would come later, when they began their adventures.
Slowly their talk ended.
The Red-Handed went to sleep quickly.
The Destroyer of the Seas and the Black Pirate
could not sleep so quickly.
They began now to have some doubt.
Had it been wrong to run away from home?
Had it been wrong to take the meat?
The meat did not belong to them.
They decided that they would never again take
what did not belong to them.
And with that decided, these pirates also
were peacefully asleep.
Island Life — Tom Quietly Leaves
Opening his eyes, Tom wondered where he was.
He sat up and looked around.
Then he remembered.
It was cool and the light was the gray color
of early morning.
There was a delightful feeling of rest and
peace in the deep quiet of the forest.
A thin blue breath of smoke rose from the
fire.
Joe and Huck were yet asleep.
Now, far away, a bird called.
Another answered.
Slowly the cool gray of the morning changed
to white.
More sounds were heard.
The life of the forest began to show itself
to the watching boy.
Bugs appeared and started their day’s labors.
Birds were making many noises now.
A big blue bird stopped very near to Tom.
It turned its head to one side, and sat watching
its strange new neighbors.
Small animals appeared and they also looked
at the boys and seemed to be talking to them.
Perhaps they had never seen a human being
before.
Perhaps they did not know whether or not to
be afraid.
Tom called to the other pirates.
Within a few moments they were all playing
in the river near the shore.
Their boat had been carried away, but this
pleased them.
They were certain now that they would never
return to their village.
Happy and hungry, they built their fire.
Huck had found some good water to drink.
While Joe cooked some meat, Tom and Huck went
to the river and caught some fish.
Joe cooked these with the meat.
No fish had ever tasted so good.
Then Huck smoked.
After that, they all started to walk through
the trees to see what they could discover.
They found much to delight them, but nothing
surprising.
The island was almost three miles long and
a quarter of a mile wide.
It was very near to the shore on one side,
but far from the shore where their village
was.
They played in the river often.
It was the middle of the afternoon before
they returned to their fire.
They ate some meat again and then they sat
in the shade to talk.
But the talk soon stopped.
The quiet, the loneliness, were beginning
to change their happiness.
They began to be sad.
Tom and Joe were thinking of home.
Finn the Red-Handed, who had no home, was
thinking of the places where he usually went
to sleep.
But they did not speak to each other of this
weakness.
Now they heard a distant sound.
They looked at each other, and listened.
There was a long quiet, and then the sound—Boom!
Then a long, long quiet, and then again, Boom!
“We must go and see.”
They jumped up and ran to the shore nearer
the town.
The trees there were small, and grew thickly.
Through them, the boys looked across the water.
They saw a big riverboat.
It was the boat that crossed the river many
times every day.
Now it was coming slowly down the river.
It was crowded with people.
There were many small boats around it.
Then from the riverboat came a cloud of white
smoke, and then another Boom!
“I understand now!” said Tom.
“Some person is drowned!”
“That is right,” said Huck.
“They did that last summer when Bill Turner
was drowned.
A big gun makes that Boom!
And then the body rises to the top of the
water.”
“I wish that I was on that riverboat now,”
said Joe.
“I wonder who is drowned,” said Huck.
They continued to listen and watch.
Then a thought came into Tom’s mind like
a sudden light.
“Boys, I know who is drowned.
They are looking for us!”
This was a wonderful thing to know.
Hearts were breaking for them.
Tears were falling.
People were sorry that they had not always
been kind to them.
The whole town was talking about them.
This was fine.
It was good to be a pirate.
All doubt of that was gone.
As darkness came, the riverboat returned to
her usual business.
The pirates returned to their fire.
They were joyful that they were so important
and were causing so much sadness.
They caught more fish to eat.
Then they talked about what the village people
were thinking and saying.
But as the night grew darker, they stopped
talking and sat looking into the fire.
Tom and Joe thought of persons at home who
were not enjoying all of this.
Joe began to speak of returning to the village.
Tom laughed at him.
Huck joined with Tom.
Huck fell asleep.
Then Joe fell asleep.
Tom sat for a long time, watching the others.
Then he stood up.
He found two pieces of thin wood on which
he could write.
After writing on the wood, he put one piece
in Joe’s hat.
He put the other in his pocket.
Then, carefully, he moved away among the trees.
When he knew that they could not hear him,
he began to run toward the river.
Tom Learns What Is Happening
A few minutes later Tom was walking into the
water toward the shore where the riverboat
was tied.
The stream was not wide here, but it was strong.
It carried Tom south.
But after a while he arrived at the river’s
edge.
He found a good place and pulled himself out
of the water.
He began walking north through the trees,
near the shore.
He arrived at an open area, across the river
from the village.
The riverboat was lying near.
Everything was quiet under the stars.
Watching with both his eyes, he entered the
water again.
There was a small boat tied behind the large
boat.
Soon he was pulling himself into the small
After a minute or two he heard a bell.
The riverboat began to move.
He knew that this was the last time it would
cross the river that night.
Twelve minutes later the boat stopped.
Tom was quickly in the water again, swimming
to the shore.
Soon he had jumped over the fence behind his
aunt’s house.
He looked through a window into a lighted
room.
There sat Aunt Polly, Sid, Mary, and Joe Harper’s
mother.
They were talking.
They were beside the bed, and the bed was
between them and the door.
Tom went to the door and opened it quietly.
He thought that he might be able to go inside
without being seen.
He began moving carefully, on his knees.
“I feel a wind.
Is that door open?” said Aunt Polly.
“How strange!
Many strange things are happening now.
Sid, go and close the door.”
Quickly Tom went under the bed.
Sid did not see him.
“But,” said Aunt Polly, “he was not
bad.
He was only wild and full of life, like any
young animal.
He did not wish to do bad things.
And no boy ever had a kinder heart.”
She began to weep.
“My Joe was the same.
He was not really bad.
And he was always kind.
And now I shall never see him again!”
“I am sorry now for so many things!
Only yesterday the cat—” Weeping, Aunt
Polly told about the cat and the Painkiller.
Tom was weeping a little now.
He could hear Mary weeping also.
Had he really always been a good boy?
It was quite surprising to think this.
But now he was beginning to believe it.
He wished to rush out from under the bed.
He wished to fill his aunt with joy.
But he remained still and listened.
Their small boat had been found five or six
miles down the river.
Now hope for them was gone.
On Sunday the whole village would pray in
the church, for the boys’ souls.
Mrs. Harper went home.
Sid and Mary went to bed.
Then Aunt Polly prayed for Tom.
Her words and her old voice were filled with
love.
Tom’s tears began falling again.
Then she got into bed.
She talked to herself and she turned over
again and again.
Tom remained quiet for a long time.
But at last she was still.
Now the boy came out and looked down at her.
He loved her and he was very sorry for her.
He took from his pocket the piece of wood
with his writing on it.
He placed it on a table.
She would see it there in the morning.
But then a new thought came to him.
He considered it.
His face grew bright.
He put the wood into his pocket again.
Then he kissed his aunt’s lips, and went
out the door.
He returned to the river and to the riverboat.
There was a man who guarded the boat, but
he would be sleeping.
Tom knew that.
It was easy to take the small boat.
He got into it and moved it first up the river.
Then he crossed to the other shore.
He had often crossed the river in a small
boat, and he knew how to do it.
He considered taking the small boat to the
island.
A real pirate would keep the boat.
But people would try to find it, and they
might find the boys also.
He got out of the boat and walked south along
the shore.
At daylight he could look straight across
the stream and see the island.
He rested.
Then he entered the water.
Soon he was on the island.
He heard Joe say:
“No.
Tom is true, Huck.
He will return.
What has he been doing?
I wonder.”
“Here I am!”
cried Tom, stepping out from among the trees.
In a short time they had caught more fish
and were eating them.
Tom told his adventures.
Then Tom found a place in the shade.
There he was able to sleep until noon.
A Night Surprise
The boys played in the water and on the shore.
But the next day Joe was very sad.
Would he ever be happy again?
It did not seem possible.
Huck also was sad.
Tom was not happy, but he tried to seem happy.
He had something interesting to tell them,
but he was not yet ready to speak.
However, if they did not feel better soon,
he would be forced to tell it.
He said, trying to seem happy, “I think
there have been pirates on this island before.
How would you like to find an old box full
of money?
We should go and hunt for it.”
But the other boys were not interested.
Joe said, “Boys, I want to go home.
It is very lonely here.”
“Oh, no, Joe.
You will feel better soon,” said Tom.
“Think of the good fishing here.”
“I am not interested in fishing.
I want to go home.”
“But, Joe, this is the best swimming place.”
“I do not want to swim.
I want to go home.”
“Baby!
You want to see your mother.”
“Yes, I do want to see my mother.
And you would want to see your mother, if
you had a mother.
I am not a baby.”
“But you like it here, Huck?
You want to stay?
You and I will stay?”
Huck said, “Y-e-s.”
He did not seem very sure.
“Let Joe go, if he wants to go,” Tom said.
“We do not need him.”
Joe began to walk into the water to start
swimming toward the shore where the village
was.
Tom looked at Huck.
Huck looked away.
Then Huck said, “I want to go, Tom.
We can go, Tom, can’t we?”
“I won’t!
You can go.
But I am going to stay.”
Huck started to walk sadly away.
Tom felt a strong desire to follow.
He hoped that they would stop, but they went
slowly forward.
Suddenly, Tom knew that it had become very
lonely and quiet.
He ran after the other boys, shouting, “Wait!
Wait!
I want to tell you something.”
They stopped and turned, and he began walking
into the water toward them.
They listened to him without an answering
word or smile.
But after a while they began to understand.
Then they shouted with joy.
They said that he should have told them his
plan sooner.
That night, after eating, Tom wanted to learn
to smoke.
Joe wanted to try, also.
With Huck’s help, they began.
Tom said, “This is easy.
I could have learned long ago.”
“This is nothing,” said Joe.
“I could smoke all day.
I do not feel sick.”
Tom said, “I wish that the other boys could
see us now.
Listen.
We won’t tell them.
And some time when they are with us, I will
say, ‘Joe, I want to smoke.’
And you will say, ‘My tobacco is not very
good.’
And I will say, ‘It does not need to be
good if it is strong enough.’
And then we will both start smoking and surprise
them.”
“That will be good, Tom!
I wish we could do it now!”
“And we will tell them that we learned to
smoke when we were pirates.
And they will wish that they had been here!”
The talk continued.
But after a little time, there was less talk.
Joe said, “I have lost my knife.
I am going to find it.”
Tom said, “Let me help you.
You go that way and I will go this way.
No, do not come, Huck.
We can find it.”
Huck sat down again and waited an hour.
Then he was lonely, and he went to find his
friends.
Both were very white, both were asleep.
But he knew that what had troubled them was
gone now.
That night they did not talk much.
When Huck began to smoke, they said no, that
something they had eaten made them feel a
little sick.
In the middle of the night Joe opened his
eyes and called to the other boys.
There was a strange heaviness in the air,
and it made them all afraid.
The night was very hot, but they moved near
to each other and near to the fire.
Sitting like that, they waited.
A sudden light filled the sky.
It turned night into day, and then it was
gone.
A fearful noise rolled across the sky and
slowly ended far away.
A breath of cold wind passed.
The sudden light appeared and went away again,
and the noise that followed came sooner and
was more fearful each time.
A little rain began to fall.
“Quick, boys, run for cover!”
Tom shouted.
They jumped up and ran, each toward a different
place.
A strong wind rushed through the trees.
The bright light appeared and went away, appeared
and went away again.
The fearful noise seemed never to stop.
And now a heavy rain came down and ran in
streams over the ground.
The boys shouted, but their voices were lost
in the storm.
After some time they came to the place where
the old sail was and pulled it over them.
It was a wild night for these boys.
The wind caught the old sail and carried it
away.
Trees fell.
The storm increased until they feared that
it might carry the island away.
But the storm grew weaker and weaker and peace
returned.
The boys found that their fire was not quite
dead.
They put more wood on it, making it burn brightly
again.
They found some of their meat and cooked it.
Then they sat by their fire until morning,
talking of the night’s adventure, because
there was no dry place for them to sleep.
When the sun began to shine, they rested in
its warm light, near the shore.
There they remained, sleeping, until the sun
became too hot.
Then they had something to eat again.
The desire for home was now strong in all
of them.
Tom tried to find a new game to interest them.
He found one.
They were not pirates now.
They were Indians and had many fierce battles.
However, when the day ended, they smoked together,
as Indians always did to show that they were
at peace.
And two of them learned joyfully that now
they could smoke a little tobacco without
being sick.
The Success of Tom’s Plan
But there was no joy in the little town that
same afternoon.
The village was more quiet than usual.
The people had little to say to each other.
The children had no pleasure in their games.
Becky Thatcher was walking near the school.
She thought, “Oh, I wish I had not returned
to Tom that bright, shining ball he gave me!
I have nothing to help me remember him.
He is gone now, and I shall never, ever see
him again.”
She walked away with tears rolling down her
face.
Then a large group of boys and girls, friends
of Tom and Joe, came to the school and stood
looking over the fence into the yard where
they had played together.
They spoke of things Tom and Joe had said,
and of things Tom and Joe had done.
They tried to learn who was the last to see
the two boys.
The children who were the last to talk with
Tom and Joe felt very important indeed.
One boy who also wished to feel important
said, “I had a fight with Tom Sawyer, and
he was stronger than I was.”
But most of the boys could say that.
The next morning the church bell did not stop
as it usually did after calling the people
to church.
It continued to ring.
The people from the village gathered.
Outside the church they talked, but in the
church all was very quiet.
The little church was filled with people.
After a long time Aunt Polly entered, followed
by Sid and Mary and by the Harper family.
All were wearing black clothes.
The other people in the church stood up.
They remained standing while the two families
walked to the front of the church and sat
down.
It was quiet again.
All prayed, and then a song followed.
Now the church leader began to talk of the
boys.
He told how good they had been.
People were sorry to remember that they had
not seen the truth earlier when they had thought
that these boys were bad.
Tears were falling from all eyes.
The sound of the church door, opening slowly,
was heard.
One pair of eyes, and then another, turned
to look.
Then all in the church seemed to turn at the
same time, and people rose and watched while
the three dead boys walked to the front of
the church.
Tom was first, Joe next, and last came Huck.
They had been listening to every word!
Aunt Polly, Mary, and the Harpers put their
arms around Tom and Joe.
Huck stood alone, not knowing what to do.
He started to move away, but Tom stopped him
and said:
“Aunt Polly, this is not right.
Some person must be glad to see Huck.”
“And some person shall be.
I am glad to see him, dear boy!”
She put her arms around him also.
And now Huck felt more strange than before.
“Sing!
And sing your best!”
cried the church leader.
And all the people did sing.
There had never been such singing in that
church.
Tom Sawyer, the Pirate, knew that no moment
in his life could be prouder than this.
Tom’s Wonderful Dream
That was Tom’s great plan—to return home
with the other pirates and go to the church
to hear people pray for their souls.
They had returned across the river in the
darkness the night before, and had stayed
in the forest until nearly daylight.
They had entered the church and finished their
sleep there before the people came.
Then they appeared at the most important moment.
The next morning Aunt Polly and Mary were
very loving toward Tom.
He had everything that he wanted to eat.
There was much more talk than usual.
Aunt Polly spoke:
“We can laugh now, Tom.
But you were not very kind to let me suffer.
You came across the river to surprise us in
the church.
Why could you not come across the river to
tell me that you were not really dead?”
“Yes, you could have done that, Tom,”
said Mary.
“I believe that you would have done it,
if you had thought of it.”
“Would you, Tom?” said Aunt Polly.
Her face was brighter at this thought.
“Would you, if you had thought of it?
I hope that you love me enough to do it.
Did you think of it?”
“Tom is always rushing,” Mary said.
“He never thinks.”
“Sid would have thought.
And Sid would have come.
Tom, some day you will be sorry.
You will wish that you had cared more for
me.
But then it will be too late.”
“I do care for you,” said Tom.
“I wish that I had thought.
But I dreamed about you.”
“A cat does as much as that.
What did you dream?”
“I dreamed that I saw you sitting there
by the bed.
Sid and Mary were sitting with you.
And I dreamed that Joe Harper’s mother was
here.”
“Indeed she was, one night.
Did you dream any more?”
“Yes.
But I can’t remember all of it.”
“Try, Tom.
Try to remember.”
“You said that the door must be open because
you could feel the wind coming in.
You said that was strange.
And you told Sid—”
“What did I tell Sid, Tom?”
“You told him—oh, you told him to close
the door.
And you were talking about me.
I remember better now.
You said that I was not bad.
You said that I was only wild and full of
life like a—like any young animal.”
“I never heard anything like this in all
my life!
And some people say that dreams are never
true.
Tell me more, Tom.”
“And then you began to weep.”
“Yes, I did.
I did.”
“Then Mrs. Harper began to weep.
She said that Joe was good, also.
And then you told about my giving the Painkiller
to the cat.
And then there was a lot of talk about finding
our bodies, and about praying in the church
on Sunday.”
“It is all true!”
“And Mrs. Harper went home.
And you prayed for me—and I could see you
and hear every word.
And you went to bed.
And I was very sorry for you.
And I had a letter for you.
It was on a piece of wood.
On the wood were the words, ‘We are not
dead—we are away being pirates.’
I kissed you on the lips and went away again.”
“Did you, Tom?
Did you?”
She took him in her arms.
“It was very kind, but it was only a dream,”
said Sid.
“Be quiet, Sid!
And Tom, here is a big apple for you.
And now, you children, go to school.”
Tom walked slowly and proudly, feeling that
all eyes were watching him.
Smaller boys followed him, proud to be seen
with him.
Boys of his own size tried not to show that
they knew he had been away.
But they did know.
They wished that they had sun-browned skin
like his.
They wished that they were as famous.
Tom decided that he no longer was interested
in Becky Thatcher.
Being famous was enough pleasure for him.
When Becky arrived at school, Tom seemed not
to see her.
But he saw her playing with other boys and
girls.
He saw that she often came near him and looked
at him.
And he began talking to Amy Lawrence.
Becky tried to go away from him, but her feet
would not do as she wished.
They carried her near to the group around
Tom.
She said to one of the girls, “Mary, where
were you yesterday?
I wanted to tell you about the picnic.”
“Oh, whose picnic?”
“My mother is going to let me have one.”
“I hope that she will let me come.”
“It will be my picnic and I may ask those
that I want.
I want you and all my friends to come.”
She looked at Tom, but he was talking to Amy
Lawrence.
Now the others in the group began asking if
they could go to the picnic.
Soon all had asked except Tom and Amy.
Tom turned away.
Becky’s legs were shaking and tears came
to her eyes.
She would not let the others see her sadness.
She went away alone, to think of what to do.
When Tom saw her again, she and a boy named
Alfred Temple were sitting together, looking
at a book.
Now Tom suddenly wanted to stop talking to
Amy.
He escaped from her and went to look again
at Becky and Alfred Temple.
And Becky seemed not to see Tom.
But she saw him, and she saw that he was suffering,
and she was glad.
“That Alfred Temple!”
Tom thought.
“Alfred Temple and his fine clothes!
I will catch you!
I will take you and—”
He began hitting the air as if he were fighting
with the other boy.
At noon Tom went home.
Becky again looked at the book with Alfred,
hoping that Tom would see them.
But Tom did not appear.
Suddenly she began to weep.
She left Alfred and walked away.
Alfred followed, hoping to find some way to
make her happy again.
But she said: “Go away!
I never want to see you again!”
Alfred was quick to understand.
Becky had been trying to make Tom suffer.
Alfred went into the school.
He saw one of Tom’s books—and thought
how he could hurt Tom.
He opened the book to the page they were to
study that afternoon.
He destroyed the page in a manner that would
make it seem that Tom had done it.
Becky, looking in the window, saw him do it.
She thought of telling Tom.
Then she decided that she would not.
She would let the schoolteacher beat Tom for
what had happened to his book.
Tom Tells the Truth
Tom arrived at home feeling very sad, and
his aunt’s first words made him feel no
better.
“Tom, I ought to beat you!”
“Aunt Polly, what have I done?”
“I went to see Mrs. Harper to tell her about
your dream.
Joe had already told her that you were here
that night.
Tom, I do not know what to think of a boy
like you.
I believed your story of your dream.
I expected her to believe it.
Why did you let me be such a fool?”
“Aunt Polly, I wish I had not done it.
I did not think.”
“Oh, child, you never think.
You never think of anything but yourself.
You could think enough to come here and laugh
at our troubles.
You could think to tell that story of a dream.
But you could not think to save us from suffering.”
“Aunt Polly, I know that it was bad.
But I did not plan to be bad.
And I did not come here that night to laugh
at you.
I came to tell you that we were not drowned.
I did not want you to be sad.”
“Tom, I would be thankful to believe that.
But I doubt that you had such a thought.”
“Yes, I did, I did.
It is the truth.
I wanted to save you from being sad.”
“Then why did you not tell me, child?”
“You began talking of Sunday and all the
people praying for us in the church.
And I began thinking about going there on
Sunday.
And I put my letter in my pocket and went
away.”
“What letter?”
“The letter to tell you that we were pirates.
I wish now that you had opened your eyes when
I kissed you.”
“Did you kiss me, Tom?
Are you sure?”
“Yes, I did, Aunt.”
“Why did you kiss me?”
“Because I loved you and you were weeping
in your sleep and I was sorry.”
The words sounded like the truth.
The old lady said, “Kiss me again, Tom!
And then go to school.”
When he was gone, she looked at his little
coat.
In the pocket she found his piece of wood
with the writing on it.
She read the words, with tears falling from
her eyes.
Then she said, “Now I could forget anything
bad that the boy does.
I could forget a million bad things.”
Becky Has a Problem
Tom was happy again.
He started walking to school, and soon saw
Becky Thatcher, also going toward the school.
Quickly he ran to her and said:
“I am sorry I acted as I did this morning,
Becky.
I won’t ever be like that again.
Please let us be friends.”
The girl stopped and looked into his face.
“Go away, Mr. Thomas Sawyer.
I will never speak to you again.”
Then she started walking again.
Tom was so surprised that he could think of
nothing to say.
And he was filled with anger.
If she were a boy, he knew that he would fight
her.
Becky was also full of anger.
She was thinking of the pleasure of watching
the teacher beat Tom for destroying a page
in his book.
She did not know that she would soon have
trouble also!
The teacher had a book that he was studying.
Every day he would read some pages when he
was not busy.
Every boy and girl in the school wondered
about this book, but none had ever seen its
pages.
Now, as Becky passed the teacher’s table,
she saw the book.
She opened it and began to look at it.
Then Tom appeared at the door.
Becky hurried to close the book.
Her hand caught the page, and suddenly, it
was in two pieces.
Becky began to weep.
“You are bad, Tom Sawyer, to come and watch
me!
And now you will tell the teacher, and he
will beat me, and what shall I do!
I have never been beaten in school.
But I know what is going to happen to you.
You wait and you will see!”
Then, weeping, she ran outside.
Tom said to himself: “What a fool a girl
is!
What is a beating in school?
That is nothing.
And I will not tell who opened the book.
The teacher will ask who did it.
He will call each name.
And when he says the right one, he won’t
need an answer.
He will see the answer in her face.”
School began, and soon Tom’s book was discovered.
He said that he had not destroyed the page,
but the teacher did not believe him.
Tom had his beating.
Becky watched, trying to feel happy about
this.
But she almost stood up to tell the truth
about Alfred Temple.
An hour passed.
The boys and girls were all busy with their
books.
The teacher opened his book.
Tom looked at Becky.
He had seen small and hunted animals in the
forest.
Now Becky seemed like one of them.
He wished that he could help her.
But what could he do?
The next moment the teacher stood before the
school.
Every eye turned away from his.
All the boys and girls were afraid of him.
He spoke:
“Who did this to my book?”
There was not a sound.
“Benjamin Rogers?”
“No.”
“Joe Harper?”
“Amy Lawrence?”
“No.”
“Gracie Miller?”
The next name was Becky Thatcher.
Tom was shaking from head to foot.
He saw her face, white with fear.
“Rebecca Thatcher, look at me!
Did you do this to my book?”
Tom jumped to his feet and shouted, “I did
it!”
All looked at him.
They could not believe what they had heard.
This was madness.
Tom stepped forward to take his beating.
The surprise, the thankfulness, the love shining
from Becky’s eyes seemed pay enough for
a hundred beatings.
Old Muff’s Friend
Summer had come.
For several months there would be no school.
Tom discovered that the days were too long.
He did not have enough to do.
He decided to make a record of everything
that happened.
But nothing happened during three days.
He decided that a record would be of no value.
Becky Thatcher had gone away.
During the summer she was living in another
town with her father and her mother.
The thought of the fearful killing in the
graveyard was always in Tom’s mind.
It was like a pain.
It would not go away.
Then Tom became sick.
For two long weeks Tom remained in bed without
knowing what was happening in the village.
He was very ill.
He was interested in nothing.
Then he seemed to be better.
But after a day he was ill again.
He was in bed for three more weeks.
In the warm, sleepy village something began
to happen.
A judge was coming to listen to the story
of the killing in the graveyard.
He would decide what to do about Muff Potter.
Every person in the village talked of this.
Tom could not escape from it.
Every word made his heart beat faster.
He was always afraid when people talked to
him about it.
He took Huck to a lonely place.
He wanted to be sure that Huck had not told
the story.
“Huck, have you told about—that?”
“About what?”
“You know what.”
“Oh.
No, I have not.”
“Never a word?”
“Never a word.
Why do you ask?”
“I was afraid.”
“Tom Sawyer, we would not live two days
if that story was told.
You know that.”
“Huck, could any person make you tell?”
“If I wanted that Indian Joe to drown me,
they could make me tell.”
“Good!
I think that we are safe if we do not talk.
But we should make another agreement.
It will be more sure.”
They made an agreement, as before, signed
in blood.
“What is the talk that you hear, Huck?”
“Talk?
It is all Muff Potter, Muff Potter, Muff Potter.
It makes me want to go where no one can see
me.”
“I hear the same talk.
They are going to hang him.
Do you feel sorry for him sometimes?”
“Almost always—almost always.
He has never done anything to hurt any person.
He only fishes to get some money so that he
can get drunk.
He is really good.
Once he gave me a fish, when he really did
not have enough for himself.
And he helped me at other times when I needed
help.”
“He helped me, also, Huck.
He helped me to catch fish.
I wish that I could get him out of jail.”
“We can’t get him out, Tom.
And if we did, they would catch him again.”
“Yes.
But I do not like to hear what they say.
For he never did—that.”
“And I do not like it, Tom.”
The boys talked for a long time, but it did
not make them happy.
As night came, they were near the little jail.
Perhaps they hoped that something good might
happen.
But nothing happened.
They went to the window and gave Potter some
tobacco.
They had done this before.
He was always very thankful for their gifts,
and his thanks always hurt them.
This time the hurt went deeper when Potter
said:
“You have been good to me, boys.
Better than the others in this town.
And I won’t forget, I won’t.
Often I say to myself, ‘I was good to all
the boys.
I showed them where the good fishing was.
I was their friend when I could be a friend.
And now they forget old Muff in his trouble.
But Tom does not forget, and Huck does not—they
do not forget him,’ I say, ‘and I won’t
forget them.’
“But, boys, I did a fearful thing.
I was drunk.
That is the only way that I can explain it.
Now I must hang for it, and that is right.
It is best, also.
I hope that it is.
But we won’t talk about that.
I won’t make you feel sad.
You have been my friends.
“But what I want to say is this.
Never get drunk.
Then you won’t ever be where I am now.
“Stand where I can see you.
It is a pleasure to see friendly faces when
a man is in trouble like this.
You are the only ones who come here.
Good friendly faces—good friendly faces.
Stand on each other’s shoulders and let
me touch your faces.
Good!
Let me touch your hands, also.
Little hands, and weak, but they have helped
Muff Potter.
And they would help him more if they could.”
Tom went home feeling very, very sad.
His dreams that night were full of fearful
things.
During the next two days he went to the town
meetinghouse.
The judge was there, listening to the story
of the killing.
Tom wished to go into the meetinghouse to
hear what was happening but he forced himself
to stay outside.
Huck was having the same experience.
They were careful not to meet each other.
They would go away from the meetinghouse,
but soon they would return.
Tom listened when people came out.
The news was always bad.
At the end of the second day people said that
Indian Joe’s story never changed.
There was no doubt what the judge would decide.
Tom was out late that night, and he entered
the house through the window.
He could not sleep for several hours.
All the people in the village went to the
meetinghouse the next morning.
This was to be the important day.
Potter, who appeared to have no hope, was
brought in.
All eyes were turned to him.
And Indian Joe was there, too.
Then the judge arrived.
Now a man was asked to tell what he knew about
the killing.
He said that he had found Muff Potter washing
his hands in a stream.
It was very early on the morning after the
killing.
Another man was asked to tell his story.
He told about finding the knife near the doctor’s
body.
Then a second man spoke about the knife.
He knew that it belonged to Potter.
A man who had studied law sat beside Muff
Potter.
He was there to help Potter.
But he asked no questions as these men told
their stories.
It seemed strange.
Was he not trying to prove that Potter had
not killed the doctor?
More men told their stories.
And the man beside Potter asked them no questions.
After a while, all the stories against Potter
had been told.
Then the man beside Potter stood up.
He spoke to the judge:
“Your Honor, we planned to prove that Muff
Potter was drunk that night.
We planned to prove that he did not know what
he was doing.
But we have changed our plans.
We wish to ask Thomas Sawyer some questions.”
Surprise appeared on every face, including
Potter’s.
Every eye was watching Tom.
He stood up and walked forward.
He looked very wild, because he was deeply
afraid.
The questions began.
“Thomas Sawyer, where were you on the night
of the killing at about the hour of twelve?”
Tom looked at Indian Joe, and he could not
speak.
The people listened, but the words did not
come.
After a few moments, however, the boy had
more strength.
Some of the people could hear as he said:
“In the graveyard!”
“Louder, please.
Do not be afraid.
You were—”
“In the graveyard.”
A cold smile appeared on Indian Joe’s face.
Then it was gone.
“Were you near Hoss Williams’s grave?”
“Yes.”
“Louder, please.
How near were you?”
“As near as I am to you.”
“Could you be seen?”
“No.
I was behind the trees at the edge of the
grave.”
“Was another person with you?”
“Yes.
I went there with—”
“That is enough.
We will call him when we need him.
Did you carry something there?”
Tom did not answer.
“Speak, my boy.
The truth is always honorable.
What did you carry there?”
“Only a—a—dead cat.”
There was a little laughing.
The judge ordered it to stop.
“We plan to show the bones of that cat.
Now, my boy, tell us everything that happened—tell
it as you wish, but tell it all and do not
be afraid.”
Tom began slowly.
Then his words came more and more easily.
Every eye looked at him.
With open lips the people listened to his
words, forgetting everything but his story.
Now he came to the end.
Interest became greater and greater.
“—and as the doctor hit Muff Potter with
the board and Muff Potter fell, Indian Joe
jumped with the knife and—”
Indian Joe jumped toward a window, striking
all who tried to hold him.
In a moment he was gone.
Days of Delight and Nights of Fear
Tom was famous once again.
The old people loved him and the young people
wished that they were like him.
His name appeared in the village newspaper.
There were people who believed that he might
some day become President of the United States,
if he escaped hanging.
Now all were kind to Muff Potter, forgetting
that they had not been kind before.
Tom’s days were days of joy, but his nights
were filled with fear.
Indian Joe was in all his dreams.
Poor Huck felt the same.
His name had not been called in the meetinghouse.
Because Indian Joe had run away, Huck’s
story was not needed.
But Huck was afraid that his part in the story
might be told.
Huck no longer trusted any human being, because
Tom had broken their agreement.
Every day, Muff Potter’s thanks made Tom
glad that he had told his story.
Every night he wished that he had not opened
his mouth.
Sometimes Tom was afraid that Indian Joe would
never be caught.At other times he was afraid
that Indian Joe would be caught.
He felt sure that he never could be safe again
until Indian Joe was dead and he had seen
the dead body.
Indian Joe had not been found.
The slow days passed.
With each day Tom became a little less afraid.
>Dead People and Spirits
There comes a time in every boy’s life when
he wants to hunt for gold and silver that
pirates have put deep in the earth.
This desire suddenly came to Tom.
He tried to find Joe Harper, but failed.
He tried to find Ben Rogers, but Ben had gone
fishing.
Then he met Huck Finn.
Tom took him to a place where they could be
alone, and he explained.
Huck agreed.
Huck always agreed to do anything that would
require time but not money.
He had no money, but much time.
“Where?” said Huck.
“Oh, almost anywhere.”
“Do you mean that there is money in the
ground everywhere?”
“No.
It is in very special places, Huck.
Sometimes on islands, sometimes in old boxes
under the end of a dead branch of an old tree,
but mostly under the floor in a house where
the spirits of the dead gather.”
“Who puts it there?”
“People who take it away from other people.”
“Why do they put it in the ground?
If I were rich, I would spend my money and
enjoy it.”
“I would, too.
But these people are different.”
“Do they never return and get it?”
“No.
They think that they will, but they forget
where it is.
Or they die.”
“How are you going to find it, Tom?
Where will you look?”
“We tried hunting for gold on the island
when we were pirates.
I know where there is a house full of spirits.
And there are old trees with dead branches
everywhere.”
“Is there gold and silver under every dead
branch?”
“No!
That would not be possible!”
“How do you know which one to choose?”
“Choose all of them!”
“Tom, we shall be working all summer!”
“What is wrong with that?
We might find a hundred dollars.
Or valuable stones, like diamonds.
How would you like that?”
Huck’s eyes were shining.
“Give me the hundred dollars, and you can
have the valuable stones, like diamonds.”
“Have you ever seen a diamond, Huck?”
“I do not remember that I have.”
“Kings have diamonds.
And I have heard that some of them are worth
a dollar or more!
Kings have hundreds of them.”
“I do not know any kings, Tom.”
“If you go to Europe you will see them jumping
around.”
“Do they jump?”
“Jump?
No.”
“Why did you say that they jumped?”
“Oh, I mean only that you will see kings
everywhere.
Not jumping.
Why should they jump?
But you will see many of them.”
The boys got some gardening things, used for
making holes in the earth.
Then they walked three miles to an old tree
with a single dead branch.
They were very hot and they sat in the shade
of another tree to rest and smoke.
Tom said, “Huck, if we find some money,
what will you do with it?”
“Spend it!
Before my father takes it and spends it.
What will you do with yours?”
“I will get married.”
“Married!
Tom, you would be a fool.
Think of my father and mother.
Fight!
They were fighting all the time.
I remember.”
“The girl I will marry won’t fight.”
“Tom, they are all the same.
Who is she?”
“I won’t tell you now.”
“If you marry, I will be more lonely than
I am now.”
“No, you won’t.
You will come to live with me.
Now we must start working.”
They worked for half an hour.
They found no box of money in the hole that
they were making.
They worked another half hour.
Then Huck said:
“Is the money always so deep in the ground?”
“Not always.
Perhaps this is not the right place.”
They began again on the other side of the
tree.
They worked without talking for a while.
Then Huck stopped to dry his hot face, and
said:
“Where do we try next?”
“There is an old tree on Cardiff Hill behind
Mrs. Douglas’s house.”
“That might be a good place.
But won’t she take the money away from us?
It is her land.”
“If you find money in the ground, it belongs
to you.
It does not belong to the owner of the land.”
That was fine.
The work continued.
After a while Tom said:
“We must be in the wrong place again.
Oh, I understand!
What a fool I was!
We must know where the shade of the dead branch
is under the light of the moon in the middle
of the night.
That is where we must hunt for the money.”
The boys stopped work, and returned to the
tree that night.
It was a lonely place.
They talked little.
When they felt that the right hour had come,
they found the shade in the moonlight under
the branch, and began to work.
Their interest was strong.
They worked fast.
The hole grew deeper and deeper.
But every time they found something hard in
the earth, it was only a rock.
After a while Tom said:
“Huck, we are wrong again.”
“We can’t be wrong.
We saw the shade of the branch.”
“But perhaps the time was not right.
We guessed.
We did not know.”
“We should stop trying,” Huck said.
“We never know the right time.
And I do not like the middle of the night,
with spirits of dead men around.
I feel that there is one behind me all the
time, and I am afraid to turn.”
“I feel the same, Huck.
And they almost always put a dead man in the
hole to guard the gold and silver.”
“They do?”
“Yes, they do.
I have always heard that.”
“Tom, I do not like to be where there are
dead people.
They will certainly cause trouble for us.”
“And I do not like it.
Suppose this one should lift his head?
He is only bones now.
Suppose his bones should speak to us.”
“Stop that talk, Tom!
That is a fearful idea.”
“Huck, I do not like this place.
We can try another.”
“Where?”
“The old house where the spirits gather.”
“Tom, I do not like spirits or their houses.
Dead people may speak to us, perhaps.
But they won’t come quietly behind us, as
spirits do, then suddenly make fearful noises.”
“But, Huck, spirits travel around only at
night.
We can go to the house in the day.”
“That is true.
But people never go near that house in the
day or the night.”
“That is because a man was killed there.
But nothing is seen except in the night.
And then only blue lights are seen.”
“When you see those blue lights, Tom, you
know that spirits are near.
Because only spirits use them.
I agree to go to the house, if you want to.
But I do not think that it is safe.”
Sleeping Spirits — A Box Full of Gold
On Saturday, soon after noon, the boys met
at the dead tree.
They smoked and talked in the shade.
Then they worked a little at their last hole.
They had no great hope.
But Tom said that people sometimes stopped
working when they had almost found the box
of gold.
Then another person came and with very little
work discovered it.
However, they failed to find anything.
But they felt that they had done everything
that was possible.
When they arrived at the old house, they were
first afraid to go in.
It was completely quiet there under the hot
sun, and very lonely.
Then they went without any noise to the door
and looked in, shaking with fear.
They saw a room with an earthen floor.
There was a place where a fire had been built,
windows without glass, and dust everywhere.
They entered.
They did not dare to speak.
Their ears were ready to hear any small sound.
Their legs were ready to carry them quickly
outside again.
Soon their fear became less.
They looked around with interest.
Then they wanted to look at the room above.
They found nothing up there and were starting
to go down when—
“Be quiet!”
Tom’s voice was shaking.
“What is it?”
Huck asked, becoming white with fear.
“There!...
Hear it?”
“Yes!...
We must run!”
“We can’t move.
They are coming toward the door.”
The boys were on the floor, looking down into
the room below through holes, sick with fear,
waiting.
Two men entered.
Both boys had seen one of the men in the village.
He seemed to be very old.
He had long white hair hanging around his
shoulders, and much white hair growing on
his face.
It seemed to the village people sad that he
could neither hear nor speak.
The other man was a stranger.
He was wearing very old clothes.
His face was not pleasant.
He was talking as they entered.
The two men sat on the ground, with their
backs against the wall.
“No,” said the other man.
“I have been thinking about it.
I do not like it.
They will catch us.”
“You fool!” said the man who was believed
not to be able to hear or speak.
“You are afraid!”
The boys were now shaking with fear.
This man was Indian Joe!
Joe said, “We were not caught before.”
“But that was different.”
“They may catch us here in this house,”
Joe said.
“I wanted to leave here yesterday.
But those boys were playing on Cardiff Hill.
They would have seen us.”
“Those boys” were Tom and Huck.
They were shaking again.
What would have happened to them yesterday,
if they had come to this house?
They wished that they had waited a year before
coming.
The two men had brought some food, and they
began to eat.
After a while Joe said, “When it is dark,
go home.
Wait there until you hear from me.
I will go into the village once again.
Then we will do the job we planned.
And then we will run.
Far away.
Now I need sleep.
You stay here as a guard.”
He was soon asleep.
And then the guard, too, was soon sleeping.
The boys took a long, thankful breath.
Tom said:
“Now is our chance—come!”
Huck said, “I can’t.
I would die if they opened their eyes.”
He would not move, and Tom started to leave
alone.
But the old floor made so much noise that
he stopped, almost dead with fear.
Slowly time passed until the sun was going
down.
Indian Joe sat up and called the other.
He said, “It is almost time for us to be
moving.
What shall we do with our money?
Shall we leave it here until we are ready
to run?
Six hundred silver dollars is heavy to carry.
We can put it in the ground.
Deep.”
His friend agreed.
He went to the place where the fire had been
built, raised one of the big stones from the
earthen floor, and took out a big bag of money.
The boys began to forget their fears.
Six hundred dollars would make six boys rich!
And they knew where Indian Joe was putting
it.
Indian Joe was in a corner, making a hole
in the ground with his knife.
The boys did not dare to speak, but they looked
at each other often.
These looks were easy to understand.
Their meaning was, “Oh, how glad we are
now to be here!”
They heard Indian Joe’s knife strike something
hard.
“Look here!” he said.
“What is it?” said his friend.
“It is an old box,” Joe said.
“Help me lift it.
No, I have broken it open.”
He put his hand in the box and then brought
it out again.
“Man, this is money!”
The two men looked at the handful of money.
It was gold.
Now the men found the gardening things that
the boys had been using and had placed in
another corner when they came into the house.
Using them, they started to work.
They soon had the box out of the earth.
It was not large, but it had once been very
strong, with iron bands to hold the wood together.
“There are thousands of dollars here,”
said Indian Joe.
“Now it won’t be necessary to do that
job in the village,” said the other.
Indian Joe said, “You do not understand.
I am not doing that job only for money.
Wrong was done to me, and I am going to pay
them for it.
I need your help.
Go home until I tell you to come.”
“What do we do with this money?
Put it in the ground again?”
“Yes.”
(Delight for the boys above his head.)
“No!”
(Deep sadness above.)
“Where did those gardening things come from?
There was fresh earth on them.
Who was here?
We must take the money away.
I have a good place for it.
At the Number Two place, under the cross.”
“It is nearly dark enough to go.”
Indian Joe went from window to window, looking
out.
Then he said, “Who could have come here?
Do you think they are in the room above us?”
The boys’ breath stopped.
Indian Joe put his hand on his knife and started
to go up.
The boys could not move; their strength was
gone.
They heard Joe coming.
Then they heard the sound of breaking wood,
and Joe fell to the ground.
“No people are up there,” his friend said.
“They saw us coming and they ran.
They thought that we were spirits or devils,
and they are running yet.”
Soon the two men went out of the house with
the box of gold and the bag of silver dollars.
Tom and Huck watched them through holes in
the wall.
But would the boys follow?
No.
They were happy enough to get away from the
house with no broken bones, and then return
to the town.
They did not talk much.
They decided to watch in the town for Indian
Joe, and then follow him to the Number Two
place.
Tom had a fearful thought.
“Indian Joe said that he would pay wrong
with wrong.
Was he talking about us, Huck?”
Feeling suddenly weak, Huck almost fell to
the ground.
Doubts
The adventure of the day troubled Tom’s
dreams that night.
Four times he had his hands on that gold.
Four times he opened his eyes and discovered
that he had nothing.
In the early morning as he was in bed, thinking
of his great adventure, it all seemed strangely
far away.
It might have happened in another world, or
in a time long past.
Then the thought came to him that the great
adventure itself must be a dream!
The amount of money was too big to be real.
He had never seen as much as half a hundred
dollars before.
He decided to find Huck and let Huck talk.
He would ask Huck no questions.
If Huck did not speak of the adventure, then
Tom would know that it had been a dream.
Huck was sitting on the edge of a boat, with
his feet in the water.
He seemed very sad.
“Hello, Huck!”
“Hello yourself.”
No words for a minute.
“Tom, if we had not put our gardening things
in that corner, we would have that money.”
“It was not a dream, it was not a dream!
But I almost wish that it was.”
“Dream!
If Indian Joe had found us, you would know
that it was not a dream!
I have had dreams about him all night.”
“We must find him!
Find the money!
We must find his Number Two place.
Perhaps it is the number of a house.”
“No, Tom.
The houses in this town do not have numbers.”
“Perhaps it is the number of a room in a
public house for travelers.
Those rooms have numbers.”
“Oh, that is the answer!
There are only two public houses here.
We can quickly learn about Number Two.”
“You stay here, Huck, until I return.”
Tom was gone half an hour.
He learned that in one public house a well-known
young man lived in room Number Two.
But in the other public house, Number Two
was always closed.
No person seemed to know much about it.
However, a light had been seen in the window
the night before.
“That is Indian Joe’s Number Two, Huck.”
“I think you are right, Tom.
Now what will you do?”
“Let me think.”
Tom thought a long time.
Then he said:
“I will tell you.
The door of Number Two opens on a little street
at the back of the house.
We must wait for a dark night.
Then we shall try to get in.
But if you see Indian Joe, follow him.
And if he does not go to that Number Two,
it can’t be the place.”
“I am afraid to follow him alone, Tom!”
“It will be night.
If I see him, and if it is dark, I will follow
him, I promise.
He might be going straight to that money.
You must not weaken, Huck, and I won’t.”
Number Two — Huck as Guard
They waited three nights.
The fourth night was dark enough.
The public house closed at a late hour, but
Tom and Huck were near.
Indian Joe had not been seen.
No other person had been in the street behind
the house.
The two adventurers moved quietly toward the
door in the darkness.
Huck stopped, to remain as a guard, and Tom
went forward.
Then there was a long wait.
To Huck it seemed hours.
What had happened to Tom?
Had he died from fear?
Huck’s breathing was very fast and his heart
beat madly.
Suddenly Tom came rushing past.
“Run!
Run for your life!”
They never stopped running until they were
at the other end of the village.
There stood an old building, now not used.
As they entered, rain began to fall heavily.
“Huck, it was fearful!
I tried and tried to open the door—and then
suddenly it opened without effort.
I stepped into the room, and—Huck, I almost
stepped on Indian Joe’s hand!”
“No!”
“Yes!
He was there, asleep on the floor.
Drunk, I believe.
I turned and ran.”
“Tom, did you see that box?”
“Huck, I did not wait to look around.
I did not see the box.
I did not see any cross.
I saw only a cup on the floor beside Indian
Joe.
And more to drink; the room is full of it.”
“Tom, if Joe is drunk, now is the time to
get that box.”
“Is it?
You get it.”
Huck began to shake.
“No, I believe not.”
“And I believe not, Huck.
Listen, Huck.
Wait until we know that Indian Joe is not
in there.
We can watch every night.
Then we can go fast and get that box.”
“I agree.
Let me watch all night and every night.
You do the other part of the job.”
“I will.
And now the rain has stopped.
You go and watch.
And when you want me at night, come to my
window and make a noise like a cat.”
The Picnic — Indian Joe’s Job
The next morning Tom heard glad news—Judge
Thatcher’s family had returned.
Both Indian Joe and the box of gold were not
so important for a while.
More good news made the day perfect.
The following day Becky would have her picnic.
Before eleven in the morning the young people
were at Judge Thatcher’s house, ready to
start.
Soon the happy group was walking toward the
river.
They were going to ride down the river on
the old riverboat.
Sid did not go; he was sick.
Mary stayed with him.
Mrs. Thatcher said to Becky, “You will return
late.
Perhaps you should stay all night at the home
of a girl friend who lives near the river.”
“I can stay with Susy Harper, Mother.”
“Good.
And be a good girl.”
The boat took them three miles down the river.
There it was tied to the shore.
The crowd ran off the boat and into the forest.
Soon shouting and laughing could be heard
from many places.
After a while, all were hot and ready to rest.
They met again near the boat, and began to
eat the good things they had brought with
them.
After eating, they rested in the shade of
the big trees.
Then there was a shout: “Who is ready to
go to the cave?”
All were ready.
They got lights to guide them in the darkness
and started to walk up the hill.
The cave could be entered through an opening
in the hillside.
A door had been placed across the opening,
but it was not closed.
Inside was a small, very cold room.
The walls were rock, and always had water
running down them.
It was a strange pleasure to stand there in
the darkness and look out at the green valley
shining in the sunlight.
But the strangeness was soon past, and the
children began to play and run through other
parts of the cave.
None of these parts was wide and some were
very small.
Some led to other rooms made of rock.
Some of these were very big; the children
could not see the top of them.
A person might walk days and nights and never
find the end of this cave.
He might go down and down, and yet further
down into the earth, always finding new parts
and new rooms.
No person knew the whole cave.
Only part of it was known, and people did
not go where others had not gone before.
Tom Sawyer knew as much of the cave as any
person.
The children walked for almost a mile before
any of them started to return to the outside.
Then one group after another began arriving
at the opening on the hillside.
They were surprised to see that it was almost
night.
The boat’s bell had been calling for half
an hour.
However, they thought this end to the day’s
adventures was delightful.
Only the captain of the boat was sorry that
he had waited so long.
Huck saw the lights of the returning riverboat.
He was already watching for Indian Joe.
There were clouds in the sky and the night
was becoming very dark.
The people in the village began to go home
to sleep.
The village clock was striking eleven and
nothing had happened.
Huck also began to think of sleep.
Then a noise came to his ear.
The next moment two men passed near him.
One was carrying something.
It must be that box!
Should he call Tom?
No.
The men would carry away the box and it would
never be found again.
He would follow them.
Without shoes, as usual, Huck moved as quietly
as a cat.
The men went toward the river, and then, turning,
went up Cardiff Hill.
Passing the house of an old man named Jones,
they arrived at the top of the hill.
There, among the trees, they could not be
seen.
Huck stopped, listened, but heard no sound
except his own heart.
He knew that he was not far from the house
of Mrs. Douglas, an old lady who lived alone.
Then, very near, he heard a voice.
It was Indian Joe.
He said, “There are lights.
It is late, but she is not alone.”
“I can’t see any lights.”
That was the other man.
Huck’s heart was cold.
This was the job Indian Joe had talked of!
Mrs. Douglas had often been kind to Huck.
Perhaps these men were planning to kill her.
He wished that he dared to run to the house
and tell her.
But the men would catch him.
“Look from here,” said Indian Joe.
“Now do you see the lights?”
“Yes.
Forget the job.”
“Forget it!
I have told you before, you can have her money,
I do not want it.
But her husband put me in jail.
Then he died.
I can’t hurt him.
But she is living yet.”
“You must not kill her!”
“I will not kill her.
But I am going to cut her face, and that hurts
a woman more than killing.
You will help me or I will kill you.
And if I must kill you, I will kill her, too.
Then she can’t tell who killed you.”
“If we must do it, then do it now.”
“No.
Wait until the house is dark.”
Huck knew that now all would be quiet, and
the quiet would be more fearful than the talk
of killing.
Very, very carefully he moved down the hill.
When he dared, he began to run.
He arrived at Mr. Jones’s house and beat
on the door.
Mr. Jones and his two strong sons opened a
window and looked out.
“What is that noise?
Who are you?
What do you want?”
“Let me come in—quick.”
“Who are you?”
“Huckleberry Finn.
Quick, let me come in.”
“Huckleberry Finn, indeed.
Is that a name to make me open a door?
But let him come in, boys.
What does he want?”
“Please never tell that I told you,” were
Huck’s first words.
“I would surely be killed—but Mrs. Douglas
has been a good friend to me.
I want to tell you.”
“Speak,” said the old man.
“We will never tell, boy.”
Three minutes later the old man and his sons,
carrying guns, were going up the hill.
Huck went only part of the way.
Then he stopped behind a large stone, and
listened.
Suddenly he heard the guns and a cry.
He waited for nothing more, but ran down the
hill as fast as his legs could carry him.
The Old Man Reports — Hope Begins to Weaken
The next day was Sunday.
In the very early morning Huck called gently
at the old man’s door.
“Please let me come in!
It is only Huck Finn.”
“That name will open this door night or
day, boy!”
These were strange words to the boy’s ears.
He could not remember hearing any so kind
and pleasant before.
The door was quickly opened, and he entered.
“Now, boy, I hope that you are hungry, because
as soon as the sun is up, we shall have something
hot to eat.
We hoped that you would come here again last
night.”
“When I heard the guns, I ran.
I ran for three miles.
I came now because I want to know what happened.
I came before daylight, because I do not want
to meet those men, living or dead.”
“They are not dead, boy.
We are sorry for that.
They heard us coming, and they ran.
Then we went down to the village to get help.
Men have gone to watch at the river.
More men will hunt through the forest today.
My sons will join them.
I wish we had seen those two men.
Could you see them in the dark?”
“I can tell you about them.
One is a man that you have seen in the village.
He has long white hair.
He can’t hear and he can’t talk.”
Then he told about the other man’s face
and clothes.
When his sons had gone, Mr. Jones asked Huck
why he had followed the men up the hill.
Huck told, after much thought, that one man
was Indian Joe.
But he did not tell about the box of money.
Soon people began coming to the house, and
Huck went where they could not see him.
Mrs. Douglas was among the first to come.
She came to thank Mr. Jones for saving her
from being hurt by the men.
“You should not thank me,” he said.
“There is another person who did more to
help you.
But he does not want thanks.”
All the people in the village went to church
early that day.
They wanted to talk about the two bad men.
The two had not been found, and nothing had
been learned about where they had gone.
Leaving the church, Mrs. Thatcher walked beside
Mrs. Harper.
She said, “Is my Becky going to sleep all
day?”
“Your Becky?”
“Yes.
She stayed with you last night, I believe.”
“No.”
Mrs. Thatcher stopped suddenly.
She seemed ill.
At that moment Aunt Polly joined them.
She said, “Good morning, Mrs. Thatcher.
Good morning, Mrs. Harper.
I suppose that my Tom stayed with Fred or
Joe last night without telling me.
And now he is afraid to come to church.”
Mrs. Thatcher seemed more ill than before.
She moved her head, saying no.
“He did not stay with us,” said Mrs. Harper.
Her face showed surprise and a little fear.
Aunt Polly also showed fear.
“Joe Harper,” she said, “have you seen
my Tom this morning?”
“No.”
“When did you see him last?”
But Joe could not remember.
People had stopped moving out of the church.
The story traveled quickly among them.
Children were questioned.
No child could remember seeing Becky and Tom
on the returning riverboat.
It was dark then.
No person had thought of counting the group.
A young man now said that Tom and Becky might
be lost in the cave.
Mrs. Thatcher closed her eyes tightly.
Aunt Polly began to weep.
Within five minutes bells were ringing and
all the people were gathering.
What had happened at Mrs. Douglas’s house
was not important now.
In half an hour two hundred men were going,
either by river or by road, toward the cave.
Through the long afternoon the village seemed
dead.
Many women went to visit Aunt Polly and Mrs.
Thatcher.
They wept with them, and that was more help
than words.
Through the long night the town waited for
news.
But in the morning only this news came: “Send
more food and more lights.”
Mrs. Thatcher was almost ill, and Aunt Polly
also.
Old Mr. Jones came home from the cave at noon,
and discovered that Huck was sick.
Mrs. Douglas came to care for him.
Other men began to return from the cave, but
the stronger men continued their hunt.
They visited the farther parts of the cave.
They shouted, and they shot guns, but they
had no answer.
Often a light would be seen far away, and
they would think that the children were found.
But the light always belonged to another of
the hunters.
The names “Becky” and “Tom” were found
marked on a rock, and the string that had
tied Becky’s hair was found.
Three days and nights passed.
Huck asked about Tom Sawyer.
Mrs. Douglas said, “Quiet, child.
You must not talk.
You are very, very sick.”
She began to weep.
There were not many now with enough hope or
strength to continue hunting for Tom Sawyer.
Lost in the Cave—Found But Not Saved
Tom and Becky had started through the branching
cave with the other children.
Then they had had enough of the games with
the others.
They had walked farther, talking, and reading
the writing on the walls.
People had put their names there.
Tom and Becky also put their names on the
wall.
They came to a place where a small stream
of water fell over the rocks.
Tom went behind the waterfall, to let his
light shine through for Becky’s pleasure.
Behind this waterfall Tom found an opening
leading down, and he wanted to discover where
this branch of the cave went.
He made a mark on the wall to guide their
return, and started down with Becky following.
They continued farther and farther, making
marks where they turned into a new branch,
and discovering many wonderful new parts of
the cave.
One great room was full of hundreds of bats,
which were hanging, asleep, on the walls.
When the children entered, the bats came flying
at the lights, and the children ran.
They came to a dark lake, and sat down at
the edge.
Now, for the first time, they felt the deep
quiet of the place.
Becky said, “It is a very long time since
I heard the others.”
“Becky, we are far below them, and far north,
or south, or east, or west.
We can’t hear them here.”
Becky was afraid.
“We should return.
Can you find the way, Tom?”
“I think that I can.
But there are those bats.
A different way would be better.”
“We must not get lost.
It would be fearful!”
They started.
But every turn now seemed strange.
Becky’s tears began to fall.
They stopped.
Tom shouted.
The answer was a deep quiet.
It increased Becky’s fear, and Tom began
now to feel afraid.
Becky said, “We must return to the lake
and then go through the room full of bats.
It would be better than being lost.”
But Tom said, “Becky, I have been a fool!”
He had not remembered to make any marks.
He had not expected to return to the lake.
“Tom, Tom, we are lost!
We are lost!
We never can get out of this fearful place!
Oh, why did we leave the others?”
She dropped to the ground and wept so loudly
that Tom feared that she might die.
He sat down beside her and put his arms around
her.
He said that he was sorry, that he should
never have brought her so far into the cave.
Then she said that she also had been wrong;
they had both been wrong to come so far.
They started to walk again.
Each had a light.
Now they decided to use only one light, and
to save the other.
They walked until they could go no farther
without resting.
They talked of home, and their friends, and
their beds, and they talked of sunlight.
Becky’s tears started again.
And then she was asleep.
Tom watched her.
Slowly her face grew peaceful, and then he
felt some peace.
She opened her eyes, laughing—but suddenly
the laugh ended.
“Oh, I wish that I had never, never opened
my eyes again!
Oh, Tom!
Do not look at me like that!
I shall not say that again.”
“We are going to find the way,” Tom said.
“We are going to try.”
They rose and started to walk, hand in hand
and without hope.
Tom said that they must go quietly, and listen
for falling water.
They found it, and sat down to rest again.
Becky said:
“Tom, I am very hungry!”
Tom had saved a piece of the picnic cake.
He took it from his pocket and divided it.
They had cold water to drink.
After eating and drinking, Becky was ready
to move again.
But Tom said, “Becky, I must tell you.
Our light is almost finished.
We must stay here, where there is water.”
Again Becky wept.
Then a new thought came to her.
“Tom, they will hunt for us!
Perhaps they are hunting for us now.
When would they discover that we were not
with the others?
On the boat?”
“It will be dark on the boat.
But your mother will know that you have not
come home.”
Now Tom learned that Mrs. Thatcher did not
expect Becky to return home that night.
Then their last light failed, and darkness
was complete.
Becky wept a long time in Tom’s arms.
Neither knew how long she wept.
Then both opened their eyes in the darkness
and knew that they had been sleeping.
Again they did not know how much time had
passed.
Tom said that it might be Sunday.
It might be a day later.
But Becky would not talk.
Her hopes were gone.
The hours passed.
They were hungry again.
Tom had saved most of his share of the cake.
He divided it.
Then they heard a sound like a distant shout.
Tom answered.
It came again.
They started moving carefully toward it.
But they arrived at an edge of rock, where
the floor fell away.
They could go no farther.
They listened.
The distant shout was now more distant.
And then they did not hear it, again.
They returned to the place where they had
water to drink.
Time passed.
After sleeping again, when they opened their
eyes, they thought that another day must have
passed.
They were very hungry.
Now Tom had a new idea.
The cave had many small branches near them.
Tom decided to learn about them.
That would be better than sitting and doing
nothing.
He had some string in his pocket.
He tied an end of this to a rock near the
little waterfall.
Then he and Becky started to walk carefully
away.
They let the string fall behind them.
It would be a guide for their return.
After twenty steps, they came to a hole in
the rock floor.
Tom went down on his knees and felt below.
Then he put his hands and his head as far
as possible around the corner to look.
At that moment a human hand, holding a light,
appeared from behind a rock not far away!
Tom shouted.
At once a body followed the hand.
It was Indian Joe!
Tom could not move because of fear.
He was deeply thankful to see Indian Joe run
away.
He did not tell Becky what he had seen or
why he had shouted.
They returned to the waterfall.
But after another long wait and another sleep,
Tom decided to try moving again.
They were very hungry now.
He thought that perhaps a week had passed.
Becky was not strong enough to go with him.
She asked him to return often.
She also asked him to return when all hope
was gone, and to hold her hand until she died.
Tom promised.
He kissed her.
Then, with the string in his hand, he started
on his hands and knees through one of the
openings in the rock.
He was sick with fear and he had no hope.
Tom Tells the Story of Their Escape
Sunday and two more days had passed.
Few of the men continued their hunt in the
cave.
Most of the people believed that the children
could never be found.
Mrs. Thatcher was very ill.
Aunt Polly’s hair had changed from gray
to white.
Then, in the middle of the night the village
bells began to ring.
In a moment the streets were filled with people
shouting, “They are found!
They are found!”
All moved toward the river and met the children
as they were carried home.
Aunt Polly’s happiness was complete.
Mrs. Thatcher’s happiness would be complete
when the news reached her husband.
He was yet in the cave, continuing the hunt.
Tom lay on a bed telling the story of his
wonderful adventures.
He had gone in one direction as far as the
length of the string.
Then he had tried another opening.
Then he had tried a third.
He was ready to try another when he saw a
distant light.
He thought that it was daylight.
He dropped the string and ran toward it, and
put his head out through a small hole.
And there was the great river on which the
boat had brought them to the picnic!
He told how he then returned for Becky.
She did not believe him.
She told him to let her die.
But after a while she went with him.
When she saw the daylight, she almost died
of joy.
He told how he got himself through the hole
and then helped her.
They saw some men in a boat, and shouted.
At first the men did not believe their wild
story.
“Because,” the men said, “you are five
miles south of the door of the cave.”
But they believed the children after a while
and took them to a house where they were given
food and allowed to rest before being taken
home.
It was several days before Tom and Becky were
strong again.
Tom learned of Huck’s sickness and went
to visit him.
Mrs. Douglas would not let Tom talk about
his adventures because Huck was not strong
enough to listen.
Also, she would not let the boys talk about
what had happened at her house on Cardiff
Hill.
Tom learned about that at home.
He heard, also, that “the other man” who
had been with Indian Joe had been found in
the river.
He had drowned while trying to escape.
About two weeks later, Tom visited Becky at
home.
Judge Thatcher and some friends were there.
They asked Tom if he wished to go into the
cave again.
Tom said yes.
“Others might wish to go, also,” the Judge
said.
“But I had that door covered with iron.
And it is closed.
It can’t be opened.
No person will get lost in that cave again.”
“Oh, Judge,” Tom said, “Indian Joe is
in the cave!”
What Happened to Indian Joe — A Return to
the Cave
The news spread.
In a few minutes men were in boats on their
way to the cave.
Tom was in the boat with Judge Thatcher.
When the door was opened, their eyes saw a
sad sight.
Indian Joe was on the ground, dead.
Tom’s experience in the cave made him understand
Indian Joe’s sufferings.
But a heavy weight of fear had been lifted
from Tom’s heart.
The next morning, Tom and Huck had an important
talk.
Now Huck told Tom about following Indian Joe
up the hill to Mrs. Douglas’s house.
This part of the story was new to Tom.
“And Indian Joe came from Number Two in
that public house,” Huck said.
“And now we shall never know any more about
that box of money.”
“Huck,” Tom said, “that money was never
in Number Two.
Huck, it is in the cave!”
“Say that again, Tom.”
“The money is in the cave.”
“Tom, is this true?”
“It is true, Huck.
Will you go there with me and help to bring
it out?”
“I will if we can go into the cave and not
get lost.”
“Are you strong enough?”
Tom asked.
“I can’t walk more than a mile, Tom.”
“It is five miles, Huck, for any other person.
But I know a shorter way.
I will take you there in a boat.
It will be easy for you.”
“I want to start now, Tom.”
Tom agreed.
“We want some bread and meat, and our tobacco,
and two bags, and some string, and some lights.”
They took a friend’s boat, and about noon
the boys started their journey.
Tom knew where to stop.
They pulled the boat up on the shore.
“Huck, the hole is near.
Try to find it.”
Huck tried and found nothing.
Then Tom proudly took him among some trees
and said:
“Here it is!”
The boys entered the hole.
Tom was leading.
They tied their string to a rock to guide
their return.
A few steps took them to the little waterfall,
and Tom felt his whole body shaking.
He told Huck that this was where he and Becky
had been when they were lost.
The boys were very quiet now.
The stillness and the darkness were heavy
on their hearts.
They continued walking and soon they came
to the place where the floor seemed to end.
With the light they could see that they were
on a hill leading to another rock floor below.
Tom said:
“Now I will show you something, Huck.”
He held his light high.
“Look as far as you can around the corner.
Do you see that?
On the big rock?”
“Tom, it is a cross!”
“That is where I saw Indian Joe, Huck.
And where is Number Two?
Remember what he said?
‘Under the cross.’
”
Huck said in a shaking voice, “Tom, I want
to go away from here.”
“What!
And leave the money?”
“Yes.
Leave it.
Indian Joe’s spirit is there.”
“No, Huck.
His spirit is near the door, where he died.
That is five miles away.”
“No, Tom.
It would guard the money.
I know about spirits, and you do also.”
Tom began to think that Huck was right.
But then he had a different thought.
“Huck, his spirit would not be near a cross.”
Huck agreed.
“Tom, I did not think of that.
But it is true.
We must go down there and find the box.”
It was not easy to go down the hill of rock
to the floor below.
Tom went first, and Huck followed.
Near the bottom of the great rock, the boys
found where some person had been eating and
sleeping.
But they found no money.
Then Tom took his knife and used it to turn
over the earth behind the great rock.
The knife touched wood.
“Huck!
Do you hear that?”
They pulled away some stones and some old
boards.
Behind these there was an opening under the
rock.
With his light, Tom went down.
Huck followed.
Tom went around a corner and shouted:
“Huck, look there!”
It was the box of money.
There were also two guns.
“We have it!” said Huck, putting his hands
among the pieces of gold.
“We are rich, Tom!”
“Huck, I was always sure that we would get
it.
And we have it.
Can I lift the box?”
He could lift it, but he could not carry it.
They put the money in their two bags, and
carried it up from the hole under the rock.
“Now we want the guns,” said Huck.
“No, Huck.
Leave them there.
We will return and use them some other time.
I think it is late.
And I am hungry.
We can eat and smoke outside, in the boat.”
After eating and smoking, they returned up
the river.
It was dark when they arrived at the edge
of the village.
“Huck,” said Tom, “we will take the
money to Mrs. Douglas’s house.
I know a place near there to leave it tonight.
Tomorrow morning we can count it and divide
it.
And then we can find a place in the forest
where it will be safe.
You wait here now and watch it.
I am going to get Benny Taylor’s little
wagon.”
He soon returned with the wagon.
They put the bags of money in the wagon and
started toward Cardiff Hill.
Near Mr. Jones’s house they stopped to rest.
Mr. Jones came out.
“Who is there?” he said.
“Huck and Tom Sawyer.”
“Come with me, boys.
They are all waiting for you.
Let me pull your wagon.
It is very heavy!
What do you have in it?
Nothing of value, I am sure of that.
Boys will always work for things of no worth.
Hurry now.”
The boys wanted to know why they should hurry.
“You will learn when you arrive.”
Soon they were entering Mrs. Douglas’s house,
leaving the wagon near the door.
All the important people of the village were
there.
The Thatchers were there, the Harpers, Aunt
Polly, Sid, Mary, and many more.
All were dressed in their best clothes.
Tom and Huck were covered with earth from
the cave.
Aunt Polly’s face was red when she saw Tom’s
face and clothes.
Mrs. Douglas took the boys to a bedroom and
said:
“Wash and dress now.
Here are new clothes for both of you.
Come and join the others when you are ready.”
Mr. Jones’s Surprise Fails
Huck said, “Tom, we can run away.
We can go through the window.”
“Why do you want to run away?”
“I can’t join that crowd, Tom.”
“Oh, that is nothing to be afraid of!
I will take care of you.”
Sid appeared.
“Sid, why are all these people here?”
“Old Mr. Jones has a surprise.
But it won’t surprise many people.
Most of us know it already.”
“What is the surprise, Sid?”
“It is about Huck following Indian Joe and
the other man to this house.
But it won’t be a surprise.
You will see.”
He laughed.
“Some person told about it.”
Tom said, “You told.
There is only one person in this town who
would destroy a good surprise.
You!
Now go away!
Or I will throw you out of this room!”
Some minutes later Huck and Tom were eating
at a big table with the others.
Then Mr. Jones stood up to speak.
He told the story about Huck.
It was true that it did not seem much like
a surprise.
But people tried to seem surprised.
Mrs. Douglas thanked Huck again and again.
She said that she would give Huck a room in
her house, and send him to school and that
later she would give him money to start a
business.
Tom said, “Huck won’t need it.
He is rich.”
People tried not to laugh.
Tom said, “Huck has money.
Perhaps you do not believe it, but he has.
I can show you.”
He ran outside.
“What is Tom doing now?” said Aunt Polly.
“I never can understand that boy.”
Tom entered, carrying the heavy bags.
He opened them and let the yellow gold fall
out on the table.
“What did I tell you?” he said.
“Half is Huck’s and half is mine.”
All looked.
None could speak for a moment.
Then they asked Tom to explain.
It was a long story, but it was full of interest.
When Tom finished, Mr. Jones said, “I planned
a surprise for this evening.
But this surprise makes mine seem very small.”
The money was counted.
There was more than twelve thousand dollars.
Some of the village people owned land and
were much richer than Tom and Huck.
But none had ever before seen so much money
at one time.
New Adventures Planned
Tom’s and Huck’s money was a great wonder
in the poor little village.
The reader may be sure of that.
It was not easy to believe that the money
was real.
People talked and talked about it.
People went hunting for more money.
Boys went, and men went, also.
They hunted in every old, lonely house.
All watched Tom and Huck and listened to them.
Every word they spoke had become important.
The village newspaper had a story about them.
Mrs. Douglas put Huck’s money in a bank.
Judge Thatcher did the same with Tom’s.
Each boy had money to spend now.
He had almost a dollar for every day of the
year.
In those days, a dollar and a quarter a week
was enough to buy a boy’s food and clothes,
and to pay for his schooling.
Judge Thatcher had a good opinion of Tom.
He said that only a very wise boy could have
brought Becky out of the cave safely.
He expected Tom to become a great man.
Huck Finn’s life had changed.
His sufferings were almost too great for him.
Mrs. Douglas had taken him to her home.
She kept him clean.
He must sleep every night in a clean bed.
He must eat like a gentleman.
He must go to church.
He suffered for three weeks, and then the
next day he was gone.
Mrs. Douglas and all the people in the village
tried to find him.
They were afraid that he had drowned in the
river.
Early on the third morning Tom Sawyer went
to an old building outside the village.
He found Huck.
Huck had been sleeping behind the building.
He was lying there now, happily smoking.
He was covered with dust.
His hair was wild.
He was wearing his old clothes.
Tom asked him to go home to Mrs. Douglas.
Huck’s face became sad.
He said, “Do not talk about it, Tom.
I tried it.
It is not for me.
She is good to me, and friendly.
But I can’t live with her.
I must get up at the same time every morning.
I must wash.
I must sleep in a bed.
I must wear those good clothes.
I can’t move in those clothes.
I can’t sit down, I can’t lie down, I
can’t roll on the ground in them.
I must go to church.
I must wear shoes on Sunday.”
“We all live like that, Huck.”
“Tom, I am different.
I can’t live like that.
It is easy to get food.
Mrs. Douglas won’t let me smoke.
And she prays all the time.
I had to leave, Tom, or I would die.
And when school begins, I would have to go
to school.
“Tom, being rich is no good.
I wish I was dead all the time.
I like these old clothes.
I like this place to sleep.
This is what I want.
Tom, I give you my share of the money.
You can give me ten cents when I need it.
But not often.
I do not like what is easy to get.
And you go now and explain to Mrs. Douglas.”
“Oh, Huck, you know that I can’t do that.
And if you try longer, you will like it.”
“Like it!
Yes, I will like it as I would like a burning
coal if I sat on it.
No, Tom, I won’t be rich, and I won’t
live in a house.
I like the forest, and the river, and a place
like this for sleeping.
But now we are rich and all our games like
being pirates are destroyed.”
“Listen, Huck.
Being rich won’t change that.”
“Is that true, Tom?”
“It is true.
But if you want to join me and the other boys,
and belong to my club, you must live like
us.”
“Tom, is that friendly?”
“I want you to join us, Huck.
But all the boys who join Tom Sawyer’s Club
must have good characters.”
Huck was quiet.
There was a battle in his mind.
After a while he said, “I will return to
Mrs. Douglas for a month.
I will try, if you will let me belong to Tom
Sawyer’s Club.”
“I agree, Huck.
Come with me now.
And I promise to ask Mrs. Douglas to change
a little, Huck.”
“Will you, Tom?
That is good.
When will you start your club?”
“Oh, soon.
This evening, perhaps, we can have the first
meeting.”
“What will we do at the meeting?”
“We will promise always to help each other,
and promise never to tell what we plan to
do, and promise to kill any person who hurts
one of us.”
“I like that, Tom.
I like it.”
“And we must make those promises in the
middle of the night, in a lonely place.
And sign with blood.”
“This is better than being a pirate, Tom.
I will stay with Mrs. Douglas.
And we will have adventures that will make
the whole village talk about us.
And then Mrs. Douglas will be proud because
she took me into her home.”
- THE END -