Even if dreams can show us the future, this
dream did not make sense.
Must I never pass a lorry on a clear road?
Can a dream show us the future and give us
the opportunity of changing it?
It is hard to believe.
If we can see the future in a dream, then
surely the future already exists.
If it does, then we are not free to act in
the ways we wish to, we are not responsible
for our own lives.
Before I tell you the dream, I must explain
a little about the context.
It was the summer of four years ago, and I
was driving my family back from Italy through
the south of France.
My son had not yet learned to drive, my daughter
was too young, and my wife doesn't drive at
all.
I had been at the wheel for the best part
of three weeks.
Perhaps I was tired; perhaps I could think
of nothing except cars.
We spent the night of the dream in a town
called Tain l'Hermitage.
Now I'll tell you the dream.
I was sitting in a big, powerful, cream-coloured
car, and I was driving at high speed through
the country.
I was coming to a bend in the road, and in
front of me, there was a very large lorry.
My foot reached out towards the brake, but
it could not find it.
I looked down: there was no brake!
Worse: my hands held empty air.
There was no wheel for them to hold.
There were no controls of any kind.
Already we were almost into the back of the
lorry.
I shouted in fear.
Then I heard a calm voice coming from my left,
and I turned my head.
A stranger was sitting there.
He was a cheerful man of about forty.
He was wearing an expensive shirt, and on
his head, he had a red hat.
I couldn't understand what he said; he spoke
very quickly in French, and my own French
is not very good.
I didn't, in fact, care what he said.
My eyes were on his clean, fat hands, which
were holding the wheel.
This car had its wheel on the left.
He, not I, was in control.
We drove safely round the bend.
He turned the wheel slightly to place the
car in the middle of the road.
He was going to pass the lorry.
The road stretched straight ahead.
It was bright in the sunlight and it was quite
empty.
Only one other person was in sight; a woman
was sitting outside a small house with white
walls, and this house was almost exactly ahead
of us.
She was sitting by a table putting some flowers
in pots.
She wanted to sell us some, and waved them
at us.
This sight, for some reason, filled me with
a terrible fear.
The flowers made me think of death and our
final resting place.
At this moment, we were level with the lorry
and ready to pass it, but then the lorry began
to turn away from the side of the road, towards
our car.
It appeared that the driver was doing this
on purpose.
The stranger by my side shouted loudly and
tried to move out of the way.
There was a terrible noise from the back of
the car, and then an explosion.
The earth seemed to turn over, and the noise
of flames burned in my ears.
At that point, I woke up in fear.
I was very worried by this dream, and could
not sleep again.
It seemed to have a message, and I wanted
to explain it.
Even if dreams can show us the future, this
dream did not make sense.
Must I never pass a lorry on a clear road?
The road to Paris is always filled with very
large lorries.
Most of them come up from Marseilles, and
I always have to pass them when the road is
clear; I can't drive slowly behind them forever.
No, this was not the meaning of the dream.
At its heart was some kind of fear.
I had to recognize my fear, and then I could
forget all about it.
I thought about my driving during the last
three weeks.
I tried to remember all the lorries and all
the small white houses.
I thought of all the cars, which were painted
cream.
I remembered nothing of any great interest.
I had imagined that the road in the dream
must be in France; it was long, empty and
straight.
But then I remembered that we had passed the
lorry on the right.
So the dream was about a road in England;
in England all cars keep to the left.
Immediately, I remembered something.
Two years before this, I was travelling in
the north of England.
An American and I were making some radio programmes.
He had brought his car from America, and of
course, the driver sat on the left side.
The brakes and other controls were also on
the left, but the colour of his car was not
cream.
The American was a careless driver, and often
passed other cars against my advice.
Remember that I was in a better position to
see: I was sitting on the right.
Once, just after Nottingham, he played chicken'.
You probably know about 'chicken'; it is a
game that is played on the roads.
It is becoming more and more popular in America,
because long journeys are often very dull.
You just move your car into the middle of
the road and stay there.
When another car appears, it comes towards
you in the middle of the road.
The driver who turns away is the chicken.
Quite often, neither driver turns away.
I expressed my displeasure at this game in
language that the American could not fail
to understand.
We did not play it again, but it had probably
left its mark on my mind.
So then, when I was asleep, I experienced
it all again in a dream.
I also remembered something else while I was
having breakfast.
When we played 'chicken', it was an uncommonly
windy day.
We stopped at Chesterfield, and the American
bought a hat.
It was a black hat, not a red one, but in
dreams, details are not always exact.
After this, I forgot about the dream until
the afternoon.
The big French lorries often play their own
game.
They stay in the middle of the road, and you
can't pass them.
You have to stay behind them.
Sometimes you have to follow them for endless
kilometres, although the roads are almost
completely empty.
This afternoon we were following a large vehicle,
which was making terrible noises.
When I blew my horn, the driver moved to the
side of the road, but it was the wrong side.
He was driving along on the left, instead
of keeping to the right.
There was enough space on the right for me
to pass him.
But to do that would be wrong.
So I just followed him for a few kilometres
and I told myself not to pass him.
I considered the situation from every point
of view.
I could certainly turn my car more quickly
than he could turn his lorry.
It was a very big, heavy lorry.
Could I, perhaps, pass him quickly on the
right before he could do anything?
If he turned to the right, though, he could
easily kill us all.
He probably wanted a bit of fun, but he might
want an accident.
If he killed us, nobody would say it was his
fault; the law would be on his side.
The road ahead was quite empty, and went on
for many kilometres.
I drove more slowly until some distance separated
us.
Then I increased my speed as much as I could.
I drove towards that empty space beside the
lorry.
My car was moving at about 110 kilometres
an hour.
The front of my car was almost level with
the back of the lorry.
Then I saw something that knocked the breath
out of my body.
On the grass beside the road, a woman was
sitting outside a small white house with a
table of flowers!
For the first time in my life, I changed my
mind while I was preparing to pass another
vehicle.
My foot went down hard on the brake.
The car rocked from side to side.
From behind me, I heard the sound of a horn.
Another car was following us at a high speed.
I knew its colour before I saw it; it was
cream.
I pressed hard on the brake and turned the
wheel slightly.
I was just able to move in behind the lorry
without touching it.
The other car passed us and the driver blew
his horn wildly.
It reached the lorry - and then the lorry
turned towards it.
For a moment I thought that the car was going
to pass the lorry safely; it was moving very
fast.
Then the front of the lorry just touched the
back of the car.
It was only a light touch, but it knocked
the car towards the side of the road and the
woman at the table.
The driver of that car knew exactly what to
do.
With the greatest skill, he turned it back
into the middle of the road.
His control was wonderful, much better than
mine.
He waved angrily at the lorry driver and drove
quickly away in a cloud of dust.
He was soon out of sight.
We stayed that night in Fontainebleau.
A big car was standing outside the hotel,
and the back showed signs of damage to the
paintwork.
It was a cream car, and so I looked for the
driver.
He was not wearing a red hat or an expensive
shirt.
He was a young man from Paris - not like the
driver in my dream.
He spoke good English, so I asked him if he
would like the number of that lorry.
I had noticed it, and I was happy to give
it to him.
But he only laughed; the law won't help you
if you pass on the wrong side of the road.
To him the whole thing had been a game.
'It tests your skill,' he said.
'If the car is powerful enough, you can do
it.
But you couldn't do it, not in your car.'
I didn't tell him about my dream, my reason
for not passing the lorry.
There was no time; he was in a hurry and wanted
to reach Paris quickly.
It made me think, though.
I don't really believe in dreams, of course;
but something saved us all from a terrible
death.
- THE END -