CHAPTER ONE
A Departure and a Romantic Adventure
It was the last day of term
at Miss Pinkerton's academy.
Miss Pinkerton was giving final
instructions to her sister, Miss Jemima.
'Is everything ready for Miss Sedley?'
she asked grandly. 'She will take
the dictionary with her, of course.'
Miss Pinkerton's academy was one of
the finest schools for young ladies.
The academy had been visited by the great
Dr Samuel Johnson. He had also mentioned
it in a poem. Miss Pinkerton could never
resist mentioning the great man's name,
and she gave her pupils a copy of his
dictionary when they left the school.
'What about Becky Sharp?' Miss Jemima now asked.
'Shall I give her a copy of the dictionary, too?'
'Becky Sharp!' Miss Pinkerton exclaimed
angrily. 'We won't waste the dictionary on her.'
Becky Sharp was an orphan. Her mother, a
Frenchwoman, had died some years previously.
She had taught Becky French. Her father
had been the school's art teacher.
He was a talented man, but very
fond of wild company and drinking.
He had begged Miss Pinkerton to take on Becky as
an 'articled pupil' at the school before he died.
Becky Sharp was a good-looking, intelligent
girl. She was small and slender, and she had
sandy hair. Miss Pinkerton had realised how
useful she could be because she knew French
and could play music. Becky Sharp despised Miss
Pinkerton and the moral atmosphere of the academy.
The relationship between Miss Pinkerton and
Becky Sharp grew worse and worse. Both of
them were glad when the girl obtained a
post as governess to Sir Pitt Crawley.
Amelia Sedley was the daughter of a rich London
stockbroker. She was a pretty girl, and she had
healthy red cheeks and a warm smile. Everyone
loved her because she was patient and kind.
Amelia had asked Becky to stay at her family's
house for a week when they left school.
Soon the two girls had said goodbye to
the headmistress, and they went out to
the carriage. Just as the carriage began
to move, Miss Jemima ran up to the window.
'Stop!' she cried out excitedly. She
pushed two parcels through the window.
'Some sandwiches, my dears,' she told
the two girls. 'And a book for you,
Becky,' she went on. 'Johnson's Dictionary,
you know. You can't leave without that.'
The good woman went back into the garden.
She had defied her sister for once, but
she was sure she had done the right thing.
The carriage drove off. Miss Jemima was
horrified to see Becky Sharp lean out of
the window and throw the precious
dictionary back into the garden.
Mr and Mrs Sedley were delighted
to have their daughter back home,
and they gave a kind welcome
to her friend Becky as well.
Amelia's older brother, Jos, was also at home.
He had recently returned on leave from India,
where he had an important and lucrative post
in the East India Company's Civil Service.
Jos Sedley had lived a very
isolated life in India,
and he was terribly shy of women.
He was also extremely vain,
and dressed in the latest fashion. This made him
look rather ridiculous, as he was very overweight.
It did not take long for Becky Sharp
to understand Jos, and a certain idea
began to take shape in her mind. She hated
the prospect of working as a governess.
That night at dinner Becky Sharp
paid particular attention to Jos.
He was flattered by the looks she
gave him, and blushed frequently.
Mrs Sedley had had a curry prepared for
her son, and Becky was offered some.
'I must try some,' she said. 'I'm sure
it's very good if it comes from India.'
Old Mr Sedley smiled quietly. He understood
her sudden enthusiasm for India and curry.
'Is it good?' he asked her softly.
'Excellent!' Becky gasped.
'Try a chilli with it,' Jos suggested.
'A chilli?' Becky said faintly. The word 'chilli'
sounded so cool that she took a whole one. It was
hotter than the curry. In a moment she was
red in the face - she could hardly breathe.
'Water!' she cried. 'Water, for heaven's sake!'
Mr Sedley laughed aloud. Even Jos laughed.
Becky was furious, but she
took the joke in good spirits.
Mr Sedley took his son aside after
dinner, and gave him a little advice.
'That girl's determined to marry you,' he said.
'Nonsense!' Jos replied,
but he was very flattered.
Jos began to think about Becky more and more. Soon
he was convinced that he was in love with her. His
behaviour towards her became stranger and stranger
as he struggled against his shyness. Becky thought
he was in love. Perhaps he might ask her to
marry him. The future looked bright for her.
There were two other frequent visitors to the
Sedley household during Becky Sharp's stay there.
They were two young army officers,
William Dobbin and George Osborne.
One evening all the young people decided
to go to Vauxhall Gardens together.
Amelia was very excited because she was in love
with George Osborne. He was a good-looking young
man, and he was Mr Sedley's godson. William Dobbin
and George had been to the same school, and they
were close friends. Dobbin was not as good-looking
as his friend - he was tall and very shy.
George and Amelia had known each
other since they were children.
Their families expected them to marry.
Becky was sure that Jos wanted to ask her to
marry him. She walked by his side, giving him
every encouragement she could. Jos himself was
sure that he wanted to ask her to marry him,
but he did not know how to approach the issue.
At last the party decided to eat something at the
restaurant in the Vauxhall Gardens. Jos ordered a
magnificent meal and the best champagne.
He ate and drank more than anyone else.
Then he ordered a bowl of punch. It was
the custom at Vauxhall to drink punch.
It was the punch that was responsible
for the whole of this story.
If Jos Sedley had not ordered
it, and then drunk most of it,
he would have proposed to Becky Sharp, and that
would have been the end of the story. As it was,
the more he drank, the more cheerful he became.
He began to sing, and this made people laugh.
George Osborne was embarrassed.
'I think we should leave,' he told
the girls. They stood up to go.
'Stop, my dearest diddle-diddle-darling!' Jos
cried out to Becky. He seized hold of her waist.
Becky could not free herself, and Jos held
on to her tightly and resumed his song.
Dobbin succeeded in freeing the unfortunate Becky.
He took Jos back to his lodgings, and
George Osborne took the girls back home.
Becky and Amelia were sure
that the moment had come
for Jos to propose to Becky, after
his behaviour the night before!
Jos, meanwhile, woke with a terrible
headache. He did not remember everything
that had happened the night before,
but he was terribly ashamed of himself.
He did not have the courage to see Becky
again. He wrote a note to Amelia saying
that he was leaving London, and asking her
to apologise to Becky for his behaviour.
It was the end of Becky's hopes of marriage.
She knew now that she had to take up the post of
governess with Sir Pitt Crawley and his family.
CHAPTER TWO
The Crawley Family
Becky's new employer was Sir Pitt Crawley. Sir
Pitt Crawley had been married twice, and he
had two grown-up sons from his first marriage -
Pitt and Rawdon Crawley. After the death of his
first wife Sir Pitt had married again, this time
choosing an ironmonger's daughter. They had two
daughters. Sir Pitt had advertised for a governess
to help in the education of these two children.
Becky Sharp was young enough to have a romantic
idea of what a baronet's establishment might
be like. She was very shocked, therefore,
to discover that Sir Pitt Crawley seemed
hardly a gentleman at all. He was an elderly
man who dressed badly and drank too much.
He was also mean about money, and
preferred to spend his time eating
and drinking with the butler, rather
than entertaining ladies and gentlemen.
Sir Pitt Crawley's country residence,
Queen's Crawley, was a large house,
but it was in poor condition.
Becky soon realised that the most important person
in the house, after Sir Pitt Crawley himself,
was the baronet's older son, Pitt. Unlike
his father, he was rather a severe man
with very strong religious opinions. It was clear
that the father and son did not get along well.
It was also clear that Sir Pitt's wife, the
ironmonger's daughter, wielded no power in
the house at all. Lady Crawley had been a lovely
young girl before she married Sir Pitt Crawley.
She had given up a decent young man who loved
her for the happiness of becoming Lady Crawley.
Vanity Fair, indeed! Her beauty faded, and
Sir Pitt became bored with her. The poor
woman was despised by all. The only person who
showed the slightest respect for her was the
baronet's older son, Pitt. He behaved with a
cold, formal correctness to her at all times.
Sir Pitt Crawley's brother, Bute, was the
local parson. He and his family lived in
the village rectory. The relationship between
the two brothers was not particularly good.
They had quarrelled about money in the past,
and they continued to plot against each other.
Their plots centred around Sir Pitt's
unmarried half-sister, Miss Crawley.
Miss Crawley was a very rich,
selfish old woman. She did not like Pitt
Crawley because of his piety. She wanted
to leave half of her money to Bute Crawley, and
the other half to Sir Pitt's second son, Rawdon.
Becky rapidly decided on the most useful
strategy to follow at Queen's Crawley.
She wanted to keep everyone happy with least
effort to herself. She won over the two daughters
by letting them educate themselves rather
than giving them difficult lessons to follow.
Sir Pitt Crawley was involved in a large number
of lawsuits with different people, and Becky soon
learned all the details of these. She ordered his
papers for him, and helped prepare his accounts.
She also helped him with the management of
the estate, and was very useful in every way.
With his older son, Pitt, Becky took
a different approach. She listened to
his religious opinions very seriously, and
encouraged his political ambitions as well.
The wealthy Miss Crawley soon arrived at Queen's
Crawley, where everyone made a great fuss of her.
Becky wrote to Amelia, describing how Sir Pitt
provided the finest food and wines for her,
and how the family at the rectory also did
their best to entertain the selfish old lady.
Sir Pitt's younger son,
Rawdon Crawley, also came to stay at
Queen's Crawley to be near his aunt.
Becky told Amelia that the young
army officer was very good-looking
and had even asked her to dance
with him at a country ball.
Miss Crawley knew perfectly well that
her relatives were waiting for her to die
so that they could inherit her fortune. She was a
shallow, pleasure-loving woman, and she only had
time for the dashing young army officer, Rawdon
Crawley. She regarded Pitt Crawley as a bore,
and was frightened of his religion and morality.
She thought Bute and his wife were dull as well.
It was not long before Becky Sharp had
become a favourite with the old lady.
Becky amused her by imitating the guests
who were invited to dine at Queen's Crawley.
Miss Crawley insisted that the governess
sit beside her and Rawdon at dinner.
'I don't care about birth and social position,'
she said to Becky. 'Look at my brother Pitt,
look at Bute at the parsonage. None of
them have got your intelligence, my dear.
They're not even the equals of
my poor old companion Briggs.
No, what I care for is wit and
breeding - and you've got both!'
She even confided in Becky
about her hopes for Rawdon.
'I admired Nelson because he didn't care
what people thought. He ran away with a
beautiful woman. I hope some great
man runs away with you, my dear!'
she went on. 'I hope Rawdon runs away
with a girl,' she added dreamily.
'A rich one or a poor one?' Becky asked.
'A rich one, of course,' Miss Crawley
replied with a smile. 'Poor Rawdon
hasn't got any money except what I give him.'
'Is he terribly clever?' Becky asked.
'Clever!' the old lady laughed.
'Rawdon hasn't got an idea
in his head. But I want him to succeed
- he's so delightfully wicked!'
Although Becky told Amelia in her
letter that Rawdon had danced with her,
she did not tell her friend everything about
the young army officer's behaviour towards her.
One evening, when Becky was playing the piano,
Rawdon stood close to her, bending over the music.
He had even written her a note while
she was singing after dinner once,
and hidden it in her music book. Becky picked
up the note and dropped it into the fire.
'What's that, my dear?'
Miss Crawley asked sleepily.
'A false note,' Becky replied with a little smile.
Rawdon blushed furiously.
CHAPTER THREE
Young Lovers
He must now leave the good people
enjoying themselves at Queen's Crawley,
and return to London to find
out what is happening to Amelia.
The ladies in Amelia's social circle agreed
that she was very good-natured but dull.
The Misses Osbornes and Dobbins patronised
the poor girl terribly, and Amelia was very
shy in their company. 'What does George see
in her?' they asked each other in wonder.
George Osborne himself became used to
the idea that he was making an enormous
sacrifice in marrying Amelia. He continued
to visit the Sedley household, of course,
but days went by when he ignored Amelia.
She suffered, but she told no one about her
suffering. Only George's friend Dobbin
realised that the girl was unhappy.
Meanwhile great events were taking place in
Europe. Napoleon's army was defeated by the
allies, and the emperor was forced to abdicate
and take up residence on the island of Elba.
The financial markets of the world were
disturbed. Mr Sedley suffered heavy losses
in his investments on the stock exchange.
One day George Osborne visited Amelia,
and invited her to dine with his family
at Russell Square that evening. Amelia
was delighted, and accepted happily.
Amelia arrived early at the house,
and was talking with George's sisters
when Mr Osborne came home. Mr Osborne
seemed surprised to see her there.
'George is home today, Papa,' one of the sisters
explained. 'He'll be coming in to dinner soon.'
'Will he indeed?'
Mr Osborne said crossly. 'He'd better come
in on time. I won't hold dinner for him.'
Mr Osborne sat down gloomily. When the
clock struck the usual time for dinner,
he rang for the butler.
'Dinner!' he ordered angrily.
'Mr George isn't in yet,' the man replied.
'Damn Mr George, sir. I'm the master here!'
Mr Osborne commented angrily. 'Dinner, I say!'
The ladies looked at each other in fright.
Dinner was a silent affair.
Mr Osborne said nothing,
and no one else knew how to make conversation.
George arrived halfway through the meal, and
did not seem to notice his father's bad humour.
He talked amusingly to Amelia and his sisters.
At last the ladies retired to the drawing room,
leaving Mr Osborne and George to their wine.
The older man was still bad-tempered.
George did his best to cheer him up.
The real reason for his visit
was that he had run out of money.
He was hoping for some money from
his father. At last his father spoke.
'How are you and Amelia getting on?' he asked.
'Anyone can see that she loves
me, sir,' George replied proudly.
'And you?' his father asked
sharply, 'What about you, my boy?'
George laughed easily.
'Didn't you tell me to marry Amelia,
sir?' he joked. 'You and Mr
Sedley arranged it all years ago!'
'Hmm,' commented his father.
'Haven't I heard about you and
your wild amusements with Captain Crawley
and that set? You should be careful, sir.'
Mr Osborne was secretly delighted that his
son was mixing in such aristocratic company.
He was very ambitious for George.
'Well, well,' he went on. 'I
suppose young men will be young men.
I'm glad you live in the best society of England.'
'One can't live in that kind of society for
nothing, you know,' George said quietly.
'Don't worry about money, my boy,' Mr Osborne
interrupted him. 'My money's as good as theirs.
Call on Mr Chopper in the City tomorrow
- he'll have something for you.'
'Thank you, sir.'
'You could marry higher than Amelia, you
know,' Mr Osborne told him. 'I don't like
the look of Sedley's affairs. There are rumours
about his losses. If I don't see Amelia's ten
thousand pounds you won't marry her. I
won't have any lame ducks in my family.'
George was very attentive to Amelia when he went
to join the ladies after his talk with his father.
She remembered long afterwards the
pleasure of that evening with him.
George hurried off to the City the next morning,
and obtained a document from Mr Chopper.
Then he hurried to the bank. He noticed
that Mr Sedley was also in the bank,
but he was too excited to notice the
grim look on the older man's face.
Meanwhile Miss Crawley had returned to
London from her visit to Queen's Crawley,
bringing Becky Sharp with her. The old
lady had eaten and drunk far too much,
and was feeling unwell. She retired
immediately to bed, and summoned her doctor.
Captain Crawley was one of the first people
to arrive at her house to ask after her.
He received gloomy reports from the
maid and from Miss Briggs her companion.
Captain Crawley was unable to see the
patient, but he did manage to have a few
minutes of private conversation with Becky.
He left the house looking very cheerful.
Miss Briggs tried to gain admission to the sick
lady's bedroom, but was refused. The poor lady
had been a loyal and faithful companion for many
years and was wounded by Miss Crawley's behaviour.
'But why won't she see me?' she asked Becky.
'I always look after her when she's ill.'
'Don't be so upset,' Becky advised her. 'She
won't see you because she prefers my nursing
to yours, that's all. Sick people are like that
sometimes. She'll be well again in a few weeks,
and then I'll go back to Queen's Crawley.'
'Never, never,' Miss Briggs said sadly.
'She'll never be well, or I'll never
go?' Becky asked with a little smile.
Captain Crawley called every day to receive
the latest news from Becky. Every day the
news was better, and soon Miss Crawley allowed the
faithful Briggs to spend time with her once more.
Becky used to mimic the good woman to her
face for the amusement of the old lady.
Once Miss Crawley was well again, she
agreed to accompany Becky to Russell Square
so that the girl could be reunited
with her old school friend, Amelia.
The visit was a short one, but Amelia made
a good impression on the rich old lady.
She talked enthusiastically about Becky's
friend, and mentioned her to Captain Crawley.
Becky was quick to explain that Amelia had a
fiance - a certain Lieutenant George Osborne.
'What regiment is he in?' Rawdon asked.
'I don't recall,' Becky replied,
'but his Captain's name is Dobbin.'
'I know Dobbin,' Rawdon told her. 'And I
know Osborne too, now that I think of it.
Osborne's a fool,' he commented happily. 'He
wants to be seen in the company of a lord.
He pays for their dinners,
and they invite the guests.'
'Pretty guests,' Becky suggested with a smile.
'Quite right, Miss Sharp,' Rawdon
laughed. 'Very pretty guests indeed.'
'Don't be so naughty, Rawdon!'
the old lady laughed excitedly. Her
nephew's cynicism delighted her enormously.
'Why don't we have him here?' Rawdon suggested.
Lieutenant Osborne and Amelia were invited
for dinner at Miss Crawley's house.
The meeting between Becky and George Osborne
was not an easy one. Becky suspected that it
was George who had discouraged Jos Sedley from
proposing to her after the dinner at Vauxhall
Gardens. She greeted him very coolly. For his
part, Osborne thought her vain and ambitious.
Amelia saw immediately that there was
a friendship between Becky and Rawdon.
Before leaving the house
she went up to her friend.
'I see it all,' she said quietly.
Becky kissed her.
One day Sir Pitt Crawley came to
London. His wife had just died,
and the baronet was desperate
to have Becky back at the house.
'You must come,' he told her.
'I'll come as soon as I can,' Becky replied.
'Everything's in a mess without you,' Sir
Pitt complained. 'Dear Becky, do come!'
Becky looked at him closely.
'Come as what?' she asked quietly.
'Come as Lady Crawley, if you like,'
the old man cried impatiently. 'Come back and
be my wife. There! Does that satisfy you?'
'Oh Sir Pitt!' Becky cried.
'Say yes,' Sir Pit begged her. 'I'm an
old man, Becky, but I'll make you happy,
you see if I don't.' The old man
got down on his knees before her.
Becky jumped back. For once
she did not know what to say.
'Oh, Sir Pitt!' she cried again.
'Oh - sir - I'm married already!'
CHAPTER FOUR
A Family Bankruptcy
Miss Briggs happened to be passing the room
where the interview between Becky and Sir
Pitt was taking place. She heard both his offer
of marriage, and Becky's refusal of it. She did
not stay long enough, however, to hear the reason
for the refusal - that Becky was already married.
Miss Briggs carried the
exciting news to Miss Crawley.
Miss Crawley was impressed that Becky had refused
the baronet, and secretly relieved. She talked the
matter over with Briggs, and the two women agreed
that Becky must be in love with someone else.
'Find out who it is,' Miss
Crawley ordered her companion.
Becky admitted to Miss Briggs that she was in love
with someone else, but she refused to tell Briggs
who the man was. She did not tell Miss Crawley
either when the old lady interrogated her.
'You will know soon enough, my dear,' she said.
That evening, when she was alone
in her bedroom, she wrote a letter.
Dear friend,
Half of our secret is known, and I'm
sure that the time has come to tell
everything. It's risky, I know,
but I'm sure we'll win in the end.
Miss Crawley is very sympathetic and generous.
I think everything will be all right!
She addressed the letter
to 'Miss Elizabeth Styles'.
The reader will not perhaps be
surprised that Miss Elizabeth Styles,
who wore a military uniform, was none
other than Captain Rawdon Crawley.
The next morning Becky's bedroom was
empty. She had left a note for Briggs,
explaining the mystery of her marriage and
asking her to break the news to Miss Crawley.
It was bad luck for Becky that Mrs Bute
Crawley arrived at the house that morning.
Briggs told her the whole story, and
they went to Miss Crawley together.
The old lady was horrified at the news,
and had another attack of illness.
'I'll never forgive them!' she said. 'And I'll
never give Rawdon another penny of my money.'
Sir Pitt also came to the house that
morning. He wanted to see Becky.
'She's got to come back to Queen's Crawley with
me,' he told Briggs. 'I can't manage without her.'
'But don't you know she's married?'
Briggs replied in astonishment.
'What do I care about that?' the baronet
said angrily. 'I know she's married.'
'She left the house this morning, sir,'
Briggs explained. 'Miss Crawley is very upset
by the news of her marriage to Captain Rawdon.'
When Sir Pitt heard that Becky
was married to his own son,
he broke into a furious rage. Then
he left the house very noisily.
'But what if she doesn't forgive me?'
Rawdon asked his wife that night, as they sat
together in their modest little apartment.
'Don't worry about that,' Becky said
sweetly. 'I'll make your fortune for you.'
'You can do anything,' he replied tenderly.
There is one event in Vanity Fair that
attracts both sentiment and satire,
and that is the auction of a bankrupt person's
household goods. People who attend these auctions
remember how things were different in the
past, how the person who is penniless now,
used to offer his guests
the finest wines and food.
An auction was taking place at the Sedley
household. Old Sedley was now a ruined man.
Captain Dobbin was at the auction. He was
very interested in a little piano that had
belonged to Amelia. His agent began to bid for the
instrument, as did Becky's agent on her behalf.
The bidding was fast, and the price rose high.
At last Becky's agent ceased to bid, and the
piano became the property of Captain Dobbin.
The piano arrived that evening at a
modest little house off the Fulham Road,
where the Sedleys were now living.
'He was a kind man, Mr Sedley,' Becky
commented dreamily to Rawdon. She was
remembering her stay at the house. 'I'm
sorry it's all gone wrong for him.'
'Oh, these stockbrokers,' Rawdon said carelessly,
'they're used to this sort of thing, you know.
I'm sorry for your little friend Amelia,
though. I suppose young Osborne will
think twice before he marries her now!'
Rawdon's guess was not far wrong.
Amelia had received a letter from
George Osborne's father immediately the news
of the bankruptcy became public knowledge.
Mr Osborne told her that her father had behaved
very badly, and that it was no longer possible for
the two families to know each other. She showed
the letter to her father, who was very angry.
He ordered her to return every letter and
present that she had received from George,
and to forget about him. Amelia sent back
the few presents that George had given her,
but she kept his letters. They
were her most precious possessions.
There was more exciting news from Europe.
Napoleon had escaped from Elba and returned
to France. Everyone knew that war was coming.
One day Dobbin found his friend George Osborne in
his room at the barracks. He looked very upset.
'She's sent me back all the presents I gave her,'
George told his friend. 'It's all over. Look,
read this.' He passed Dobbin a letter from Amelia.
Dobbin had visited Mr Sedley and the family
in their new house off the Fulham Road.
He knew that Amelia was very ill.
'She's dying, George,' he said quietly.
A few hours later George Osborne
paid a visit to the Sedley household.
Mrs Bute Crawley established herself at Miss
Crawley's house in London to nurse the old lady.
She made sure that letters from Rawdon
Crawley were intercepted. She read Miss
Crawley religious stories, and encouraged her
to consider serious matters. It was her hope
that Miss Crawley was planning to write a new
will, leaving some of her money to Bute Crawley.
Mrs Bute Crawley was very successful in her
arrangements. Perhaps she was too successful.
She frightened and depressed Miss Crawley instead
of amusing her. Even her doctors thought that the
effect of Mrs Bute Crawley's influence was
dangerous. One of them tried to talk to her.
'You have done a lot for our poor patient,' he
told her. 'But she is not as ill as she was.
Indeed, she needs fresh air now. If you
keep her in the house, she may really die!'
At last an expedition to the park was organised.
Miss Crawley's carriage was soon spotted
by Becky and Rawdon, who were also out
driving. Rawdon drove past his aunt, and
saluted her gravely. His aunt ignored him.
'That's it, then,' he commented to
Becky. 'She won't acknowledge me.'
CHAPTER FIVE
A Wedding and a Disinheritance
Captain Dobbin now found himself in a very painful
and difficult position. He could see that
George was less and less keen to marry Amelia,
and he realised that he himself
was falling in love with her.
'She will die if George does
not marry her,' he thought.
He determined to make sure
that the wedding went ahead.
George and his father, meanwhile,
had quarrelled bitterly.
Mr Osborne wanted his son to marry a
rich girl. George, however, who had been
influenced by Dobbin's account of Amelia's
sufferings, promised to be true to his word.
'I'll have no beggars in my family,
sir!' his father roared. 'Marry Amelia
and you leave this house for ever - you
leave it a penniless man, I tell you!'
'I've done it, Dobbin,' George
told his friend afterwards.
'Done what?' Dobbin asked.
'I've told my father,'
George informed him. 'I'll marry her tomorrow
- I love her more and more each day!'
One morning a quiet wedding took place in London.
Amelia was the bride and George the bridegroom.
The best man was the faithful Dobbin.
Jos Sedley was also in attendance, as was Mrs
Sedley. Mr Sedley did not attend the ceremony.
George and Amelia went to Brighton for their
honeymoon. They were accompanied by Jos Sedley.
Here they met up with Captain Crawley and his
wife. Jos was now wearing military-style clothing
in honour of the coming war, and George
and Captain Crawley teased him about it.
The two couples spent most of their time together.
The gentlemen had their own amusements after
dinner. They usually played billiards or cards,
and this allowed Captain Crawley to
acquire some much-needed ready money.
One day Dobbin came down to
Brighton to see his friends.
He greeted them in a friendly
way, but his face was serious.
'What's the news?' George asked
eagerly. 'What does my father say?'
'I'll tell you everything later,' Dobbin said
quietly. 'The really important thing is - '
'Come on, tell us!' George cried excitedly.
'The campaign's started. We're going to Belgium,
old boy. O'Dowd's in command. We leave next week.'
It was true that Dobbin had been to see Mr
Osborne, to break the news of his son's marriage
to Amelia. The interview had not been a success.
Mr Osborne was furious at his son's disobedience,
and furious with poor Dobbin as well
for having encouraged the match.
When he returned home that evening, Mr Osborne sat
for many hours in his study. He adored his son,
but he was a very proud man, and George's
marriage had disappointed him bitterly.
Mr Osborne took down the family Bible, where
the names of all his children were inscribed.
He eliminated George's name. Then
he wrote a letter to the bank,
instructing the cashier not to
pay further funds to his son.
Another visitor who was staying
at Brighton was Miss Crawley.
Becky made Rawdon write the old lady
a note. Then Becky took the note to
Briggs and begged her to deliver it.
Miss Crawley laughed when she read it.
'Don't you see,' she cried,
'Rawdon never wrote a word of it!
His letters are always about money, and
they're full of spelling mistakes and bad
grammar. It's that little governess of his who
told him what to say!' In her heart she felt
sad and bitter. She knew that everyone
wanted her dead; they wanted her money.
'You may tell Captain Crawley,' she informed
Briggs, 'that he can call on my lawyer in London.
There will be something for him there.'
Rawdon and Becky were delighted
at the news from Miss Crawley.
They hurried as fast as they
could to London. Rawdon then
made his way to the lawyer's office.
He looked gloomy when he joined Becky.
'It's a rotten trick, Becky,' he told her.
'The old lady's only given me twenty pounds!'
The joke was too good for Becky to resist.
She looked at Rawdon's serious
face, and burst out laughing.
CHAPTER SIX
Preparations for War
The Osbornes and Dobbin now made their way
to Chatham, from where the regiment was to
embark for Europe. Amelia was presented to
Peggy O'Dowd, the commanding officer's wife.
Peggy O'Dowd was a friendly Irishwoman,
and she made Amelia very welcome.
'We're all good friends here,'
she explained cheerfully. 'There
isn't a happier regiment in the whole army.'
Jos had agreed to accompany Amelia to Europe,
and everyone noticed that his appearance
became more and more military every day.
At last they arrived in Brussels
where the regiment was quartered.
Everyone was delighted with the city, and all
the Vanity Fair booths were laid out before them
with their usual attractions. There
was gambling for those who liked it,
there was a theatre, and above all, there was
a huge throng of lords, ladies and gentlemen.
George was enthusiastic about the social
life of Brussels. One evening he danced with
one of Lady Bareacre's daughters. He even
invited the Bareacres to a grand dinner.
They accepted the invitation, but
they refused to speak to poor Amelia,
whom they considered their social inferior. She
passed a very miserable evening in their company.
One day Captain Crawley and
Becky arrived in the city.
They were travelling with General Tufto, and
they mixed in the very highest military circles.
George was quite proud to know the Crawleys,
and to be seen around the city with them.
Becky was in the very best of humours. She
teased poor Jos about their old romance,
and she flirted with George. Amelia
was uncomfortable in her presence.
She felt that Becky's influence
on her husband was not a good one.
Dobbin was more forthright still.
'What a humbug that woman
is!' he commented to George.
A grand ball was planned, and everyone was
desperate to have a ticket to the social
event of the year. Jos and Mrs O'Dowd were
unlucky, but the Bareacres obtained tickets
for Captain Osborne and his wife. Dobbin
was given a ticket by a general he knew.
George bought new clothes for Amelia, and drove
her to the ball. She did not know anyone there,
and sat by herself while her husband
went off to look for his friends.
Amelia was unhappy, and the only person
who came to talk to her was honest Dobbin.
Becky, meanwhile, had made a splendid entrance.
She immediately joined the most select
group of people at the ball, and was soon
the centre of attention with the men there.
She spoke French perfectly, and everyone wanted to
dance with her. Then she spotted Amelia, and came
over to join her on the bench. She criticised
her clothes, commented happily on the ball,
and then gave her friend a lot of advice
that humiliated poor Amelia even more.
When George saw that Becky had joined his wife,
he too hurried over to the bench. He
asked Becky to dance, and she agreed.
They danced together two or three times. Amelia
was very unhappy. Tears came into her eyes.
Then George ran back to collect
Becky's shawl and flowers.
Becky was leaving the ball.
George carried her bouquet to her,
but when he gave it to her she saw that there
was a note lying among the flowers. Becky had
received many such notes in her life. She smiled
at George, and turned towards her husband.
Amelia was watching the scene between
George and Becky. She turned very pale.
'William,' she said quietly, 'I don't
feel very well. Please take me home.'
Dobbin escorted her away from the ball.
George, meanwhile, was in a very elated mood. He
did not notice that his wife had left the ball.
He gambled at the tables, winning repeatedly.
Then he began drinking heavily. Dobbin found
him in a very excitable mood when
he returned from Amelia's hotel.
'Come out, George,' Dobbin said quietly.
'Nonsense!' George cried. 'Come
and drink with me, my old friend!'
Dobbin came close to him.
'The enemy is advancing,' he whispered.
'We're leaving in three hours.'
There was little sleep for anyone that night.
Everyone was busy preparing for the
sudden departure for the battlefield.
George made his way quickly to the
hotel, where Amelia was already in bed.
He thought about the short weeks
of his marriage and blushed with
shame when he thought about the
note he had given to Becky Sharp.
'What will happen to Amelia
if I die?' he asked himself.
He wrote a letter to his father, asking him
to look after his wife if he was killed,
and thanking him for his past kindness.
He was very kind to her the next morning before
he went away. Amelia was very upset to see him go.
The O'Dowds were also making their
preparations for the departure.
'Call me at half-past one, my dear,' the Major
said quietly to his wife. 'And have my things
ready for me.' This was his way of indicating
that the regiment was marching the next morning.
Rawdon spent the last hours with Becky reckoning
up what he could leave behind for
Becky if anything happened to him.
'Look,' he said, 'I've been
lucky recently at cards - here's
two hundred and fifty pounds in
cash. Then there are my horses.'
Captain Crawley, who cheated his friends at cards,
and who never paid his debts, had tears in his
eyes when he lifted Becky up to kiss her goodbye.
Becky had wisely decided not
to give in to her emotions.
Captain Dobbin called on Jos
very early in the morning.
Jos was not pleased to be woken up and
he greeted Dobbin without enthusiasm.
'What can I do for you?' he enquired coldly.
'George and I are marching in an hour,' Dobbin
explained. 'I want you to look after your sister.
If something happens to the army, take her back
to England. You're the only person she's got!'
Soon after they all marched out of the city.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Battle of Waterloo
There was great excitement in Brussels after
the British army had marched
out to meet Napoleon's troops.
Jos, meanwhile, was surprised to receive
a visit from Becky Sharp that morning.
He had not been invited to any of the
grand social events in which she had
played such a brilliant part, and he
was offended at her neglect. Becky,
who was not sure of a British victory, decided
to become friends with her old admirer again.
'I'm sure you're getting ready to join the army,'
she told him. 'Soon there'll be nobody
left in Brussels to protect us poor women!'
Jos was delighted at the idea that
she thought he was joining the army.
'I should like to see the battle,' he replied
grandly, 'but I have my sister to protect.'
'What a good brother you are!' Becky exclaimed.
She put her handkerchief to her eyes.
'Your heart is true to your sister,' she went on,
'but I remember a time when it was false to me!'
Jos blushed furiously. He did
not know what to say to her.
'I've avoided you here in Brussels,' Becky
went on. 'What else could I do? Do you think
my husband could bear to speak to you? You're the
only man he's ever been jealous of, you know!'
Poor Jos was delighted at this speech. He
forgot his doubts and suspicions of Becky.
Becky observed him closely.
'At least he'll give me a place in his
carriage if the army is defeated,' she thought.
Becky then went into Amelia's room to greet her.
She found her ill because she was worried about
George. Amelia regarded her as an enemy now, and
the interview was a painful one for the two women.
'You tried to do me wrong,' Amelia complained.
'You tried to take my husband from me,
Rebecca. But he came back to me, you see -
he came back to me!' She burst into tears.
Becky left Amelia's room. For once she was silent.
Her friend's tears had moved her. She happened to
encounter Mrs Peggy O'Dowd in the street outside,
and she told her that Amelia was very
upset. The good lady hurried to the house.
Brussels was full of rumours
about the great battle.
Jos grew increasingly nervous.
He was not a brave man,
and what he heard from his servants frightened
him. He began to think about leaving the city. He
told Amelia that he thought it was best to prepare
to leave, but she refused to listen to him.
That night Jos's fears increased to panic. Some
Belgian soldiers had retreated into the city,
and one of these took refuge with the maid
in Jos's house. The young soldier was tired
and hungry, and he told terrible stories
about the defeat of the British army.
'The Duke of Wellington is
a prisoner,' he insisted,
'and the whole army is in
flight. Napoleon has won.'
Jos had come into the kitchen
to hear the soldier's account,
and he was now wild with terror. He changed out of
his military-style clothes as quickly as he could,
and ordered his servant to prepare the carriage.
'There are no horses left in
Brussels, sir,' the servant told him.
Jos dashed into the street. He ran to all
the hotels in a desperate search for horses.
In one hotel he saw Lady Bareacres and
her daughters sitting in a carriage.
They, too, were waiting for horses.
Lady Bareacres was also
desperate to abandon the city.
This proud lady, who had refused to acknowledge
Becky when they passed on the stairs,
now came to ask her to sell
Captain Crawley's horses.
'I won't sell you my horses, my
Lady,' Becky told her proudly,
'not for the two largest
diamonds you wore at the ball.'
Just then Becky caught sight
of Jos entering the hotel.
The frightened expression on
his face told her everything.
'He will buy my horses,' she decided.
Jos and Becky were soon in earnest
conversation together. The price
she asked for the horses was a huge one, but
Jos was so terrified that he agreed to pay.
Jos now told his servant to prepare the horses.
He had decided to ride out of the city as soon
as he could. He went back once more to
Amelia to persuade her to come with him.
'Emmy, I'm leaving today,' he told her, 'and
you must come with me. There's no time to lose!'
'You're a coward, Mr Sedley,'
Peggy O'Dowd told him quietly.
'Never mind her!' cried Jos. 'Are
you coming with me or not, Emmy?'
Amelia was too ill to move.
'Without my husband, Jos?' Amelia replied.
Jos saw that it was useless.
'Goodbye, then,' he said in a rage, and left the
room. A few minutes later the two ladies saw him
riding awkwardly down the street on one of Becky's
horses, followed by his servant on the other.
The noise of the great battle could be
heard throughout the city all that day.
At last the guns grew silent.
The English had their victory.
Darkness fell. Amelia was praying for
her husband, who was lying on his face,
dead, with a bullet through his heart.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Miss Crawley
Miss Crawley was now living in Brighton,
and she read the news of the Battle of
Waterloo with great interest. Rawdon
had been promoted; he was now a Colonel.
'What a pity that fine young
man behaved as he did!'
said the kind-hearted Briggs. She wanted
Miss Crawley to forgive Rawdon and Becky.
'Rawdon's a fool,' the old lady replied angrily.
'He could have married well if he'd had my
money behind him. But he won't get any of it now!'
Rawdon and Becky took good care to
write regularly to Miss Crawley,
and the old lady was amused by their letters,
although she knew perfectly well that it
was Becky who wrote them and not her nephew.
Miss Crawley's attitude to the family
at the rectory was not so warm.
She had been frightened by Mrs Bute Crawley
during her illness in London. Worse than that,
she had been bored by the rector's wife. Still,
presents of farm produce arrived regularly at Miss
Crawley's house in Brighton, with tender notes
of affection from the family at the rectory.
Rawdon's brother, Pitt, was
also attentive to his aunt.
He came frequently to Brighton to visit his
fiancee, Lady Jane Sheepshanks, who lived in the
town with her sisters and mother, the formidable
and religious-minded Countess Southdown.
Pitt hinted to Lady Southdown that
it might be beneficial for her family
to make a friendship with his aunt. He told her
that Miss Crawley was now all alone in the world.
'I'll certainly visit the poor lady,' the Countess
responded enthusiastically. 'I'll leave
her some religious literature as well.'
'No, my dear lady,' said the artful Pitt. 'She
has been seriously ill, and she has not been
accustomed to think of spiritual matters. We
must proceed slowly. Besides,' he added quietly,
'we don't want to frighten the poor lady. She
has seventy thousand pounds. Think of that.'
Countess Southdown nodded her head in agreement.
The next day the Southdown carriage
pulled up outside Miss Crawley's house.
The visit was a great success, and Miss Crawley
took particularly to Pitt's fiancee Lady Jane.
Pitt was in high spirits,
and spent his time daydreaming about
the old lady's seventy thousand pounds.
News of the friendship between Pitt Crawley
and his aunt soon reached the rectory,
and Mrs Bute Crawley decided to
make one further effort to win
the old lady's fortune for her family. She
sent her son James to visit Miss Crawley.
James was a student. He was a simple young fellow,
more interested in sport and beer than in his
studies. He was no match for Pitt Crawley. The
older man encouraged him to drink too much wine,
and led him on to entertain the ladies with some
exciting sporting stories. James swayed drunkenly
up the stairs to his bedroom. When he arrived
there he opened the window and lit his pipe.
He stared happily out at the sea, smoking
contentedly. He had forgotten, however,
to close the bedroom door behind him - and the
smell of pipe tobacco spread through the house.
The following morning he
received a note from Briggs.
Dear Sir,
Miss Crawley has spent a sleepless night because
of the smell of pipe tobacco throughout the house.
She is to unwell to see you
before you leave the house.
And so ended the rectory family's hopes
of receiving Miss Crawley's fortune.
Rawdon and Becky, meanwhile, were enjoying
themselves in Paris, where they had enough
money to live in luxury thanks to the
huge price Jos had paid for the horses.
Becky gave birth to a son during their stay in
Paris. Miss Crawley was furious at the news,
and immediately ordered
Pitt and Lady Jane to marry.
She promised to leave them the bulk
of her fortune after her death.
The newlyweds settled into
Miss Crawley's Brighton home,
and they were all ruled over by Lady
Southdown from her neighbouring house.
Lady Southdown was so terrifying that Miss Crawley
lost all her cheerfulness. She even began to treat
Briggs kindly as she moved slowly towards death.
The old lady died clinging in fear to Lady Jane.
CHAPTER NINE
Life on Nothing a Year
News was continually arriving in England of the
terrible casualties of the Battle of Waterloo.
The Osborne family learned of George's
death. Old Mr Osborne was grief- stricken
but he carried on his business as usual.
He never mentioned George's name to anyone.
One day Dobbin's father, Sir William
Dobbin, called at Mr Osborne's house.
'My son has sent me a letter
for you,' he explained.
Mr Osborne looked at the letter, and his
heart began to beat quickly. The writing
was his son's. It was the letter George had
written before leaving Amelia in Brussels.
Mr Osborne suffered greatly in this period.
He travelled to Belgium to visit the site of
the historic battlefield, and
he saw George's burial-place.
One evening, as he was coming back into Brussels,
Mr Osborne saw a carriage driving towards him.
An officer was riding by the side
of it. Mr Osborne was surprised to
see that one of the occupants of the
carriage was his son's widow Amelia,
and that the officer on horseback was his son's
friend Dobbin. Amelia was pale and withdrawn,
and did not notice her father-in-law. He,
however, gazed at her in fury and hatred.
A few minutes later Dobbin rode
up to Mr Osborne's carriage.
He held out his hand but Mr
Osborne refused to take it.
'I have a message for you,' Dobbin said quietly.
'I am the executor of George's will, and am
therefore responsible for his widow's welfare.
Are you aware how little money he left her?'
Dobbin explained that Amelia was expecting
a child. He tried to persuade Mr Osborne
that the time for hatred and bitterness was
gone, and that Amelia needed his support.
'I have promised to have nothing
to do with that woman, sir,'
Mr Osborne commented angrily.
'I shall not change my mind.'
Months now passed, and Amelia gave birth to
a son. The loyal Major Dobbin was constantly
in attendance upon her, and brought her
back to her parents' house in England.
He became the baby's godfather. The poor
girl was so depressed by the death of
George that she did not seem to notice the
Major's kindness to her. Dobbin, however,
never dared to mention his love to her. He knew
that Amelia was loyal to her husband's memory.
One day the Major came to Amelia's
house looking particularly serious.
'I'm going away,' he told her. 'I shall be gone a
long time. You'll write to
me, won't you, my dear?'
'I'll write to you about little
Georgy,' Amelia replied with a smile.
'How kind you've been to us, dear William!'
Three or four years after their triumphant stay in
Paris, Rawdon Crawley and Becky were living in a
fine little house in Curzon Street, Mayfair.
They entertained their friends splendidly.
Yet there were few of their friends
who did not sometimes wonder
how Colonel Crawley managed to live so well.
He did not seem to have any income at all.
There are many people in Vanity Fair
who succeed very well on nothing a year.
The Colonel, for example, was an excellent
card-player, and excelled at billiards and
other games of chance. He spent many
evenings playing against his friends,
and his winnings provided him and Becky with
the small amounts of cash they required.
For the rest, the couple lived on credit, as
many others in Vanity Fair are obliged to do.
The house in Curzon Street
belonged to a Mr Raggles,
who had previously been Miss Crawley's butler.
After leaving Miss Crawley's service, Mr Raggles
and his wife had bought a shop selling foodstuffs.
They worked hard and saved their money carefully.
After many years Mr Raggles was able to
buy the little house in Curzon Street.
He intended to rent out the property and was
delighted to have a member of the Crawley
family as his tenant. The young couple also
ordered their food from the Raggles' shop.
One of Becky's first plans when they
settled in London was to establish
good relations with Rawdon's brother, Pitt. He
had inherited most of Miss Crawley's fortune.
Although Rawdon and Becky had their house in
Mayfair and gave select little parties there,
society ladies did not want anything to do with
Becky. They had heard too many unpleasant stories
about her from people like Lady Bareacres. Most
of the visitors to Curzon Street were gentlemen.
Becky found this position humiliating, and
she determined to do something about it.
One of the regular visitors to the Crawley
household was Lord Steyne, a great and powerful
nobleman who occupied a very strong position in
London society. Lord Steyne was one of Becky's
greatest admirers. Becky thought that Lord
Steyne could introduce her to London society.
This was not a happy time for Rawdon himself.
He knew that people came to the house
to see his brilliant and charming wife,
and that they found him a bore. He preferred
to spend his time with his little son, Rawdon.
He went for long walks with the boy, and he
took him to see his old friends at the barracks.
CHAPTER TEN
Misleading Letters
Jos Sedley returned to India
after his adventures in Brussels.
He sent a small amount of money to his parents
to maintain their modest little house in Fulham.
The Sedley household lived in a very small way.
Old Mr Sedley tried various little business
schemes in an effort to recover his fortune,
but all of them came to nothing. Amelia herself
had no thoughts for anything except her son.
The family received few visitors
now that Dobbin was abroad again,
although the local curate at the church
where they worshipped called quite often.
People said the reason for his calls was Amelia,
but she took little notice of the young man.
The years went by, and George
grew into a healthy young boy.
He was full of energy, and everyone
said he looked just like his father.
Old Sir Pitt Crawley died, to the relief of all
his family. He had become increasingly eccentric
in his final years, and his behaviour had been
a scandal throughout the county. His son, Pitt,
inherited the property and the title, and as he
had already inherited Miss Crawley's fortune,
he was now a man of substance and importance.
His thoughts turned to a career in politics.
Rawdon and Becky were, of course, invited to
attend the old man's funeral at Queen's Crawley.
Becky received the invitation with delight.
'Why are you so happy about it?' Rawdon
asked in astonishment. 'There's no money
coming to me from my father's death.
You don't really want to go, do you?'
'Of course we're going!' Becky cried. 'Lady
Jane shall present me at Court next year,
and Pitt will give you a seat in Parliament!'
'What about little Rawdy - is he coming with us?'
Rawdon asked tenderly. He did not like being
parted from his son for more than a few days.
'No,' said Becky, 'he can stay here
with Briggs - she'll look after him.'
The faithful Briggs had come to work for
the young couple after Miss Crawley's death.
The visit was a great success for Becky. She
behaved herself with modesty and tact in front
of the new Sir Pitt Crawley, and flattered his
political ambitions. She talked sentimentally
about her son in front of the kind-hearted
Lady Jane, and won that lady's friendship.
With Lady Jane's mother, the Countess
of Southdown, she talked religion.
Amelia, meanwhile, wrote
regularly to Major Dobbin,
who was with the army in India. She
gave him all the news about Georgy.
She also visited his sisters sometimes. One
day the sisters told her some important news.
'William's getting married.'
She wrote to congratulate him, and
to wish him happiness for the future.
Georgy went to see Dobbin's sisters by
himself sometimes, and he came back from one
such visit wearing a beautiful gold watch.
He said that a lady had given it to him.
Amelia guessed that the lady was
a member of the Osborne family.
In fact, it was George Osborne's sister, who
had also been visiting the Dobbin sisters.
When Miss Osborne arrived home that afternoon,
she told old Mr Osborne that she had seen Georgy.
'He looks just like his
father,' she said tearfully.
The old man did not reply, but he went very red
in the face and began to shake with emotion. He
still hated the Sedleys, but he wanted to see his
grandson. Slowу a plan began to form in his mind.
Dobbin was astonished to receive Amelia's letter
congratulating him on his coming marriage.
It was true that Peggy O'Dowd had been trying
to persuade him to marry a relative of hers,
but Dobbin was in love with Amelia. He
was not interested in any other girls.
When he read Amelia's letter he realised that
she did not understand what he felt for her.
'Don't you realise that it's you I love?'
he thought. 'Don't you remember how I looked
after you when George was killed - how
I brought you safely back to England?'
A little while later Dobbin received
another letter from England. His
sisters told him about Amelia. 'She's
going to marry the curate at her local
church,' they wrote. 'And Georgy is
going to live with his grandfather.'
Both pieces of news disturbed Dobbin very much.
'Amelia will not marry again,' he thought,
'and I'm sure she'll never give up Georgy to Mr
Osborne.' He suspected that she was in trouble,
and once again he was determined to help her.
He immediately asked for
urgent leave to go to England.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Amelia Makes a Sacrifice
Becky was now back in London preparing Sir
Pitt Crawley's house for his return there.
Sir Pitt knew that Rawdon
and Becky were very poor.
He was very fond of money, however,
and did not offer his brother any.
Little Rawdon thought his mother was
the most beautiful woman in the world,
but he preferred spending time with his
father, who talked to him and played
with him. Becky usually ignored him, and made
him eat in the kitchen when she had visitors.
One evening the boy was in bed when he heard
his mother singing. Becky had a fine voice,
and the little boy crept downstairs to listen.
He opened the door of the drawing room so that
he could hear better. Lord Steyne was in the
room with his mother, and he saw the boy.
Becky rushed out of the drawing room and smacked
Rawdon very hard. The boy ran away to the kitchen.
'I'm not crying because she hit me,' he told the
servants. 'But why can't I listen when she sings?
She sings for that man, but
she never sings for me!'
Rawdon and Becky had many creditors,
but the sight of Lord Steyne's carriage
outside the house every night made
them confident that Becky was rich.
They knew that Lord Steyne was
one of the richest men in England.
As for Colonel Crawley, he felt out of place with
the fashionable people who came to visit his wife.
He spent most of his time playing with
little Rawdon, or dining at one of his
clubs with his old army friends. He saw
very little of Becky in this period.
Trouble came to the Sedley household. The family
had just enough money to live off from Jos,
but old Mr Sedley began to invest the money that
Jos sent from India. All his investments failed,
however, and he lost the money. Mrs Sedley was
afraid of the tradesmen who wanted to be paid.
Amelia did not know anything about the
financial difficulties of the household.
Just when Mrs Sedley was desperate about money,
a letter came for Amelia from old Mr Osborne.
He said that he wanted Georgy to come and live
with him. He wanted to give the boy a splendid
education, and Mr Osborne promised to leave him
all his money when he died. He also offered to pay
Amelia a small allowance. Amelia was offended
by Mr Osborne's offer and she refused it.
The great day came for Becky when she
was presented at Court to George IV.
She attended the event with Sir
Pitt and his wife Lady Jane.
Everyone noticed that she was wearing
some splendid diamonds for the occasion.
'Where did they come from, Becky?'
Rawdon asked her in wonder.
'Where do you think, you silly man!'
she said with a laugh. 'I hired them,
of course. You don't suppose that all the diamonds
that ladies wear to Court belong to them, do you?'
Becky never returned the diamonds to a shop,
however, after her appearance at Court. She
hid them away in her desk. The only other person
who knew the truth about them was Lord Steyne.
Lord Steyne called on Becky later that day.
'Send that Briggs woman away,' he complained.
'I can't come here without running into her.'
'I can't,' said Becky sadly.
'I owe her money, you see. She gave me all her
money to invest for her and I've spent it.'
Lord Steyne swore angrily.
'How much is it?' he asked angrily.
That evening Becky received
a cheque from Lord Steyne.
She did not pay off her debt to Briggs,
however. She paid some of her other bills,
and the rest of the money she hid
away in the desk with the diamonds.
At last Amelia discovered the truth about her
father's investments. The Sedleys were now
completely ruined. The only way to save the family
was to accept old Mr Osborne's offer to look after
Georgy. The boy himself was quite excited at the
idea of going to live with his rich relatives.
He did not realise how much his mother
suffered at the change. It nearly broke
her heart to see the boy go off to his new
home, but there was nothing else she could do.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Imprisonment and Violence
Little Rawdon had been sent off to an expensive
school paid for by his Lordship, and Briggs had
been found another job. Lord Steyne often passed
the evening with Becky and Rawdon at their house.
One night Becky and Rawdon went
to a party at Lord Steyne's house.
Rawdon stayed behind after his wife left, to smoke
a cigar with Lord Steyne's assistant, Wenham.
The two men strolled through the streets
together. Suddenly they were joined by
three other men, one of whom touched Rawdon on
the shoulder. He knew immediately what it was.
These men had come to arrest him for debt.
'Lend me a hundred, Wenham,' Rawdon asked.
'I haven't got any money,' Wenham replied.
The men took Rawdon off to prison. He was not
worried, as he was sure that Becky had money
to save him. He wrote her a note explaining
what had happened. Then he lay down to sleep.
He waited all the next day for some message from
Becky. At last a letter arrived in the evening.
Becky said she was ill in bed, but that
Lord Steyne had some money to send him.
Rawdon blushed as he read his wife's letter. He
remembered that he had been walking with Lord
Steyne's assistant when the men arrested him.
Had there been a plot to get him out of the way?
He wrote to Sir Pitt Crawley now, and in an hour
Lady Jane arrived with the money that he needed.
Rawdon was ashamed. He realised that Lady Jane
was kind, and he wanted to change his life.
Rawdon hurried home. He was surprised to see
that the drawing room was lit up, when Becky
had told him she was ill. He entered the house
quietly and approached the drawing-room door.
He could hear Becky singing.
When he opened the door
he saw that there were only two people in the
room, Becky and Lord Steyne. He saw that Becky
was wearing the splendid diamonds that were
supposed to have been hired and returned.
Becky looked up in horror as she saw her husband.
'I'm innocent, Rawdon,' she cried.
'You must believe me, I'm innocent!'
Lord Steyne, meanwhile, thought that Rawdon and
Becky had planned to trap him. He was furious.
'Innocent, you!' he shouted at Becky.
'I've given you thousands of pounds
that you and this man have spent
together. Don't try to fool me.'
Rawdon hit Lord Steyne, who fell to the floor.
Then he made Becky remove all of her jewellery,
and he hurled it at the frightened
nobleman. One of the pieces struck
Lord Steyne on the forehead. It left a scar
that he carried for the rest of his life.
Now Rawdon made Becky open her desk. He
saw that there was a lot of money inside,
including the cheque from Lord Steyne.
'I'll send this back to him in the
morning,' he told her grimly. 'You
might have got me out of prison,' he told
her sadly. 'I always shared with you.'
Then Rawdon left the house. Becky
understood that he was gone forever.
All her plans had come to nothing.
Rawdon was determined to
fight a duel with Lord Steyne.
First he went to see Sir Pitt to ask him to
look after his son if anything happened to him.
Then he went to his club to ask one of
his officer friends to arrange the duel.
Later that day Becky came to see Sir Pitt
Crawley. Sir Pitt had seen something in
that morning's newspaper that he wanted to
discuss with her. There was an article saying
that Colonel Rawdon Crawley was expected to
be appointed Governor of Coventry Island.
'It's true,' Becky told him.
'Lord Steyne organised it for him.
Don't you see, Pitt, everything I
did was for Rawdon. I'm innocent!'
Lady Jane was not happy to see Becky.
She asked her to leave the house.
Rawdon's army friend had also seen the
newspaper article and he showed it to Rawdon.
Wenham walked into the club.
'You're making a terrible mistake,
Crawley,' Wenham said. 'It was only
by chance that your wife and Lord Steyne
were alone in the house that evening.
My wife and I had also been invited, but we
couldn't come because Mrs Wenham had a headache.'
Rawdon did not believe Wenham's story, but
he saw that he could not fight Lord Steyne
now in the light of Wenham's evidence.
He thought very carefully about what he should do.
In the end he decided to accept the Governorship
of Coventry Island. He wrote very regularly
to little Rawdon from there, but he never
contacted his wife again. Little Rawdon spent
his school holidays with Sir Pitt and Lady Jane.
Becky herself was now ruined. Her servants
and creditors all demanded to be paid,
and Mr Raggles took his house back. He
was ruined as well. Thus Vanity Fair
makes other people pay for its
pleasures. Becky fled the country.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Final Destinies
Major Dobbin came as quickly as he could
back to England. He met Jos on the journey,
and they travelled together. Jos told Dobbin
that Amelia had not mentioned any plan to marry,
and this news cheered the Major up considerably.
Dobbin hurried to Amelia's house as soon as
he arrived in England. There he learned that
Mrs Sedley had died, and that Georgy was now
living with Mr Osborne. Georgy was happy in the
old man's house. He did not think often about
his mother. He did not understand her pain.
Mr Sedley died soon after Dobbin's arrival
in the country, and Dobbin was now George's
guardian. He had to pay a visit to Mr
Osborne to discuss the boy's futures.
Old Mr Osborne had looked through his son's
papers, and he now realised that Dobbin had
been sending Amelia money for years. He
asked Dobbin to explain what had happened.
'Well, sir,' Dobbin told him, 'the marriage was
very much my doing. I thought George had gone too
far to let Amelia down. And so, when she was left
without money, I did what I could to help her.'
Mr Osborne turned very red in the face.
'You did me a great injury,' he said. 'But you're
an honest man, sir. Let me shake your hand.'
Dobbin did everything he could to make peace
between the Sedley and the Osborne families.
'It's true that Amelia took your son away
from you,' he said once to Mr Osborne,
'but you have also taken her son away from her.'
Finally Mr Osborne's hatred for
the Sedleys began to fade away.
He made a new will, leaving some money
to Amelia as well as Georgy. He never
met Amelia again, however, because he
died suddenly after a heart attack.
Dobbin, meanwhile, had told
Amelia that he loved her,
but all she offered him was
her friendship and gratitude.
Jos, Amelia, Dobbin and Georgy now
went on a tour of Europe together.
They stopped at a large town in Germany,
and Jos went off - to play roulette.
He was very surprised to be greeted
by the woman sitting next to him.
'Mrs Crawley!' he gasped in astonishment.
'Call me Becky,' she replied
softly. 'You always used to.'
Becky now used all her charm on the gullible Jos.
She told him that she was very poor now, and
that she had enemies who made her life miserable.
Jos told Dobbin that he had met Becky.
'Her again!' Dobbin exclaimed.
'She causes trouble everywhere.'
Amelia did not want to see Becky at first,
but at last Jos persuaded her. He told her
that Becky was very unhappy. The meeting
went well, and Jos and Amelia invited
Becky to come and stay in their hotel.
For once Dobbin was angry with Amelia.
'Don't let her come,' he advised her.
'She wasn't always your friend, Amelia.'
Amelia was suddenly very angry with
Dobbin. She remembered how unhappy she
had been when her husband had abandoned
her at the ball to dance with Becky.
'That was cruel of you!' she cried.
The next day Dobbin apologised for his remark.
He said that he had heard bad things about Becky.
Amelia did not forgive him.
'I've loved you for many years,' he told
her bitterly. 'Now I see that you were not
worth the devotion I have spent on you. You can
cherish memories, but you cannot love as I do.
It's not your fault, but I have decided:
I'm going away. I shan't ever come back.'
Becky overheard the argument
between Amelia and Dobbin.
'She's a fool,' she thought. 'That man loves her.'
Dobbin left the town and returned to England.
The days went by, and Jos and
Becky spent more time together.
Amelia and Georgy missed Dobbin terribly.
Amelia wrote to him, but she did not
tell anyone that she had done so.
'You must go away from here,' Becky told Amelia.
'You must go away and marry again.
You must accept your faithful friend.'
'I shall never marry again,'
Amelia told her. 'I have tried,
but I can't forget George. He
was the only man in my life.'
Becky gave her friend an old letter. Amelia was
astonished to recognise George's handwriting.
It was the letter he had put among Becky's
flowers the night of the dance in Brussels.
He had asked Becky to run away with him.
At first Amelia cried when she thought about her
faithless husband. Then she began to remember
Dobbin and his constant love for her. She
realised that she was free to love Dobbin now!
Soon Amelia and Dobbin were happily married in
England. At last Dobbin had married his true love.
They went to live near Sir Pitt and Lady
Jane. The two families became great friends.
Jos remained in Europe with Becky.
There were rumours that Jos was ill,
and that he had taken out a huge
insurance policy on his life.
Amelia was worried about her brother, and
asked Dobbin to find out what was happening.
Dobbin discovered that Jos and Becky
were in Brussels. He managed to see
Jos without Becky knowing about his visit.
Jos looked unwell and he seemed frightened.
'Don't let Becky know you've been here,'
he begged Dobbin. 'I'm afraid of her.'
'Come away with me now,' Dobbin suggested.
But it was no good. Jos could
not bring himself to leave Becky.
Three months later Jos was dead.
The circumstances were suspicious,
and at first the insurance company refused to pay
the sum due on his life policy. The company had
no evidence that Jos's death was due to unnatural
causes, however. In the end they paid the money.
Becky, who now called herself 'Lady Crawley',
settled in England once more. Her husband Rawdon
died of yellow fever on Coventry Island, six
weeks before the death of his older brother
Sir Pitt Crawley. The whole Crawley estate thus
came to Becky's son who became Sir Rawdon Crawley.
He always refused to see his mother,
but he made her a generous allowance.
Amelia and Dobbin saw Becky once again when
they were in London with their children. Becky
smiled as Dobbin and Amelia grabbed their
children and walked quickly away from her.
- THE END -