Mr Hiram B. Otis was a rich
American from New York.
He had come to live and work in England,
but he did not want to live in London.
He did not want to live in the city. He wanted
to live in the countryside outside London.
Canterville Chase was a large
and very old house near London.
Lord Canterville, the owner, wanted to sell it.
So Mr Hiram B. Otis visited Lord Canterville.
'I do not live in Canterville Chase,' Lord
Canterville said to Mr Otis. 'I do not want
to live there. The house has a
ghost - The Canterville Ghost.'
'I come from America,' said Mr
Otis. 'America is a modern country.
I don't believe in ghosts. Have
you seen this Canterville Ghost?'
'No,' said Lord Canterville,
'but I have heard it at night.'
'I don't believe in ghosts,' Mr Otis
said again. 'No one has found a ghost.
No one has put a ghost in a museum. And
you haven't seen this ghost either.'
'But several members of my family have seen it,'
said Lord Canterville. 'My aunt saw the ghost.
She was so frightened that she
was ill for the rest of her life.
Also, the servants have seen it so they
will not stay in the house at night.
Only the housekeeper, Mrs Umney, lives in
Canterville Chase. Mrs Umney lives there alone.'
'I want to buy the house,' said Mr Otis.
'I'll buy the ghost as well. Will you sell
Canterville Chase? Will you sell the ghost?'
'Yes, I will,' said Lord
Canterville. 'But, please remember,
I told you about the ghost
before you bought the house.'
Mr Hiram B. Otis bought Canterville Chase.
Then his family came to England from America.
He had a wife called Lucretia,
three sons and a daughter.
The eldest son, Washington, was almost twenty
years old. He was good-looking and had fair
hair. His two young brothers were twins. They
were twelve years old. The daughter, Virginia,
was fifteen years old. She had
large blue eyes and a lovely face.
Mr Otis took his family to
live at Canterville Chase.
The old house was in the countryside west of
London. Mr Otis and his family travelled from
London by train. Then they rode to the
house in a wagon pulled by two horses.
Canterville Chase was big and old. Trees grew
all around the house. The Otis family wanted to
stop and look at the outside of the house, but
the sky darkened. A thunderstorm was coming.
Rain started to fall, so the family
went inside the house quickly.
Mrs Umney, the housekeeper, was waiting for them
by the front door. She was an old woman and wore
a black dress and white apron. She lived at
Canterville Chase and looked after the house.
'Welcome to Canterville Chase,' said
Mrs Umney. 'Would you like some tea?'
'Yes, please,' said Mrs Otis.
The Otis family followed Mrs Umney into the
library. There was a big table in the centre of
the room and many chairs. Mrs Umney put teacups
on the table, then she brought a pot of tea.
The Otises sat in the library and drank their tea.
They looked out of a large window at the rain.
The rain was falling heavily and the sky was
black. They heard thunder and they saw lightning.
Mrs Otis looked around the room. There were many
books on bookshelves. There were paintings on
the walls. There was also a red stain on the
floor. The red stain was by the fireplace.
'What is this red stain?'
Mrs Otis asked Mrs Umney.
'It is blood,' answered the old
housekeeper in a quiet voice.
'I don't want a blood-stain in my library,'
said Mrs Otis. 'Please remove the stain.
Please clean the floor immediately.'
The old woman smiled. 'It is the
blood of Lady Eleanore de Canterville.
She was murdered by her husband, Sir
Simon de Canterville, in 1575. The
blood-stain has been here for over three
hundred years. It cannot be removed.'
'Nonsense,' said Washington Otis. 'I have
some Pinkerton's Stain Remover from America.
It can remove any stain. Watch.'
Washington Otis took the stain remover
from a bag. Pinkerton's Stain Remover
looked like a small black stick. He rubbed
the stick on the blood-stain. A minute later
the floor was clean. The stick had
removed the stain quickly and easily.
Mrs Umney looked at the floor. She was
frightened. No one had removed the blood-stain
for three hundred years. Mrs
Umney was very frightened.
'Pinkerton's can remove anything,' said
Washington Otis. 'The blood-stain has gone.'
Lightning flashed and lit the library. Thunder
crashed over the house. Mrs Umney fainted.
Mr and Mrs Otis ran across the library. They
helped the old housekeeper who lay on the floor.
Mrs Umney's eyes were closed
and her face was pale.
'Mrs Umney! Mrs Umney!' cried
Mrs Otis. 'Can you speak?'
Mrs Umney opened her eyes.
'Trouble will come to this house,' she said. 'I
have seen the ghost. The ghost will come to you.'
All the Otises helped Mrs Umney to stand
up. 'The ghost will come,' she said again.
'You must not remove the blood-stain. You must not
clean the library floor. The ghost will be angry.'
Then Mrs Umney went upstairs to her room.
'Let's look for the ghost,' said the
Otis boys. 'Let's look round the house.'
The Otises looked round the house together.
But they did not see the Canterville Ghost.
That night the family went to bed early.
The storm continued all night. Next
morning they went into the library. The
blood-stain had reappeared on the floor.
'I'll remove this blood-stain
once more,' said Washington Otis.
'Mother doesn't want a blood-stain in
the library. I'll clean the floor again.'
He removed the blood-stain
with Pinkerton's Stain Remover.
The library floor was clean. But the next
morning the stain had come back again.
'This is very strange,' said Mr Otis.
'I'll lock the library door at night.
No one can come into the library. No
one can put a stain on the floor.'
'I don't think Pinkerton's Stain Remover is bad,'
said Washington Otis. 'I think there really is a
ghost. The ghost is making the blood-stain. The
ghost puts the stain on the floor at night.'
'We must find this ghost,' said Mr Hiram
B. Otis. 'It must stop making these stains.
Your mother does not like
blood on the library floor.'
That day the family went out. They walked
around the countryside near Canterville Chase.
They went to the nearby village. They looked
at the old village houses. Then they walked
back to Canterville Chase through the woods. It
was a summer evening and the weather was fine.
It was late when they got back to the house.
The Otises were hungry and tired. After eating
supper they went to bed. The bedrooms were
upstairs. There was a long corridor upstairs.
The bedroom doors were along this corridor.
Mr Otis woke up after midnight. There
was a strange noise outside his room.
The sound was like metal chains.
The chains were nabbing together.
Mr Otis got out of bed and opened the
bedroom door. He-looked into the corridor.
He saw the Canterville Ghost in the corridor.
The ghost was an old man with burning red eyes.
He had long grey hair and wore very old-fashioned
clothes. There were chains on his hands and feet.
He was rubbing the chains
together so they made a noise.
'My dear sir, your chains make a terrible noise,'
Mr Otis said to the ghost. 'You
must put some oil on those chains.
Here is some Tammany Rising Sun Oil from the
United States. Please put the oil on your chains.'
Mr Otis put a bottle of oil
on a table in the corridor.
Then he closed his bedroom
door and went back to bed.
The Canterville Ghost was very surprised.
He had lived in Canterville Chase for
three hundred years. Everyone was frightened
of him, because everyone was afraid of ghosts.
But this American gentleman was not afraid.
The Canterville Ghost decided to
work harder. He wanted to frighten
the American. He made a terrible noise and
shone a horrible green light in the corridor.
Another door opened at the end of
the corridor. Mr Otis's youngest
sons came out of their bedroom. The two young boys
had the pillows from their beds in their hands.
They threw the pillows at the
ghost. They laughed at the ghost.
The ghost was amazed and upset. No one
had laughed at him before. He was a ghost.
Everyone is frightened of ghosts. No one had
ever laughed at the Canterville Ghost before.
The Canterville Ghost did not know what to do.
He disappeared through the wall
and the house became quiet.
The ghost went to the secret room where he lived.
He sat down on a chair. He
thought about what had happened.
He had frightened people for three hundred years.
He had looked through windows and frightened the
servants. He had knocked on bedroom doors.
He had frightened people in their beds.
He had blown out candles in the night. He had
turned green and made noises with his chains.
Everyone had always been frightened. No one had
given him Rising Sun Oil to put on his chains.
No one had thrown pillows at
him. He was a very unhappy ghost.
Washington Otis removed the blood-stain in
the library every day. Every morning the
stain had reappeared. But the stain
was no longer the color of blood.
One morning it was brown. Another morning
it was purple. Then it became bright green.
The Otises laughed at the blood-stain. They
looked for it every morning before breakfast.
'What color is it today?' asked Washington Otis.
'It's green!' shouted the
twins. 'It's green blood today.'
They laughed at the green
blood-stain on the library floor.
Virginia Otis did not laugh. The
young girl was silent at breakfast.
The blood-stain made her feel sad and she almost
cried when she saw the bright green stain.
She was sure that the ghost put the stain
on the floor. She felt sorry for the ghost.
'The stain has been here for three hundred years,'
said Virginia. 'We have been here for three weeks.
The poor ghost puts the stain on the floor
every night. Can't you leave the stain there?'
But the others did not listen to Virginia.
The second appearance of the ghost was on
a Sunday night. The Otises had all gone
to bed. Suddenly they were woken up. They
heard a terrible crashing noise downstairs.
The whole family ran out of their bedrooms. They
ran downstairs. It was dark but Mr Otis and his
eldest son carried candles. They heard another
crashing noise in the hallway near the front door.
There was a suit of armor in the hallway. This
suit of armor was more than three hundred years
old. It had fallen over and made a loud noise.
The Canterville Ghost was sitting
on the floor next to the armor.
The ghost had tried to put on the suit of armor.
He wanted to walk around the house and frighten
the Otis family. But the metal suit was too heavy.
The suit of armor had fallen onto the floor.
The Canterville Ghost was
sitting beside the armor.
He was rubbing his knee. He had hurt himself.
Mr Hiram B. Otis pointed a gun at the ghost.
Washington Otis held his candle high in
the air. The Otis twins laughed loudly.
Virginia was afraid and stood beside her mother.
They all looked at the Canterville Ghost.
The ghost was very angry. He stood up and gave a
loud shout. He blew out the candle in Washington
Otis's hand. There was no light in the hall.
Then the ghost ran up the stairs in the darkness.
He stopped at the top of the stairs and
laughed. He had a frightening laugh.
Men's hair had turned grey when they heard
him laugh. But the Otises were not afraid.
'Are you in pain?' asked Mrs Otis. 'I
have a bottle of Dr Dobell's medicine.
It is good for stomach-aches and
headaches. Please take the medicine.'
The ghost looked at Mrs Otis angrily.
Then he disappeared in a green cloud
and went back to his secret room. He was very
unhappy. He had tried to put on the suit of armor,
but it was too heavy. The armor had fallen
over and the ghost had hurt his leg.
The ghost stayed in his room during
the day. He came out at night
to visit the library. He repainted the
blood-stain every night. And every morning,
Washington Otis removed the blood-stain
with Pinkerton's Stain Remover.
But the ghost had a problem. He had quickly
finished all his red paint. Now his brown and
purple paints were finished as well. So, sometimes
he painted the blood-stain green, sometimes blue.
The ghost made plans. He wanted to frighten
the Otis twins. He planned to visit the
twins in the night. He planned to turn himself
green and make a horrible noise. He planned to
visit the twins in their bedroom. He planned to
touch them with his ice-cold hands in the dark.
He left his secret room at
midnight. The house was dark.
He climbed the stairs and walked along
the corridor. The twins' bedroom was
at the end of the corridor round a corner.
He turned the corner. Suddenly he stopped.
In front of him was a round face with
a terrible mouth and burning eyes. Fire
shone out of the mouth and eyes of this
horrible face. It was the face of a ghost!
The Canterville Ghost gave a shout and ran back to
his secret room. He had never seen a
ghost before and felt very frightened.
Before daylight came, the
Canterville Ghost felt better.
Were there two ghosts in the house? He must
find out. He must meet the second ghost.
He went back upstairs and walked along
the corridor towards the twins' room.
The second ghost was still there,
but its eyes were no longer burning.
He went up to it. He touched it. The head
of the second ghost fell onto the floor.
It was not a ghost at all. It was a head made
from a large round vegetable called a pumpkin.
The twins had put a candle inside
it. There was a card on the floor.
THE OTIS GHOST THE ONLY TRUE CANTERVILLE GHOST
The twins had put the head in the corridor to
frighten him. This made the Canterville Ghost very
angry. What could he do? He could think of nothing
at that moment, so he went back to his room.
The ghost felt very weak and tired.
He stayed in his room for five days.
He did not repaint the blood-stain in
the library. There had been a blood-stain
on the library floor for three hundred
years. Now the library floor was clean.
After a week the ghost felt better. He decided
to try once more to frighten the Otis twins.
He planned to make his face look as horrible as
possible. He waited until the middle of the night.
Slowly and silently he walked to the
twins' bedroom. It was one o'clock
in the morning. The house was quiet. The
door of the twins' room was slightly open.
The ghost took off his head
and carried it under his arm.
It is terrifying to see a headless
ghost. He wanted to terrify the twins.
He pushed open the door of the twins'
bedroom. The door banged against the wall.
He had planned to shout and
hold his head in his hinds.
But a heavy jug of water fell
from the top of the door.
The twins had played a trick on him. He was
soaked with water. The twins shouted and laughed.
The ghost ran back down the corridor. He could not
frighten the twins. He could not
frighten anyone in the Otis family.
Washington Otis came out of his bedroom.
The ghost stopped running. Behind
him, the twins ran down the corridor.
They shouted - 'Boo!' - in his ears and waved
their arms. Washington Otis laughed at him.
The ghost did not know what to do. He
ran through the nearest door, went back
to the secret room and lay down. He could not
frighten anyone. He was a very unhappy ghost.
The Otises did not see the
Canterville ghost at night again.
The twins waited for him when it was
dark. They put a rope across the corridor.
They tied metal tins to the rope. But
the ghost did not walk into the tins.
Only Mr Otis came along the corridor. He
fell over the rope and was very angry.
Virginia Otis was also angry with the twins.
'Can't you leave the poor ghost alone?' she said.
'Why do you want to hurt him? Why
do you want to play tricks on him?
He has lived here for a very
long time. Leave him alone.'
The twins did not listen, but the ghost heard
Virginia's words. The words gave him hope.
One afternoon, Virginia went to the library.
The library door was slightly open. She pushed the
door wide open and quietly walked into the room.
There was somebody sitting by the
window. It was the Canterville Ghost!
He was looking at the library window
which was made of colored glass.
There were words painted on the glass.
He was wearing his best clothes
and had combed his long grey hair.
'I feel very sorry for
you,' said Virginia quietly.
'I'm sorry that my brothers were not very kind
to you. But you did try to frighten them.'
'Yes I did,' said the ghost. 'It is my job to
frighten everyone who comes to Canterville Chase.'
'You are very wicked, I know,' said Virginia,
'Mrs Umney, the housekeeper, told
us that you killed your wife.'
'Yes I did,' replied the ghost.
'But she wasn't very kind. And it wasn't very
kind of her brothers to starve me to death.'
'Starve you to death?' said Virginia. 'Oh, poor
ghost, are you hungry? Would you like a sandwich?'
'No thank you,' he replied. 'I never
eat anything. But you are very kind.
You are much kinder than the rest of your
family. They are rude, nasty and unkind.'
'Stop!' cried Virginia. 'You
are nasty and unkind too.
You stole my paint box. You used my paints
to make the blood-stain in the library.
I never told anyone about it. But
now I'm going to fetch my father.'
She turned to go, but the ghost spoke again.
'Please do not go, Miss Virginia,'
said the ghost. 'I am so lonely
and so unhappy. I do not know what to
do. I want to go to sleep and I cannot.'
'It's easy to sleep,' said Virginia.
'You go to bed and close your eyes.'
'I have not slept for three hundred years,'
said the ghost. 'I have not slept since
I was murdered by my wife's brothers.'
Virginia walked across the library and looked
at the old face of the ghost. It was a sad face.
'Poor ghost,' said Virginia,
'how can I help you to sleep?'
'Far away in the woods,' said the
ghost, 'there is a little garden.
In the little garden the grass grows long
and thick. There are many flowers and trees.
A nightingale sings all night long.
The bird's sweet song is beautiful
and sad. The white stars and the pale moon look
down on this little garden. It is very peaceful.'
Virginia's eyes were full of tears.
She put her hands over her face.
'You mean it is the Garden
of Death,' she said quietly.
'Yes, the Garden of Sleep,' said the ghost.
'It is very beautiful. There is peace
and silence. There is no yesterday
and no tomorrow. But only Love can open the door
to the garden. For Love is stronger than Death.'
Virginia did not know what to say.
She listened as the ghost spoke again.
'Have you read the writing on the library window?'
'Yes,' said Virginia, 'but
I do not understand it.'
'Look,' said the ghost. 'Read
the lines on the window.'
Virginia looked at the window
and read the lines of poetry:
When a golden girl shall weep
For the ghost that cannot sleep,
Then the dead at last shall die
And in restful earth may lie.
'The words mean you must weep for me,'
said the unhappy ghost. 'Then the
Angel of Death will let me rest.
Will you help?'
'What do I have to do?' asked Virginia.
'You must come with me into the darkness.
You will see strange things. You will hear
strange voices, but nothing will hurt you. You
are good and kind. The dark cannot hurt you.'
Virginia did not answer and the ghost waited.
He had waited for three hundred years.
This was the longest minute of all that time.
'I am not afraid,' said Virginia at last.
'I will come with you into the dark.'
The ghost kissed her hand. His lips were
cold like ice, but they burned like fire.
The ghost held her hand and they
walked to the wall of the library.
The wall opened. There was
darkness beyond the wall
and a cold wind. Voices spoke out of the wind. 'Go
back, Virginia. Go back before it is too late.'
Virginia walked into the darkness with the ghost.
Virginia and the ghost disappeared
through the library wall.
Virginia did not come downstairs for supper.
Mr Otis sent one of the servants to her room.
The servant could not find Virginia so everybody
searched the house. They looked everywhere
but they could not find her. Mr
and Mrs Otis were very worried.
It was a summer evening and the sun had
not set, so the family and the servants
searched the gardens before it was dark. In the
garden there were many trees and a deep pond.
They looked in the pond. They looked in the trees.
Then they asked people at the railway station. But
no one had seen Virginia. Mr Otis went to tell the
village policeman that Virginia had disappeared.
But, by that time, it was dark and no
one could search any more that night.
None of the family wanted to eat or sleep.
They sat in the library and waited. They hoped
Virginia would return safely. They planned
to search for Virginia again in the morning.
It was midnight when the family decided to
go to bed. They left the library and started
to walk up the stairs together. Suddenly all
the clocks in the house struck twelve and they
heard a terrible noise. Thunder crashed outside
the house and the Otises heard a dreadful cry.
Strange music sounded inside the house and
a door opened at the top of the stairs.
Virginia stood in the doorway. She
looked down the stairs at them.
Her face was very pale and she
carried a small box in her hand.
'Where have you been?' Mr Otis asked
angrily. 'Your mother has been very worried.
You have frightened us all. You must
never play a trick like this again.'
'Except on the ghost,' said the twins.
'You can play tricks on the ghost!'
'Father,' Virginia said quietly, 'I
have been with the ghost. He is dead
and now he can rest. He gave me this
box of beautiful jewels before he died.'
She showed her father the small box.
Inside was a necklace made of red stones.
'Where did you get this?' asked
her father. 'Where have you been?'
Mr Otis forgot to be angry. He was so
pleased to see that Virginia was safe.
'Come. I'll show you,' said Virginia.
She turned back to the door
at the top of the stairs.
All of the family followed her.
Washington Otis carried a lighted candle.
Virginia led them along a secret corridor. They
came to an old wooden door which was open. Beyond
the door was a little room with a low ceiling.
There was an iron ring in the wall and two chains.
At the end of the chains was a body.
Only bones remained. It was a skeleton.
'This is the body of Sir Simon de Canterville,'
said Virginia. 'He murdered his wife in 1575.
Then his wife's brothers shut him in this
room. He was given no food. Sir Simon
starved to death. His ghost was in this house for
three hundred years. But now he has found peace.'
The Otis family looked around the little room
and did not know what to say. Virginia knelt on
the floor beside the skeleton and began to pray.
There was a funeral four nights later. The Otises
buried the body of Sir Simon de
Canterville in a grave among the trees.
The Otises, Mrs Umney the housekeeper, and all
the servants from Canterville Chase stood near
the grave. Behind them were people from the nearby
village. Many people had come to the funeral.
Virginia carried white flowers. She
looked up at the stars and the pale moon
and the dark trees. She remembered what the
ghost had said about the Garden of Death.
A nightingale began to sing. The bird's
sweet song was beautiful and sad.
Virginia smiled. 'God has forgiven
him for murdering his wife,' she said.
Hughie thanked him and looked at the envelope.
These words were written on the envelope:
A wedding present to Hugh Erskine
and Laura Merton, from an old beggar.
Inside was a check for ten thousand pounds.
- THE END -