CHAPTER ONE
News of a Wedding
Scarlett O'Hara was not beautiful, but men
did not realize this when caught by her charm
as the Tarleton twins were. Her eyes were
green, and her skin was that soft white skin
which Southern women valued so highly, and
covered so carefully from the hot Georgia
sun with hats and gloves.
On that bright April afternoon of 1861, sixteen-year-old
Scarlett sat in the cool shadows of the house
at Tara, her father's plantation. Stuart and
Brent Tarleton sat each side of her. They
were friendly young men with deep red-brown
hair, and were clever in the things that mattered
in north Georgia at that time - growing good
cotton, riding well, shooting straight and
behaving like a gentleman.
'Don't you two care about being sent home
from the University of Georgia for bad behaviour?'
Scarlett was saying.
'The war will start soon,' said Brent. 'You
didn't think we'd stay in university with
a war going on, did you?'
'There isn't going to be a war,' said Scarlett,
looking bored. 'Ashley Wilkes and his father
told Pa just last week that our men in Washington
will come to an agreement with Mr Lincoln
about the Confederacy. Anyway, the Yankees
are too frightened of us to fight. And if
you say "war" once more, I'll go inside the
house and shut the door!'
They looked across the red earth of Gerald
O'Hara's land, which stretched away as far
as the eye could see. The white house was
like an island, sitting in a wild red sea,
the earth blood-coloured after the rains of
recent weeks.
'Scarlett, you'll promise to dance with us
at the party at Twelve Oaks tomorrow, won't
you?' said Brent.
'If you do, we'll tell you a secret,' said
Stuart.
'What secret?' asked Scarlett. 'Who told you?'
'Miss Pittypat Hamilton, Ashley Wilkes' cousin
who lives in Atlanta. Charles and Melanie
Hamilton's aunt,' said Stuart.
'She said that we'll hear news of a wedding
tomorrow night, at the party,' said Brent.
'Oh, I know that!' said Scarlett, disappointed.
'It's about Charlie Hamilton and Honey Wilkes.
Everyone knows they'll get married some day.'
'No, it's about Ashley,' said Stuart. 'He's
going to marry Charlie's sister, Miss Melanie!'
Scarlett's face did not change but her lips
went white - like a person who is in the first
moments of shock.
'They weren't going to marry until next year,'
said Stuart, 'but with all the talk of war,
both families think it will be better if they're
married soon.' He smiled. 'Now, Scarlett,
you must promise to eat supper with us at
the party.'
'Of course I will,' said Scarlett automatically.
'And give us plenty of dances?'
'Yes.' She spoke as if in a dream.
'And sit with us at lunch, too?' said Brent.
'What?' said Scarlett. 'Oh, yes, of course.'
The twins were unable to believe their good
luck. They talked on about the dance, and
Ashley Wilkes and Melanie Hamilton. They laughed
and joked, and waited for Scarlett to invite
them to supper; and it was some time before
they realized she was not listening to them.
***
Scarlett watched the twins ride away.
Ashley was going to marry Melanie Hamilton!
Oh, it couldn't be true! It was all a mistake.
Ashley was in love with her, not Melanie!
Mammy came out of the house. She was a big
old negro who loved Ellen O'Hara and her family.
'Are the gentlemen gone?' she asked. 'Why
didn't you ask them to stay to supper?'
'I didn't want to listen to them talking to
Pa about the war all through supper,' said
Scarlett.
'You just ain't polite, Miss Scarlett,' said
Mammy. 'Now come into the house before you
get cold.'
'I want to watch the sun go down,' said Scarlett.
'I'll sit here until Pa comes home. Just fetch
me a light coat, Mammy.'
Mammy went back into the house and Scarlett
made a sudden decision. 'I'll go and meet
Pa,' she thought. 'He'll be coming back from
Twelve Oaks soon, and he'll know about Ashley.'
As a child, Scarlett had not given Ashley
Wilkes a single thought. But two years ago,
he had arrived home after touring Europe - riding
up to Tara with the sun so bright on his fair
hair that it shone like silver. 'You've grown
up, Scarlett,' he had said, kissing her hand.
And from that moment on, she wanted him as
simply as she wanted food to eat, and horses
to ride, and a soft bed to sleep in.
For two years, he took her to dances and suppers,
and a week did not go past without Ashley
calling at Tara. It was true he never spoke
to her of love, and his clear grey eyes never
burned with that hot light Scarlett knew so
well in other men. But she was sure that he
loved her. She saw him looking at her sometimes,
in that sad, strange way of his.
Scarlett heard the sound of Gerald O'Hara's
horse and saw him coming across the fields
at full speed. Gerald was sixty years old,
a small man with silver-white hair and hard
little blue eyes. He was surprised to see
her.
'How is everyone at Twelve Oaks?' she asked
him.
'They're all talking about the war,' he said,
'and-'
'Did they speak about the party?' Scarlett
asked quickly.
'Yes, I think they did,' said Gerald. 'Miss
Melanie Hamilton and her brother Charles have
come from Atlanta and-'
'Oh, so she did come!' Scarlett's heart became
heavy. 'Was Ashley there, too?'
'Yes, he was.' Gerald looked closely at his
daughter. 'That's why you came to meet me,
isn't it? Why didn't you say so before? Now
what's all this about you and Ashley?'
'There's nothing, Pa,' she said.
'Has he asked to marry you?'
'No,' said Scarlett, quietly.
'And he won't,' said Gerald. 'John Wilkes
says that Ashley is to marry Miss Melanie.
They'll tell everyone tomorrow.'
A pain cut across Scarlett's heart and she
found it hard to breathe. Her father watched
her, and looked uncomfortable.
'Have you run after a man who's not in love
with you?'
'No!' said Scarlett.
'You're lying!' said Gerald. Then went on
in a kind way, 'There are lots of other young
men, Scarlett. I want you to be happy, and
you wouldn't be happy with him.'
'Oh, I would! I would!'
'The Wilkes are different from other people,'
said Gerald. They marry their cousins and
keep their strangeness in the family. Look
how they read books, and go to Boston and
New York to see paintings and hear music.'
'Nobody rides a horse better than Ashley!'
said Scarlett.
'Oh, yes, Ashley can ride and drink with the
best of men, but he cares nothing about those
things,' said Gerald. 'Now listen, there are
other fine boys to marry, Scarlett. And when
I'm gone, I'll leave Tara to you and-'
'I don't want Tara!' cried Scarlett, angrily.
'Plantations don't mean anything when-' She
was going to say when you don't have the man
you want, but Gerald's shout stopped her.
'Not mean anything! Land is the only thing
in the world that does mean anything!' he
cried. 'It will come to you, Scarlett, this
love of the land. It's in your blood and there's
no denying it.' He held her arm as they walked
towards the house. 'I'll not worry your mother
with this, and nor must you.'
They met Ellen O'Hara at the door. She was
carrying the black bag in which she always
kept the medicines she used for the slaves.
Mammy was with her, and did not look pleased.
'Mr O'Hara,' Ellen said, 'a baby is dying
at the Slattery house and Mammy and I are
going to see what we can do.'
'The Slatterys!' shouted Gerald. 'Those white
trash?'
'She is always nursin' negroes and white trash
who could not look after themselves,' said
Mammy, annoyed.
'Take my place at supper, Scarlett,' said
Ellen, touching her daughter's cheek. She
was a tall woman, with a quiet, gentle voice
and a warm smile that charmed everyone.
There was something magical about her mother's
touch, thought Scarlett, and for a moment
forgot all about Ashley.
But later an idea came to her. 'Ashley doesn't
know I love him!' she thought. 'He thinks
I love Brent or Stuart, and he's marrying
Melanie because he thinks he can't have me!
I must tell him, then we can run off to Jonesboro
and get married! By this time tomorrow night,
I might be Mrs Ashley Wilkes!'
CHAPTER TWO
Rhett Butler
Early the next morning, Gerald told his plantation
manager, Jonas Wilkerson, to pack his things
and leave. Jonas, Ellen had discovered, was
the father of Emmie Slattery's dead baby,
and now Ellen would not have him working at
Tara. Jonas was a Yankee and hated all Southerners,
and he was angry at losing the best manager's
job in the neighbourhood.
Ellen told Gerald that she was not going to
the party at Twelve Oaks. 'I must check Jonas's
figures in the plantation books,' she said.
'Mammy will stay and help me.'
So Gerald rode on his horse beside the carriage
that took Scarlett and her two sisters down
the road to Twelve Oaks.
Scarlett thought about her plans to marry
Ashley. 'No one must suspect anything,' she
thought, 'so I'll flirt with every man there,
from old Frank Kennedy to shy Charlie Hamilton.
It will be cruel to Ashley, but it will make
him want me more.'
'I don't know why you look so happy this morning,'
said her sister, Suellen, looking at Scarlett.
'You know Ashley's going to marry Melanie,
Pa said so. And I know you love Ashley!'
'Suellen, that's not true!' said Careen, the
youngest of the three. 'It's Brent that Scarlett
cares about.'
The whole family knew that Careen loved Brent
Tarleton. But he never gave her a thought
except as Scarlett's baby sister. 'I don't
care about Brent,' said Scarlett, smiling,
'and he doesn't care about me. He's waiting
for you to grow up!'
Careen went red in the face, 'Oh, Scarlett,
is he really?' she said.
They went over the hill, and saw Twelve Oaks.
The house was white and beautiful under the
blue sky. Lunch was going to be served outside,
and Scarlett saw the Tarleton twins with their
two brothers, Boyd and Tom; and Alex and Tony
Fontaine; and the two Calvert boys, Raiford
and Cade.
'Good! Everyone is here!' thought Scarlett.
John Wilkes stood on the entrance steps, a
silver-haired man with a quiet charm that
was as warm as a summer sun. Next to him was
his daughter, Honey Wilkes. His other daughter,
India, was nowhere to be seen, and Scarlett
guessed that she was in the kitchen giving
final orders to the servants.
'Poor India,' thought Scarlett. 'She's been
so busy looking after Twelve Oaks since her
mother died that she's had no time to catch
any man except Stuart Tarleton, and it's not
my problem if he thinks I'm prettier than
her.'
John Wilkes helped Scarlett from the carriage,
and Frank Kennedy hurried to give a helping
hand to Suellen, who went red but looked delighted.
Frank was forty, with a thin red beard. He
was nervous with women and was surprised when
Scarlett, remembering her plan, gave him one
of her best smiles.
Stuart and Brent Tarleton moved towards her,
and Scarlett looked around as she talked and
laughed with them. Suddenly, she noticed a
stranger standing alone. He looked at least
thirty-five and was tall and strong, with
a black moustache. Scarlett went red as he
stared at her with a cool smile. Then he turned
away as someone called, 'Rhett! Rhett Butler!'
Rhett Butler? Did she know the name? Scarlett's
thoughts turned to Ashley and she forgot about
the smiling man.
'I must go and comb my hair,' she told Stuart
and Brent. 'You boys wait for me, and don't
run off with any other girl!'
As she went up the wide stairs, a shy voice
behind her called her name. Scarlett turned
and saw Charles Hamilton, a nice-looking boy
with soft brown hair and deep brown eyes.
She gave him her biggest smile. 'Why, Charles
Hamilton, you handsome old thing! I'm sure
you came all the way from Atlanta just to
break my poor heart!'
Charles almost fainted. This was the way girls
talked to other boys, not to him!
'Now you wait here until I come back,' said
Scarlett. 'And don't talk to those other girls
or I'll be very jealous!'
'I - I won't,' he said.
Scarlett saw Rhett Butler, a few feet away.
He was smiling again, and had a strange look
in his eye as he stared at her. Scarlett went
red again and hurried on up the stairs.
Cathleen Calvert was in the bedroom.
'Cathleen,' said Scarlett, 'who is that nasty
man Butler?'
'My dear, don't you know?' whispered Cathleen,
excitedly. 'He's from Charleston, but his
family won't speak to him!'
'Really?' said Scarlett. 'Why?'
'He took a girl out riding in a carriage one
afternoon and they stayed out nearly all night!
When they finally arrived home, he said that
the horse ran away and that they got lost
in the forest. And guess what?'
'Tell me,' said Scarlett, hoping for the worst.
'He refused to marry her the next day!'
'Oh,' said Scarlett, disappointed.
'He said that he did nothing to her, but her
brother invited him to fight - and Mr Butler
shot him! Well, after that, Mr Butler had
to leave Charleston.'
'Did she have a baby?' whispered Scarlett.
'No,' said Cathleen, 'but no one will ever
marry her now.'
'I wish Ashley would stay out all night with
me,' thought Scarlett. 'He's too much of a
gentleman not to marry me afterwards.'
CHAPTER THREE
Changes
Scarlett sat under a large tree, with her
lunch on a plate in front of her. But although
there were seven handsome young men sitting
around her, Ashley was not one of them and
she was not happy. He was sitting on the grass
with Melanie Hamilton, talking quietly and
smiling the slow, lazy smile that Scarlett
loved. Melanie had dark hair and a heart-shaped
face. She was small, but seemed older than
her seventeen years.
Scarlett saw Rhett Butler talking to John
Wilkes. He looked at her and laughed, and
she had the feeling that this nasty man knew
her true feelings about Ashley, and was amused.
It was two o'clock and the sun was warm. Scarlett
was just wondering if India would suggest
that the ladies went into the house, when
she heard Gerald arguing with John Wilkes.
'Hope for peace with the Yankees?' Gerald
was shouting. 'No, the South must show that
it's strong and ready for a fight!'
Other men joined in the discussion. 'Of course
we'll fight!'
'Yankee thieves!'
'One Southerner can fight twenty Yankees!'
Charles Hamilton found himself alone with
Scarlett as the others moved away. 'Miss O'Hara,'
he said, 'if I go to fight, will you be sorry?'
Scarlett thought men were stupid to think
women were interested in these things, but
she answered, 'I'll cry into my pillow every
night,' not meaning a word of it.
'Miss O'Hara, I must tell you something,'
said Charles, suddenly feeling brave. 'I - I
love you! I want to marry you!' Scarlett wanted
to tell Charles he looked silly, but said
automatically, 'This is so sudden. I don't
know what to say.'
'I'll wait for ever!' cried Charles.
Scarlett noticed that Ashley was now with
the group of men. 'If Georgia fights, I'll
go with her,' Ashley was saying. 'But most
of the sadness in the world was caused by
wars, and when they were over, no one knew
what they were about.'
More arguing burst out after this until Rhett
Butler spoke. 'Gentlemen,' he said, 'can I
say a word? There's not one gun factory in
the South, and not a wool or cotton factory
either. We haven't a single war-ship, and
the Yankees could quickly stop us selling
our cotton abroad with a blockade. They have
all the things we haven't got, gentlemen.
All we have is cotton and slaves - and brave
talk!'
Everyone was shocked, but Scarlett could not
help feeling he was right. She had never seen
a factory, and did not know anyone who had.
'But he's no gentleman to say these things
at a party, where everyone is having a good
time,' she thought.
***
It was late afternoon, and the ladies were
resting in the six great bedrooms at Twelve
Oaks, to be ready for the dance that evening.
They had their dresses off, and most were
asleep.
Scarlett checked that Melanie was lying down
next to Honey Wilkes before she quietly left
the room and went down the stairs. From a
window, she saw Ashley drinking and talking
with a group of men on the step outside. She
walked silently across to the library. 'I'll
wait in here until he comes into the house,'
she thought, 'and then I'll call to him.'
The library was half-dark with the curtains
closed to keep out the sun. Across the room
was a sofa with its high back towards her,
and around the walls were hundreds of books.
Scarlett left the door open and tried to remember
what she was going to say to Ashley. 'Perhaps
it will help if I pray,' she thought, and
closed her eyes.
'Scarlett!' It was Ashley's voice. She opened
her eyes and saw him looking at her from the
doorway. 'Are you hiding from Charles or the
Tarletons?' he said.
She pulled him into the room.
'What is it?' he said. 'Have you got a secret
to tell me?'
'Yes - a secret,' she said. 'I love you!'
He was silent, and there was a worried and
confused look in his eyes. Then he made himself
smile and said lightly, 'You have every other
man's heart here today, Scarlett, isn't that
enough? Do you want mine, too? Well, you've
always had it.'
'He doesn't believe me!' she thought. 'He
thinks I'm just flirting with him!' Scarlett
looked into his eyes. 'Ashley! Tell me you
love me, my dear!' she cried.
He put his hand across her lips. 'Don't say
these things.'
'But I love you,' she cried, 'and I know you
love me. Ashley, you do care, don't you?'
'Yes,' he said quietly. 'I care.'
'And you do want to marry me?' she said.
'I'm going to marry Melanie,' he replied.
He took her hands in his. 'How can I make
you understand, Scarlett? Love just isn't
enough when two people are as different as
we are.'
'But you said you cared for me,' said Scarlett.
'I was wrong to say it.'
She began to get angry. 'You're afraid to
marry me!' she said, her voice getting louder.
'You'll marry that stupid little fool who
can only say "No" and "Yes"!'
Ashley's face went white. 'Stop!' he said.
She pulled away from him. 'I'll hate you until
I die!' she shouted, and she hit him hard
across the face.
He said nothing, but lifted her hand to his
lips and kissed it. Then he was gone, and
the memory of the sad and hopeless look on
his face would stay with her until the day
she died.
Scarlett began to shake. 'Now he'll hate me,'
she thought. 'Every time he looks at me he'll
remember me saying all those things.' She
began to feel hot all over. Did other people
know how she felt about Ashley? Was everyone
laughing at her?
Her hand dropped to a little table next to
her, and her fingers closed around a pretty
glass bowl. She picked it up and threw it
wildly across the room. It missed the top
of the sofa but crashed against the wall beyond.
'This,' said a voice from the other side of
the sofa, 'is too much!' A man had been lying
on it, but now he stood up.
It was Rhett Butler.
Scarlett almost fainted. 'Sir,' she said,
'you are no gentleman to listen to other people's
conversations!'
'And you, Miss, are no lady,' he said. 'But
ladies rarely interest me, and I cannot understand,
my dear Miss O'Hara, what a wild and hot-blooded
girl like you can find to like about the handsome
but very boring Mr Wilkes.'
'You aren't good enough to clean his boots!'
she shouted.
He laughed. 'And you were going to hate him
all your life!' She wanted to kill him, but
she walked out of the room and pulled the
heavy door shut behind her with a crash.
***
A horse came fast towards the house, its rider
low over the animal's back. Excitement was
in every line of the man's face as he jumped
down. The other men crowded round him, and
he spoke quickly. Suddenly, Stuart Tarleton
gave a shout.
Scarlett saw these things through a window
as she went quietly back up the stairs. 'Somebody's
house must be on fire,' she thought. She went
on to the bedroom and was about to open the
door when she heard voices inside.
'Scarlett flirted with every man here today,'
Honey Wilkes was saying. 'She was certainly
going after Charles, and you know Charles
and I are going to be married.'
'Are you really!' whispered other voices excitedly.
'Yes, but don't tell anybody yet,' said Honey.
'But there's only one person Scarlett cares
about - and that's Ashley!'
'Honey, you know that isn't true,' said Melanie.
'And it's so unkind to say it.'
'It is true! Scarlett took Stuart from India,
and today she tried to take Mr Kennedy from
Suellen. And Ashley-'
Scarlett ran back down the stairs. 'I must
get home!' she thought. But when she was on
the steps outside, she stopped. She couldn't
go home! She couldn't run away and show them
how ashamed she was feeling! It would only
make things worse.
She hated them. She hated Ashley. She hated
everyone!
'I'll stay and make them sorry,' she thought.
'I will!'
She turned towards the house - and saw Charles
Hamilton.
'Do you know what's happened?' he cried.
She said nothing, only stared at him.
'Mr Lincoln called for soldiers!' he said.
'Seventy-five thousand of them! Of course,
it will mean fighting, Miss Scarlett, but
don't you worry, it'll be all over in a month.'
Scarlett was only half-listening. 'He has
plenty of money,' she was thinking. 'He lives
in Atlanta, and if I marry him quickly it
will show Ashley that I don't care - that
I was only flirting with him. And it will
just kill Honey. She'll never get another
man, and everyone will laugh at her! And it
will hurt Melanie because she loves Charles
so much.'
'Will you wait for me, Miss Scarlett?' Charles
was saying.
Scarlett made a decision. 'I don't want to
wait,' she said.
He held her hand, his mouth wide open. Twice
he tried to say something, but the words wouldn't
come. At last he said, 'Can - can you possibly
love me?'
She said nothing but looked down at the floor,
pretending to be shy. Charles wanted to shout
and sing and kiss her, and then to tell everyone
that Scarlett O'Hara loved him!
'Will you marry me soon?' he said, not daring
to breathe.
'The sooner the better,' she said.
***
Within two weeks, Ashley was married to Melanie,
and Scarlett was married to Charles. Two months
later she was a widow.
Charles died from typhoid. He never fought
a battle. He never got close to a Yankee.
Soon after, Scarlett discovered that she was
going to have a baby, and she became the mother
of Charles son. She called him Wade. She did
not love or want the child, and it did not
seem possible that he was hers.
Every time she thought of Ashley, she cried,
and went back to her bed and refused to eat.
Ellen tried to help but failed. And then Charles
aunt, Miss Pittypat Hamilton, wrote asking
if Scarlett could come to Atlanta for a long
visit. She and Melanie wanted very much to
see Charlie's dear little baby.
So Scarlett went to Atlanta with Wade, and
Prissy, her young slave. She did not want
to go, but any change was welcome.
CHAPTER FOUR
Atlanta
The war was making Atlanta a busy city. Trains
thundered in and out, and the narrow, muddy
streets were full of army wagons and ambulances.
Scarlett rode from the railway station in
Miss Pittypat's carriage, with 'Uncle Peter',
a tall, thin negro who was Aunt Pitty's old
slave.
She saw a tall, handsome woman in a bright
coloured dress, and with hair so red that
it couldn't possibly be the real colour. 'Who
is that, Uncle Peter?' she whispered.
'I don't know,' said Uncle Peter, looking
away quickly.
'Yes, you do. Who is she?'
'Belle Watling,' he said after a moment. 'Miss
Pitty ain't going to like you asking questions
about women like that.'
Scarlett was suddenly shocked. 'She must be
a bad woman!' she thought, staring. She had
never seen a prostitute before.
Miss Pittypat's red-brick house was on Peachtree
Road, and Aunt Pitty was waiting excitedly
on the front step. Melanie was with her and
Scarlett saw the loving smile of welcome on
the little heart-shaped face - and felt a
rush of dislike.
This jealous dislike grew as the days went
by, and sometimes Scarlett had to leave the
room when Melanie talked about Ashley. But
Atlanta was more interesting than Tara, and
she was busy nursing at the hospital with
Mrs Meade, the doctor's wife, and other women.
All married women in Atlanta nursed the soldiers,
and most were glad to do it. But Scarlett
was a nurse only because she had to be.
'Melanie is content to stay at home and never
go to parties, and to wear black for her brother
when she's only eighteen years old,' thought
Scarlett. 'But she was never popular like
me and she doesn't miss the things I miss.
And she's got Ashley and I haven't got anybody!'
And she began to cry.
One afternoon, two ladies of the town - Mrs
Merriwether and Mrs Elsing - visited Aunt
Pitty.
'The McLure girls were called to Virginia
to bring home their brother,' Mrs Elsing told
them. 'He was hurt.'
'Pitty, we need you and Melanie to take their
places at the sale tonight,' said Mrs Merriwether.
'Oh, but we can't go,' said Aunt Pitty. 'With
poor Charlie dead only a-'
'Don't say "can't" to me, Pittypat Hamilton,'
said Mrs Merriwether. 'We need you to watch
the negroes with the food, and we need Melanie
for the McLure girls' table. Just remember,
it's to make money for the Cause!'
'I think we should go,' said Scarlett suddenly,
trying not to look too enthusiastic. 'We must
do it for the hospital.'
They all looked surprised that it was Scarlett
who offered, but Mrs Merriwether said, 'Scarlett's
right. You must all come.'
***
Scarlett sat behind a table with Melanie at
the sale. They were in a large room, which
was usually full of soldiers learning the
business of war. But tonight there were flowers
and coloured lights around the room, and music
was playing. There would be dancing soon,
but already Scarlett's feet were secretly
moving in time with the music.
Across the room, a tall man, dressed in black,
with a fine white shirt, was staring at her.
He smiled and she smiled back - until she
remembered who he was, and then her hand flew
to her mouth! It was Rhett Butler, and now
he was coming over!
'I did not think you would remember me, Miss
O'Hara,' he said. There was laughter in his
eyes, and Scarlett's face went bright red
as she remembered their last meeting.
Melanie turned at the sound of his voice.
'Oh, it's Mr Rhett Butler, isn't it?' she
said, smiling. 'I met you-'
'At Twelve Oaks,' he finished for her.
'What are you doing so far from Charleston,
Mr Butler?'
'Business,' he said. 'I find I must not only
bring things into your city but must also
stay here to sell them.'
Melanie gave him a delighted smile. 'You must
be the famous Captain Butler we've heard so
much about - the blockade runner. Scarlett,
what's the matter? Are you feeling faint?'
Scarlett sat down on a chair. 'Of all the
people to come here,' she was thinking, 'why
did he have to come?'
'It's quite warm in here,' Rhett was saying.
'Can I take you across to a window, Miss O'Hara?'
'No,' said Scarlett, so rudely that Melanie
stared.
'She's not Miss O'Hara any longer,' said Melanie,
smiling in a kind way. 'She is Mrs Hamilton,
and my sister now.'
'Oh,' said Rhett, looking closely at Scarlett.
'And are your husbands here tonight?'
'My husband is in Virginia,' said Melanie,
proudly. 'But Charles-' She could not go on.
'Charles is dead,' said Scarlett.
'My dear ladies!' said Rhett. 'I'm so sorry.
But to die for one's country is to live for
ever.'
Melanie smiled at him through her tears while
Scarlett felt herself hating him. 'He doesn't
mean a word,' she thought.
Melanie forgot about Captain Butler and Scarlett
as customers crowded round her table. Scarlett
sat quietly on her chair, wishing that Captain
Butler was back on his ship.
'Has your husband been dead long?' he asked
her.
'Yes, almost a year.'
'And this is the first time-?'
'I know it looks strange,' she said, 'but
the McLure girls couldn't come, so Melanie
and I came-'
'For the Cause,' he finished for her.
'Why does he make it sound so cheap?' thought
Scarlett. When Mrs Merriwether spoke of 'the
Cause', she spoke proudly. Scarlett wanted
to tell him this but then remembered she was
only here because she was tired of sitting
at home.
He seemed to guess her thoughts, because he
said, 'Would you be here if the Confederacy
didn't need you, Mrs Hamilton?'
'Of course not,' said Scarlett. 'People would
think I hadn't loved-' And she stopped. She
could not pretend to him that she had loved
Charlie, not after the things he had heard
in the library at Twelve Oaks.
He moved close to her. 'Don't worry.' he whispered.
'Your guilty secret is safe with me!'
'How can you say those things!' she said,
angrily. But then she looked at him, saw the
laughter in his eyes and realized he was joking
with her - and she found herself laughing,
too.
Several people near them were shocked to see
Charles' widow laughing with a strange man,
and began to whisper about it.
Dr Meade called for everyone to be quiet.
'Gentlemen,' he said, 'if you want to dance
with a lady this evening, you must pay for
her! Remember, all the money is for the Cause!'
The young girls whispered excitedly, while
the men laughed. 'Oh, if only I could wear
an apple-green dress and have flowers in my
hair!' thought Scarlett. 'Twenty men would
fight to dance with me and pay their money
to the doctor!'
Rhett Butler was watching her. Suddenly, he
called out: 'Mrs Charles Hamilton - one hundred
and fifty dollars in gold!' Scarlett was so
surprised, she could not move. Everyone looked
at her, and she saw the doctor whisper to
Rhett Butler, probably telling him that widows
could not dance.
'Another one of our young ladies, perhaps?'
said Dr Meade.
'No,' said Rhett. 'Mrs Hamilton.'
'Impossible,' said the doctor. 'Mrs Hamilton
will not-'
'Yes, I will!' Scarlett heard herself shout.
She saw the shocked faces of Melanie and the
older women; she saw the surprised and annoyed
faces of the younger girls. But Scarlett didn't
care. She was going to dance again!
'I - I'm doing it for the Cause,' Scarlett
told Rhett, and he began to laugh. 'Stop laughing,
everyone is looking at us!'
'Do you care if people talk?' said Rhett.
'No - but - well, a nice girl is supposed
to care.' She changed the subject. 'Tell me,
do you have a lot of money?'
'What a rude question, Mrs Hamilton!' he laughed.
'But the answer is yes, and I'll make a million
on the blockade. One can always make money
from a war, whether one is on the winning
side or not.'
'Do you think the Confederacy will lose?'
'Yes,' he said.
'Oh, well, these things bore me,' said Scarlett.
'Captain Butler, don't hold me so tightly,
people are looking.'
'If no one was looking, would you care?' he
said, smiling.
'Captain Butler!' she said, pretending to
be shocked. Then added, 'You dance very well
for a big man, but it will be years and years
before I'll dance again.'
'I'll offer more money for you in the next
dance,' he said, 'and the next, and the next.'
'Oh, it's the end of the music,' said Scarlett.
'And here's Aunt Pittypat coming out of the
back room. I suppose Mrs Merriwether told
her. Her eyes are as big as saucers.'
***
'I don't care if they talk,' said Scarlett,
next morning. 'I'm sure I made more money
for the hospital than any girl there.'
'What does the money matter?' cried Aunt Pitty.
'Poor Charlie dead only a year! And that Captain
Butler is a terrible person, Scarlett.'
'I can't believe he's all that bad,' said
Melanie, gently. 'When you think how brave
he's been, running the blockade-'
'He isn't brave,' said Scarlett. 'He does
it for money. He doesn't care about the Confederacy,
and he says we're going to lose. But he dances
wonderfully.'
Pittypat and Melanie were so shocked they
could not speak.
'I'm tired of sitting at home and I'm not
going to do it any more,' Scarlett went on.
'If they all talked about me last night, then
it won't matter what they say about me now.'
Melanie put her arm round Scarlett. 'You did
a brave thing last night,' she said, 'and
it's going to help the hospital a lot. Aunt
Pitty, it's been difficult for Scarlett. And
war times aren't like other times. Think of
all the soldiers who are far from home and
without friends. We've been selfish. We must
have a soldier here to dinner every Sunday
from now on.'
CHAPTER FIVE
Heroes
The autumn of 1862 went quickly for Scarlett,
with nursing, parties and visits to Tara.
The visits to Tara were disappointing, because
Ellen worked from morning until night, and
Gerald was busy because he could not get a
manager to take Jonas Wilkerson's place. Suellen
was waiting for the war to end so that she
could marry Frank Kennedy, and Careen dreamed
about Brent Tarleton. So Scarlett was never
sorry to return from Tara to Atlanta.
There were many things she did not tell Ellen,
but her biggest secret was that Rhett Butler
called at Aunt Pittypat's house whenever he
was in town. Scarlett went riding with him
in his carriage, and he took her to dances
and sales. She looked forward to his visits
because there was something exciting about
him, something different from any other man
she knew. 'It's as if I'm in love with him!'
she thought. 'But I'm not.'
He sat and listened to Melanie for hours as
she talked about Ashley and how proud she
was of him. 'But I only have to say Ashley's
name and he smiles nastily at me!' thought
Scarlett.
'Why are you nicer to Melanie than to me?'
she asked him one day. 'I'm much prettier
than she is.'
'Dare I hope that you're jealous?' he said,
smiling.
'Don't be silly!' she said.
'Another hope gone! If I am "nicer" to Mrs
Wilkes, it's because she is one of the very
few kind and unselfish people I know. And,
although she is still young, she is one of
the few great ladies I have been lucky enough
to meet.'
'Don't you think I'm a great lady, too?' said
Scarlett.
'My dear, I think we agreed when we first
met that you were no lady at all,' said Rhett.
'Oh, you rude, horrible man, reminding me
of that again!' she said. But he only laughed
at her.
The older men and women in Atlanta did not
like Rhett, but they agreed that he was brave.
But when they told him this, he replied that
he was as frightened as the 'brave boys' who
were fighting. This annoyed them because everyone
knew there wasn't a cowardly Confederate soldier
anywhere. He always said 'our brave boys'
or 'our heroes in grey', but made it sound
like an insult. And when young ladies thanked
him for being one of the heroes who fought
for them, he smiled and said that he would
do the same thing for Yankee women if the
Yankees paid him enough money.
At an evening of music at Mrs Elsing's home,
Rhett was talking with a group of men when
Scarlett heard an angry voice arguing with
him, 'Are you saying, sir, that the Cause
for which our heroes are dying is not sacred?'
'All wars are sacred to those who have to
fight them,' replied Rhett, in a bored and
lazy voice. 'If the people who started wars
didn't pretend they were sacred, who would
be foolish enough to fight? No, it's money
that wars are really fought about, but few
people realize it. Their ears are too full
of fine words from stay-at-home speakers.'
And before Scarlett could reach him, he was
leaving.
'Let him go,' said Mrs Elsing, holding her
arm. 'He's not one of us. He's a snake-in-the-grass
who we were foolish enough to invite into
our homes!'
Later, Mrs Merriwether rode home in Aunt Pitty's
carriage, and immediately said what she thought.
'He insulted us all and the Confederacy, too,'
she said. 'Saying that we were fighting for
money! Saying that our leaders have lied to
us! Pitty, you must never let that man into
your house again!' She turned to Scarlett
and Melanie. 'And I don't want to hear you
two girls speaking to him again - Melanie,
what's the matter?'
Melanie was white and her eyes were wide open.
'I will speak to him again,' she said in a
low voice. 'I will not be rude to him. I will
not tell him to stay away from the house.'
Mrs Merriwether's mouth fell open, and Aunt
Pitty's did the same. Uncle Peter turned to
stare.
'Now why didn't I say that?' thought Scarlett.
Melanie's hands were shaking but she went
on quickly. 'I won't be rude to him because
of what he said, because it's - it's what
Ashley thinks.'
'Melanie Hamilton, that's a lie!' said Mrs
Merriwether. 'There was never a Wilkes who
was a coward-'
'I never said Ashley was a coward,' said Melanie.
'I said he thinks what Captain Butler thinks,
and he does. But he says it differently. In
his letters, Ashley says we should not be
fighting the Yankees. He says war isn't wonderful
or sacred or any of those things, it's just
dirty and useless and a terrible waste of
men's lives.'
Scarlett said nothing. She was shocked to
realize anyone as perfect as Ashley could
think the same as a man like Rhett Butler.
'They both understand what is true about the
war,' she thought, 'but Ashley will fight
and die for it and Rhett won't. I think that
shows Rhett is sensible.'
It was all very confusing.
CHAPTER SIX
Missing
In the early part of 1863, the war went well
for the Confederacy, but on the fourth day
of July, there was news about hard fighting
in Pennsylvania, near a little town called
Gettysburg. The news came slowly, and fear
began to spread across the town. Mothers prayed
that their boys were not in Pennsylvania,
but those who knew their relations were fighting
next to Dr Meade's son, Darcy, said they were
proud for them to be in the big fight that
would win the war.
In Aunt Pitty's house, the three women looked
into each other's eyes with fear. Ashley was
fighting with Darcy.
People waited outside the newspaper office
for news. Scarlett, Melanie and Aunt Pitty
came and waited in their carriage. Scarlett
saw Mrs Meade with her youngest son, Phil,
waiting for news of Darcy. Then the crowd
began to move as Rhett Butler came through
on his horse.
'The first lists will be out soon,' he said.
'Yes, look!'
The side window of the newspaper office opened
and a hand came out. In it were the lists
of the dead - long, narrow pieces of paper
with the names close together. The crowd began
to fight for them and there were shouts of,
'Let me through!'
Rhett got off his horse and pushed his way
forward, his heavy shoulders above the rest
of the crowd. Then he was back with five or
six lists in his hand. He gave one to Melanie,
and the others to the ladies in the carriages
near him.
Melanie's hands shook so much that she gave
the list to Scarlett, who quickly began to
read. 'White... Wilkins... Winn... Zebulon...
Oh, Melanie, he's not on it! He's not on it!'
Melanie began to cry with happiness, while
Scarlett's heart seemed ready to burst. Ashley
was alive! Ashley was alive!
Mrs Meade sat in her carriage and looked across
at Melanie. 'Darcy won't need those new boots
now,' she said.
'Oh, my dear!' cried Melanie, and jumped from
her carriage.
'Mother, you've still got me,' said Phil.
'And if you'll just let me, I'll go and kill
all the Yankees-'
'No!' cried Mrs Meade.
'Phil Meade, don't talk like that!' said Melanie,
climbing in with Mrs Meade. 'Drive us home.
Captain Butler, can you tell the doctor? He's
at the hospital.'
Scarlett looked at the list again. So many
names from Atlanta, and from all of Georgia.
Calvert - Fontaine - Munroe. And surely there
couldn't be three Tarletons! But there were.
'Tarleton - Brenton, Stuart and Thomas.' And
Boyd killed the first year somewhere in Virginia.
All the Tarleton boys gone!
'I'm sorry, Scarlett,' said Rhett. 'Many of
your friends?'
'Yes,' she said. 'Oh, Rhett, why do there
have to be wars? Why didn't the Yankees just
pay for the negroes? Or why didn't we just
give them the negroes for nothing?'
'It isn't about the negroes, Scarlett,' he
said. 'They were just the excuse. There'll
always be wars because men love wars.' He
turned away. 'Now, I'm going to find Dr Meade.'
***
After losing the battle of Gettysburg, the
tired and much smaller Confederate army were
pushed back into Virginia for the winter.
As Christmas got closer, Ashley came home
for a week. His father and his sisters - Honey
and India - came to Atlanta to join him and
Melanie.
Scarlett wanted to cry with happiness when
she saw him. There was something new and strange
in the lines of his sun-burned face. He was
the same handsome Ashley, but much more exciting!
He looked at her and said, 'Oh, Scarlett!
You pretty, pretty thing!' and kissed her
on the cheek.
Each day she tried to speak to Ashley alone,
but Melanie was always with him. They all
had questions to ask him about the war but,
although he told them jokes and funny stories
about friends, it seemed to Scarlett that
he did this to stop them asking the questions
he did not want to answer.
The week passed quickly, and Ashley had to
return to Virginia. He said goodbye to Melanie
in their room, and then Scarlett was at last
able to see him alone.
'Ashley, may I go to the station with you?'
she asked him.
'Father and the girls will be there,' he said.
'I want to remember you saying goodbye here.
Will you let me do that?'
'Ashley, I'd do anything for you,' she said.
'Would you?' he said. 'There's something you
can do for me.'
'What is it?' she asked, happily.
'Will you look after Melanie for me?' he said.
'Look after Melanie?' she said, disappointed.
'She loves you so much,' he said. 'Scarlett,
when I think of what might happen to her if
I was killed-'
'Don't say it!' she said. 'It's bad luck to
speak of death!'
'I can't tell what will happen to me or to
any of us,' said Ashley. 'But when the end
comes, if I'm alive, I'll be far away from
here. Too far to look after Melanie.'
'The - the end?' said Scarlett.
'The end of the war - and the end of the world.'
'Ashley, surely you don't think the Yankees
will win.'
'All this week I've talked lies,' he said,
'I didn't want to frighten Melanie or Aunt
Pitty. But yes, Scarlett, I think the Yankees
will win. Gettysburg was the beginning of
the end.'
'I couldn't live if you were dead!' she thought
wildly.
'Don't repeat what I've said,' he told her.
'I don't want to frighten the others. You're
strong, and it will be good to know that you
and Melanie are together if anything happens
to me. You will promise, won't you?'
'Oh, yes!' she cried, ready to promise him
anything. 'Ashley! I can't let you go away!
I can't be brave about it!'
'You must be brave,' he said. He took her
face in his hands and kissed her lightly.
'Scarlett! Scarlett! You're so fine and good
and strong. So beautiful - not just your sweet
face, my dear, but your mind and your body.'
'Oh, Ashley,' she whispered happily, waiting
for him to say the three magic words 'I love
you'. But they didn't come. Instead, she heard
Uncle Peter with the carriage outside. 'Goodbye,'
Ashley said softly.
'Kiss me,' she whispered. 'Kiss me goodbye.'
At the first touch of his lips on hers, she
threw her arms around his neck and pulled
him to her. For a moment he held her close,
but then quickly pushed her away.
'No, Scarlett, no,' he said in a low voice.
'I love you!' she cried. 'Ashley, say you
love me!'
She looked into his face - and it was the
unhappiest face she was ever to see. 'Goodbye!'
he said, his voice a whisper.
***
For the next two months, Scarlett was happy.
She had felt the quickness of Ashley's heart
when her arms went round his neck. She had
seen the look on his face. Oh, he loved her!
She was sure of this now, and could almost
feel sorry for Melanie.
But then in March Melanie said that she was
going to have a baby, and a sharp pain cut
right through Scarlett.
'Dr Meade says it will be here in late August
or September,' Melanie said happily. 'Oh,
Scarlett, isn't it wonderful?'
'Dear God!' thought Scarlett. 'A baby! Ashley's
baby. Oh, how could he when he loves me and
not Melanie? I can't go on living here now.
I'll go home to Tara.'
And the next morning she got up intending
to pack her things, but something happened
that stopped her.
News came that Ashley was missing. He'd been
missing for three days, after going on a five-man
search to discover where the Yankee army were
preparing to fight their next battle.
A shocked Scarlett was certain that God was
punishing her for loving a married man. Melanie's
face was white and frightened, like a child
lost in the dark.
'Scarlett,' she said. 'You're all I've got
now. Oh, I know Ashley is dead!' Suddenly,
she was in Scarlett's arms, and they were
crying and holding each other close.
'At least I've got his baby,' whispered Melanie.
'And I've got nothing,' thought Scarlett.
'Nothing but the look on his face when he
said goodbye.'
***
The first reports were 'Missing - believed
killed,' but they changed to 'Missing - believed
to be a prisoner.' Melanie, her hopes alive
again, met every train, praying for a letter.
She refused to obey Dr Meade and stay in bed,
and one afternoon she fainted at the station
and Rhett Butler brought her home.
'Mrs Wilkes, you're going to have a baby,
aren't you?' he said. And when she gave an
embarrassed nod, he went on, 'Then you must
take better care of yourself or you'll harm
the baby. I'll talk to some people I know
in Washington. If Mr Wilkes is a prisoner,
he'll be on a prisoners' list, and if he isn't
- well, there's nothing worse than not knowing.
But you must promise me you'll take care of
yourself, or I won't help.'
'Oh, you're so kind,' cried Melanie.
A month later, Rhett brought news that Ashley
was not dead but at Rock Island, a cruel and
terrible prison in Illinois where many men
would die before the end of the war.
'He had a chance to get out, but refused it,'
said Rhett. 'The Yankees need men to fight
the Indians in the West, and any prisoner
who will join the Yankee army and fight the
Indians for two years can get out of prison.'
'Why didn't he do that?' cried Scarlett. 'Why
didn't he join, and then run away and come
home as soon as he got out?' Melanie became
angry. 'How can you suggest that? I'd prefer
to know he was dead at Rock Island than he
was no longer a Confederate but a Yankee soldier!
Of course he refused.'
When Scarlett was alone with Rhett, she asked,
'Wouldn't you join the Yankees to get out
of that place, and then run away?'
'Of course,' said Rhett, with a cold smile.
'Then why didn't Ashley?' said Scarlett.
'He's a gentleman,' said Rhett - meaning Ashley
was a fool.
CHAPTER SEVEN
News from Tara
That summer, for the first time since the
war began, the people of Atlanta heard the
sound of battle. The Yankees were getting
closer! Many old men, like John Wilkes, and
young boys, like Phil Meade, were sent to
guard the bridges at Chattahoochee River,
at the back of the main Confederate army.
Then, on a hot July afternoon, after a terrible
battle at Peachtree Creek, a stream of Confederate
soldiers began to arrive in Atlanta. Some
were covered in blood, others helped those
who couldn't walk to get to the hospitals.
Within days, the Yankees were on three sides
of Atlanta, and the railway to Tennessee was
under Yankee control. Only one railway to
the south, to Macon, was still open. But if
they could hold it, Atlanta could stand against
the Yankees.
But when shells began to fall in the streets,
women, children and old people began leaving
the city. Mrs Elsing and Mrs Merriwether refused
to leave. They were needed at the hospital,
they said proudly, and no Yankee was going
to run them out of their homes. Mrs Meade
also refused. Phil was fighting not far away
and she wanted to be near. Aunt Pitty was
among the first to leave. She went to Macon
to stay with a cousin. 'You girls should come
with me,' she said.
But Scarlett did not like Aunt Pitty's cousin.
'I'll go to Tara, and Melanie can go to Macon
with you,' she said.
'Scarlett, don't leave me!' cried Melanie.
'I'll die if you aren't with me when the baby
comes! You promised Ashley that you'd take
care of me. He told me he was going to ask
you.'
'I'll keep my promise,' Scarlett said, tiredly,
'but I won't go to Macon. I'll go home to
Tara, and you can come with me.'
But Dr Meade stopped Melanie going to Macon
or Tara. 'You cannot travel,' he said. 'It
might be dangerous. Miss Pitty, you go to
Macon and leave the young ladies here. Miss
Melanie, you must stay in bed until the baby
comes.'
He spoke privately to Scarlett 'She is going
to have a difficult time,' he said. 'You must
stay with her until the baby comes. With these
shells falling, it may be at any time.'
So Aunt Pitty went to Macon, taking Uncle
Peter with her. And Scarlett and Melanie were
left alone in Atlanta with Wade and Prissy.
***
Those first days, Scarlett would not go into
the streets. Every time she heard the scream
of a shell coming, she rushed to Melanie's
room and threw herself on the bed, and the
two of them hid their heads in the pillow.
Prissy and Wade hid under a table downstairs,
Wade crying and Prissy screaming.
'I'd rather let Melanie die than go out and
find the doctor when the shells are falling,'
thought Scarlett.
But Prissy calmed Scarlett's fears. 'Don't
you worry, Miss Scarlett. I know all about
deliverin' babies,' she said. 'Ain't my mother
told me all about it? Just leave it to me.'
At the end of July, Scarlett received a letter
from Gerald telling her that Careen was ill
with typhoid and that Scarlett must not come
home. That night, she sat outside the house
and thought of Tara. Life there would never
be the same. She would never again hear the
wild, happy voices of the Tarleton boys. Or
the Munroe boys, or little Joe Fontaine, or
-
The front gate opened and she quickly brushed
tears from her face before looking up.
It was Rhett Butler. 'So you didn't go to
Macon,' he said. 'Why did you stay?'
'To be with Melanie. She - well, she can't
go just now.'
'Is Mrs Wilkes still here?' he said. He lit
a cigar. 'And you stayed with her. How strange.'
'I see nothing strange about it,' she said,
uncomfortably.
'You think Mrs Wilkes is silly and stupid,'
he said. 'So why do you stay when there are
Yankee shells falling all around?'
'Because she's Charlie's sister and - and
like a sister to me,' said Scarlett, her cheeks
getting hot.
'You mean because she's Ashley Wilkes' widow,'
said Rhett.
Scarlett became angry. She liked to think
she was a mystery to men, but Rhett could
see through her like glass.
He took her hand in his. 'How lucky, to find
you alone,' he said, and something in his
voice made her face go hot again.
'He's going to tell me he loves me!' she thought.
'Then I can tell him he's wasting his time,
and he'll feel a fool!'
He kissed her hand, and something electric
passed through her whole body as his warm
mouth touched her skin. 'I'm not in love with
him,' she told herself. 'I'm in love with
Ashley.'
'Scarlett, you do like me, don't you?' he
said.
'Well... sometimes,' she said.
'Could you ever love me?'
'I've got him!' she thought, and answered
in a cool voice. 'Certainly not! Not until
you behave like a real gentleman.'
'And I don't intend to do that,' he said.
'So you don't love me? Good, because although
I like you, Scarlett, I don't love you, and
I didn't want to be the second man not to
return your love, my dear.'
'You - you don't love me?' she said.
'Did you hope that I did? I'm sorry. But I
do like you a lot. I know you still think
lovingly of the wooden-headed Mr Wilkes, who
has probably been dead these last six months.
But there must be room in your heart for me,
too. Scarlett, I want you more than I've ever
wanted any woman.'
Scarlett was surprised and confused. 'Are
you asking me to marry you?' she said.
He dropped her hand and laughed loudly. 'No,
I'm not a marrying man, didn't I tell you
that?'
'But - but - what-?'
'My dear,' he said quietly. 'I'm asking you
to be my lover.' Lover! Scarlett felt shock
and disappointment at the same time. 'Get
out!' she cried. 'Get out and don't ever come
back! I'll - I'll tell my father, and he'll
kill you!'
She watched him smile. He was not ashamed,
he was amused! She ran into the house and
tried to crash the door shut behind her, but
it was too heavy.
'May I help you?' he asked.
And he crashed it shut for her as she ran
upstairs.
***
As the hot, noisy days of August came to an
end, the shelling stopped. Then worrying news
came from the south. The Yankees were trying
to take the railway at Jonesboro, and Tara
was close to the fighting. Eventually a soldier
came to say that the Confederate army had
pushed the Yankees back, but the railway was
damaged and it would be some time before trains
could travel again. He brought Scarlett a
letter from her father, after meeting him
in Jonesboro, and was able to tell her that
the Yankees hadn't got to Tara.
'But what was Pa doing in Jonesboro?' she
asked.
The soldier looked nervous. 'He - he was looking
for an army doctor to go to Tara with him,'
he said.
Scarlett opened her father's letter and began
to read:
Dear Daughter, Your mother and both girls
have typhoid and are very ill, but we must
hope for the best. When your mother went to
her bed, she told me to write and say that
you must not come home and put yourself and
Wade in danger, too. She sends her love and
asks you to pray for her.
For the next week, Scarlett waited nervously
for more news, but none came. No one knew
where the Confederates were, or what the Yankees
were doing. She had seen enough typhoid in
the Atlanta hospitals to know that a week
was a long time with that terrible illness,
and she wanted to be at home. 'Oh, why doesn't
this baby come?' she thought.
The last day of August arrived, and with it
came rumours of a big battle south of Atlanta.
People waited for news. If the Yankees won
the Macon railway, they would soon be in Atlanta!
On the first of September, Scarlett woke to
hear a sound like distant thunder. 'Rain coming,'
she thought at first. Then she went to the
window. 'No, not rain, guns! And from the
south!' There lay Jonesboro, Tara - and her
mother.
Scarlett went to Melanie's room. Melanie was
in bed, her eyes closed and with dark circles
around them. She looked worse than any sick
person Scarlett had ever seen. Then her eyes
opened and a soft warm smile lit her face.
'Scarlett,' she said. 'There's something I
want to ask you.' Scarlett sat down on the
bed and Melanie held her hand.
'I'm sorry about the guns, dear,' said Melanie.
'They're towards Jonesboro, aren't they? I
know how worried you are. You could be at
home if it weren't for me, couldn't you?'
'Yes,' said Scarlett, rudely.
'You're so good to me, and I love you for
it. If I die, I want you to take my baby.
Will you do that?'
Scarlett pulled her hand away, frightened.
'Don't be silly, Melanie,' she said. 'You're
not going to die.'
'Promise me, Scarlett, then I won't be afraid,'
said Melanie. 'I'm sure my baby will come
today.'
'Oh, all right, I promise,' said Scarlett.
'Why do you think it will come today?'
'I've been having pains.'
'I'll send Prissy for Dr Meade,' said Scarlett.
'No, you know how busy he is. Just send for
Mrs Meade.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
The Yankees Are Coming
Scarlett sent Prissy for Mrs Meade and, after
a long time, the little black girl returned
alone.
'She wasn't there,' said Prissy. 'She got
news that Mr Phil was shot and she went with
a carriage to fetch him home.'
Scarlett stared, wanting to shake her. 'Well,
don't just stand there, go and fetch Mrs Merriwether!'
'She ain't there,' said Prissy. 'I stopped
on my way home, but the house was shut up.
She's probably at the hospital.'
Scarlett thought for a moment. 'Go to Mrs
Elsing and explain everything,' she said.
'Ask her to come. And hurry!'
She went back to Melanie's room where Melanie
was lying on her side, her face white. 'Mrs
Meade is at the hospital,' lied Scarlett.
She didn't want to worry Melanie by telling
her about Phil getting shot. 'But Mrs Elsing
is coming.'
It was an hour before Prissy came back, walking
slowly along the road. Scarlett hurried out
to meet her.
'Mrs Elsing is over at the hospital,' said
Prissy. 'A lot of soldiers came in on the
early train, most of them hurt bad-'
'You must go to the hospital,' said Scarlett.
'I'll give you a letter for Dr Meade, but
if he isn't there, give it to one of the other
doctors. And hurry back this time!'
Minutes later, Prissy went off with a letter
and Scarlett went back upstairs. Melanie asked
no questions, but her face was full of pain.
An hour passed and then another. Afternoon
came, and Melanie's pains were worse. Where
was Prissy? Why didn't she come? Scarlett
went to the window. Had the sound of the guns
died away, or was it her imagination? Then
she saw Prissy running down the street, fear
written all over her little black face. Scarlett
quickly moved from the window.
'I'll get some cooler water,' she told Melanie.
She got downstairs as Prissy came in. 'They're
fighting at Jonesboro, Miss Scarlett! They
say we're losing the war!'
'Where's Dr Meade? When is he conning?' said
Scarlett.
'He ain't at the hospital. Mrs Merriwether
and Mrs Elsin's ain't there either. A man
told me the doctor was down at the railway
station with the soldiers from Jonesboro.
But, Miss Scarlett, I was too frightened to
go down there. People are dying down there,
and I'm frightened of dead people.'
'What about the other doctors?' asked Scarlett.
'Miss Scarlett, I couldn't get them to read
your letter,' said Prissy. 'They're working
in the hospital like they're all crazy! "Don't
worry me about babies when we've got men dying
here!" one of them shouted at me.'
'Listen,' said Scarlett. 'I'll get Dr Meade
and you sit with Miss Melanie. Don't tell
her where the fighting is, and don't tell
her that the other doctors won't come, do
you hear?'
Scarlett hurried out of the house and into
the hot sun. A soldier came riding past and
she stopped him.
'Are the Yankees coming?' she asked him.
'Yes, Miss,' he said. 'The army are leaving
Atlanta soon.' Scarlett began to run. People
rushed past her as she pushed her way through
the crowd and on towards the station. But
as she went round the side of the Atlanta
Hotel, she stopped.
There, lying on the ground under the heat
of the sun, were hundreds and hundreds of
men. Some were screaming with pain. There
was blood everywhere, and the smell of unwashed
bodies came to meet her. She put a hand across
her mouth and nose.
Then she lifted her skirts and stepped over
dead men, and men with blood on their uniforms,
and men making sounds which had to mean: 'Water!
Water!'
'Dr Meade!' cried Scarlett. 'Is Dr Meade here?'
A man looked up. It was the doctor. His shirt
and trousers were red with blood, and his
face was grey with tiredness.
'Thank God you're here,' he said to Scarlett.
'I can use every pair of hands. Quickly, come
here!'
She went to him as fast as she could across
the rows of bodies. 'Doctor, you must come!
Melanie is having her baby!'
'Baby?' thundered the doctor. 'Are you crazy?
I can't leave these men. Get some woman to
help you. Get my wife.'
She started to tell him why Mrs Meade could
not come - then stopped. She could not tell
him his son was hurt.
'Doctor, please!' she cried. 'Please come!'
He looked at her. 'The Yankees are coming
and the army is moving out of town. I don't
know what they'll do with these men. There
aren't any trains. The Macon line is under
Yankee control. Listen, I can't promise, Scarlett,
but I'll try.'
Scarlett went back through the rows of men.
On the streets beyond the Atlanta Hotel, soldiers
were moving out of the city. There seemed
to be thousands of them. Wagons went past,
throwing up clouds of dust. There were drunken
women with painted faces among the crowd.
Scarlett saw Belle Wading, and heard her drunken
laugh as she held on to a one-armed soldier.
Scarlett began to run again. When she got
back to the house, Wade was waiting outside.
'Wade hungry,' he cried.
'Be quiet!' said Scarlett. 'Go and play in
the back garden.' She looked up and saw Prissy
at the bedroom window. Scarlett waved at her
to come down, then went into the house. Prissy
came down the stairs three at a time.
'The doctors can't come,' said Scarlett. 'You've
got to deliver the baby, and I'll help you.'
Prissy's mouth fell open.
'What's the matter?' said Scarlett.
'I - Miss Scarlett - I don't know nothin'
about deliverin' babies,' said Prissy, looking
at the floor.
Scarlett took Prissy's arm and squeezed it.
'You black liar! What do you mean? You said
you knew everything about-'
'I was lyin', Miss Scarlett!' cried Prissy.
Scarlett had never hit a slave in all her
life, but she hit Prissy's black cheek as
hard as she could. Prissy screamed loudly
and tried to pull away.
'Scarlett, is it you?' Melanie's weak voice
came from upstairs. 'Please come! Please!'
Scarlett tried to remember what Mammy and
Ellen did when Wade was born. 'Build a fire
and make sure there's plenty of water,' she
told Prissy. 'Bring all the towels you can
find, and some string and a pair of scissors.
Quickly!'
She pushed Prissy towards the kitchen, then
took a deep breath before going upstairs.
***
There was never an afternoon as long as this
one. Or as hot. Scarlett pulled the bedroom
curtains across to keep out the sun. Melanie
tried to be brave, but when evening came,
she began calling for Ashley - over and over
- until Scarlett wanted to cover her face
with a pillow. 'Perhaps the doctor will come
after all,' thought Scarlett, and she told
Prissy to go to the Meades' house and see
if he or Mrs Meade were there.
Prissy went, but came back soon after, alone.
'The doctor ain't been home all day,' she
reported. 'An', Miss Scarlett, Mr Phil is
dead. He was shot. I didn't see Mrs Meade
because she was gettin' his body ready for-'
'All right,' said Scarlett quickly.
Melanie opened her eyes and whispered, 'Are
the Yankees coming?'
'No,' said Scarlett. 'Prissy's a liar.'
'Yes, Miss, I am,' agreed Prissy.
'The Yankees are coming,' whispered Melanie,
guessing correctly. 'My poor baby. Scarlett,
you mustn't stay here.'
'You know I won't leave you,' said Scarlett.
'Why not?' said Melanie. 'I'm going to die
anyway.'
CHAPTER NINE
Escape from Atlanta
Scarlett came down the dark stairs slowly,
like an old woman. She went outside and sat
on the front step. It was all over. Melanie
was not dead, and Prissy was giving the small
baby boy his first bath while Melanie was
asleep.
The night air was cool and fresh on her face
and arms. More soldiers were leaving the city,
passing by the house, although she could not
see them clearly in the darkness.
What could she do? Where could she turn for
help? Scarlett remembered Rhett. He was strong
and clever, and he wasn't afraid of the Yankees.
And he had a horse and carriage, too.
She called Prissy. 'Captain Butler lives at
the Atlanta Hotel,' she said. 'Go there quickly
and tell him about the baby. Tell him that
I want him to get us out of here.'
'Suppose Cap'n Butler ain't at the hotel?'
said Prissy.
'Go to the bar-rooms, go to Belle Watling's
house,' said Scarlett. 'Just find him, or
the Yankees will get us all!'
Scarlett went back into the house and waited.
After some time, she saw that the sky was
becoming pink over the east of the city. Then
a large flame shot high into the darkness.
'The Yankees are burning the city!' she thought.
Moments later, Prissy ran into the room.
'The Yankees-?' Scarlett began.
'No, it's our men,' said Prissy. 'They're
burnin' the gun factory, an' what the army
left. We're all going to burn up!'
'Did you see Captain Butler?' said Scarlett.
'Yes, I saw him, an' I says "Come quick, Cap'n
Butler, and bring your horse and carriage."
And he says they took his horse but he'll
steal another one.'
'He's coming? He's going to bring a horse?'
'So he says.'
Scarlett began to feel better. She would forgive
Rhett anything if he got them out of this
mess. 'Wake up Wade and dress him,' she told
Prissy. 'Then pack some clothes for all of
us. Don't tell Miss Melanie we're going, not
yet, but put two thick towels around the baby
and pack his clothes, too.'
It seemed hours before Rhett finally came
with a wagon. He was dressed as if he was
going dancing, in a white coat and trousers.
He carried two guns, and his pockets were
full of bullets.
'Good evening,' he said, smiling and taking
off his hat. 'Fine weather we're having! I
hear you're going on a trip.'
'If you make any jokes, I'll never speak to
you again,' said Scarlett, her voice shaking.
'You're frightened!' He pretended to be surprised.
'Yes, I am! And if you had any sense, you'd
be frightened, too!' she said. 'We must get
out of here.'
'And where are you going?' he asked politely.
'I'm going home,' she said.
'You mean to Tara?' he said. 'Scarlett, are
you mad? The Yankees may be all over Tara
by now. You can't go right through the Yankee
army!'
'I will go home!' she cried, tears running
down her cheeks. Suddenly, she was in his
arms. His hands smoothed her hair gently,
and when he spoke his voice was gentle, too.
'Don't cry, my brave little girl,' he said.
'I'll take you home.'
***
Rhett turned west along the narrow street,
and the wheel of the wagon hit a stone so
hard that Melanie cried out in the back of
the wagon. Wade and Prissy were next to her
with the new baby. Scarlett was in the front
next to Rhett.
'Must we go through the fire?' she asked him.
'Not if we hurry,' he said.
He stopped the horse suddenly. 'Soldiers,'
he said.
Long lines of Confederate soldiers walked
through Marietta Street, too tired to care
about the burning buildings around them. Many
had no shoes, and their uniforms were torn
and dirty. They went past silently, like ghosts.
'Take a good look,' said Rhett, 'so you can
tell your grandchildren that you saw the last
soliders of the sacred Cause.'
Suddenly she hated him for insulting these
broken men. She thought of Charles, of Ashley
who might be dead, and all those brave young
boys, now dead. She forgot that she had once
thought they were fools.
Rhett watched the soldiers with a strange
and thoughtful look on his face. Then there
was a crash of falling wood and Scarlett saw
a thin flame above the building next to them.
'Rhett, hurry!' she shouted.
They went quickly from one narrow street to
another until the sound of the flames died
behind them. Rhett did not speak. His face
looked cold and hard, as if he'd forgotten
where he was. Scarlett wanted him to say something
- anything - but he only sat and stared at
the dark road ahead.
'Oh, Rhett,' she said. 'I'm so glad you aren't
in the army!'
At this, he turned his head - and she saw
in his eyes how angry and confused he was.
After that, she said nothing.
At last, they were on a wider, smoother road.
'We're out of the city,' said Rhett. 'Do you
still want to do this crazy thing? The Yankee
army are between you and Tara.'
'Yes!' she said. 'Please, Rhett, let's hurry!'
'You can't go to Jonesboro down this road,'
he said, 'they've been fighting up and down
there all day. Do you know any wagon paths?'
'Oh, yes,' cried Scarlett. 'I know a wagon
path. Pa and I used to ride it. It comes out
only a mile from Tara.'
'Good,' said Rhett. 'Maybe the Yankees aren't
there yet. Maybe you can get through if-'
'I can get through? Aren't you going to take
us?'
'No,' he said. 'I'm leaving you here.'
'Leaving us?' she said wildly. 'Where are
you going?'
'I'm going with the army,' he said.
'Rhett, stop joking!'
'I'm not joking, my dear,' he said, smiling.
'Think how delighted our soldiers will be
at my last-minute appearance.'
'Oh, Rhett!' she cried. 'Why are you going?'
He laughed. 'Perhaps because I'm a Southerner,
and I'm ashamed. Who knows?'
'You should die of shame, leaving us alone
and helpless-'
'Scarlett, anyone as selfish and strong-minded
as you is never helpless. God help the Yankees
if they get you!' He stepped down from the
wagon. Then he put his hands up, caught her
under the arms and brought her to the ground
next to him. He took her several steps away
from the wagon. 'I'm not asking you to understand
or forgive,' he said. 'I'll never understand
or forgive myself for this foolishness. But
the South needs every man, so I'm off to the
wars.' His warm, strong hands moved up her
arms. 'I do love you, Scarlett, although I
told you I didn't. Do you want to change your
mind about what I suggested before? A soldier
would go to his death with beautiful memories.'
He was kissing her now with slow, hot lips.
Charles had never kissed her like this. The
kisses of the Tarleton and Calvert boys never
made her go hot and cold like this.
A voice came from the wagon. It was Wade's.
'Wade frightened!'
And suddenly Scarlett remembered that she
was frightened, too, and that Rhett was leaving
her. And on top of it all, he was insulting
her with his shocking suggestions!
She pulled herself away from him. 'You coward!'
she screamed. 'You nasty, horrible thing!'
And she hit him across the mouth with all
her strength.
He put a hand to his face. 'I see,' he said
quietly.
'Go on!' cried Scarlett. 'I don't want to
see you ever again! I hope a shell lands right
on you. I hope it blows you into a million
pieces. I hope-'
'Never mind the rest,' said Rhett, smiling.
'I understand your general idea.' He walked
back to the wagon. 'Mrs Wilkes?'
Prissy's frightened voice answered from the
wagon. 'Miss Melanie fainted a long way back,
Cap'n Butler.'
'That's probably best,' he said. 'If she was
awake, I doubt that she could live through
all the pain. Take good care of her, Prissy.'
He turned round. 'Goodbye, Scarlett.'
Scarlett knew he was looking at her but she
did not speak. She saw his big shoulders moving
in the dark, then he was gone. She came slowly
back to the wagon, her knees shaking. She
put her head against the neck of the horse
and cried.
CHAPTER TEN
Home
Many times on that journey Scarlett heard
soldiers coming, and had to hide the wagon
in fields among the trees; then wait while
the men went past like ghosts in the darkness.
She lost her way and cried when she could
not find the little wagon path she knew so
well. But a few miles after she found it,
the horse dropped to its knees, too tired
to go any further.
Scarlett climbed into the back of the wagon,
heard Melanie whisper, 'Scarlett, can I have
some water please?' and heard herself answer,
'There isn't any,' before she went to sleep.
When she woke, the sun was pouring through
the trees and everything was silent. She sat
up and looked round quickly, but there were
no soldiers anywhere. In the wagon, Melanie
lay so still and white that at first Scarlett
thought she must be dead, but then she saw
Melanie's shallow breathing.
They were under some trees in someone's front
garden, Scarlett noticed. 'It's the Mallory
place!' she thought, excited at the thought
of friends and help. But the stillness of
death lay over the plantation and, when she
looked towards the house, there were only
some smoke-blackened stones left.
'Is this what Tara will be like?' she thought.
She woke Prissy, then looked over and saw
that Melanie's eyes were open.
Scarlett found some apples under the trees,
then got some water from a stream near the
house. They all had a drink, then Scarlett
gave the rest of the water to the horse. The
animal was on its feet again but it was very
old, she saw now.
They were fifteen miles from Tara, but the
horse moved so slowly it took all day to travel
there. Every empty, burned-out house they
passed frightened Scarlett more. There were
dead men and dead horses lying by the road,
and the fields and trees seemed full of ghosts
in the afternoon sun.
There was a sudden noise and Prissy screamed
loudly. But it was only a cow coming from
behind some trees. The animal looked at them
with large, frightened eyes.
'She needs milking,' said Prissy.
'It must be one of Mr Macintosh's that the
Yankees didn't get,' said Scarlett. 'We'll
take it with us, then we can have some milk
for the baby.'
It was evening when they reached the top of
a hill and went down through the line of trees
that led to Tara. Was it there? Or was the
darkness hiding just a few smoke-blackened
stones like the Macintosh place? But no! Tara
had escaped! It was there! The white walls
showed through the darkness.
Then Scarlett saw a shadow come from inside
the house. Someone was home! A shout of delight
started in her throat - but died there. The
shadow did not move or call to her but, stiffly
and slowly, came down the steps.
'Pa?' she whispered. 'It's me, Scarlett. I've
come home.'
Her father looked at her. 'Daughter,' he said.
'Daughter.'
'He's an old man!' thought Scarlett, shocked.
A baby's cry came from the wagon and Gerald
looked across.
'It's Melanie and her baby,' whispered Scarlett.
'She's very ill - I brought her home.'
Gerald went to the wagon, straightening his
shoulders. 'Cousin Melanie!' he said. 'Twelve
Oaks is burned. You must stay with us.'
'We must carry her,' said Scarlett. 'She can't
walk.'
Another person came from the house. It was
Pork, Gerald's personal slave. He ran down
the steps. 'Miss Scarlett!'
Scarlett caught him by the arms and felt his
tears on her hands as he held them. 'Glad
- glad you're back!' he cried.
It was Pork who carried Melanie indoors. Prissy
took the baby, Wade followed them up the steps
into the house. Scarlett caught her father's
arm before he could follow, too.
'Did they get well, Pa?' she said.
'The girls are getting better,' he said. 'Your
mother-'
'Yes?'
'Your mother died yesterday,' said Gerald.
***
Gerald said it over and over again as he followed
Scarlett around the house. 'She died yesterday
- she died yesterday.' Scarlett felt nothing
except a great tiredness. She would think
of Mother later, or she would simply cry and
cry.
Later, when she was alone with her father,
she asked, 'Why didn't the Yankees burn Tara?'
'They used the house for offices,' said Gerald.
'Yankees - in this house?' The thought made
her feel sick.
'They were, daughter,' said Gerald. 'We saw
the smoke from Twelve Oaks before they came.
But Miss Honey and Miss India were in Macon,
so we didn't worry about them. We couldn't
go to Macon. The girls were so sick - your
mother - we couldn't go. Our negroes ran away.
They stole the wagons and the horses. Only
Mammy, Dilcey and Pork stayed. The Yankees
came up the road from the river and I met
them at the front door.'
'Oh, brave little Gerald!' thought Scarlett.
'They told me to leave,' went on Gerald. 'They
told me they were going to burn the place.
I told them that we had typhoid in the house
and they would burn it over the heads of three
dying women. The young officer was - was a
gentleman.'
'A Yankee gentleman? Pa!'
'A gentleman,' said Gerald. 'He rode away
and came back with an army doctor who looked
at the girls - and your mother.'
'You let a Yankee into their room?'
'He had medicine and we had none. He saved
your sisters,' said Gerald. 'They didn't burn
the house, they moved in. The officers filled
all the rooms except the sick room, and the
soldiers lived in tents around the place.
They killed the cows, the chickens and the
pigs. They took the pictures and some of the
furniture.'
'And - and Mother? Did she know Yankees were
in the house?'
'She never knew anything.'
'Thank God,' said Scarlett.
'And then they moved on.' He was silent for
a long time and then he held her hand. 'I'm
glad you're home,' he said simply.
***
After Gerald went to bed, Scarlett went to
the room where Careen and Suellen were sleeping.
Mammy was there, watching them. Her eyes lit
up when she saw Scarlett.
'My child is home!' Mammy said softly. 'Oh,
Miss Scarlett, now that Miss Ellen is dead,
what are we going to do?'
Scarlett sat down next to the bed. 'I want
you to tell me about Mother,' she said, 'I
just couldn't ask Pa about her.'
Tears came from Mammy's eyes. 'It was those
Slattery trash that killed Miss Ellen. I told
her and told her not to-'
'Slatterys?' said Scarlett, confused.
'Emmie Slattery was sick with typhoid and
Miss Ellen went to nurse her,' said Mammy.
'I told her to leave those white trash alone,
but she didn't listen. Then, when Emmie was
getting better, Miss Careen went down with
typhoid, and then Miss Suellen. So Miss Ellen
had to nurse them, too. With all the fighting
up the road, and the Yankees across the river,
and the field negroes running off every night,
I was nearly crazy with worry. But Miss Ellen
was cool and calm, except that she worried
because we couldn't get medicines. And then
she went down with typhoid, too.' Mammy dried
her tears before she went on. 'Miss Ellen
went fast, Miss Scarlett. Even that nice Yankee
doctor couldn't do anythin' for her. She died
a few nights after the cotton burned-'
'Has the cotton gone?' said Scarlett. 'Tell
me!'
'Yes, Miss Scarlett. The Yankees burned it.'
'Three years' cotton!' thought Scarlett. 'One
hundred and fifty thousand dollars, in one
big fire!'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Murder
Next morning, when Scarlett went down to breakfast,
Gerald was sitting at the table. As Scarlett
sat down, he said, 'We will wait for Mrs O'Hara.
She is late.'
Scarlett stared at him. He was looking at
her in a strange and confused way, and his
hands were shaking.
'Has Pa lost his mind?' thought Scarlett.
'No! He'll get better. He must get better!
I won't think about it now. I won't think
of him or Mother or any of these awful things!'
She left the room without eating.
Pork was outside the house. 'Have you been
over to Twelve Oaks or the Macintosh place
to see if there's anything left in the gardens
that we can eat?' Scarlett asked him.
'No, Miss,' said Pork, 'We ain't left Tara.'
'You go to Macintosh, and I'll go to Twelve
Oaks,' she said.
The road was hot and dusty, but she was hungry,
and they needed food from somewhere. At the
bottom of the hill was the river, and Scarlett
took off her shoes and put her feet into the
cool water before going on to Twelve Oaks.
It was burned down, and just a few blackened
stones were left of the house where she had
danced and flirted with the men, and dreamed
her dreams of marrying Ashley.
'Oh, Ashley, I hope you are dead!' she thought.
'I don't want you to see this!'
She walked to the garden and found some potatoes
in the soft earth. Without stopping to clean
it, Scarlett picked up a potato and began
to eat. But it was old and the taste was bitter,
and Scarlett was sick almost immediately.
Then she lay down, her face against the earth,
and thought of the people who were dead, the
way of life that had gone forever, and the
dark and frightening future.
But the past was the past, Scarlett told herself,
sitting up. Those lazy, happy old days were
gone, never to return. There was no going
back. 'I'm going to live through this,' she
said aloud. 'And when it's over, I'm never
going to be hungry again. If I have to steal
or kill - as God is my witness - I'm never
going to be hungry again!'
***
After two weeks, she knew that her father
would never get any better. He would always
be waiting for Ellen, always listening for
her. When Scarlett asked him for advice, his
only answer was, 'Do what you think best,
daughter.'
One morning, she was at the open window of
her bedroom. She had hurt her foot and was
sitting in a chair. Melanie was in her room
with the children, Careen and Suellen were
in their room, and Gerald, Mammy, Pork and
Dilcey were in the fields.
Scarlett was wondering how they were going
to buy food. The only money in the house was
Confederate money, and that had almost no
value now. 'And if I can get my hands on some
money,' she thought, 'how can we carry food
from Jonesboro to Tara?' The old horse that
brought them from Atlanta had died.
It was while she was worrying that she heard
the sound of a horse. She looked up quickly
- and saw a Yankee soldier. He was a rough-looking
man with an untidy black beard - and a gun!
And he was getting off his horse outside the
front door.
Scarlett heard him come into the house and
walk through the rooms downstairs. 'In a moment,'
she thought, 'he'll walk into the kitchen!'
There, cooking over the fire in two large
pots, were apples and vegetables - brought
painfully from Twelve Oaks and the Macintosh
garden - dinner for nine hungry people, but
only really enough for two. The thought of
the Yankee eating their meal made Scarlett
so angry that she began to shake.
She went to the cupboard and took out the
heavy gun which Charles had never used. Then,
quickly and silently, she ran downstairs,
holding it behind her.
'Who's there?' he shouted. And she stopped
in the middle of the stairs. He was standing
in the doorway of the dining room, his gun
in one hand. 'So there is somebody home,'
he said, smiling and putting his gun away.
He walked across until he was standing below
her. 'All alone, little lady?' he said.
Before he could move again, Scarlett lifted
her gun and shot him in the face. The noise
filled her ears and the man crashed backwards
on to the floor. Scarlett ran down and stood
over him, looking into what was left of his
face. As she looked, two streams of blood
ran across the floor, one from his face and
one from the back of his head. He was dead.
She had killed a man. 'Murder,' she thought.
'I've done murder. Oh, this can't be happening
to me!'
A sound behind her made Scarlett turn round.
Melanie, wearing only a night-dress, was coming
down the stairs. She saw the dead Yankee,
then smiled proudly at Scarlett.
'She - she's like me!' thought Scarlett. 'She
would do the same thing!'
'Scarlett! Scarlett!' cried the frightened
voices of her sisters. Then Wade began to
scream. Melanie climbed back up the stairs
and opened the door of the girls' room.
'Don't be frightened!' she said, laughing.
'Your sister was trying to clean Charles gun,
and it went off and nearly frightened her
to death! Wade, your mother just shot your
dear Pa's gun. When you get older, she'll
let you shoot it, too.'
'What a cool liar!' thought Scarlett. 'I couldn't
think that quickly. But why did she lie? They've
got to know I've done it.'
Melanie came back downstairs, although she
was weak and in pain. 'Scarlett, we must get
him out of here,' she said. 'He may not be
alone, and if more soldiers come and find
him-'
'He must be alone,' said Scarlett. 'I didn't
see any others from the upstairs window.'
'Well, no one must know about it,' said Melanie.
'The negroes might talk and then they'll come
and get you. We must hide him before they
come back.'
'I could dig a hole in the corner of the garden
and put him in it,' said Scarlett. 'But how
will I get him there?'
'We'll each take a leg and pull him,' said
Melanie.
'You couldn't pull a cat. You'll kill yourself.'
'All right,' said Melanie. 'You pull him out
and I'll clean up the mess. But can't we go
through his bag and his pockets first? He
might have something to eat.'
Scarlett found a wallet inside his coat. It
was full of money - United States money as
well as Confederate money, and one ten-dollar
gold coin and two five-dollar gold coins.
Melanie found some coffee in the bag, and
there were rings and other small pieces of
jewellery in his pockets.
'A thief!' whispered Melanie. 'He stole all
this! I'm glad you killed him, Scarlett.'
***
No one asked where the horse came from, they
were just pleased to have him. The Yankee
lay covered in the hole in the corner of the
garden. No ghost came to frighten Scarlett
during the long nights when she lay awake
afterwards.
'I won't think about it,' she said to herself.
But whenever she had to do something difficult
after this, she thought: 'I've done murder,
so I can do this.'
CHAPTER TWELVE
Peace, At Last
By May, 1865, the war was over and the Confederacy
had lost. The dream they had loved and hoped
for, the Cause which took the lives of their
friends, was finished. But Scarlett cried
no tears. She simply thought: 'Thank God!
Now the cow won't be stolen. Now the horse
is safe. Now I won't be afraid to drive round
the country looking for something to eat.
And if Ashley is alive, he'll be coming home.'
In that warm summer after peace came, a stream
of Confederate soldiers came through Tara,
on their way home. Most were walking, although
a few lucky ones had a horse. They asked each
soldier for news of Ashley, and Suellen asked
about Mr Kennedy, but none of them knew anything.
Then, one afternoon, Uncle Peter surprised
them all by arriving from Atlanta. He came
on an old horse and brought news of Aunt Pitty,
who wanted Melanie and Scarlett to come back
to live with her again.
He also brought a letter - from Ashley.
'He's coming home!' Uncle Peter told them.
'He's alive!'
Melanie fainted, but Scarlett took the letter
and opened it quickly. She recognized Ashley's
writing:
My love, I am coming home to you.
Tears filled her eyes so that she could not
read any more. Holding the letter, she ran
to her mother's room while the others tried
to help Melanie. She shut the door, then crying
and laughing and kissing the letter, she whispered,
'My love, I am coming home to you!'
***
When weeks went by and Ashley did not come,
Scarlett began to worry that something had
happened to him along the way.
The never-ending line of soldiers went through,
and Scarlett's heart began to grow hard. They
were eating the food which was meant for the
mouths of Tara. Food was hard to get, and
the money in the Yankee's wallet would not
last forever.
Will Benteen was a soldier who was very ill
when he arrived. One of his legs finished
at the knee, and a roughly cut wooden leg
was fitted to it. He looked like a poor farmer,
not a plantation owner, but this did not stop
the girls working to save his life. Then,
one day, he opened his light blue eyes and
saw Careen sitting beside him.
'Then you weren't a dream, after all,' he
said.
Will had owned a small farm in Georgia, and
two negroes. He knew that his slaves were
free now, and that his farm was burned, but
these things did not seem to worry him.
'You've been good to me, Miss Scarlett,' he
said. 'And, if you'll let me, I'm goin' to
stay here and help you with all the work until
I've paid you back. I can't ever pay it all,
because there's no price a man can pay for
his life.'
So he stayed and, slowly and quietly, a large
part of the work and worry of Tara, passed
from Scarlett to him.
***
It was a warm September afternoon, and Will
was sitting on the front steps of Tara, talking
to Scarlett. Melanie came out to join them.
Although she did her share of the work at
Tara, she was thin and never completely well.
Will was talking about his trip to Fayetteville
that morning when he looked along the road
leading to Tara.
'Another soldier,' he said.
Scarlett looked and saw a man with a beard,
wearing the usual grey and blue uniform which
was dusty and torn.
'I hope he isn't very hungry,' she said.
'He'll be hungry,' said Will.
Melanie stood up. 'I'll tell Dilcey to-'
She stopped so suddenly that Scarlett turned
to look at her. Melanie's hand was at her
throat and her face was white. 'She's going
to faint,' thought Scarlett, jumping to her
feet.
But Melanie was running down the steps, her
arms stretching out towards the soldier. And
then Scarlett knew the truth.
The man lifted his face and looked towards
the house, as if he was too tired to take
another step. Melanie, crying out, threw herself
into his arms.
Scarlett took two steps forward, but Will
stopped her.
'Don't spoil it,' he said quietly.
'Let me go, you fool! Let me go! It's Ashley!'
Will held her. 'He's her husband, ain't he?'
he said calmly.
Scarlett looked at him angrily - and in the
quiet kindness of his eyes she saw understanding
and pity.
- THE END -