CHAPTER ONE
Three Bodies
The man who was waiting on the shore looked
like a farmer. He wore the right kind of clothes,
and his van, which was parked on the dirt
road above the beach, was suitably covered
in mud.
It was midnight on the first Monday in October,
and for the next thirty minutes he had to
wait there. He stared out to sea. He was alone,
as he knew he would be; it was planned that
way. This beach was always empty at this time
of night. No cars drove along the dirt road.
The clouds were low and thick. It would be
difficult to see the boat until it was close.
That was planned as well.
After he had waited twenty minutes he heard
the sound of a quiet engine from the water
and then saw a black rubber boat, low in the
water, approach the shore. The engine stopped
when the boat was about thirty feet from the
shore. The farmer looked around. There were
no people, no cars.
He carefully put a cigarette in his mouth
and started to smoke it. A man's voice came
from the boat on the water: 'What kind of
cigarette is that?'
'Lucky Strike,' the farmer answered.
Satisfied, the man in the boat asked, 'Luke?'
'Sam,' replied the farmer. The man in the
boat was Khamel, not Sam, and Luke knew it.
Luke had often heard of Khamel, but he was
not sure that they had met before. Khamel
had many names and many faces, and he spoke
several languages. He was the most famous
and most feared killer in the world. He was
the best. At first, twenty years ago, he had
killed for political reasons, but now he would
kill anyone, anywhere, if the money was right.
Luke was excited. Khamel was going to be working
in America. He wondered who was going to die.
Whoever it was, the killing would be quick
and clean, and there would be no clues.
At dawn, the stolen van stopped at a hotel
in Georgetown, part of Washington, DC, the
political capital of the United States of
America. Khamel got out of the van without
a word to Luke. They had not spoken throughout
the journey, and Luke had been careful not
to look at Khamel. He didn't want to die;
he didn't want Khamel to think he could recognize
him.
The room in the hotel was ready, of course.
The curtains were tightly closed. The car
keys were on the table. The gun was in a briefcase
next to the bed.
He had received three million dollars already
for this job. He would phone his bank in three
hours to ask whether the next four million
had arrived. While he waited, he practised
his English in front of the mirror. The job
would be over by midnight tonight, so another
three million would reach his bank by midday
tomorrow. By then he would be in Paris. It
was satisfactory. He allowed himself a short
sleep.
***
The Supreme Court is the highest court in
the USA. It consists of nine judges, who hear
only the most difficult cases in the country
- those cases which might actually threaten
the Constitution. Judges are appointed to
the Supreme Court by the government, so a
Republican government will try to get Republican
judges appointed and a Democratic government
will try to get Democrats appointed. Judges
become members of the Supreme Court for life.
They can retire if they want, but if not the
job ends only with death. Judge Rosenberg
was so old that he found it hard to stay awake
sometimes, even during trials. He was a liberal,
and proud of it. He defended the Indians,
the homosexuals, the poor, the blacks, the
Mexicans and the Puerto Ricans. Some people
loved him for it, but more people hated him.
Throughout the summer there had been the usual
number of messages threatening death to the
judges of the Supreme Court, and as usual
Rosenberg had received more than the others.
The FBI had to behave as if the judges really
were in danger, although they were threatened
year after year and it was very rare for anything
to happen. When it did, it was usually a single
madman, whose daughter had died in a road
accident or something. The political groups
made a lot of noise, but it was easier for
them to bomb buildings than people, and especially
people who were as well guarded as the Supreme
Court judges.
Rosenberg refused to have FBI guards in his
own home; he had lived to be ninety-one and
was not afraid of death. Judge Jensen had
different reasons for not wanting guards in
his house: he wanted to be able to come and
go as he pleased. Both of them allowed the
guards to wait outside, in cars or on foot,
but they could enter the house only when they
had permission.
A little after ten at night, when the house
was dark and still, the door to a bedroom
cupboard opened and Khamel came quietly out.
He was dressed in running clothes. He had
shaved off his beard and coloured his hair
blond.
Silently, he went down the stairs. He knew
there were two FBI men in a car that was parked
on the road outside the front of the house;
he knew there was another guard, Ferguson,
walking around the house outside.
Rosenberg and his male nurse were asleep in
the downstairs bedroom. Outside the door,
Khamel fitted a silencer on to his gun. He
stepped inside, put the gun to the head of
the nurse and fired three times. The hands
and legs jumped, but the eyes stayed closed,
and there was no sound. Khamel quickly reached
across to the grey old head of Judge Rosenberg
and shot three bullets into it.
He watched the two bodies for a full minute,
and then went out to the kitchen. He opened
the back door, waited until Ferguson appeared
in the back garden, and then called his name.
He knew that the nurse often invited Ferguson
in for a cup of coffee and something to eat.
Ferguson obediently came into the kitchen.
Khamel fired three bullets into the back of
his head and he fell loudly on to the table.
Khamel left the gun there and went out of
the back door. As soon as he reached the road
at the back of the house, he began running.
He was just another American, out for his
nightly run.
***
In the dark of the Montrose Theatre, Glenn
Jensen sat by himself and watched the men
on the big screen in the front of the theatre.
He was dressed in ordinary clothes - clothes
that no one would remember - and wore dark
glasses too. Nobody would know that he had
been here. He came to this homosexual film
theatre once or twice a week, and not even
his FBI guards knew about it.
It was easy to get out of the house. There
were several apartments in the building, and
the two FBI men could watch only one entrance
at a time. All he had to do was change his
clothes and drive away in a friend's car.
He liked the Montrose because the films went
on all night and there was never a crowd.
Tonight there were only two old men, sitting
together in the middle of the theatre and
holding hands. Jensen watched their backs
and wondered if he would be like them in twenty
years. At forty-four, he was the youngest
of the Supreme Court judges.
He was not a favourite of either the Republicans
or the Democrats, but had been a safe appointment
for the Republican President four years ago.
He was not particularly liberal, except in
cases involving homosexuals and those where
industry threatened the environment. He usually
tried to judge his cases according to their
rights and wrongs, rather than any political
opinions.
A fourth person entered the theatre where
Jensen and the two old men were now enjoying
a film in which several young men were in
bed together. He wore tight jeans, a black
shirt, an earring, dark glasses and a moustache.
Khamel the homosexual. He smiled when he saw
Jensen there. The information they had given
him was good.
At 12:20 the old men left the theatre, arm
in arm. Jensen did not look at them; he was
too busy watching the film. Khamel moved like
a cat to a seat behind Jensen. He pulled some
rope from round his waist and wrapped the
ends round his hands. He suddenly put the
rope around the front of Jensen's neck and
pulled backwards and downwards. Jensen's neck
broke over the back of his seat. Just to make
sure, Khamel twisted the rope until it bit
deeply into Jensen's neck and held it there
for two minutes.
An hour later he was waiting at Dulles airport
for his flight to Paris.
CHAPTER TWO
Political Planning
The phone woke the President at 4:30 in the
morning. He listened to the voice for a minute
and then jumped out of bed. Eight minutes
later he was in the office. Fletcher Coal,
his chief of staff, was waiting for him.
'What the hell happened?' the President asked.
Coal walked up and down in front of the President's
desk. 'We don't know much,' he said. 'They're
both dead. Two FBI men found Rosenberg at
one a.m. His nurse and guard were also dead.
Three bullets each - very clean, very professional.
While the FBI were at Rosenberg's house, they
heard that the police had found Jensen's body
in a homosexual club. Voyles called me, and
I called you. He'll be here in a minute.'
'Rosenberg is dead,' the President said.
'Yes. At last.' Rosenberg and the Republican
Government had not been friends. 'I suggest
you go on TV in two or three hours' time and
tell the country about it all. Mabry is already
working on your speech. We don't want to leave
it until later, because we want to be the
first to tell them. The press already have
the news.'
'I didn't know he was a homosexual.'
'There's no doubt about it now. This is the
perfect crisis. We didn't cause it; we didn't
do anything wrong. The country will be shocked
and they'll turn to you. You're going to be
more popular than ever, and next year you'll
be elected again for another four years. It's
great.'
'And I can get two new men into the Supreme
Court.'
'Exactly. That's the best bit. They'll be
your men, and they'll be there for ever. You'll
have a first list of names by tomorrow.'
'Are there any suspects?'
'Not yet.'
The President smiled. 'Voyles's FBI men were
supposed to protect the judges, weren't they?
Good. I want you to leak that information
to the press. Maybe we can get rid of Voyles
too.'
When Voyles arrived a moment later, the President
and Coal tried to look worried. Voyles told
them that there were no suspects yet, and
the President asked for a list by five o'clock
that evening. They agreed that the killings
must be connected. Voyles denied that his
men had been careless.
'Rosenberg and Jensen are dead because they
refused to let us guard them properly,' he
said. 'We're guarding the other seven, and
they're still alive.'
'At the moment,' the President said, and looked
at Coal. They almost smiled. They could easily
make Voyles look stupid and inefficient over
this business. Voyles knew it too. He was
going to have to be careful. The President
- or rather Coal, who told the President what
to think - wanted his head, and the press
would eat him alive. Back in his office, he
ordered a full enquiry into the murders.
***
Darby Shaw woke up a little before dawn. After
fifteen months of law school at Tulane University
in New Orleans, her mind refused to rest for
more than six hours. The work had not been
so hard at her first university, in Phoenix,
Arizona, where she had specialized in environmental
science. Then she decided to become a lawyer
and to defend the environment in the courts.
The price was hard work and more hard work.
There were some rewards, however. She turned
over in the bed to look at the man sleeping
next to her. Thomas Callahan was one of the
most popular teachers in the university. He
was forty-five years old, but seemed a lot
younger. He drank a lot, wore jeans, drove
a Porsche, lived in the French Quarter and
managed to make even constitutional law interesting.
He was also good in bed. And for the first
time in his life he had stayed with one woman
for more than a few weeks. Darby and he had
been together now for several months. She
smiled and wondered what her fellow students
would think. Only her very best friends knew
the secret.
She turned the TV on and suddenly there was
the President. She listened for a minute and
then shook Thomas awake. 'Thomas! Wake up!
Listen to this!' She turned the sound up louder.
Callahan sat up and stared at the screen,
still half asleep. He understood what the
President was saying, though. 'Rosenberg?
Murdered?' he said. Darby knew that Rosenberg
was his hero.
'Jensen too,' she said.
The President finished his speech and Darby
switched the TV off.
'No suspects, according to the President,'
Callahan said.
'I can think of at least twenty groups who
wanted Rosenberg dead,' Darby said, 'starting
with the Ku-Klux-Klan.'
'Yeah, but why those two judges? OK, lots
of people wanted Rosenberg dead, but why Jensen?
Why not McDowell or Yount? They're both more
liberal than Jensen.'
'Maybe they both just got killed on the same
night by chance,'
Darby suggested, without believing it.
'No, I don't think so,' said Callahan. 'These
are the first Supreme Court judges ever to
be murdered - and then two in one night? There
must be some connection between the murders.
But you know the worst thing? That fool President
will be able to fill their places. That means
that eight out of the nine will be Republicans.
We won't be able to recognize the Constitution
in ten years. This is awful.'
'Perhaps that's why they were killed, Thomas.
Someone or some group wants a different Supreme
Court, filled with Republicans.'
'But why Jensen? He was appointed by a Republican.'
'I don't know, but there must be some connection.
Maybe there's a clue in the cases the Supreme
Court was due to hear this year. The library
will have that information. I think I'll spend
some time on this today.'
CHAPTER THREE
No Clues
Denton Voyles put Eric East in charge of the
case. On Thursday, East reported back to Voyles
with a list of their top suspects. There were
a number of political groups - especially
the Underground Army, the Ku-Klux-Klan and
the White Defenders - but also some individuals
who were rich enough to afford the kind of
professional killer who had obviously done
this job. There was Nelson Muncie, who had
lost his daughter in a sex killing in Florida;
the police had caught the man, who was black,
but thanks to Rosenberg the man had walked
free. There was Clinton Lane, whose son was
a homosexual who had died of Aids. The problem
with all these suspects, however, was that
the killings were so professional and clean
that there were no clues except for the gun
and the rope. There were not even any clues
about how the killer had entered Rosenberg's
house. Still, Voyles and he agreed to have
between five and twenty men investigate each
suspect or group of suspects.
In the law library and on the computers of
Tulane University, Darby Shaw was gathering
pages and pages of information.
What was the connection between Rosenberg
and Jensen? She could see reasons for killing
one or the other, but not both together. But
there had to be a single reason.
***
Thomas Callahan slept late and alone. Darby
had been too busy to see him since Wednesday.
Now it was Friday morning. He made some coffee
and, as he drank it, watched the busy French
Quarter through his window.
What was it he had to do? Oh, yes, phone Gavin.
On Monday he was going to Washington for a
conference about constitutional law. He and
his old friend Gavin Verheek were going to
meet and get drunk together on Monday evening.
Gavin had been a friend ever since law school.
He and Callahan were the only two in their
year who refused to go into private practice
and get rich. While Callahan had become a
teacher, Verheek had joined the FBI as a legal
adviser.
When Verheek came on the phone, he said, 'Thomas,
how are you?'
'It's ten-thirty. I'm not dressed. I'm sitting
here in the French Quarter drinking coffee
and watching the world outside. What are you
doing?'
'Well, here it's eleven-thirty, and I haven't
left the office since they found the bodies
on Wednesday morning.'
'It makes me sick, Gavin. The President will
get two Nazis on to the Supreme Court. I suppose
you've already seen the list. I bet your office
is already checking that they've lived good,
clean lives. Go on, Gavin, tell me who's on
the list. I won't tell anyone else.'
'No chance. I'll only tell you this: your
name's not on the list'
'I'm so disappointed.'
'How's the girl?'
'Which one?'
'Come on, Thomas. The girl?'
'She's beautiful and brilliant and gentle.
Oh, and rich. She has red hair and the longest
legs you've ever seen.'
'Wow! What's her name?'
'Darby Shaw. But I haven't seen her for a
couple of days. She's trying to solve the
murders all by herself. Why don't you tell
me who did it, and then I can tell her and
she'll come back to me?'
'Don't you read the papers? We have no suspects.
Not one.'
'At least I tried. Are we going to meet on
Monday?'
'I hope so. Voyles wants us to work day and
night until the computers tell us who did
it.'
'I'll expect a full report on Monday, Gavin
- not just the gossip.'
'Why don't you bring Darby? How old is she?
Nineteen?'
'Twenty-four, and she's not invited. I'll
see you on Monday at seven p.m., in the usual
restaurant. OK?'
'OK. See you.'
***
Darby's enquiries had brought her to the court
in Lafayette. Of all the Supreme Court cases
due to be heard in the next few months, there
was one that could explain the killings. She
needed to see the court's files on the case.
When the clerk brought them to her table,
however, her heart sank. There were lots of
files, each inches thick. The case was seven
years old. Only one person was involved, but
he had hidden behind thirty-eight different
businesses, which had used no fewer than fifteen
law firms over the last seven years.
She pulled her chair in to the table and began
to work.
CHAPTER FOUR
Ideas and Information
The meeting East and Voyles had with Coal
and the President did not go well. Not only
could they not report any progress, but they
had to admit that investigations like this
could take many months. Then Coal handed Voyles
a list of eight possible members of the Supreme
Court, two of whom would fill the places left
empty by Rosenberg and Jensen. 'We want a
report on these people in ten days, Voyles,'
he said, 'and make sure the press doesn't
get to hear about them.'
'You know we can't promise that,' Voyles said.
'We can't guarantee no leaks. As soon as we
start to dig around these people, someone
will realize what's going on.'
'The FBI can't guarantee secrecy?' Coal said.
'You'd better keep this out of the papers,
Voyles.'
Voyles jumped out of his chair. 'Listen, Coal,'
he shouted. 'Why don't you investigate these
people yourself? Don't start telling me what
to do.'
The President tried to make peace. 'All we're
saying is do your best, Voyles,' he said.
'These people are young and they're good Republicans.
They'll be giving the Constitution shape long
after I'm dead. So it's important to me that
the two who become members of the Supreme
Court are clean, so that they can stay there
for ever. So no drugs, no unusual sexual habits
- nothing like that. OK?'
'Yes, Mr President. But we cannot guarantee
total secrecy.'
'I understand. Just try your best.'
'Yes, sir.'
***
Callahan went round to Darby's apartment with
a pizza and a bottle of wine. He hadn't seen
her for four days. He rang on her doorbell.
'Who is it?' she called through the door.
'Thomas Callahan,' he said. 'Do you remember
me?'
The door opened and Callahan stepped in. 'Are
we still friends?' he asked, and gave her
a kiss.
'Of course. I've just been busy.'
'So what did the great detective find?'
She was opening the bottle of wine and didn't
answer straight away. She poured wine into
two glasses and they went and sat together
on the sofa. She put her legs up on to him,
and he stroked them. He repeated the question.
'Nothing, really. I was following a path,
and it took me somewhere. I even typed it
up as a brief, but I don't think it's worth
anything.'
'What? You've been running around playing
detective for four days, and refusing to see
me, and now you're just going to throw it
away?'
'It's over there on the table, if you want
to see it,' she said.
'I don't want to see it now,' he said. 'We
have more important things to do. I'm going
to be away in Washington for a few days, remember?
I'll read your brief and then we'll talk about
it. But not till we've been to bed, OK?'
She pulled him towards her and they kissed
long and hard.
***
There was a cleaner in the White House whom
everyone called Sarge. He was old, very black,
and had white hair. He wore dark glasses all
the time, and everyone thought that he was
half blind.
In fact, Sarge could see very well. He could
see round corners. He had been working in
the White House for thirty years now, cleaning
and listening, cleaning and seeing. He knew
which doors stayed open and which walls were
thin. No one ever noticed him.
His son Cleve was a policeman. This is how
it worked: Cleve would contact Gray Grantham
of the Washington Post and arrange a meeting.
Sarge and Grantham would meet. No one knew
how Grantham got his political information,
but it was always good and always correct.
Sarge never talked to anyone except Grantham,
and he didn't tell even him everything he
found out.
This time they met at Glenda's, a little cafe
on Fourteenth Street. Sarge was able to tell
Grantham two of the people on the list of
possible Supreme Court judges.
CHAPTER FIVE
An Implausible Theory
Verheek had drunk too much the night before
with Callahan, as he had known he would. What
had he said? Had he given away any secrets?
He remembered explaining that the connection
between Rosenberg and Jensen was not political.
The connection was so obvious that for several
days no one in the FBI had seen it.
They were killed because the killer could
get to them. It was as simple as that. They
weren't guarded as well as the others. Of
course this still didn't answer the question
why someone wanted two Supreme Court judges
dead.
He remembered that they spent most of the
evening talking about their student days together
in Washington, and about women. Callahan had
given him a copy of the brief his girl-friend
- what was her name? Darby - had written about
the death of the two judges. Callahan had
said it was an interesting theory. She didn't
believe it, nor did he, but it was worth reading.
Verheek pulled the brief out of his briefcase
now and started to read it. It was better
written than most briefs, and he enjoyed it.
The theory was implausible, but no one else
had thought of it. It was worth considering.
He would show it to Eric East.
***
The phone went four times, the answering machine
came on, but the caller left no message. The
phone went again, and the same thing happened
again. The third time Grantham climbed out
of bed and answered the phone. It was still
dark. 'Yes?'
'Is that Gray Grantham, of the Washington
Post?'
'It is. Who's calling?'
'I can't give you my name.'
'OK. Why are you calling?'
'I saw your story yesterday about the White
House and the possible next two Supreme Court
judges.'
'Good. But why are you calling me so early
in the morning?'
'I'm sorry. I'm in a pay phone. I'm on my
way to work. I can't call from home or the
office.'
'What kind of office?'
'I'm a lawyer.'
Great. Washington was home to half a million
lawyers. 'Private or government?'
'I'd rather not say.'
'OK. Anyway, why did you call?'
A hesitation. 'I may know something about
Rosenberg and Jensen.'
Grantham sat up straight. 'What, exactly?'
'Are you recording this?'
'No. Should I?'
'I don't know, Mr Grantham. I'd prefer it
if you didn't record this. OK?'
'Whatever you want. I'm listening.'
'Can you trace this call?'
'I could. But you're at a pay phone - what
difference would it make?'
'You're right. I'm just frightened. You see,
I think I know who killed them.'
Now Grantham was standing. 'That's valuable
information.'
'It could get me killed. Do you think they're
following me?'
'Who? Don't worry. Tell me your name.'
'You can call me Garcia.'
'That's not your real name, is it?
'Of course not, but it's the best I can do.'
'OK, Garcia, talk to me.'
'I'm not certain, you understand. But I think
I accidentally saw something at the office
that I was not supposed to see.'
'Do you have a copy of it?'
'Maybe.'
'Do you want to talk or not?'
'I don't know. What will you do if I tell
you something?'
'First try to find out whether it's true.
We won't print the names of the killers of
two Supreme Court judges in a hurry, believe
me.' There was a very long silence. 'Garcia,
are you still there?'
'Yes. I need to think about this. I might
call you later.'
'OK, if that's what you want.'
'Sorry I woke you up.'
The phone went dead. Grantham pushed seven
numbers on his phone, waited, and then pushed
six more. Another wait, and then four more.
The small screen on his phone showed him a
row of numbers. He wrote them down on a piece
of paper. The pay phone was on Fifteenth Street.
***
East and K. O. Lewis, Voyles's second-in-command,
met with Coal alone, because the President
was out of Washington. They had two bits of
information for him. First, they told him
that cameras at the airport in Paris had recorded
the arrival from Dulles of the killer Khamel.
Coal thought about this for a minute. 'What
if Khamel was involved in the killings? What
does it mean?'
'It means we'll never find him,' Lewis replied.
'Nine countries around the world have failed
to find him for the last twenty years. It
means that he was paid a lot of money by someone
or some people here to do the killings.'
'So we know or we think that Khamel did the
killings, but it doesn't really help us, does
it?'
No, you're right.'
'OK. What else have you got for me?'
Lewis looked at East. 'There's no real progress
to report, except.
'Except what?'
'Well, there's this theory which has appeared
in the last twenty- four hours. A law student
in New Orleans wrote it up as a brief. We
call it the Pelican Brief. Here's a copy of
it. Voyles liked it, but he was afraid it
could hurt the President.'
'How?'
'Read it. You'll see.'
***
This time Garcia called Grantham during office
hours. He didn't tell him anything new. He
was still frightened and uncertain.
They agreed that he would call again at lunch-time
the next day. The call came from a pay phone
on Pennsylvania Avenue.
***
Later, when the President returned, Coal told
him about the brief. 'The theory is implausible,'
he said. 'But Voyles likes it. He probably
doesn't believe the theory any more than anyone
else, but we've made him look bad over these
killings so far and he wants revenge. He's
going to investigate this new suspect. If
the press get to hear about the investigation,
that could be bad for you. We'd better do
something about it.'
'Is the suspect someone we know?'
'Yes.' Coal explained what was in the brief.
'Did we get a lot of money from him?'
'Millions, one way or another,' said Coal.
But the President preferred not to know the
various ways in which money came in, especially
when they weren't always perfectly legal.
CHAPTER SIX
Hunted!
Thomas was drinking too much over dinner.
She didn't like it, and she told him so. He
wanted to prove that she was wrong, so he
drank even more. They had an argument.
After dinner, outside the restaurant, he pulled
the keys to his Porsche out of his pocket.
'Thomas, no! You're too drunk to drive. Give
me the keys.'
He held on to the keys and set off in the
direction of the car park. He couldn't walk
straight and his foot kept slipping off the
pavement into the road. She followed him,
but stayed some way behind; she was too angry,
and just wanted to get back to her apartment
alone. He shouted something over his shoulder
about how he could drive better when he was
drunk.
She stood with her arms crossed on the other
side of the car park and watched him put the
key into the lock. It took him three or four
attempts. Then he was inside and she lost
sight of him between two other cars. She heard
him start the engine, though.
The explosion knocked her to the ground. She
lay there for a moment, and then jumped to
her feet. The Porsche was a ball of fire.
Darby ran towards it, screaming his name.
Bits of the car were still falling all around
her, and the heat stopped her thirty feet
away. She screamed with her hands over her
mouth.
A second explosion tore through the car and
pushed her back. She fell and her head hit
the side of a parked car hard. Everything
went blank for a minute.
Then there were people everywhere, and voices
shouting:
'Whose car is it? Call 911! Was there anyone
in it?'
She was repeating the name Thomas. Someone
put a cold cloth on her head. She heard the
sound of the police and firemen coming, and
then there were red and blue lights everywhere.
A black man was bending over her. 'Are you
all right, miss?' he asked.
'Thomas,' she said. 'Where's Thomas?'
'Miss, who's Thomas?' asked the man. 'Was
he in that car?'
She nodded and then closed her eyes. She could
hear men shouting in the distance. They were
all over by the burning car. She sat up and
was sick between her legs. Then she felt better.
She got up and walked away. She knew who the
bomb had been for: her. And she knew why.
She had to hide; they were hunting her. Were
they behind her even now? She wandered deep
into the French Quarter, found a cheap hotel
and paid for a room with her card. As soon
as she was in the room, she locked the door
and curled up on the bed with all the lights
on.
***
Mrs Verheek answered the bedside phone. 'It's
for you, Gavin,' she called into the bathroom,
where he was shaving.
He came and took the phone from her. 'Hello,'
he said angrily. Who could be calling this
early in the morning?
'This is Darby Shaw. Do you know the name?'
'Yes. We share a friend.'
'Did you read the little theory I wrote?'
'Yes, the Pelican Brief, as we call it.'
'And who is "we"?'
Verheek sat up straight. She was not calling
for a friendly chat. 'Why are you calling,
Darby?'
'I need some answers, Mr Verheek. I'm frightened
to death.'
'It's Gavin, OK?'
'OK, Gavin. Where's the brief?'
'Why? What's wrong?'
'I'll tell you in a minute. Just tell me what
you did with the brief.'
'Well, I read it, and then I passed it on
to someone else, who passed it on to Denton
Voyles, who liked it.'
'Has anyone outside the FBI seen it?'
'I can't answer that.'
'Then I won't tell you what's happened to
Thomas.'
'All right. Yes, it's been outside the FBI,
but I don't know exactly where and I don't
know how many people have read it.'
'He's dead, Gavin. He was murdered last night.
Someone put a bomb in the car. I was lucky.'
Gavin was shocked. 'Where are you? Are you
safe?'
'New Orleans. Who knows if I'm safe? They
must be after me too. It was me they really
wanted.'
'I'll have some men come and get you, Darby.
You can't stay on the streets. Then I'll catch
a plane and I'll be there by midday.'
'I don't think so. Thomas is dead because
he talked to you. Why should I want to talk
to you? Give me your number at work. I may
call you later.'
'OK. But Darby, just tell me: did he feel
any pain?'
There were tears in her voice. 'No, it was
very quick.' Then she put the phone down.
She could let herself cry now, because there
wouldn't be time later. Crying could get her
killed.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Keep Moving
It was nearly time for the President's daily
meeting with Voyles. By now he was tired of
the whole business; he just wanted to get
his men into the Supreme Court. Coal was telling
him something, but he wasn't really listening.
Voyles and Coal hated each other so much now
that Coal had to leave the office whenever
Voyles came. They had nearly fought last time.
It didn't matter to Coal whether he was in
or out of the office; there were enough hidden
microphones and cameras for him to listen
and watch any conversation there.
The President felt better knowing that Coal
was at least watching. He greeted Voyles warmly
at the door and led him over to the sofa for
a friendly chat. Voyles was not impressed.
'Denton,' the President said, 'I want to apologize
for Coal's be-haviour last time.'
'He can be stupid, can't he?' Voyles said,
knowing that Coal was listening.
'Yes. He's very clever, and works amazingly
hard, but he goes too far sometimes. Anyway,
that's all behind us now. I want you to tell
me all about this Pelican Brief. How seriously
are you taking it?'
Voyles tried not to smile. This was great
- he had managed to get Coal and the President
worried. 'We are investigating all suspects,
Mr President,' he replied. 'We have fourteen
men on this one.'
'I don't have to tell you, Denton,' the President
continued, 'how much damage this theory could
do if the press heard about it.'
'We won't tell the press, Mr President.'
'I know. All I'm saying is that I want you
to pull back from this one. The theory is
crazy anyway, and I could really get hurt.
Do you understand what I'm saying?'
'Are you asking me not to investigate a suspect,
Mr President?'
'I'm just saying that you must have better
things to do with your men. The press is watching
this investigation closely. You know how they
are - they don't like me at all. So why don't
you leave this one alone and chase the real
suspects?'
'Is that what you're asking me to do?'
'I'm not asking you, Denton; I'm telling you
to leave it alone for a couple of weeks. If
you need to go back to it later, of course
you must. But I'm still the boss around here,
remember?' ***
Gavin stayed near Voyles's office until the
secretary let him in. He couldn't believe
it when Voyles and Lewis told him that they
were no longer investigating the Pelican theory.
'My best friend is dead because of that brief,'
he said. 'He was killed by a car bomb. Someone
is worried about the brief, don't you think?'
'The brief has already been very valuable
to us, Gavin,' Lewis said.
'Yeah, it let you play some games with the
White House,' Gavin said bitterly. 'But there's
a girl out there running for her life. What
am I going to tell her?' ***
Darby made sure she could not be followed
in the crowds in the shopping district. She
bought some new clothes and hid her hair under
a hat. She went into the Sheraton Hotel and
found a row of pay phones. First she called
Mrs Chen, who lived in the apartment next
to hers: no, she had not seen anything; yes,
there had been a knock at her door early this
morning. Then she called Gavin.
'Where are you?' he asked.
'Let me explain something. For now, I'm not
going to tell you or anyone else where I am.
Clear?'
'Yes, but don't go home.'
'I'm not a fool. They've already been there.
What did Mr Voyles say?'
'I haven't been able to see him.'
'You've been at the office for four hours,
Gavin. I expected you to do better.'
'Be patient, Darby.'
'Patience will get me killed. I've got to
keep moving.'
She saw a face. He walked among the tourists
at the hotel's front desk. He was trying to
look as though he belonged here, but his eyes
were searching. The face was long and thin,
and he wore round glasses. He was a little
over six feet tall.
'Gavin, listen to me,' she said. 'I have to
go. I can see a man I've seen before, about
an hour ago.'
'OK. Take care, Darby, and call me again soon.'
'I'll try.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
Photos and Phone Calls
The photographer's name was Croft. He was
parked on Pennsylvania Avenue in Grantham's
Volvo, because it had a phone. The pay phone
was easy to see, about fifty yards in front
of the car. With his powerful camera he could
almost read the names in the phone book. A
large woman was using the phone at the moment.
At 12:20 the woman put the phone down and
walked away. From nowhere a young man in a
suit appeared and walked over to the phone.
Croft felt sure that this was the man. He
picked up his camera and looked through it.
The man was pushing numbers on the phone and
looked nervous. He kept looking this way and
that. Croft took a couple of pictures.
The phone in the car went three times. Croft
didn't pick it up. It was Grantham at the
office, signalling that this was their man.
Croft used a whole film on the first camera.
When the man had finished talking on the phone,
he walked straight towards the Volvo along
the pavement. Beautiful. Croft took several
more pictures with a second camera and stopped
well before the man could possibly see inside
the car. An easy job.
***
Grantham got plenty of excellent pictures
from Croft. Garcia didn't look Spanish, despite
the name he had chosen. He looked like thousands
of other young lawyers up and down the country.
From Garcia he got nothing. It didn't matter.
He let him talk about his wife and child,
and how frightened he was. One day, and one
day soon, Garcia would give him the information,
whatever it was.
From Sarge he got a copy of a White House
document naming Khamel as the probable killer
of Rosenberg and Jensen. This was good. There
was little in the office files about Khamel,
and only two pictures, which looked like two
different people, but he wrote it up into
a story and they decided to use both pictures
and the story on the front page the next day.
***
The phone was going. After twenty-four hours
on the run, she had drunk a bottle of wine
the night before and fallen asleep on her
bed in the Marriott Hotel. But first she had
cut off her long red hair and coloured it
black; they would be expecting blonde. They
would also be expecting her to run away, so
despite her fears she stayed in New Orleans.
They would be watching all the police stations,
so she had stayed away from them.
The phone was still going. She picked it up
and heard 'Darby? This is Gavin.'
Now she was awake. 'How did you find me?'
'We are the FBI. We have our ways.'
'Wait. Let me think. Of course, you can trace
me when I use my cards to pay for things.
How stupid of me! But if you can find me,
they can find me too. They could be outside
the door now.'
'Stay in small hotels, then, and pay with
cash. Now, listen. I'm coming to New Orleans;
it's Thomas's funeral tomorrow.
'I think we should meet tonight. You have
to trust me, Darby.'
'What did Voyles say?'
Gavin hesitated. 'We're taking no action at
this time.'
'That's lawyer talk, Gavin. What does it mean?'
'I don't want to talk on the phone. That's
why we have to meet.'
'No. Tell me why Voyles is doing nothing about
this.'
'I'm not sure why. Honestly.'
'What do you think, Gavin? Do you think Thomas
was killed because of the brief?
'Yes.'
'Thanks. If Thomas was murdered because of
the brief, then we know who killed him. And
if we know who killed Thomas, then we know
who killed Rosenberg and Jensen. Am I right?'
'Probably.'
'That's good enough - "probably" means "yes"
when a lawyer says it. But the FBI is still
doing nothing about my suspect.'
'Calm down, Darby. Let's meet tonight and
talk about this. I could save your life.'
She carefully put the receiver of the phone
under the pillow. She threw her things into
a bag and left the room. She walked up two
floors to the seventeenth, then took the lift
down to the tenth. Then she walked down the
stairs to the ground floor. She hid in the
women's room for half an hour, and then left
the hotel.
On Dumaine Street, in the French Quarter,
she found an empty cafe with a phone at the
back. She called Verheek.
'Where will you stay tonight?' she asked him.
'At the Hilton.'
'I'll call late tonight or early in the morning.'
'Can you get the Washington Post down there?
You should read it today.'
'I can't wait. I'll speak to you later.'
She bought a Post and read it at another cafe.
If the report was right, it fitted in with
her theory. The local paper had a picture
of Thomas on the second page, with a long
story about the explosion. The police were
looking for a white female whom several witnesses
had seen there at the time. She looked slowly
at the photo of Thomas. He was so handsome.
Tears filled her eyes.
***
Alice Stark, Darby's best friend, got the
key to the apartment from Mrs Chen and let
herself in. She had been there plenty of times
before, and everything looked all right. Nothing
was out of place; the whole apartment was
tidy. The kitchen smelled of stale food.
It was dark when she got there, but Darby
had told her not to switch on the lights,
and certainly not to open the curtains. She
used a torch to see her way around.
She sat down at the computer and turned it
on. She looked for the files Darby had mentioned,
but they weren't there. By the light of the
torch she looked in the boxes of diskettes;
they were empty.
Alice returned the key to Mrs Chen and walked
half a mile to where she had left her car.
She met Darby as arranged in the restaurant,
and she told her what she had discovered.
Darby did not seem surprised, and refused
to answer Alice's questions.
***
Verheek was angry. She had said she would
call him. Now it was midnight and she still
hadn't called. He could save her life if she
called. He had to do something. He decided
to visit a few student bars to find out if
anyone knew her and had seen her recently.
He got back to his room at three in the morning.
There were no messages. She hadn't called.
Was she still alive?
CHAPTER NINE
Searching for Darby
Another phone call from Garcia. The man still
wouldn't talk. Why was he calling him before
dawn on a Saturday? They'd had the same conversation
every time - that he had to think about the
safety of his wife and child, that he had
seen something in his office - but there was
never anything new.
Grantham had just gone back to sleep when
the phone went again.
'Hello?' It was not Garcia this time; it was
a female voice. 'Is this Gray Grantham of
the Washington Post? He must get an unlisted
telephone number.
'It is. And who are you?'
'Are you still on the story about Rosenberg
and Jensen?'
'Yes.'
'Have you heard of the Pelican Brief?'
'The Pelican Brief. No. What is it?'
'It contains a theory about who killed the
judges. It was given to the FBI last Monday
by a man called Thomas Callahan. Suddenly,
on Wednesday, Callahan is killed by a car
bomb.'
'How do you know all this?'
'I wrote the brief.'
He was wide awake now, listening hard. 'Where
are you?'
'New Orleans.'
'Are you in danger?'
'I think so. But I'm OK for now. I'll call
you again soon. See if you can find out anything
about the brief.'
***
She came early to Thomas's funeral, and she
would stay late. She found an empty room on
the third floor of a student building that
looked out over the university church. She
sat with her face to the window and saw his
parents and brother arrive. Students and staff
came in twos and threes. She pressed a handkerchief
to her eyes.
Then she saw him: it was the thin-faced man
with glasses! He was wearing a coat and tie.
He walked towards the church, looking carefully
in every direction. First they kill him, then
they come to his funeral.
Ten minutes later he came back out of the
church. He looked sad, as if Thomas had been
a friend. He put a cigarette in his mouth
and walked past some parked cars and behind
the church. Two minutes later, another man
got out of one of the cars and followed him.
The two of them reappeared after a minute,
walking together now. Then Thin-face disappeared
down the street while the other man, who was
short, returned to his car and waited for
the funeral service to finish.
***
The Cubans lowered the small rubber boat into
the water from their ship. They heard the
sound of the little engine as the man went
west through the darkness towards the coast.
He would never use a commercial airline again;
the photographs in Paris were embarrassing
for a professional like himself, and his client
was not pleased. Now he was going to have
to do two jobs in a single month, which he
had never done before. But this one would
be easy - just a young woman.
In the hotel room in New Orleans, he spoke
on the phone to a man calling himself Mr Snellen
'Tell me about her,' he said.
'There are two photos in the briefcase.'
Khamel opened the case and took out the photos.
'I've got them. She's beautiful. It will almost
be a pity to kill her.'
'Yes. But all that red hair has gone. We found
some hair on the floor of a hotel room. She
has coloured it black.'
'Where is she now?'
'We don't know. She has stopped using her
cards to pay for things. She took out a lot
of money from her bank, and since then she
has disappeared. We think she's still in New
Orleans, though. Someone was in her apartment
last night. We just missed them.
'The bomb failed. We don't expect you to fail.'
***
Gavin was tired. He had spent two nights searching
the bars, and he was too old for these late
nights. When the phone went, he was still
asleep.
'Gavin?'
'Darby, is that you?'
'Yes.'
'Why haven't you called before?'
'That doesn't matter now. You should know
that they're here, in New Orleans. I've seen
two of them - a thin-faced man and a short
man. They were at the funeral service yesterday.'
'Where were you?'
'Watching. How long will you be in town?'
'Until we meet. When will that be?'
'I don't know yet. I'll call again soon.'
The phone went dead. Gavin picked it up and
threw it across his hotel room.
CHAPTER TEN
Another Body
The first thing she did when she woke up on
Sunday morning was listen. Was the door opening?
Was the floor outside making a noise? When
she was sure she was safe, she thought about
Thomas. She remembered their times together;
she remembered how he loved her. It was a
surprise for him, the first time he had really
been in love. And she loved him too.
After a few minutes of thinking about Thomas,
she thought about them. She had to think like
them too, to stay alive. Where would they
be today? Where could she go? Was it time
to move hotels again? Yes. Did they know that
she was now a blonde?
She felt hungry. She had hardly eaten for
days. This hotel didn't do breakfast on Sundays,
so she had to go out. She left by the back
door, through the kitchen.
He saw her when she reached Burgundy Street.
The hair was different, but she couldn't change
her long legs. He started to follow her.
***
Khamel was practising his English when the
phone went. It was Sneller. 'She's here,'
he said. 'One of our men saw her this morning.
He chased her, but she noticed him and lost
him in the football crowds.'
Khamel said, 'So how am I supposed to find
her, if your men can't tell me where she's
staying?'
'It might not matter,' Sneller said. 'There's
an FBI lawyer in town. The fool has been visiting
bars and asking questions about her, spreading
his name around. He's asked anyone who knows
her to contact him at his hotel, the Hilton.
My men will continue trying to find the girl,
and you can stay close to him. He's in
'Room 1909. He was Callahan's best friend.
She might call him.'
***
Gavin was lying on his bed, watching TV. It
was eleven at night. He would wait until twelve
and then try to sleep. He had decided to go
home tomorrow if she didn't call. He couldn't
find her. It wasn't his fault: even taxi-drivers
got lost in this city.
When the phone went, he switched the TV off
and picked it up.
'It's me, Gavin,' she said.
'You're alive,' he said.
'Yes, but I was followed today. It was the
short man.'
'Did he follow you from somewhere?'
No, he just happened to see me in the streets.'
'Listen, Darby, I can't wait here any more.
I've got a job to go back to. I want to leave
New Orleans tomorrow, and I want you to come
with me. I'll have three men guarding you,
and you'll be safe. You can tell us all you
know, and then the FBI will finish the job.'
Darby thought for a minute. 'All right. Behind
your hotel there's a shopping area called
Riverwalk.'
'I know it.'
'Good. Find a shop called Frenchmen's Bend
and be there, at the back of the shop, at
midday tomorrow. I don't know what you look
like, so wear a black shirt and carry a newspaper.'
'This is silly.'
'No, it's not. I've had to learn fast how
to stay alive. Believe me, this is the way
to do it.'
'OK, you're the boss.'
'That's right. Only you and I will leave the
city. I don't want anyone else knowing about
this. Do you understand?'
'All right.'
'How tall are you?'
'About five feet, ten inches.'
'And how much to you weigh?'
'About a hundred kilos. I usually lie about
it. I'm going to start doing some exercise.'
'I'll see you tomorrow, Gavin.'
'I hope so.'
He put the phone down and smiled. 'Great!
At last!' he said out loud. He went into the
bathroom for a shower.
When he came out, the room was dark. Dark?
But he had left the light on, hadn't he? He
started to walk over to the light switch.
The first blow caught him in the throat. He
fell to his knees, which made the second blow
easy. It landed like a rock on the back of
his neck, and Gavin was dead.
Khamel switched on a light. He lifted up the
body and put it on the bed. He turned the
sound on the television up loud, opened his
bag and took out a cheap gun. He held it to
the right side of Gavin's head and fired.
Then he carefully put the gun in Gavin's right
hand and curled the fingers around it. It
wouldn't take a doctor very long to find out
how Gavin had really died, but Khamel didn't
need very long -by the evening of the next
day he would be out of the country.
He opened up the receiver of the telephone
and took out the little microphone. He pulled
the recorder out from under the bed. Finally,
he checked that the cupboard where he had
waited was clean. Then he left the room. No
one had seen him enter, and no one saw him
leave.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Riverwalk
Grantham couldn't find out anything about
the brief. Even Sarge hadn't heard of it.
When Darby's call came through to his office
on Monday morning he had nothing to tell her.
'It doesn't matter. I'll tell you everything
soon, I think. I don't want to die without
telling the world what I know. They're following
me here in New Orleans.'
'Who?'
'The same people who killed Rosenberg and
Jensen. If you've read the report about Callahan's
death, you know about the white female the
police want to talk to. That's me. My name
is Darby Shaw. Thomas Callahan was my teacher
and my lover. I wrote the brief, gave it to
him, he passed it on to the FBI, who took
it to the White House, and you know what happened
next. Are you recording this?'
'I'm writing it down,' Grantham said.
'I'm going to leave New Orleans. I'll call
you from somewhere else tomorrow. Can you
get a copy of the list of people who gave
large amounts of money to help the President
get elected?'
'Easy; it's public information. I'll have
it by the time you call.
'Do you have a copy of the brief?'
'No, but I remember it all.'
'And you know who's doing the killing?'
'Yes, and as soon as I tell you, your life
will be in danger too.'
'Tell me now.'
'Not so fast. I'll call you tomorrow.'
After the phone conversation Grantham went
in to see his boss, Smith Keen. He explained
the situation to him. Keen was excited, but
said, 'Even if she tells us what's in the
brief, we can't print the story; we'll need
an independent witness.'
'I'm working on it,' Grantham said, and told
him about Garcia.
'This is going to be big,' Keen said. 'This
is going to put the
'Post right back up at the top.'
***
She arrived on Riverwalk at eleven. She sat
in a restaurant and nervously drank a coffee
while watching the people pass. She didn't
see Thin-face or Shorty or anyone else she
recognized. At 11:45 she got up and walked
towards Frenchmen's Bend. If he wasn't there
by 12:15 she would leave. But he was there,
wearing the black shirt and carrying a newspaper.
He looked nervous too. She liked that. At
exactly twelve o'clock he walked into the
shop and went to the back.
She came up behind him and said, 'Gavin.'
He had practised Gavin's voice for hours,
but wasn't sure he had it exactly right. He
turned around quickly and said, 'Darby.' Then
he pretended to cough. She wouldn't expect
the same voice from someone with a cold. 'Let's
get out of here,' he said.
'Follow me,' she said. Darby took his hand
and led him out of the shop and towards the
river.
'Have you seen them?' he asked.
'No, but they're around somewhere.'
'Where are we going?'
'Just come with me.'
'You're walking too fast, Darby. It will look
strange to people. Let me make a phone call.
I can have men here in ten minutes and then
we'll be safe.' He was pleased with himself;
he sounded just right.
'No,' she said, but she slowed down. They
joined the queue for the riverboat Bayou Queen.
'The boat will take us to where I've parked
a car,' she explained. 'Then we get out of
here fast.'
Khamel was uncomfortable; he was wearing a
great many un-derclothes, so that he would
look as fat as Verheek. But he could wait
an hour until they were out of the city. And
then . . .
The man with the gun pushed his way through
the queue. He had killed before, but never
in such a public place. The queue was moving,
but he was getting through it. The man and
the woman were just about to step on to the
boat when he reached them. He pulled the gun
out of his pocket, held it to the man's head
and fired. He disappeared through the crowd.
Gavin was falling to the ground. Darby screamed
and moved back in horror. 'He's got a gun!'
a woman shouted, and pointed at Gavin, who
was on his hands and knees, with a small gun
in his right hand. Blood poured from his nose
and chin, and formed a small pool under his
face. His head was hanging down until it nearly
touched the ground. He was speaking some words
in a language Darby didn't recognize.
'He's Egyptian,' someone in the crowd said.
He fell forward, dropping the gun into the
water, and died in a widening pool of blood.
Darby walked away as the crowd moved forwards
to see the dead man, and two policemen started
to push their way through.
***
She left Riverwalk after dark. She had bought
new clothes and wore a new coat as well. She
waved at a taxi.
'How much to take me to Baton Rouge?' she
asked.
'That's a long way,' the driver said. 'You
should go by bus or train.'
'How much?' she asked again.
'One hundred and fifty dollars,' the man said,
after a moment's thought.
'Here's two hundred,' she said. 'Get me there
fast.' Thomas had talked to her about his
friend Gavin Verheek. She knew he wasn't an
Egyptian.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Darby Explains
Voyles sent East down to New Orleans to learn
the truth about Verheek's death. Lewis brought
the news to his office.
'Denton, when are we going to start taking
this Pelican Brief seriously?' he asked. 'People
keep dying because of it. We'd better investigate
it. It must be Mattiece.'
'I know,' Voyles said. 'We'll send down a
team of men, but I don't want the fool in
the White House or Coal to hear that we're
investigating it - I want to surprise them.
When the President told me to leave the brief
alone, I was carrying a small recorder in
my pocket. I've got every word, loud and clear.
If we find that the brief is accurate, the
press will love us, and we can let them know
that the President told us not to investigate
it.'
'That'll be the end of him and Coal,' Lewis
said happily.
'I know. He'll have no chance in the election
next year. We've got him.'
They smiled at each other. 'But what about
Mattiece?' Lewis said. 'If he hadn't killed
all -those people, we wouldn't have thought
the brief was right. He must be crazy.'
'There are rumours that he is,' Voyles replied.
'I've spoken to the CIA. They had men in New
Orleans. They don't know where Mattiece is.
He's probably not in this country. He owns
houses all over the world. We'll need their
help to get him. They were following the girl
too, but they lost her in Chicago airport.
She could be anywhere by now.'
'She could be dead,' Lewis said. 'Mattiece's
men are following her as well.' ***
Grantham traced two old photographs of her
- one from her high school, one from her first
university. He pinned them up beside his desk.
She was beautiful.
She called him as she had promised. He had
read about the killing of a lawyer in New
Orleans, and she told him the true story.
She also told him about the other killing,
which had not appeared in the newspapers.
Then she said, 'Can you come to New York tomorrow,
Grantham?'
'Of course. It'll only take a few hours. But
please call me Gray.' He looked at the photographs
of her.
'I'll ring tomorrow morning to tell you where
to meet me. And tomorrow I'll tell you who
killed Rosenberg and Jensen.'
'Do you know who did it?'
'I know who paid for the killings. I know
his name. I know his business and his politics.'
'And you'll tell me tomorrow.'
'If I'm still alive.'
A pause. 'Perhaps we should talk immediately,'
he said. ***
They met in her room in the St Moritz Hotel
in New York. They chatted for a while, getting
to know each other. It was the first normal
conversation Darby had had for a week, and
it was a great pleasure. They sent out for
some food, and after they had eaten he switched
on a recorder and she told him a story:
'For centuries, the Mississippi River has
been carrying mud down to the sea. Where the
river meets the sea, marshes have spread out
over an enormous area. These marshes are the
home for a great many rare and unusual animals,
birds, reptiles and fish.'
'Then oil was discovered there in 1930. The
oil companies began to destroy the marshes.
Where the river mud had been creating new
land, now the sea was able to wash the land
away. Since the discovery of oil, tens of
thousands of acres of Louisiana marshland
has gone. Every fourteen minutes, another
acre disappears under water.'
'In 1979 an oil company owned by Victor Mattiece
found a very rich oilfield, worth thousands
of millions of dollars. Mattiece wanted it
all. He knew that others would buy the surrounding
land if they heard there was a major oilfield
there, so he pretended that nothing had happened.
He stopped work there, and waited. Slowly
and patiently, as the years passed, he bought
the surrounding land. He created new companies,
lots of them, so that no one would know that
he was the buyer. At last he was ready to
begin drilling.'
'Then a small environmental group called Green
Rescue made a legal request to the courts
to stop the drilling. The request was un-expected,
because for so long Louisiana had profited
from the oil companies. The court in Lafayette
agreed that all drilling should stop until
the case was settled.'
'Mattiece knew that this could take years.
He was dangerously angry. He spent weeks with
his lawyers, making plans. But every move
they made was disallowed by the courts.'
'People were sympathetic to Green Rescue's
case. A lot of wildlife was at risk. The marshland
where Mattiece wanted to drill was home to
a great many rare and beautiful sea birds,
including brown pelicans. There were very
few of these pelicans left. When people thought
about the case, they thought about the pelicans.'
'At last the case came to trial. Green Rescue
lost, and that was not surprising: Mattiece
had spent millions of dollars and had the
best lawyers in the country. But the judge
still forbade the drilling to start. The pelican
was a protected bird under Louisiana law,
and Green Rescue weren't finished yet: they
would take the case all the way to the Supreme
Court.'
'How long would it take to reach the Supreme
Court?' Gray asked.
'Between three and five years.'
'By then Rosenberg would be dead anyway.'
'Yes, but it might be a Democratic President
who was choosing the judge to take his place;
Mattiece couldn't take that chance. And Jensen
was always soft on environmental cases. Mattiece
needed two Republican judges in there, both
of whom were supporters of big business.'
'Can you prove that all the companies involved
in buying the land in Louisiana are owned
by Mattiece?'
'It's in the brief, and I've written it all
out for you. And then there's the photograph.'
'Tell me.'
'Seven years ago, before the President was
elected, he was in New Orleans getting money
for the Republicans. Although Mattiece stays
out of the public eye, he was there that day,
and some clever photographer got a picture
of him shaking hands with the President. Both
of them are smiling, and they look like old
friends. It's beautiful.'
'I can easily find a copy of that. This whole
thing is beautiful. It's the biggest story
since Watergate - maybe even bigger.' Gray
turned off the recorder and sat back in his
chair. They were silent for a short while.
Then he asked, 'Do you think Mattiece himself
chose Rosenberg and Jensen?'
'No, I'm sure he had advice from a lawyer.
He's got lawyers all over the country.'
Gray sat up again. 'Does he have any in Washington?'
'Yes, there are two firms there who do some
work for him - Brim, Stearns and Kidlow is
one of them; the other is White and Blazevich,
a very old, Republican firm. But why are you
interested?'
Gray quickly told her about Garcia. 'Maybe
he works at one of those two firms,' he said.
'That would make it much easier to find him.'
They were both tired. She asked him to sleep
on the sofa in her room that night, so that
she could get a good night's sleep for the
first time for days. He agreed. She was so
beautiful that he would do anything to be
close her; he would even sleep on a five-foot
sofa.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Washington
Darby worked in the library all morning and
rang Grantham at midday. She had been reading
lists of the members at both the Washington
law firms that worked for Mattiece; there
was no one called Garcia on either list, of
course. There were four Spanish names among
the 190 lawyers who worked for Brim, Stearns
and Kidlow, but none among the 412 who worked
for White and Blazevich.
She rang Gray with this information from a
pay phone in a cafe on Sixth Avenue. As she
turned to leave she saw the short man who
had been looking for her in New Orleans. He
was here, in New York, walking the streets.
He didn't look inside the cafe, however. For
the moment she was safe, but it was time to
leave New York. Two hours later, she was at
Newark airport.
When this was all over - if she was still
alive - where could she go? She thought of
the thousands of islands in the Caribbean;
no one could find her there. She no longer
wanted to practise law. All she wanted to
do was reach her twenty-fifth birthday, and
maybe her thirtieth too.
***
Croft spent a week waiting outside the offices
of Brim, Stearns and Kidlow. There were plenty
of lawyers who looked as young as Garcia,
and they all dressed similarly in dark suits,
but there was no Garcia. He was sure of it.
***
Some of the people employed by the White House
didn't work at the White House; some were
so secret that their offices were elsewhere
and very few people knew of their existence.
Matthew Barr was one of these shadowy people.
He was riding in the back of the car with
Coal. Coal was silent while Barr read the
Pelican Brief. When he had finished, Barr
said, 'I'd love to know how much of this is
true.'
'So would we,' Coal said.
'What did the President say about it?'
'He agreed that the theory was implausible,
so he asked Voyles not to investigate it.'
'Really? And what if it's true?'
'Then the President has got problems. Me too.'
They rode in silence for a while and watched
the traffic. Then Coal said, 'We need to know
if the brief is true.'
'If people are dying, it's true. Why else
did Callahan and Verheek die?'
There was no other reason, and Coal knew it.
'I want you to do something.'
'Find the girl?'
'No, go to Mattiece and talk to him.'
'It won't be easy. He isn't exactly listed
in the phone book.'
'You can do it. You've done more difficult
things for us in the past. You've done worse
for us too.'
'And you think Victor will trust me and tell
me his secrets?'
'Why not? You're not a policeman. You can
help him; you can tell him that the press
will have the story soon and so it would be
a good idea for him to disappear. Then he'll
trust you.'
'What if it's true? What will you do next?'
'The first thing will be for the President
to appoint two nature-lovers to the Supreme
Court; that will show people that we really
care for the environment. Then, at the same
time, he will get the FBI to start an official
investigation into Victor Mattiece.'
Barr was smiling with admiration. 'What about
the photograph?' he asked.
'Easy. It's seven years old. We say that in
those days Mattiece was a good citizen, not
a madman as he is now. Anyway, by Sunday I'll
tell you where he is. I've got a man working
on it. Be ready to leave.'
***
Darby called Gray at 9:30 the next morning
at his office. 'I'm here,' she said.
'Where are you calling from?' Gray asked.
'I'm staying at the Tabard Inn. I saw an old
friend in New York and decided it was time
to leave. I hope I didn't bring any of them
with me. I bought two plane tickets with my
card, for them to follow, but I paid cash
for the one I really used. Even then I changed
planes four times. If they follow me here,
they must be magicians. If I see any of them
here, I think I'll just surrender.'
'When do we meet?'
'Meet me in the restaurant here at nine tonight.
But, Gray, don't use your own car; hire another
one. And be ready to stay away from your home
and office for a few days. I've booked you
a room at the Marbury Hotel.'
'Surely the office is safe, Darby.'
'I'm not in the mood to argue. If you're going
to be difficult, Gray, I'll simply disappear.
I'm sure I'll live longer out of the country,
anyway. I've got to go now. You be careful.'
***
The Marbury was close to where his boss, Smith
Keen, lived, and there were some things they
had to talk about. The next morning he rang
Keen from his room and they arranged to meet
outside the front of the hotel in fifteen
minutes. While they drove around in Keen's
car they discussed various ways in which they
could use the information they had. They agreed
that finding Garcia was the key to the whole
story; without Garcia they had little more
than rumour and an unlikely theory. They hoped
that Garcia's information really was as important
as they were guessing it was.
She had told him to stay off the streets and
to eat in his room. After Keen had left him
near his hotel, he bought a sandwich and a
cup of coffee, and returned to his room. An
Asian cleaning woman was working outside his
room. 'Did you forget something, sir?' she
asked. Gray looked at her. 'What do you mean?'
'You just left your room, sir, and now you're
back.'
'I left two hours ago.'
'No, sir. A man left your room ten minutes
ago.' She hesitated and looked at his face
closely. 'But now I see that it was another
man, sir.'
He walked quickly to the stairs and ran all
the way down to the ground floor. What was
in his room? Nothing important - just some
clothes. Nothing about Darby. Her phone number
at the Tabard Inn was in his pocket.
He had to find her, and quick.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Curtis D. Morgan
Darby spent the day in the Georgetown law
library, reading and taking notes about the
members of the Washington law firms that Mattiece
used. It was boring work, and her mind often
wandered.
She thought a lot about Thomas.
***
Matthew Barr went to New Orleans, where he
met a lawyer who told him to fly to a certain
hotel in Fort Lauderdale, Florida.
He wouldn't tell Barr what was going to happen
there, but when Barr arrived he found a room
waiting for him. A note at the front desk
of the hotel said he would receive a phone
call in the early morning.
He called Fletcher Coal at home at ten and
told him the news.
***
She stepped on the note when she opened her
door. It said: Darby, I'm in the garden. It's
urgent. Gray. She locked the door, went downstairs,
through the restaurant and out into the garden.
She found him sitting at a small table, half
hidden behind a wall.
'Why are you here?' she demanded in a whisper.
He told her what had happened, and what he'd
done for the rest of the day. He had spent
it riding round the city in a dozen different
taxis, waiting for dark. Then he came to the
Tabard. He was certain that no one had followed
him.
She listened. She watched the restaurant and
the entrance to the garden, and heard every
word.
'I have no idea how anyone could find my room,'
he said.
'Did you tell anyone your room number?' He
thought for a second. 'Only Smith Keen, but
he didn't have time to tell anyone else.'
'Where were you when you told him?'
'In his car.'
She shook her head slowly. 'I told you not
to tell anyone, didn't I? You think this is
all a game. It's not, Gray, it's real. This
isn't just a great newspaper story, which
is going to make Gray Grantham famous and
win him prizes. I've seen people die. God
knows how many times I've been close to death
myself. These people are dangerous, and they're
professionals. They know about you and the
Washington Post. They've probably been listening
to you since you wrote the first story about
this matter. They'll have microphones hidden
in your apartment, your car and your office.
It looks as though they've got microphones
in Keen's car as well. Do you understand what
I'm saying? Last night at dinner we tried
to pretend we were two normal people getting
to know each other. But that wasn't real:
this is real.'
She was right, of course. He felt like a schoolchild
in front of an angry teacher.
'You can stay here tonight,' she said, 'and
tomorrow I'll find you another small hotel.'
***
After breakfast the next morning she got on
the phone. She rang the Georgetown law school
and pretended to be from White and Blazevich.
She said that their computers were not working,
and that for the sake of her records she needed
to know which students had worked for White
and Blazevich last summer. She waited, with
her hand over the mouthpiece of the phone,
and looked at Gray. The secretary from the
law school came back on the phone. 'Seven
of them,' Darby said. 'Thank you.' She wrote
down their names. 'And do you have their addresses,
please? We need them for our records.' She
wrote down this information too.
'That was brilliant,' Gray said when she had
finished. 'Now all we need to do is find as
many of these students as we can, show them
your photograph of Garcia, and hope that one
of them recognizes him and can tell us his
real name.'
'Why couldn't we just wait outside the firm's
building until he came out, and then follow
him? That's what Croft was doing at Brim,
Stearns and Kidlow.'
'Too risky. It seems likely that White and
Blazevich were involved in some way in the
killings. There are people who know my face,
and we know they're looking for you too. What
if they're guarding White and Blazevich? They
would see us, and then we'd be dead.'
They hired a car and began to try to find
the seven students. Gray found two of them
at home and Darby spoke to another as he was
leaving a class at the school; none of them
recognized Garcia. They met at 10:45 and compared
notes. At eleven, students were leaving their
classes and she found another of the seven
students, but he too knew nothing. A fifth
was working in the library; she didn't like
answering Darby's questions, but she admitted
that she didn't know Garcia.
Only two left - Edward Linney and Judith Wilson.
Wilson was expected back at her apartment
at one o'clock, so Gray spent the rest of
the morning trying to find Linney, but he
was not at home and no one at the school seemed
to know where he was. They hadn't seen him
for several weeks.
They drove together to Judith Wilson's apartment.
She wasn't there at one, so they waited. She
arrived an hour later. Gray jumped out of
the car, ran up to her and caught her at her
front door. He showed her the photograph,
and Darby saw her shake her head.
'Linney had better be good,' he said as he
got back into the car. 'But where is he?'
'I hope we find him today,' she said, 'because
tomorrow I leave the country if we don't.'
Back at the law school, one of his fellow
students at last told them where he was: in
a private hospital. He was well on the way
to becoming an alcoholic, and his parents
had ordered him to spend some time there.
The nurse at the front desk of the hospital
told Gray that Mr Linney was in Room 22, but
refused to let him see him. Gray asked to
see the manager, and while the nurse was fetching
him Gray whispered to Darby, 'Room 22.'
She left the waiting-room and boldly walked
to his room. She knocked and went in. The
young man looked surprised to see her.
'I'm Sara Jacobs,' she said. 'I work for the
Washington Post. May I ask you a question?'
'Yes, but how did you get in?'
'I just walked in. You worked at White and
Blazevich last summer, didn't you? Do you
recognize this man?' She showed him the photograph.
'Yes, he's . . . what's his name? I can't
remember. He works in the oil and gas department.'
Darby held her breath.
Linney closed his eyes and thought. 'Morgan.
Yes, that's it. His surname is Morgan, but
I can't remember his first name. What's this
all about?'
'I'll tell you later,' Darby said, and left.
Gray was waiting for her back in the car.
She didn't say anything but immediately looked
at the notes she had taken in the law library.
There he was. 'Garcia is Curtis D. Morgan,'
she said. 'Let's go.'
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Two Appointments
After five hours at sea in the small, fast
boat, every bone in Matthew Barr's body was
aching, and he was wet and cold. His only
companion had been a man called Larry, who
was extremely tall and looked very strong.
Larry had met him in Fort Lauderdale and had
not said a word to him since then.
They landed in a country Barr believed was
the Bahamas. A car took them to a small airfield,
where a Lear jet was waiting. The flight took
about forty-five minutes. Another car took
them to a large house. Barr had no idea where
they were.
Barr was met by a man who called himself Emil,
who led him round the outside of the house
to a sunroom.
'I'm afraid you must take off your shoes,'
Emil said with a polite smile, 'and be careful
not to step on the towels.'
Inside, Barr saw that towels were lying on
the floor of the sun- room, making paths around
the room. A door on the other side of the
room opened, and Victor Mattiece came in.
Barr stared. Mattiece was an extraordinary
sight. He was extremely thin, and had long
grey hair and a beard. He wore only a pair
of black sports shorts. His toenails were
yellow and very long. He looked completely
crazy.
'Sit over there,' he said, pointing at a chair.
'Don't step on the towels.'
When Barr was seated, Mattiece asked, 'What
do you want?' He was staring out of a window.
'The President sent me,' Barr began.
'He did not. Fletcher Coal sent you.'
'All right. We need to know whether the Pelican
Brief is true. Have you read it?'
'Have you?'
'Yes.'
'Does Mr Coal believe it to be true?'
'I don't know. He's very worried. That's why
I'm here, Mr Mattiece. We have to know.'
'What if it is true?'
'Then we have problems.'
Mattiece turned away from the window, looked
at Barr and said, 'Do you know what I think?
I think Coal is the problem. He let too many
people see the brief.'
Barr could not believe what he was hearing.
The man who had ordered so many deaths was
blaming someone else for the situation. 'Is
it true, Mr Mattiece? That's all I want to
know.'
Behind Barr, a door opened without a sound.
Larry, in his socks and avoiding the towels,
stepped silently into the room.
Mattiece walked over to the door and said
softly, 'Of course it's true.' He left the
sun-room and went into the garden.
Now what? Barr thought.
Larry put the rope round Barr's neck, and
Barr did not hear or feel anything until it
was too late. Mattiece did not want blood
on the floor, so Larry simply broke his neck.
***
They reached the building where White and
Blazevich's offices were before five o'clock.
She was wearing a dress, and Gray said she
looked just right. She could tell that he
liked the way she looked, and she found to
her surprise that it didn't make her angry,
just a little sad about Thomas.
She walked up to the secretary at the desk,
who said, 'Can I help you?'
'Yes, I have an appointment at five o'clock
with Curtis Morgan. My name is Dorothy Blythe.'
The secretary's mouth fell open and she said
nothing.
Darby's heart stopped. 'Is something the matter?'
'Can you wait a moment?' the secretary said.
She got up and disappeared into another room.
Run, Darby's mind was telling her, run! There's
something wrong here. But before she had time
to do anything, the secretary returned with
a man.
'Good afternoon,' he said. 'I'm Jarreld Schwabe,
one of the partners of the firm. You say you
have an appointment with Curtis Morgan?'
'Yes. Is there a problem?'
'There's nothing in his appointment book.'
'Well, that's your fault, not mine.'
'And what was the meeting about?'
She felt weak. 'I don't see why I have to
tell you that. Why can't I see Mr Morgan?'
'Because he's dead.'
She was in shock. 'Dead?'
'Yes,' Schwabe said. 'He was mugged in the
street. I'm sorry. I can see this has been
a shock for you.'
She decided to act really upset. She didn't
want them to ask any more questions; she wanted
them to think that she was just a weak young
woman. 'I'm sorry,' she said, 'I think I'd
better go. I'll phone again for another appointment.'
Schwabe led her to the lift himself.
Edwin Sneller knew that he and his men had
been wasting their time in New York; the place
was just too big. Then at last she moved some
money from her bank in New Orleans to Grantham's
bank in Washington. Sneller's client owned
the bank, so he received any information he
asked for. That meant that she was in Washington,
and that she and the reporter were working
together. He had two men with him, and he
had asked for more. They had to do the job
quickly. But he felt less confident without
Khamel. The girl had escaped so far, and she
could be hiding anywhere. He would start with
the Washington Post building: Grantham had
to come back there some time.
***
Gray found Curtis D. Morgan's address in the
suburbs, and they drove out together to the
house. Mrs Morgan's father, however, refused
to let them in to see her. Gray left his business
card, so that she could call him if she wanted
to. He told her father that Morgan had spoken
to him three times just before he died.
'Is that the end of Garcia?' Darby asked as
they drove away.
'We'll see tomorrow,' he said. 'How do you
feel at the moment? Do you feel safe? I'll
be glad to sleep in your room tonight, just
like I did in New York.'
'But I don't have a sofa here,' she said.
'Where would you sleep?' She was smiling and
this was a good sign. But then she remembered
Callahan. 'I'm not ready, Gray. I'm sorry.'
She rested her head on his shoulder while
he drove the car. 'I'm still frightened to
death,' she said.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Morgan's Story
Beverly Morgan called Gray at four o'clock
the next morning. 'My father would be angry
with me if he knew I was calling,' she said.
'The reporters were horrible to us after Curtis
was killed. But I need to talk to someone.'
She asked him how he knew her husband, and
Gray explained about his phone calls, and
the murders of Rosenberg and Jensen. He spoke
to her patiently for a long time, until he
won her confidence.
'What do you think he knew?' she asked.
'I have no idea. If he had written something
down on paper, where would it be?'
'In our lock-box in the bank. But that's where
all his legal papers were, so I've already
looked in there. I did find another key in
his desk, though, last Saturday.'
Gray held his breath. 'A key to another lock-box?'
'Yes, a box at First Columbia Bank. That's
odd, because we've never used that bank. I
wasn't in a hurry to go to the bank and look
in the box, because I already had all his
legal papers. Maybe it was even something
I wouldn't want to see.'
'Would you like me to look in the box for
you?' Gray asked.
'I hoped you would say that. Yes, please.'
'I'll come round and get the key now'
***
He and Darby drove to the bank the next morning.
Mrs Morgan had given Gray written permission
to open the lock-box, so the clerk let them
into the strong-room. It didn't take them
long to empty the box: all it held was a thin
envelope.
Darby opened the envelope when they were back
in the car. Inside was a document written
by Morgan and properly signed by a legal witness.
The document started: 'Since you are reading
this, I am probably dead.' It was a powerful
first sentence.
In the document Morgan described who he was
and where he worked. He said that he often
worked for one of the firm's clients who was
called Victor Mattiece. The partner in charge
of Mr Mattiece was F. Sims Wakefield. Morgan
explained the Louisiana case and how important
it was to Mr Mattiece. It was important to
White and Blazevich too, since Mattiece had
promised them a share of the profits from
the oil.
On or about 28 September, the document continued,
Morgan had been in Wakefield's office collecting
some files. When he returned to his own office,
he found that by mistake he had picked up
a note from Wakefield's desk together with
the files. A copy of the note was joined on
to Morgan's document. The note was dated 28
September and was from Marty Velmano, another
partner. It read: Sims: Tell our client that
the Court will be easier on him if Rosenberg
is retired. The second retirement is a bit
unusual - it is Jensen (who, as you know,
has those other problems). The note amazed
and frightened Morgan. Realizing its importance,
he made a copy of it and returned the original
to the bottom of the pile of files.
Ten minutes later Wakefield came into his
office, looking pale and worried. They found
the note under the files and Wakefield asked
Morgan if he had read it; Morgan said no.
Wakefield looked at him very closely, but
seemed satisfied.
That night he left the papers on his desk
very tidy. The next morning he could see that
someone had searched his desk. He began to
see Velmano in Wakefield's office more than
usual. Wakefield stopped him working for Mattiece.
Then Rosenberg and Jensen were killed. He
was sure that Mattiece had ordered the killings.
He thought that people were following him.
He had decided to hide his copy of the note
together with this document in a bank, in
case he was killed. He was very frightened.
That was the end of the document.
***
The thin-faced man watched the car come fast
round the corner and park illegally outside
the Post building. The man and the woman jumped
out of the car and ran past him into the building.
He had a gun inside his jacket, but it all
happened too fast.
***
Smith Keen and the Post's lawyer, Vincent
Litsky, read through Morgan's document. When
they had finished, Gray said, 'Well, gentlemen,
there's your independent witness. Can we print
Darby's story now?'
Keen and Litsky looked at each other. Keen
left the office for a few minutes to speak
to the newspaper's owner. When he came back
he said, 'OK, Gray. We do the story. How long
will it take you to write it?'
'I already know the shape of it,' Gray replied.
'I only have to write the details. It should
take me about two hours.'
'It's eleven o'clock now,' Keen said. 'Try
to finish it by three. Litsky needs time to
read it before we print.'
With Darby's help, he finished the story on
time. Keen and Litsky read it and made some
changes. Darby was watching something out
of the window.
'When I've rewritten the story,' Gray said,
when Keen and Litsky had finished, 'I have
to make some phone calls.'
'We'll be back at half past three,' Keen said.
'They're outside,' Darby said softly, when
Keen and Litsky had left the room.
'Who are?'
'I was watching a man standing on the corner.
He looks innocent enough; he's just standing
there drinking coffee from a cup. But he's
been there a long time - I saw him earlier
as well. And just now, when you were talking,
I saw the short man who chased me last week
come up to the coffee-drinker. They talked
for a minute and then the short man disappeared
again. They're just waiting for us to leave
the building.'
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Time to Trust Someone
The first phone call was to a friend of Grantham
at the FBI.
'Phil, this is Gray Grantham. I've got the
recorder on.'
'That sounds serious. Go on.'
'We're going to print a story tomorrow about
the Rosenberg and Jensen killings. We're going
to name Victor Mattiece as the man behind
the killings, and also two of his lawyers
here in Washington. We'll connect this story
with the killing of Verheek in New Orleans.
We believe the FBI knew about Mattiece early
on but refused to investigate at the request
of the White House. We want to give you the
chance to comment.' There was silence. 'Phil,
are you there?'
'Yes, I think so.'
'Any comment?'
'I'm sure we will have a comment, but I'll
have to call you back.'
'OK. I'll look forward to it.'
In fact it was Voyles himself who called back,
about ten minutes later. He demanded to speak
to Smith Keen.
'What are you doing, Smith?' he said. 'We're
still investigating Mattiece. It's too early
to be sure. What have you got?'
'Does the name Darby Shaw mean anything to
you?' Keen asked.
'Yes.'
'We have the Pelican Brief, Denton, and I'm
sitting here looking at Darby Shaw.'
'I was afraid she was dead.'
'No, she's not. And she and Gray Grantham
have an independent witness to support the
brief. It's a big story, Denton.'
'We need to meet. I'll come round in twenty
minutes.'
'OK.'
Keen put the phone down and smiled. He was
amused at the idea of the great F. Denton
Voyles coming round to his office for a meeting.
The next phone call Gray made was to Fletcher
Coal in the White House. Coal agreed that
Mattiece had given large amounts of money
towards the President's election, but denied
that Mattiece and the President were close
friends. He had to admit that he was familiar
with the Pelican Brief. When Gray asked why
there had not been an immediate investigation
of Mattiece, Coal angrily denied that the
White House had tried to slow down such an
investigation.
Then Voyles arrived with K. O. Lewis. Keen
took him into his own office and gave him
a copy of the story to read while Gray made
the third phone call. He rang White and Blazevich
and was put through to Marty Velmano. For
the third time he explained that he was recording
the conversation.
'Mr Velmano,' Gray said, 'we're printing a
story in the morning which names your client
Victor Mattiece as the man behind thekillings
of Rosenberg and Jensen.'
'Good!' said Velmano. 'We'll take you to court.
By the time we're finished, Mr Mattiece will
own the Washington Post.'
'Mr Velmano, we have a copy of the Pelican
Brief. Have you heard of it?'
Silence.
'We also have a copy of a note you sent to
Sims Wakefield on 28 September. In the note
you suggested that your client's position
would be a lot better without Rosenberg and
Jensen on the Supreme Court.'
Silence.
'Mr Velmano, are you there?'
'Yes.'
'We wanted to give you the chance to comment.
Do you have any comment?'
'You're going to destroy me,' Velmano said.
***
Voyles and Lewis entered the room with Smith
Keen. Keen introduced them to Darby and Gray.
Voyles smiled at Darby and said, 'So you're
the one who started all this.'
'No, sir,' she said, 'I think it was Mattiece.'
They sat around a table. Voyles had a piece
of paper. He said, 'I'm going to read you
something. This is official, and you can use
it in your paper. Anything else Lewis or I
say is unofficial, and you can't use it. Is
that clear?'
Keen and Grantham said yes.
'All right,' Voyles said. 'We received a copy
of the Pelican Brief two weeks ago and showed
it to the White House on the same day. It
was personally delivered by K. O. Lewis to
Fletcher Coal. Eric East was also present
at the meeting. We thought it was worth investigation,
but nothing happened for six days, until Gavin
Verheek was murdered in New Orleans. The FBI
began a full investigation into Victor Mattiece,
involving over four hundred men. We believe
Victor Mattiece to be the main suspect in
the murders of Rosenberg, Jensen, Thomas Callahan
and Verheek, and we are trying to find him.'
'Did the White House interfere with your investigation
of Mattiece?' Grantham asked.
'This is now unofficial,' Voyles said. 'You
can't use it. OK?'
'OK.'
'Yes, the President asked me not to investigate
Mattiece. He said it could be embarrassing
to the Government. I recorded the conversation.'
They could hardly believe what they were hearing.
He recorded the President!
'I will not allow anyone to hear that recording,'
Voyles continued, 'unless the President denies
what I have just told you. Anyway, will you
use the official story I've given you? Will
you put Coal's name there on the front page
along with everyone else?'
'Yes, I think he belongs there,' Keen said.
'Good,' said Voyles. 'Can you give me some
early copies of the newspaper tomorrow morning?
I want to take them round to him myself and
watch his face.'
'He'll take the blame,' Keen said. 'It will
be the end of his career, but he'll make the
President look innocent.'
'Yes, I think you're right,' said Voyles.
'Now, I'd like to speak to Miss Shaw alone,
please, if that's all right with her.'
'OK,' she said, 'but Grantham stays.'
'All right.'
When everyone else had left the room, Voyles
asked, 'What are you going to do next?'
'First tell me who killed Gavin Verheek,'
she said.
'It was Khamel. And Khamel was the one who
was shot in the head as you were holding his
hand by the river.'
'Who killed him?'
'We think it was someone from the CIA. We
know the CIA were investigating Mattiece in
a small way. In his oil business Mattiece
had connections with some unfriendly Arab
countries, so the CIA were already keeping
an eye on him. When they saw a copy of the
Pelican Brief they sent a few men down to
New Orleans to look after you.'
Darby got up and went to the window. It was
dark outside now. 'They didn't do a very good
job, then,' she said. 'There are men out there
now who have been following me for a week
or more. One of them chased me in New Orleans,
so I don't think he's CIA. Mattiece is so
crazy that he'll go on trying to kill me even
after he goes to prison - if you catch him.'
'We can help,' Voyles said. 'We can get you
out of the country.'
It was time to trust someone. She took a deep
breath. 'All right,' she said.
'I'll go and make the arrangements,' Voyles
said.
Alone in the room, Darby walked into Gray's
arms. 'It's going to be all right now,' he
said, holding her. 'It's over. You're safe.'
'I'm going alone, Gray,' she said. 'I'll call
you when I'm ready.'
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
Away From It All
By 11 p.m. only four lawyers remained in the
offices of White and Blazevich. They were
Velmano, Sims Wakefield, Jarreld Schwabe and
a retired partner named Frank Cortz.
Cortz finished a phone conversation with one
of Victor Mattiece's staff. 'That was Strider,'
he said. 'They're in Cairo, in some hotel.
Mattiece won't talk to us and, of course,
he isn't coming back over here. Strider says
he's behaving very strangely. They've told
the boys with the guns to leave town immediately.
The chase is over.'
'So what are we supposed to do?' asked Wakefield.
'We're on our own,' said Cortz. 'Mattiece
isn't going to help us.'
There was silence around the table as they
all looked into the future. Then Velmano said,
'Grantham only mentioned me and Sims. You
two may be OK. And I've got enough money saved
to spend the rest of my life hiding in Europe.'
'It's all right for you,' Wakefield said.
'I can't hide. I've got a wife and six children.'
'I think you should go home and tell your
wife what to expect,' Velmano said.
'I can't do that,' Wakefield said. He got
up and left the room.
A minute later they heard the sound of a single
gunshot from his office.
***
After eight days in the sun of the Virgin
Islands her skin was brown enough and her
hair was returning to its natural colour.
She walked miles up and down the beaches and
ate nothing except fish and fruit. She slept
a lot the first few days.
She looked at her wrist and then remembered
that her watch was in a bag somewhere. She
didn't need it here. She woke with the sun
and went to bed after dark. But now she was
waiting, so she had looked at her wrist.
It was almost dark when the taxi stopped at
the end of the small road. He got out, paid
the driver and looked at the lights as the
car disappeared back up the road. He had one
bag. He could see a light from the house between
the trees at the edge of the beach, and he
walked towards it. He didn't know what to
expect. He knew how he felt about her, but
did she feel the same?
She was waiting at the back of the house,
looking out to sea, with a drink in her hand.
She smiled at him, put down her drink and
let him come to her.
They kissed for a long minute. 'You're late,'
she said.
'This is not the easiest place to find,' Gray
said. 'Even when you have directions.'
'I know,' she said. 'That's the idea. It's
beautiful, though, isn't it?'
'It is. You are too.'
'Let's go for a walk,' she said.
He changed into a pair of shorts and they
walked together on the beach, hand in hand.
'You left early,' she said.
'I got tired of it. I've written a story a
day since the big one, and they kept wanting
more. I was working eighteen hours a day.
Yesterday I said goodbye.'
'I haven't seen a paper for days,' she said.
'Coal's finished. The President will be OK.
I don't think he did anything really bad;
he's just stupid. He won't get reelected,
though. You read about Wakefield?'
'Yes, that was in the last paper I saw.'
'They've got Schwabe. They want Velmano too,
but he's disappeared. Of course Mattiece is
in deep trouble, and they're after four of
his men too.'
They walked in silence along the beach. She
put her arm round his waist and he pulled
her closer. 'I've missed you,' she said softly.
He breathed deeply, but said nothing. 'How
long will you stay?' she asked.
'I don't know. A couple of weeks. Maybe a
year. It depends on you.'
'Let's take it a month at a time. OK, Gray?'
'Perfect.'
- THE END -