CHAPTER ONE
Prince Zigfried
Once upon a time, in a faraway land, there
lived a Prince. His name was Zigfried,
and he was very unhappy. His father, the King,
had died, and since then, everyone in the palace
had forgotten how to smile. Without his father,
Zigfried thought he would never feel happy again.
Every day, Zigfried sat at the window in his room
in the palace, looking at the birds in the trees.
"How can they sing and fly so
free? They must not feel like me."
His servant, Ozlowe, tried to
make the prince smile by telling
him jokes or doing funny tricks for
him. But the Prince would not smile.
"I know you love me Ozlowe, but I
cannot smile. My heart is broken."
Ozlowe would not give up.
"Let's go for a walk, good Prince. Maybe we can
find something outside which will make you happy."
"If you wish Ozlowe, but I don't think
there's anything that can make me happy."
Ozlowe put on his hunting
cap, and he took his crossbow.
He enjoyed hunting and he hoped to
catch a bird or a rabbit for the Prince.
They walked through the forest until they came to
a lake. On the lake there was a beautiful white
swan. It had a gold crown on its head, that only
Princesses wear. The swan swam towards the prince
and looked into his eyes. The swan's eyes were
so sad that Prince Zigfried felt sorry for it.
"Here is a creature which feels worse than I do.
But why do you have that crown on your head?"
The swan opened its wings and cried out.
"I think it's trying to tell me something."
Ozlowe had his crossbow in his
hands. He wanted to shoot the swan.
"I'll get that swan for you.
Prince. Just one minute."
"Ozlowe, no!"
Before Ozlowe could shoot, a magic owl flew
from a tree and took Ozlowe's cap off his head.
This cast a spell on him, and he was turned
to stone. The Prince did not understand.
"Ozlowe, what has happened to you? Speak to me!"
He looked back at the lake. The swan was gone.
"Everything I do goes wrong. This
must have happened because of me!"
The Prince returned to the palace
sadder than before, thinking to himself:
"If only Ozlowe were here! There is
nothing good in my life any more".
Zigfried's mother came to see him that
night. She had something important to say.
"Zigfried, soon you will be eighteen years
old. You must take your father's place as King.
I am having a ball on your birthday
so that you may choose a wife,
and I will invite all the
princesses from the other kingdoms."
"But I do not wish to marry,
Mother. I do not love anyone."
"You will learn to love someone. First,
you must stop thinking of yourself."
"If this will make you happy, I'll do it, Mother."
"It is not for my happiness that I am doing this.
It is for yours, and all the other people in this
land. You see, love is more powerful than we
know. Without it, you will not be a great King."
His mother left him. He sat at the
window, thinking of what she had said.
He wanted to love someone with all his
heart, but he didn't know who it would be.
CHAPTER TWO
The Beautiful Princess
On the morning of the Royal Ball,
everybody was very busy in the palace.
The Queen's maids were preparing the
Queen's dress. The servants cleaned
the floors and windows, and the cooks were
cooking enough food for a thousand people.
The prince looked handsome in his red
outfit. But he was still not happy.
He left the palace to be alone and think,
and went to the stone statue of Ozlowe.
"It's my birthday today Ozlowe. I'm eighteen. That
means that I must marry someone and become King.
The problem is I don't want to
get married; I don't love anyone."
There was a quiet splashing in the lake.
Zigfried looked and saw the
beautiful swan with the gold crown.
"There it is! The beautiful swan has come back."
He went closer to the water to look at it. Its
eyes had the same sadness in them, but it was
happy to see Zigfried and it swam close to him.
Zigfried looked into its eyes and talked to it.
"I think you understand me. I
think you know how people feel."
A tear fell from the swan's eye.
"Don't cry. You should be
happy that you are a swan.
You will never have to marry someone you do not
love. You will never feel sad when someone dies."
The swan made a loud cry. Its wings
moved back and forth at its sides.
Suddenly, an owl appeared as if from nowhere
and flew at Zigfried's head, but it missed.
The owl flew off, and the swan began to swim away.
"Wait. Don't leave."
Zigfried ran round the edge of the lake, following
the swan. He had to run fast to see where it went.
Soon, he was in a part of the forest he did
not know. Tall trees blocked out the sun.
It was very dark.
The swan swam to an ugly old castle. When it
left the water, something magical happened;
the swan turned into a beautiful Princess.
She had long blonde hair and she wore a long
white dress. The crown was still on her head.
Zigfried ran to where she
stood at the castle door.
"Wait! Where are you going?"
The Princess stopped, but she did not look at him.
"Look at me, please. My name is Prince
Zigfried and I want to know who you are."
The Princess turned to look at the Prince.
She had the same dark, sad eyes of the swan.
"My name is Princess Odile."
"But why were you a swan? Why do you look so sad?"
"An evil wizard called Rocford cast a spell on me.
I may only leave the castle
during the day as a swan."
"Where is this wizard? I will talk to
him. I will tell him this is wrong."
"No, you mustn't. He will hurt you, I know.
He does not want me to see another man."
"Tell me where this man is! I
will fight him and free you."
"No, you must leave. He is dangerous."
"I won't leave until I see
him; You must be set free."
"Please. You are very kind, but you must go away."
"I won't!"
She looked into his eyes again.
"If you want to do something
for me, you will leave now."
"Odile, I will leave if you want me to.
But I want you to come to the ball tonight.
I must choose a wife and I want to choose you."
"I can't. The wizard won't let me."
"Find a way. Promise me you'll try."
She spoke softly.
"All right. I'll try."
CHAPTER THREE
Odet
Zigfried left, and Odile went inside the castle.
Odet, the wizard's evil daughter, was behind a
tree. When she saw Odile talking to the Prince,
she was jealous; she wanted to go to the ball,
and what was more, she wanted to marry the Prince.
She didn't like Odile, because
she was so beautiful and kind.
But the wizard loved her, so Odet couldn't
do anything to hurt her... until now!
Odet went to the wizard's
room, but he was not there.
The room looked like a museum. There
was an Egyptian statue against one wall,
and large aquariums full of strange fish. On
a table stood many different coloured bottles.
Odet opened one of the bottles. Smoke came
out of it. It smelled of burning wood.
The magic owl flew into the
open window, unseen by Odet,
and changed back into the
wizard. "Do you like the smell?"
"Oh, Father! You scared me."
"You wouldn't be afraid if you were
not in my room when I wasn't here."
"I know father, but I have something very
important to tell you. It's about Odile."
The wizard opened his eyes wide. He was a
tall man, with a long, white beard and long,
white hair. He wore a big black hat
and a long black robe with stars on it.
"Tell me what you know!"
"First, you must promise to do something for me."
"What is it?"
"I can't tell you now.
First, I must tell you about Odile, then
I will ask for something. Will you do it?"
"Tell me, before I turn you into a frog!"
The wizard was very much in love with Odile.
He would change his daughter into a frog
because he wanted to know about Odile.
"Today, I saw Odile talking to Prince
Zigfried. The Prince asked Odile to go to
the royal ball tonight. He wants to marry
her and free her from your evil powers."
The wizard turned in a circle and
pointed his hand at the floor.
Fire came from his fingers and hit
the floor. The whole castle shook.
"I should have destroyed the Prince
today, when I saw him with Odile."
"You saw him, too?"
"Yes, at the lake. I attacked
him, but I was only an owl.
Odile knew this and she left him.
He must have followed her here."
"Oh yes Father, and he is so
handsome! You should see his face!"
"Silence!"
The wizard turned himself into a large, stone
ball. He threw himself against the walls,
making the castle shake again. Alone in
her room, Odile felt the castle shaking.
She hid her head under a pillow on her bed;
she hated it when the wizard got angry.
The wizard changed back into himself in his room.
"Now Father, you promised
you'd do something for me."
"I never promised you anything!"
"Oh, Father. I want to go to the
ball! I want to marry the prince."
The wizard angrily raised his hand again. Then, he
thought of something. Slowly, he lowered his hand.
"You would like to go to the ball, wouldn't you?"
"Oh yes, Father!"
"And you would like to marry the prince?"
"Yes, I would."
"Then you will, and he will
think that you are Odile."
"Oh Father, what a wonderful idea!"
She put her arms around him. His body was cold
as stone, and his eyes were filled with fire.
CHAPTER FOUR
A bird in a cage
Odile's room was at the top of the
castle tower. Rocford had put her there,
after he had taken her from her parents. She
was the most beautiful Princess in the land,
and her parents were good and kind. Rocford
had asked her father if he could marry Odile.
"We must ask my daughter what she thinks."
Odile was brought to the wizard.
"Odile, this man lias asked to
marry you. He says he is very
rich and that he will make you the happiest
princess in the world. What do you think?"
Odile looked into the wizard's eyes.
"Do you promise to love me forever,
with all your heart?" Will you love
me so much that you will not think of what
you want, even if it hurts you to do this?"
The look in her eyes and her
questions made Rocford uncomfortable.
"Why do you ask me such questions?
I told your father I could give
you everything you could want."
The Princess smiled and turned her head away.
"I'm sorry Father, but I will not marry
this man. He does not know what love is."
They did not know then that he was a wizard.
Rocford had looked like a Prince. He wore
beautiful clothes and looked very handsome. But,
when he heard what Odile said to her father,
his face began to change. It became old and
ugly. His clothes changed from blue to black.
"You do not know what you
are saying, you silly girl.
I do not have to ask for what I want. I am
a wizard, and I can do anything I please."
He waved his hands through the air,
and a fire started in the castle
where the Princess and her parents lived. He
had turned Odile into a small bird in a cage,
and carried her to his castle
where he locked her up in a tower.
The entire kingdom was destroyed by
this fire, and her parents were killed.
There was a real bird in a cage in Odile's room at
the wizard's castle. The wizard had put it there
so that Odile would remember the power he had over
her. He only let her leave the castle as a swan
because he did not want other
men to fall in love with her.
At night, she stayed in her room talking
to the bird, who was her only friend.
She called the bird Patrice,
because it was her mother's name.
"Oh Patrice, what should I do? The ball
is tonight, and I am a prisoner here.
I believe the Prince loves me with all his heart.
I saw it in his eyes. He loved me even as a swan."
The bird began moving its wings wildly. It always
knew when something horrible was about to happen.
"What is it Patrice, what are you afraid of?"
Odile heard keys in her locked door. She
put the bird and its cage behind a curtain,
because she did not want the bird
to see what was about to happen.
CHAPTER FIVE
Odet's New Voice
The wizard entered Odile's room with Odet.
Odet was the same age and height as Odile,
but she had dark hair. However,
she wasn't as beautiful as Odile,
and this made her very jealous.
The wizard spoke first.
"Sit down, Odile. I would
like to ask you something."
The wizard waved his hand and a large and very
comfortable pink chair appeared. Odile sat on it.
"Odet tells me that you would like to
go to the ball tonight. Is that true?"
"Yes."
"If I let you go to this ball,
will you promise to marry me?"
"I have told you, I will only marry
a man who loves me and who I love."
"But you know I love you."
"If you loved me,
you wouldn't keep me locked up in this
castle. You wouldn't have killed my parents."
"You are a fool! Would you like
to marry the Prince? Is that it?"
"He loves me more than you do."
"How do you know? He left you here with me.
That shows you that you are wrong. He is afraid of
me. He can't love you very much if he is afraid."
"He did it for me! I asked him to do it!"
"And did you tell him that
you would go to the ball?"
"Yes."
"Then you lied. You knew I would not let you go."
"I said I would try. He knows that if I do
not go it is not because I do not want to."
"And how does he know this?"
"You do not have to cast a spell on
someone or make them rich to love you.
You understand it by looking in their eyes.
You know it by the way they speak and act."
"You are a dreamer!"
"And you have no heart!"
"Silence!"
The wizard raised both his
arms and the castle shook.
The curtain on the wall fell down, and
the wizard saw the bird in the cage.
"Ah, the bird."
"If you hurt that bird you
are worse than I thought."
The bird flew wildly as the wizard
walked towards it. He picked up the cage.
"Now, why would I hurt this bird?
It is like me. It has no heart. It
does not feel anything when I do this."
The wizard pointed his fingers at Odet. She
changed into Odile. She had the same blonde hair,
the same eyes. She was even
wearing the crown. Odile stood up.
"Tonight, Odet will go to the ball as you,
Odile. Zigfried will marry her and we will
see what true love is. Your hearts
are nothing compared to my magic."
"You may look like me Odet, but there
is something missing from your eyes.
The prince will know this."
"He does not love you Odile. He
only loves what you look like."
"I almost forgot!" The wizard waved his hand.
"Odet, say something."
When Odet spoke, she sounded just like
Odile. "Hello, Prince Zigfried. It's me,
Odile. I love you." Odile ran to her bed,
crying. She fell on the bed and covered
her face. Rocford laughed loudly. He took Odet
out of the room and locked the door behind him.
When Odile looked up, only the bird was
with her. It too, had a tear in its eye.
CHAPTER SIX
The Ball
The ballroom in the palace was very big.
There were hundreds of men and
women dancing in the centre.
Along the walls there were long white tables.
They had candles and all kinds of food on them.
At the top of the room, on a stage, were three
large chairs. The Queen sat in the middle
and Zigfried sat on her right.
The chair on the left was empty. It was for
the Princess who would be Zigfried's wife.
"Which Princess do you like the best?"
"The one I will choose is not here yet."
"But you have met them all, surely?"
"There is another one, mother, and
she is a surprise. You will see."
Every time a new guest arrived, the ballroom
doors were opened, and everyone fell silent.
A servant called out the
guests' names as they entered.
Each time this happened, the Prince became
very excited. But Odile never arrived.
It was almost twelve o'clock. Zigfried
had promised his mother that he would
choose a bride by midnight.
The two large doors opened.
"Please, let it be her!"
It was a giant cake with 18 candles on
it. Everyone in the room began to sing.
"Happy Birthday to you,
Happy Birthday to you,
Happy Birthday Prince Zigfried,
Happy Birthday to you!"
Zigfried and his mother walked
towards the enormous cake.
"Now, make a wish and blow out all the candles."
No one heard him, but Zigfried said,
"I wish Odile would come and be my wife."
He blew out the candles and everyone cheered.
The doors opened.
"Princess Odile."
It was Odet dressed as Odile.
She wore a long white dress and long white
gloves. The gold crown was shining on her head.
She held a bouquet of flowers in her arms. She
smiled as she walked towards the Queen and Prince.
She gave the Queen the flowers, then bowed.
"Mother, this is Odile, the
Princess I met in the forest."
"I knew your father. I'm sorry.
I thought everyone had died in the fire.
You must be the only one who lived."
Odet did not know what the wizard had done
to Odile's parents. She stopped smiling.
"Oh Mother, her story is too sad to
tell. Let us enjoy this evening together.
We are her family now."
"Do you mean you wish to choose
Princess Odile as your wife?"
"Yes, Mother, I do."
The Queen raised her hand for the men to
sound their horns. Everyone was quiet.
"Ladies and gentlemen, I would like to announce
the engagement of my son, Prince Zigfried. After
tonight, he will be the King of this land, and
he has chosen Princess Odile to be his wife."
Zigfried and Odet danced together.
Everyone around them clapped their hands.
"Odile, I knew you would come. How
did you escape from the evil wizard?"
"I... I ran away."
"And he did not see you?"
The Prince stepped back so he could look at Odet's
eyes. His heart sank when he saw those eyes.
They looked like Odile's, but there
was something missing in them.
He didn't love her. Odet began to
lie about her escape from Rocford.
"I saw a falling star in the sky.
I closed my eyes and made a wish.
When I opened them, I was in a carriage
pulled by horses. That's how I got here.
It must mean we were meant to be together. Oh
Zigfried, tell me you will love me forever."
He held her close, because he did not want to
look in her eyes. He knew he had loved Odile
when he had first seen her. Now he didn't know.
He thought there must be something wrong with him.
"Odile, I promise always to
love you and never leave you."
CHAPTER SEVEN
Odile Escapes
Odile stood at her window,
looking at the stars and the moon.
There were bars at the window, but they
were not necessary. Her window was high
above a river. If she tried to escape, she would
almost certainly fall into the water and die.
Her bird, Patrice, chirped behind
her. She turned to look at the bird.
"Oh Patrice, I understand you. I am in a cage,
too. But you must want to get out. I'm sorry I
never thought of it. I have kept you locked
up just like Rocford has kept me locked up.
Because you are my only friend in this world, I
wanted you to stay. But you must be free to fly."
Odile took the bird cage to the
window. She opened its small door.
"Fly away, Patrice, and be free! Find another bird
to love. It is the only thing worth living for."
The bird flew from its cage, through the bars on
the window, into the night. Odile closed her eyes.
She imagined that she was Patrice
flying over the forest and lake.
She flew into the garden of the palace, she
landed on a palace wall and looked into a
large window at the ball. Beautiful women in
beautiful dresses were dancing with handsome men.
She saw the prince with his mother and the
cake with the eighteen candles. Then, Odet
entered the room dressed as her. When she opened
her eyes, she found to her amazement that she was
outside the palace window. When she had set the
bird free, she had also set herself free. Because
she believed with all her heart in love and
freedom, everything that she imagined came true.
The wizard knew that Odile hated
him, and it made him angry.
He wanted to make her love him, so
he decided to have a ball for her.
Using his magic, he made a large room full
of people dancing. He changed himself into a
young man again, the same young man he was
when he had taken Odile from her parents.
He went to her room with
flowers. He knocked on her door.
"Odile, I have a surprise for you."
There was no answer. He
couldn't even hear the bird.
"Odile, it's me, Rocford. I've
decided to take you to a ball."
When there was no answer and he
heard nothing, he became angry.
He made the door disappear. His anger turned
him back into the old, evil man that he was.
He saw the bird cage on the
floor. The room was empty.
Roaring with anger, he turned himself into an owl
and flew from the castle towards the palace.
CHAPTER EIGHT
The Prince Chases the Princess
When Odile saw Odet dancing with Zigfried, she ran
to the palace entrance. The guards stopped her.
"Who are you?"
"My name is Princess Odile.
The Prince is expecting me."
"No. Princess Odile has already
entered. You must be lying."
"Please, you must believe me. That
is not Princess Odile. She is lying."
But the guards wouldn't believe
her. She ran back to the window
and knocked hard on it.
Everyone turned to look at her.
The Prince could not believe what he
saw - two Odiles. He looked at Odet.
"What is going on?"
"I don't know. The evil wizard must
have changed someone to look like me."
Odile kept knocking on the window. She was
crying. Zigfried could now see that she had
the same eyes as the swan. Rocford flew down next
to Odile as the owl. He held her in both arms.
"Did you think you could escape from me?"
The Prince ran from the ballroom. He
saw Odile fighting with the wizard.
"Take your hands off her, Rocford."
Rocford let go of Odile's arms.
"I should have killed you that day at the
lake. But I will be happy to do it now."
The wizard lifted up his hand. Odile stopped him.
"Wait! Don't do it. I'll go with you. I'll
do what you want. Just don't hurt him."
"Odile, what are you saying?
Don't leave me again!"
She could not look at him, because if
she did, she would not want to leave.
"I'm doing this for us. If
you die, I will die with you.
It is better for us to live and
hope to be together one day."
Odet ran out of the palace.
She still looked like Odile.
"Who is this, then?"
"It is Odet, the wizard's evil daughter.
She only looks like me. Look
into her eyes and you will know."
"I knew it."
Odet also had magical powers. She
changed herself back to her real body.
"It is too late Zigfried. You promised
to marry me and love me forever.
If you do not keep this promise, you
will never be able to keep another."
Odet changed herself into a bird. The
wizard was an owl and Odile was a swan.
They flew together away from the
palace, back to Rocford's castle.
The Queen and many others came out of
the palace to see what had happened.
Zigfried went after Odile.
"Guards, bring me my horse."
"Zigfried, where are you
going? Where is the Princess?"
"She has gone away, Mother, and I must find her."
The guards brought the prince a beautiful
white horse, and gave him his sword.
"Do you want us to call the men, Your Highness?"
"No, this is something I must do alone."
"Zigfried, do not leave the palace alone.
If something happens to you, we will be without
a king. It is your duty to stay with me!"
"Mother, being a King means nothing if
you are not with the woman you love.
I would rather die than leave
Odile with that evil wizard."
The Prince spurred his horse on and
rode quickly towards the dark forest.
CHAPTER NINE
The Fir
Rocford, Odet and Odile flew onto the tower
of the castle. They changed back into people.
Odile was weeping loudly. The wizard
just laughed his evil laugh and said:
"Odile, now I know how to get
you to marry me. If you don't,
I will kill the Prince, and
you will watch him die."
"Father, you do not have to kill Zigfried.
He has already promised to marry
me. He cannot break such a promise."
"Neither of you has a heart.
How can you ever expect to be happy if
you know that someone does not love you?
But you will see. Love is stronger than spells.
You will never succeed in getting what you want."
At this, they saw Zigfried coming
towards the castle on his horse.
"We shall see which is stronger, love or hate!"
The wizard made a wall of fire appear in front
of Zigfried. Zigfried could only think of Odile.
He rode right through the
fire without getting hurt.
Odile said triumphantly: "You see. I am right."
As she ran from the wizard, he tried to block her
way by making the doors close in front of her.
But Odile just ran faster
and escaped through each one.
The Prince saw Odile on the steps going
up to the tower. He took her in his arms.
"Odile, I will never let you leave me again.
Say that you will stay with me forever."
"I will, I will! I love you Zigfried!"
The wizard appeared at the top of
the steps. Odet was behind him.
"You will not escape death this time, Zigfried."
The Prince took out his sword.
Odile tried to stop him.
"Do not fight him, Zigfried. If he kills
you, I will lose everyone I've ever loved."
"You are right Odile. Zigfried is only a boy. He
is no match for me. Now, come back to your room,
and let this little boy go home to his mother."
"Rocford, your words will not discourage
me. I would kill you now, but I will give
you one last chance to live. Let us leave
in peace and never come near Odile again."
"You really are a little boy if
you think that you can harm me."
Rocford raised his hand, and Odile flew
through the air to where Odet stood.
Zigfried ran at Rocford and tried to stab
him with his sword. Rocford put his hand
up. The sword touched it and turned into water.
Without a sword, Zigfried attacked the wizard.
Rocford threw Zigfried down the steps. He
picked up a stick and turned it into a sword.
He pointed it at Zigfried's
heart as he lay on the ground.
"Rocford! Don't!"
"Say you will marry me Odile,
and I will let him live."
''Don't do it Odile! Don't make
yourself more unhappy just for me!"
The wizard prodded Zigfried with the sword.
"And you have promised to marry me,
Zigfried. You said you would always love me."
"I said that because I thought you were Odile.
I would never marry you. I would rather die."
Zigfried took the wizard's sword and
pushed it deep into his own heart.
"Zigfried, no!"
Something strange began to
happen. The castle began to shake.
Large stones fell from the ceiling,
and Rocford and Odet were killed.
Odile ran to Zigfried. She
took the sword out of his heart
and pulled his body out of the castle,
before it fell to the ground.
CHAPTER TEN
The Wedding
Dawn broke in the forest, but no birds sang.
The castle was nothing but a pile of stones.
The only sound was Odile
crying over Zigfried's body.
"Oh Zigfried, my one true
love! Why did you have to die?"
At this, the Prince opened
first one eye, then the other.
"You're alive! Oh, Zigfried!"
She hugged the Prince and
cried tears of happiness.
"I love you, Odile. I knew that my love was
stronger than that sword. Nothing is more
powerful than a person's heart. Tell me you
will marry me, and I will love you forever."
"Of course I will Zigfried.
You have made my dreams come true.
We were right to believe in love!"
They left the old castle
together on Zigfried's horse.
When they came to the lake near
the palace, they saw Ozlowe.
He was not a statue anymore.
He stood scratching his head.
All of the wizard's spells had been broken
when he died. The Prince was full of joy.
"Ozlowe!"
"Master Zigfried, I don't know what happened.
I was standing here about to shoot a swan."
"That will teach you never to kill
anything. This is Princess Odile.
She was the swan you tried to kill."
Ozlowe was very confused.
"Prince Zigfried, I think I'd better
go to bed. I don't feel very well."
When the servants and the Queen heard
about Zigfried and Odile's marriage,
there was a big celebration.
All the people in the land and the surrounding
kindoms were invited to the wedding.
It took place at the edge of the lake,
where Zigfried had first seen Odile.
Odile wore a beautiful long wedding dress.
Zigfried's mother walked towards them.
"Zigfried, I want you to know
that what you did was right.
Though I asked you to stay at the palace, you
left for a better reason. You should always
follow your heart, especially when it is full
of love. You father would be very proud of you."
Zigfried's mother was so happy she had tears
in her eyes. The Prince took Odile's hands.
They stood together in front of the lake. The
Queen put the King's crown on Zigfried's head.
The priest spoke to the new King and Queen.
"Marriage is a wonderful thing. And what makes
this marriage special is that the love you have
for each other will affect everyone
in this land. Through your happiness,
we will become happy. Through your love for each
other, we will love each other. Is this what you
want? Is your love strong enough to lead a
land of people who need joy in their lives?"
Odile spoke first.
"It is."
"Of course, it is!"
"Then by the power that is given to me by
God, I pronounce you husband and wife."
At that moment a joyful chirp was heard
and a little bird flew from a
rose bush and sat on Odile's hand.
"Patrice, my little friend! You're back!"
Then Odile turned to Zigfried and said:
"You see my beloved King, love
is stronger than anything in
this world. When you love somebody
or something you never lose them."
Zigfried looked lovingly into his bride's
eyes, they kissed and everybody cheered.
- THE END -