CHAPTER ONE
The New Computer System
At exactly 8.20 Mr Henry Williams walked through
the doors of the bank. He was the manager
and had worked there for twenty years. He
wasn't always calm and relaxed when he arrived
at work but yesterday something had happened
to make his life much easier. He looked around
the bank. There were beautiful new computers
on every desk.
Some were connected to printers, others to
scanners. The CPUs were hidden under the desks
and the keyboards waited to be used. On each
mouse pad was a mouse with a small red light,
which lit up when the computer was switched
on. The VDUs shone as the sun came through
the window. Mr Williams smiled. When he entered
his office, he saw that his secretary had
already arrived.
"Morning, Mr Williams," she said happily.
She was a very nice girl with long, blonde
hair and a big smile but she wasn't the most
efficient secretary in the world.
"Good morning, Belinda. Are you looking forward
to discovering the wonderful things that your
new computer can do?"
She looked worried. "Yes, but I hope I don't
make too many mistakes. Yesterday I nearly
lost some important information because I
pressed the wrong key."
"Don't worry. I know you've only been here
for six months. Mike has assured me that we
now have the most up-to-date computer hardware
and software are the most secure system money
can buy."
Mike Black was the bank's network manager
and head of technology. He had organized and
set up the new system.
At that moment someone knocked on the door
and Mike came in.
"Morning, Mr Williams. How are you?" he said.
"Very well, thank you, Mike. Now, are you
sure the system is functioning properly? Can
I go on holiday next week to the Caribbean
without worrying about things back here?"
Mike smiled. "Things couldn't be better. Our
LAN is working perfectly. It is now connected
to the bank's WAN and the security access
rights are..."
"Mike, you know that my knowledge of computers
is very limited. I'm afraid I belong to another
generation - which is why I pay you to solve
our IT problems."
IT terms were a foreign language to Henry
Williams. His son Robbie was only 15 but he
was already a computer genius and sat in front
of his monitor for hours every day. He had
no problem logging on and off, surfing the
net or downloading files. His father was an
excellent bank manager but unfortunately he
had no idea what these terms meant. He was
grateful for experts like Mike who could decipher
these mysteries for him.
"Don't worry. You can have a wonderful time
in the Caribbean. Things couldn't be better
here," replied Mike.
He left the office and Mr Williams sat down
at his desk on which there was no computer
at all, either new or old.
He was dreaming of blue seas and white beaches
when a cry from Belinda's desk brought him
back to reality. "Mr Williams, my computer
has crashed!" As soon as she had said the
words, they heard similar cries of alarm coming
from the bank's main area downstairs.
One by one the computers were crashing...
CHAPTER TWO
A Problem
Mr Williams ran down the escalator and into
the main office area. What was happening?
All the computers were down. Everyone was
trying to reboot but it was impossible. Henry
Williams tried not to panic. He asked Belinda
to call Mike and tell him to come immediately.
Then he said to his staff, "Don't worry, everyone.
I'm sure it's a minor problem that Mike will
soon resolve." A young bank teller whispered
to a colleague, "He said that last week when
that virus destroyed most of our files. Remember?"
His friend smiled. Someone had sent an e-mail
to all the staff which promised to show photos
of Belinda's new boyfriend. Belinda was very
popular with the staff in the bank so naturally
everyone opened it. But there was no photo,
just a virus which corrupted the entire system.
Mike, who still didn't know about the problem,
arrived in the lift just as strange things
began to happen. First the lights went off,
leaving the bank in darkness. Then a client
came in to complain to a cashier that he couldn't
access his account from the ATM outside the
bank. Then the lights came on again but the
doors closed automatically, locking everyone
in the bank. Mr Williams said sarcastically,
"As you can see, Mike, our new system is working
perfectly. Nobody can do any work, the clients
are angry, and we are all prisoners in the
bank!"
Mike smiled nervously. "I'm sure it's nothing.
I'll take a look at the server and see what
the problem is." Mike was the only person
with total security access rights for the
system and he had the only copy of the password
list. He was very good at his job so he wasn't
too worried about these "hiccups." He went
to the main computer and put in his password.
A message appeared on the screen:
Access Denied
Password Invalid
Everyone in the bank was watching him. Mike
took his password list from his wallet. He
typed in his password again, slowly and carefully.
Every time he tried the same message appeared
on the screen. "That's impossible," he cried.
His face was white with tension. Mr Williams
was waiting for an explanation. "Is everything
OK?" he asked. Mike prepared to give his boss
the bad news.
"It seems that... someone has obtained the
passwords for the new system and... has changed
them."
"And what exactly does that mean?" asked his
boss angrily. Mike took a deep breath.
"It means that this person now has total control
of the bank."
At that moment the doors of the bank miraculously
opened again. No one spoke. The silence was
broken only by the noise of the clock on the
wall. All the staff were waiting for Mr Williams'
reaction.
"And tell me, how did this person get the
passwords?" asked Mr Williams quietly.
"I have no idea," replied Mike. "I always
keep the password list in my wallet. No one
else has ever seen it. It's a complete mystery."
"No!" shouted Mr Williams. "The mystery is
why I gave you a job. First the virus and
now this. Well, you can start looking for
a new job. You're sacked!"
Mike left the bank without a word. He didn't
look at anyone. He knew that it was his fault.
Belinda's voice broke the silence. "Oh, Mr
Williams, what are we going to do?" Before
he could answer, the computer displayed a
new message:
E-mail arriving for Henry Williams
CHAPTER THREE
Are You Ready to Play, Henry?
Mr Williams turned to the bank staff and said,
"Please, continue to work as normal. There
is nothing to worry about."
Everyone looked surprised. How could they
work without computers? It would be impossible.
No one moved and no one spoke. Mr Williams
repeated his message: "Back to work now, please.
Our clients will arrive soon and we must be
ready." As his staff slowly began to return
to work, the bank manager sat down in front
of the server. Belinda stood next to him.
Mr Williams looked at the screen. He was now
extremely worried. He hesitated for a moment.
Belinda thought he was in difficulty and she
wanted to help. "You have to click on the
e-mail icon in the comer of the screen," she
said. "I know, I know. I'm not completely
stupid!" her boss shouted. Some members of
staff looked at one another and smiled. Belinda
knew Mr Williams well. She knew that when
he was angry, as he was now, it was better
to say nothing. She watched silently as he
clicked on the icon. The mailbox appeared
and revealed the subject of the new message:
Are you ready to play, Henry Williams?
Yes, he was ready. He had no idea who had
sent the e-mail but he wanted an explanation
and an end to this situation. He opened the
message and the screen filled with words.
Hello Henry!
How are you today? Happy? Or maybe worried?
Or even angry! I haven't seen you for a long
time but I can tell you that I am very, very
annoyed with you. You are not my favorite
person. How many enemies do you have? AT least
one - me! I am going to make you pay for what
you did to me before. As you know, I have
entered your new and secure (ha! ha!) computer
system and guess what? It's MY system now.
It was so easy to discover the passwords.
You should be more careful, Henry. You don't
mind if I call you Henry, do you?
Mr Williams was definitely angry now, and
confused. He asked Belinda, "Who is this person?
What does he want? Or maybe it's a woman?
Why is he (or she) angry? I'm an honest and
respectable man and people like me - well,
most people. Isn't that true, Belinda?" He
turned to look at Belinda, hoping that she
would give him the answer he wanted to hear,
but she wasn't listening. She was reading
the rest of the message as it appeared...
I have changed all the passwords so now I
control everything in your bank. Be nice to
me or I will lock the door again - or perhaps
I'll do something much worse! But don't be
afraid; I know that you're an intelligent
(ha! ha!) man, Henry, so I am going to give
you a chance to save your precious bank. We
are going to play a game. If you win, the
bank will be saved. If you lose... the bank
will be destroyed! Do you like my idea? I
think it's great! It means that the fate of
the bank, your bank, is in your own hands.
So, Henry, my friend... are you ready to play?
CHAPTER FOUR
Don't Call the Police!
It was very noisy in the bank. Clients were
arriving and the staff had to tell them that
there was a problem with the computers. Some
clients left immediately, some were angry
and began to shout, others wanted to see the
manager. But Mr Williams had no time to speak
to anyone. He had a problem too. A big problem.
Two members of his staff had moved the server
to his office. It was much quieter in there
and he could think without anyone disturbing
him.
Belinda was sitting next to him. She was beginning
to panic and when she felt like that she couldn't
stop talking.
"What a horrible man. I'm sure it's a man.
He's so evil. What are you going to do, Mr
Williams? What a terrible situation! I want
to help you but I just don't know what to
do. Shall we call the police? I'm sure..."
Mr Williams couldn't concentrate. His secretary
was talking faster and faster.
"Belinda, why don't you go and make me a nice
cup of tea?"
Belinda smiled brightly and went out of the
office. A nice cup of tea was the solution
to all problems in her opinion.
So, undisturbed, Mr Williams was able to read
the final part of the mysterious e-mail.
This is the game: I will send you three puzzles,
one at a time. You must solve these puzzles
in just 24 hours.
That's plenty of time for an intelligent man
like you, Henry. You'll probably need to be
a computer expert to solve them, but you use
computers every day, don't you? (Ha! ha!)
If you fail to solve all three puzzles, I
will empty every bank account in your bank
from the smallest to the largest. all the
money will disappear and your bank will be
destroyed.
One final thing - DON'T call the police. That
would be very stupid. If you call the police,
I will know.
Remember that I can destroy your bank in a
few seconds. Don't risk it, Henry.
Do you think this is all a joke? I want to
show you that I am very serious. Henry, do
you know how much money you have in your bank
account? Are you sure?
Why don't you check? I think you'll be surprised!
Now I am going to give your staff access to
the computers so the bank can function as
normal. You see, I'm not so evil, but remember
that I can switch off the computers or change
anything at any time.
Bye for now, but don't worry... I'll be back
soon.
Mr Williams sat back in his chair. He had
a bad headache. Things were not improving.
He was thinking about what to do when he heard
shouts of joy coming from the bank staff downstairs.
The door opened and Belinda came in with the
tea. "The computers are working again, Mr
Williams. Isn't that wonderful? Everything
is back to normal. Maybe the e-mail was just
a joke."
"Well, we'll know in a moment, Belinda," he
replied. There were two things that Mr Williams
could do on a computer - use e-mail and access
his own bank account. Why did the mystery
hacker tell him to check his account? He put
in his password and then his account number
and waited. After a few seconds the information
he wanted appeared on the screen...
CHAPTER FIVE
Puzzle Number One
Mr Williams stared at the computer screen,
horrified. His hank account was empty! The
bank manager quickly closed the page but Belinda
had already seen it. She dropped her cup of
tea and began to cry. Before Henry Williams
could say a word, another message appeared
on the screen.
E-mail arriving for Henry Williams Puzzle
Number One
Mr Williams clicked to open the message and
looked at the first puzzle. There were just
a few words and lots of strange symbols and
abbreviations.
It's 9.15 and time to play!
WU Henry? I C that UR : - ( Y?
U can't C me U R : - ( but I am >-(
IMO U R >:-C OR PRHPS <:-O
TAFN I'll BBL
EOM HAND (LOL)
Henry, do you like the first puzzle? Isn't
it cool? Cool and wicked. The clock has started
to tick. Hurry, hurry, hurry! BFN :-)
Mr Williams didn't understand anything. He
looked at Belinda, who was still crying. "Belinda,
please, stop crying for just one minute and
call Mike. Tell him to come here at once.
We need his help."
She looked at him in amazement and replied,
"But Mr Williams, you sacked Mike about an
hour ago. Don't you remember?"
Yes, now he did remember. There was no one
to help him.
His headache was getting worse. He couldn't
think. Then Belinda's voice came from behind
his chair. "Why don't you call your son, Robbie?
He's very good with computers, isn't he?"
Mr Williams got up and hugged her. "Yes! Belinda,
you're fantastic. Why didn't I think of that?"
It was a school holiday so Robbie would be
in his bedroom, playing on the computer and
listening to music but definitely not studying.
It was rare to see an open textbook in that
bedroom. There were two things Mr Williams
always associated with his son - his mobile
phone and his baseball cap. Mr Williams picked
up the phone and dialled his home number.
"Robbie? This is your father. Listen, I have
a problem with the computers at the bank.
Can you come and help me? I don't care if
you're fighting Lara Croft. This is really
important. Come as soon as possible please.
Thank you."
Mr Williams put down the phone and smiled.
"That was a great idea of yours, Belinda.
Robbie's a teenager so I'm sure he'll understand
all the strange symbols and abbreviations
in the puzzle."
Belinda blushed. "If I could make another
suggestion, Mr Williams? I think you can see
where the e-mail came from. Look at the top
of the page."
She was right. "Well done again, Belinda!
It was sent from the local library. So, our
mystery hacker thinks he's clever, does he?"
Mr Williams picked up the phone again. This
time he called the security office.
He explained the situation and told the head
of security to send two guards to the library
to find and arrest the hacker.
He was feeling a little bit better and Belinda
had stopped crying. Then he noticed something
appear on the computer screen. It was a clock
icon and an hourglass. Fifteen minutes had
already passed and the sand was falling.
The countdown had begun...
CHAPTER SIX
Trouble in the Library
It was only 9.30 but there were already a
lot of people inside the library; some were
looking for a bestseller on the bookshelves,
others were reading the newspapers or books
in the study area and a few were using the
photocopying machine and the computers. A
man was reading the messages on a big notice-board.
A mother and her child were going upstairs
to the children's section.
A librarian was pushing a trolley of books.
It was very quiet.
In the library anyone who had to speak, spoke
quietly. The librarians were there to help
anyone who had a problem.
This was the scene when Bill and Ben, the
two security guards from the bank, arrived
to investigate. They walked to the desk where
a librarian was helping an old lady.
"We believe that a criminal has sent an e-mail
message from a computer in this library and
we want to see the list of people who have
used the Internet this morning," said Bill.
The librarian calmly replied, "I'm sorry but
I'm busy now. If you would like to wait, I'll
be happy to help you as soon as I can."
Ben was not a patient man. "I don't think
you understand, madam. We are here to arrest
a criminal and we want to do it now!" he shouted.
The old lady, who was in front of Ben, was
angry and she hit both guards with her handbag.
"Hey, I was here first! You are very rude
men!" she said. The librarian tried to calm
everyone down. She said to the men, "Please
don't shout. This is a library. I'm afraid
we can only give information about the people
who use our library to the police. Are you
policemen?" Bill replied, "No, we're security
guards from the bank on London Road and we..."
The librarian interrupted him, "Then I can't
help you. Now, will you please leave the library?"
But the men didn't want to leave. Bill had
an idea. "Hey, Ben, maybe the hacker is still
using the computer. Let's go and see."
They ran to the computer area and began to
question the four people who were using the
computers. Now everyone in the library, including
the librarians, came to watch.
The guards were shouting and the people at
the computers were frightened.
Mr Page, the head librarian, came out of his
office to see why there was all this noise
in his usually quiet library. The scene he
saw shocked him. He walked to the computer
area and demanded to know what was happening.
About twenty people answered him at the same
time so it was impossible to understand. But
he soon realized that the two men dressed
in blue uniforms were causing the problem
and were disturbing everyone.
He shouted, "You two, get out of my library
now!" And with the help of some people in
the library, he pushed them to the door and
then out of the library and into the street.
"And don't come back!" yelled the old lady,
furiously. All the people in the library were
talking about what had just happened.
Nobody noticed a man who was hiding behind
the shelves. He was laughing...
CHAPTER SEVEN
Robbie the Hero
- Robbie Williams arrived at the bank a few
minutes after the phone conversation with
his father. He wasn't very happy. It was the
school holidays and he wanted to go out with
his friends but his mother told him at least
ten times a day to open a textbook and study.
Today he had wanted to buy a new football
scarf and a computer game but instead he had
to help his father at the bank! He went inside
and up the stairs to the office.
"Hey, Dad, what's up? I have to meet my friends
at the shopping centre at lunchtime. I'm going
to buy a new computer game. It's wicked. It's
called..." Mr Williams interrupted his son.
"Robbie, please, take those headphones off
and listen to me." He quickly explained the
problem of the hacker. Robbie couldn't believe
it.
"Bad luck, Dad. How can I help?"
Mr Williams showed him the first puzzle. Robbie
gave his father a big smile.
"Relax, Dad. This is so easy I can do it with
my eyes shut! I use these abbreviations every
day when I'm in a chat room or when I text
my friends on my mobile phone. I'll show you.
WU stands for 'What's up?' I C stands for
'I see.' And these symbols are called 'emoticons.'
They look like a face and they express the
way you feel. I can easily decode this message
for you." Robbie sat down, clicked on the
reply icon and wrote out the message:
What's up Henry? I see you are sad. Why? You
can't see me. You are sad but I am angry.
In my opinion you are surprised or perhaps
afraid. That's all for now. I'll be back later.
End Of Message Have a nice day (laughing out
loud) Bye for now!
"See? I told you it was easy. Now I'll click
on 'Send' and the message will go back to
the sender." Mr Williams thanked his son and
slowly he began to relax... but for how long?
It was now 10.15. Only one hour had passed.
Belinda came into the office and said to her
boss,
"The ATM is working again..." Mr Williams
smiled. "But," she added quickly, "it's giving
the customers too much money..."
Mr Williams tell back into his chair. Why
was life so difficult?
The security guards Bill and Ben knocked at
the door and came into his office. Did they
have some good news for him?
"Well?" he asked hopefully. "Did you find
him?"
Bill answered, "Not exactly, Mr Williams.
We tried but the people at the library were
very unfriendly."
"Yes," added Ben. "They didn't want to help
us and in the end they asked us to leave.
There was an old lady who..." Mr Williams
was angry.
"I'm not interested in the old lady. You obviously
didn't catch the hacker. You are both completely
incompetent. Now go back to your office before
I sack you."
His headache had returned, worse than ever.
Then his son said, "Dad, look. There's another
message from the hacker." He looked at Robbie
and then at Belinda. Then they all looked
at the screen...
CHAPTER EIGHT
My Name is Trentine
Hello Henry,
Well, that was an easy puzzle. I imagine someone
helped you - your son Robbie perhaps? He's
intelligent but your security guards are really
stupid.
They didn't see me at the library but I saw
them! Never mind! Maybe they'll have better
luck next time... Here's your second puzzle
- impossible, I think. Have fun! BFN
Puzzle Number Two
My name is TRENTINE - I am power and knowledge.
These are my friends:
Berrows limea rodlw ediw bew thac moro frus
Henry Williams wasn't very worried. He had
his secret weapon - Robbie!
"You can solve this puzzle too, can't you,
Robbie?" he asked. Then he saw his son's face.
"Dad, I'm really sorry but I don't understand
it. But, look - the hacker sent it from the
Internet Cafe in the city centre."
Belinda was crying again. Mr Williams phoned
the security office for the second time that
day and told Bill and Ben to go to the Internet
Cafe to find the hacker. As soon as he put
down the phone, a bank teller came into his
office with more bad news.
"A customer has just told me that the bank's
website is advertising a special offer - a
credit card with 0% interest. Is it true?"
he asked.
"Of course it isn't!" yelled Mr Williams.
"Don't give any new credit cards to any of
our customers! Now go back to work!"
The teller disappeared. The minutes became
hours and Mr Williams became more and more
agitated. Robbie continued to look at the
puzzle perplexed, and Belinda continued to
cry. Suddenly Robbie had an idea. "I know
what to do!" he shouted.
His father jumped up. "Have you solved the
puzzle?'" he asked.
"No, but I bet my friend Joe can help us.
I'll send him a text message on his mobile."
Mr Williams sat down again while Robbie sent
the message.
Come to Bank Now. Rob
When Joe arrived it was already 5 o'clock.
"What's up, Robbie?" he asked. Then he saw
Belinda, who smiled at him. He smiled back.
Wow! She was beautiful! He immediately fell
in love with her.
"Joe, listen to me," said Robbie. He explained
about the hacker and showed Joe the second
puzzle. Joe didn't want to take his eyes off
Belinda but he had to look at the computer
screen. Mr Williams was beginning to panic.
"Hurry, boys. There isn't much time left."
"Take it easy, Mr W. We can solve this. Come
on, Robbie. Let's do it."
After four long hours they solved the puzzle.
"So, who is Trentine?" asked Mr Williams.
"The Internet," replied Joe.
"Of course," said Robbie. "And the friends
are all words connected with the Internet
- browser, e-mail, world wide web, chat room
and..."
"Surf," said Belinda happily.
Joe looked at her. "Belinda, you are so cool.
You're the perfect girl tor me," he said as
he clicked on the "Send" icon.
Mr Williams looked at them and said to himself:
"What are they talking about? I think I'm
getting old."
It was nine o'clock. The hourglass was half-empty
but they had solved the puzzle in time. Mr
Williams was very relieved. The situation
was improving at last. At that moment the
telephone rang. When Mr Williams answered
he heard a voice say: "Good evening. This
is the police..."
CHAPTER NINE
A Surprise for Henry
Mr Williams put down the phone. He said, "That
was the police. It seems that Bill and Ben
created a disturbance at the Internet Cafe
and they have been arrested. They didn't catch
the hacker, of course. Why doesn't that surprise
me? Well, they can stay at the police station
until we find the hacker." There was no reply
from the others. Robbie was sending a text
message on his mobile phone to his friends
to say why he hadn't met them that afternoon.
Joe was talking to Belinda.
"Will you go out with me tonight, Belinda?
There's a great hamburger place near here."
Belinda smiled at him.
"But you're only 15, Joe. I'm too old for
you."
"I'm very mature for my age," he replied quickly.
"Come on! We'll have a fantastic time. I'll
pay and..." Their conversation was interrupted
by the hacker.
Congratulations, Henry. You've solved the
second Puzzle. I suppose Robbie helped you
again. It's a pity those security guards aren't
as intelligent as your son. They failed again,
didn't they? Henry, there's still another
puzzle to solve. If you solve it, you will
discover my identity. I'll send the Message
later. First, you need to relax and... cool
down. Are you ready for a surprise?
BFN
"A surprise. What does that mean, Mr Williams'"
asked Belinda.
"I have no idea but I'm sure we'll soon find
out," replied her boss.
All the staff had gone home at 5 o'clock as
usual. The offices were silent. He was suddenly
very tired. His eyes began to close...
He was on holiday in the Caribbean. He was
on the beach. It was hot and sunny. There
were no clouds in the sky. It was too hot
so he went swimming in the sea to cool down.
He was wet, very wet... Mr Williams woke up.
He was wet! Was it raining in his office?
He heard Belinda's voice:
"Mr Williams, what's happening? I'm all wet.
Where is the water coming from? My hair and
clothes are ruined!"
Mr Williams answered, "This is our surprise,
Belinda. Our friend the hacker has started
the sprinkler system. Very funny. Let's get
out of here."
They all ran out of the office and went downstairs.
Joe tried to console Belinda, and Robbie wanted
to know if he could go home.
"Please, Dad. It's late and I want to watch
TV tonight."
"Not yet," replied his father. "We still have
another puzzle to solve."
"What do you mean 'we,' Dad? You haven't done
anything yet," replied his son sarcastically.
Mr Williams looked at his son but he knew
that Robbie was right. The boys had solved
the first two puzzles.
In the distance they heard
a siren. Was it the police? Mr Williams and
Robbie went to the doors of the bank. Slowly
Mr Williams opened the door...
CHAPTER TEN
Where's the Fire?
Mr Williams opened the door and three firemen
ran into the hank.
"OK, where's the fire?" they said. Mr Williams
was very confused.
"What do you mean, 'fire'? There's no fire
here. I think you've made a mistake."
The firemen were not convinced. "Mr Williams,
have you forgotten that the bank's sprinkler
system is connected to the alarm at the tire
station? The sprinklers started, the alarm
sounded and we came here to put out the fire.
Now, where is it?" This time Robbie spoke.
"There is no fire. The sprinklers started
because there must be a problem with the system."
"Yes," added Mr Williams. "I'm so sorry that
you've come here for nothing."
"Well, I must say I can't see any fire. We'll
come back tomorrow morning to check if there's
some kind of problem with the sprinklers,"
the fireman replied. "You're working very
late tonight, Mr Williams," he added.
"Yes, we have a lot to do," came the tired
reply. When they had gone, Mr Williams told
Belinda that she could go home. He opened
the door for her and Robbie tried to go out
at the same time. His father pulled him back.
"I need you here," he said. "Let's go back
to the office."
"Oh, Dad," Robbie protested but he followed
his father upstairs.
It was four o'clock in the morning when the
final puzzle arrived. Robbie and Joe were
sleeping on the floor. They had been too tired
to stay awake. Henry Williams forced himself
to look at the computer screen.
Hi, Henry. Here's the final puzzle.
You have to read these sentences about a famous
person and find the four words.
Puzzle Number Three
The first word is his first but it's your
second. The second word is a barrier but also
a way to enter. The third word is the baby,
or is it a monster? The fourth word is where
it all began.
Now take the first letter of each word, then
add the letters I and A. You now have six
letters and in these letters you will find
my name.
BFN
It was incredible. A few hours ago everything
was fine. Now someone wanted to destroy his
bank and his life. Why? He touched Robbie
gently and said, "Robbie, wake up! The last
puzzle has arrived. We've only got a few hours
to solve it." There was no response from his
son, who continued to sleep. Mr Williams tried
to wake Joe, but Joe simply mumbled in his
sleep, "Belinda, do you want a hamburger or
a cheeseburger?" Mr Williams sat with his
head in his hands. The boys were sleeping
and he couldn't wake them. What was he going
to do? He looked at the clock again - it was
already four thirty! Then another e-mail arrived.
Come on, Henry. Admit it. You've lost.
Soon I will start to empty the bank accounts.
Who shall I choose first? Perhaps the police
station? OR maybe I'll choose Mrs Miller,
the poor old lady from the library. No, I
think I'll start with the Town Council - it's
the end of the month and wages must be paid.
Was the hacker right? Was this the end...?
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Is It the End?
At 8.30 Mr Williams opened his eyes. For a
moment he didn't remember the events of the
previous day. Then slowly his mind formed
a picture of a computer hacker and some strange
puzzles. He wondered if he had dreamt it all.
Then he saw Robbie and Joe, who were still
asleep on the floor and he saw the computer
screen. The final puzzle was still there and
the hourglass was almost empty. It wasn't
a nightmare; it was real!
The door of the office opened and Belinda
came in. "Oh, Mr Williams. Have you been here
all night? And poor Robbie and Joe too. Did
you find the solution to the last puzzle?"
She saw his expression and already knew the
answer. "I'll make you a nice cup of tea and
you'll soon feel better," she said.
There were only thirty minutes left. Mr Williams
was angry with himself. He felt responsible
for everything. His bank was in danger and
he couldn't save it. He tried to wake Robbie
again but it was difficult to wake his teenage
son before midday! Belinda returned with the
tea. Mr Williams drank three cups.
He looked out of his window. The bank teller
were arriving for another day's work - maybe
the last day. What could he tell them? In
desperation he sat down in front of the computer
again. "Belinda, if we win, I promise that
I will learn about computers and become an
expert. My son is only 15 and he knows much
more than me. I'm living in the past and I
have to change."
"That's a wonderful idea, Mr Williams. And
of course, I'll help you as much as possible.
I know a lot of things now and..."
She didn't finish her sentence because Mr
Williams shouted so loudly that Robbie and
Joe woke up. "That's it! I've found the solution!
I know the answer to the puzzle!"
Robbie and Joe got up right away. They looked
at one another and then at Mr Williams. Robbie
said hesitantly, "Are you sure Dad? It looks
impossible to me."
"Yes, of course I'm sure. I've done it. Now,
first I click on the reply icon, right? And
then I write the answers. The first word is
Bill - it's the man's first name and the abbreviation
of my second name, Williams. The second word
is gate. It's a barrier and a way to enter."
"So the man is Bill Gates," said Joe.
"Exactly," replied Mr Williams. "The third
word is Microsoft - his baby, his creation,
but also a monster in the opinion of some
people. And the last word is Seattle. That's
where Bill Gates lives and where he started
Microsoft, the beginning."
"That's brilliant Dad. Well done!" said Robbie.
"Now," continued Mr Williams, "if we take
the first letter of each word we have B, G,
M, and S. We have to add two more letters
- I and A - and these six letters should spell
the name of the hacker." Everyone looked at
the six letters:
B G M S I A
They tried to see a name but they could only
see words like big and bags but no names.
Then suddenly Mr Williams jumped up and yelled,
"Yes! Yes! I know the name of the hacker..."
CHAPTER TWELVE
A Holiday for Someone
"Sam Gib," said Mr Williams. "I don't believe
it. But why does he hate me?"
"Maybe because you sacked him two weeks ago,"
suggested Belinda. Robbie asked, "Who's Sam
Gib?" Mr Williams explained, "He used to work
here at the bank. In the beginning he was
a good bank teller. Then he started to arrive
late for work every day. Instead of working
he used to surf the net and log on to chat
rooms. He spent hours talking to people all
over the world. So I sacked him. But wait
a minute. If he left two weeks ago, how did
he know the new computer passwords?"
Belinda had the answer to his question.
"He came back to the bank a few days ago to
empty his desk. I think you were in a meeting.
I remember that he went to Mike's office and
stayed there for a long time. I thought he
was talking to Mike, but now I think about
it Mike wasn't there all the time. Anyway,
Mr Williams, you're a hero. You've saved the
bank!"
"Yes, and there are only two minutes left.
Look, it's 9.13," said Joe.
They all looked at the computer screen. Suddenly
Robbie said, "Dad, did you remember to click
on the 'send' icon to return the message to
the hacker, I mean, Sam Gib?"
"Oh, no! Quickly, click, CLICK before it's
too late!" shouted Mr Williams. Four hands
tried to operate the mouse but in the confusion
it fell on the floor. Finally Robbie picked
up the mouse, clicked and the message disappeared.
For a moment nobody spoke. Then they all began
laughing and hugging each another.
"We've won! We've won, you've won, Dad," said
Robbie while Joe hugged Belinda again. Mr
Williams went downstairs to give the good
news to the staff, who also laughed and applauded
their boss. When Mr Williams returned to his
office he picked up the phone.
"Now I can call the police and tell them everything
and they can go to Sam's house and arrest
him." But before he could do it, another e-mail
arrived.
Hello Henry
Now you know who I am. Congratulations!
Did you enjoy playing my game?
When you sacked me I wanted my revenge so
I sent the virus that infected the bank's
computers. But it wasn't enough. You installed
a new computer system so I came to visit Mike
and saw the new passwords on his desk. It
was so easy. You really need to improve security
at the bank. Maybe I can help you?
But Henry, I still have a surprise for you...
This time Mr Williams went white.
"Oh please no! Not another puzzle!" he cried.
I think I need a holiday. As you booked your
holiday to the Caribbean on the net, I changed
the address and the tickets arrived at my
house instead of your house yesterday. I also
changed the date of the holiday and I'm leaving
at 10.00 today. I'm sending this message from
the airport on my new laptop. To show you
that I am a kind person, I have returned all
the money to your bank account.
Thanks for the holiday. Maybe we can play
another game when I come back...