CHAPTER ONE
Failure and Success
The older Monsieur Bovary, Monsieur
Charles Denis Bartholome Bovary,
had been a good-looking man when younger,
with a big moustache and rings on his fingers.
He was not, however, an impressive man,
and although he wore expensive clothes,
he always looked like an uncomfortable mixture
of a military man and a cheap shopkeeper. His
good looks and ability to sell himself did,
nevertheless, win him a wife with a good income.
After he was safely married, he lived for two or
three years on her money. He ate and drank well,
and spent his days lying in bed till midday,
smoking his pipe and never coming home
till the theatres and cafes closed.
When his father-in-law died, the old man
left very little money to his daughter.
Disappointed, Monsieur Bovary tried to start a
textile business, but lost a lot of money and
finally retired into the country with the idea
of showing the people there how to run a farm.
However, he knew as little about agriculture as he
did about textiles. He rode his horses instead of
making them work, ate the fattest chickens instead
of selling them, and cleaned his shooting-boots
with his own best bacon-fat. He soon discovered
that he had little chance of making a fortune.
Around this time he found a place on the
borders of Caux and Picardy, half farm,
half private house, which he could rent for two
hundred francs a year. He took it and there,
an angry, disappointed man, at war with the rest
of the world, he shut himself up at the age of
forty-five. He said that he was disgusted with
other people and wanted only to live by himself.
At the beginning, his wife had
loved him above all others,
but this only seemed to add to his dislike of
the world and he never had a kind word for her.
She had been cheerful, kind-hearted
and friendly, but as she grew older,
in the same way that good wine turns into
vinegar, she became bad-tempered and bad company.
She was a hard worker, though, unlike her
husband. She was always on her feet, always busy,
hurrying to see the lawyers, knowing exactly
when the next bills had to be paid. Indoors
she was always working: sewing, washing, keeping
an eye on the men and paying them their wages.
Her lord and master, paying no attention to what
was going on around him, sat smoking by the fire.
When the first Madame Bovary had a
child, it became the centre of her
world. The child's father, however, would
have been happy to let him go without shoes.
He said that it would be more natural not to
give him clothes and to let him run around
like a young animal. In contrast to his wife's
ideas, he thought a boy would grow up to be a
better man if he undressed in the cold, learned to
drink alcohol and laughed at the village priest.
The child, a gentle little thing, made
little progress in this kind of education.
His mother always kept him close to her; she
cut out pictures for him from the newspaper
and made up countless stories. In loving her son,
she was looking for something to make up for the
loneliness of her life. She dreamed he would be
famous. She could see him as a tall, handsome,
clever man, high up in the government service.
She taught him to read, and to sing - while she
played on her old piano. Monsieur Bovary said this
was all a waste of time. How were they ever going
to afford to educate him for a government job, or
help him start in business? Madame Bovary bit her
lip and did not argue with her husband, and the
child was allowed to run wild in the village.
He went around with the farm workers, scared
the birds by throwing stones at them, looked
for wild fruit, helped in the fields, wandered
through the woods and played with other children.
On Saints' days, he helped
ring the bells in the church,
and he loved to hang on to the big rope and
feel himself carried up as it rose in the air.
And he grew as strong as a young oak
tree, with big hands and red cheeks.
When he reached the age of twelve, his
mother managed to arrange for him to begin
his studies with the priest, but the lessons were
so short and badly organized that they did not do
him much good. Sometimes it would be hot and the
child would grow tired, and before long the old
man would be sleeping with his mouth wide open. At
other times the priest would see Charles playing
with his friends and would call him over to test
his Latin verbs. But then, perhaps, it would begin
to rain, or someone they knew would come along,
and lessons would be over for that day. The priest
always had a good word for his pupil, though, and
said that the young man had a very good memory.
By the time young Charles was thirteen, even
his father saw that something must be done,
and Charles left his unhappy home to spend
three unhappy years in the College at Rouen.
He wrote to his mother every
week; he did his homework.
He never did very well in his studies, but he
never failed altogether. At the end of three
years, his mother took him away from the College,
with the plan that he should study medicine.
She got him a room on the fourth floor of a house
overlooking a little river. She made arrangements
for his meals, found some bits of furniture - a
table and a couple of chairs and an old bed - and
made sure there was plenty of firewood to keep
her poor boy warm. After a week of preparations
she went back home, asking him over and over
again to look after himself and to study hard.
The list of lectures which he read at the
beginning of the term made his head spin.
There were lectures on subjects he had never
heard of, with names he could not even pronounce.
He listened as hard as he could, but he could not
understand what the lecturers were talking about.
However, he attended every lecture
and filled notebook after notebook.
He got through his work like a horse that is
used to turn a mill-wheel, going round and round
in the same place with his eyes covered, never
knowing what he was doing or where he was going.
Charles failed his medical examinations the
first time - the course was too difficult for
him. But his mother still believed in him,
and made his father pay for one more year.
This time Charles managed to pass
and his mother began to plan again.
First he must have somewhere to
work, and then he must have a wife.
The first problem was solved when the old
doctor in Tostes, a small town near Rouen, died.
Charles became the next doctor. Then his
mother found a 45-year-old widow in Dieppe,
with an income of twelve hundred francs a year.
Though she was ugly and bad-tempered (and
twenty-five years older than Charles),
her income made her attractive and Charles
thought the marriage would make his life better.
He thought he would now have freedom and money
to spend. He was wrong. His wife was in charge.
She told him what to say, and what not to say.
She opened his letters, watched his movements
and, when women patients were in the
surgery, she listened from the next room.
At night, when Charles came to bed, she put her
long bony arms round his neck and told him all her
troubles. He did not love her, he loved someone
else. Yes, she knew she would always be unhappy.
And she always ended by asking him for some
medicine - and for a little more love.
CHAPTER TWO
Mademoiselle Emma
One night, Charles received a letter asking him
to come at once to a farm at Les Bertaux where the
farmer had broken his leg. The night was dark
and the farm was twenty-five kilometres away,
but the farmer was a rich man and Charles was
still building up his business. So at four o'clock
in the morning, Dr Bovary set out. A child was
waiting at an open gate as he approached the farm.
'Are you the doctor?' he asked.
As Charles rode along, he learned from
the boy that Monsieur Rouault had broken
his leg the night before. He also learned
that he had lost his wife two years ago,
and had no one with him now except for his
daughter, who looked after the house for him.
Mademoiselle Emma, the farmer's daughter, came
to the door and showed him into the kitchen.
A fire was burning and the men's dinner
was cooking in big polished pans.
Charles went upstairs to see the farmer.
The broken leg was a simple problem
and Charles asked the servant and the
young woman to help with the patient.
As they tied up the farmer's leg, Charles was
surprised to see how white her nails were.
Her hands, however, were not beautiful
- perhaps a little too red. She herself
was too tall, and she did not have the kind
of soft figure Charles liked. Her good point
was her eyes. They were dark, almost black,
and she looked at you honestly and fearlessly.
As soon as he had finished looking after
his patient, the doctor was invited by
Monsieur Rouault to eat before he left. Charles
went down into the room below, where two places
had been laid with shining silver on a small
table and Mademoiselle Emma was waiting for him.
A smell of flowers and clean
clothes came from a cupboard
opposite the window and on the floor, in
the corner, stood a few bags of wheat.
Someone had hung a drawing of a Greek
god in the middle of one of the walls.
It was in an attractive frame, and written at
the bottom were the words 'To my dear Father'.
They began by talking about Monsieur
Rouault, and went on to discuss the
weather and the cold winter. Mademoiselle
Emma did not like the country very much,
especially now she had almost all the
responsibility of the farm on her shoulders.
When Charles, who had been upstairs to say goodbye
to the farmer, came back into the dining room,
he found her standing by the window looking
out into the garden. She turned round.
'Are you looking for something?' she asked.
'Yes, I'm trying to find my
riding-whip,' he replied,
and he began to look behind
the doors and under the chairs.
Mademoiselle Emma found it between the bags of
wheat and the wall, and Charles went over to help.
As he bent down, he felt the young woman's
back rubbing against his chest. She stood up,
blushing, and, looking at him over
her shoulder, handed him his whip.
Instead of going back to Les Bertaux three days
later, as he said he would, he returned the next
day, and he then went to the farm twice a week.
After forty-six days, Monsieur Rouault could move
around without help, and people began to say
what an excellent doctor Monsieur Bovary was.
Pere Rouault said the very best doctors in Yvetot
or Rouen itself could not have treated him better.
Charles did not ask himself why
he liked going to Les Bertaux.
If he had thought about it he would have
said to himself that it was a serious case,
or he expected to earn a good fee. But was that
really the reason why these visits to the farm
were so pleasant? On days when he was visiting,
he got up early and rode to the farm as quickly
as he could, only stopping to clean his boots and
to put on his black gloves before going into the
house. He liked to ride into the yard, and see
the farm boys as they came forward to meet him.
He liked the house, and Monsieur Rouault, who
held his hand and said he had saved his life;
he liked the sound of Mademoiselle Emma's wooden
shoes on the clean stone floor of the kitchen.
When he left, she always came
with him to the top of the steps,
and would wait with him until
the boys brought his horse.
One day, at the end of the winter, it
started to rain as he was leaving the house.
She went back inside for an umbrella and put it
up. It was a silk one, and it caught the sunlight,
reflecting little coloured patches of
light on to the whiteness of her skin.
She smiled at him, and you could hear
the sound of the rain drops as they fell,
one by one, on to the tight surface of the silk.
When Charles first began his visits to Les
Bertaux, his wife always asked about his patient.
But when she learned that the farmer's daughter
had been to school and had learned dancing,
geography and drawing, and could play the piano,
her interest changed to anger and dislike.
At first she made unfriendly remarks about
Mademoiselle Rouault, but Charles ignored them
because he did not want an argument. So at last
she told him to his face what she thought of him,
and he did not know what to reply.
Why did he keep going to Les Bertaux?
Monsieur Rouault was well again
now and he had not paid his bill.
Ah, she knew all about it! There was someone
else there, someone who was a good talker,
someone who was well educated and clever.
That was what he liked - young, pretty ladies!
So Charles agreed to stop his visits to
Les Bertaux, but now that he could not see
Mademoiselle Emma he decided he could love her.
His wife was so unattractive, just skin and bone.
She wore the same black clothes and gray
stockings, the same ugly shoes all year round.
So if he could not see the farmer's
daughter any more, he would dream of her!
This unhappy situation lasted for several
months until, one fine day in the early spring,
the lawyer who had looked after Madame Bovary's
affairs left town with all his clients' money.
She still had a share in a ship
that was worth six thousand francs,
and her house in Dieppe, but there was nothing
left of that fortune she had been so proud of.
And when her financial affairs
were looked into more carefully,
Charles's father found out that the house in
Dieppe was mortgaged and her share in the vessel
was not worth more than two hundred francs. She
had lied, the good lady! Monsieur Bovary senior
was so angry that he took up a chair
and smashed it on the stone floor,
and he told his wife she had ruined her son
by making him marry an old woman like that.
They came to Tostes to tell Charles's
rich wife what they thought of her.
There was a terrible argument. Heloise begged
her husband to defend her against his parents,
and Charles did his best, but the old people
were still angry when they left the house.
The damage had been done. A week later, as
she was hanging out the washing in the yard,
Heloise Bovary found that she was spitting blood.
The next day, while Charles had his back to her,
opening the curtains, she cried out, 'Oh God!'
and fell to the floor. She was dead! How amazing!
When the funeral was over,
Charles returned to the house.
He went up into the bedroom and saw her
dress hanging up at the foot of the bed. He
stayed there until it was dark, lost in sorrowful
thought. After all, perhaps she had loved him.
CHAPTER THREE
A New Wife
One morning Pere Rouault came to pay Charles
for his treatment, and to say how sorry he was
to hear about his wife's death. Seeing how unhappy
Charles looked, he said, 'You must make an effort,
Monsieur Bovary; you will be happy again one day.
Come and see us. My daughter asks about you and
says that you are forgetting her. Spring will
soon be here. Come and shoot a rabbit or two!'
Charles took his advice. He
went back to Les Bertaux,
and found everything there just the same as
before. The apple trees were already in flower,
and Pere Rouault did his best to make the doctor
feel comfortable. He even told him a few stories,
and Charles was surprised to find himself
laughing. When he remembered his wife
he became serious again, but then the coffee
came in and he thought no more about her.
Back home, he also thought of her less
and less as he got used to living alone.
He was free now to have his meals when he liked,
he could go out and come in without having to
give explanations, and when he was very tired
he could stretch out his arms and legs in bed as
far as he liked. He gave himself little treats,
let himself feel self-pity and let people be
nice to him. Moreover, his wife's death had been
rather good for him professionally because,
for a whole month, people had been saying,
'Poor young man! What bad luck!' So his name
had been heard and his practice had increased
and he could go to Les Bertaux whenever he wanted
to. He was strangely happy and, looking at himself
in the mirror as he brushed his moustache,
he thought he had become better-looking.
He arrived at the farm one day at about three
o'clock when everyone was out in the fields.
He went into the kitchen, but did not see Emma at
first. The sunlight shone on the kitchen floor in
long narrow bars, reflecting on the ceiling. Flies
on the table crawled up the glasses that had not
been washed, or drowned in the cider in the bottom
of a jug. Between the window and the fireplace
Emma sat sewing. She had no scarf around her neck,
and he could see the fine hairs on her shoulders.
Like all country people, she offered him a drink.
He said no at first, but at last, with a laugh,
she persuaded him to have a glass with her. She
went to the cupboard and brought out the bottle,
took down two small glasses, filled one, poured
two or three drops into the other and, tapping it
against the doctor's, put it to her lips. As it
was nearly empty, she leaned back to drink and,
with her head back, she began to laugh because
she could not taste anything. At the same time,
she tried to catch some of the drops from the
bottom of the glass with the tip of her tongue.
Then she sat down and took up her work again
- a white cotton sock which she was repairing.
She worked with her head bent forward. She did
not talk, nor did Charles. As he watched her,
the only sound he could hear was the excitement
of a hen that had laid an egg in the yard outside.
After some time, Emma started to talk to him.
She had been complaining ever since the spring
about feeling dizzy; she wondered whether
bathing in the sea would do her any good.
She began to talk about her convent
school, and Charles about his college days.
They went upstairs to her room, where she showed
him her old music books and the prizes she had
won. And she went on to speak of her mother,
and even pointed out the bed in the garden
where she gathered flowers on the first Friday
in every month, to lay on her mothers grave.
She said she would like to live in town in
the winter, although perhaps the long days
made the country even more boring in the
summer; and according to what she was saying,
her voice was clear and strong, musical or almost
a whisper, as if she were speaking to herself.
That night, as he was riding home, Charles
thought about the different things she had said,
trying to remember them exactly
to discover what they meant,
so that he might understand how her
life had been before he met her.
Then he began to wonder how she would become
if she married - and whom she would marry.
Unfortunately, old Rouault was apparently
very wealthy, and she herself... so beautiful!
But the thought kept coming to him: 'The doctor
wants a wife. Yes, the doctor wants a wife.'
That night he could not sleep. He got up, took a
drink from the water-jug and opened his window.
The sky was filled with stars, a warm
breeze was blowing and, a long way off,
some dogs were barking. He turned his head
towards Les Bertaux. Thinking that, after all,
he had nothing to lose by it, Charles made up his
mind to ask her to marry him. But every time he
was alone with her, the fear of being unable to
find the right words left him unable to speak.
In fact Pere Rouault would have been
happy to see his daughter married,
especially as she was very little use in the
house. He made excuses for her, telling himself
that she had too much intelligence for the farming
life. When, therefore, he noticed that Charles
blushed each time he was near his daughter, and
that the young man was clearly interested in her,
he gave the matter some thought. Although
Charles was not the sort of man he would have
chosen for a son-in-law, he was well educated
and a hard worker, and would not ask him for
too much money to take his daughter off his
hands. This mattered, as Monsieur Rouault had
debts with most of his suppliers and had
just had to sell a large amount of land.
'If he asks me,' he said to
himself, 'he can have her.'
A little later, Charles came to spend three
days at Les Bertaux. The time went quickly,
and he never seemed to find
the right moment to speak.
As he was leaving, Monsieur Rouault
came out to see him on his way.
They had reached a bend in the road and were
preparing to say goodbye. It was now or never.
Charles gave himself until the corner of the
field and at last, when they had passed it,
he said, almost in a whisper, 'Monsieur Rouault,
there is something I want to say to you.'
They stopped. Charles could not speak.
'Come on then, out with it! Do you
think I don't know what it's all about?'
said the farmer, laughing quietly.
'Pere Rouault... Pere Rouault...'
'Well,' the farmer went on,
'there's nothing I would like better. But,
though I am sure my little girl will agree,
we must put the question to her. You go on; I'll
go back to the farm. If it's yes, there'll be no
need for you to come back... She'll need some time
to get used to the idea! But so you can be sure,
I'll open the window in the front bedroom.
You'll be able to see it from the back here.'
And with these words he returned to the house.
Charles tied his horse to a tree. He hurried
back to take up his position, and waited.
Half an hour went by, then nineteen more
minutes, which he timed by his watch. Suddenly
something banged against the wall. The
window was open. She had accepted him!
Next day, by nine o'clock, he was at the farm.
Emma blushed when he came in,
but tried to laugh a little, too.
Pere Rouault took his son-in-law in his arms. Then
they began to talk about the arrangements. They
had plenty of time before them, since the wedding
could not take place until at least twelve months
after the death of Charles's first wife, and
that meant the spring of the following year.
The wedding dinner was a grand affair. Forty-three
people sat down at the table and remained there
for sixteen hours, and the party which followed
went on for several days. For most of the guests
it was a wedding to remember. The only
person who did not enter the spirit of things
seemed to be Madame Bovary senior, who sat through
the whole event with a sour look on her face.
No one had asked her about the bride's dress, or
the arrangements for the party. She went to bed
early. Her husband, however, did not follow
her, but sent into Saint-Victor for cigars.
He sat with the men and smoked until the morning,
drinking and laughing until the sun rose.
On the day of the wedding, Charles had not been a
great success; he was neither a confident speaker
nor a great teller of jokes. Next day, however,
he seemed a different man. While Emma did not
give the smallest idea of what she thought about
it all, Charles was completely changed. He called
her his wife, his dear, kept asking where she
was, looked for her everywhere and frequently
took her out into the yard, where he was seen
among the trees with his arm round her waist.
Two days after the wedding,
the newly married couple left.
Charles could not be away
from his practice any longer.
Monsieur Rouault sent them home in his carriage,
and went with them himself as far as Vassonville.
There he kissed his daughter goodbye, and started
for home again on foot. When he had gone about
a hundred metres he stopped and looked back
at the carriage disappearing down the road.
Then he thought of his own wedding. Like
Charles, he, too, had been happy when he
took his wife from her father's house, back to his
own. She had ridden behind him through the snow;
it was near Christmas and the country all white.
One of her arms held on to him, and over the other
she carried her basket. When he turned his head
he saw close by him, just above his shoulder, her
little smiling face. To warm her fingers she had
pushed them, from time to time, inside his jacket.
How far away it seemed now. He looked back again,
and there was nothing to be seen along the
road. He felt as sad as an empty house.
Monsieur and Madame Charles arrived
at Tostes at about six o'clock.
The neighbours came to their windows to
take a look at the doctor's new wife.
The old servant came to meet them and made
excuses for the dinner not being ready,
and suggested that, for the moment, Madame
should come in and look around the house.
CHAPTER FOUR
Two Worlds
The front of the house looked straight on to
the street. Hanging up behind the front door
were the doctor's coat, a belt, a black leather
cap and, on the floor in the corner, a pair of
boots covered with dried mud. To the right was
the sitting room, where meals were also eaten.
White cotton curtains with a red
border were hung along the windows,
and above the fireplace there was a splendid clock
and a head of Hippocrates. On the other side of
the passage was Charles's consulting room, a
little box of a place about two metres wide
with a table, three ordinary chairs
and one armchair. A set of books,
the Dictionary of Medical Science, took up
almost all the six shelves of the bookcase;
they had been owned by many earlier doctors in
Tostes, but never read. The smell of cooking
would come in through the thin wall during
consultations, and anyone in the kitchen could
hear the patients coughing and talking to the
doctor as clearly as if they were in the room.
The long, narrow garden ran down to the fields.
Fruit trees grew along the stone walls and four
flower beds, planted with weak-looking roses,
were set around a square area which was
used for vegetables. At the far end,
under some low trees, there was a small white
statue of a priest reading a prayer book.
Emma went up to see the bedrooms. There was
no furniture in the first one but the second,
their bedroom, contained their new bed with its
red curtains. There was a box made of seashells on
a chest of drawers and on the desk, by the window,
stood a glass bottle with a bunch of dried flowers
tied with white ribbon. They were the
flowers from his first wife's wedding.
Charles saw her looking at them, and took them
out of the room. Sitting in an armchair, while her
maid unpacked her things, Emma thought about her
own wedding flowers, lying in one of the boxes,
and she wondered what would
happen to them if she died young.
Charles was a happy man now. In bed in the
morning, with her head on the pillow beside him,
he would look at the sunlight on her cheek
and at her beautiful eyes when she woke.
He could lose himself in those eyes, looking
into them until he saw a tiny picture of himself,
his nightcap on his head and the collar of his
shirt open. As soon as he was up and dressed, she
would go to the window to see him start his day.
Down in the street below, Charles would prepare to
get on to his horse while she went on talking to
him from above. Sometimes she might find a feather
and send it floating through the air to be caught
in the long hair on his old white horse's neck.
As he rode off, Charles would blow her
a kiss and she would wave back to him.
It was the first time in his life
that he had tasted such happiness.
He had been lonely and friendless at
school and when he was studying medicine.
And then he had had fourteen months
of married life with the widow,
whose feet, in bed, were like lumps of ice.
But now this lovely woman was his for life!
Before she married, Emma too had thought she was
in love, but the happiness that should have come
from love was somehow missing. It seemed to
her that she must have made a mistake, must
have misunderstood things in one way or another.
And as she stood by her bedroom window, morning
after morning, Emma tried hard to understand
what, exactly, the words joy, love, desire
meant. They had always seemed so beautiful to her
in books, but what did they mean in real life?
Novels had always seemed more real
to her than the life she had to live.
When she was at her convent school, a teacher
sometimes secretly lent such books to the
older girls. They were all about love, lovers,
beautiful girls, ladies in danger, horses ridden
till they dropped dead, dark forests, tears
and kisses, and gentlemen as brave as lions.
When she was fifteen, Emma read the works of
Walter Scott for the first time and found she
was happier in this imagined past than her rather
boring present; the characters she read about in
these books were much more interesting than
the teachers and students she saw around her.
She had felt a thrill each time she blew back
the thin paper which protected the pictures.
She saw young men holding young women in white
dresses in their arms, or English ladies with
golden hair, who looked at you with big, bright
eyes. In her reading she was able to listen to the
sound of heavenly music and of falling leaves.
Later, after her mother died, she even fell in
love with the church and thought of staying in
the convent, of never going out into the world.
But in her last year of school, she
began to lose her interest in religion.
When her father took her away, her
teachers were not sorry to see her go.
She had, they thought, stopped showing
any respect for their community.
On her return home, Emma tried to find an
interest in managing her father's house,
but she soon grew tired of the country
and wished herself back in her convent.
When Charles came to Les
Bertaux for the first time,
she thought of herself as a disappointed woman,
one for whom life had nothing new to offer,
either in knowledge or experience. Maybe her wish
for a change - possibly, too, the unrest caused by
the presence of an unknown man - had been enough
to make her believe that she was at last in love.
But now she could not believe that her present
state was the happiness she had dreamed about.
Nevertheless, she sometimes thought that these
were, in fact, the happiest days of her life.
Of course, it would have been so much better if
they could have gone far away to lands whose names
fall like music on the ear, where the weddings of
lovers are followed by mornings of soft delight
and where, when the sun goes down, you breathe,
sitting beside the sea, the sweet perfume of
the lemon trees. Why did her bedroom window not
look out on to the Swiss or Scottish mountains?
Why did her husband not stand
beside her in a black silk jacket,
the wind blowing his long hair
back from his pale, white forehead?
But Charles could not read these thoughts, and
was not able to share her dreams, and as their
lives became closer Emma, in fact, began to have
a secret feeling of distance from her husband.
Charles's conversation was uninteresting to her.
He told her that when he lived in Rouen he never
had the smallest desire to go to the theatre. He
could not swim, he had no idea of how to use a
sword, he could not fire a gun. He knew nothing,
and he wanted nothing. He thought she was happy,
and his heavy, comfortable
happiness had begun to annoy her.
A few weeks after they came to Tostes, one of
Charles's patients presented Madame with a little
Italian hunting dog. She took it with her for
walks, because she used to go out sometimes just
to get a few moments to herself and to enjoy
a change from the garden and the dusty road.
She would go as far as the woods near Banneville,
along by the empty summer house at the end of the
wall, towards the open country. There, at the side
of the lake, the plants grew higher than a man and
had leaves as sharp as knives. Sitting at the edge
of the wood among the pink and blue wild flowers,
her thoughts would wander here and there,
like her dog, which ran from one place to the
next chasing the birds and insects. But in the
same way that her dog always came back to her,
she always came back to the same
question: 'My God, why did I marry him?'
She would then call Djali (the name she had given
her dog) to come to her and, stroking her long,
graceful head, would say, 'Come, kiss your
mistress; you have no worries, have you?'
Then she would look into the
creature's beautiful, sad eyes,
and a feeling of tenderness would come over her.
Pretending the animal was herself, she would talk
to her aloud as if she were comforting someone.
Towards the end of September, however, an
extraordinary event happened in her life:
she was invited to La Vaubyessard, the home of
the Marquis d'Andervilliers. The Marquis, who
had been a Minister in the national government,
wanted to get back into politics, and he was now
doing his best to make himself popular. During the
winter months he had given firewood to the poor,
and he was always the first to demand new roads
for his district. During the summer, he had had
a painful mouth infection, which Charles had
managed to cure before it became really serious.
The servant who was sent to Tostes to pay for
the treatment told his master, when he got back,
that he had seen some splendid cherries in
the doctor's little garden. Cherries did not
grow well at La Vaubyessard, and the Marquis
asked Bovary to let him have a few baskets.
He then decided to come in person to thank
the doctor, saw Emma, and noted that she
had a pretty figure and good manners. After
this, the Marquis decided that he would not
harm his chances in the coming vote if he sent
the young people an invitation to his house.
And so, one Wednesday at three o'clock, Monsieur
and Madame Bovary set off in their carriage to
La Vaubyessard, with a big travelling bag tied on
behind, and a hatbox fixed in front. They arrived
when it was getting dark, just as the lamps were
being lit in the park to guide the carriages.
The Chateau la Vaubyessard, a large building in
sixteenth-century style, stood in the centre of
parkland. A stream flowed between tall trees
and beneath a bridge, and through the evening
mist they could see cottages and farm buildings.
Charles stopped the carriage at the foot of the
steps leading up to the front door, and two
servants came down to take their bags. Then
the Marquis came forward and, offering his arm to
the doctor's lady, walked with her into the hall.
Under the high ceiling, their voices and footsteps
sounded as if they were in a church. As she passed
through on her way to the main room, Emma saw
large, dark paintings of the Marquis's relatives,
some in the clothes of the royal court, others
in the uniforms of army or navy officers.
When the Marquis opened the door
for them, one of the ladies rose
(it was the Marquise herself) and came forward
to welcome Emma. She made her sit down beside
her on a low chair, and began to chat with
her, as if she had known her for a long time.
At seven o'clock dinner was served. The men
were seated at the first table, in the hall,
the ladies at the second, in the dining
room, with the Marquis and the Marquise.
At the long dining tables, the glasses were filled
with iced champagne. Emma felt a thrill go through
her as she tasted the coldness of it in her mouth.
She had never seen some of the fruit that they had
on the table, and even the sugar seemed whiter
here, and more finely powdered, than elsewhere.
After dinner, there was dancing. More guests
were arriving and the room filled with people.
Emma sat down near the door and watched the
men talking and smoking cigars in small groups
in their black and white evening dress, as the
servants moved among them carrying drinks and
more small, delicate things to eat. All along
the rows of seated women she could see smiles
half-hidden, half-revealed, by the flowers
the ladies held; everywhere there was silk,
the flash of jewels and gold, white arms,
and hair piled high on elegant heads.
Emma's heart beat faster when, her partner holding
her by the tips of her fingers, she took her
place in line and stood waiting for the dance to
begin. But her nervousness soon disappeared and,
moving to the music, she flew on as light as a
bird. The memories of her past life, which until
then had always been so clear, disappeared
so completely in the magic of the moment
that she could hardly persuade herself they were
not a dream. There she was. No doubt about that!
During a break in the dancing supper was
served, and again the wine flowed freely,
accompanied by sea-food soup, sweet
puddings and all kinds of cold meats.
Now people with longer journeys
began to get into their carriages
and drive off one after another. Charles was
half-asleep with his back against a door.
But not everyone was ready to leave, and it was
at three in the morning when the last dance began.
Only the guests who were staying the
night at the chateau were still there.
One of these, a Viscount whose evening dress
fitted him like a glove, came a second time to
invite Madame Bovary to dance. They began
slowly, and then increased their speed.
They turned, and everything around them turned
- the lamps, the furniture and the floor.
As they swung past the doors, Emma's dress blew
up in the air. The Viscount looked down at her,
she raised her eyes to his; for a moment she lost
her breath and stopped. Then off they went again,
quicker than ever, racing down to the high windows
at the far end of the room, where she nearly fell
and, for a moment, rested her head on his chest.
And then, still turning, but more gently now,
he took her to her seat. She leaned back against
the wall and covered her eyes with her hands.
Then there was a little more conversation and,
after saying goodnight (or good
morning), the guests went off to bed.
Charles dragged himself upstairs on
heavy legs. But Emma did not want to
sleep. She opened the window and sat with
her head in her hand. The night was dark.
A few drops of rain were falling. She breathed in
the damp wind that blew cool against her eyelids.
The dance music was still playing in her ears,
and she tried to keep awake in order to keep
the dream alive for as long as she could.
As she stood there, the sun began to rise
beyond the trees and she shivered with cold.
She undressed and got down between the
sheets, close up to Charles, who was asleep.
There were twelve or fifteen of them at
breakfast, which, to Charles's surprise,
was all over in ten minutes. After that, a small
group went with Mademoiselle d'Andervilliers for
a walk through the park, and then, to amuse the
lady, the Marquis took Emma to see his stables,
while Charles went to ask one of the
men to bring his horse and carriage.
When Emma returned, the Bovarys said
their goodbyes to the Marquis and Marquise
and turned their horse's head towards Tostes
and home. Emma sat in silence. Their bags
banged against the back of the carriage as
they made their way down the rough road.
They had reached the high ground at
Thibourville when suddenly a group of gentlemen,
laughing and smoking cigars, rode past them. Emma
thought she recognized the Viscount who had danced
with her last night. She turned round to have
another look, but they were already too far away.
A little later, they had to stop to
make a small repair to the carriage.
When he had finished, Charles noticed something
lying on the ground between his horse's legs. He
bent down and picked up a beautifully-made green
silk cigar-case with two cigars still inside it.
'They'll be good this evening after dinner.'
He put the case in his
pocket and started the horse.
When they got home,
the evening meal was not ready. Madame became
angry and the maid, Nastasie, replied rudely.
'You can leave,' said Emma.
'You are finished here!'
So all they had for dinner was onion soup with
a small piece of meat and some vegetables.
'How nice it is to be back
home again!' said Charles,
cheerfully rubbing his hands
as he sat down opposite Emma.
They could hear Nastasie weeping as they ate.
Charles was rather fond of the poor girl,
who had kept him company after his first
wife died, when he had nothing to do.
She had been his first patient, the first
person he ever got to know in Tostes.
'Have you really told her
to leave?' he said at last.
'Yes. Why not?' she replied.
After supper, they went into the
kitchen to warm themselves while
the bedroom was being prepared. Charles
began to smoke. He pushed out his lips,
spat repeatedly, and pulled his head back every
time he breathed in the smoke from the cigar.
'You'll make yourself ill!' she said.
He put the cigar down, and went
to get himself a drink of water.
Quick as lightning, Emma picked up the cigar-case
and threw it into the back of the cupboard.
Time went so slowly the next day! Emma
walked around her little garden, up and down,
up and down, stopping to look at
the flower-beds, at the fruit trees;
looking at all these familiar things, things that
she knew so well but which now seemed so strange.
How far away the chateau seemed already! Her
journey to La Vaubyessard had changed her life,
but left it feeling empty.
However, she accepted her fate.
She folded up her beautiful dress and laid
it carefully away in the chest of drawers,
with her dancing shoes. She had now known wealth
and luxury, and life would never be the same.
The memory of this visit to the chateau became
part of her life. Each Wednesday she would sigh as
she awoke and say to herself, 'A week ago today...
a fortnight ago... three weeks ago, I was there!'
But little by little the faces of the people
became faint in her memory, and she forgot the
tunes she had danced to. The servants' clothes,
the look of the rooms came back less clearly to
her vision. Some of the details faded away,
but the empty space in her heart remained.
CHAPTER FIVE
Moving Home
Often, when Charles was out of the house,
Emma would go to the cupboard and take
out the green silk cigar-case she had hidden
there. It must have belonged to the Viscount.
Perhaps it was a present from a lady friend in
Paris, made with love and care in every stitch.
Paris! What sort of a place was it? 'Paris!' -
she said the name under her breath, because she
loved the sound of it. It was like the great
bell in an old church; the word seemed to add
a golden light to everything around it - even to
the labels of her little pots of cheap make-up.
She bought a guidebook to Paris and, with
her fingertip on the map, she would make
little imaginary journeys around the capital. She
pretended she was walking along the wide streets,
looking in wonder at the great houses. At last,
growing tired, she would let her eyes close,
and then in the darkness she dreamed
she saw the flame of the street lamps,
and the steps of the carriages being
let down at the entrance to the theatre.
She buried herself in women's magazines,
reading every word about opera and
fashion and the life of the rich.
She read the latest novels - even bringing
her book with her to the table and turning
the pages while Charles ate and talked. And as she
read, the memory of the Viscount came back to her
and her dreams became more important, more real
to her than her life as a country doctor's wife.
But she tried to improve things in her house.
She taught her maid to hand a glass of water
held in a white cloth, to knock before entering a
room, to dress her mistress. In the daytime, Emma
wore a long dress with a silk belt and little red
silk shoes. She had bought herself a writing-case,
a pen-holder and some envelopes, although she had
no one to write to. She thought she would like to
travel, or to go back to her school. She wanted
to die - and she wanted to go and live in Paris.
And Charles rode from farm to farm on his old
horse. He ate breakfast in farmhouse kitchens,
visited sick people in their dirty
beds, got blood on his hands and face
and listened to the last words of the dying. But
every night he came home to a fire, a good dinner,
a comfortable chair, and a pretty wife who
had so many little ways of giving pleasure.
It might be paper shades for the candles, a new
ribbon for her dress or an extraordinary name
for a very ordinary dish, which Charles
ate happily, enjoying every bit of it.
Everything Emma did added something to the
pleasure of his senses and of his home.
It was like finding gold-dust in the
middle of the narrow pathway of his life.
He felt well, and looked well. People liked
him. He talked to their children, did not drink,
could be trusted and was especially good with the
chest complaints that were so common among country
people. A major reason for Charles's success was
that he was so afraid of killing his patients
that he never gave them anything more than simple
medicines - but he was not frightened of surgery,
and had a strong wrist when he pulled teeth. The
people of the region were happy with their doctor.
Charles did have some ambitions. He tried to
read a professional journal after dinner, but
the warmth of the room and the good meal he had
eaten would send him to sleep after five minutes.
And there he sat, his head resting on his two
hands and his long hair hanging over his face.
Emma looked at him and asked herself
why she had not got one of those strong,
silent men for a husband, men who sit up at
night with their books, and become famous,
if not rich. She would have liked the name
of Bovary, which was hers now, to be famous,
to be seen in the bookshops,
talked about in the papers,
known all over France. But Charles did not have
that kind of ambition, and sometimes she felt
like hitting him. 'What a man! What a poor kind
of man!' she said to herself, biting her lips.
So as time went on, Emma felt herself less
and less able to put up with her husband.
He was growing more unpleasant as he got older. He
sucked his teeth after eating, and made a horrible
noise at every mouthful of soup he swallowed.
As he was beginning to put on weight, his eyes,
which were already small, looked as if they would
start to disappear into his increasingly fat face.
Deep down in her heart, she was waiting
for something to happen. She did not know
what it would be, what the wind would blow
to her. But every morning when she awoke,
she hoped it would come that day. She listened
to every sound, watched every new face in the
street outside her house for a sign, and could
not understand why nothing happened. And then
at sunset, sadder than ever, she
would long for the next day to come.
The spring came again. With the first touch of
heat, when the apple trees were in flower, she
began to have attacks of dizziness. And when July
came, she counted on her fingers how many weeks
it would be to October, thinking that perhaps
the Marquis d'Andervilliers would be giving
another dance at La Vaubyessard. But September
came and went, and no one called or wrote.
After this disappointment there was the same
emptiness in her heart, and the empty days began
again as before. The future was like a corridor
in which there was no light, and at the end of it
only a closed door. She gave up her music. What
was the use of playing? Who was there to hear?
She stopped her drawing. What was the good, what
was the good of it all? Even sewing bored her.
'There's nothing left to read,' she
said to herself. And there she sat,
staring at the falling rain.
Was this hopeless life going to last for ever? Was
there no escape? She knew she was just as good as
the luckier ones. At La Vaubyessard she had seen
great ladies who were not as pretty or intelligent
as her; why was she so unlucky? She would lean
her head against the wall and weep, wanting so
much for a life of excitement, pleasures, all the
delights which must be out there in the world,
but which were not hers. There were days when she
would talk and talk; then the excitement would die
away, and she would fall back into a kind of dream
world and sit without moving or saying a word.
As she was always saying how she hated Tostes,
Charles thought her illness must be caused by
the place itself. The idea grew on him, and he
began seriously to think of going elsewhere.
Then she started drinking vinegar
to make herself lose weight,
coughed a little dry cough
and could not touch her food.
It was hard for Charles to leave Tostes. He had
been there for four years and was building a
good practice. However, what must be must be.
He took her to Rouen to see another doctor.
The doctor said it was a case of nerves. What she
needed was a change. So Charles looked around all
over the place, and at last heard of a busy little
market town called Yonville-l'Abbaye, somewhere in
the Neufchatel area, where the doctor had recently
left town and no replacement had been found.
He wrote to the local pharmacist asking him to let
him know how many people there were in the place,
what sort of competition there was, and
how much a year the other man used to make.
The answers were satisfactory, and Charles
decided he would make a move in the spring
if Emma's health had not improved.
One day, when she was emptying a
drawer in preparation for the move,
Emma felt something sharp against her finger. It
was the piece of wire around her wedding flowers,
faded and dusty now, and the ribbon eaten
by insects. She threw them on the fire,
where they burned like a handful of dry grass
and then lay like a red bush in the fireplace.
As she watched them burn, the paper berries
burst, the wire bent and twisted, and the
paper flowers were held in the hot air like black
insects until, at last, they flew up the chimney.
In March, when they left Tostes,
Madame Bovary was pregnant.
CHAPTER SIX
Yonville
Yonville-l'Abbaye is a market town
about twenty-six kilometres from Rouen,
between the Abbeville and Beauvais roads.
It is on the borders of Normandy, Picardy and
the Ile-de-France, the sort of place where the
language has no accent and the landscape no
character. Here they make the worst cheese in
the whole district, and farming is expensive
because the sandy, stony soil is so poor.
Until 1835 there was no good road to Yonville,
and although a new one has been built, nothing has
really changed there for a hundred years. Walking
into the town you still pass small farmhouses set
in their own gardens, and see that the fields
stretch almost into the centre of the town.
The market, with its red roof supported by twenty
or more wooden posts, takes up half of the town
square. The Town Hall is a large, important
looking building, but what really catches
the eye is the pharmacy of Monsieur Homais just
opposite the town's one hotel, the Lion d'Or.
The pharmacy is especially attractive at night
when the lamps are lit and the big red and green
glass bottles in the window send long beams
of coloured light far out along the ground.
From top to bottom, the building is covered with
advertisements for medicines and mineral water,
and the shop-sign which goes right across the
front carries in golden letters the words 'Homais,
Pharmacist'. At the far end of the shop, the word
'Laboratory' appears over a glass door on which,
halfway up, the name 'Homais' is
repeated in more gold letters on black.
And that is all there is worth seeing in Yonville.
The one and only street, with a shop or two on
either side of it, stops at the bend in the road.
If you turn to your right and follow the path at
the foot of the hill, you come to the cemetery.
The night the Bovarys arrived in Yonville,
Madame Lefrancois, who ran the inn,
was so busy that the sweat ran down her face
as she rushed around among her pots and pans.
Tomorrow was market day and she still
had the meat to cook, the soup to make
and the coffee to get ready. Then there
was the meal for her regular customers,
as well as for the new doctor and his wife and
maid - whose coach was now half an hour late.
Shouts of laughter came from the bar, where
three workmen were calling for more wine
and the wood fire was burning. A man in soft
green leather shoes, a smoking cap on his head,
was standing warming his back by the fire. He had
a look of complete self-satisfaction on his face,
and he appeared to be as carefree as the small
bird in the cage which hung from the ceiling. It
was the pharmacist, waiting for the evening
meal which he regularly ate at the hotel.
He did not have to wait too long.
Soon, Madame Lefrancois heard the
sound of wheels and the metal shoes
of a tired horse on the road outside.
As soon as the coach stopped, other villagers
came to the inn, and all began to speak at once,
asking for news, explanations and
packages they had been waiting for.
As he gave out his parcels, Hivert,
the coachman, told them they had been
delayed because Madame Bovary's little
dog had run away and had not been found.
Emma had, in fact, been crying for the
last hour. She said it was Charles's fault.
Monsieur Lheureux, who was travelling inside the
coach and who had the fabric shop in the village,
had done his best to make her happier
by telling her of several cases in which
dogs had come back to their masters after
years of separation. There was a story,
he said, of a dog that found its way back
to Paris all the way from Constantinople!
Dog or no dog, they had arrived at their new home,
and had to leave the coach. Emma got out first,
then Felicite, her maid, and then Monsieur
Lheureux. They had to wake Charles up;
he had fallen asleep in his
corner as soon as it grew dark.
Homais introduced himself, offered his services
to Madame and his respects to Monsieur,
told them he was charmed to have
been able to do them a service,
adding with a smile that he had invited himself
to dinner as his wife was away from home.
As soon as she was in the kitchen,
Madame Bovary went over to the fire.
With the tips of two fingers she took hold of
her dress at the knee and, raising it above
her ankles, stretched out a foot to the flames - a
little foot in a black boot. The fire lit her from
top to toe, its red light making her dress shine
and showing the perfect white skin of her face.
On the other side of the fireplace, a
fair-haired young man watched her in silence.
Monsieur Leon Dupuis, clerk to the town's only
lawyer, also ate regularly at the Lion d'Or.
As he found life in Yonville
almost impossibly boring,
he would often delay his meal in the hope
that a traveller would arrive at the inn
with whom he could enjoy a conversation
in the evening. It was therefore with some
pleasure that he accepted the suggestion
that he should sit down with the Bovarys.
At the table, Homais asked permission to
keep on his cap, for fear of catching cold.
'Madame must be a little tired,' he said, turning
to Emma. 'It is not a comfortable journey.'
'Very true,' she answered, 'but I love
moving around. I hate staying in one place.'
'Oh, I agree. Staying in one place
is horrible!' said the clerk.
'But if you were like me,' said Charles,
'and always had to be on your horse...'
And so the meal continued. Charles spent most
of his time discussing medical matters with
Monsieur Homais, while Leon told Madame Bovary
about the attractions of the neighbourhood.
They quickly discovered that they
shared the same romantic tastes.
'I think there's nothing so beautiful as a sunset,
especially by the sea!' said Madame Bovary.
'Oh, I love the sea!' Monsieur Leon replied.
'And doesn't it seem to you,
somehow, that you think more freely,
and that it raises your soul and makes you
think of the endless nature of things?'
'It's just the same where there
are mountains,' Leon went on.
So they continued talking of Switzerland and
Italy, which they had never visited, and music,
which neither of them could play,
and reading - the one thing that
both of them did enthusiastically.
'What can be better than sitting by
the fire in the evening with a book,
when the lamp is lit and the wind
beats against the window?' said Leon.
'That's just what I think,' she replied,
looking at him with her big, dark eyes.
'You forget everything,' he went on. 'The
hours slip by. Sitting still in your armchair,
you can wander in strange places and
imagine they are there before your eyes.'
'Oh yes, that's true!' she said.
They had been at the table for
two and a half hours by now,
since Artemise, the servant, did not hurry as
she brought the dishes in from the kitchen.
Quite unconsciously, Leon had put his foot
up on one of the bars of the chair on which
Madame Bovary was sitting, moving closer
so he could catch everything she said.
And so, while Charles and the pharmacist went on
with their discussion, Emma and Leon sat close
to one another, and entered into a conversation in
which they talked about the interests they shared:
the Paris theatres, names of novels, the latest
dances, the world of fashion, which neither of
them knew anything about, Tostes, where she
had lived, and Yonville, where they were now.
They discussed anything and everything,
and talked all through dinner.
When the coffee was brought in, Felicite
went to arrange the bedroom in the new house,
and the group around the dinner
table soon afterwards rose to go.
Madame Lefrancois had fallen
asleep by the dying fire,
while the manservant, lamp in hand, was waiting
to show Monsieur and Madame Bovary to their house.
The house felt damp and cold after the warmth of
the inn. The walls were new and the wooden stairs
had no carpet. Upstairs in the bedroom, a pale
light came in through the curtainless windows.
The tops of some trees could just be seen,
and beyond them, the fields in the moonlight.
This would be the fourth time Emma had slept in
a new bedroom. The first was when she went to the
convent, the second when she came to Tostes,
the third at La Vaubyessard, and now this was
the fourth. And every time, it had seemed as
if she were entering a new stage in her life.
She could not believe that things would look
and be the same in different places. The most
recent period of her life had been bad, so
the next part would have to be better.
CHAPTER SEVEN
In Love
Next morning, when she awoke, Emma saw the
clerk walking across the square. She was in her
dressing-gown. He looked up and took off his hat.
She gave a little nod and quickly shut the window.
All day long, Leon waited for six o'clock to
arrive. But when he went round to the inn,
the only person there was Monsieur Binet, the
tax collector, already seated at the table.
The dinner of the night before had been an
important event for Leon. It was the first time in
his life that he had talked to a woman for a whole
evening. How did he manage to tell her, and in
such brilliant language, so many things he could
not have expressed so well before? Unfortunately,
it did not look as if he would have the chance
to repeat his performance for the moment.
Monsieur Homais, the pharmacist, however, was
able to visit Madame Bovary and show what a
good neighbour he was. He told her all about the
shopkeepers, where to get her butter cheaply,
and he helped her find a gardener. It has to
be said, however, that he was not doing this
out of pure kindness. Monsieur Homais had,
a year earlier, broken the law which forbade
the practice of medicine by all unqualified
persons. Someone had told the authorities,
and Monsieur Homais had been given a very
severe warning by the magistrate in Rouen.
The problem was that he still liked to give
quick, innocent consultations in his shop,
but the Mayor did not like him, others were
jealous, and he was playing a dangerous game. So
Monsieur Homais thought to himself that if he did
things for Monsieur and Madame Bovary, Monsieur
Bovary would be grateful, and a grateful man does
not make complaints to the authorities in Rouen.
Every morning, Homais would come across with
the newspaper and often, during the afternoon,
he would leave his shop for a minute
or two to chat with the new doctor.
Charles was not a happy man; patients did not
come. He sat for hour after hour in silence,
or he went to sleep in his surgery or watched
his wife sew. He even started doing some small
jobs at home, trying to paint the bedroom
with some paint the men had left behind.
Money was his great worry. He had spent
such a lot on repairs at Tostes, on his
wife's clothes and on moving, and most of his
savings and Emma's money had gone in two years.
But Charles also had something
pleasant to think about,
as his wife was expecting a child,
and the closer they got to the time,
the more loving he became. It was another link
between them, real evidence of their marriage.
When he watched her heavier walk, when she sat
opposite him at the table, or when she was in her
armchair after dinner, he could not stop himself
getting up, kissing her, stroking her face,
calling her 'little mother'. The idea of being a
father pleased him very much. He lacked nothing.
At first Emma was surprised by his attention; then
all she wanted was to have the baby as soon as
possible, so that she would know how it felt to
be a mother. Their shortage of money meant that
she could not buy all the things she wanted for
the new arrival, so perhaps she did not feel as
much love for the child she carried as she wanted
to give. But she thought about it all the time.
She hoped it would be a boy. He should be
strong and dark, and they would call him
George. And the thought of having
a boy somehow made her feel better.
A man would be free, while a woman
is always limited. She is weaker and
economically dependent, and the habits of
society do not permit her the same freedom.
Emma's baby was born on a Sunday morning
at about six, just as the sun was rising.
'It's a girl,' said Charles.
She turned away her head and fainted.
Madame Homais came to the house as soon as the
news was given to congratulate her, and so did
Madame Lefrancois of the Lion d'Or. The pharmacist
offered his congratulations through the half-open
door. He then asked to see the baby and declared
it was the most well formed he had ever seen.
As the doctor felt that his wife was not
strong enough to feed the baby herself,
the little girl was sent to a wet nurse. With
nothing else to do in the days after the birth,
Emma tried to think of a name for her daughter.
First she went through names with Italian endings,
like Clara, Louisa, Amanda. She rather liked
old names like Galsuinde, or Yseult or Leocadie.
Charles wanted the child to be called
after her mother. Emma said no.
At last Emma remembered that at
the Chateau de la Vaubyessard
she had heard the Marquise call a young woman
by the name of Berthe. That decision was made.
Four or five weeks after the birth, Emma
felt a sudden need to see her little girl,
so she set out in the direction of the wet
nurse's house at the far end of the village.
It was midday and the sun beat down from
a cloudless sky. A hot wind was blowing
and when she had gone some way, Emma began
to feel weak from the effort of walking.
She started to think she should return
home or go in somewhere and sit down.
Just then, Monsieur Leon came out from
a house close by, with some papers under
his arm. He came up and spoke, and took her into
the shade outside Lheureux's shop. Madame Bovary
said she was on her way to see her baby,
but that she was beginning to feel tired.
'If...' began Leon, but he
stopped, not daring to continue.
'Are you very busy?' she asked.
And when the clerk said that he was
not, she begged him to walk with her.
To reach the nurse's house they had to go along
to the end of the street and then turn, as if
they were going to the cemetery. They set off side
by side, and recognized the house by an old tree
that shaded it. It was a low, badly maintained
house with a brown roof and small, untidy garden.
Hearing the gate open, the woman came out,
carrying a baby at her breast. With her other hand
she was dragging along a poor, miserable-looking
two-year-old with spots all over his face.
'Come in,' she said. 'Your
little one is in there asleep.'
She went into the dark bedroom, and showed
Emma where the little girl was sleeping. Emma
took the baby in her arms, wrapped up in a dirty
blanket, and began to sing gently as she held her.
Leon walked up and down the room. It seemed
strange to him to see this beautiful, elegantly
dressed woman in such poor surroundings. Madame
Bovary saw him looking and blushed bright red.
He turned away, thinking he
had perhaps seemed too curious,
as she gave the baby back to the nurse.
It had just been sick all over her collar.
Having lost enthusiasm for her baby,
Emma again took Monsieur Leon's arm,
and they left the nurse holding the child
and waving as they went down the path.
Emma walked quickly for some distance,
then slowed down. As she looked around her,
her eyes rested on the young man's shoulder and
on his well-cut coat with its smart black collar.
She noticed how his golden brown hair was
smooth and carefully brushed, and that his
fingernails were longer and much more carefully
cared for than most fingernails in Yonville.
They went back to the village on the path beside
the river. The stream flowed on noiselessly,
deep and cool; dark plants moved in the water
like long green hair, and insects walked over
its smooth surface or waited with shining
wings on the tall grass at the water's edge.
All around, as far as the eye could see, the
fields had emptied of people. It was dinner-time
in the farms, and the only sounds that fell on
the ears of the young woman and her companion
were their footsteps on the path, the words they
spoke and Emma's dress brushing against the grass.
The garden walls were hot in the sun, and the
wild plants that were growing between the stones
had died. As she passed, Madame Bovary
touched some of their dry flowers,
which made them fall into yellow dust.
They were talking about some Spanish dancers who
were going to perform at the theatre in Rouen.
'Will you go?' she asked.
'If I can,' he replied.
Was this all they had to say to one
another? They tried to speak of ordinary,
everyday things, but all the time they
felt a deep change coming over them.
It was like a whisper from the soul, deep down,
stronger than the spoken word. Lost in wonder
at this strange sweetness, they did not speak
of it or try to explain what was happening.
But both felt that there could be
future pleasures waiting for them.
When they came to her garden, Madame
Bovary pushed open the little gate
and, running up the steps, disappeared from view.
Leon went back to his office. His boss was out.
He looked quickly at some papers, prepared a
pen for writing, but then put on his hat and
went out. He went up to the edge of the woods,
threw himself down on the ground under the
trees and looked at the sky through his fingers.
'Oh!' he sighed. 'I am so bored!'
As soon as the weather began to turn cold, Emma
spent her days in the sitting room. It was a long
room with a low ceiling, and above the fireplace
there was a picture of the sea and a large mirror.
She pulled her chair close to the window
so that she could watch the villagers
as they went by on the pavement.
Twice a day, Leon passed from
his work to the Lion d'Or.
Emma could recognize his steps from a long
way away. She leaned forward and listened,
and the young man walked past, always dressed the
same and always looking straight in front of him.
In the evening, when she had dropped her piece
of unfinished sewing on her lap and was sitting
with her chin resting on her left hand, she would
again notice his figure moving past the window,
and then she would get up and tell
the girl to lay the table for dinner.
Monsieur Homais would often come in while they
were eating. Smoking cap in hand, he would come in
quietly, not wanting to disturb anyone, and always
saying the same thing: 'Good evening, everybody.'
Having taken his usual place at the table,
between husband and wife, he asked the doctor
about his patients, and the doctor consulted
him about the sort of fees he ought to charge.
Then they began to discuss the news in the paper.
At eight o'clock the pharmacist's assistant,
Justin, would come for him to
go over and shut up the shop.
On Sundays, the Bovarys would return these
visits and spend the evening at the pharmacist's.
They would begin with cards - Monsieur Homais
usually being Emma's partner. Leon would stand
behind her and tell her what to play. Every time
she threw a card on the table, the movement would
pull up her dress on the right side, and her hair
would move across her neck like soft brown silk.
When they had finished the cards, the pharmacist
and the doctor would settle down to discuss
the news of the day and drink their wine and
Emma, changing her place, would sit with her
elbow on the table, turning over the pages of an
illustrated magazine. Leon sat down beside her,
and they looked at the pictures together,
waiting for each other at the bottom of the page.
Sometimes she would ask him to read some poetry.
And so a kind of friendship began between them.
The problem for Leon, however, was to know
what sort of friend Madame Bovary might be.
They gave each other small presents,
they were happy in each other's company,
but would there be more? He thought
and thought about this in his lonely
room. Should he tell her what he was
feeling? Did he love her, or didn't he?
He was torn between fear of hurting her
and shame at his own lack of courage.
Sometimes he would make up his mind to act, and to
act quickly. He wrote letters - and tore them up;
decided on a day to speak to her - and put it off.
Sometimes he walked out of the lawyer's office
with his mind made up. But all his courage melted
when he found himself face to face with Emma;
and when Charles came home and invited him
to come with him to see a patient at a farm
a few kilometres away, he at once accepted and,
with a bow to Madame, left with her husband.
But Emma did not ask herself if she was in love.
Love, she thought, was something that must come
suddenly, like a great thunderstorm, blowing away
your old life and carrying your heart and soul
away, to heaven or to hell. She never thought
about the way a river can rise slowly, getting
higher day by day, until after a night of rain it
breaks its banks and floods the land around it. In
fact, she had no idea of the danger she was in.
CHAPTER EIGHT
A Dream Ends
One snowy Sunday afternoon in February, Monsieur
and Madame Bovary, Homais and Monsieur Leon
went to look at a new mill that
was being built outside Yonville.
Homais had brought his children, to give them a
little exercise. The place did not interest Emma,
and she stood away from the group, leaning on
Leon's arm, while Homais and her husband talked
about the technical wonders - the thick walls,
the great machinery - they saw all around them.
Turning from the pale sunlight coming through
the mist, she saw Charles, his cap pulled down
over his ears, his thick lips and his stupid face.
Even his back was annoying, a stupid back covered
in a stupid, boring winter coat. Leon moved
forward a step. The cold air had made him pale,
even more beautiful than normal. The
collar of his shirt was open a little,
showing his white skin; the tip of his
ear was visible under his long hair,
and his big blue eyes, raised upwards to
the clouds, seemed to Emma to be clearer,
more beautiful than those mountain
lakes in which the skies are mirrored.
Madame Bovary did not go over to her neighbours'
that evening, and when Charles had left and she
felt she was all alone, she lay down on the carpet
in front of the fire and thought about Leon once
more. She thought he was charming. She could not
put him out of her thoughts. She remembered how he
had stood, the things he had said, all about him.
And she said over and over again, 'Oh, charming!
Charming!... And in love?' she asked herself.
'But with whom?... But it must be with me!'
The evidence was suddenly clear to
her and her heart gave a great leap.
The firelight became brighter, and she turned
on her back and stretched out her arms.
After the first excitement, she then
thought, as so many people have before,
'Ah, why did this happen when it was too
late? Why not before? What prevented it?'
It was midnight when Charles got back.
She pretended she had just woken up
and, as he made a noise undressing,
she complained of having a headache. Then she
asked what sort of an evening it had been.
'Monsieur Leon,' he said, 'went to bed early.'
She could not help smiling. When
she turned over to go to sleep,
her heart was filled with a new happiness.
Next day, however, she could not settle to her
work in the house; she was happy, but still could
not take pleasure in the things she usually liked
to do. So when Monsieur Lheureux, the draper,
visited and showed her a beautiful scarf, even
offering to let her pay later, she refused. And
when Leon visited her in the afternoon, all
she could do was to talk about her husband!
The same sort of thing went on for days. Her
manner and conversation changed completely.
She became interested in housekeeping,
started going to church again regularly,
and stopped the cook stealing the sugar. She even
took her little daughter Berthe away from the wet
nurse and showed her to all her visitors. She told
everyone she loved children. They were such a joy
and comfort, she said, as she kissed the child
and held her close to her. When Charles got home,
he would find his chair ready by the fire. His
clothes were brushed and cleaned, the buttons
were always on his shirts, and his shirts were
folded carefully after they had been ironed.
When Leon saw him at the fireside after
dinner, with his hands on his stomach,
his cheeks red from the meat and wine,
the child crawling around on the carpet,
and this elegant woman who would lean over
and kiss him over the back of the chair,
he would say to himself, 'What a fool I am
to imagine I could make her care for me!'
And as each day passed, Emma became thinner and
paler. She was so sad and so calm, so gentle
and, at the same time, so distant, that you
felt a sort of icy charm when you were with her.
This charm changed the
attitudes of her neighbours;
they no longer saw her as the outsider
who did not know how to behave properly.
'She's a wonderful woman,' said the pharmacist,
and the married women of Yonville admired her for
her good management, the patients for her pleasant
manners, the poor for her charity. But beneath her
calm, Emma was in a state of desire and anger and
hatred. Her plain, simple dress hid a heart that
was breaking, and she could tell no one, no one!
She was in love with Leon, but she did not want to
see him. Her heart beat faster when she heard
him coming, and then, when he was there, the
excitement went away and was replaced by a feeling
of fear and sadness. She did not know what to do.
What made it harder to bear was that Charles had
no understanding of what she was going through,
and she began to hate him for his lack of feeling.
She would have liked Charles to beat her so
that she could have a reason for hating him.
She was torn between a love she could not
admit to, and a hatred she could not show.
And there she sat at the end of another empty
day, broken, motionless, her face wet with tears.
'Why don't you tell the doctor about it?' said
her maid when she came in and found her like this.
'It's only nerves,' answered Emma. 'Don't
mention it to him. He would only worry.'
If Emma was unhappy, Leon was also
less than pleased with his life,
feeling he had nothing to look forward to. He
was so tired of Yonville and its inhabitants
that the sight of certain people
and certain houses made him angry.
And when Monsieur Homais, the pharmacist, tried to
amuse him, he found himself disliking him too. The
problem was, however, that the thought of changing
things alarmed him as much as it excited him.
And the more he thought about it
all, the more impatient he became.
'Paris' was the word he kept saying to
himself. Since he had to go there for his final
examinations, why not go now? What was stopping
him? And he began to plan a new life for himself.
He would live like an artist. He would take
guitar lessons. He would wear a red coat
and a blue hat; he would go to the opera
every night and drink wine with actresses!
The great difficulty would be to persuade
his mother to agree - but, in fact,
it was quite easy. His own employer had been
telling him to take up work in another office
and widen his experience, and his mother
wanted Leon to qualify as soon as possible.
Two days after he had sent his letter, she
wrote back to him giving her permission!
When he knew he could leave, however, he
did not hurry. Every day, for a whole month,
boxes and parcels were delivered to his
rooms in Yonville; and although Leon had
soon made enough preparations - and more
than enough - for a voyage round the world,
he kept putting things off from week to week.
However, at last the time came to leave, and he
hardly had time to say goodbye to Monsieur Bovary.
He ran up the stairs to the sitting room,
and as he went in Madame Bovary rose quickly.
'Here I am again!' said Leon.
'I knew you would come!'
She bit her lip hard, and could feel herself
blush from the roots of her hair to the edge
of her collar. She remained standing,
leaning her shoulder against the wall.
'Is the doctor in?' he said.
'No, he's gone out.' And she
repeated, 'He's gone out.'
Then there was silence.
'I would like to kiss Berthe goodbye,' he said.
Emma went down a few stairs and called Felicite.
He gave a long look round -
at the walls, the shelves,
the fireplace - as if to carry
the memory of it away with him.
Emma returned, and the servant came in with
Berthe. Leon kissed her several times on the neck.
'Goodbye, my poor little thing;
goodbye, my darling, goodbye.'
And he gave her back to her mother.
'Take her away,' she said.
And now they were alone.
Madame Bovary had her back to him, her
face against the glass of the window.
Leon was holding his cap in his hand
and beating it gently against his thigh.
'It's going to rain,' said Emma.
'I've got a coat,' he answered.
'Ah!'
She turned away again, her face down.
No one could have said what Emma
was looking at through the glass.
'Well, this is goodbye!' he sighed.
She raised her head with a sudden movement.
'Yes, goodbye... Oh, go!'
They advanced towards each other.
He held out his hand. She hesitated.
'In the English style, then!' she said,
putting hers in his, forcing herself to laugh.
Leon felt her hand between his fingers, and
it seemed that his whole life flowed into it.
Then he released her hand, their eyes
met for a moment, and he was gone.
CHAPTER NINE
Starting Again
The next day, for Emma, was like a funeral.
She felt the same grey unhappiness she had
known when she came back from La Vaubyessard with
the dance tunes playing in her head and her boring
husband sitting opposite her. In her imagination,
Leon came back to her, taller, more beautiful than
ever; though he was separated from her, he had
not left her. He was there, and the walls of the
house seemed to hold his shadow. She asked herself
again and again why she had not taken the chance
when it was offered to her. Why hadn't she held
him back with both hands, begged and prayed to
him on her knees, when he tried to leave? She
cursed herself for not giving her love to Leon;
she was thirsty for his lips. She wanted to fly
after him and join him, to throw herself into his
arms and say, 'I have come, I am yours!' But Emma
was afraid of all the difficulties in the way;
she wanted Leon and dared not give herself,
and her desire seemed to grow day by day.
And so the memory of Leon became the centre
of her sorrow. It shone in the darkness,
and she hurried towards it to
warm herself by the dying flames.
But the fires died down and, little
by little, the flame of love cooled.
Then the unhappy days of Tostes began all
over again, but she felt herself much more
unfortunate now; she had experience of grief, and
she knew with certainty that it would never end.
A woman who has given up as much as she
had, had the right to a few luxuries.
In a single month, she bought fourteen
francs' worth of lemons to clean her nails.
She wrote to Rouen and ordered a blue silk
dress, and from Lheureux she bought the
finest scarf he had in his shop. She tied it
round her waist, outside her dressing-gown,
and would lie by the hour on the sofa with
the curtains closed and a book in her hand.
But despite her little comforts, Emma did not
become happy. She had that tight look at the
corners of her mouth which you see in people who
have failed in their lives. She was pale, white
as a sheet, and she had an uncertain, hunted look
in her eyes. And because she had discovered three
grey hairs, she talked about being an old woman.
Also, she had frequent attacks of dizziness.
One day she spat blood and, as Charles rushed
over to her, obviously very anxious, all she
said was, 'Bah! What does it matter?' Charles
went and shut himself in the surgery and wept.
Although the Bovary household had
become a place of unhappiness again,
life in Yonville continued as usual.
People went to the church on Sundays,
and on Wednesdays the market was held in
the town square. From early morning the
square filled up with farmers and people
with goods to sell from as far as Rouen.
On Wednesdays the pharmacy never emptied. Some
came to buy medicine, others to get advice.
Monsieur Homais was a well-known man in all the
villages near Yonville, and they thought he knew
more about doctoring than all the doctors
put together. Emma was seated at her window
and was amusing herself by looking at the crowd
of country people, when she noticed a gentleman
in a green coat. He was wearing yellow gloves
and heavy, highly polished brown leather boots,
and was making his way towards the
doctor's house, followed by a farm worker.
'Can I see the doctor?' he asked the maid.
'Tell him Monsieur Rodolphe
Boulanger of La Huchette is here.'
Charles came into the room, and Monsieur Boulanger
presented his man, who said he wanted to be bled
to cure his dizziness. So Bovary told
them to bring him a bandage and a basin,
and asked the maid to hold it.
'Don't be afraid,' he said, turning to the
farm worker, who had gone as white as a sheet.
'Not me, sir!' he replied. And he stuck
out a great arm for Charles to cut,
and out shot the blood.
'Hold the bowl nearer!' cried Charles.
'Look!' said the worker. 'You'd
think it was a little fountain.
My blood's red enough! You'd say that
was a good sign now, wouldn't you?'
'Sometimes they feel nothing to start with.
Then faintness begins, especially with big,
strong people like this man here,'
said Charles to Monsieur Boulanger.
Hearing this, the man gave a sudden
movement and fell back into the chair.
'I knew it!' said Bovary,
putting his finger on the vein.
But now the bowl of blood was beginning to shake
in the maid's hands, and she also turned pale.
'Emma! Quick! I want you!' shouted Charles.
She ran down the stairs.
'Get me some vinegar,' he said.
'Good Lord, two of them at once!'
'It's nothing at all,' said
Monsieur Boulanger calmly,
as he took the maid in his arms
and leaned her against the wall.
Madame Bovary took hold of the basin.
She bent down to put it under the table,
and as she did so her long yellow dress
spread out all around her on the floor.
Then, as she stretched out her arm, she
swayed a little and the cloth moved with her,
following the shape of the body beneath it. After
a moment she went to fetch a jug of water, and she
was putting some pieces of sugar in it when the
pharmacist arrived to see what was happening.
When things had become calmer, they
began to talk about fainting attacks.
Madame Bovary said she had never had one herself.
'That's unusual for a woman,' commented Monsieur
Boulanger. 'But there are some sensitive people
around. I have seen soldiers faint at the
sound of the big guns being prepared.'
Emma listened to him with admiration in
her eyes. 'Anyway, my man's fainting has
given me the pleasure of meeting Madame,'
he added, looking at Emma as he spoke.
He put down three francs on
the corner of the table, bowed
and departed. He was soon on the other side of the
river, on the road back to La Huchette, and from
the bedroom window Emma could see him slowing down
from time to time, like someone lost in thought.
'Pretty little woman, this doctor's wife - very
pretty indeed! Lovely teeth, dark eyes, neat foot.
She could be a Parisian. Where does she come from,
and where did our fat country doctor pick her up?'
Monsieur Rodolphe Boulanger was a man of
thirty-four, hard-hearted but clever. He
had plenty of experience with women, and knew how
to get on with them. This latest one had attracted
his attention. 'The doctor looks a dull dog to me.
I expect she's sick of him. He's got dirty nails
and three days' beard. While he's out seeing
his patients, she sits at home mending socks.
And she's sick to death of it, wants to live in
town and go to a dance every night. Poor little
woman! She's dying for love. A word or two about
hearts and flowers and she'd be at your feet.
But getting rid of her afterwards,
that's where the trouble would come in.'
There was no one around, and
the only sounds Rodolphe heard
were the grass brushing against his boots
and the cry of the insects in the fields.
Once more he imagined Emma, dressed as he had seen
her, and he started to undress her in his mind.
'Oh, I'll have her!' he cried, striking
out at the earth with his stick.
Two weeks later it was the day of the
famous Yonville Agricultural Show,
the most important event of the year. On the
morning of the great day, the inhabitants were
all out on their doorsteps discussing the
arrangements. The front of the Town Hall
had been decorated, a tent had been put up for the
lunch, and the whole town was alive with activity.
The crowd poured into the High
Street from both ends of the village.
What caused the greatest admiration were two tall
poles covered with tiny lamps, standing beside the
platform where the most important guests would
sit. Madame Lefrancois, the landlady of the Lion
d'Or, and Monsieur Homais, the pharmacist, stood
on the steps of the hotel watching the growing
crowd and the men going in and out of the Cafe de
France - the main competition to the Lion d'Or.
'Well, that won't last much longer,' she said.
'One more week and that will be the end of it.'
Homais looked at her in surpise.
She walked down her three steps.
'What!' she said, speaking into his ear. 'Didn't
you know? They're going to have to close down
and move this week. It's Lheureux that's making
them do it, he's got them so deep into debt!'
And Madame Lefrancois began to tell Monsieur
Homais how the draper had lent the owners of the
Cafe de France more money than they could ever pay
back, and now they were having to sell everything.
'Look!' she said. 'There he
is, Lheureux - over there,
in the market. Look! He's bowing to Madame Bovary.
Do look! She's got a green hat on. Do you see
her? She's leaning on Monsieur Boulanger's arm.'
'Madame Bovary!' said Homais. 'Oh,
I must go over and say how do you do to her!
She might like to have a seat on the platform.'
Rodolphe saw him coming and
walked more quickly but then,
as Madame Bovary was getting
out of breath, he slowed down.
'I wanted to avoid that fool - you know, that
chemist fellow,' he said to her with a laugh.
Emma smiled at him.
'What does that smile mean?' he
wondered. 'Is she making fun of
me?' And he looked at her out of the corner
of his eye as they walked on more quickly.
When they reached the corner, Rodolphe,
instead of going right into the square,
suddenly turned down a side-path,
dragging Emma with him.
'Good evening, Monsieur Lheureux,'
he called out. 'See you later.'
'You did that very well!' said Emma, laughing.
'Why should I let these people
bother me? And today of all days,
when I have the luck to be with you...'
Emma blushed. He did not finish his sentence.
Then he remarked on the fine weather,
and said how nice it was to walk on the grass
where small yellow flowers had sprung up.
'Look,' he said, 'young girls in love
use these to see if they are loved.
Suppose I picked one of these. What
do you think it would tell me?'
'Are you in love?' she said, with a little cough.
'Ah! Who knows?' answered Rodolphe.
The market square and the fields around continued
to fill up with people. The judging was now going
on and the farmers, lined up one after another,
were all crowding into a ring. There were the
farm animals in a long, irregular line. Among the
sleepy pigs and cows, bare-armed men were holding
on to great male horses which pulled with all
their strength in the direction of the females.
These stood quite still, holding their heads
down, while their young rested in their shadows.
By now, Emma and Monsieur Boulanger
had come round to the field.
They discussed the people they saw, how
Paris was so much more interesting than
a place like Yonville, and they laughed
at the fashions of the farmers' wives.
'But anyway,' he said, 'when
you live in the country -'
'What's the point of looking good?'
'I agree,' answered Rodolphe. 'Not one of these
people knows when a coat is
well cut and when it isn't.'
And they agreed that life away
from town was hardly worth living.
'Which is why,' said Rodolphe,
'I am so sad at times.'
'You!' she broke in with amazement. 'I
thought you had nothing to worry about!'
'Ah, yes, it seems so, but we cannot
always show the world who we really are,
our true selves. Whenever I
look at a cemetery by moonlight,
I ask myself if I wouldn't be happier
lying there asleep with the rest of them.'
'But what about your friends?
You don't think of them.'
'My friends? What friends? What friends
have I got? Who cares about me?'
So they walked on arm in arm, ignoring
the arrival of the guests of honour,
Emma leaning against this strong
man with such pain in his heart.
As the crowd gathered to hear the speeches,
Rodolphe, accompanied by Madame Bovary,
went up on to the first floor of the Town
Hall into the empty council meeting room.
He fetched two chairs and, bringing them close
up to the window, they sat down side by side.
As soon as the speeches began,
people quietened down a little,
and Emma leaned forward to see better.
'I'd better get a bit
farther back,' said Rodolphe.
'Why?' asked Emma.
'They might see me from down below.
And then I would have to give explanations for
at least a fortnight, and with my reputation...'
'Oh, you're making yourself sound
much worse than you are,' said Emma.
'No, no; it's horrible, I tell you!'
The voice of the next speaker went on
like an angry insect in the hot sun.
'But,' added Rodolphe, 'the world may be right.'
'What do you mean?' she asked.
'Well,' he said, 'don't you know that there
are some people who are never at peace;
people who desire dreams and action, the wildest
pleasures - but after passion comes regret!'
She looked at him as if he were a traveller who
has journeyed through strange and far-off lands.
'We poor women, we never have such
good reasons for regret,' she said.
'Ah, but to behave as badly as I
have does not make you any happier!'
'But does one ever find happiness?'
'Yes, one day,' he replied.
The speaker continued to praise the farmers,
their animals and their rich fields. Some
listened and some began to sleep in their
seats, heads falling forward in the summer heat.
'Yes,' said Rodolphe, 'you don't have to
think about it; one day you meet someone,
and the horizon opens up in front of you. There
are no more questions. It's as if you have already
met one another in your dreams.' (Here he looked
at Emma.) 'There in front of you is the jewel
you have been looking for; there before your
eyes. Nevertheless, you dare not believe it;
you cannot see clearly, it is as if you had just
stepped out of the darkness into the light.'
And as he said this, Rodolphe passed his hand
over his face, then he let it fall on Emma's,
who took hers away. Still the speaker read on,
praising those who did their duty on the land.
'Ah, there he goes again!' said Rodolphe. 'Duty,
duty - always duty! I'm sick to death of the word!
We must follow our hearts
- that is our true duty!'
'Yes, but - but -' said Madame Bovary, 'don't you
also think we must follow the laws of society?'
'Ah! But there are two laws,' he replied.
'There is the little, unimportant man-made law,
always changing, made by fools like that one down
there. And there is the other, which never changes
and is all around us, like the countryside
and the blue heavens that give us light.'
The whole square was now crowded with people.
They could be seen leaning on
their elbows at every window,
others standing at their doors. In spite of the
silence, the speaker's voice was lost in the
air. It rose in broken phrases, interrupted here
and there by the sound of chairs on the stones.
Rodolphe had moved nearer to Emma,
and said to her in a low voice,
speaking rapidly, 'Don't society's
demands disgust you? The best feelings,
the purest thoughts are attacked, controlled, and
if at last two souls do meet, they cannot unite.
They will try, they will call out to each
other. But sooner or later - in six months,
ten years - they will come together, they
will love; they are born for each other.'
Lifting his face towards Emma,
he looked closely at her.
She noticed in his eyes small golden
lines coming from the dark centre,
she smelt the perfume on his hair, and
she half closed her eyes to breathe it in.
She took off her gloves, she wiped her hands,
then tried to cool her face with her handkerchief.
Through the sound of her blood beating in
her ears, she heard the sound of the crowd
and the voice of the speaker telling
them to work harder, to be good citizens.
Now Rodolphe took her hand and she did not
take it away. As the names of the prize
winners in the show were read out below, he
told her he had never loved anyone before her,
and he would love her for the rest of his
life. He pressed her hand, and felt its
warmth and life - like a bird held for a moment,
perhaps trying to escape, perhaps responding.
'Oh, thank you, thank you!' he
cried. 'You do not reject me.
How sweet you are! You know that I am yours.'
Suddenly the wind rose, shaking the curtains
and causing the peasant women in the square
to hold on to the wings of their white hats.
The speaker began to speak more
quickly, more enthusiastically,
but neither Rodolphe nor Emma were listening.
They sat and looked into each other's eyes.
Their lips were dry, their bodies full of desire,
and Emma no longer felt a need to resist. Down
in the square the speakers continued, the prizes
were given. The celebrations would be over soon.
Madame Bovary took Rodolphe's arm, and he walked
with her back to her house. They said goodbye at
her front door, after which he went and
walked in the fields near the river.
CHAPTER TEN
Presents for a Lover
Six weeks went by, and
Rodolphe did not contact Emma.
'I must not go back too soon,' he had
said to himself. 'It would be a mistake.'
The week after the show, he went off shooting.
When the hunting was over he wondered if he had
left it too long, but then he thought to himself,
'If she loved me from the first day, by now she
will love me even more. I will let her wait.'
When he saw how pale she became when he entered
the room, he knew he had made the right decision.
She was alone and it was getting dark.
Rodolphe remained standing, and Emma was
barely able to answer his first greeting.
'I've been busy,' he said. 'I haven't been well.'
'Nothing serious?' she asked quickly.
'Oh, well, no,' said Rodolphe, sitting
down. 'I didn't want to come here again.'
'Why?'
'Can't you guess?'
He looked at her again, but with such a look
of love that she lowered her eyes with a blush.
'Emma!' he began again.
'Sir!' she cried, moving back a little.
'Ah! You see perfectly well now that I
was right not to return,' he said sadly,
'but I have been thinking of you; thinking
and thinking till I've become almost mad.
Ah, forgive me! I'll go away - far away - and
you will never hear of me again. But today,
somehow, it seemed that
something, I don't know what,
made me come to you. Who can help falling in love
with someone who is so beautiful, so charming?'
It was the first time in her
life Emma had heard such words.
She turned towards him with tears in her eyes.
'Oh, how kind you are!' she said.
'No,' he said, 'I love you, that's all. You know
I do, don't you? Tell me you know it - just one
word, one little word!' And Rodolphe began to
go down on his knees. But there was a noise of
someone moving around in the kitchen, and
he noticed that the door was not closed.
'It would be so kind of you,' he said, getting up,
'if you could let me see your
house. It's such a charming place.'
Madame Bovary said she would be happy to do this,
and they were just getting
up when Charles came in.
'Good morning, Doctor,' said Rodolphe. 'Madame,'
he continued, 'was talking to me about her health.
I was saying that a little horse
riding might be a good thing.'
'An excellent idea... You
should do that, darling.'
When she replied that she had no horse, Monsieur
Rodolphe offered to lend her one. She refused,
and he did not insist. And
that was the end of the visit.
'Why didn't you accept Monsieur Boulanger's
offer? It was very good of him,'
said Charles when they were alone.
She said that perhaps people
would think it rather odd.
'Well, who cares about that?' said Charles.
'Health, that's the main
thing. It was silly of you.'
'And how do you expect me to go riding
when I haven't got the right clothes?'
'We will get you some,' he replied.
The promise of new clothes was
enough to make Emma change her mind.
When Emma's riding clothes were ready,
Charles wrote to Monsieur Boulanger
saying that his wife could go any time, and
that they were grateful for his kind offer.
Next day, Rodolphe appeared at Charles's
door with two horses. He had put on a pair
of new riding-boots, telling himself that she had
certainly never seen anything like them before,
and Emma was charmed with the way he looked.
As soon as he felt the grass under him,
Emma's horse started to move more quickly,
and Rodolphe came along beside her. Every
now and then they exchanged a word or two.
She rode with her head a little forward, her
hand well up and her right arm stretched out,
and she let herself follow the movements
of the horse. They rode on like this for
fifteen or twenty minutes until, at the
top of a small hill, the horses stopped.
It was early in October, and a thin mist was
spread over the land. Sometimes the sun would
shine through a break in the clouds and
light up the distant roofs of Yonville,
with the gardens near the water, the yards, the
walls and the church. Emma half closed her eyes
to see her house, and never had this poor
village in which she lived seemed so small.
After a moment, Rodolphe and Emma turned
off and rode along the edge of the wood.
She turned away her head every
now and again to avoid his eyes,
and saw only the trunks of the trees. Just
as they entered the wood, the sun came out.
'God is with us!' said Rodolphe.
'You think so?' she answered.
'Come on! Come on!' was his reply.
The path narrowed as they went into the wood,
and sometimes, to keep away the branches,
he rode close up to her and Emma felt his knee
rubbing against her leg. The sky was blue now, and
not a leaf moved. They got down from their horses
and Emma walked a little further down the path.
Rodolphe came up behind her, stretched
out his arm and put it round her waist.
She made an effort to break away,
but he continued to hold her,
so she turned and walked back
towards where they had stopped.
'Oh, stay!' said Rodolphe.
'We must not go yet! Stay!'
And he took her to a little pool, whose surface
was covered with small green water plants.
'It is wrong of me! Wrong, wrong!' she
cried. 'I am mad to listen to you.'
'Why? Emma! Emma!'
'Oh, Rodolphe!' she cried, dropping
her head against his shoulder.
With a deep sigh she threw back her head,
giving her white neck to his kisses and,
almost fainting, in tears, her whole body shaking
with emotion, hiding her face in her hands,
she surrendered herself to him.
When evening began to fall the sun, shining
through the branches, was bright in her eyes.
Everywhere was silence. She could feel
her heart as it began to beat again,
she could feel the blood moving
through her body like a stream of milk.
And then, far, far away, beyond the wood, on
the hills across the valley, she heard a cry,
strange and distant, a voice that hung in the
air, and she listened to it in silence. Rodolphe
was standing with a cigar between his teeth,
cleaning his fingernails with a small knife.
They returned to Yonville by the way they
had come. They saw the tracks of their horses
in the soil, side by side, and there were the
same bushes and the same stones in the grass.
Nothing about them had changed,
but for her something had happened,
something more surprising than if the
mountains had fallen into the sea.
When she was alone in her room after dinner, she
looked at herself in the mirror and was amazed at
her own face. Never had her eyes looked so big,
so dark, so deep. It was as if she had become
another woman. And she kept saying to herself
over and over again, 'I have a lover, a lover.'
From that first day they wrote to each other
every night. Emma took her letter to the end of
the garden near the river and put it in a gap
in the wall. Rodolphe would come and take it
and put another in its place, and always she
complained that his letters were too short.
The time she had with him was too short too,
so whenever Charles was called out early,
Emma got up, threw on some clothes and ran
through the fields to Rodolphe's house.
At this early hour Rodolphe would still
be asleep, and Emma seemed like a spring
morning coming into his room. Laughing, he would
pull her towards him and down on to his breast,
and afterwards it would take them a quarter of an
hour to say goodbye. Emma would burst out crying;
she would have liked to stay with Rodolphe
always and never leave him any more.
But one day, when she came in unexpectedly,
a look of annoyance passed over his face.
'What's the matter?' she said.
'Don't you feel well? Tell me!'
At first he said nothing, but then,
looking very serious about it,
he told her that he was worried
about these early morning visits.
People would start talking about her.
They needed another meeting place.
Rodolphe said he would look out for a house
outside Yonville where they could be together,
but all through the winter, three or four times a
week, and when it was quite dark, the only place
they could find was Emma's garden. They would come
together there after Charles had gone to sleep.
The cold made them hold each other tighter;
their eyes, though they could hardly see them
in the growing darkness, seemed bigger. On wet
nights they would take shelter in the surgery.
She would light one of the kitchen candles
and Rodolphe made himself quite at home.
The sight of the bookcase and the desk -
everything in the room, in fact - seemed to amuse
him, and he could not stop himself from making
all sorts of little jokes about Charles. This
did not please Emma. She would have liked him to
be a little more serious, a little more dramatic.
But Rodolphe felt no need to change his ways and
was, in fact, becoming a little bored with Emma's
delicate emotions and sensitivities. She even
talked about wanting a ring - a proper wedding
ring - as a symbol of their union. He never spoke
to her now as he used to, saying the sweet, tender
things that had made her cry with happiness. He
never kissed her and held her in the old way.
No! That great love of theirs, on
whose waves she had been carried away,
seemed to be growing shallower beneath her,
like the waters of a river in a dry summer,
and now she could see the mud that lay beneath it!
As Emma grew to understand that this
great love affair might not be for ever,
Rodolphe found her becoming more and more distant,
even cooler towards him. For a few weeks she even
spent more time with Charles, trying to see if
she could love him better. But it was no use,
and Rodolphe thought to himself, 'She'll get
over it. It's just one of her little ways.'
He was right. All he had to do was
to keep away, to miss their meeting
for three or four nights, and once again
her complaints stopped and she was his!
So love began for them again.
Often, in the middle of the day,
Emma would take up a pen and write to him. And
she did not only send letters, but also presents,
small expensive things that she could not afford,
and which she could not ask her husband to buy.
It was Monsieur Lheureux, the draper,
who was able to help her here.
As soon as he heard that Madame Bovary was
buying gifts for someone, he made sure he
met her as often as he could. He told her
all about the latest deliveries from Paris,
was very helpful and never asked for his money.
Emma found this a very easy way to satisfy her
wish to please her lover, and she took full
advantage of it. For example, she wanted to
buy Rodolphe a very handsome riding whip that
was on show at an umbrella shop in Rouen.
And next week, there was Monsieur Lheureux
putting it on her dining room table.
But the day after that, he came along with a bill
for two hundred and seventy francs! Emma did not
know what to do. All the drawers in the desk had
been emptied out. She owed wages to the servants,
and Bovary was anxiously waiting for
a payment from Monsieur Derozerays,
who, in previous years, had always paid
his doctor's bill some time in July.
At first she managed to get rid of Lheureux, but
in the end he lost patience. He had to pay his
bills, other people were asking him for the money!
He would be forced to ask her to return the goods.
'Very well, take them,' said Emma.
'Oh, I was only joking!' he replied. 'The
only thing that worries me is the riding whip.
I know! I'll ask the doctor
to let me have it back.'
'No, don't!' she cried out.
'Aha, I've got you!' thought Lheureux to
himself. And, sure of being on the right track,
he went out, saying under his breath,
'Right! We shall see, we shall see!'
She was wondering how she was going to get out
of this difficulty when the maid came in and
put a little packet on the table, 'From Monsieur
Derozerays.' Emma took the envelope and tore it
open. It was enough money to pay her debts!
She heard Charles coming up the stairs and,
without thinking, she threw the money to the back
of the drawer, locked it, and took out the key.
Three days later Lheureux reappeared.
'I want to suggest an arrangement,' he said.
'If, instead of the sum agreed, you would...'
'There you are,' said she, putting
the four hundred francs in his hand.
She was safe for the moment, but what would
happen next time? What could she do to escape?
Her dream now was to go away with Rodolphe.
One night when they met in the garden, and
she was at her saddest and most beautiful,
he asked her what he could do to help
her, to bring back the smile to her face.
'What must we do? What do you want?'
'Take me away!' she cried. 'Take
me from here... Oh, I beg you!'
'But...' Rodolphe began.
'Yes?'
'What about your little girl?'
She thought a minute or two and then answered,
'We'll take her with us.
It's the only thing to do.'
'What a woman!' he said to himself, as he
saw her disappear. Someone was calling.
But now Emma believed that she would be able
to escape, and this became her only topic
of conversation with Rodolphe. She would
lean her head on his shoulder and whisper,
'Ah, when we are in the coach! Can you
imagine it? Is it possible? It seems
to me that the moment I feel it moving, it
will be as if we were going up in a balloon,
as if we were going to the clouds. Do you
know, I'm counting the days! Aren't you?'
Never had Madame Bovary looked so beautiful as
now. Charles thought her as delicious as on the
day she became his bride. When he came home
late at night, he did not dare to wake her.
The night-lamp threw a ring of light on the
ceiling as she lay sleeping beside her daughter.
Charles would stand and look at
them, dreaming of the future,
of his beautiful wife and his growing child. But
he was not in Emma's dreams; she was heading for
a new land in a coach pulled by four white
horses and with her lover by her side.
She was so certain she would be leaving that
she sent for Monsieur Lheureux and ordered a
heavy travelling coat and a travelling case. She
told him to keep the things at the shop when they
arrived, and she would collect them in a week
or two. It was, in fact, the following month
that they were going to run away. She would leave
Yonville as if she were going shopping in Rouen.
Rodolphe would have booked the seats, arranged
the passports, and written to Paris in order
to have the mail coach all to themselves
as far as Marseilles. There they would buy
a carriage and go right through to Genoa. In
all this planning the child was never mentioned,
and Rodolphe avoided any reference to her;
perhaps Emma had given up the idea of taking her.
However, Rodolphe then found he needed a
fortnight to complete certain business matters;
then, after a week, he needed another fortnight.
Then he found he was not feeling very well so
there was another delay, and then he went away
on a journey. The whole of August went by and
finally, after all these delays, the date of their
departure was fixed for 4 September, a Monday.
On the evening of their last Saturday in Yonville,
Rodolphe came to see her earlier than usual.
'Is everything ready?' she asked.
'Yes.'
'You're sad,' said Emma.
'No. Why?'
'Is it because you are going away?' she
went on. 'Leaving the things you love,
the things that have been your
life? Ah, I understand! But I,
I have nothing in the world! You are everything
to me. And so I shall be everything to you.'
'Oh, what a lovely night!' said Rodolphe.
'We shall have many more nights together,' she
answered. And then, as if speaking to herself,
she went on, 'Yes, it will be good
to travel. But why is my heart so
sad? Is it fear of the unknown... or
the break with all I have been used to?
Or else...? No, it is because I am too happy
in my happiness! How weak I am! Forgive me!'
'There is still time,' he exclaimed.
'Think! You may regret it later.'
'Never!' she cried.
The clock struck twelve.
'Midnight!' she said. 'Tomorrow is already
here! We have just one more day to wait!'
He rose to go.
'You've got the passports?'
'Yes.'
'You haven't forgotten anything?'
'No.'
'You're sure?'
'Quite sure.'
'You'll be waiting for me at the Hotel de
Provence, won't you? At twelve o'clock?'
He nodded.
'Tomorrow, then!' said Emma,
and she watched him go.
He did not look back.
After a few minutes Rodolphe stopped, and when he
saw her white figure disappear into the shadows
his heart began to beat so wildly that he had to
lean against a tree to keep himself from falling.
'What a fool I am! But, never mind, she was a fine
little woman!' And as he said it, Emma's beauty,
the thought of all the times they had had
together, came back into his mind. For a moment
tears came to his eyes, but then he
felt a wave of anger against her.
'After all,' he cried, 'I couldn't just go and
bury myself alive like that - and have to look
after the child too! And think of the worry, the
expense! Ah, no, it would have been too silly!'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Goodbye
The letter Rodolphe wrote that
evening ended with the words:
... I shall be far away when
you read these sad lines.
I have made up my mind to go at once, so that
I cannot see you again! I shall come back,
no doubt, and perhaps one day we shall talk
together of the time when we were lovers.
Your Friend.
As she read these words the next morning,
Emma's first thought was to kill herself. Life
no longer had meaning; how could she eat another
meal, sit in the same room as her husband?
Rodolphe! How could she live without him? The room
started to spin around her, nothing was still,
she could not see, and everything went black.
Then Charles was shouting for
help, Berthe was screaming,
and Felicite, the maid, with shaking hands,
was loosening her mistress's clothing.
Emma herself lay stretched out on
the floor, shaking from head to foot.
'Speak! speak!' Charles kept on saying.
'Emma! It's me, your own Charles,
who loves you. Don't you know me? Here!
Here's your little one. Kiss her, Emma!'
The child stretched out her arms to
her mother, to put them round her neck.
But Emma turned away her head
and cried, 'No, no... No one!'
She fainted away again. They carried her
up to bed. She lay there, her mouth open,
her eyes shut, her hands open, quite still.
The tears ran from her eyes on to the pillow.
For forty-three days Charles never left Emma's
side. His patients had to take care of themselves.
He called in Monsieur Canivet, in consultation.
He sent to Rouen for Dr Lariviere, his old master;
he was desperate. What scared him most was
Emma's depressed condition. She did not speak,
took no notice of anything, and did
not even seem to suffer - as if her
soul and body were both resting after
the shock through which they had passed.
About halfway through October she was able to
sit up in bed, supported by pillows. Charles
cried when he saw her eating her first piece of
bread and jam. She began to recover her strength
and got up for an hour or two in the afternoons,
and one day, when she was feeling much better,
he persuaded her to walk a little
in the garden, leaning on his arm.
So they went, arm in arm, to the bottom of the
garden and its low wall. Slowly she looked up
and, shading her eyes with her hand, she
looked away, far, far away, into the distance.
But there was nothing on the skyline except
the smoke of burning grass on the hills.
She turned back to look into the
garden, and remembered Rodolphe,
remembered their nights of love in this place,
and fell back into Charles's arms, seeing nothing.
That night she was as ill as before, though
this time her condition was more complicated.
First it was her heart that troubled
her. Then her chest, or her head.
Then she had attacks of vomiting, which Charles
thought might be the early signs of cancer.
And on top of all this trouble, the
poor man was worried about money.
First, he did not know how he was going to pay
Monsieur Homais for all the medicines he had had
from him. And the bills kept pouring in. Monsieur
Lheureux, the draper, was especially difficult.
In fact, when Emma's illness was at its worst,
Lheureux, taking advantage of the situation,
had rushed over with the coat, the travelling
bag, two travelling boxes instead of one, and
other unordered items as well! Charles, of course,
said he had no use for them, but it was no good;
the goods had been ordered, and the
draper was not going to take them back.
In the end, Bovary found himself signing a
document promising to pay in six months - and
then borrowing another thousand francs! So
Charles's problems worsened, while Lheureux
was delighted to have both husband and wife
in his debt. He saw it as a good investment.
Charles often wondered how he was going
to pay all this money back next year.
He thought and thought; maybe he
should ask his father for help,
or sell something. But his father would not
listen, and he - well, he had nothing to sell.
And then the whole situation began to look so
black that he hurriedly pushed it out of his mind.
The winter was a hard one, and Emma took longer
to recover this time. When the weather was fine,
they pushed her chair up to the window,
so that she could look out on the square.
She had now taken a violent dislike to the garden,
and the curtains on that side were always closed.
Now she passed her time reading religious texts
which the priest brought for her, and Rodolphe
was pushed back into a hidden place in her heart.
And although her recovery continued, she was so
much changed that she even enjoyed the company
of the respectable married women of Yonville.
When the spring came, she had the
whole garden torn up from end to end.
Her old energy had begun to return as her health
improved, and although Monsieur Bournisien,
the priest, still continued to visit her
every day, she went to church less often.
She began to enjoy time spent out of doors,
looking over the new garden, even sitting
outside with Charles and Monsieur Homais in the
warmer evenings. It was on one of these evenings,
as Monsieur Homais talked about the pleasures
one could gain from literature and music,
that the idea of going to see Lucia di Lammermoor
at the theatre in Rouen was raised. Emma was
against the idea at first, but Charles felt that
the change would do her good, and he wanted to
give her a little pleasure, despite his debts and
their other worries. So Monsieur and Madame Bovary
drove in to Rouen on the Friday coach and got
down at the Hotel de la Croix Rouge, in the place
Beauvoisine. Leaving Emma at the hotel, Charles at
once went out to buy tickets for the theatre.
CHAPTER TWELVE
A Visit to the Theatre
Emma was pleased that her husband had bought
good seats, and when she sat down she could
not resist a little smile of pride as she
looked at the ordinary people down below.
Soon the candles were being lit, the musicians
were taking their places and the opera was
starting. When they began to play, she lost
herself in the music, her eyes almost blinded
by the richness of the colours, the beauty of
the singers. And their voices, their beautiful
bodies dressed in the finest clothes you could
imagine, their noble emotions - it was too much!
Poor Charles, however,
could understand none of it.
'Why is he so unkind to her?' he whispered.
'But he isn't,' she answered. 'He's her lover.'
Emma tried to explain as well as she
could, but he confessed that he could
not follow the story because all this
music stopped him from hearing the words.
'What does it matter?' said Emma. 'Be quiet!'
'Well, you see,' he answered,
leaning over on her shoulder,
'I like to understand things;
you know I always do.'
'Oh, please be quiet!' she cried impatiently.
So Charles sat in silence while Emma
became more and more involved in the story
of the tragic heroine, a story which
made her think about her own life.
As the singer came to the front of
the stage, supported by her women,
white flowers in her hair, and as pale as
death, Emma began dreaming of her own marriage.
She saw herself back again on the little
footpath, when she and her father were
making their way to the church. Why had she not
fought against her father, as Lucia had done?
Instead, she had been happy and light-hearted,
never realizing how she was throwing herself away!
The curtain fell at the end of the first
act. Emma wanted to go out; the corridors
were crowded with people, and she sank back in
her seat feeling as if she could not breathe.
Charles thought she was going to faint, and
rushed off to the bar to get her a glass of water.
When he returned with the water, he also
brought the news that he had seen Monsieur Leon.
'Leon?'
'The man himself! He's coming
round in a minute to see you!'
And before these words were out of his mouth, the
ex-clerk from Yonville came and sat beside her.
He put out his hand, and Madame Bovary gave him
hers, mechanically, as if obeying some force of
attraction she could not resist. She had not
felt this hand since that spring evening when
the rain was falling on the green leaves and
they said goodbye standing beside the window.
'Oh, how do you do? Imagine it! You here?'
They could not talk now, as the opera had begun
again, but from that moment she stopped listening.
Everything seemed to be taking place far away,
like the sound of music from a distant room.
As soon as the opera had finished, all
three of them went and sat in the open air,
outside a cafe. They began by talking about her
illness, Emma interrupting Charles every now and
then for fear, she said, of boring Monsieur Leon.
Then Leon told them how he was going to spend
two years in a lawyer's office here in Rouen.
He said that he needed the experience as the
work in Normandy was very different from the
kind of thing he had been doing in Paris.
People coming away from the theatre passed along
in front of them on the pavement, some still
singing the tunes from the opera. Although Leon
had not been impressed by the leading male singer,
Charles (who had begun to understand
things better towards the end of the show)
had appreciated his voice and said
he would love to hear him again.
'Oh, well,' said Leon, 'he'll be
giving another performance soon.'
But Charles replied that they
were going home in the morning.
'Unless you'd like to stay a little longer
by yourself,' he added, turning to his wife.
When Leon saw that there was a chance Emma might
be able to stay, he began to praise the singer,
and Charles became even more certain that
she must stay in Rouen for an extra night.
'You can come back on Sunday.
It's silly of you not to stay,
if you feel it's doing you even
the slightest bit of good.'
And so it was arranged that Charles
would return to Yonville in the morning,
and Leon would go to the opera with
Madame Bovary on the following evening.
Since leaving Yonville,
Leon had not forgotten Emma.
In Paris, he had worked at his studies and
had not had the wild time he had imagined.
It had been a happy but unexciting period,
and he had sometimes dreamed of the love that
might have been between them. Seeing
her again, after three long years,
all his hopes returned. This time he thought he
really would have to bring things to a conclusion.
He was less shy now, more sure of himself, and
after his time in Paris he felt quite confident
that he could have his way with this country
doctor's wife. He would not have been brave
enough to make the attempt in Paris, but
away from the capital he had the courage.
When they met the following afternoon, he did
his best to make himself interesting to her.
He talked, therefore, about how unhappy
he had been since he left Yonville,
and how his dreams had been disappointed.
'If you only knew,' she said,
'the dreams that I have dreamed.'
And tears shone in her beautiful eyes
as she raised them to the ceiling.
'And I, too!' cried Leon. 'I often
went out, trying to lose myself in
the noise of the crowd, but I was never
able to get you out of my thoughts.'
Madame Bovary turned away her head so that he
should not see the smile she felt on her lips.
She let him speak, saying nothing, waiting
for him to say what she wanted to hear.
She did not have to wait long.
'And,' he went on, 'I wrote you so
many letters that I never sent.'
'But why?' she asked.
'Why?' And he hesitated a
moment. 'Because I loved you!'
Congratulating himself for having said the words,
Leon watched her out of the corner of his eye.
It was like looking at the sky after
the sun has chased away the clouds.
Her whole face was lit up with joy.
He waited, and at last she said,
'I always thought you did.'
Then they talked about all the things that
had happened when he lived in Yonville.
They spoke of the flowers in her
garden, the dresses she used to wear,
the furniture in her bedroom, and of
all the things in and around the house.
They talked and talked, and before they realized
how time had passed, it was eight o'clock.
She rose to light the candles;
then she came and sat down again.
'Well?' said Leon, and he
reached out and touched her hand.
'What could stop us from
beginning all over again now?'
'No, my friend,' she replied. 'I am too old...
you are too young... Forget all about me.
Others will love you... and you will love them.'
'Not as I love you,' he cried.
'What a child you are! We have
to be sensible! I mean it!'
And she did mean it - she intended to keep her
distance, to be responsible. She had suffered too
much to want to open those wounds again. However,
she was not prepared for Leon's shyness. If he had
been another Rodolphe, it would have been easy;
she could have pushed him away without an effort.
But Leon was so beautiful, so full of desire
for her - she could see it in his eyes - but so
gentle, she did not know what to do. When he
took her face in his hands and kissed her,
she could not resist, because he did
it without force, with such care.
But still, she could not let this happen!
So she looked at the clock
above the fireplace and said,
'Heavens, look at the time! We have forgotten
all about the theatre! And I must go back to
my poor husband tomorrow, so
there is my last chance gone!'
'Are you really going back?' said Leon.
'I am.'
'But I must see you again,' he said. 'I
had something I wanted to tell you...'
'What is it?'
'Something... Oh, something
very serious, very important!
Ah, but no! You won't go back.
You can't. If you only knew...
Listen, you mustn't go like this! Let me
see you again, I beg you. Once, just once!'
'Well...' And she stopped. And then, as if on
second thoughts, she said, 'Oh, no. Not here!'
'Wherever you like.'
'Will you...?' She seemed to be thinking.
Then suddenly she said, 'Tomorrow,
at eleven, in the cathedral.'
'I shall be there,' he
cried, taking both her hands.
But that night Emma wrote a long, long
letter, excusing herself from meeting him.
It was all over now, and, for their own sakes,
it would be better for them not to meet.
But when the letter was sealed up, she
realized she did not know Leon's address.
'I will give it to him myself,'
she said. 'He is sure to come.'
Leon arrived early at the cathedral, and had to
wait in the cool shadows for what seemed like
hours. Suddenly, at around eleven o'clock,
there was the sound of silk upon the stones,
the shadow of a hat on the wall... It
was Emma! Leon rose and went to meet her.
Emma was pale, and she was walking quickly.
'Read this!' she said, holding out a paper.
But then, seeming to change her mind,
she cried out, 'Oh no! Never mind!'
And she quickly tore away her hand, and went out
into the sunshine again. She did not know what
to do, how to go on. She wanted to be here, to be
with him, and at the same time to fly, fly away.
Leon followed, feeling that his love was
in danger of disappearing like smoke.
Wanting to take back control of the situation
(which he felt was slipping through his fingers),
he decided to hire one of the carriages
which were waiting. They could drive away,
be together in this private, dark space.
They could not go to his room, nor to hers,
so a carriage, hired for the
day, would be their shelter.
'Leon, really... I don't know whether I ought.
It's not the proper thing
to do. You know it isn't!'
'Why not?' answered the
clerk. 'It's done in Paris.'
Emma had no reply to this.
'Where to, sir?' said the driver.
'Wherever you like,' said
Leon, pushing Emma inside;
and so they set off, first going
down to the bridge over the river,
then across the main square, past the
town hall and stopping beside a statue.
'Keep going,' said a voice from inside.
The carriage started again and, following the
downhill road after leaving the centre of town,
it drove at full speed into the square
in front of the railway station.
'No, no, straight on!' shouted the voice again.
The driver took them out of town through
the big gates, down to the waterside.
Along by the river the vehicle went,
towards the little town of Oyssel.
And on and on went the carriage, with
its sweating driver and tired horse.
Each time they stopped, the man's
voice cried out, 'Drive on, drive on!'
until, at about six in the evening, the carriage
stopped in a side street and a woman got out. She
walked away with her face hidden, looking
neither to the right nor to the left.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Love Once More
When she got back to her hotel, Emma was shocked
not to find the Yonville coach. The driver had
waited fifty-three minutes, and had at last
set off without her. Although there was no
strong reason why she should go home, she had
promised that she would be back that evening,
and she knew Charles would be expecting her.
In her heart she was also feeling guilty for
her afternoon of love with Leon. Going home this
evening was an easy way of making herself feel
better about what she had just done. So she
threw her things into her bag, paid her bill,
hired a small carriage from the hotel and,
telling the driver to drive like the wind,
managed to catch up with the coach just
as it was driving into Quincampoix.
She had hardly sunk into her
corner when she closed her eyes,
and did not open them again till they were
at the bottom of the hill. Some way off,
she recognized her maid, Felicite, who was
waiting for her at the entrance to the village.
The driver pulled in to the side, and
the maid called up to her mistress,
'Madame, you must go at once to
Monsieur Homais. Something very urgent!'
The village was as quiet as usual, but
when she went into Monsieur Homais' house
she found the pharmacist waiting for her
with a serious expression on his face.
'Madame, I fear I have bad news for
you. Your father-in-law is dead!'
In fact, Monsieur Bovary senior
had died the previous evening
quite suddenly just after getting up
from dinner. As Charles was anxious
that Emma should not be upset, he had asked
Monsieur Homais to break the news to her.
He had thought it might be less of a shock if it
came from someone outside the family. Although
Charles's thought was kind, Emma was not, in fact,
greatly upset, and went immediately to her house.
When he heard Emma knock, Charles came
forward to greet her with open arms and said,
with tears in his voice, 'Ah! My dear...'
He bent down to kiss her, but at the touch of his
lips, the memory of her lover took hold of her
and she passed her hand over her
face to hide her look of disgust.
Nevertheless, she managed to
say, 'Yes, I know... I know...'
He showed her the letter in which
his mother told him the news.
Emma gave the letter back, and at dinner, out of
politeness, pretended to have no appetite. But
as he encouraged her, she forced herself to eat,
while Charles sat facing her in motionless sorrow.
Every now and then he would raise
his head and look at her sadly.
Once he said, 'I wish I could have seen him
one more time!' She made no answer. Then,
realizing that some sort of comment was required
of her, she asked, 'How old was your father?'
'Fifty-eight.'
'Oh!'
And that was all.
A quarter of an hour afterwards he added,
'Poor mother! What will happen to her now?'
Emma had no idea, and made a silent gesture.
Feeling that her silence was the
result of sorrow at the news,
Charles made an effort to be more cheerful.
'Did you have a good time yesterday?'
'Yes,' she replied.
When the table was cleared,
neither Bovary nor Emma moved.
As she continued to look at him, she found that
she could not pity him. He seemed a weak thing,
a poor man in every way. How could she get
rid of him? The evening would be endless!
Next day Charles's mother arrived,
and the weeping started again.
Emma said she had a lot of
things to organize and went out.
Charles thought of his father, and he was
surprised at feeling so affectionate towards him.
He had never thought he loved his father. Madame
Bovary senior also thought of her husband. It was
all over now, and even the worst of her
days with him were pleasant memories.
While the son thought about his lost father, Emma
thought that only forty-eight hours earlier she
and Leon were together, with the world shut out,
drowning in love, amazed by each other's beauty.
She tried to recover the details of
that lost day of happiness and pleasure.
She would have liked to hear and see nothing
new in order not to lose a moment of remembered
delight, but she found that her husbands noisy
sorrow was driving it all from her memory.
The next afternoon, when all three of them
were sitting in the garden, they saw Monsieur
Lheureux coming through the gate. He had heard
of the sad event, and had come to visit them.
After he had expressed his sorrow
at their loss, he said to Charles,
'Could I have a word in private with your
wife? It's about that matter, er... you know!'
Charles blushed to the roots
of his hair as he answered,
'Ah, yes... of course. Darling, do you think...?'
She seemed to understand, and got up.
'It's nothing!' said Charles to his
mother. 'Only a little household matter.'
As soon as they were alone, Monsieur
Lheureux began to congratulate Emma
on the money she and her husband would have
now that Monsieur Bovary's father had died.
'And as you are well again,' he continued, 'I was
coming to make proposals for another arrangement.'
What he in fact proposed was that Emma should
take over the responsibility for all the debts 'to
stop her husband worrying'. Then she and Monsieur
Lheureux would be able to settle all the details.
She did not understand, so she said nothing.
Lheureux quickly added that there were some
things that Madame could not possibly do
without. For example, he would send her across a
dozen metres of beautiful black silk for a dress.
'The one you have on is good enough for the house,
but you need another one for visiting. I
saw that straight away, when I came in.'
He did not send the fabric; he brought it. Then
he came back for the measurements. He kept coming
back, doing everything he could to be of use,
to make himself liked. And every time he came,
he reminded her that she should be
the one who managed the couple's legal
and financial affairs. He never mentioned
the old bills, and she never let them enter
her head. Charles certainly had said something
about them when she was beginning to get better,
but she had so many things to worry her at
the time that she thought no more about them.
Moreover, she avoided starting any discussion
about money while her mother-in-law was there.
But, as soon as she had left, Emma began to amaze
her husband with her practical good sense. They
really did have to manage things better. She used
a number of technical terms, spoke impressively
about planning for the future, and never missed a
chance of exaggerating how complicated it would be
to make the right arrangements. Finally, she put
in front of him one day a form which gave her
the power to manage all his financial affairs.
She had profited well from Lheureux's lessons.
Charles - good, simple man - asked her where
the form came from. She told him it had
been written by Monsieur Guillaumin,
the Yonville lawyer, and then added,
'But I wouldn't trust him further than I
could see him. These lawyers are nearly as
bad as the criminals they work with. Perhaps
we ought to consult... No, there's no one!'
'What about Leon?' said Charles, thinking hard.
He had said exactly the
name Emma wanted him to say.
Now she could suggest that it was difficult to
explain matters by letter, and she offered to go
over to Rouen and speak to him directly. Charles
would not hear of troubling her. She insisted.
It was a battle of kindness. Finally, she cried,
'Now, not another word, please! I am going!'
'How kind you are!' he said,
kissing her on the forehead.
The next morning she was
off to Rouen in the coach,
to consult Monsieur Leon.
She stayed for three days.
They were three wonderful days. They stayed
down near the harbour at the Hotel de Boulogne,
and there they lived, with the
curtains closed, the doors locked,
the floor covered with flowers, and
iced drinks brought up every morning.
Towards evening they would take a boat and
go and have dinner on one of the islands.
As they left the town, smoke rose up among
the trees, and the red sun, reflected on the
oily water of the harbour, looked like blood on
polished metal. They went down between the rows
of boats, and the noises of the town grew fainter
and fainter. When, finally, they arrived at their
favourite restaurant, she untied her hat and
they stepped out of the boat on to their island.
They went into a small cafe with dark fishing-nets
hung up at the door, and sat themselves down
in the low-ceilinged room. They ate small
fried fish, followed by cherries and cream,
and then went and sat on the grass. They kissed
and held one another under the trees, out of view;
they would have liked to live for ever in that
little spot which, in their present happiness,
they thought the most beautiful place on earth.
They had both seen trees before, and blue sky,
and grass. It was not the first time they had
heard the sound of water and the music of the wind
in the trees, but they had never really admired
these things till now. It was as if nature had not
really existed before, or had only begun to show
its beauty after they had satisfied their desires.
When it was dark, they started for home
again. The boat kept close to the shores
of the little islands. They did not speak, but
sat silently in the back of the boat, listening
to the water. Emma looked across at Leon. Her
head was raised, her hands were held together,
her eyes raised to the sky. She was beautiful
tonight. Then Leon put his hand on a piece
of red ribbon lying in the bottom of the
boat. The boatman took it and examined it.
'Ah,' he said at last, 'maybe it belongs to
one of the people I took out a few days ago.
They were having fun I can tell
you - ladies and gentlemen,
with cakes, and bottles of wine. I remember one of
them in particular. A fine, handsome man he was,
with a little moustache. Lord, he was
funny, though! They kept on saying,
"Come on, tell us another... Adolphe...
Rodolphe..." Yes, Rodolphe, that was his name.'
Emma shook from head to foot.
'What's the matter?' said Leon, moving closer.
'Oh, it's nothing! The
night air is a little cool.'
'The sort of gentleman who has plenty
of lady friends,' added the old boatman.
The morning after this last dinner on the island,
Emma had to return to Yonville, and Leon had to
get back to his normal life in Rouen. However, he
found this difficult and he started ignoring his
friends and not looking after his business. Every
day he waited for her letters; he read them again
and again, and he wrote back to her immediately,
remembering every detail of their time together.
And unlike most memories, these did not seem
to fade, but grew stronger. The need to see her
became so great that one Saturday morning he ran
out of his office and took the coach to Yonville.
When he came to the top of the hill above the
village and, looking down over the valley,
saw the church tower, he felt like a man
who has gone abroad and made his fortune
and now returns to visit his native village.
He walked down to her house and saw that
there was a light in the kitchen. He watched
to see if he could catch sight of her shadow
behind the curtain. But nothing could be seen.
Madame Lefrancois met him, and could not believe
her eyes. He had dinner in the little dining room,
as in the old days, but alone. He then
went and knocked at the doctor's door.
Madame was upstairs in her bedroom, and
did not come down for a quarter of an hour.
The doctor appeared delighted to see him
and, to their regret, stayed at home all
that day and the next. The only chance to
see her alone came very late in the evening,
in the lane at the end of the garden - the
lane where she used to meet 'the other one'.
There was a thunderstorm and they talked under an
umbrella, with lightning flashing all around them.
Their separation was becoming impossible to bear.
'I would rather be dead,' she said,
holding him, with tears in her eyes.
'Goodbye! Goodbye! When shall I see you again?'
They turned back for one last kiss, and she
promised to find some way of seeing him regularly,
at least once a week. She was full of hope.
She would soon have some money to play with.
In fact, she was soon behaving as if
she had all the money in the world.
She bought a pair of yellow curtains for her
bedroom, which Monsieur Lheureux had told
her were a bargain. She had dreams of a carpet
and Lheureux, saying that to want a carpet was
not like wishing for the moon, helped her to
get one. She had begun to depend on Lheureux.
She sent for him twenty times a day,
and he immediately stopped what he
was doing and came to see Madame. It
was a dangerous friendship for Emma.
It was about this time - around the beginning
of winter - that she suddenly appeared to
develop a tremendous enthusiasm for music.
One night, while Charles was listening to her,
she began the same piece over again, stopping
four times, finding fault with herself each time.
He, never noticing any difference, cried, 'Oh well
done! Splendid! What did you stop for? Go on!'
'Oh, no! It's too bad! My fingers
feel as if they were stiff with rust!'
Next day he begged her to play him something more.
'Oh, well, if you want me to.'
Charles confessed he had heard her play
better. She kept hitting the wrong notes,
and finally came to a sudden stop.
'Ah, it's no good! I ought
to have some lessons, but...'
She bit her lip and added, 'Twenty
francs a time. It's too expensive!'
'Well, yes... it is...' said Charles. 'But
perhaps it could be managed a bit cheaper.
Sometimes a less well-known artist can be
better than a teacher with a big reputation.'
'They are not easy to find,' said Emma, and did
not open the piano again - although whenever she
went near it (if Charles was in the room)
she would say sadly, 'Ah, my poor piano!'
And when she had visitors, she never failed
to tell them she had given up her music
and could not now start again
because of their lack of money.
And they would say what a pity it was, since
she had such a gift. They even spoke to Charles
about it, especially the pharmacist,
saying it was really too bad of him.
'You're making a mistake. You should never let
a natural gift lie unused. Besides, my friend,
you should remember that by encouraging your wife
to study now, you will be saving on your child's
musical education later. In my opinion, children
ought always to be taught by their own mother.'
So Charles again came back to this piano question.
Emma replied bitterly that they might as well
sell it, for all the good it was. But to sell
this piano, something she had been so proud
of, was an idea that Bovary could not accept.
'Well,' he said, 'if you want a lesson
now and again, it might be possible.'
'Yes,' she replied, 'but it's no good having
lessons unless you take them regularly.'
That was how she managed to get permission from
her husband to go to Rouen once a week to see
her lover. At the end of a month, everyone
said that she had made a lot of progress.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Debts
Thursday was the day. She got up and dressed
very quietly, in order not to disturb Charles,
and took the early coach to Rouen, arriving
just as the city was beginning to wake up.
For fear of being seen, she usually avoided the
main streets, going instead down narrow lanes and
alleys until she reached the rue Nationale, and
turned down a side street, and yes, there he was.
Leon made no sign, but continued on his way.
She followed him until they came to the hotel.
In he went and up the stairs, opened the door of
their room and entered; and then how they kissed,
and then how they talked! They spoke of all
the worries they had had during the week,
all the things they had done.
But that was all over now,
and they looked at each other with little sounds
of delight, and words of tenderness and love.
The bed was large, with red curtains,
and there was nothing so beautiful in
the world as her dark head and
white skin against the dark red
when, with a shy little gesture, she put her
arms together and hid her face in her hands.
How they loved this room. They had their
lunch by the fire on a little side-table.
They were so completely involved in each other
that it seemed like being in their own home,
and they dreamed they would continue to live
there always. They talked about 'our room',
and for the first time in his life Leon tasted
the sweetness of female company, a woman's life.
He knelt on the ground in front of her and,
with his two elbows on her knees, looked
at her with a smile, leaning his face towards
her. And she leaned down to him, and whispered,
'Oh, don't move! Don't speak! Look at me! There
is something in your eyes so sweet - it does me
so much good.' And she called
him 'child': 'Do you love me,
child?' And she hardly heard his reply, so
wildly did he press his lips to her mouth.
At the end of their day she would say,
'Goodbye till Thursday! Thursday!'
Then suddenly she would seize
his head in both her hands,
kiss him quickly on the forehead and,
crying 'Goodbye', run down the stairs.
Charles would be at home and waiting
for her and, at last, Madame arrived.
She hardly looked at her child and, if
dinner was late, did not criticize the
cook. Often her husband, seeing how pale
she was, asked her if she was feeling ill.
'No,' said Emma.
'But,' he answered, 'you seem so strange tonight.'
'Oh, no! It's nothing. I'm all right.'
But her whole life had become a
lie, in which her love for Leon
lay hidden from the world. Lying became a
necessary part of her day, almost a hobby.
One day, however, Monsieur Lheureux
met her in Rouen as she was coming
out of the Hotel de Boulogne with Leon;
it gave her a shock, and she thought he
would tell everyone. He was not such a fool.
But three days later he came into her room,
shut the door behind him and said,
'I need some money, and soon.'
She told him she could not let him have any.
Lheureux reminded her how
helpful he had always been
and pulled out of his pocket an account of goods
not paid for - more than two thousand francs.
She lowered her head.
'But if you haven't got cash, you've got
property,' and he mentioned a farm near Aumale
that Charles had inherited
from his father. Lheureux
knew everything - how big the farm
was, how much rent it was worth.
'If I were you,' he said, 'I would pay my debts,
and there would still be some money left over.'
He came back the following week, saying that
after a lot of trouble he had found a buyer
willing to pay four thousand francs for the farm.
Emma was happier than she had been for months.
But Lheureux shook his head and told her how much
richer she would be if she let him manage these
affairs. Finally he persuaded her to borrow
even more money from him and to sign a series
of documents which she did not understand.
He told her this would give her more cash
now - cash she could use to pay her other debts
and buy some of the little things she wanted.
Emma, with her mind full of thoughts of
Leon and what they could do together,
did not even read the papers, but simply signed
her name where Lheureux placed his dirty finger.
With this money in her hands, she
felt she might begin to be free.
Freedom, however, was a disappointment.
Despite her hopes, she now found Leon
less pleased to meet her than before, less in
love. Because she had more money in her pocket
she made more demands on him, but his
employer was worried about his work,
and his friends asked him why they could no
longer see him. And the more Emma demanded,
the less Leon wanted to give, and while
her love, her need continued to grow,
so did her anger. In the end, she brought roses
for him from Yonville and threw them in his face.
So Emma was not happy. Why was there this
emptiness in her life? Why did whatever she
want turn into dust? Everything was a lie, every
smile hid a bored yawn; every promise hid a curse.
To make matters worse, one day a small,
red-faced man came to the house explaining
that he came from a Monsieur Vincart of
Rouen. He politely handed her a paper.
It was a bill for seven
hundred francs, signed by her.
Lheureux had sold her bills to a money-lender!
She sent the servant to fetch him. He was busy
and could not come, and the stranger asked
what reply he should take to Monsieur Vincart.
'Well,' said Emma, 'tell him I haven't got it...
It will have to be next week. Ask him
to wait... Yes, next week, tell him.'
The man left without another word.
Next day, at twelve o'clock, a
legal document was handed to her,
and the sight of the piece of paper
with the government stamp on it,
and the name 'Maitre Hareng, Bailiff at Buchy,'
written on it in big letters, scared her so much
that she ran without a moment's
delay to Monsieur Lheureux's shop.
She found him there, tying up a big parcel.
'What can we do for Madame today?' he asked, and
he showed Madame upstairs to his little office.
'What's the matter?' said Lheureux,
seating himself in his big armchair.
'Look at that.' And she showed him the paper.
'Well, what can I do?'
This made her more angry than frightened.
Hadn't he promised not to sell her bills?
He agreed that he had but added, 'I had
no choice. I had a knife at my throat.'
'What's going to happen now?'
'Oh, I'll tell you what will happen;
that's easy. You go before the judge,
you pay or they sell your
things. It's quite simple.'
Though Emma wanted to hit him,
she asked him sweetly if there was anything
she could do to keep this Vincart quiet.
'Oh, no! Keep Vincart quiet! You don't
know much about him, that's clear.
He's more bloodthirsty than a tiger!'
Emma cried out that Monsieur Lheureux
really would have to do something.
'I think I've been pretty good
to you! Look at this,' he said,
opening a record book and running his finger up
the page. 'Here... and again, here... 3 August,
two hundred francs... 17 June, a hundred and
fifty... 23 March, forty-six. In April...'
He stopped. 'Anyway, I've had enough
of these delays, and that's that!'
Emma said no more. What could she do?
When she went to Rouen, Leon
gave her little comfort.
He had just heard that he was going to be
promoted to chief clerk in his law firm.
It was time for him to think about his future.
No more love-making! Besides, it rather bored
him now when Emma began weeping on his chest,
and he had grown tired of so much emotion.
Feeling him withdraw from her, she now began
to wonder how she could get rid of him!
She even began to wish that something terrible
would happen which would force them to separate.
She stopped her excuse of music lessons, and
her visits to Rouen. She stayed in her room, too
depressed to pay attention when more legal demands
for money came to the house, too depressed to talk
to her husband or her child. She would have liked
to stop living or else to go on sleeping for ever.
However, she could not stop the world coming
to her, and one morning, two weeks after
the first visit by Vincart's man, Felicite
brought her a piece of grey-coloured paper.
She took it and read the complicated legal
language which told her the simple truth
that within twenty-four hours she had to pay
the total amount of eight thousand francs.
Lower down, she read the words which
told her that if she did not do this,
all her household goods would be sold! What could
she do? Twenty-four hours! That meant tomorrow.
Maybe Lheureux was just trying to frighten
her, that's what it was! She went to see him.
'Do you know what's happening?'
she said. 'I suppose it's a joke.'
'It isn't.'
'What do you mean?'
He turned to her slowly and then, folding his
arms, said, 'Did you think, my little lady, that
I would keep on supplying you with goods and money
for ever, simply for the love of it? Be fair!
I must recover my money one way or the
other. Anyway, it's not me, it's Vincart.'
'Couldn't you possibly...?'
'I can't do anything.'
'But... just look at it like this...'
And she began to say she had not
known... it had taken her by surprise...
She begged and prayed, she even put
her white hand on Lheureux's knee.
'That's enough of that!' he shouted. 'Anyone
would think you were trying to make love to me.'
'You horrible man!'
'Well, who's got a temper?' he said, with a laugh.
'I'll tell everyone what you've
done. I'll tell my husband...'
'All right, but I don't think
your husband will be very pleased
when he understands what you've been doing!'
She fell back, as if someone
had hit her in the face.
And then he went close up to her, saying sweetly,
'It's not very pleasant, I know. But, after all,
it never killed anybody, and it seems that it's
the only way to make you pay me back my money...'
'But where can I get it?' said Emma.
'What about all those friends of yours?'
And he gave her a look so searching and
so terrible that she shook with fear.
'I promise you,' she said. 'I'll sign any...'
'I've had enough of you and your signatures!'
'And I can still sell...'
'Don't be a fool,' he said.
'You've got nothing left to sell!'
'But if I brought you three thousand francs,
a quarter, a third, nearly all of it?'
'No, it's no good.'
He pushed her gently towards the stairs.
'I beg you, Monsieur Lheureux, give me a
few days longer!' and she burst into tears.
'Oh look, more tears!'
'But I'm desperate!'
'I don't care,' he whispered in her ear,
so close she could smell his sour breath,
and then he shut the door.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
A Death
She was brave next day, when Maitre Hareng, the
bailiff, accompanied by two witnesses, came to
make a list of the goods to be sold. They began
with Charles's consulting room, then went into the
kitchen and bedroom. They examined her dresses,
they searched through her dressing room - and her
whole way of life, with all its little secrets,
was laid bare, like a body on an operating table.
Maitre Hareng, with his black coat buttoned up
to the neck, his white tie and polished boots,
would say from time to time, 'Pardon me,
Madame; will you allow me?' And he frequently
made little comments, such as, 'Charming! Very
pretty!' Then he would make some more notes.
When they had gone through the rooms,
they went up to the room under the roof.
She had a desk up there in which she kept
Rodolphe's letters. That had to be opened.
'Ah, letters!' said Maitre
Hareng, smiling politely.
'But allow me. I must make sure
the box contains nothing else.'
At last they went and Felicite returned.
Emma had sent her to look out
for Charles and keep him away.
Charles that evening seemed rather worried.
She looked at him, then at the curtains,
the chairs, all the things which had made her a
little happier, but which would now ruin them.
The next day, Emma went to Rouen
to see if she could find a way out.
She visited every banker she knew the name
of. Some of them laughed in her face when
they heard her story. All of them refused.
At two o'clock, she ran to Leon's office.
She knocked at the door, but no one
came. At last Leon himself appeared.
'I've something I must say to
you,' she said. She was very pale.
'Leon,' she said, 'I want you to do
something for me.' Then, taking him
with her two hands and giving him a shake, she
said, 'Listen, I want eight thousand francs.'
'What? You're mad!'
'Not yet.'
And she told the story of what had happened,
how she had let Lheureux lead her into disaster.
And Charles knew nothing. She must have the money.
'How do you expect me...?'
And her lover would do nothing to
help her. She had nowhere to turn to.
'What must be must be!' she said to herself.
She was woken at nine the next morning by
voices in the square. There was a crowd
of people outside, all trying to read a big
piece of paper stuck to the wall of her house.
'Madame! Madame!' cried Felicite,
rushing in. 'It's a terrible shame!'
And the poor girl held out a yellow paper
which she had just torn off the front door.
Emma read that all her furniture was to be sold.
They looked at each other in silence. Servant
and mistress had no secrets from one another.
'If I were you, Madame,' sighed Felicite at
last, 'I would go and see Monsieur Guillaumin.'
'You would?'
'Yes, you go. That's the right thing to do.'
She dressed and, in order not to be seen
(there were always a lot of people in the
square), she took the path by the river.
'Monsieur,' she said, after she was
let into the lawyer's dining room,
'I want to ask you...' And
she told him her situation.
Maitre Guillaumin knew all about it. In fact,
he was a secret friend of Lheureux's, and knew
the story better than she did herself. As
he listened, he smiled a strange smile.
When she asked him for help with the money
that was being demanded, he said how sad
he was that she had never come to him before.
Then he put out his hand and took hold of hers,
and kissed it greedily, playing with her fingers
and looking in her face with his colourless eyes.
She felt his breath on her
cheek and could not bear it.
She jumped to her feet. 'Monsieur,'
she said, 'I am waiting.'
'What for?' said the lawyer,
suddenly going as white as a sheet.
'This money.'
'But...'
Then, giving in to a desire
he could not resist, he said,
'Very well, yes! You can have your money!'
And he dragged himself along on his knees towards
her, shouting, 'For God's sake, stay! I love you!'
He took her by the waist. Madame Bovary fell back
with a terrible expression on her face, crying,
'I know I have fallen, Monsieur, but I am not to
be sold.' And she turned and ran from the house.
Felicite was waiting for her on the doorstep.
'Well?' she asked.
'No!' said Emma.
And for the next quarter of an hour they went
together through the names of all the people in
Yonville who might perhaps help her. But every
time Felicite mentioned a name Emma answered,
'Do you really think so? Oh,
no, I'm sure they wouldn't.'
'And the Doctor will be here in a minute or two.'
'Yes, I know that... Leave me alone.'
Rodolphe! She had to see Rodolphe. He
would help her, but what should she say,
how should she begin? Emma entered the park
by the side gate, and walked to the house.
She climbed the stairs and went to his room.
He was sitting in front of the fire, with his
feet up on the fireplace, just lighting a pipe.
'Hello! Is that you?' he said, getting up quickly.
'Yes, it's me. Rodolphe, I
want to ask your advice.'
'You haven't changed, you
are as charming as ever.'
'Ah,' she answered bitterly, 'sad charms.
You said goodbye to them easily enough!
Oh, Rodolphe!' she sighed. 'If
you only knew... I loved you so!'
'You've been crying!' he said. 'Why is that?'
Now she began to weep uncontrollably.
'I am ruined, Rodolphe! I want you
to lend me three thousand francs.'
'But... but...'
Hurrying over her words, she told him her story,
to which he listened carefully. When she had
finished, he looked sadly at her and replied,
very calmly, 'I haven't got it, dear lady.'
It was no lie. If he had had it,
he would have given it to her.
She stood for a few minutes looking at him.
'You haven't got it? Haven't got it?'
She repeated it several times, then she went out.
The walls seemed to be shaking, and she
felt that the ceiling would fall on her.
When she was outside, she felt a
little better, but all her memories,
all her ideas seemed to fill her head and burst
in a single flash. She felt she was going mad.
Night was falling, and dark birds were flying into
the trees. The sky seemed full of balls of fire,
falling slowly to earth, turning and turning.
What could she do? How could she face the world?
She went running down the hill, through the market
place and into the pharmacist's shop. The door was
open and no one was there, though she could hear
Justin, the assistant, talking to Monsieur Homais.
She entered the passage where the laboratory door
was. On the wall hung a key labelled 'Room 6'.
It turned in the lock, and she went straight
over and reached up to the third shelf,
knocking over a small bowl
which had stood beside it.
'Is anyone there? Who is that?'
She could hear Justin walking down the corridor.
She must be quicker. She read the labels, her eyes
desperately searching for one particular bottle,
a bottle which might give her a way
out of this impossible situation.
'Is there anyone there?'
She took down a blue jar with a small,
hand-written label on it, pulled off the lid,
and pushed her hand inside. She took it out full
of a white powder which she
began to eat then and there.
Justin ran into the room.
'Stop!' cried the boy, terrified,
throwing himself on her.
'Be quiet, they'll come! They will blame
your master for not locking his room.'
Then she left. They could do nothing to her
now, and she felt a great peace in her heart.
Charles had come back to the house just
after Emma left it to find Rodolphe.
He did not know what to do. He sent Felicite
to the Homais', the Tuvaches', Lheureux's,
the Lion d'Or, everywhere. Whenever
anxiety for his wife lifted for a moment,
he saw his own life ruined, his money gone,
Berthe's future destroyed. How? Why? Not a word.
He waited until six o'clock in the evening.
Then, unable to stand it any longer, he went
out along the road for a couple of kilometres,
saw no one, waited, and then came back again.
She had come home.
'What was the matter? Why? Tell me all about it.'
She sat down at her desk and wrote a letter, which
she slowly closed, adding the date and the hour.
Then she said, 'You will read that tomorrow.
Until then, I beg you, do not ask me
a single question... No, not one!'
'But...'
'Oh, leave me!'
And she lay down on her bed and seemed to fall
asleep. She felt a bitter taste in her mouth,
and it woke her up. She caught sight of Charles,
and shut her eyes again. She tried to keep awake,
wondering whether she had any pain. But
no, nothing yet. She could hear the clock,
the sound of the fire. Charles was standing by
the bed, and she heard the sound of his breathing.
'Ah, it's nothing very much - dying!'
she thought. 'I shall just fall asleep,
and it will all be over.'
She drank some water and
turned her face to the wall.
But there was still that horrible
taste of ink in her mouth.
'I'm thirsty... oh, I'm so thirsty!' she sighed.
'What can it be?' said Charles,
bringing her a glass of water.
'It's nothing... Open the
window... I can't breathe.'
And she began to vomit so suddenly
that she hardly had time to take her
handkerchief from under her pillow.
He questioned her. She did not answer. She kept
perfectly still, for fear the slightest movement
would make her vomit again. And she began to feel
an icy coldness rising from her feet to her heart.
'Ah, it's beginning now!' she whispered.
'What did you say?'
She kept moving her head gently from side
to side, opening and shutting her jaws,
as if she had something very heavy on her tongue.
At eight o'clock the vomiting began again.
Charles, examining the basin, noticed
something white at the bottom.
'That's extraordinary, most unusual!' he said.
'No, no, you're wrong,' she
replied in a strong voice.
Then, very lightly, he passed
his hand over her stomach.
She gave a horrible scream.
He stepped back, terrified.
Then she began to shake and became paler
than the sheet that she was holding.
Her heartbeat was irregular. There
were drops of sweat on her face.
Her eyes stared without seeing, and she answered
every question with a shake of her head. She even
smiled two or three times. Gradually her breathing
became noisier. Then she started to scream.
'Oh, God, it's terrible!'
He threw himself on his knees at her bedside.
'Tell me! What have you
eaten? For God's sake, speak!'
And he looked at her with a tenderness in
his eyes that she had never seen before.
'All right - over there...
there!' she said weakly.
He ran to the writing-table, tore
open the letter, and read aloud:
'Let no one be blamed...' He stopped, passed
his hand across his eyes and then read on.
'What!... Help! Help me!' And all he could
say was the word, 'Poisoned, poisoned!'
Felicite ran to Monsieur Homais' shop and he came
back as soon as he heard what was the matter.
'Be calm,' said the pharmacist.
'What is the poison?'
Charles showed him the letter and the
pharmacist realized there was little to be done.
Emma saw the two of them and looked at Charles.
'Don't cry,' she said, 'I will not
be here to worry you much longer.'
'Why did you do it? Who made you do it?'
And she replied, 'It had to be, my dear.'
'Weren't you happy? Was it my
fault? I did everything I could.'
'Yes, you did... You are kind, so kind.'
And she passed her fingers
slowly through his hair.
'Bring the little one to me,' she
said, raising herself on her elbow.
'The pain isn't getting any
worse, is it?' asked Charles.
'No!'
The child came in, in her long nightdress.
She looked thoughtful and not yet fully
awake. She opened big, wondering eyes when
she saw the room, and the bright candles.
'Oh, Mummy, how big your eyes are! How
pale you are! And your face is all sweaty!'
Her mother was staring at her.
'I'm frightened,' cried the little one.
Emma took her hand and tried to kiss
it; she struggled to free herself.
'That's enough! Take her away!' cried Charles.
After that Emma seemed a little better, but then
she began to vomit blood, her limbs became stiff,
her body was covered with brown patches, and her
heartbeat raced. Then she began to scream again.
She cursed the poison, she begged
it to hurry up and finish its work.
She pushed away everything that
Charles tried to make her drink.
He was standing stiffly by the bed, his whole
body shaking from head to foot. Felicite ran
from one end of the room to the other. There was
nothing to be done except to call the priest.
When he came, Emma was lying
with her chin sunk on her breast;
her eyes were staring and her
poor hands picked at the sheets.
Pale as death, with eyes like burning coals,
Charles - not crying now - was standing facing
her at the foot of the bed, while the priest,
resting on one knee, was whispering his prayers.
Slowly she turned her head and suddenly,
as she saw the priest kneeling beside her,
a look of joy came over her face. The priest
rose from his knees to show her the cross,
and she leant forward and pressed her lips to the
body of the Man-God. It was as if she kissed the
figure on the cross with more love than she
had ever given any person during her life.
She then fell back on to the bed, and they
hurried to her side. Her life had ended.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Endings
Death always comes as a shock,
however much it has been expected.
So when, at last, Charles saw her lying there
so still, he threw himself on her, weeping.
'That's right,' said the pharmacist. 'Let
nature have her way. You'll feel much better!'
Later, funeral arrangements had to be made.
Charles thought carefully about these and wrote:
I want her to be buried in her wedding
dress, with white shoes and white flowers,
and her hair loose over her shoulders. She should
be covered with a large piece of green silk.
These are my wishes. Make sure
that they are carried out.
The gentlemen were surprised at Charles's
ideas, and Monsieur Homais spoke to him.
'It seems to us,' he said, 'that
silk is a little expensive...'
'That's none of your business!' shouted Charles.
'Leave me alone! You didn't love
her, so just get out of my sight!'
That night, Charles, Homais and the priest sat
beside Emma's body. She was lying with her head
leaning over her right shoulder. The corner
of her mouth, which was open, looked like a
black hole at the bottom of her face; her
two thumbs were held tightly in her hands.
The sheet that covered her lay quite flat from
her breasts down to her knees, rising up again
at the tips of her toes, and it seemed to Charles
as if an enormous weight was pressing down on her.
Early in the morning, Madame
Bovary senior arrived.
Charles, as he kissed her, again broke
down and cried. Like the pharmacist,
she criticized him about the funeral expenses,
but he became so angry that she grew quiet.
Charles stayed by himself all afternoon.
Berthe had been taken over to Madame Homais.
In the evening, various people came in
to see him and to express their regrets.
He stood up and shook hands,
but he could not say anything,
and each newcomer sat down with the rest of
the group, in a big circle round the fireplace.
They all looked at the floor with
serious expressions on their faces,
and although everyone was
bored, no one got up to go.
Upstairs Felicite, Madame
Lefrancois and Madame Bovary senior
were standing around Emma, busily
finishing their task of dressing her.
'Oh, my poor mistress!' wept
Felicite. 'My poor, poor mistress!'
'Just look at her!' said the landlady of the
Lion d'Or. 'How pretty she looks even now!'
Then they all bent over to put the flowers on
her hair. They had to lift her head a little,
and as they did so, a stream of
black liquid poured from her mouth.
'Oh, my God! The dress! Take
care!' cried Madame Lefrancois.
Charles had to listen to the sound of hammers on
wood as she was put into her last little home.
Four men carried her to the
door, the house was thrown open,
and all the people of Yonville crowded near.
Emma's father, Farmer Rouault, arrived as they
were bringing her out, and fell unconscious in
the market place when he saw the funeral carriage.
At the church Charles tried to think about the few
times when they had been happy together - or when,
at least, he had been happy with her. But
remembering that she was there, underneath
that green cloth, his heart was filled with
black anger against God and against the world.
They sang, they went down on
their knees, they got up again;
there seemed to be no end to it all. He
remembered how once, in the early days,
they had gone to church together. They had sat on
the other side, on the right, against the wall.
Outside the church Charles walked in
front, holding himself very upright.
Six men carried Emma's body, and the priest
followed saying the prayers for the dead.
His voice was carried over the fields, rising and
falling on the wind. Sometimes a sudden turn in
the path hid them from sight, but always the
great silver cross rose high among the trees.
The women followed, dressed in black, and each
in her hand carried a tall lighted candle.
Charles recognized every garden as he passed, and
remembered how often, on mornings like this one,
he had come away from one of them
and set out for home and Emma.
Now they had arrived at the place
where her grave had been dug.
The people stood around, and all the time the
priest was speaking, the red earth that had
been piled beside the grave ran noiselessly
down the slope into the dark hole. Then,
when the four ropes were in position, they
lowered her into the grave. Charles watched
the wooden box go down until, at last, it arrived
at the bottom and the ropes were pulled up again.
The priest took the spade held out to him by his
assistant and pushed the earth into the grave,
then Charles sank down on his knees,
throwing in handfuls of earth as he cried,
'Goodbye!' He sent her kisses, and dragged himself
to the edge of the grave, wanting to lie with her.
They led him away, and he soon grew calm
again, perhaps feeling, like all the others,
a sense of relief that it was now all over.
As the crowd walked back to the village,
they talked about her death and
what a terrible thing it was -
especially Lheureux, who had
made an effort to be there.
'Poor little lady! What a
terrible thing for her husband!'
Emma's father insisted on going
straight back to Les Bertaux,
saying that he could not sleep in that house.
He would not even see his little grandchild.
'No, no! I couldn't bear the pain of it.
Goodbye, then. You're a good man,' and, pointing
at his thigh, 'I shan't forget that leg,
not as long as I live. You'll always get a
bird from me at Christmas, don't you worry.'
When he reached the top of the hill he turned
again, just as, years ago, he had turned and
looked back along the Saint-Victor road when
she had left him to go with her husband.
The windows in the village were all on fire
in the light of the evening sun. He put up
his hand to shade his eyes and far away, on
the horizon, he saw the place where she lay,
with the trees, here and there, dark among
the white stones. Then he went on his way.
Next day, Charles had Berthe brought home
from the nurse. She asked for her mummy
and they told her that she had gone away,
that she would bring her back some toys.
Berthe spoke of her again many
times, but as the days went by
she stopped thinking about her and Charles
could not bear the child's happy laugh.
Life continued around Charles,
but it had lost its meaning.
When Madame Dupuis wrote to him to
tell him of the 'marriage of her son,
Monsieur Leon Dupuis, a lawyer in Yvetot, to
Mademoiselle Leocadie Leboeuf, of Bondeville',
Charles wrote: 'How delighted my poor wife
would have been!', but he did not really care.
Besides, before long, his money troubles began
again. Monsieur Lheureux's Vincart returned once
again with his demands. Now everyone
tried to profit from Charles's loss.
A music teacher in Rouen sent in a bill for six
lessons, although Emma had never been to her once;
a Madame Rollet demanded payment
for delivering letters to Rouen.
And day by day Charles had to sell the silver,
piece by piece; then he got rid of the best
furniture. All the rooms were robbed of their
contents - except for one. Her room, her bedroom,
was left as it had always been. When he had had
his dinner, Charles went up there. He pulled the
round table in front of the fire, moved her
chair nearer, and then sat down facing it.
A candle would be burning, and Berthe would be
sitting near him, busy with her painting book.
Despite these efforts to keep Emma's memory
alive, Bovary realized with sorrow that her face
was fading from his memory. But every night he
dreamed of her and it was always the same dream.
He moved close to touch her, but just as he
was taking her in his arms, she fell to dust.
And he was still in debt. Lheureux refused to
wait any longer and Charles did not know what to
do. At last, he decided he had to look in Emma's
desk. There, instead of an answer to his problems,
he found Leon's letters. He read them all,
to the last line, then searched through
every other piece of furniture, opening
every drawer, emptying every box. In this
way he also discovered a picture of Rodolphe -
staring at him from a mountain of love letters.
Now people were shocked to see him so depressed.
He never went out or had visitors; he even refused
to go and see his patients. The only times he went
out now were when he took his little girl by the
hand, and they went together to the cemetery.
One day, when he had gone to the market
at Argueil to sell his horse - his last
possession - he met Rodolphe. They both
turned pale. Rodolphe, who, when Emma died,
had only sent his card, tried
to give a few apologies.
Then he grew braver, and invited Charles to have
a bottle of beer with him at the inn. As they
walked on, he talked about farming, the price of
land, trying to avoid any uncomfortable subjects.
Charles was not listening, Rodolphe noticed,
and he anxiously watched his companion's face.
At last Charles said, 'I'm not angry with you.'
Rodolphe remained silent and
Charles, with his head in his hands,
repeated in a flat voice, a voice full of
endless sorrow, 'No, I'm not angry with you now.'
Then he said a great thing, the only great
thing he had ever said: 'Fate is to blame!'
Rodolphe, who had controlled the direction
of this particular fate for some time,
thought this was rather a weak, even ridiculous
response from a man in Bovary's position.
Next day, Charles went out and sat
down on the seat in the garden.
The sunlight came through the leaves,
making shadows on the path, the perfume
of the roses filled the air, the sky was blue,
and bees flew from one open flower to the next.
Charles felt disturbed, like a
young man with an aching heart.
At seven o'clock little Berthe, who
had not seen him that afternoon,
came to fetch him in to dinner. His
head was leaning back against the wall,
his eyes were shut, his mouth was open, and
his right hand was holding some long dark hair.
'Come on, daddy!' she said.
And, thinking he was only playing, she gave him a
little push. He fell to the ground. He was dead.
When everything had been sold, just twelve francs
remained, enough to pay for Mademoiselle Bovary's
journey to her grandmother's house. That lady
died the same year. As Farmer Rouault was by
then too unwell to look after Berthe, she
was taken in by an aunt. She is there still,
but the aunt is poor and sends the little
girl to earn her living in a cotton mill.
- THE END -