CHAPTER ONE
Meet Maxim de Winter
What would I be today if I had not gone
to Monte Carlo with Mrs Van Hopper?
I would have lived another life. I
would have become a different person.
Mrs Van Hopper was not a pleasant woman. She
loved to meet people who were rich and famous.
Every summer, Mrs Van Hopper stayed at the Hotel
Cote d'Azur, the biggest and most expensive hotel
in Monte Carlo. Here, Mrs Van Hopper found out
which well-known people were staying in the town.
She always found an excuse to speak to
them. Then, pretending to know them well,
she asked her victims rude questions
in her loud American voice.
I was young and shy. I hated my life
with Mrs Van Hopper, but she paid me
a little money to be her companion. I was not
exactly a servant and certainly not a friend.
We must have looked a strange pair as we
walked into the hotel restaurant that day.
Mrs Van Hopper walked in front of me on
her high-heeled shoes. Her fat, heavy body
swayed above her short fat legs. I followed
slowly, my eyes looking down at the floor.
With my straight hair and badly-fitting
clothes I looked like an awkward schoolgirl.
Mrs Van Hopper sat down at her usual table
and stared at everyone in the restaurant.
'There isn't one well-known person
here,' she said in her loud voice.
'There's no one I want to talk to.'
Mrs Van Hopper was very greedy. She ordered a
large lunch for herself. Soon she was eating a
large plateful of spaghetti. We ate in silence.
The rich sauce ran down Mrs Van Hopper's chin.
I looked away. Then I saw that a new
guest was sitting down at the next table.
Mrs Van Hopper saw him too. She put
down her fork and stared at him hard.
How an excited look come into her small eyes.
'It's Max de Winter,' she said to
me. 'The man who owns Manderley.
You must have heard of it - a beautiful
old house in the west of England.
He looks ill, doesn't he? His wife died suddenly
last year. They say he's broken hearted.'
I felt sorry for de Winter already. He was
Mrs Van Hopper's next victim. She finished
her meal as quickly as possible.
I knew what she was going to do.
There was a long seat in the hotel
lounge, with a low table in front of it.
The seat was between the restaurant
and the main door of the hotel.
Everyone who left the restaurant
had to walk past this seat.
'I'll take my coffee in the lounge,' Mrs
Van Hopper told the waiter, 'straight away.'
She turned to me, her eyes shining: 'Go upstairs
and find that letter from my nephew, Billy.
Bring it to me in the lounge and the photographs
too. Billy met Max de Winter in London. Be quick.'
I went up to Mrs Van Hopper's
rooms as slowly as I could.
I hoped that de Winter would
get away before I returned.
When I came back with the letter, Mrs Van Hopper
was already on the seat in the lounge. De Winter
was sitting next to her. He was a dark-haired,
handsome man. His face was pale and his dark
eyes had a sad, lost look. De Winter stood up
politely as I gave Mrs Van Hopper her letter.
'Mr de Winter is having coffee
with us. Go and ask the waiter
for another cup,' Mrs Van Hopper told me.
'No, you are my guests,' said
de Winter. He called the waiter.
In a moment, de Winter was
sitting on a small chair
and I was next to Mrs Van Hopper on the long seat.
'I recognized you at once,' Mrs Van Hopper said.
'I met you at my nephew's party, in
London. But I don't suppose you remember an
old woman like me?' And Mrs Van Hopper
gave de Winter one of her biggest smiles.
'You are wrong, I could never forget you,'
said de Winter in a cold, hard voice.
'Billy's on holiday now,' Mrs Van
Hopper went on. 'He loves travelling.
But if he had a home like Manderley, he would
never leave it. People say that Manderley's
one of the most beautiful houses in England. I
wonder what you are doing here in Monte Carlo?'
For a few moments there was
silence. Then de Winter spoke.
'Manderley was looking very
lovely when I came away.'
There was another silence. De Winter had not
answered Mrs Van Hopper's question. She was not
silent for long, of course. She started to tell de
Winter all the unpleasant gossip of Monte Carlo.
After his moment of rudeness, de Winter
listened to her politely. I looked down
at the floor and tried not to hear Mrs Van
Hopper's loud voice. At last she had to stop.
A waiter came up to her with a message. Mrs Van
Hopper's dressmaker was waiting for her upstairs.
De Winter stood up at once. 'You mustn't
keep your dressmaker waiting,' he said.
Mrs Van Hopper smiled. 'You
must have a drink with me,'
she said. 'Why not tomorrow evening?
I'm having a few friends...'
'I'm sorry,' de Winter said quickly.
'I shall be away all day tomorrow.
If you will excuse me...' He turned
and walked out of the lounge.
'What a strange man Max de Winter is,' said
Mrs Van Hopper when we were standing in the
lift. 'He left so suddenly. But he is certainly
an attractive man. By the way, dear, you were
rather rude to him. You must look at people when
they are speaking. You are not a child, you know.'
Mrs Van Hopper was soon busy with her dressmaker.
I sat on a window seat, looking at the bright day
outside. I could not go out. Some of Mrs
Van Hopper's friends were coming to tea.
They were fat, rude women like
herself. My job was to talk to them,
light their cigarettes and tidy
the room after they had gone.
There was a knock on the door. A waiter came
in with a note in his hand. 'Madame is in the
bedroom,' I told him. But the note was for me.
There were a few words in an unknown handwriting.
'Forgive me. I was very rude after lunch.'
The note was not signed, but
I knew it was from de Winter.
'Is there an answer?' the waiter asked
me. I looked up. 'No. No answer,' I said.
After the waiter had gone, I put the note
in my pocket. Mrs Van Hopper called me from
her bedroom. I got up slowly, thinking
about de Winter and about Manderley.
CHAPTER TWO
A Day Out Together
The following day, Mrs Van Hopper woke up
with a sore throat and a high temperature.
I rang up her doctor and he came round at once.
'You have flu, Madame,' the doctor
told her. 'You won't get better
unless you stay quietly in
bed. Your heart isn't strong.
You'll need a nurse to look after you.
You must stay in bed for a week or two.'
'I'm sure I could look after Mrs Van Hopper,'
I said. But the doctor said no. To my surprise,
Mrs Van Hopper agreed with him. Monte Carlo had
begun to bore her. She would enjoy staying in bed.
She would enjoy giving orders
to the nurse as well as to me.
The nurse soon arrived and I was no longer wanted.
I went down to the restaurant by myself. I was
glad to be alone. It was half an hour before our
usual lunch-time. The restaurant was almost empty.
I went to our usual table. Then I saw
that de Winter was already at his table.
It was too late for me to go back. I sat down
awkwardly trying not to look at him. As I picked
up the menu, I knocked over the flowers on the
table. The water went all over the cloth and
ran down on to my skirt. The waiter was at the
other end of the restaurant and saw nothing.
In a moment, de Winter was standing by my chair.
'You can't sit here now,' he said. He
called to the waiter who came up at once.
'Lay another place at my table,' de Winter
said. 'This lady is lunching with me.'
'Oh no,' I said. 'I couldn't...'
'Why not?' he said. 'I want you to have
lunch with me. I was going to ask you anyway.
Come and sit down. You needn't
talk if you don't want to.'
We ordered our food and sat for a
time in a pleasant, easy silence.
'What's happened to your friend?' de Winter asked
me. I told him about Mrs Van Hopper's illness.
'I'm sorry,' he said politely.
'You got my note, I suppose.
It's very kind of you to lunch
with me after my rudeness.'
'You were not rude,' I said. 'At
least, she did not think you were.
She is always so curious about anyone important.'
'Important? Why does she think that
I'm important?' de Winter asked.
'I think it's because of Manderley,'
I said. He did not answer. I felt that
he did not want to talk about his home.
'Your friend is very different
from you,' he said at last.
'And she's much older than
you too. Is she a relation?'
'Mrs Van Hopper is not my friend,' I said.
'I work for her. I have to, I need the money.
I have no family and there
is nothing else I can do.'
De Winter asked me more questions about myself.
I forgot my shyness. I told him about my father,
who had been a painter. I talked about my
mother and her great love for my father.
When my father had died very suddenly, my
mother had lived only a few weeks after him.
I suddenly realized that we had been
sitting at the table for more than an
hour. I began to apologize.
'But I've enjoyed this hour
so much,' de Winter said.
'We are alike in some ways. We are both alone
in the world. I have a sister, but that's all.'
'You forget,' I told him, 'that
you have a home and I have none.'
'An empty house, even a very beautiful
one, can be lonely,' de Winter said.
I thought for a moment that he was
going to tell me about Manderley.
But instead he said, 'Well, I suppose you have a
holiday this afternoon. What are you going to do?'
I told him that I was going to do some sketching.
I wanted to draw some of the old houses in a
nearby town. The bus left at half past two.
'I'll drive you there in my car,' de Winter
said. 'Go upstairs and get your coat.'
I got my things very quietly. I did not want Mrs
Van Hopper to hear me. I ran down the stairs,
holding my gloves in one hand. I felt excited
and grown-up. I did not feel shy with de Winter.
He enjoyed my company. He had asked
me to go out with him in his car.
We soon reached the place where
I wanted to sketch. But the wind
was too strong - it blew the paper away.
We got into the car again and drove on,
up the steep mountain road. Then suddenly
the road came to an end. De Winter stopped
the car at the very edge. Far below us lay
the sea. I felt cold and a little afraid.
'Do you know this place?' I said.
'Have you been here before?'
De Winter looked at me as though I were
a stranger. He was lost in the past.
There was a strange, faraway look on his face.
He looked like a man walking in his sleep.
'It's getting late, shall we go home?'
I said. Then he looked at me and smiled.
'I'm sorry,' he said. 'I should
not have brought you up here.
Yes, I have been here before, many years ago.'
Those years seemed to stretch between us. For
the first time, I wished that I had not come.
De Winter turned the car carefully, and
we drove down the twisting road again.
The sun was setting now and
the air was cold and clear.
Then, at last, he began to talk about
Manderley. He did not talk about his life there,
but about the house itself. He told me about
the gardens and the flowers in the woods.
He told me about the sea. It was so near
that the sound of its waters could always
be heard from the house. He told me about
a little, secret valley close to the sea.
This little valley, hidden away from the
world, was full of the scent of flowers.
Then we were back in Monte Carlo.
We drove slowly through the brightly
lit streets towards the hotel. I took
my gloves from the shelf of the car.
There was a book there. I looked
at it, trying to read the title.
'You can take the book and look at it, if you
like,' de Winter said. I was glad and I held
the book tightly in my hand. I wanted to have
something of his now that our day was over.
'Out you get,' he said, 'I must put the car away.
I won't see you tonight. I shall
be out. But thank you for today.'
I walked slowly up the hotel steps. I felt
like a child going home after a party.
I thought of the long hours to
bedtime. I could not meet Mrs Van
Hopper and answer the endless questions.
I went into the lounge and ordered tea.
The waiter brought me tea that was
nearly cold. The sandwiches were dry,
but I ate them without thinking. In my
mind I was with Max de Winter at Manderley.
If he loved his home so much, why had he left it?
I picked up the book he had
given me. It was a book of poems.
On the front page there was some writing
- hard, clear writing in black ink:
"Max - from Rebecca, 17th May."
The name Rebecca stood out black and strong. The
"R" was tall, much bigger than the other letters.
I shut the book quickly. I remembered what Mrs
Van Hopper had told me about de Winter's wife.
'It was dreadful,' she had said. 'Her death
was in all the newspapers. They say he never
talks about it, never says her name. Rebecca was
drowned, you know, in the sea near Manderley.'
I stood up slowly, the book in my hand.
I walked unhappily to the lift
and back to Mrs Van Hopper.
CHAPTER THREE
In Love
I was twenty-one and de Winter was
the first man I had ever loved.
First love is not always happy. It can
sometimes be like a terrible illness.
Mrs Van Hopper had been in bed for about ten days.
She was bored now, and more bad tempered than
usual. She asked me what I had been doing.
'You haven't got enough to do and so you
are doing nothing,' she said unpleasantly.
'You never have any drawings to show
me. When I ask you to do some shopping,
you always forget something. You are
getting lazy without me to watch you.'
I did not reply. I could not tell
Mrs Van Hopper that every morning
I drove with de Winter in his car. Every
day I had lunch with him at his table.
I have forgotten the places we went to, but I have
not forgotten the excitement of those mornings.
I remember how I ran down the stairs
because the lift was too slow.
He was always waiting in his car, reading the
paper. When he saw me, he would smile and say,
'Well, how is the companion this
morning? Where would you like to go?'
If we had driven round-in
circles, I would not have cared.
I was happy to sit next to him, to be alone
with him. But the time always went too quickly.
There was a clock in the car. I could
not help looking at it as we drove along.
'If only we could keep our
memories like scent in a bottle,'
I said one day. 'And then we could open the bottle
when we wanted to remember the moment again.'
'And what moment would you like to
keep?' de Winter said with a smile.
'I'm not sure,' I began. Then I said quickly, 'I'd
like to keep this moment and never forget it.'
De Winter laughed. I suddenly
felt very young and very silly.
'I wish,' I said angrily, '...
I wish I was a woman of about
thirty-six. I wish I was wearing a lot
of make-up and had expensive clothes.'
'You would not be in this car now
if you were like that,' he said.
'Why do you ask me to come out in
your car, day after day?' I said.
'I'm young, I know nothing. I am
not an interesting person at all.
You know all about me now. I have told you
everything. But I know nothing about you,
nothing - except that you live at Manderley
and... and that your wife is dead.'
I had said the words, at last. Your wife.
Your wife. He would never forgive me.
I shall never drive with him again, I
thought. He slowed down the car and we
stopped by the side of the road.
Then he turned to me and spoke.
'A little while ago, you said you
wanted to keep your memories. For me,
it is different. All my memories are unhappy. I
want to forget them. Something happened a year
ago that changed my whole life. I want to forget
everything that happened to me before that time.
That's why I came to Monte Carlo. If you had
not been here, I would have left long ago.
I ask you to drive with me because
I like you. I enjoy your company.
If you don't believe me, you
can get out of the car now.'
I sat very still. I could not speak. I
could feel the tears coming into my eyes.
'I want to go home now,' I said.
Without a word, he started
the car and we drove on.
The tears began to run down my cheeks.
Suddenly de Winter took my hand and kissed it.
Then he gave me his handkerchief. I wiped
my red eyes. I had never felt more alone.
'To hell with this,' he said and put his
arm round my shoulders. 'You are so young,
I don't know how to speak to you. Forget
everything I told you. Let's start again.
My family always call me Maxim.
I'd like you to call me that too.'
I smiled then, and he laughed back at me.
The morning was happy again. The afternoon
with Mrs Van Hopper did not matter. I could
look forward to tomorrow morning and the morning
after. I could call him Maxim. He had kissed me.
I had to play cards with Mrs Van Hopper that
afternoon, but I was still happy. When we had
finished our game, Mrs Van Hopper said, 'Tell
me, is Max de Winter still in the hotel?'
'Yes. Yes, I think so. He comes into
the restaurant sometimes,' I said.
Someone has told her, I thought.
Someone has seen us together. I waited for
her to ask more questions. But she did not.
'He's an attractive man,' she said, 'but
not easy to know. I never saw his wife.
People say she was very lovely. She was clever
too, and always beautifully dressed, of course.
Her death was very sudden.
Everyone says he adored her.'
I did not answer. I was thinking about Rebecca -
beautiful and clever. People could not forget her.
Somehow, she and her beauty had not died.
In my bedroom was a book that Rebecca had held in
her hands. His family called him Maxim. Rebecca
had called him Max. I thought of the writing
on that page. It was bold and full of life.
Rebecca was all the things that I would never
be. I thought of all the letters Rebecca had
written to her husband. They must have
been full of the life they had shared.
I thought I could hear her voice
calling him. She called him Max.
It was her special name for him.
And I had to call him Maxim.
CHAPTER FOUR
I Leave Monte Carlo
Two days later, everything had changed. Mrs Van
Hopper and I were ready to leave Monte Carlo.
All the trunks and bags were packed. All
the drawers and cupboards were empty.
Mrs Van Hopper had read a letter
from her daughter at breakfast.
'Helen is sailing for New York
on Saturday. Her child's ill.
We are going too. I'm tired of living
here. How would you like to see New York?'
The thought of leaving Monte Carlo and
Maxim de Winter was a terrible one.
My unhappiness must have shown on my face.
'What a strange child you are,'
Mrs Van Hopper said. 'I can't understand
you. I thought you didn't like Monte Carlo.'
'I've got used to it,' I said.
'Well, you'll have to get used to New York,
that's all. We're going on the same boat as Helen.
You'll have to arrange everything at
once. Go down to the hotel office now.
You will be too busy to feel unhappy.'
She laughed unpleasantly at my sad face.
She walked over to the telephone. She wanted
to tell everyone that she was leaving.
I went into the bathroom and locked the
door. I wanted to be alone for a few minutes.
My happiness was at an end. By tomorrow evening,
I should be on the train. The train would carry
me away from Maxim, mile by mile. He would be
sitting in the restaurant, reading perhaps and not
thinking of me. Where would I say goodbye to him?
In the lounge, with Mrs Van Hopper standing near?
I was going and everything was over. We
would say goodbye like two strangers.
Mrs Van Hopper knocked on the bathroom door.
'What are you doing in there?'
she said. 'There's no time to dream this
morning. There's too much to be done.'
I washed my face with cold water and came out of
the bathroom at once. I spent the rest of the day
packing and arranging the journey. In the evening,
Mrs Van Hopper's friends came to say goodbye.
We had dinner upstairs and Mrs Van Hopper went to
bed early. I had not seen Maxim all day. I went
down to the lounge at half past nine. A waiter
saw me. He knew who I was looking for, of course.
'Mr de Winter is out this evening,' he told
me. 'He will not be back before midnight.'
I walked slowly back up the
stairs. Tomorrow would be too late.
I should not be able to speak to
him at all. That night I cried.
My pillow was wet with tears. In the
morning, my eyes were red and swollen.
'You haven't got a cold, have you?' said
Mrs Van Hopper when she saw my face.
'No,' I said, 'I don't think
so.' I tried not to look at her.
'I hate waiting around when everything is packed,'
Mrs Van Hopper said bad temperedly. 'We ought to
have gone on the earlier train.' She looked at
her watch. 'I think we could still catch it.
Go down to the reception desk and ask. Hurry up.'
So my last morning was to be taken away from me.
I would not see Maxim. Suddenly, I made up my
mind. Instead of going down to the reception desk,
I ran up the stairs. I knew the number
of his room. I knocked on the door.
'Come in,' Maxim shouted. I opened the
door. He was having breakfast at a small
table in his sitting-room. I stood by
the door, feeling silly and awkward.
'What do you want?' he said. 'Is something wrong?'
'I've come to say goodbye,' I said. 'We're
going this morning. In about an hour.
I thought I would not see you again.'
Maxim stared at me. 'Why didn't you
tell me about this before?' he said.
'Mrs Van Hopper only decided to leave
yesterday. Her daughter sails for New
York on Saturday and we're going with her.
I don't want to go. I'll hate New York.'
'Why go there, then?'
'I have to. I work for her, you know
that. I can't afford to leave her.'
'Sit down,' he said. 'Have some coffee.'
'I haven't time,' I told him.
'I should be downstairs now.'
'Never mind about that, I've got to talk to you.'
I sat down at the table.
'So Mrs Van Hopper wants to go
home,' said Maxim. 'So do I.
She goes to New York and I go to Manderley.
Which do you prefer? You can take your choice.'
'Please don't joke about it,' I
said. 'I must say goodbye now.'
'I'm not joking,' said Maxim. 'Either
you go to America with Mrs Van Hopper
or you come home to Manderley with me.'
'Do you want a secretary?' I
asked, not understanding him.
'No, I'm asking you to marry me, you little fool.'
I sat with my hands in my lap,
watching him drink his coffee.
'You can't marry me,' I said at
last. 'I'm different from you.
I don't belong to your kind of world. I
don't belong to a place like Manderley.'
'What do you know about Manderley?' Maxim said.
'I want you to marry me. Are you going to?'
I sat there, staring at him.
I could not think clearly.
'The idea doesn't seem to please you,' Maxim
said. 'I'm sorry, I thought you loved me.'
'I do love you,' I said, 'I do. I've been crying
all night. I thought I would never see you again.'
When I said this, Maxim laughed
and put his hand over mine.
'One day I'll remind you of those words.
It's a pity you have to grow up,' he said.
Was Maxim laughing at me? Was it all a joke?
He saw the look on my face. 'I haven't done
this very well, have I?' Maxim said. 'Men don't
usually propose at breakfast. But I'll take you to
Venice for our honeymoon. We'll travel round Italy
for a time. Then, in the spring, we'll go back to
Manderley. I want to show you Manderley so much.'
Maxim wanted to show me Manderley. Suddenly I
believed everything. I would be Maxim's wife.
We would walk in the gardens of
Manderley together. We would walk
through that hidden valley to the sea.
Mrs de Winter - I would be Mrs de Winter.
'Am I going to tell Mrs Van Hopper
or are you?' said Maxim with a smile.
I had forgotten all about Mrs Van Hopper.
'You tell her,' I said. 'She'll be so angry.'
We got up from the table and
walked out of the room together.
Maxim took my hand. 'I'm forty-two,' he
said. 'That must seem very old to you.'
'Oh, no,' I said. 'I don't like young men.' I was
still afraid that Maxim would change his mind.
We came to the door of Mrs Van Hopper's rooms.
'I think I'll talk to her alone,' Maxim said.
'I'll tell her we are getting married very soon.
We'll have a quiet wedding. Everything
can be arranged in a few days.'
'Of course,' I said. 'I don't want a lot of fuss.'
I opened the door.
'Is that you?' called Mrs Van Hopper. 'Where have
you been? What have you been doing all this time?'
I did not know whether to laugh or cry.
Maxim walked towards the sitting-room.
'I'm afraid it's all my fault,' he said
and then he shut the door. I
went into my bedroom and waited.
I wondered what Maxim was
saying to Mrs Van Hopper.
Was he saying, 'I love her. I
want to marry her at once.'?
Love. Maxim had not said anything to me about
love. He had said we would get married. But he had
not said that he loved me. He had loved Rebecca,
of course. How could he love me, after her?
I would be a companion for him.
Someone to make him laugh perhaps.
The book of poems was beside me, on the bed. I
opened it. I read again, 'Max, from Rebecca.'
She was dead. But the writing
still looked fresh and alive.
I took some scissors and cut the page out of the
book. I tore up the page. I lit a match and set
fire to the pieces. The paper twisted, blackened
and turned to ashes. The letter "R" was the
last to be burnt. Then the flame destroyed it. I
washed my hands. I felt better, much better now.
As I stood there, the door
opened and Maxim came in.
'Everything is all right,' he said. 'She could
not speak at first. She was too surprised.
Go in and talk to her. I'm going
downstairs to arrange about her train.
I don't want her to come to the wedding.'
Maxim was smiling, but he said nothing about
being happy. He said nothing about love.
I walked slowly into Mrs Van Hopper's bedroom. She
was standing by the window, smoking a cigarette.
She turned round and looked at me carefully.
'Well,' she said, 'you are more clever
than I thought. How did you do it?'
I did not know what to say. Mrs Van Hopper was
smiling, but there was no kindness in her smile.
'It was lucky for you that I was ill,' she said.
'You certainly made the most of your time.
He tells me that he wants to marry you in
a few days. Well, I can't stop you.
He's much older than you, you know.'
'He's only forty-two,' I said.
'I know what I'm doing.' Mrs Van Hopper looked
at me again with the same unpleasant smile.
'I hope you do. You won't find
it easy to look after Manderley.
You haven't any experience and you're too shy.
Max de Winter is very attractive, of course.
But I think you're making a big mistake.'
I did not say anything. I was young
and shy, I knew that. But I was going
to be Mrs de Winter. I was going to live at
Manderley. And I was going to make Maxim happy.
Mrs Van Hopper put out her cigarette.
She walked slowly towards me.
'Of course,' she said, 'you know
why he is marrying you, don't you?
He's not in love with you. The truth is he's
lonely by himself at Manderley. He can't live
in that empty house without Rebecca. He's marrying
you because he can't go on living there alone.'
CHAPTER FIVE
I Come to Manderley
Wе саmе to Manderley early in May. It was the
best time of year, before the heat of summer.
When we left London, it was raining
hard. I remember Maxim saying,
'This is London rain. The sun will be
shining for you when we come to Manderley.'
He was right. Long before we reached
Manderley, there was blue sky over our heads.
I was glad to see the sun. I
welcomed it as a sign of happiness.
'Feeling better?' said Maxim, looking at me.
I smiled at him and took his hand. It was so
easy for Maxim. He was going back to his own home.
But for me, everything was new and strange. I was
going to Manderley for the first time. And I was
going there as the second wife of Maxim de Winter.
'Only two more miles,' said Maxim
at last. 'Can you see those trees
on the hill in front of us? Manderley
is in the valley beyond those trees.'
I tried to smile but suddenly
I felt lonely and afraid.
I was like a child on her first day at school.
Turning a corner, we came to a crossroads
and the beginning of a high wall.
'Here we are,' Maxim said. 'Manderley at last.'
I could hear the excitement in his voice.
The road turned again. On the left, were two
high iron gates and beside them a small lodge.
The gates were wide open for us. People were
looking out of the windows of the lodge.
They were looking at me. I sat back in my
seat. I wanted to hide from their curious eyes.
'You mustn't mind if people stare at you,'
Maxim said. 'They are all very interested
in you. Don't worry. Be yourself and
everyone at Manderley will love you.
Mrs Danvers looks after the house. She's been
housekeeper here for years. Leave everything to
her. She may be rather strange at first, but don't
worry about that. She will soon get used to you.'
We were going along the drive now that led up
to the house. The drive turned and twisted like
a snake. The tall trees met over our heads. Only a
little sunlight came through their thick branches.
Everything was very quiet. On and on we went.
Then suddenly the trees came to an end. The sun
shone again. Beautiful high bushes covered with
bright red flowers stood on either side of us.
We were not far from the house now. The drive
widened. We turned the last corner and there was
Manderley. The old house was perfect.
It was built in a small hollow and
its grey stones glowed in the sunlight.
Smooth green lawns surrounded the house.
Beyond the lawns were gardens
and beyond the gardens, the sea.
Maxim drove up to the wide stone steps
and stopped the car in front of them.
At the top of the steps, a
big door stood wide open.
I saw that the hall beyond was full of people.
I could see their faces, all turned towards us.
I was suddenly shy and afraid again. 'What's
the matter?' I said. 'Who are all those people?'
'I'm sorry,' Maxim said. 'This must be
Mrs Danvers' idea. Everyone who works
at Manderley is here. Don't look so frightened.
You won't have to say anything. I'll do it all.'
An old man with a kind face came down the steps.
'Well, here we are, Frith,'
said Maxim. 'Everyone well?'
'Yes, thank you, sir,' said Frith. 'We are
all very glad to see you at home again.
We hope you are well. And Madam too, of course.'
'Yes, we are both well, thank you, Frith. But
we're tired from the drive and we want our tea.
I didn't expect all these people.'
'Mrs Danvers' orders, sir,' said Frith.
'I thought so,' Maxim said.
'Come on,' he said to me. 'It won't take long
and then you can have your tea in peace.'
We went together up the wide stone steps. Inside
the open door, the servants stood in two lines.
A tall, thin woman dressed in black came towards
us. Her pale, thin face was hard. There was no
welcome in her dark eyes. The hand she placed
in mine was cold and heavy, like something dead.
'This is Mrs Danvers, our housekeeper,' said
Maxim. The woman began to speak in a cold,
lifeless voice. I remember nothing of what she
said. I suppose she was welcoming me to Manderley.
As I thanked her, Mrs Danvers looked at me with
her hard, dark eyes. I dropped my gloves on
the floor and Mrs Danvers picked them up
with a twisted little smile on her lips.
She could see that I was awkward and shy, and
a little afraid of my new life at Manderley.
Maxim noticed nothing. He thanked Mrs Danvers
quickly and took me into the library for tea.
We were alone at last.
A dog ran up from the fireside to greet us. He
went first to Maxim and then sat down beside me.
I was glad of the dog's friendly welcome.
The library was a large comfortable room.
Its walls were covered with books
from the floor to the ceiling.
Comfortable chairs stood on either
side of a great open fireplace.
From its long windows I could see the lawns
and beyond the lawns, the sea. There was a
quiet peace in the room. It was a place for
rest, for reading and for quiet thinking.
Tea was brought to us by Frith and a younger
servant. There was a special table and a
snow-white cloth to cover it. The teapot and
kettle were of silver and the china was very fine.
There were sandwiches, bread and
butter and several kinds of cake.
There was far too much food for two people. But
this was the tea served at Manderley every day.
Maxim sat in a chair by the fire reading
the letters that had been waiting for him.
Now and again, he looked up at me and smiled.
I leant back in my chair, drinking my tea
and trying to feel at home. It was true.
Manderley was my home now - my home and Maxim's.
But somehow I still could not believe it.
My thoughts were interrupted by the
opening of the door. It was Frith.
'Excuse me, Madam,' he said. 'Mrs Danvers
asked if you would like to see your room.'
Maxim looked up from his letters. 'What do the
rooms in the east wing look like now?' he said.
'Very nice indeed, sir,' Frith replied. 'I
think you will be very comfortable there.'
'Have you been making changes?' I asked.
'Oh, nothing much,' said Maxim. 'They have been
getting the rooms in the east wing ready for us.
There is a lovely view of the rose-garden from
there. You go and make friends with
Mrs Danvers. I'll come up later.'
I got up slowly and went out with Frith into
the hall. I did not want to be alone with
Mrs Danvers. The hall seemed very big, and my
footsteps sounded very loud on the stone floor.
Mrs Danvers was standing at the top of the wide
flight of stairs. Her dark eyes watched me as
I walked slowly up the stairs towards her.
'I hope I haven't kept you waiting,' I said.
'It is my duty to wait for you, Madam,' Mrs
Danvers said. 'I'm here to carry out your orders.'
She led me along a wide passage. We passed
through doors and up and down wide stairs.
At last Mrs Danvers opened a door leading
into a small room. This room led into a large,
light bedroom with wide windows. I went at once
to a window and looked out. The rose-garden lay
below me. Beyond the rose-garden, the
smooth grass stretched to the woods.
'You can't see the sea from here,'
I said, turning to Mrs Danvers.
'No, not from this wing,' she answered,
'and you can't hear it either. You
would never know the sea was so near.'
Mrs Danvers spoke in a strange way, as
though this was somehow important to her.
'I'm sorry about that; I like the sea,' I said.
'But this is a very charming room.
I'm sure I shall be comfortable here.'
'Mr de Winter gave very careful
orders in his letter about this room.
The rooms here have been
specially arranged for you.'
'Then this was not his bedroom before?'
'Oh, no, Madam. He has never used this room.'
There was silence. I did not know what to
say. I wished Mrs Danvers would go away.
'I suppose you have been at
Manderley for many years,' I said.
'Yes, Madam. I came here when the first Mrs de
Winter was a bride.' Her voice was suddenly harsh.
There was some colour in her pale face now. And
for a moment I saw a look of hatred in her eyes.
'Mrs Danvers,' I heard myself
saying, 'I hope we shall be friends.
This sort of life is new to me. I
do want to make Mr de Winter happy.
I know I can leave the housekeeping to
you. I shan't want to make any changes.'
'Very well,' she said. 'I
hope you will be satisfied.
I have been looking after the house for the past
year. When the late Mrs de Winter was alive, there
were lots of parties and visitors, of course.
She liked to look after everything herself.'
'I would rather leave it to
you, Mrs Danvers,' I said.
'And I'm sure we'll be very
comfortable in these rooms.'
'Mr de Winter said you would rather be on this
side of the house. They used the rooms in the
west wing when Mrs de Winter was alive.
The windows there look down to the sea.'
There was a sound outside the door and Mrs
Danvers stopped talking. Maxim came into the room.
'Well, what do you think?'
Maxim said to me. 'I hope you like the rooms.
I think you've done very well, Mrs Danvers.'
'Thank you, sir,' she said. Then she
turned and went quietly out of the room.
Maxim walked to the window. 'I love the
rose-garden,' he said. 'There's something
very quiet and peaceful about this room.
How did you get on with Mrs Danvers? She's
a strange woman in many ways. I think that
some of the young servants are afraid of her.'
'I expect we'll get on well when
she knows me better,' I said.
'She may not like me at first, of course.'
'Not like you? Why shouldn't she like you?'
said Maxim and he came across
the room and kissed me gently.
'Let's forget about Mrs Danvers,' he said.
'Come along, and I'll show you Manderley.'
I felt happier as I walked
through the house with Maxim.
We looked at the pictures in the long
gallery and at most of the rooms downstairs.
Maxim put his arm round my shoulder. I began
to feel that Manderley really was my home.
After dinner, we sat in the library. The curtains
were drawn and more logs put on the fire. It was
new for us to sit together quietly like this.
In Italy we had walked about in the evenings,
or gone for a drive. Maxim sat in the
chair to the left of the fireplace.
He picked up the paper. He put a cushion
behind his head and lit a cigarette.
This is what he always did, I thought.
This is what he did before he knew me.
It is what he has done every evening for years.
Maxim did not look at me. He went on reading
his paper. He was comfortable, the master of
his house. I poured myself another cup of coffee.
I bent down to the dog and stroked its soft ears.
Suddenly I shivered as though a door had opened
behind me. Someone else had sat in my chair.
Someone else had poured
coffee and stroked the dog.
I was sitting in Rebecca's chair. I
was leaning against Rebecca's cushion.
The dog, Jasper, came to me because
in the past he had come to Rebecca.
CHAPTER SIX
In the Morning-Room
Life at Manderley was very carefully planned. The
same things happened at the same time every day.
I remember our first morning there very clearly.
I had slept well and came downstairs a little
after nine o'clock. To my surprise, I found
that Maxim had nearly finished his breakfast.
Maxim looked up at me and smiled.
'I always get up early here,' he said. 'Looking
after Manderley takes a lot of my time.
I work very hard. But you don't have
to. Help yourself to anything you want.'
I remember the size of that breakfast.
It was the normal Manderley breakfast,
but far too much for two people.
As I took an egg and some coffee, I wondered
what happened to the food that was left. Would
it be eaten or thrown away? I would never know of
course. I would certainly be too afraid to ask.
'My sister, Beatrice, is coming over to
lunch with her husband,' Maxim told me.
'She invited herself, of course. I
suppose she wants to have a look at you.'
They're coming today?' I said,
feeling less happy than before.
'Yes, but she won't stay long. I think you'll
like Beatrice. She believes in telling the truth.
If she doesn't like you, she'll tell you so.'
Maxim stood up and lit a cigarette.
'I've so many things to do this morning.
Why don't you go into the garden.
You don't mind being alone, do you?'
'Of course not,' I said. 'I
shall be perfectly happy.'
But I did not feel very happy
as Maxim walked out of the room.
I had thought we would spend our
first morning at Manderley together.
I had thought that perhaps we would walk down to
the sea, or sit under the great tree on the lawn.
I finished my breakfast alone. I left the
dining-room and went into the library.
The room was cold. The fire was laid, but
not lit. I looked round for a box of matches,
but I could not find one. I went across the
hall and into the dining-room once more. Yes,
there was a box of matches on the table. I picked
it up. At that moment, Frith came into the room.
'Oh, Frith,' I said awkwardly,
'I could not find any matches.
I thought I would light the fire in the
library. It's rather cold in there.'
'The fire in the library is not usually
lit until the afternoon, Madam,'
he said. 'Mrs de Winter always used
the morning-room before lunch. There
is a good fire in there. Of course, I can give
orders for the fire in the library to be lit.'
'Oh no,' I said. 'I'll go into the
morning-room. Thank you, Frith.'
'Mrs de Winter always wrote her letters
in the morning-room after breakfast.
The house telephone is there too,
if you want to talk to Mrs Danvers.'
'Thank you, Frith,' I said. I went into the hall
again, I did not know which way to go. I could not
tell Frith that I had never seen the morning-room.
Maxim had not shown it to me the night before.
'You go through the drawing-room
to the morning-room, Madam,'
Frith said, watching me. 'Then turn to your left.'
'Thank you, Frith,' I said. I felt very stupid.
I found my way into the little morning-room.
I was glad to see the dog, Jasper,
there, sitting in front of the fire.
The morning-room was quite small and very
different from the library. It was a woman's
room, graceful and charming. Someone had chosen
everything in this room with the greatest care.
Each chair, each rug, each small ornament
had been put there to make the room perfect.
Flowers filled the room, glowing blood-red
flowers. They were the same flowers we had
seen in the drive. A beautiful old
writing-desk stood near the window.
I went over and opened the desk carefully. Every
drawer was labelled and everything was in order.
Inside one of the drawers was a flat leather
book: 'Guests at Manderley'. I opened the book.
The writing inside the book and the
writing on the labels was the same.
I had seen that tall sloping writing before. It
was Rebecca's writing. This was Rebecca's desk.
I sat down and opened the Guest Book. Every
page was covered with the same writing.
I felt that Rebecca would come
back into the room at any moment.
The mistress of the house would come in and
find me, a stranger, sitting at her desk.
Suddenly the telephone on the desk began to ring.
My heart jumped. I picked up the phone.
'Who is it?' I said. 'Who do you want?'
'Mrs de Winter?' said a hard,
deep voice, 'Mrs de Winter?'
My hand was shaking.
'I'm afraid you have made a mistake,' I said.
'Mrs de Winter has been dead for over a year.'
I suddenly realized what I had said.
'It's Mrs Danvers, Madam,' said the voice.
'I'm speaking to you on the house telephone.'
'I'm so sorry, Mrs Danvers,' I said.
'I didn't know what I was saying.
I did not expect the telephone to ring.'
'I wondered if you had seen the menus for the day.
You will find the list on the desk beside you.'
I found the piece of paper
and looked at it quickly.
'Yes, Mrs Danvers. Yes, very nice indeed.'
'I'm very sorry to have disturbed you, Madam.'
'You didn't disturb me at all.
Thank you, Mrs Danvers,' I said.
I put down the phone and looked at the
desk. I felt very stupid. Rebecca would
not have answered like that. I thought of
Rebecca sitting at that desk. Here she had
chosen her guests and written letters to her
friends. Who could I write to? I knew nobody.
Then I thought of Mrs Van Hopper, far away in
New York. I took a piece of paper and a pen.
'Dear Mrs Van Hopper,' I began. As I wrote I
noticed my own handwriting for the first time.
How weak and childish it was! It was
like the writing of a schoolgirl.
CHAPTER SEVEN
You Are So Very Different...
When I heard the sound of a car in
the drive, I stood up in sudden fear.
Beatrice and her husband had arrived.
They were earlier than I expected.
And Maxim had not come back. I
could not meet them by myself.
I ran quickly out of the morning-room.
I took a door to the left.
I was in a stone corridor. A servant stared at me
in surprise. I hurried up some stairs, hoping that
I could find my way to my bedroom in the east
wing. I could stay there until Maxim came back.
Somehow I lost my way. But I went on and
came to a wide staircase. I went up it.
All was quiet and dark. I was in a corridor
with doors on either side. I walked on and
at last I came to a long window. I looked out.
Below me I could see green lawns and the sea.
The sea was bright green, with white-topped
waves. It was closer than I thought, much closer.
I knew then that I had walked right round
the house. I was standing in the corridor
of the west wing. Yes, Mrs Danvers was
right, you could hear the sea from here.
I was glad that my rooms were in the east wing.
I loved the quiet beauty of the rose-garden.
The sea was too near here. As I turned to
go back to the stairs, I heard a door open
behind me. Mrs Danvers stood there. We stared
at one another for a moment without speaking.
'I lost my way,' I said, 'I
was trying to find my room.'
'This is the west wing,' she said.
'Did you go into any of the rooms?
If you wish to see them, please tell
me. I could show them to you now.'
I shook my head. 'No, no thank you,' I said.
'I must go downstairs.' As I began to walk
towards the stairs, Mrs Danvers followed me.
'If you want to see the rooms in the west
wing, I can show them to you at any time.'
'It's very kind of you, Mrs Danvers,' I said. 'I
will let you know.' Mrs Danvers walked beside me.
'Major and Mrs Lacy have been here some
time,' she said. 'Didn't you hear their
car? Frith took them to the morning-room.
I think you know your way now, don't you?'
'Yes, Mrs Danvers,' I said. I knew
then that she had been watching me,
laughing at my fear. As I went into
the drawing-room, I looked back.
Mrs Danvers was still watching
me from the top of the stairs.
I could hear the sound of voices from
the morning-room. I stood for a moment
and then walked in.
'Here she is at last,' Maxim
said. 'Where have you been hiding?
Here is Beatrice and this is Giles.
And this is Frank Crawley, our agent.'
Beatrice was tall, broad-shouldered and very
much like Maxim. She shook hands with me and
said to Maxim, 'She's quite different from what
I expected. Not like your description at all.'
Everyone laughed, but they seemed friendly.
Giles was a big, heavy man. His eyes smiled at
me from behind his thick glasses. Frank Crawley
was a thin man with a pleasant, worried face.
Maxim had told me how hard Frank
Crawley worked for Manderley.
The men began to talk together and I
had to answer Beatrice's questions.
'What do you think of Manderley?' she asked me.
'I haven't seen much of it yet,' I said.
'The house is beautiful, of course. I haven't
seen the gardens, but I'm sure I shall
never get tired of them. I love walking.
I can swim too, when the weather is warmer.'
'My dear, the water is always far
too cold here,' said Beatrice.
'I don't mind that, I love swimming.
Is it safe to swim in the bays?'
Everyone stopped talking. I realized what
I had said. Rebecca had been drowned in the
bay. I could not look at Maxim. I bent
down to stroke the dog's head. Then,
thank God, Frith came in to say that lunch was
ready. Beatrice walked with me through the hall.
'You know,' she said, 'you are much younger than
I expected. Tell me, do you love Maxim very much?'
Beatrice looked at my surprised face and laughed.
'Don't answer,' she said. 'I can see that
you do. Maxim looks very well. We were all
very worried about him last year. But
of course, you know the whole story.'
But Beatrice was wrong. I did not know
what had happened down in the bay.
Maxim had told me nothing. I had
never asked him about Rebecca's death.
Beatrice talked to Maxim all through lunch.
Frank Crawley told me a lot about Manderley.
I could see that he loved it as much as Maxim did.
When lunch was over, I could
see that Maxim was tired.
I wished we hadn't had visitors so soon.
I took Beatrice out on to the terrace.
She asked me how I had met Maxim. I told her about
Mrs Van Hopper and how surprised she had been.
'It was rather a shock to us too,' Beatrice said.
'Maxim said in his letter that you were very young
and pretty. We expected a very modern sort of
girl.' Beatrice laughed and I laughed with her.
'Poor Maxim. He had a terrible time,' Beatrice
said. 'Let's hope you have made him forget all
about it. He loves Manderley so much.
But you never know what he is thinking.
How do you get on with Mrs Danvers?'
I was surprised by Beatrice's question.
'She frightens me a little,' I said.
'She may try to make things
unpleasant for you,' Beatrice went on.
'She's very jealous, of course.
She must hate you being here.'
'Why?' I asked. 'Why must she
hate me being at Manderley?'
'My dear child,' Beatrice answered
slowly, 'I thought Maxim had told you.
Mrs Danvers adored Rebecca. She still does.'
At that moment, the men came out of the house.
A servant brought rugs and chairs and we all sat
under the great tree on the lawn. I hoped everyone
would go soon. I wanted to be alone with Maxim.
I was sitting on a rug, leaning against Maxim's
chair. I listened to the others talking. The
afternoon was sleepy and peaceful. Everything was
quiet and still. Even the sea seemed far away.
This is what I wanted, I thought. This is
how I thought life at Manderley would be.
This moment was safe. It could not be touched.
Here we sat together, Maxim and I, hand in hand.
The past and the future did not matter
at all. At this moment I was not afraid.
The moment passed. Beatrice stood up.
'We must be going,' she said.
'We've got people coming to dinner.'
We all got up and Giles looked up at the sky.
'I'm afraid we're going to have some rain,' he
said. We all walked slowly back to the drive.
Beatrice took my hand. Then
she bent down and kissed me.
'Forgive me if I've asked you a
lot of rude questions, my dear.
As I said before, you are not what we expected.
You are so very different from Rebecca.'
As we reached the car, the sun went behind
a cloud and a little rain began to fall.
Maxim and I watched the car drive away. We
turned and walked back into the house.
CHAPTER EIGHT
The Happy Valley
As we stood in the hall, Maxim
put his arm round my shoulders.
'Thank God that's over,' he said.
'Get a coat quickly and let's go out.
Never mind the rain, I want a walk.'
Maxim looked white and ill. Had Beatrice said
something to make him angry? I could not remember.
'Just a moment,' I said. 'I'll
get my coat from upstairs.'
'There are plenty of raincoats
downstairs,' Maxim said.
'Robert, will you fetch a coat for Mrs de Winter?'
Maxim was standing in the
drive now, calling to Jasper.
'Come on, you lazy little fellow. You're too fat.'
Jasper ran round in circles, barking loudly.
The young servant, Robert, ran out of the hall,
carrying a raincoat. I put it on quickly.
It was too big, of course, and too long.
But Maxim was waiting impatiently and
there was no time to change the coat.
We set off together across the lawns
to the woods. Jasper ran on in front.
'I soon get tired of my family,' Maxim
said. 'Beatrice is very kind-hearted,
but she always says the wrong thing.'
I was not sure what Beatrice had said
and I thought it better not to ask.
'What did you think of Beatrice?' Maxim asked
me. 'What did she talk to you about after lunch?'
'I think I did most of the talking,' I said.
'I was telling her about how we met. She said
I was quite different from what she expected.'
'What on earth did she expect?'
'Someone much smarter, I
think. A modern young woman.'
Maxim did not answer. He bent down and
threw a stick for Jasper to run after.
We climbed the grass bank above the
lawns and walked down into the woods.
The trees grew very close together
over our heads and it was very dark.
We walked on last year's leaves. The green
shoots of flowers were beginning to show through.
Jasper was silent now, with
his nose to the ground.
We came to a clearing in the woods.
There were two paths, going in opposite
directions. Jasper ran on ahead and took
the right-hand path without waiting for us.
'Not that way,' called Maxim. 'Come on, old boy.'
The dog looked back at us. He
stood there, wagging his tail.
'Why does he want to go that way?' I asked.
'I suppose he's used to it,' Maxim said quickly.
'It leads to a small bay where we used to keep
a boat. Come on, Jasper, old boy, this way.'
We turned on to the left-hand
path, not saying anything.
I looked over my shoulder and
saw that Jasper was following us.
'This path brings us to the valley
I told you about,' Maxim told me.
'You can smell the flowers already. Never
mind the rain, it will bring out the scent.'
Maxim seemed all right again now, happy
and cheerful. He began talking about
Frank Crawley. He told me what a good
agent he was and how he loved Manderley.
I held Maxim's arm and looked up into his face.
Talking about Manderley
always made Maxim happy again.
We had reached the top of a small hill.
The path ran down into a little valley,
by the side of a stream.
'There,' said Maxim, 'look at that.'
There were no dark trees in this valley, no thick
bushes. On either side of the narrow path stood
high graceful bushes covered with flowers.
The flowers were pink, white and gold. They
were things of beauty and grace. The soft summer
rain fell and the air was full of a sweet scent.
There was no sound except for
the noise of a little stream
and the quiet rain on the leaves. When
Maxim spoke, his voice was gentle and low.
'We call it the Happy Valley,' he said.
We stood still, not speaking. I looked down
at the clear white flowers. Maxim picked up
a fallen flower and gave it to me. As I rubbed it
between my hands, the scent was sweet and strong.
A bird began to sing, a high, clear sound.
Other birds began to sing too. I had never
been in so beautiful a place. As we walked along
the path, drops of rain fell on my hands and face.
I held Maxim's hand. The Happy
Valley was the heart of Manderley,
the Manderley I would soon know and love.
CHAPTER NINE
The Cottage in the Bay
We came to the end of the path. The bushes made an
arch over our heads so that we had to bend down.
I stood straight again, brushing the rain from
my head. I saw that the valley was behind us.
We were standing in a little narrow bay.
There, almost at our feet was the sea.
Maxim looked down at me, smiling
at the surprise on my face.
'It is a surprise, isn't it?' he
said. 'No one ever expects it.'
Maxim picked up a stone and threw
it across the beach for Jasper.
'Fetch it, good boy,' he said. Jasper ran
after the stone, barking with excitement.
We both went down to the water's edge and threw
more stones. The tide was coming up into the
bay and the water was beginning to cover the
stones. Maxim turned to me, laughing and wiping
the hair out of his eyes. I rolled up the long
sleeves of the raincoat. It was a happy moment.
Then we saw that Jasper had gone. We
called and whistled, but he did not come.
'Has he gone back to the Happy Valley?' I asked.
'He was by that rock a minute ago,' said Maxim.
We walked up the beach towards the valley again.
'Jasper, Jasper,' called Maxim.
In the distance, beyond a line of rocks to
the right of the beach, I heard a sharp bark.
'Do you hear that?' I said. 'He's gone over
this way.' I began to climb up the wet rocks.
'Come back,' Maxim said sharply,
'we don't want to go that way.'
'I must get him,' I said. 'He may be hurt.'
'He's all right,' said Maxim.
'Leave him. He knows the way home.'
I began climbing over the rocks towards Jasper.
I thought Maxim was being very unkind. I got to
the top of the largest rock and looked beyond
it. There was another bay. A small stone wall
across the bay made it into a small harbour. In
the bay was a green and white buoy, but no boat.
The woods came right down to the shore. At the
edge of the woods was a low stone building,
a cottage or a boat-house. There was a man
standing on the shore, dressed like a fisherman.
Jasper was barking at him and running round
and round. The man took no notice of the dog.
'Jasper,' I shouted, 'Jasper, come here.'
The dog looked up, but he did not come to
me. I looked back, but I could not see Maxim.
I climbed down into the bay and the man looked at
me for the first time. There was something strange
about him. He had small, stupid looking eyes. His
face was fat and round and he had thick, red lips.
'Bad weather, isn't it?' the
man said with a stupid smile.
'It's not very nice weather,' I said.
'Come on Jasper, we must go home now.'
But Jasper ran away, barking.
'Have you got any string?' I asked the
man. 'I want something to tie the dog.
He won't follow me.'
'I know that dog, it's not
yours. It comes from the house.'
'He's Mr de Winter's dog,' I said
kindly. 'I must take him back.'
The man said nothing, but stared
at me in the same stupid way.
I walked up the shore to the cottage.
Perhaps there was some string there.
The grass round the little house had grown
very long. The windows had pieces of wood
over them. I pushed at the door. To my
surprise it opened and I went inside.
The room was furnished and
there were books on the shelves.
But everything was covered with thick
dust. The air was damp and still.
Another door at the end of the room led into a
small boat-house. I saw some string on a shelf
and an old knife. I cut a piece of string
for Jasper and went out of the cottage.
There was something frightening about that
small, dark room. I was glad to be outside again.
The man was still watching
me, staring like a child.
Jasper was quiet now and let me tie the string.
'I saw you go in there,' the man said.
'She doesn't go in there now. She's gone
in the sea. She won't come back, will she?'
'No,' I said. 'She won't come back.'
'I didn't say anything, did I?'
The man's eyes were full of fear.
He turned away and walked back towards the sea.
Maxim was waiting for me beside
the rocks. He looked angry.
'I'm sorry,' I said. 'I had to get some
string for Jasper. Who is that man?'
'That's Ben. He's a bit mad, but he won't
hurt you. Where did you get that string?'
'I found it in the cottage. The door was open.
There's dust everywhere. The
place ought to be cleaned.'
'The door should be locked,' Maxim
said. He was walking very fast now.
He went up past the cottage and on to
a path through the woods. It was very
different here from the Happy Valley. The path
was steep and the trees were thick, and dark.
It was cold now and my legs ached. Jasper
was tired too, and walked very slowly.
'Come on, Jasper, for God's sake,'
said Maxim angrily. 'Pull at that
string, can't you?' he said to me.
'It's your fault,' I said, 'you walk so fast.'
'If you had listened to me,
we would be home by now. There was
no need for you to go after Jasper.'
'I thought you would come with me,' I answered.
'Why should I run after the damned
dog?' Maxim said, not looking at me.
'That's an excuse. You didn't want
to go over the rocks,' I answered.
'All right, I didn't. I didn't want
to go to the other bay. I never
go near the place or that damned
cottage. If you had my memories,
you would not go there either. You wouldn't
talk about it or even think about it.'
Maxim's face was white. His eyes had a dark,
lost look. I took his hand and held it tight.
'Please, Maxim, please,' I said. 'I
don't want you to look like that.
I'm sorry, darling. Please don't let us quarrel.'
'We should have stayed in Italy,' Maxim said.
'I was a fool to bring you back to Manderley.'
I had to run to keep up with him now. At last
we came to the top of the path and out on to
the lawn. Maxim's face was hard. He walked
straight into the house and spoke to Frith.
'We want tea at once,' said Maxim. Then he went
quickly into the library and shut the door.
I tried to keep back my tears. Frith must not see
them. I turned away as he helped me off with
the raincoat. He picked up a handkerchief.
'Is this yours, Madam?' he said.
I put the handkerchief in my pocket and
walked slowly across the hall to the library.
Maxim was sitting in his usual
chair, with Jasper at his feet.
I walked across the room and
knelt down by Maxim's chair.
'Don't be angry with me any more,' I said.
Maxim looked down at me.
'I'm not angry with you,' he said.
'But I've made you unhappy,' I replied. 'I
want you to be happy so much. I love you.'
'Do you?' he said. His eyes
were full of pain and fear.
'What is it, darling?' I said.
'Why do you look like that?'
The door opened before Maxim could answer.
It was Frith and Robert with the tea.
The small table was put near the fire
and covered with the white cloth.
Frith brought in the silver teapot and kettle.
Then came the cups, the sandwiches and cakes.
Everything was the same as yesterday.
When the servants had gone,
I looked at Maxim's face. The colour had
come back into it. He took a sandwich.
'Pour me a cup of tea, darling,' he said to
me. 'And forgive me for being so unkind.'
There was nothing more to say. Maxim
smiled at me and picked up his paper.
Maxim's smile was like a pat
on the head given to Jasper.
I was not hungry and I felt very tired. I
gave Jasper a piece of cake and took out the
handkerchief to wipe my hands. The handkerchief
was not mine. It must have come from the raincoat
pocket. There were some letters in the corner
- a tall "R" and "de W." It was Rebecca's.
The raincoat, too wide, too long
for me, must have been hers too.
Rebecca had worn that raincoat. She had
left the handkerchief in the pocket.
I could smell a scent, a scent I knew. I shut
my eyes and tried to remember what it was.
Suddenly I knew. The scent on the handkerchief
was the scent of the flowers in the Happy Valley.
Was there nowhere I could escape from Rebecca?
CHAPTER TEN
Questions and Answers
The weather was wet and cold for over a
week. We did not go down to the beach again.
I could see the sea from the terrace and
the lawns. It looked cold and grey. When
I stood on the terrace, I could hear
the sound of great waves on the shore.
I began to understand why some people
hated the low, angry voice of the sea.
I was glad that our rooms were in the east
wing. If I could not sleep, I went to the
window and looked out on to the rose-garden.
I was not troubled by the sea's unhappy music.
Sometimes I thought about
the cottage down in the bay.
There were so many questions I wanted to
ask Maxim. I could not forget the lost look
in Maxim's eyes. I could not forget his words:
'I was a fool to bring you back to Manderley.'
It was all my fault. I had gone down into the bay.
I had reminded Maxim of the past. We
lived our lives together sleeping,
eating, walking. But, every hour of the
day, the past made a wall between us.
I became nervous and afraid. I did not want
anyone to talk about the sea or boats. When
visitors came to Manderley, I was shy and awkward.
I knew that they compared me with Rebecca. She
had been charming, interested in everyone.
I was dull and stupid, like a schoolgirl.
One afternoon, I was having tea alone
when the wife of the bishop called.
She was a kind woman and tried hard
to make me talk. At last she said,
'Will your husband hold the
Manderley Fancy Dress Ball this year?
I remember the last one so well. It was such
a lovely sight. I shall never forget it.'
I smiled and said, 'We have not decided.
There have been so many things to do.'
I could not tell the woman that Maxim
had never spoken about the ball.
'Manderley looked so beautiful,'
the bishop's wife went on.
'And there was dancing, and
music and flowers everywhere.'
'Yes,' I said. 'Yes, I must ask Maxim about it.'
'We came to a garden-party too, one summer,'
the bishop's wife went on. 'It was a lovely day.
We all had tea in the rose-garden. It was such a
clever idea. Of course, she was a clever person.'
She stopped, her face rather
red. I heard myself saying,
'Rebecca must have been a wonderful person...'
I had said her name at last.
'Rebecca.' I had said it aloud.
'You never met her then?'
the woman asked. 'Yes, she was a lovely
person. So full of life. Everyone loved her.'
'She was so good at everything too,' I
said. 'Clever, beautiful and fond of sport.'
'Rebecca was certainly beautiful,' my visitor
went on. 'I remember her on the night of the Ball.
She had a cloud of dark hair. Her skin was
very white. And she had such a lovely dress.'
'She looked after everything in the house, too,'
I said. 'I'm afraid I leave
it all to the housekeeper.'
'Oh well, you are very young, aren't
you? We can't all do everything.
I must go now. Do ask your
husband to have another ball.'
'Yes, of course I will.'
I sat in the library after my visitor had gone.
I thought about Manderley, full of people in
beautiful costumes, dancing in the hall. I thought
of Rebecca, lively and beautiful, arranging
everything. What must people think about me?
I suddenly sat up straight. I did not mind. I did
not care. I was Mrs de Winter now, not Rebecca.
I decided that I would find out more about the
Fancy Dress Ball. But I did not want to ask Maxim.
Later that afternoon, Frank
Crawley came up to the house.
'I have been hearing about the Fancy Dress Ball,
Frank,' I said. 'I did not
know you had dances here.'
Frank did not reply at once. Then he said,
'The Manderley Ball was held every year.
People came from miles around.
They even came down from London.'
'It must have been a lot of work,' I
said. 'I suppose Rebecca did most of it.'
Frank looked straight ahead.
'We all helped,' he said.
'Will you ask Maxim about the Ball?'
I asked. 'It does seem a good idea.'
Frank did not answer me.
'I went into that cottage in
the bay a few days ago,' I said.
'It's very dirty. Why doesn't
someone do something about it?'
'Maxim would tell me if he wanted
anything done,' Frank replied.
'Are they Rebecca's things?' I asked.
'Yes,' Frank said.
'Did Rebecca use the cottage a lot?'
'Yes, she did. She slept in the cottage sometimes.
She had moonlight picnics on the shore.'
I noticed that Frank always called
Rebecca 'she'. He never used her name.
'Why is there a buoy in the bay?' I asked.
'There's no boat there. What happened to it?
Was it the boat Rebecca
was sailing when she died?'
'Yes,' said Frank, quietly.
'It turned over and sank.
She was washed overboard and drowned. The
sea is sometimes very rough in the bay.'
'Couldn't anyone have helped her?' I asked.
'Nobody saw the accident. Nobody knew she was
sailing. She often went out alone like that.'
'When did they find her?' I
felt I must know everything now.
I had been thinking about that
terrible night for so long.
'They found her two months later. The sea
had carried her forty miles up the coast.
Maxim had to identify the body.'
Suddenly I was ashamed of all my questions.
'Frank,' I said, 'I'm sorry I asked you
all those questions. But everything is so
strange to me at Manderley. And when I meet
anyone new, I know what they are thinking:
"How different she is from Rebecca." '
'Mrs de Winter, you mustn't think that,'
said Frank, looking at me for the first time.
'I am so glad you have married Maxim. It
will make such a difference to his life.
And Manderley needs someone like you,
someone young, fresh and charming.'
'But Rebecca was so charming - and
clever. People still remember her.'
'Maxim would be very unhappy to hear you talking
like this, Mrs de Winter. Forget the past, as
Maxim has done. None of us want to bring back the
past. Your job here is to lead us away from it.'
I was much happier now. But I had
to ask Frank one more question.
Tell me, Frank,' I said.
'Was Rebecca very beautiful?'
Frank turned away from me so
that I could not see his face.
'Yes,' he said slowly. 'Yes, I suppose she was
the most beautiful woman I ever saw in my life.'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
The China Cupid
Frank had told me to forget the past. I wanted
to. But Frank did not sit in the morning room
every day as I did. He did not sit at Rebecca's
desk and touch the things she had touched.
Dear God, I did not want to think about
Rebecca. I wanted to be happy. I wanted
Maxim to be happy too. But Rebecca
was always in my thoughts and dreams.
Beatrice, Maxim's sister, had promised to give me
a wedding present. She did not forget. One day,
Robert brought a large parcel into the
morning-room where I was sitting alone.
I cut the string excitedly and tore off the
dark brown paper. Beatrice had sent me four
big books about painting. She knew that I enjoyed
sketching and she had really tried to please me.
I was glad to have something at Manderley that
belonged to me. I looked round the room for
somewhere to put the books. I stood them in
a row on top of the desk and looked at them.
But the books were far too heavy. First one
fell and then the others followed. A little
china ornament which always stood on the desk was
knocked on to the floor. The ornament broke into
many pieces. It was a beautiful little cupid
and one of the loveliest things in the house.
I was suddenly very frightened. I found an
envelope in a drawer and carefully put the
pieces of china into it. Then, like a
child, I hid the envelope in the desk.
I decided to put my new books in the
library and I said nothing about the cupid.
The following day, after lunch, Frith
brought our coffee to the library as usual.
Instead of leaving, he stood by Maxim's chair.
'Could I speak to you, sir?' he
said. Maxim looked up from his paper.
'Yes, Frith, what is it?'
'It's about Robert, sir. He's very upset. Mrs
Danvers has accused him of taking a valuable
ornament from the morning-room. Mrs Danvers
noticed it was missing late this morning.
She says that Robert must have taken it or broken
it. Robert says he knows nothing about it.'
'Perhaps it was one of the maids,' said Maxim.
I knew he hated any kind of
trouble with the servants.
'No, sir. No one except
Robert has been in the room,
apart from Madam, of course. Mrs Danvers
doesn't let the maids clean the morning-room.'
'Well, Mrs Danvers had better come
and see me. What ornament was it?'
'The china cupid, sir. It stands on the desk.'
'Oh dear,' said Maxim. 'That's very valuable.
It must be found. I'll see Mrs Danvers at once.'
'Very good, sir,' said Frith
and quietly left the room.
'Darling,' I said to Maxim when we were alone,
'I meant to tell you before, but I
forgot. I broke the cupid yesterday.'
'You broke it?
Why didn't you say so when Frith was here?
You'll have to explain to Mrs Danvers now.'
'Oh no. Please, Maxim, you
tell her. Let me go upstairs.'
'Don't be silly,' said Maxim angrily. 'Anyone
would think you were afraid of Mrs Danvers.'
'I am afraid of her. At least not afraid, but...'
The door opened without a sound
and Mrs Danvers came into the room.
I looked nervously at Maxim. His
face was half amused, half angry.
'It's all a mistake, Mrs Danvers,'
Maxim told her. 'Mrs de Winter broke the
cupid herself. She forgot to tell us.'
I felt like a child again.
'I'm so sorry,' I said, 'I never
thought Robert would get into trouble.'
'Is it possible to repair the cupid, Madam?'
said Mrs Danvers. She did not seem surprised.
I felt she had known the truth all the time.
'I'm afraid not,' I said.
'It's in hundreds of pieces.'
'What did you do with the pieces?' said Maxim.
They are in an envelope in a
drawer of the writing desk.'
'Find the pieces, Mrs Danvers.
Try to get them mended in London.'
'I never thought that Mrs de
Winter had broken the ornament,'
said Mrs Danvers. As she left the room I
could see the scorn and hatred in her eyes.
'I'm very sorry, darling,' I said. 'It
was very silly and careless of me.'
'Forget it,' said Maxim. 'But
you do act strangely sometimes.
More like a servant than
the mistress of Manderley.
Even when we have visitors, you sit on the edge
of your chair and say only "yes" and "no".'
'I can't help being shy.'
'I know you can't, darling.
But you must learn to hide it.'
'I do try. But I'm not used to this kind of life.
People look at me and ask me so many questions.'
'What does it matter? They are
interested in us, that's all.'
'They can't find me very interesting,' I
said. 'I suppose that's why you married
me. You knew I was dull and quiet.
No one would ever gossip about me.'
Maxim threw his paper on the
ground and got up from his chair.
His face was dark with anger
and his voice was hard.
'What do you know about any gossip down
here?' he said. 'Who's been talking to you?'
'No one. No one at all.'
Maxim stared at me.
'Perhaps I did a very selfish
thing when I married you,'
he said slowly. 'I am so much older than you.'
I felt cold and frightened.
'Age doesn't matter,' I said. 'I'm happy. You know
I love you more than anything else in the world.
I love Manderley too. I love everything
here. You're happy too, darling, aren't you?'
Maxim did not answer. He stood
staring out of the window.
'If you don't think we're happy, you must tell
me,' I went on. 'I don't want you to lie to me.'
Maxim took my face in his hands.
'How can I answer you?' he said. 'If
you are happy, then we are both happy.'
He kissed me and walked across the room.
'But you are disappointed in me. You
think I am not right for Manderley.
If only I hadn't broken that
cupid. Was it very valuable?'
'I think so,' Maxim answered. 'It was a wedding
present. Rebecca knew a lot about china.'
Maxim went on staring straight in front of him.
He is thinking about Rebecca, I said to myself.
I have broken one of their wedding presents.
Maxim went back to his chair and picked up his
paper. I sat on the long seat under the window.
After a time, Jasper came to
me and climbed on to my lap.
CHAPTER TWELVE
In the West Wing
Maxim had to go up to London at the end of June.
It was the first time that I had been left alone
at Manderley. I was sure that Maxim would
have a terrible accident or even be killed.
I was too worried to eat any lunch. At about two
o'clock, Robert brought me a message. Maxim had
arrived safely in London after a good journey.
I felt happy again and also rather hungry.
I went back into the dining-room
and took an apple and some biscuits.
Then I called Jasper and we
went together into the woods.
As I sat there I felt happier
than I had ever been at Manderley.
I could not understand it. I had not wanted Maxim
to go to London, but now I was glad to be alone.
I walked through the Happy Valley
to the bay. The sea was very calm.
Jasper ran up the rocks leading to the next bay.
'Not that way, Jasper,' I
called. The dog took no notice.
Oh well, it doesn't matter, I thought. Maxim isn't
here. And I climbed over the rocks after Jasper.
The tide was out and there was
very little water in the bay.
The white and green buoy was still
there. I could read the name on it now:
Je Reviens. A strange name for a boat - "I'll come
back". And that boat would never come back now.
I walked slowly across the beach to the cottage.
The sun was shining today and the cottage did
not look frightening any more. I pushed open
the door. Everything was exactly as before.
There was a sound in the boat-house and
Jasper ran up to the doorway, barking angrily.
'Is anybody there?' I said.
I looked through the door and saw Ben sitting
by the wall. He looked very frightened.
'I think you should come out,' I said. 'Mr de
Winter doesn't like people coming in here.'
Ben followed me out into the sunshine.
'I'm not doing anything wrong,' he
said. 'You won't lock me up, will you?'
His whole body was shaking with fear and
tears were rolling down his fat, round face.
'I didn't do anything. I
didn't tell anyone,' he said.
'That's all right, Ben. No one's going to hurt
you. But don't go into the cottage again.'
Ben smiled.
'You're not like the other one,' he said. 'She
was tall and dark. She had eyes like a snake.
She came here at night. She
saw me once, looking at her.
"You'll be locked up. People will hurt you,"
she said. But you won't lock me up, will you?'
'No, of course not, Ben,' I said.
Ben smiled again and went off
down the beach to the sea.
I went up towards the wood. Jasper followed me.
When I looked back, Ben had gone. But I had a
strange feeling that someone was watching me.
Someone tall and dark, who watched and listened.
I started to run up the path and did not feel safe
until I reached the lawn. The house stood there,
safe and secure. The sun shone on something metal
in the drive. A green sports car was parked there.
I had never seen it before and I hoped
the visitor did not want to stay to tea.
As I walked across the lawn, I looked up at the
west wing. One of the shutters was open and a
man stood at the window. Then another figure,
dressed in black, closed the shutter. I was sure
it was Mrs Danvers. But who was the man? And
why had he come when Maxim was away in London?
I walked up the steps, through the
hall and into the morning-room.
I could smell cigarette smoke. Then I heard voices
and, without thinking, I hid behind the door.
I heard Mrs Danvers say, 'I expect she went
into the library. Wait here while I go and see.'
She was talking about me of course.
I did not know what to do. Jasper had moved
towards the drawing-room, wagging his tail.
'Hallo, Jasper, old boy,' said a man's voice
and Jasper ran back into the morning-room.
The man followed. He saw me standing behind the
door. I have never seen anyone more surprised.
'I beg your pardon,' the man said, looking down at
me with a rather unpleasant smile. He was a big,
handsome man, but his face was red and his eyes
were a hard blue. His breath smelt of whisky.
'I'm so sorry,' he said. 'I called to
see Danny. She's an old friend of mine.'
He lit a cigarette and looked round the room.
'How's old Max?' he asked.
'Maxim's very well, he's in London,' I said.
'What? He's left you all alone? That's not
fair, is it?' The man gave an unpleasant laugh.
I did not like him at all.
At that moment, Mrs Danvers came
back. She looked at me angrily.
'Well, Danny,' the man said, 'aren't you
going to introduce me to the new bride?'
'This is Mr Favell, Madam,' said Mrs Danvers.
'How do you do?' I said
politely. 'Will you stay to tea?'
The man laughed again.
'Now isn't that kind, Danny,' he
said. 'But I had better be going.
Come and look at my car,' he said to me. 'It's
a good car. Much faster than the one Max has.'
I did not like the way that Favell spoke about
Maxim. I did not want to look at his car.
But I followed him out into the hall.
'Goodbye, Danny. Take care of yourself.
You know my telephone number.'
'Dear old Manderley,' Favell said
as we walked out of the house.
'What do you think of it?
Aren't you lonely living here?'
'I'm very fond of Manderley,' I said.
'I have enjoyed meeting you,'
Favell said, standing by his car.
'But I'd rather you didn't
tell Max about my visit.
I'm afraid your husband doesn't like me very
much. He might be cross with poor old Danny.'
'No, all right,' I said awkwardly.
'I won't say anything to Maxim.'
He got into the car and started the engine.
'That's very kind,' he said. 'Perhaps I'll
come back and see you one day. Goodbye.'
Favell drove away noisily and much too fast. I
walked slowly back to the house. Mrs Danvers had
gone. I wondered who Favell was. He had certainly
been to Manderley before. And, like Rebecca,
he called Maxim 'Max'. Had Favell known Rebecca?
What had he been doing in the west wing?
There were some very valuable things in
the house. Perhaps the man was a thief.
I decided to go up to the west wing. I must see
that everything was all right. The house seemed
very quiet as I began to walk up the stairs.
My heart was beating in a strange, excited way.
I was again in the corridor where I had stood on
my first morning at Manderley. I turned the handle
of the nearest door and went inside. Everything
was dark. I found the light and switched it on.
I was surprised to see that the room was
completely furnished. There was no dust
and everything was clean and tidy. The room, a
bedroom, was the most beautiful I had ever seen.
There were flowers on the dressing
table and on the table beside the bed.
A satin dressing-gown lay on a chair.
There was a pair of slippers under a chair.
I walked slowly into the middle of the room. No,
it was not used. It was not lived in any more.
The air was not fresh. Rebecca would
never come back to this room again.
I could hear the sea clearly. I went
to the window and opened a shutter.
Yes, I was standing at the window where
I had seen Mrs Danvers and Favell.
I felt afraid and my legs began to tremble. I
sat down on the stool by the dressing-table.
I looked round the room, the most beautiful
in Manderley. A room that was never used now.
I got up and went to the chair. I
touched the satin dressing-gown.
I picked up the slippers and held them in my hand.
On the bed lay Rebecca's
nightdress. I went to the bed
and held the nightdress to my face. It was cold
and smelt of the flowers in the Happy Valley.
As I stood looking down at the
bed, I heard a step behind me.
I turned quickly. It was Mrs Danvers.
I shall never forget the look on her face. It
was a look of strange, terrible excitement.
She came nearer and I could
feel her breath on my face.
'Is there anything the matter, Madam? Are you
feeling unwell?' Mrs Danvers said quietly.
'I did not expect to see you here, Mrs Danvers.
I came up to fasten one of the shutters.'
'I will fasten it,' Mrs Danvers said.
Mrs Danvers came back from the
window and stood beside me.
'You opened the shutter yourself, didn't you?' she
said. 'You wanted to see this room, didn't you?
Now you are here, let me show you everything.'
Her voice now was as soft and sweet as honey.
'It's a lovely room, isn't it? That was her bed.
I keep it just as it was. This was her nightdress.
She was wearing it the night before
she died. These are her slippers.'
Mrs Danvers put the slippers back under the chair
and walked across the room to a large wardrobe.
'All her evening clothes are here. Her furs,
too. Mr de Winter was always buying
clothes for her, beautiful clothes.'
Mrs Danvers held my arm tightly with her long
thin fingers. Her eyes looked deep into mine.
'I blame myself for the accident,' she said.
'I was out that evening. When I came in,
I heard she had gone down to the bay. I
was worried. The wind was blowing hard.
Mr de Winter came in at about eleven. The wind was
blowing harder, and still she had not come back.
'I sat on my bed until after five. Then I
put on my coat and went down to the bay.
I saw at once that the boat had gone.'
Mrs Danvers' hand fell back to her side.
'That is why Mr de Winter doesn't use
these rooms any more. Listen to the sea.'
Even with the shutters and windows closed, I could
hear the dull, harsh sound of the sea in the bay.
'I come into these room and dust
them every day,' Mrs Danvers said.
'If you want to come again, ask
me. No one comes here but me.
'Sometimes I feel she is standing here, behind me.
I feel her everywhere. In the morning-room
and in the hall. You feel her too, don't you?'
I tried to smile, but I felt sick and ill.
'Do you think she can see us
now?' Mrs Danvers asked me. 'Do you
think the dead watch the living?'
'I don't know,' I said. 'I don't know.'
'Sometimes I think she watches you and Mr
de Winter together,' Mrs Danvers whispered.
We stood there by the door, staring at one
another. I could not take my eyes away from hers.
Then I turned and walked into the corridor. I went
down the stairs and through the door to the east
wing. I pushed open the door to my own bedroom.
I shut the door of the room and locked it.
Then I lay down on my bed and closed
my eyes. I felt terribly sick.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
More About Jack Favell
Maxim rang up the next morning. I heard
the phone ring while I was having breakfast
and Frith answered it. I hoped that
Maxim would ask for me but he did not.
'Mr de Winter will be back at about
six this evening,' Frith told me.
'All right, Frith. Thank you,' I said.
I went on eating breakfast as slowly as I could.
Jasper was sitting at my feet. I wondered what
I should do all day. I had slept badly. I
could not forget my visit to the west wing.
I knew now how much Mrs Danvers hated me.
About ten o'clock, the telephone rang
again. This time it was Beatrice.
'Well, my dear, how are you?' she said.
'Shall I come and have lunch with you today?'
'I'd like you to come very
much, Beatrice,' I said.
'All right, my dear. See you later.'
I put the phone down. I was glad that Beatrice was
coming. It gave me something to look forward to. I
wandered out on to the lawn. I felt different
from yesterday. I wanted Maxim to come home.
I tried not to remember my visit to the west wing.
But I could not stop thinking about Favell and his
friendship with Mrs Danvers. I began to feel that
Mrs Danvers was watching me. There were so many
rooms that Maxim and I never used. It was easy for
Mrs Danvers to watch me from one of their windows.
Beatrice arrived by car at about half past twelve.
This time I went out to the drive to meet her.
'Well, my dear, here I am,' she
said. 'It's a lovely day, isn't it?'
She gave me a kiss and then
looked at me carefully.
'You don't look well,' Beatrice said.
'You are much too thin. Your face is pale,
too. What's wrong with you?'
'Nothing,' I said. 'My face is always pale.'
'You looked quite different
when I saw you before,'
Beatrice told me. 'You are not
going to have a baby, are you?'
'No, I don't think so,' I said.
'Well, I hope you will sometime.
Maxim would be so happy to have a son.
What have you been doing with
yourself? Have you done much sketching?
Did you like the books I sent
you? Have you had anyone to stay?'
I had forgotten that Beatrice
asked so many questions.
'No, we've had no one to stay. People
come to tea sometimes, of course.'
I wondered whether to tell Beatrice about
Mrs Danvers' visitor, Favell. I did not want
Beatrice to tell Maxim about the visit. But
I did want to find out more about the man.
'Have you ever heard of a man called
Jack Favell, Beatrice?' I asked her.
'Jack Favell?' said Beatrice slowly. 'Yes, I do
know the name. Wait a minute - Jack Favell. Yes,
of course. I remember him now. He's an
awful man. I met him once, years ago.'
'He was here yesterday,' I told
her. 'He came to see Mrs Danvers.'
Beatrice did not look at me.
'Oh well,' she said, 'I suppose
he knows Mrs Danvers quite well.'
'But why?' I asked.
'Jack Favell is Rebecca's cousin,'
Beatrice said. 'I think he came to Manderley
quite a lot when Rebecca was alive. I'm not sure.'
'I did not like him,' I said.
'No, I don't suppose that
you did,' Beatrice answered.
I hoped that she would tell me more about Favell,
but she did not. For the rest of the
time we talked about other things.
Beatrice stayed for tea and left soon afterwards.
She had promised to meet her
husband, Giles, at the station.
'I hope you won't be so thin next time I see
you,' Beatrice said as she got into her car.
'Give Maxim my love. Look after
him, and look after yourself, too.'
I watched Beatrice's car go down the drive.
Maxim would not be back for another hour.
I did not feel like sitting
in the house by myself.
I called Jasper and we went for a walk through
the woods. But I did not go near the sea.
I missed Maxim now and felt lonely without him.
Beatrice's questions had made me feel tired too.
When I came back from my walk, I saw
Maxim's car standing in front of the house.
At once, I felt much happier. I ran
quickly up the steps and into the hall.
As I walked towards the library,
I heard the sound of voices.
One voice was Maxim's, very loud and angry. The
door was shut, but I could hear what he said.
'You can tell Favell to keep away from
Manderley. Tell him I said so,' Maxim was saying.
'I know he was here. Never mind who told
me. His car was seen here yesterday.
If you want to meet him, meet him somewhere
else. I don't want that man at Manderley.
I won't even have him in the gardens.
I'm telling you for the last time.'
I heard footsteps. I ran quickly
up the stairs and hid myself.
Mrs Danvers came out of the library. She
shut the door and walked up the stairs.
Her face was grey with anger and
the look in her eyes frightened me.
Thank God she did not know I was watching her. Mrs
Danvers went through the door to the west wing.
I waited a moment and then went
downstairs and into the library.
Maxim was standing by the window. When he
heard the door open, he turned round quickly.
I smiled and held out my hand to him.
'Oh, it's you,' Maxim said.
I could tell that he was very angry. His face was
white and his mouth hard. I took his hand in mine.
'I missed you so much,' I said.
'I hate being here without you.'
'Do you?' Maxim said. He did not say
anything about Mrs Danvers or Favell.
'Are you worried about something?' I asked.
'I've had a long day,' Maxim answered.
'And London was very hot and noisy.
I always hate going there.'
Maxim lit a cigarette and moved away from me. I
knew then that he was not going to tell me about
his anger with Mrs Danvers. Maxim still thought
of me as a child - someone who must not hear
unpleasant things. But he was wrong. I felt
I was growing up a little more every day.
My life at Manderley was
turning me into a woman.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Preparations for the Ball
It was on a Sunday afternoon when someone
spoke about the Fancy Dress Ball again.
Frank Crawley had come to lunch and the three
of us were hoping to have a quiet afternoon.
But as we were walking out to the big tree on
the lawn, we heard a car in the drive. We had
to go back into the house to welcome the visitors.
Very soon, more people arrived and then some more.
They all stayed to tea, of course. As we sat
in the drawing-room eating cake and sandwiches,
one of our visitors suddenly
said to Maxim, 'Oh, Mr de Winter.
There is something I must ask you. Are you having
a Fancy Dress Ball at Manderley this year?'
Maxim answered quietly.
'I haven't thought about it,' he said. 'And
I don't think anyone else has, either.'
'Oh, but you are wrong,' said another
woman. 'We have all been thinking about it.
We used to enjoy the Manderley Ball so much.'
'Well, I don't know,' said Maxim.
'There would be a great deal to do.
You had better ask Frank Crawley.
He would do most of the work.'
'I don't mind the work,' said Frank, looking at
me. 'It's for Maxim and Mrs de Winter to decide.'
Everyone looked at me and started to talk at once.
'Now, Mrs de Winter, you must help
us. Your husband will listen to you.
After all, you are a new bride.
The Ball will be for you.'
'Yes, of course,' said a man, 'we all missed your
wedding. There ought to be some
kind of party here at Manderley.'
Everyone laughed and clapped their hands.
Maxim looked at me.
'What about you? Would you like it?' he said.
I did not know what Maxim was thinking. Perhaps
he thought I was too shy to want the Ball.
'I think I rather like the
idea,' I said with a smile.
Maxim turned away.
'All right, then, Frank. We'll have
the dance. Mrs Danvers can help you.
She will know what to do. Now, if we've all
finished tea, we'll go into the garden.'
We all went outside. Our visitors were talking
happily now about their costumes for the Ball.
I felt excited too.
'What will you wear?' I said to Maxim.
'I never wear fancy dress,' Maxim replied.
'I'm the host, so I can do as I like.'
'What shall I wear?' I
said. 'I've no idea at all.'
Maxim smiled at me.
'If you look pretty, I don't mind
what you put on,' he told me.
'All right,' I said. 'My costume will be
a secret. I shall keep it as a surprise.'
Maxim laughed and patted me on the shoulder.
As usual, he was treating me like a child.
I did not want to be a child. I
wanted to be a grown-up woman.
I shall wear a beautiful dress
at the Ball, I told myself.
Everyone will say how charming I am. They will
think of me as the real Mrs de Winter at last.
Maxim will love me as his
wife and forget about Rebecca.
Soon everyone at Manderley was
talking about the Fancy Dress Ball.
My little maid, Clarice, spoke of nothing else.
'Oh, Madam, it's so exciting,' she said.
'I'm looking forward to it so much.'
The preparations went on. Frank was
very busy and so was Mrs Danvers.
I saw very little of her, and I was glad.
I began to get worried about my
costume. I did not know what to wear.
I looked through the books that Beatrice had
given me. I made sketches of some of the costumes,
but I did not like any of them. I wanted
something that was pretty and simple too.
That evening, as I was getting ready for
dinner, there was a knock at my bedroom door.
To my surprise, it was Mrs Danvers. She
was holding a piece of paper in her hand.
It was a drawing of a costume which
I had sketched and then thrown away.
'I found this, Madam,' Mrs Danvers said. 'I
thought you had thrown it away by mistake.'
'No, Mrs Danvers, I don't want
it, thank you,' I said quickly.
I hoped she would go, but she stood at the door.
'So you haven't decided what to wear,
Madam,' Mrs Danvers said in a friendly voice.
'No, I haven't decided yet,' I replied.
'Perhaps you could copy one of the pictures
in the gallery,' Mrs Danvers suggested.
'Many of them would make beautiful
costumes. What does Mr de Winter think?'
'I don't know,' I said. 'I wanted to surprise
him. I was going to keep my costume a secret.'
Mrs Danvers looked pleased at my words.
'Then I suggest that you have your
costume made in London, Madam.
There is a shop in Bond Street that would
do it really well. I have always liked
the picture of the girl in white,' Mrs
Danvers went on in the same friendly way.
'The picture is about two hundred years
old. The girl's wearing a very simple dress.
It would be easy to copy.'
I did not know what to say. I knew the picture
well. I wished I had thought of the idea myself.
'Thank you, Mrs Danvers,' I said.
Mrs Danvers went out quietly. I
wondered why she was so friendly.
Perhaps Maxim's anger had frightened her a little.
As I went down to dinner, I stopped in
front of the picture of the young girl.
Her name was Caroline de Winter and she had been
famous for her beauty. The dress was very simple,
with short sleeves and a long, full skirt. Her
hair was in curls. I would have to wear a wig
over my own straight hair. I felt very excited.
I was glad that I had chosen my costume at last.
I said nothing to Maxim. The next
day I made a sketch of the picture.
Then I sent the drawing to the shop in London with
careful instructions about the dress and the wig.
The preparations for the great day went
on. No one expected me to do anything.
Slowly, the great house began to change.
Furniture was moved as the great hall was
prepared for dancing. Coloured lights were hung in
the trees outside. There were flowers everywhere.
Hundreds of them were brought in from the garden
and Mrs Danvers knew exactly how to arrange them.
Manderley took on a new beauty. I had never
seen the old house looking so lovely.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Miss Caroline de Winter
On the day of the Ball, Maxim
and I had lunch with Frank.
My dress and the wig had arrived and they
both looked perfect. Maxim and Frank asked
me about my costume but I told them nothing.
The secret made me feel excited and important.
'You won't know it's me,' I told them. 'You
will both have the surprise of your lives.'
Maxim and I went back to the house after lunch.
The band had arrived and we welcomed the men.
The afternoon seemed very long.
I thought about going for a walk.
Then suddenly, it was tea-time and Beatrice
and her husband, Giles, had arrived.
'This is like old times,' said Beatrice, looking
around. 'Everything is as beautiful as ever.
What's everyone going to wear? I suppose
you refuse to wear fancy dress, Maxim?'
'Of course,' Maxim said. 'I
prefer to be comfortable.'
'I'm going to dress as an Arab,' said
Giles. 'I got the idea from a friend.'
'What about you, Mrs Lacy?'
Frank said to Beatrice.
'I'm in Eastern dress, too. I'm
wearing a veil and lots of jewellery.
I'll be cool and comfortable.
That's all that matters.'
Beatrice turned to me.
'And what is our hostess going to wear?'
she asked. 'The Ball is for you, after all.
We all expect you to wear
something really special.'
'Don't ask her,' said Maxim. 'She won't tell
anyone. She's had the dress made in London.'
'It's quite simple really,' I said.
'What fun it all is,' said Beatrice.
'I'm getting excited already.'
'You've got her to thank for
it,' said Maxim, smiling at me.
Everyone looked at me and
smiled. I felt pleased and happy.
This Ball was for me because I was
a bride, the new Mrs de Winter.
Manderley had been made into a place
of light and beauty, just for me.
'What's the time?' I said. 'I think
we ought to be getting ready.'
I found Clarice waiting for me in my bedroom,
her face full of excitement. I locked the door
and took the dress from its box. It fitted
perfectly. I looked at myself in the mirror.
I smiled. I felt different already. I was someone
more exciting and interesting than my usual self.
'Give me the wig, Clarice,' I said. 'Be
careful, the curls mustn't be flat.'
I brushed back my own straight hair.
Carefully, I put the wig in place.
I looked in the mirror again. The wig and the
tightly fitting dress made me almost beautiful.
'Oh, Clarice,' I said. 'What
will Mr de Winter say?'
There was a knock on the door.
'Who's there?' I called. 'You can't come in.'
'It's me, my dear,' said Beatrice. 'Are
you ready? I want to have a look at you.'
'No, no,' I said, 'you can't come in. Tell Maxim
that he can't come in either.
I'll come down when I'm ready.'
I looked in the mirror
again. My eyes looked larger
and the curls made a soft cloud round my head.
I lifted the skirt of the dress in my hands.
'Unlock the door,' I said to
Clarice. 'I'm going down.'
I stood in the gallery and
looked down on the hall below.
There was Giles in his white Arab costume.
Beatrice was wearing a long green dress.
Frank was dressed as a sailor. Only
Maxim was wearing evening clothes.
'I don't know what she's
doing,' I heard Maxim say.
'What's the time, Frank? She must be down soon.'
I looked up at the picture of Caroline
de Winter. Yes, her dress was exactly
like mine and she had the same curled hair.
The band was playing softly in the gallery.
'Beat the drum,' I said, 'and call
out: Miss Caroline de Winter.'
The drum sounded. Everyone looked up.
'Miss Caroline de Winter,' the man shouted.
I stood at the top of the stairs, smiling.
I expected everyone to laugh and
clap as I walked down the stairs.
Nobody laughed. Nobody clapped. They all
stared at me without moving. I smiled at Maxim.
'How do you do, Mr de Winter?' I said.
Maxim stared up at me. His
face was completely white.
Something was wrong. Why was Maxim looking
like that? He moved towards the stairs.
'What the hell do you think
you're doing?' he said.
His eyes were on fire with anger.
'It's the picture,' I said.
'The one in the gallery.'
There was a long silence. Still nobody moved.
'What is it?' I said. 'What have I done?'
When Maxim answered, his voice was cold and
hard. 'Go and take off that dress! It doesn't
matter what you wear. Any evening dress
will do. Go quickly, before anyone comes.'
I could not speak. I stood staring at Maxim.
'What are you standing there for?' he
asked me. 'Didn't you hear what I said?'
I turned and ran up the stairs.
My eyes were full of tears.
I did not know what I was doing.
The door to the west wing was open.
Mrs Danvers was standing there. I shall
never forget the terrible look on her face.
It was a look of joy - of joy and the most
terrible hate. She stood there, smiling at me.
Then I ran from her, back to my room, tripping
and nearly falling over my long skirt.
Clarice was waiting for me in my
bedroom. She had heard what had happened.
When she saw my face, Clarice started to cry.
'It doesn't matter, Clarice,' I said.
'Help me take off this dress. Quickly.'
'What will you wear, Madam?' Clarice asked
me. 'I don't know,' I said. 'Leave me alone
now. I'll be all right. Go down and enjoy the
party. Don't tell anyone what has happened.'
After Clarice had gone, someone knocked at
the door. It opened and Beatrice came in.
'My dear,' she said, 'are you all right?' I
put a hand up to my head and took off the wig.
'Of course I knew at once that it was a mistake,'
Beatrice said. 'You could not have known.'
'Known what?' I said, turning to look at her.
'Why, about your costume. It was exactly what
Rebecca wore at the last Fancy Dress Ball here.
As you stood on the stairs, I
thought for one terrible moment...'
'I ought to have known,' I said.
I was thinking of Mrs Danvers. She had
planned this. She had known what would happen.
'How could you know?' said Beatrice.
'But it was a terrible shock to Maxim.
He thinks that you did it as a joke. He thinks
that is why you kept your dress a secret. But he
will understand when you speak to him. I'm going
to tell everyone that your dress didn't fit.'
I did not say anything.
'Now, what can you wear?' Beatrice said. 'Here,
this blue dress is very pretty. Put this on.'
'No,' I said. 'I'm not going down.'
Beatrice stared at me before she spoke.
'But, my dear, you must. It will look so strange.'
I felt very tired.
'What does it matter?' I said.
Beatrice looked shocked at my words.
'Think of Maxim. You must
come down for him,' she said.
'I can't, I can't,' I answered.
Beatrice stared at me.
'I must go down now,' she said at last.
'They will be waiting for me at dinner.
I'll tell Maxim you'll be
down in a minute, shall I?'
I did not answer and Beatrice walked
slowly to the door and went out.
After a long time I got up from
the bed where I was sitting.
I walked across to the window. I could
see the coloured lights in the trees.
I walked back to the dressing-table and looked
at my white face and red eyes in the mirror.
Then slowly I washed my face and combed my hair. I
put the white dress and the wig back into the box.
I never wanted to see them again. I
picked up the blue dress and put it on.
When I was ready, I opened the
door and walked along the corridor.
Everything was still and quiet.
Then I heard the sound of voices.
The door of the dining-room was open. The guests
were coming out of dinner. Someone laughed.
I walked slowly down the stairs to meet them.
I remember very little of the first party
at Manderley. It was the first and the last
we ever held there. I remember that Frank
tried to make me drink a little champagne.
I remember Beatrice smiling at
me. I remember dancing with Giles.
The band played and people danced.
I stood there smiling at everyone.
Maxim stood beside me. His eyes were cold and
hard, not the eyes of the man I knew and loved.
All through that long night,
Maxim never looked at me.
Once, Beatrice came up to me and said, 'Why
don't you sit down? You look like death.'
What was the time? I did not know.
The night passed, hour after hour.
Then at last Giles came up to me and said,
'Come and look at the fireworks on the terrace.'
I remember standing on the terrace and staring
up at the sky. The fireworks rose into the sky
and turned into stars and flowers. The sky
was red and gold. Every window of the house
was coloured by the falling lights. The grey
walls of Manderley looked heavy and dark.
Then suddenly, the sky was dark too. The
fireworks were over. I heard the sound of cars
starting in the drive. 'They're beginning to go,'
I thought. 'Thank God, they're beginning to go.'
People came up to me to say goodbye.
'Such a wonderful party,' they said. 'Thank you so
much for a wonderful evening. The best
party I've been to for a long time.'
I shook hands with them all. I smiled.
'I'm so glad, so glad,' I said.
I could think of no other words.
Maxim had gone with Frank to stand
in the drive. Beatrice Came up to me.
'Well done, my dear,' she said. 'The Ball was
a great success. No one had any idea about...
you know. You must go to bed now. You look
very tired. Have your breakfast in bed.'
'Yes. Yes, perhaps I shall,' I said.
'I'll tell Maxim you've gone up to bed, shall I?'
'Yes, please, Beatrice.'
'All right, my dear. Sleep well.'
I walked slowly into the house. The lights
had been turned off. The rooms were empty.
I went up the stairs and along the corridor
to my room. It was almost light now and a bird
had started to sing. I undressed slowly and
got into bed. I lay back and closed my eyes.
My body was tired, but my mind would not rest.
I wondered how long Maxim would be. The little
clock by my bed ticked away the minutes.
I lay on my side, watching it. An hour
went by. But Maxim did not come.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
'Why Don't You Jump?'
I fell asleep at about seven o'clock.
When I woke up again, it was after eleven.
Clarice had brought me some tea.
It was cold now, but I drank it.
Maxim's bed was empty. He had not come to bed at
all. I sat up, looking straight in front of me.
My marriage was a failure. It had failed after
only three months. I was too young for Maxim,
I knew too little about the world. The fact
that I loved him made no difference. It was
not the sort of love he needed. Maxim was
not in love with me. He had never loved me.
He did not belong to me, he belonged to
Rebecca. Rebecca was the real Mrs de Winter.
I could never be the mistress of Manderley.
Wherever I walked, wherever I sat,
I saw Rebecca. I knew her well. I knew her tall,
slim figure, her small face and clear white skin.
If I ever heard her voice, I would know it.
Rebecca - always Rebecca. I would never escape
from Rebecca. She was too strong for me.
I got out of bed and opened the
curtains. Sunlight filled the room.
I could not hide in my bedroom any longer.
I had a bath, dressed and went downstairs.
The servants had been very busy. The rooms
were clean and tidy. The flowers had gone.
Soon there would be nothing to
remind us of the Fancy Dress Ball.
I met Robert in the dining-room.
'Good morning, Robert,' I said. 'Have
you seen Mr de Winter anywhere?'
'He went out soon after breakfast,
Madam. He has not been in since.'
I went into the small room behind the
library and picked up the telephone.
Perhaps Maxim was with Frank. I had to talk
to Maxim. I had to explain about last night.
'Frank, it's me,' I said when
he answered. 'Where's Maxim?'
'I don't know. I haven't seen him,' Frank said.
'How did he sleep? How was he at breakfast?'
'Frank,' I said slowly, 'Maxim
did not come to bed last night.'
There was silence.
'I was afraid something like that
would happen,' Frank said at last.
'Where do you think he's gone?'
I asked. 'I must see him.
I've got to explain about last night.
Maxim thinks I did it as a joke.'
I could not stop my tears now. They
poured down my face as I spoke.
'You mustn't talk like that,' Frank
said. 'Let me come up and see you.'
'No,' I said. 'It has happened.
Nothing can be changed now.
Perhaps that's a good thing. I
understand things more clearly now.'
'What do you mean?' said Frank, quickly.
'Maxim doesn't love me, he loves Rebecca,' I said.
'He's never forgotten her. He's never loved me,
Frank. It's always Rebecca, Rebecca, Rebecca.'
I heard Frank cry out.
'I've got to come and see you,' he said.
I put down the telephone stood up. I did
not want to see Frank. He could not help me.
No one could help me, but myself.
Perhaps I would never see Maxim again. Perhaps
Maxim had left me and would never come back.
I could not get these thoughts out of my mind.
I went to the window and looked
out. A fog had come up from the sea.
I could not see the woods. It was very hot,
but the sun was hidden behind the wall of fog.
I could hear the sea and I
could smell it in the fog.
I walked out of the house and on to the lawn. I
looked back at the house. One of the shutters in
the west wing had been pulled back. Someone was
standing there, looking down at me. For a moment,
I thought that it was Maxim. Then the figure
moved and I saw that it was Mrs Danvers.
I felt that she knew about my tears.
She had planned all this to happen.
This was her triumph - hers and Rebecca's.
I remembered Mrs Danvers smiling at me, like a
devil. But she was a living woman like myself.
She was not dead, like Rebecca. I could not speak
to Rebecca, but I could speak to Mrs Danvers.
I walked back across the lawn. I went through
the house, along the dark silent corridor of
the west wing to Rebecca's room. I turned
the handle of the door and went inside.
Mrs Danvers was still standing by the window.
The shutter was folded back. She turned to me
and I saw that her eyes were red with crying.
There were dark shadows on her white face.
'You've done what you
wanted, Mrs Danvers,' I said.
'You wanted this to happen, didn't you?
Are you pleased now? Are you happy?'
She turned her head away from me.
'Why did you ever come to Manderley?' she said.
'Nobody wanted you. We were
all right until you came.'
'You seem to forget that I
love Mr de Winter,' I said.
'If you loved him, you would never
have married him,' Mrs Danvers said.
'Why do you hate me?' I asked.
'What have I done to you?'
'You tried to take Mrs de
Winter's place,' she said.
'But I changed nothing here. I left everything
to you. I wanted to be friends with you,' I said.
She did not answer.
'Many people marry twice,' I said. 'My
marriage to Mr de Winter isn't a crime.
Haven't we a right to be happy?'
'Mr de Winter is not happy,' Mrs
Danvers said, looking at me at last.
'Look into his eyes. He's in hell. He has
looked like that ever since she died.'
'It's not true,' I said. 'It's not true. He
was happy when we were in Italy together.'
'Well, he's a man, isn't he?' she said with a hard
laugh. 'Every man likes to enjoy his honeymoon.'
I was suddenly very angry and not
afraid of Mrs Danvers any more.
I went up to her and shook her by the arm.
'How dare you speak to me like that? How dare
you? You made me wear that dress last night. You
wanted to hurt Mr de Winter. Do you think his pain
and unhappiness will bring Mrs de Winter back?'
Mrs Danvers moved away from me.
'What do I care for his pain?' she said.
'He's never cared about mine. How do you
think I've felt, watching you sit in
her place, using the things she used?
I hear the servants calling you Mrs de Winter.
And all the time, the real Mrs de Winter,
with her smile and her lovely face is
lying cold and dead in the church.'
Mrs Danvers' face was twisted with
pain. Her voice was loud and hard.
'Mr de Winter deserves his pain, marrying a
young girl like you - and only ten months
afterwards. Well, he's paying for it now.
He knows she is watching him. My
lady comes at night and watches him.
'I looked after her when she
was a child. Did you know that?'
'No,' I said, 'no. What's the use of this,
Mrs Danvers? I don't want to hear any more.'
Mrs Danvers did not seem to hear me. She
went on speaking in a high, harsh voice.
'Mrs de Winter was a lovely child,' she
said. 'When she was only twelve years old,
the men could not stop looking at her. But
even then, she cared for nothing and nobody.
And that's how she was when she grew up. She
was beaten in the end. But it wasn't a man.
It wasn't a woman. The sea got her. The
sea was too strong for her in the end.'
Mrs Danvers began to cry noisily,
with her mouth open and her eyes dry.
'Mrs Danvers, you're not well.
You ought to be in bed,' I said.
She looked at me angrily.
'Leave me alone. Why shouldn't
I cry? What's it to do with you?
You came here and thought you
could take Mrs de Winter's place.
You! Why, even the servants laughed
at you when you came to Manderley.'
'You'd better stop this, Mrs Danvers,'
I said. 'You'd better go to your room.'
'Yes. And then what will you do? You'll
go to Mr de Winter and tell him that Mrs
Danvers has been unkind to you. You'll go to
him like you did when Mr Favell came here.
'Mr de Winter was jealous of
Mr Favell when she was alive.
He's jealous now. That shows you
he's not forgotten her, doesn't it?
Of course Mr de Winter was jealous. She didn't
care. She only laughed. All the men fell in
love with her, Mr de Winter, Mr Favell,
Mr Crawley. It was like a game to her.'
'I don't want to know,' I
said. 'I don't want to know.'
Mrs Danvers came close to me
and put her face near to mine.
'It's no use, is it?' she said. 'She's
the real Mrs de Winter, not you.'
I backed away from her, towards the
window. She took my hand and held it.
'Why don't you go?' she said again.
'He doesn't want you, he never did.
He can't forget her. He wants to be
alone in the house again, with her.'
She pushed me towards the open window. I
could see the stones of the terrace below.
Beyond the terrace was a white wall of fog.
'Look down there,' Mrs Danvers said.
'It's easy, isn't it? Why don't you
jump? It wouldn't hurt. It's not like drowning.
Why don't you try it? Why don't you go?'
The fog came in through the
open window, damp and thick.
I held on to the window ledge with both hands.
'Don't be afraid,' said Mrs
Danvers. 'I won't push you.
You can jump. You're not happy. Mr de Winter
doesn't love you. Why don't you jump now?'
The fog was thicker than before.
There was fog below and all around me.
If I jumped now, I would not see the stones.
The fall would kill me. Maxim did not love me.
'Go on,' whispered Mrs Danvers.
'Go on, don't be afraid.'
I shut my eyes. My fingers
ached from holding the ledge.
The thick fog made me forget my unhappiness.
I could forget about loving Maxim. I could
forget about Rebecca. I would not have
to think about Rebecca any more...
A loud explosion shook the window where we
stood. The glass cracked. I opened my eyes
and stared at Mrs Danvers. The first explosion was
followed by another, then a third and a fourth.
'What is it?' I said. 'What has happened?'
Mrs Danvers let go my arm. She stared
out of the window into the fog.
'It's the rockets,' she said. 'There
must be a ship in trouble in the bay.'
We listened, staring into the white fog together.
And then we heard the sound of
footsteps on the terrace below us.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Rebecca Has Won
It was Maxim down on the terrace. I could
not see him, but I could hear his voice.
I heard Frith answer from the hall.
'A ship's hit the rocks in the bay,' Maxim
called out. 'The fog is terrible out there.
Tell Mrs Danvers to have food
and drink ready for the men.
I'm going back to the bay to
see if I can do anything.'
Mrs Danvers moved back from the window.
'We had better go down,'
she said in her usual voice.
'Frith will be looking for me. Be careful of
your hands. I am going to close the window.'
Then she went to the door and held it open for me.
'When you see Mr de Winter, Madam,
please tell him there will be a hot
meal ready for the men at any time.'
I stared at her.
'Yes,' I said. 'Yes, Mrs Danvers.'
She turned her back on me and went along the
corridor. I walked slowly out of the room. I
felt as though I had just woken up from a long
sleep. When I reached the hall, I saw Frith.
'Did you hear the rockets, Madam?' he
said. 'Mr de Winter's gone down to the bay.
He went across the lawn only a few minutes ago.'
I went out on to the terrace. The
fog was beginning to clear and I
could see the woods again. I looked up
at the window above my head. It looked
very high. I suddenly felt very hot.
My head ached and my hands were wet.
I stood very still. Then for the first time I
realized that Maxim had not gone away. I had heard
his voice and he was down there in the bay. Maxim
was safe. Nothing else mattered if Maxim was safe.
I began to walk along the path through
the woods. The fog had almost gone now.
When I came to the bay, I could see the
ship at once. She was on the rocks about
two miles from the shore. There
were some small boats near her.
I climbed up the path to the cliffs above the bay.
Frank was there talking to a
coast-guard, but I could not see Maxim.
'They're going to send a diver down soon,
Mrs de Winter,' said the coastguard.
'They want to see if they can
get the ship off the rocks.'
'Have you seen Maxim?' I asked Frank.
'He's taken one of the sailors to hospital,' Frank
told me. 'The man was hurt. Maxim is always a
great help at times like this. What are you going
to do? Can I walk back with you to the house?'
'I think I'll stay here. I want
to see the diver go down,' I said.
'Very well,' Frank said. 'I shall
be at the office if you want me.'
The coastguard looked at his watch.
'Well, I must be getting along
too,' he said. 'Good afternoon.'
The sea was calm now. The diver went down and came
up again. Nothing else happened. It was very hot.
I sat on the cliffs for a long time
doing nothing, thinking of nothing.
When I looked at my watch again, it was three
o'clock. I got up and walked down the hill to
the bay. When I came to the other side,
I saw Ben. He stood there, smiling at me.
'Seen the big ship?' he said.
'Yes,' I said. 'She's on the rocks, isn't she?'
'She'll break up,' he said. 'The big
ship won't go down like the little one.
She won't come back, will she?'
'Who?' I asked him.
'Her,' he said. 'The other one.'
I did not know what Ben meant. I left him and
walked towards the path through the woods.
I did not look at the cottage. As I went up the
path, a strange fear began to fill my heart.
The house looked very peaceful.
Manderley was a place of safety
and looked more beautiful than I had ever seen it.
I felt, for the first time, that it was my home.
I belonged to Manderley and
Manderley belonged to me.
I went through the house and into the library.
Jasper was not there. He must have gone out with
Maxim. I suddenly felt very hungry, and so I
asked Robert to bring in the tea. I still had
a strange feeling of fear in my heart. I felt that
I was waiting for something - something terrible.
As I sat drinking my tea,
Robert came back into the room.
'Captain Searle, the harbour-master,
is on the phone, Madam,' he told me.
'He wants to come here and speak to Mr de
Winter at once. He says it's very important.'
'Mr de Winter is not back yet, Robert,' I told
him. 'Ask Captain Searle to come up and wait.'
Robert went out of the room with the message.
I wondered what Captain Searle wanted to say.
It must be something to do with the ship out
in the bay. But why did he want to see Maxim?
Captain Searle came into the
library about fifteen minutes later.
He looked at me with his bright blue eyes.
'I'm afraid I've got some bad news for Mr
de Winter. I don't know how to tell him.'
'What sort of news, Captain Searle?' I asked him.
'Well, Mrs de Winter, it's not very pleasant.
When we sent the diver down to look at the ship,
he found something else. It
was a little sailing boat.
It's the boat that belonged
to the late Mrs de Winter.'
'I'm sorry,' I said. 'Must you tell Mr
de Winter? Can't the boat be left there?'
'The man found something else,' Captain Searle
answered slowly. 'The cabin door was closed,
so he broke a window and looked in. Then he got
a terrible fright. There was a body in there
on the cabin floor. I must tell your husband,
Mrs de Winter. The police will have to know too.'
This was the reason for the
strange fear in my heart.
Someone had been in the boat
with Rebecca that night.
'Do we have to tell him?' I asked.
'I've got to do my duty,' Captain Searle said.
He stopped. The door had opened. It was Maxim.
'Hello,' he said. 'Is something
the matter, Captain Searle?'
I felt very afraid. I went out of the room
quickly and shut the door behind me. Jasper was
in the hall and he walked out on to the terrace
with me. I sat down. I must not fail Maxim now.
I sat on the terrace until I heard
Captain Searle's car drive away.
Then I stood up and walked
slowly back to the library.
Maxim was standing by the window.
I went and stood beside him.
I took his hand and held it against my face.
'I want to help you, Maxim,' I said. 'I've
grown up, you know. I'm not a child any more.'
Maxim put his arm round me and held me closely.
'I was angry with you last
night, wasn't I?' he said.
'Maxim,' I asked him, 'can't we start again?'
'It's too late, my darling, too late,' he said.
'We've lost our chance of happiness. Something
has happened. Something I've dreamt about, night
after night. I knew we could never be happy.'
Maxim held both my hands and looked into my face.
'Rebecca has won,' he said.
I stared at him. My heart began to beat
fast. What was Maxim trying to tell me?
'I always knew this would happen,' Maxim said.
'Rebecca has kept us apart all this time. I
remember how she looked at me before she died.
I remember her smile. She knew this would
happen. She knew she would win in the end.'
'Maxim,' I whispered. 'What are you trying to tell
me? Captain Searle told me about the boat. There
was someone sailing with Rebecca. You have to
find out who it was. That's it, isn't it, Maxim?'
'No,' he said, 'you don't understand. There
was no one with Rebecca. She was alone.'
I stood there watching his
face, watching his eyes.
'It's Rebecca's body lying
there on the cabin floor.'
'No,' I said. 'No!'
'The woman buried in the church is not Rebecca.
I always knew that,' Maxim said. 'Rebecca was
not drowned. I killed her. I shot Rebecca in
the cottage. I carried her body to the cabin,
took the boat out that night and sank it. It's
Rebecca who's lying there on the cabin floor.
Will you look into my eyes and
tell me that you love me now?'
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
The Truth About Rebecca
It was very quiet in the library. When people have
a great shock, they feel nothing at first. I stood
beside Maxim and I had no feelings at all. Then
Maxim took me in his arms and began to kiss me.
I shut my eyes. He had never
kissed me like this before.
'I love you so much,' he whispered.
This is what I had wanted him to say, every day
and every night. But I could feel nothing now.
Maxim stopped suddenly and
pushed me away from him.
'You see, I was right,' he said. 'It's
too late. You don't love me now.'
'It's not too late,' I said, putting my arms round
him. 'I love you more than anything in the world.'
'It's no use now,' said Maxim. 'We have no time.
They've found the boat. They've found Rebecca.'
I stared at him, not understanding.
'What will they do?' I said.
'They will make sure that the body in
the cabin is Rebecca. Then they will
remember that other body in the church. The
other woman - the one I said was Rebecca.'
'What are we going to do?' I said.
Maxim did not answer.
'Does anyone know? Anyone at all?' I said.
Maxim shook his head.
'Are you sure Frank doesn't
know?' I asked quickly.
'How could he?' said Maxim. 'There was
nobody there but me. It was dark...'
He stopped. He sat down on a chair
and I went and knelt beside him.
'Why didn't you tell me?' I whispered.
'I nearly did, once,' Maxim said. 'But
you always seemed so unhappy and so shy.'
I answered very quietly.
'I knew you were thinking
about Rebecca all the time.
How could I ask you to love me
when I knew you loved Rebecca?'
'You thought I loved Rebecca?' he said.
'I hated her. We never loved each other.
Rebecca never loved anyone except herself.'
I sat on the floor, staring at him.
'She was clever of course,' Maxim went on.
'Everyone thought she was the kindest, the
most charming person. When I married her, people
told me I was the luckiest man in the world.'
'I found out the truth five days after
we were married. We were in the hills
near Monte Carlo. It was the same place I went
to with you. Do you remember? She sat there in
the car and told me terrible, evil things about
herself. Things that I could not tell anyone.'
Maxim stared out of the window.
'I did not kill her then,'
he said. 'I let her laugh.
She knew that I would take her to Manderley.
She knew I would never divorce her.
I would never tell people all the
terrible things she had told me.'
Maxim came up to me and held out his hands.
'You hate me, don't you?' he said.
'You can't understand me, can you?'
I did not say anything. I held
his hands against my heart.
Only one thing mattered. Maxim did not love
Rebecca. He had never loved her, never, never.
Maxim was talking again.
'I thought about Manderley too much,' he said.
'I put Manderley first, before anything else.
I can't tell you about those terrible
years with Rebecca. But she made
Manderley the place of beauty it is today. And
I accepted everything, because of Manderley.
'Rebecca was careful at first,' Maxim went
on. 'She had a flat in London. She met her
friends there. Then she began to grow careless.
She invited friends down here, to Manderley.
I warned her. I told her that Manderley was mine.
Rebecca did not say anything. She only smiled.
'Then Frank came to me and
told me he wanted to leave.
He wouldn't say why at first. But I
got the truth from him in the end.
Rebecca never left him alone. She was always
going to his house and asking him to her cottage.
'Rebecca went up to London for a time. When
she came back, she took Giles out sailing
with her. I knew what had happened as soon as
they came back. Beatrice and Giles never stayed
at Manderley again. After that, I knew
I could never trust Rebecca with anyone.
'She had a cousin, an awful man, called Jack
Favell. He started to come here when I was away.'
'I've met him,' I said. 'He came here the
day you went to London. I didn't tell you.
I didn't want to remind you of Rebecca.'
'Remind me?' said Maxim. 'Oh God,
I never needed to be reminded.
'Favell often stayed with Rebecca down at the
cottage. He is a bad man. He's been in trouble
with the police many times. I told Rebecca that I
would shoot Favell if he came to Manderley again.
'Then, one night, I could
stand our life here no longer.
Rebecca came back from London very
late. She went to the cottage.
I thought Favell was with her. I went
after them. I took a gun to frighten him.'
Maxim was talking in quick, short
sentences. I held his hand tightly.
'I saw a light in the cottage and went in.
To my surprise, Rebecca was
alone. She looked ill and strange.
"This is the end," I told her. "I can't stand
any more." Rebecca looked at me and smiled.
"It won't be easy to divorce me," she said.
"Everyone believes our marriage is perfect."
'Then she stood up and walked towards me.
"If I had a child, Max," she said, "Everyone
would think it was yours. You would like a son,
wouldn't you? A boy to grow up at Manderley.
And you would never know who his father was."
'And she smiled at me again. She was smiling when
I killed her. The bullet went through her heart.'
Maxim's voice was very low. He spoke slowly.
'There was blood all over the floor. I had
to get water from the sea to clean the place.
'There was no moon and it was very dark,'
Maxim went on. 'I carried Rebecca's body
to the boat. I laid the body on the floor of
the cabin. Then I took the boat out into the
bay. I wanted to take the boat a good way
out, but the wind was too strong for me.
'I made some holes in the wooden planks with a
metal spike. I opened the sea cocks and the sea
water flowed in. In a few minutes it had covered
my feet. I shut the cabin door behind me, climbed
into the dinghy and rowed back. Rebecca's boat was
already sinking. I sat and watched it go down.'
Maxim looked at me.
'That's all,' he said. 'There's no more to tell.'
The library was very quiet. We sat there together
for some minutes without saying anything.
Then Maxim began to speak again.
'I knew the boat would be found one day,' he said.
'Rebecca knew she would win in the
end. I saw her smile when she died.'
'But Rebecca is dead,' I told him.
'That's what we must remember.'
'The diver has seen the body. They're
going to get the boat up tomorrow morning.
They'll find out that it's
Rebecca's body in the cabin.'
'Then you must say you made a mistake about
the other body. Nobody saw you that night.
We are the only two people who know
what happened that night, Maxim.'
'Yes,' he said. 'Yes, I suppose so.'
'They will think the boat sank when
Rebecca went down into the cabin.
They'll think she was trapped there. They'll
think that, won't they, Maxim?' I said.
'I don't know,' Maxim replied
slowly. 'I don't know.'
At that moment, the telephone in
the next room began to ring.
CHAPTER NINETEEN
Colonel Julyan
Maxim went into the little room and closed
the door. I sat there, listening to the sound
of Maxim's voice. I was no longer afraid
of Rebecca; I did not hate her any more.
Maxim and I were going to fight this
together. Rebecca had not won, she had lost.
'That was Colonel Julyan,' said Maxim, as he came
back into the room. He is the local magistrate.
He has to be there when they get
the boat up tomorrow. He asked
me if I had made a mistake about the other body.'
The telephone began to ring again. Maxim answered
it quickly and came back into the library.
'It's begun,' he said.
'What do you mean?' asked.
'That was a reporter. The whole thing will be in
the papers tomorrow. There's nothing we can do.'
After dinner, we went back
into the library as usual.
I sat at Maxim's feet, my head against his knees.
In a strange way, we were completely happy.
Rain fell in the night. When I woke up in
the morning, Maxim had already gone out.
I went down to breakfast as usual. There were
a lot of letters thanking us for the Ball. How
far away that seemed! I felt calmer, much older
now. I took the letters into the morning-room.
To my surprise, the room was dusty and untidy.
The windows were tightly closed and some of the
flowers were dead. I rang the bell for a maid
and when she came, I spoke to her angrily.
I wondered why I had been
frightened of the servants before.
The menu for the day lay on the desk.
It was the same food as the day before.
I crossed everything out and rang for Robert.
'Tell Mrs Danvers to order
something different,' I told him.
Then I went out into the garden and cut some
roses. Very soon Maxim will be back, I thought.
I must be calm and quiet. I took the roses back
into the morning-room. It was clean and tidy now.
As I began to arrange the flowers,
there was a knock at the door.
It was Mrs Danvers, holding the menu
in her hand. She looked pale and tired.
'I don't understand,' she said. 'I'm not
used to having messages sent by Robert.
When Mrs de Winter wanted any change
in the menu, she spoke to me herself.'
'I am Mrs de Winter now, Mrs Danvers,' I
said. 'And I shall do things in my own way.'
Mrs Danvers stared at me.
'Is it true,' she asked slowly,
'that Mrs de Winter's boat has been found
and that there was a body in the cabin?'
'I am afraid I don't know
anything about that,' I said.
'Don't you?' Mrs Danvers said. She
stood looking at me. I turned away.
'I will give orders about the lunch,' she said.
She waited, but I did not say
anything. She went out of the room.
Mrs Danvers did not frighten me any more.
She was my enemy and I did not care.
But if she learnt the truth about Rebecca's
death, she would become Maxim's enemy too.
I suddenly felt sick and ill. I went out on
to the terrace and began to walk up and down.
At half past eleven, Maxim
phoned me from Frank's office.
He told me he was bringing Colonel
Julyan and Frank back for lunch.
The time dragged by. At five to one, I
heard the sound of a car in the drive.
Maxim came into the hall with
Frank and Colonel Julyan.
Colonel Julyan, the magistrate, was a
middle-aged man with a kind face and grey hair.
'This is most unpleasant for you and
your husband,' Colonel Julyan said to me.
'I feel very sorry for both of you.'
Maxim and Frank went on into the dining-room and
Colonel Julyan continued to speak to me quietly.
'We found a body in the boat this morning.
It is the body of the late Mrs de Winter.
As you know, Mr de Winter identified the
other body found in the sea as his wife.
That makes things rather difficult for us now.'
The Colonel stopped suddenly as
Maxim came back into the hall.
'Lunch is ready; shall we go in?' he said.
I did not look at Maxim during lunch. We talked
about the weather and Colonel Julyan asked me
about my life in France. Frith and Robert were in
the room and no one wanted to talk about the boat.
At last Frith served coffee
and the servants left us.
'I wish an inquest wasn't
necessary,' Colonel Julyan said,
'but I'm afraid it is. I don't
think it will take very long.
De Winter will have to say that the body in
the boat was the late Mrs de Winter. Then the
boat-builder will say that the boat was in good
order when he last saw it. This must be done.'
'That's quite all right,'
Maxim said. 'We understand.'
'I suppose Mrs de Winter had to go down into
the cabin for something. Then the door shut and,
somehow, she was trapped there. Don't you
think so, Crawley?' the Colonel asked Frank.
'Oh yes, of course,' said Frank. I had a
sudden feeling that Frank knew the truth.
'The inquest will be on Tuesday
afternoon,' Colonel Julyan told us.
'We'll keep it as short as possible, but
I'm afraid the reporters will be there.'
There was another silence.
'Shall we go into the garden?' I said.
We all stood on the terrace for a moment
and then Colonel Julyan looked at his watch.
'Thank you for the lunch,' he said
to me. 'I'm afraid I must leave now.
Would you like a lift, Crawley?'
Maxim walked with them to the car. When they
had gone, he came back to me on the terrace.
'It's going to be all right,' Maxim said.
'There won't be any trouble at the inquest.
There is nothing to show what I did.
Colonel Julyan thinks she was trapped
in the cabin and the jury will think that too.'
I said nothing.
'It's you I'm sorry for,' Maxim told me
sadly. 'I don't care about anything else.
I'm glad that I killed Rebecca. But I can't forget
what this has done to you. You have lost that
young, sweet look. And it will never come back. In
twenty-four hours, you have grown so much older.'
Frith brought in the newspapers
at breakfast the following day.
The story was in all of them. There was a
picture of Manderley and an awful one of Maxim.
All the papers said that Rebecca's body
had been found after the Fancy Dress Ball.
They said how everyone had loved Rebecca. They all
said that Maxim had married his young, second wife
within a year of Rebecca's death. It all made a
good story. Maxim's face went whiter and whiter.
I wondered what the papers would
say if they knew the truth.
That terrible word - murder -
would be on every front page.
Frank was a great help to us. We had no more
phone calls from reporters and no visitors.
It was just a question of waiting
- of waiting until Tuesday.
Maxim and I stayed quietly in
the house or in the gardens.
We did not walk in the
woods or go down to the sea.
The weather was very hot and the air was heavy.
There were clouds, but the rain did not fall.
CHAPTER TWENTY
The Inquest
Tuesday came at last. The
inquest was at two o'clock.
After an early lunch, I drove
into the town with Maxim.
'I think I shall stay here in the car,' I
said. 'I won't come in with you after all.'
'I didn't want you to come,' Maxim said.
'I wish you had stayed at Manderley.'
Maxim went off and left me sitting
there. The minutes went by.
I wondered what was happening at the inquest. I
got out of the car and began walking up and down.
A policeman looked at me.
'Excuse me, Madam,' he said. 'Aren't you Mrs
de Winter? You can wait inside if you like.'
The policeman took me into an empty room.
Five minutes passed. Nothing happened.
I got up and walked out of the little room.
The policeman was still standing there.
'How long will they be?' I asked him.
'I'll go and see if you like,' the policeman
said. He was back again in a moment.
'It won't last much longer,' he told me. 'Mr de
Winter has just finished giving his evidence.
There's only the boat-builder,
Mr Tabb, to speak now.
Would you like to go in? There's
an empty seat near the door.'
I followed the policeman. He opened the door
for me and I went in quietly and sat down. The
room was small and full of people. The air was hot
and stuffy. Frank was sitting next to Maxim. To my
surprise, Mrs Danvers was there too, with Favell
beside her. I wondered whether Maxim had seen him.
Tabb, the boat-builder, standing in the centre of
the room, was answering the Coroner's questions.
'Was the boat in good condition?'
the Coroner was asking.
'Yes, it certainly was the last time I saw it,'
Tabb said. 'It was a strong little boat. I
can't understand why it sank that night.'
'Accidents have happened
before,' the Coroner said.
'Mrs de Winter was careless
for a moment and she died.'
'Excuse me, sir,' said the boat-builder.
'I would like to say something else.'
'Very well, go on,' said the Coroner.
'It's this, sir. There was nothing wrong
with that boat when I last saw it. So
what I want to know is this. Who made those
holes in the planks? Rocks didn't do it.
The boat sank too far away from them. And
those holes were mad with something sharp.'
I could not look at anyone.
I stared down at the floor.
For a moment, the Coroner
was too surprised to speak.
Then he said, 'What do you
mean? What sort of holes?'
'There were three of them, in
different parts of the boat.
And that's not all. The sea-cocks
had been turned full on.'
'The sea-cocks? What are they?' asked the Coroner.
'The sea-cocks close the pipes
leading to the wash-basins, sir.
They must be kept tightly closed when the boat
is sailing. Otherwise the sea water comes in.'
It was hot in that crowded room, far too
hot. I wished someone would open a window.
The boat-builder was speaking again.
'With those holes, sir, and the sea-cocks open,
a small boat like Mrs de Winter's would soon
sink. It's my opinion that there was no
accident. That boat was sunk on purpose.'
I must try and get out of the door,
I thought. There was no air. People
were standing up and talking loudly. I
heard the Coroner say, 'Mr de Winter.'
Maxim was standing up. I could not look at him.
'Mr de Winter,' the Coroner said,
'you have heard James Tabb's evidence.
Do you know anything about those holes?'
'Nothing.'
'Can you think why they are there?'
'No, of course not.'
'This news is a shock to you, of course?'
'Of course it is a shock. Does it
surprise you that I am shocked?'
Maxim's voice was hard and angry.
Oh God, I thought, don't
let Maxim lose his temper.
The Coroner was speaking again.
'Mr de Winter, I want to find out
exactly how your late wife died.
Who looked after Mrs de Winter's boat?'
'She looked after it herself.'
'Then whoever took the boat out that night also
made those holes and opened the sea-cocks.'
'I suppose so.'
'You have told us that the door and
windows of the cabin were shut?'
'Yes.'
'Doesn't this seem very
strange to you, Mr de Winter?'
'Yes, it does.'
'Mr de Winter, I'm afraid I
must ask you one other question.
Were you and the late Mrs
de Winter happily married?'
It was hot, so hot. I tried
to stand up, but I could not.
The ground came up to meet me. And then
I heard Maxim's voice, clear and strong.
'Will someone take my wife
outside? She is going to faint.'
I was sitting in the little
room again. Frank was beside me.
'I'm sorry,' I said. 'It was so hot in there.'
'Are you feeling better,
Mrs de Winter?' Frank asked.
'Maxim has told me to take you back to
Manderley.' Frank helped me to get up.
'I'd much rather stay,' I said.
'I want to wait for Maxim.'
'Maxim may be some time,' Frank told me.
'They may have to go over the evidence again.'
'But what are they trying to find out?'
Frank did not answer. We were in his
car now and he was driving very fast.
'Did you see Favell there?' I asked.
'He was sitting with Mrs Danvers.
I don't trust them, Frank.
They might make trouble.'
Frank did not answer. He could not know how much
Maxim had told me. Then we were back at Manderley.
'Will you be all right now?' Frank asked
me. 'I shall go back. Maxim may want me.'
He got quickly back into the
car again and drove away.
I went upstairs to my room, and lay down on
my bed. What were they all saying now? What
was happening? What would I do if Frank
came back to Manderley without Maxim?
I thought again of that dreadful word - murder.
God, let me not think about it. Let me
think about something else, anything...
I must have fallen asleep. I woke up suddenly. It
was five o'clock. I got up and went to the window.
There was no wind. Lightning
flashed against the grey sky.
I heard thunder in the distance.
A few drops of rain began to fall.
I went downstairs and sat
with Jasper in the library.
CHAPTER TWENTY ONE
A Visit From Jack Favell
It was after six when I heard
the sound of Maxim's car.
I tried to stand up but my legs were so
weak that I had to lean against a chair.
Maxim came into the room and stood
by the door. He looked tired and old.
'It's all over,' he said. I waited. I
could not speak or walk towards him.
'Suicide,' Maxim said. 'That's the verdict.
They said that Rebecca killed herself.'
I sat down. 'Suicide,' I repeated.
'Why do they think Rebecca did that?'
'God knows,' Maxim said.
He went and stood by the window. 'There's one more
thing to be done. Rebecca's body has to be buried.
I'm going down to the church now. We'll
talk about everything when I get back.
We've got to start our lives all over again. The
past can't hurt us if we are together. We'll have
children too, I promise you. I must go now. I'm
meeting Frank and Colonel Julyan at the church.'
He left the room quickly and then I
heard the sound of his car driving away.
It was quiet in the library. I thought about the
church where Rebecca was being buried at last.
Just before seven, the rain began to fall
heavily. I opened the windows to let in the
cold, clean air. The rain was falling so
heavily that I did not hear Frith come in.
'Excuse me, Madam,' he said. 'There's a
gentleman to see Mr de Winter. It's Mr Favell.'
I was very surprised.
'I think I had better see Mr Favell,'
I said. 'Bring him in here, please,
Frith.' I hoped that Favell would go before Maxim
came back. I could not think why Favell had come.
'I'm afraid Maxim is not here,' I
said, when Favell walked into the room.
His eyes were red. I wondered
if he had been drinking.
'I don't mind waiting,' Favell replied.
'Max will be back for dinner, I'm sure.'
'Mr Favell,' I said. 'I don't want
to be rude, but I am very tired.
It will be better if you
come back in the morning.'
'No, no,' he said, coming towards me,
'I've got something to say to Max.
This has been a shock to me, you
know. I was very fond of Rebecca.'
'Yes, of course,' I said.
'I'm very sorry for you.'
'I was fonder of Rebecca than
of anyone else in the world,'
Favell went on. 'And she was fond of me. That's
why I've come here to find out the truth.
Suicide... my God. You and I know
it wasn't suicide, don't we?'
As Favell was speaking, the door
opened and Maxim and Frank came in.
'What the hell are you doing
here?' Maxim said to Favell.
'Why, hello, Max, old man,' Favell said. 'You
must be feeling very pleased with yourself.'
'Do you mind leaving the house?' said
Maxim coldly. 'I don't want you here.'
'Now, wait a minute, Max,' Favell answered.
'You've been very lucky. But I can still
make life unpleasant for you. And dangerous
too, perhaps.' Maxim stared hard at Favell.
'Oh yes?' he said. 'In what way
can you make things dangerous?'
'I'll tell you, Max,' said
Favell with an unpleasant smile.
'You know all about Rebecca and
me. Her death was a great shock.
Then I read about Rebecca's boat and
the body in the cabin. So I went to the
inquest. I heard the boat-builder's evidence.
What about those holes in the boat, Max?'
'You heard the verdict,' Maxim told him. 'I
have nothing more to say.' Favell laughed.
'You know Rebecca didn't kill herself. I've
a note here that may interest you. I kept
it because it was the last thing
Rebecca ever wrote to me. Listen.'
Favell took a piece of paper from his pocket.
I recognized Rebecca's hard, black writing.
"I tried to phone you," Favell
read, "but you were out.
I'm leaving London now and going back
to Manderley. I'll wait for you in
the cottage. Come down as soon as you
can. I've got something to tell you." '
Favell put the note back in his pocket.
'I found that in my London flat. It was
too late to drive down to Manderley.
When I phoned the following day, Rebecca was dead.
Do you really think Rebecca killed
herself after writing that note?'
Maxim said nothing.
'Now, Max, old man,' Favell said at last,
'you know I'm not a rich man. If I had two
or three thousand pounds, I could live quite
well. I'd never come back, I promise you.'
'I've already asked you to leave the house,'
Maxim said. 'The door is behind you.'
Favell laughed again.
'Think again, Max,' said Favell.
'I don't suppose your new bride wants
to be known as the wife of a murderer.'
'You can't frighten me, Favell,' Maxim answered.
'Shall I phone Colonel Julyan?
You can tell your story to him.'
'You wouldn't dare, Max,' said Favell. 'I
have enough evidence to hang you, Max.'
Maxim walked slowly towards
the telephone in the next room.
'Stop him,' I said to Frank.
'Stop him for God's sake.'
But it was too late. Maxim was already speaking.
'Is that Colonel Julyan? It's de Winter here.
Could you come over to Manderley at once?
No - I can't say anything over the
phone. Thank you very much, goodbye.'
Maxim came back again into the room.
'Colonel Julyan will be here
in ten minutes,' he said.
We waited in silence. The rain was so heavy
that we did not hear the sound of the car.
We were taken by surprise when Frith
brought the magistrate into the library.
'Good evening, Colonel
Julyan,' Maxim said at once.
'This is Jack Favell, my late wife's
cousin. He has something to say to you.'
Favell went up to Colonel Julyan.
'I'm not happy about the verdict.
I want you to read this note. Tell me whether you
think the writer had decided to kill herself.'
Colonel Julyan took the note and read it slowly.
'I see what you mean,' he said.
'But the note is not clear.
What do you think really happened to
Mrs de Winter?' Favell looked at Maxim.
'I'll tell you what I think,' he said slowly.
'Rebecca never opened those sea-cocks.
She didn't make those holes in the
boat. Rebecca didn't kill herself.
I say she was murdered. Do you want to
know who the murderer is? He's there,
standing by the window. Mr Maximilian de Winter
- he's your murderer. Take a good look at him.'
Favell began to laugh, a high stupid laugh, as he
twisted the note round and round in his fingers.
CHAPTER TWENTY TWO
Rebecca's Diary
Thank God for Favell's laugh. I saw a look
of disgust come into Colonel Julyan's face.
'The man's drunk,' he said quickly.
'He doesn't know what he's saying.'
'Drunk, am I?' shouted Favell. 'Oh no,
I'm not drunk. Max de Winter murdered
Rebecca, and I'm going to prove it.'
'Wait a minute,' said Colonel
Julyan. 'I want to hear your proof.'
'Proof?' said Favell. 'Aren't those
holes in the boat enough proof for you?'
'Certainly not,' said Colonel Julyan. 'Unless
you can find someone who saw him do it.'
'I'll get your proof for you,' shouted Favell.
'De Winter killed Rebecca because of me.
He was jealous because she loved me. He went
down to the cottage and killed her there.
Wait a minute... I think I
can find someone who saw him.'
I suddenly knew what Favell meant. Someone had
seen it all happen - someone who was
often down there in the bay - Ben.
'There's an idiot who was always
around the cottage,' Favell said.
'He often slept on the beach.
I'm sure he saw everything.'
'Can we get this man and question
him?' asked Colonel Julyan.
'Of course,' said Maxim. 'His name
is Ben. Could you go and get him,
Frank? Take your car.' Frank went out quickly.
Favell laughed angrily. His face was very red.
'You all help each other down here, don't
you?' he said. 'Crawley knows the truth,
I'm sure. He'll be there to hold the young
bride's arm when Max is sentenced to death.'
Without warning, Maxim went
up to Favell and hit him hard.
Favell fell heavily to the floor. I
wished that Maxim had not hit him.
Favell got slowly to his feet, walked over to
a small table and poured himself some whisky.
I saw Colonel Julyan look thoughtfully at Maxim.
Was he beginning to believe Favell's story?
The door opened and Frank came in.
'All right, Ben,' he said
quietly. 'Don't be frightened.'
Ben stepped into the room and stared at everyone
with his small eyes. Favell walked up to him.
'You know who I am, don't you?'
he said. Ben did not answer.
'Come on,' said Favell. 'You've seen
me in the cottage, haven't you?'
Ben held Frank's arm. 'I've never seen him,'
he said. 'Is he going to take me away?'
'No, of course not,' said Colonel Julyan.
'Now listen to me, Ben. You remember the lady
with the boat. Were you on the beach when
she took her boat out for the last time?'
'You were there, weren't you?'
said Favell, standing over Ben.
'You saw Mrs de Winter go into the cottage
and Mr de Winter too. What happened then?'
Ben shook his head and
moved back against the wall.
'I didn't see anything,' he said. He began to cry.
'You damned little idiot,' Favell said slowly.
'I think Ben can go home now,
don't you, Colonel Julyan?'
Maxim said. Frank took Ben out of the
room as the Colonel nodded his head.
'That poor fellow was terrified,' he said.
'He's no use to you, Favell. I'm
afraid you can't prove your story.'
Favell did not answer. Instead, he rang the bell
and when Frith came in, he said, 'Ask
Mrs Danvers to come here, Frith.'
'Isn't Mrs Danvers the housekeeper?' asked
Colonel Julyan as Frith left the room.
'She was also Rebecca's friend. She knew her for
years,' Favell said, with his unpleasant smile.
We all waited, watching the door. Then Mrs
Danvers came in and shut the door behind her.
'Good evening, Mrs Danvers,' Colonel Julyan said.
'I would like to ask you a question.
You knew the late Mrs de Winter well.
Mr Favell has told us that Mrs de Winter
was in love with him. Is that true?'
'No, it is not,' Mrs Danvers answered.
'Now, listen, Danny,' Favell began to
shout, but Mrs Danvers took no notice.
'She was not in love with you, Mr Jack. Or
with Mr de Winter. She was not in love with
anyone. She thought men were fools. She
amused herself with you, that was all.'
Maxim went very white. Favell stared at Mrs
Danvers as though he did not understand her.
'Mrs Danvers,' Colonel Julyan said quietly,
'can you think of any reason why
Mrs de Winter killed herself?'
Mrs Danvers shook her head.
'No, certainly not,' she said.
'There you are! What did I
tell you?' Favell shouted.
'Be quiet, will you. Let Mrs Danvers read the
note. She may understand it,' Colonel Julyan said.
Mrs Danvers took the note, read
it and then shook her head again.
'I don't know what she meant. If it was
something important, she would have told me.'
'Can you tell us how Mrs de Winter
spent that last day in London?
Did she keep a diary?' asked Colonel Julyan.
'I've got her diary in my
room,' Mrs Danvers replied.
'I kept all her things. I'll go and get it.'
'Well, de Winter,' said Colonel Julyan,
'do you mind us seeing this diary?'
'Of course not,' said Maxim. Once again, I
saw Colonel Julyan give Maxim a hard look.
This time Frank saw it too. Somehow I felt
sure that the truth was in that diary.
Mrs Danvers came back with
a small book in her hand.
'Here is the page for the day Mrs de Winter died,'
she said. Colonel Julyan looked at it carefully.
'Yes,' he said, 'here it is. Hairdressers
at twelve o'clock. Then lunch. And
then - Baker - two o'clock. Who was Baker?'
He looked at Maxim. Maxim shook his head.
'Baker?' repeated Mrs Danvers.
'She knew no one called Baker.'
'We must find out who this
person was,' said Colonel Julyan.
'If he wasn't a friend, perhaps
it was someone she was afraid of.'
'Mrs de Winter afraid?' said Mrs Danvers.
'She was afraid of nothing and no one.
Only one thing worried her. That was the
thought of illness, of dying slowly in her bed.'
'What does all this matter?' said Favell. 'If
Baker was important Danny would know about him.'
Mrs Danvers was turning the pages of the diary.
'There's a telephone number here at the
back,' she said. 'And the name Baker again.'
'Well,' said Maxim, lighting a cigarette.
'Perhaps someone should phone that number.
Would you mind, Frank?'
Frank took the diary without a word and went
into the next room. He shut the door behind him.
When he came back, he said,
'That was a doctor's number.
Dr Baker used to live there,
but he left six months ago.
They gave me his new address. I have written
it here.' And Frank held out a piece of paper.
It was then that Maxim looked at me. He looked at
me like a man saying goodbye for the last time.
That piece of paper was enough to hang Maxim.
I knew why Rebecca had gone to a doctor.
I knew what she had wanted to tell Favell.
Rebecca had been pregnant when
she died. She had been going
to have a child. It was the one clear
proof that Rebecca had not killed herself.
I was sure that this was the
truth. I knew Maxim thought so too.
'Well done, Frank,' said Maxim calmly.
'Where does the doctor live now?'
'In north London,' Frank replied. 'But he's not on
the phone. He's a very well-known women's doctor.'
'Well,' said Colonel Julyan. 'There must have
been something wrong with her after all.'
'I'll write him a letter,' Frank said.
'I don't think he would tell
you anything,' Colonel Julyan
answered. 'I think de Winter
should see him and explain.'
'I'm ready to go,' said Maxim quietly.
'Shall I go up in the morning?'
'He's not going alone,' Favell said
with a laugh. 'You go with him,
Julyan. And I think I'd better
go too. What time do we start?'
Colonel Julyan looked at Maxim.
'Nine o'clock?' he said. 'Perhaps
you will take me in your car.'
'We'll meet at the crossroads just after
nine,' Favell said. He walked to the door.
'I suppose you're not going to ask
me to dinner, so I'll say goodbye.
Come on, Danny. I'll see you in the morning, Max.'
Colonel Julyan came up to me and took my hand.
'Good night,' he said. 'Get
your husband to bed early.
Tomorrow will be a long day.'
He held my hand for a moment,
but he did not look into my eyes. He and Frank
went out together. Maxim and I were alone at last.
'I'm coming with you tomorrow,' I said.
'Yes,' Maxim answered. 'We must
be together as long as we can.'
I put my arms around him and held him. We
did not say anything. Then Maxim held me
tightly. We began to kiss each other, like
guilty lovers who had never kissed before.
CHAPTER TWENTY THREE
Dr Baker
I woke up early the following
morning at about six o'clock.
I got up and went to the window.
The trees were covered in mist.
There was a sharp coolness in
the air. Autumn had arrived.
This was the start of a new day at Manderley.
Soon the servants would be starting work.
Whatever happened to us, life at Manderley would
go on. The peace of Manderley could not be broken.
Its beauty could not be destroyed.
The flowers would come every year,
the birds would sing. Manderley would always be
here, safe and secure, within sound of the sea.
Maxim slept on and I did not wake him.
The day ahead would be long and tiring.
London was many miles away. We did not know
what we should find at the end of the journey.
Somewhere in London lived a man called
Baker. He had never heard of us.
But our future was in his hands.
I had a bath, dressed and then woke Maxim. He
got up and went into the bathroom. I began to
pack a few things. We might have to stay
overnight in London. I looked at my small
case. It seemed so long since I had used it. But
it was only four months. I could not believe it.
We had breakfast together and
I went out on to the terrace.
The air was fresh and clear now.
It was going to be a perfect day.
At nine o'clock exactly, Frank
brought up Colonel Julyan in his car.
We were going in Maxim's car. I sat beside
Maxim and Colonel Julyan got into the back.
'You will telephone, won't you?'
Frank said as he stood on the steps.
'Yes, of course,' Maxim said. As we
drove away, I looked back at the house.
It had never looked more beautiful. For
some reason, my eyes filled with tears.
Then we were round the bend of the drive
and I could see the house no longer.
When we came to the crossroads,
Favell was already waiting.
He waved when he saw us and started up his car.
I settled down for the long journey to London.
The hours passed and the miles went
by, Favell's car always behind us.
We had lunch somewhere and reached London at
about three o'clock. It was then that I began to
feel tired. It was warm and the streets were busy.
The drive through the centre of London seemed very
long. Maxim looked pale and tired, but he did not
say anything. Favell's car was always behind us.
We reached Baker's house at about five o'clock.
Maxim stopped the car and we got out. Favell came
up to meet us. We all walked slowly up the path
to the front door. Colonel Julyan rang the bell.
A woman opened the door.
'Is Dr Baker at home?' said Colonel Julyan.
'He is expecting us. I sent a telegram.'
'Yes, of course,' said the woman. 'My husband
is in the garden. I'll tell him you are here.'
She took us into a cool room
at the back of the house.
She went out and in a few minutes
a tall man came into the room.
'I'm Dr Baker. I'm sorry to keep you
waiting. Please sit down,' he said.
'We are sorry to trouble you, Dr Baker,' Colonel
Julyan said. 'My name is Julyan. This is Mr de
Winter, Mrs de Winter and Mr Favell. We have
come about the death of the late Mrs de Winter.
You may have read the report in the papers.'
'The verdict was suicide,' Favell said. 'I
knew Mrs de Winter very well. She did not kill
herself. She had no reason to. We want to know
why she came to see you on the day she died.'
Dr Baker looked surprised. 'I
think you've made a mistake,'
he said. 'No one called de
Winter has ever come to me.'
'But we found your old telephone
number in Mrs de Winter's diary.'
Dr Baker looked at the page from the diary
that Colonel Julyan was holding out to him.
'That certainly was my number,' he said.
'Perhaps Mrs de Winter gave you a
different name,' Colonel Julyan suggested.
'It's possible,' said Dr Baker slowly.
'If you have any record of a visit
on that day, could we see it?'
Colonel Julyan asked. 'This
is an important matter.'
'Murder,' Favell said.
'Of course,' said the doctor. 'I had
no idea there was any question of that.
I'll go and get my book.'
While Dr Baker was out of
the room, we said nothing.
No one looked at anyone else. Favell
whistled quietly under his breath.
Dr Baker came back into
the room with a large book.
He opened the book and turned the
pages. We all stood watching his face.
'I saw a Mrs Danvers on the 12th at
two o'clock,' Dr Baker said at last.
'Danny? Why did...?' Favell began. Maxim broke in.
'Rebecca gave the wrong name, of course,'
he said. 'Do you remember the visit now,
Doctor?' But Dr Baker was already searching
his files. He picked out a card and read it.
'Yes,' he said slowly, 'I remember now.'
'Was she tall and dark, a beautiful
woman?' Colonel Julyan asked.
'Yes,' said Dr Baker. He put back the card
and looked at Maxim. The doctor spoke slowly.
'The woman who called herself Mrs Danvers was
very ill indeed. She had come to me the week
before. I took some X-rays. She had come back to
hear the result. I remember her words exactly.
"I want to know the truth," she said. "If I'm
really ill, I want to know." So I told her.'
Dr Baker stopped and looked down at the files.
'There was nothing to be done,' he went
on. 'An operation would have been useless.
I told her that. In six months,
she would have been dead.'
No one said a word and the doctor went
on, 'Mrs de Winter looked a healthy woman.
She had very little pain at that time. But
the pain would have come. The X-rays showed
that she could never have had a child. But
that was nothing to do with her illness.'
Everyone was standing up. We shook hands with Dr
Baker and he walked with us to the front door.
'Shall I send you my report?' Dr Baker asked.
'We may not need it,' said Colonel Julyan. 'We'll
write to you if we do. Thank you very much.'
'I am glad to have been of some use,' said
Dr Baker. 'Goodbye.' And he shut the door.
CHAPTER TWENTY FOUR
The Return to Manderley
We went and stood by the car. No
one said anything for a few minutes.
Favell's face was grey. His hand
shook as he lit a cigarette.
'She kept it a secret from everyone, even Danny.
It's been a dreadful shock to me,' Favell said.
'You're all right, of course, Max.
You've been lucky, haven't you?
You and your young wife can
go back to Manderley now.
You think you've won, but don't be too
sure, I haven't finished with you yet.'
'Shall we get into the car and
go?' Colonel Julyan asked Maxim.
Favell smiled unpleasantly. As we drove away,
he was still standing there, watching us.
'Favell can't do anything,'
Colonel Julyan told us.
'I'll soon deal with him if he comes near
Manderley again. I don't think the papers will
bother you any more. There may be some talk, but
I'll make sure that people hear about Dr Baker.'
'Thank you very much,' Maxim said.
'What a dreadful thing illness is,' Colonel
Julyan went on. 'I suppose she could not
face the pain. She was such a lovely young
woman, too.' Neither of us answered him.
Colonel Julyan's sister lived in London and
he asked Maxim to take him to her house.
'We must thank you for all your help,' Maxim
said as the magistrate got out of the car.
'I've been glad to help.
You must forget it all now.
Why don't you have a holiday, go abroad perhaps.
Goodbye, both of you. It's been a long day.'
As Maxim started up the car, I leant
back in my seat and closed my eyes.
We drove on through the traffic and I felt
full of peace. Nothing could hurt us any more.
We had dinner in a restaurant
and Maxim phoned Frank.
'Do you think Colonel Julyan knows
the truth about Rebecca's death?'
I asked Maxim as we were drinking our coffee.
'Of course he knows,' Maxim said. 'But he will
never say anything. I believe that Rebecca lied to
me on purpose. She wanted me to kill her. That's
why she laughed. She was laughing when she died.'
I did not say anything. It was all over. There was
no need for Maxim to look so white and troubled.
'I'm not sure that Rebecca hasn't
won, even now,' Maxim went on.
'Frank told me something rather strange on
the phone. Mrs Danvers has left Manderley.
There was a long-distance call for her at
six. By a quarter to seven, she had gone.'
'Isn't that a good thing?' I said. 'Favell phoned
her, of course. But they can't do anything to us.'
I was glad that Mrs Danvers had
gone. Manderley could be ours.
We would have people to stay. And soon,
very soon Maxim and I would have children.
'Have you finished your coffee?'
Maxim said to me suddenly.
'I feel that we must get back to Manderley as soon
as possible. Something's wrong, I know it is.'
'But you'll be so tired,' I said.
'No, I shall be all right. We can
be at Manderley by two o'clock.'
We went out to the car and Maxim covered me with
a rug. It was dark now and I fell asleep almost
at once. I started to dream. I saw the staircase
at Manderley and Mrs Danvers standing there in
her long, black dress. Then, in my dream,
I was alone in the woods near Manderley.
I wanted to get to the Happy
Valley, but I could not find it.
The dark trees were all round me. Then I
was standing on the terrace. Moonlight shone
on the windows. The gardens had gone and the
dark woods came up to the walls of the house.
I woke up suddenly.
'You've slept for two hours,' Maxim told me. 'It's
quarter past two. We shall be home by three.'
The early morning was very cold. The sky
was dark now and there were no stars.
'What time did you say it was?' I said suddenly.
'It's twenty past two,' Maxim replied.
'That's strange,' I said. 'The dawn seems to
be coming up over there, behind those hills.
But it can't be, it's too early.'
'It's the wrong direction, too,'
Maxim said 'you're looking west.'
I went on watching the sky.
It was still getting lighter.
A blood-red light was spreading across the
sky. Maxim began to drive faster, much faster.
'That's not the dawn,' he
said, 'that's Manderley.'
We reached the top of the hill. The road to
Manderley lay before us. There was no moon
and the sky above our heads was black. But the
sky in front of us was full of dreadful light.
And the light was red, red like blood.
The wind blew towards us from the sea.
The wind smelt of smoke and it was grey with
ashes. They were the ashes of Manderley.
-
THE END -