CHAPTER ONE
On board the Parvina
Leaning on the rail at the stern of the cruise
ship Parvina, sipping his champagne, Eddie
Munro looked out across the water and into
the darkness. There was a warm, gentle breeze,
and the sea was calm except for the dizzy
trail of water churned up by the ship's angry
propellers. It was a beautiful evening and
there was no one else on deck. Eddie liked
it that way.
He looked down at his watch, which showed
10.31 p.m., and the ship was already half
a mile from the harbour. He was amazed that
such a huge cruise ship could move so fast
- he was amazed it stayed afloat at all! He
watched St Thomas island getting further and
further away. He stared at the silhouette
of the island, at its faint black shapes of
hills rising up into the night sky. Eddie
smiled to himself as he noticed he could no
longer see where the lights ended and the
stars began.
He finished his champagne and, for good luck,
threw the glass far out into the sea. He never
heard it drop. He couldn't see much at all
in the warm Caribbean darkness, but he noticed
for the first time how high up he was. The
sea was a long, long way down, he thought.
At this point his wife, Lynn, came out looking
for him, wearing her long black evening dress
and the silk purple scarf she had bought on
the excursion earlier in the day. Her hair
was dark and short with plum-coloured highlights.
He turned to put his arm around her as she
joined him. He noticed her perfume, a powerful
and luxurious scent.
"Hello," he said, turning round. "You smell
nice. And you look lovely. Are you married?"
"Yes, thank you. To a very wealthy man, so
you have no chance," she said, smiling.
"Ah. But so am I."
"Ah, so you're married to a wealthy man, are
you?"
"I mean I'm wealthy. Very rich, in fact."
"Well aren't you the lucky one," Lynn said.
"Yes, so if you're lucky, I might buy you
dinner," said Eddie, turning back to look
out to sea once more.
"Well, lucky me. How can I refuse such charm?"
She looked at him and took hold of his hand.
She smiled and stared out into the night,
too, to the island which was now even further
away.
"I thought I'd find you out here," she said.
"How many glasses have you thrown into the
sea this evening?"
"Only two," he said.
"Eddie!"
"It's good luck."
"No, it isn't. Not if you're a fish and you
get hit by a glass."
"The fish might like it. It's probably quite
boring being a fish. The sudden arrival of
a champagne glass might brighten up your life."
"Or end it," she said.
"It's fun," said Eddie. "You should try it."
"I think I've had enough champagne," his wife
said.
"I love the way the glass disappears the minute
it leaves my hand, and the sea eats it up.
You can't see it falling and you can't hear
it hit the water. But you know it's landed,
dived in and sunk to the bottom. Imagine - a
tiny glass holding a giant ocean."
"You think too much," she said, moving away
and pulling him with her. "Why don't you come
back inside? They're serving coffee and I
think there's going to be some jazz."
"All right," he said. "Just a few more minutes."
"We have two more weeks on this cruise, Eddie.
You have plenty of time to take it all in."
"It's incredible, though, isn't it? So beautiful.
It's perfect."
Lynn laughed. "It's completely black. I can't
see anything in the dark."
"I know. But it's all out there. The blue
sea, the white sand, the palm trees, the boats..."
"The champagne glasses..."
"Very funny," said Eddie. Then he pointed
to the horizon. "Look over there at the dots
of light. Do you think they're lights on the
island or stars?"
Lynn looked hard into the night and gave it
some thought. "Erm... lights."
"But you're not sure."
"I am sure. I'm always sure."
"Hmm," he said. "How is that?"
"Because I'm always right," she said, smiling.
"Oh really?"
"Of course. I was right about setting up your
own business, wasn't I?"
"Yes."
"And I was right about selling the business
off this year for twenty million - only sixteen
years after starting."
"Possibly," he teased. He wouldn't give in
so easily.
"And I was right to let you take me on this
cruise to relax and celebrate in style."
"Oh, I see. How generous."
"Just think. You don't have to work ever again.
You're a millionaire, Mr Edward Munro. How
does that sound?"
"Lucky me," he said proudly.
"Yes, lucky you. Lucky us. Now come inside
before we lose all our money paying for missing
champagne glasses."
Back inside, the dining room was full of people.
It was hot, but the lighting made it welcoming
and comfortable. In the time Eddie had been
outside, a space had been cleared for dancing
and a few couples were already on their feet.
In the corner, four musicians, three men and
one woman, were playing a song Eddie knew
well, but he couldn't recall its name. The
singer was wearing a navy blue cocktail dress,
and the men were wearing tuxedos, black ties
and formal dinner suits.
Eddie noticed how young the woman looked.
Too young to have known the tune when it first
appeared, Eddie thought, but her voice was
strong and clear. And she seemed to believe
in the words, at least. How old was she? Twenty-five?
Twenty-six? Imagine singing on a cruise ship
in your twenties! What a life! The fun, the
parties, the people. The places to go and
things to see - before your life had even
started.
It seems so easy now, Eddie thought. His twenties
had been very different. And his thirties.
Eddie tried not to think about his own past.
Now was all that mattered. The past was the
past. 'What doesn't kill you makes you stronger,'
Clive, his business partner, always said.
'No such thing as luck,' he once said, 'it's
simply the moment when preparation meets opportunity.'
By now, Eddie was sitting back at his table
and next to his wife. She was watching the
band and tapping the table. She smiled at
the other passengers opposite her, who smiled
back, relaxed and enjoying the moment. Eddie
looked at his watch. It was almost 11 p.m.,
but he wasn't tired. Quite the opposite. He
felt relaxed and energized. He'd always been
an evening person, never a morning person.
He looked around at the giant lounge with
its circular tables and well-dressed diners,
and the perfect white tablecloths. The waiters
and waitresses in their smart uniforms moved
smoothly in and out of the room, and Eddie's
eyes followed them as they carried plates
and coffee and cakes and trays around the
tables, along the aisles and past the bar.
Eddie watched the barman throwing ice cubes
and cocktail shakers in the air and juggling
them as he made the drinks in acrobatic style.
He was confident and polished, and also young.
Possibly the same age as the singer. Why was
everyone so young these days? Where were all
the cruise ship jobs when Eddie was trying
to get started in life? Why hadn't he thought
of working on a ship in the Caribbean?
He found himself staring at the bar in the
distance. He was no longer thinking of anything
in particular. He was simply listening to
the sounds of jazz and the noise of a few
hundred people talking and laughing.
And that was when he saw him.
That was the moment when he saw Dominic for
the first time in many, many years. The man
was sitting at the bar, leaning forward and
smoking a large cigar. He was older now, clearly,
and his hair was very grey, but Eddie had
no doubt that it was him. He couldn't believe
that awful man was here on the ship.
And then everything was different.
Nothing was the same. All was spoiled.
Just like before.
CHAPTER TWO
Argument with Dominic
"You know your problem, Eddie?" said Dominic
Stephens in his office. "You're too hands-on."
He leaned back in his large, leather chair
behind his glass desk. He seldom made eye
contact. His shoulders looked tense and his
neck was hidden.
"I don't understand," said Eddie. "How can
that be a problem? The team really appreciates
my style and the customers love it. It's what
I do best. It's why I was brought here in
the first place."
"Oh, really?" said Dominic, clearly unimpressed.
"I know for a fact that Ann and Gary didn't
want an executive to run things. They wanted
someone with practical experience, and drive
- and lots of it. They said dull and uninspiring
executives and managers have come and gone
and there's been no direction, no feeling
for the business. No passion."
"And you have passion?" said Dominic.
"Yes. Do you?"
"This isn't about me, Eddie. It's about you,
and it takes more than passion to do this
job. You need to be a leader."
"I am a leader," replied Eddie. "I've done
it for years. My track record speaks for itself."
"Well, you can't do it all by yourself."
"I'm not trying to do it all by myself, Dominic.
I'm building a team. I'm training new people.
Resources are limited. It takes time."
"We don't have time, Eddie."
What did Dominic Stephens know about passion
or time? wondered Eddie. The only passion
he seemed to have was being in charge. And
golf. He seemed to have a lot of time for
that. He even kept his clubs in the corner
of his office. And today was Thursday. On
Thursdays he always left early to play golf
and he didn't even try to hide it.
Eddie was so angry his mouth was dry. "I don't
know why you have a problem with me, Dominic.
There's nothing wrong with my performance.
Quite the opposite in fact."
"Oh, really?"
"Yes. When I joined Fenton's, they were only
producing software for small businesses in
the UK. They had some accounting packages
and sales and marketing databases, but not
much else. I was brought in to expand the
business and build exports, and that is exactly
what I have done. I brought in some very talented
people to develop our products, and we now
offer some unique and very powerful programs
used by the biggest and best companies globally.
When I proposed and won the Moscow account,
you said it couldn't be done, and now we supply
the entire Russian region."
"Erm, excuse me, Mr Passion. I won the Moscow
contract for you," said Dominic, pointing
firmly at his own chest.
Eddie could not believe his ears. This was
so unfair. Rage filled his whole mind and
body. "You did not win that contract. You
knew some of the people in the Russian state
department there, that's all. I spent most
of last year - and the year before - going
to Russia and working long, long hours to
build a business plan that would work. Don't
take the credit away from me, Dominic. Without
me, this company could never have won such
a high-profile project."
"Well, I still haven't seen the final numbers,
and I still haven't seen the new business
plan," Dominic said, throwing his arms around.
"Yes, you have. I've kept you informed the
whole time with numerous emails."
"Oh, emails, emails! I don't have time for
emails. I get about three hundred a day. How
on earth can I keep up with all that?"
Well, it would help if you didn't play so
much golf, Eddie wanted to say. It would help
if you let me do my job and didn't interfere.
It would help if you weren't so aggressive.
Instead, he tried to remain diplomatic and
said, "Well, if you don't read my emails,
how can we communicate?"
"Simple. Pick up the phone."
He made it sound so easy. This was ridiculous.
"I do call you, Dominic. You're never there.
I leave messages but you don't call back.
When we do get time to meet, I don't think
you're really listening."
"I'm always listening to you, Eddie," said
Dominic in a weary voice. "Because you talk
so much, that's all you ever do. Talk, talk,
talk."
"You're making personal comments, and that
is not professional. I talk because I'm passionate.
And I deliver. If I say I'll do something,
I do it, and within budget, and you know it."
"You were not on budget. Last year you went
over budget by 25,000 pounds"
Not this again. Eddie was so tired of the
same story. "I can account for every penny
my department spent. No one seems to know
what happened to that 25,000 pounds."
Dominic looked at him accusingly.
"Don't look at me like that," said Eddie.
"Like what?"
"Look, the way I see it..." Eddie began, but
again he was cut off in mid-sentence. Dominic
always interrupted everyone. He was like a
spoilt child.
And so the situation was impossible. Eddie
simply wanted to leave. He could no longer
focus. He could never win.
Eddie came out of the office. His whole body
was trembling, and he tried very hard not
to slam the door, scream or break something.
He realized he was too angry and too upset
to go back to the team or finish his work.
He decided to slip out of the office for ten
minutes, just to calm down. He would have
a coffee. Or call Lynn. Come on, Ed, he told
himself. Get things in perspective. It's only
a job.
He was almost at reception and the main door,
when Clive passed him on the way to the photocopier.
"Ed, what's wrong?" he asked, stopping in
the corridor.
Eddie couldn't speak. He was afraid to say
anything, as he didn't know what might come
out. His face was red and tears were stinging
his eyes. He looked down, ignored Clive and
walked out of the door into the street and
towards the local cafe.
CHAPTER THREE
Someone from the past
"You all right, Eddie?" asked Lynn, who had
noticed Eddie staring at the bar. Eddie took
a moment and then said, "Yes, fine. Why?"
But he was still lost in thought. He wasn't
sure if the ship was moving or if he was dizzy.
"You look so serious. Come on, let's dance."
He was still staring at the bar. The man was
still there. It was Dominic. Sitting at the
bar barely fifty meters away, drinking and
smoking. As simple as that. Was the world
so small? thought Eddie. Couldn't it be a
bit bigger? Why here? Why now? After all this
time. Why on this ship? A familiar sickness
in his stomach returned.
"Well, don't get too excited, will you?" Eddie
heard his wife say.
"Sorry?" he said, turning his attention to
Lynn.
"A dance! Can we dance?" Lynn said impatiently.
"Yes, sure. Sorry."
They both got up and walked to the dance floor.
They held each other and danced slowly for
the final verse of yet another song whose
name Eddie couldn't remember.
Turning in the dance, Eddie was pleased that
Lynn was there with him as he tried to take
in the fact that he was now staring at the
distant shape of Dominic Stephens, on the
far side of the ship's dining room. The man,
Eddie saw, now turned to watch the dining
room and the dancing. He was hidden in a fog
of his own cigar smoke. How Eddie had hated
him. And how, after all this time, he still
hated him.
The memories.
The anger.
The pain.
"Are you sure you're feeling all right, Eddie?"
asked Lynn when they got back to their cabin.
Eddie was sitting on the bed staring into
space.
"Yes. Just tired. I think I'm still jet-lagged,
and I'm tired after walking on the island
today."
"You sure?"
"Yes."
"That trip on the glass-bottomed submarine
was amazing, wasn't it?"
"Yeah," said Eddie. But he still couldn't
think straight. His mind was filling up more
and more with the terrible realization that
Dominic was on the ship.
Lynn knew him too well. "Eddie," she said,
sitting down beside him, taking his hand and
looking at him. She stroked the back of his
head. "What's wrong?"
Eddie had decided to accept that the trip
was now spoiled. Did he need to spoil it for
his wife? She didn't have to know. They would
have their luxury cruise and go home to a
new life. The ship was big enough. Dominic
and Eddie both looked older and Dominic probably
wouldn't even remember him, so why worry about
it?
But all the old feelings were there again,
and Eddie could sense his energy slipping
away just thinking about it. It showed on
his face and Lynn could see it. Eddie could
never hide much from his wife, and before
he knew it he found himself weakening.
"It's Dominic. He's on the ship." It sounded
so strange to Eddie to even say those words.
There was a pause.
Lynn looked more closely at her husband.
"What?" said Lynn quietly. "Dominic Stephens?
You're kidding."
"I'm not kidding, Lynn. I wish I was," said
Eddie.
"I haven't heard that name in a long time."
"Well, he's here."
"How do you know he's here?"
"I saw him. He was sitting at the bar this
evening when we came in from the deck."
"Eddie, we were sitting on the other side
of the dining room - you could hardly see
anything. How can you be sure it was him?"
"Oh, I'm sure, Lynn. No mistake. The same
fat, lazy bloke. But less hair now. And grey.
And fatter."
Lynn was still trying to take it in. "Dominic
Stephens is on this ship?"
"Yes."
She waited a moment. "Oh, Eddie."
They both sat there for a moment. Then Lynn
spoke again. She was already recovering. "Well,
look, it's a long time ago, Ed. It doesn't
matter any more. He doesn't matter any more.
He's nothing. You don't have to talk to him."
"I know."
"It's a big ship," Lynn continued. "It's extremely
unlikely you're going meet him..."
"I saw him at the bar!" said Eddie.
"... and even if you met him by chance, as
I said, he won't remember you." Then she looked
closely at Eddie and asked softly, "You didn't
speak to him, did you?"
"No," replied Eddie. "Of course not."
"And did he see you?"
"No." Eddie wasn't sure if Dominic had seen
him or not. Probably not. "Well, that's OK
then," Lynn said, but she knew it was an unhelpful
thing to say.
"It's not OK, Lynn. It's not OK at all. That
man is back."
"He's not back. Try to calm down."
"Calm down?!" said Eddie, raising his voice
and standing up. "We lost everything because
of him, Lynn, everything - he cheated and
bullied and took it all away!"
"Yes, I know, Ed, but it was sixteen years
ago. We've come a long way since then. You
and Clive have each just put ten million quid
in the bank!"
"So what? Dominic got away with it all at
Fenton's!"
"It's all in the past. It doesn't matter anymore."
"It does matter. He's still getting away with
it. He still looks very pleased with himself."
"You don't know that. You don't know his life
now. I can't believe we're talking about all
this after so long."
"Because he's here, Lynn. On the ship. On
our cruise!"
"Eddie, listen to me. Calm down. He and Neal
gave you a bad time, I know. But you fought
back and survived, and you became successful
anyway. Without him. In spite of him and the
things he said and did. You're here with me
now, on holiday, with financial security for
the rest of our lives. You did it. You climbed
back out of the hole and it's OK. He can't
hurt you anymore."
"He nearly destroyed us, Lynn."
"But he didn't, did he? We didn't let him."
Eddie wiped the tears from his eyes. "I can't
believe he's on board! Why? He's still out
there getting in the way. Spoiling everything."
"He's not spoiling anything. Only if you let
him. You've come a long way since he pushed
you out."
"So why do I suddenly feel so angry? I can't
believe it. I think of him and those days
at Fenton's from time to time, sometimes a
lot, and it never upsets me.
"Well, you went through a tough time. It was
very hard. If you really did see him tonight,
of course that's going to upset you. It's
not the same as the occasional memory."
"Oh, I saw him all right. He still smokes
those hideous cigars."
"OK," said Lynn.
"You went through it too, you know," he reminded
her.
"I know."
Another pause.
"We lost so much, Lynn: the house, the money.
Us. I was off sick for a year. A year!"
"I know," said Lynn. "There's no getting away
from the damage the man caused. But you have
to calm down. Nothing is going to happen.
You don't have to see him again or talk to
him."
"Well, what if he takes the same excursion
as us at some point? Or sits at our table
for dinner?"
"Eddie, there are almost 2,000 people on board.
It won't happen. We can ignore him. Being
the sort of person Dominic is, he's probably
treated lots of people the way he treated
you, so he won't know who you are or remember
what he did."
"Somehow that makes it worse."
"Well, there's nothing we can do about it.
If we see him again or he even recognizes
you, we'll cross that bridge when we come
to it, all right?"
Eddie was quiet.
"All right?" Lynn repeated, holding his face
in her hands.
"OK," said Eddie.
CHAPTER FOUR
After the argument
Eddie sat in a cafe not far from the office,
dipping his teaspoon into a large cappuccino,
and tried to think of what he could do about
his job. He could leave, but that would mean
giving in and letting Dominic have exactly
what he wanted. Besides, it would take several
months, possibly a year, to find another good
job, and he would still have to put up with
him in the meantime. He could officially complain
about Dominic's behavior. He had a strong
case. But that would only make things worse.
Somehow Dominic had Gary, the CEO, on his
side. And Ann Blake, the Financial Director,
would never support getting rid of Dominic,
since she had hired him in the first place.
"He's unbelievable. He actually said I was
too hands-on," said Eddie, stabbing at his
drink with his spoon.
"Really?" said Clive, who had left the office
and found Eddie sitting in the cafe.
"Yes. He also said I wasn't a leader and that
Moscow was his deal."
"You're joking," said Clive. He seemed genuinely
surprised. "That deal was yours. Everyone
knows that."
"Then he said my communication wasn't good
enough."
"Eh? He can talk. He's got no people skills
whatsoever. Anyway, he never reads his emails."
"I know. I told him that. He says I should
phone him," and Eddie laughed in disgust.
"He's never there!"
"Exactly! I said that too. It's pointless,
Clive. He doesn't listen and he interrupts
all the time. He's so smug. He thinks he's
right about everything."
"At least you're not alone. Everyone has the
same problem with him."
"Well, what is his problem?"
"It's obvious. He's insecure."
"Well, it's not obvious when you're sitting
in a meeting with him."
"He's a bully in a shirt and tie. All bullies
are insecure. Maybe his dad didn't show him
any love. Maybe his dad's worse!"
Eddie tried to smile as he looked out of the
window, as if the answer were out there somewhere.
Maybe if he were to look long enough, the
answer would come and find him. He doubted
it. He was exhausted.
"Clive, how do they get to be in charge, these
people? They're utterly useless. He's useless."
"Yes, and he knows it. Deep down. That's why
he picks on people and moves responsibility.
No one actually knows what he does."
"Yeah, and by the time they find out they
have to pay him a year's salary, and then
he gets another job."
"That's his skill, though. He talks well to
the top guys. But the real people don't respect
him. I spoke to someone at Gallagher's the
other week, where Dominic worked for about
two years. They said the same thing."
"Do you think he has any idea what people
really think and say about him?"
"No, I don't think he does. He's so superior
in his own mind he probably thinks we're all
losers."
"But he knows I'm good. He knows you're good
too, and that really irritates him, because
we know this job and he doesn't. He just moves
tasks and people around all day and calls
it strategy."
"I know," said Clive.
They both stared out of the window.
"Did you hear what he said to Steve the other
day?" asked Clive. "No, what?"
"'Dominic told Steve that he got the top job
because Ann and Gary saw him as a wise ambassador.'"
"Wise? Ambassador? Ambassador for what?"
"Who knows? He's in his own dream world."
"Did he really say that?"
"Yes. And when Steve questioned it, Dominic
then said he was older than anyone else anyway."
"Unbelievable."
"Who knows what he thinks? He's not like us.
I think that scares him."
"Where do these people come from?"
"I don't know, mate, but they soon move on.
We just have to hold on. Look on the bright
side - it couldn't get any worse."
But Eddie wasn't so sure. Eddie had the feeling
that things were going to get a lot worse.
And he was right.
Back at home, Eddie spent the evening trying
to catch up on the work he'd missed that afternoon,
and looking at the many emails he had sent
Dominic. It was a nightmare.
Again and again he considered walking away
from the job, but it hurt him more simply
to give up. Besides, he was enjoying the Moscow
project, and he had done so much work for
it. When he was in Moscow, he could get on
with things. He loved Russia and he loved
the people there. It was such a different
world from the UK; and the owners of Zariya,
Dima and Tatiana, always made him feel so
welcome. Over time Eddie had had to explain
to them some of the difficulties back in London,
and they had been very helpful. Eddie was
reading one of Dima's emails and smiling again
when Lynn walked into the room.
"Will you be much longer?" asked Lynn.
"Maybe. I'm behind on some deadlines, and
today's battle with Dominic didn't help."
"Just leave it now, Ed. Come to bed," said
Lynn.
"I can't. There's so much. Too much."
"There's always too much," Lynn replied. "It
will still be there in the morning. Give yourself
a break."
"Yeah, well, that's true, but with Dominic
I have to be extra careful. He picks on everything."
"He's an idiot."
"Yeah, I know it, and you know it, and everyone
else knows it, but he's still the boss."
"Well, what I mean is just ignore him."
"How can I ignore him, Lynn? He's the boss!
He runs the division. He runs me."
"Well, don't let him," said Lynn.
"I'm not letting him!" shouted Eddie. "I'm
trying to stop him. That's the problem!"
"There's no need to shout, Eddie. I'm not
deaf."
"Well, you're not being very helpful."
"Thanks a lot," she said sarcastically. "I'm
doing my best."
"Sorry. I was hired to build a team, win a
project like the one in Moscow and make things
profitable. He was brought in to oversee the
whole division. Then he gets bonuses for doing
very little, and I get the blame when the
numbers suddenly don't add up."
"Your numbers are fine."
"Not according to Dominic."
"Why?"
"Oh, well, during our useless meeting today,
he brought up that old story about being 25,000
pounds over budget, when everyone knows he
fixed the numbers. Somehow he gets his bonuses
and puts any blame on me. I'm almost certain
now that he wants me out, Lynn."
"Surely not. He needs you. If it weren't for
you, good people would have left ages ago.
Besides, who else could move Russia along?"
"Oh, don't mention Russia."
"Why? That's your big success story."
"Oh, he keeps going on about the fact that
he won the Moscow contract, not me."
"What? That's just not true."
"I know."
"What about Ann and Gary? Can't you talk to
them about all this?"
"They've changed, Lynn. I've hardly seen them
since the new partners came in. Besides, Gary
and Dominic are always playing golf at the
weekends. Ann's OK still, but she's very political,
and I think she's embarrassed that Dominic's
upsetting everyone. After all, she was the
one who recruited him."
'And Human Resources? Can't you report him
to them?"
"What do I tell them? That he's got the people
skills of a goat!"
"Well, that's one thing. And the intimidation,
the lies and the..." It's very hard to prove,
Lynn. He's got his back covered, and they
would only report the whole thing to Ann and
Gary. And then what?"
"Well, presumably they tell Dominic and you
all get together and sort it out."
"Easy, really. Why didn't I think of that?"
"You know what I mean, Eddie. There's no need
to be sarcastic. I'm only trying to help.
I hate it when you're like this."
"Well, you're not living in the real world,
are you, Lynn? You're a Primary school teacher,
for goodness' sake. If things go wrong, you
all get into a circle and sing a song about
it. Or draw a picture. It's not that simple
when you're in a multi-million pound business
and..."
But Lynn had heard enough.
She was already leaving the room. Eddie stared
back at the open screen on his laptop at hundreds
and hundreds of emails. He thought about how
much more he had to do before he could go
to bed, about the hurt he had caused Lynn
and about the injustice of Dominic and of
people like him.
Eddie slammed down the laptop lid.
The job was broken, the evening was broken,
and now his relationship was broken.
CHAPTER FIVE
Eddie's dream
Although the sea was calm, Eddie didn't sleep
well. He had a dream that seemed to last all
night.
It began with him lying in bed in the cabin
of the ship, and waking up to find himself
in his old bedroom from his childhood. But
the bedroom was on the ship. He sat up in
the top bunk of some familiar bunk beds. In
the bottom bunk should have been his sister
Ellen, but he knew his wife was the occupant
now. The bottom bunk was empty, however, and
he saw water coming in quietly but rapidly
under the door.
In his dream, he jumped out of his bunk and
straight into half a meter of water. It was
ice-cold and Eddie gasped in shock. He was
wearing a grey suit and black shoes, but no
socks, shirt or tie. With his feet already
going numb in the cold water, he opened the
small wardrobe to look for them and found
a public telephone. Business cards were stuck
all over the wall. He noticed his own from
years ago with the familiar Fentons logo.
But his details were in Russian.
His stomach was tight.
His head ached.
In his dreaming mind, a thousand tasks and
deadlines seemed to weigh upon his shoulders.
The phone started ringing. He picked it up.
"Where are you?" a voice shouted on the other
end.
It was Dominic.
"The unmistakable, cold, demanding tone of
voice: "Do you know what time it is?"
Eddie lifted the sleeve of his suit to look
at his watch, but its face was frosted over
and unclear. Water had got into it somehow.
The hands were barely visible.
"I can't tell," he heard himself say.
"You can't tell the time? Typical! What's
the matter with you? We're all waiting for
you. Come on."
"Who's waiting for me? Where are you?"
Eddie heard laughter in the background.
"On the bridge. Where do you think?" Then
the line went dead.
The water was up to Eddie's knees now, and
rising fast. He decided to leave the socks,
shirt and tie and make his way to the bridge
- dressed or not dressed. How much worse could
it be?
As Eddie opened the door, water poured in
at waist level, and with it thousands of champagne
glasses. Most of them were intact, but many
were broken. Too many for Eddie to avoid.
His chest and legs were cut many times as
he waded out into the corridor.
He saw Clive at the far end.
"Clive!" he shouted. "Clive, it's me! Over
here!"
But Clive didn't hear him. He, too, was struggling
with the strong current of water dragging
him down and away at the far end of the corridor.
"CLIVE!" shouted Eddie in his sleep.
Opposite Eddie in the dream was a metal ladder
which went up to the next level of the ship
through a small hole. It was big enough for
him to get through. This ladder led to another
ladder and another hole. And another. And
another. Ladders stretched all the way in
a giant tunnel leading upwards. Eddie climbed
and climbed. He could hear the laughter getting
louder, so he decided to follow the sound.
When he reached the top, he suddenly found
himself on the ship's funnel. It was dark,
and a strong sea wind took his breath away.
He was scared and excited at the same time.
He thought the funnel would be hot, but it
was not. It was at an angle, and he was looking
up into the sky, almost touching the stars
themselves.
"They're stars, Lynn. Not lights. You were
wrong," he shouted again (in reality, his
shouting woke Lynn up).
Then he looked around and saw that the front
part of the ship was already underwater and
the ship was sinking.
"Lynn!" he shouted. This time it was a scream.
That was when he slipped and fell and, in
his sleep, flung out his arms to save himself.
But there was no impact. Instead he was now
standing on the bridge of the ship, which
was full of people from work - from his days
at Fenton's. People he hadn't thought of in
all this time. People he thought he'd never
remember again. People he certainly didn't
want to see again.
Ann and Gary were there, but they were behind
Dominic, who stood by the wheel in his captain's
uniform staring at him. He was older now and
heavier. The way Eddie had seen him at the
bar.
"Glad you could join us. We're only sinking,
you know!"
"What's going on?" said Eddie, looking around.
The jazz band was playing in the corner, but
the female singer was not the girl he had
seen earlier. Instead it was Lynn. Singing
a song whose name escaped him.
"Lynn?"
She didn't look at him. She was looking away
and singing.
"LYNN! What are you doing here?" shouted Eddie,
confused and frightened.
"I'm the captain. What does it look like?"
said Dominic.
"No. Not you. Lynn. What's she doing here?"
She wasn't paying him any attention.
More and more people were coming on to the
bridge. He saw Dima and Tatiana. They spoke
in Russian. Eddie couldn't hear them over
the laughter of the crowd.
"Ssh. I can't hear what they're saying. And
I can't remember the name of the song."
"Never mind that, Eddie. We've got more important
things to do."
"What?"
Laughter.
"We're sinking, no thanks to you."
"Why? What have I done?"
More laughter from the crowd.
A familiar face appeared. It was Neal.
"Champagne glasses, Eddie. Champagne glasses,"
he said.
"What about them?"
What about them?" shouted Dominic. "They put
a hole in the ship, you fool."
"That's impossible." Fear filled Eddie's mind
and body.
"Oh, really? Take a look around. Glass everywhere.
Holes in the side of my ship."
"It's not your ship!" protested Eddie.
"Who cares? We'll be underwater in ten minutes.
Fifteen at the most," added Neal.
"Shut up, Neal. You're only here because of
Dominic."
Then he heard a loud buzzing.
A giant helicopter arrived and flew over the
front decks. And another. Three, four, five.
Dozens. Like bees around a beehive. Buzzing,
louder and louder. They flew around and shone
powerful lights on to the bridge. So many
lights. The noise and lights were unbearable.
Then sirens. Police sirens. People screaming.
Eddie covered his ears and shut his eyes.
He cried out: "LYNN!"
The noise lessened but the lights were bright,
so bright. He was trying to open his eyes,
but he couldn't. Now someone was pulling at
his arms.
"Let me go! Let me go!" he shouted.
"Eddie..." Lynn said, trying to wake him up.
"Lynn?" His eyes were opening. It was so bright.
"It's all right, I'm here," she said, holding
him.
"We've got to get off! We're sinking!"
"It's all right," she said again.
Then his eyes opened and he was finally awake.
CHAPTER SIX
Another bad meeting
The next morning Eddie woke early and his
mind was racing. The house was quiet and there
was little traffic outside. He felt like he
hadn't been to sleep at all, and he was still
angry.
Lynn was still asleep. It was 5.50 a.m. He
listened to the radio for a while until he
heard the news, and then he got up, had a
shower and got dressed. By 6.45 a.m. he was
ready for work and quickly said goodbye to
Lynn before walking to the station to get
the train into central London.
The train was full, but Eddie managed to get
a seat by the window. It was a fast train
with only a couple of stops before Paddington.
As the train picked up speed and aimed for
the city, Eddie looked out at the fields and
industrial estates passing by. He took deep
breaths and tried to calm himself before the
day started. He thought about his conference
call with Moscow at 9.30 a.m., his scheduled
sales meeting at 12 noon, and a lunch appointment
at 1.30 p.m. with Neal Skinner in Production.
Then he was hoping to block off a couple of
hours in the afternoon to catch up on emails
and paperwork.
He got to the office at 8.15 a.m. and sat
at his desk with a double espresso and a bagel.
As his PC started up, Eddie sorted through
some of his papers and wrote a quick to do
list for the day ahead. He logged on to his
email and took care of a few basic queries,
before noticing that Dominic had sent a meeting
schedule for 10 a.m. There was no subject
heading. Eddie saw that it clashed with his
Moscow call, so he rejected it and suggested
rescheduling for 11 a.m., and wrote a line
to ask what the meeting was about. To support
his message, he mentioned that he had an important
call at 9.30 a.m. and asked Dominic for his
patience in the matter. It annoyed him to
think that his day with Dominic was already
starting on a negative note, but he tried
to put it to the back of his mind.
By 9 a.m. the open-plan office was filling
up, and Maxine, Paula and Gavin arrived, who
all worked in Eddie's department and sat near
him in the office.
"Hi, Ed! How's it going?" asked Paula.
"Fine, thanks," replied Eddie.
"How was the meeting with Dominic yesterday?"
asked Gavin. "Oh, well, you know. A challenge,
shall we say," said Eddie, trying to smile
and not give too much away.
"I bet it was. Rather you than me, mate,"
said Gavin. Eddie knew that Gavin and the
team were on his side, but what could they
do?
Eddie went back to dealing with his emails
and preparing for the call to Moscow at 9.30
a.m.
At 9.20 a.m. his phone rang. It was Dominic.
"Did you get the meeting schedule I sent?
10 a.m. this morning."
"Yes, I replied. I can't do that time. I've
got a call at 9.30 with Dima and his team
in Moscow. I'm dialing in Adam in IT, who
needs an update on the platform they're using
for the new software."
"It's too early for IT. Why are you bothering
them with this?"
"Because we need their input on..."
"Look, Eddie. Forget IT and forget your call.
Do it tomorrow."
"I can't. It's taken ages to find a time when
we can all..."
"You and I have a meeting at 10."
"What about?"
"Let's discuss that then. OK?" Dominic hung
up.
Eddie glanced around and noticed Maxine looking
at him.
"You OK?" she asked.
"Not really. Max, can you get hold of Dima
for me and ask if he can reschedule the call
for any time this afternoon?"
"He won't like it," she said.
"I know. Tell him I'm really sorry, and tell
him Dominic has to see me at 10 a.m. Tell
him I didn't have any warning. He'll understand."
Eddie tried to smile again. This smile was
more fake than the last, and Maxine could
see it.
"OK," she said.
Eddie calmly got up out of his seat and walked
across to the far side of the office floor,
took the lift upstairs and went into the gents'
toilet. It was empty.
He went to the sink, turned on the cold tap,
collected water in his cupped hands and splashed
it on his face to freshen up. The situation
was impossible, he thought. Eddie felt he
could no longer do his job.
For a moment or two he stayed where he was,
leaning over the sink, staring at the pouring
water and watching it go down the plughole.
Then he looked up, reached for some towels
and dried his face.
At that moment the phone in his pocket announced
the arrival of a text with the sound of a
mystical harp. It was from Lynn.
sorry about last night, hope u r ok. stay
strong. D is a useless robot and he knows
it. love u. L. x
Eddie smiled and punched back a quick reply:
thanks, love u 2. X
The text and cold water seemed to give Eddie
enough strength to go back and face another
meeting with Dominic. It was almost ten o'clock.
He had enough time to grab a coffee before
going to Dominic's office.
Eddie knocked on the door, walked in and sat
down. Dominic was engrossed in something on
his PC. Without looking up he muttered, "I'll
be with you in a moment," and spent the next
five minutes doing more work and ignoring
Eddie. He even made a phone call to someone
Eddie had never heard of. Eventually, Dominic
turned his attention away from his computer
and on to Eddie.
"Right. What's the latest from Moscow?"
"I haven't called them yet."
"Why not?" Dominic's tone was sharp. Eddie
was always amazed at how unpleasant and cold
this man was. Was he like this at home? What
kind of friends did he have? Did he have any
friends?
"I had a call planned for this morning at
9.30, but you asked me to change it so that
we could have this meeting."
"So when are you talking to them?"
"I don't know yet," said Eddie.
"You need to get a call sorted as soon as
possible."
"Maxine's doing that now."
"Maxine shouldn't be doing that sort of thing.
She's only a temp."
"Well, she sometimes takes phone calls for
us in the office and sets UP meetings."
"She's not a secretary, Eddie, she's a student!
She types in data. You can't ask her to phone
our biggest customers..."
Eddie's face was red, he could feel it. Already
things were out of control.
"She's only setting up a conference call,"
he said.
"Do it yourself," said Dominic impatiently.
"Fine," Eddie. It wasn't fine at all.
"And copy me in on the schedule. I want to
join the call."
"Why?"
"I want to find out when Dima's going to order
the rest of the software for all the offices
in the region."
"Dominic, please leave that to me. This call
is more for product training and looking at
any specific problems so far. I don't want
to distract him with pressure for more orders.
We have time for that."
"We don't have time, Eddie."
"Yes, we do. At least until my next visit
to Moscow. That's when we will be looking
at the next orders. As a matter of fact I've
got a meeting with Neal in Production today
to look at costs."
There was a knock on the door and Neal Skinner,
Head of Production, walked into the office.
"Well, well. Here he is!" said Dominic. "Come
in, Neal. We were just talking about you."
"Nothing bad, I hope," said Neal. His smile
was insincere.
He was a very tall, thin man who always looked
pale and wore dull suits. The Grey Man, they
called him in the office. Neal was Eddie's
main contact in Production for all things
related to the Moscow project.
He was a cold character who took himself very
seriously and had little sense of humor. Like
Dominic, he had a superior manner and was
stubborn. When engaged in conversation he
looked at the other person critically, judging
them negatively. Neal always tried to give
the impression that he knew everyone and that
he was in charge, but it was clear he was
not really comfortable in his role and didn't
really know what he was doing. He hid behind
business jargon, name-dropping and things
he had learned from going on too many training
courses. But bosses liked him. Employees and
customers did not. They thought he was a waste
of time. Eddie knew he was a waste of time.
"Neal, thanks for joining us."
"No problem," Neal replied. So agreeable.
So good with a boss around. Neal crossed his
long legs and folded his arms.
Eddie now had a feeling that this meeting
had been arranged, and that Neal was part
of it. It was no coincidence that he had turned
up at that point.
"Did you see the match last night?" Neal asked
Dominic. Still no smile.
"No, I missed it. I heard that new defender
Slater scored an own goal and saved us. That
was very kind, thank you."
"We're still five points ahead of you, though."
"Not for long. You've got Chelsea on Saturday,
and then you're away to Liverpool the following
week."
"Gentlemen," interrupted Eddie, "if it's OK
with you... could we get back to business?"
"The thing is, Eddie," said Dominic, "we need
more people on the Moscow account..."
Eddie wasn't sure where this was going, but
he was slightly encouraged by the possibility
of getting more assistance. "Right. That's
good," he said, trying to be positive. "We're
short-staffed, as you know, and we could use
more help." But he still wasn't sure why Neal
was there - he remained still and quiet, looking
first at Dominic and then at Eddie.
"... so Neal has agreed to take charge and
give you guys a hand." Dominic looked back
at his computer screen, then tapped something
on his keyboard. Eddie looked at Neal.
"Take charge of what, exactly?" he asked,
looking back at Dominic.
"Take charge of the account. In Moscow." Dominic
gave a little laugh.
Eddie went cold. He could feel the sharp blade
of realization enter his back. "Are you moving
to Moscow, Neal?" he asked, confused but hopeful.
"No, mate. I'm staying in London." Neal smiled
his superior smile.
Eddie did not like the sound of this. He didn't
like being laughed at either.
Eddie turned his attention to Dominic. "Dominic,
I don't quite follow. What's going on?"
"I've decided to make some changes in the
team. Neal has a lot of experience in this
field, so you will report to him. He is now
Head of Product and Business Development.
It's a new position."
Neal kept his eyes on Dominic the whole time.
He looked very pleased with himself, as if
he was waiting to be given a trophy of some
sort.
'It makes sense, Eddie. Really," said Neal.
"I'm not interested in your opinion," snapped
Eddie. He was trying to stay calm but inside
he was ready to explode. He tried to keep
his voice steady. He leaned forward on Dominic's
desk and looked him in the eye.
"So what's my position?" he asked.
CHAPTER SEVEN
An encounter in Barbados
The Parvina docked quietly at Bridgetown,
Barbados, at 7.20 a.m. Eddie and Lynn were
already awake and they lay in bed listening
to the radio. At 7.30 there was a knock on
the door.
"Good morning. Breakfast," said the voice
outside.
Eddie got out of bed, almost believing he
would step into cold water once more, and
opened the door. A young, smiling man brought
in a large tray full of cereals, orange juice,
pastries and a cafeteria of coffee. Eddie
led him through the cabin to the balcony door,
which he opened. The humid air struck him
immediately.
"Phew, it's warm. Leave the tray inside,"
he said to the man. "Thanks." Eddie gave him
a few dollars and the man left.
Eddie looked out across the harbour view to
where blue sea met white sand, to the houses
dotted about the town, and to the green palm
trees inland. Market stalls were already being
set up near the ship, where locals could sell
souvenirs and fruit to the passengers. Eddie
heard the distinctive metallic sound of a
steel band and saw five boys playing down
below. He could see at least three other ships
in the harbour. Given his nightmare, he really
appreciated the fact that this was the reality.
"Good morning, Mrs Millionaire. Another day
in paradise," he said.
"What's for breakfast?" asked Lynn, yawning.
"Get up and have a look."
"You seem very awake and lively," she said.
"Yes, well, after last night's trip to hell
and back, this comes as a relief."
"You were in a terrible state. Do you remember?"
"Yes. I'm trying not to think about it," said
Eddie. And he really was trying not to think
about it - about the dream, about Dominic
Stephens, about the real nightmare of sixteen
years ago. But he knew it wouldn't be easy.
"Damn him," he said under his breath.
Lynn and Eddie had decided to do different
things that day. Eddie had chosen to go on
a catamaran and snorkeling trip in the morning,
while Lynn had booked tennis lessons. They
took a taxi to the Tropical Beach Hotel and
Spa, where they were welcomed with fruit punch
and given a short talk about the area by one
of the hotel guides.
The catamaran was scheduled to depart from
the hotel's private beach at 10.30 a.m., and
Eddie put on his life jacket and joined several
other passengers and hotel guests for the
two-hour trip. He was given a mask, snorkel
and fins, and he waved to Lynn as he walked
down to where the boat was tied up. He was
carrying his deck shoes and had a towel in
his hand as he made his way, barefoot, across
the fine, smooth sand.
As he waited his turn to get on board, he
looked down at his feet in the warm, green
water and thought again about the nightmare
and about Dominic. He wondered where Dominic
was today. Was he on a trip? Was he even still
on board?
In the taxi on the way to the hotel, Eddie
had worried that Dominic would be on the same
excursion. But how likely was it that he would
meet him? He started feeling angry again that
Dominic was on the ship. And that he still
existed at all.
In spite of this, Eddie was able to relax
during the boat trip. After an hour of sailing
around the bay and past some spectacular beaches
and coves, the catamaran dropped anchor and
the small group went snorkeling near an old
shipwreck. They watched and fed some stingrays,
and Eddie enjoyed the calming effect of being
below the surface and in a very different
world underwater. He was a good swimmer and
very fit. He had swum for his school and his
university, and he had won medals for long-distance
swimming. Even now, at home, he tried to get
to the local pool at least twice a week.
When he got back to the beach hotel, he was
feeling tired but refreshed. He'd caught the
sun too, and his forehead and nose were burnt.
He found Lynn sitting on a sun lounger by
a small pool with fountains. She was reading
and sipping another fruit punch.
"Hello, you. I thought I'd find you here,"
he said.
"Oh, hi. How was it?"
"Brilliant."
"You've caught the sun."
"I know. I forgot to take some decent sun
block. I borrowed some off the guys on the
boat, but I think it was too late."
"Here," she said, reaching for some cream
in her bag. "Use some of this." She passed
him a tube of cream and Eddie squeezed some
into his hand and rubbed it on his face.
"How was the tennis?" he asked.
"It was cancelled. The guy never turned up,
and it was too late to get another trainer."
"Really? That's not good. We've already paid
for it."
"I know," said Lynn, "but they're giving us
lunch for free instead, so I don't mind really.
I'm booked for tennis again in St Lucia in
a few days, so that's OK."
He mocked her: "Listen to you! I 'm booked
for tennis again in St Lucia in a few days,
she says, sipping her cocktail." Then he said,
"This is the life, eh?"
"It certainly is. Oh, look, here's Jen."
"Who's Jen?" asked Eddie, looking around.
He thought she looked familiar.
"She was booked for the tennis as well, so
we came here for a drink instead and we started
chatting. You'll never guess who she is."
"I know her, don't I?" asked Eddie.
"Yes and no. The same thing happened to me
when I first saw her."
"She's from the ship. She must be," he said.
Jen was almost at the pool where they were
sitting.
"Yes. Not only that. She's the singer in the
band!"
"Oh yes!" said Eddie, turning to meet her.
She had on wide sunglasses and a baseball
cap. She wore a colourful sarong with palm
tree patterns, and her T-shirt was orange
with a black saxophone logo. She was carrying
a drink in one hand and a cigarette in the
other.
"Hi, Lynn. Is this your man then?" asked Jen.
"Yes, this is Eddie. Eddie, this is Jen."
"Nice to meet you, Jen," Eddie said, shaking
her hand.
"Likewise," she said. "How was the boat trip?"
"Great, thanks. They took us around some fabulous
beaches. Then we stopped and swam off the
reef near an old shipwreck."
"Cool!" said Jen.
"Some stingrays came by and we were given
some food for them."
"Oh, I'd love to do that, but I'd be terrified,"
said Jen.
"They're not that dangerous actually, although
they can give you a nasty bite."
"Ugh!" said Lynn.
"Or sting with their tail," added Jen.
"Yeah, well, that's true. It's rare, though,"
said Eddie. "That usually happens if you stand
on one when they're buried in the sand in
shallow water."
"Aren't you afraid of sharks?" asked Jen,
lifting up her sunglasses.
"I try not to stand on sharks," said Eddie,
smiling.
"You know what I mean."
"There weren't any in the area we were in,"
said Eddie, sitting down on a sun lounger
next to his wife.
"How do you know?" asked Lynn.
"Well, you don't. You have to hope that there
aren't any."
"You must be mad," said Jen.
"It's worth it. The fish you can see near
the reef are so beautiful."
"Well, Jen and I have been doing as little
as possible, haven't we, Jen?"
"Absolutely," said Jen, sitting back on her
lounger and sipping her drink.
"So, no tennis, then?" asked Eddie.
"No," said Jen. "But we get a free lunch,"
she added.
"So I heard," said Eddie. "What are you doing
later?"
"Well, my partner will be here soon and we're
booked to go on the Island Safari."
"Oh, I saw that in the brochure," said Lynn.
"Is that the trip where you get a private
jeep and go around the island and see the
Wildlife Reserve?"
"Yes, that's it. I love all the animal trips.
I can't wait. Dominic isn't keen at all, but
he says he doesn't mind as long as he gets
his golf, Typical! It's like he's married
to the stupid game. I find it so dull. He
loves it, though. Do you play golf, Eddie?"
CHAPTER EIGHT
Eddie's departure
"So, what's your position?" asked Clive later
that evening at Eddie house. Eddie had come
straight home after the meeting and no one
had been able to reach him. Clive had been
worried, and so he ha called in to see Eddie
after work.
"That's what I said," replied Eddie.
"And what did he say?" asked Clive.
Lynn, clearly angry and upset, interrupted
at this point to add, "Oh Clive, listen to
this..."
Eddie was trying to stay calm. He was in shock.
"He couldn't give me a straight answer. He
went on and on about budget control, an Neal's
experience in Austria when he was with Gallagher's."
"Neal doesn't do anything. And Austria is
very different from Russia. Doesn't he realize
that? This project is completely different."
"I know, Clive, I said all that. There was
nothing I could say. When I got a chance to
speak, he either didn't listen or simply interrupted.
Or Neal joined in with a useless reason to
justify himself. It was pathetic to watch."
"No one at Gallagher's has a good word to
say about Neal, or the work he did in Austria.
In fact, the rumor is that he was sacked because
he messed it up. That's how he got into Fenton's
in the first place. He needed a job and Dominic
is an old mate of his from university. It
makes me sick."
"I know." That was all Eddie could say. He
was so tired. He rubbed his eyes.
"So there's no position for you?" asked Clive,
but he could see the answer coming.
"Right," said Eddie.
"They're making you redundant, then?"
"No."
Clive was confused, and Eddie could not bring
himself to say any more. So Lynn continued
for him. "They fired him," she said.
There was a brief silence.
"They what"
"Can you believe it? It's disgusting," said
Lynn.
Clive turned to Eddie. "I don't believe it,"
he said.
"Neither do I," said Eddie, staring into space.
"Fired for what?"
"He's using the issue about the 25,000 pounds
in last year's budget, but he also said I
was a negative influence on the project and
not hands-on enough'."
"You have got to be joking!" Neither Eddie
nor Lynn said anything. It was no joke.
"You're very hands-on. The other day he said
you were too hands-on, didn't he?"
"Exactly," said Eddie.
"And in what way are you negative? You are
more enthusiastic and positive than the two
of them put together," said Clive.
Eddie didn't say anything.
"He just wants a yes-man," continued Clive.
"Neal is the true corporate yes-man. He plays
the game and does what he's told. But he's
useless otherwise, and too frightened to say
anything and rock the boat."
"Who would want to be like that?"
"These guys think they're above everyone else.
It's as simple as that. They have no idea
what other people really think of them. They
either scare you so you won't tell them, or
they just talk over you in case they look
weak."
"Meanwhile, Neal gets a job and Eddie doesn't,"
said Lynn.
"It's funny, but I really don't care anymore,"
said Eddie. "They deserve each other. I don't
want to be a part of their grey world with
their grey suits and grey ideas. They have
no imagination. Only a selfish need to justify
themselves."
"They can't do this, surely?" Lynn asked Clive.
"They can and they have."
"But it's unfair dismissal. You can take them
to a tribunal."
"I'm not sure I can cope with that," said
Eddie.
"But you have to," said Lynn. "You've got
to fight it."
"All I do with him is fight. Now he has Neal
to do his fighting. And he says he has the
full support of Ann and Gary, so they're no
help."
"You should have played more golf, Ed," said
Clive sarcastically.
Eddie thought about that for a moment and
then said, "Now that I have no job, maybe
I'll have the time."
The next morning Eddie went into the office
early again to clear his desk. There were
only a few people there. He saw Adam from
IT, who came over to him. He noticed Eddie
was busy emptying drawers and throwing files
and old documents away.
"Hi, Ed, how's it going? Doing a spring clean?
Good man. Long live the paperless office!"
"Not exactly, Adam. I'm leaving, as a matter
of fact."
"No way!" he said. "I had no idea."
"Me neither," said Eddie, reaching for a folder
and glancing quickly at its contents. He got
halfway through and then threw the folder
into the bin.
"What's happened?"
"I was fired yesterday," said Eddie. The words
sounded unreal when they came out.
"What for?"
"Oh, it doesn't matter."
"You're one of the best people here, Ed. I
mean it."
"Thanks, Adam, but they don't want the best
here. They just want..." Eddie stopped for
a moment and looked across the office, deep
in thought. "You know what, Adam, I have absolutely
no idea what they want." He turned and looked
at Adam. "And do you know what the worst thing
is?"
"What?"
"They don't know either. My guess is they
just want to be in charge. Nothing else matters.
They just want to move people around and feel
important," said Eddie, slamming a cupboard
door shut and pushing his chair away from
the desk. "They don't think about the people,
their work, their customers. They don't care
about loyalty. They don't care about building
a business. They talk, have meetings and play
golf, but they don't know the business and
they know they need us to make it work."
"You know your problem," came a voice from
behind them. "You were never a corporate man,
Eddie."
It was Neal. Eddie was completely taken by
surprise. He was both embarrassed and furious
to see him standing there.
Adam started walking away. "Look, Ed, I'll
catch you later," he said. "Let's have a drink
before you go, OK?"
"Sure," said Eddie, who decided to ignore
Neal and finish clearing his desk.
"You need the skin of a crocodile in this
business, I'm telling you." Eddie tried to
ignore him and carried on throwing away files,
paper, software manuals. Everything.
"Besides," continued Neal, "Dominic needs
someone like me. Someone more... academic.
He needs someone who can talk to him." Eddie
stopped and looked at him. Was there no end
to Neal's patronizing arrogance?
"Neal, you're deceiving yourself. Dominic
wants a yes-man. Pure and simple. Now he's
got one. Congratulations."
"You're upset."
"No, really? Amazing. How did you guess?"
"Look, I don't have a problem with you. It's
nothing personal."
"That's so generous of you, Neal. I feel so
much better," said Eddie, moving up close
to him. He could smell Neal's stale cigarette
breath. "Well, I have a big problem with you,
and, believe it or not, I am taking this very
personally. I guess I'm human, not a crocodile.
What would you rather be?"
"I know how you feel," said Neal.
"You have no idea how I feel, and don't talk
to me about how to talk to people like Dominic.
He needs someone more academic, indeed. What
does that mean? And corporate. What is corporate?"
"You have to play the game, Eddie."
"Maybe. But I'm not interested if the end
result is turning into a grey yes-man like
you. Ask yourself the question: are you true
to yourself? I wonder."
"Nice, Eddie. Very professional," said Neal,
finally showing his irritation.
"And you know all about professional, do you?
Open your eyes. Really open your eyes. Listen
to what people say about you. You're deceiving
yourself and I actually feel sorry for you.
And if you want a second opinion, go and ask
people here or your old friends at Gallagher's."
Neal was walking away now, so Eddie shouted
after him: "Did they give you a good reference,
by the way? It wasn't redundancy, was it?"
Eddie carried on putting things in his bag
before sitting down to write an email to all
his customers and colleagues to inform them
of his departure.
CHAPTER NINE
The fight
As Dominic Stephens came out of the hotel
towards them, Eddie froze. He looked at Lynn
and her face said the same. Before they could
make an excuse to leave, Dominic was already
on the cafe terrace. His hair was grey and
combed back, and he was wearing white trousers,
grey golf shoes and a green polo shirt which
was too tight for his large stomach.
It was definitely Dominic. The same hard face
but now with a dark tan, though his chin and
cheeks were fuller than the last time Eddie
had seen him. He looked older and different.
"Hello, everyone. New friends, I see," he
said, putting out his hand. In a reflex action,
Eddie noticed his hand go out to shake Dominic's.
He instantly felt he had betrayed himself.
Dominic's handshake had not changed: his palm
at an angle, the fingers locked tight, difficult
to grip. Do Not Enter, it said.
Again, automatically, Eddie lifted his sunglasses
to be polite, but Dominic kept his on. Eddie
waited for the moment when Dominic would recognise
him. But he did not. This cannot be true,
he thought. Is this really Dominic? After
all this time, am I shaking hands with him
and he does not know me? He looked at Lynn,
who was shaking his hand, too. Eddie could
see that she was not comfortable either.
"Nice to meet you," she said, putting on her
best smile.
"How was the tennis?" Dominic asked, leaning
on the back of Jen's chair.
"Cancelled," she said. "Then I met Lynn and
we've been working hard on cocktails since
we got here."
"Ah, it's a hard life," he said.
Yes, thought Eddie. It can be very hard. And
some people make it harder. His head was quickly
filling up with flashes of memory. Angry words
and images.
"So, what are you guys going to do?" asked
Dominic.
"Er, we've got to get back to the ship," said
Eddie.
"I thought you were staying for the free lunch,"
said Jen.
"Ah, there's no such thing as a free lunch,
eh, Eddie?"
Eddie wasn't sure if Dominic had recognised
him. Maybe. Maybe not. Or maybe he was unsure
and was playing for time? He never showed
much emotion, and behind the dark glasses
he looked almost robotic.
"I don't really know," said Eddie. He was
still trying to recover from the shock of
Dominic standing there in front of him after
so long.
"Sure. I've been in business twenty-five years
and I can tell you no lunch is free."
"Right," said Eddie. "Right, well, nice to
meet you both."
"Come on," said Jen, "stay for lunch."
"No, really, I've had too much sun, I think,"
said Eddie.
"Well, we can sit in the shade," said Jen.
"No, I mean I don't feel too well," Eddie
said.
"Hmm..." said Dominic, finally lifting up
his glasses and having a good look at Eddie's
face, "... your nose is burnt, but you do
look quite pale otherwise. You look like you've
seen a ghost."
Eddie looked into Dominic's eyes. He did not
see any signs of recognition. He looked away.
"Right. Yes. Anyway. Lynn?" he said.
"Yes," she said, standing up. "I'm coming."
"Well, maybe we could meet for a drink after
I finish tonight?" asked Jen.
"She's a great singer, isn't she?" said Dominic.
"Yes," said Eddie.
"Wonderful," said Lynn.
'I'm off at about eleven, so I'll come over
to the bar and we can meet you both then."
"We'll see how Ed feels," said Lynn.
Sure. Well, tomorrow then? Or breakfast?"
Dominic was laughing. "We're stuck together
on the ship for the next two weeks, so there's
no getting away, is there?"
Eddie had never imagined Dominic on holiday.
He only remembered that Dominic always came
back from holidays complaining about the children.
"Ah, it's good to be back in the office,"
he used to say, "away, from the kids." Eddie
felt sorry for Dominic's family whenever he
heard him say that.
"What would his kids say if they heard him
say that?" Eddie had once asked Clive. "Why
did he have kids or a family at all if he
preferred to be in an office?"
"Because these guys like to be the center
of the universe, and kids and partners take
that away from them. Besides, family life
and kids are all about showing emotion, and
they find it too scary. That's why they hide
behind desks and power. Can you imagine Dominic
or Neal trying to be with their kids? They
don't know how. They probably didn't know
how to be with kids when they were kids."
"That's so sad," Eddie had said.
"They are sad. They've missed the best things
in life and think money and status are enough.
But they are so superior in their own minds
that they don't know it."
"So they're actually happy? Ignorance is happiness?"
"Maybe. I'm not so sure. How often do you
see these guys relax, laugh or even smile?"
"True."
"Well, there's your answer."
"Eddie?" Lynn's voice suddenly brought Eddie
back to reality. "Eddie? Are you coming?"
"Yeah. Sorry," he said. "See you guys later."
"Bye," said Jen and Dominic together.
Eddie and Lynn walked back through the hotel
to the taxis. As they went back to the port
and the ship, Lynn spoke first.
"Well?"
"He looks older. He's still got that arrogant
look. And he's put on a lot of weight." Eddie
glanced out of the window.
"Are they married, do you think? What happened
to his wife?"
"Don't know," said Eddie. "I hope she left
him. For her sake."
"I wonder what Jen is doing with a man like
him, then?"
"Goodness knows. He's old enough to be her
father."
The taxi moved along the harbour and passed
the yachts in the marina. Eddie was shaking
his head in disbelief.
"I don't believe it, Lynn," he said. "Can
you believe it?"
"No. But at least he doesn't remember you,"
she said, looking at him. Eddie kept staring
out of the window. "Do you think not?" he
said. "Oh, come on. It's over sixteen years,
Ed. If he had remembered you, he would have
said something - don't you think?"
"Not necessarily. You never know with him.
I never knew with him. He's a snake. A fat
snake now, of course. But still a snake."
"Maybe he's changed," said Lynn hopefully.
"I doubt it."
The taxi slowed down and stopped near the
gangway for the Parvina. They paid the driver
and got out.
"It doesn't matter if he's an angel now. I'll
never forgive him. The three things I hate
most in the world are arrogance, bullying
and betrayal. He's guilty of all three."
"Well, let's hope he doesn't remember you.
We don't have to see them anyway."
"He's with the singer of the ship's band,
Lynn - we'll see him every night!" Lynn walked
in silence on to the ship and into the reception
deck. What could she say?
That night Eddie and Lynn had dinner in the
main dining room, which was full, as it was
every night. As the sun went down and the
room got darker, Eddie found it harder to
see if Dominic was in the room or not. Throughout
dinner he had expected him to turn up, but
he was not there.
As they finished dessert and drank their coffee,
however, Dominic appeared and took a seat
at the bar to watch Jen.
"There he is," said Eddie.
"Oh yes. Well, maybe we could go back to the
cabin, or the casino."
"No, Lynn. We're not letting him push us around
again."
"But he'll soon see us and come over."
"I doubt it. He was always antisocial."
"Maybe he's changed."
"You keep saying that. People like him never
change."
Eddie sipped his coffee and said, "I think
I need to know for sure if he remembers me.
I'd feel a lot happier."
"But why, Ed? What good will that do?" she
asked.
"I can't explain."
"Eddie, please... Look, he's leaving anyway.
He's not going to bother us."
But Eddie had already got up from the table
and was walking over to the bar and the exit
to follow him.
He followed Dominic down the corridor and
past the Starlight Lounge, where people were
playing cards and reading. He followed him
through the door, out on to the side deck
and to the stern of the ship. It was dark,
and Eddie thought he had lost him. But then
he swelled the unmistakable cigar smoke and
he saw him. The earlier breeze had been replaced
by a strong wind and the sea was quite rough.
He noticed Dominic in a small area, alone,
sheltered from the wind, leaning on to the
rail and looking out to sea.
"Hello," said Eddie, walking up to him.
"Oh, hello there. Getting some fresh air?"
"I suppose so."
"Me too," said Dominic. "Feeling better?"
he asked.
"Yes, thanks."
They both looked out to sea together for a
long minute. Eddie broke the silence.
"You don't remember me, do you?" he asked,
looking at Dominic.
"Yes, I just asked if you were feeling better.
We met at the hotel today. Your wife's tennis
was cancelled."
"No, not here. Back home. At work."
"What do you mean?" asked Dominic, looking
at Eddie. "Where?"
Eddie knew Dominic had been in many companies.
Creeping his way in, then getting thrown out.
Dominic called them redundancies. Others knew
better.
"Fenton's."
Dominic looked at him and then looked harder,
using the light coming from the spotlight
on the wall. "What's your surname?" he asked.
"Munro."
Dominic appeared to be trying to remember.
"I was in sales. There was the big project
at Zariya in Moscow."
"Ah," said Dominic. "Eddie Munro. Yes." He
smoked his cigar some more, buying time. "When
was that?" he asked finally.
"Sixteen years ago."
"Wow, good memory," said Dominic.
"Not really..." said Eddie, "... you fired
me and it's not something one forgets."
"Did I?" and Dominic actually laughed. Over
the years Eddie had imagined meeting him again
and confronting him. He had never imagined
the man laughing.
"You did, yes. You found a way to blame me
for a budget loss of 25,000 pounds."
"It's a long time ago. I honestly can't remember,"
said Dominic, still smoking, looking back
at the sea. Eddie was staring at him. His
mouth was dry. He was trembling.
"Well, I remember."
"Good for you," said Dominic, and now his
tone was changing.
Less interested. Colder.
"Actually, I remember you were an incompetent
bully. You made my life miserable."
Dominic turned around and looked at Eddie.
"Is that so?" It was too dark to see if he
was angry or not. Eddie felt that the situation
was getting out of control, but there was
no turning back. The words were coming out
on their own.
"I was very successful at Fenton's," said
Dominic firmly, "and one reason was probably
because I was able to get rid of useless rubbish
like you."
"They fired you from there eventually, I heard.
Why was that?"
Dominic started walking away. "An interesting
reunion, my friend, but it's late and I'm
bored with this conversation. I suggest you
leave the past in the past and move on."
Eddie grabbed his arm. He felt Dominic's body
stiffen.
"Get your hands off me," Dominic said, putting
his cigar in his mouth to free his hand.
"I moved on, Dominic. I moved on after you
took away my job, my money, my peace of mind
and almost my wife."
Eddie was angry now. The words were not coming
out right any more.
"I've seen your wife, Eddie," Dominic said,
laughing. "I can tell you that you still need
to move on."
"What does that mean?" This time Eddie pushed
him against the rail of the ship and hit the
cigar out of Dominic's mouth. The light was
shining on Dominic's face, and Eddie saw a
mixture of surprise and anger.
"Hey! What is your problem?!" he shouted,
but they were out on deck in the wind and
darkness and it was like a whisper. Dominic
pushed back against the rail, but Eddie would
not let him move.
"You! You are my problem!" Eddie shouted.
He had no idea what he was doing any more.
He was scared, and angrier than he had been
for a long time.
"Move away, Eddie. This is unacceptable."
"Unacceptable? Unacceptable? Oh, really? So,
after all these years you know what is acceptable
and unacceptable. What you and Neal Skinner
did to me was unacceptable. The way you patronized
and intimidated me was unacceptable. You cheated
and lied. You were so smug, so superior."
"I was the boss. I made tough decisions. You
were a casualty. It happens in business. Sink
or swim, my friend. Get over it."
Without thinking, Eddie brought his knee hard
and fast up into Dominic's groin. Dominic
shouted out in shock and blinding pain, but
was able to push his hand hard into Eddie's
face. Eddie lost his balance for a moment,
giving Dominic time to stand up straight.
Dominic pushed Eddie in the chest, but Eddie
did not feel it. He was too busy getting his
hands around Dominic's neck. He squeezed and
squeezed, and Dominic tried to get himself
free. But he could not. Eddie's hands were
locked around Dominic's throat. He dug in
his nails to be sure. He pressed his thumbs.
Dominic was trying to speak, but he couldn't.
He choked out some words but Eddie could make
no sense of them.
"Just shut up! Shut up! You stupid... arrogant
man!" Eddie growled at him.
Eddie could finally see fear in Dominic's
face, which had gone pale, and his eyes stared
back at him. Eddie could see he was going
to pass out, so he loosened his grip. What
am I doing? he thought. This is madness.
But the moment he let go, pain suddenly shot
into Eddie's ear as Dominic threw a punch
to the right side of Eddie's head, and then
to his right side into his ribs. Eddie was
wild and angry once more, this time pushing
Dominic back on to the ship's rail. Hard against
the rail. Fast against the rail. Dominic shouting
in pain once more. Eddie punching and punching.
"OK, OK, enough, enough. Stop," pleaded Dominic,
his arms up in defense.
Eddie stopped. He loosened his grip again
and waited for a reaction from Dominic, but
none came. Eddie stood back and watched Dominic
try to stand up against the rail. Dominic
was holding his stomach and breathing heavily.
He coughed a couple of times. His head was
down.
Eddie was out of breath himself. He hadn't
been in a fight since he was fifteen. It felt
just the same even as an adult - tiring, frightening
and sore. That time there was a crowd watching.
This time there was no one.
"Don't come near me or speak to me again...
ever. Do you hear me?"
Dominic was still trying to get his breath.
Either he could not speak or he did not want
to. But he said nothing. Eddie took one last
look at him and backed away until he was at
a safe distance. Then he left the deck and
went back inside.
That was the last time anyone ever saw Dominic
Stephens.
CHAPTER TEN
Sinking not swimming
For a few days after his dismissal from Fenton's,
Eddie actually felt quite excited. He was
relieved. A great weight had been lifted from
his shoulders. But this feeling did not last
long, and he soon started to feel irritable
and, later on, angry.
For weeks he couldn't get Fenton's and Neal
and Dominic out of his mind. He thought over
and over again about the injustice of it all.
He thought about all the arguments and frustrations.
All the work he had done. All the work he
could have done. Wasted. He missed his colleagues
and a sense of belonging, and he missed going
to Russia and working with Dima and the team.
To cheer himself up, he tried to remind himself
that, apart from people like Dominic, there
were things he would not miss, like emails.
On the day Eddie left Fenton's for the last
time, there were over four hundred unanswered
emails in his inbox. Eddie always tried to
get back to people, but it had become impossible.
Every time he got rid of one email, a dozen
more would appear within half an hour. The
world had gone mad, he thought. At first,
like everyone else, Eddie had welcomed the
new form of communication. It was neat, cheap,
fast and flexible. But soon it dragged him
down. He didn't like to admit it, but Dominic
was right about not reading emails. They were
never-ending.
Dominic.
Back in his mind again.
Many times he had terrible thoughts about
what he would like to do to Dominic, and to
Neal for that matter. He thought of storming
into the office and using Dominic's own golf
clubs to smash up computers and break windows,
and then going into the car park and doing
his worst on Dominic's Mercedes. The shiny
paintwork, the windows - all slashed, scratched
and broken. It felt good but his conscience
would not let him.
In the end, he followed Lynn's advice, which
was to get out of the house more and go for
walks, or go swimming. Keep busy. Get some
exercise. They lived two miles from their
local sports center, so every morning Eddie
got up with Lynn and then walked through the
park to the pool at the sports center. He
made this his morning routine, but he couldn't
get used to being in a swimming pool on a
weekday morning at 10 a.m. He normally swam
after work, so it was strange for him to find
the pool almost empty, except for some elderly
swimmers and sometimes small school groups.
As he sat in the cafe afterwards, drinking
a coffee or two, he always felt better. He
wanted to stay there all day and hide. Then
his heart would sink at the thought of heading
home to nothing.
In fairness, Eddie had started looking for
jobs in the same week that he was fired. But
as depression set in, he lost interest and
motivation. Then, to his alarm, he lost confidence.
In a way, this was worse than the depression,
but these were all new feelings and he was
overwhelmed. Everything he had done seemed
meaningless, and he wondered how he would
ever do a serious job again.
He and Lynn had enough money saved to last
for about four months, but the time soon passed
and there were no vacancies. His chances with
the best companies in his sector were also
harmed by the news of his dismissal over the
budget fiasco.
By the time there were a couple of opportunities,
Eddie was physically unwell and his doctor
had agreed he was not fit for work. It took
time for sickness benefits to be paid, and
with the two of them living on Lynn's small
teaching salary the financial pressures grew.
Bills turned into reminders. Reminders turned
into final reminders. And final reminders
became phone calls from angry gas and electricity
companies, TV companies and insurance companies.
Then finally the bank called. Eddie was having
a bad day anyway. This was the last thing
he needed.
"Hello, Mr Munro, this is CNTS bank. May I
ask you some security questions?" said a young
male voice.
"Not really," said Eddie. He almost hung up
straight away.
"I just want to ask you some security questions
and then talk to you about your account,"
the voice insisted.
"Well, how do I know you're the bank? You
could be anyone," said Eddie. He had decided
to stay on the phone, but he wasn't going
to make it easy for the person at the other
end.
"I can assure you this is the CNTS bank calling."
"OK, then, well I can assure you that this
is Mr Munro. What do you want?"
"I can't do that, Mr Munro. I need to ask
some security questions."
"Well, my bank told me not to give my security
questions away."
"Mr Munro..."
"Ah, you don't know I am Mr Munro yet, do
you?" said Eddie. "When is your date of birth?"
"I'm not telling you that until you prove
you are the bank."
"All right, sir, ask me a question about your
account."
"OK, how much money is in my account?"
"I can't tell you that. I have to ask you
some security questions first." Eddie hung
up.
Thirty seconds later the phone rang again.
Eddie considered ignoring it, but he was bored
and was enjoying being in control for once.
"Hello?"
"Good morning, Mr Munro. This is CNTS bank..."
"Hi, how are you?"
The voice didn't know what to say for a moment,
but then sprang back into action. "I'm fine,
thank you, sir."
Eddie had to admit that the young man was
professional. If he was annoyed, he was hiding
it well. Eddie felt a little guilty - the
man was only doing his job. Then he thought
of Dominic and Neal and what bosses like them
would do to such youthful enthusiasm. He realized
that the voice was still speaking, but Eddie
wasn't paying attention. "Sorry? I wasn't
listening," he said.
"That's OK, sir. I was just saying that we
need to talk to you about your account, and
I can get my supervisor if you wish."
Eddie decided to give some ground. This was
getting boring.
"Go on, I believe you. You're CNTS bank. What
do you want?"
"Thank you, Mr Munro. I just need to ask you
some security questions. Is that OK?"
"Fine."
"Thank you. Can you confirm your telephone
banking password?"
"Chinatown."
"Thank you. And can you give me the second
and last numbers in your security code?"
"Eight and three."
"Thank you, Mr Munro."
"You're welcome."
"That completes the security with you."
"I'm so pleased."
"I was calling because your account had insufficient
funds to pay some direct debits this month,
and your credit card with us is now stopped
until you make further payments."
"Great. Thank you for telling me. Goodbye."
"No, Mr Munro. You are currently overdrawn
by 3,478.11 pounds, and the balance on your
credit card is 4,490.30 pounds I have to ask
if and when you will be making payments into
your account."
"I have no idea. I've lost my job and I can't
work. I'm thinking of doing the lottery on
Saturday, so give me a call on Monday and
I'll tell you if I can pay you or not. If
it helps, I'll enter my bank account number
and see if it wins."
"Mr Munro, my supervisor is here. He would
like to have a word with you. Would that be
OK?"
"Not really." Eddie hung up.
This time the phone did not ring again, which
surprised Eddie in a way. He walked slowly
into the kitchen, made a coffee, picked up
the newspaper and sat in an armchair to flick
through the pages to see what was on TV.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
After the fight
Eddie went back inside the ship and made his
way to the toilets, where he locked himself
inside a cubicle. He was shaking and sweating.
He sat down and put out his hands in front
of him, watching the shaking in fascination
and fear. He could feel the pain in his chest
now, and his ear was sore. He wiped his face
with the palm of his hand; there was blood
coming from his nose. He used some toilet
paper to stop the bleeding. He felt exhausted.
Eddie stayed where he was for about ten minutes.
The toilets were empty and no one else came
in during that time. He almost expected Dominic
to come in, and he imagined the fight starting
all over again. A struggle by the sinks, mirrors
breaking, doors slamming.
He decided to make his way back to the dining
room. He came out of the cubicle and looked
in the mirror to straighten his clothes and
his hair. The bleeding had stopped. He washed
his face.
The dance floor was full and the dining area
was being cleared. Lynn was at the table talking
to some other guests when Eddie found her.
"Hello, stranger," she said. "You took your
time. Where's Dominic?"
Eddie wasn't ready for a conversation about
this right now. "I couldn't find him."
"So where've you been all this time?"
"I went to get some fresh air, then I went
over to the Starlight Lounge and checked some
emails on the internet."
"Eddie, you're on holiday!" she said, putting
her arm around him.
"I know. Sorry."
"Come on, what do you want to drink?"
"I'll have a large scotch. No ice."
"Really?"
"Well, why not? We're on holiday." Eddie tried
to smile. His ear and nose were stinging.
His chest ached. Maybe he had a broken rib?
"OK. Wait here. I'll get them," she said,
and Eddie turned to watch the dancing and
the band. He was calmer now. The shock felt
less. He glanced over at the band and saw
Jen looking at him, and she gave a small wave.
He waved back, but suddenly wondered if she
was in fact waving to Dominic somehow. He
looked behind him, but Dominic wasn't there.
When Lynn came back, they had their drinks
and danced for a while. Eddie was tense the
whole time, waiting for Dominic to launch
a sudden attack on the table. Or maybe he
had gone back to his cabin to rest and would
wait until tomorrow or the next day to continue
the fight.
"I wonder where Dominic is?" said Lynn.
"No idea," said Eddie. "Come on. I'm tired.
Let's go to bed."
Even as they reached the cabin, Eddie was
looking around for Dominic, but he knew now
that he must have gone to his own cabin. He
felt relieved as they walked in, and he sat
down on the couch.
Lynn was looking in the mirror, taking off
her necklace and earrings. In the mirror she
watched Eddie sitting down. "You OK?" she
asked.
"Not really."
"What happened to your face?"
Eddie laughed briefly. He suddenly saw the
absurdity of it all. "I had a fight with Dominic,"
he said, looking at the bruises on his hands.
"You mean you had an argument?"
"No, I mean I had a fight. A proper fight.
You know, where people hit each other a few
times." He was trying to laugh again. But
the tears in his eyes and on his cheeks were
not happy ones. Lynn stopped what she was
doing and came to sit beside Eddie.
"You're shaking."
"Yeah."
"What happened?" she asked.
"To be honest, I can't really remember. It
all happened so fast. We were outside on deck
one minute, and the next I was trying to strangle
him." Eddie made a strangling gesture with
his hands, and again he saw that they were
shaking.
"What?"
"I know. I can't really believe it myself.
At one point I think he was going to pass
out. I almost pushed him over the side."
"Eddie!"
He was shaking his head.
"Was anyone watching all this? You must have
looked like madmen."
"No. It was just us. By the lifeboats."
"Where is he now?" asked Lynn.
"I don't know. I thought he followed me back
inside, but he must have gone back to his
cabin."
Lynn got Eddie a glass of water.
"Thanks," he said. "Sorry."
"I can't believe this. You're like a pair
of kids. It's one thing to find him on board,
but it's another to start fighting like kids
in a playground."
"He started it," said Eddie.
"Listen to yourself, Ed!"
"I know."
"Look, it's a shock that he's on the same
cruise, I admit, and I know it brings it all
back. But I thought the plan was to keep a
low profile now. Ignore him. Forget him."
"How can we forget him when he's on the same
cruise ship?"
"Well, we'll have to manage, and I suggest
we wait and see what happens. If he approaches
you at breakfast or something, don't get involved.
Apologise and walk away."
"Apologise?!"
"OK, well, maybe not apologise. Just ignore
him. Promise?"
"Yes, I promise," said Eddie.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Lynn and Eddie argue
Six months had passed since Eddie's departure
from Fenton's, and no work offers were coming
in. Summer was over and the evenings were
getting darker. Eddie had lost weight and
his relationship with Lynn was in a bad way.
Either they argued over most things or they
didn't speak at all.
One Thursday afternoon Lynn came in from work
and Eddie was sitting in his armchair as usual,
watching a TV show from America. A couple
and their neighbours were arguing over a dog.
Lynn was soaking wet. The rain was heavy outside.
"These people are so stupid," he said, not
looking up. "This guy says he can't sleep
because of his neighbours dog, and the neighbour
says the other guy's been shooting at it with
an air rifle!"
"It's OK. I'm fine, thanks. Don't get up,"
Lynn said, putting down heavy shopping bags
as she came through the front door.
"So this guy..." Eddie continued, "... the
guy with the dog, is suing the other guy for
a hundred thousand dollars in damages!"
Lynn was neither interested nor amused. She
took off her coat, picked up the bags and
went into the kitchen. On the way, she threw
the post on to the sofa.
"But the other guy - the guy with the gun
- he's suing the dog owner because he says
the dog barks all night and messes up his
garden."
Eddie knew he had already upset Lynn, but
he stayed where he was. She was always upset
these days. He decided to shout out the rest
of his commentary so that Lynn could hear
him in the kitchen.
"And now their wives are complaining that
the men are obsessed with arguing with each
other. They've been fighting over the dog
for three years, and now they both want a
divorce."
Eddie heard Lynn say something from the kitchen.
"What?" he shouted.
"Nothing."
"No, go on," he shouted. "What did you say?"
"Nothing. Go back to your show. It sounds
fascinating," she said. Eddie got up and went
to see her. "What's wrong?"
Lynn ignored him and started putting shopping
away in cupboards and in the fridge.
"What's wrong?" he asked again.
This time she stopped and looked at Eddie.
"Erm, well, let me see. I get up in the morning
and go to work while you sit and watch telly.
I come in from work, and you're still sitting
and watching telly. I do the shopping, I get
no help. I do the cooking, I get no help.
I try to talk to you, and I get nothing. You
used to have breakfast with me in the mornings,
and now you don't get up at all! We never
go out. Our friends don't call us. The house
is a mess, and you're here all day making
it messier. You don't clean up, you don't
tidy. You look a mess..."
"Thanks very much."
"... and I don't hear anything positive from
you about anything. Anything! I'm sick of
it."
There was a pause after she stopped.
"Bad day then?" he said.
"It's not funny, Eddie. I worry so much about
you, your job situation, money - and then
I go into work and I have at least twenty
- five kids in my class all day. I try to
keep them under control and happy, but I just
want to cry. I want to tell them all to shut
up. I want to tell them to enjoy drawing pictures
and singing songs, because after that life
is pointless."
"So, you did have a bad day."
"Bad year, Eddie. Bad year."
"So it's all my fault?"
"That is not what I mean."
"Yeah, right."
At that point, Lynn picked up a full box of
eggs and threw it at Eddie. He ducked just
in time, and the whole thing exploded on the
kitchen wall.
"I guess we can have omelets for dinner,"
said Eddie, but he knew things had gone too
far.
"You can have omelets for dinner. I'm going
out."
"Where to?"
"I'm going to Angela's."
"Angela's? That's two hours away. When will
you be back?"
"Saturday."
"Saturday?"
"Maybe Sunday. I don't know."
"Lynn, please."
"No, Eddie. I've had enough. We're broke - worse
than broke - we are in so much debt. You've
got no job and you can't get a job, or you
don't want one. I don't know."
"Lynn, listen to me."
"You sit in the house all day, feeling sorry
for yourself..."
"Lynn..."
She was crying now.
"... and it isn't getting better," she sobbed.
"It's getting worse and I hate it. I'm sorry
you lost your job, and I'm sorry it made you
ill. I'm sorry I'm not strong enough now,
but I can't help you anymore. I tried. I've
lost you. You're here, but you're not here.
I want a break. We want a break."
"No, Lynn. Please, we have to talk..."
"I'll call you when I get to Angela's."
She was walking out of the kitchen and into
the hall. She opened the door under the stairs
and took out an overnight bag. Eddie could
see she had already packed it.
"I don't believe this. You're leaving me?"
"No. I'll be back on Sunday. Maybe. I don't
know."
"This is ridiculous. You can't go. Lynn, we've
been together for ten years."
She was putting on her coat.
"What about your job?"
"I don't care about the job. You don't care
about work. Now I don't care about work."
She was walking down the hall towards the
front door. Eddie grabbed her arm.
"Get your hands off me."
"Lynn."
"Get your hands off me!"
He let go.
"Lynn, I'm sorry."
But she had walked out of the door and got
into her car, and was driving down the road.
Eddie stood in the doorway and watched the
car disappear. The rain had stopped, but the
clouds were ready for another storm. He went
back inside and the house felt very strange.
Panic was in his mind, heart and stomach.
The kitchen door was open, and he saw broken
eggs dripping off the clock and down the wall.
He sat down on the sofa. The neighbours were
still arguing about the dog, which was now
in the studio, and a dog psychologist was
trying to talk to it. This time last year
he was in Moscow working on the project of
his career with good money in the bank, and
he and Lynn had even discussed starting a
family. Now, he had lost his job, his money,
his health, his confidence, and even his wife.
Instead of taking the company to the next
level and building a future, he was sitting
in his lounge watching a dog in therapy.
He looked around for the remote control to
change channels, and saw the post. There were
some letters for Lynn, the new programme for
the theatre, more bills, and a letter from
Steve Scott, his solicitor. He knew what the
letter said before he opened it. It was the
result of many difficult meetings with his
solicitor and financial adviser. The letter
now confirmed that he was bankrupt.
Bankrupt.
A death.
The end of a life with money.
For a few more minutes Eddie watched two American
adults fighting and a dog being hypnotized.
Then he put the letter back in its envelope
and went into the kitchen to clean the eggs
off his kitchen wall.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The search
The next morning Eddie and Lynn walked into
the dining room and saw Jen having breakfast
with some members of the band. Two men in
uniform were also sitting at the table. They
were asking questions and taking notes. Eddie
assumed it was a discussion about the coming
evening's performance. He was relieved to
see that Dominic was nowhere to be seen. He
still didn't feel ready for the inevitable
second confrontation.
"She looks upset," said Lynn as they sat eating
their breakfast at a table nearby.
"Maybe Dominic went back last night and started
another fight."
"Where is he then?"
"Maybe she strangled him?"
"Eddie!"
"Sorry. He's having a lie-in, I suppose. Who
knows? Who cares?"
At this point Jen looked across and saw Eddie
and Lynn. She pointed at them and got up to
come over. The two men in uniform accompanied
her.
"Hello, Jen," said Lynn. "Is something wrong?"
"It's Dominic. He's missing. He never came
back last night. Have you seen him?"
Eddie went cold. Lynn looked at him.
"Not this morning, no," said Eddie. Lynn shook
her head to say the same thing.
"Did you see him last night at all?" said
one of the men.
"Yes, I did," said Eddie. "I went out for
some fresh air, and Dominic was outside. We
chatted for a bit and then I came in. Dominic
stayed outside. I didn't see him after that."
Eddie could honestly say that this was the
truth. He decided not to mention the part
about trying to kill each other.
"When was this?" asked the other man.
"Oh, about midnight, I think. Or just after."
"What did you talk about?"
"Not much really. The cruise, the weather,
the food - that kind of thing." Eddie decided
he needed to tell them more. Just in case
people became suspicious. Get his story out
first. "I remembered him from a long time
ago, though," he said.
"What do you mean?" asked the second man,
looking up from his notes.
"Mr Stephens used to work at the same company
as me years ago - at Fenton's - a software
manufacturer in the UK. He was the divisional
boss for a while. I was in sales. When Lynn
and I first saw him yesterday, we weren't
sure if it was him or not. I wasn't feeling
well anyway, so we thought we'd meet him later
and find out then."
"And was it him? You knew him from work?"
"Yes."
"And did you talk to him about it when you
saw him later?"
"He didn't really remember me, and it was
almost twenty years ago. I don't blame him.
Anyway, we're both here to get away from work,
so I guess that's why we didn't really talk
about it. I wasn't outside with him for that
long."
"Did he seem upset or stressed in any way?"
Eddie suddenly recalled Dominic's face again.
He had looked very upset and considerably
stressed when Eddie had his hands around his
neck. "Not particularly."
"What about you, ma'am?" asked the first man.
"I only met him on the cruise for the first
time yesterday. Jen introduced us when we
all met by chance at the hotel around lunchtime
yesterday."
"And how did he seem to you?"
"Normal, I suppose. Eddie wasn't feeling well,
so we came back. I didn't see him after that."
The Parvina returned to Barbados, where the
cruise was delayed and an official search
began. Eddie saw helicopters come and go,
and he saw police coming and going at the
harbour. There was even a TV crew.
The atmosphere on board had not changed very
much. The ship was so big and there were so
many people, with so many things going on,
that Dominic's disappearance seemed only a
minor problem. It was almost like an additional
activity for the passengers to talk about.
Who was the man? When did he disappear? Why?
What happened? Was he injured on the ship
somewhere? Did he fall overboard?
Eddie and Lynn walked into town to get away
from things. They walked for hours around
the streets and marinas. Here and there they
stopped and looked at their map, and read
their guidebook about the history of Bridgetown.
They tried not to talk about Dominic, or even
to think about it. But Eddie could see that
Lynn was worried, and Lynn could see the same
in Eddie. Sooner or later they had to talk
again. So they had lunch in a cafe overlooking
a small bay, and Lynn was the first to speak.
"What do you think has happened, Ed?"
"I've no idea. I left him standing by the
rail. He was OK. After the fight, he was obviously
tired and so was I. To be honest, I think
we were both a bit shocked and embarrassed
- and bruised. But he was all right when I
left him. Actually, I thought he would come
after me. I was in the toilet for about ten
minutes. Then I came back in to find you."
"Do you think he fell overboard?" she asked.
"Not from where we were. There was another
deck below, and the rail was too high. To
go overboard he'd need to jump."
"So, do you think he jumped?"
"The man thinks he's better than anyone else.
Why would he do that?"
"Who knows? Sixteen years is a long time.
People change."
"Yeah, well, people like him don't change.
Unfortunately."
When they returned to the ship, the police
asked him to go to the office in Bridgetown
to give an official statement. Jen had made
her statement and given all the information
she could. When she mentioned meeting Lynn
and Eddie, it did not take them long to follow
it up.
"And you met at the hotel, is that right?"
asked a tall policeman sitting at his PC.
"Yes."
"Were you friends?"
"No, but I worked with him many years ago.
We never stayed in touch. We were only colleagues,
and I never knew much about him or his life.
I couldn't believe it when I saw him again
after so long. He didn't even recognise me."
"So did you meet later, back on the boat?"
"Not together, no. As I said, his girlfriend
met my wife by chance. We met briefly at lunch,
and we agreed to meet later for a drink."
Eddie didn't mean to say that, but then he
realized Jen had probably said that in her
statement.
Eddie waited for another question. The policeman
looked up at him. "How did he seem when you
met him at the hotel? Happy? Sad?"
"It was hard to tell," said Eddie. That was
true. "He had his sunglasses on the whole
time. We only chatted for a few minutes."
"And did you meet for a drink?"
"No, we didn't. We were supposed to meet at
the bar after Jen, his girlfriend, finished
her session with the band. I met him briefly
on deck though."
"I see," said the policeman, tapping information
on his keyboard. "What did you talk about?"
"Not much really. I was only with him for
about five minutes, but I came inside because
I was cold." Then Eddie thought he should
add something else. "I was hoping to find
out what he'd been up to since the old days,
but I never saw him after that."
"Why not?"
"I'm not sure, to be honest. I was with my
wife for the evening, but we went back to
our cabin earlier than we had planned. We
were tired. I was feeling unwell. I was unwell
at the hotel. Too much sun, I think."
"Ah yes, Mr Stephens' girlfriend mentioned
that. What time did you go to your cabin?"
"I have no idea." Eddie didn't like to end
his statement with uncertainty, so he added:
"On the ship you lose track of time. We both
went to sleep. The first thing we heard about
Dominic's disappearance was this morning when
Jen came to tell us at breakfast."
The policeman nodded and carried on typing.
"So what do you think has happened?" Eddie
asked the policeman. "We're not allowed to
say, Mr Munro. A thorough search of the ship
and the area is being carried out. If we hear
anything, there will be an announcement."
"Is that all then?" asked Eddie.
"Yes, thank you, that's all for now. We have
your details if we have any more questions."
"OK," said Eddie. He got up and walked out
of the office into the bright Caribbean sunshine.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Swimming not sinking
In the end, Lynn stayed with Angela for five
months. She told Eddie that she needed some
time to feel normal again. They didn't argue
anymore and it was only a separation, but
it frightened Eddie. When Lynn left and stayed
away for five months instead of three nights,
he really thought he'd lost her forever. He
was as low, lost and lonely as anyone can
feel, but he knew this was a turning point.
Losing Lynn was a thousand times worse than
losing his job, and he needed to make changes.
As Clive said to him during that time: "When
you hit rock bottom, the only way is up."
It was a mess, however. Eddie's mental health
was not good, and it got much worse when Lynn
left. He couldn't find work, and his depression
made it impossible to do so. Lynn also lost
her job when she didn't come back immediately.
They had to sell the house and furniture to
cover all their debts, and they were no longer
in a position to borrow money to start again.
Steve Scott, their solicitor, was an enormous
help to both of them, handling their finances
and their legal problems. He did everything
except start a divorce action for them, and
they had Clive to thank for that. Clive realized
that the separation could not last long, and
he kept in touch with both of them to make
sure that it didn't result in total breakdown.
By Christmas that year Eddie was staying at
Clive's and Lynn was I still at Angela's.
On New Year's Day Eddie called Lynn to give
her his best wishes.
"Happy New Year," he said.
"Same to you. All the best," she said.
"I hope it's better than the last one," he
said.
"That won't be difficult. It couldn't be worse,"
she said.
Silence.
"It's strange," said Eddie. "We have never
been apart on New Year's Eve."
"No," said Lynn.
"What did you do?"
"Well, you know me. I don't like it much.
Angela and I stayed in on our own and watched
DVDs. Then some neighbours came around just
before midnight. We got to bed around two
o'clock."
"Sounds good."
"Not really."
"Why?"
"Well, you know..." she said.
Eddie knew. "Yes," he said.
"You?" asked Lynn.
"What?"
"What did you do?"
"Oh, Clive and I went to the pub and stayed
there until about one. It was OK."
"How is Clive?"
"He's here. Do you want to speak to him?"
"No, it's all right. I'll text him."
"OK."
A pause.
"Lynn?" said Eddie eventually.
"I'm still here."
"I miss you."
"I know."
"Come back. Please."
"I can't."
"Why?"
"Because... you haven't got a house, and neither
have I!"
They both laughed a little.
"OK. If I get a house, will you come back?"
"Only if you get a big one."
"OK."
"Very big."
"With a garden."
"Right."
"A big garden."
"I'l1 try."
"And a swimming pool."
"Erm, OK."
"Liar."
"OK, the swimming pool will take time. I'll
work on that."
"Fine. A large bathroom and modern kitchen
will be OK instead."
"With or without egg on the walls?"
He heard her laugh on the other end.
Another pause.
"How are you feeling?" she asked. "Generally."
"Not bad. Clive makes me go swimming and read
his car magazines."
"Good for you."
"Hmm," muttered Eddie.
Silence.
Eddie wanted to tell Lynn again that he missed
her.
"Don't give up, Ed," she said.
"I know," he said.
Lynn was Eddie's motivation to rebuild his
life, and Clive was his support. But Eddie
realized that only he could turn things around.
He was encouraged that over the time he was
out of work, he had actually started missing
his work and his friends in the business.
Over the next few years, Eddie put together
a business plan and borrowed money from friends
and family.
He began as an export agent in London for
various UK software companies. He still had
a strong and loyal commercial network throughout
Europe, and many of his old customers and
contacts were glad to have him back. Some
had already become disillusioned with the
larger companies like Fenton's, and Eddie's
introduction of new products and a faster
and more personal service brought good results.
His enthusiasm and energy returned, and every
day he enjoyed the thought that he was his
own boss; no one could undermine his plans
or take away the credit.
He set up a small office not far from Notting
Hill and started off with a part-time office
assistant. At the end of the first year he
had taken on three full-time people. By the
following year he had moved to larger offices
and had a team of ten. It was the beginning
of a sixteen-year journey which turned Eddie
from a bankrupt, broken individual into a
confident and very wealthy man.
Over time Eddie poached some of the team from
Fentons, including Clive, who soon joined
him as a partner. Clive then head hunted some
of the best people from Fenton's production
and development team. With investment from
some overseas partners, they then created
a series of online titles for companies to
provide general training, systems and platforms
to run their businesses.
This was a turning point. Clive and Eddie's
team developed a unique way of linking online
training with mobile phone technology, and
their best-seller was a twelve-module course
called People Skills for Successful Business.
They licensed it worldwide and won an innovation
award. At the awards night at the Savoy Hotel
in London, Clive suggested they send a copy
of the whole series to Dominic and Neal, but
Eddie said it was a waste. "They wouldn't
understand," he said. "Some people think they
know everything anyway. Let them suffer."
And they toasted their success.
Business went from strength to strength, and
Eddie travelled extensively to build strategic
partnerships using the training catalogue
of integrated online-mobile training (OMT).
His contacts and friends in business were
loyal and supportive. Within five years they
had offices in Hong Kong, San Francisco, New
York, Sydney, Bucharest, Munich and Paris.
On the day when he and Clive sold the business
for 20 million pounds, Eddie came home to
Lynn, who was sitting in the garden reading.
"It's done," he said, smiling.
"Really?"
"Really. We signed the agreement this afternoon.
It's over."
"Twenty million?" she asked.
"Twenty million."
"Oh, Eddie!" She jumped up and put her arms
around him. "I am so pleased for you. For
us. You deserve it."
"Thanks. Let's open the champagne."
"It's in the fridge. I'll go and get it,"
she said.
When she came back, Eddie handed her a large
envelope.
"What's this?" she asked excitedly.
"Open it."
Lynn tore open the envelope and pulled out
a large, colourful holiday brochure. "What's
this?" she asked.
"It's a holiday brochure."
"I know it's a holiday brochure," she said,
smiling. "Where are we going?"
"We're going on a cruise."
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Revelations
Two more days passed with no sign of Dominic.
Then three days, then four, then five. Soon
a whole week had passed. Eventually the authorities
decided to call off the search, and let the
ship continue on its voyage. The shipping
line did not want to cause any further inconvenience
for the passengers. The longer they stayed
there, the more bad publicity they faced from
the press. From their point of view the sooner
things got back to normal, the better. Cruise
life continued and the Parvina took Eddie
and Lynn, and its mystery, to St Lucia, Antigua,
Martinique and Grenada.
Back in Barbados, before flying home, Eddie
and Lynn went shopping and stopped at a cafe.
The TV was on by the bar, but the sound was
off. Eddie stared at the news and saw some
familiar pictures of the ship, the helicopter
searches, and the same photograph of Dominic
that was used in all the reports of his disappearance.
They had seen all these pictures before, but
this time the report seemed to continue with
interviews with people back in the UK.
Eddie could see a businessman talking to a
TV journalist. Then another. Then there were
pictures of some buildings. They were offices
where Dominic had worked, but Eddie didn't
recognise them. There were pictures of Dominic's
house, and an interview with an elderly couple.
The caption read that they were Dominic's
neighbours. There was no time to get up and
see if he could turn on the sound before the
news moved on to another topic.
"Lynn, they've just shown the report on Dominic
again. But they're showing more stuff from
home and about where he worked - and interviews
with his neighbours!"
"Well, everyone loves a good mystery, I suppose,"
she said.
"No, I think the story's changed. Something's
going on."
"Well, maybe you should get a newspaper or
look on the internet."
"Good idea," said Eddie, looking around. There
were no papers, but there were two computer
screens in the corner. Eddie bought a username
and password from the waiter and went online.
He keyed in the address for The Times' website,
and there he saw a headline below the UK political
news that took him completely by surprise.
Under a familiar photograph of Dominic, it
read:
Missing businessman stole thousands. Police
suspect suicide.
Eddie couldn't believe it. He clicked on the
headline and a new page revealed itself on
the screen. Underneath the headline there
was a picture of a younger Dominic, and a
new article appeared. Eddie could not read
it fast enough:
The search for missing London businessman
Dominic Stephens has finally been called off.
Authorities now believe that Mr Stephens took
his own life whilst on a cruise in the Caribbean,
leaving behind large debts and a trail of
fraud and corruption.
Mr Stephens went missing over a week ago on
the American cruise ship Parvina some time
after midnight on 20 June in the south Caribbean
sea. After days of searching, it is now believed
that Mr Stephens may have jumped overboard
somewhere between Barbados and St Lucia in
an act of suicide. The exact time of his disappearance
is not known. Search and rescue teams have
been covering an area of thousands of square
miles with no sign of Mr Stephens.
The disappearance follows reports that Mr
Stephens had recently been fired from Flash
Electronics Inc. by partners in the firm.
It had been discovered that Mr Stephens had
embezzled at least 145,000 pounds from the
company during the seven years he had worked
there as CEO. Further interviews with police
are also being held at other companies, who
have also reported acts of fraud, corruption
and intimidation in connection with Mr Stephens.
The sixty-one-year-old businessman was due
to appear in court on 15 June, charged with
theft, but failed to make an appearance. He
was reported missing by his wife, Margaret
Stephens, but it is believed Mr Stephens left
the country on 16 June to join the cruise
ship Parvina. Friends and colleagues spoke
of their shock and disappointment...
Eddie looked up from the screen and turned
around to Lynn who was sipping an iced tea.
"Lynn, you're not going to believe this,"
he said.
On the last night of the cruise Eddie and
Lynn had a quiet dinner together in the Starlight
Lounge, danced for a while, and then went
for a walk on deck before bed.
Although the day's intense humidity had gone,
the evening was still warm. The sky was clear,
and bright stars mixed once more with island
lights on the far horizon. Eddie leaned on
the rail and looked out.
"I'm going to miss all this," he said.
"I know. Me too. But we can do it again, can't
we?"
"Yes. Definitely."
"But maybe next time we can do it without
your ex-boss turning up and creating an international
incident."
Eddie smiled. "Well, if he does turn up next
time, he'll have a lot of explaining to do."
"Unbelievable. It's like a story from a film
or a book."
"Yes. Truth is often stranger than fiction."
A pause. Both of them looked out to sea.
"Do you really think he's out there?" asked
Lynn.
"He must be. He's not on the ship, that's
for sure."
"It's a scary thought. He must have been so
desperate, to jump off a ship at sea. If he
did jump. Can you imagine?" said Lynn.
"Maybe he fell."
"Maybe you pushed him," she said, smiling
and nudging Eddie in the side with her elbow.
It still hurt where Dominic had punched him.
The man was still a pain in his side.
"Maybe someone else pushed him?" suggested
Eddie. "Back home there was probably a long
queue of people waiting to do something like
that to him, and to all the superior-minded,
arrogant Dominic's of the world."
"Sad," she said.
"Very," said Eddie. "Some are pushed and some
jump anyway. That's the way it is. That's
the way it's always been. The trick is what
you do next."
Eddie took a deep, relaxed breath, let out
a long sigh and looked out to sea to the Caribbean
horizon once more and for the last time.
And then he smiled.
It was very clear to him now.
He could easily make out the difference between
the stars and the lights of the island, and
he wondered why he had never noticed it before.