CHAPTER ONE
Uncle Ralph
'I can understand a broken neck or a broken
leg, but not a broken heart.'
Mr Ralph Nickleby closed the thick book that
contained the names of all the people who
owed him money.
His money-lending business was doing well,
he thought with a satisfied smile.
Life had never been better.
It was true that he had never married, he
had no friends and he was unpopular with his
neighbours, but he did not care.
People admired him because he was rich, and
that was good enough for him.
In his world, money was the only thing that
mattered.
While Mr Nickleby was congratulating himself
on his own success, there was a knock at the
door.
A tall, middle-aged man with strange, wild
eyes walked into the room.
It was Newman Noggs, Mr Nickleby's clerk.
'What do you want, Newman?'
Mr Nickleby said, annoyed by his interruption.
'I have a letter for you,' the clerk replied,
one eye looking at his employer, the other
looking out of the window.
'Well, bring it here, man!'
Mr Nickleby said impatiently.
Newman took the letter carefully out of his
badly fitting suit, carried it slowly across
the room and gave it to his employer.
Mr Nickleby read it quickly.
'My brother's dead,' he said.
'That was sudden.'
He stood up, walked across to the window,
and stared thoughtfully through its dirty
glass into the smoke-blackened yard behind
his house.
'Children alive?'
Noggs asked.
'Unfortunately for me, yes,' Mr Nickleby said.
'Both of them.
And the mother, too.
No money, and now they expect me to take care
of them.
They're all in London now, waiting for my
help.
What do I care about them?
I never met them.'
Noggs looked at his employer's back with a
strange expression on his face.
It was not exactly a smile, but it was not
a look of sadness either.
Nobody could ever understand the expressions
on Newman Noggs's face.
'Get me my coat and gloves, Newman,' Mr Nickleby
suddenly decided, turning away from the window.
'I have a visit to make.'
Mr Nickleby walked quickly to the Strand,
one of the busiest streets in London.
He knocked several times on the door of a
small house and waited.
The door was finally opened by a servant girl.
'Is Mrs Nickleby at home?' he demanded.
'You mean Miss La Creevy?'
the girl replied.
'No, I mean Mrs Nickleby!'
'Show the gentleman up, Hannah,' a voice called
from inside the house.
Mr Nickleby walked straight past the servant
girl into the hall of the house and quickly
up the stairs.
On the first floor he met a small, bird-like,
middle- aged woman wearing black gloves and
a yellow cloth tied around her head.
'My name's Miss La Creevy,' the woman said
with a friendly smile.
'I'm an artist.
Would you like me to paint your picture for
you?
You have a wonderfully serious face.
Such strong eyes!'
'I'm not here for a painting, madam,' Mr Nickleby
replied impatiently.
'I'm looking for a Mrs Nickleby.
Is she here?'
'A lady from the country and her two children
have rented a room on the second floor,' the
woman said.
'She's a widow.'
'A poor widow?'
'I'm afraid so.'
'That's her,' Mr Nickleby sighed.
The servant girl led him upstairs and into
a small room.
When he entered, a woman wearing a long black
dress rose from her chair.
A beautiful girl of about seventeen moved
across the room to take her arm.
A young man, two or three years older than
his sister, stepped forwards and greeted Ralph
as his uncle.
'You are Nicholas, I suppose?'
Ralph said.
'That is my name, sir,' the young man smiled.
Ralph did not return his nephew's smile, but
turned immediately to Mrs Nickleby.
'Well, madam, how are you?' he said.
'You must be brave in your sadness.
I always am.'
'This is no ordinary sadness,' Mrs Nickleby
said, putting her handkerchief to her eyes.
'I disagree,' Ralph said, calmly unbuttoning
his coat.
'Husbands die every day, ma'am, and wives,
too.'
'And brothers also, sir,' Nicholas said, already
beginning to dislike his uncle.
'Yes, sir, and dogs and cats,' Ralph replied,
sitting down.
'You didn't say in your letter how my brother
died, ma'am.'
'Nobody knows,' Mrs Nickleby said, her eyes
filled with tears.
'We believe that he died of a broken heart.'
'Impossible!'
Ralph said angrily.
'I can understand a broken neck or a broken
leg, but not a broken heart.
It is an excuse for people who want to escape
their debts.'
'Some people, I believe, have no hearts to
break,' said Nicholas quietly.
Ralph turned round in his chair and looked
at his nephew with scorn.
'How old is this boy?' he demanded.
'Nicholas is nearly nineteen,' said the widow.
'Nineteen, eh?' said Ralph.
'And do you have a job?'
'Not yet,' Nicholas answered proudly, 'but
I'll find one.'
'You'd better,' Ralph said, staring at him
with cold, grey eyes.
'You haven't got a penny in the world, have
you?'
'That's true,' Nicholas said.
'But don't worry.
I won't need your help.'
Nicholas's mother begged the emotional young
man to control himself and asked Ralph to
forgive her son for his rudeness.
Ralph gave Nicholas another scornful smile,
then turned to Mrs Nickleby again.
'You say in your letter, ma'am, that my brother
left you nothing when he died,' he said.
'That's true,' the widow said.
'I've had to sell our home to pay my husband's
debts, and I've spent the last of my money
on the journey to London.
'I hoped that you would be able to help your
brother's children.
That was his dying wish.'
'What can your daughter do, ma'am?'
Ralph asked.
'She has learnt a little French and music.'
'And have you ever done anything?'
Ralph said to Nicholas.
'No,' Nicholas replied.
'I thought not!'
Ralph said, looking again at Mrs Nickleby.
'Your husband was a dreamer, ma'am.
That's why he left you with no money, and
left me with the problem of helping you.
He was a foolish, selfish man.'
'Yes, that's true, I suppose,' Mrs Nickleby
agreed.
'He never listened to my advice about money.
I often think that I made a bad mistake when
I married him...'
Ralph listened to Mrs Nickleby's complaints
about her husband with a halfsmile.
When she had finished, he looked at his nephew
and said, 'Are you willing to work, sir?'
'Of course I am.'
'Then I have something here that may interest
you.'
He took a newspaper from his pocket, and showed
him an advertisement:
Mr Wackford Squeers's School for Boys, Dotheboys
Hall, near Greta Bridge in Yorkshire, needs
an assistant.
He will be paid five pounds a year.
Mr Squeers is staying in London, at the Saracens
Head Hotel, Snow Hill.
'Five pounds a year isn't much,' Kate complained.
And Yorkshire is so far away!'
'Be quiet, dear,' Mrs Nickleby told her.
'I'm sure your uncle knows best.'
'And if I get this job,' Nicholas wanted to
know, 'what will happen to my mother and sister?'
'I will take care of them,' Ralph promised.
'I will find your sister a job with a dressmaker
that I know.
But only if you take this job.
Do you understand?'
'Then I agree,' Nicholas said, forgetting
his anger of minutes earlier and shaking his
uncle's hand.
'I'll take the job - if Mr Squeers will have
me.'
He will accept you - I can promise you that,'
Ralph said.
Now, get your hat and coat, young man.
We must go to the Saracen's Head immediately!'
CHAPTER TWO
Dotheboys Hall
Nicholas's heart was filled with pity for
these poor children,who suffered such cruel
treatment.
Wackford Squeers was a strange-looking man
with flat, oily hair.
His black jacket was much too big for him,
and his trousers were much too short.
But the strangest thing about him was his
face.
He only had one eye, which looked like a dirty
window.
When he smiled, it seemed to shine with a
frightening green light.
At first, Mr Squeers was unwilling to accept
Nicholas as his assistant because he was too
young and had not been to college.
But after a few quiet words with the boy's
uncle, he offered Nicholas the job.
'The coach leaves at eight o'clock tomorrow
morning,' he said.
'You mustn't be late.'
Nicholas woke up at six o'clock the next morning
and hurried to the Saracen's Head.
While he was helping Mr Squeers to lift a
few small, frightened-looking boys onto the
coach, he was surprised to see his mother
and sister.
His uncle had brought them to say goodbye.
'Why didn't you wake us?'
Mrs Nickleby said, throwing her arms around
her son.
'You left without breakfast!'
'There's no time for this, Nickleby!'
Squeers interrupted rudely, buttoning his
coat against the cold.
'Get onto the coach immediately.
One of my boys has already nearly fallen off.
If a boy died now, I'd lose twenty pounds!'
'Dear Nicholas,' whispered Kate, leading her
brother away.
'What kind of place are you going to?'
'I don't know, Kate,' Nicholas replied, pressing
his sister's hand.
'I suppose the people in Yorkshire are rougher
than people in London.'
'He's a nasty little man.
He's so rude.'
'But he's my employer,' Nicholas reminded
her.
Nicholas kissed his tearful sister and mother
and shook his uncle's hand.
Then he jumped up into his seat on the coach.
However, as he was waving goodbye, an odd
thing happened.
Somebody started pulling softly at his leg.
He looked down and saw a tall, thin man with
strange, wild eyes.
'What's this?'
Nicholas asked, when the man pushed a dirty
letter into his hand.
'You don't know me,' the man whispered nervously,
'but I work for your uncle.
Take it and read it.'
Before Nicholas could say another word, the
man had gone.
The journey to Yorkshire was long and uncomfortable.
It snowed heavily on the way, and everybody
felt cold and hungry.
At six o'clock the next evening, they finally
arrived at Greta Bridge.
Mr Squeers and Nicholas took the boys off
the coach and put them into a small cart.
'Is it much further to Dotheboys Hall, sir?'
Nicholas asked Squeers when the cart had left
Greta Bridge.
'About three miles,' Squeers replied.
'But we don't call it a "Hall" up here - only
in London, because it sounds better.'
Squeers laughed to himself, and Nicholas stared
into the darkness until they reached Dotheboys
Hall.
Then he understood.
The 'Hall' was just a long, low, cold-looking
house with a few old farm buildings behind
it.
While Nicholas sat in the cart with the boys,
Squeers jumped down and shouted for someone
to open the gate.
Several minutes later, a tall boy in old,
thin clothes ran out of the house.
'Why did you take so long, Smike?'
Squeers shouted.
'Sorry, sir, but I fell asleep by the fire.'
'Fire?
What fire?'
the schoolmaster demanded angrily.
'Mrs Squeers said that I could sit by the
fire in the kitchen to keep warm.'
'Mrs Squeers is a fool,' Squeers replied.
'You'd stay awake better in the cold!'
The boy called Smike opened the gate, looking
nervously at Squeers.
A few minutes later, Nicholas was standing
outside the door with the boys and the luggage.
He stared up at the cold-looking house with
its dark windows and sighed.
He was a long way from his home and family,
and he had never felt so lonely.
Life at Dotheboys Hall was very hard.
There was no heating in the school, and the
boys had to wash with buckets of icy water
in the mornings.
They wore the same clothes every day, and
they were always hungry.
Mrs Squeers fed them a thick, horrible soup
every day which Mr Squeers called their 'medicine'.
It was the cheapest food that they could find.
The classroom was cold and dirty with broken
windows.
There were a couple of old, long desks for
the children, and two desks at the front of
the room - one for Squeers, and a smaller
one for his assistant.
During the lessons, the boys sat quietly,
shaking with the cold.
Letters from home were opened in front of
the whole class and Squeers took all their
money.
He did the same with packages of clothes.
If the boys complained, Squeers hit them with
a big stick.
Nicholas watched this happen with tears of
anger in his eyes, but he felt powerless to
do anything.
Squeers gave to his son, young Wackford, all
the clothes that he stole from the boys.
He, of course, was the only boy in the school
who was never cold and hungry.
He was also as nasty as his father.
His favourite activity was kicking the other
boys and making them cry.
If they tried to defend themselves, young
Wackford reported them to his father and they
were cruelly punished.
Nicholas's heart was filled with pity for
these poor children, who suffered such cruel
treatment.
All the beauty of innocence had disappeared
from their pale, thin faces.
He never heard them laughing, and there was
no hope in their dull, empty eyes.
He was especially sorry for the boy called
Smike.
He was older than the other boys - about eighteen
or nineteen years old.
He was tall for his age but wore children's
clothes that were much too short for him.
He did not have lessons, but was made to do
all the hard, dirty jobs around the school.
If he did something wrong, Mr Squeers beat
him and shouted at him.
Smike had been left at the school many years
earlier by parents who did not want him.
However, Squeers still received money for
him from somewhere.
He kept him at the school because he was useful.
One evening, Nicholas sat on his hard, wooden
bed in the crowded, unheated room that he
shared with several other boys.
He was thinking sadly of home when suddenly
he remembered the letter which the man with
wild eyes had given him.
He took it out of his pocket and read:
My dear young man, I know the world.
Your father did not, and you do not either.
If you knew the world, you would not go on
this journey.
If you ever want help in London don't be angry,
go to the Crown Hotel, in Golden Square.
They will give you my address.
You can come at night.
Many years ago, people were not ashamed to
know me.
Now things are different - but that is not
important.
There is no future.
Newman Noggs.
While Nicholas was putting the letter back
in his pocket, a strange thing happened to
him.
His eyes filled with tears.
The next day, Nicholas saw Smike on his knees,
trying to light a fire.
Smike looked up at Nicholas with a frightened
expression.
'Don't be afraid, ' Nicholas said kindly.
'I'm not going to hurt you.
Are you cold?'
Smike covered his face with his thin, dirty
hands and started crying.
'My heart will break if I stay in this horrible
place,' he said.
'Before you arrived, a boy died here.
He was my last friend.
Just before he died, his face was lit up by
a lovely smile.
He said that he could see the faces of his
friends around his bed.
They had come from home and they were smiling
and talking to him.
What faces will smile at me when I die?
There's no hope for me, alive or dead.
No hope.'
'There's always hope,' Nicholas said gently,
resting his hand on the boy's bony shoulder.
Eventually, Smike stopped crying and moved
away, like a frightened animal, into the shadows.
Nicholas sighed sadly and went to bed.
CHAPTER THREE
Fanny Squeers
'When did he ask you to marry him?'
'Oh, he hasn't asked me yet,' Fanny said.
Wackford Squeers had a twenty-two-year-old
daughter, Fanny, who was short and ugly, like
her father.
One evening, she was having dinner with her
parents while they were discussing Nicholas.
Fanny had never met Nicholas because she was
staying with her friend Tilda when he arrived.
She therefore listened to her parents' conversation
with interest.
When she heard her father say that he was
the 'son of a gentleman', she became very
interested!
Later that night, she asked her servant about
the new teacher.
She heard that he had beautiful dark eyes,
long straight legs and a sweet smile.
She decided that she wanted to meet this interesting
young man as soon as possible.
The next day, she went into the schoolroom,
pretending that she needed a pen.
When she saw Nicholas, her face went red.
'I'm sorry,' she said.
'I thought my father was here.
Oh, how embarrassing!'
'Mr Squeers is out,' Nicholas explained politely.
'Could you lend me a pen?'
the young lady asked, looking shyly at her
feet.
'He does have a beautiful smile,' she thought,
giving him a secret, sideways look.
Nicholas gave her a pen, and Fanny left the
classroom.
Outside the door, she held the pen to her
heart.
'I've never seen such wonderful legs!'
she sighed, walking away in a dream.
Minutes later, she put on her hat and coat
and hurried out of the school.
'I have to tell Tilda about him,' she thought.
Fanny was jealous of Tilda Price, who was
five years younger than her.
A week earlier a farmer, John Browdie, had
asked Tilda to marry him.
'Now I can tell her that I'm going to get
married, too!'
Fanny thought.
Tilda was surprised when she heard Fanny's
news.
'This is wonderful!'
she said.
'When did he ask you to marry him?'
'Oh, he hasn't asked me yet,' Fanny said.
'But I know that he wants to.
He smiles at me in a very special way.'
'Oh, Fanny,' Tilda said, hugging her friend.
'I'm so happy for you.
When can I meet the lucky young man?'
'In two days' time, my parents are away on
business.
Then you and John can both come for tea.'
'What a lovely idea!'
Tilda said excitedly.
'I can't wait!'
Two days later, Tilda arrived early at Dotheboys
Hall.
'John will be here later,' she explained.
'He's gone home to wash and change his clothes.'
The two girls helped each other with their
hair and clothes, then went downstairs.
While Fanny was talking excitedly about her
'future husband', there was a knock on the
door.
'Come in,' Fanny called nervously.
'Good evening...'
Nicholas said, a look of surprise on his face.
He had expected to find Mr Squeers.
'Father can't be with us today,' Fanny said.
'But that only makes it better for us, doesn't
it?'
Nicholas thought that these words were strange,
but he paid no attention to them.
He greeted Tilda politely, and stood calmly
by the window.
'Don't be embarrassed,' Tilda said, smiling
at him.
'I don't mind what you two do in front of
me.
You can pretend that I'm not here!'
'Tilda!'
Fanny said, her face going red.
The two girls started laughing.
Nicholas thought that the girls' behaviour
was so silly that he started laughing, too.
Soon, the three of them were sitting happily
at the table, eating bread and butter and
drinking tea.
Ten minutes later, John Browdie arrived.
He was a big, strong man, but he was not very
good at conversation.
He seemed happy just to eat bread and butter.
When the plates were empty, John stared at
Nicholas and said, 'You're a lucky man to
have bread and butter here.'
'What do you mean, sir?'
Nicholas replied.
'The last teacher nearly died of hunger,'
John laughed.
'Mr Squeers doesn't like spending money!'
Nicholas went red with anger and he told Mr
Browdie to apologise for his rudeness in front
of Mr Squeers's daughter.
Tilda was angry, too.
'If you say another word, John,' she said,
'I'll never speak to you again!'
Then she turned to Nicholas and whispered,
'John and I will go into the kitchen.
We'll leave you two alone for a few minutes.'
'Why do you want to do that?'
Nicholas asked, confused.
'Mr Nickleby, I'm shocked!
Look at poor Miss Squeers.
She was so excited about today, and she's
dressed so prettily because of you.'
'Because of me?
Why?'
Tilda looked at Nicholas with a strange smile.
'Does this handsome man think that I'm more
beautiful than Fanny?'
she thought.
'Perhaps he doesn't want to marry her now.'
'Let's have a game of cards,' she said suddenly.
'There are only four of us, Tilda,' Fanny
said, looking at Nicholas out of the corner
of her eye.
'We'd better play with partners, hadn't we?
Two against two.'
'What do you think, Mr Nickleby?'
Tilda asked.
'I'll be happy to be your partner, Miss Price,'
Nicholas replied.
'Mr Browdie,' Fanny said, looking at Tilda
angrily.
'Will you be my partner?'
John Browdie agreed, although he could not
understand why Fanny seemed so upset.
'We're going to win everything,' Nicholas
said cheerfully, after he and Tilda had won
the first game.
'I think Tilda has already won something that
she didn't expect - haven't you, dear?'
Fanny said nastily.
'Only a game of cards, my dear,' Tilda replied,
pretending not to understand.
She was enjoying Fanny's jealousy.
'How boring you are tonight!'
Fanny said with a bitter smile.
'Not at all,' Tilda replied.
'I'm in an excellent mood.
I was thinking that you seemed unusually boring
tonight.'
'Me!'
Fanny cried, biting her lip and shaking jealously.
'And your hair's beginning to look untidy,'
Tilda said.
The two friends argument became worse and
worse.
Finally, Fanny started crying.
'Tilda, I hate you,' she shouted.
'I feel the same way about you,' Tilda said.
John Browdie hit the table hard with his enormous
hand.
'I've had enough!' he shouted.
'I'm going home!'
'Me, too,' Tilda said, standing up and putting
on her hat.
She hurried out of the room, followed by John
Browdie.
Nicholas looked at Fanny.
He was unsure of what to do.
Fanny was crying into her handkerchief, shouting
things at the closed door.
After a few minutes, he quietly left the room.
'In a horrible place like this, I need all
the friends I can get,' he said to himself.
'But instead, I only seem to make enemies.
What have I done?'
With these unhappy thoughts, he climbed into
his dirty, cold bed.
But as he lay awake, listening to the other
boys in their beds crying with cold and hunger,
he soon forgot his own problems.
'Why do places as terrible as this exist?'
he thought angrily.
'These poor children are treated worse than
animals.
Why do their families send them here?'
The next day, things became even worse.
When it became clear that Nicholas did not
love her, Fanny was filled with anger and
confusion.
She could not understand why a poor teacher
like him did not find her attractive.
In addition to this, he had embarrassed her
in front of her friend.
This showed that Nicholas was not grateful
to her father for giving him a job.
'Well,' she thought, 'he has an enemy instead
of a friend.
I'm going to make life very difficult for
him.'
She noticed that Smike seemed to like Nicholas
a lot.
He followed the young teacher everywhere,
and was happy just to be near him.
Fanny complained about this to her father,
who began to treat Smike even more roughly
than before.
One January morning, Smike disappeared.
Squeers and his wife went out to look for
him, and eventually found him several miles
away by the side of the road.
He was covered in mud, frozen, tired and hungry.
They tied his hands and feet together and
brought him back to the school.
Then Squeers ordered everybody to go to the
schoolroom.
He pulled Smike into the room and threw him
onto the floor.
'Have you anything to say?'
Squeers said to Smike, lifting a stick above
his head.
'Please don't hit me, sir,' Smike cried.
Squeers laughed, and brought the stick down
hard on the boy's back.
Smike screamed with pain while the other boys
watched silently.
Squeers lifted the stick again, but a loud
voice shouted, 'Stop!'
'Who said that?'
demanded Squeers, turning round angrily.
'I did,' said Nicholas.
'Sit down!'
Squeers told him angrily.
He lifted his stick to hit Smike again, but
Nicholas moved quickly towards him.
'I warn you not to touch him,' he said.
'I've seen enough of your evil school and
your treatment of the children here.'
Without warning, Squeers screamed wildly and
hit Nicholas across the face with his stick.
Nicholas immediately jumped on Squeers, took
the stick from his hand and began to hit him.
Mrs Squeers and Fanny tried to pull Nicholas
away, but Nicholas was too strong for them
all.
He pushed them off and threw the schoolmaster
across the room.
Squeers hit the wall hard and sank to the
floor without moving.
Nicholas looked around, but he could not see
Smike.
After a moment's thought, he decided that
he had no choice.
He had to leave the school immediately.
He packed his bag quickly and marched out
of the front door into the snow.
After walking for a few miles, he calmed down
and thought about his situation more clearly.
He did not know how he was going to get to
London.
He only had a little money, and London was
over two hundred and fifty miles away.
While Nicholas was worrying about this, he
noticed a man on a horse riding towards him.
It was John Browdie.
They exchanged greetings but did not smile.
After a few seconds' silence, Nicholas said,
'I'm very sorry about our argument.
It was my fault.
Will you shake hands?'
John Browdie jumped down from his horse with
a big smile and shook hands.
Then he noticed the cuts on Nicholas's face.
When Nicholas told him what had happened,
he laughed and shook his hand again.
'You've beaten the schoolmaster?'
he said.
'That's the best thing I've heard for years!
I love you for it!'
But he became more serious when Nicholas told
him about his plan to walk to London.
He pulled an old purse out of his pocket and
gave Nicholas enough money for the coach journey.
Nicholas tried to refuse, but John Browdie
did not listen.
'Good luck, young man,' he said, when Nicholas
had finally accepted the money.
With a cheerful wave, he climbed back onto
his horse and rode away, laughing loudly.
Nicholas continued his journey, but he did
not travel far that afternoon.
It was nearly dark and there had been a heavy
fall of snow, so he went into an empty farmhouse
and fell asleep.
When he woke up the next morning, he saw a
dark shape sitting in front of him.
It was Smike!
'What are you doing here?'
Nicholas asked with surprise.
'I want to go with you,' the boy replied.
'You're the only friend I have.
Please take me with you.'
'I'm as poor and lonely as you are,' Nicholas
said.
'How can I help you?'
'Please!'
the boy begged.
'I'll be your servant.
I won't ask for anything.
I only want to be near you.'
Nicholas agreed, and Smike's face lit up with
happiness.
He did not know where they were going, but
he did not care.
He was with his friend, and away from Dotheboys
Hall.
That was enough to fill his heart with happiness.
CHAPTER FOUR
Return to London
'Will you, sir, return that boy to the school
where he belongs?'
'I will not.'
Newman Noggs had lodgings at the top of a
house near Golden Square.
Arriving home from work one night, he saw
two tired, wet travellers waiting patiently
outside his door.
He invited them straight in and gave them
some hot soup and some dry clothes.
'I read your letter,' Nicholas explained as
the three of them sat around the fire.
'I got your address from the Crown Hotel,
as you suggested.
Tell me, how are my mother and sister?'
'Well.
Your uncle is letting them live in an empty
old house that belongs to him.
It's near the river, and it was in a terrible
condition when they first moved in.
It was smelly and dirty, with rats everywhere.'
A strange expression crossed his face when
he said this.
Nicholas did not know whether Newman felt
amused or sickened.
'But your mother and sister have cleaned a
couple of rooms and made them quite comfortable,'
Newman continued, noticing the anxious look
on Nicholas's face.
And they don't have to pay any rent.'
Nicholas looked relieved.
'I wanted to come here before visiting them,'
he explained.
'I didn't want to cause them any unnecessary
problems.'
He then described his recent adventures at
Dotheboys Hall.
When he had finished, Newman looked at him
seriously.
'My dear young man,' he said, 'you'll never
make progress in the world if you behave like
that... but I'm proud of you!'
'Has my uncle heard about it yet?'
Nicholas asked.
Newman opened and shut his mouth several times,
but did not say anything.
'I must know the bad news sooner or later,'
Nicholas said.
'Please tell me now.'
Newman rose from his chair and took a piece
of paper from a drawer.
It was a copy of a letter which Ralph had
received from Fanny Squeers two days earlier.
In it, she described how Nicholas had attacked
her father, stolen a valuable ring and run
away with Smike 'an evil, ungrateful boy'.
'She's lying,' Nicholas said angrily.
'I must find my uncle and tell him what really
happened.'
'Your uncle's out of town,' Newman replied.
'He won't be back for three days.
He won't answer this letter before he returns.
Don't worry.
Nobody else knows about it.'
'Are you sure?
Not even my mother and sister?
Then I must go and see them.'
'No, you mustn't,' Newman said.
'Speak to your uncle when he returns.'
The next day, Nicholas found small, cheap
lodgings for himself and Smike, and immediately
started looking for a job.
He went to a small but busy job agency near
Oxford Street, in the centre of London, where
he was offered work as a French teacher for
the daughters of a local businessman.
Nicholas accepted the job happily.
As he was walking out, a girl of about eighteen
years old came in from the street.
He stood to one side as she shyly walked past
him.
She was so beautiful that he stood and watched
her for a long time.
He had never seen such a lovely, innocent
face, although there was something sad about
her soft blue eyes.
Eventually, he turned away and walked home,
unable to stop thinking about her.
Two days later, Nicholas went to visit his
uncle, who had just returned to London.
His uncle was not at home, so he went instead
to see Miss La Creevy.
'Mr Nicholas!'
Miss La Creevy cried happily when she saw
him at her door.
Come in.
You must join me for breakfast.
You look so thin, and your face is so pale.'
While they were having breakfast, Miss La
Creevy asked him why he had returned to London.
Nicholas explained to her what had happened.
Then he said, 'I came here because I want
to see my uncle.
I have to persuade him that I'm not a thief.
I went to his house this morning, but he wasn't
at home.
I must see him before he tells my mother and
sister these lies about me.
Perhaps you can help me.'
'How can I do that?'
Miss La Creevy asked, looking worried.
'My mother and sister don't know that I've
returned from Yorkshire.
Could you show me where they live?
I want to see them before my uncle does.'
Miss La Creevy took him straight to the house
by the river, and Nicholas was shocked when
he saw it.
It's windows were covered with mud, and its
walls were wet and dirty.
It had probably been empty for many years.
Miss La Creevy led him through the door, across
a dark, smelly hall and up some stairs.
She stopped outside a freshly painted door.
'This is it,' she said.
'Your mother and I have worked very hard to
make this as comfortable as possible.'
However, as she was going to knock on the
door, she stopped.
There was the sound of a man's deep voice
from inside the room.
Ralph Nickleby had arrived before them!
He was telling Mrs Nickleby and Kate about
Nicholas, and they were both crying.
'It's impossible!'
Kate said.
'Nicholas isn't a thief.
Mother, how can you sit and listen to such
things?'
Mrs Nickleby, who had never been very good
at understanding situations, just cried even
more loudly into her handkerchief.
'If my nephew's innocent, why is he hiding
from us?'
Ralph said.
'I'm afraid you must both accept the fact
that he's a dangerous criminal.'
'That's a lie!'
an angry voice shouted, and Nicholas rushed
in.
Ralph turned and stared angrily at his nephew.
'Dear Nicholas,' Kate cried, throwing her
arms around her brother.
'Be calm, don't do anything foolish...'
'Be calm?'
Nicholas replied, his face red with anger.
'How can I be calm in front of this man?
He sent me to an evil place to work for the
cruellest man that I've ever known.
And now he's poisoning the ears of my family
against me...'
'Be patient,' Kate begged him.
'Calm down.
Tell us what really happened.'
'It's true that I attacked the schoolmaster,'
Nicholas said.
'But I did it to save a poor, innocent boy
from certain death.
I'm not sorry.
I'd do the same again if I had the chance.'
'Do you hear this?'
Ralph said, turning to Mrs Nickleby.
'Your son isn't even sorry!'
Oh dear!
cried Mrs Nickleby.
'I don't know what to think.
'But I'm not a thief!'
Nicholas continued, staring proudly at his
uncle.
'I found a ring in my pocket after I'd left
that horrible school.
It was a cheap ring.
I believe that Mrs Squeers put it there to
make me look like a thief.
I sent it back to the school immediately.'
'And what about the boy, Smike?'
Kate asked.
'Is it true that you ran away with him?'
'Yes.
He's the boy that I saved from the schoolmaster.
He's suffered years of cruel treatment at
that school.
He wanted to come with me, and he's with me
now.'
'So everything is true,' Ralph said.
'You don't deny it!
Will you, sir, return that boy to the school
where he belongs?'
'I will not.'
'You refuse?' said Ralph.
'Then you must listen to me.'
'Why?
I will not listen to any more of your lies.'
'Then I will speak to your mother.
She understands the real world.
Ma'am, I tried to help you by finding your
son honest work, but he is a lazy, selfish,
ungrateful boy.
I will not help him - or you, if he stays
with you.
If that boy stays, I will leave you now.
You will never see me again.'
'You've been kind to us, sir,' Mrs Nickleby
replied from behind her handkerchief 'But
I can't send my own son away, even if he is
guilty of these terrible crimes.'
'Why do you say "if", Mother?'
Kate asked.
'You know he's innocent.'
'I don't know what to think,' Mrs Nickleby
replied.
'Nicholas is sometimes very bad-tempered,
and your uncle has been so good to us.
But let's not talk about it anymore.
I can't send my own son away.
Even if it means that we don't have a penny
in the world...'
Ralph turned towards the door, but Nicholas
stopped him.
'You needn't leave this place, sir,' he said.
'I'll go, and you won't see me for a very
long time.'
'Nicholas!'
Kate said, throwing her arms again around
her brother.
'You can't go.
You'll break my heart if you do.'
'I have to,' Nicholas replied gently.
'If I stay, I'll only bring you unhappiness.
We won't forget each other, I promise.
And I'm sure that better days will come.'
He kissed his sister gently, then turned again
to his uncle.
'I leave my family to you, sir,' he whispered.
'But I promise - if anything bad happens to
them, you'll be punished.'
Nicholas left the room without another word
and, a few days later, he and Smike left London.
CHAPTER FIVE
Sir Mulberry Hawk
'Let me go immediately; sir,' Kate whispered
angrily.
'My dear girl, why do you pretend to dislike
me so much?'
Soon after Nicholas had left London, Kate
lost her job at the dressmaker's.
Her mother looked through the newspapers and
quickly found an interesting advertisement:
a woman called Mrs Wititterly was looking
for a companion.
Although Kate did not really want the job,
she was too tired and upset by recent events
to argue.
She went with her mother for an interview
with Mrs Wititterly.
Mrs Wititterly - a nervous, ill-looking woman
- lived in a large house near Sloane Square,
a very expensive part of London.
Kate's gentleness and intelligence pleased
her, and she offered Kate the job as her companion.
Mrs Nickleby was very excited.
'Mrs Wititterly looks very ill,' she thought.
'Perhaps she'll die soon and Mr Wititterly
- a fine-looking gentleman!
- will fall in love with Kate.
He'll ask her to marry him and all our troubles
will end!'
A week after the interview, Kate moved all
her things to Mrs Wititterly's house and started
work.
Ralph Nickleby had a very important business
customer, Sir Mulberry Hawk, an ugly old man
with lots of money, who had met Kate once
at dinner at Ralph's house.
Unfortunately for Kate, this horrible old
man had liked her a lot.
He had sat next to her at dinner and had embarrassed
her all evening with his rude jokes and horrible
wet-lipped smiles.
She had been so upset by his impolite behaviour
that she had left the table.
After dinner, Sir Mulberry had told Ralph
that he wanted to meet Kate again.
He asked Ralph to help him and Ralph agreed
immediately, thinking that this would be good
for his business.
He arranged for Sir Mulberry to meet Mrs Nickleby
at his office.
Mrs Nickleby liked Sir Mulberry because he
said so many nice things about her and her
daughter.
'Such a beautiful, intelligent girl!' he said.
'But I'm not surprised.
She has such a beautiful, intelligent mother.'
Mrs Nickleby smiled proudly, and let Sir Mulberry
walk home with her.
When he had said goodbye, she closed her eyes
with excitement.
'I don't believe it,' she thought.
'Such a fine gentleman!
He will be an even better husband for Kate
than Mr Wititterly!'
One evening, Sir Mulberry invited Mrs Nickleby
to the theatre with him.
She put on her best clothes and sat with him
in the most expensive seats.
Sir Mulberry was a drunk, but Mrs Nickleby
did not care.
She felt proud to be with such a well-dressed
gentleman - especially as he was so interested
in her daughter.
He was telling her for the twentieth time
how beautiful Kate was when suddenly he stopped.
'Listen!' he said.
'Some people have come into the next seats.
I'm sure I recognise one of the voices.'
Mrs Nickleby listened, and opened her mouth
with surprise.
She bent forwards and looked around the curtain
between the seats.
'Kate!'
she said.
'What a lovely surprise!'
'Mother!'
Kate replied, equally surprised.
'What are you doing here?'
Then she noticed a man sitting in the shadows
behind her mother.
He was smiling at Kate and kissing the back
of his hand.
'Who is that man with you?'
Kate whispered.
'You'll never guess!'
replied Mrs Nickleby loudly, so that Mrs Wititterly
could hear.
'This is Sir Mulberry Hawk.'
Kate remembered the horrible old man from
her uncle's dinner party, and her face went
pale.
However, Mrs Nickleby mistook the strange
look on her daughter's face for shyness - the
shyness of love!
Mrs Wititterly was as excited as Mrs Nickleby,
because Sir Mulberry Hawk was such an important
gentleman.
She told her husband to invite Sir Mulberry
and Mrs Nickleby to sit with them.
'Dear Kate,' said Mrs Nickleby, kissing her
daughter.
'How ill you looked a moment ago!
You frightened me!'
'It was nothing, Mother,' Kate replied, but
it was too late to explain her true feelings
to her.
She greeted Sir Mulberry politely, then turned
her head towards the stage.
Sir Mulberry sat behind her all evening, and
she could not enjoy the play.
When the play had finished, Sir Mulberry took
her arm.
Kate tried to escape and walk away, but Sir
Mulberry pulled her back.
'Don't hurry,' he said.
'Let me go immediately, sir,' Kate whispered
angrily.
'My dear girl, why do you pretend to dislike
me so much?'
'Pretend!'
Kate repeated.
'How impolite of you, sir, to talk to me in
this way!'
'You look prettier when you're angry,' Sir
Mulberry said, moving his face closer to hers.
'I hate you, sir,' Kate said, pulling back
from him.
'You show scorn for my feelings.
If you do not let me join my friends immediately,
you'll be sorry.
I can be rude, too.
I know how to embarrass a man like you in
public.'
Sir Mulberry smiled, but did not let go of
her arm.
When they had reached the front of the theatre,
Kate pulled away from him angrily.
She hurried past her mother and the Wititterlys
without a word.
Then she jumped into the waiting carriage,
threw herself into the darkest corner and
cried.
The next day, Kate received a long letter
from her mother, congratulating her on her
choice of future husband!
Kate felt more upset than ever, but she had
to try to forget her unhappiness.
Her job was to be cheerful with Mrs Wititterly.
That afternoon, while she was reading to her
employer, there was a knock on the door.
'That's Sir Mulberry Hawk,' Mrs Wititterly
smiled from her sofa.
'I gave him permission to visit.
Aren't you pleased?'
Before Kate could answer, the door opened
and Sir Mulberry walked into the room.
He sat with the two ladies for over an hour.
Mr Wititterly sat with them, too, enjoying
the visit of such an important guest.
But Kate refused to be friendly.
Sir Mulberry seemed to find Kate's unfriendliness
attractive, and he visited the house every
day for the next two weeks.
However, as his feelings for Kate became clearer,
there was a change in Mrs Wititterly's behaviour.
Jealous of the attention that he gave to Kate,
she became less friendly towards her.
Poor Kate had never been so sad.
She already had to suffer Sir Mulberry Hawk's
visits every afternoon.
Now she had to suffer Mrs Wititterly's increasing
coldness towards her, too.
Eventually, the two women had a big argument,
and Kate hurried to her uncle's house.
Ralph Nickleby was counting money in his office
when his niece arrived.
He quickly hid the money, put an empty purse
on his desk and told Newman Noggs to show
her in.
'Well, my dear, what's the matter now?' he
asked.
Her eyes shone with anger as she told him
about Sir Mulberry.
'He's such a rude, unpleasant man,' she said.
'Mother thinks that he's a gentleman, but
she's wrong.
Why did you allow him to meet me in this way?'
Something about her proud expression reminded
Ralph of Nicholas.
'There is some of that boy's blood in you,
I see,' he said.
'I hope there is!'
replied Kate.
'And I'm proud of it.
As I am your brother's child, I will not accept
these insults anymore.'
'What insults, girl?'
'That man treats me like a toy.
Uncle, you have to stop him.
I'm sure that you will help me.
I have no one to advise me or protect me except
for you.
Please help me.'
'How can I help you, child?'
Ralph said, rising from his chair and walking
up and down behind his desk.
'Tell him to leave me alone.'
'No,' Ralph shook his head.
'I can't do that.'
Kate looked at him in surprise.
'He's an important customer.
I can't afford to offend him.
You'll have to live with it.
He'll soon get bored with you.
Just be patient...'
'Patient!'
Kate cried.
'I'd rather live on the street than have to
see that man again.'
Before Ralph could say another word, she left
the room.
As she was closing the door behind her, she
was surprised to find Newman Noggs standing
in the hall.
'I heard everything,' he said.
'You're right to be strong in front of him.
Oh, yes!
Ha-ha-ha!
Oh, yes, you poor thing.'
He walked slowly across the hall and opened
the door to let her out into the street.
'Don't be sad,' he whispered.
'I shall see you soon.
Ha-ha-ha.
And so will somebody else.
Yes, yes.'
'Thank you,' Kate answered, hurrying past
him.
'You're very kind.'
She walked quickly back to Mrs Wititterly's
house, trying to understand Newman's strange
words.
She did not know that Newman had received
a letter from Nicholas.
Her brother and Smike were working for a small
theatre company in the south of England.
Newman knew Nicholas's address, and planned
to write to him about Kate's problems as soon
as he could.
CHAPTER SIX
Nicholas Fights Back
Nicholas's anger was greater than his pain,
and he threw himself at Sir Mulberry.
When Nicholas received Newman's letter, he
and Smike returned to London immediately.
They went straight to Newman's lodgings, but
the clerk was not at home.
Nicholas left Smike to wait for him, and went
to see Miss La Creevy, who was not at home
either.
After thinking for a moment, he decided to
see his mother.
A servant girl told him that Mrs Nickleby
was at the theatre for the evening.
She also told him that his sister now lived
at a different address.
Nicholas walked anxiously along the streets,
wondering what to do.
Feeling hungry, he stopped outside a handsome
hotel.
An expensive place,' he thought.
'But a glass of wine and a piece of cake will
not cost too much.'
He went into the hotel and entered the coffee-room.
It was empty except for a noisy group of four
gentlemen at one table.
Nicholas sat down at a table near the fire,
ordered some wine and cake, and began to read
a newspaper.
Suddenly, he heard one of the men at the other
table say his sister s name, and looked up
from his paper with surprise.
'Little Kate Nickleby!'
the other three men said, lifting their glasses.
The four men drank their wine, put their empty
glasses on the table and started laughing.
Nicholas's face burned with anger, but he
did not move.
'She's a clever little thing,' the first man
said.
'She pretends that she doesn't like me, but
she's only playing a game.
She's like her uncle.'
'Perhaps her mother is jealous,' another man
said.
'She's locked her daughter up.
That's why you can't see her.'
'That's no problem,' the first man said.
'I can do anything with the old lady.
She'll believe anything I tell her.'
The four men started laughing again.
Nicholas rose angrily and walked across to
their table.
'I'd like to speak to you, sir,' he said,
staring at the man who had spoken last.
'With me, sir?'
Sir Mulberry Hawk replied, looking at Nicholas
with drunken scorn.
'With you, sir, in private,' Nicholas replied
quietly.
'A mysterious stranger!'
Sir Mulberry laughed, lifting his wine-glass
to his thick, ugly lips and looking round
at his friends.
'Do you refuse to speak to me?'
Nicholas said.
'Tell me what you want or go away,' Sir Mulberry
answered, drinking more wine.
Nicholas took a card from his pocket and threw
it on the table.
'There, sir,' he said.
'You will know what I want when you see my
name.'
Sir Mulberry read the name on the card, threw
it back onto the table and continued drinking.
'Your name and address, sir?'
Nicholas said quietly, shaking with anger.
'I shall give you neither,' replied Sir Mulberry.
'If you are not a gentleman, sir, perhaps
one of your friends is.
Can anybody give me this man's name and address?'
There was silence around the table.
'I am the brother of the young lady who has
been the subject of conversation at this table,
Nicholas said.
'This man is a lying coward.
If no one will tell me his name or address,
I can easily discover it.'
Sir Mulberry looked at Nicholas with scorn,
then said to his friends, 'Let him talk until
midnight if he wants.
I have nothing serious to say to a boy of
his low class.
The four men continued laughing and drinking,
so Nicholas returned to his table and waited.
Eventually, three of the men went home, leaving
Sir Mulberry alone in the room with Nicholas.
Sir Mulberry sat in silence, staring at the
wall with drunken, empty eyes.
Nicholas watched and waited, but said nothing.
At last, Sir Mulberry gave Nicholas another
long, scornful look and rose slowly to his
feet.
With the waiter's help, he put on his gloves,
hat and coat.
Then he walked outside.
Nicholas followed him into the street.
'Will you tell me who you are?' he said again.
'No.'
'I shall hold on to your carriage if you don't
tell me.'
'I shall tell my driver to hit you if you
do.'
'You're an evil man.'
'And what are you?'
'I'm the son of a country gentleman,' Nicholas
replied.
'I'm the same as you in birth and background,
and better than you in everything else.
I tell you again, Miss Nickleby is my sister.
Will you or will you not tell me who you are?'
'I'd tell a real gentleman, but not a boy
like you.
Get out of my way, dog!'
Sir Mulberry pushed him to one side and got
into his carriage.
Nicholas jumped forward and put his hands
on the door.
'I will not let you leave until you...'
Before he could finish his sentence, Sir Mulberry
lifted his stick and hit him hard on the side
of the head.
Nicholas's anger was greater than his pain,
and he threw himself at Sir Mulberry.
In the fight that followed, he managed to
take hold of the stick and hit Sir Mulberry
across the face with its heavy handle.
Sir Mulberry fell back into the carriage and
Nicholas fell to the ground.
Frightened by the fighting, the horse ran
off wildly down the street, pulling the carriage
behind it.
Nicholas felt sick, but he rose painfully
to his feet.
There was loud shouting all around him as
the driver and other men ran after the carriage.
As soon as the carriage disappeared around
a corner, there was a loud crash, a scream
and the sound of breaking glass.
When Nicholas arrived back at the lodgings,
he found Newman Noggs sitting by the fire
with Smike.
'What have you been doing?'
Newman asked when he saw Nicholas's blood-covered
face.
'Don't worry about me,' Nicholas replied.
'I'm not badly hurt.
But I want you to tell me about my sister.
I've learnt part of the story tonight.
You must tell me the rest.'
Newman made Nicholas take off his coat and
washed the blood from his face.
While he was doing this, he told him everything
about his uncle, Sir Mulberry Hawk and his
sister.
Nicholas listened in silence, then told Newman
about his fight earlier that evening.
'I'm sure that was Sir Mulberry,' Newman said.
Tomorrow morning, we must find another place
for my mother to live,' Nicholas replied.
Could you send Miss La Creevy to tell her?
Please don't say anything about what happened
tonight.
I also want you to deliver a short letter
to my uncle.'
Early the next morning, Nicholas went to see
his sister at Mrs Wititterly s house.
Brother and sister immediately fell into each
other's arms.
'I've been so unhappy, dear brother,' Kate
cried.
'Don't leave me here or I shall die of a broken
heart.'
'I'll never leave you anywhere again,' Nicholas
promised.
Apologising quickly to the Wititterlys, he
hurried with his sister to their mother's
house by the river.
'Miss La Creevy has told me everything,' Mrs
Nickleby sighed when they arrived.
'But I still don't understand.
Is Sir Mulberry such a bad man?
Why don't you speak to your uncle?
Perhaps there has been some mistake...?'
'My dear mother,' Nicholas replied, 'the time
for talking has gone.
After the terrible things that he has done,
you must throw him out of your life.
We do not owe him anything except our scorn.
You must leave this house at once.
We can stay in our old place at Miss La Creevy's
until I can make other arrangements.'
'Everything is ready for you,' Miss La Creevy
said.
'You'll all be very welcome.'
'But I've just spent eighteen pence on painting
the ceiling,' Mrs Nickleby complained, and
started crying.
While Miss La Creevy looked after their mother,
Nicholas and Kate carried the furniture into
a waiting cart.
After the three women had finally left, Nicholas
hurried to meet Newman.
He gave him a letter for his uncle and the
key to the house.
'When you see my mother and sister at Miss
La Creevy's, don't say anything about last
night,' he reminded him.
Newman took the letter and key, and gave them
to Ralph in his office.
'What's this?'
Ralph said, picking up the key.
'It came with the letter.
A boy brought them a quarter of an hour ago,'
Newman lied.
Ralph opened the letter and read:
I know all about you and your evil plans.
Your brother's widow and her daughter refuse
any more of your help.
They hate you as much as I do.
I hope that on your death-bed you will feel
ashamed of yourself.
Ralph Nickleby read the letter twice, then
dropped it to the floor.
He sat quietly at his desk, staring angrily
at the wall.
He did not notice the small smile on his old
clerk's lips.
CHAPTER SEVEN
A Change of Luck
'But I am looking for work,' Nicholas replied.
'What?' the old man said with surprise.
Two days later, Ralph Nickleby learnt about
Nicholas's attack on Sir Mulberry Hawk.
He sat in his office and wondered what to
do about the boy.
While he was thinking, he received an unexpected
visit from Wackford Squeers.
Squeers had come to London to find more pupils
for Dotheboys Hall, and he also wanted to
talk to Ralph about his nephew.
The two men sat together, planning their revenge.
Meanwhile, Mrs Nickleby and Kate were back
in their old rooms in Miss La Creevy's house,
and Nicholas decided to introduce them to
Smike.
Smike was shy at first, but Kate and Miss
La Creevy were very kind to him.
They soon persuaded Mrs Nickleby, who was
unsure of him, to let him stay.
The next day, Nicholas returned to the job
agency near Oxford Street.
Before he went in, he looked at the advertisements
in the window.
While he was looking, an old gentleman in
a blue coat and white hat walked towards the
window and stood in the street next to him.
Nicholas looked at him out of the corner of
his eye.
The old gentleman suddenly looked at Nicholas,
and Nicholas looked away.
'I'm sorry,' he said, his face red with embarrassment.
'I didn't mean to be rude.'
'I'm not offended,' the man said with a smile.
There was something so friendly about the
man's smile, his round face and the warm look
in his eyes, that Nicholas spoke again.
'There are a lot of jobs here, sir,' he said,
half-smiling.
'There are,' the man agreed.
'I feel so sorry for the people who have to
come here.'
He began to move away, but then noticed Nicholas's
expression.
'You wanted to say something, young man?'
he said.
'I was wondering why you were looking at these
advertisements,' Nicholas replied.
'Did you think I was looking for work?'
Nicholas shook his head.
'Ha!
Ha!' laughed the old gentleman.
'A very natural thought, I suppose.
I thought the same about you.'
'But I am looking for work,' Nicholas replied.
'What?' the old man said with surprise.
'A well-behaved, polite young gentleman like
you?
I don't believe it.'
Nicholas told him about the death of his father
and the unhappy situation of his poor mother
and sister.
Before he realized it, he had told the kind
old man almost everything about his life.
He did not, however, say much about his uncle.
The old man listened with great attention.
When Nicholas had finished his story, he said,
'Come along with me.
We mustn't lose a minute.'
The old gentleman took Nicholas across London
to a quiet square in East London, near the
Bank of England, and led him into the oldest,
cleanest-looking house in the square.
The name Cheeryble Brothers was above the
door.
Nicholas followed the old gentleman across
a large, busy hall that was filled with boxes
of cotton and other material.
They went across a yard and into another building.
Inside this building, which was the counting-house,
an old, large-faced man with silver glasses
was sitting at a desk.
'Is my brother in his room, Tim?' asked the
old gentleman.
'Yes, he is, Mr Cheeryble,' replied the old
clerk, looking at Nicholas over the top of
his glasses.
Mr Cheeryble led Nicholas into another office.
Nicholas couldn't believe his eyes when he
saw Mr Cheeryble's brother - the two gentlemen
looked exactly the same!
'Brother Ned, I'd like you to meet a young
friend of mine who needs our help.'
'What does he need, Brother Charles?'
the other man asked, looking at Nicholas with
a kind smile.
Charles told his brother the details of Nicholas's
situation and, after a long conversation,
Ned went next door to speak to the old clerk,
Tim Linkinwater.
When he returned, he brought Tim Linkinwater
with him.
'We've decided,' Ned told Nicholas, 'that
you can work in the counting-house with Mr
Linkinwater.
Would you like that?'
Nicholas's eyes filled with tears of happiness.
He did not know what to say.
'No, no, not a word now,' Charles said as
Nicholas tried to thank him.
'You must return home.
Your mother and sister will be worried about
you.
After we have checked a few details about
you, Tim Linkinwater will visit you tonight.'
Nicholas returned home and told everybody
his good news.
That evening, Tim Linkinwater arrived and
invited Nicholas to start work the next morning.
'The brothers will pay you 120 pounds a year,'
Tim informed him.
'In addition to this, you and your family
are welcome to move into a small cottage that
belongs to them.
It's not far from the office, the rent is
very low, and they will also lend you the
money to buy furniture.'
One week later, Mrs Nickleby, Kate, Smike
and Nicholas moved into their new home.
Meanwhile, several miles away, Ralph Nickleby
was still busy planning his revenge.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Kidnap
As Smike was crossing the corner of a side-street,
he felt a hand on his collar.
While Mrs Nickleby, Kate and Miss La Creevy
were busy decorating the cottage and Nicholas
was busy in his new job, Smike spent all his
time working in the garden.
As the garden filled with flowers, his heart
filled with happiness.
'You've made the garden a place of great beauty,
Smike,' Kate told him one evening, standing
next him and looking at the flowers.
'We're all so happy to see you so happy.'
Mrs Nickleby also saw how enthusiastically
he worked and how much pleasure the garden
gave him.
She became very fond of him, too, and soon
everybody was treating him as a member of
the family.
Smike had never felt so happy.
One evening, he was walking back to the cottage
in East London from Miss La Creevy's house.
As he was crossing the corner of a side-street,
he felt a hand on his collar.
Then he was pulled backwards and pushed against
a wall.
'Well, what a surprise!' said Wackford Squeers,
looking at Smike with his one eye.
Then he turned to his son, who was jumping
up and down with excitement next to him.
'Wackford, my boy, go and find a coach.'
Smike fought and kicked as hard as he could,
but he was too weak to escape.
Soon a coach arrived and Squeers pushed Smike
inside.
He sat down opposite the frightened boy and
stared at him with an unpleasant smile.
Then, with a loud laugh, he hit Smike several
times across the face.
'It isn't a dream!' he laughed.
'It's real.
You thought that you could escape me, didn't
you?
Well, you were wrong!'
'Let me go home!'
Smike cried, looking wildly around.
'You are going home!'
Squeers replied, hitting him again.
'You'll soon be back at Dotheboys Hall, where
you belong.'
After a long journey, the coach stopped outside
a small house with green windows.
Squeers pulled Smike out of the coach, paid
the driver and pushed Smike into the house.
In the front room, a fat man was having dinner
with his wife.
His name was Snawley, and he had sent his
two sons to Dotheboys Hall.
When he had invited Squeers and his son to
stay at his house while they were in London,
Squeers had accepted immediately - it was
much cheaper than staying at the Saracen's
Head!
'Here's the boy that ran away and stole my
wife's ring,' Squeers told the surprised couple.
'The ungrateful little animal!
If there wasn't a lady here, I would hit him!'
'Where has he been staying?'
Mr Snawley asked.
'Probably with that man Nickleby.
Is that right, Smike?'
Smike refused to answer, so Squeers pushed
him upstairs into a small room.
He took the boy's shoes and coat and locked
him inside.
The next morning, Squeers was having breakfast
at the Saracen's Head with his son when three
people walked into the coffee-room.
His daughter, Fanny, with her friend Tilda
and Tilda's new husband, John Browdie, had
just arrived from Yorkshire for a short holiday
in London.
While they were all having breakfast, Squeers
told them about Smike.
'Poor boy,' John Browdie said when Squeers
had finished his story.
'Where are you keeping him?'
'On the top floor of my lodgings,' Squeers
replied.
John Browdie laughed loudly and shook the
schoolmaster's hand.
'The cleverest schoolmaster in all England!'
he said.
'Congratulations!'
'Thank you,' Squeers said, pulling his hand
away.
'It's lucky you came today.
We're travelling back to Yorkshire tomorrow
morning.
If you don't come for tea with me this evening,
you won't see us again in London.'
'We'll be at your lodgings at six o'clock
tonight,' John Browdie promised.
Squeers gave the farmer Mr Snawley's address,
then left with his son.
That evening, John Browdie, Tilda and Fanny
arrived at Snawley's house at six o'clock
exactly.
John seemed strangely quiet while they were
having tea in the front room.
After a short time he said, 'I don't feel
very well.
It's probably the long journey and all the
excitement.
I think I need to lie down for half an hour.'
Tilda helped him upstairs into Squeers's bedroom.
John closed his eyes, and Tilda returned downstairs.
'He's sleeping like a baby,' she told the
others.
In fact, John Browdie was not sleeping at
all.
When his wife had gone downstairs, he got
off the bed, took off his shoes and softly
left the room.
The key to the room next to his was still
in the door.
Quietly turning it, he opened the door and
hurried inside, where Smike was lying quietly
on the bed under a thin blanket.
'Don't be afraid,' John whispered, putting
his big hand gently over Smike's mouth.
'I'm here to help you escape.'
Not knowing who this big stranger was, and
shaking with fear, Smike went with the farmer
into the next bedroom, where he found his
coat and shoes on a chair.
He put them on and followed the big man quietly
down the stairs.
He felt even more frightened when he heard
Squeers and the others talking in the front
room.
'Don't worry,' John whispered when they reached
the bottom of the stairs.
'I'll make sure that no one follows you.'
He opened the front door quietly.
'Quickly!
Go now!'
Smike gave Browdie a confused but grateful
look, and ran off into the darkness.
A few hours later, he arrived at Newman Noggs's
lodgings and, after a hot drink, told him
his story.
'You're tired,' Noggs said, when Smike had
finished talking.
'You must stay here for the night.
I'll tell the others that you're back.
They've been worried about you all day.'
But Smike refused to be left alone and walked
with Noggs through the dark, empty streets
of London.
They arrived at the Nickleby's cottage just
as it was getting light.
Everybody was relieved to see him.
There was much congratulation and noisy conversation,
and Smike cried with happiness to be safely
back with his 'family' again.
CHAPTER NINE
Love and War
'But I have a secret that will interest you.
'
'Tell the world about it.
I don't care.'
Later that morning, in the counting-house,
Nicholas found it difficult to work.
He was thinking about how to punish Wackford
Squeers for kidnapping Smike.
He was sure that his uncle had planned it.
He was still thinking about this when he opened
the door into Charles Cheeryble's office.
There, he saw a young lady on her knees at
Mr Cheeryble's feet.
It was the same girl that he had seen on his
first visit to the job agency!
Nicholas was so filled with surprise and affected
by the girl's beauty that he could not move
or speak.
All thoughts of revenge against his uncle
and Squeers disappeared from his mind.
There were tears in the girl's eyes as she
repeatedly thanked Mr Cheeryble for his kindness.
Mr Cheeryble looked embarrassed and was asking
her to rise.
Nicholas quietly left the room before the
girl could see him.
Later that morning, he asked Tim Linkinwater
about the young lady in Mr Cheeryble's office,
but the old clerk pretended not to hear.
Nicholas waited for the mysterious young lady's
next visit, but days passed and there was
no sign of her.
Then, one day, he was sent out on some unusual
business.
He was sure that the young lady was visiting
the office while he was away.
This happened several times.
Why, Nicholas thought, was everybody so unwilling
to talk about her?
As the days passed, Nicholas could think of
nothing except the beautiful young lady.
Soon, he realised that he had fallen in love.
He had to find out more informadon about her!
Eventually, he could not keep the secret to
himself.
He told Newman Noggs about her and Newman
promised to help.
'The next time you're sent away on business,'
he said, 'I'll wait outside the building.
When she leaves, I'll follow her home.
Then I can tell you where she lives.'
Two days later, Nicholas was sent out on another
piece of strange business.
That evening, he returned excitedly and asked
Newman for news.
Unfortunately, Newman could not help him.
He had followed the wrong girl!
One evening, Ralph Nickleby was walking near
St James's Park, on his way home.
Although he had collected a lot of money for
his business that day, he was in a bad mood.
His heart was still poisoned with anger for
his nephew, and he was still thinking of revenge.
Sir Mulberry Hawk could not help him.
He had been so badly hurt and publicly embarrassed
after his fight with Nicholas that he had
left London as soon as possible.
Squeers had returned to Yorkshire, but that
was no problem.
He was thinking of a plan, and Squeers was
going to help him succeed!
While he was walking it began to rain, so
Ralph stood under a tree, still lost in thought.
Suddenly, he noticed a man standing next to
him.
He was the same age as he was, but wore dirty,
old clothes, and had a thin, hungry face.
His skin was sunburnt, and his hair was pure
white.
'You don't remember me, do you?'
the man said.
Ralph stared at him.
Then he stepped back in shock.
Yes, he remembered the man.
His name was Brooker.
He had known him for a long time, but he had
not seen him for eight years.
'I used to be your friend,' Brooker reminded
him.
'I'm hungry.
I only need a little bread...'
'Is this the way that you usually beg for
money?'
Ralph coldly replied.
'Yesterday was my first day back in London,
the old man continued.
I've been looking for you.
I'm nearly sixty years old and I have nothing
in the world.'
'I'm sixty years old, too, Ralph said.
But I don't beg people for bread.
I work and earn money for it.'
'I used to bring you good business, but you
never thanked me.
When I asked you for more money, you refused.
Instead, you told the police about my debts
and I was sent away on a prison ship for eight
years.
What help will you give me now:
'None.'
'But I have a secret that will interest you.'
'Tell the world about it.
I don't care.
I'm not giving you any help.
Now go away, or I shall make sure you go to
prison again.
And this time you'll never get out.'
With those words, Ralph walked off into the
rain.
Brooker stared at his back, his eyes filled
with hate.
At the end of their holiday in London, John
Browdie and Tilda were having tea at the Nicklebys'
cottage.
While everybody was laughing and joking, there
was a loud knock on the door and Ralph Nickleby
walked in, followed by Wackford Squeers and
Mr Snawley.
'Listen to what I have to say,' he told them.
John Browdie and Nicholas stood up angrily,
but Ralph looked straight past them at Mrs
Nickleby.
'I shall talk to you, ma'am,' he said.
'I know that your mad son will refuse to listen
to me.
I am here to return a child to his parent.'
He pointed at Smike, who was shaking with
fear behind Nicholas's back.
'I have brought that boy's father here with
me tonight.'
'My son!'
cried Mr Snawley, hurrying past Nicholas and
taking Smike in his arms.
'I've found you at last!'
'This is the boy's father,' Ralph said, pointing
at Snawley, 'and here are the documents that
prove it.'
He left the documents on the table for Nicholas
and John Browdie to study.
'Dear Nicholas,' Kate said at last, looking
over her brother's shoulder, 'is it true?'
'I'm afraid it is,' Nicholas replied quietly.
'Good!' said Squeers.
'So he's coming with us.
There's a coach waiting outside, and the horses
are getting cold.'
'No!'
cried Smike, pulling away from Snawley.
'I'm not leaving!'
Squeers moved forwards, but John Browdie pushed
him away and he fell to the floor.
After a lot of loud argument and angry shouting,
Nicholas picked Squeers up by the collar and
threw him out of the door.
'I want my son,' Snawley demanded.
Your son wants to stay here,' Nicholas replied.
'And I will not let him go back to that school!'
Snawley left the room, but Ralph stayed behind.
He stared at Nicholas angrily.
Mr Snawley is the boy's father,' he said,
'and he will have him.'
CHAPTER TEN
Madeline Bray
Nicholas left the room and went down the stairs,
his heart illed with happiness.
He had found his love at last!
The next day, Nicholas told Charles Cheeryble
everything that had happened.
Charles listened carefully.
'Your story does not surprise me,' he said.
'Your uncle visited us this morning.
He came here to complain about you, to poison
our ears with lies.
But we refused to listen and made him leave.'
'How can I ever thank you?'
Nicholas said, relieved that he had such good
friends.
'By saying nothing more about the subject,'
Charles replied.
'Don't worry.
We shall protect you and your family.
But now I have a job for you.
It's a special job.
You accidentally saw a young lady in my office
some time ago.
Or perhaps you have forgotten...
'Oh no, sir,' Nicholas said, a feeling of
great excitement rising inside him.
'I remember it very well.'
'Her mother was a very beautiful woman,' Charles
said.
'I was in love with her, but she married another
man.
Their life was not happy.
They had a daughter - the girl you saw in
my office - but they had no money.
Twelve months before her death, the mother
came to me for help.
I gave her money, which her husband wasted.
When she died, she was a sad, heart-broken
woman.
'Her husband is still alive.
He owes money to a lot of people, and he lives
in a secret place to hide from them.
His daughter worked for two long years to
give him money, but eventually she needed
help.
She came to me because I had been a friend
of her mother's, and I offered to help her.
But she only accepted a very small amount
of money.
I wanted to help her more, but she refused.
Her father is still alive and he hates me.
He knows that his wife really wanted to marry
me.
If he knew the money came from me, he would
waste it all.
Madeline comes to me secretly, usually by
night, but only accepts the smallest amount
of money.
This situation cannot continue, Nicholas,
and I want you to help me.
'I'd be glad to,' Nicholas said.
'What do you want me to do?'
She's a wonderful artist, but she doesn't
sell anything.
You can visit her and pay for some paintings.
Madeline will know that Ned and I have sent
you, but her father will not know that you
have not ordered any.
You will pay a good price and her father will
not know that the money comes from Ned and
myself.'
Nicholas, of course, agreed to help at once.
The young lady and her father (whose name
was Bray) lived in a cheap, dirty house near
the prison.
Nicholas knocked on the door nervously, and
was shown upstairs.
Although there was not much furniture, the
small room was filled with flowers and paintings.
And at a little table by the window sat the
young lady of Nicholas's dreams!
She was quietly painting, and seemed to Nicholas
more beautiful than ever.
In a chair by the empty fireplace sat her
father - a sick man in his fifties who looked
much older.
'Madeline, who is this?'
Mr Bray said.
'Who said that strangers could visit us here?'
'I've come to pay for some paintings that
your daughter did for me, Mr Bray,' Nicholas
said, placing an envelope on the table in
front of the girl.
'Check the money, Madeline,' Mr Bray said.
'I'm sure the money's correct, Father,' Madeline
said softly.
'If that's true, ring the bell.
Tell the servant to get me a newspaper, some
fresh fruit and a bottle of wine!'
'I also want to order something else,' Nicholas
said.
'Perhaps a picture of the trees in the park?
Don't worry about the time or cost.
When would you like me to call again?'
'Three or four weeks,' Madeline replied, looking
at Nicholas shyly.
'No - sooner!'
her father said.
'We'll need more money before then!'
Nicholas left the room and went down the stairs,
his heart filled with happiness.
He had found his love at last!
Meanwhile, several miles away, Ralph was talking
to a man in his office.
Arthur Gride was also a moneylender.
He was an ugly old man of about seventy-five
years old, with a pointed chin, toothless
mouth and unhealthy yellow skin.
But this did not stop him from talking about
love!
'I'm a lucky man,' said Arthur Gride.
'I'm going to get married.'
'You?
Who would want to marry you?'
Ralph smiled scornfully.
'A toothless old woman as ugly as yourself?'
'No,' Arthur said.
'She's a beautiful young girl with dark eyes,
and lovely red lips - and she's only eighteen
years old!'
'What s her name?'
Ralph asked, staring at Gride coldly.
'Do you remember Walter Bray?
We both did business with him, and he owes
us both money.
I've visited him several times over the last
six months.
He owes me 1700 pounds.'
'And he owes me over 900 pounds,' Ralph said.
'But why are you telling me about him now?
'Well, I'm going to marry his daughter, Madeline.
I haven't asked her father yet, but he'll
agree.
If he lets me marry his daughter, I'll forget
his debts.
I'll even give him some money and a place
to live across the river.
I've talked to his doctor, and he won't live
long.
He's certain to agree to my request, don't
you think?
His daughter will have to obey him, but I
need your help.'
'How?'
'I'm a shy, nervous man.
I need you to talk to the father for me.
You're good with words.
He'll listen to you.'
'There's something more, isn't there?'
Ralph said, narrowing his eyes and studying
Arthur's ugly old face.
'No, no...'
'Don't lie.
I know you.
You're as greedy as I am.
If you don't tell me everything, I won't help
you.'
'Well, there's a little house that belongs
to this girl.
Nobody knows about it - not even her.
If I marry her, the house will be mine.'
'All right,' Ralph said, smiling thoughtfully.
'I agree to help you.
But you must promise to pay me all of the
money that Bray owes me.
I also want an extra 500 pounds.'
After much complaining, Gride unwillingly
agreed.
The two men left immediately to visit Walter
Bray and, after half an hour of listening
to Ralph, Bray agreed to his daughter's marriage
one week later.
Life for the Nicklebys in their cottage was
good.
The Cheeryble brothers visited them often.
Sometimes, they brought with them their nephew,
Frank, who had just returned from abroad.
They spent many happy evenings together.
Although Nicholas was happy, too, he was worried
about Smike.
The boy had recently become much quieter.
He also seemed to be growing weaker, and spent
more time alone in his room.
However, the doctor told Nicholas not to worry.
The kidnap had been a bad experience for Smike,
and he needed time to forget it.
One night, while Frank Cheeryble was telling
Mrs Nickleby and Kate about his adventures
abroad, Nicholas went up to Smike's room.
The boy was lying quietly in his bed.
'What's the matter?'
Nicholas asked softly.
'Are you feeling ill?'
'No, I'm all right,' Smike replied.
But you seem so sad.
Won't you tell me why?'
'I can't.
Not now.
I hate myself for being like this.
You're all so good and kind to me.
But my heart is full.
You don't know how full it is.
One day, I'll tell you the reason.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
An Evil Marriage
'No gentleman would make his daughter do what
you are making your daughter do.'
Nicholas met Newman Noggs for a drink and
Noggs gave him news about his uncle.
A strange man called Brooker kept coming to
the office, but Ralph refused to meet him.
Nicholas then told Noggs about his job, and
about the beautiful girl with the sick father.
When he told him her name, Newman jumped up
from his chair.
'Oh, no!' he cried.
'How can you do nothing and let this terrible
marriage happen?'
'What do you mean?'
Nicholas said, confused by his friend's strange
behaviour.
'Haven't you heard?'
Newman said, his eyes moving around wildly.
'Tomorrow she's going to marry a horrible
old moneylender called Arthur Gride - a man
worse than your uncle, if that's possible.
Your uncle has arranged it all.
I heard them discussing it in his office last
week.'
Nicholas stood up and forced Newman down into
his chair.
'Tell me everything!' he demanded.
Newman told him the details of what he had
heard.
When he had finished, a wild look came into
Nicholas's eyes.
'What are you going to do?'
Newman asked, frightened.
'What can I do?'
Nicholas replied, his face pale with anger.
'The brothers are out of town on business.
If I visit my uncle, I'll only make things
worse.
No, I must go and see Madeline immediately
and tell her of my true feelings for her.
When her father sees how much I love his daughter,
perhaps he'll change his mind.
It's my only hope!'
Before Newman could say anything to stop him,
Nicholas ran out into the street.
When he arrived at their lodgings, Madeline
and her father were sitting in their room.
Nicholas had not seen Madeline for three weeks,
and he was shocked by the terrible paleness
of her face and the dark shadows under her
lovely eyes.
The room had changed, too.
There were no paintings on the walls or flowers
on the table.
'What do you want?
Bray said from his chair by the fire.
'Be quick, because my daughter and I have
important things to think about.
'There's something that I need to discuss
with your daughter in private, sir,' Nicholas
said politely, hiding his anger with difficulty.
'We don't need your business anymore,' Bray
replied rudely 'So you can leave, unless you
have something else to say?'
'Only this,' Nicholas said, unable to control
his anger anymore.
'I thought you were a gentleman, sir, but
I was wrong.
No gentleman would make his daughter do what
you are making your daughter do.'
'You can't talk to me like that!'
Bray said angrily.
'You're only an ordinary shop-boy!'
He tried to stand up, but his anger had made
him weak.
He fell back in his chair and closed his eyes.
Nicholas took Madeline's arm and led her quietly
out of the room.
'If you have more business for me,' Madeline
said anxiously when they were outside the
room, 'please leave it until the day after
tomorrow.'
'That will be too late,' Nicholas replied.
Madeline tried to walk away, but Nicholas
gently stopped her.
'Please listen to me,' he said.
She stared at him quietly as he tried to persuade
her not to marry Arthur Gride.
'I have no choice,' she explained.
'It is my duty to my father.'
He tried again, but she refused to listen
and she went back into the room to be with
her father.
Nicholas returned home, his heart aching with
unhappiness.
That evening, he visited Arthur Gride.
He told the old moneylender that Madeline
Bray hated him.
'If you were a gentleman, you would think
about the pain in that innocent girl's heart,'
Nicholas said.
Gride listened to him in scornful silence,
then said, 'I understand you better than you
think.
You want her for yourself, don't you?
But you can't have her!
She's my lovely little wife.
Do you think she'll cry for you?
I hope so, because she looks prettier in tears.'
'You evil old man,' Nicholas said, his face
red with anger.
Without warning, Arthur Gride ran across the
room and put his head out of the window.
'Help!
Help!' he shouted into the street.
'Thief!
Robber!'
Nicholas was so angry that he almost attacked
Arthur Gride.
Instead, he turned quickly and left the room.
The next morning, Arthur Gride got up early
and put on his best suit.
He spoke to his half-deaf old housekeeper,
Peg Sliderskew, about the arrangements for
food, and then he went to Ralph Nickleby's
house.
Ralph laughed when he heard about his nephews
visit the night before.
'Good!' he thought.
'I'm getting revenge on him at last!'
The two men hired a coach and went to Walter
Bray's lodgings.
'Where's the lucky girl?'
Ralph asked Bray as soon as he and Gride had
entered the room.
'She was very ill last night,' Bray explained.
'She's crying in her room.
But don't worry; she'll be better in a minute.
It's only a girl's usual nervousness just
before her wedding.'
'She won't delay us, will she?'
Ralph asked.
'No, I've been talking to her all morning.
She'll be down in a minute,' Bray replied.
Arthur Gride sat in a corner of the room and
played impatiently with the buttons of his
coat.
Bray looked at him scornfully.
'Look at that man,' he whispered to Ralph.
'This marriage is a cruel thing to do to an
innocent young girl, don't you think?'
'No,' Ralph replied coldly, surprised by Bray's
sudden pity for his daughter.
'It would be more cruel if he were younger.
He's an old man.
He'll die soon, and Miss Madeline will become
a rich young widow.'
'That's true,' Bray said thoughtfully, but
he still did not look happy.
'I'll go upstairs to finish dressing,' he
said.
'When I come down, I'll bring Madeline with
me.'
When he had left the room, Ralph turned to
Gride.
'He looks very ill,' he said.
'If he doesn't die soon, I'll be very surprised.'
Gride laughed quietly, but did not reply.
The two men sat waiting in silence.
After a short time, they heard footsteps outside
the door - but it was not Bray and his daughter.
It was Nicholas and his sister, Kate!
Ralph stood up, his face pale with anger.
Gride took Ralph's arm, his eyes filled with
fear.
'What do you want?'
Ralph demanded.
'I've come here to save Madeline from this
evil marriage,' Nicholas replied.
'Leave the room, girl,' Ralph told Kate.
'I advise you not to see what I'm going to
do to your brother.'
'I will not go,' Kate said, standing proudly
by her brother.
'I'm going to speak to the girl and her father.
Perhaps they will listen to me.'
'I know how jealous your brother is, Arthur
Gride said from behind Ralph's back.
'But it's too late!
The girl is mine!
Suddenly, there was a loud scream from the
room above them.
Nicholas ran upstairs and saw a crowd of neighbours
already in the bedroom.
'What's happened?'
Nicholas asked.
'It's Mr Bray,' replied an old woman.
'He's dead.'
Nicholas pushed through the crowd and saw
Bray lying on the floor.
Madeline was lying with her head on his shoulder,
crying.
Nicholas gently took her arm and led her from
the room.
'I'm the young girl's nearest friend,' he
informed the watching crowd of neighbours.
'My sister and I will take care of her until
she is well.'
Nobody tried to stop him as he led Madeline,
who was too upset and shocked to refuse, down
the stairs and into the street.
As Kate ran across the road to hire a coach,
Ralph called from the doorway, 'Leave the
girl here!'
'I warn you,' Nicholas shouted back at his
uncle, 'that your evil world is finished!'
With those words, he helped Madeline into
the coach which Kate had found.
Ralph angrily watched the coach disappear
around a corner, then unwillingly agreed to
go back to Gride s house.
When they arrived, Gride knocked on the door,
but there was no answer.
'What's the matter?'
Ralph said impatiently.
'Why doesn't anyone answer?'
'It's Peg, my housekeeper,' Gride explained.
'She's deaf.'
He knocked more loudly until the whole street
could hear him, but still no one answered
the door.
Finally, the two moneylenders climbed over
a fence into Gride's back yard.
The house was dark and empty.
The two men looked in every room, but there
was no sign of Peg.
Then Gride fell on his knees beside a large
box and screamed like an animal in pain.
'I've been robbed!' he cried.
'Robbed?
Of money?'
Ralph wanted to know.
'No, worse than money!
Worse than money!'
Gride shouted, throwing papers around the
room.
'It's my business papers with all my secret
information.
She saw me reading them last night.
She'll show them to someone and they'll take
all my money.
She's destroyed me!'
'Calm down!'
Ralph said, shaking Gride roughly.
'She probably isn't far away.
I'll call the police...'
'No!'
Gride shouted, even more frightened than before.
'If the police see my papers, I'll go to prison!'
Eventually, when Gride had calmed down, Ralph
went home.
A short time later, he sent Newman Noggs with
a letter to the Saracen's Head.
'If Mr Squeers is there,' he told Newman,
'tell him to see me at once.'
When Squeers arrived, Ralph told him how his
nephew had ruined Arthur Gride's wedding to
Madeline Bray.
'If my nephew marries her, he'll become a
very rich man,' he said.
'And that will make him a very dangerous enemy.'
'How will he become rich?'
'It seems that Madeline owns a house.
She doesn't know it, but there are secret
documents to prove it.
Arthur Gride had the papers, but his housekeeper
has stolen them.
I want you to find this woman, and bring the
papers to me.
If I can destroy them, my nephew will never
get the money.
I'll pay you fifty pounds as soon as I have
those papers.'
Squeers listened to this with greedy ears,
his one eye and his mouth wide open.
'But how do I know where to find her?' he
asked.
'Don't worry about that.
People have tried to hide from me before,
but I've always found them.
When I know where she is, I'll tell you.
Your part of the job will be easy.
You will become her friend.
Then you can discover where she has hidden
the papers.
Squeers thought for a moment, then said, 'I'll
do it for a hundred pounds.'
Ralph agreed immediately.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Poor Smike
'I saw him - over there, behind the trees!
It was the man who took me to that horrible
school, years ago!'
Madeline was now living with the Nicklebys
in their cottage, but the shock of her father's
death had made her very ill.
While she stayed in bed, Kate took care of
her, and by the time Madeline's health improved
she and Kate had become good friends.
These were proud times for Mrs Nickleby.
She noticed that Frank Cheeryble often came
to the cottage with Nicholas after work.
She was sure that he was interested in Kate,
and began to dream of a wonderful wedding
for her daughter!
When she told Nicholas about Frank's interest
in Kate, Nicholas was surprised, but he was
also secretly relieved.
He had been afraid that Frank was also in
love in Madeline.
He liked Frank a lot, and he was glad that
they would not have to become enemies.
However, Nicholas became increasingly worried
about Smike, who had become very ill.
The doctor told him that Smike's condition
was serious and he advised him to take the
boy away from London as soon as possible.
The fresh country air might cure him.
So Nicholas took Smike to Devon, in southwest
England, where he had lived as a child.
Meanwhile, Ralph Nickleby had discovered where
Peg Sliderskew, Gride's housekeeper, was living.
She was in an upper room in a dirty old house
near Lambeth, in southeast London.
Ralph informed Squeers, who moved into an
empty room in the same house and soon became
friendly with her.
One evening, he took a bottle of strong alcohol
into her room and sat talking to her by the
fire.
After the old woman had drunk a few glasses,
Squeers told her how Arthur Gride's wedding
plans were ruined.
Peg Sliderskew laughed so much that she nearly
fell out of her chair.
'I'm glad,' she said.
'Gride's a horrible, greedy old man.
He treated me very badly.
That's why I ran away with his papers.'
'I'll be happy to help with Gride's papers,'
Squeers suggested, when Peg was completely
drunk.
'I can tell you which ones to keep and which
ones to burn.'
The old woman walked with a drunken smile
to a cupboard.
She took the papers out of a box and spread
them out on the floor by the fire.
Squeers was so busy studying them that he
did not hear the door opening behind him.
He did not see Frank Cheeryble and Newman
Noggs walking quietly into the room.
Eventually, he found the paper that he wanted.
'Madeline Bray!' he said excitedly, putting
it in his coat pocket.
'What did you say?'
Peg asked, turning her head.
She saw the two men, but it was too late to
save Squeers.
Newman Noggs lifted his arm and brought a
thick stick down heavily onto his head.
The old schoolmaster's one eye opened wide
with surprise, then he fell forwards across
the floor.
After a two-day journey to Devon, Nicholas
rented a small farmhouse.
At first, Smike was strong enough to go for
short walks in the surrounding fields.
Nicholas also hired a horse and cart and drove
Smike around the countryside.
He showed the boy the house where he had lived,
and he even found a rose-tree in the garden
that his little sister Kate had planted.
However, as Smike grew weaker, travelling
became impossible.
On sunny days, Nicholas sat outside with him
under some apple trees.
One evening, they were watching the sun go
down behind the hills.
It was so warm that Nicholas fell asleep.
Suddenly, he was woken by a scream.
'What is it?' he asked anxiously.
'I saw him - over there, behind the trees!
It was the man who took me to that horrible
school, years ago!'
Nicholas searched among the trees, but there
was no one there.
'You were dreaming,' he said when he returned.
'No, I wasn't dreaming,' Smike replied, holding
tightly onto Nicholas's arm.
'Promise me you'll never leave me!
Promise!'
Over the next few days, Smike became much
weaker.
Nicholas saw now that there was no hope for
his young friend.
A life of suffering and pain had made him
too weak to fight his illness.
One fine, autumn day, Nicholas sat by Smike's
bedside.
Smike was lying with his eyes closed, breathing
gently.
Suddenly, he opened his eyes.
There was a small smile on his pale face.
'I've had such pleasant dreams,' he said softly.
'What about?'
Nicholas asked.
The dying boy turned towards him and hugged
his neck.
'I shall soon be there.'
There was a short silence, then Smike spoke
again.
'I'm not afraid to die,' he said.
'But first I must tell you something.
You've been so good to me, and I can't keep
any secrets from you.
You asked me once why I had changed.
Do you remember?
You wondered why I spent so much time alone.
Shall I tell you why?'
Not if it makes you unhappy.'
Smike explained that he had been in love with
Nicholas's sister.
'I've been so unhappy,' he said.
'I'm so sorry.
Will you ever forgive me?'
Nicholas went on his knees by Smike's bed
and held his hand.
'Oh, you poor boy, he said with tears in his
eyes.
'Of course I forgive you.'
Now, Smike said softly, 'I am happy.'
He died later that night, quietly, in his
sleep.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Ralph's Final Defeat
What good was all his money now?
He had murdered his own child.
Ralph sat alone in his room and stared at
his untouched breakfast.
He had a strange feeling that something was
wrong.
It was nearly midday, and Newman Noggs had
still not come to work.
He sent his housekeeper to Noggs s home to
find him.
'He's not there,' she informed him when she
returned.
'He hasn't been home all night, and no one
knows where he is.
But there's a gentleman waiting for you downstairs.'
Ralph went downstairs, where Charles Cheeryble
was waiting to speak to him.
Ralph refused to speak to him, and sent him
away at once.
Then he put on his hat and coat and went to
visit Snawley.
But Snawley's wife angrily refused to let
him see her husband.
'He's in so much trouble because of you!'
she said, and shut the door in his face.
Next, Ralph went to the Saracen's Head for
news about Squeers, but nobody had seen him
for ten days.
He decided to visit the house in Lambeth where
Squeers and Peg Sliderskew were staying, but
he found the two rooms empty.
He eventually discovered from a neighbour
that a one-eyed man and a drunken old woman
had been carried away from the building by
two men the night before.
'They've been caught by the police,' Ralph
thought.
'I must tell Arthur Gride at once.'
Arthur Gride, however, did not want to speak
to him.
'Go away,' he called from an upstairs window.
'It isn't safe.'
'Come down and open the door,' Ralph demanded,
but without success.
Gride closed the upstairs window, and there
was silence inside the house.
'This is mad!'
Ralph said to himself.
'Nobody wants to talk to me.
I must find out what's happening.'
Unwillingly, he decided to visit the Cheeryble
brothers.
'Which of you visited me this morning?'
Ralph asked, looking from one man to the other,
unable to tell the difference.
'It was my brother,' said brother Ned.
Without waiting for an invitation, Ralph sat
down and crossed his legs.
'Now, gentlemen, what do you wish to say?'
Ned rang a bell and Newman Noggs walked into
the room.
'What are you doing here?'
Ralph asked with a scornful smile.
'I'm here because I hate the cruel way that
you treat honest people,' Noggs replied.
'You enjoy making innocent people suffer.
I've seen how you've treated your own family.
I've seen you lie about Smike's father and
persuade a selfish father to sell his daughter
to Arthur Gride.
I've seen it all.'
'You can't prove any of this,' Ralph said,
still smiling.
'Yes, we can,' brother Charles said.
'Last night, the man Snawley told us everything.'
The smile went from Ralph's face.
'Mr Noggs came to us for help a few weeks
ago,' Charles explained.
'He had been spying on you for a long time,
and had heard all your conversations with
Snawley, Gride and Squeers.
We quickly discovered that Snawley was not
Smike's real father.
He told us that the whole lie had been your
idea.
Last night, Mr Noggs and my nephew found your
friend Squeers with the stolen papers in his
pocket.
You were trying to stop Madeline Bray getting
the house that belonged to her, weren't you?
Well, your friend Squeers is already with
the police.'
'If all this is true, said Ralph, 'why am
I not in prison with him?'
'We wanted to help you,' brother Ned said.
'We have told you all this before telling
the police about you.
We have given you the chance to leave London.'
Ralph smiled scornfully.
'I don't believe a word that you say.
I shall not leave London.
You have not heard the last of me!'
With these proud words, he left the room.
He went straight to the police station, where
he found Squeers sitting in a prison room.
What happened last night?'
Ralph asked him.
Squeers explained everything, his one eye
filled with hate as he spoke.
'It's all your fault,' the schoolmaster said
angrily.
'Why didn't you let me burn the papers?
Now the police have them.
Madeline Bray will get her house, and my life
is ruined because of you.'
'The police can't do anything,' Ralph said.
'We'll invent a story, and...
But Squeers refused to listen.
'No,' he said.
'I'm finished with you.
I'm going to tell the police everything.'
Ralph left Squeers and angrily walked home.
He sat down in the dark, put his head in his
hands and did not move for an hour.
At ten o'clock there was a knock on the door.
It was Tim Linkinwater.
'Mr Nickleby,' Tim said.
'Something important has happened.
You must come with me at once.
'Why should I?
For a repeat performance of this morning?'
'No,' replied Tim.
'It's bad news for you, I'm afraid.
You must come.'
Ralph paused for a moment.
Then he put on his coat and hat and followed
Tim Linkinwater.
'What have you got to tell me?' he said to
the Cheerybles when he arrived.
'It's about a death,' said brother Charles.
Ralph's eyes brightened for a second.
'Is it my nephew?'
'You should be ashamed of yourself!' said
brother Ned.
'You're a hard-hearted, unnatural man.
We are here to tell you about the death of
a poor, innocent boy - a warm-hearted boy
who never knew love, who never did harm to
anybody.
A boy who has died because of you.'
'Just tell me that my nephew is dead,' Ralph
said.
'That's all I want to hear.'
A figure stepped out of the shadows into the
centre of the room.
It was Brooker.
'These gentlemen are talking about your only
son,' he said quietly.
Ralph stared in silence as Brooker told his
story.
'Twenty-five years ago,' he said, 'you secretly
married a girl for her money.
You had a son, but you sent him away so that
nobody would know about the marriage.
Seven years later, your wife ran away with
another man.
She died soon afterwards.
Although your wife was dead, you still wanted
revenge.
'That's when you met me.
I was a rough, hard-drinking man in those
days.
I had lost all my money.
You wanted me to find your child, and I agreed.
I brought the child home to you, but you weren't
grateful.
You treated me badly, and I began to hate
you.
I, too, wanted revenge.
Eight years ago, while you were away on business,
I took your child to a school in Yorkshire
- Dotheboys Hall.
After your return, I told you that your son
had died.
'A short time later, I was sent abroad on
a prison ship.
When I returned, I went to Dotheboys Hall
to find the boy.
I heard that he had run away with an assistant
schoolteacher - called Nickleby!
- so I came to London to find you.
I wanted to tell you about your son, hoping
that you would give me money for the information,
but you refused to listen.
I discovered from Newman Noggs that the boy
was very ill and had gone to Devon, so I went
down there to see him.
Unfortunately, he saw me watching him from
behind a tree and was frightened.
When I returned to the farmhouse a few days
later, your nephew told me that the boy was
dead.
This is my story.
I've been a bad man, I know, but I want you
to know what you've really done.
You tried to punish your nephew, but you killed
your own child instead.'
When Brooker finished, there was silence in
the room.
Suddenly, Ralph Nickleby picked up the lamp
and threw it to the floor.
In the darkness and confusion, he escaped.
As he ran home, there was an unfamiliar feeling
in his heart - pain.
He had always been scornful of people who
suffered from broken hearts - he had always
believed that they were lying.
Now he knew what such pain felt like, and
it frightened him.
When he reached home, he sat alone in his
room with his head in his hands.
He had been blinded by his hate for Nicholas,
and had murdered his own child!
He could not believe it.
He had tried to destroy the only person in
the world who had shown his son love.
What good was all his money now?
He had murdered his own child.
Interrupted by a loud knocking at the door,
he opened the window and called down into
the street, 'Who is it?'
'The twins want to know what to do with Brooker,'
an unknown voice called up from the darkness.
'Tell them to bring him here tomorrow,' Ralph
replied.
'Bring my nephew with them.'
'At what time?'
'In the afternoon.
It doesn't matter what time.'
Ralph closed the window and returned to his
chair.
A church bell struck one o'clock.
Rain began to fall.
The glass in the window shook in the wind.
'My nephew was right,' Ralph said quietly
to himself.
'It's the end.'
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Happiness at Last
Nicholas's happiness was complete.
He was with all the people that he loved.
All his enemies had been defeated.
The same evening, Nicholas returned home from
Devon and there was much crying and sadness
over poor Smike's death.
Then Kate told him everything about his uncle.
The next day, the Cheeryble brothers, Brooker
and Nicholas arrived at Ralph Nickleby's house.
Although they knocked loudly on the door,
there was no answer.
Soon, a large group of neighbours were standing
outside the house.
One man climbed through a window at the back
and let everybody in.
They searched every room, but there was no
sign of Ralph.
Finally, they reached a room at the top of
the house.
'It's very odd,' one of the neighbours whispered.
'He's hiding in the dark behind the door.
Look.'
Everyone pressed forwards to see.
Then one of them pushed the others to one
side and ran in with a loud cry.
He took a knife from his pocket and cut down
the body.
Ralph had hanged himself.
After a few weeks, the shock of these events
slowly passed into memory.
Madeline got better and moved in with the
Cheeryble brothers, who treated her like a
daughter.
Kate was sad to see her friend leave, but
Nicholas was relieved.
He did not want anyone to know that he was
in love with Madeline.
One day, the Cheerybles invited Nicholas,
Kate, Mrs Nickleby and Miss La Creevy to dinner.
When they arrived, brother Charles took Kate
by the arm.
'Have you seen Madeline, my dear,' he said,
'since she left your house?'
'No, sir,' Kate replied.
'Not once.
I've only received one letter from her.
I expect that she'll soon forget all about
me.'
'Well, if you go into that room,' Charles
said, 'there's a letter from her for you on
the table.'
When Kate had gone, Charles asked Nicholas
to follow him into his private room.
Nicholas was surprised to see Frank Cheeryble.
I thought you'd gone abroad again!'
Nicholas said.
Charles watched with a big smile while the
two young men shook hands.
'I'm glad, he said.
I want you two to be good friends.'
He then showed Nicholas a copy of Madeline's
grandfather s will.
Nicholas read until he reached the line: Madeline
Bray will receive a house valued at twelve
thousand pounds when she gets married.
He did not know what to say.
Charles turned to Frank.
'My brother and I love Madeline very much.
You saved this will from the fire, and we
would be very happy if you married this girl.
What do you say?'
'No, I can't,' Frank said.
'She's in love with a man who deserves her
more than me.
I love another woman.'
'Mr Nickleby's sister?'
Charles asked with amusement.
While Frank was trying to think of a reply,
Charles took Nicholas's hand with a warm smile.
'I know that Madeline loves you, Mr Nickleby,
and my brother and I are very happy.
We are equally happy with Frank's choice of
wife.
Would you, sir, allow him to marry your sister?'
At that moment, the door opened and brother
Ned came in with Mrs Nickleby, Kate - and
Madeline!
'Did you find the letter?'
Charles asked, taking Kate's hand.
'Or did you find Madeline herself?'
Everybody started laughing, shaking hands,
hugging and kissing each other.
Little Miss La Creevy sat in a window-seat
and cried with happiness.
Tim Linkinwater, who had known Miss La Creevy
for a long time, put his arm around her shoulders.
When Newman Noggs arrived, Nicholas's happiness
was complete.
He was with all the people that he loved.
All his enemies had been defeated.
Dinner that night was probably one of the
happiest dinners in history!
Nicholas wanted to share his happiness with
everybody, so a few days later he travelled
to Yorkshire to see John Browdie and his wife,
Tilda.
They were excited to see him.
Tilda prepared an enormous breakfast and they
sat around the table in the warm kitchen,
talking.
Eventually, the conversation turned to the
subject of Squeers.
'They were talking about him in town last
night,' John said.
'News from London is very slow to reach us
here.
They say that he's been sent to prison for
seven years.
Is that true?'
'Yes.
He's been sent abroad on a prison ship for
stealing a will.'
John Browdie laughed loudly, hitting the side
of his enormous leg with his hand.
'If the news has reached Dotheboys Hall, I
wouldn't like to be in the old woman's shoes.
Or Fanny's either!
Let's go and find out.'
But Nicholas refused.
'I'll only make things worse for them both
if I go, too,' he said.
'That's true,' John agreed.
He kissed his wife, shook Nicholas's hand
and rode through the snow to Dotheboys Hall
on his horse.
When he arrived, he heard a loud noise coming
from inside the school.
The news about Squeers had already reached
Dotheboys Hall!
The boys had locked Mrs Squeers and Fanny
into the classroom and were breaking all the
furniture.
They had stolen Mrs Squeers's hat and forced
her to her knees.
One of the boys was pushing a long wooden
spoon into her mouth.
He was making her take her own 'medicine'
- the horrible thick soup that she usually
made them eat!
Another boy was pushing young Wackford's head
into the pot of soup.
When John saw other boys attacking Fanny Squeers,
he rushed into the room.
What's happening here, boys?' he shouted.
'Squeers is in prison, and we're going to
run away!'
they shouted back.
'We won't stay!
We won't stay!'
'Well, don't stay, John said.
'But don't hurt the women.'
The boys cheered loudly.
A few minutes later, the school was empty.
All the boys had run away.
'You'll pay for this, John Browdie!'
Fanny Squeers said angrily.
'You've helped our boys run away!'
John looked at her quietly for a minute, then
said, 'I'm glad your father is in prison,
Fanny.
He deserves his punishment.
But if you need a friend, don't forget Tilda
and me.
We'll be glad to help you if we can.'
With those words, he hurried back to his wife
and Nicholas.
For the next few days, the countryside was
filled with boys.
John and his wife helped as many as they could.
They gave them food and money.
Some boys were found crying under trees in
the snow.
One poor child was found dead beside the road,
frozen to death.
But soon, most of the boys had returned to
their families.
Dotheboys Hall became just a dark and painful
memory.
Nicholas and Madeline married a few months
later.
On the same day, Kate Nickleby became Mrs
Frank Cheeryble.
Then Miss La Creevy married Tim Linkinwater
in secret.
Nicholas put the money that he received from
Madeline into the Cheeryble brothers' business,
which became known as 'Cheeryble and Nickleby'.
The brothers stopped working, and were free
to enjoy the happiness that they had given
everyone else.
Ralph Nickleby had not left a will, but nobody
wanted to touch his money, so eventually the
government took it all.
His money, the most important thing in his
life, had made no one happy.
As soon as he became rich, Nicholas bought
his father's old house in Devon.
As the years passed, he and Madeline had several
children.
Kate and Frank Cheeryble also had children.
They moved into a house not far away, and
the two families spent many happy times together.
Mrs Nickleby sometimes lived with her son,
sometimes with her daughter.
A quiet, grey-haired gentleman lived in a
little cottage near Nicholas's house.
His main pleasure in life was playing with
the children.
The children all loved dear old Newman Noggs.
Every spring and summer, by the rose-tree
in Nicholas's garden, the children always
made sure that there were fresh flowers on
Smike's grave.
Although they had never known him, they spoke
about him softly, with tears in their eyes.
They knew that he had once been their father's
only friend.
To them, he would always be their much-loved
cousin, Smike.