CHAPTER ONE
August 1940: The Doctor and his Daughter
Dr Iannis had enjoyed a satisfactory day in which
none of his patients had died or got any worse.
He had removed a tooth, attended the
surprisingly easy birth of a lamb,
and had performed a successful,
though minor, operation.
He had been called to the house of old man
Stamatis, who was suffering from earache.
After gazing into the dark, hairy hole of the
old man's ear, the doctor had cleaned up the
inside of the ear using a matchstick, cotton wool
and alcohol. He was aware that old man Stamatis
had been deaf in that ear since childhood, but
was nevertheless surprised when the tip of the
matchstick touched something hard, something
that had no excuse for its presence there.
He took the old man to the window, where the light
was better, and stared down into the ear again;
then with his long matchstick he
pushed the grey hairs to one side.
There was something round inside. He
scratched its surface and saw a pea.
It was undoubtedly a pea; it was light green
and slightly lined. Dr Iannis considered the
problem for some moments, then requested
a small fishhook and a light hammer.
The old man and his wife looked at each other
with the single thought that the doctor must
have lost his mind. 'What does this have to do
with my earache?' asked Stamatis suspiciously.
But the hook and hammer were fetched, and the
doctor carefully placed the straightened hook
into the hairy hole and raised the
hammer. There was a terrible scream.
'Oh, oh, the fishhook will enter his brain.
May God protect us!' cried the old wife,
hiding her head in her hands.
This speech caused the doctor to pause and
consider the possibility that the hammer
might only drive the pea further into the
ear. 'Change of plan,' he announced, and gave
instructions that Stamatis should lie on his side
till evening with his ear filled with warm water.
He returned at six o'clock, hooked the softened
pea successfully without the aid of a hammer,
small or otherwise, and pulled it out. Stamatis
clapped his hand to his ear and exclaimed,
'It's cold in there. My God, it's
loud. I mean everything is loud!'
'Your deafness is cured,' announced Dr Iannis.
'A very satisfactory operation, I think.'
Shortly afterwards he walked home
with a fat chicken under each arm,
and an ancient pea wrapped up in his handkerchief.
The doctor was now left with an
entire evening in which to write his
'New History of Cephallonia', a project which he
had begun at least a dozen times. He seemed unable
to achieve objectivity and so had never been
satisfied with the result. He sat down and wrote:
'The ancient, half-forgotten island of
Cephallonia rises from the Ionian Sea,
its rocks and red earth heavy with the heat
of the sun and the weight of memory. In the
stories of ancient Greece, the island played
its part and had its gods - among them Poseidon,
the god of the Sea and Apollo, the god of the Sun.
Yes, once this island, with its brilliant light,
its transparent waters, was an island
filled with gods. But today Cephallonia
has become a factory that breeds babies for
export. There are more Cephallonians abroad
or at sea than there are at home. There is no
industry here that keeps families together,
there is not enough agricultural land, there are
not enough fish in the ocean. Our men go abroad
and return here to die. The only good thing about
it is that only the beautiful women find husbands
among the men who are left, and consequently we
have the most beautiful women in all of Greece...'
The doctor refilled his pipe and read this
through. He listened to Pelagia moving about
in the kitchen, preparing the evening meal. He
read what he had written about beautiful women
and remembered his wife, who had died from
lung disease despite all his efforts and
who had been as lovely as his daughter was now.
'This island betrays its own people,' he wrote,
then seized the sheet of paper and threw
it forcefully into the corner of the room.
This was not good enough. Why could he not
write like a writer of histories? Why could
he not write without passion, without anger
at the many betrayals and oppressions that the
island had suffered in the past? He went outside
for a breath of fresh air, returning indoors
just in time to catch Pelagia's little goat eating
his writings with a look of satisfaction on its
face. He tore the paper from the animal's mouth,
chased it outside, then marched into the kitchen.
'That unpleasant animal of yours has
eaten everything I've written tonight,'
he exclaimed crossly. 'Any more incidents
like this, and it'll end up on our plates.'
Pelagia looked up at her father and smiled.
'We'll be eating at about ten o'clock.'
'Did you hear what I said? No more goats inside
the house.' Pelagia paused in her slicing of a
tomato, brushed her hair from her face and
replied, 'You're as fond of him as I am.'
Dr Iannis turned away, defeated. It was an
annoying thing when a daughter spoke cheekily
to him and reminded him of her mother at the
same time. He returned to his table, took the
title page, 'A New History of Cephallonia', and
crossed out the first two words, writing instead,
'A Personal'. Now he could express his opinions
as freely and unpleasantly as he wished.
When Pelagia heard from a neighbour that a
strongman was giving a performance in the
village square, she put away her broom and hurried
to join the group of curious islanders that had
gathered there. Megalo Velisarios, famous all over
the islands of Ionia as one of the strongest men
who had ever lived, was jumping up and down in
time to the clapping of hands. On each of his
outstretched arms sat a full-grown man. One of
them held on tightly to his body while the other
calmly smoked a cigarette. On Vehsarios's head
sat an anxious little girl of about six years,
who was making matters more complicated by
holding her hands firmly across his eyes.
'Lemoni!' he roared. 'Take your hands from my eyes
and hold on to my hair, or I'll have to stop.'
Lemoni was too frightened to move her hands and
Megalo Velisarios stopped. With one graceful
movement he threw both men to their feet, lifted
Lemoni from his head, threw her high into the air
and caught her, kissed her dramatically upon the
tip of her nose and set her down. Raising himself
to his full height, he cried, 'I will lift
anything that it takes three men to lift.'
The village priest, Father Arsenios,
chose just this moment to walk with a
self-important expression across the square
on his way to the church. He lacked respect,
not because he was completely round but
because he was greedy for both money and food
and was much too interested in women.
'Lift Father Arsenios,' someone called.
'Impossible,' called another.
Father Arsenios quite suddenly found himself
grasped around his chest and lifted up on to
the wall. He sat there speechless with surprise,
his mouth opening and closing like a fish, and a
guilty silence descended. Pelagia felt her heart
overflow with pity for the poor man. She stepped
forward and extended a hand to help him down,
and the priest walked off without a word. Pelagia
now spoke sharply to Velisarios. She was only
seventeen but she was proud and knew her own mind,
and her position as the doctor's daughter meant
that even the men were forced to respect her. 'You
shouldn't have done that, Velisarios,' she said.
'It was cruel and horrible. You must apologize.'
He looked down at her from his great height.
This was without doubt a difficult situation.
He thought of lifting her above his head.
'We want to see the cannon,' called an old
lady, and others in the crowd echoed her.
Velisarios was immensely proud of his
ability to raise the old Turkish cannon,
which had the date 1739 on it and was
much too heavy for anyone else to lift.
He looked down at Pelagia and said, 'I'll
apologize later, pretty one,' then announced,
'Good people of the village, to see the cannon,
you must bring me your old nails, your broken
pots, and the stones of the streets. Find me
these things while I pack the gun with powder.'
People ran off eagerly in all
directions to seek out these objects,
and the cannon was soon prepared for the
great explosion. 'I will fire the gun
down the road,' said Velisarios when all was
made ready. 'Everybody out of the way now.'
With a theatrical expression, the enormous man put
a match to the cannon and lifted it to his waist.
Silence fell. Breaths were held. There was
a great roar as the old pots and nails burst
from the gun... and then a long, low cry of pain.
There was a moment of confusion and hesitation.
People looked around at each
other to see who had been hit,
and Velisarios dropped his cannon and ran
forward to a young man lying in the dust.
Mandras later thanked Velisarios for firing at him
as he came round the bend at the entrance to the
village. But at the time he greatly disliked
being carried in the arms of the strongman
to the doctor's house and he did not enjoy
having a bent nail removed from his shoulder.
What he thanked Megalo Velisarios for was that in
the doctor's house he first set eyes on Pelagia.
There was a moment when he became aware that he
was being bandaged, that a young woman's long
hair was brushing against his face. He opened
his eyes and found himself gazing into a pair
of anxious eyes. 'At that moment,' he liked
to say later, 'I recognized my future wife.'
Dr Iannis put on a fresh shirt in readiness
for his daily visit to the kapheneion,
and stepped out into the yard. He was
entirely unsurprised to see Mandras there,
talking to Pelagia. The young fisherman's
face went red when he saw him.
'Oh, good evening, doctor. I've
brought you some fish,' he said.
The doctor twisted his mouth and pretended to
sigh. 'Mandras,' he said, 'you know perfectly
well that I know perfectly well that you
have only come here to flirt with Pelagia.'
'Flirt?' repeated the young man, attempting
to appear both innocent and shocked.
'Yes. Flirt. Yesterday you brought us another
fish and then flirted with Pelagia for an hour.
Well, you'd better get on with it.'
'Then I have your permission
to talk to your daughter?'
'Talk, talk, talk,' said Dr Iannis, waving
his hands, and he set off for the kapheneion.
'Your dad's a funny fellow,'
Mandras said to Pelagia.
'There's nothing wrong with my father,' she
exclaimed, 'and anyone who says there is gets
a broom in the face.' She pushed the broom at him
and he caught it and twisted it out of her grasp.
'Give it back,' she said laughing.
'I'll give it back... in return for a kiss.'
Pelagia gave the young man a flirtatious smile.
At the kapheneion, the doctor collected his
tiny cup of coffee and sat next to Kokolios,
as he always did. The coffee shop was full of
the usual characters: the Communist Kokolios,
with his splendid moustache; old man
Stamatis; Father Arsenios, round and sweating.
'What's the news of the war?' Kokolios asked.
The doctor twisted the ends
of his moustache and said,
'Germany is taking everything, the Italians are
behaving like fools, the French have run away,
the Americans have been playing ball games, the
British have been drinking tea, the Russians
have been sitting on their hands. Thank God we
are out of it. Why don't we turn on the radio?'
The large British radio in the corner of the
room was switched on, its whistles reduced to
a minimum by moving it around. Just then,
Pelagia appeared at the door, gesturing
urgently, greatly embarrassed by her presence
in the men-only kapheneion. The doctor raised
his eyes to the ceiling, put his pipe in his
pocket and went to the door. 'What is it, girl?'
'It's Mandras, he's fallen
out of a tree on to a pot.'
The doctor shook his head in disbelief and
allowed his daughter to hurry him home.
There, he made Mandras lie on the kitchen
table while he removed tiny pieces of the
broken pot from the young man's muscular
back. 'You're a fool,' he told his patient.
'I know, doctor,' said Mandras, biting
his lip as another piece came out.
'Stop being so polite. I
know what you're planning.
Are you going to ask her to marry you or not?'
'Not yet, doctor. Everyone
says there's going to be a war,
and I don't want to leave a widow.
You know how people treat a widow.'
'Quite right,' said the doctor and wondered,
as he wiped away a spot of blood, whether his body
had ever been as beautiful as this young fool's.
It was several hours before he returned to the
kapheneion. When he entered, he knew immediately
that something was wrong. Warlike music came
from the radio and Dr Iannis was astonished to
see that the faces of several of the men were
shiny with tears. 'What's going on?' he asked.
'Those Italian pigs have sunk one of our ships
at Tinos. And they fired on the harbour there.
It was full of people. On a holy day too.'
The doctor put his hands to his face and
felt his own tears fighting to appear.
He was possessed by a feeling of helpless
anger. He did not stop to question whether
war with Italy was inevitable. Although he did
not believe in God he found himself saying,
'Come on boys, we're all going to the church.' The
men of the kapheneion rose and followed him.
CHAPTER TWO
Pelagia and Mandras
Pelagia (resting in the afternoon): Papas says
that Mandras is going to have tiny pieces of that
pot in his back for the rest of his life. I like
his body, what I've seen of it. God forgive me,
I have such wicked thoughts. Thank God no
one can read my mind, or I'd be locked up
and all the old women would throw stones at me.
I wonder what Mandras is doing. He's so beautiful
and so tunny too. He made my stomach ache
with laughing before he fell out of the tree.
That's when I knew I loved him; it was
the fear I felt when he fell on the pot.
When will he ask me to marry him? But he's
not a serious fellow, and it gives me doubts.
He's so funny, but I can't talk to him about
anything and you have to be able to discuss
things with a husband, don't you? I say, 'Is there
going to be a war?' and he just grins and says,
'Who cares? Is there going to be a kiss?'
I don't want there to be a war. Let there
be Mandras standing in the yard with a fish in his
hands. Let there be Mandras every day with a fish.
Mandras (leaving the harbour in his boat): It's
going to be too hot again today, I know it,
and all the fish will hide in the rocks and
go to the bottom. Let the clouds hide the sun,
let me catch some fine fish and I'll take one
to Pelagia and she'll ask me to eat with them,
and I can rub her leg with my foot under the
table while the doctor discusses ancient poetry.
I know he likes me, but he doesn't think I'm good
enough for her - he's always calling me a fool.
The trouble is that I can't be myself when I'm
with her. I mean, I am a serious man. I follow
politics, I want to improve the world. But
when I'm with Pelagia it's as if I'm twelve
again. I want to amuse her and what else am I
supposed to do? I can't imagine myself saying,
'Come on, Pelagia, let's talk about politics.'
Women aren't interested in that sort of thing,
they want you to entertain them.
Perhaps she thinks I'm a fool as well.
I'm not in her class, I know that. The doctor
taught her Italian and a bit of English,
and they're not a typical island family. I
mean, the doctor's sailed all over the world,
he's even been to America. And
where have I been? What do I know?
I love Pelagia, but I know that I will never
be a man until I've done something important,
something people can respect me for. I feel so
useless and insignificant here on the island.
Pelagia (taking roast lamb from the village
oven): Where is Mandras? He's usually here by now.
I want him to come, I can hardly breathe, I
want him so much. My hands are shaking again.
I'd better take this silly smile off
my face or everyone will think I'm mad.
Come, Mandras, please come, stay for dinner
and stroke my ankles with your feet, Mandras.
Mandras (mending his nets): We're going
to go to war with Italy very soon.
I've got a letter saying that I'll be ordered
to join the army in the next few weeks.
I know one thing, I'm going to ask
Pelagia to marry me before I leave.
With no jokes. I'm going to make her understand
that in defending Greece I'm defending her
and every woman like her, and if I die, I'll die
with the name of Pelagia and the name of Greece
equally on my lips. And if I live, I'll walk
with my head held high for the rest of my life,
and everyone will say, 'That's Mandras, who fought
in the war. We owe everything to people like him.'
The island's saint, St Geronimos, dead for
five centuries, had lived a genuinely holy
life and had left his ancient blackened body
in an island church as evidence of this.
He was so loved by the islanders that he had two
feast days, one in August and another in October,
and on these days he tolerantly looked elsewhere
as the population of the island became excessively
drunk. It was eight days before Greece
and Italy declared war on each other,
but it might have been any October
feast day in the last hundred years.
The cruelty had gone out of the
sun, and the delightfully warm day
was made even more pleasant by a light wind from
the sea that wandered in and out of the trees.
From all over the island, people made their
way to the church where the saint's body lay,
packing the church tightly and
squeezing together in the yard outside.
At different points in the crowd,
Velisarios, Pelagia, Dr Iannis, Kokolios
and Stamatis all turned their heads sideways
to hear the distant prayers of the priest.
The sun climbed higher and the people, packed
together, began to sweat. The heat was just
becoming unbearable when the service ended,
the bells rang out and the celebrations began.
A small band began playing while a line of pretty
girls stepped from side to side at the back,
and a row of young men danced with
their heads twisted backwards.
Those who were drunk began to insult each other,
and in some places fighting had already begun.
Pelagia moved nearer the
church and sat on a bench.
Someone tapped on her shoulder and she looked up
and saw Mandras. He fell drunkenly to his knees
and declared dramatically, 'Pelagia,
will you marry me? Marry me or I die!'
She regarded him silently for a moment, then
said quietly, 'Of course I'll marry you,'
When he heard this, Mandras leapt
joyfully but unsteadily into the air,
then suddenly became extremely serious and
said, 'My darling, I love you with all my heart,
but we can't get married until
I get back from the Army.'
'Go and speak to my father,' said Pelagia. Then,
worried by the strange way in which she did not
feel as happy as she ought, she made her way back
to the church in order to be alone with the saint.
Time passed, and Mandras failed to find
the doctor before drink overcame him.
He slept sweetly in a pool of something
disgusting but unidentifiable, while, nearby,
Lemoni attempted to set fire to the
beard of the sleeping Father Arsenios,
and Kokolios and Stamatis became lost in
the bushes while searching for their wives.
Pelagia walked back from the feast
with her father, bursting with a
painful mixture of anxiety and happiness,
desperate to mention Mandras's proposal.
But the doctor was in a much too drunken state
to be sensitive to his daughter's feelings, and
when they reached the house, he danced about the
yard before falling onto his bed fully clothed.
Pelagia went to bed and could not sleep. 'I love
you, Mandras,' she declared, at the same time
as doubts rose in her like an invasion of tiny
devils. How much did she really know Mandras?
What evidence did she have that he was patient
and kind? Can you trust someone who replies
immediately, without thought? She was frightened
by the suspicion that there was something hard
about his heart. If it were not love that she
felt for Mandras, then why this breathlessness,
this endless desire that made her heart beat
fast? She imagined that Mandras had died, and
as the tears came she was shocked to
discover that she also felt relief.
In the morning she took herself to
the yard and created tasks that would
cause her to see him as soon as he
came around the curve of the road.
But he did not come, and Pelagia passed
the day with feelings of impatience
that soon turned into real concern. That evening,
when he had still not appeared, her father said,
quite unexpectedly, 'I expect he hasn't come
because he's feeling as sick as everyone else.'
Pelagia took his hand and kissed it gratefully.
'He's asked me to marry him. I told
him I'd have to ask you,' she said.
'I don't want to marry Mandras,' said Dr Iannis.
'It would be a much better idea
if he married you, I think.'
'Don't you approve of him, Papakis?'
He turned and looked at her
gently. 'He's too young. Also,
I have not done you a favour. You read poetry,
you speak Italian. He isn't your equal,
and he would expect to be better than his wife.
He is a man, after all. I have often thought that
you would only ever be able to marry happily with
a foreigner, a dentist from Norway or something.'
Pelagia laughed at the ridiculous
thought, then closed her eyes.
The doctor went inside and came out with
something that he handed very formally to her.
She took it, saw what it was, and dropped
it into her skirts with a cry of horror.
The doctor remained standing. 'There's going to
be a war, and terrible things happen in wars,
especially to women. Use the gun to defend
yourself. It might happen that your marriage
will have to wait. We must make sure first that
Mussolini does not invite himself to the wedding.'
He turned and went into the house, leaving Pelagia
to her fears, and after a few minutes she went to
her room and placed the gun under her pillow,
imagining once again that Mandras was dead.
It was not until the third day after
the feast that there was a quiet knock
at the door. Mandras stood, speaking
fast, a bucket of fish in his hand.
'I'm sorry I didn't come sooner, but
I was ill the day after the feast,
and yesterday I had to collect my Army papers,
and I'm leaving for Athens the day after tomorrow,
and I've spoken to your father, and he's agreed
to the marriage, and I've brought you some fish.'
Pelagia sat on her bed and went cold inside;
it was too much happiness, too much pain.
She was engaged to a man who mixed
marriage together with fish and war,
a man who was too beautiful to go away and die in
the snows of Tsamoria. Suddenly Mandras seemed to
her to be an extraordinarily delicate creature,
so delicate and beautiful that he was sure to die.
Her hands began to shake and she
whispered, 'Don't go, don't go.'
CHAPTER THREE
The Homosexual
I, Carlo Piero Guercio, write these
words with the intention that they
should be found after my death, when
what is written here will not harm me.
I know only silence. I have not told the priest,
since I know in advance what I will be told;
it is a wicked sin and I must marry and lead the
life of a normal man. Nor have I told a doctor,
as I know that I will be informed that I
am sick and can be cured of my disease.
What could I say to such priests and
doctors? I would say to the priest that
God made me like this for a purpose, that
I had no choice. I would say to the doctor,
'I have been like this from the start, it is
nature that has created me.' But they would
not understand. I am like someone who is the only
person in the world that knows the truth, but is
forbidden to speak. And this truth weighs more
than the universe, this burden cracks my bones.
In my search to understand myself, I have
read everything, from the most modern to
the most ancient, and it was in the work
of the ancient Greek philosopher, Plato,
that I finally found myself. In his writings,
he explained that there were three sexes,
the third sex being men who loved men, and
this idea made sense to me. Plato also wrote
that if an army was made up of men who loved
one another, they would be the bravest army
in the world, because men would become
heroes, ready to die for their lovers.
I admit that I joined the Army because the men are
young and beautiful, and because I knew that in
the Army I would find someone I could love though
never touch. I would not abandon him in battle,
I would win his admiration, I would die for him if
necessary and in this way give purpose to my life.
In the Army I found my family. It was a world
without women, and for the first time in my life
I did not have to pretend. I was very fortunate
at first; our unit was sent to Albania,
where there was no real fighting, and we did not
realize that we might be ordered to invade Greece.
No one outside the Army can understand the joy
of being a soldier, of being part of a group
where you are all young and strong and
quickly learn everything about each other.
We believed we could not die, we could march
eighty kilometres a day, singing battle songs.
We were new and beautiful, we loved
each other more than brothers.
I fell in love with Francesco, a young married
soldier from Genoa, who accepted me as his best
friend without ever suspecting my passion
for him. He was an entirely beautiful boy,
reminding me of one of those elegant cats that
give the impression of immense but easy strength.
I was attracted most of all to his face,
with its strong, high cheekbones, wide mouth
and one-sided smile. He was always
amusing and respected no one,
constantly entertaining us with his wickedly
accurate imitations of Mussolini and Hitler.
Everyone loved him, he never got
a promotion and he did not care.
We soldiers loved the army life but had no love
of the Fascist leaders of our country, nor did we
have any idea of why we were in Albania. However,
looking back, it seems clear that an invasion of
Greece must have been the final intention; there
were clues everywhere, if only we had seen them.
In the first place, there was the fact that all
the roads that we built (which, we were informed,
were for the benefit of the Albanians) led
towards the Greek border. In the second place,
we heard stories from reliable sources about
how our frontier posts were attacked a number
of times by our own people dressed as Greeks, so
that we could blame the latter for the attacks.
When some Albanians shot at our soldiers,
we announced that our attackers were Greeks.
We also learned that one of our
leaders arranged to have his own
offices blown up so that Mussolini could
finally declare war against the Greeks.
I have related these things as if they were
amusing, but really they were acts of madness.
When war against Greece was finally declared,
we were told that the Greeks would be defeated
within days. We were sent off to die, with no
transport, no equipment and too few men. At first,
having no idea of what the future held for us,
we whistled and sang, and from time to time
Francesco, marching beside me, looked at me
and smiled. 'Athens in two weeks,' he said.
Then the weather turned against us and rain
poured from the skies, turning the ground to mud
so that we struggled through it, ten thousand
men whose uniforms were weighted down with water,
our aeroplanes unable to fly because of the bad
weather. Our twenty heavy guns sank into the mud,
and our animals were unable to pull them out. We
struggled on in these conditions for several days,
at a height of three hundred metres,
our legs turned to ice so that we
could no longer feel our feet. 'Athens in two
months,' said Francesco with a twisted smile.
But we saw no sign of the Greeks and believed
that we were winning without fighting.
On 1 November, a bomb fell among us and there was
a scream as a poor fellow from Piedmont lost his
legs, followed by the short, sharp sound of
gunshot from the trees. We realized that the
Greeks had cleverly got us into a position where
we could be surrounded and cut off from all help.
We were trapped in the valley floor and the
Greeks, whom we very rarely saw, moved like
ghosts among the upper slopes, so that we never
knew when we would be attacked or from where.
Their bombs seemed at one moment to come from
behind, at another moment to come from the side or
from the front. We fired at ghosts and at mountain
goats. The heroic Greeks seemed to rise out of the
ground and fall on us as if we had raped their
mothers. It shocked us. We had no air support.
'Athens in two years,' said
Francesco. We were completely alone.
We ate only dry biscuits, but
when our horses died, we ate them.
We were ordered to turn back and had to fight
our way through the soldiers that surrounded us.
We grew immense beards, we
were half buried in snowstorms,
our red, swollen eyes sank deep into our
heads, our hands were torn as if by cats.
We became desperately thin, digging for
food in the frozen ground like pigs.
It was a hell of machine guns, bombs and ice,
a hell in which battles were fought without
rest for eight hours at a time, while on the
mountains our dead lay in forgotten piles, body
upon body. We fought on but we lost our hearts
as a great darkness settled across the land.
The snow fell endlessly. My boots,
crawling with insects, fell apart.
I think it must have been December when we
understood that we were as broken as our boots.
Waking up in the morning, ten degrees below zero.
The first question: who has frozen to death now?
Who has slipped from sleep to death?
These were the days of the white death,
in which the legs became swollen and turned
bright purple, deep blue, coal black.
I was exhausted, shaken by the screams of men in
unimaginable pain as their legs were cut off by
our army doctors. I lived in fear of the white
death and inspected my feet every few hours.
Francesco was undoubtedly mad. His mouth moved
continually, his beard became a column of ice,
his eyes rolled in his head and he did not
recognize me. We had lost four thousand men.
There was nothing in our
lives except the white death,
the bitter absence of our friends,
the joylessness of the icy mountains.
One morning Francesco turned to me with a wild
expression in his eyes, speaking to me for the
first time in weeks. 'Look,' he said and rolled
up his trousers, revealing the purple stripes
on the white flesh. He touched the dead
flesh with a look of horror in his eyes,
rolled his trousers back down again and said
to me, 'It's enough, Carlo. It's too much.'
He began to weep, trembling all over. Then he
took up his gun and, before I could prevent him,
advanced towards the enemy, stopping to fire
every five steps. In recognition of his heroism,
the Greeks did not return his fire, but a bomb
fell next to him and he disappeared beneath a
shower of mud. There was a long silence. I
saw something move where Francesco had been.
I put my gun down and ran
towards the place where he lay.
The Greeks did not shoot at me and I saw that
although the side of his head had been blown away,
he was still alive. I knelt and
gathered him into my arms, then stood up
and faced the Greeks, offering myself to
their guns. There was a silence, and then
a cheer came from them. I turned and carried
the bleeding bundle back to our side.
Francesco took two hours to die. His blood ran
down my uniform, his mouth formed silent words,
the light in his eyes faded and he began the
long, slow journey towards death, suffering
what must have been indescribable pain. I buried
him in a deep hole, the home of enormous rats.
We lost the war and were saved only when the
Germans invaded from Bulgaria, forcing the
Greeks to fight two different armies at the same
time. We fought and froze and died for no purpose.
I took no part in the shameful conquest of
Greece because the day after I buried Francesco,
I shot myself in the flesh of my thigh.
CHAPTER FOUR
The Wild Man
On 28 October, Greece and Italy
formally declared war on each other.
All the young men of Cephallonia disappeared to
join the army, and Dr Iannis attempted to join too
but was turned down when it was discovered that
he had learned all his medical knowledge on ships
and had no proper qualifications. Several
Italian families on the island were attacked
and their houses were burnt down, and the
islanders developed a silent, sorrowful
expression as they learnt to live with the
thought that their sons and brothers might die.
As the weeks passed, however, they were comforted
by the news that their country was winning the war
and that the Greeks were winning back territory
that was theirs by right in Albania. The villagers
went often to church and Father Arsenios surprised
them by making fine, emotional speeches and by
not getting drunk. Almost immediately, shortages
of certain foods and other household essentials
developed, and beans became the greater
part of the doctor's and Pelagia's diet.
The war had the effect of increasing the
importance of Dr Iannis, as the village
community turned to him for advice and leadership.
The doctor watched his daughter progress through
a series of emotions, all of which seemed to him
to be unhealthy and worrying. At first Pelagia had
been in a state of painful anxiety, and then in
storms of tears. She would sit by the wall outside
as if she expected her fiance to arrive at
the bend of the road where he had been shot
by Velisarios. Later, she developed the habit of
remaining silently in the room with her father,
her hands motionless in her lap as tears
followed each other silently down her cheeks.
Pelagia calmed her fears by writing letter
after letter to Mandras, relating island
news and gossip, telling him about her terrible
dreams and her fears for him, and begging him to
write back to her. She began the task of making
a cover for their marriage bed, but lacked the
benefit of a mothers instruction in such matters.
Each time it reached a certain stage, it began to
look suspiciously like a dead animal, and she
felt forced to undo her work and begin again.
As day followed day it became clear that not only
had Mandras not written, but that he never would.
After careful observation of his daughter, her
father realized that she was becoming bitter
and increasingly certain that her fiance
could not love her. When he realized that
Pelagia was seriously depressed, the doctor
made her accompany him on his medical visits,
sent her to bed early and let
her sleep in the mornings.
He made a habit of making her laugh against her
will, and deliberately made her angry by such
tricks as moving all the knives from one drawer
to another. The doctor considered the return of
her normal cheerful manner to be a sign that
she had given up her passion for Mandras.
On the one hand, he was glad of this, since
he did not truly believe that Mandras would
make a good husband, but on the other
hand, Pelagia was already engaged,
and the breaking of an engagement would cause
great shame. The awful possibility occurred to him
that Pelagia might marry a man she no
longer loved out of a sense of duty.
Pelagia returned from the village with a jar of
water upon her shoulder, set it down in the yard
and came through the door, singing. The news had
been bad for some weeks - not only had Kokolios
lost two of his sons, but the Germans had attacked
the Greek army so that the courageous Greek troops
were at last facing defeat. Strangely, the bad
news made Pelagia even more appreciative of
the first signs of spring on the island. She was
feeling strong and whole and was enjoying having
the house to herself while her father was away
visiting a friend on the other side of the island.
Pelagia's singing was brought to a
sudden stop when she entered the kitchen.
There was a stranger seated at the kitchen
table, a most wild and horrible stranger,
whose hands trembled ceaselessly and whose
head was utterly hidden beneath a mass of dirt,
mud and hair. An enormous beard hid the lower
half of the stranger's face, in which Pelagia
could see only two tiny bright eyes that would
not look at her. Rags covered the stranger's
body and in the place of shoes there were
bandages, stained with blood both old and new.
Overcome with fear and pity, not
knowing what to do, Pelagia said,
'My father's out. He should be back tomorrow.'
'You're happy, anyway. Singing,' said the man
in a cracked voice, and his whole body shook.
'You can't stay, I'm on my own,' said Pelagia.
'I can't walk,' replied the
man. 'I walked from Epirus.
No boots.' Just then, the goat
wandered through the open kitchen door,
approached the stranger and made a gentle
attempt at tasting the stranger's rags. 'Ah,
at least your goat remembers me,'
the man whispered, and began to weep.
Pelagia was astonished by these
words and said, 'Mandras?'
The man turned his face towards her and said,
'Don't touch me, Pelagia. There are insects
crawling all over me and I smell terrible.'
Pelagia felt guilt, pity, disgust.
It seemed unimaginable that this pitiful ghost hid
the mind and body of the man she loved. 'You never
wrote to me,' she said, making the accusation that
had destroyed her love for him and left her empty.
Mandras replied, 'I can't write.'
For a reason she did not understand,
Pelagia was more disgusted by this confession
than by Mandras's physical condition. 'Couldn't
someone else have written for you? I thought you
were dead. I thought you... couldn't love me.'
'How could I let everyone know? How could
I have my feelings discussed by the boys?'
He glanced up again so that at last
she recognized his eyes, and said,
'Pelagia, I got all your letters. I couldn't read
them but I got them.' From inside his clothing
he drew out a huge, dirty packet. 'I carried
you in here,' he said, beating his chest.
'Every day, all the time, I was thinking of you,
talking to you. I was not a coward because of you,
I even prayed to you. And when the Germans
attacked us I got through their lines, and
all I could think of was that I had to get home
to you, and now...' His body shook as he wept.
'Now only the animals know me.'
'I'll fetch your mother,' Pelagia whispered and
ran out of the house, down to the small, fishy
but extremely clean house by the harbour where
Kyria Drosoula, Mandras's widowed mother, lived.
Kyria Drosoula was a woman so large and ugly
that at their first meeting people wondered
how she had ever found a husband.
She was in fact a brave, kind woman,
and during Mandras's absence she and
Pelagia had comforted one another.
Now the two women returned,
breathless, to the doctor's house,
and found Mandras in exactly the same
position that Pelagia had left him in.
Drosoula ran into the kitchen with
a cry of joy and then stepped back
with an astonished look that in
other circumstances would have
been amusing. 'It is him,' said Pelagia.
'I told you he was in an awful state.'
'My God,' Drosoula exclaimed, then began to
inspect Mandras as if he were an animal she
was considering purchasing. 'Go and put a big pot
to boil,' she said finally, 'because I'm going to
wash him from head to foot, but first I'm going to
get rid of this hair, so bring me some scissors.'
Mandras sat motionless as his mother,
making terrible faces as she did so,
cut away the ropes and lumps of his hair and
beard, revealing the horribly infected state of
the skin below and the insects creeping all over
it. Pelagia felt sickened where she knew that she
should feel pity, and went indoors to look in her
father's medicine cupboard. She realized with a
small shock that she had learned enough from her
father over the years to become a doctor herself.
Hurrying outside, she told Drosoula which
treatments to use on Mandras's face and head and
where to use them. After a brief discussion about
whether it was correct for a woman to see her
fiance with nothing on, the two women decided that
in these circumstances it was entirely acceptable.
They removed Mandras's rags, and after gazing
sorrowfully at the parcel of skin and bones
that sat before them, again under Pelagia's
expert guidance, Drosoula began washing her son
and rubbing healing oils and creams on him.
Pelagia forced herself to remove the bandages from
Mandras's feet, and despite the fact that at first
sight they did not look as if they could be saved,
on closer examination she realized that the flesh
was quite dry. She fetched a bowl of clean water,
salted it heavily, and as gently as she could,
she washed and treated the terrible mess.
When Dr Iannis returned the following morning,
he found not only a half-dead man asleep in his
daughter's bed, but his daughter and an
amazingly ugly woman asleep in his own.
He listened to Pelagia's account of everything
she had done, then examined the patient carefully,
paying particular attention to the feet.
Pelagia nervously waited for his anger.
'Well done, I have never been so proud,' he
declared. Drosoula smiled at Pelagia, who was so
relieved that her hands were shaking, and the two
women made more plans for Mandras's recovery.
CHAPTER FIVE
30 April 1941: Invasion
Though he said little, being almost incapable
of speech due to his physical condition,
Mandras was fully aware of the change in Pelagia's
attitude towards him and he hated the way in which
his mother and fiancee had undressed him, washed
him and discussed him as if he were not present.
But the horrors of war and starvation
had taken away from him the will to live,
so that he lay for weeks in bed in his mother's
house, incapable of moving or even speaking,
constantly revisiting in his mind the
terrible experiences that had been his.
The brilliance of his Greek leaders had enabled
him and many of his companions to survive the
war against the Italians, but the freezing
conditions in the mountains and lack of food
meant that his body aged more in a few months
than it would normally do in sixty years.
Then, when the Germans had attacked from
the south, Mandras's unit had marched back
down into Greece and had fought bravely but
uselessly against their enemy, leaving Mandras
the only survivor in his unit. With a vision of
a loving, smiling Pelagia constantly before him,
Mandras had found the strength to struggle
home, wearing bandages instead of boots,
through the wild hills, mountains and forests
that made up the greater part of Greece.
For much of his journey he had met very few people
and had consequently almost died from starvation.
If he had been met on his return to
Cephallonia by the loving Pelagia of
his dreams, Mandras's recovery might have been
faster. But as week followed week, Pelagia,
though she tried hard to love Mandras, felt only
coldness towards him, coldness and the growing
conviction that Mandras was remaining ill in order
to punish her for her lack of warmth towards him.
'He thinks that nobody wants him,' said Dr Iannis,
'and he's doing this in order to
force us to show him that we do.'
'But I don't want him,' thought
Pelagia, again and again,
as she sat making the bedcover that had
never grown beyond the size of a towel.
But although she spent a lot of time either
with or thinking about Mandras, there were
other matters that occupied her mind just as much.
By April 1941, the German army had reached Athens,
and the royal palace there was occupied not by
King George of Greece but by German soldiers. On
the 28th of the month, the Italian army, claiming
that the Ionian islands belonged to them by right,
invaded the island of Corfu, making it inevitable
that Cephallonia would be next on the list.
For the islanders, the waiting was painful. Every
last moment of freedom and security was rolled
about on the tongue, tasted and remembered.
Fathers who expected to be beaten to death
stroked the hair of pretty
daughters who expected to be raped.
Sons sat with their mothers on doorsteps
and talked gently of their memories.
Father Arsenios knelt in his church,
attempting to find words to a prayer,
puzzled by an odd sensation of having been
abandoned by God instead of the other way round.
In these last weeks before the invasion,
Dr Iannis wrote what he believed to be the
final part of his 'History of Cephallonia':
'Among those who invaded and occupied our island
- the Romans, the Turks, the Russians, the French,
the British' - he began, 'the Italians made the
greatest impression upon us, because we spent the
period from 1194 to 1797 under Italian rule. This
explains a great many things that may puzzle the
foreigner, for example, the numerous Italian words
that exist in our vocabulary, and the architecture
of the island, which is almost entirely
Italian.' He continued on this subject for
a number of pages, then, when it seemed that the
Italian invasion was due at any moment, he wrote:
'I wait in the knowledge that this
may be the last thing I ever write.
I beg that whoever finds these papers
should preserve and not destroy them.'
Placing the papers in a black tin box, the doctor
lifted the old carpet beneath the table and opened
a trapdoor, revealing the large hole that had been
made in 1849 in order to hide island rebels sought
by the British, who then governed the island.
He placed his work safely inside the hole,
then went outside to listen for the
sound of approaching aeroplanes.
On 30 April foreign aircraft and ships
were seen approaching from the horizon.
Drosoula ran inside to Pelagia shouting,
'Italians, Italians. It's the invasion,'
Pelagia's immediate reaction was to run up
the hill to be with her father, whom she found
standing in his doorway, as everyone else stood
in theirs, protecting his eyes against the sun
as he watched the planes. Out of breath,
she flew into his arms and felt him tremble,
then realized with a small shock that he
shook, not from fear, but from excitement.
'History,' he cried, 'all this time
I have been writing history, and now
history is happening before my eyes.'
The Italian soldiers stepped apologetically
out of their aircraft and ships
and waved cheerfully but hesitantly to the people
in their doorways. In the village, Pelagia and her
father watched the Italian units go by, their
leaders consulting maps with puzzled faces.
A line of men marched by, led by Captain
Antonio Corelli, with the mandolin that he had
named Antonia hanging on his back. When he saw
Pelagia he shouted, 'Bella bambina eyes left!'
The heads of the soldiers turned in her direction,
and for one unbelievable minute Pelagia was forced
to watch the most ridiculous behaviour. There was
a soldier who crossed his eyes and folded down
his lower lip, another who pushed his lips out
and blew her a kiss, another who pretended at
each step to stumble over his own feet. Pelagia
put her hand to her mouth. 'Don't laugh,'
ordered the doctor. 'It's our duty to hate them.'
All over Cephallonia the islanders painted rude
remarks about the invaders in huge letters on all
available walls. The men related Italian jokes.
What is the shortest book in the world? The
Italian Book of War Heroes. Why do Italians wear
moustaches? To be reminded of their mothers. A
decision was made that the local population should
provide Italian officers with accommodation.
So one day the doctor came home and found a
round Italian officer standing in the kitchen.
'Buon giorno,' said the officer.
'Buon giorno,' the doctor replied. 'Perhaps
you could tell me why you are here.'
'Ah,' said the man uncomfortably,
'I am sorry to say, you are going to have
to provide accommodation for an officer.'
'Impossible,' said the doctor angrily.
Then an interesting thought occurred to him
and he asked, 'Do you have a supply of medicines?'
'Naturally,' replied the officer.
The two men exchanged glances, understanding
perfectly what the other was thinking.
'There are many things I need,' said the doctor.
'And I need accommodation. So?'
'So it's a deal,' said the doctor.
'A deal,' repeated the
officer. 'Anything you want,
send me a message through Captain
Corelli. You will find him charming.'
In the early evening Captain Corelli
arrived, driven by another soldier,
Carlo Piero Guercio. The captain looked around,
appreciating the signs of a quiet domestic life.
There was a goat tied to a tree, and a
young woman with dark eyes at a table,
with a scarf tied round her head and a large
cooking knife in her hand. The captain fell to
his knees before her and exclaimed dramatically,
'Please don't kill me, I am innocent.'
Pelagia smiled, against her will, and glanced
at Carlo, amazed to see that he was as big as
Velisarios. The captain leapt up. 'I am Captain
Antonio Corelli and this...' he took Carlo by
the arm, '... is one of our heroes. He
rescued a fallen friend under fire.'
'It's nothing,' said Carlo with a shy smile, and
Pelagia knew immediately that, despite his size,
he was a soft and saddened man. 'This...' Corelli
continued, tapping a case in his hand, '... is
Antonia. By what name do men know you, may I
ask?' Pelagia looked at Corelli properly for
the first time and realized that this was the
same officer who had commanded his men to march
past at 'eyes left'. At the same moment Corelli
recognized her. 'Ah,' he exclaimed and smacked
himself on the wrist, then fell to his knees once
more and said softly, 'Forgive me, I have sinned.'
Dr Iannis came out, saw the
captain on his knees and said,
'Captain Corelli? I want a word with you. Now.'
Surprised by the authority in the older man's
voice, Corelli stood up and held out his hand,
but the doctor did not put out his own, instead
saying sharply, 'I want an explanation please.
Why has the teaching of Greek
history been forbidden in schools?
And why is everyone being
forced to learn Italian?'
The captain felt himself wanting
to run away like a little boy.
'I am not responsible for it,' he said.
The doctor frowned fiercely and
shook his finger at the captain.
'There would be no wars, captain, if
men like you took more responsibility.'
'I must protest,' the captain replied weakly.
'Fool,' said the doctor forcefully and returned
inside, very satisfied with himself. Pelagia could
not help feeling sorry for the captain. 'Your
father is...' he said, and the words failed him.
'Yes, he is,' confirmed Pelagia.
'Where shall I sleep?' asked
Corelli, eager to change the subject.
'You will have my bed,' said Pelagia.
Under normal circumstances Antonio
Corelli would have asked brightly,
'Are we going to share it then? How kind,' but
now, after the doctor's words, he received this
information with horror. 'Impossible,' he
said. 'Tonight I shall sleep in the yard
and tomorrow I shall request
alternative accommodation.'
Pelagia was shocked by the feelings
of anxiety that rose in her.
Could there be something inside her
that wanted this foreigner, this
invader, to stay? She went inside and told
her father about the captain's decision.
'He can't go,' he said. 'How am I supposed
to be nasty to him if he isn't here?
And anyway, he seems like a pleasant boy.' He took
his daughter's arm and went back out with her.
'Young man,' he said to the captain, 'you
are staying here whether you like it or not.
It is quite possible that we
will be sent someone even worse.'
'Yes,' said the captain,
overcome with embarrassment.
'Kyria Pelagia will bring water, some coffee and
food. You will find we look after our guests,
even those who do not deserve it. Your
vast friend is welcome to join us.'
The captain went to call Carlo to the meal in a
state of miserable obedience and utter defeat.
When the captain woke after his first night in
the doctor's house, he went into the kitchen,
saw Pelagia fast asleep and did not know what
to do. He looked down upon her and realized
he wanted to crawl in beside her - nothing
could have seemed more natural - but instead
he returned to his room and took his
mandolin, Antonia, out of its case.
After practising for five minutes or so, he
began playing a very fast, complicated piece,
forgetful of the sleeping girl next door, so that
Pelagia woke to indescribably beautiful music
coming from somewhere in the house. She lay
listening, then went to dress in her father's
room, and Corelli, realizing that she had
risen at last, came out into the kitchen.
'That was lovely,' commented Pelagia.
He looked unhappy. 'I'm sorry, I woke you up.'
'That's very beautiful,' she said,
gesturing towards the instrument.
'Why do you play the mandolin?'
'Why does one do anything? My uncle gave me
Antonia and I discovered I could be a good
musician. When the war's over, I'm going to become
a professional concert player and composer.'
'You're going to be rich and famous,
then,' Pelagia said jokingly.
'Why don't you play me something?'
The captain picked up the mandolin, and a stream
of notes poured from it that made Pelagia's mouth
fall open. She had never before heard such
complex, lovely music. She realized for the
first time that music was not just a sweet
sound, but was, to those who understood it,
an emotional and intellectual journey,
a journey that she wanted to share.
She leaned forward and put her hands
together as if she were at prayer.
'There you are,' said the
captain when he had finished.
In her excitement at the music, she wanted to
dance and spin round, but she only said, 'I
just don't understand why an artist like you would
descend to being a soldier. It's a waste of time.'
'Of course it's a waste of time.' He rose and
glanced at his watch. 'Carlo should have been
here by now. I'll have to go and find him.' He
looked at her with one eyebrow raised and said,
'By the way, Signorina, I couldn't help noticing
that you have a gun in the pocket of your skirt.'
Pelagia began to tremble
but the captain continued,
'I understand why you might want to have
it, and in fact I haven't seen it at all,
but you must realize what would happen
if someone else saw it. Be more careful.'
She looked up at him, appealing
with her eyes, and he smiled,
tapped the side of his nose and was gone.
Carlo had not arrived with the
car to pick up Captain Corelli,
because it had broken down some
kilometres from the village.
After kicking the car a number of times, Carlo had
set off on foot towards the village. Velisarios
passed him and the two men looked at one
another with something like recognition,
because both men had become accustomed to the sad
suspicion that they were unique in a peculiar way.
They were both amazed at the other's size and
for a moment forgot that they were enemies.
'Hey!' said Velisarios, raising his hands
in a gesture of pleasure. Carlo offered
him one of his disgusting cigarettes, Velisarios
accepted, and they made sour faces to each other
as they smoked. They then went their separate
ways, more content than before they had met.
As Carlo walked up the hill towards the house,
his mind turned towards Captain Corelli.
For the first time since the death of
Francesco in the mountains of Albania,
the soldier was experiencing a kind of
happiness; in the captain he had once
again found a man whom he could love and serve.
In his eyes, Corelli was endlessly optimistic,
a clear fountain, a kind of saint who remained a
man of honour because he knew no other way to be.
Carlo knew that some people thought that
Corelli was a little mad, but for him, the
captain was a man who loved life so much that he
did not care what kind of an impression he made.
One of the pleasures of Carlo's life, at
that time, was an opera group called La
Scala that the captain had organized from
among those of his men who could sing.
Carlo, who had a fine singing voice, had been
invited to join when the captain had heard
him singing as he polished his boots. There was
another more unusual member of the opera group,
a young German soldier called Gunter Weber,
part of a troop of three thousand German
soldiers who had accompanied the Italian
army on their invasion of the island.
Although relations between the Germans and
Italians appeared friendly, the Germans thought
of the Italians as inferior, and the Italians were
puzzled by German discipline and lack of humour.
But Captain Corelli had made
friends with Gunter Weber,
a boy who spoke some Italian and whom the captain
liked because his face was open and friendly,
and because when he got drunk he
laughed and lost his German seriousness.
Weber became a member of the opera club despite
the fact that he could not sing a note. Neither
Corelli nor Carlo knew that one day the German
would betray his friends with a storm of bullets
that would open red and bleeding wounds in the
bodies of the companions he had grown to love.
CHAPTER SIX
The Freedom Fighter
After Captain Corelli had left, Pelagia did
some household tasks, then went outside to
brush her goat, thinking about the captain
as she did so. Mandras caught her dreaming.
He had climbed out of bed, cursing and completely
cured, on the day of the invasion, as if the
arrival of the Italians was something so important
that illness was a luxury to be left behind.
He had gone down to the sea and
swum as if he had never been away,
and had returned with a smile on his face
and a fish for Pelagia. But Pelagia only felt
guilty now, whenever she saw
him, and deeply uncomfortable.
She jumped when he tapped her on the shoulder
and despite her effort to force a bright smile,
he did not fail to see the look of alarm in her
eyes. He ignored it but would remember it later.
'I'm going to join the freedom fighters,'
he said. 'I'm leaving tomorrow.'
'Oh,' said Pelagia. There was a long silence,
then she said, 'I won't be able to write.'
'I know.'
Pelagia shook her head slowly and
sighed. 'Promise me one thing.
Whenever you are planning to do something
terrible, think of me and don't do it.'
'I'm a Greek,' he said gently. 'Not a Fascist.
And I will think of you every minute.'
She heard the sincerity in his voice
and felt herself wanting to cry.
They embraced, like brother and sister,
not people who were engaged to be married.
'God go with you,' said Pelagia,
and he smiled sadly. 'And with you.'
'I shall always remember
you swinging in the tree.'
They laughed, then he looked at
her lovingly for one last moment,
took a few steps, paused, turned and
said softly, 'I shall always love you.'
***
Mandras joined a group of three men in the
hills of the Peloponnisos in southern Greece.
They had neither plan nor purpose. All they
knew was that they were driven by something
from the depths of the soul, something that
commanded them to rid their land of strangers
or die in the attempt. They set fire to lorries,
and one of their number stabbed an enemy soldier
and afterwards sat shaking with fear and disgust
while the others comforted and praised him.
They lived on the edge of a forest in a cave,
living off supplies brought by the priest
of a neighbouring village. There were several
other groups of freedom fighters in the area,
the most organized being
a Communist group known as
ELAS (although it did not declare itself as
communist, preferring to disguise the fact).
Mandras joined ELAS at first because
he had no choice. He and his companions
were lying in a small leafy
shelter that they had built,
when they were suddenly surrounded
by ten men with thick beards,
pointing guns at them. Their leader, who wore
a dirty red cap, said, 'Come out,' and the men
slowly stood up and came out, fearing for their
lives, their hands upon the backs of their heads.
'Who are you with?' demanded the man with the cap.
'With no one,' replied Mandras, confused.
'The deal is that either
you go back to your villages
and leave us your weapons,' said the leader
commandingly, 'or you fight us and we kill you,
or you join us under my command. This is my
territory and no one else's. Which is it?'
'We came to fight,' explained
Mandras. 'Who are you?'
'I am Hector, not my real name, and we are the
local branch of ELAS.' Hector's men grinned in
a very friendly fashion, and Mandras looked
from one of his companions to the others.
'We stay?' he asked, and they nodded. They had
been too long in the hills to give up the fight
and it was good to have found a leader
who might know what ought to be done.
'Good,' said Hector. 'Come with us,
and let's see what you are made of.'
He led Mandras and his companions three kilometres
to a tiny house guarded by one of Hector's men.
'Bring him out,' Hector said, and the man kicked
and pushed a thin old man out into the sunlight,
where he stood trembling and blinking. Hector
handed Mandras a length of knotted rope
and, pointing to the old man, said, 'Beat him.'
Mandras stared at Hector in disbelief
and the latter stared fiercely back at him.
'If you want to be with us, you've got to
learn to teach these people a lesson. This
man has been found guilty. Now beat him.'
Mandras struck the man once with the
rope, lightly, because of the man's age,
and Hector impatiently exclaimed,
'Harder, harder. What are you? A woman?'
Mandras struck the old man once more, a
little harder. 'Again,' commanded Hector.
It was easier each time he hit him. In fact
it became a pleasure. It was as if all the
anger from the earliest years of his childhood
rose in him and was given expression. The old
man threw himself to the ground, screaming, and
Mandras suddenly knew he could be a god. Hector
stepped forward, took the rope from his hand,
and placed a gun in his grasp. 'Now kill him.'
Mandras knelt down and placed the gun against
the old man's head, but he could not do it. He
closed his eyes tight and told himself that
he had to be a man in front of other men.
Anyway, he was only doing what Hector had
ordered him to do. The man was going to
die anyway. Mandras tightened the muscles
of his face and shot the man in the head.
Afterwards he looked not at the
bloody mess of bone and brain,
but in disbelief at the smoking gun. Hector
patted Mandras on the back and said, 'Well done'.
Mandras tried to struggle to
his feet but could not do so,
and Hector helped him up. 'Revolutionary
justice,' he said. 'Historical necessity.'
As they left the village, Mandras found
that he could not look anyone in the face
and he stared down into the dirt.
'What did he do?' he asked finally.
'He was a dirty old thief. He took a bottle of
whisky from supplies that were meant for us.
You have to be tough with these people
or they start doing what they like.
They're full of the wrong ideas and it's
just something we have to get out of them.'
***
During his time with Hector, Mandras learnt a
great many things. Hector taught Mandras to read
and write, and taught him all about Communism.
Mandras learnt that he was not a fisherman
but a worker, and that he was as good as Dr Iannis
and deserved the same pay. He learnt to take food
and animals from hungry villagers without payment,
since ELAS was working so hard on behalf of the
Greek people. When villagers attempted to resist
them, then Hector and his men punished them,
not just by shooting them but by tearing out
eyes and cutting mouths so that people died
smiling. Hector explained to Mandras that the
villagers were Fascists and loyal to the king,
and that a good lesson would
help them to change their ways.
Mandras also learnt to rape women and to enjoy
their screams, since it was all in a good cause.
A new and better Greece would be built, and you
did what you liked with the inferior bricks that
were going to be thrown away anyway. It was
like making an omelette and throwing away
the eggshells, said Hector, and Mandras
drank in every word his leader said.
CHAPTER SEVEN
A Problem with Eyes
Pelagia treated the captain as badly
as she could. If she served him food,
she would deliberately spill it as she put it
down, and eventually she noticed that he had
acquired the habit of not pulling in his chair
until she had already put the food on the table.
His failure to protest at her treatment
of him and his constant politeness
made her even more annoyed. Her anger was so
deep and so bitter that she needed to shout at
him or even strike him in order to release
it. After two months of sleepless nights,
months during which she had done her best to
annoy him, the captain remained calm and friendly.
One day he left his gun on the table. After
some thought, Pelagia decided to put the gun
in a bowl of water for a few minutes in
the hope that this would do some damage.
The captain came in and caught her just as
she was lifting the gun out of the water.
She heard a voice behind her and, in
her fear, dropped it back in the bowl.
'Oh God,' she exclaimed, 'you frightened me!'
The captain looked down at the gun, raised his
eyebrows and said coolly, 'I see you're trying
to make trouble for me.' This was not what she
had expected, but nevertheless her heart beat
faster with fear and anxiety. 'I was washing it,'
she said weakly at last. 'It was terribly oily.'
'How charming to know so little
about guns,' said the captain.
Pelagia went red, strangely
angered by his suggestion,
which she knew he did not mean, that she was
a sweet and silly girl who did stupid things.
'You are not a good liar,' the captain added.
'What do you expect?' she demanded,
immediately wondering what she had meant.
The captain seemed to know, however.
'It must be very difficult for you all
to have to put up with us.' He removed
the gun from the bowl, sighed and said,
'I suppose you have done me a
favour. It does need cleaning.'
'Aren't you angry, then? Why aren't you angry?'
'What's anger got to do with music? Do you really
believe I've got nothing important to think about?
Let's just think about important
things and leave one another in peace.
I'll leave you alone and you can leave me alone.'
This idea struck Pelagia as new and unacceptable.
She did not want to leave him alone, she wanted
to shout at him and hit him. Suddenly overcome
with emotion, she struck him with all her force,
right across the left cheek.
He tried to step back in time,
but was too late. He steadied himself and touched
a hand to his face, as if comforting himself,
then held out the gun. 'Put it back in the water,'
he said, 'I might find it less painful.' This
remark made Pelagia even angrier. She rushed
out into the yard and kicked an iron pot,
injuring her toe, then threw the pot over the
wall. The captain, watching her from the window,
shook his head in amazement. These Greek girls,
such passion and fire, he thought admiringly, and
then wondered why no one had ever written an opera
set in modern Greece. A tune entered his mind and
he began to sing it softly to himself, thinking
that perhaps he would call it 'Pelagia's March'.
As the months went by, Pelagia noticed that she
was losing her anger, and this puzzled and upset
her. The fact was that the captain had become
as much a part of the house as the goat or her
own father, and she was quite used to seeing
him playing with little Lemoni in the yard,
or seated at the table, deep in concentration,
composing music for the mandolin. Early in the
morning she looked forward with pleasure to the
moment when he would enter the kitchen and say,
'Kalimcra Kyria Pelagia. Is Carlo here yet?'
and in the evening she would actually
begin to worry if he were a little late.
A new source of anger developed, the problem
being that this time the anger was directed
against herself. It seemed that she just could not
help looking at him, and he was always catching
her. There was something about him, sitting
at the table as he went through his paperwork,
that made her look up at him regularly.
But every time she looked up, he did too,
and she would be caught in his steady gaze as
surely as if he had grasped her by the wrists.
For a few seconds they would look at one another
and then she would grow red and look down.
Then a few seconds later she would look up,
and at that moment he would return her glance.
It was impossible and embarrassing. 'I've got
to stop doing this,' she would tell herself and,
certain that he was deep in his tasks,
would look up and get caught again.
She knew he was playing a game with her,
that she was being played with so gently
that it was impossible to protest. After
all, she had never caught him looking at her,
so it was all her fault, obviously. Nevertheless,
it was a game of which he was in absolute command,
and in that sense she was its victim. She decided
that she would not be the one to look down;
she would wait until he broke away. She searched
for every last bit of courage and looked up.
They looked at one another for what seemed
like hours and Pelagia wondered foolishly if
it was considered acceptable to blink. Her
eyes began to water and she started seeing
two captains instead of one. He did not
look away but began to make funny faces,
showing his teeth like a horse, and moving
the tip of his nose from side to side,
so that Pelagia began a smile, then laughed
aloud and blinked. Corelli jumped to his feet,
crying, 'I won! I won,' and the doctor looked
up from his book, exclaiming, 'What? What?'
'You cheated,' protested Pelagia, laughing. The
doctor looked from the captain to his daughter,
adjusted his glasses and sighed. 'Whatever next?'
he demanded, knowing perfectly well what was next,
and working out in advance how to deal with it.
Some days later they passed each
other at the door, she going out
and he returning from work. Unselfconsciously, she
raised one hand to his left cheek and, in passing,
kissed him on the other. He was astonished and,
by the time she reached the entrance to the yard,
so was she, because it was not until then that she
realized what she had done. She stopped as if she
had walked straight into a wall, felt her blood
rising to the roots of her hair, and realized that
she did not dare look back at him. He called
out, as she knew he would, 'Kyria Pelagia,'
'What?' she demanded.
'What's for dinner?'
'Don't laugh at me. I thought you were my father.
I always kiss him like that when he comes in.'
'Very understandable. We are both old and small.'
'If you are going to laugh at me,
I shall never speak to you again.'
He came out and threw himself
upon his knees before her.
'Oh no,' he cried, 'not that. Shoot me, beat
me, but don't say you'll never speak to me.'
He grasped her round the
knees and pretended to weep.
'The whole village is looking,'
she protested. 'Stop it at once.'
'My heart is broken,' he cried and, taking
her hand, he began to cover it with kisses.
'Stupid goat, you are insane.'
Corelli laughed and got to his
feet. 'Come inside,' he said,
'I've got something very interesting to show you.'
Relieved by this sudden change of subject,
she followed him through the door,
but found that he was passing
her on the way out again.
He put his hands on each side of her head, kissed
her dramatically on the forehead, exclaimed,
'I'm sorry, I thought it was the doctor,' and
then ran away across the yard and down the street.
She stared after him in amazement, making
every effort not to laugh or smile.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Snails
When the doctor glanced out of the window and
saw Captain Corelli creeping up behind Lemoni
in order to surprise her, he laid down his
pen and went out into the afternoon sunlight.
'Excuse me, children,' said the doctor,
ignoring the captain's embarrassment,
'Lemoni, do you remember that you told me you
know a place where there were lots of snails?
Can you come round this evening
and show me where they are?'
Lemoni nodded importantly.
'What's all this about?' asked the captain.
Stiffly, the doctor said, 'Thanks to you Italians,
there's almost no food. We're going
out this evening to find snails.'
The captain wiped the sweat from his forehead
and said, 'Permit me to come and help.'
So in the evening, an hour before sunset, Pelagia
and her father, Lemoni and the captain climbed
over a low wall and then began crawling through
impossibly thick undergrowth in their search for
snails. It became immediately apparent that there
were quantities of snails everywhere they looked.
The child and three adults became so involved
in their task that they did not notice they
had become separated. The captain found
himself on his own and paused for a second,
realizing that he could not remember
ever having felt so content.
'Oh, oh no,' came Pelagia's voice from nearby.
Fearing that perhaps she had been hurt, the
captain crawled towards the place where her
voice had come from and found her unable
to move, her hair caught in some briars,
her neck pulled backwards.
'Don't laugh,' she said crossly.
'I'm not laughing,' he said, laughing.
'I was afraid you were hurt.'
'If you don't help me, I'll
murder you. Just stop laughing.'
'Hold still,' he told her, and reaching
over her shoulders he began to pull the
hair out piece by piece, as gently as he could.
'I've done it,' he said, pleased with himself,
and as he drew back and his lips passed her
cheek, he kissed it tenderly, before the ear.
She touched her fingertips to
the place of the kiss, and said,
shaking her head at him, 'You
shouldn't have done that.'
He knelt back and held her gaze with his
own. 'I couldn't help it. I'm sorry.'
They looked at one another for a long moment,
and then Pelagia began to cry. 'What's the
matter?' asked Corelli, frowning in concern as
Pelagia's tears rolled down her cheeks and fell
into the bucket among the snails. 'You're drowning
them,' he said, pointing. 'What's the matter?'
She gave a sad smile, and started crying again.
He took her in his arms and patted her back.
Suddenly she said, 'I can't stand it
any more, not any of it. I'm sorry.'
'Everything is horrible,' agreed the captain,
wondering if he too might start to cry.
He took her head gently in his hands and
touched at the tears with his lips. She
gazed at him wonderingly and suddenly they
found themselves underneath the briars,
in the sunset, surrounded by escaping snails,
deep in their first, secret, guilty kiss. Hungry
and desperate, filled with light, they could
not move away from each other, and when finally
they returned home, they brought back fewer
snails together than Lemoni brought on her own.
They became lovers in the old-fashioned sense.
Their idea of making love was to kiss in the dark
under the trees or sit on a rock watching the sea.
He loved her too much to risk her unhappiness,
and she had too much sense to take risks. Again
and again she had seen the tragedy of girls with
an unwanted child and the poisoned deaths of
girls who had tried to end their pregnancies.
It was hard for Pelagia to love an invader and
sometimes she shouted at Corelli, her eyes filled
with tears of anger: 'How can you bear to be
here? Orders? Orders from a madman! Don't you
know you're being used? Why don't you take your
guns and leave? Don't you know who the enemy is?'
At these times the captain listened silently and
bowed his head, the bitterness of his shame eating
like a worm at the muscles of his heart. But they
could not stop themselves from loving one another.
Gunter Weber managed to obtain
a motorcycle for the captain,
who turned up outside the doctor's
house one day wearing a cap and goggles.
'Do you want to come for a ride?' he asked.
Pelagia crossed her arms.
'I've never been on one. In fact I've never
been in a car either and I'm not starting now.'
'I've never been on one either,'
he said, 'but it's very easy.'
'Somebody might see us,' said Pelagia.
The captain solved this problem by bringing
Pelagia a disguise consisting of a cap,
goggles and a long leather coat, and the next day
they met around the bend of the road and
rode off on the bike. They fell off twice,
without injury, and she gripped his waist,
whitefaced with terror. She climbed off,
shaking, and realized she could not wait to get
back on; it was splendid to ride a motorcycle.
They went to places where Pelagia could not have
been recognized and to places that were deserted,
and there she would put her arm through his and
walk beside him, leaning her weight against his
shoulder, always laughing. With him, she
would always remember that she laughed.
One day they discovered a ruined hut so old that
the floor had sunk into the earth. They called it
'Casa Nostra', and in this secret house they would
spread a blanket and lie embracing and talking.
All their lovers' talk began
with the phrase, 'After the war'.
'After the war, when we are married, let's go to
America; I've got relatives in Chicago. After the
war we won't bring up our children with any
religion, they can make their own minds up
when they're older. After the war, we'll go all
over Europe and you can give concerts in hotels
and that's how we'll live. After the war I'll
love you, I'll love you forever after the war.'
***
It was during this period of
happiness for Pelagia and the captain
that Dr Iannis was woken one night
by a gentle tapping on his window.
Puzzled, the doctor looked out and saw a villager
accompanied by a very tall fair-haired man wearing
the Greek national costume, something that a
wealthy man might wear once a year on a feast day.
'We thought you were the man to help him,' the
villager told the doctor, before departing.
The tall stranger smiled and held out his hand,
speaking in an extraordinarily old-fashioned Greek
that the doctor found almost impossible
to understand. The stranger then climbed,
uninvited, through the doctor's window into the
house, and took a huge radio out of his bag.
Pelagia woke and came into her father's room,
saw the stranger and put her hand over
her mouth, wide-eyed with amazement.
'Who's this?' she demanded of her father.
'How am I supposed to know,'
replied the doctor. 'He
says he's called Bunnios and he
talks Greek like a Spanish cow.'
The stranger bowed politely and shook
Pelagia's hand, then smiled charmingly
and said, 'Greek of the old days. Homer.'
'Ancient Greek?' exclaimed Pelagia,
disbelievingly. The doctor tapped his
finger to his forehead. 'English?' he asked.
'English,' agreed the man.
'But, I must beg you...'
'Of course we won't tell anyone.'
The man smiled. It had been an awful
burden to speak the finest ancient Greek
and not be understood.
'We are having an Italian officer sleeping
in a room,' said the doctor, whose English
was not as good as he liked to believe, 'so we
are being very quiet, please. Are you a spy?'
The man nodded and asked, 'Do you have any
clothes I could have? I would be so grateful.'
The Englishman departed for the town of Argostoli
at dawn, wearing trousers that ended half way
down his legs, and having received some good
advice from the doctor: 'Look, OK? You accent
terrible-terrible. Not to talk, understand?
You are quiet until you learning. Also,
you watch out Communists - they thieves.
Italians OK, Germans not good, see?'
Bunnios, whose real name was Bunny Warren,
soon found an empty hut in the hills where,
using his huge radio, he reported in
great detail to his British masters,
informing them of troop movements
in the area. He also set himself
the task of learning modern Greek, and was
assisted in this by the willing islanders.
***
The captain's opera group, La Scala, became
accustomed to meeting in the doctor's house.
'Your soldiers are stealing from
people's vegetable patches, when
we're dying of hunger already,' said the doctor
to Corelli one day, when the group was there.
'If it's true, they will be
punished,' the captain replied,
already deeply shamed and embarrassed
by the fact that some nights previously
someone, obviously an Italian
soldier, had stolen Pelagia's goat.
'We Germans do not do this,' said Gunter
Weber, with a pleased expression on his face.
'Germans can't sing,' replied Corelli,
'and anyway, I'll get this investigated
and I'll put a stop to it. It's too bad.'
Weber smiled. 'You are very famous for
defending the rights of the Greeks.
I wonder if sometimes you
understand why you are here.'
'I try to think of it as a holiday. I
don't have your advantages, Gunter.'
'Advantages?'
'Yes. I don't have the advantage of thinking
that other races are inferior to mine.'
'It's a question of science,' said Weber.
'You can't alter a scientific fact.'
Corelli frowned. 'Science?
I don't care about science. Moral
principles are important, not science.'
'We disagree,' said Weber in a friendly fashion.
'Science tells us that the strong survive.
Strength needs no excuses and
doesn't have to give reasons.'
'Science is about facts, and
morality is about values,'
said Carlo, who had been listening closely.
'It's also a matter of being able to
live with yourself,' Corelli added.
'You're a good man,' said Gunter, 'I admit
it. Why don't I get my record player from
my car and we can all sing with Marlene
Dietrich.' He went to his car and proudly
returned with the record player, which he
put down on the table. He put on the record
and Dietrich began to sing, her voice full of
the sadness of knowledge, the longing for love.
'Oh,' exclaimed Weber, 'her voice makes
me melt,' and Corelli said, 'Antonia likes
this. She's going to sing.' He began to
accompany the song, playing so beautifully
that in the village people stopped what they were
doing and listened to Corelli fill the night.
Pelagia left the kitchen, her form
ghostlike in the light of the candles.
'Please play that song again,' she
asked Weber. 'It was so beautiful.'
'Do you like it?' asked Weber, and she nodded.
'All right,' he continued, 'when I go home after
the war, I'll leave it with you. It would
please me very much for you to have it.'
Pelagia was delighted. She looked at the smiling
boy with his smart uniform and blond hair
and was filled with pleasure. 'You're so sweet,'
she said, and kissed him naturally on the cheek,
so that the boys of La Scala cheered and
Weber went red and hid his eyes with his hand.
***
The time came when the doctor decided that it was
necessary to discuss certain matters with Pelagia.
'There's something I have to
talk to you about,' he told her.
'It has not escaped my notice that you
have fallen in love with the captain.'
She went violently red and looked terribly
shocked. 'The captain?' she said foolishly.
He began a long speech. 'It's not that I don't
like the captain. Of course, he's a little mad,
which is quite simply explained by the fact that
he is Italian. In fact I like him very much,
but you must remember that you are
engaged to Mandras, and technically,
the captain is an enemy. Can you imagine the pain
you will suffer when people discover that you
have given up the love of a Greek in favour of an
invader? People will throw stones at you and spit,
you know that, don't you? You would have to move
away to Italy if you wanted to stay with him,
because here you might not be safe. Are you
prepared to leave this island and this people?
'And another thing. Love is a temporary madness.
When it ends you have to work out whether your
roots have so joined together that it is
unimaginable that you should ever separate.
Because that is what love is. Love isn't
breathlessness, it is not excitement,
it is not lying awake at night imagining that
he is kissing every part of your body. No,
don't look so embarrassed, I'm telling you
some truths. That is just being "in love",
which any fool can do. Love itself is what is
left over when being in love has burned away.
'I say to you that to marry the captain is
impossible until our country is free again.
I would be happy for you to do this, but this
means that you have a love that will be delayed.
Pelagia, you know as well as I do that love
delayed means that physical passion increases. No,
don't look at me like that. Do you think I don't
know that young girls can be eaten by desire?
Imagine if you got pregnant, what would you do?
I would not assist in the murder of an innocent.
Would you have the child, and then find that no
man would ever marry you? I would not abandon you
as long as I live, even under such circumstances.
But imagine if I should die. What then?'
Pelagia had never felt so crushed in all her
life and wept bitterly, but when she looked up,
she found her father looking
at her sympathetically.
'You make everything sound so disgusting,'
she said. 'You don't know how it is.'
'I went through a lot of this
with your mother,' he replied.
'She was engaged to someone
else. I do know how it is.'
'You don't forbid everything
then?' she asked hopefully.
'No, I don't forbid everything. I say you
must be careful and act honourably to Mandras.
Don't give in to your desires, that's
all. The captain is a good man.
Pray for our freedom, Pelagia, because
then everything becomes possible.'
Pelagia stood up to go and her father said, 'I
did not intend to upset you. I was young once.'
'Not everything was different in your
day, then,' she said as she left the room,
and her father smiled, pleased that his
words had not crushed his daughter's spirit.
***
The doctor and the captain were sitting indoors
at the kitchen table while the latter was removing
a broken string from his mandolin. The doctor
leaned back and sighed, then suddenly asked,
'Are you and Pelagia planning to be married?
As her father, I think I have a right to know.'
The captain was so surprised by the frankness
of the question that he was unable to think
of a reply. His relationship with Pelagia
had only been able to proceed on the basis
that no one ever brought the issue out into
the open. He looked at the doctor anxiously.
'You can't live here,' said the
doctor. He pointed to the mandolin.
'If you want to be a musician, this is the
last place to be. And I don't think that
Pelagia could live in Italy. She is a Greek.
She would die like a flower without sunlight.'
'Ah,' said the captain, for the
lack of any intelligent remark.
'It's true,' said the doctor. 'I know you
have not thought about it. Italians always
act without thinking. Anyway, Pelagia is
a Greek, that's my point. So can it work?'
There was a silence between the two
men. 'I love her,' said Corelli at last,
as if this were the answer to
the problem, which to him it was.
'I know that. You'd have to live here,
that's all,' said the doctor. 'You might
have to choose between loving
her and becoming a musician.'
The doctor left the room, more for dramatic effect
than for any other purpose, and then came back in.
'And another thing. This is a very ancient land
and we've had nothing except murder for two
thousand years. We've got so many places full
of bitter ghosts that anyone who goes near them
or lives in them becomes heartless or insane.
I don't believe in God, captain,
but I do believe in ghosts.
And there will be many more deaths. It's only a
question of time. So don't make any plans.'
CHAPTER NINE
Autumn 1943: Betrayal
The Allies invaded Sicily, Italy's southern
island, and so they betrayed their most
loyal and courageous friend, Greece, and
did not come to its aid. The angry Greeks
demanded to know why their country, which was
occupied by the Italians, had been ignored,
and received no answers. The Allies had abandoned
Greece, the little nation that had given Europe
its culture and its heart. To make matters
worse, during this period the Greek Communists
were committing unimaginably vicious acts, but
for a long time the world did not believe it.
On Cephallonia, the Italian
soldiers listened to their radios
and followed the course of Allied progress
up Italy, their homeland, while the German
soldiers were angered and disgusted by the Italian
army's lack of resistance to the Allies. Corelli
and his brother officers sensed ice in the air,
and visits between the Germans and the Italians
became less frequent. When Weber turned up at
meetings of La Scala, he seemed quiet and distant.
'What happens,' Corelli asked
Pelagia with a troubled look,
'when we have to surrender before the Germans do?'
'We'll get married.'
He shook his head sadly. 'It's going to be a
complete mess. There's no chance of the British
coming. They're going straight for Rome. No
one will save us unless we save ourselves.
We should attack the Germans on the island
now, while there aren't many of them,
but our generals don't do anything.
They say we should trust the Germans.'
'Don't you trust them?'
'I'm not stupid.'
'Come inside,' she said, 'my father's out.'
'There's no point. My mind is just
a blank that's filled with worry.'
Corelli came to the doctor's house less often,
and day and night he trained his men, working
them hard in the terrible August heat,
so that the sweat ran down their faces and arms,
and the sun burned the flesh of their shoulders.
They did not complain. They knew that
the captain was right to prepare them.
He himself stopped playing the mandolin; there was
so little time for it that when he picked it up
it felt foreign in his fingers in comparison with
a gun. He went home to Pelagia on his motorbike at
times when her father was likely to be out, and
he brought her bread, honey, bottles of wine,
a photograph signed on the back with the words
'After the War...' written on it in his elegant,
foreign-looking handwriting, and he brought her
his tired, grey face, and his saddened eyes.
'My poor darling,' she would say, her arms about
his neck, 'don't worry, don't worry, don't worry,'
and he would move back a little and say,
'Koritsimou, let me just look at you.'
And then came the time when Carlo was listening
to the radio, trying to find a signal. It was 8
September, and the evenings had become
much cooler than they had been before.
Carlo had recently been thinking about Francesco
and about the horror of Albania, and now more than
ever he knew that it had all been a waste, and
that his time in Cephallonia had been a holiday
from a war that was going to destroy his life once
more, perhaps forever. He found a voice and turned
up the volume: '... all aggressive acts by Italian
Armed Forces against the forces of the British and
the Americans will cease at once, everywhere.' The
Italians had formally surrendered to the Allies.
Outside, the bells of the island began to
ring; they rang all over the island in the
towns of Argostoli, Lixouri, Soulari, Dorizata.
On the radio there was a message from Eisenhower,
the American president: '... All Italians
who take steps to rid themselves of the
German presence in their country will have
the assistance and support of the Allies...'
Carlo ran out and found Corelli just arriving on
his bike, a great cloud of blue smoke behind him.
'Antonio, Antonio, it's all over, and the
Allies have promised to help us,' he cried.
He threw his enormous arms around the man he loved
and picked him up, dancing in a circle. 'Carlo,
Carlo,' the captain cried, 'put me down. Don't
get so excited. The Allies don't care about us.
We're in Greece, remember. Carlo, you don't
know your own strength. You half killed me.'
'They'll help us,' said Carlo,
but Corelli shook his head.
'If we don't act now, we're finished. We've got to
get the Germans on the island to surrender to us.'
That night the Italian warships in the
harbours of the island sailed for home,
without informing anyone they were going, or
taking with them a single Italian soldier. In
a terrible act of cowardice, the warships withdrew
their protection from the soldiers on the island,
so that the German soldiers laughed and
Corelli's men smelled betrayal. Corelli waited
at the telephone for orders, and when
none came he fell asleep in his chair.
Carlo, now realizing that Corelli's
pessimistic predictions were probably correct,
wrote his captain a long letter in which
he declared his undying love for him
and also his unselfish hope that Corelli would
find true happiness with Pelagia. Strangely
convinced that he was going to die soon, Carlo
added this letter to his other writings and
brought them to the doctor's house, with the
request that his papers should be placed in
the hiding-hole under the trapdoor and only
opened and read in the event of his death.
Like Corelli, Gunter Weber also slept from time to
time in his chair, waiting for orders, desperately
tired and with all his confidence gone. He
missed his Italian friends, but worse than that,
his country was losing and he no longer felt proud
and full of strength. He felt inferior and so
betrayed by his country's allies, the Italians,
that if he had been a woman he would have wept.
He tried to pray but the words
turned bitter in his mouth.
Corelli stopped his motorcycle
on his way back to camp
and beneath the shade of a tree, by a ruined wall,
he sat and thought about going back to Italy,
about surviving, about Pelagia. The truth
was that he had no home and that was why
he never talked about it. Mussolini
had forced his family to move to Libya,
and there they had been attacked by rebels and had
died, while he lay in hospital with a high fever.
Of all the relatives' houses where
he had stayed, which one was home?
He had no family except his soldiers and his
mandolin, and his heart was there in Greece.
Had he suffered so much pain, so much loneliness,
had he finally found a place to be, only to have
it torn away? His memories of his parents were
as thin and indefinite as those of a ghost,
and for the first time he began to feel as
if Pelagia already belonged to his past.
He thought about dying and wondered how
long Pelagia would weep, and what a shame
it would be to spoil her lovely flesh with
tears; it broke his heart to imagine it.
He wanted to reach out from beyond the grave and
comfort her, even though he was not yet dead.
He went to the doctor's house and asked
them to look after his mandolin, and Pelagia
wrapped it in a blanket and put
it under the hole in the floor.
They told him about Carlo's visit, and how
he had left a thick pile of papers with them.
The captain had not known that Carlo had ambitions
to be a writer and was curious about the content
of the big man's papers. He thought that
Pelagia looked very thin and almost ill,
and when she sadly stroked his cheek, he
almost did not know how to prevent his tears.
***
After Italy's surrender to the Allies,
General Gandin, leader of the Italian troops
on Cephallonia, suffered terrible indecision
about the course of action he should take.
He had two choices. Compared to the
number of Italian soldiers on the island,
there were many fewer German
troops, and he could insist
that the German soldiers laid down their arms
and surrendered to the superior Italian forces.
If the Germans rejected this, then the
Italian troops could theoretically attack
and overcome them. But Gandin knew that he
would receive no support from the Allies,
and moreover, that he would have neither air nor
sea support from his own country. He knew that the
Germans still had a large number of bomber planes
based in mainland Greece, and the thought of
those death machines screaming over the island as
they dropped their bombs filled him with horror.
These thoughts led the General to the second
option, which was to surrender to the Germans,
on condition that the latter gave written
guarantees of the safety of the Italian soldiers
on the island. This would mean trusting
the Germans not to break their promises
and attack the Italians. It was this second
route that Gandin was tempted to take. He was,
in a strange way, a man of honour, and still
considered the Germans to be his allies.
Unlike General Gandin, the Italian troops on
Cephallonia knew exactly what should be done.
They heard from the radio that the Germans, as
they withdrew in Italy, were killing and looting
along the way and they could see no reason why
the Germans would not do the same in Cephallonia,
given the chance. While Gandin delayed, unable to
make up his mind, and his soldiers became almost
crazy with anger and fear, the Germans quietly
flew more arms and troops to the island.
Finally General Gandin came to a decision. Despite
the universal demand of his men that the Germans
should be forced to surrender, the General
agreed with the German leaders on the island
that the Italians should be allowed to keep their
weapons and peacefully leave Cephallonia. There
were no ships, however, to take the Italians away,
a point which did not seem significant to Gandin.
Some of the Italian troops, guessing what was
likely to happen, became deeply depressed,
while others, like Corelli, developed an
iron determination and prepared their men
to the last degree for the terrible battle
that they were certain lay ahead of them.
When the German bomber planes arrived,
early in the afternoon, tipping their wings,
it was almost a relief to the waiting Italians.
Now everything was clear; it was at last obvious
that the Germans had betrayed them and that
every Italian soldier would have to fight for
his life. Gunter Weber knew that he would
have to turn his weapons on his friends.
Corelli knew that his musician's fingers,
so well accustomed to the arts of peace,
must now tighten around a gun. General Gandin
knew too late that he had made the wrong decision
and that, as a result, his men were going
to die. Pelagia knew that a war that had
always been somewhere else would now settle
upon her home and turn its stones to dust.
The German planes attacked Argostoli first
because that was where most Italian troops
were concentrated. Gandin made the
foolish mistake of bringing his troops
into the town in increasing numbers, and this
made it easier for the Germans to isolate and
cut them down. Houses were crushed by the bombs
and soldiers and islanders died in large numbers.
More and more German soldiers were flown in, and
spread all over the island, killing as they went.
Everyone knew that no ships or planes would come
to aid an island of Cephallonia's insignificance.
On a hillside, Bunny Warren sat by his
radio and tried to persuade his superiors
that they should provide the Italians with
air and sea support, but without success.
***
Dr Iannis and his daughter sat side by side
at their kitchen table, unable to sleep,
holding each others' hands. Pelagia was
weeping. The doctor wanted to relight his pipe,
but out of respect for his daughter's feelings
he allowed his hands to stay in hers, and he
repeated, 'Koritsimou, I am sure he is all right.'
'But we haven't seen him for days,'
she cried. 'I just know he's dead.'
'If he was dead someone would have
told us, someone from La Scala.
They were all nice boys, they would let us know.'
'Were?' she repeated. 'You think they're all
dead? You think they're dead too, don't you?'
'Oh God,' the doctor sighed.
It was on the morning of 22 September that Captain
Antonio Corelli, knowing that his leaders were
planning to surrender to the Germans, having had
no sleep for three days, climbed on his motorcycle
and sped towards Pelagia's house. He threw
himself into her arms, resting his burning
eyes upon her shoulder, and told her, 'We
are lost. The British have betrayed us.'
She begged him to stay, to hide in
the house, in the hole in the floor,
with his mandolin and Carlo's papers,
but he took her face in his hands,
kissed her without the tears that he was too
tired to weep, and then rocked her in his arms,
squeezing her so tightly that she
thought that her bones would crack.
He kissed her again and said, 'Koritsimou,
this is the last time I shall ever see you.
There has been no honour in this
war, but I have to be with my boys.'
With his head hanging down,
he told her, 'Koritsimou,
I am going to die. Remember me to your father. And
I thank God I have lived long enough to love you.'
She watched him go as he drove away on his
motorcycle, the dust cloud surrounding his
head, then she went inside and sat at the
kitchen table, terror gripping her heart.
CHAPTER TEN
The Order to Kill
Gunter Weber stood before his superior officer
and, his face hard with determination, said,
'Sir, I must request that you give this task
to someone else. I cannot carry it out.'
His superior raised an eyebrow but
somehow failed to feel any anger.
The truth was that in this position he
hoped that he would have done the same.
'Why not?' he asked.
'Sir, it is against international
law to murder prisoners of war.
It is also wrong. I must request to be excused.'
'They have betrayed us, their allies.'
'I realize that, but I am not a criminal,
sir, and I do not wish to become one.'
The officer sighed. 'War is a dirty business, you
know that. We all have to do terrible things. For
example, I like you and I admire you for taking
this position, but I must remind you that the
punishment for refusing to obey an order is
death. I don't state this as a threat but as
a fact of life. You know this as well as I do.' He
walked to the window and then turned. 'They're all
going to be shot anyway. Why add your death to
theirs? It would be a waste of a fine officer.'
Gunter Weber swallowed hard and his
lips trembled so that he found it hard
to speak. At last he said, 'I request that my
protest is recorded and put in my file, sir.'
'Your request is granted,' said
the officer and left the room.
Weber leaned against the wall and lit a cigarette,
but his hands shook so much
that he immediately dropped it.
'Let's sing, boys,' said Antonio Corelli, looking
round the inside of the truck where his men sat,
watched by expressionless German soldiers.
One of the Italians was already tearful,
others were praying, their
heads bowed down to their knees.
Corelli felt strangely happy as if he were
drunk with tiredness and the absolute certainty
of death. Why not smile in the face of death?
'Let's sing, boys,' he repeated, 'Carlo, sing.'
Carlo gazed at him with eyes full of endless
sorrow, and began very softly to sing a song
from an opera they all loved, Madame Butterfly,
and soon others joined in, when they felt able to.
The tune comforted them, and it was
easier to sing than to think on death;
it gave the heart something to do.
When the truck arrived, Gunter Weber's knees
began to shake. Almost before it had arrived,
it seemed that he had known that life had
called him to the killing of his friends.
He had not expected them to arrive singing the
tune that he and La Scala had sung together
late at night at the doctor's house, nor had he
expected them to jump so lightly from the truck.
He ordered a German soldier to put his friends
against the wall, lit another cigarette and turned
away, but finally he turned again and approached
the Italians. More than half of them were praying,
kneeling in the soil, and others wept like
children at a death. Antonio Corelli and
Carlo Guercio were embracing. Weber reached for
his packet of cigarettes and approached them.
'Cigarette?' he asked them, and Corelli took one,
Carlo refusing. Corelli looked at Weber and said,
'Your hands are trembling and your legs.'
'Antonio, I am very sorry, I tried...'
Corelli sucked on his cigarette and said, 'I
am sure you did, Gunter, I know how it goes.'
Weber's face trembled with the
effort of hiding his tears,
and at last he said suddenly, 'Forgive me.'
Carlo made a sound of disgust in his throat
and said, 'You will never be forgiven.'
But Corelli put his hand up to
silence his friend and said quietly,
'Gunter, I forgive you. If I do not, who will?'
Weber held out his hand. 'Goodbye, Gunter,'
said Corelli, taking it. Allowing his hand
to remain in his former friend's, he shook
it briefly one final time and released it.
He linked an arm through
Carlo's, and smiled up at him.
'Come,' he said, 'we two have been companions
in life. Let's go together to heaven.'
It was a beautiful day to die. A few soft clouds
hid the top of Mount Aenos and nearby a goatbell
rang. Corelli realized that his own legs were
shaking and that he could do nothing to prevent
it. He thought about Pelagia, with her dark
eyes, her passionate nature, her black hair.
He saw her clearly in his mind's eye: making
a blanket that grew smaller every day;
arm in arm with her father, returning from the
sea; kissing Gunter Weber on the cheek at the
offer of the record player. Pelagia, whose form
had been so sweetly rounded, now so pale and thin.
A Croatian soldier approached Weber, a man who, in
Weber's opinion, had a dangerously violent nature.
The Croatian said, 'Sir, more
will be arriving. We can't delay.'
'Very well,' said Weber. He
closed his eyes and prayed,
a prayer without words to a God who did not care.
There was nothing formal about the killings, and
the victims were not lined up against the wall
or made to face forwards. Many of them were
left on their knees, praying or weeping or
begging for mercy. Some stood smoking as if at a
party, and Carlo stood next to Corelli, glad to
die at last and determined to die a soldier's
death. Corelli put one hand in his pocket to
steady the shaking of his leg, and deeply breathed
the Cephallonian air that held Pelagia's breath.
The German boys heard the command
to fire and fired in disbelief.
Those of them whose eyes were open aimed
wide or high, or aimed to avoid a death.
The Croatian soldier shot to kill,
firing rapidly and taking careful aim.
Weber's head spun. His former friends were
leaping and dancing in the rain of bullets,
were crying out, stumbling to their knees, arms
waving, their mouths filled with blood. But
what no one had seen, even Weber, was that at the
order to fire, Carlo had stepped quickly sideways
in front of Corelli, and had gripped the latter's
wrists so tightly that he was unable to move.
Corelli stared wonderingly
into the middle of Carlo's back
as great holes burst though from inside the
latter's body, releasing fountains of blood.
Carlo stood unbroken as one bullet after another
entered his chest like white-hot knives. He stood
perfectly still and counted to thirty, looked up
at the sky and then threw himself over backwards.
Corelli lay beneath him, unable to move,
so astonished by this extraordinary,
saintly act of love that he did not
hear the Croatian soldier's voice.
'Italians, it's all over. If any of you are
living, stand up now and you will go free.'
He did not see the two or three
stand up and see them fall again
as the Croatian shot them down. Then
he heard the single shots as Weber,
drunk with horror, wandered among the dead,
putting those still living out of their pain.
Next to his head he saw Weber's boot and he
saw Weber bend down and look directly into his
eyes where he lay trapped beneath Carlo's great
weight. He saw the shaking gun approach his face,
he saw the ocean of sorrow in Webers eyes,
and then he saw the gun withdrawn, unfired.
He tried to breathe more freely, and realized
he was having difficulty, not only because of
Carlo's weight but because the bullets that had
passed through his friend had also struck himself.
***
Corelli lay beneath his friend for hours, their
blood mixing in the soil, in their uniforms,
in their flesh. It was not until evening that
Velisarios came across the heap of tragic bodies,
and recognized the man as big as himself who had
once reached a hand across the barrier of war
and offered him a cigarette. He looked down into
the vacant and staring eyes, reached down and
tried to close them. He failed, and was struck by
the horror of leaving such a brother to the wind
and birds. He knelt down and with a huge effort he
lifted Carlo from the ground, and, as he did so,
he saw the mad captain who was staying at the
doctor's, the one whose 'secret' love for Pelagia
was known and discussed by everyone on the island.
The man's eyes were not vacant and they blinked.
The lips moved. 'Doctor,'
said the dying man. 'Pelagia.'
The strong man put Carlo against the wall.
Then he carefully picked the captain up,
felt how light he was, and set off
across the stony fields to save his life.
Nobody knows the exact number of the Italian
dead that lay upon the earth of Cephallonia,
but at least four thousand were murdered, possibly
nine thousand. The evidence was lost in flame,
because the Germans, displaying knowledge
of their guilt, burnt the bodies, cutting
down trees that were a thousand years old to
make the fires. They changed flesh into smoke,
they put one dead boy after another across
their shoulders and tipped them into the flames,
working until their legs weakened and
the flames became too hot to approach.
One of the bodies that they burned
was the body of General Gandin,
who trusted his enemies and tried to save his men.
Another who died at this time was Father Arsenios,
the priest from Pelagia's village. He wandered
among the bodies and the flames until he was
so mad with grief that he began to beat the heads
and shoulders of the German soldiers with a stick.
At first the soldiers, who had murdered thousands,
did not know what to do, but then an officer came
up behind Arsenios and fired a single shot into
the back of his neck, exploding his brains.
Men and women and the few Italian soldiers who
had escaped approached the fires as closely as the
heat permitted and began to pull away the bodies
at the edge of the fires. All of them thought the
same things: 'Is this what it will be like under
the Germans? How many of these boys could there
have been? How many of these boys did I know? Can
I imagine how it is to die of bleeding, slowly?'
At dawn a thick, black cloud hung
over the land and blocked out the sun,
and the people returned to their
houses and locked their doors.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
An Operation
When the door was suddenly kicked open just as
it was getting dark, Pelagia's first thought
was that it was the Germans, since she
knew that all the Italians were dead.
Like everybody else she had heard the sounds
of battle and seen truck after truck pass by,
bearing either cheering German soldiers
or the dead bodies of Italians. At night
she had gone out with her father, whose cheeks
were trembling with tears of anger and pity,
and looked for lives to save among
those bodies abandoned in the fires.
It had left her speechless, not with
fear or sorrow, but with emptiness.
When the door flew open she was
frightened, but she had nevertheless,
somehow been expecting it. Her
gun was ready in her pocket.
She stood up, her hand tightening around the
gun, her face colourless, and saw Velisarios,
breathing hard. He advanced to the table
and gently placed his burden on it.
'Who is it?' asked Pelagia.
'He's alive,' said Velisarios.
'It's the mad captain.'
She bent down to look with eyes full of both
horror and hope, but she did not recognize him;
there were too many holes, too much blood.
She wanted to touch him but withdrew her hand.
Where does one touch a man like this?
The body opened its eyes and the
mouth smiled. 'Kalimera, koritsimou,'
it said, and she recognized the voice.
'It's the evening,' she said foolishly.
'Kalispera, then,' he
whispered and closed his eyes.
Pelagia looked up at Velisarios, her
eyes wide and desperate, and said,
'Velisarios, you have never done a greater thing.
I'm going to get my father. Stay with him.'
She found her father at the
kapheneion and dragged him out,
ignoring the angry stares of the other
men, and Kokolios, who roared at her.
The doctor looked at the body and knew
he had never seen anything worse. There
was enough blood to fill the veins of a horse.
'It would be kinder to kill him,' he said, but
before Velisarios could say, 'I thought so too,'
Pelagia began beating her father with both hands.
And so water was put on to boil and the rags
of the captain's uniform were gently cut away.
Dr Iannis complained as he cleaned away the blood.
'What am I supposed to do? I have no
equipment to perform an operation.'
'Shut up, shut up, shut up,' Pelagia shouted,
her heart racing with both fear and
determination. 'Just shut up and do it.'
Because the doctor was unaware that most of
the blood and flesh had belonged to the broad
back of Carlo Guercio, it seemed unbelievable to
him that Antonio Corelli was as little wounded
as he was. Once he was cleaned, it was clear
that the victim had six bullets in his chest,
one in the stomach, and one through the outer
flesh in his right arm. But the doctor knew
too much to be optimistic and it still seemed
hopeless. Frightened of the task that lay ahead
of him, he opened a bottle of raki, drank
deeply and passed the bottle to Velisarios,
who did the same. Then, with the comforting
taste of alcohol in his mouth, he reached for
an instrument and moved it gently around in
each wound until he felt it reach a bullet.
He stood up amazed, realizing that the holes
were not even deep and that the bullets should
have passed right through the victim's body
but had not done so. 'Daughter,' he said,
'I swear by all the saints that this man's
flesh is made of steel. I think he'll live.'
'Antonio,' he called, and Corelli opened his eyes.
'Antonio, I'm going to operate. I haven't got much
morphia. Can you drink?' Corelli nodded, and
Pelagia poured a cup of raki down his throat
while the doctor injected morphia into his arm.
Pelagia looked at that desperately damaged body,
helpless as a worm, and knew that it
was not exactly a body that one loved,
but that one loved the man who shone out through
the eyes and used his mouth to smile and speak.
The doctor saw her dreaming and
said, 'Don't just sit there.
We need more boiling water. And wash
your hands, especially under the nails.'
Pelagia discovered in that hour how difficult
the task was that she had set her father.
Her hands trembled, and at first she could
hardly force herself to touch the captain.
She looked up and saw her father cutting
wide holes around the bullet wounds
and had to resist her desire to be sick. The
doctor started on the bullet in the stomach,
since he needed to do something that was
relatively easy in order to increase his
confidence. He found it not far beneath the
surface of the skin and picked it out, amazed by
its flattened shape. 'It's unbelievable,' he said,
showing it to Pelagia. 'How do you explain this?'
'He was behind that big man, the one as
big as me,' said Velisarios. 'The big man
was holding him from behind, like this.' He
stood up and put his hands behind his back
to show how one could grip another's wrists. 'I
think he was trying to save the man,' he said.
'Carlo,' said Pelagia,
suddenly bursting into tears.
Carlo was the first of the boys of La Scala
whom they now knew with certainty was dead.
'No man who dies like that has died for
nothing,' said the doctor, fighting back
his own need for tears. Pelagia wiped her
eyes on the sleeve of her dress and said,
'Antonio always said that Carlo
was the bravest in the Army.'
'Velisarios, is the man's body still there?
We would like to bury it and not
see it burned,' said the doctor.
'It's after dark, I'll go and look,' said the
strongman. 'On the way, I might kill a German, who
knows?' He departed, happy to be out of that house
where the sights were enough to make one ill.
When the doctor had finished cleaning out the
wound, he gave Pelagia the task of sewing it up,
and she did so with accuracy and care, despite
her feeling of the unreality of it all.
Velisarios buried Carlo Guercio's remains
that night in the yard of the doctor's house.
Just before dawn, when the operation on the
captain was finished at last, and father and
daughter were both utterly exhausted, they came
out to say their goodbye to that heroic soldier.
Pelagia combed the hair and kissed the forehead,
and Velisarios placed a
cigarette in the dead man's lips.
'I owed him one,' he said. The doctor made a
speech while Pelagia wept beside him. 'Sleep
long and well,' he ended. 'As long as we remember
you, you will be remembered fair and young.'
Leaning upon each other, the doctor
and his daughter returned inside.
Carefully, they carried Corelli to Pelagia's
bed, and outside the first birds sang.
***
It was only a short time before the Germans began
to take an interest in loot. Not only did the
doctor have to hide his valuables, he also had to
hide an Italian officer who lay, unable to move,
in his daughter's bed. Pelagia made a bed for
him at the bottom of the hole in the kitchen,
and once again Velisarios
was called in to carry him.
There Corelli was reunited with his mandolin
and Carlo's papers were temporarily removed.
The lid of the hiding-place was left open
unless troops were in the neighbourhood.
For the first day after the operation the captain
slept, but when he first woke, the pain was so bad
that he could not move at all, and he felt
as if he had been run over by a lorry.
'I can't breathe,' he told the doctor.
'If you couldn't breathe you couldn't speak.' The
captain said nothing and the doctor continued,
'It appears that Carlo saved your life.'
'It doesn't "appear". I know he did.
Of all of us, he died the best.
And he's left me to remember it.'
'You shouldn't weep, Captain. We are going to
get you well, and then get you off the island.'
'When I am better you must
move me from the house, Doctor.
I don't want you in danger. If I
am caught, I should die alone.'
'We can move you to your secret house, where you
used to go with Pelagia. Don't look so surprised.
Everybody knew. And you may
not get better. Remember that.'
'My God, Doctor, please tell me some lies.'
'The truth will make us free. We
overcome fear by looking it in the eyes.'
The captain fell into a fever two days later and
Pelagia remained in the hiding-place with him,
wiping his forehead to reduce his temperature.
The fever came to a crisis on the fourth day,
and Corelli was sweating so much
and talking so nonsensically
that both the doctor and Pelagia feared for
his life. But two days later the fever left,
and the patient opened his eyes with wonder,
as if realizing that he existed for the first
time. He felt weaker than it ought to be
possible to feel, but by the same evening
he was able to stand with the doctor's help and
let himself be washed. Pelagia fetched a mirror
and showed him his new-grown beard, and that
night he was fed his first solid meal. Snails.
***
In later life, Pelagia remembered the
time of Corelli's recovery and his escape
not as a period of exciting adventure, nor even as
a time of fear and hope, but as the slow beginning
of her sorrows. The war had reduced her anyway.
Her skin, stretched tightly over her bones,
was transparent from lack of food, and when she
ate she chewed carefully in case she lost a tooth.
Her rich black hair had thinned and lost
its shine, and showed the first grey hairs
that should not have appeared for at least
another decade. It was hard to obtain food,
and the doctor was reduced to trapping snakes
and other such creatures. Things were not
hopeless, however; there was always the
sea, the source of Cephallonia's being.
As soon as Corelli could walk, he went in
the company of the doctor and Velisarios to
Casa Nostra at night, while Pelagia remained at
home in the hiding-place in which the mandolin,
the doctor's History and Carlo's papers had been
replaced. As long as the German rapists were on
the island, she hardly left the house. Corelli
had given her his ring, too big for any of her
fingers, and she turned it round and round in
the lamplight. The captain came frequently,
after dark, complaining that the hut was cold, his
new beard scratching her cheeks as they lay fully
clothed upon her bed, wrapped in each other's
embrace, talking of the future and the past.
'I will always hate the Germans,' she said.
'Gunter saved my life.'
'He murdered all your friends.'
'He had no choice.
It wouldn't surprise me if he shot himself
afterwards. He was trying not to cry.'
'There is always a choice.'
'He wasn't brave like Carlo. Only one in a million
is made like that, you mustn't blame poor Gunter.'
Pelagia desperately wanted to
keep her captain on the island,
but knew that she would kill him if she did. There
were people who were prepared to betray for bread,
and it could only be a matter of time
before the Germans became aware of his
presence in their lives. She asked Kokolios
and Stamatis to enquire for news of Bunnios,
the English spy, and to tell
him to call on her if he could.
For some time now Bunny Warren had been
encouraging the owners of boats to help the
few surviving Italian soldiers to escape from
the island, and it was easy for him to arrange
the captain's departure. He called at Pelagia's
home one night, tapping softly on her window,
and when she had removed herself from Corelli's
embrace, she looked out and saw the man whose
help she had both sought and feared. He came in
through the door and very formally shook her hand.
'Who is this?' asked Corelli, who for a moment
had been fearing a visit from the Germans.
'Bunnios,' said Pelagia, without answering his
question, 'this is an Italian soldier and we have
to get him out.' By chance a boat was leaving
for Sicily the following morning and it would
be easy to put the captain on board. They simply
had to go to a certain bay at one o'clock in the
morning with a lamp, and flash out to sea in
answer to the signals flashed from the boat.
Corelli did not go back to
Casa Nostra before dawn,
but stayed with Pelagia in the house. The
three of them sat in that familiar kitchen,
saddened and fearful, talking quietly and
shaking their heads over all the memories.
'I owe my life to you, Doctor,' the captain said.
'I am sorry about the scars.
It was the best I could do.'
'And I am sorry, Doctor, about the rape of the
island. I don't suppose we will ever be forgiven.'
'As you know, Captain, I
must have forgiven you, or
I would not have given you
permission to marry my daughter.'
Pelagia and Corelli looked at each other and the
captain said, 'We have decided that if we have
a son, we will name him Iannis.' The doctor
was visibly delighted, even though this was
exactly what he would have expected under the
circumstances. He looked up, his eyes watering,
and said simply, 'Antonio, if I have ever had a
son it was you. You have a place at this table.'
Corelli stood up and the two men
embraced, clapping each other on the back,
and then the doctor embraced his daughter.
'I'll leave you two children together,' he said.
'There is a little girl dying and I should visit.'
The doctor left the house and the
two lovers sat opposite each other,
unable to speak. Finally the tears began to
follow each other slowly down Pelagia's cheeks,
and Corelli knelt beside her, put his arms
around her and laid his head against her chest.
He was shocked again at how thin
she was and closed his eyes tightly,
imagining that it was another world. 'I am so
afraid,' she said. 'I think you won't come back,
and the war goes on and on forever, and there's no
safety and no hope and I'll be left with nothing.'
'I shall not forget you and I
will come back,' replied Corelli.
'Promise?'
'I promise. I have left you my ring and Antonia.'
'We never read Carlo's papers.'
'Too painful. We'll read them when I return.'
She stroked his hair in silence and said finally,
'Antonio, I wish that we had...
lain together. As a man and woman.'
'Everything at the right time, koritsimou.'
'There may not be a time.'
'There will be. You have my promise.'
At eleven o'clock Bunny Warren scratched at
the window. He carried a knife in his belt
and sounded extremely efficient as he
gave detailed instructions to the doctor,
who translated them for Corelli's benefit.
It was a cold December night, there
was no moon, and since most Germans
preferred to be indoors on such a night, the
journey to the beach was relatively safe.
Nevertheless, Pelagia's heart beat fast and a dark
hole seemed to be opening in her heart. Corelli
felt so sad he almost wished that they would
meet some German soldiers so that he could die,
fighting and killing, and end it all. He knew that
to leave the island would be to lose his roots.
For warmth, the four of them stood close together
on the tiny patch of sand, waiting for the flash
of a lamp that would come to them from the
sea. Corelli walked to the waterline and,
seeing the black waves, wondered how
he would ever survive the journey.
He felt his love for the island turning
in his chest like the twist of a knife,
because he had his own village now and
even his thought and speech had changed.
Returning to Pelagia, he held her face
in his hands and then embraced her.
When the light flashed three times from
the sea and Warren returned the signal,
Corelli shook his hand, kissed his father-in-law
on both cheeks and went to Pelagia once more.
There was nothing to be said. He knew
that her mouth was trembling with grief
and his throat was tight with the same emotion.
He stroked her cheek tenderly and kissed her eyes.
He heard the sound of the boat approaching
and looked up to see the shadows of two men
inside it. The four approached the boat and the
doctor said, 'Go well, Antonio, and return.'
'May God hear you,' said the captain,
and for the last time he held Pelagia.
After he had climbed into the boat,
disappearing into the darkness like a ghost,
Pelagia ran into the waves until the sea reached
her thighs, but though she tried to catch sight of
him, she saw nothing. A terrible emptiness seized
her and she put her hands to her face and wept,
bent over in pain, her cries carried off in the
wind and were lost in the sound of the sea.
CHAPTER TWELVE
1943-9: The Years of Terror
Of the German occupation there is little to say,
except that it caused the islanders to feel more
appreciation for the Italians they had lost.
It seldom happens that a people can learn
to feel friendly towards their oppressors,
but hardly since Roman times had there
been any other kind of rule in Cephallonia.
Now there were no more Italians working in the
fields beside the farmers in order to escape the
boredom of army life, there were no more football
matches between teams that quarrelled and cheated,
there were no flirtations with girls by
soldiers who had a cigarette hanging from
the corners of their mouths. There were no
more voices sending out opera tunes across
the pine trees of the mountains. Gone were
the charming chicken-thieves, and in their
place came a period of time that the doctor
recorded in his History as the worst time of all.
The islanders remember that the Germans were
not human beings. They were machines without
principles, machines that only knew how to loot
and kill, without any passion except the love of
strength, and without belief except in their
natural right to destroy an inferior race.
The Italians had of course been thieves, but their
shame when caught showed that they recognized
their guilt. The Germans came into the house
at any time of day, kicked over the furniture,
beat the occupants, however old or young, and
in front of their eyes carried away whatever
they liked. Both Pelagia and her father were
beaten at different times for no apparent
cause. Drosoula had cigarettes burned into her
skin for frowning at an officer. The doctor had
all his precious medical equipment, gathered
together over twenty years of poverty, broken
in his presence by four officers whose hearts
were as dark and empty as the caves of hell.
When in November 1944 the German
troops were ordered to withdraw,
they destroyed every building
for which they found the time,
and the inhabitants of Cephallonia rose up against
them and fought them all the way to the sea.
But the night before he left, Gunter Weber, who
had ashamedly stayed away from the house since the
time of the killings, brought his record player
and his collection of Marlene Dietrich records
and left them outside Pelagia's door,
as he had promised in happier days.
He wrote a note in Italian: 'God be
with you, I will remember you always.'
Pelagia hid the record player in the hole in the
floor, with Antonio's mandolin and Carlo's papers,
and it survived the terrible years that followed.
***
The Germans left and the celebrations began,
but no sooner had the bells begun ringing than
the members of the Communist organization ELAS,
now calling themselves EAM, came out from hiding
and attempted to take control of the country.
They formed Workers' Councils and elected
themselves to every post of authority. In
Cephallonia the Communists began to send
awkward characters to prison camps. On the
mainland they poisoned, with dead animals,
the water of villages that opposed them. Into
mass graves they threw the dead bodies of Greeks
who had had their eyes torn out and their
mouths cut into the shape of a smile.
They kidnapped 30,000 little children and sent
them across the border into Communist Yugoslavia
to be taught how to be true Communists.
ELAS soldiers captured by the British were
so frightened of their leaders that they begged
to be allowed to remain in British prison camps.
Pelagia and the doctor were two out of millions
of people whose lives were forever destroyed
by these butchers. The doctor was dragged away
in the night by three men who had decided that
since he was a doctor he must be a Fascist.
They threw Pelagia into a corner and beat
her unconscious with a chair. When Kokolios
came out from his house to defend the doctor,
he too was carried away, even though he was
a Communist. He was accompanied by Stamatis,
a supporter of the royal family, and the three
men were taken to the harbour for transportation.
Pelagia did not know what
had happened to her father,
and none of the authorities would tell her.
Alone in the house, penniless and helpless,
for the first time in her life she thought
of ending everything by killing herself. The
island seemed to be cursed by an endless series of
oppressors. When would Antonio return? The war was
continuing in Europe, and probably he was dead.
She heard that the Communists had been killing the
Italian soldiers who had come to fight alongside
them against the Greeks. Had the time come,
finally, to hate the Greeks? Of the nations
who had broken into her house to beat her
and steal her possessions, only the
Italians were innocent, it seemed.
Fortunately she had a friend. Drosoula had long
known that Pelagia had lost her love for Mandras,
and that by his long silence he had given up his
rights. She knew also that Pelagia was waiting
for an Italian, but she felt no bitterness and
never uttered a single word of blame. When Pelagia
stumbled bleeding through her door after the
Communists had taken Dr Iannis, Drosoula, who had
also suffered much, stroked her hair and uttered
loving words, as if Pelagia were her own daughter.
Within a week she had closed up her little house
on the harbour and moved into the doctor's house
on the hill. She found his Italian gun in a
drawer and kept it at her side in case of attack.
Like Pelagia, Drosoula had been reduced by
the war. The layers of fat had melted from
her waist and thighs, and her great ugly moon
of a face had sunk inwards. However, her tall,
thin form and grey hairs demanded respect,
and her unbroken spirit gave Pelagia strength.
For comfort they slept together in the doctor's
bed, and by day they made plans to find supplies
of food and listened to each others complaints and
stories. They dug for roots in the undergrowth,
and Drosoula took her young friend
down to the harbour to learn to fish.
But Drosoula was out when Mandras returned, full
of selfimportance and new ideas, expecting the
admiring attention of the young woman he had
not seen for years, and determined to take
revenge. He came in through the door without
knocking and leaned his gun against the wall.
When she heard the noise in the kitchen,
Pelagia, who was in her room, called out,
'Drosoula?' A man came in who she did not
recognize, except that he looked very like
Drosoula had done before the war; there
was the same swollen stomach and thighs,
the same round, coarse face and thickened
lips. Puzzled, Pelagia stood up.
Mandras also was confused. There was something
about this desperately thin, frightened girl
that reminded him of Pelagia, but this woman
had silver threads in her thin black hair, her
blouse and skirt hung straight to the ground, her
cheeks were hollow. He looked quickly around the
room to see whether Pelagia was there, assuming
that this must be a cousin or an aunt. 'Mandras,
is it you?' said the woman,
and he recognized the voice.
He stood, amazed and confused, with
much of his hatred knocked out of him,
while she looked at those coarse and
altered features and felt deep disgust.
'I thought you must be dead,' she said finally.
He closed the door and leaned against it. 'You
mean you were hoping I was dead. As you see,
I am not. I am very much alive and well.
Don't I get a kiss from my fiancee?'
She advanced fearfully and
placed a kiss on his right cheek.
'I am glad you are alive,' she said.
He caught both her wrists and held them tightly.
'I don't think you are. How is your
father, by the way? Is he not here?'
'Let me go,' she said softly, and he did so.
'The Communists took him away' she told him.
'Well, he must have done something to deserve it.'
'He did nothing. He healed the sick. And they
beat me with a chair and took everything.'
'There must be reasons. The party is never
wrong. Whoever is not with us is against us.'
She noticed that he wore the red star
of ELAS sewn into the front of his cap.
'You're one of them,' she said.
He leaned against the door,
placing all his weight against it,
increasing her sense of imprisonment and her fear.
'Not just one of them, an important one of them,'
he stated, sounding pleased with himself, then
added challengingly, 'Soon we will have a nice
big house to live in. When shall we get married?'
She trembled and, seeing
this, his anger increased.
'We will not be married,' she said. 'We were
very young, it was not what we thought it was.'
'Not what we thought? And there was I, fighting
for Greece, thinking of you all day and dreaming
of you at night. And now I come back at last
and find a faded cow who has forgotten me.'
'What's the matter with you?' she asked.
'The matter with me?' He took from
his pocket a thick bundle of papers.
'This is what is the matter with me.' He threw
them towards her feet and she picked them up
slowly. She held the bundle in her hands
and realized that it consisted of her
letters to him in Albania. 'My letters?'
she said, turning them over in her hands.
Mandras gave a sudden roar of disgust and,
seizing the letters, he found the last one,
held it up to the light and read, 'You never
write to me, and at first I was sad and worried.
Now I realize that you cannot care and this
has caused me to lose my love for you also.
I want you to know that I have decided to
release you from your promises. I am sorry,'
He gave a smile that was both humourless
and threatening. 'Yes, I'm able to read now,
and this is what I found in the letters
I had been carrying next to my heart.
And now I know the truth. Do you know the
first thing I heard when I arrived back here?
I heard, "Mandras, did you hear about your old
fiancee? She's going to marry an Italian." So
you've found a Fascist for yourself, have you?
Is this what I've been fighting for, you cow?'
Pelagia stood up, her lips trembling,
and said, 'Mandras, let me out.'
'Let me out,' he repeated, 'let me out.
Poor little thing's frightened, is she?'
He came up to her and struck her across the
face so hard that she spun round before she
fell. He kicked her in the stomach and bent down
to pick her up by the wrists, then he threw her
on the bed and, quite against his original
intentions, began to tear at her clothes.
This rape of women was something that he could
not help, it seemed. It was a feeling that came
from deep inside him, something he had learned
in years of not needing to explain his actions to
anyone. It was his natural right, and the violence
was much more exciting than the sexual act itself.
But Pelagia fought. Her nails broke in his flesh,
she struck him with hands and knees and elbows,
she screamed and struggled. To Mandras her
resistance was unreasonable, he was failing
despite his weight and strength, and he sat back
and hit her repeatedly. Then suddenly he tried to
pull up her skirts. The solid weight of her gun
fell out of its pocket and landed beside her head
on the pillow, but Mandras did not see it, and
when the bullet cracked through his shoulder,
the shock knocked him backwards and he
gazed at Pelagia in shock and accusation.
Drosoula heard the crack of the gunshot
just as she came through the kitchen door
and at first she did not recognize the sound,
but then she knew what it was and took the
Italian gun from the drawer. Without thinking,
knowing that thought would make her a coward,
she pushed open the door of Pelagia's
room and saw there the unthinkable.
She had thought that Pelagia might have
shot herself, that there might be thieves,
but when she burst in, she saw the doctor's
daughter leaning up on her elbow, her face
swollen and bloody, her lips split, her clothes
torn. Drosoula followed Pelagia's gaze and saw,
leaning against the wall behind the door, a man
who might have been her son. She ran to Pelagia's
side and took her into her arms, rocking her, and
heard the words, 'He... tried ... to... rape me.'
Drosoula stood up, and mother and son examined
each other in disbelief. So much had changed.
As the anger grew in the woman, the fire in
Mandras died. A wave of self-pity overcame him
and all he wanted to do was weep; everything
had come to nothing, everything was lost.
The horror of the war in Albania, the years in the
forest, his new power and importance, it was all
a dream, and he was a frightened little boy
again, trembling before the anger of his mother.
And his shoulder hurt so much.
He wanted to show it to her, to win her
attention. He wanted her to touch and heal it.
But she pointed the gun at him and spat the one
word that seemed to mean the most, 'Fascist'.
'Mother...' he said in a voice
that was low and frightened.
'How dare you call me "mother"? I
am no mother and you are not my son.
I have a daughter...' she pointed to Pelagia, who
had curled into a ball, '... and this is what you
do. I do not know you, never in my life do I want
to see you again, I have forgotten you, my curse
goes with you. May you never know peace, may your
heart burst in your chest, may you die alone,'
She spat on the ground and shook her head with
disgust. 'Pig rapist, get out before I kill you.'
Mandras left his gun leaning against the wall
of the kitchen, and with bright red blood on
his right hand where he still held his wound,
he stumbled out into the cold December sun.
He looked through tearful eyes at the
tree where once he had swung and laughed,
and where, he seemed to remember, there
had once been a goat. It was a tree that
was incomplete without Pelagia as she was,
fresh and beautiful, slicing onions beneath it
and smiling through the tears. A wave of grief
overcame him and his throat tightened with sorrow.
It did not occur to him that he was just
one more life twisted and ruined by the war.
He was aware only that heaven had disappeared,
that hope had turned to dust, that joy,
which had once shone brighter than the summer
sun, had disappeared into the black light
and cold heat of mass murder. He had struggled
for a better world and instead had destroyed it.
There was once a place where all had shone with
delight and innocence. He stood still for a
moment, recalling where it was; then he went down
to the sea, stood on the waterline, and kicked off
his boots. With his right hand he slowly removed
his clothes till he stood with nothing on.
He realized he wanted only to feel the sea and
sand upon his skin. He needed to be washed.
He remembered days in his boat with nothing to do
except fish; he remembered his joy when something
fine was landed for Pelagia, his pleasure at her
pleasure when he gave it to her. He remembered
that in those days he was beautiful. He began
walking into the sea that would take his life,
and by drowning him make him clean,
make him pure and innocent once more.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Antonia
There had been so many rapes that Pelagia and
Drosoula were not surprised to find an abandoned
bundle on their doorstep. It had been born at
a time when its father could have been a German
or a Communist, and the mother might have
been any unfortunate girl at all. Whoever this
sorrowing and dishonoured girl had been,
she had cared enough about her child
to leave it upon the doorstep of a
doctors house, knowing that those inside
would be able to cope. The disorder of the
times was so great that the two women could
think of no solution except to try and care
for it themselves, thinking that in time
the child could be adopted by someone childless
or handed to a charitable organization.
They had taken the child inside and unwrapped
it and discovered that it was a girl. She was
very calm and cried only a little. She sucked the
thumb of her right hand (a habit she never lost,
even in old age), and she smiled a lot, her
legs and arms waving up and down in delight.
The two women, who had suffered so greatly from
loss and unhappiness, found that the child,
whom they named Antonia, gave new meaning to their
lives. Because of her, the women's tragic memories
began to fade, and she took her place in their
lives as if she had always been meant to be there.
In all her life, Antonia never asked
a question about her father, and only
when she applied for a passport to go abroad did
she discover that she did not officially exist.
She did have a grandfather, however. When Dr
Iannis returned after two years, stumbling
into the kitchen supported by two charity workers,
utterly broken by his treatment in the prison camp
and forever speechless, he bent down and
kissed the child before retiring to his room.
Just as Antonia did not enquire about a father,
Dr Iannis did not enquire about the child. It
was enough for him to know that the world had gone
down a path that he had no hope of understanding.
He accepted that his daughter and
Drosoula would sleep in his bed,
and that he would take Pelagia's, because,
whichever bed it was, he would dream the
same dreams of a forced march of hundreds of
kilometres without his boots, without food
or water. He would hear the cries of villagers
as their houses burned, the crack of gunshots
as they were murdered, and he would witness,
over and over again, Stamatis and Kokolios dying
in each other's arms and begging him to leave
them in the road in case he himself was shot.
In his wordlessness, Dr Iannis drew the same
comfort from Antonia that he had drawn from
his daughter after his own young wife had
died. He would put the child upon his knee,
arranging her black hair, gazing into her brown
eyes as if this alone was the way to speak,
her smile filling his heart with sorrow, because
when she was old she would lose her innocence,
and learn that tragedy destroys the muscles
of the face until a smile becomes impossible.
In 1949 the national government succeeded at
last in defeating the Communists, who lost their
control of the country. Dr Iannis took up medicine
again, helping his daughter in a reversal of their
roles. It upset Pelagia to see the shaking of
his hands as he dealt with patients' wounds,
and she knew also that he worked despite a
terrible sense of uselessness. Why preserve
life when all of us must die, when health is only
an accident of youth? She wondered sometimes at
the strength of his desire to heal, despite all he
had suffered. In the evening she wrapped her arms
around him and held him as his mind wandered back
over the past, his eyes wet with sadness, and she
buried her head on his chest, understanding that
by comforting him she was comforting herself too.
She attempted to interest him in working on his
History, and when she took the papers from the
hiding-hole and arranged them in front of him
at his table, he seemed willing enough to work.
He read through them, but at the
end of a week Pelagia found he had
added only one short paragraph in a shaky
handwriting that did not look like his old,
firm handwriting at all. Then she saw that
across the bottom of the last page her father
had written, 'In the past the horrors came from
outside. Now we have only ourselves to blame.'
While she had been in the hiding-hole,
Pelagia had rediscovered Antonio's mandolin
and Carlo's papers. She read through the latter
in a single evening and was astonished; she had
never imagined that that powerful, good-natured
man had suffered so greatly from a secret sadness
that had made him a stranger to himself. She saw
that he had been as determined to lose his life
as he had been to save Corelli's and she realized
that if her own adopted child was at risk,
she would find the same
extraordinary courage in herself.
Antonia grew tall and lovely, a child whose
movements were filled with confidence and grace.
She was incapable of behaving like a 'lady',
and when she sat in her grandfather's armchair
she not only sucked her thumb but also
hung one leg over the arm of the chair,
ignoring her mother's and Drosoula's protests with
laughing cries of, 'Don't be so old-fashioned.'
The family were regarded as eccentric. The
empty-headed gossips of the village regarded
Drosoula, with her extreme ugliness, and Pelagia,
with her assumption that she was any man's equal,
as a pair of crazy women. Children
threw stones at them as they passed,
and adults warned their children to keep away and
encouraged their dogs to bite them. Nevertheless,
Pelagia earned a living, because after darkness
people would arrive secretly in the belief
that her treatments were sure to work.
During all this time Pelagia became certain that
Antonio Corelli was dead and, like her father,
she also became certain beyond
doubt of the reality of ghosts.
It had happened first in 1946 when, one day in
October, she was standing outside the house with
the infant Antonia in her arms. She was making
baby noises and giving the baby her finger to
suck, when something made her look up. She saw
a figure dressed in black, standing before her
in exactly the same place that Mandras had been
when he had been shot by Velisarios' cannon. The
figure was looking at her, as if it wanted to take
a step towards her, and her heart leapt. There was
an atmosphere around him of nine thousand weeping
ghosts, and sorrow seemed to pour from his face.
Thin and bearded though he was, she was
sure it was him. Excited beyond all joy,
she put the baby down in order to run to
him, but when she looked up he had gone.
Her heart jumping in her chest, she ran. Around
the bend she stopped and looked wildly around,
crying out, 'Antonio! Antonio!' But no voice
responded and no man came towards her. He had
disappeared. Her hands rose to the sky in
confusion and fell down again to her sides.
She stood watching and calling until her shouts
hurt her throat and tears blinded her eyes.
The same ghost appeared at the same place in
1947 and every year after that at roughly the
same time, but never exactly. It was because
of this that Pelagia came to the conclusion
that Antonio had kept his promise to return and
that it was possible to keep such a promise and
continue to love even from beyond the grave. She
was able to live satisfied, knowing that she had
not been abandoned, and, filled with happy dreams
of being desired and loved, she looked forward to
her own death when she would once again have
all that had been stolen away in life.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
1953: Earthquake
The thirteenth of August, 1953 was a fine
day, with small white clouds scattered
here and there most charmingly in the deep blue
sky. That morning Antonia, now eight years old
but as tall as a child of twelve, went to pick
up a sheet of paper from the floor, and when the
sheet flew upwards and stuck to her hand, she
cried, 'It's magic,' and ran excitedly outside.
Strange things were happening
all over the Ionian islands.
There were no birds in the sky; on
the hillsides and in the undergrowth,
snakes and rats left their holes, and in
the villages all the dogs began barking.
Drosoula came inside sweating and shaking and told
Pelagia, 'I am ill, I feel terrible, something has
happened to my heart.' She sat down heavily with
her hand to her chest, taking deep breaths, and
Pelagia went to her medicine cupboard and made a
drink for her. Antonia, who had come back inside,
suddenly burst into tears, exclaimed, 'Mama,
I've got to get out,' and ran outdoors.
Drosoula and Pelagia were exchanging surprised
glances when suddenly there came a low, terrible
roar from the earth that made the two women feel
as if their hearts were exploding in their chests.
'A heart attack,' thought Pelagia
desperately, and she saw Drosoula,
with her hands on her stomach and her eyes
staring, stumble as if someone had struck her.
It seemed that time had stopped and
the indescribable roaring of the earth
would never end. Dr Iannis rushed out of the room
that used to be Pelagia's and spoke for the first
time in years. 'Get out! Get out!' he cried.
'It's an earthquake! Save yourselves!' His voice
sounded small and far away, and immediately
afterwards he was thrown violently sideways.
More frightened than they had ever been in their
lives, the two women stumbled towards the door,
were thrown down and attempted to crawl. But
again and again they were thrown upwards and
sideways and, unable to crawl on their hands
and knees, they spread their hands and legs
and moved towards the door like snakes,
reaching it just as the roof began to fall in.
Outside in the yard dust was slowly
rising as the earth went up and down,
while in the centre of the street a stream of
water suddenly rose to a height of twelve metres
and then disappeared as if it had never been.
Houses suddenly leapt upwards and solid stone
walls moved like paper in the wind, and then
suddenly there was a stillness like that of death.
Pelagia, spitting and covered in dirt, filled with
a sense of utter helplessness, began to struggle
to her knees. Suddenly the strange silence
was broken by the wild cries of the priest,
who rushed from the church with his arms
raised to heaven. 'You pig!' he roared. 'You
evil dog!' He fell to his knees and, with tears
in his eyes, struck at the earth with his fists.
At this point, as if in response to his cries,
the terrible roaring began again and once more
the Cephallonian earth danced, the peaks
of the mountains rocking like boats.
During those intervals when the motion stopped,
Pelagia, Drosoula and Antonia held tightly on to
each other, gazing in horror at the old
house, of which there was little left.
The walls were reduced to half their height
and the roof lay in ruins on the floor.
This ruin contained the sad soul and tired
old body of the doctor, who had planned his
last words for years and now died beneath
the stones without the chance to say them.
***
The British were the first to arrive, sending
four large ships carrying water, food, medicines,
doctors and rescue equipment. Italy, remembering
its shameful past, sent ships loaded with rescue
workers, and American ships arrived carrying
earthmovers, helicopters and 3,000 sailors.
The Greek Navy turned up late but eager, and the
King of Greece and his family travelled around the
islands. The earthmovers began the slow work
of clearing the ruined houses, and foreign
aid workers built cities of tents as temporary
accommodation for the islanders. Aeroplanes and
helicopters dropped food to hillside communities
whose roads had been cut off by the earthquake.
In Cephallonia, because of the
wide streets and the fact that
most buildings were only one storey high,
few people actually died in the earthquake.
There were the usual stories concerning people
who had lost their sense of time and appeared
from beneath the ruins of houses after nine
days, believing it had been a few hours.
The islanders reacted differently, according to
whether or not they found a natural leader among
themselves. Where none appeared, people became sad
and purposeless and had terrible dreams of falling
into endless space. During the earthquake
itself perhaps a quarter of the islanders,
like the doctor, had remained calm, but
afterwards the remaining three-quarters
suffered terrible shame remembering the way they
had abandoned their children and elderly parents.
Although he had always been
considered a slow-thinking man,
Velisarios, who was now forty-two years old and
stronger than he had ever been, took command
in Pelagia's village. With a strength that seemed
greater than that of the earthquake itself,
he threw off the beams and stones that
imprisoned the crushed body of the doctor,
because he was aware that decay was
followed by disease. Then he gathered
together the confused and hopeless villagers
and ordered them into small working parties.
For months after the earthquake, there were
times when the earth would shake and tremble,
not violently as it had done in the earthquake
itself, but enough to make people scream in fear.
It was Velisarios who told people to get back
to work, threatening them with broken bones
unless they returned to their tasks. Even
Pelagia, who was almost crazy with grief,
was given the work of caring for
people's wounds, while Drosoula,
who at first could only cry, was put in charge
of the children so that their parents could work.
When the aid workers finally arrived at the
village, they found a small community living
in tents made of sheets of iron, with toilets
dug at a safe distance from the water supply.
An enormous man was in charge, who in old age
would be more loved and respected
than the teacher or the priest.
For three months the earth moved, as if it was
breathing. Then, at last, it became quiet and
motionless once again, and reconstruction
began, to be completed three years later.
Ancient and beautiful Italian towns
were rebuilt as plain white boxes.
Pelagias village was put up further down
the hill and her old house was abandoned,
the contents of the hiding-hole in the
kitchen buried, it seemed, forever.
The earthquake changed lives so greatly that,
even today, it is still the most important
topic of conversation in Cephallonia.
Islanders cannot resist informing strangers of
the facts, and tourist guides will mention the
earthquake when it seemed they were
only going to discuss the weather.
Old people remember an event
according to whether it was before
or after the earthquake. The disaster
caused people to recall the war as
unimportant by comparison, and they woke up
each morning amazed and grateful to be alive.
In the new house that Pelagia,
Drosoula and Antonia now lived in,
Pelagia's guilt was the central
issue in the three women's lives;
the thought that she had played a part in her
father's death made Pelagia suffer horribly.
'He was seventy,' said Drosoula sensibly.
'It was better to die quickly
like that, trying to save us.'
But Pelagia could not accept this. She
knew that in the moment of disaster,
her mind had been spinning with nothing
except the need to save herself, and she
knew that when her father had fallen she should
have tried, even at the risk of her own life,
to drag him through the door before the roof fell
in. She fell into a bottomless pit of self-blame,
took no interest in her appearance and
did not perform her household tasks,
preferring to sit by the doctor's grave,
chewing her lips until they bled. With her
untidy greying hair and her pale face, she simply
sat and watched, as if expecting his ghost to rise
up through the earth and speak to her. Time after
time, in the winter storms and rams, Drosoula
and Antonia would go to the grave and drag
Pelagia away, while she sighed and wept.
One day Antonia and Drosoula could stand no
more; they began to feel impatient and angry,
and the old woman and the young girl discussed
how they could cure Pelagia of her sorrow.
'Why don't we just tie her to the
bed and hit her?' suggested Antonia.
Drosoula sighed with pleasure at the thought
and for a moment wondered whether or not
it would work. Then her eyes brightened
and she kissed the young girl on the top of
her forehead. 'I've had an idea,' she said.
At breakfast the next morning,
Antonia suddenly announced,
'I had a dream about Granddad last night.'
'That's funny,' said Drosoula, 'so did I.'
They looked at Pelagia for some kind of reaction,
but she simply continued to tear
a piece of bread into tiny pieces.
'He told me he was glad he
was dead,' said Antonia,
'because now he can be with Mama's mother.'
'That's not what he told me,'
replied Drosoula, and Pelagia asked,
'Why are you talking as if I'm not here?'
'Because you're not,' replied Drosoula truthfully.
'You haven't been here for a long time.'
'What did he tell you then?' enquired Antonia.
'He told me that he wants Mama to write the
History of Cephallonia that got buried in
the earthquake. He said it spoils the fun
of being dead, knowing that it's got lost.'
Pelagia regarded them suspiciously
and Antonia asked her innocently,
'So are you going to write it?'
'There's no point in asking her,' said
Drosoula. 'She's on another planet.'
'That's not true,' protested Pelagia.
'Welcome back,' said Drosoula rudely.
Pelagia went back to her father's grave
and thought about what Drosoula had said;
although she knew that the story of the
dream was nonsense, it occurred to her
that rewriting the History would indeed be
a way to keep her father's spirit alive.
She travelled into Argostoli and returned
with pens and a thick pad of paper.
It was surprisingly easy. Although the
History had been destroyed in the earthquake,
she had read it so many times that the old
phrases rolled through the kitchen door
and flowed down her arm and
right hand into her pen:
'The ancient, half-forgotten island of
Cephallonia rises from the Ionian Sea...'
Drosoula and Antonia spied on
her as she sat at her table,
tapping her teeth with her pen. They crept away to
a safe distance, embraced each other and danced.
Pelagia almost became the doctor. She did hardly
any housework, leaving it all to the women.
Her father's pipe had been found in the ruins
of the old house, and she stuck it between her
teeth as he had done, but did not light it. She
began to add small details to the text that she
remembered so well, supplying information
about such matters as clothes and baking,
and the cruel but traditional treatment of widows.
The joy of the work caused a deep change in her.
She sent letters of enquiry to universities
and discovered that all over the world there
were people who loved knowledge so much that they
would spend months making enquiries on her behalf.
Finally, at the end of 1961, she put
her completed work into an enormous file
and wondered what to do next.
She learnt from publishers
that such a book would have no market and was
advised instead to give it to a university.
'I will when I'm dead,' thought Pelagia, and she
left it proudly on her shelf as visible evidence
of the fact that she was an intellectual
in the tradition of the Ancient Greeks.
By this time Antonia was a fresh and beautiful
seventeen-year-old, who opposed her adopted
mother's ideas as a matter of principle, and the
two would sit up late into the night discussing
philosophy. 'When you're my age, you'll look
back and see I was right,' Pelagia would say.
Antonia had no intention of reaching
Pelagia's age and said so. 'I want
to die before I'm twenty-five,' she
said. 'I don't want to get old. You
old people caused all the problems and
it's us young ones who have to solve them.'
'Enjoy your dreams,' commented Pelagia.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Alexi
It was about this time that mysterious postcards
in rather poor Greek began to arrive from all
over the world. From Santa Fe came one that said,
'You would like it here. All the houses are made
of mud.' From London: 'Mad people: terrible
fog.' From Madrid: 'Too hot. Everyone asleep.'
Although Pelagia's first thought was that
her father's ghost was visiting his favourite
countries and was sending her communications
from beyond the grave, her second thought was
that they might be from Antonio. But he too was
dead. Perhaps, she thought, these unsigned cards
were from someone with whom she had exchanged
letters during the writing of the History. Puzzled
but pleased, she tied her collections
of cards together and put them in a box.
'You've got a secret boyfriend,' suggested
Antonia, who was pleased to discuss the
matter since it drew attention away from
her own romantic affairs, which both Pelagia
and Drosoula were attempting to discourage.
They had met while Antonia was earning a little
money by serving coffee in a cafe on the plaza
of Argostoli. There had been a noisy band playing
in the square, and the gentleman who had had to
rise and shout his order in the young girl's
ear had at the same moment realized what a
deliciously attractive ear it was. Antonia
had also realized that here was a man whose
eyes expressed exactly the correct mixture of
strength and gentleness, calmness and humour.
Alexi waited at the cafe day after day, choosing
the same table whenever he could, his heart
bursting with his desire to see the tall young
woman with her perfect teeth and long fingers.
She brought him his coffee eagerly,
forbidding the other girls,
the waiters, and even the owner himself
to serve him. One day he took her hand
while she was putting down a cup, looked
passionately up at her and said, 'Marry me.'
Alexi was a lawyer whose skilful speeches could
make a judge weep, but while Pelagia recognized
his excellence in this area, she could not stand
the thought of him marrying Antonia. She was very
tall, he was short. She was only seventeen, and
he was thirty-two. She was tall and graceful,
he was overweight and had a habit of tripping
over things. Pelagia remembered her passion for
Mandras at the same age and forbade the marriage,
certain that this was the right thing to do.
The wedding day was nevertheless
delightful. Antonia, beaming with happiness,
kissed even the strangers who had come to
stare, and Alexi, sweating with alcohol and joy,
made a long and extremely poetic speech, much of
it very wisely in praise of his mother-in-law.
She would always remember the exact moment during
the celebrations when she had seen what it was
about him that had awakened Antonia's heart. It
was when he put his arm around her, kissed her
on the cheek and said, 'We are going to buy a
house in your village, with your permission.'
The humble tone of his voice and his implied
doubt that she might not want him near her
was enough to cause her to
become extremely fond of him.
While Pelagia waited impatiently for a grandchild,
Drosoula became deeply involved in work.
In the empty space by the harbour
that had once been her own house,
she put up a wooden roof and some romantic lamps.
She borrowed some ancient tables and chairs,
bought a cheap oven and
grandly started the taverna
that she would run eccentrically but with great
success until the day of her death in 1972.
It was the 1960s, and tourists were just
beginning to arrive in Cephallonia. Wealthy
boat owners passed on information to their
friends about the most unusual places to eat.
German soldiers who had turned into gentle
citizens with vast families brought their sons
and daughters and told them, 'This is where
Daddy was in the war. Isn't it beautiful?'
Italians arrived by ferry, bringing their pretty
white dogs. Consequently, as the owner of the only
taverna in the little port, Drosoula earned enough
in the summer to do nothing at all in the winter.
Lemoni, who was now married, immensely
fat and the mother of three children,
helped with the serving, and Pelagia came down,
taking the opportunity to practise her Italian.
The service was not fast; to tell the truth,
it was extremely slow. The guests were treated
unapologetically as members of Drosoula's patient
family, and quite often there was no service at
all if Drosoula happened to like a particular
customer with whom she was deep in conversation.
The foreigners, who loved and feared her, never
complained about her forgetfulness and her
indefinite delays, and would say, 'She's so nice,
poor old thing, it seems a shame to hurry her.'
Meanwhile, year after year, Pelagia
waited for a grandchild that never came.
'It's my body,' declared Antonia, 'and I have the
right to choose. Anyway, the world's population
is already too large. Alexi agrees with me,
so don't think you can go and shout at him.'
'I'm getting old,' Pelagia
would say, 'that's all.'
Time passed. It was Drosoula who died first,
perfectly upright in her rocking chair,
so quietly that it seemed she was
apologizing for having lived at all.
She was a courageous woman who had lived
a few short years of happiness with a
husband that she had loved, a woman who had
rejected her son as a matter of principle
and lived the rest of her days in
willing service to her adopted family.
After Drosoula was buried near the doctor,
Pelagia realized that she was now truly
alone. She had no idea any more how to run a
life, and it was with fear and hopelessness in
her heart that she took over Drosoula's
taverna and attempted to make a living.
Alexi, who by his early thirties had lost all his
hair, achieved success as a lawyer, as Pelagia
had known he would, and acquired, among other
things, a big Citroen car. When at last, in 1979,
Antonia gave in to the demands of nature and
became pregnant, she and Alexi started to
hold hands again in public, stared dreamily at
babies and made long lists of possible names.
'It's going to be a girl,' said Pelagia.
'Really, you must call her Drosoula.'
'But Drosoula was so big and...'
'Ugly? It doesn't matter. We loved
her anyway. Her name should live.'
'Oh, I don't know, Mama...'
'I am an old woman,' declared Pelagia,
who gained great satisfaction from repeating
this statement. 'It might be my last wish.'
'You're sixty. These days that isn't old.'
'Well, I feel old.'
'You don't look it.'
'I didn't bring you up to be a liar,' said
Pelagia, terribly pleased, nevertheless.
'I'm thirty-four,' said Antonia. 'That's old.'
When the little boy appeared, Pelagia
began to refer to the child as Iannis,
and she did this so frequently that it soon seemed
obvious to its parents that it could not be called
by any other name. If you called it Iannis,
it smiled and blew bubbles, so Iannis it was.
Alexi, now realizing that a man must pass
something on to his son, began to look around
for good investments. He built a small block
of holiday apartments and installed a modern
kitchen and toilets in the taverna. He persuaded
Pelagia to allow him to hire a proper cook,
leaving her as the manager, and they split
the profits fifty-fifty. On the white walls
Pelagia stuck all the postcards that continued
to arrive from the four corners of the world.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
An Unexpected Lesson
At five years old, Iannis, who spent nearly all
his time at the taverna in his grandmother's care,
already knew how to say 'Hello' and 'Isn't he
sweet?' in six different languages. The reason
for his continual presence at the 'Taverna
Drosoula' was that his father was building
new holiday apartments and tennis courts and his
mother was opening shops that sold cheap souvenirs
all over the island. Their son grew up contentedly
in his grandmother's company, playing in the clear
waters of the port and slowly learning the Italian
that Pelagia insisted on speaking to him. In the
evening, the reunited family would sit together in
the taverna, arguing both in Italian and in Greek,
while Pelagia would embarrass Iannis
with references to his infant years.
When he was ten years old, Pelagia hired a bozouki
player to entertain her guests in the taverna.
His name was Spiridon and he
played his bozouki with such skill
that he could persuade even the Germans to
put their arms around each other's shoulders
and dance in a circle while stamping on the floor.
Iannis loved Spiridon, with his broad shoulders
and his wide mouth that seemed to contain a
hundred flashing teeth. Pelagia also loved
him because he reminded her of her long-lost
captain, and occasionally her heart wished
desperately for a time-machine to take her back
to the days of the only real love of her life.
Iannis did not fail to notice that Spiridon
was popular with women, who at the end of every
performance would seize the red roses from
the vases in the middle of their tables, and
throw them at him. So one day Iannis demanded that
Spiridon should teach him how to play the bozouki.
'Your arms aren't long enough yet,'
said Spiro. 'It would make more sense
to start with a mandolin. It's the same
thing really, but small enough for you.'
'Will you teach me to play it?'
'Of course, but we'll have to find a mandolin.
Otherwise we might have to do just the theory.'
Iannis begged his mother and father to get
him one, and they promised to buy one when
they next went to Athens, but forgot. Eventually
Pelagia told him, 'In fact we have one already,
but it's buried under the old house. I am
sure Antonio wouldn't mind you digging it up.'
'Who's Antonio?'
'My Italian fiance who was killed in
the war. It belonged to him. There
was a big trapdoor in the middle of the
floor and it was in a hole underneath.'
So Iannis dragged Spiridon up the hill and showed
him a ghostly ruin overgrown with long grass,
its broken stones just visible above the growth.
All around it lay the silent and
deserted remains of lonely little houses.
'It's the saddest place,' said Iannis.
'I come here to explore sometimes.' He pointed.
'My grandfather died in there. I'm named after
him. Grandma says he was the best doctor in Greece
and that he could cure people by touching them.'
The two of them went through what had
once been the door and scratched their
heads when they saw the rubbish that lay all
around. Spiro blew out his cheeks and sighed.
'We've got two days work here,' he said.
'We'll just have to get on with it.'
By the next evening there was a clear
space in the middle of the old floor
and the trapdoor lay revealed in the
area that had once been the kitchen.
Spiro tried to get his fingers under the
iron ring of the door but, hard as he tried,
he could not move it. He and the child were
gazing at the ring and scratching their heads
when they became aware of a very big old man in a
black suit, standing a little bent in the doorway.
'What are you doing?' he asked. 'Oh, it's you,
young Iannis. I thought you were looters.'
'We're trying to open this,'
said the boy. 'It's stuck,
and it's got something inside that we want.'
The old man came inside and examined the trapdoor
with his watery eyes before slowly bending down
and putting the tips of the fingers
of one hand under the iron ring.
He leaned sideways, putting all his weight and
strength into lifting the ring and, with a sudden
loud crack, the door flew upwards in a cloud
of dust. Velisarios rubbed his hands together,
blew on the tips of his fingers and seemed
suddenly to become a tired old man again.
'Goodbye, my friends,' he said, and made his
way slowly down the path to the new village.
'Unbelievable,' said Spiro.
Inside the hiding-place, in perfect condition,
they found an antique German record player,
a handmade blanket, a bundle
of papers written in Italian
and another package of papers with the
title, 'A Personal History of Cephallonia'.
There was also a cloth bundle containing the
most beautiful mandolin that Spiro had ever seen.
When Iannis showed Pelagia the
mandolin, she started crying
and, to Iannis's amazement, she did not stop for a
whole week. Iannis comforted her as best he could,
climbing on to her knees, which he was really
a little too old for, and wiping her tears,
wondering how it was possible to love an old
woman with stiff knees and thin grey hair so much.
While Iannis comforted Pelagia, Spiro
carefully cleaned and polished the mandolin.
He tightened and tuned each string and
told Iannis, with great seriousness,
that the mandolin was the most precious thing he
would ever own, so that Iannis learned to regard
the instrument with a respect that he had never
felt in church, when dragged there by Pelagia.
***
In October 1993 Iannis was fourteen, and he had
had a whole summer in which to play in public
with Spiridon and have red roses thrown at him.
In order not to annoy his grandmother with his
constant practising - in fact not to make her cry
again - he had gone up to the ruins of the old
house to play in private, and was concentrating
very hard on a particularly difficult piece of
music. He was biting his lip with the effort,
and did not notice an old man who approached him
and watched him with critical but
delighted interest. Iannis nearly
jumped out of his seat when a voice said, in
a very strange accent, 'Excuse me, young man.'
'Ah!' Iannis exclaimed. 'You frightened me.'
'I couldn't help noticing,' said the man,
'that you are doing something wrong.'
'I know, I'm having trouble with this piece,'
replied Iannis, noticing how unusually bright-eyed
the old man was, and how there was about
him an atmosphere of energy and laughter.
'Let me show you how to place your fingers.' The
old man came over to Iannis and started to pull
the boy's fingers into place, explaining
as he did so why the fingers were better
in this position. Then he stood upright and
added, 'You can always tell a really good
musician because a good musician doesn't
seem to be moving his fingers at all.'
'You seem to know a lot about it,' said Iannis.
'Well, I ought to. I've been a
professional mandolin player for
nearly all my life. I can tell
that you're going to be good.'
'Play me something?' asked the
boy, offering him the mandolin.
The old man took the mandolin, settled it into
this body and began to play in such a way that
Iannis's mouth fell open with amazement. Suddenly
the old man stopped, turned the mandolin over,
examined it with an expression of disbelief
and exclaimed, 'Mother of God, it's Antonia.'
'How did you know it's called Antonia?'
asked Iannis, both surprised and
suspicious. 'Have you seen it before?'
'Where did you find it? Who gave it to you?'
'I dug it out of that hole,' said
Iannis, pointing to the open trapdoor.
'Grandma told me it was there.'
'And would your grandmother be Kyria
Pelagia, daughter of Dr Iannis?'
'That's me. I'm called Iannis, after him.'
The old man sat next to the boy on the wall,
still holding the mandolin, and wiped his
forehead with a handkerchief,
seeming suddenly very anxious.
'Tell me, young man, is your grandmother
alive? Is she happy?' he asked finally.
'She cries sometimes, ever since we dug Antonia
and all the other things out of the hole.'
'And what about your grandfather? Is he well?'
The boy seemed confused.
'What grandfather?' he asked.
'Not your father's father. I
mean Kyria Pelagia's husband,'
said the old man, wiping his forehead again.
'There isn't one. I didn't even know she had one.'
'Are you saying that Kyria Pelagia hasn't got
a husband? You haven't got a grandfather?'
'I suppose I must have,
but I've never heard of him. I've only got
my father's father, and he's half-dead.'
The old man stood up, looked around him and said,
'This was a beautiful place. I had the best years
of my life here. And do you know what? I
was going to marry your grandmother once.
I think it's time I saw her again.'
The two of them were walking down the
hill when Iannis stopped suddenly.
'If you're the one who played the mandolin and was
going to marry Grandma... does that mean you're
the ghost?' The autumnal sun shone briefly through
the cloud, and the old man paused for thought.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
The Return
Antonio Corelli, although in his seventies,
rediscovered a certain youthful energy in his old
limbs as he danced about, trying to avoid being
hit by the frying pans that Pelagia was busily
throwing at him. 'You pig!' she screamed. 'All my
life waiting, all my life thinking you were dead.
And you alive and me a fool. How can
you break such promises? Betrayer!'
Corelli backed against the wall, trying to hold
off the broomstick that Pelagia was waving at him.
'I told you,' he cried. 'I
thought you were married.'
'Married!' she exclaimed bitterly.
'No such luck! Thanks to you,
you rat.' She made a move as if she was going to
hit him across the head with the broom handle.
'I came back for you. 1946. I came
round the bend and there you were with
the little baby, looking so happy.'
'Was I married? Who told you that? So I adopt
a baby that someone leaves on my doorstep...
Couldn't you have said, "Excuse
me, but is this your baby?"'
'Please stop hitting me. I came back
every year, you know I did. You saw me,
I always saw you with the child. I was so
bitter I couldn't speak. But I had to see you.'
'Bitter? I don't believe my ears. You? Bitter?'
'For ten years,' said Corelli, 'for ten years
I was so bitter that I even wanted to kill you.
And then I thought, well, OK, I was away for three
years, perhaps she thought I wasn't coming back,
perhaps she thought I was dead,
perhaps she thought I'd forgotten,
perhaps she met someone else and fell in love.
As long as she's happy. But I still came back,
every year, just to see you were
all right. Is that betrayal?'
'And did you ever see a husband? And did you
think what it did to me when I ran to you
and you disappeared? Did
you think about my heart?'
'OK, so I jumped the wall and hid. I had
to. I thought you were married, I told you.
Pelagia, please, this is a terrible
embarrassment for the customers.
Can't we go for a walk and
talk about it on the beach?'
She looked round at all the
faces, some of them grinning,
some of them pretending to look the other way.
Everywhere there were overturned chairs and tables
that Pelagia had thrown to the floor in her anger.
'You should have died,' she shouted, 'and left me
with my dreams. You never loved me.' She marched
out of the door, leaving Corelli bowing repeatedly
to the customers and saying, 'Please excuse us.'
Two hours later they were sitting on a familiar
rock, gazing out over the sea at the yellow lights
of the harbour reflected in the blackened waters.
'I see you got my postcards, then,' he said.
'In Greek. Why did you learn Greek?'
'I was ashamed of being an invader. I was so
ashamed that I didn't want to be Italian any
more. I've been living in Athens for about
twenty-five years. I'm a Greek citizen.'
'Did you become a composer?'
'Yes, I've played my music all over the world.
I wrote my first big piece of music for you.
It's called "Pelagia's March".' He
noticed that she was trying not to cry,
and thought how emotional she had become in her
old age. She had even knocked out his false teeth,
so that they had fallen in the sand
and had to be washed in the sea.
'I feel like an unfinished poem,'
said Pelagia, with a heavy sigh.
Corelli felt a sting of shame and avoided a reply.
'Everything's changed. Everything
here used to be so pretty
and now the houses look
like boxes made of cement.'
'And we have electricity and telephones
and running water and proper toilets
and earthquake-resistant houses. Is that so bad?'
There was a silence, during which the
thoughts of both of them returned to the past.
'I see you still have my ring,' he said.
'Only because I couldn't get it off,'
she answered. 'I had it altered to fit
and now I regret it.' She hesitated. 'So
did you get married? I suppose you did.'
'Me? No. As I said, I was very bitter for
years and years. I was horrible to everyone,
especially women, and then I became successful
and I was all over the world, flying from one
place to another. And, anyway, who wants to be
with someone who is dreaming of someone else?'
'Antonio Corelli, I can see that you can
still tell lies with your silver tongue.
And how can you bear to look at me now? I'm an
old woman. I feel ashamed to be so old and ugly.
You look the same, just old and thin,
but I look like someone else, I know it.
I want you to remember me
properly. Now I'm just a lump.'
'You forget that I came to spy on you. If you
see things happen gradually, there's no shock.
You're just the same.' He
squeezed her hand gently and said,
'Don't worry, it's still Pelagia. Pelagia
with a bad temper, but still Pelagia.'
'Did you ever think that I might have
been raped and that was why I had a baby?'
'Yes, I did.'
'And...?'
'I admit it made a difference.
We had some ideas about dishonour then,
didn't we? Thank God we're not so stupid now.'
'The man who tried to rape me... I shot him.'
He looked at her in disbelief. 'You shot him?'
'I was never dishonoured. He was
the fiance I had before you.'
'You never said anything about a fiance.'
'Jealous?'
'Of course I'm jealous.' The emotion was
beginning to stir him a little too much
and he tried to control his feelings. Pelagia
decided it was time to change the subject.
'I want to show you something. You
never read Carlo's papers, did you?
Come back to the taverna and eat, and I'll give
you his writing. We do an excellent snails dish.'
'Snails!' he exclaimed. 'I
remember all about snails.'
Corelli sat at the table with its plastic cloth
and read through the stiff old sheets that had
curled up at the corners. As he read, he frowned,
and once or twice he blinked as if in disbelief.
When he had finished reading, Pelagia came
and sat opposite him. 'Well?' she asked.
He tapped the pile of papers.
'I wish you hadn't shown me these. I'm more
old-fashioned than I thought. I had no idea.'
'He loved you. Are you disgusted?'
'Sad... It's a shock. I can't help it.'
'He wasn't just another hero, was he?
He was more complicated. Poor Carlo.'
They began to talk more freely. 'Are
you very famous then?' Pelagia asked.
'Only in the sense that other
musicians have heard of me.
I've retired now... In fact, I was thinking...
I want to rebuild the old house. I want to
live in a nice place. A place with memories.'
'Without water and electricity?'
'I'll put them in. Would you sell me the site?'
'You're insane. I don't even know if we own it.'
'Then you don't mind. I'd pay you to
come and clean it,' he said wickedly.
She took him seriously. 'What? Do
I need money? With this taverna?
Go home to Athens. Anyway, Lemoni would do it.'
'Little Lemoni? She's still here?'
'She's as big as a ship and a grandmother.'
He fell silent again,
remembering the past, then said,
'So do I have your permission
to rebuild the house?'
'No,' she said, still holding on to her anger.
'Oh.' He looked at her doubtfully. He would
return to the topic at a later date, he decided.
'I'm going to come and see you
tomorrow,' he said, 'with a surprise.'
'I don't want any surprises. Go to hell
with your surprises. You owe me a life.'
'Ah. I'll bring you a life then.'
'Stupid old man.'
He turned up the next day with screaming brakes
in a cloud of blue smoke. Pelagia shook her head
disapprovingly as he climbed carefully off the
motorbike, which was bright red and looked as if
it had been designed for racing. 'Do you know
where we're going?' the captain said. 'We're
going to see if Casa Nostra is still there...'
he tapped the machine '... on a motorbike.'
'Do you really think the
hut survived the earthquake?
And do you really think I'm going
on a thing like that? At my age?'
'I hired it specially. It goes very well.'
'No,' she said. 'My knees are too stiff.'
'Don't you want to see Casa Nostra?'
'Not with a madman.'
'I've got it for two days. We can
sit on a rock and watch the sea.'
It took a long time to persuade her. As they
swung dangerously from side to side along
the stony roads, she held on tightly to his
waist, her face buried between his shoulders.
Corelli noticed that she held on to him even more
desperately than in the old days, and from time
to time he deliberately swung to one side of
the road so that she would hold him tighter.
'May the saints save me,' thought Pelagia,
and in search of safety slid her arms right round
his waist and linked her fingers together.
- THE END -