At this time of year, and this time of day,
there were very few people in the park.
It was probable that the young lady, who was
sitting on one of the benches, had just wanted
to rest for a while and think about the coming
spring.
She sat there, thoughtful and still.
The sadness in her eyes seemed to be something
new, because it had not yet changed her bright
young face, nor turned her soft lips into
a thin hard line.
A tall young man came walking through the
park along the path near the bench where she
was sitting.
Behind him came a boy carrying a suitcase.
When the man saw the young lady, his face
changed to red and back to pale again.
He watched her face as he came closer, and
his own face showed both hope and worry at
the same time.
He passed her only a few meters away, but
she gave no sign that she had seen him, or
even knew he was there.
Fifty meters further on the young man suddenly
stopped and sat down on a bench by the path.
The boy dropped the suitcase and stared at
him with wondering eyes.
The young man took out his handkerchief and
wiped his face.
It was a good handkerchief, a good face, and
the young man was good to look at.
He said to the boy:
'I want you to take a message to that young
lady on that bench.
Tell her I am on my way to the station, to
leave for San Francisco.
From there I shall travel north to the wild
places of Alaska.
Tell her that, as she has ordered me neither
to speak nor to write to her, I am taking
this chance to appeal to her one last time.
Tell her that she has been unkind and unjust
to someone who has done no wrong; and she
has given him no reasons and no explanations.
Tell her that I do not believe her to be an
unjust person.
Tell her that I have disobeyed her orders,
in the hope that she will return to the paths
of justice and reason.
Go, and tell her that.'
The young man dropped a half-dollar into the
boy's hand.
The boy looked at him for a moment with bright,
intelligent eyes out of a dirty face, then
turned and ran down the path.
As he came closer to the lady on the bench,
he studied her carefully.
The lady looked back at him coolly.
'Lady,' the boy said, 'that guy on the other
bench sent yer a song and dance by me.
If yer don't know the guy, and he's tryin'
to do some funny business, say the word, and
I'll call a cop in three minutes.
If yer does know him, and he's all right,
then I'll give yer the song and dance that
he gave me.'
The young lady showed a little, just a little
interest.
'A song and dance!'
she said, in a very sweet voice that seemed
to suggest something not at all sweet.
'A new idea - a kind of traveling singer,
I suppose.
I used to know the gentleman who sent you,
so it will not be necessary to call the police.
Please begin your song and dance, but do not
sing too loudly.
It is not really the time or the place for
that kind of thing.'
'Aw, come on, lady,' said the boy, 'yer know
what I mean.
It ain't a song and dance really, it's a lot
of hot air.
He told me to tell you he's got his shirts
in that case and he's movin' on to 'Frisco.
Then he's goin' on up to Alaska.
He says yer told him not to send round no
more love notes, nor stand around lookin'
over the garden gate.
He says yer threw him out like last year's
hat, and never gave him no chance to argue.
He says yer told him to go, and never said
why.'
The interest in the young lady's eyes did
not go away.
Perhaps her interest was in the cleverness
of the future Alaskan traveler, who had found
a way to get round her orders.
She fixed her eyes on an untidy-looking tree
in the park, and spoke to the messenger:
'Tell the gentleman that he knows very well
what my ideals are.
He knows what they have been, and he knows
what they still are.
In this matter, the two most important ideals
are that a person should be true, and loyal.
Tell him that I have studied my own heart,
and I know that it can be weak, as well as
strong.
That is why I do not wish to listen to his
arguments or to hear any words from him at
all.
I am not unjust, and have never been unjust.
But if he really wants to hear what he already
knows, you may tell him this...
'Tell him I entered the garden room that evening
from the door at the back, to cut a flower
for my mother.
Tell him I saw him and Miss Ashburton beneath
the pink oleander bush.
It was a pretty picture indeed, but the juxtaposition
told the whole story without the need for
a single word.
I left the garden room at once, without the
flower, and with my ideals broken into a hundred
thousand pieces.
You may take that song and dance to your dancing
teacher.'
'Juxta...
juxta?
Help me out, lady,' said the boy.
'Give me an easier word, will yer?'
'Juxtaposition... or, if you like, closeness
- the kind of closeness that can destroy an
ideal in a second.'
At once the boy turned and ran back to the
other bench.
The young man's eyes questioned him, hungrily.
The boy's eyes shone with excitement at his
new job as translator.
'The lady says that she knows that girls just
can't stop listenin' when a guy comes tellin'
stories and tryin' to be real nice and friendly.
That's why she won't listen to no sweet words
from yer.
She says she caught yer in the hothouse under
the flowers with yer arms around a girl.
She just stepped in the back to get a flower
for her ma, and yer was holdin' this other
girl real nice and close.
She says it looked pretty, all right all right,
but the juxta... but it made her sick.
She says yer gotta get busy and get off and
get that train real quick.'
The young man's eyes opened wide and his eyes
lit up with a sudden thought.
His hand flew to the inside pocket of his
coat, and pulled out a handful of letters.
Choosing one, he gave it to the boy, together
with a silver dollar from another pocket.
'Give that letter to the lady,' he said, 'and
ask her to read it.
Tell her that it should explain everything.
Tell her that she needs another ideal - she
must learn to trust, and that trust can prevent
much unnecessary heartache.
Tell her that her ideals are not broken.
Tell her that the true and loyal person is
still true and loyal, and has not changed
in any way.
Tell her I am waiting for an answer.'
The messenger stood before the lady again.
'The guy says there's been bad things said
about him, and it ain't right, it ain't just.
He says he ain't a bad guy.
And, lady, yer read that letter, and you're
goin' to see that he's all right, all right.'
The young lady took the letter.
She seemed unsure about it, but she opened
it, and read it.
Dear Dr Arnold
I want to thank you for the very kind help
that you gave to my daughter last Friday evening,
when she became suddenly ill with her old
heart trouble in the garden room at Mrs Waldron's
party.
It was so lucky that you were near enough
to catch her as she fell, and were able to
give her a doctor's care at once.
We are sure that you saved her life.
I would be happy if you would visit us soon
as her doctor.
Gratefully yours,
Robert Ashburton
The young lady closed the letter, and gave
it back to the boy.
'The guy wants an answer,' said the messenger.
'What's the word, lady?'
The lady's eyes were suddenly very bright
and smiling.
'Tell that guy on the other bench,' she said,
with a happy, shaky little laugh, 'that his
girl wants him.'