CHAPTER ONE
Monkey's Story
Monkey pulled out some hairs from his chest
and, crying 'Change!' threw them into the air.
At once, they became several
hundred small monkeys.
From the beginning of time, the rock was
smoothed and cleaned by Heaven and Earth,
by the strong sun and the gentle moon,
until one day it broke into two pieces
and gave birth to a stone egg, about as big as a
child's ball. From the egg came a stone monkey.
At once, this monkey learned to climb
and run. But first, it looked north
and south and east and west. As it looked,
a strange light came from its eyes.
The light shone as far as the Jade Emperor, who
sat in the Cloud Palace of the Golden Gates. The
Jade Emperor asked his ministers to open the gate
of the Southern Heaven and look out at the light.
'This light,' reported the ministers,
'comes from the small country of Ao-lai,
to the east of the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit.'
And in the country of Ao-lai,
the monkey ran and jumped.
He picked flowers, ate grass and fruit,
and drank from streams and rivers.
His friends were all the animals of that
country, and the other monkeys were his family.
At night, he slept among the rocks and
in the day he walked through the caves.
One day, the monkeys were washing in
a stream when one of them spoke. 'None
of us knows where this stream comes
from. Let's follow it and find out.'
So they all ran up the stream until
they came to a great waterfall.
The monkeys shouted, 'Lovely water, lovely
water! It starts in a mountain cave and
runs all the way to the Great Sea. Who can
find the place where the water comes from?
If one of us could find this place and
return safely, we would make him our king!'
'I will go!' shouted the
Stone Monkey. 'I will go!'
Look at him! He shuts his eyes, and with one
big jump he passes through the curtain of water.
But there is no water where he has landed.
Instead he finds a great, shining
iron bridge in front of him.
Monkey walked along the bridge and came to
a cave. Outside the cave there was a sign:
This Cave of the Water Curtain in the Country of
the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit Leads to Heaven.
Monkey laughed and jumped with happiness.
He ran back across the bridge, shut his eyes and
jumped through the waterfall to the other monkeys.
'Good news!' he shouted. 'Good
news! Come with me, all of you!'
They followed the Stone Monkey
to the Cave of the Water Curtain.
There the Stone Monkey sat
down and talked to them.
'Gentlemen!' he said. 'I have
been through the waterfall
and have come back again. I have given you a
home in this cave, so am I not your king now?'
The monkeys bowed to the Stone Monkey and they
all cried, 'Great King for a thousand years!'
The Stone Monkey became the Monkey King
and he made other monkeys his ministers.
And all the monkeys were happy. During
the day they walked and played on the
Mountain of Flowers and Fruit, and
at night they slept in the Cave
of the Water Curtain. They had everything
they wanted. Their lives were complete.
The Monkey King enjoyed this simple
life for several hundred years.
But one day at a great party with all the
other monkeys, he suddenly started to cry.
The other monkeys all bowed,
saying, 'Why is our king so sad?'
'Today,' said the Monkey King, 'I am not sad.
But I am worried about the future. Sadly, the
time will come when I will become old and weak.
Yama, King of Death, is waiting to destroy me.
I do not want to be born again on Earth. How can
I live for all time among the people of the sky?'
The monkeys all started to cry, each thinking of
his own mortality. One of them said, 'Only Buddhas
and Immortals do not go to Yama, King
of Death. Only they live forever.'
'Where can I find these
Immortals?' asked the Monkey King.
'Here on Earth they live in
very old caves far to the West.'
'Tomorrow,' said the Monkey King, 'I shall say
goodbye to you. I shall go down the mountain and
travel to the end of the world. I want to learn
to live for all time and to escape from death.'
Next morning, he walked to the sea and sailed in
a boat to the borders of the Southern World. There
he climbed out on to the beach. And then he walked
and walked, through towns and cities, to the West.
On the way, he learned to wear clothes and
to behave like a human. But he met humans
who wanted only to be rich and famous. He
met nobody who worried about his mortality.
One day, he came to the Western Ocean, where
he built another boat. Then he sailed to the
Western Continent, where he saw a very high
and beautiful wooded mountain. At the top
of the mountain was the Cave of the Moon and
Three Stars, where the Immortal Subodhi lived.
Monkey at once bowed and touched the
ground with his head three times.
'Where do you come from?' asked the Immortal.
'I am from the Cave of the Water Curtain,'
said Monkey, 'on the Mountain of Flowers
and Fruit in the country of Ao-lai.'
'That is impossible!' shouted the Immortal.
'Between there and here are two oceans and the
whole of the Southern Continent. You are lying!'
'I have sailed across the oceans and
walked over the continents for more
than ten years,' said Monkey.
'At last I have reached here.'
Monkey told the Immortal how
he had come from a magic stone.
The Immortal thought that Monkey was
a natural product of Heaven and Earth,
so he agreed to teach him. Monkey
jumped up and down with happiness.
Day after day, he and the other students learned
to speak and behave correctly. They learned to
write well and to study the Scriptures. When they
were not studying, the students grew flowers and
trees. They lit fires and fetched water. And so
Monkey lived in this way for six or seven years.
Finally, the Immortal sent
for Monkey late one night
because he wanted to teach
him the Way of Long Life.
'Come close and listen
carefully,' said the Immortal.
Monkey went down on his knees on the floor
at the Immortal's feet, listening carefully.
The Immortal recited a magic poem with many lines.
The words shook Monkey's soul and he was never the
same Monkey again. He thanked the Immortal many
times, because now he knew the Way of Long Life.
Time passed quickly and three years later the
Immortal again invited Monkey to his room,
where he taught him seventy-two transformations.
Monkey was a quick learner and he practised until
he could change himself into something
else, using all seventy-two ways.
One day, when the Immortal and his
students were in front of the cave
admiring the evening view, the Immortal spoke
to Monkey. 'Monkey, how much have you learned?'
'Thanks to you,' said Monkey,
'I have learned a lot.
In addition to changing myself into
other forms, I can already fly.'
'Let me see you do it,' said the Immortal.
Monkey put his feet together, jumped twenty
metres into the air and rode the clouds for a
few minutes. Then he dropped to the ground,
saying, 'You see, I can ride the clouds.'
'That is not riding the clouds,' said the
Immortal, laughing. 'A real cloud-rider
can start in the morning from the Northern Sea,
cross the Eastern, the Western and the
Southern Seas and land again in one day.'
'It sounds very difficult,' said Monkey.
'Nothing in the world is difficult,' said the
Immortal. 'Only our own thoughts make things
seem difficult. Now I will teach you
to fly from one continent to another.'
The other students laughed, saying,
'If Monkey flies all that way,
he will be able to earn a living as a postman.'
But Monkey spent all night practising
what the Immortal had taught him.
By morning he could fly wherever he wanted.
One summer day, some students
were sitting under a tree.
A student said, 'Monkey, why do you
deserve private teaching by the Immortal?
Has he taught you the transformations,
by all the seventy-two ways?'
'I have been working on them day and night
and now I can do them all,' said Monkey.
'Could you show us?'
Proudly, Monkey made a magic sign, said some
magic words and transformed himself into a tree.
'Well done, Monkey, well done!' shouted
the other students. They all laughed.
The Immortal heard their laughter and
he came running out from the cave.
'Who is making all this noise?' he asked.
Monkey changed himself back from a tree to
a monkey. He sat with the students again
and said, 'Immortal, we are
practising our lessons out here.'
'You were all shouting and laughing!' said
the Immortal, angrily. 'I want to know why.'
Then one student said, 'Monkey was transforming
himself into a tree, just for fun.'
'You, Monkey, come here!' shouted the Immortal.
'Why do you think I taught you these secrets
of life? So you can make other people laugh?'
'I am very sorry,' said Monkey.
'I will not punish you,' said the Immortal.
'But you cannot stay here. You must leave us.'
Monkey started to cry. 'Where can I go?' he asked.
'Go back to where you came from. Go as
quickly as you can. Never tell anyone
that you were a student of mine. I am
sure that no good will come of your life.'
And so poor Monkey said goodbye to everybody.
He flew back to the Eastern Sea and his home
in the Cave of the Water Curtain on
the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit.
'Little ones,' shouted the
Monkey King, 'I have come back!'
At once, big and small monkeys leapt out of
trees with cries of 'Long live our King!'
Then, pushing each other to get near him,
they cried, 'Why did you go for so long?
We have been watching for your return day
after day! While you were away, a demon took
our cave and everything we own and many of our
children. Now we dare not sleep, night or day.'
'What demon dares to do this?'
cried Monkey. 'I will make him pay!'
'King, he is called the Destroying Demon,
and he lives north of here. But he
comes and goes like a cloud, like wind,
like rain, like thunder and lightning, so we
do not know where his home is or how far away.'
'Well, don't worry,' said Monkey.
'I will go and look for him.'
Dear Monkey! He leapt into the sky and
soon saw in front of him a high mountain
and a cave, where the Destroying
Demon was waiting for him.
'Where is the owner of the Cave of
the Water Curtain?' cried the Demon.
'You have such large eyes,' shouted
Monkey, 'but you cannot see Monkey?'
'Oh! You are not half a metre high!
If I killed such a small creature
with my sword, I would look foolish.'
So the two of them fought with their hands and
feet, hitting and kicking each other. Soon the
Demon was fighting like a wild animal. Monkey
pulled out some hairs from his chest and, crying
'Change!' threw them into the air. At once,
they became several hundred small monkeys.
See how the monkeys jump on the
Demon, pulling and hitting him.
Then Monkey takes up the Demon's great sword and
brings it down on his head, breaking it in two.
Then, by his magic, he transforms
all the monkeys back into hairs.
When Monkey returned home to the cave
on the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit,
he brought the great sword
of the Destroying Demon,
and he amused the other monkeys by
teaching them to make weapons of wood.
Then, one day, the Monkey King
called all the other monkeys to him.
'All this,' he said, pointing
to their wooden weapons,
'is only a game. We cannot defend
ourselves from a real enemy with these.'
'We know a city that is full of soldiers. They
must have plenty of weapons,' the others said.
They quickly told Monkey where it was.
'Stay here and amuse yourselves,'
Monkey said. 'I will see what I can do.'
Dear Monkey! Using his magic, he flew to the city
and, with his breath, blew such a strong wind that
all the people locked themselves indoors. This was
his chance. He found where the weapons were kept,
kicked down the door, and changed his hairs into
thousands of small monkeys who took the weapons.
Carried on a magic wind, they
were soon back at the cave.
The monkeys learned to use the weapons,
and all sorts of wild animals and demon
kings began to call Monkey their king.
But Monkey found his own weapon too heavy,
so he went to the Dragon of the Eastern Sea in
search of something lighter. The Dragon King
welcomed him to the palace, with his dragon
children, dragon grandchildren and fish soldiers.
Monkey made his request, and a fish
soldier brought out a great sword.
'Too heavy,' said Monkey.
More fish soldiers brought out an enormous fork.
'Too light,' said Monkey.
The dragon mother and her daughter
came from a back room in the palace
and suggested their magic iron cudgel.
'The Gods used it when they
decided how deep the rivers
and the seas should be,' said the Dragon
King. He agreed that Monkey should have it.
When it was brought, Monkey saw that it
was a thick piece of iron six metres long.
He used his magic to bring
it down to less than a metre.
Then he waved it over his head, striking
terror into everybody in the room.
But now he demanded something
to wear, to go with the weapon,
and this was too much. A pair of cloud-stepping
shoes, a cap of red gold and a coat of light metal
were brought to him, but the angry Dragon King
also sent for his brothers from the Southern,
Northern and Western Seas and told
them about Monkey's many requests.
The Dragon of the South was angry.
'Put him in prison!' he cried.
'No, no,' warned the Dragon King.
'We cannot go near him now. If he touches
us with that iron cudgel, he will kill us.
Let him keep the clothes. We will complain
to Heaven, and Heaven will punish him.'
Monkey took the clothes, but he knew that
they were going to complain about him.
Soon after that, the Jade Emperor received the
complaint from the Dragon of the Eastern Sea.
'How long,' the Jade Emperor asked his ministers,
'has this Monkey existed, and why
does he behave like an Immortal?'
'In the last three hundred years, he has
learned a lot,' said a minister. 'Let's
give him work here in Heaven where
we will be able to watch hint.'
This suggestion pleased the Jade Emperor, and
a minister was sent to bring Monkey to Heaven.
Monkey tidied his clothes, told the older
monkeys to look after the younger ones,
and followed the minister to Heaven.
'I am going to give you a job,'
said the Jade Emperor to Monkey.
'You are going to look after the Apple Garden.'
Monkey was very happy and ran to the Apple Garden
to start work. He was told that on the outer side
of the garden were special apples. They were
ready to eat once in three thousand years.
If you ate one of these, you would become wise,
with strong arms and legs and a light body.
In the middle were trees with apples that
were ready to eat once in six thousand years.
If you ate these, you would go up in the air
and stay there, and would never grow old.
At the back were trees with apples chat were
ready to eat once in nine thousand years.
If you ate these, you would live
longer than Heaven and Earth.
Monkey was very happy with this information.
He watched the trees closely, making up his mind
to eat the fruit before anybody else got a chance.
Soon, noticing that some apples were
ready to eat, he sent his helpers away.
He climbed into a high tree and
ate until he could eat no more.
When the Queen of Heaven sent
her lady assistants for apples,
they were turned away at the
gates by Monkey's helpers.
'We must ask the Monkey King first,' they
said. 'He is resting in one of the trees.'
But when they came to the tree, they found only
Monkey's cap and shoes. They could not see him.
In fact, Monkey had made himself five
centimetres long and was asleep under a leaf.
The Queen of Heaven's lady assistants picked three
basketfuls from each of the first two groups of
trees. When they came to the third, they found
just one apple. When one of the ladies tried to
pick it, Monkey woke up. At once,
he changed back to his true size.
'Who are you?' shouted Monkey.
The lady assistants went down on their
knees. 'Monkey King, don't be angry.
We were sent by the Queen and we could
not find you. Please forgive us.'
'Get up from your knees,' said Monkey,
his voice full of kindness. 'I have
heard that the Queen of Heaven is having a
banquet. Can you tell me who is invited?'
Monkey was told that all the Immortals,
Emperors of the Four Quarters and Gods
of the seas and hills would be there. He
immediately asked, 'Will I be invited?'
'I have not heard,' said one of the
lady assistants. 'We do not know.'
'Quite right, ladies,' said Monkey.
'Just wait here while I go and see.'
Dear Monkey! He recited some
magic lines, crying 'Stay, stay,
stay!' The lady assistants were suddenly unable
to move while he went off on his magic cloud.
No one had arrived at the banquet yet,
but Monkey could smell the food and wine.
He sent the servants to sleep by magic. Look
at them, how their hands fall to their sides,
their heads drop on to their chests, their
eyes close! Monkey then took some of the
finest and best of the food and drank glass
after glass of wine until he was quite drunk.
'Bad! Bad!'
he thought to himself. 'I will certainly get
into trouble, so I will go home and sleep.'
But it was too late for that.
Back at the Apple Garden, the
Queen's ladies were finally saved.
They reported that the Monkey King had eaten many
of the biggest apples and had now disappeared.
When the great Goddess Kuan-yin arrived for
the banquet, she found half the food eaten and
all the wine gone. When the servants were
woken, they explained that the Monkey King
had sent them to sleep. That was the last
time they had seen the food and the wine.
The Jade Emperor was informed and he
sent heavenly soldiers to find Monkey.
Monkey was burned in fire for nine
days, and at the end of it his
eyes were red but he was still alive. He
was attacked with swords and the Gods of
Thunder threw thunder at him.
But nothing could destroy him.
In the end, hearing of this situation, the great
Buddha himself arrived and called Monkey to him.
'How long ago,' he asked him, 'did you
try to become an Immortal and learn
the things that make you dare behave like this?'
Monkey at once recited:
Born of Earth and Sky, I am a magic Immortal.
I am an old monkey from the
Mountain of Flowers and Fruit;
In the Cave of the Water Curtain,
I work and laugh and play.
I found a friend and teacher
who taught me the Great Secret;
I made myself perfect in the Ways of Immortality,
I learned transformations without limit or end,
I tired of the narrow world of
men, and lived in the Jade Heaven.
But why should Heaven's
palace have only one emperor?
On Earth king follows king, as
the strong bow to the stronger.
Only a hero fights with the Gods of Gods.
That was what Monkey recited.
Buddha laughed. 'But you are only a
monkey-spirit,' he said. 'The Jade Emperor
has been making himself perfect for countless
years. How can you hope to take his place and
become emperor yourself? You are only an animal
that looks half human! Talk no more of this.'
'Why should he be emperor for all time?
Tell him to go and to give me my chance,'
said Monkey. 'That is all I ask. And if he will
not, I will see that he never has any peace.'
'What magic have you got that would
help you to take Heaven for yourself?'
'I have a lot of magic,' replied Monkey. 'I
can jump through the clouds from continent
to continent. Am I not good enough
to live in the palaces of Heaven?'
Buddha said, 'If you are really so clever, you
will sit here in my right hand and then jump off.
If you succeed, you can become the Jade Emperor.
But if you fail, you will go back to Earth
and you will be punished for centuries.'
Monkey thought, 'This Buddha is a complete
fool. How could I fail to jump off his hand!'
Buddha held out his hand, which
looked about the size of a large leaf.
Monkey took the magic iron cudgel
that the Dragon King had given him,
and that he had transformed into
a stick the size of a needle.
He put it behind his ear and then he jumped
from the hand as far and as fast as he could.
He was flying very fast, but Buddha
watched him with the eye of wisdom.
Monkey came at last to five high pink towers.
'This must be the end of the world,' said
Monkey to himself. 'Now I will return to Buddha,
become emperor, and all Heaven will be mine. But
I had better leave some sign that I was here.'
Pulling out a hair, he changed it
into a writing-brush heavy with ink,
and at the bottom of the middle tower he wrote:
The great Monkey King reached this place.
Then he jumped back to where he had come from.
Standing on Buddha's hand, he said,
'I have gone and I have returned. You can
tell the Jade Emperor that his job is mine.'
'You smelly creature,' said Buddha,
'you have been on my hand all the time.'
'You are completely wrong,' said Monkey.
'I travelled to the end of the world,
saw five pink towers and wrote on one of them.
Would you like me to take you and show you?'
'No need,' said Buddha. 'Just look down.'
Monkey looked down, with his eyes
still red from the nine days of fire.
There, at the bottom of the
middle finger of Buddha's hand,
he saw the words "The great
Monkey King reached this place."
Monkey could not speak and his
red eyes opened wide in surprise.
At last he said, 'Impossible! Impossible! I
wrote that on a tower going high into the sky.
How did it get on the Buddha's finger?
It is magic! I shall go back to look!'
Dear Monkey! He was preparing to jump again
when Buddha pushed him out of the Western
Gate of Heaven. As he did, he changed
his five fingers into Metal, Wood, Water,
Fire and Earth. They became a mountain which
pressed poor Monkey down with its great weight.
The name Mountain of Metal, Wood, Water, Fire and
Earth was written on a large rock on the mountain.
Under the mountain there was
enough air for Monkey to breathe,
but no opening which Monkey's head
or hand could squeeze through.
Buddha then told a spirit to look after
Monkey and give him food and drink.
'And when the days of his punishment are
finished,' said Buddha, 'a man will come here
and save him.'
Time passed, and then one day the Buddha said to
his followers, 'I have noticed a lot of difference
between the people who live in the four continents
of the world. The people in the East are polite,
peaceful and cheerful. People in the North
are lazy and stupid, so do little harm.
In our Western Continent, there is no killing,
although there is little real wisdom. But in the
South, they are greedy and murderous. A knowledge
of the True Scriptures might improve them.'
'Do you have these Scriptures?'
asked his followers.
'Yes, three baskets of them,' said Buddha. 'One
speaks of Heaven, another of Earth, and a third
can save people from the Wrong Way. These are the
path to perfection, the only gate to the True Way.
But down in the real world, people are so stupid
that they laugh at them. I need to find someone
who will go to the Eastern land. There he might
find a believer who could come here from China.
I would give this believer the Scriptures
to take back to China and change
the hearts of the people.'
The Goddess Kuan-yin came
forward and bowed three times.
'I would like to go to the Eastern land
and find someone to fetch the Scriptures.'
'Who would be better than you!' said Buddha.
So Kuan-yin called her bodyguard, Hui-yen,
who carried a great iron cudgel,
and they started at once.
After they had travelled a long way,
they came to the River of Sands. There,
a horribly ugly creature leapt out of the water
and began a terrible fight with the bodyguard.
Suddenly, the creature stopped fighting,
looked hard at the bodyguard and asked, 'Who
dares to fight with me? Surely I have seen you
before in the gardens of the Goddess Kuan-yin?'
'The Goddess herself is here, in
front of you,' Hui-yen replied.
'I ask you to forgive me!' cried the creature.
'I am not really the ugly creature that you see.
I was given this horrible shape as a
punishment for a crime that I did in Heaven.
I was sent to the world below, where I am always
hungry and I must attack travellers and eat them.'
'But you are adding new crimes
on Earth to your crime in Heaven
by killing people,' said the Goddess Kuan-yin.
'Why not come with us? If
our journey is successful,
you will be forgiven and
allowed to return to Heaven.'
'I would gladly go back,' the creature
answered. 'But I have eaten so many humans.
Even now, nine heads are lying on
the waters of the River of Sands.
I have played games with them and I do not think
I will be allowed back into Heaven after that.'
'Don't be silly,' she replied. 'Take
the heads and hang them round your neck.
I shall make you a priest and
give you the name "Sandy Priest".
Wait here and never again take a human life.
You will see that a man will come this way.
He will be looking for the Scriptures and a
good use will be found for the nine heads.'
So the Goddess and her bodyguard continued
their journey and came to a high mountain
with a most horrible smell. A
dirty, smelly, piglike creature
leapt out and attacked Kuan-yin with a great
fork and fought hard with her bodyguard.
For safety, Kuan-yin stood in the sky above them
and then threw down flowers, which fell
between the bodyguard's cudgel and the fork.
'Fighting with flowers?' cried the
pig. 'What kind of priest are you?'
'The great Goddess Kuan-yin threw
them down on us from her cloud,
where she is standing,' replied the bodyguard.
At once, the pig bowed to the sky.
'Forgive me, Goddess, forgive me!
I am not really a pig at all. For a crime in
Heaven, the Jade Emperor sent me down here.'
'This is a chance for you,' said Kuan-yin. 'We
are on our way to China to look for a man who
will collect the Scriptures. If you went with
him to India, we would forgive all your crimes.'
'I will! I will!' the pig-like creature shouted.
So they gave him the name of Pigsy,
and left him to watch for the pilgrim
who would collect the Scriptures.
The Goddess and her bodyguard went on their way
and soon they met a dragon who
had fought against the Gods.
'Can you help me?' the dragon cried out.
Kuan-yin went back to Heaven. She
asked the Gods to forgive the dragon
if he would transform himself into a white
horse and carry the pilgrim to India.
Continuing their journey,
the Goddess and her bodyguard
suddenly saw a mountain covered in magic
fog and lit by golden light from Heaven.
They recognised it at once as the
mountain which covered the Monkey King.
Kuan-yin looked sad and recited:
Long ago he was purposelessly brave.
In his blackness of heart he
spoiled the Heavenly Apple Banquet
And tried to take the place of the Jade Emperor.
Will he ever again be free and win back his name?
Then came a voice from inside the mountain:
'Who is reciting a list of my crimes?'
Kuan-yin found the spirit who looked after Monkey.
This spirit led her to Monkey's prison under
the mountain, which was a kind of stone box.
Monkey looked out through a thin opening with his
red eyes and cried, 'You are the Goddess Kuan-yin!
Why have you come here? Buddha tricked me and
I have sat in this little box for five hundred
years. But I am very sorry for the things I have
done and now I want to do good in the world.'
Kuan-yin was very happy. 'Just wait quietly here
until I return with my pilgrim
and he will save you,' she said.
And so they left Monkey and went on
to the East, to find the pilgrim.
CHAPTER TWO
The Journey Begins
'I can tell you that I have
killed quite a lot of people.
And I am still the great
Monkey King!' answered Monkey.
At a time when the great and
very old city of Ch'ang-an
was the capital of China, there was an examination
to find the cleverest men in the country.
These men would do the work of the government.
A man by the name of Ch'en O decided
to try his luck at the examination,
as it was his mother's wish. Arriving late,
he found that the examination had begun.
But to his surprise, he won first place and
he received a letter signed by the Emperor.
In those days, the winner of first place in
the examination was led through the streets
on horseback. And by chance, on that day, the
only daughter of a minister sat in her high
tower with a ball in her hand. Seeing the handsome
Ch'en riding by, and knowing of his success in the
examination, she threw the ball cleverly on to
his hat. This was how a lady chose her husband.
No time was wasted. Ch'en and the minister's
daughter were married, and hand in hand they
went into the bedroom as man and wife. Early next
morning, Ch'en was made Governor of Chiang-chou
and, as he was told to begin work at once,
he started on the journey with his wife.
It was late spring. There was a gentle wind in
the trees and a light rain fell. The road to
Chiang-chou took Ch'en and his wife close to his
home, so they stopped at his mother's house. Ch'en
said to his mother, 'You wanted me to take
the examination, and look at all the good
luck that has come from it. I would like to
thank you and to ask you to come with us.'
His mother happily agreed and after travelling
for some days, the three arrived at the Hotel of
Ten Thousand Flowers. But here the mother
suddenly became ill and asked to rest.
Next day, a man arrived with a gold-coloured fish
for sale and young Ch'en bought it for his mother.
Suddenly, he noticed that the fish's eyes were
strange. 'This is not an ordinary creature,' he
said. He asked where it was caught and then
returned it to the river in the same place.
'You were right to put the
fish back in the river,'
said his mother when he told her
about the fish's eyes. Then she said,
'Leave me here with some of the luggage and
I shall follow when the days are cooler.'
When Ch'en, his wife and servants arrived at the
same river, they were met by two boatmen who Ch'en
had harmed in an earlier life. They stared
at his young wife, who was very beautiful.
Then they took the boat to a lonely place
and killed first the servants and then Ch'en
himself. The young woman tried to throw
herself into the river, but they stopped her.
One of the murderers, whose name was Liu,
put on the Governor's clothes, took the official
papers and left for Chiang-chou with Mrs Ch'en.
Liu left the boat with the other boatman, Li,
who threw the bodies into the river. The bodies
of the servants could be seen on the river,
but Ch'en's body went straight to the bottom.
A servant of the Dragon King saw it there and went
to the palace to tell the Dragon King himself.
The Dragon King asked to see it.
When Ch'en's body was brought
to him, he recognised this man.
In the body of a gold-coloured fish, the Dragon
King had been saved by him only a few days before.
In return for Ch'en's kindness, the Dragon
King sent his servant to the place where the
souls of the newly dead go. The servant returned
with Ch'en's soul and Ch'en woke from the dead.
When he had heard Ch'en's story, the
Dragon King said, 'You certainly helped me.
So I shall now give you back your life.
I want you to work in my Water Office.'
While this was happening, Mrs
Ch'en was so unhappy with Liu
that she could not eat or sleep. But because
she was going to have her husband's child,
she thought it was best to
follow this terrible man quietly.
After a long journey they reached Chiang-chou,
where Liu the boatman became the new governor.
Time passed and Mrs Ch'en gave birth to a son.
At the same time a mysterious voice whispered
in her ear, 'Listen to what I am telling you.
This child will be famous around the world.
But you must protect him from Liu, who will
certainly try to harm him. Your husband is safe
with the Dragon King and one day you will all be
together again and your enemies will be punished.'
Then there was silence. Mrs Ch'en
held her son in her arms, but she could
think of no other way to protect him.
And as the voice had said, when Liu returned he
ordered the death of the child. But the unhappy
mother wanted more time with her son. 'I will
put him in the river tomorrow,' she promised Liu.
'Perhaps,' she thought, 'a
kind god will save him.'
She bit her finger and, with her blood, wrote a
letter giving the names of the child's parents.
Then, so that she would know her child again,
she bit off the top of the little toe
of his left foot. When morning came,
she tied the baby into one of her shirts
and went quietly down to the river with him.
As she stood at the water's edge, a large piece
of wood came down the river. Quickly, she tied the
shirt with the baby in it to the wood and put
the letter she had written in the shirt. Then
she pushed the wood to the centre of the river
and walked back, crying every step of the way.
The piece of wood with the baby on it was carried
at last to the Temple of the Golden Mountain.
The Holy Master, hearing
the sound of a baby crying,
went to the river and found the strange boat.
He read the letter about the child's father, and
immediately gave the child the name of River Wood.
Then he asked some farmers to look after him.
Seventeen years later, the young man had been
given the new name of Hsuan Tsang and had been
made a priest in the Holy Master's temple. One
day an old and stupid priest cried out, 'Who do
you think you are? No one even knows your real
name!' He was jealous of the young man's wisdom.
The unhappy boy ran to the Holy Master. 'Can there
be,' he asked, 'a man without a father or mother?'
From a hiding-place in his room, the Holy Master
took down a small box containing the blood-letter
and the shirt. Soon Hsuan Tsang knew the whole
story and the terrible wrong done to his parents.
He wanted to kill his father's murderer.
'If you must go,' said the Holy Master, 'take
these things with you. Travel as a poor priest,
go to Chiang-chou and demand to see your mother.'
That same night, his mother dreamed of a moon
behind the clouds. When the clouds moved,
she saw a full moon, and then she thought
of her son. 'He must be seventeen by now.
Perhaps Heaven will bring us together again.'
Suddenly, she heard a priest asking
for money at the gate and went out to
him. When she heard his place of birth, the
Golden Mountain, she looked at him closely
and said, 'Little priest, you are very
like my husband. Who were your parents?'
'A wrong was done to my parents,' was the answer.
'My Holy Master told me to come here and find my
mother. My father's name is Ch'en, but my holy
name is Hsuan Tsang.' Then he took from the box
the blood-letter and the shirt. She recognised
them at once and she put her arms around him.
'Leave me, leave me!' she cried. 'If Liu finds
you, he will kill you. Go now, as fast as
lightning! But tomorrow I will say that I have
promised a hundred pairs of shoes to the poor
and I must journey to the temple to offer
this present to the Gods. There we can talk.'
True to her promise, within five days a
hundred pairs of shoes were put on a boat
and, with some servants, she made
the journey to the Golden Mountain.
All the priests came out to welcome the visitor,
but when she had prayed she asked them to leave.
Then, on her knees in front of Hsuan Tsang, she
took off the shoe and sock from his left foot.
As she expected, the top of
his left toe was missing.
Again the mother and son put
their arms around each other,
and she thanked the Holy Master for his great
kindness. Then she gave Hsuan Tsang a ring to
take to the Hotel of Ten Thousand Flowers,
where his grandmother had been left behind.
'Here, also, is a letter to
my father in the capital,'
she said. 'Tell him to ask the Emperor to
send horses and men to kill Liu and save me.
Now I dare not stay any
longer, but must return home.'
Hsuan Tsang went to the Hotel of Ten Thousand
Flowers and asked about his grandmother. The
owner of the hotel told him, 'The lady was
here for several years. But she went blind
and now, asking people in the streets
for money, she lives in a box.'
Hsuan Tsang finally found his
poor grandmother, who cried,
'Oh! I thought my son had forgotten me! And
now Heaven has sent a grandson to find me.'
After paying her bills and leaving her
in a comfortable room at the hotel,
Hsuan Tsang rushed back to the capital
and to the house of Minister Yin. But
they refused to let him in. 'No one in
our family is a priest,' he was told.
'Last night I dreamed about my daughter,' said
the wife. 'Perhaps he has a message from her.'
Hsuan Tsang bowed to them and took out
the letter that his mother had written.
The minister cried, 'Wife! This is our grandchild.
Ch'en has been killed and our daughter has been
forced to live with the murderer. I will ask
the Emperor for soldiers to kill that man.'
The Emperor was wild with anger and sent an
army of sixty thousand men to Chiang-chou.
They easily found Liu and took
him away to cut his head off.
Now Yin sent for his daughter. She did not wish
to see her father because she was ashamed. Had she
not lived as the wife of her husband's murderer?
But Yin told her that it was not her fault.
He put his arms around her and around his grandson
and kept them in his arms for a long, long time.
By now, the soldiers had found the other boatman,
Li, and had cut his head off too. And where he had
killed Ch'en, Li's body was cut open. His heart
was offered to the soul of the man he had killed.
The Dragon King heard of this and he sent
a message to Ch'en. 'Congratulations!
Your wife and her father and
your child are all by the river,
offering the heart of the man who killed you. I
will now return your soul to you and let you go.'
Mrs Ch'en wanted to throw herself into
the river where her husband had died,
but suddenly a body came up
from the bottom of the river.
Mrs Ch'en recognised it as her
husband's body and cried and screamed.
The hands moved, and then the legs, and then the
whole body, until Ch'en himself climbed out of the
water. He looked at them in great surprise
and said, 'What are you all doing here?'
A great banquet was ordered and next day they
all left for home. On the way, they called
at the Hotel of Ten Thousand Flowers for the
grandmother and took her back to the capital.
At last Chen became a government advisor.
His son, Hsuan Tsang, went back to his work
as a priest at the Temple of the Golden
Mountain. But when the Emperor died,
priests all over China were asked to choose
the holiest priest, and they chose Hsuan Tsang.
At this time, the search was still continuing for
a priest holy enough to fetch the Scriptures from
India. The Goddess Kuan-yin, realising
that the holiest priest was River Wood,
said to herself, 'No one could
be a better man than him.'
In the great city of Ch'ang-an,
the new Emperor asked Hsuan Tsang to
go to India and fetch the Scriptures.
When Hsuan Tsang agreed to go, the Emperor said,
'If you dare to go on a journey as long as this,
with all its dangers, I will make you here and now
the brother of my soul.' Then he bowed four times.
'If I do not reach India and do not
bring the Scriptures back to China,
I must be sent to Hell,' the young priest replied.
The Emperor called for wine and
said, 'I suggest that you take the
name of the Scriptures in India
- Tripitaka. What do you think?'
Hsuan Tsang accepted the name and
from that day he was called Tripitaka.
It was three days before the full moon when
Tripitaka left the gates of Ch'ang-an. After
a day or two of hard riding, he reached the Temple
of the Low Cloud. There the Holy Master and almost
five hundred priests discussed his journey
and its terrible dangers and difficulties.
Tripitaka pointed in silence to his heart.
'It is only the heart that can win against
difficulties. I have made my promise and I
cannot go back until I have reached India,
seen Buddha and got the Scriptures.'
Next morning, Tripitaka got up early. A bright
moon was shining on the snow on the ground
as he left. Almost immediately, he lost his way,
and suddenly the ground moved under his horse.
The horse and rider fell into a deep hole.
'Take him! Take him!'
Looking up, Tripitaka saw a crowd of ugly
creatures looking down at him. They pulled him
out of the hole. Their leader was an ugly
Demon King, who gave orders to eat him.
But two dark ugly creatures arrived as guests, and
two other men were brought out as a meal for them.
The ugly creatures ate like wild animals,
their teeth pulling at the men until they
had completely eaten them. Watching this,
Tripitaka was almost dead with fear.
But then all the ugly creatures went to sleep.
Tripitaka was losing all hope of escape
when suddenly an old man appeared.
He blew in Tripitaka's face and asked him
if the horse belonged to him. Tripitaka
saw to his surprise that his horse was
not harmed. He asked what this place was
and who the ugly creatures were. He was told it
was a mountain full of demons and animal-spirits.
'They did not eat you because your
soul was too good,' said the old man.
'It was your soul that saved you. Follow me
and I will show you the way out of here.'
The old man led him out of that place; then,
as Tripitaka turned to thank him, the old man
flew up into the sky on a great white bird. A
piece of paper blew down, and on it was written,
'I was sent by the Gods to protect you on your
journey. Remember, the Gods will be watching you.'
Tripitaka could only bow low in thanks
before he began his journey again.
After half a day he found himself
in difficult mountain country,
moving forward slowly over sharp rocks. In front
of him, two tigers waited. Realising the danger,
he looked behind him and there he saw an insect
that could kill him. On his right stood a wild
animal that he had never seen before. His
frightened horse went down on its knees.
As the terrible creatures all
started attacking him at once,
a man appeared with a sword. He
took Tripitaka from his horse.
'I am a hunter who these animals know
and fear. You and I are from the same
country and you and your horse can
rest at my house until tomorrow.'
On the way to his house the hunter
killed a tiger, saying, 'This is luck!
Enough meat to last you for days!'
Arriving at a mountain farm, Tripitaka
was presented to the hunter's mother,
who invited him to stay overnight. But when
the cooked tiger was put in front of him
he had to say that, as a priest, he did not
eat meat. He was given rice and salad instead.
Then, putting his hands
together, he said a prayer.
The hunter was surprised. 'You priests
are certainly strange,' he said.
'You cannot even eat without a prayer.'
After dinner the hunter led his guest
to a little house full of animal skins.
Tripitaka did not like that very much, so his host
took him instead to a field of red and gold
flowers. There, animals ran to him when he called.
Tripitaka had been asked by the hunter's
mother to say prayers for her dead husband.
So scriptures were read and prayers were
said all through the next day until evening.
That night everyone in the family dreamed the
same dream: the hunter's father had been allowed
to leave the Lower World and was born again as the
child of a rich landowner. This, they were sure,
was a result of Tripitaka's prayers and they all
thanked him. They wanted to give him presents of
silver, but he refused the presents and left
on his journey, with the hunter as his guide.
At the Mountain Between Two
Countries, which was steep and rocky,
the hunter climbed quickly
but Tripitaka was very tired.
'This country to the East,' said the hunter,
'is our land of Tang, and to the West is the
country of the Tartars. I cannot go into
their country, so you must continue alone.'
Feeling a great fear and hopelessness,
Tripitaka held the hunter's arm.
Suddenly, from under the mountain, a voice
cried, again and again, 'The Master has come.'
'Who is that?' Tripitaka asked, fearfully.
'It is the voice of the old monkey calling from
his stone box under the mountain. The story is
that long ago, when the mountain was called the
Mountain of Metal, Wood, Water, Fire and Earth,
a magic monkey was put in
a stone box by angry gods.
He is certainly still alive. You need not
be afraid. We will go down and have a look.'
As the hunter had said, there was
a stone box with a hole in it,
and through the opening they
could see the head of a monkey.
'Master! Master! Free me from here and I will
protect you on your journey to the West!'
The hunter said, 'First, we
want to know more about you.'
'I will not tell you anything,' said
Monkey. 'I wish to speak to the priest.'
'What do you want to say to me?' asked Tripitaka.
'Were you sent by the Emperor of T'ang
to fetch the Scriptures from India?'
'I was.'
'I am the Monkey King and five hundred years ago I
made trouble, so Buddha put me in this stone box.
The Goddess Kuan-yin has visited me. She
said that if I protect the pilgrim on his
way to India I will be forgiven and
freed. So let me be your follower.'
'But how can I get you out of this stone box?'
'If you make a wish, Master, I will be out,'
said Monkey. 'Go to the top of the mountain and
there you will see a rock with letters of gold
written by Buddha himself. Lift
the rock and I will be free.'
'How can we believe him?' the
hunter whispered to Tripitaka.
'It is true! It is true!' screamed
Monkey, from inside his box.
Tripitaka and the hunter climbed up
again to the top of the mountain,
and there they saw golden light pouring
from a rock which had gold writing on it.
Tripitaka went down on his knees and
said, 'If this is the wish of the Gods,
I will take this Monkey with me to
India. Take away this rock and free him.'
A warm and sweet-smelling wind blew across the
mountain and lifted the rock and Buddha's writing
up into the air. Tripitaka and
the hunter returned to Monkey.
'You can come out,' they said. With
a great noise of breaking stone,
Monkey came out of the stone box
and bowed in front of Tripitaka.
He cried, 'Master, I am out,' and then he began
to prepare Tripitaka's horse for the journey.
Tripitaka thanked the hunter for his kindness
and he and Monkey continued their journey.
When Tripitaka and Monkey left the mountain,
a tiger appeared in front of them, showing its
teeth. Monkey seemed very happy. 'He
has come to give me his coat,' he said.
He took a needle from behind his ear and the
needle was immediately transformed into a cudgel.
'It is five hundred years since I
last used this weapon,' he cried.
Look at Monkey! He walks forward bravely, down
comes the cudgel, and the tiger falls dead.
'Sit down,' said Monkey to
Tripitaka, 'while I take his coat.'
Dear Monkey! He took a single hair from his own
tail, blew on it, and said some magic words.
The hair became a sharp little knife, and
with this knife he cut off the tiger's skin.
'Now we can leave this place,' he
said. 'When we reach the next house,
I will make a fine coat from the skin.'
Monkey then explained the magic of his cudgel,
which was not only for killing tigers and dragons,
but also for making rivers go backwards
or starting storms on the sea.
But then he saw a house in some trees,
where they could spend the night.
He got down from his horse
and cried, 'Open the door!'
A very old man, angry at the rude command, began
to push open the door. But seeing Monkey carrying
a tiger skin and looking like a demon, he became
very frightened. Then he saw that Monkey was
with a priest and he was told that Monkey was the
priest's follower. Suddenly, he recognised Monkey.
'You are the Stone Monkey in the stone
box,' said the old man in great surprise.
'How did you get out?'
Monkey told his story and then was asked his age.
'First, how old are you?' asked Monkey.
'One hundred and thirty.'
'You are young enough to be
my great-great-grandson,'
said Monkey. 'I was under that
mountain for five hundred years.'
'True,' said the old man. 'And when I was a boy,
there was grass on your
head and dirt on your face.'
'Yes!' said Monkey. 'I do not
wish to make trouble, but it
is five hundred years since I last washed.
Could you let us have a little hot water?'
When they had both washed,
Monkey took Tripitaka's white
shirt, made himself a tiger-skin coat and
asked, 'How do I look in these clothes?'
'Fine!' said Tripitaka. 'You really look like
a pilgrim!' And he let Monkey keep the shirt.
Many days later, the two travellers
were attacked by six men with swords.
The men demanded their horses and
everything they had with them.
'You are just thieves!' cried Monkey.
'If you give me one seventh of everything
you have ever stolen, I will let you live.'
Angrily, they all hit Monkey
on the head, again and again.
Monkey said, 'Let me know when you are
tired and I will take out my needle.'
Of course the needle from behind Monkey's
ear transformed itself into a cudgel,
and soon he had killed all six of them.
He returned, crying, 'Master, we can
start now. I have killed them all.'
'You should never kill,' said Tripitaka, sadly.
'But I had to! They were going to kill you!'
'It is better for a priest
to die than to kill others.'
'Well, I can tell you that I have
killed quite a lot of people. And I
am still the great Monkey King!' answered Monkey.
'Your bad behaviour in Heaven caused you to
live in a stone box for five hundred years,'
said Tripitaka. 'If you hope to come with me
to India, you will need to change your ways.'
Monkey was very angry that Tripitaka
had spoken to him like that.
'Master,' he shouted, 'I am leaving.'
Tripitaka said nothing, so Monkey leapt up,
ran away and was soon out of Tripitaka's sight.
Tripitaka thought, 'It is no use trying
to teach people who are like that.' So,
putting all the luggage on the horse's
back, he left alone and on foot.
The young priest had not gone far when
he met an old woman carrying a cap.
She asked him why he was travelling
alone without a follower to help him.
'I had a follower, but he behaved badly.
When I told him that, he ran away.'
'That is unfortunate,' she said. 'This
cap belonged to my son, who died.
I can gladly give it to your
follower if he would like it.'
'He ran away to the East,' said Tripitaka.
'Then he will certainly go to my
house and I shall send him back.
If you want him to return, you will need a spell.'
She told him the words. 'You must make him wear
this cap. When he disobeys, say the words of
the spell and he will give you no more trouble.'
The old woman transformed herself into a
golden light and disappeared towards the East.
Tripitaka knew then that she
was really the Goddess Kuan-yin.
Monkey had jumped on to a cloud and was returning
to his cave in the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit.
On the way, he decided to
drink tea with the Dragon King.
When Monkey had told his story, the Dragon
King told him about the value of patience.
'Monkey King, it is necessary to control yourself
if you do not want to spoil all your chances.'
Monkey thought about that and then jumped up.
'Don't say another word!' he said.
'I will return to my Master at once.'
'Master,' said Monkey, when he found Tripitaka
sitting sadly by the side of the road,
'what are you doing, still sitting here?'
'Waiting for you,' he answered.
'I could not continue alone.'
'I only went to drink tea with
the Dragon King,' said Monkey.
'If that is true, you should think
about my thirst and my hunger too.'
Monkey went to their luggage to look
for food and found the gift of the cap.
'If a person wears that cap,' said Tripitaka,
'they can recite the Scriptures
without learning them first.'
'Let me put it on!' cried Monkey.
'Yes, put it on.'
As Monkey put it on, Tripitaka
pretended to eat some dried fruit,
but he was really reciting the magic spell.
'My head is hurting!' screamed Monkey.
Monkey fell on the ground,
trying to take the cap off, but a metal ring
inside the cap was getting tighter and tighter.
Tripitaka stopped reciting the spell because he
was afraid that Monkey would break the metal ring.
The pain in Monkey's head disappeared,
but the cap was still tightly there.
'You have put a spell on me,' cried Monkey.
'Yes,' said Tripitaka. 'It is called the Scripture
of the Tight Cap. Will you make trouble again?'
'Never! I promise,' answered Monkey,
but in his heart he was very angry.
He ran at Tripitaka with his cudgel.
Quickly, the priest again
recited the words of the spell,
and Monkey fell to the ground screaming.
The cudgel dropped from his hand.
'Were you going to hit me?' Tripitaka asked.
'Hit you? I dare not!' cried Monkey.
Tripitaka stopped reciting because he did not
like to see Monkey suffering such terrible pain.
'Who taught you this trick?'
Monkey asked when the pain stopped.
'An old woman who I met recently.'
'Then it was the Goddess Kuan-yin. I will go to
the Southern Ocean and hit her with my cudgel!'
'As she taught me this spell, she can
surely use it herself,' said Tripitaka.
Monkey sat up, holding his head, which
still hurt him. 'I am very sorry,' he said.
'I will travel to India and never leave
you. I will protect you until the end.'
Unable to defend himself,
Monkey put the luggage together, and they started
off again towards the West.
CHAPTER THREE
Tripitaka Finds New Followers
With her magic breath she shouted 'Change!'
She transformed the Dragon into
the horse that he had just eaten.
It was the middle of winter and a
cold wind was blowing from the North.
There was ice everywhere and deep snow was
lying on the ground. But the brave priest,
his follower and the white horse continued
their journey across the mountains.
They were looking down at a river when
suddenly a dragon appeared in it and
then climbed slowly out of the water. While
Monkey and Tripitaka ran and hid, the Dragon,
moving along at speed and without stopping,
opened its mouth and ate the horse.
Monkey left Tripitaka sitting on a rock
and went back to get the horse and luggage,
but he could not find the horse. He took the
luggage to the place where he had left Tripitaka.
'The Dragon is gone,' said Monkey,
'and the horse is too. It probably
ran away because it was frightened.'
'How are we going to find it?' asked Tripitaka.
'Wait here and I will have a look,' said Monkey.
Monkey leapt into the sky and looked
for it with his bright red eyes.
'I cannot see it anywhere,' he told
Tripitaka. 'I think the Dragon ate it.'
'How can I travel if it has been
eaten? It is much too far to walk,'
cried Tripitaka. Poor Tripitaka was
so sad that he could not stop crying.
Monkey, who hated that kind of
attitude, shouted at Tripitaka,
'You look like a fool, sitting there crying!
Wait there while I go after the Dragon.'
'You cannot do anything to the
Dragon if he is in the water,'
said the young priest, still crying.
'And next time he will eat me!
'You are hopeless! Hopeless!'
shouted Monkey, angrier than ever.
'Do you want to sit there
staring at the luggage forever?'
He was still shouting angrily when the voices
of Gods were heard in the sky. 'Monkey,
don't be angry. Priest, don't cry. We
are here to protect you,' they said.
'Then you had better stay here and
look after the Master,' said Monkey.
'I am going to find that
horse! Don't worry about me!'
Tripitaka, feeling better,
asked Monkey to be careful.
Dear Monkey! He pulled his
tiger-skin coat around his body,
picked up his cudgel and walked down to the river.
'You demon fish, return my horse
to me,' he called into the water.
The Dragon leapt out of the river. 'Who is
making all that noise?' it shouted, angrily.
'Come and fight,' shouted Monkey, as he waved
his cudgel. 'And give me back my horse!'
Monkey hit the Dragon's head with his cudgel. The
Dragon came forwards with his mouth wide open.
It was a long and brave fight. They fought
backwards and forwards, round and round, and
up and down until the Dragon began to feel
weak. With a quick turn of his long tail,
he disappeared back into the river. Monkey
shouted for him to come back and fight,
but the Dragon did not listen. Monkey
decided to go back and tell Tripitaka.
When Monkey returned, Tripitaka said
something that Monkey did not like.
'The other day, after you fought the tiger,
you said you could also kill dragons.
I do not understand why you are having
such difficulties with this dragon.'
'Not another word!' he cried. 'I
will soon show you who is master!'
Annoyed, Monkey went back to the river
and used his magic to make a storm. The
Dragon leapt up and shouted, 'What sort of
creature are you? Where do you come from?'
'That is not your business
- just return my horse!'
'How can I? Your horse is inside me. And
if I do not, what will you do to me?'
'Look at this cudgel,' said
Monkey. 'If you do not give
me back the horse, you will
pay for it with your life.'
Again they fought, and then
the Dragon transformed himself
into an insect and disappeared into the long
grass. Beating the grass with his cudgel,
Monkey danced around wildly, trying
to find him. But it was impossible.
So Monkey returned to Tripitaka, who
was feeling quite sorry for himself.
'I will be dead from cold or hunger before
we get across this river,' said Tripitaka.
Monkey danced and jumped and leapt in anger,
but finally he had to ask the Goddess Kuan-yin
for help. When he saw her, he became angry again.
'You told me to look after this priest,' shouted
Monkey. 'So why did you give him a cap that I
cannot take off my head? It gives me terrible
pains when he says the words of the spell!'
The Goddess laughed. 'Because you are so full of
tricks, there is no other way to control you.'
'But what about this dragon?
That is your work too.
Why did you let him eat my Master's
horse? You should be ashamed of yourself!'
'That dragon,' said the Goddess Kuan-yin,
'behaved badly in Heaven. If he carries the priest
of the Emperor T'ang on his journey to India,
he will be forgiven and he knows this. No
ordinary Chinese horse could possibly do it.
I cannot understand why he ate the
horse. I will go with you and find out.'
She got down from her seat inside her cave
and rode on a magic light to find the Dragon.
When the Dragon saw Kuan-yin,
he changed into a human.
'Did you know that this is
Tripitaka's follower?' asked Kuan-yin.
'How could I? I asked him what kind of
creature he was and he shouted at me,
"That is not your business." I ate
his horse because I was hungry.
He never said anything about looking for
Scriptures. He never once used the word "T'ang".'
'Monkey is fonder of showing others his own
powers than explaining anything,' said Kuan-yin.
'But in future, if anyone questions him, he
must say that he is looking for Scriptures.
Then there will be no more trouble.'
The Goddess went to the Dragon and put some drops
of sweet water on him. Then with her magic breath
she shouted 'Change!' She transformed the
Dragon into the horse that he had just eaten.
She told the Dragon to change his bad behaviour
and to promise never to go back to his old ways.
'If you keep this promise, you will be given a
golden body,' she told him,
'and you will be given wisdom.'
The Dragon said, 'Thank you.
I will keep this promise.'
Then the Goddess turned to go, but Monkey held her
arm saying, 'That is not good enough! How can I
help a priest to travel over these mountains with
only a horse? I cannot continue this journey.'
'That is strange,' said the Goddess. 'You
always used to be brave, if nothing else.
But there is one more power I can give you.'
She took three leaves from a tree
and dropped them on Monkey's back,
where they immediately became magic hairs.
'These,' she said, 'will
get you out of any trouble.'
Monkey thanked her. Then he took
the horse and led him to Tripitaka.
'This horse is in much better
condition than the old one.
How did you manage to find it?' asked Tripitaka.
Monkey answered, 'Kuan-yin changed the
Dragon into the horse that he had eaten.'
Tripitaka wanted to say 'thank you' to Kuan-yin,
but Monkey said that she was already far away.
So Tripitaka bowed towards the South. Then
he helped Monkey to prepare their luggage.
'We still need a boat to cross
this river,' said the priest.
'Just sit on the horse and he will
carry you across,' Monkey replied.
But then an old fisherman in a strange
boat appeared. Monkey waved to him.
'We have come from the East to fetch scriptures.
My Master does not know how to get
across the river. Could you take him?
The old fisherman took them all across
the river, without asking for payment.
'Do you know who that fisherman was?' said Monkey.
'He is the God of the River and he did not
help us in our fight against the Dragon.
He knew he had done wrong. That
is why he did not take any money.'
Tripitaka did not know how true that story was.
But he sat on the horse and followed
Monkey along the road to the West.
One evening they saw a group
of houses in the far distance.
'Let me go and see if it is a farm and if
it seems lucky or unlucky,' said Monkey.
A young man in a blue jacket came out of the farm
and tried to walk past Monkey without a word.
But Monkey held his arm tightly
while the young man tried to escape.
'Now, you must not be angry,' laughed Monkey,
holding him even tighter. 'We only
want to know the name of this place.'
The young man, seeing that he could not get away
from Monkey, answered, 'The place is called Kao
Farm and I am Kao Ts'ai. Old Mr Kao has
a daughter of twenty who is unmarried.
Three years ago, a creature took her and has
lived with her here as his wife. Six months ago
the creature locked her in his little house,
and none of the family has seen her since then.
I am going to find someone with strong
enough magic to fight this creature.'
'This is your lucky day,' said Monkey.
'Here I am, and I can help you.
Come, lead us to the master of the house.'
'Your words are true, I hope,' said the young man.
'You will get me into great trouble if you fail.'
'I promise,' said Monkey. 'Now, take us in.'
Seeing the young man returning, old Mr Kao
shouted, 'You fool!' But he quickly became
more polite when he saw the young priest. Seeing
Monkey, though, he said, 'It is surely bad enough
to have a dirty creature living with my daughter.
Now another ugly creature has come to visit me.'
'You have lived a long time but have learned
very little wisdom,' said Monkey. 'You should
not judge people only by appearances.
But I shall return your daughter to you.'
'I do not understand. I thought
you wanted a bed for the night.'
'Yes, we do,' said Monkey. 'But I am also
happy to kill any dirty creatures for you,
for something to do.'
'We have three daughters. Our hope was that the
youngest would marry a farmer and work this farm.
Well, about three years ago, a nice-looking young
man came here and said his name was Pig. He seemed
the right man for our daughter and at first he
worked hard on the farm. But then he started
to change: his nose became longer, his ears
became bigger, he ate more and more. Finally,
he turned into a pig. But that was not all.
He could bring magic winds, he could disappear
and then appear again, he could make stones fly
through the air. And now he keeps our daughter,
Blue Flower, in his little house, and for six
months we have not known if she is alive or dead.'
'Have no fear,' said Monkey. 'I shall catch
him tonight and return your daughter to you.'
'But do you need weapons?'
'I have my weapon already,'
said Monkey, taking his needle from behind
his ear and changing it into an iron cudgel.
'I need only a nice old person to sit with my
Master and talk to him. And now I will leave you!'
Old Mr Kao led Monkey to the little house and
Monkey broke the door with one blow of his hand.
Inside it was dark as the old man
called, 'Number three daughter!'
'Father, I am here.'
Monkey looked hard with his red eyes and saw
a sad sight. The daughter's face was unwashed,
her hair was full of dirt and her lips were pale.
She walked slowly forwards and fell,
crying, into her father's arms.
'Don't make that noise. But where
is the creature?' asked Monkey.
'I do not know,' said the unhappy girl.
'He goes out early in the morning and
does not come back until late at night.'
'Take your daughter back to
the house and stay with her,'
said Monkey to Mr Kao. 'I shall
wait here and end your troubles.'
When the girl and her father had gone, Monkey
transformed himself into a girl who looked like
Blue Flower. Then he waited. Soon stones
came flying through the air and there in
front of him stood a terrible creature. He
had short hairs on his dark skin, a long
nose and enormous ears. He wore a green jacket and
had a spotted handkerchief tied round his head.
Dear Monkey! He did not say hello to the
creature. He lay on the bed making noises
like a person who is ill. When the creature tried
to kiss him, he pushed it hard across the room.
'Why are you angry with me?' asked the creature.
'I am not angry. Get into bed.'
The creature undressed in the dark,
but could not find his wife in the bed.
Then he heard her crying on
the far side of the room.
'Oh, I am so unhappy!'
'What are you complaining
about?' asked the creature.
'Have I not kept my promises to
you? I have worked on the farm,
built walls and dug new fields. You have
all the food and clothes that you need.'
'That is not the problem,' said Monkey in Blue
Flower's voice. 'Today my parents came and
shouted through the wall that you are ugly. And
nobody knows anything about you or who you are.'
'There is no mystery about who I am.
Because I look a little like a pig, I am called
Pigsy. Next time they ask, just tell them that.'
'They are looking for a priest to send you away,'
said Monkey. 'In fact, old Mr Kao has called
the great Monkey King himself to help.'
'If that is true, I am leaving this minute,' cried
the creature. 'That Monkey is very powerful!'
And getting dressed quickly,
he opened the door to leave.
With a magic spell, Monkey
transformed himself back again.
'Look around,' he cried, 'and
you will see that I am Monkey.'
When Pigsy turned and saw Monkey, with
his sharp little teeth and big smile,
his red eyes, flat head and hairy face,
he ran like the wind back to his cave.
Monkey cried after him, 'Where are you going?
If you go up to Heaven, I will follow you.
And if you go down to the deepest part
of Hell, I will follow you there too.'
Monkey followed the creature to his
cave and it came out waving a fork.
They fought together all night, but at last
the creature leapt back into the cave and
locked the door. Monkey now saw the name of
the cave on a rock: it was Cloud-Ladder Cave.
'I had better return to my Master
now, because he might want something,'
Monkey thought. 'I can always
return and catch this creature.'
And leaping from one cloud to
another, he was soon back at the farm.
No one had slept all night,
waiting for Monkey's return.
Tripitaka was sitting with the
old man when Monkey arrived.
'Master, here I am,' he said.
'Did you have to go a long way to
catch the creature?' asked Tripitaka.
'That is no ordinary creature. He used to
live in Heaven, where he was in charge of
water-spirits. But he did wrong and he was
sent down to Earth as a pig-like creature.
He still has all his magic powers. I chased him to
his mountain cave, where he fetched a large fork
and we fought all night. As the sun came up,
he gave up the fight and locked himself in his
cave. I was going to beat down the door, but I
knew it was going to take some time. I thought
Master might be getting anxious
so I wanted to report back here.'
'Monkey King,' said old Mr
Kao, 'you have driven him away,
but he is certain to come back. If you can get him
for us, you can have half of all that is ours.'
'I think you worry too much about
him. He knows that he eats a lot.
But he has also done a lot of work around
here. He feels that his work easily pays
for the cost of feeding him. He is a god
who has been sent to Earth as a punishment.
It seems that he has done no harm
to your daughter,' said Monkey.
'It is true,' said old Mr Kao,
'that he has done her no harm.
But it is very bad for our family
name. Everywhere I go, I hear,
"Mr Kao has taken a dirty creature for his
daughter's husband." What can I say to that?'
'Monkey,' said Tripitaka, 'do you not think that
you should return? Have one more fight with him
and see if you can find a way to
end this difficult situation.'
'Don't worry. I was only having a little
game with him. This time I will catch him
and bring him back here. Look after my Master
until I get back!' Monkey said to Mr Kao.
Monkey disappeared into the clouds
and soon arrived at the cave.
This time, Pigsy was asleep in his cave
when Monkey broke the door in pieces.
Angrily, Pigsy jumped out of
bed and took up his fork again.
'You dirty rat! What do you think you are doing?
It is a crime to break down someone else's door!'
shouted Pigsy. 'I remember you now...'
he said, looking more closely at Monkey.
'You once lived in a cave behind a
Water Curtain. How did you get here?'
'I am a priest now. I am going with
a Chinese pilgrim called Tripitaka
to fetch scriptures from India.'
The fork fell from Pigsy's hand. 'Where is
the pilgrim?' he said. 'Take me to him.'
'Why do you want to see him?' asked Monkey.
'The Goddess Kuan-yin put me here to prepare
myself for the arrival of a pilgrim who I
must follow. After doing this, I will receive
wisdom. I have been waiting for this pilgrim for
years. Why did you not tell me that you are his
follower? Why did you prefer to fight with me?'
'I am not so sure that your story is true. If
you really want to follow my Master to India,
you must promise that this story is
true. Then I will take you to him.'
Pigsy threw himself down on his knees and
bowed repeatedly. 'I promise holy Buddha, this
is true - every word. If it is not true, let the
judges in Heaven cut me into ten thousand pieces.'
'I believe you,' said Monkey, 'but give
me your fork.' Then Monkey took a hair,
blew on it with his magic breath, and
changed it into a long thick string.
He tied Pigsy's hands behind his back, took
him by the ear and pulled him along with him.
When Monkey arrived at Mr Kao's farm
with Pigsy, everyone was very happy.
After hearing Pigsy's story,
Tripitaka told Monkey to untie him.
Tripitaka said some prayers and then
they sat down and ate supper together.
The next day, Tripitaka sat on the white horse
that had been a dragon. Pigsy carried the luggage
and Monkey carried his cudgel,
as they all left for the West.
At last they came to a flat country.
Summer had passed and autumn had come,
and now in front of them was a great, wild river.
Monkey leapt into the air and
looked far down into the water.
'Master,' he reported, 'this will not be easy.
For me, it will not be difficult because I can
jump across in one leap, but for you it
will be impossible. When I looked down,
I saw that this river is twelve
thousand kilometres across.'
Tripitaka was very unhappy but, looking down,
he saw a rock with some writing which said
River of Sands. Under that, in
small letters, were the words:
In the River of Sands, twelve thousand wide,
In Dead Waters, fifteen thousand deep,
Nothing will stay on the water -
Even the lightest flower
goes straight to the bottom.
As they looked, a terrible creature came
towards them through the water. His eyes
were like bright lights, and around his neck were
nine heads. He rushed straight at the pilgrims.
Monkey pushed Tripitaka to
a safe place while Pigsy
attacked the creature with his
fork. The creature fought hard
and the fight was a good one. Monkey was impatient
to join in and at last, with a wild scream,
he leapt at the creature. As he brought his cudgel
down on its head, it disappeared into the water.
Pigsy was very angry. 'Brother, who asked you to
fight my fight? That creature was just getting
tired and I had almost finished
him. You have spoilt everything.'
'I am sorry,' laughed Monkey. 'But I could
not stand and watch. I have not used my
cudgel for months and I got so excited that I
could not stop myself. I wanted to join the fun.'
So, hand in hand, they returned to Tripitaka.
'It will be your turn next time,' promised Pigsy.
'Thank you, but I am really not at my best in
water,' said Monkey. 'I am happier in the clouds
and I have enough tricks on land. If you
can make this creature leave the river,
I will come and help you.'
Pigsy went into the river and
discovered that he had not
lost his water-magic. He soon found the
creature at the bottom of the river.
'You ugly pig,' the creature shouted. 'Can you
not see that I am not an ordinary creature?
I am a god. One day, at a banquet in Heaven,
I accidentally broke the Jade Emperor's bowl.
He was very angry and I was sent down here to the
River of Sands. When I am hungry, as I am now,
I eat people. You would taste very good if I
cut you up and put some sugar and salt on you.'
'You will not eat me! You can eat my fork!'
So again they started fighting, and they fought
for two hours. After that, Pigsy pretended to
be tired and ready to stop. When he left the water
and climbed on to the land, the creature followed.
'Come on,' cried Pigsy. 'With
the hard earth under our feet,
we will have a better fight than we did before.'
'I know what you are trying to do,' said the
creature. 'You are trying to get me out of the
river so your friend can help you. We will go
back in the water and finish the fight there.'
The creature refused to move, so
they fought on the water's edge.
Monkey was watching from a distance.
'Wait here,' he said to Tripitaka,
'while I try one of my tricks.'
Monkey leapt into the air and jumped
straight down at the creature.
But the creature saw him coming
and ran back into the water.
'He is probably not going to
come out again,' Monkey said.
'This is difficult,' said Pigsy.
'What are we going to do?'
'Let's go and see the Master,' said Monkey.
They told Tripitaka, who started crying loudly.
'We will never get across,' he said sadly.
'Don't worry,' Monkey said. 'It
is true that we cannot get across
yet. That creature is a terrible
problem, but he is not going to stop us.'
'What are we going to do?' asked Pigsy.
'Pigsy,' said Monkey, 'stay here with the
Master while I go to the Southern Ocean to
find the Goddess Kuan-yin. This search for the
Scriptures was her idea and she must help us now.'
'You had better go now,' said
Tripitaka, 'and get back here quickly.'
Leaping through the clouds, Monkey reached
the Southern Ocean in no time at all.
He found the Goddess with
the Dragon King's daughter.
'Why are you not looking after
your Master?' she asked at once.
'When we came to the River of Sands,' said Monkey,
'we found a creature that we cannot destroy.
He is a very good fighter. My friend Pigsy tried
hard to beat him, but he was not successful.
This is why I have come to you.'
'Monkey, do you ever listen? It
is the same story again and again.
Why did you not say that you
are with the Priest of T'ang?'
'I suppose we were too busy
trying to catch him,' said Monkey.
'I put him there. I intended him to
help the Master and his pilgrims,'
said Kuan-yin. 'You did not tell him that you
were from China and looking for the Scriptures,
did you? That was your mistake. He
is there to help you, you fool!'
'He is sitting at the bottom of the river
and he is not happy,' said Monkey. 'How
can I make him come out and help us? And how
is Tripitaka going to get across the river?'
Kuan-yin gave a red water-bottle to
her follower Hui-yen. She told him,
'Go with Monkey to the river and shout "Sandy!"
The creature will come out at once. Take him
to the Master. Then put this red water-bottle in
the middle of the nine heads that he wears around
his neck. A ship will be sent from the Gods. It
will carry Tripitaka across the River of Sands.'
Hui-yen went to the river and called, 'Sandy,
Sandy! Come out and meet the Master and his
pilgrims. They are looking for the Scriptures
and they have been here for a long time.'
The creature came up at once. He bowed
politely and asked, 'Where are the pilgrims?'
'They are sitting over there, on
the eastern side,' replied Hui-yen.
'Well,' said Sandy, looking at Pigsy,
'that dirty creature never said a word
about Scriptures and I fought
with him for two whole days.'
Then, seeing Monkey, he cried, 'Him
too? I am not going near them.'
'The first is Pigsy,' said Hui-yen,
'and the second is Monkey. They are both
Tripitaka's followers and both were made
priests by Kuan-yin. You have nothing to fear.
I myself will introduce you to the Master.'
Sandy came out of the river, tidied himself and
went down on his knees in front of Tripitaka.
He said, 'I did not recognise you, Master,
so forgive me for being so impolite.'
'You rude creature,' said Pigsy,
'why did you want to fight with us,
instead of joining us from the beginning?'
'Brother,' laughed Monkey,
'don't be angry with him,
because it is all our fault. We never told
him that we are going to get the Scriptures.'
'Do you really want to be a priest
in our religion?' asked Tripitaka.
Sandy said that he did, so Monkey
was asked to shave Sandy's head.
Monkey took a knife and soon Sandy
had no hair left on his head.
Sandy bowed many times in front of Tripitaka,
but only once in front of Monkey and Pigsy.
Tripitaka liked Sandy's new appearance and
he was very pleased with his new follower.
'You had better be quick and start
your boat-building,' said Hui-yen.
Taking the heads from his neck, Sandy
laid them at the edge of the water
in the shape of a magic square. He put
Kuan-yin's water-bottle in the middle.
At once, the heads and the bottle
became a ship, sent by the Gods.
Tripitaka came down to the water and walked on to
the holy ship. Pigsy supported him on the left,
Sandy on the right. Monkey, behind him, held
on to the white horse, which followed as well
as it could. They soon arrived perfectly
safely at the other side.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Dead King and a Competition
Then Manjusri said a spell, the magician
returned to his tiger shape, and the
God rode him away over the clouds.
Tripitaka sat in the Great Hall of the Wood Temple
reciting the True Scriptures. It was midnight and
he was tired. Soon he lay across his reading
desk and slept. Although his eyes were closed,
he seemed to know what was happening. He heard
a voice outside the Hall whispering 'Master.'
Tripitaka lifted his head. In his dream he saw
a man who was wet from head to foot. When he
looked more closely, he saw that the man was
a king. The King told Tripitaka his story:
'Five years ago, the rain stopped falling,
the grass stopped growing and all my people
were dying of hunger. I prayed to the
Gods, but still the rivers were empty.
But then a magician came who could call the
wind and the rain. I asked him to pray for rain
and he did. The rain came pouring down. For the
next two years I was very kind to this magician.
Then, in spring, when the two of us were
walking by the great water hole in my palace,
I suddenly saw a white light and he pushed
me into the hole. He covered the top of it
and then made a tree grow over it. Pity me! I
have been dead for three years and nobody knows.'
Tripitaka was white with fear, but at last
he said, 'Why did nobody look for you?'
'Ah, with his great power the magician
transformed himself into a man who looked like me.
Now he is the king of my people. But the
Night Spirit blew me to you and gave me
hope with talk of a great Monkey King
who can kill demons with his cudgel.'
'But everybody in your country
thinks that the magician is you.
My follower would be attacked if
he tried to help,' said Tripitaka.
'I have a son, the Prince, who spends most
of his time in the Palace of Golden Bells.
He is not allowed to see his mother, the
Queen, because she might say something. He
knows nothing about his true father except
that I had this piece of white jade.'
'But how can a poor priest like me
get to the Palace of Golden Bells?'
'Tomorrow my son will hunt with three
thousand followers, and when you give
him the jade he will know what to do. But now
I must tell my Queen everything in a dream.'
As he turned to go, the dead
king hit his head on the floor
and Tripitaka woke up. 'Followers!'
he called. 'Where are my followers?'
'Now what?' said Pigsy. 'I was happier with
my old life, although the food was bad.
Now I am woken up in the middle of
the night to look after a priest.'
'I had a strange dream,'
said Tripitaka, uncertainly.
Monkey then came in and said, 'Master, your
dreams come from your waking thoughts because
you worry all the time. I think only of seeing
Buddha in the West, and no dream comes near me.'
But Tripitaka made Monkey
listen to the dead king's story.
'Say no more,' said Monkey. 'This is work for me!'
'The King left this,' said Tripitaka,
remembering, and he gave Monkey the piece of jade.
Dear Monkey! He pulled a hair from his
tail, blew on it, and said a magic spell.
When a beautiful small box appeared,
he put the piece of jade in it.
'In the early morning,' he told Tripitaka,
'read the Scriptures in the Great Hall. I
shall transform myself into a little priest,
five centimetres high, and I shall jump into the
box with the jade. When the Prince opens the box,
I shall jump out, show him the
jade and tell him the dream.'
Both the follower and his teacher
were too excited to sleep that night.
At last, the first light of morning came
in the East. After giving whispered orders
to Pigsy and Sandy to wait quietly for
him, Monkey leapt into the air and flew.
At once, his red eyes found a walled city to the
West. The sadness of its people hung in clouds
over the city. But as Monkey was watching this sad
sight, the gates opened and the huntsmen came out.
It was clear from his fine clothes
which huntsman was the Prince.
'Let me play a trick on
him,' said Monkey to himself.
Dear Monkey! Coming down from his cloud, he
transformed himself into a small woodland animal
and ran in front of the Prince's horse. The Prince
chased it and the huntsmen followed the Prince.
Soon, Monkey had led all
of them to the Wood Temple.
'Of course, I have known of
this place,' said the Prince,
'although I have never visited it. I will go in.'
As the Prince and his followers went into the
Great Hall, everybody welcomed him and bowed,
except Tripitaka. The angry Prince told his
followers to take the priest and tie him up.
But Monkey, now five centimetres high and in
the box, told the Gods to protect Tripitaka,
so the huntsmen could not touch him.
'What magic are you using,' asked
the Prince, 'to protect yourself?'
'I have no magic,' replied Tripitaka. 'I am
only a priest from China, on the way to India
to fetch the Scriptures. But in this box there
is someone who knows something very important.'
As he spoke, Tripitaka opened the box
and out leapt a very small Monkey.
The Prince laughed and said, 'What
can that little creature know!'
But Monkey, to the great surprise of everybody,
used his magic to return to his full size.
'Prince,' he said, 'please listen to me.
Five years ago your country had no food
because no rain fell, but then a magician
came and he brought rain. Is this true?'
'Yes, yes, yes. Go on!'
'And what happened to the magician?'
'Three years ago, when he and my father were
walking in the garden, a magic wind blew a
piece of jade out of the King's hand and the
magician went back to his mountains with it.
But the King, my father, still misses the
magician and he has locked the garden.'
Monkey laughed, but he asked the huntsmen to move
away so he could speak privately to the Prince.
'Sir, it was your father who disappeared. The man
in the palace is the magician who brought rain.'
'That is not true!' said the Prince.
'Here is the piece of jade,' said Monkey.
'You stole the jade!' shouted the
Prince to the priest. 'Take him away!'
Tripitaka shouted fearfully to Monkey,
'Oh Monkey, you fool. What have you done?'
'Wait!' cried Monkey. 'I am the Monkey King
and a follower of Tripitaka. Last night
in this temple your father
came to my Master in a dream.
He told him that the magician had pushed
him into a great water hole in the palace
and changed into a man who looked like
him. He could then pretend to be the king.
I changed into a hunted animal to lead
you here because I wanted to tell you
this. Will you believe my story or not?' The
young Prince did not know what to believe.
'Ride home,' suggested Monkey. 'Take
this piece of jade with you and ask
your mother, the Queen, if the
present king is her husband.'
The young Prince agreed and
went back to the palace.
He found his mother, the Queen, still worried
about a dream she had had the night before.
'Mother,' said the Prince, 'forgive
my words before I speak them.
Compare your life with my
father in the last three years
with the years before that, and tell
me if his love is as warm today.'
In answer the Queen recited:
'Three years ago something warm and kind. These
last three years has been as cold as ice.'
The Prince told his mother everything
that he had heard that day.
Then he showed her the piece of jade.
'Oh, my son,' said the Queen, 'when you came I
was crying because of a dream I had last night.
I dreamt I saw your father. His head was
under water and he was dead. But his soul
had visited a priest of T'ang and asked him to
destroy the magician. He also asked him to save
his own body from where it had been thrown.
Go quickly and ask that priest to help us.'
The young prince ran out, jumped on his horse,
rode back to the Wood Temple and asked the
pilgrims to find his father. So the next
night Monkey and Pigsy were at the gates of the
locked Flower Garden. But Monkey had told Pigsy
that there was gold at the bottom of the water
hole. He had said nothing about the dead king.
Pigsy brought his fork down on the
lock of the gates and broke it.
Inside the garden, Monkey could not stop
himself jumping and shouting happily.
'Brother,' said Pigsy, 'you will
ruin us, making all that noise!'
'Why are you trying to make
me nervous?' said Monkey.
They found the tree that the magician
had planted on top of the hole.
'Now, Pigsy, the gold is hidden
under this tree,' said Monkey.
At once, the fool Pigsy hit the tree
with his fork until it fell down.
Then he used his nose to dig under it until,
about a metre down, he found a big stone.
'Brother!' he cried. 'This is
luck. The gold will be under this.'
Pigsy used his nose again
and lifted the big stone.
Below it something was shining. 'That is
the gold!' cried Pigsy. But looking closer,
they saw it was the light of the
stars and the moon in the water.
Monkey made his cudgel grow until it was
ten metres long, and Pigsy climbed down it.
When he was in the water, he began to swim. Monkey
called down to him, 'The gold is at the bottom.'
So Pigsy dived down and, opening his eyes
again, saw a door with a sign on it that said
The Palace at the Bottom of the Water Hole.
Pigsy went in and a servant called out,
'Great King, something awful has happened
- a priest with a long nose has come in.
The Dragon King of the Water Hole was not
surprised. 'That must be Pigsy,' he explained.
'He has come with the Monkey King
to find the dishonest magician.
Please come in and sit down,' he called to Pigsy.
Pigsy, happy and wet, sat in the best
seat and asked, 'Where is the gold?'
'I am sorry,' said the Dragon King,
'but I live down here in this hole and never
see the sky above. Where would I get gold from?'
'Oh, please!' said Pigsy. 'I know it is here
somewhere, so you had better bring it out.'
'I have one thing that is of value.
You can look,' said the Dragon King.
He led Pigsy to the body of the dead king.
Pigsy went back up to Monkey. Monkey told him
that the body was better than gold. So Pigsy
dived back down again and brought the body up.
Monkey looked closely at the body,
which had been dead for three years.
He asked Pigsy, 'After three years,
how can it still look so fresh?'
'The Dragon King used a magic stone to keep it
like that,' Pigsy answered. 'That was a bit of
luck,' said Monkey. 'But we must still get his
enemy and make him pay for this terrible murder.
And we will be thanked for our good work.
Quickly, Pigsy, carry the King away.'
'Where to?' asked Pigsy.
'To the temple,' said Monkey,
'to show him to Tripitaka.'
'What an idea!' Pigsy complained to himself.
'I was tricked into doing this job. I
do not want to carry this dead body.'
'Hurry, Pigsy,' said Monkey impatiently.
'I am not going to carry it,' said Pigsy.
'If you do not want to be beaten, you
will carry it away now,' said Monkey.
Pigsy feared the cudgel, so he lifted
up the dead body and put it on his back.
'This Monkey,' he said to himself, 'has
played a dirty trick on me, but he will be
sorry. When we get back to the temple, I will tell
Tripitaka that Monkey can bring the dead to life.
Monkey will say that he cannot. And I
will tell Tripitaka to recite the spell.
Monkey's head will hurt, but I will not be
happy until his brains shoot out of his head.'
They took the body back to the
temple and showed it to Tripitaka.
He told Monkey to bring it back to life.
'Only Yama, King of Death,
can do that,' said Monkey.
'Don't believe him!' cried Pigsy.
'Just tighten that cap on his head.'
Poor Monkey! He was soon holding his head in
great pain as Tripitaka recited the spell.
The cap became tighter and tighter.
'But Master,' said Monkey,
'what will happen if I fail?'
'If someone puts a good breath into him,
he will be himself again, even after
three years under water,' said Tripitaka.
Pigsy at once offered his breath, but
Tripitaka knew that it was not pure.
Pigsy had eaten the bodies of humans. So
he asked for Monkey, whose food had been
only apples and food from the forest. Monkey blew
hard into the King's mouth and his soul returned.
Then they all went back to the city to find the
magician who had taken the appearance of the King.
When they were led to him, they refused to bow.
'And who are you?' asked
the false king, surprised.
'My Master,' said Monkey, 'is called
Tripitaka and he is like a younger brother
to the Emperor of China. I am his main
follower.' Then he told the false king
about Pigsy and Sandy, but he introduced
the true king as a temple servant.
The false king wanted to know more about this
'temple servant'. He looked at the true king,
who was afraid of him, but Monkey whispered,
'It is all right! I will speak for you.'
Dear Monkey! He stepped forwards and cried
to the magician in a loud, clear voice.
'Oh, King, this old man has had some
hard times in his life. Five years ago,
disaster came to his family when Heaven sent no
rain and people died because there was no water.
Then from the mountains came a magician who helped
the people. But he then destroyed this man's life.
He pushed him into a great water hole in the
palace and became a false king of the people.
But I have returned life to the dead man and
he should be king again - not this magician.'
The magician felt fear deep in his heart.
Taking a sword from a soldier, he
jumped on a cloud and disappeared.
Both Sandy and Pigsy were very angry. 'Now we
will never be able to find him,' they shouted.
Dear Monkey! Telling Pigsy and Sandy to take
good care of the Prince, the King, his ministers,
the Queen and Tripitaka, he suddenly leapt into
the clouds. Looking down, he saw the magician
running to the North-east. He shouted, 'Where
do you think you are going? Monkey has come!'
'Keep out of my way,' shouted the magician.
Monkey fought a terrible fight with his cudgel
against the magician and his sword, but suddenly
the magician escaped back to the city.
He transformed himself into someone who
looked like Tripitaka. Monkey followed
him but did not dare use his cudgel.
'Which is the real Tripitaka?'
he shouted to Pigsy and Sandy.
'We do not know,' they
answered. 'We have no idea.'
'Master, recite your spell,' called Monkey.
The real Tripitaka at once recited. Pigsy lifted
up his fork as the magician flew up into the air.
Dear Pigsy! He chased the magician,
with Sandy and Monkey close behind him.
What a fight there was then, with three
wild priests hitting and kicking at one
terrible ugly creature again and again. In the
end, Monkey leapt above the creature, and he
was going to cut him in half with his cudgel
when a voice said, 'Monkey, stop the fight.'
It was the God Manjusri. He
had come down from Heaven
with a magic mirror which showed
demons in their true form.
'But I do not understand,' said Monkey.
'In this mirror, the magician is a tiger.'
'Yes,' said Manjusri. 'As a magician,
he was acting under Buddha's orders.'
'What!' cried Monkey. 'The magician is
protected by Buddha! How can that be?'
'Let me explain,' said Manjusri.
'In the beginning, the true king pleased
Buddha so much that he sent me to fetch
him to the Western Heaven. But I said
something to the King that offended him.
He told his soldiers to throw me into the river.
Then Buddha sent this magician to throw the King
into the water hole for three years. But
now, with your help, he has been forgiven.'
'Yes, but the people of the city?' asked Monkey.
'Nothing has happened to them. During these three
years, rain has fallen and there has been peace.'
'And the Queen, who has
slept with him as his wife?'
'He has not been a husband to her,' was
the answer. 'He is not a whole man.'
'Then take him away,' said Monkey. 'He can thank
you for saving him.' Manjusri said a spell,
the magician returned to his tiger shape,
and the God rode him away over the clouds.
As the pilgrims travelled further
on their journey to the West,
they heard a noise that
sounded like a thousand voices.
Dear Monkey! He leapt high into the clouds,
looked down, and at a little distance he saw
a hill outside a city. There, a great crowd of
Buddhist priests were carrying bricks and wood
for building. They were hot and tired and crying
out to the God of Power to give them strength.
'They are going to build
a temple,' thought Monkey.
But suddenly the gates of the city
opened and two Taoist priests came out.
Monkey saw at once that the Buddhists
were afraid of them. He thought,
'This must be the city I have heard about. The
religion of Buddha has been destroyed here.'
Monkey transformed himself into a Taoist magician,
walked towards the two young
Taoist priests and bowed low.
'Can a poor Taoist find food in this city?'
'Oh, yes,' said the priests. 'Even the King is
pleased to give food to Taoists. Twenty years ago
there was not enough food in this place
and it was saved by three Taoist Immortals
who came out of the sky. They can bring
wind or rain or turn stones into gold.'
'Your king is lucky to have these
Immortals here. I would like to meet him.'
'That is no problem,' said the priests.
'But first we must count those Buddhists
and check that they are working well.'
'But they are priests, like us!
We should not make them work.'
'Well, when we had no food, the Buddhists
prayed to Buddha with no success at all.
We Taoists prayed to our gods and we were
successful. So they are not really priests and we
should really destroy their temples. But now
they work for us as builders and cleaners.'
'Then I cannot meet your masters,' Monkey said,
'because I am looking for an uncle
who became a Buddhist priest.'
'That is no problem,' they replied. 'Take our list
and check while we wait here. See
if your uncle is among our priests.'
As Monkey walked towards
the priests with the list,
they all went down on their knees in front of him.
'Please don't harm us, Father!' they said.
'We have all worked hard and we
have never been ill or missed work.'
Monkey told them to get up. He said that they did
not need to fear him - he was
only looking for his uncle.
Hearing this, they all crowded near him.
'Which of us do you want?' they asked.
Monkey laughed. 'You are priests!' he said.
'Why do you work as servants
instead of reading the Scriptures?'
'Ah, don't laugh at us,' cried the
priests. 'Our King has chosen other masters
and we do what they tell us. The three
Immortals are very powerful and can perform
a lot of magic. Now they are using magic to
keep the King young. That is why he obeys them.'
'Why do you not run away?' asked Monkey.
'There are pictures of us
in every part of the country
and there are police everywhere. Many of us
have taken our own lives. But the spirits
tell us that one day a pilgrim will come and
with him is a follower called the Monkey King.
He will use his great powers to
right wrongs, and he will free us.'
Monkey went back to the two Taoist priests.
They asked him if he had found his relative.
'They are all relatives of mine,' replied
Monkey. 'Two hundred on my father's side
and three hundred on my mother's.
I would like you to free them.'
'We cannot do that!' said the priests.
'One or two of them can stop work if they are ill,
but all of them? Impossible! You must be mad!'
'Really?' said Monkey and, taking his
cudgel, he killed them where they stood.
The Buddhists came running. 'Oh, what have you
done!' they said. 'The people will say that we
killed the priests! You must come to the King
at once and explain that you are responsible.'
'I am not what you think I am,' said Monkey.
'I am the one who has come to free you.'
'But you are a murderer!' said the Buddhist
priests. 'The spirits described the one who
will free us. He has a flat head, bright
red eyes, a hairy face and no chin.'
Monkey transformed himself
back from a Taoist priest
into himself, and the Buddhists
bowed in front of him.
'Now go away from here!' cried Monkey. 'But
first I shall give you some protecting magic.'
Dear Monkey! He pulled out a handful of his hairs,
bit them into pieces and gave a
small piece to each of the Buddhists.
'Put this behind your ear. If you are in any
danger, press your ear and call out "Monkey King!"
I will come at once to help you, even
if I am thousands of kilometres away.'
Some of the braver priests tested the
hairs and called out 'Monkey King!' At once
a thunder god with a great cudgel appeared.
'If you say "Quiet", he will disappear,'
Monkey told them. And at the
word 'Quiet', he disappeared.
'Don't go far from this place and
there will be news for you soon,'
Monkey called as the priests departed. He
left to tell Tripitaka what had happened.
As the pilgrims entered the city,
some people were afraid of them.
But an old Buddhist priest recognised Monkey
and shouted, 'I have dreamt of you, Monkey
King. Thanks to you, we are not
ghosts - we are living men.'
That night, Monkey's head was so full of plans for
the next day that he could not sleep. He got up,
looked down into the street and saw that the
Taoists were all celebrating in the temple.
They were led by the three Immortals.
At once, Monkey went to find Pigsy and Sandy.
'Come and have some fun,'
he whispered in Sandy's ear.
'Who wants fun in the middle of
the night?' said Sandy, sleepily.
'The Taoist Temple has plenty of food in it,'
said Monkey. 'Bread, cake, fruit, sweets...'
Pigsy woke up at the sound of a list of
food. 'Brother, I am coming too,' he cried.
When they arrived at the temple, Pigsy could not
wait. 'They are all still praying!' he complained.
'I will soon stop that,' said Monkey,
and he blew hard. A great wind passed through
the temple, blowing everything on to the ground
and putting all the lights out. Frightened
in the dark, all the Taoists ran away.
The three pilgrims went inside and the
three of them finished all the food.
But a little Taoist remembered that he had left
his hand-bell in the temple and went back for it.
He opened the door and saw that all the food was
gone. He ran away to fetch the three Immortals.
When they came, one of them thought
that their gods had eaten the food.
'Let's pray to them,' the Immortal
said, 'for long life for the King.'
Then Monkey jumped out and called to them.
'How could you be such fools?' he said. 'We
are not gods, we are priests from China. We
have eaten all your food and your king will
have to go somewhere else for a long life.'
The Taoist Immortals attacked the pilgrims,
but Monkey took Sandy in one hand and Pigsy in
the other and leapt on to a cloud with them.
In no time, they were back in their beds, in the
hotel where they were staying with Tripitaka.
Next day, the King was very angry when he heard
that three Buddhist pilgrims wanted to see him.
But one of his ministers stepped forward.
'The country of T'ang is fifty
thousand kilometres away,' he said.
'If they really come from there, they
must have magic powers. Let's hear them.'
So the King allowed the pilgrims to come in,
but before they could speak, three important
Taoists came in and made a report to the King.
'Yesterday,' they said, 'these three killed two
of our followers and helped five hundred Buddhist
priests to escape. That night, they went
into our temple and ate all the food.'
The angry King ordered the immediate
death of the three pilgrims.
But before anyone could do anything about the
order, some men arrived asking urgently for rain.
The King thought about the pilgrims' magic powers.
'There will be a rain-making competition between
you and the Immortals,' he said to the pilgrims.
'If you win, you will go free.
If you lose, you will die!'
A tower was quickly built and the King, the
pilgrims and the Immortals went outside.
'You must say what you are going to
pray for,' said Monkey to an Immortal.
'How else will we know if you are successful?'
When the King heard Monkey's words, he said,
'This little priest is a sensible Monkey.'
'There is no need to tell you,' said the
Immortal. 'The King knows what I am going to do.'
'That is not what I mean. We must each have our
programme. If we do not, we will get confused.'
'Yes, fine. I shall cry out four times,' said
the Immortal. 'At the first cry, wind will come;
at the second, clouds will appear in the
sky; at the third, you will hear thunder;
at the fourth, rain will fall. But I shall
cry out once more and the rain will stop.'
'Please begin,' said Monkey. 'This
will be very entertaining for us.'
The tower was ten metres high. On each side
there were the twenty-eight flags of the Great
House of the Moon. There was a long table with
burners on it, which gave a sweet-smelling smoke.
There was a metal plate with the name
of the thunder-spirit written on it
next to each burner. At the foot of the table
there were five great bowls of clear water
with flowers in them. Behind the tower were
some Taoists writing down religious teachings.
The Immortal went to the
tower and climbed to the top.
With his sword in his hand, he recited spells, and
a strong wind was heard and felt in the air above.
'That is bad,' whispered Pigsy. 'He is winning.'
'Quiet, Brother,' whispered
Monkey, 'and leave it to me.'
Dear Monkey! He leapt into the air and
cried, 'Who is in charge of the wind?'
At once, the Old Woman of the Wind appeared.
'I am protecting Tripitaka on his way
to India,' said Monkey. 'We are having
a rain-making competition with the Immortals
here. Why are you helping them instead of us?
Stop that wind!' cried Monkey,
and immediately the wind stopped.
The Immortal now hit the tower hard
and the sky filled with clouds.
'Who is in charge of the clouds?' cried Monkey,
and the Cloud Boy appeared in front of him.
'Stop the clouds!' he commanded,
and again the sky became clear.
The Immortal loosened his hair and then
knocked again on the tower. The Thunder God
and the Mother of Lightning appeared in
the sky, but they bowed towards Monkey.
'The Jade Emperor in Heaven,' they
said, 'ordered us to make a storm.'
'You are allowed to do that,'
said Monkey, 'but not yet.'
As there was no thunder and no lightning,
the Immortal was confused as well as angry.
'Listen well,' said Monkey, up in the sky.
'Here are my orders. When I point my cudgel
upwards once, you will give me wind. Twice, and
you will give me clouds. Three times, thunder
and lightning. And four times, rain. 'And when I
point it a fifth time, you will stop the storm.'
The Immortal sadly left the tower
and went to speak to the King.
'I have been watching,' said the King. 'You have
not produced either wind or rain. What is wrong?'
'The rain-dragons are not at
home today,' said the Immortal.
'Don't believe him!' cried Monkey. 'They are
all at home. That Immortal has no real power
over them. We, the followers of Buddha,
will soon put them to work. You will see!'
'Go to the tower,' said the King to Monkey. 'I
will wait here and see if there is any rain.'
'I need your help too,' said Monkey to Tripitaka.
'Go quietly to the tower and
start reciting your Scriptures.'
'My dear friend,' said Tripitaka, 'I do
not know anything about making rain!'
'Don't let him pull you into this,'
whispered Pigsy to Tripitaka. 'He
will blame you if no rain comes.'
'It is true that you do not know how to
make rain,' said Monkey to Tripitaka. 'But
you know how to recite the Scriptures.
If you do that, I will do the rest.'
Tripitaka went up the tower, sat
down and began silently reciting.
Then Monkey took his cudgel from behind his ear,
and made it bigger until it was nearly a
metre long. He pointed it towards the sky.
The Old Woman of the Wind brought out her bag and
when she opened it, a great wind rushed out of it.
It blew through the city, lifting stones and rocks
high into the air. Monkey pointed again and a
black cloud covered the sky, so the people of the
city could not even see their palace. He pointed
again and loud thunder shook the Earth. When he
pointed a fourth time, rain fell down until it
seemed that the Yellow River had fallen out of the
sky. In seconds, the whole city was under water.
The people of the city were filled with terror
and they all began saying their prayers. The
rain fell from early morning until midday.
'Enough!' cried the King. 'Stop the
rain or nothing will grow this year!'
Monkey at once pointed a
fifth time with his cudgel
and the storm stopped. There
was not even a cloud in the sky.
'Wonderful priests!' cried the happy King. 'So
it is true! There is always a stronger magic
than the strongest! In the past we have seen our
Immortals bring rain successfully. But even they
could not stop it suddenly. Light rain
always continued for the rest of the day.
But these priests stopped the rain completely!'
The Immortal began making excuses.
'You said that the rain-dragons were not at home,'
the King said, 'and that made
it impossible to get rain.
But look! The Buddhists, in their quiet way, made
the rain fall. They were successful, not you.'
Again, the Immortal tried
to change the King's mind,
but Monkey jumped in front
of him and spoke to the King.
'Sir, the Dragon Kings made the wind, the
clouds and the rain. They are still in the sky,
so would you like to see them?'
'Of course!' cried the King. 'I have been king
for a long time, but I have never seen a dragon. I
will reward anyone who can show me one. But if you
do not produce a dragon, you will be punished.'
The Taoists knew quite well that
this was beyond their powers.
They tried, but no dragon answered
their call. Then it was Monkey's turn.
'Are you there?' Monkey called up into the sky.
'Let's have a look at you and your brothers.'
When the four Dragon Kings immediately
appeared through the clouds, the King began
to burn sweet-smelling sticks. His ministers
went down on their knees in front of them.
'I feel ashamed,' said the King. 'I have
troubled them for no reason. Tell them that
I do not want to trouble them anymore. I will find
an opportunity to repay them soon with offerings.'
'Spirits, you can leave us now,'
said Monkey. 'The King will repay you with
offerings at the earliest opportunity.'
The Dragons flew off, each to his own
ocean, and again the sky was clear.
The King gave orders for a banquet the next day,
to thank the pilgrims. All the Buddhists were
invited to return to the city, and they were
welcomed to the banquet by the King himself.
After the banquet, the Buddhist priests
took the pilgrims to the gates of the city,
and they gave Monkey back the hairs he had
given them. Then Monkey said, 'Now you can see
that Buddhism is the True Way, but you
must obey all priests - Taoist priests
too - and become better men. Then these
hills and streams will be safe forever.'
The King himself rode out with the pilgrims
far beyond the city's walls, where
they said goodbye.
CHAPTER FIVE
The River to Heaven
'What has happened to Tripitaka?'
shouted Monkey from the air.
'There is no Tripitaka now!' Pigsy shouted back.
They travelled without stopping for
many days. Then Tripitaka stopped his
horse and said to Monkey, 'Follower,
when and where are we going to rest?'
'Comfort,' answered Monkey, 'is for ordinary
people, so pilgrims cannot expect it. By day
or by night, in wet or dry weather, if there
is a road to travel, we must continue.'
Soon Sandy shouted, 'There is
a great river in front of us!'
'Wait here!' cried Monkey, leaping
high into the air. Soon he was back.
'I cannot see land on the other side,' he
said, 'but I thought I saw a fisherman. He
was standing at the water's edge.
I will ask him about the river.'
But it was not a fisherman that Monkey had seen.
It was a sign that said: The River That Leads to
Heaven. Few people have reached the other side.
When Tripitaka read this, he cried quietly.
'I knew so little of the difficulties in
our way, on the road to India,' he said.
'Listen,' said Pigsy. 'That music means there
are priests praying somewhere near here.
They will tell us how we
can get across the river.'
Following the sound, they soon
saw a village of several hundred
houses. One of them had a flag
at its gate and lights outside.
'I shall go in first,' said Tripitaka,
'because you three look a little strange
and I do not want people to be frightened.'
An old man came to the door and
when he saw Tripitaka he said,
'You have come a little late. The banquet is
almost finished and there is not much to eat.'
'I did not come for the
banquet,' answered Tripitaka.
'I have come from China and I would like
a bed for the night if that is possible.'
'China is a very long way away,' said the old man,
whose name was Ch'en. 'How do I
know that your words are true?'
'My three followers have helped me on the journey.
They have made it possible
for me to travel so far.'
'Well, they had better come in with you.'
The three pilgrims came rushing in out
of the dark, leading the white horse,
carrying the luggage and shouting. The old man
fell on the floor, crying, 'Demons! Help! Demons!'
'Not demons,' said Tripitaka, 'but
my followers. I know they are ugly,
but they are very good at fighting
tigers, dragons and other creatures.'
A group of praying priests jumped up
and ran away in fear. The pilgrims
laughed so loudly at this that
the priests ran even faster.
'You fools!' cried Tripitaka to his followers.
'I have tried so hard to teach you to behave
correctly! Learn this: It is admirable
to be good without being taught.
It is normal to be good after being taught.
Only a fool is taught and then is still
bad. Do you not understand that I
will have to take the blame for this?'
The three stood silently, so the old man believed
that they really were followers of Tripitaka.
He sat Tripitaka in the best place at the table,
and food was brought for them all. Tripitaka
began to recite the Scripture Before Eating,
but Pigsy poured all the food into his mouth
from the bowl before Tripitaka had finished.
As Pigsy was calling 'More food, more food' to the
servants, the old man spoke to Tripitaka. 'Did you
read the sign by the river? You were quite near
the Temple of the Great King of Magic,' he said.
'He is the god who sends us rain. He makes things
grow.' But as he spoke, he began to cry loudly.
'Why are you crying when you
speak of the God?' asked Monkey.
'That god is an angry god and every year he
takes the life of a boy and a girl, so we have
few children here. I have one child, a son called
War Boy, and my brother has one girl, called
Much Gold. This year our family must give the
children to the God and both of them must die.'
'Let me see the boy,' said Monkey.
The boy was brought down from his bed and
ran around eating fruit. Without a word,
Monkey transformed himself into a
boy who looked exactly the same.
'That is unbelievable,' cried the father.
'Look! When I call, both come running to me.'
Monkey then changed back to his own form. 'I
am going to save this child's life,' he said
to the father. 'I will let the Great
King of Magic kill me for the gods.'
The old man's brother was standing
in the doorway, watching and crying.
'I think you are worried about
your daughter,' said Monkey.
'Father,' said the old man, 'I cannot lose her.
She is my only child. Who
will cry for me when I die?'
Monkey pointed at Pigsy. 'If you feed that
long-nosed brother of mine enough,' he said,
'he will transform himself into your girl
and do anything else you ask. The Great
King of Magic can kill us both together.'
Pigsy was shocked. 'Leave
me out of this!' he said.
'You know what they say,' said Monkey.
"'Even a chicken must work for its food.'"
'I am no good at transformations,' complained
Pigsy. 'I can change into a mountain or a tree,
but it is much more difficult
to change into a small girl.'
'Don't believe him,' said Monkey to
the girl's father. 'Bring your child.'
Soon the man returned with his child, and all
the priests and servants asked Pigsy to save her.
'Here she is,' said Monkey.
'Have a look and be quick.'
The fool Pigsy shook his head, said
a spell and cried 'Change!' His head
was now the same as the child's but
his big stomach had not changed.
'You can hit me if you like,' complained
Pigsy, 'but I cannot do any better than that.'
'I can see that I will have to help,' said Monkey.
And he blew on Pigsy, who was soon
like the child from head to foot.
'What happens now?' asked Monkey.
'How are we brought to the God?'
The girl's father came forward. 'It is quite
simple,' he said. 'You sit in two dishes,
two men carry you to the temple, and
then the Great King of Magic eats you.'
'Watch me,' Monkey said to Pigsy. 'While he
is cutting me into pieces, you can run away.'
'But he might begin with the girl!' cried Pigsy.
'No,' said War Boy's father quietly.
'The meal always begins with the boy.'
'Well, that is lucky,' said Pigsy.
Suddenly, they all saw lights outside and
heard the sound of voices as the gate opened.
A loud voice cried, 'Bring
out the boy and the girl!'
The two fathers cried while the Great King's
servants carried the boy and the girl away.
'Great King,' said the villagers,
when everything was ready,
'we now offer you a boy child, War
Boy, and a girl child, Much Gold,
with a pig, a sheep and some wine.'
They then went back to their homes.
'I think I will go home too,' said Pigsy.
'You have no home,' said
Monkey. 'What rubbish you talk!
We have started this job and
now we have to finish it.'
Just then, a strong wind blew through the
door, and as it opened the Great King appeared.
He was a horrible creature, with
eyes like fire and teeth like a pig.
'Which family do you come
from?' asked the Great King.
'The family of Ch'en,' answered Monkey.
The King did not understand why the
boy was so brave. Usually the children
were too frightened to talk
before they were killed.
'You understand that I am now going to eat you?'
'Do it!' said Monkey.
'You are too brave,' said the Great King.
'This time I shall begin with the girl.'
'No, no!' said Pigsy. 'It is never
a good idea to change an old custom.
Do what you usually do - that is always best.'
The fool leapt off his dish, changed back into
Pigsy, took his fork and hit the Great King.
Then he and Monkey leapt into the air,
just as the Great King changed into a
wind and disappeared into the river.
'Oh, let him go now,' said Monkey. 'We will finish
him tomorrow and get our Master across the river.'
So they returned to Ch'en's farm, where they
were soon asleep in the best room in the house.
But under the river, the Great King was unhappy.
He told his fish-servants what had happened.
He told them about Tripitaka, who was like a
god. If somebody ate him, they would never die.
The Great King's fish-sister made a suggestion.
'Start a cold wind and a great fall of snow,
so the river freezes. Then some of us will
change into human form and walk across it,
carrying luggage. Tripitaka is in such a hurry to
get to India that he will walk across it too. When
you hear him above you, heat the ice. The pilgrims
will fall through it and you will have them all.'
Just before the sun came up, Tripitaka and
his followers began to feel cold. 'Pilgrims,'
said Monkey, 'should not
feel either heat or cold.'
But they could not sleep, and when they looked
out of the window everything was white. The
snow was so lovely that they sat and watched it
fall. It was like small pieces of white jade.
Soon servants brought them hot water to wash
in, hot tea to drink and hot food to eat.
They even brought heaters for the rooms, but when
the meal was finished the pilgrims were colder
than ever. By now there was nearly a metre of snow
outside and, seeing this, Tripitaka began to cry.
But towards evening everyone
was talking about the river.
It had frozen and people were walking
on the ice. The next morning the ice was
even thicker and Tripitaka gave thanks to the
Gods for this chance to walk across the river.
'Master,' said Sandy, 'should we not wait
until the ice goes away? Then we can go
across the river in Mr Ch'en's boat.'
'But if we wait until the spring,' said Tripitaka,
'we will lose half a year's travelling. I promised
the Goddess Kuan-yin that the journey would
take three years. Already seven have passed.'
He ordered Pigsy to put the luggage
on the horse, and they left.
When they had gone fifteen or
twenty kilometres across the ice,
Pigsy showed Tripitaka how to
carry his stick across his body.
'Ice often has holes in it,' he explained.
'If you put your foot in a hole, you will go
down into the water. It will close above you
and you will never get out again. Carry your
stick across your body and you will feel safer.'
Monkey looked disbelieving, but
they all did as Pigsy had said.
They rode all night until the sun
began to come up. Then they stopped to
eat some food from their luggage
and then continued towards the West.
But after some time, the ice began to
break and the white horse almost fell.
They continued walking, not knowing that the Great
King and his fish-followers were waiting below.
Suddenly, a great hole opened in the ice.
Monkey at once leapt high into the air,
but the white horse and all the
others fell through it. The Great King
took Tripitaka and carried him down
to the Great Palace under the water.
'Where is my fish-sister?' said the Great King.
'Come, fetch the sharp knives. Let's
eat Tripitaka and live forever.'
'Great King,' answered the Fish-Sister. 'Let's
wait for a couple of days until we can be sure
that his followers cannot spoil our fun.'
The King agreed, and Tripitaka was put in a
great stone box at the back of the palace.
At the same time, Pigsy and Sandy had
managed to get the luggage out of the water
and put it on to the horse's back. They
started swimming back the way they had come.
'What has happened to Tripitaka?'
shouted Monkey from the air.
'There is no Tripitaka now!' Pigsy shouted
back. 'We are going back to Ch'en's farm.'
Mr Ch'en cried uncontrollably when he
heard what had happened to Tripitaka.
'Don't worry,' said Monkey. 'I think
the Master will live for a long time.
Let's dry our clothes and then we will
go back and finish that creature!'
Back at the river, Monkey asked Pigsy to carry
him down while Sandy swam behind them. And at
the bottom of the river they found a gate
with the sign Turtle House written on it.
Monkey whispered, 'You two hide at each side of
the door!' Then he changed himself into a fish and
swam inside. The Great King and his fish-followers
were talking about eating Tripitaka,
but Monkey could not see his Master. Then he
heard Tripitaka crying inside a stone box.
'Don't worry,' said Monkey,
'we will soon get you out.'
'Be quick! Oh, be quick!' cried
Tripitaka from inside his box.
'I am going now,' said Monkey, 'but I
shall return.' And soon he and Pigsy
and Sandy were back at the riverbank.
'I am not at my best in the water, so it
is not a good plan for me to go down again
and fight the Great King,' said Monkey.
'I shall go to the Goddess of the Southern
Ocean for help. I shall not waste a minute.'
Dear Monkey! He shot up in the air on a magic
light, leapt on a cloud and found Kuan-yin.
She was expecting him, but had
not finished getting dressed.
'Let's leave now,' she said, when she saw
Monkey. 'We will go and save Tripitaka.'
Monkey went down on his knees in front of her. 'Do
you not want to finish dressing first?' he asked.
'It is too much trouble,' she
answered. 'I am going like this.'
She left on her cloud, followed by Monkey.
'Well, that was quick!' said Pigsy,
as they appeared. 'You did well to
get a goddess to come immediately, before
she had even finished combing her hair!'
The Goddess sailed low over
the river like a cloud.
Untying the belt from her dress, she tied a basket
to it and pulled the basket through the water.
She repeated the words, 'The dead go, the living
stay,' seven times and pulled the basket up.
There was a gold fish in it. Its
tail moved and its eye stared.
'Go at once into the water and fetch
your Master,' said the Goddess to Monkey.
'But what shall I do with the
Great King?' asked Monkey.
'The Great King is in the basket,' said the
Goddess. 'He used to live in a little pool
in my garden. Every day he used to put his head
out and listen to the Scriptures, until at last
he held great magical powers. But one day
there was a great storm and the water took
him far out to sea. I thought that he might
be using his magic against your Master.
So without stopping to comb my hair, I
made this magic basket to catch him in.'
'If you want to make humans believe in the
Gods,' said Monkey, 'you will wait here. I
will call the people of the village to hear
this story and look at your golden face.'
So men and women, young and old,
were soon hurrying to the river to go down
on their knees in front of the Goddess.
One of them later painted a famous painting
called Kuan-yin with the Fish Basket.
When the Goddess had returned to the
Southern Ocean, Pigsy and Sandy dived
down to the Great King's palace. All the
Great King's fish-followers were dead,
so they soon helped Tripitaka out of the
stone box and took him back to Ch'en's farm.
'We are sorry, Sirs,' said the Ch'en
brothers, 'that you had so many problems.'
'Oh, that is all finished now,' said Monkey.
'The important thing is that next year,
and every other year, your village
will not lose its children.
But we would be glad if you could give
us a boat to carry us across the river.'
All the villagers started to make boats. But
when the pilgrims went back to the river,
they heard a voice: 'Oh, great Monkey
King, you do not need to build a boat.
I will take you.' And above the waters they saw
the white head and the enormous body of a turtle.
'You!' cried Monkey. 'You demon! If you come
near us, I will kill you with my cudgel.'
'Great Monkey King,' said the turtle,
'listen to me. I am not a follower of the Great
King. His palace below the river used to be mine.
Then one day that creature came swimming into
the river killed many of my family and made the
others work for him. I am grateful for all that
you have done - you have made us free again.'
'Promise me and promise the Gods
that this is all true,' said Monkey.
The turtle opened his red mouth wide.
'I promise you and all the Gods.
If I do not take Tripitaka safely across
the river, my bones will turn to water.'
The turtle came out of the river, and people
saw that his back was fifteen metres wide.
'Climb on the turtle's back,' called Monkey
to the others. 'He has promised that we
will be safe. When creatures speak human
language, their words are usually true.'
The white horse was led to the middle of the
turtle's back. Tripitaka stood to the left, Sandy
to the right, and Pigsy behind the horse's tail.
Monkey put himself in front of the horse's head.
'Now, turtle,' he cried. 'Go gently, because if
you do not, there will be a cudgel on your head!'
With this warning, the turtle
moved smoothly over the water.
As the pilgrims left, all the people of
the village bowed and thanked Buddha.
The turtle travelled quickly, and in less
than a day they had arrived at the other side.
Tripitaka said to the turtle, 'I
have nothing that I can give you.
But I would like to thank you
for taking us across the river.'
'Master,' replied the turtle, 'there is something
that you could do for me. I have been trying to
become perfect for about a thousand years, and
that is a long time. I can now use human speech,
but I am still a turtle. Please ask
the Buddha if I can become a human.'
Tripitaka gladly promised
to ask Buddha the question,
and the turtle swam back to his home in the river.
Again Pigsy carried the luggage, and Monkey
helped Tripitaka on to the white horse.
With Sandy behind them, they
soon found the road to the West.
They travelled for many months. The country was
very different from anything they had seen before.
The flowers were like jewels,
the grass looked magical
and there were strange and wonderful trees.
In every village, families were entertaining
priests. On every hill, Immortals were
practising control over their bodies. In every
wood, pilgrims were reciting and singing.
Every night, they found somewhere to stay and left
again at the first light of day. They travelled on
in this way for many more days until suddenly the
light grew bright and they saw a wonderful castle.
'Monkey,' said Tripitaka admiringly,
pointing at it, 'that's a fine place!'
'Do you remember,' said Monkey, 'how often
on our journey you have bowed in front of
the caves and hiding-places and palaces
of false magicians? It is strange that
you do not even get off your horse now -
when you see the Buddha's holy castle!'
So Tripitaka, in great excitement,
jumped down from his horse. When they reached
the gates, a young priest came out to greet them.
He asked, 'Are you the pilgrims who have
come from the East for the Scriptures?'
The boy was dressed in beautiful clothes
and carried a bowl of jade dust in his hand.
Monkey knew him at once, and turned to Tripitaka.
'This,' he said, 'is the Golden-Headed Immortal of
the Jade Temple at the foot of the Holy Mountain.'
'Here you are at last!' said
the Golden-Headed Immortal.
'It is now ten years since the Goddess
Kuan-yin told me to expect your arrival.
Year after year I have waited,
but there has been no sign!'
'Great Immortal,' said Tripitaka, bowing low,
'I cannot thank you enough for your patience.'
Inside the temple, sweet-smelling
hot water was brought to wash in,
and after supper the pilgrims
were shown to their beds.
Early the next day, Tripitaka put
on his finest clothes and jewellery
and greeted the young Immortal.
'That is better,' said the young Immortal.
'Yesterday you looked rather untidy,
but today you look like a true child of Buddha!
You must let me show you the way. Monkey knows it,
but only by air, and you
must travel on the ground.'
Taking Tripitaka by the hand, he led
the pilgrims through the temple gardens
to the back of the building and
up a path to the hill behind.
'Do you see that mountain in front of you?'
said the young Immortal, pointing up. 'That is
where Buddha has his home. I shall now turn back.'
Tripitaka at once began bowing low,
hitting his head on the holy ground.
'If you are going to do that
all the way up,' said Monkey,
'there will not be much of your
head left by the time we get there!'
So Tripitaka stopped bowing and they
climbed some way, walking easily.
Then they came to a fast-moving
river with rough water.
Tripitaka said, 'This cannot be the way.'
But then he saw a bridge and a sign which said
Cloud Reach Bridge. When they came to the bridge,
they saw that it was just some trees laid end to
end. It was only a little wider than a man's hand.
'Monkey!' cried Tripitaka, afraid.
'I cannot walk across that!'
'Yes, yes, people walk across it to get
to the Buddha. Wait while I show you how!'
Dear Monkey! He walked
confidently up to the bridge,
leapt lightly on to it and was
soon waving from the other side.
'Follow me!' he shouted back.
But Pigsy and Sandy repeated to themselves, 'It
cannot be done.' Tripitaka did not move at all.
Monkey leapt back again and
started pulling at Pigsy.
'Fool, follow me across!' But Pigsy lay
flat on the ground and refused to move.
'If you do not come, how will you
ever become a Buddha?' said Monkey.
'Buddha or no Buddha,' answered
Pigsy, 'I will not go on that bridge!'
As they all started arguing, a boatman
appeared with a boat. He was shouting,
'Who wants to cross the river?' But when the
boat came nearer, they saw that it had no bottom.
Monkey, with his sharp eyesight,
had recognised the boatman as the Bringer
of Souls, but he did not tell the others.
'How can you take people across a river
in a bottomless boat?' asked Tripitaka.
'Many pilgrims ask me that,' he answered.
'But since the beginning of time
I have carried too many souls to count.'
'Get in the boat, Master,' said Monkey.
'You will find that it will carry
you quite easily and pleasantly.'
But Tripitaka still did not get in,
so Monkey pushed him into the boat
and Tripitaka immediately fell out into the water.
The boatman caught him and pulled him in again.
He sat there, unhappily squeezing the water
out of his clothes and complaining to Monkey,
who had more important things to think about.
Monkey put Pigsy, Sandy and the white horse
on the side of the boat with Tripitaka.
The boat left and the boatman had
taken them some way down the river
when they saw a body in the water.
Tripitaka looked very frightened.
Monkey laughed. 'Don't be frightened,
Master,' he said. 'That is you.'
And Pigsy cried, 'It is you, it is you!'
The boatman said the same words to Tripitaka,
adding, 'There you go! Congratulations!'
Safe on the other side of the river, Tripitaka
stepped out of the boat. His earthly body was gone
now, gone into the river, and all the foolishness
of his early years was washed away. He now had the
highest wisdom, the Wisdom of the Far Side of
the River, and there is no end to that wisdom.
Before they could thank him, the
boatman and his boat had disappeared,
and now Monkey explained who
the boatman was. Tripitaka began
thanking his followers for all they had
done for him, but Monkey interrupted.
'We should all give thanks to each other,'
he said. 'This journey was too difficult
for one man alone, and without all of us
the Master could not lose his human body.'
With a strange feeling of
lightness and great happiness,
they went up the Holy Mountain. Near the
top, Immortals greeted the pilgrims and
then they were met by the Keeper of
Metal, Wood, Water, Fire and Earth.
'So you are here at last,
Great Priest,' he smiled.
'Your follower Hsuan Tsang, the priest Tripitaka,
has finally arrived,' said Tripitaka, bowing.
The Great Buddha was very pleased at the news
and ordered all the Gods to come to him. Then
his command was shouted for everyone to hear:
'The priest of Tsang must be brought in.'
Tripitaka, Monkey, Pigsy and Sandy all went in,
followed by the white horse and the luggage. In
the Great Hall they first lay flat in front of
Buddha, then bowed to the right and to the left.
Then Tripitaka said, 'The follower of Buddha,
Hsuan Tsang, has come by order of the Emperor
of the great land of T'ang to fetch
the True Scriptures. They will save
all the people of the world. I ask
the Great Buddha for these Scriptures
and also to allow me a quick
return to my own country.'
Then the Great Buddha said these words:
'In all your great Eastern Land there is killing
and lying; there are bad thoughts and bad actions.
But I have three baskets of Scriptures that
can save the people. One contains the Law,
which tells of Heaven. One contains the
Lessons, which tell of Earth. One contains
the Scriptures, which save the Dead. They
are written in fifteen thousand one hundred
and forty-four books. They are the Path to
Perfection, the gate that leads to True Good.
In them you can learn everything about men, birds,
animals, flowers, trees, stars and Earth. I would
like to give them all to you. But the people
of China are too foolish to understand them. So
a few books from each basket will be given
to these priests to take back to the East.'
The pilgrims were taken to a lower room
and shown the books from each basket.
Then they were given food of a beauty and
taste that was unknown on Earth. When they
had finished eating, two followers of Buddha
took them to a special room down some stairs.
The door was opened and a magic light filled the
room. On the many beautiful jewelled boxes were
written the names of the holy books. The two
followers of Buddha led Tripitaka to the place
where the Scriptures lay. After inviting him to
study the titles, they asked Tripitaka to show
them the gifts he had brought for them. They
planned to give him the Scriptures in return.
'I have brought nothing at
all for you,' said Tripitaka.
'On my journey I have sometimes received gifts,
but nobody has ever asked for gifts in return.'
And Monkey, hearing these words, shouted angrily,
'Come with me, Master! We will
see what Buddha says about this!'
One of the two followers said
quickly, 'There is no need to shout.
Come here and fetch your Scriptures.'
The pilgrims hid their anger, put
the Scriptures on the horse's back
and bowed to Buddha's followers.
Then they left, down the mountain.
The Buddha of the Past was sitting in an
upper room and had heard everything the two
followers had said. He was sure they had given the
pilgrims Scriptures with nothing written on them
because they had received no gifts. So he sent a
messenger after the pilgrims and, of course, the
Buddha of the Past was correct. When the pilgrims
opened the Scriptures, they saw only white pages.
Tripitaka cried, 'How can I go back
to the Emperor of T'ang with these?
He will think I am laughing at
him. He will order my death.'
'I know the reason for this. Those two
followers did not get any gifts, so you did
not get any Scriptures! We will have to go back
to Buddha,' said Monkey. They went back at once.
'Listen to this!' shouted Monkey to Buddha.
'They have given us white pages with no words
on them because we did not bring them gifts.'
'You need not shout,' said Buddha, smiling.
'I have sometimes thought that perhaps
it should not be too easy to get the
Scriptures. My two followers expected a
gift because of a bad experience they had.
Not long ago, I gave them permission to go down
the mountain with some Scriptures. After letting
Chao read a few Scriptures to his people, my
followers were given only some rice in return.
The result of hearing these Scriptures was that
his people were protected from all their enemies.
Afterwards I told my two followers that
they had sold the Scriptures too cheaply.
So, you see, they are not to blame. In fact,
these white pages are the True Scriptures.
But the people of China are not very clever,
so they cannot understand such things.
You had better have some
scriptures with writing on them.'
This time Tripitaka offered the two
Buddhist followers the only gift he
could think of - his golden bowl. He had
received this bowl from the Emperor of China,
who told him to use it for collecting
money from kind people on his journey.
The followers accepted the gift, but many of the
Gods laughed because it was such a small present.
As they started to leave again, the Goddess
Kuan-yin appeared in front of Buddha. 'I
found this man for you and he has now fetched the
Scriptures. It took him five thousand and forty
days. The number of chapters in the Scriptures
is five thousand and forty-eight. Please allow
him to make the return journey in eight
days. Then the numbers will be the same.'
'That is a good idea,' said Buddha.
'I will make sure that it is done.'
Buddha then sent for eight of his messengers
and said to them, 'Use your magic powers
and carry Tripitaka back to the East. When he
has left the Scriptures, bring him back here.
All of this must be done in eight days.
Buddha's messengers went immediately to put
Tripitaka and the pilgrims on a magic cloud. And
as the pilgrims flew away, they had little idea
of what was going to happen next.
CHAPTER SIX
The End of the Journey
'Hey!' said Pigsy. 'You have just made the
others Buddhas. Why am I not a Buddha too?'
Many Protectors had watched over Tripitaka
and his followers on their frightening but
wonderful journey to the West. Now
the Protectors appeared to Kuan-yin.
'We wish to report that we
have followed your holy orders.
And, without his knowledge, we have protected the
young Priest of T'ang on his journey to the West.'
'I would like to know,' said the Goddess,
'how the pilgrims behaved on their journey.'
'They were brave, they never gave up, and they
never forgot the importance of their work.
They had many problems along
the way - too many to tell.
But we have a record of
the most difficult fights.'
The Protectors then read to the Goddess
Kuan-yin a list of all the fights that the
pilgrims had fought. They had fought on their
journey against animals, humans and spirits.
Kuan-yin read the list slowly and carefully:
'Tripitaka falls into a hole and is attacked by
a tiger, but is saved by his follower Monkey...'
She finished with Tripitaka losing his human
body when he stepped into the bottomless boat.
'In our religion, nine times
nine is a very important number.
You have listed eighty fights,' said the
Goddess. 'That is one short of the holy
number of eighty-one. There has to be
one more fight, so please arrange it.'
When the Goddess had spoken, the Protectors
immediately stopped the magic wind that
was carrying the pilgrims through space.
Suddenly, and without any warning, the horse,
the Scriptures, the Master, Monkey,
Sandy and Pigsy all fell down to Earth.
Tripitaka looked very surprised to find himself
standing on the ground instead
of flying through the air.
Pigsy laughed and laughed. 'Well, you never know
what is going to happen next, do you?' he said.
'One minute we are rushing at great speed; the
next minute we have both feet on the ground.'
Sandy said, 'I think that
it was very thoughtful of
them. They probably thought we would like a rest.'
'Well,' said Monkey, 'if you
sit without moving for ten days,
then surely you will speed down
nine waterfalls in one day.'
'That is enough rubbish!' said Tripitaka.
'Will you please try to find out where we are.'
'I know, I know,' said Sandy, looking
around. 'Listen to that sound of water.'
'It makes Sandy feel at home,' said Monkey.
'It must be...' Pigsy started to
say, but Sandy interrupted him.
'It is the River That Leads to Heaven and
this is the western riverbank,' Sandy said.
'I recognise it now,' said Tripitaka.
'On the other side is Mr Ch'en's farm,
where you saved the boy and the girl from
the Great King. They were very grateful
to us and wanted to build a boat for us.
In the end, the turtle carried us across.
I remember that on this side there are no houses
at all. How are we going to manage this time?'
'A trick like this from humans is to be expected,'
said Pigsy. 'But not from Buddha's own followers.
Buddha told them to take us straight back
to China. What do they mean by dropping
us in the middle of the journey? They
have left us in a difficult situation.'
'I do not know what you two are complaining
about,' said Sandy. 'The Master is not a common
mortal now. We saw his earthly body go past us
down the Cloud River. He will not sink into the
water this time. With all three of us to help
him, he will surely be able to get across.'
Monkey smiled to himself. 'It is not
going to be as easy as that,' he said.
Why did Monkey say that it was not going
to be easy? They had enough magic power to
cross a thousand rivers! But Monkey knew that the
number 'nine times nine' had not yet been reached.
He knew that Buddha expected one more fight.
They walked along slowly, wondering what to do.
Suddenly, they heard a voice saying, 'Priest
of T'ang, Priest of T'ang, come over here.'
As there was nobody on land
and no boat on the river,
they were very surprised. But suddenly a
large white head appeared in the water.
'Well,' called the turtle, 'I have
been waiting for you all this time.'
'We are very glad to meet you,'
said Monkey. 'Come a little closer.'
Once again, the turtle came out of the river.
Monkey led the white horse and then the pilgrims,
carrying their luggage, on to its back. Pigsy sat
behind its tail, Tripitaka stood on one side of
its head and Sandy on the other. Monkey stood with
one foot on its neck and the other on its head.
Monkey cried, 'Time to go, Old Turtle! Go gently!'
And the turtle swam easily through
the endless waters until evening came.
But when they were nearly at the far side,
the turtle suddenly asked Tripitaka an
important question. 'When I took you across
last time, I asked you to find out from
Buddha how long I have to wait before I become
a human. Did you remember to ask Buddha?'
Unfortunately, Tripitaka had been so busy with
his own problems - losing his mortal body,
going up the mountain, meeting
Buddha and all his followers,
taking the Scriptures - that he had
had no time to think of anything else.
Tripitaka did not want to tell a
lie but he did not know what to say.
When no answer came, the turtle
knew that he had not asked.
It was very annoyed. The turtle did not think it
had asked for much. And it was true, it had not.
'You have broken your promise!' said the
turtle. Without another word, it dived deep
down into the water, leaving the four pilgrims,
the horse and the holy Scriptures in the river.
But there was some good fortune in their
misfortune. First, Tripitaka was now immortal
and could not die under water. Second, the
white horse was really a dragon and could swim
very well. Third, Pigsy and Sandy were
both perfectly happy in the water.
Monkey, of course, just leapt into the air
and helped his Master back to the land.
But the Scriptures and all the luggage were wet,
and as they climbed to the riverbank a great wind
began to blow. The sky grew black and
lightning lit up the sky. Tripitaka
held the Scriptures close to him while Sandy
held the luggage and Pigsy held the white horse.
Monkey knew that this storm was caused
by demons who were trying to steal the
Scriptures. The demons attacked all through the
night, stopping only when the sun began to come
up. And although nobody could see them,
Monkey hit out with his cudgel at them,
holding it in both hands and hitting
first to the right and then to the left.
Tripitaka, who was already wet from
the storm, was left shaking with fear.
'Monkey,' he asked in a shocked
voice, 'what does all this mean?'
'It is jealousy,' answered Monkey. 'The success of
our journey has put jealousy in the heart of every
demon in Heaven and on Earth, because our power
is almost as great as theirs now. It is good that
you kept the Scriptures close to you. That and
my cudgel saved us from losing the holy words.'
Tripitaka then understood and he
thanked Monkey for his protection.
When the sun was hotter, they dried their clothes
and the Scriptures on a rock. Even today this rock
is called The Rock Where the Scriptures Were
Dried. They also dried their shoes and clothes.
When they had almost finished,
some workers came past.
They said, 'Are you not the gentlemen who crossed
the river to fetch the Scriptures from India?'
'That is right,' said Pigsy.
'How do you recognise us?'
'We are from Mr Ch'en's farm,' they answered.
'How far is it from here?' Pigsy asked.
'If you went about twenty kilometres south from
here, you would come to it,' they answered.
'Let's take the Scriptures
and dry them at the farm,'
said Pigsy. 'If we go there, we can sit
down comfortably and get something to eat.'
'I am not going,' said Tripitaka. 'We
can dry the scriptures very well here.'
But then Mr Ch'en himself appeared.
'I see that you have got the Scriptures,'
he said happily. 'Please come home with me!'
'Wait until our Scriptures are dry,' said
Monkey. 'Then we will go home with you.'
'I see that your clothes are wet too.
What has happened to you?' asked Mr Ch'en.
Tripitaka explained about the
white turtle. When he finished,
Mr Ch'en again asked them to follow him home.
In the end, Tripitaka accepted the kind offer.
But when they were collecting the
Scriptures, some of the paper stuck
to the rock, and part of the last sheet of paper
was lost. That is why it is incomplete today.
And still today you can find some writing
on the Rock Where the Scriptures Were Dried.
Tripitaka was very upset. 'We were
not careful enough,' he said sadly.
'Don't get yourself so upset,' said Monkey. 'These
Scriptures are now as they are supposed to be.
Heaven and Earth are not more complete. The
missing part is a secret and it is not meant
to be read by others. You were as careful
as you needed to be. You did nothing wrong.'
Back at the farm, they were welcomed by everybody
there, young and old, and given all the best wine
and food. As a Buddha, though, Tripitaka had
lost his taste for earthly food, and Monkey
wanted only fruit. Sandy ate very little,
and even Pigsy ate less than he had before.
'I do not know why I cannot
eat more,' he said sadly.
After they had eaten, Mr Ch'en said, 'We have had
some pictures painted of you. We wanted to thank
you for saving War Boy and Much Gold.' Then War
Boy and Much Gold came into the room and bowed.
The pilgrims were invited to look at pictures
of themselves in the upstairs room of the farm.
'Yours is very like you,' said Pigsy,
pushing his elbow gently into Monkey's side.
'I think yours is wonderfully like you too,'
said Sandy to Pigsy. 'But the Master's
painting is a little too handsome, really.'
'I think it is very good,' said Tripitaka.
The brothers Ch'en and all their workers
prayed to these pictures every day.
Since their prayers had started, there
had been no more damage from rain
and everybody had had plenty to eat.
'That is a gift from Heaven, not from us,' said
Monkey. 'But we will certainly try to protect you.
You will have many children and those
children will have many children.
Your animals will grow fat, and the wind and
the rain will come at the right time of year.'
The people thanked him again. And
again they offered more fruit and cake.
'It is my bad luck,' said Pigsy. 'I used
to be able to eat a lot, but in those days
no one pushed food on me. Now I eat very
little and everybody wants to see me eat more!'
Because he did not want to
insult the Ch'en family,
Pigsy managed to eat eight or nine dishes
of vegetables and twenty or thirty cakes.
It was now late at night. Tripitaka watched the
Scriptures but he felt nervous. 'I think we should
leave,' he told Monkey. 'If we stay here too
long, people will try to get our secrets from us.'
'I agree with you,' said Monkey. 'We had better
go quietly while everyone is still asleep.'
Pigsy was not a fool now. Sandy and the horse
clearly saw the need to go too. And as the
pilgrims left the farm, a sweet-smelling
wind took them up and away on a cloud.
In the morning, the villagers came again
with offers of fruit and other special food.
It was a terrible surprise when they
found that the pilgrims had disappeared.
They looked everywhere for them, but
after a few hours they gave up hope.
'Why have you taken our living Buddha away?'
they cried to the God of Continuing Days.
Since that time, four times a year, the
villagers have performed a special dance
in front of the pictures of the Master and his
followers. The farm has been turned into a temple
and at every hour of every day there are people
praying on their knees there. Some pray for better
health, some pray for protection on a journey
and others pray for their children's future.
Less than a day after they left Ch'en's farm, the
pilgrims could see in the distance the towers of
Ch'ang-an. It was thirteen years and
nine months since Tripitaka had departed.
The Emperor had ordered a high tower
to be built outside the western gates
and had named it the Scripture Lookout Tower.
And now, looking out, he suddenly saw the whole
western sky fill with a magic light. A minute
later, he noticed a sweet smell in the wind.
The Protectors went with the pilgrims
as far as the gates of the city.
'We prefer to wait here for you,' they said
to Tripitaka. 'The people around here are very
tricky. We do not want them to know that we are
here. And there is no need for your followers
to go with you. But you, Master, had better go
at once and give the Emperor the Scriptures.
We will wait for you here and then we will all
go back and report to Buddha's Holy Mountain.'
'That sounds fine,' said Monkey. 'But
how can the Master carry the Scriptures
and who is going to lead his
horse? We had better go with him.'
'Kuan-yin promised Buddha that the whole journey
would take only eight days. If you all go,
Pigsy will be looking around for food, and you
will lose time,' said one of the Protectors.
'How can you be so rude?' cried
Pigsy. 'Why should I waste time here?
I am as anxious as anyone to get
back to Buddha's Holy Mountain.
The Master has become a Buddha and I intend
to become a Buddha too. You wait here. When
we have given the Emperor the Scriptures, I
will go back with you and will get my reward.'
Then, with Pigsy carrying the luggage, Sandy
leading the horse and Monkey at Tripitaka's side,
they stopped in front of the tower.
The Emperor and his ministers
came down to meet them.
'So my dear brother has come at last!' the Emperor
cried, giving him a horse to ride into the city.
When they were seated in the Great Hall, the
Scriptures were put in front of the Emperor.
Tripitaka told the story of how
he arrived at the Holy Mountain.
He told of the trick played by Buddha's
two followers. He described how he had,
in the end, got the written Scriptures
by giving his golden bowl as a gift.
'There are, in total, five thousand
and forty-eight chapters,' he added.
The Emperor was very happy and he ordered a
banquet. Suddenly, he noticed the three pilgrims,
who were sitting at the far end of the
Hall. He thought they looked unusual.
'I suppose these gentlemen are
foreigners?' said the Emperor.
'My oldest follower, named
Monkey,' said Tripitaka,
'came from the Cave of the Water Curtain
on the Mountain of Flowers and Fruit.
Five hundred years ago he made trouble
in Heaven and Buddha sent him to a stone
prison under a mountain. But he became a holy
man with the help of the Goddess Kuan-yin.
I was able to free him and take him with
me as my follower. He protected me on the
journey to India and he helped me to get the
Scriptures. Without him, I would not be here now.
'My second follower, Pigsy,
came from the Cloud-Ladder Cave
and was at the farm of Mr Kao when I found him.
He has carried the luggage all through our travels
and he was very helpful when
we had to get across rivers.
'My third follower, Sandy,
came from the River of Sands.
He too was brought to me by the Goddess Kuan-yin.
And our horse is not the one that you gave to me.'
'Really?' said the Emperor. 'It looks the
same to me. Why did you change horses?'
'Actually,' said Tripitaka, 'my first horse was
eaten by this one. But Monkey went to Kuan-yin and
the Goddess explained that this horse was really
a son of the Dragon King of the Western Ocean.
He got into some trouble, but he took me to the
West and so his life was saved. He has carried me
well, over the most difficult hills and
mountains. On the way there, I rode on its back;
on the way home, it carried the Scriptures. As
you can imagine, we are all very grateful to him.'
'You have been served well. Tell me,' said
the Emperor, 'how far is it to India?'
'I know only that the summer
turned to winter fourteen times.
There was no day when we did not ride over
hills or mountains. Often we rode through
large forests or crossed great rivers and we
passed through too many countries to count.'
When the banquet was ready, the Emperor asked,
'Do your followers know how to
behave at an Emperor's banquet?'
'I am afraid that they do not,' said
Tripitaka. 'They have spent their time
mostly in rough country conditions.'
'Don't worry,' said the Emperor. 'I will not
blame them. Tell them to come to the banquet.'
There was dancing and singing and music and food
at the banquet, and it was a very happy day.
In the evening, when the meal ended, the pilgrims
went to Tripitaka's old temple in the woods.
There the priests welcomed them with a bow.
This time, inside the temple,
Pigsy did not shout for more food
and Monkey and Sandy behaved perfectly.
All three were now Spirits of Wisdom,
and it was not difficult for them to stay
quiet. When night came, they all went to sleep.
Early next morning, the Emperor
woke and called for his secretaries.
'All night I could not sleep because
I was thinking of good enough words
to thank my brother for his success. I
have now, in my head, a few sentences,
although they are nothing compared
to the wisdom of the Scriptures.'
He asked the secretaries to write down his words,
which later became known to all as the
Introduction to Buddha's Holy Teachings.
The Emperor then asked Tripitaka to read from
some of the Holy Scriptures in the holiest
temple in the city. As the Scriptures were so
valuable, the Emperor ordered his secretaries
to make copies, which were later
sent to every city in China.
As Tripitaka started reading, he smelled the
sweet wind and the Protectors appeared in the
air above the pilgrims. They said, 'You must all
leave the Scriptures and follow us to the West.'
At once Monkey and the others, including the white
horse, got up from the ground. Tripitaka put down
the Scripture that he had started reading. He
was lifted straight up to the Ninth Heaven.
The Emperor and his ministers bowed low
to the ground as they were carried away.
Later, all the people of the city prayed
and read the Great Scriptures, and
their lives were much better after that.
The four pilgrims and the white horse
were taken back to Buddha's Holy Mountain
by the Protectors. There they found that
their great journey had taken just eight days.
On the Holy Mountain they and
all the Gods waited for Buddha.
When everyone was ready, Buddha
appeared and spoke first to Tripitaka.
'Holy priest,' he said, 'in a past life you
were close to me and you were called Golden
Tree. But because you did not obey my teaching,
you had to start life again in the East. Now you
have obeyed me so well that I am making you a
Buddha. Your title will be Buddha of Ability.
'Monkey, because you made trouble in Heaven, you
were put under the Mountain of Metal, Wood, Water,
Fire and Earth. Fortunately, when your time there
was finished, you turned your heart to religion,
to the fight against wrongdoing and the fight for
good. On your recent journey you have done so well
that I am making you a Buddha. You will be
the Buddha of Success in Difficult Times.
'Pigsy, you were a soldier of the water armies
of Heaven. But at a banquet you drank too much
and insulted a goddess. And for this
you were born again in the human world,
looking very much like an animal. When
you were living at the Cloud-Ladder Cave,
you found religion and offered your protection to
Tripitaka on his journey. You are still greedy,
but because you carried the luggage all the way, I
am now making you the Keeper of the Holy Temple.'
'Hey!' said Pigsy. 'You have just made the
others Buddhas. Why am I not a Buddha too?'
'Because,' answered Buddha, 'your conversation
and appearance are still not fine enough
and you still eat too much. But I
have so many followers in the world
that you will get plenty to eat in your new
job. You will have nothing to complain about.'
Pigsy knew that he had to accept his
new job. He did not say another word.
'Sandy, you were a great spirit, but at a banquet
you broke a dish of great value and you were sent
to the human world. There you lived in the
River of Sands and you hungrily ate people.
But after that you found religion. You promised to
protect and help Tripitaka, and you did. Because
of this, I am lifting you high among us and
giving you the title of Golden-Bodied Soldier.'
Sandy bowed. Happily, he accepted his new title.
Then Buddha turned to the white horse. 'You,'
he said, 'were a child of the Dragon King of
the Western Ocean, but you disobeyed your father
and were guilty of bad behaviour. Fortunately,
you found religion. Because you
carried Tripitaka to the West,
and the Holy Scriptures on the return
journey, you too must have your reward.
From this day, you will be one
of the eight Heavenly Dragons.'
The white horse made a sign
to show how grateful it was.
It was led to the back of the Holy Mountain,
where there was the Pool of Magic Dragons,
and it was pushed into the pool. After a short
time, it began to change shape and its coat began
to change to a golden colour. Its four feet rested
on the clouds and then it flew up out of the pool.
It was now changed from a horse to a magic dragon.
'Master,' said Monkey to Tripitaka,
'I am now a Buddha, like you.
I should not have to wear a cap
so that you can control me.'
'It was put on you,' said Tripitaka, 'at a time
when you knew nothing. Then we needed to control
you. Now you are a Buddha and it has gone. Feel
your head and you will see. It is not there now.'
Monkey put his hand on his
head. Tripitaka was right;
the cap had gone. A grateful
smile spread across his face.
All the spirits of Heaven
watched as Tripitaka, Monkey,
Pigsy, Sandy and the horse
received their new, holy titles.
While they went to their places in the Great Hall,
many loud voices began to pray to them.
They were accepted with open arms.
And from that day, Pigsy did not shout for more
food and Monkey and Sandy behaved perfectly.
The reason for this was simple. All three
had received the greatest of gifts - wisdom.
I give this, my book, to you, dear reader, so
you can understand the beauty of Buddha's Land.
It will be a reward for kindness, and it will help
with the suffering of the lost souls of this
world. I would like to think that my readers
will turn their hearts towards the True Way, and
will be born again in the World of True Happiness.
Look at him!
He shuts his eyes, and with one big jump he
passes through the curtain of water.
But there is no water where he has landed.
Instead he finds a great, shining iron bridge
in front of him.
Monkey walked along the bridge and came to
a cave.
Outside the cave there was a sign: This Cave
of the Water Curtain in the Country of the
Mountain of Flowers and Fruit Leads to Heaven.
Monkey laughed and jumped with happiness.
He ran back across the bridge, shut his eyes
and jumped through the waterfall to the other
monkeys.
'Good news!' he shouted.
'Good news!
Come with me, all of you!'
They followed the Stone Monkey to the Cave
of the Water Curtain.
There the Stone Monkey sat down and talked
to them.
'Gentlemen!' he said.
'I have been through the waterfall and have
come back again.
I have given you a home in this cave, so am
I not your king now?'
The monkeys bowed to the Stone Monkey and
they all cried, 'Great King for a thousand
years!'
The Stone Monkey became the Monkey King and
he made other monkeys his ministers.
And all the monkeys were happy.
During the day they walked and played on the
Mountain of Flowers and Fruit, and at night
they slept in the Cave of the Water Curtain.
They had everything they wanted.
Their lives were complete.
The Monkey King enjoyed this simple life for
several hundred years.
But one day at a great party with all the
other monkeys, he suddenly started to cry.
The other monkeys all bowed, saying, 'Why
is our king so sad?'
'Today,' said the Monkey King, 'I am not sad.
But I am worried about the future.
Sadly, the time will come when I will become
old and weak.
Yama, King of Death, is waiting to destroy
me.
I do not want to be born again on Earth.
How can I live for all time among the people
of the sky?'
The monkeys all started to cry, each thinking
of his own mortality.
One of them said, 'Only Buddhas and Immortals
do not go to Yama, King of Death.
Only they live forever.'
'Where can I find these Immortals?'
asked the Monkey King.
'Here on Earth they live in very old caves
far to the West.'
'Tomorrow,' said the Monkey King, 'I shall
say goodbye to you.
I shall go down the mountain and travel to
the end of the world.
I want to learn to live for all time and to
escape from death.'
Next morning, he walked to the sea and sailed
in a boat to the borders of the Southern World.
There he climbed out on to the beach.
And then he walked and walked, through towns
and cities, to the West.
On the way, he learned to wear clothes and
to behave like a human.
But he met humans who wanted only to be rich
and famous.
He met nobody who worried about his mortality.
One day, he came to the Western Ocean, where
he built another boat.
Then he sailed to the Western Continent, where
he saw a very high and beautiful wooded mountain.
At the top of the mountain was the Cave of
the Moon and Three Stars, where the Immortal
Subodhi lived.
Monkey at once bowed and touched the ground
with his head three times.
'Where do you come from?' asked the Immortal.
'I am from the Cave of the Water Curtain,'
said Monkey, 'on the Mountain of Flowers and
Fruit in the country of Ao-lai.'
'That is impossible!'
shouted the Immortal.
'Between there and here are two oceans and
the whole of the Southern Continent.
You are lying!'
'I have sailed across the oceans and walked
over the continents for more than ten years,'
said Monkey.
'At last I have reached here.'
Monkey told the Immortal how he had come from
a magic stone.
The Immortal thought that Monkey was a natural
product of Heaven and Earth, so he agreed
to teach him.
Monkey jumped up and down with happiness.
Day after day, he and the other students learned
to speak and behave correctly.
They learned to write well and to study the
Scriptures.
When they were not studying, the students
grew flowers and trees.
They lit fires and fetched water.
And so Monkey lived in this way for six or
seven years.
Finally, the Immortal sent for Monkey late
one night because he wanted to teach him the
Way of Long Life.
'Come close and listen carefully,' said the
Immortal.
Monkey went down on his knees on the floor
at the Immortal's feet, listening carefully.
The Immortal recited a magic poem with many
lines.
The words shook Monkey's soul and he was never
the same Monkey again.
He thanked the Immortal many times, because
now he knew the Way of Long Life.
Time passed quickly and three years later
the Immortal again invited Monkey to his room,
where he taught him seventy-two transformations.
Monkey was a quick learner and he practised
until he could change himself into something
else, using all seventy-two ways.
One day, when the Immortal and his students
were in front of the cave admiring the evening
view, the Immortal spoke to Monkey.
'Monkey, how much have you learned?'
'Thanks to you,' said Monkey, 'I have learned
a lot.
In addition to changing myself into other
forms, I can already fly.'
'Let me see you do it,' said the Immortal.
Monkey put his feet together, jumped twenty
metres into the air and rode the clouds for
a few minutes.
Then he dropped to the ground, saying, 'You
see, I can ride the clouds.'
'That is not riding the clouds,' said the
Immortal, laughing.
'A real cloud-rider can start in the morning
from the Northern Sea, cross the Eastern,
the Western and the Southern Seas and land
again in one day.'
'It sounds very difficult,' said Monkey.
'Nothing in the world is difficult,' said
the Immortal.
'Only our own thoughts make things seem difficult.
Now I will teach you to fly from one continent
to another.'
The other students laughed, saying, 'If Monkey
flies all that way, he will be able to earn
a living as a postman.'
But Monkey spent all night practising what
the Immortal had taught him.
By morning he could fly wherever he wanted.
One summer day, some students were sitting
under a tree.
A student said, 'Monkey, why do you deserve
private teaching by the Immortal?
Has he taught you the transformations, by
all the seventy-two ways?'
'I have been working on them day and night
and now I can do them all,' said Monkey.
'Could you show us?'
Proudly, Monkey made a magic sign, said some
magic words and transformed himself into a
tree.
'Well done, Monkey, well done!'
shouted the other students.
They all laughed.
The Immortal heard their laughter and he came
running out from the cave.
'Who is making all this noise?' he asked.
Monkey changed himself back from a tree to
a monkey.
He sat with the students again and said, 'Immortal,
we are practising our lessons out here.'
'You were all shouting and laughing!' said
the Immortal, angrily.
'I want to know why.'
Then one student said, 'Monkey was transforming
himself into a tree, just for fun.'
'You, Monkey, come here!'
shouted the Immortal.
'Why do you think I taught you these secrets
of life?
So you can make other people laugh?'
'I am very sorry,' said Monkey.
'I will not punish you,' said the Immortal.
'But you cannot stay here.
You must leave us.'
Monkey started to cry.
'Where can I go?' he asked.
'Go back to where you came from.
Go as quickly as you can.
Never tell anyone that you were a student
of mine.
I am sure that no good will come of your life.'
And so poor Monkey said goodbye to everybody.
He flew back to the Eastern Sea and his home
in the Cave of the Water Curtain on the Mountain
of Flowers and Fruit.
'Little ones,' shouted the Monkey King, 'I
have come back!'
At once, big and small monkeys leapt out of
trees with cries of 'Long live our King!'
Then, pushing each other to get near him,
they cried, 'Why did you go for so long?
We have been watching for your return day
after day!
While you were away, a demon took our cave
and everything we own and many of our children.
Now we dare not sleep, night or day.'
'What demon dares to do this?'
cried Monkey.
'I will make him pay!'
'King, he is called the Destroying Demon,
and he lives north of here.
But he comes and goes like a cloud, like wind,
like rain, like thunder and lightning, so
we do not know where his home is or how far
away.'
'Well, don't worry,' said Monkey.
'I will go and look for him.'
Dear Monkey!
He leapt into the sky and soon saw in front
of him a high mountain and a cave, where the
Destroying Demon was waiting for him.
'Where is the owner of the Cave of the Water
Curtain?'
cried the Demon.
'You have such large eyes,' shouted Monkey,
'but you cannot see Monkey?'
'Oh!
You are not half a metre high!
If I killed such a small creature with my
sword, I would look foolish.'
So the two of them fought with their hands
and feet, hitting and kicking each other.
Soon the Demon was fighting like a wild animal.
Monkey pulled out some hairs from his chest
and, crying 'Change!'
threw them into the air.
At once, they became several hundred small
monkeys.
See how the monkeys jump on the Demon, pulling
and hitting him.
Then Monkey takes up the Demon's great sword
and brings it down on his head, breaking it
in two.
Then, by his magic, he transforms all the
monkeys back into hairs.
When Monkey returned home to the cave on the
Mountain of Flowers and Fruit, he brought
the great sword of the Destroying Demon, and
he amused the other monkeys by teaching them
to make weapons of wood.
Then, one day, the Monkey King called all
the other monkeys to him.
'All this,' he said, pointing to their wooden
weapons, 'is only a game.
We cannot defend ourselves from a real enemy
with these.'
'We know a city that is full of soldiers.
They must have plenty of weapons,' the others
said.
They quickly told Monkey where it was.
'Stay here and amuse yourselves,' Monkey said.
'I will see what I can do.'
Dear Monkey!
Using his magic, he flew to the city and,
with his breath, blew such a strong wind that
all the people locked themselves indoors.
This was his chance.
He found where the weapons were kept, kicked
down the door, and changed his hairs into
thousands of small monkeys who took the weapons.
Carried on a magic wind, they were soon back
at the cave.
The monkeys learned to use the weapons, and
all sorts of wild animals and demon kings
began to call Monkey their king.
But Monkey found his own weapon too heavy,
so he went to the Dragon of the Eastern Sea
in search of something lighter.
The Dragon King welcomed him to the palace,
with his dragon children, dragon grandchildren
and fish soldiers.
Monkey made his request, and a fish soldier
brought out a great sword.
'Too heavy,' said Monkey.
More fish soldiers brought out an enormous
fork.
'Too light,' said Monkey.
The dragon mother and her daughter came from
a back room in the palace and suggested their
magic iron cudgel.
'The Gods used it when they decided how deep
the rivers and the seas should be,' said the
Dragon King.
He agreed that Monkey should have it.
When it was brought, Monkey saw that it was
a thick piece of iron six metres long.
He used his magic to bring it down to less
than a metre.
Then he waved it over his head, striking terror
into everybody in the room.
But now he demanded something to wear, to
go with the weapon, and this was too much.
A pair of cloud-stepping shoes, a cap of red
gold and a coat of light metal were brought
to him, but the angry Dragon King also sent
for his brothers from the Southern, Northern
and Western Seas and told them about Monkey's
many requests.
The Dragon of the South was angry.
'Put him in prison!' he cried.
'No, no,' warned the Dragon King.
'We cannot go near him now.
If he touches us with that iron cudgel, he
will kill us.
Let him keep the clothes.
We will complain to Heaven, and Heaven will
punish him.'
Monkey took the clothes, but he knew that
they were going to complain about him.
Soon after that, the Jade Emperor received
the complaint from the Dragon of the Eastern
Sea.
'How long,' the Jade Emperor asked his ministers,
'has this Monkey existed, and why does he
behave like an Immortal?'
'In the last three hundred years, he has learned
a lot,' said a minister.
'Let's give him work here in Heaven where
we will be able to watch hint.'
This suggestion pleased the Jade Emperor,
and a minister was sent to bring Monkey to
Heaven.
Monkey tidied his clothes, told the older
monkeys to look after the younger ones, and
followed the minister to Heaven.
'I am going to give you a job,' said the Jade
Emperor to Monkey.
'You are going to look after the Apple Garden.'
Monkey was very happy and ran to the Apple
Garden to start work.
He was told that on the outer side of the
garden were special apples.
They were ready to eat once in three thousand
years.
If you ate one of these, you would become
wise, with strong arms and legs and a light
body.
In the middle were trees with apples that
were ready to eat once in six thousand years.
If you ate these, you would go up in the air
and stay there, and would never grow old.
At the back were trees with apples chat were
ready to eat once in nine thousand years.
If you ate these, you would live longer than
Heaven and Earth.
Monkey was very happy with this information.
He watched the trees closely, making up his
mind to eat the fruit before anybody else
got a chance.
Soon, noticing that some apples were ready
to eat, he sent his helpers away.
He climbed into a high tree and ate until
he could eat no more.
When the Queen of Heaven sent her lady assistants
for apples, they were turned away at the gates
by Monkey's helpers.
'We must ask the Monkey King first,' they
said.
'He is resting in one of the trees.'
But when they came to the tree, they found
only Monkey's cap and shoes.
They could not see him.
In fact, Monkey had made himself five centimetres
long and was asleep under a leaf.
The Queen of Heaven's lady assistants picked
three basketfuls from each of the first two
groups of trees.
When they came to the third, they found just
one apple.
When one of the ladies tried to pick it, Monkey
woke up.
At once, he changed back to his true size.
'Who are you?'
shouted Monkey.
The lady assistants went down on their knees.
'Monkey King, don't be angry.
We were sent by the Queen and we could not
find you.
Please forgive us.'
'Get up from your knees,' said Monkey, his
voice full of kindness.
'I have heard that the Queen of Heaven is
having a banquet.
Can you tell me who is invited?'
Monkey was told that all the Immortals, Emperors
of the Four Quarters and Gods of the seas
and hills would be there.
He immediately asked, 'Will I be invited?'
'I have not heard,' said one of the lady assistants.
'We do not know.'
'Quite right, ladies,' said Monkey.
'Just wait here while I go and see.'
Dear Monkey!
He recited some magic lines, crying 'Stay,
stay, stay!'
The lady assistants were suddenly unable to
move while he went off on his magic cloud.
No one had arrived at the banquet yet, but
Monkey could smell the food and wine.
He sent the servants to sleep by magic.
Look at them, how their hands fall to their
sides, their heads drop on to their chests,
their eyes close!
Monkey then took some of the finest and best
of the food and drank glass after glass of
wine until he was quite drunk.
'Bad!
Bad!' he thought to himself.
'I will certainly get into trouble, so I will
go home and sleep.'
But it was too late for that.
Back at the Apple Garden, the Queen's ladies
were finally saved.
They reported that the Monkey King had eaten
many of the biggest apples and had now disappeared.
When the great Goddess Kuan-yin arrived for
the banquet, she found half the food eaten
and all the wine gone.
When the servants were woken, they explained
that the Monkey King had sent them to sleep.
That was the last time they had seen the food
and the wine.
The Jade Emperor was informed and he sent
heavenly soldiers to find Monkey.
Monkey was burned in fire for nine days, and
at the end of it his eyes were red but he
was still alive.
He was attacked with swords and the Gods of
Thunder threw thunder at him.
But nothing could destroy him.
In the end, hearing of this situation, the
great Buddha himself arrived and called Monkey
to him.
'How long ago,' he asked him, 'did you try
to become an Immortal and learn the things
that make you dare behave like this?'
Monkey at once recited:
Born of Earth and Sky, I am a magic Immortal.
I am an old monkey from the Mountain of Flowers
and Fruit;
In the Cave of the Water Curtain, I work and
laugh and play.
I found a friend and teacher who taught me
the Great Secret;
I made myself perfect in the Ways of Immortality,
I learned transformations without limit or
end,
I tired of the narrow world of men, and lived
in the Jade Heaven.
But why should Heaven's palace have only one
emperor?
On Earth king follows king, as the strong
bow to the stronger.
Only a hero fights with the Gods of Gods.
That was what Monkey recited.
Buddha laughed.
'But you are only a monkey-spirit,' he said.
'The Jade Emperor has been making himself
perfect for countless years.
How can you hope to take his place and become
emperor yourself?
You are only an animal that looks half human!
Talk no more of this.'
'Why should he be emperor for all time?
Tell him to go and to give me my chance,'
said Monkey.
'That is all I ask.
And if he will not, I will see that he never
has any peace.'
'What magic have you got that would help you
to take Heaven for yourself?'
'I have a lot of magic,' replied Monkey.
'I can jump through the clouds from continent
to continent.
Am I not good enough to live in the palaces
of Heaven?'
Buddha said, 'If you are really so clever,
you will sit here in my right hand and then
jump off.
If you succeed, you can become the Jade Emperor.
But if you fail, you will go back to Earth
and you will be punished for centuries.'
Monkey thought, 'This Buddha is a complete
fool.
How could I fail to jump off his hand!'
Buddha held out his hand, which looked about
the size of a large leaf.
Monkey took the magic iron cudgel that the
Dragon King had given him, and that he had
transformed into a stick the size of a needle.
He put it behind his ear and then he jumped
from the hand as far and as fast as he could.
He was flying very fast, but Buddha watched
him with the eye of wisdom.
Monkey came at last to five high pink towers.
'This must be the end of the world,' said
Monkey to himself.
'Now I will return to Buddha, become emperor,
and all Heaven will be mine.
But I had better leave some sign that I was
here.'
Pulling out a hair, he changed it into a writing-brush
heavy with ink, and at the bottom of the middle
tower he wrote: The great Monkey King reached
this place.
Then he jumped back to where he had come from.
Standing on Buddha's hand, he said, 'I have
gone and I have returned.
You can tell the Jade Emperor that his job
is mine.'
'You smelly creature,' said Buddha, 'you have
been on my hand all the time.'
'You are completely wrong,' said Monkey.
'I travelled to the end of the world, saw
five pink towers and wrote on one of them.
Would you like me to take you and show you?'
'No need,' said Buddha.
'Just look down.'
Monkey looked down, with his eyes still red
from the nine days of fire.
There, at the bottom of the middle finger
of Buddha's hand, he saw the words "The great
Monkey King reached this place."
Monkey could not speak and his red eyes opened
wide in surprise.
At last he said, 'Impossible!
Impossible!
I wrote that on a tower going high into the
sky.
How did it get on the Buddha's finger?
It is magic!
I shall go back to look!'
Dear Monkey!
He was preparing to jump again when Buddha
pushed him out of the Western Gate of Heaven.
As he did, he changed his five fingers into
Metal, Wood, Water, Fire and Earth.
They became a mountain which pressed poor
Monkey down with its great weight.
The name Mountain of Metal, Wood, Water, Fire
and Earth was written on a large rock on the
mountain.
Under the mountain there was enough air for
Monkey to breathe, but no opening which Monkey's
head or hand could squeeze through.
Buddha then told a spirit to look after Monkey
and give him food and drink.
'And when the days of his punishment are finished,'
said Buddha, 'a man will come here and save
him.'
Time passed, and then one day the Buddha said
to hi