CHAPTER ONE
Staff Plans
July 1956
It seems increasingly likely that I will undertake
the expedition that has been on my mind for
some days.
It is an expedition which I will undertake
alone, in the comfort of Mr Farraday's Ford.
It will take me through much of the finest
countryside in England to the West Country,
and may keep me away from Darlington Hall
for five or six days.
Mr Farraday himself suggested the idea to
me one afternoon almost a fortnight ago, when
I was dusting the paintings in the library.
I was, in fact, on the stepladder when my
employer entered the room.
He was carrying a few books which he presumably
wished to return to the shelves.
He took the opportunity to inform me that
he had arranged to return to the United States
for a period of five weeks between August
and September.
After making this announcement, he put his
books down on a table, sat down and stretched
his legs.
Then he said:
'Stevens, I don't expect you to be locked
up here in this house all the time while I'm
away.
Why don't you take the car and drive off somewhere
for a few days?'
This was so unexpected that, at first, I did
not quite know how to reply.
I certainly thanked him for his consideration,
but I probably said nothing very definite,
for my employer went on:
'I'm serious, Stevens.
I really think you should take a break.
I'll pay for the petrol.
You fellows, you're always locked up in these
big houses.
How do you ever manage to see anything of
this beautiful country of yours?'
'It has been my privilege to see the best
of England over the years, sir, within these
walls,' I replied.
Mr Farraday did not seem to understand this
statement, for he continued:
'I mean it, Stevens.
It's wrong that a man can't explore his own
country.
Take my advice and get out of the house for
a few days.'
As you might expect, I did not accept Mr Farraday's
invitation immediately.
I regarded it as just another example of an
American gentleman's unfamiliarity with English
custom.
The change in my attitude to this same suggestion
over the following days is mainly due to - and
why should I hide it?
- the arrival of Miss Kenton's letter, her
first in almost seven years.
But let me make it immediately clear what
I mean by this.
Miss Kenton's letter gave me an idea concerning
professional matters here at Darlington Hall.
Over the past few months, I have been responsible
for a series of small errors in the performance
of my duties.
None of these errors has been at all serious.
Nevertheless, I am not accustomed to making
errors, and I have found this development
rather upsetting.
The arrival of Miss Kenton's letter, however,
opened my eyes to a simple truth: that these
small errors of recent months have been the
result of a faulty staff plan.
It is, of course, the responsibility of every
butler to take great care when creating a
staff plan.
I agree with the view that the ability to
organize staff duties is central to the skills
of a good butler.
If, therefore, the present staff plan is at
fault, I can only blame myself.
However, in my defence, I must say that my
task has been unusually difficult.
After purchasing Darlington Hall, Mr Farraday
had to remain in the United States for four
months.
He was, however, keen to keep the staff that
had served Lord Darlington so well.
This 'staff' was, in fact, only a small team
of six people who continued to look after
the house for Lord Darlington's relatives
until it was sold.
I regret that, when the purchase was completed,
I could not prevent four of the five other
members of staff leaving for new employment.
Only Mrs Clements and I remained.
I informed my new employer of the situation,
and was told to employ more staff.
But, as you know, it is not easy to find satisfactory
staff nowadays.
By the time Mr Farraday arrived at Darlington
Hall, I had only employed two new people.
When I told him of my difficulties, Mr Farraday
requested a staff plan which would allow the
present staff of four to run the house.
Parts of the house, he said, might have to
be shut down.
He was sure, though, that, with my skill and
experience, I could keep most of the rooms
in use.
There was a time when a staff of twenty-eight
had been employed here at Darlington Hall,
so I felt, at that moment, a little anxious.
Mr Farraday must have noticed the worried
look on my face, although I tried to hide
it from him, because he added:
'Of course, if it is necessary, you may hire
an additional member of staff.
But I would be most grateful if you could
try working with four.'
I spent many hours on the staff plan.
I wanted Mrs Clements to suffer as little
change to her routine as possible.
The two new young girls, Rosemary and Agnes,
were inexperienced, so I could not expect
them to do too much.
This meant, of course, that I undertook for
myself a number of duties which are not usually
part of a butler's life.
I think my staff plan was as good as possible
under the circumstances.
However, I now realize that I gave myself
too much to do.
You may be amazed that I failed to notice
such an obvious weakness in the staff plan.
But an accidental, external circumstance often
brings to one's attention a simple truth.
In this case, the circumstance was the arrival
of Miss Kenton's letter.
The letter, with its happy memories of Darlington
Hall, made me realize that I was making errors
because I was overworked.
And I was overworked because we were understaffed.
I recalled Miss Kenton's great affection for
this house, and her high professional standards.
She was, I knew, just the person I needed
to enable me to complete a fully satisfactory
staff plan for Darlington Hall.
As a result of this analysis of the situation,
I was soon reconsidering Mr Farraday's kind
suggestion.
If I took his advice and had a few days' break,
I would be able to drive to the West Country
and visit Miss Kenton.
I could then explore in more detail her wish
to return to employment here at Darlington
Hall.
I did not, however, discuss the matter with
Mr Farraday for several days.
I needed more time to consider the practicalities
of the expedition: the cost, the time, the
possibility that I might have misunderstood
the purpose of Miss Kenton's letter.
Mr Farraday himself might not have been serious
in his offer.
Eventually, I decided to speak to Mr Farraday
about this as I served afternoon tea in the
drawing room.
Mr Farraday has usually just returned from
a short walk in the grounds at this time,
and he is rarely busy.
In fact, when I bring him afternoon tea, he
often closes the book or journal that he is
reading, stands up and stretches his arms
in front of the windows.
He appears to expect conversation with me.
I had forgotten, however, that, in the afternoon,
Mr Farraday prefers humorous chat to serious
conversation.
He likes to banter.
I should not, therefore, have mentioned the
fact that a former housekeeper of Darlington
Hall was living in the area that I was planning
to visit.
It gave Mr Farraday the opportunity to banter.
He grinned at me and said:
'You surprise me, Stevens.
A lady-friend.
And at your age.'
Lord Darlington would never have placed an
employee in such an embarrassing situation.
But I do not mean to imply that Mr Farraday
is unkind.
He was, I am sure, simply enjoying the sort
of bantering which, in the United States,
may be a sign of a good, friendly understanding
between employer and employee.
Bantering has been a regular feature of our
relationship over the last few months, although
I am still rather unsure of how to respond.
When Mr Farraday first moved into Darlington
Hall, I was once or twice astonished by some
of the things he said to me.
For example, I once asked him if a certain
gentleman was likely to be accompanied by
his wife on his visit to the house.
'God help us if she does come,' Mr Farraday
replied.
'Maybe you could take her out, Stevens.
You could take her to one of those stables
around Mr Morgans farm.
She may be just your type.'
For a moment or two I had no idea what my
employer was saying.
Then I realized that he was making a joke
and I attempted to smile appropriately.
Over the following days I learnt not to be
shocked by my employer's joking remarks.
I smiled in the correct manner whenever I
noticed a bantering tone in his voice.
Nevertheless, I could never be sure what he
expected of me on these occasions.
Should I laugh, or should I respond with a
similar type of remark?
This last possibility has made me quite anxious.
It is possible that my employer considers
my inability to respond to his bantering as
a serious failure of mine.
I did once attempt to banter, but my employer
simply looked up at me and said:
'I beg your pardon, Stevens?'
This was so discouraging that, I must admit,
I have not made any more recent attempts.
But, at the same time, I cannot help feeling
that Mr Farraday is not satisfied with my
various responses to his banter.
You will understand, therefore, how uncomfortable
the situation was for me yesterday afternoon.
If I had replied to my employer's banter at
that moment, the situation would only have
become more embarrassing.
I therefore said nothing.
'I didn't think you were a lady's man, Stevens,'
Mr Farraday went on.
'Keeps the spirit young, I guess.
But then I really don't know if I should help
you with such improper activities.'
I smiled slightly, and continued to stand
there awkwardly, waiting for my employer to
give me permission to undertake the motoring
trip.
After a short delay, Mr Farraday kindly gave
his permission and remembered his generous
offer to pay for the petrol.
So now there seems little reason why I should
not undertake my motoring trip to the West
Country.
I would, of course, have to write to Miss
Kenton to tell her I might be in her area.
I would also need to consider the matter of
suitable clothes for the journey.
There would be other questions concerning
arrangements here in the house during my absence.
But, on the whole, I can see no real reason
why I should not go.
CHAPTER TWO
Unfamiliar Territory
September 1956
Tonight, I have taken a room at a guest house
in the city of Salisbury.
The first day of my trip is completed and
I feel quite satisfied with it.
It is hard to explain my feelings when I finally
left Darlington Hall this morning.
For the first twenty minutes of motoring,
I cannot say that I was filled with excitement
or anticipation.
As I motored in the sunshine, I continued
to be surprised by the familiarity of the
countryside around me.
But eventually the surroundings became unrecognizable
and I knew that I had gone beyond all previous
boundaries.
I confess, I experienced a mild sensation
of alarm.
This increased when I found myself on a road
curving around the edge of a hill.
I could sense the steep drop to my left, although
I could not see it through the trees and thick
bushes that lined the roadside.
I felt now that I had truly left Darlington
Hall behind, and I was suddenly afraid that
I was not on the correct road.
It was only the feeling of a moment, but it
caused me to slow down.
Even when I had assured myself that I was
on the right road, I felt I had to stop the
car for a moment to consider my situation.
I decided to get out and stretch my legs a
little.
When I had stepped out of the car, the feeling
of being halfway up a steep hill increased.
On one side of the road, the bushes and trees
rose steeply on the other, as I looked down
through the trees, I could see the distant
countryside.
I suddenly decided that I wanted a clearer
view, and I walked along the road until I
found a narrow footpath which led up the hill.
I hesitated for a moment, for the path looked
steep and rather rough.
Then I began to climb.
It was a long, hard walk, but it did not cause
me any great difficulty.
Finally, I came out of the trees and saw a
bench in the middle of a small, open area.
I walked to the bench and, turning round,
I was pleased to see that the climb had not
been a waste of time.
I had a most marvellous view of the surrounding
countryside.
There were hundreds of fields bordered by
hedges and trees, and the land rose and fell
gently towards the distant horizon.
As I listened to the sounds of summer and
felt the light wind on my face, my feelings
of alarm and anxiety about leaving my familiar
territory disappeared.
I told myself that it was foolish to worry
about meeting Miss Kenton again.
Indeed, as I looked at that wonderful view,
I even began to feel, for the first time,
a sense of excitement at the journey ahead.
Now, this evening, I find myself in this small
but comfortable guest house not far from the
centre of Salisbury.
The landlady, a woman of about forty, noticed
my car and my high-quality suit, and seems
to think that I am a rather grand visitor.
When I wrote my address in her register as
'Darlington Hall', she looked at me with alarm.
She probably assumed that I was a gentleman
who was accustomed to expensive hotels, and
that I would angrily leave her guest house
as soon as I saw my room.
But my room is very clean, with good-sized
windows overlooking the street.
It is perfectly adequate for my needs.
And here, in the quiet of this room, my thoughts
return to that marvellous view this morning
of the English countryside.
I am willing to believe that other countries
offer more dramatic scenery, although I have
never had the privilege of observing those
sights myself.
But I am confident that the finest English
countryside possesses a quality that the landscapes
of other nations do not possess, the quality
of 'greatness'.
But what exactly is this 'greatness'?
Wiser heads than mine are needed to answer
such a question, but I believe that the beauty
of our land lies in its calmness, in its lack
of obvious drama.
The land, it seems, knows its own beauty,
its own greatness, and feels no need to shout
about it.
This reminds me of a question that has caused
much debate in my profession over the years:
what is a 'great' butler?
There have been very few attempts to answer
this question officially, but great butlers
do seem to me to share one essential quality,
and that is best described by the word dignity.
Of course, one can enjoy most interesting
debates on the subject of what this 'dignity'
actually is.
To me, though, it is the butler's ability
not to abandon his professional self under
any circumstances.
A great butler wears his professionalism as
a decent gentleman wears his suit; he will
take it off when, and only when, he chooses
to.
And this will always be when he is entirely
alone.
It is sometimes said that butlers only truly
exist in England; other countries have manservants.
I believe this may be true.
Continentals are unable to be butlers because
they are incapable of the emotional self-control
- the dignity - which only the English possess.
For this reason, when you think of a great
butler he must, almost by definition, be an
Englishman.
Some of my colleagues have argued that attempts
to analyse greatness are pointless; one can
recognize immediately whether a person does
or does not have it.
But it is surely our professional responsibility
to think deeply about these things.
In this way we may make every effort to achieve
'dignity' for ourselves.
***
I have rarely been happy in strange beds.
It took me a long time to fall asleep last
night, and I woke up over an hour ago while
it was still dark.
I tried to return to sleep but this was impossible.
I decided therefore to get up.
Now, in these quiet moments as I wait for
the world to awake, I am thinking about Miss
Kenton's letter.
I should perhaps explain that her name is
not 'Miss Kenton' now.
She has been 'Mrs Benn' for the last twenty
years.
However, I am unable to think of her as 'Mrs
Benn', as I have not seen her since she married
and moved to the West Country.
I must continue to call her 'Miss Kenton',
for this is how I have always thought of her.
Unfortunately, her letter has given me another
reason for continuing to think of her as 'Miss
Kenton'.
It seems that her marriage has sadly come
to an end.
The letter does not contain details of the
matter, and I would not expect it to.
But Miss Kenton clearly says that she has
now moved out of Mr Benn's house in Helston
and is staying in the neighbouring village
of Little Compton.
It is, of course, tragic that her marriage
has ended in failure.
Miss Kenton is now a lonely, unhappy, middle-aged
woman and probably greatly regrets her decision
to leave Darlington Hall.
It is easy to see why she would want to return
there now.
It is true that she does not say this directly
in her letter, but she speaks about the old
days at Darlington Hall with such affection
and nostalgia that I am sure that this is
her real message.
Of course, Miss Kenton must realize that times
have changed at Darlington Hall since she
left twenty years ago.
It will be my first duty to emphasize this
when we meet.
I will have to explain that the days of working
with a large staff will almost certainly never
return within our lifetime.
But Miss Kenton is an intelligent woman.
She probably already understands these things.
Miss Kenton's letter reveals at times a sense
of hopelessness at her present situation,
which worries me.
She begins one sentence: Although I have no
idea how I shall usefully fill what remains
of my life...
And again, elsewhere, she writes: The rest
of my life stretches out emptily before me.
The tone of most of the letter, however, is
nostalgic.
For example, she writes: This whole incident
reminds me of Alice White.
Do you remember her?
Who could forget her awful vowel sounds and
ungrammatical sentences!
Have you any idea what happened to her?
I have no idea what happened to Alice White,
although it amused me to remember her.
After a very bad start, she became one of
Darlington Hall's most devoted housemaids.
In another part of her letter, Miss Kenton
writes: I was so fond of that view from the
second-floor bedrooms.
I remember the lawn and the hills visible
in the distance.
Is it still like that?
On summer evenings there was a magical quality
to that view.
I will confess to you now that I used to spend
a lot of time in those bedrooms looking out
of the windows.
Then she adds: If this is a painful memory,
forgive me.
But I will never forget standing with you
at one of those bedroom windows.
We were both watching your father.
He was walking backwards and forwards in front
of the summerhouse, looking at the ground.
He seemed to be looking for a precious jewel
that he had dropped there - do you remember?
It surprises me that Miss Kenton can still
remember this incident.
It must have occurred on a summer evening
over thirty years ago.
I can clearly remember climbing to the second-floor
landing.
Evening sunlight shone through the half-open
bedroom doors into the dark corridor.
As I made my way along the corridor, I saw
Miss Kenton standing by a window in one of
the bedrooms.
She turned as I was passing and called softly:
'Mr Stevens, do you have a moment?'
As I entered, Miss Kenton turned back to the
window.
Down below, the shadows of the trees were
falling across the lawn.
To the right, the lawn sloped up towards the
summerhouse.
And there was my father, walking slowly backwards
and forwards, looking anxiously at the ground.
CHAPTER THREE
Small Errors
Miss Kenton and my father arrived at Darlington
Hall at the same time.
This was because the previous housekeeper
and under-butler had decided to marry one
another and leave the profession.
My father had, until this time, been butler
to Mr John Silvers at Loughborough House.
When his employer died, my father lost his
job and his accommodation.
Although he was still, of course, a professional
of the highest class, he was now in his seventies
and was showing signs of his age.
He would have found it difficult to find a
new job in competition with younger butlers.
It therefore seemed reasonable to ask my father
to bring his great experience to Darlington
Hall.
One morning, a short time after my father
and Miss Kenton had joined the staff, I was
working at the table in my office.
Suddenly I heard a knock at my door.
I was a little surprised when Miss Kenton
opened the door and entered before I had given
her permission.
She came in holding a large vase of flowers
and said with a smile:
'Mr Stevens, I thought these would brighten
your room a little.'
'I beg your pardon, Miss Kenton?'
'Your room is so dark and cold, Mr Stevens,
and there's such bright sunshine outside.
I thought these would add a touch of colour.'
'That's very kind of you, Miss Kenton.'
She put her vase down on the table in front
of me, then glanced around my office again.
'If you wish, Mr Stevens, I could bring in
some more flowers for you,' she said.
'Miss Kenton, I appreciate your kindness,'
I replied.
'But this is not a room of entertainment.
More flowers will not be necessary.'
'But surely, Mr Stevens, there's no need to
keep your room so dark and colourless.'
'I prefer my office to be like this, Miss
Kenton, though I appreciate your thoughts.
In fact, since you are here, there was something
I wished to discuss with you.'
'Oh, really, Mr Stevens?'
'Yes, Miss Kenton, just a small matter.
I was walking past the kitchen yesterday when
I heard you calling to someone named William.'
'Did you, Mr Stevens?'
'Indeed, Miss Kenton.
I heard you call several times for "William".
May I ask whom you were talking to?'
'I was talking to your father, Mr Stevens.
There are no other Williams in the house.'
'It is an easy error to make,' I said with
a small smile.
'May I ask you, Miss Kenton, to refer to my
father as "Mr Stevens" in future?
I would be very grateful.'
I returned to my work but, to my surprise,
Miss Kenton did not leave.
'Excuse me, Mr Stevens,' she said after a
moment.
'Yes, Miss Kenton.'
'I'm afraid I don't quite understand.
I'm accustomed to using the servants' first
names.
It is usual, I believe.'
'A most understandable error, Miss Kenton.
However, you must understand that you are
speaking to my father, not just another servant.'
'I still don't understand, Mr Stevens.
I believe I am the housekeeper of this house,
while your father is the under-butler.'
'He is of course the under-butler, as you
say.
But I am surprised that you have not noticed
that he is, in fact, much more than that.'
'I have obviously been very unobservant, Mr
Stevens.
I have only noticed that your father is an
excellent under-butler.'
'Then you have not observed him carefully
enough, Miss Kenton.
If you had, you would have realized that it
is not appropriate for someone of your youth
and inexperience to call my father by his
first name.'
'Mr Stevens, I may not have much experience,
but I am considered by many to be good at
my job.'
'I am sure you are an excellent housekeeper,
Miss Kenton.
But you should have realized that my father
is a man of great experience.
You would learn many things from him if you
observed him more carefully.'
'I am grateful to you for your advice, Mr
Stevens.
So do please tell me, what marvellous things
might I learn from observing your father?'
'That is obvious to anyone with eyes, Miss
Kenton.'
'But I thought we had already agreed, Mr Stevens,
that my powers of observation are not as good
as they should be.'
'Miss Kenton, if you believe that you are
already a perfect housekeeper, you will never
reach the top of your profession.
I have noticed, for example, that you are
still often unsure of where to put certain
items.'
Miss Kenton said nothing for a moment.
Indeed, she looked a little upset.
Then she said:
'I had a little difficulty when I first arrived,
but that is surely only normal.'
'Exactly, Miss Kenton.
If you had observed my father, who arrived
in this house a week after you did, you would
have seen that he made no mistakes at all.
His house knowledge was perfect from the beginning.'
Miss Kenton seemed to think about this before
saying:
'I am sure Mr Stevens senior is very good
at his job, but I assure you, Mr Stevens,
I am very good at mine.
I will remember not to use your father's first
name in future.
Now, please excuse me.'
After this meeting, Miss Kenton made no more
immediate attempts to bring flowers into my
office.
I also noticed that she stopped using my father's
first name.
However, one afternoon two weeks later, she
came into the library where I was working
and said:
'Excuse me, Mr Stevens.
But if you are searching for your dustpan,
it is out in the hall.'
'I beg your pardon, Miss Kenton?'
'Your dustpan, Mr Stevens.
You have left it out here.
Shall I bring it in for you?'
'Miss Kenton, I have not been using a dustpan.'
'Ah, well, then forgive me, Mr Stevens.
I naturally assumed you were using your dustpan
and had left it out in the hall.
I am sorry to have disturbed you.'
She started to leave, but then turned at the
doorway and said:
'Oh, Mr Stevens.
I would return it myself but I am busy at
the moment.
I wonder if you will remember it?'
I waited until Miss Kenton had gone upstairs,
then I crossed the library and looked out
into the hall.
There, in the middle of the polished floor,
was a dustpan.
This was an unimportant, but annoying error.
The dustpan could have been seen not only
from the five ground-floor doorways, but also
from the stairs and the first-floor landings.
Then, as I moved across the hall to pick it
up, I suddenly realized the importance of
this mistake.
My father had been brushing the entrance hall
half an hour earlier.
At first, I found it hard to believe that
my father could have made such an error.
But I soon reminded myself that everybody
makes mistakes from time to time.
I began, instead, to feel annoyed with Miss
Kenton for exaggerating the importance of
such a small mistake.
A week later, as I was coming down the back
corridor from the kitchen, Miss Kenton came
out of her room.
She wanted to tell me that there were remains
of polish on the dining-room silver.
'The end of one of the forks is almost black,'
she informed me.
I thanked her for this information, and she
returned to her room.
She did not need to say, of course, that my
father was responsible for polishing the silver.
There were probably other similar incidents,
which I have now forgotten, but things soon
reached a climax.
One grey, wet afternoon, while I was polishing
Lord Darlington's sporting cups in the games
room, Miss Kenton entered and said from the
door:
'Mr Stevens, I have just noticed something
outside which puzzles me.'
'What is that, Miss Kenton?'
'The Chinaman which normally stands on the
landing is now outside this door.'
'I'm afraid, Miss Kenton, that you are a little
confused.'
'I don't believe I am confused at all, Mr
Stevens.
If you don't believe me, perhaps you will
come and see for yourself?'
'I am busy at present, Miss Kenton.'
'But Mr Stevens, you must come and see for
yourself if you don't believe me.'
'I will look at it later, Miss Kenton.
There is no hurry.'
'Does that mean that you believe me, Mr Stevens?'
'I don't know, Miss Kenton.
I must see for myself.'
'Then come and see.'
'I have already told you, Miss Kenton, I am
busy.'
I returned to my business, but Miss Kenton
remained in the doorway, observing me.
Eventually, she said:
'I can see you don't have much more to do,
Mr Stevens.
I'll wait outside for you.'
With those words, she left the room.
I spent as long as I could polishing Lord
Darlington's cups in the games room, thinking
that Miss Kenton would soon become bored with
waiting for me.
Eventually, however, there were no more tasks
for me to do and I had to leave.
To my surprise, when I walked out into the
corridor, I saw that Miss Kenton was still
waiting for me.
I turned and walked away from her as quickly
as I could, but she ran and stood in front
of me.
I was forced to stop.
'Mr Stevens,' she said.
'That is the incorrect Chinaman, do you not
agree?'
'Miss Kenton, I am very busy.
I am surprised you have nothing better to
do than stand in corridors all day.'
'Mr Stevens, is that the correct Chinaman
or is it not?'
'Miss Kenton, I must ask you to keep your
voice down.'
'And I must ask you, Mr Stevens, to turn around
and look at that Chinaman.'
'Miss Kenton, please!
What would the other employees think if they
heard us shouting at the top of our voices
about Chinamen?'
'The fact is, Mr Stevens, all the Chinamen
in this house have been dirty for some time!
And now they are in incorrect positions!'
'Miss Kenton, you are being ridiculous.
Kindly let me pass.'
'Mr Stevens, will you kindly look at the Chinaman
behind you?'
'If it is so important to you, Miss Kenton,
I admit that it is possible that the Chinaman
has been placed incorrectly.
But I really cannot understand why you are
so worried about such unimportant errors.'
'These errors may be unimportant, Mr Stevens,
but you must realize their larger significance.'
'Miss Kenton, I do not understand you.
Would you kindly let me pass?'
'The fact is, Mr Stevens,' she said, 'your
father has too much responsibility for a man
of his age.
He is too old to cope with it.
He is making more and more mistakes.
If you don't take notice of them now, something
much more serious is going to happen.'
'Miss Kenton, you are making yourself look
foolish.'
'I'm sorry, Mr Stevens, but I must go on.
I believe there are many jobs your father
should not be expected to do at his age.
He should not have to carry heavy trays.
Have you seen the way his hands tremble?
One day soon, a heavy tray will fall from
his hands on to a lady's or gentleman's lap.
And furthermore, Mr Stevens - and I am very
sorry to say this - I have noticed your father's
nose.'
'Have you indeed, Miss Kenton?'
'Yes, I have, Mr Stevens.
The evening before last I watched your father
walking very slowly towards the dining room
with his tray.
I regret to say that I clearly saw a large
drop on the end of his nose hanging over the
soup bowls.
If a lady or gentleman had seen that, Mr Stevens,
I am sure they would have lost their appetite.'
CHAPTER FOUR
An Embarrassing Fall
The more I think about it, the less certain
I am that Miss Kenton spoke to me on that
day as boldly as I have just reported.
It was still early in our relationship, and
I am sure that she did not say things like:
'These errors may be unimportant, but you
must realize their larger significance.'
In fact, I think it was Lord Darlington who
used those words.
March 1923
Two months after my conversation with Miss
Kenton about the Chinaman, Lord Darlington
called me into his study.
The situation concerning my father had become
very serious because it was after he had had
his accident.
Whenever Lord Darlington wished to speak to
me about something, he often pretended to
be reading a book.
He would wait for me to pass, then he would
look up from his book and say:
'Oh, Stevens.
There was something I meant to say to you.'
I am describing this small detail in order
to show that Lord Darlington was a shy and
modest man.
A lot of nonsense has been spoken and written
recently about his lordship.
Many reports have criticized the part he played
in this country before and during the war.
They claim that he was a selfish and foolish
man.
Let me say here that all these reports about
him are completely false.
Lord Darlington was a good man with a good
heart.
I am proud to have given my best years of
service to such a true gentleman.
On this particular afternoon, Lord Darlington
hardly looked up from his book as he asked:
'Your father feeling better now, Stevens?'
'Much better now, thank you, sir.'
'Very pleased to hear that.
Very pleased.'
There was a short, uncomfortable pause, then
Lord Darlington said:
'I wonder, Stevens, have there been any - well
- signs at all?
Any indications that your father might prefer
an easier life these days?
Work a little less hard, I mean?'
'I believe, sir, that you can still completely
depend on him to do his job.
It is true that he has made one or two errors
recently, but none of them has been serious.'
'That's true, Stevens.
But nevertheless, we don't want to see an
accident like that again, do we?
It could happen during dinner, while he was
serving at table.'
'It is possible, sir.'
'Listen, Stevens.
The first guests will be arriving here for
the conference in less than a fortnight.
What happens within this house may be very
important for our country.
I am not exaggerating, Stevens.
We cannot possibly afford to have any accidents
then.'
'Indeed not, sir.'
'I am not suggesting that your father should
leave us, Stevens.
I am simply asking you to reconsider his duties.'
His lordship then looked down again into his
book and said: 'These errors may be unimportant,
Stevens, but you must realize their larger
significance.
Another accident might threaten the success
of our conference in two weeks' time.'
'Indeed, sir.
I fully understand.'
Lord Darlington had witnessed my father's
accident himself a week or so earlier.
He had been with two guests, a young lady
and gentleman, in the summerhouse and had
seen my father crossing the lawn with a tray
of refreshments.
As my father began to climb the stone steps
to the summerhouse, however, he fell.
By the time I reached the scene of the accident,
his lordship and his guests had turned my
father on to his side and had tried to make
him comfortable.
My father was unconscious, and his face was
strangely grey in colour.
With the help of a wheelchair, my father was
transported with difficulty into the house.
By the time Doctor Meredith arrived, my father
had woken up and was beginning to feel better.
The whole incident was clearly a great embarrassment
to my father, but he soon forgot about it
and returned to work.
It was not easy, therefore, for me to tell
him that it had been decided to reduce his
work load.
He was a proud man.
Another difficulty for me was the fact that
my father and I hardly ever talked to each
other.
For several years, even the smallest professional
conversation had seemed to embarrass us.
I had never really understood why.
In the end I decided to talk to my father
privately in his room.
Early one morning, I climbed up to the top
floor of the house and knocked gently on his
door.
My father was sitting on the edge of his bed
in full uniform.
He had obviously been sitting there for some
time.
'Ah,' I said, and gave a short laugh.
'I thought Father would be up and ready for
the day.'
'I've been up and ready for the last three
hours,' he said, looking me up and down rather
coldly.
'I have come here to tell you something, Father.'
'Then be quick.
I haven't all morning to listen to you.'
'The fact is, Father has been making a number
of errors recently.
His lordship believes - and I agree with him
- that he is working too hard for a man of
his age.
His lordship is very worried about the smooth
running of this house.
He does not want any more unfortunate accidents,
especially during next week's important international
conference.'
My father's face, in the half-light, showed
no emotion.
'It has been decided, therefore, that Father
should no longer have to serve at table.'
'I have served at table every day for the
last fifty-four years,' my father said slowly
and calmly.
'Furthermore,' I continued, 'it has been decided
that Father should not carry trays.
I have here a list of his new duties.'
I did not wish, for some reason, to hand him
the piece of paper directly, so I placed it
on the end of his bed.
My father glanced at it, then looked at me
again.
Eventually he said:
'I only fell that time because of the steps.
They're not straight.'
'Indeed.
Now, I hope that Father will study this sheet
of new duties.
Good morning.'
That summer evening which Miss Kenton mentioned
in her letter came very soon after that conversation.
Indeed, it may have been the evening of that
same day.
As I have said before, I can remember the
evening sunlight shining through the open
bedroom doors into the dark corridor.
And as I was walking past the bedrooms, Miss
Kenton called to me.
I stood next to her by the window and looked
down.
We could see my father standing by the stone
steps in front of the summerhouse.
A soft wind blew through his hair and there
was a deep frown on his face.
Then, as we watched, he walked very slowly
up the steps.
At the top he turned and came back down, a
little faster.
He repeated this several times, his eyes never
once leaving the ground.
It was exacdy as Miss Kenton describes it
in her letter: He seemed to be looking for
a precious jewel that he had dropped there.
***
Some people might consider me to have been
rather insensitive when I spoke to my father
about his declining abilities.
But the fact is, I had to deal with the problem
in an impersonal and businesslike manner - as
I am sure you will agree when I have explained
the situation in more detail.
Lord Darlington had been preparing for the
conference of March 1923 for many years.
He had made his first trip to Berlin in 1920,
and was unhappy when he returned to Darlington
Hall.
When I asked him how he had enjoyed his trip,
he said:
'Upsetting, Stevens.
Deeply upsetting.
It is not right for us to treat a defeated
enemy like this.
The war ended two years ago.
We are making the people of Germany suffer
too much.
It is not like the British to be so unforgiving.'
After that, Lord Darlington spent more and
more time trying to help the German people.
Powerful and famous gentlemen became regular
visitors to the house.
Many of them came in secret, so I am unable
to reveal their names to you.
Some of the guests were so secret that I was
not permitted to tell the staff who they were.
However - and I say this with pride - his
lordship never hid things from me.
Over the following two years, his lordship
and a close friend of his, Sir David Cardinal,
became the leaders of a powerful and important
group of people who all agreed that the people
of Germany had suffered enough.
They believed that if the economic crisis
in Germany became any worse, all of Europe
would be in danger.
By the beginning of 1922, his lordship had
a clear plan.
He wanted an 'unofficial' international conference
at Darlington Hall.
He would invite people from European governments
who agreed with his ideas about helping Germany.
After this conference, these people would
return to their countries and attempt to change
their governments' attitudes towards Germany.
As the date for the conference approached,
the pressures on me began to increase.
It was my responsibility to make sure that
nothing went wrong.
If any of the guests were, for some reason,
dissatisfied with their stay at Darlington
Hall, it could threaten the success of the
conference.
Great damage might be done to the future peace
of Europe.
However, it was not possible for me to plan
things as carefully as I wanted.
I was aware that there would be twenty guests
- eighteen gentlemen and two ladies.
Each guest, however, was going to arrive with
a team of secretaries and servants, and nobody
knew exactly how many.
It was impossible for me, therefore, to know
how many rooms would be needed.
Furthermore, a number of guests would be arriving
some time before the conference, but nobody
knew the exact dates of these arrivals.
I prepared for the conference like a general
preparing for a battle.
I produced a staff plan, and held a special
meeting with everybody who worked in the house.
'I know you all have a lot of extra work to
do,' I told them.
'We are all under great pressure, but you
can take great pride in performing your duties
in the days ahead.
It is possible that history will be made under
this roof!'
The staff knew that I was not the kind of
person to make exaggerated statements.
They understood that something extraordinary
was going to take place.
This was the general atmosphere of Darlington
Hall at the time of my father's accident.
It was only two weeks before the conference,
and I had many other urgent problems to think
about.
You will understand, therefore, why I might
have seemed a little insensitive with my father
when I informed him of the reduction in his
duties.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Birds and Bees
In the busy days just before the conference,
there was a great change in my father's behaviour.
He had a trolley loaded with cleaning equipment,
teapots, cups and saucers.
He seemed filled with a strange, youthful
energy, and he pushed his trolley all around
the house.
He moved so quickly that a stranger might
have thought that there were several men pushing
trolleys around Darlington Hall, not just
one.
The increasing pressure of the days just before
the conference affected Miss Kenton, too,
although in a completely different way.
I remember, for example, meeting her in the
back corridor.
I reminded her that the sheets for the bedrooms
on the upper floor needed to be ready.
'The matter is perfectly under control, Mr
Stevens,' she replied.
I began to move away, but Miss Kenton took
one more step towards me with an angry expression
on her face.
'Unfortunately, Mr Stevens, I am extremely
busy now,' she said.
'I wish I had as much spare time as you do.
Then perhaps I too could happily wander about
this house and remind you of tasks that you
have perfectly under control.'
'Now, Miss Kenton, there is no need to be
so bad-tempered.
I simply wanted to remind you...'
'This is the fourth or fifth time this week,
Mr Stevens, that you have reminded me to do
something that I have already done,' she interrupted
me.
'It is very strange to see you with so much
spare time that you have nothing better to
do.'
'Miss Kenton, you must be very inexperienced
if you think that I have any spare time.
I hope that, in future years, you will understand
more clearly how difficult it is to organize
a great house like this.'
'You are always talking about my "great inexperience",
Mr Stevens, but have you noticed anything
wrong with my work?
If you had, I'm sure you would have told me
about it before now.
Now, I have a lot of work to do.
I would be grateful if you would stop interrupting
me like this.
If you have so much spare time, I suggest
that you go for a walk outside and get some
fresh air.'
With those words, she marched past me along
the corridor.
I was so surprised that I did not know what
to do at first.
Then, deciding that it was best not to say
anything, I continued on my way.
I had, however, almost reached the kitchen
doorway when I heard the sound of angry footsteps
coming back towards me again.
'In fact, Mr Stevens,' she called, 'I would
be grateful if, in future, you did not speak
to me directly at all.
If it is necessary to communicate with me,
please use a messenger.
Or you may like to write a note and have it
sent to me.
Now, I must return to my work.
And you can continue to wander around the
house criticizing people for no reason!'
Although I was annoyed by Miss Kenton's behaviour,
I had no time to think about it because the
first guests had arrived.
Two Foreign Office officials and Lord Darlington's
friend, Sir David Cardinal, had arrived before
the other guests to discuss the conference.
As I went in and out of the various rooms
in which these four gentlemen sat, I could
not avoid hearing parts of their conversation.
They seemed to be talking most of the time
about one man - an extremely important Frenchman
whom I shall call Monsieur Dupont.
On one occasion, I came into the smoking room
and heard one of the gentlemen saying:
'The future of Europe depends on persuading
Dupont that we are right.'
In the middle of these discussions, his lordship
asked me to perform a rather unusual task.
He called me into his study, sat down at his
desk and, as usual, pretended to start reading
a book.
'Oh, Stevens,' he began.
Then he did not seem to know how to continue,
for he turned a page of his book and fell
silent.
A few moments later he tried again.
'Stevens, I realize that this is a strange
request.'
'Sir?'
'It's just that I have so much to think about
at present.'
'I would be very glad to assist, sir.'
'I'm sorry to have to ask you to do a thing
like this, Stevens.
I know you must be extremely busy yourself.
But I can't think of any other solution.'
He studied the book in front of him for several
long seconds before continuing, without looking
up:
'You are familiar, I assume, with the facts
of life.'
'Sir?'
'The facts of life, Stevens.
Birds, bees, that sort of thing.'
'I'm afraid I don't quite understand, sir.'
'Let me be frank, Stevens.
Sir David is a very old friend of mine.
He's brought his son, Reginald, to our conference
as his secretary.
Young Reginald is engaged to be married.'
'Yes, sir.'
'Sir David has been trying to tell his son
the facts of life for the last five years.
The young man is now twenty-three.'
'Indeed, sir.'
'Well, Stevens, this is the problem.
Sir David has asked me, as his oldest friend,
to tell young Reginald about the facts of
life.
Sir David himself is nervous about doing it.
He thinks it would be much better if I performed
the task.
The trouble is, I'm so busy with this conference.'
His lordship paused and went on studying the
page.
'Do I understand, sir, that you wish me to
give young Mr Cardinal the necessary information?'
'If you don't mind, Stevens.
It would be a great help.
Sir David continues to ask me every couple
of hours if I've done it yet.'
'I see, sir.
It must be very difficult for you.'
'Of course, I realize what an awkward task
this is, Stevens.'
'I will do my best, sir,' I assured his lordship.
'It might, however, be difficult for me to
find the right moment to deliver the information.'
'I'd be grateful if you even tried, Stevens.
It's very decent of you.
But listen, there's no need to go into great
detail.
Just give him the basic facts, that's all.'
An hour after my conversation with Lord Darlington,
I noticed young Mr Cardinal alone in the library.
He was sitting at one of the writing tables,
working on some documents.
Deciding to perform my awkward task as quickly
as possible, I entered the library and gave
a little cough.
'Excuse me, sir, but I have a message for
you,' I said.
'Oh, really?' said Mr Cardinal, looking up
from his papers.
'From Father?'
'Yes, sir.
In an indirect sort of way.'
The young gentleman reached down into the
black bag at his feet, brought out a notebook
and pencil and said:
'I'm ready, Stevens.'
I coughed again and said:
'Sir David wishes you to know, sir, that ladies
and gentlemen are different in a number of
ways.'
I must have paused a little to consider the
wording of my next sentence, because Mr Cardinal
said:
'I am aware of that, Stevens.'
'You are aware, sir?'
'My father constantly underestimates me, Stevens.
I've done quite a lot of reading on the subject.'
'Really, sir.
Then, in that case, perhaps my message is
unnecessary.'
'You can assure Father that I have discovered
everything I need to know.
This bag is full of notes I have made on the
subject.'
'Indeed, sir?'
'Unless, of course, Father has new information
he wants me to think about.
Is there anything more, for example, on this
Dupont fellow?'
'I believe not, sir,' I said, attempting to
hide my disappointment.
I thought I had successfully completed the
task, but found instead that I hadn't even
started it.
However, before I could make another attempt
on the subject, Mr Cardinal rose to his feet
and said:
'Well, I think I'll go outside for some fresh
air, Stevens.
Thanks for your help.'
I had intended to speak again to Mr Cardinal
immediately, but that afternoon - two days
earlier than expected - Mr Lewis, the American
senator, arrived.
More guests arrived the next morning: two
ladies from Germany who had brought with them
a large team of servants as well as a great
many trunks.
Then, in the afternoon, an Italian gentleman
arrived.
He was accompanied by a servant, a secretary,
an adviser and two security men.
Several more guests arrived the following
day, and Darlington Hall was already filled
with people of all nationalities two days
before the conference began.
Although the guests were always polite to
each other, there was a strange atmosphere
in the house.
The visiting servants seemed to look at one
another very coldly, and my own staff were
glad to be too busy to spend much time with
them.
One afternoon, while I was becoming increasingly
busy with the many demands made of me, I glanced
out of a window and saw young Mr Cardinal.
He was taking some fresh air around the grounds.
Although I had much more important things
on my mind, I immediately thought of the task
which Lord Darlington had asked me to perform,
and which I had not yet completed.
I decided that this was a suitable time and
place for me to deliver the message.
I crossed the grass quickly and waited behind
a bush until I heard Mr Cardinal's footsteps
along the path that bordered the lawn.
Unfortunately, I misjudged the timing of my
appearance from behind the bush.
I had intended to come out on to the path
while Mr Cardinal was still some distance
away.
I could have pretended to notice him for the
first time, and started a conversation with
him in a natural manner.
However, I moved out from behind the bush
a little too late, and, I regret to say, I
frightened the young gentleman.
He stepped backwards in alarm, holding his
black bag tightly.
'I'm very sorry, sir.'
'Stevens!
You gave me a shock.'
'I'm very sorry, sir,' I repeated.
'But I have a message to deliver to you.
If I may speak directly, sir, You will notice
the geese not far from us.'
'Geese?'
He looked around, a little confused.
'And also the flowers and bushes.
This is not, in fact, the best time of year
to see them, but you will appreciate, sir,
that in spring we will see a change - a very
special sort of change - in these surroundings.'
'Yes, I'm sure this is not the best time of
year to see the grounds.
But frankly, Stevens, I wasn't paying much
attention to the beauty of nature.
It's all rather worrying.
That Monsieur Dupont has arrived in a very
bad mood.'
'Monsieur Dupont has arrived here at this
house, sir?'
'About half an hour ago.
He's in a terrible temper.'
'Excuse me, sir.
I must attend to the matter immediately.'
'Of course, Stevens.
It was kind of you to come out here and talk
to me.'
'Please excuse me, sir, but I have not quite
finished my message on the topic of - as you
say - the beauty of nature.
If you would allow me to continue on another
occasion, I would be most grateful.'
'I shall look forward to it, Stevens.
Although I'm more interested in fish than
flowers and geese.
I know all about fish.'
'All living creatures will be relevant to
our future discussion, sir.
However, you must now please excuse me.
I had no idea that Monsieur Dupont had arrived.'
With those words I hurried back to the house.
Monsieur Dupont was a tall, elegant gentleman
with a grey beard.
He had arrived in the sort of clothes that
European gentlemen often wear on their holidays.
As Mr Cardinal had said, Monsieur Dupont had
not arrived in a good temper.
A lot of things had upset him since his arrival
in England.
Among other things, he had painful sores on
his feet after sightseeing in London.
I told his manservant to speak to Miss Kenton,
but this did not prevent Monsieur Dupont from
shouting at me every few hours:
'Butler!
I need some more bandages!'
His mood seemed to improve, however, when
he saw Mr Lewis.
He and the American senator greeted each other
as old colleagues.
They went everywhere together, chatting quietly
or laughing about old memories.
The other guests, meanwhile, did not go near
Monsieur Dupont.
They seemed suspicious of him, which somehow
seemed to emphasize his importance to the
conference.
CHAPTER SIX
The Conference
The conference began on a rainy morning during
the last week of March.
On the first morning, I had to go constantly
in and out of the drawing room, where all
the serious, dark-jacketed gentlemen had gathered.
I noticed that Monsieur Dupont did not speak
very much.
Once, while I was leaving the room in the
middle of a speech by a German gentleman,
Monsieur Dupont rose to his feet and followed
me out.
'Butler,' he said, as soon as we were in the
hall.
'I wonder if I could have the bandages on
my feet changed.
They are so uncomfortable that I can hardly
listen to these gentlemen.'
I sent a messenger to ask Miss Kenton for
assistance, then left Monsieur Dupont sitting
in the games room.
However, just as I was going to continue my
duties, the first footman came down the stairs
towards me.
He informed me that my father had suddenly
become very ill upstairs.
I hurried up to the first floor and, when
I reached the landing, I saw something very
strange.
My father was at the far end of the corridor.
He was kneeling on the floor with both hands
on the trolley.
He had bowed his head and seemed to be staring
at something on the carpet.
He did not move at all.
Two housemaids were standing beside him, not
knowing what to do.
I went to my father, released his hands from
their grip on the trolley and gently lowered
him on to the floor.
His eyes were closed, and his face was covered
in sweat.
I called for more help, and my father was
eventually put in a wheelchair and taken up
to his room.
When my father was in bed, I did not know
what to do.
I did not want to leave him but, on the other
hand, I was too busy to stay.
As I hesitated in the doorway, Miss Kenton
appeared at my side and said:
'Mr Stevens, I'm not as busy as you are.
If you like, I can look after your father.
I'll bring Doctor Meredith up and tell you
if he has anything important to say.'
'Thank you, Miss Kenton,' I said, and I went
downstairs.
I returned to the drawing room and was immediately
busy serving the guests tea and coffee.
A short time later, as I was leaving the drawing
room with an empty teapot in my hand, Miss
Kenton stopped me and said:
'Mr Stevens, Doctor Meredith is leaving now.'
The doctor was putting on his hat and coat
in the hall when I arrived.
The teapot was still in my hand.
'Your father's not good,' he said.
'If he gets worse, call me again immediately.'
I thanked the doctor and showed him out.
***
The next day, the discussions in the drawing
room were much more serious.
Several of the guests seemed to be getting
angry with Monsieur Dupont and were making
bold accusations against him.
The French gentleman did not reply.
He just sat quietly in his armchair and stroked
his beard.
Whenever there was a break in the conference,
Mr Lewis took Monsieur Dupont away to a quiet
corner and whispered to him in private.
Meanwhile, my father's condition remained
the same.
When I had a spare moment, which was not often,
I went up to his room and found him asleep.
I did not, therefore, have a chance to talk
to him until the second evening.
On that occasion, too, he was sleeping when
I entered the room.
But the housemaid stood up when she saw me
and began to shake my father's shoulder.
'Foolish girl!'
I said.
'What do you think you are doing?'
'Mr Stevens asked me to wake him if you returned,
sir,' she replied, and shook my father's shoulder
again.
My father opened his eyes, turned his head
a little and looked at me.
'I hope Father is feeling better now,' I said.
He stared at me for a moment, then asked:
'Everything under control downstairs?'
'It is very busy in the kitchen at the moment,
as Father can imagine.'
An impatient look crossed my father's face.
'But is everything under control?' he said
again.
'Yes, I can assure Father that it is.
I'm glad that Father is feeling better.'
Very slowly, he took his arms from under the
bedclothes and stared tiredly at the backs
of his hands.
He continued to do this for some time.
'I'm glad Father is feeling so much better,'
I repeated.
'Now really, I should get back.
As I say, it is very busy in the kitchen at
the moment.'
He went on looking at his hands for a moment.
Then he said slowly:
'I hope I've been a good father to you.'
I laughed a little and said:
'I'm so glad you're feeling better now.'
'I'm proud of you.
You're a good son.
I hope I've been a good father to you.
I suppose I haven't.'
'I'm afraid we're extremely busy now, but
we can talk again in the morning.'
My father continued to look at his hands.
He seemed to be slightly annoyed with them.
'I'm so glad you're feeling better now,' I
said again, and left the room.
***
At the second and final dinner of the conference,
the guests seemed friendlier and more relaxed
than they had throughout the previous days.
I and my staff served much more wine than
we had before.
At the end of the dinner Lord Darlington rose
to make a speech.
He thanked his guests for coming to the conference,
and proceeded to talk for a long time about
his hopes for a better future for Europe.
When he had finally sat down, everybody was
surprised to see Monsieur Dupont rise to his
feet.
There was immediate silence in the room.
He thanked Lord Darlington for his hard work,
and everybody in the room voiced quiet approval.
He then surprised everybody by criticizing
the American senator, Mr Lewis, for trying
to create trouble between him and the other
guests at the conference.
When he eventually sat down, there was an
awkward silence.
Finally Mr Lewis rose to his feet and proceeded
to criticize Lord Darlington for not understanding
the problems of the real world - for not being
a professional, like him.
'The world is too complicated for true gentlemen
to understand,' he said.
'It's time for politicians and businessmen
to take control.'
When he had finished speaking, there was a
shocked silence and no one moved.
Then Lord Darlington stood up and defended
himself against Mr Lewis's attacks.
He talked about honour, justice and goodness.
'Professionalism,' he said, 'is just another
word for greedy dishonesty.'
Everybody in the room clapped with great enthusiasm
at this part of his lordship's speech, except
for Mr Lewis.
He just looked into his wine glass and shook
his head with a tired smile.
Just at that moment, I became aware of the
first footman beside me.
'Miss Kenton would like a word with you, sir,'
he whispered.
'She's just outside the door.'
I left as quietly as possible while his lordship
was still speaking.
Miss Kenton looked rather upset.
'Your father has become very ill, Mr Stevens,'
she said.
'I've called for Doctor Meredith, but I believe
he may be a little late.'
I must have looked a little confused, for
Miss Kenton then said:
'Mr Stevens, he really is in a bad state.
You had better come and see him.'
'I only have a moment.
The gentlemen will be needing me in the smoking
room very soon.'
'Of course.
But you must come now, Mr Stevens, otherwise
you may deeply regret it later.'
When I arrived in my father's room, Mrs Mortimer,
the cook, was standing by his bed.
My father's face had gone a dull, reddish
colour.
I had never seen that colour in a living person's
face before.
I looked at my father for a moment, touched
his forehead slightly, then withdrew my hand.
'In my opinion,' Mrs Mortimer said, 'he's
suffered a stroke.
'With that she began to cry.
I turned away and said to Miss Kenton:
'This is most upsetting.
Nevertheless, I must now return downstairs.'
'Of course, Mr Stevens.
I will tell you when the doctor arrives.'
I hurried downstairs and was in time to see
the gentlemen going into the smoking room.
There was now a genuine atmosphere of celebration
among the guests as I moved around the crowded
smoking room with my tray.
I had just finished serving a glass to a gentleman
when a voice behind me said:
'Ah, Stevens, you're interested in fish, you
say.'
I turned to find the young Mr Cardinal smiling
happily at me.
I smiled also and said:
'Fish, sir?'
'When I was young, I used to keep tropical
fish in a tank...
My God, Stevens, are you all right?'
I smiled again.
'Quite all right, thank you, sir.'
'As you so rightly explained, I really should
come back here in spring.
Darlington Hall must be lovely then.
The last time I was here...'
Mr Cardinal stopped again and looked at me.
'Are you sure you're all right, Stevens?'
'Perfectly all right, thank you, sir.'
'Not feeling unwell, are you?'
'Not at all, sir.
Please excuse me.'
I proceeded to serve drink to some other guests.
Then I felt something touch my elbow and turned
to find Lord Darlington.
'Stevens, are you all right?'
'Yes, sir.
Perfectly.'
'You seem to be crying.'
I laughed and, taking out a handkerchief,
I quickly wiped my face.
'I'm sorry, sir.
The strains of a hard day.'
'Yes, it's been hard work.'
I was continuing around the room when I saw
Miss Kenton standing in the doorway.
She signalled for me to go over to her.
I began to make my way towards the doors but,
before I could reach them, Monsieur Dupont
touched my arm.
'Butler,' he said, 'I wonder if you would
find me some fresh bandages.
My feet are hurting again.'
'Yes, sir.'
As I moved towards the doors, I realized Monsieur
Dupont was following me.
I turned and said:
'I will come and find you, sir, as soon as
I have the bandages.'
'Please hurry, butler.
I am in pain.'
'Yes, sir.
I'm very sorry, sir.'
As I entered the hall, Miss Kenton walked
silently towards the stairs.
Then she turned and said:
'Mr Stevens, I'm very sorry.
Your father died about four minutes ago.'
'I see.'
She looked at her hands, then up at my face.
'Mr Stevens, I'm very sorry,' she said.
Then she added:
'I wish there was something I could say.'
'There is no need, Miss Kenton.'
'Doctor Meredith has not arrived yet.'
For a moment she bowed her head.
She seemed to be crying.
But almost immediately she looked up again
and said in a steady voice:
'Will you come up and see him?'
'I'm very busy now, Miss Kenton.
Soon, perhaps.'
'Then, Mr Stevens, will you permit me to close
his eyes?'
'I would be most grateful, Miss Kenton.'
She began to climb the stairs, but I stopped
her and said: 'Miss Kenton, please don't think
that I'm cold-hearted because I'm not coming
up to see my father at this moment.
You see, I know my father would have wished
me to continue working just now.'
'Of course, Mr Stevens.'
I turned away and re-entered the smoking room.
As I was moving among the guests with my tray,
Monsieur Dupont touched my shoulder and said:
'Butler, have you found my bandages yet?'
'I'm very sorry, sir.'
'What's the problem, butler?
Why haven't you found them yet?'
'Sir, a doctor is on his way.'
'Ah, very good!
You called a doctor.'
Monsieur Dupont turned away and continued
his conversation.
A short time later, a footman approached me
and said:
'Miss Kenton would like to have a word with
you, sir.'
I made my way towards the doors, but noticed
that Monsieur Dupont was guarding them.
'Butler, is the doctor here?' he asked.
'I am just going to find out, sir.
I won't be a moment.'
'I am in pain.'
'I'm very sorry, sir.
The doctor should not be long now.'
This time, Monsieur Dupont followed me out
of the door.
Miss Kenton was again standing in the hall.
'Mr Stevens,' she said.
'Doctor Meredith has arrived and gone upstairs.'
She had spoken in a low voice, but Monsieur
Dupont behind me immediately said:
'Ah, good!'
I turned to him and said:
'Perhaps you would follow me, sir.'
I led Monsieur Dupont into the games room,
then returned to the hallway.
Miss Kenton was still waiting for me.
Without a word, she accompanied me up the
stairs to my father's room.
Doctor Meredith, who was sitting by my father's
bed, stood up when I arrived and said:
'I'm sorry, Stevens.
He suffered a severe stroke.
I can assure you, however, that he was not
in any pain.'
'Thank you, sir.'
'I'll be on my way, now.
You'll make the arrangements?'
'Yes, sir.
However, would you mind seeing a gentleman
downstairs?
He is in need of your attention.'
'Urgent?'
'He is very keen to see you, sir.'
I led Doctor Meredith downstairs, showed him
into the games room, then returned to the
smoking room, where the atmosphere among the
guests had grown even more cheerful than before.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Silver
September 1956
I am now on the third day of my trip to the
West Country.
Last night I stayed in an inn named The Coach
and Horses, an attractive, quiet-looking cottage
just outside the market town of Taunton in
Somerset.
Unfortunately, however, the inn was not as
quiet as it had seemed when I arrived.
Although the landlord's wife did not actually
shout, I could hear her talking late into
the night and, again, early this morning.
As a consequence, I slept rather badly, although
I did not, of course, say anything about this
when I thanked the landlord and his wife this
morning.
Now, however, I am enjoying a pleasant mid-morning
cup of tea in a small tearoom in the high
street ofTaunton, very close to the market
square.
Although I am sitting at the back, I can see
clearly out into the sunlit street.
There is an interesting signpost on the pavement
opposite the tearoom.
It is pointing to several local destinations,
one of which is the village of Mursden.
Giffen and Company once had a factory in the
Somerset village of Mursden This company was
famous for manufacturing polish.
Giffen's polish was the finest silver polish
available for many years.
Then, just before the war, new chemical substances
became available and the demand for Giffen's
silver polish began to decline.
Giffen's silver polish first appeared at the
beginning of the 1920s.
In my opinion, it was responsible for an important
change of attitude in my profession.
The polishing of silver suddenly became a
central part of a butler's responsibilities.
Before Giffen's existed, the butlers of my
father's age did not consider the polishing
of silver so important.
But in the 1920s, the full significance of
silver was recognized by the younger butlers.
Visitors to a house would examine the silver
during a meal more closely than anything else.
Guests would often judge the quality of a
house by its silver.
I, of course, was very aware of the appearance
of this new, high-quality product, and I immediately
made the polishing of silver my top priority.
I can remember with pride many occasions when
visitors to Darlington Hall commented on the
silver.
Lady Astor once said our silver shone more
brightly than any silver she had seen.
Mr George Bernard Shaw, the famous writer,
came to dinner one evening and held a silver
dessert spoon up to the light.
But perhaps my proudest moment was when Lord
Halifax, the government minister who later
became head of the Foreign Office, came to
dinner.
This visit was the first of a series of 'unofficial'
meetings arranged by Lord Darlington between
Lord Halifax and the German Ambassador, Herr
Ribbentrop.
Lord Halifax, on that first night, had been
very suspicious when he arrived at Darlington
Hall.
He was not happy about meeting the German
Ambassador in secret like this.
Lord Darlington suggested a tour of Darlington
Hall.
In the past, this had often helped many nervous
visitors to relax.
However, Lord Halifax continued to express
his doubts about the evening as he walked
around the rooms.
Lord Darlington tried to reassure him, but
without success.
But then, as I was going about my business,
I heard Lord Halifax say:
'My God, Darlington, the silver in this house
is a delight.'
I was, of course, very pleased to hear this
at the time.
Two or three days later I was even more satisfied
when Lord Darlington told me:
'By the way, Stevens, Lord Halifax was very
impressed with the silver the other night.
It put him in a very good mood.'
I honestly believe, therefore, that the high
quality of the silver that evening was probably
responsible for the success of Lord Halifax's
first meeting with Herr Ribbentrop.
I should, perhaps, now say a few words concerning
Herr Ribbentrop.
Nowadays, of course, most people believe that
Herr Ribbentrop was just a liar.
They say that he was part of Hitler's plan
to deceive the English for as long as possible
- to stop the English from understanding his
true intentions.
I do not wish to disagree with this view.
It is, however, rather annoying when people
today say that they always knew Herr Ribbentrop
was a liar.
They say that Lord Darlington was the only
man in England who believed that the German
Ambassador was an honest gentleman.
The truth is very different.
In the mid-1930s, Herr Ribbentrop was a welcome
guest in the very best houses.
The same people who invited Herr Ribbentrop
to their homes say now that Lord Darlington
betrayed his country.
In my opinion, anyone who suggests that his
lordship was secretly trying to help the enemy
is conveniently forgetting the true atmosphere
of those times.
I would also like to correct another false
accusation, which is now often made against
Lord Darlington.
It is nonsense to claim, as people do, that
his lordship disliked Jews.
People who make these claims know nothing
about the sort of gentleman Lord Darlington
was.
I heard him express his disgust on several
occasions when somebody made insulting comments
about Jews.
And the accusation that his lordship never
allowed Jewish people to enter the house or
any Jewish staff to be employed is completely
false.
Except, perhaps, for one minor incident in
the 1930s...
But I am moving away from the subject of silver.
Perhaps I should not spend so much time looking
back to the past.
After all, I still have before me many more
years of service.
Mr Farraday is not only a most excellent employer.
He is an American gentleman, and one has a
special duty to show him all that is best
about service in England.
It is essential, then, to keep one's mind
on the present, and not on the achievements
of the past.
It is, unfortunately, true that, over these
last few months, things have not been perfect
at Darlington Hall.
There have been a number of small errors,
including one incident last April concerning
the silver.
Fortunately, Mr Farraday had no guests, but
it was nevertheless a moment of genuine embarrassment
to me.
It occurred at breakfast one morning.
After sitting at the table, Mr Farraday picked
up a fork, examined it for a brief second,
then turned his attention to the newspaper.
While he was reading, I moved quickly to remove
the fork from the table.
I took it immediately to the kitchen and returned
without delay with another fork.
I thought for a second about putting the fork
quietly on to the tablecloth without attracting
Mr Farraday's attention.
But then I thought it was possible that Mr
Farraday did not want to embarrass me, and
was only pretending not to have noticed.
I therefore decided to put the new fork down
on the table with a certain emphasis.
This made my employer look up from his newspaper
and say:
'Ah, Stevens.'
Errors like this have been, as I have already
said, a result of the shortage of staff.
If Miss Kenton returned to Darlington Hall,
these errors would, I am sure, no longer be
made.
Of course, I must not forget that Miss Kenton
says nothing directly in her letter about
wishing to return.
Last night, when I was unable to sleep because
of the noise in the small inn outside Taunton,
I read her letter again carefully.
It was surprisingly difficult to identify
any passage which clearly indicated her desire
to return.
But, on the other hand, it seems foolish to
worry about such things.
Within forty-eight hours I will be face to
face with Miss Kenton.
I shall be able to discover for myself whether
she truly wishes to return to Darlington Hall
or not.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Sarah and Ruth
I should perhaps, at this point, return to
the question of Lord Darlington's attitude
towards Jewish people.
I want, in particular, to discuss the false
belief that Lord Darlington banned Jews from
working on the staff at Darlington Hall.
I am in the perfect position, as head of staff,
to deny these accusations absolutely.
There were many Jewish people on the staff
throughout all my years with his lordship,
and they were never treated differently as
a result of their race.
The only possible reason for these ridiculous
accusations is, perhaps, one brief incident
in the summer of 1932.
1932-33
One afternoon, his lordship called me into
his study.
'I've been doing a lot of thinking, Stevens,'
he said.
'And I've decided that we cannot have Jews
on the staff here at Darlington Hall.'
'Sir?'
'It is for the good of this house, Stevens.
In the interests of the guests we have staying
here.'
'Of course, sir.'
'Tell me, Stevens, we have a few Jews on the
staff at the moment, don't we?'
'I believe two of the present staff come into
that category, sir.'
'Ah.'
His lordship paused for a moment, staring
out of his window.
'Of course, you'll have to dismiss them.
It's regrettable, Stevens, but we have no
choice.
I've thought about this very carefully.
It's in all our best interests.'
The two Jewish members of staff were both
housemaids.
It was right, therefore, to speak to Miss
Kenton first and inform her of the situation.
I decided to do this that same evening when
I met her for cocoa in her room.
I should perhaps say a few words here about
these meetings in her room at the end of the
day.
Our conversations were completely professional,
although some informal topics were discussed
from time to time.
Our reason for having these meetings was simple:
our lives were so busy that we hardly had
time to speak to each other during the day.
This lack of communication was a serious danger
to the continued smooth running of operations
in Darlington Hall.
Fifteen minutes in private together at the
end of the day in Miss Kenton's room seemed,
therefore, the simplest solution to the problem.
I was a little anxious about telling Miss
Kenton that I had to dismiss two of her maids.
They had both been perfectly satisfactory
employees, and I was not personally in favour
of dismissing them.
Nevertheless, it would have been irresponsible
of me to display my true feelings on the matter.
It was a difficult task, but it had to be
performed with dignity.
When I finally introduced the subject towards
the end of our conversation that evening,
I was as clear and as businesslike as possible.
I finished by saying:
'I will speak to the two maids in my office
tomorrow morning at ten thirty.
I would be grateful, Miss Kenton, if you could
send them to me.'
At first, Miss Kenton said nothing.
So I continued:
'Well, Miss Kenton, thank you for the cocoa.
It is time for me to go to bed.
Another busy day tomorrow.'
As I was leaving, Miss Kenton suddenly said:
'Mr Stevens, I cannot quite believe my ears.
Ruth and Sarah have been members of my staff
for over six years.
They have served this house excellently.'
'I'm sure that is true, Miss Kenton.
However, we must not allow personal feeling
to affect our judgement.'
'Mr Stevens, I'm shocked that you can sit
there and speak about this so calmly.
You are saying that Ruth and Sarah have to
be dismissed because they are Jewish?'
'Miss Kenton, I have just explained the situation
to you.
His lordship has made his decision and there
is nothing for you or I to debate.'
'Have you not considered, Mr Stevens, that
it would be quite wrong to dismiss Ruth and
Sarah because they're Jewish?
I will not work in a house in which such things
can occur.'
'Miss Kenton, please do not excite yourself.
Remember your position.
This is a very simple matter.
If his lordship wishes to end their contracts,
there is no more to be said.'
'I'm warning you, Mr Stevens, I will not continue
to work in such a house.
If my girls are dismissed, I will leave too.'
'Miss Kenton, may I suggest that you and I
are not in a position to judge what is right
and what is not.
The world of today is a very complicated and
dangerous place.
His lordship is in a much better position
than we are to judge what is best.
Now, Miss Kenton, I really must go to bed.
I thank you again for the cocoa.
Send the two employees to me at ten thirty
tomorrow morning, please.'
As soon as the two maids stepped into my office
the following morning, I could see that Miss
Kenton had already spoken to them.
They both came in crying.
I explained the situation to them as briefly
as possible, emphasizing the fact that their
work had been satisfactory.
The whole interview lasted perhaps for three
or four minutes, and they were still in tears
when they left.
Miss Kenton was extremely cold towards me
for some time afterwards.
At times she was quite rude to me, even in
front of the staff.
Although we continued our habit of meeting
for cocoa in the evening, our conversation
was brief and her tone unfriendly.
When there had been no improvement in her
behaviour after a fortnight, I started to
become a little impatient.
I therefore said to her one evening:
'Miss Kenton, I am surprised that you haven't
left yet.'
I accompanied this with a little laugh to
show that I was joking.
Miss Kenton, however, was not amused.
She frowned at me and said:
'I still intend to leave, Mr Stevens.
I have been too busy to organize it, that's
all.'
This made me think that she was, perhaps,
serious about her threat.
But then, as the weeks passed, it became clear
that she was not going to leave Darlington
Hall.
The atmosphere between us gradually improved,
and I began to joke about her threat to resign.
For example, if we were discussing a future
large occasion to be held at the house, I
sometimes finished the conversation by saying:
'Of course, Miss Kenton, if you are still
with us.'
Even months after the event, such remarks
still made Miss Kenton go quiet - although
I think that this was due more to embarrassment
than anger.
Eventually, of course, we stopped mentioning
the subject.
But I remember one last reference to it more
than a year after the maids had left.
His lordship mentioned it one afternoon when
I was serving his tea in the drawing room.
'Oh, Stevens,' he said to me.
'I've been meaning to talk to you about that
business last year.
About the Jewish maids.
Do you remember?'
'Indeed, sir.'
'I suppose there's no way of finding out where
they are now, is there?
It was wrong, what happened.
One would like to compensate them for it somehow.'
'I will certainly investigate, sir.
But I am not sure that it will be easy to
discover their whereabouts after all this
time.'
'See what you can do, Stevens.
That business should never have happened.'
I thought that Miss Kenton would be interested
in what his lordship had said, and I decided
to mention it to her - even at the risk of
getting her angry again.
However, when I finally spoke to her about
it, my conversation with her produced strange
results.
One foggy afternoon, I was crossing the lawn
towards the summerhouse in order to clear
away some cups and saucers.
As I approached the steps where my father
had once fallen, I noticed a figure moving
about inside the summerhouse.
It was Miss Kenton.
When I entered, however, she had stopped moving
about and was sitting down on a chair, apparently
busy with some needlework.
When I looked more closely, I noticed that
she was repairing a cushion.
As I began to gather up the cups and saucers,
Miss Kenton and I talked to each other about
unimportant things.
It was a pleasant change to be outside in
the summerhouse after so many continuous days
in the main building.
Neither of us was in a hurry to return indoors.
As the daylight rapidly faded and the fog
began to thicken over the lawn, Miss Kenton
and I often stopped working and stared out
of the windows in silence.
Then, during one of our silences, I finally
introduced the topic of the maids' dismissal.
'I was just thinking earlier, Miss Kenton,'
I said.
'It is rather funny to remember now, but only
a year ago you were still insisting you were
going to resign.
It rather amused me to think of it.'
I gave a laugh, but behind me Miss Kenton
remained silent.
When I finally turned to look at her, she
was staring quietly through the windows at
the fog.
'You probably have no idea, Mr Stevens,' she
said eventually, 'how seriously I thought
of leaving this house.
I felt so strongly about what happened.'
She paused for a while, and I turned my attention
back to the window.
Then she continued in a tired, dreamy voice:
'I was a coward, Mr Stevens.
I did not leave because I had nowhere to go.
I have no family, only my aunt.
I love her dearly, but I can't live with her
for a day without feeling that my life is
wasting away.
I told myself, of course, that I would soon
find another job somewhere.
But I was so frightened, Mr Stevens.
I feel so ashamed of myself.'
Miss Kenton paused again and seemed to be
deep in thought.
I thought that this was an appropriate moment
for me to inform her of my recent conversation
with Lord Darlington.
I finished by saying:
'The past cannot be undone.
But it is, at least, comforting to hear his
lordship say that it was all a terrible mistake.
I just thought you would like to know, Miss
Kenton, since I recall that you were as upset
by the incident as I was.'
'I'm sorry, Mr Stevens,' Miss Kenton said
behind me in an entirely new voice.
'I don't understand you.'
I turned in surprise and saw that Miss Kenton
was no longer looking dreamily out of the
window.
She was staring directly at me with a look
of challenge in her eyes.
'As I recall, Mr Stevens, you thought that
it was right and proper for Ruth and Sarah
to leave.
You were positively cheerful about it.'
'Now really, Miss Kenton, that is quite incorrect
and unfair.
The whole matter upset me terribly.
It is hardly the sort of thing I like to see
happen in this house.'
'Then why, Mr Stevens, did you not tell me
this at the time?'
I gave a laugh, but for a moment was rather
lost for an answer.
Before I could think of one, Miss Kenton put
down her sewing and said:
'Do you realize, Mr Stevens, how much it would
have meant to me if you had shared your feelings
with me last year?
You knew how upset I was when my girls were
dismissed.
Why, Mr Stevens, why, why, why do you always
have to pretend?'
I gave another laugh.
The conversation was, in my opinion, becoming
rather ridiculous.
'Really, Miss Kenton,' I said.
'I'm not sure I know what you mean.'
'I suffered so much over Ruth and Sarah leaving
us.
And I suffered more because I believed I was
alone.'
'Really, Miss Kenton...'
I picked up the tray of cups and saucers.
'Naturally, I disapproved of the dismissals.
I thought that was obvious.'
She did not say anything and, as I was leaving,
I glanced back towards her.
She was again looking out at the view, but
it had by now grown very dark inside the summerhouse.
I could only see the dark shape of her figure
against a pale and empty background.
I excused myself and walked out into the fog.
CHAPTER NINE
Lisa
One of the replacements for the two dismissed
maids was a young woman called Lisa.
I remember not being very impressed with her
references.
Moreover, when Miss Kenton and I interviewed
her, it became clear that she had never remained
in the same job for longer than a few weeks.
Her whole attitude suggested to me that she
was quite unsuitable for employment at Darlington
Hall.
To my surprise, however, Miss Kenton was extremely
keen to employ her.
'This girl has a bright future,' she insisted,
despite my protests.
'I will be responsible for her, Mr Stevens.
I will make sure that she does well.'
I continued my protests, but Miss Kenton eventually
won the argument.
To my amazement, her judgement on the matter
seemed to be correct.
During the following weeks, the young girl
made extremely good progress.
Her attitude and her manner of walking - which,
during the first days, had been so bad that
I had to look away - improved dramatically.
As the weeks passed, Miss Kenton took great
delight in her victory.
She enjoyed giving Lisa tasks that required
more and more responsibility.
If I was watching, she would smile at me with
a victorious look in her eyes.
'No doubt, Mr Stevens,' she said to me one
night as we drank our cocoa, 'you will be
extremely disappointed to hear Lisa has still
not made any serious mistakes.'
'I'm not disappointed at all, Miss Kenton.
I will admit, you have had some modest success
with the girl.'
'Modest success!
Look at that smile on your face, Mr Stevens.
It always appears when I mention Lisa.
That smile tells an interesting story.
A very interesting story indeed.'
'Really, Miss Kenton?
And may I ask, what story is that?'
'It is very interesting that you have been
so critical of her from the beginning, because
Lisa is a pretty girl.
And I've noticed that you dislike having pretty
girls on the staff.'
'You know perfectly well you are talking nonsense,
Miss Kenton.'
'Ah, but I've noticed it, Mr Stevens.
Is it possible that our Mr Stevens feels uncomfortable
with pretty girls?
Perhaps our Mr Stevens is flesh and blood
after all and cannot completely trust himself?'
'Really, Miss Kenton, you're making no sense.
I shall simply sit and think of other things
while you go on talking.'
'Ah, but why then is that guilty smile still
on your face, Mr Stevens?'
'It is not a guilty smile at all, Miss Kenton.
I am slightly amused by your ability to talk
nonsense, that's all.'
'It is a guilty smile, Mr Stevens.
And I've noticed how you can hardly bear to
look at Lisa.
Now it is becoming very clear why you didn't
want her on the staff.'
'The girl was completely unsuitable when she
first came to us, as you well know.'
Our conversation continued in this way for
several more minutes.
Of course, we would never have talked in this
way in front of the other staff.
But our cocoa evenings, although still basically
professional in tone, had begun to allow room
for a little harmless talk of this nature.
Playful conversations like this helped us
to relax after the demands of a busy working
day.
However, eight or nine months after she had
joined us, Lisa disappeared from the house
with a footman.
This kind of thing is, unfortunately, a normal
part of life for any butler of a large house.
It is extremely annoying when it happens,
but one learns to accept it.
They had also both left letters.
The footman, whose name I cannot remember,
left a short note addressed to me.
It said something like, Please do not think
too badly of us.
We are in love and are going to get married.
Lisa had written a much longer note addressed
to 'the Housekeeper'.
Miss Kenton brought this note into my office
the morning after their disappearance.
The letter, which was full of spelling and
grammar mistakes, talked about how much in
love the couple were, and their plans for
a future life together.
One line said: We don't have money but who
cares we have love and who wants anything
else we've got one another.
Although the letter was three pages long,
Lisa did not once thank Miss Kenton for the
kindness she had shown her.
Miss Kenton was clearly upset.
As I was reading the young woman's letter,
she sat at the table before me, looking at
her hands.
When I had put the letter down on the table,
she said:
'So, Mr Stevens.
It seems you were right and I was wrong.'
'Miss Kenton, there is no reason for you to
blame yourself.
These things happen.'
'I was wrong, Mr Stevens.
I accept it.'
'Miss Kenton, I cannot agree with you.
You achieved great things with that girl.
You must not blame yourself for anything.'
Miss Kenton continued to look unhappy.
She said very quietly:
'You're very kind, Mr Stevens.
I'm very grateful.'
Then she said, in a tired voice:
'She's so foolish.
She might have had a real career ahead of
her.
She had ability.
So many young women like her throw away their
chances, and for what?'
We both looked at the notepaper on the table
between us, then Miss Kenton turned her head
away with annoyance.
'Indeed,' I said.
'Such a waste, as you say.'
'So foolish.
And the girl is sure to be disappointed.
She could have become a housekeeper one day,
but she's thrown it all away.
All for nothing.'
'It really is most foolish of her,' I agreed.
I started to gather up the sheets of paper
in front of me, planning to keep them in my
office, but then I hesitated.
I was not sure whether Miss Kenton had intended
me to keep the letter or not.
I therefore put the pages back down on the
table between us and looked at Miss Kenton.
But she seemed far away, lost in thought.
'She's sure to be disappointed,' she said
again.
'So foolish.'
CHAPTER TEN
A Lonely Hill
September 1956
I have, it seems, become rather lost in these
old memories.
This was never my intention.
But thinking about the past has at least helped
me to forget the events of this evening.
For, I have to admit, these last few hours
have been extremely difficult for me.
I am now staying in an upstairs room of a
small cottage in the tiny village of Moscombe
in Devon.
It belongs to a retired couple called Mr and
Mrs Taylor.
It is very kind of the Taylors to allow me
to stay in this room.
Mrs Taylor has not only made the bed for me,
she has tidied and cleaned the room, too.
Although I have repeatedly offered to pay
for the room, they have refused to accept
a penny.
I am staying in this cottage because I made
one foolish, annoyingly simple, mistake.
I had forgotten to check the petrol.
It is true, I had been thinking about other
things just before the car stopped.
I had planned to stay in the town of Tavistock,
but I could not find a room anywhere because
of an agricultural fair.
After I had tried several inns and guest houses,
one landlady suggested that I should drive
to a roadside inn which belonged to a relative
of hers.
She gave me thorough directions, which had
seemed clear enough at the time, but I was
unable to find this roadside inn.
Instead, after about fifteen minutes, I was
driving along a misty road that curved across
wild, open land.
To my left, I could see the last red light
of the sunset.
Through the mist, I could see the distant
shape of an occasional farm building.
Apart from these, there was no sign of civilization.
I turned the Ford round and drove back, trying
to find a road I had passed earlier.
After some time I managed to find it, but
I was still lost.
This new road was even more isolated than
the one I had just left.
I drove in near-darkness between high hedges,
then the road began to climb steeply.
By now, I had given up hope of finding the
roadside inn.
I decided to drive on until I reached the
next town or village.
Halfway up the hill, however, the engine made
a strange noise, and I noticed for the first
time that the petrol tank was empty.
The Ford continued to climb for several more
metres, then stopped.
When I got out of the car, it was almost completely
dark.
I was standing on a steep road bordered by
trees and hedges.
Further up the hill I could see, through a
break in the hedges, the shape of a wooden
gate against the sky.
I made my way up towards this gate, hoping
to find a farmhouse or something.
I was disappointed to find, however, that
instead of a farmhouse there was just open
land.
I stopped at the gate and stared across the
fields.
The land sloped downwards about twenty metres
from the gate and disappeared into shadow.
About two kilometres further ahead, the land
rose into sight again, and I could see the
distant shape of a church.
Around the church there were small clouds
of white smoke rising from chimneys.
I admit that I felt, at that moment, a little
discouraged, but I tried to be positive.
The situation was not absolutely desperate,
I told myself.
The Ford was not damaged, simply out of fuel.
It would take me about half an hour to walk
across the fields to the village.
When I was there, I was sure to find accommodation
and a can of petrol from somewhere.
Nevertheless, despite these positive thoughts,
I did not feel happy up there on that lonely
hill, looking over the gate through the mist
and darkness at the lights of a distant village.
After returning to the Ford to collect my
case and a bicycle lamp, I searched for a
footpath that might take me to the village.
I was, however, unable to find one, so I had
to climb over the gate and walk across the
fields.
The journey was not as bad as I had imagined.
It consisted of a series of fields, each one
muddier than the last.
The worst thing was when I tore the shoulder
of my jacket while squeezing through a small
gap in one of the hedges.
Eventually I discovered a path which led down
into the village.
On my way along this path I met Mr Taylor.
He touched his cap when he saw me with my
torn clothes, muddy shoes, bicycle lamp and
case.
He then asked if I needed any help.
When I explained my situation to him, Mr Taylor
shook his head thoughtfully and said:
'I'm afraid there's no inn in our village,
sir.
But if you don't mind something less comfortable,
my wife and I could offer you a room and a
bed for the night.
It's nothing special.
It used to be our son's room before he went
to live in Exeter.'
I protested that I did not wish to cause him
and his wife so much inconvenience, but he
paid no attention and said:
'It would be an honour to have you, sir.
We don't get gentlemen like you passing through
Moscombe very often.
Besides, sir, I don't know what else you could
do at this hour.'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Secrets
When I said earlier that this evening's events
had been extremely difficult, I was not only
referring to the fact that I had had to walk
for half an hour in complete darkness across
muddy fields.
In many ways, what occurred during supper
with Mr and Mrs Taylor and their neighbours
was even worse than that.
After supper, it was a great relief for me
to come up to this room and to be alone with
my thoughts and my memories.
I have recently been spending more and more
time thinking about the old days at Darlington
Hall.
Since I received the letter from Miss Kenton,
I have tried to understand what happened to
our relationship.
We had developed a fine professional understanding
over many years.
Then, in 1935 or 1936, things started to go
wrong between us.
By the end of this period, we had even abandoned
our routine cup of cocoa together at the end
of the day.
But, despite all the time I have spent thinking
about this, I have never been able to decide
the exact moment when things between us began
to change.
1935-36
One important turning point in our relationship
might have been the evening when Miss Kenton
came uninvited into my office.
I cannot remember now why she came.
However, I do clearly remember her words:
'Mr Stevens, your room looks even worse at
night than it does in the day.
That electric bulb isn't bright enough.
You'll ruin your eyes trying to read by that
light.'
'It is perfectly comfortable, thank you, Miss
Kenton.'
'Really, Mr Stevens.
This room looks like a prison cell.'
I did not reply to this.
I continued with my reading, waiting for Miss
Kenton to excuse herself and leave.
But a few minutes later I was surprised to
hear her voice again:
'I wonder what you are reading there, Mr Stevens.'
'Simply a book, Miss Kenton.'
'But what sort of book?'
I looked up and saw Miss Kenton walking towards
me.
I shut the book and rose to my feet.
'Really, Miss Kenton,' I said, holding the
book close to me, 'this is my own private
time.
I must ask you not to disturb me like this.'
'But why are you so shy about your book, Mr
Stevens?
Is it something embarrassing?
A naughty book, perhaps?'
'There are no "naughty" books - as you call
them - on his lordship's shelves.'
'Then you have no reason to be shy, Mr Stevens.
So you can let me see what you are reading.'
'Miss Kenton, I must ask you to leave me alone.
I do not have much free time for myself, and
you are disturbing the little free time that
I have.'
But Miss Kenton continued to advance.
I was tempted for a moment to lock the book
away in my desk, but this seemed over-dramatic.
I took a few steps back.
'Please show me the book,' Miss Kenton insisted.
'Then I promise I will leave you alone to
your reading.'
'The book is not important, Miss Kenton,'
I replied.
'But I do object to this interruption of my
private time.'
She continued to smile playfully.
'Perhaps, Mr Stevens, the book is so naughty
that you want to protect me from its shocking
influence?'
She was now standing in front of me, and my
back was pressed against the wall.
Then suddenly there was a peculiar change
in the atmosphere.
I am afraid it is not easy to describe what
I mean by this.
I can only say that everything around us suddenly
became very still.
Miss Kenton's playful smile disappeared and
there was a sudden seriousness in her expression.
She seemed to be almost frightened of something.
'Please, Mr Stevens.
Let me see your book.'
She reached forward and began gently to release
the book from my grip.
I judged it best to look away while she did
this.
However, because her face was so close to
mine, I had to twist my head away from her
at a very unnatural angle.
Miss Kenton continued to lift my fingers off
the book - one at a time - until finally I
heard her say:
'Mr Stevens, this book isn't naughty at all.
It's simply a love story.'
At these words, I decided that I could stand
no more.
I cannot remember exactly what I said, but
I remember showing Miss Kenton firmly out
of the office.
Perhaps I should explain here something about
the book I was reading.
It is true, it was only a love story - one
of many kept in the library and guest bedrooms
for the entertainment of lady visitors.
I agree that these love stories are usually
very silly, and I rarely had the time or the
desire to read any of them from cover to cover.
But I had a simple reason for reading these
books: it was an efficient way of developing
my command of the English language.
In my opinion, it is extremely important for
a butler to have a good accent and command
of language, and I have always considered
it my duty to develop them as much as I could.
One way of doing this is to read a few pages
of a well-written book whenever one has a
spare moment.
Love stories are, in my opinion, especially
suitable for developing one's command of language.
The characters speak in an elegant way, which
is of great practical value to me.
A more serious book may improve one's mind,
but would not develop one's ability to hold
normal conversations with ladies and gentlemen.
But I am moving away from the incident with
Miss Kenton in my office.
It brought to my attention something that
I had not realized before: the fact that things
between Miss Kenton and myself had gradually
become, over a period of many months, too
familiar.
After I had shown Miss Kenton from my office,
I decided that we had to return to a more
professional relationship in future.
This was not, however, the only incident between
Miss Kenton and myself that led to the great
changes in our relationship.
There were other equally important developments
that might explain what took place later.
For example, there was the matter of Miss
Kenton's free days.
***
Until about a month before the incident with
my book, Miss Kenton's free days had followed
a regular pattern.
Every six weeks she would take two days off
to visit her aunt in Southampton.
Apart from this, she would follow my example
of only taking days off if we were going through
a quiet time.
But then the pattern changed.
She suddenly began to use all her free time,
and she disappeared regularly from the house
without saying where she was going.
Of course, she never took more time than she
was allowed, so I felt it was not my business
to ask her about her little trips.
But I suppose this change in her routine did
worry me a little, for I remember talking
about it to Mr Graham.
He was a regular visitor to our house because
he was the butler to Sir James Chambers, an
old friend of Lord Darlington's.
I had not intended to talk to Mr Graham about
Miss Kenton.
I had only mentioned that the housekeeper
had been 'a little moody' recently.
I was therefore rather surprised when Mr Graham
nodded, leaned towards me and said:
'I'd been wondering how much longer it would
be.'
When I asked him what he meant, Mr Graham
explained: 'How old is Miss Kenton now?
Thirty-three?
Thirty-four?
She has missed her best mothering years, but
it's not too late yet.'
'Miss Kenton,' I assured him, 'is a devoted
professional.
I know that she has no wish for a family.'
But Mr Graham smiled and shook his head, saying:
'Never believe a housekeeper who tells you
she doesn't want a family.
You and I have known at least a dozen housekeepers
who said they didn't want families, then got
married and left the profession.'
I could not accept Mr Graham's theory at first.
Afterwards, however, I must admit that I began
to suspect that Miss Kenton had an admirer.
There were little signs which seemed to support
Mr Graham's theory.
For instance, I noticed that Miss Kenton had
started to receive letters about once a week.
I also noticed sudden changes in her general
mood which I had not noticed before.
Sometimes she became extremely cheerful for
no apparent reason.
I do not know why, but this alarmed me more
than the times when she suddenly became silent
and depressed.
She was always thoroughly professional, of
course, and I had no reason to complain about
her work.
Nevertheless, it was my duty to think about
the future of the house.
I therefore asked her about her plans one
evening while we were drinking our cocoa:
'Will you be going out again on Thursday,
Miss Kenton?
On your day off, I mean.'
Instead of being angry at my question, as
I had expected, Miss Kenton actually seemed
rather pleased to discuss this topic with
me.
'Oh, Mr Stevens,' she said, 'it's just someone
I once knew when I was at Granchester Lodge.
In fact, he was the butler there at the time,
but now he's left service altogether and he
works for a local business.
He somehow found out that I was here and started
writing to me.
In one of his letters a few weeks ago, he
suggested that we meet occasionally in town.'
'I see, Miss Kenton.
I'm sure it is a good idea to leave the house
at times.'
Miss Kenton agreed, and there was a short
silence.
Then she went on:
'I remember when he was butler at Granchester
Lodge, he had very ambitious ideas.
I'm sure he planned, one day, to become butler
of a house like this.
Oh, but when I think of some of his methods!
I'm not surprised that he never progressed
in his career.'
I gave a small laugh.
'At these higher levels, Miss Kenton, the
profession is not for everybody.
Without certain qualities, a butler will simply
not progress beyond a certain point.'
Miss Kenton seemed to consider this for a
moment, then said: 'It occurs to me, Mr Stevens,
that you are a contented man.
You are at the top of your profession.
I really cannot imagine what more you might
wish for in life.'
I could think of no immediate response to
this.
There was an awkward silence, during which
Miss Kenton stared down into her cocoa.
In the end, after some consideration, I said:
'I will not be perfectly content, Miss Kenton,
until I have done everything I can to help
his lordship through the great tasks that
he has set himself.
Only when his lordship's work is complete,
Miss Kenton, will I be able to call myself
a contented man.'
She may have been a little puzzled by my words,
or perhaps in some way they displeased her,
for her mood suddenly seemed to change.
Our conversation rapidly lost its personal
tone and became more formal.
Not long after this, we stopped having meetings
over cocoa in her room.
In fact, I can remember our last cocoa together
very clearly.
I was discussing with her the complicated
plans I had made for a weekend gathering of
important people from Scotland.
When I had been talking for a while, I realized
that Miss Kenton was contributing very little
to our conversation.
It was obvious that she was thinking about
something else.
I did, from time to time, stop talking in
order to ask her:
'Do you understand, Miss Kenton?'
Then her attention would briefly return, before
floating away again a few seconds later.
After several more minutes of this, I finally
said to her:
'I'm sorry, Miss Kenton, but I can see no
reason to continue our conversation.
You do not seem to appreciate the importance
of this discussion.'
'I'm sorry, Mr Stevens,' she said, sitting
up a little.
'It's just that I'm rather tired this evening.'
'You are increasingly tired now, Miss Kenton.
You never used to make tiredness your excuse.'
To my amazement, Miss Kenton responded to
this with sudden anger:
'Mr Stevens, I have had a very busy week.
I am very, very tired, Mr Stevens.
Can you not understand that?'
I decided not to enter into an argument with
her.
I paused for a moment before saying quite
calmly:
'If that is how you feel about it, Miss Kenton,
there is no need for us to continue with these
evening meetings.
I had no idea how inconvenient they had become
to you.'
'Mr Stevens, I only said that I was tired
tonight.'
'No, no, Miss Kenton, it is perfectly understandable.
There are many other ways for us to communicate
with each other without having to meet every
evening.'
Miss Kenton made more protests, but she could
not change my mind.
There was no point in continuing our evening
meetings if she was always too tired to say
anything.
'May I suggest,' I said finally, 'that in
future we communicate important information
to each other during the working day.
If we are unable to find each other, I suggest
that we leave written messages.
Now, Miss Kenton, I apologize for keeping
you up so long.
Thank you for the cocoa.'
CHAPTER TWELVE
Miss Kenton's Aunt
Over the following weeks, Miss Kenton suggested
several times that we start meeting again
over cocoa in the evenings.
I have often wondered whether things would
have happened differently if I had agreed.
It seems clear to me now that my small decision
to stop our evening meetings was, in fact,
another important turning point in our relationship.
But, I suppose, if one keeps searching one's
past for 'turning points', one will start
seeing them everywhere.
Perhaps the most important 'turning point'
of all was neither of the two incidents I
have just described.
Perhaps it was my meeting with Miss Kenton
in the dining room soon after she had heard
of her aunt's death.
News of the death had arrived some hours earlier.
Indeed, I had handed the letter to Miss Kenton
myself.
I had stepped inside her room for a brief
moment to discuss a professional matter, and
she had opened the letter while we sat at
her table, talking.
She suddenly became very still, but she showed
no emotion as she read the letter through
at least twice.
Then she put the letter carefully back in
its envelope and looked across the table at
me.
'It is from Mrs Johnson, a companion of my
aunt.
She says my aunt died the day before yesterday.
The funeral takes place tomorrow.
I would be grateful if I could have the day
off, Mr Stevens.'
'I am sure that can be arranged, Miss Kenton.'
'Thank you, Mr Stevens.
Forgive me, but perhaps I may have a few moments
alone.'
'Of course, Miss Kenton.'
I made my exit but, just after I had left
her room, I realized that I had not offered
her my condolences.
Her aunt had been like a mother to her, and
her death must have come as a terrible shock.
I paused outside her door in the corridor,
wondering if I should go back and say a few
words.
But then it occurred to me that she might
prefer to be alone with her private grief.
I hesitated for several minutes outside her
door.
Eventually, however, I decided that it would
be best to express my condolences later, and
I continued on my way.
I thought about Miss Kenton all morning, wondering
how I could help her in her time of grief,
but I did not see her again until the afternoon.
I was busy with a task in the hall when I
heard her footsteps entering the dining room.
I waited for a couple of minutes, then followed
her in.
'Ah, Miss Kenton,' I said.
'How are you this afternoon?'
'Quite well, thank you, Mr Stevens.'
'Is everything in order?'
'Yes, thank you.'
'I was wondering about the new members of
staff.
Have you been experiencing any problems with
them?'
I gave a small laugh.
'There are often problems when so many new
people join the staff at once.'
'Thank you, Mr Stevens, but the new girls
are very satisfactory.'
'You don't think that there should be any
changes to the present staff plan?'
'I don't think so, Mr Stevens.
However, if I change my view on this, I will
let you know immediately.'
She turned her attention back to her work
and, for a moment, I thought about leaving
the dining room.
In fact, I actually took a few steps towards
the doorway, but then I turned to her again
and said:
'So, Miss Kenton.
The new members of staff are making good progress,
you say?'
'They are both doing very well, I assure you.'
'Ah, that is good to hear.'
I gave another short laugh.
'I was only wondering because neither girl
has previous experience of working in a house
of this size.'
'Indeed, Mr Stevens.'
I watched her while she worked, waiting to
see if she would say anything more.
When, after several moments, it became clear
that she was not going to speak, I said:
'There is actually something that I would
like to say, Miss Kenton.'
Miss Kenton glanced over her shoulder in my
direction, but continued working.
'I have noticed that there has been a slight
fall in standards recently, Miss Kenton.
One or two errors have been made.
I do feel that you need to pay a little more
attention to the new members of staff.'
'Whatever do you mean, Mr Stevens?'
'I myself like to pay extra attention to things
whenever there are new staff members.
I check everything, and see how they behave
with other members of staff.
I regret to say this, Miss Kenton, but I believe
you have been a little careless in the matter.'
For a second, Miss Kenton looked confused.
Then she turned towards me, and a certain
strain was visible in her face.
'I beg your pardon, Mr Stevens?'
'For instance, Miss Kenton, I have noticed
that the dishes are not being put back correctly
on the shelves in the kitchen.'
'Indeed, Mr Stevens?'
'Yes, Miss Kenton.
Furthermore, that little corner outside the
breakfast room has not been dusted for some
time.
And there are one or two other small things
I could mention.'
'You have made your point, Mr Stevens.
I will, as you suggest, check the work of
the new maids.'
'It is not like you to be so forgetful, Miss
Kenton.'
Miss Kenton looked away from me with a look
of confusion on her face.
She looked more tired than upset.
Then she suddenly turned away from her work,
said, 'Please excuse me, Mr Stevens,' and
left the room.
But it is pointless now to wish that particular
incidents had ended differently.
Naturally, when one looks back on moments
like this, they may indeed seem to be 'turning
points'.
But of course, at that time, these things
did not seem so important.
There seemed to be a never-ending number of
days, months and years ahead - plenty of time
in which to sort out the small problems that
existed between Miss Kenton and me.
There was nothing at the time to indicate
that small incidents like these would, in
the end, be responsible for destroying whole
dreams.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
A Difficult Evening
September 1956
I see that my memories are becoming more and
more upsetting.
This is probably because of the difficult
evening I have just had.
My present mood is also possibly connected
to the fact that tomorrow - if I can find
some petrol - I shall be arriving in Little
Compton and I shall be seeing Miss Kenton
again for the first time in twenty years.
Of course, I expect our interview to be polite
and professional in character.
The most important thing is for me to discover
whether Miss Kenton is interested in returning
to Darlington Hall or not.
I have to confess that, having re-read her
letter, I am beginning to have doubts.
Although it seems that her marriage, sadly,
has broken down, and that she is without a
home, I cannot find any words which state
clearly that she wishes to return.
But there is something about the way she describes
her memories of the house that is definitely
nostalgic.
It would not surprise me to discover that
she would be happy to come back.
But again, why am I wasting time imagining
what might or might not happen in the future?
It will happen soon enough.
And I have moved away from the subject of
this evenings events.
These last few hours, I have to say, have
been very difficult for me.
I am sure that my kind hosts, Mr and Mrs Taylor,
did not deliberately intend to make me suffer.
But as soon as I had sat down to supper at
their table, a most uncomfortable situation
began to develop.
***
A large, rough wooden table dominated the
room downstairs at the front of the cottage.
On its surface there were many small marks
left over the years by bread-knives and other
sharp instruments.
I could see them clearly despite the fact
that the only light in the room came from
an oil lamp on a shelf in one corner.
'We've been without electricity for almost
two months,' Mr Taylor explained.
'But we don't miss it much.
There are a few houses in the village that
have never had electricity at all.
Oil gives a warmer light.'
Mrs Taylor served us with a good soup, and
I was looking forward to an hour or so of
pleasant conversation before going to bed.
However, just as we had finished supper and
Mr Taylor was pouring me a glass of home-made
beer, we heard footsteps on the stony path
outside.
'I wonder who that is?'
Mr Taylor said, a tone of mild curiosity in
his voice.
'It's George Andrews,' a voice came from outside.
'I was just passing.'
The next moment a well-built, middle-aged
man in farming clothes entered the room, and
Mr and Mrs Taylor gave him a warm welcome.
With the easy informality of a regular visitor,
he sat down on a small chair by the doorway
and removed his muddy boots.
Then he came towards the table, stopped and
stood in front of me like a soldier reporting
to an officer.
'The name's Andrews, sir,' he said.
'A very good evening to you.
I'm very sorry to hear about your problem,
but I'm sure you'll be happy spending the
night here in Moscombe.'
The fact that Mr Andrews had heard about my
'problem' puzzled me.
But I replied with a smile that I was very
grateful for the warm treatment I had received.
I had of course been referring to Mr and Mrs
Taylor's kindness, but Mr Andrews seemed to
think that my expression of thanks included
him because he immediately said:
'Oh no, sir, you're most welcome.
We're very pleased to have you.
We don't have gentlemen like you passing this
way very often.
We're all very pleased you could visit us.'
The way he said this seemed to suggest that
the whole village was aware of my 'problem'
and of my arrival at this cottage.
A few minutes later another visitor arrived.
He looked and behaved so much like Mr Andrews
that at first I thought they were brothers.
But then the newcomer introduced himself to
me as:
'Morgan, sir.
Trevor Morgan.'
Mr Morgan expressed regret concerning my 'problem',
and assured me that all would be well in the
morning.
He finished by saying:
'It's a privilege to have a gentleman like
yourself here in Moscombe, sir.'
Before I could think of a reply to this, a
middle-aged couple arrived and were introduced
to me as Mr and Mrs Harry Smith.
As they took their places around the table,
Mr Harry Smith said:
'I believe that beautiful old Ford up there
on Thornley Bush Hill, sir, is your car?'
I agreed, then added:
'But I'm surprised to hear you've seen it.'
'I've not seen it myself, sir.
But Dave Thornton passed it on his tractor
a short time ago as he was coming home.
He was so surprised to see it there, he actually
stopped and got out.'
Then Mr Smith turned to the others around
the table.
'It's an absolute beauty.
Dave said he'd never seen a car like it.'
'Your health, sir,' somebody said, lifting
a glass of beer, and everybody around the
table drank to my health.
I smiled and said:
'I assure you, the privilege is all mine.'
'You're very kind, sir,' Mrs Smith said.
'You're a real gentleman.
Not like Mr Lindsay.
He may have had a lot of money, but he was
no gentleman.'
There was general agreement with this comment,
and Mr Taylor explained by saying:
'Mr Lindsay used to live in the big house
not far from here, sir.
He wasn't very popular.'
Mrs Smith then leaned towards me and said:
'We told Doctor Carlisle you were here, sir.
The doctor would be very pleased to meet you.'
'I expect he has patients to see,' Mrs Taylor
added apologetically 'I'm afraid we can't
say for certain when he'll be here.'
Before I could reply, Mr Harry Smith leaned
forward and said:
'That Mr Lindsay, he had it all wrong, see?
Acting the way he did, thinking he was so
wonderful.
But he soon learnt his lesson.'
'He was no gentleman,' Mr Taylor agreed.
'That's right, sir,' Mr Harry Smith said.
'He had a fine house and good suits, but we
could all tell he was no gentleman.'
'That's true,' Mr Taylor said.
'You can always tell a real gentleman.
You, for example, sir.
It's not just the style of your clothes, or
your fine way of speaking.
There's something else that shows you're a
gentleman.
Hard to say exactly what it is, but it's clear
for everyone to see.'
There were more sounds of agreement around
the table.
Mr Morgan, who had said little since his arrival,
bent forward and said to me:
'What do you think it is, sir?
Maybe someone who's got it has a better idea
of what it is.
We're all talking about who's got it and who
hasn't, and we don't know what we're talking
about.
Perhaps you could tell us, sir?'
There was silence around the table and everybody
looked at me.
I gave a small cough and said:
'It is hardly for me to say what qualities
I may or may not possess.
But in answer to your question, I suspect
that the word you're looking for is dignity.'
'There's a lot of truth in that, sir,' Mr
Andrews nodded, and a number of voices agreed
with him.
But Harry Smith said:
'Excuse me for not agreeing with you completely,
sir, but in my opinion dignity doesn't just
belong to gentlemen.
Dignity's something every man and woman in
the country can get, if they try.
Forgive me, sir, but we like to express our
opinions directly around here.'
I decided that it would be too complicated
to attempt to argue with him, so I just smiled
and said:
'Of course, you're quite correct.'
Mr Harry Smith, however, had not finished.
He leaned even further forward and began to
talk about the war.
In his opinion, everybody who fought Hitler
was a hero.
Every Englishman who risked his life in order
to defend the country had an important part
to play.
There should be freedom of speech and dignity
for all Englishmen, rich or poor.
It didn't matter how poor or uneducated a
person was.
Everybody's opinion was important, and the
government should pay attention to what people
from villages like Moscornbe wanted to say.
Mr Taylor tried to interrupt, but nothing
could stop Mr Harry Smith.
After several minutes, he finished by saying:
'I'm not talking politics, sir.
I'm just saying that you can't have dignity
if you're a slave.
That's why we fought Hitler.
For the freedom to have dignity, however poor
we might be.'
'This may seem like a small, unimportant place,
sir,' his wife then added.
'But we lost many young men in the war.'
At this, the room went very quiet.
Finally, Mr Taylor broke the silence by saying
to me:
'Harry does a lot of organizing for our local
member of parliament.
He loves telling everybody what's wrong with
the country.'
'Ah, but I was saying what's right about the
country.'
Mr Harry Smith attempted to start arguing
again.
But Mr Andrews ignored him and asked me:
'Have you had any connection with politics
yourself, sir?'
'Not directly,' I said.
'And certainly not these days.
More before the war, perhaps.'
'It's just that I remember a Mr Stevens who
was a member of parliament a couple of years
ago.
That wasn't you, was it, sir?'
'Oh no,' I said with a laugh.
I am not at all sure what made me make my
next statement.
I can only say that it seemed somehow appropriate
to the circumstances.
For then I said:
'In fact, I was more involved in international
affairs than domestic ones.'
At these words, my listeners looked at me
with a mixture of wonder and respect.
I added quickly:
'Of course, I was never in government myself.
I was only an unofficial adviser.'
But they continued to stare at me quietly.
Finally Mrs Taylor broke the silence and said:
'Excuse me, sir, have you ever met Mr Churchill?'
'Mr Churchill?
He did come to the house on a number of occasions.
But frankly, Mrs Taylor, while I was involved
in great affairs, Mr Churchill was not as
important as he later became.
People like Mr Eden and Lord Halifax were
more frequent visitors in those days.'
'But you have actually met Mr Churchill, sir?
That must have been a great honour.'
'I don't agree with many things Mr Churchill
says,' Mr Harry Smith said, 'but he's a great
man.
It must have been an honour to discuss things
with him.'
'It was, as you say, a privilege to be in
such a great man's company,' I said.
'It is true that I have been very fortunate.
I have met not only Mr Churchill, but also
many other great men from America and Europe.
I have been very lucky to be able to advise
such important people on the great topics
of the day.
I do feel most grateful for my good fortune.'
The conversation continued in this way for
some time.
I was asked about the famous people I had
met, and Mr Harry Smith kept repeating how
important it was for people 'in high places'
to listen to the opinions of ordinary people
like himself.
Suddenly his wife said:
'I wonder where Doctor Carlisle is.
I'm sure the gentleman would appreciate some
educated talk now.'
Everybody laughed.
I decided the time was right for me to go
to bed.
'Although it has been extremely enjoyable
to meet you all,' I said, 'I must confess
I'm beginning to feel a little tired...'
'Of course, sir,' Mrs Taylor said, 'you must
be exhausted.
Perhaps I'll fetch another blanket for you.
It's getting much colder at night now.'
'No, I assure you, Mrs Taylor, I'll be perfectly
comfortable.'
But before I could rise from the table, Mr
Morgan said:
'Ah, there's someone coming.
I expect that's the doctor.'
'I really must go,' I said.
'I feel quite exhausted.'
'But I'm sure this is the doctor now, sir,'
said Mrs Smith.
'Do wait a few more minutes.'
Just as she said this, there was a knock on
the door and a voice said:
'It's only me, Mrs Taylor.'
Doctor Carlisle was a tall, thin gentleman
of about forty years old.
No sooner had he said good evening to everybody
than Mrs Taylor said to him:
'This is our gentleman here, Doctor.
His car's stuck up at Thornley Bush and he's
been having to listen to Harry's speeches
as a result.'
The doctor came up to the table.
'Richard Carlisle,' he said with a cheerful
smile as I rose to shake his hand.
'Bad luck about your car.
Still, I hope you're being well looked after.'
'Thank you,' I replied.
'Everyone has been most kind.'
'Well, nice to have you with us.'
Doctor Carlisle sat down directly opposite
me.
'Which part of the country are you from?'
'Oxfordshire,' I said.
Indeed, I found it hard to resist the urge
to add 'sir'.
'I have an uncle who lives just outside Oxford.
Fine part of the country.'
'The gentleman was just telling us, Doctor,'
Mrs Smith said, 'that he knows Mr Churchill.'
'Really?
I used to know a nephew of his, but we've
lost touch.
Never had the privilege of meeting the great
man, though.'
'And not only Mr Churchill,' Mrs Smith went
on.
'He knows Mr Eden and Lord Halifax.'
'Really?'
The doctor's eyes examined me closely.
Before I could make an appropriate remark,
however, Mr Andrews said to the doctor:
'The gentleman was telling us that before
the war he was involved in foreign affairs.'
'Indeed?'
The doctor went on studying me for several
seconds, then he regained his cheerful manner
and asked:
'Touring around for pleasure?'
'Mainly,' I said, and gave a small laugh.
'Plenty of nice country around here.'
Then he turned to talk to Mr Andrews about
something he had borrowed and had not yet
returned.
For a short time, I was no longer the centre
of attention and I was able to remain silent.
Then, at an appropriate moment, I rose to
my feet and said:
'Please excuse me.
It has been a most enjoyable evening, but
I am really very tired.'
Mrs Smith and a few others tried to persuade
me to stay, while Doctor Carlisle studied
me closely.
Eventually, however, I began to make my way
around the table.
To my embarrassment, everyone in the room,
including Doctor Carlisle, rose to their feet.
I thanked everybody again for their kindness
and good company.
I had almost left the room when the doctor's
voice caused me to stop at the door.
'Mr Stevens, I have to go to Stanbury first
thing in the morning.
I'd be happy to give you a lift to your car.
It will save you the walk.
And we can pick up a can of petrol on the
way.'
'That's most kind,' I said.
'But I don't wish to put you to any trouble.'
'No trouble at all.
Seven thirty all right for you?'
'That would be most helpful, thank you.'
There was another exchange of goodnights,
and I was at last allowed to withdraw to my
room.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Dignity
I feel very uncomfortable about what has just
happened, but I don't know how I could have
prevented the misunderstanding regarding my
identity.
By the time I was aware of what was happening,
things had already gone too far.
I could not have told these people the truth
without much embarrassment.
On the other hand, I do not see that any real
harm has been done.
I will, after all, be leaving these people
in the morning and will probably never meet
them again.
I ought to stop worrying myself about the
matter.
However, apart from the unfortunate misunderstanding,
there is something else about this evening
that deserves some thought: Mr Harry Smith's
comments regarding the nature of 'dignity'.
There is, I suppose, some truth in the idea
that poor people are as capable of dignity
as rich people.
Perhaps everybody in the land has a duty to
think about the important matters of the day.
But in reality, how can ordinary people be
expected to have 'strong opinions' on everything
- as Mr Harry Smith believes that the villagers
here do?
In my opinion, these expectations are not
only impossible but also undesirable.
There is, after all, a real limit to how much
ordinary people can learn and know It cannot
be wise, surely, to expect every single person
to be able to contribute 'strong opinions'
to the great debates of the nation.
I remember an instance which illustrates the
limitations of Mr Harry Smith's arguments
rather well.
It occurred before the war, around 1935.
Very late one night, I was called to the drawing
room, where his lordship had been entertaining
three gentlemen since dinner.
I had, of course, been called to the drawing
room many times that evening.
On each occasion, the three gentlemen had
been deep in serious conversation.
When I entered the drawing room on this last
occasion, however, all the gentlemen stopped
talking and looked at me.
Then his lordship said:
'Step this way a moment, will you, Stevens?
Mr Spencer here wishes to have a word with
you.'
Mr Spencer looked at me for a moment from
his armchair, then said:
'My good man, I have a question for you.
We need your help on a certain topic that
we've been debating.
Tell me, do you think our debts to America
are responsible for the present low levels
of trade?'
I was naturally a little surprised by this,
but then quickly understood the situation.
The gentleman clearly expected me to be puzzled
by his question.
It took me a moment or two to realize what
was happening, but in that time I must have
given the wrong impression.
The gentlemen in the room probably thought
that I was trying to think of an answer to
the question, for I saw them all exchange
amused smiles.
'I'm very sorry, sir,' I said, 'but I am unable
to be of assistance on this matter.'
I was by now in control of the situation,
but the gentlemen went on smiling.
Then Mr Spencer said:
'Then perhaps you will help us with another
matter.
Do you think that the economic problems in
Europe would improve if there was a military
agreement between France and Russia?'
'I'm very sorry, sir, but I am unable to be
of assistance on this matter either.'
'Oh dear,' said Mr Spencer.
'So you can't help us.'
There was more quiet laughter, then his lordship
said:
'Thank you, Stevens.
That is all.'
But Mr Spencer had not finished.
'Please, Darlington,' he said.
'I have one more question to ask your good
man here.
I very much wanted his advice concerning a
problem that has been bothering us all recently.
My good fellow, please help us.
What was Monsieur Laval really intending when
he made his recent speech about North Africa?'
'I'm sorry, sir, but I am unable to assist
in this matter.'
'You see, gentleman,' Mr Spencer turned to
the others and said, 'our man is unable to
assist us in these matters.'
The laughter became louder, and he went on:
'But we still continue with the ridiculous
belief that our good man here, and a few million
others like him, should decide how to run
the country.
With a parliamentary system like ours, I'm
not surprised that we never seem able to find
solutions to any of our problems.
It would be just as good to ask the mothers'
union to organize a war.'
There was open laughter at this comment, during
which his lordship said quietly:
'Thank you, Stevens.
That is all.'
The following morning his lordship came into
the games room, where I was dusting the paintings,
and said:
'I'm sorry, Stevens.
"We were awful to you last night.'
'Not at all, sir,' I said from the top of
my stepladder.
'I was only happy to be of service.'
'It was terrible.
I think we'd all had too much to drink.
Please accept my apologies.'
'Thank you, sir.
But I am happy to assure you I was not offended
at all.'
His lordship walked over to a leather armchair
and sat down with a tired look on his face.
For a while he stared out of the windows at
the winter sunshine over the hills.
I looked down from my stepladder and was suddenly
aware of how much his lordship had changed
in recent years.
The pressures of life had had a great effect
on him.
He had become extremely thin, his hair had
gone completely white and there were deep
lines on his face.
Suddenly, his lordship spoke.
'You must understand, Stevens, we're making
terrible mistakes in this country.
If it's any comfort to you, last night you
did contribute to our discussion.
There's too much nonsense nowadays about ordinary
people telling the government what to do.'
'Indeed, sir.'
'We're really too slow in this country to
recognize when something's out of date.
Other great nations have recognized the fact
that change is needed.
But our country...'
Lord Darlington stared in silence at the view
from the window for a moment, and sadly shook
his head.
'Our country is always the last to change.
One day soon, we'll need to accept the fact
that democracy is old-fashioned and doesn't
work in today's complicated world.'
'The nation does seem to be in a regrettable
condition, sir,' I said.
'Absolutely, Stevens.
Look at Germany and Italy.
See what strong leadership can achieve if
they're free to act.
No democratic nonsense there.
If your house is on fire, you don't call the
staff into the drawing room and discuss the
best method of escape for an hour, do you?'
As I remember these words, it occurs to me
that many of Lord Darlington's ideas probably
seem rather odd today - perhaps even unattractive.
But there is surely some truth in what he
said to me that morning in the games room.
Of course, it is ridiculous to expect a butler
to answer the sort of questions that Mr Spencer
asked me that night.
It is clearly nonsense, therefore, for Mr
Harry Smith to say that people can only have
dignity if their voices are heard in high
places.
The fact is, the great affairs of the nation
will always be too complicated for people
like you and me to understand.
Only great gentlemen like Lord Darlington
can decide what is right and what is not right
for our country.
It is the duty of the rest of us to serve
these gentlemen to the best of our ability.
Throughout the years I served him, Lord Darlington
always made all the important decisions.
I was not expected to offer him advice or
judgement.
It was my duty to be loyal to him, and not
to worry about whether he was right or wrong.
I was devoted to him and I performed my duties
as well as I was able.
Indeed, many may consider my performance of
my duties to have been 'first class'.
It is hardly my fault if many people now believe
that his lordship's life and work were a sad
waste.
The passage of time may now show that some
of Lord Darlington's efforts were foolish,
but I have no regrets about my part in things.
It is illogical for me to feel any shame.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
The Rose Garden Hotel
I have finally arrived at Little Compton,
in Cornwall.
I have recently finished lunch and am now
sitting in the dining hall of the Rose Garden
Hotel.
Outside, the rain is falling steadily.
I have spent much of the past hour watching
the rain falling on the village square.
I have considered leaving now to meet Miss
Kenton, but in my letter I informed her that
I would see her at three o'clock.
I do not want to surprise her by arriving
too early.
If the rain does not stop, I shall probably
remain here and drink tea until the proper
time for me to go.
I am surprised that it is raining, because
the sun was shining brightly this morning
when I got up.
Mrs Taylor cooked me a fine breakfast of farm
eggs and toast, and Doctor Carlisle called
for me at seven thirty, as he had promised.
'I found a can of petrol for you,' he announced
as soon as I had said goodbye to the Taylors.
I thanked him and offered to pay, but he refused
to accept my money.
'Nonsense,' he said.
'It's just enough for you to reach the next
village.
They have a proper garage there.'
I sat in the passenger seat of Doctor Carlisle's
car as he drove out of the village and up
a narrow road between tall trees.
After asking me how I had slept at the Taylors,
he said quite suddenly:
'I hope you don't think I'm being rude.
But you aren't a manservant by any chance,
are you?'
I must confess, I felt some relief when I
heard this question.
'I am indeed, sir.
In fact, I am the butler of Darlington Hall,
near Oxford.'
'I thought so.
When I heard that you had met Winston Churchill,
I thought that you were either lying or that
you must be a kind of servant.'
He turned to me with a friendly smile, and
I said:
'It was not my intention to deceive anyone,
sir.
However'
'Oh, there's no need to explain.
I can see how it happened.
I mean, the people around here are sure to
think you're at least a lord.'
The doctor laughed loudly.
'It's probably good to be mistaken for a lord
from time to time.'
We travelled in silence for a few moments,
then Doctor Carlisle said to me:
'Well, I hope you enjoyed your little stay
with us here.'
'I did very much, thank you, sir.'
'I wish you wouldn't call me "sir" all the
time, Mr Stevens.
Now this road should be familiar to you.
Probably looks rather different in the daylight.
Is that the car there?
What a handsome vehicle!'
Doctor Carlisle stopped just behind the Ford,
got out and said again:
'What a handsome vehicle.'
Then he quickly produced the can of petrol
and kindly filled the tank of the Ford for
me.
When I sat once again in the driving seat
and turned the key, the engine came to life.
I thanked Doctor Carlisle and we said goodbye
to each other.
I followed his car along the twisting hill
road for two or three kilometres, and then
he turned off towards Stanbury and I was alone
again.
I crossed the border into Cornwall at about
nine o'clock.
This was three hours before the rain began,
and the clouds were still a brilliant white.
In fact, the scenery was some of the most
beautiful I had ever seen.
Unfortunately, I did not pay it the attention
it deserved, because I was thinking for most
of the time about Miss Kenton.
Before the end of the day, I kept thinking,
I would be meeting her again for the first
time in twenty years.
And now, as I sit here in Little Compton,
watching the rain as it splashes on the pavements
of the village square outside, my mind keeps
returning to the past.
I have been thinking about one thing in particular
all morning.
I remember standing alone in the corridor
outside Miss Kenton's room.
I was standing half turned towards her door,
wondering whether or not I should knock.
For some reason I was sure that behind that
door, just a few metres away from me, Miss
Kenton was crying.
As I stood there, a very strange feeling rose
inside me.
I can't remember exactly why I was standing
there.
I suggested earlier that this might have been
just after Miss Kenton received news of her
aunt's death.
But now, having thought more about it, I believe
I may have been a little confused about this
matter.
I think it is more likely that this incident
took place one evening a few months later.
It was the evening when the young Mr Cardinal
arrived at Darlington Hall rather unexpectedly.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Events of International Significance
Mr Cardinal's father, a close friend and colleague
of his lordship's for many years, had been
tragically killed in a riding accident three
or four years earlier.
Meanwhile, young Mr Cardinal had become a
journalist famous for his funny, clever articles
on international affairs.
Lord Darlington did not like Mr Cardinal's
articles very much.
He often used to look up from his newspaper
and say something like:
'Young Reggie's writing such nonsense again.
I'm glad his father's not alive to read this.'
But Mr Cardinal's articles did not prevent
him from being a frequent visitor at the house.
Indeed, his lordship treated him like a member
of his own family, although Mr Cardinal still
always gave prior warning of his visits.
That evening, therefore, I was a little surprised
when I answered the door and saw him standing
there.
'Oh, hello, Stevens, how are you?' he said.
'I was just wondering if I could stay for
the night.
I've got a bit of a problem, I'm afraid.'
'It is very nice to see you again, sir.
I shall tell his lordship you are here.'
'I had intended to stay at Mr Roland's place,
but there's been a misunderstanding and they've
gone away somewhere.
I hope it's not too inconvenient.
I mean, there aren't any special arrangements
for tonight, are there?'
'I believe, sir, that his lordship is expecting
some gentlemen to call after dinner.'
'Oh, that's bad luck.
I seem to have chosen a bad night.
I'd better stay out of the way, I think.
I've got some work to do, anyway.'
'I shall tell his lordship that you are here,
sir.
You are in good time to join him for dinner.'
I left Mr Cardinal in the drawing room and
made my way to the study, where his lordship
was working on some papers.
When I told him of Mr Cardinal's arrival,
a look of surprised annoyance crossed his
face.
Then he leaned back in his chair with a deep
frown.
'Tell Mr Cardinal I'll be down soon,' he said
finally.
When I returned downstairs, I discovered Mr
Cardinal walking around the drawing room.
He seemed rather nervous.
I gave him his lordship's message and asked
him if he would like some refreshments.
'Just some tea, thank you, Stevens.
Who is his lordship expecting tonight?'
'I'm sorry, sir.
I'm afraid I'm unable to tell you.'
'No idea at all?'
'I'm sorry, sir.'
'Hmm, interesting.
Oh well, I'd better stay out of the way.'
Soon afterwards, I went down to Miss Kenton's
room.
She was sitting at her table, although there
was nothing in front of her and her hands
were empty.
Indeed, something about her suggested that
she had been sitting like that for some time.
'Mr Cardinal is here, Miss Kenton,' I said.
'He'll require his usual room tonight.'
'Very well, Mr Stevens.
I shall prepare it before I leave.'
'Ah, you are going out this evening, Miss
Kenton?'
'I am indeed, Mr Stevens.'
Perhaps I looked a little surprised, for she
went on:
'You will recall, Mr Stevens, that we discussed
this a fortnight ago.'
'Yes, of course, Miss Kenton.
I beg your pardon.
I had forgotten.'
'Is something the matter, Mr Stevens?'
'Not at all, Miss Kenton.
Some visitors are expected this evening, but
your presence will not be required.'
'We agreed a fortnight ago, Mr Stevens, that
I could have this evening off.'
'Of course, Miss Kenton.
I do beg your pardon.'
I turned to leave, but then I was stopped
at the door by Miss Kenton saying:
'Mr Stevens, I have something to tell you.'
'Yes, Miss Kenton?'
'It is about my friend, whom I am going to
meet tonight.'
'Yes, Miss Kenton.'
'He has asked me to marry him.
I thought I ought to tell you.'
'Indeed, Miss Kenton.
That is very interesting.'
'I have not made up my mind yet.
He starts a new job in the West Country next
month.
As I say, I haven't decided yet.
But I thought you should be informed of the
situation.'
'I'm very grateful, Miss Kenton.
I do hope you have a pleasant evening.
Now please excuse me.'
I met Miss Kenton again about twenty minutes
later.
I was halfway up the back stairs carrying
a heavy tray when I heard the sound of angry
footsteps on the floor below me.
Turning, I saw Miss Kenton staring up at me
from the foot of the stairs.
'Mr Stevens, do I understand that you wish
me to remain on duty this evening?'
'Not at all, Miss Kenton.
As you explained, you did inform me of your
intentions some time ago.'
'But I can see you are very unhappy about
my absence tonight.'
'Not at all, Miss Kenton.'
'Then why are you making so much noise in
the kitchen?
And why do you keep marching up and down the
corridor outside my room?
Were you hoping to make me change my mind?'
'Miss Kenton, the slight excitement in the
kitchen is only because Mr Cardinal has come
to dinner.
There is absolutely no reason why you should
not go out this evening.'
'I intend to go out, Mr Stevens.
I wish to make this clear.
I made arrangements weeks ago.'
'Indeed, Miss Kenton.
And once again, I wish you a very pleasant
evening.'
There was an odd atmosphere at dinner that
evening between the two gentlemen.
For long moments, they ate in silence.
During one of these silences, Mr Cardinal
said:
'Something special tonight, sir?'
'Eh?'
'Your visitors this evening.
Special?'
'I'm afraid I can't tell you, my boy.'
'Oh dear.
I suppose this means I can't join you.'
'Join me in what?'
'Whatever's taking place tonight.'
'Oh, it wouldn't interest you.
Besides, it's private.
And you're a journalist.'
After dinner, the gentlemen went into the
smoking room.
However, in contrast to their quiet mood at
dinner, they soon began to exchange angry
words with each other.
Of course, I did not stop to listen, but I
could not avoid hearing his lordship shouting:
'But that's not your business, my boy!
Not your business!'
I was in the dining room when the two gentlemen
eventually came out.
They seemed calmer.
As they crossed the hall, his lordship turned
to Mr Cardinal and said:
'Now remember, my boy I'm trusting you.'
'Yes, yes,' Mr Cardinal said with some annoyance.
'I promise.'
At eight thirty, I heard the sound of motors
outside.
I opened the door to a policeman.
Over his shoulder I could see that other policemen
with guns were moving off in different directions.
The next moment, I was showing two very important
gentlemen into the hall, where they were met
by his lordship.
He quickly took them into the drawing room.
Ten minutes later there was the sound of another
car and I opened the door to Herr Ribbentrop,
the German Ambassador.
He, too, disappeared quickly into the drawing
room.
A few minutes later, when I was called in
to provide refreshments, the four gentlemen
were discussing sausages.
The atmosphere seemed, on the surface, quite
friendly.
After serving the four gentlemen with drinks,
I went to my position near the entrance in
the hall.
I had been standing there for two hours when
the back doorbell was rung.
When I went down, I discovered a policeman
standing there with Miss Kenton.
He asked me to confirm her identity.
Minutes later, as I was shutting the door,
I noticed Miss Kenton waiting for me, and
said:
'I hope you had a pleasant evening, Miss Kenton.'
She made no reply, so I repeated my comment
as we were crossing the floor of the unlit
kitchen.
'I did, thank you, Mr Stevens,' she said at
last.
'I'm pleased to hear that.'
Behind me, Miss Kenton's footsteps suddenly
stopped, and I heard her say:
'Are you not at all interested in what took
place between my friend and me, Mr Stevens?'
'I do not mean to be rude, Miss Kenton, but
I really must return upstairs immediately.
Events of international significance are taking
place in this house.'
'Very well, Mr Stevens.
As you are in such a hurry, I shall be brief.
I have accepted my friend's proposal of marriage.'
'Really, Miss Kenton?
Then may I offer you my congratulations.'
'Thank you, Mr Stevens.
Of course, I will not break my contract, but
I would be very grateful if you could release
me earlier.
My friend begins his new job in the West Country
in two weeks' time.'
'I will do my best to find a replacement at
the earliest opportunity, Miss Kenton,' I
said.
'Now please excuse me.
I must return upstairs.'
I started to walk away again but, just as
I had reached the door, I heard Miss Kenton's
voice.
'Mr Stevens,' she said, her voice echoing
strangely in the dark and empty kitchen.
'After the many years of service I have given
in this house, is that all you have to say?'
'Miss Kenton, you have my warmest congratulations.
But I repeat, there are matters of international
importance taking place upstairs, and I must
return immediately.'
'Did you know, Mr Stevens, that you have been
a very important figure for my friend and
me?'
'Really, Miss Kenton?'
'Yes, Mr Stevens.
We often amuse ourselves with little stories
about you.'
'Indeed, Miss Kenton.
Now please excuse me.'
I went up to the hall and returned to my position
by the main door.
However, five minutes later, Mr Cardinal appeared
in the doorway of the library and signalled
for me to come over.
'Hate to bother you, Stevens,' he said.
'But could you possibly fetch me a little
more whisky?
The bottle you brought in earlier seems to
be finished.'
'You are very welcome to whatever refreshments
you desire, sir.
However, as you have some work to do, I wonder
whether another bottle is a good idea?'
'My work will be fine, Stevens.
So be a good fellow and get me another bottle.'
'Very well, sir.'
When I returned to the library a moment later,
Mr Cardinal was wandering around, reading
the names of books on the shelves.
As I approached, he sat down heavily into
a leather armchair.
I went over to him, poured a little whisky
and gave him the glass.
'You know, Stevens, we've been friends for
some time, haven't we?'
'Indeed, sir.'
'I always look forward to a little chat with
you whenever I come here.
Would you like to join me in a little drink?'
I politely refused his kind invitation, but
Mr Cardinal insisted.
'I do wish you'd sit down, Stevens.
I want us to talk as friends.'
'I'm sorry, sir.'
I put down my tray and sat down - in an appropriate
fashion - in the armchair that Mr Cardinal
was indicating.
'That's better,' Mr Cardinal said.
'Now, Stevens, I really ought to be truthful
with you.
As you have probably guessed, I didn't come
here tonight by accident.
Somebody told me about what's going on here.
I don't suppose you can tell me whether the
Prime Minister's here, can you?'
'The Prime Minister, sir?'
'Oh, it's all right, you don't have to tell
me.
I understand you're in a difficult position.'
He looked away tiredly for a moment towards
his papers, which were scattered over the
desk.
Then he turned to me again and said:
'You know, Stevens, his lordship's been like
a second father to me.
I care for him very deeply.
But we must face facts.
He's in trouble, and I'm extremely worried
about him.
He's dealing with very powerful people here,
and he doesn't really understand what's going
on.'
'Really, sir?'
'Stevens, do you know what's happening at
this exact moment in that room across the
hall?
There are four men in that room - I don't
need you to confirm it.
His lordship, the British Prime Minister,
the head of the Foreign Office and the German
Ambassador.
His lordship has worked hard for this meeting,
and he genuinely believes he's doing something
good and honourable.
Do you know why his lordship has brought these
gentlemen here tonight?'
'I'm afraid not, sir.'
'Tell me, Stevens, don't you care at all?
Aren't you curious?'
'I do not believe that I am not curious, sir.
However, it is not my job to display curiosity
about such matters.'
'I suppose you think that's being loyal?
To his lordship?
Or to the King?'
'I'm sorry, sir.
I fail to understand what you are proposing.'
Mr Cardinal shook his head sadly.
'I'm not proposing anything, Stevens.
Quite frankly, I don't know what we can do.
But I wish you would be more curious.'
He was silent for a moment and seemed to be
staring emptily at the area of carpet around
my feet.
Finally he looked up and said:
'Are you sure you won't join me in a drink,
Stevens?'
'No thank you, sir.'
'The fact is, Stevens, his lordship doesn't
realize what's happening.
He's become Herr Hitler's puppet.
Have you noticed what's been happening over
the last three or four years?'
'I'm sorry, sir, I'm afraid I have not.'
'Of course not, Stevens.
You're not curious.
The problem is, Stevens,' Mr Cardinal said,
moving into a more upright position in his
armchair, 'his lordship is a true, old English
gentleman.
He feels it is honourable to offer generosity
and friendship to a defeated enemy.
But they're using him, Stevens - the Nazis
are using him to help them achieve their own
terrible aims.
Do you remember that American senator all
those years ago?
He said the world was too complicated for
true gentlemen.
Well, he was right.
You've seen how they have used his lordship,
haven't you, Stevens?'
'I'm sorry, sir, but I cannot say that I have.'
'Well, I don't know about you, Stevens, but
I'm going to do something about it.
If Father were alive, he would do something
to stop it.
You have no idea what they're discussing in
that room across the hall, Stevens?
Then I'll tell you.
His lordship has been trying to persuade the
Prime Minister to accept an invitation to
visit Herr Hitler.
And that is not all, Stevens.
His lordship is discussing the possibility
of a royal visit to Germany.
Everybody knows the new king has always been
enthusiastic about the Nazis.
Well, apparently he's keen to accept Herr
Hitler's invitation.
His lordship is now trying to persuade the
British government to agree to this awful
idea.'
'I'm sorry, sir, but I have to say that I
trust his lordship's judgement completely.'
At that moment I heard the bell from the drawing
room.
I asked Mr Cardinal to excuse me, and I left
the room.
In the drawing room, the air was thick with
tobacco smoke.
The gentlemen sat and smoked in silence, while
his lordship asked me to bring up a bottle
of wine from the cellar.
As I was making my way along the darkness
of the corridor towards the cellar, the door
to Miss Kenton's room suddenly opened.
'I am surprised to find you still awake, Miss
Kenton,' I said when I saw her in the doorway.
'Mr Stevens, I was very foolish earlier,'
she said.
'Excuse me, Miss Kenton, but I have no time
to talk just now.'
'Mr Stevens, you must not take anything I
said earlier seriously.
I was simply being foolish.'
'Miss Kenton, I cannot remember what you may
be referring to.
Besides, events of great importance are developing
upstairs, and I cannot stop to chat with you.
I suggest that you go to bed.'
With that, I hurried on.
It did not take me long to find the bottle
in the cellar.
Just a few minutes after my brief meeting
with Miss Kenton, I was walking along the
corridor again on my return journey.
As I approached Miss Kenton's door, I saw
from the light around its edges that she was
still awake.
And that was the moment, I am now sure, that
has remained clearly in my memory to this
day.
At that moment, as I paused in the darkness
of the corridor, a tray in my hands, something
told me that just a few metres away, on the
other side of the door, Miss Kenton was crying.
I do not know why I was so sure of this.
I had certainly not heard any sounds of crying.
I do not know how long I remained standing
there.
At the time it seemed a significant period,
but in reality it was probably only a few
seconds.
For, of course, I was required to hurry upstairs
to serve some of the most important gentlemen
in Europe.
I'm sure that I would not have delayed there
for long.
After serving the gentlemen in the drawing
room, I returned to my position in the hall.
I stood there for another hour until the gentlemen
finally departed.
As I stood there, a strange thing began to
happen.
I began to experience a deep feeling of pride.
I had, after all, just come through an extremely
difficult evening, throughout which I had
managed to preserve my dignity.
My father would have been proud of the way
I had performed my duty that night.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Old Friends
September 1956
For many years I have often thought of visiting
the seaside town of Weymouth.
I have heard various people talk of pleasant
holidays here.
All of them mentioned the pier in particular,
and I have been walking up and down along
it for the last half-hour.
They especially recommended visiting the pier
in the evening, when it becomes lit up with
bulbs of various colours.
A moment ago, I learnt from an official that
the lights would be switched on soon, so I
have decided to sit down here on this bench
and wait for them to come on.
I have a good view of the sun setting over
the sea.
Although there is still plenty of daylight
left - it has been a splendid day - I can
see, here and there, lights starting to come
on all along the shore.
I arrived in this town yesterday afternoon,
and have decided to remain here for a second
night.
I need a rest from motoring, and if I make
an early start tomorrow, I shall be back at
Darlington Hall by tea-time.
It is now two days since my meeting with Miss
Kenton in the tea lounge of the Rose Garden
Hotel in Little Compton.
Miss Kenton surprised me by coming to the
hotel.
I was looking out of the window at the rain
when a member of the hotel staff came to inform
me that a lady wished to see me at reception.
I rose and left the dining hall, but at reception
I was told that the lady had gone into the
tea lounge.
The tea lounge was empty apart from Miss Kenton.
She rose as I entered, smiled and held out
her hand to me.
'Ah, Mr Stevens.
How nice to see you again.'
'Mrs Benn, how lovely.'
We moved two armchairs close to the window,
and sat and talked for the next two hours.
While we talked together, the rain continued
to fall steadily on the square outside.
A grey light from the window fell across her
face, and I noticed the lines around her eyes
and mouth.
But, on the whole, Miss Kenton looked surprisingly
similar to the person I remembered from twenty
years ago.
It was a great pleasure for me to see her
again.
For the first twenty minutes we chatted politely
about my journey.
As we talked, I began to notice other ways
in which Miss Kenton had changed since I last
saw her.
For instance, she appeared, somehow, slower.
It is possible that this was simply the calmness
that comes with age, but I could not help
thinking that it was more a sort of tiredness
with life.
Every now and then, when she was not speaking,
I thought I saw something like sadness in
her expression.
But I may have been mistaken about this.
The initial awkwardness of our conversation
soon developed into something more relaxed
and personal.
We spent some time remembering various people
from the past, or exchanging recent news about
them.
This was, I must say, most enjoyable.
As we talked, the past began to come back
to life for me.
It was not just the memory of people and places
that we talked about.
I watched Miss Kenton while she was speaking,
and suddenly recognized little expressions
on her face, little movements of her hands,
that brought back memories of our conversations
all those years ago.
The little smile that she gave when she finished
speaking, and a certain gesture with her shoulders,
had not changed at all.
After we had talked about people we had once
known, Miss Kenton began to tell me about
herself.
I learnt, for instance, that her marriage
to Mr Benn was not in as much trouble as I
had understood from her letter.
Although she had left her home for a period
of four or five days - which was when she
had written me her letter - she had returned,
and Mr Benn had been very pleased to have
her back.
'It is fortunate that one of us is sensible
about these things,' she said with a smile.
I am, of course, aware that details of Miss
Kenton's personal life with her husband were
really not my business.
I would not have talked to her about such
private matters if there had not been an important
professional reason.
And my reason for encouraging conversation
on this subject was the present staffing problem
at Darlington Hall.
But Miss Kenton did not seem to mind talking
to me about these matters.
In my opinion, this is pleasing evidence of
the fact that we had once enjoyed a close
working relationship together.
For a short time, Miss Kenton went on talking
more generally about her husband, who is retiring
soon because of the health.
She also talked to me about her daughter,
who is now married and expecting a child in
the autumn.
In fact, Miss Kenton gave me her daughter's
address in Dorset.
'Catherine's heard all about you, Mr Stevens,'
she said.
'She'd be so thrilled to meet you.'
Then I began to tell her about myself.
I tried to describe to her what Darlington
Hall is like today.
I attempted to tell her what a good employer
Mr Farraday is, and I described the changes
to the house itself and the present staffing
arrangements.
Miss Kenton, I thought, became visibly happier
when I talked about the house, and we were
soon laughing again together over various
old memories.
I spoke about Lord Darlington only once.
We had been talking about the young Mr Cardinal,
and I had to tell Miss Kenton that he had
been tragically killed in Belgium during the
war.
I continued:
'Of course, his lordship was very fond of
Mr Cardinal.
He suffered very badly when the young man
died.'
I did not wish to spoil the pleasant atmosphere
with unhappy talk, so I quickly tried to change
the subject.
However, Miss Kenton wanted to hear more about
Lord Darlington.
She had read in the newspapers about his unsuccessful
court action and, inevitably, took the opportunity
to ask me about it.
'The fact is, Mrs Benn, throughout the war,
people said some truly terrible things about
his lordship.
The newspaper that young Mr Cardinal worked
for was especially vicious towards him.
His lordship did nothing about it while the
country was in danger, but the accusations
against him continued after the war had ended.
He was unable to continue suffering in silence.
His lordship sincerely believed that he would
get justice if he took that newspaper to court.
Instead, of course, the newspaper simply became
more popular, and his lordship's good name
was destroyed for ever.
Afterwards, his lordship became very ill.
The house became so quiet.
I would take him tea in the drawing room and,
well...
it really was most tragic to see.'
'I'm very sorry, Mr Stevens.
I had no idea things had been so bad.'
'Oh yes, Mrs Benn.
But enough of this.
I know you remember Darlington Hall in the
days when it was filled with important visitors.
That is how his lordship deserves to be remembered.'
We did not mention Lord Darlington again.
We talked for the rest of the time about happy
memories, and we spent an extremely pleasant
two hours together in the tea lounge of the
Rose Garden Hotel.
Indeed, I could hardly believe that two whole
hours had passed when Miss Kenton looked up
at the clock and said that she would have
to return home.
When I discovered that she would have to walk
in the rain to a bus stop just outside the
village, I insisted on taking her there in
the Ford.
Soon we were motoring together down the village
high street, past the shops, and out into
the open country.
Miss Kenton sat quietly watching the passing
view, then turned to me and said:
'Why are you smiling to yourself like that,
Mr Stevens?'
'Oh...
You must excuse me, Mrs Benn, but I was just
thinking about some of the things you wrote
in your letter.
I was a little worried when I read them, but
I see now that there was no cause for alarm.'
'Oh?
What things in particular are you referring
to, Mr Stevens?'
'Well, for instance, Mrs Benn,' I said with
a laugh, 'in one part of your letter you write:
The rest of my life stretches out emptily
before me.
Or something like that.'
'Really, Mr Stevens,' she said, also laughing
a little.
'I could not have written that.'
'I assure you, Mrs Benn, you did.
I recall it very clearly.'
'Oh dear.
Well, perhaps there are some days when I feel
like that.
But they pass quickly enough.
Let me assure you, Mr Stevens, my life does
not stretch out emptily before me.
For instance, my husband and I are both looking
forward to becoming grandparents.'
'Yes, indeed.
That will be splendid for you.'
We drove on quietly for a few moments.
Then Miss Kenton said:
'And what about you, Mr Stevens?
What does the future hold for you back at
Darlington Hall?'
'There is work, Mrs Benn.
Work and more work.
I wish I had some emptiness to look forward
to.'
We both laughed at this.
Then Miss Kenton pointed to a bus shelter
further along the road.
As we approached it, she said:
'Will you wait with me, Mr Stevens?
The bus will only be a few minutes.'
The rain was still falling steadily as we
got out of the car and hurried towards the
shelter.
Miss Kenton sat on the seat that was provided.
I, however, remained on my feet where I would
have a clear view of the approaching bus.
After we had been waiting in silence for a
few minutes, I finally managed to say:
'Excuse me, Mrs Benn.
But the fact is, we may not meet again for
a long time.
I wonder if you would perhaps permit me to
ask you a rather personal question.
It is something that has been bothering me
for some time.'
'Certainly, Mr Stevens.
We are old friends, after all.'
'Indeed, as you say, we are old friends.
Please do not reply if you feel you shouldn't.
But the fact is, over the years I have had
a number of letters from you, and they have
all seemed to suggest that you are - how might
one express it?
- rather unhappy.
I simply wondered if you were being badly
treated in some way.
Forgive me, but I have been worried about
this for some time.'
'Mr Stevens, there is no need to be so embarrassed.
We are old friends after all, are we not?
In fact, I'm very grateful that you are so
concerned.
And I can reassure you on this matter absolutely.
My husband does not treat me badly in any
way.
He is not a cruel or bad-tempered man at all.'
'I am so pleased to hear that, Mrs Benn.'
I leaned forward into the rain, looking for
signs of the bus.
'I can see you are not very satisfied, Mr
Stevens,' Miss Kenton said.
'Don't you believe me?'
'It's not that, Mrs Benn.
Not that at all.
It's just that you do not seem to have been
very happy over the years.
You have - forgive me - left your husband
a number of times.
If he does not treat you badly, then, well...
I find the cause of your unhappiness rather
difficult to understand.'
I looked out into the rain again.
Eventually, I heard Miss Kenton say behind
me:
'Mr Stevens, how can I explain?
I hardly know myself why I do such things.
But it is true, I have left him three times.'
She paused a moment while I continued to look
out towards the fields on the other side of
the road.
Then she said:
'I suppose, Mr Stevens, you're asking whether
or not I love my husband.'
'Really, Mrs Benn, I would never...'
'I feel I should answer you, Mr Stevens,'
Mrs Benn interrupted me.
'As you say, we may not meet again for many
years.
Yes, I do love my husband.
I did not at first.
I did not for a long time.
When I left Darlington Hall all those years
ago, I never realized I was really, truly
leaving.
I believe I thought of it, Mr Stevens, as
simply another way to annoy you.
It was a shock to come out here and find myself
married.
For a long time I was very unhappy, very unhappy
indeed.
But then the years passed, there was the war
and Catherine grew up.
Then suddenly, one day, I realized that I
loved my husband.
If you spend so much time with someone, you
get used to him.
He is a kind, steady man, and yes, Mr Stevens,
I do love him.'
Miss Kenton fell silent again for a moment.
Then she went on: 'But there are times, of
course, when one thinks to oneself: "What
a terrible mistake I have made with my life."
And one thinks about a different life, a better
life one might have had.
For instance, I started to think about a life
I might have had with you, Mr Stevens.
And I suppose that is when I get angry over
something small and unimportant and leave.
But I always return to my husband.
We cannot turn the clock back now.
We cannot spend our lives dreaming about what
might have been.
One should be grateful for what one has.'
I do not think I responded immediately, for
it took me a moment or two to fully understand
her words.
Moreover, the implication of Miss Kenton's
words did create a certain amount of sorrow
within me.
Indeed - why should I not admit it?
- at that moment, my heart was breaking.
Before long, however, I turned to her and
said with a smile:
'You are absolutely right, Mrs Benn.
As you say, it is too late to turn back the
clock.
We must both be grateful for what we do have.
And from what you tell me, Mrs Benn, you have
many good reasons for feeling happy.
In fact, it seems that you and Mr Benn have
some extremely happy years ahead of you.
You really must not let any more foolish ideas
come between yourself and the happiness you
deserve.'
'Of course, you are right, Mr Stevens.
You are so kind.'
'Ah, Mrs Benn, I think that the bus is coming
now.'
I stepped out into the rain and signalled,
while Miss Kenton stood up and waited at the
edge of the shelter.
As the bus slowed down, I glanced at Miss
Kenton and noticed that her eyes had filled
with tears.
I smiled and said:
'Now, Mrs Benn, you must take good care of
yourself.
Many people say that retirement is the best
part of life for a married couple.
You must make these years happy ones for yourself
and your husband.
We may never meet again, Mrs Benn, so I ask
you to remember what I have just said to you.'
'I will, Mr Stevens, thank you.
And thank you for the lift.
It was so very kind of you.
It was so nice to see you again.'
'It was a great pleasure to see you again,
Mrs Benn.'
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
The Best Part of the Day
The pier lights have been switched on, and
a crowd of people behind me have just given
a loud cheer to celebrate this event.
There is still plenty of daylight left - the
sky over the sea has turned a pale red - but
it seems to me that everybody on this pier
will be happy for night to fall.
This confirms something that the man who was
next to me on this bench said to me a short
time ago.
He claimed that, for many people, the evening
was the best part of the day.
It was the part of the day that they most
looked forward to.
There seems to be some truth in this.
Otherwise, why would people cheer so loudly
simply because the pier lights have come on?
The man had been sitting next to me for some
minutes before I noticed him.
I was so lost in my own thoughts that I did
not know he was there until he said:
'Sea air is very good for you.'
He was a heavily built man in his late sixties,
wearing an old brown jacket and an open-necked
shirt.
He was staring out across the water, so I
was not sure whether he was talking to me.
But since no one else responded, I eventually
said:
'Yes, I'm sure it is.'
'The doctor says it's good for you, so I come
up here as often as I can.'
The man went on to tell me about his various
illnesses.
He turned to me occasionally and gave me a
nod or a grin, but most of the time he kept
staring out to sea.
I only really started to pay him attention,
however, when he mentioned that he had once
been a butler.
Until he retired three years ago, he had been
the butler in a small house near Weymouth.
He had been the only full-time member of staff.
When I asked him if he had ever worked with
a proper staff under him, perhaps before the
war, he replied:
'Oh, in those days I was just a footman.
I didn't have enough experience to be a butler
in those days.
Being a butler was a difficult job in those
big houses before the war.'
When he told me this, I thought it was appropriate
to reveal my identity.
My companion seemed suitably impressed when
I mentioned Darlington Hall.
'And I was trying to explain the job to you,'
he said with a laugh.
'You never know who you're talking to when
you meet a stranger.
So you had a big staff, I suppose.
Before the war, I mean.'
He was a cheerful fellow, and seemed genuinely
interested, so I was happy to tell him about
Darlington Hall in the old days.
Eventually, I said:
'Of course, things are quite different today
under my present employer.
An American gentleman.'
'Americans are the ones who can afford it
now,' he said, giving me a little grin.
'Yes,' I said, laughing a little.
'That's true.'
The man turned back to the sea again and took
a deep breath.
We sat quietly for several moments.
'The fact is, of course,' I said after a while,
'I gave my best to Lord Darlington.
I gave him the very best I had to give.
And now - well - I find I do not have much
left to give.'
The man nodded but said nothing, so I went
on:
'Since my new employer, Mr Farraday, arrived,
I've tried very hard.
But whatever I do, I find I'm making more
and more errors with my work.
Unimportant errors, it's true, but I would
never have made these errors in the past.
And I know what these errors mean.
I've given everything that I had to give.
I gave it all to Lord Darlington.'
'Oh dear, do you want a handkerchief?
I've got one somewhere,' my companion said.
'No thank you, it's quite all right.
I'm very sorry.
I'm afraid the travelling has made me tired.
I'm very sorry.'
'You must have been very devoted to this Lord
Darlington.
And he died three years ago, you say?'
'Lord Darlington wasn't a bad man.
He wasn't a bad man at all.
At least he was able to say at the end of
his life that he had made his own mistakes.
His lordship was a courageous man.
He chose a certain path in life.
It proved to be a mistaken path, but at least
he chose it for himself.
I cannot claim that about myself.
You see, I trusted in his lordship's wisdom.
All those years I served him, I trusted that
I was doing something worthwhile.
I can't even say I made my own mistakes.
Really - one has to ask oneself - where is
the dignity in that?'
'Now look, I'm not sure I understand everything
you're saying.
But if you ask me, your attitude's all wrong,
see?
Don't keep looking back all the time, you'll
only get depressed.
Maybe you can't do your job as well as you
used to, but it's the same for all of us.
We've all got to relax at some time.
Look at me - I've been very happy since I
retired.
We may not be as young as we were, but we
have to keep looking forward.'
I believe it was then that he said:
'You've got to enjoy yourself.
The evening's the best part of the day.
You've done your day's work.
Now you can relax and enjoy things.
That's how I look at it.
Ask anybody, they'll all tell you.
The evening's the best part of the day.'
'I'm sure you're quite correct,' I said.
'I'm sorry.
I'm probably too tired.
I've been travelling rather a lot, you see.'
The man left twenty minutes ago, but I have
remained here on this bench to witness the
switching on of the pier lights.
As I have already said, the happiness of the
people around me at this small event seems
to confirm what my companion said.
For many people, the evening is the most enjoyable
part of the day.
Perhaps I should stop looking back so much.
I should adopt a more positive attitude towards
what remains of my day.
After all, what purpose is there in forever
looking back and blaming ourselves for what
might or might not have happened?
The hard reality, for people like you and
me, is that our lives are in the hands of
those great gentlemen who employ our services.
What is the sense in worrying about whether
we could or could not have taken more control?
Surely it is enough that people like you and
me have at least tried to make a real contribution,
however small.
Whatever the result is, surely that is a reason
to be proud.
A few minutes ago, soon after the lights came
on, I turned around on my bench and studied
the crowd of people behind me.
They were laughing and chatting.
There are people of all ages wandering around
this pier: families with children, couples,
young and elderly, walking arm in arm.
I paid particular attention to a group of
six or seven people just a little way behind
me.
I thought at first that they were a group
of friends.
However, as I listened to their conversation,
I realized that they were strangers who had
never met before.
As I watch them now, they are all laughing
happily.
It is strange how people can build such warmth
among themselves so quickly It is possible
that these people are simply sharing the anticipation
of the evening ahead.
On the other hand, I think the warmth between
them is probably more a result of their skill
at bantering.
I can hear them exchanging one bantering remark
after another.
Perhaps it is time for me to pay more serious
attention to the subject of bantering.
After all, when one thinks about it, it is
not such a foolish thing to do - particularly
if, for some reason, it contains the key to
human warmth.
I have, of course, already spent much time
practising my bantering skills.
It is possible, however, that I need to be
more enthusiastic about it.
Perhaps, when I return to Darlington Hall
tomorrow - Mr Farraday will be away for another
week - I will make a new start.
I shall start practising bantering again with
new energy.
If I do this, I shall be able to pleasantly
surprise Mr Farraday with my new skill when
he returns.