Riding a motorbike is a great way to travel.
Who cares if the bike is an old Norton or
a shiny new Suzuki?
It's the speed, the noise of the wind in your
ears, the engine roaring under you, burning
up the miles.
Bikers are free, alone, they go where they
want...
Free, alone - sometimes lonely.
And danger waits at every bend in the road.
But for Roy, riding home to Auckland as night
falls, it's still a great feeling...
Coming up from the river towards the road,
Roy looked at his watch.
It was half past four.
It was cooler now; he could do an hour or
two of the journey before dark.'
He started off down the road, feeling the
heavy fish in the bag against his leg as he
walked.
He played the fish again in his mind, feeling
it pull on the line, fighting him all the
way.
He walked happily through the afternoon stillness.
A car was parked off the road by the bridge,
with three men standing beside it.
They watched him coming.
They stood drinking from metal cups, looking
pleased with themselves, pleased with the
wild boar they had shot.
It was tied to the roof of their old American
car.
They looked at Roy and his fish as he came
by.
'Good fishing, then,' one of them said.
'Sure,' Roy said.
'It looks like everybody's got what they came
for.'
He stepped into the long grass, found his
old Norton, and pushed it up to the road.
He felt the men watching him.
'Have a beer,' one of them offered.
'Well, thanks,' Roy said.
He took a cup from one of the bags on his
bike and went over to the car.
'That's a nice fish,' the man said, filling
his cup with beer.
'Not bad,' Roy said.
'He nearly took the fly last night, and I
went back to get him today.'
He drank his beer.
'He must have a poor memory then,' the man
said.
'He just loves Black Gnats,' Roy said, touching
the fishing fly pinned to his shirt.
They all looked.
You could tell that they were not fishermen.
Roy looked at the dead boar with its long
dangerous teeth.
'Big one,' he said, and finished the beer.
The guy offered the bottle.
'No, thanks.
I've got to get going.'
He walked back to the bike and went on packing.
The men stood around with their beer, watching
him.
Roy picked up the fish and held it up to show
them how big it was, and they smiled.
He packed it away in one of the bags.
He sat down on the grass and pulled on his
boots, thinking that it hadn't been a bad
weekend.
He felt the men watching him.
They were friendly, but there was something
about it, a kind of feeling he wasn't sure
about.
He put on his crash helmet and his gloves.
Then he started the bike and waved goodbye.
The men smiled, and one of them lifted his
beer for good luck.
'I'm on my own,' Roy thought.
'That's what it is.
They're three friends out together in the
afternoon, and I'm on my own, with two hundred
miles to go.
It's a small thing, but that's what it is,
all right.'
He turned away and rode the Norton down the
road.
The road stayed near the river for the next
eight or ten miles.
Sometimes the rocky walls of the valley hid
the river, and sometimes you could see it
far below you.
In places, road and river went side by side,
and you could see the wet rocks shining in
the late afternoon sun, and the deep black
water at the bends.
It was always good to be close to a river,
Roy thought.
Next time he would fish down river from the
bridge.
The road turned away from the river at last,
and joined the highway.
Roy let the bike go faster.
He felt the old feeling coming as the miles
went by.
All the things that hurt disappeared, all
the things that didn't matter.
He didn't need to think, not about being alone,
not about anything.
He did sixty-five miles in the first hour.
He felt calm and easy.
Sometimes it worried him, riding fast, but
this afternoon was fine.
When it was dark, he would slow down.
He rode on past the rich farmland.
He thought about the farmers, finishing work,
perhaps having their tea.
That made him feel a little hungry.
Maybe about halfway he would stop for a cup
of coffee and something to eat.
He came round a bend and saw a car just disappearing
round the next bend.
He slowed down a little, waiting for a place
to pass it.
It was a big, old car, and as he came up behind
it, the driver speeded up and went fast into
the next bend.
Roy stayed behind him, waiting for a straight
piece of road.
Maybe the guy just didn't like bikes.
The place came at last, half a mile of straight
empty road, going up a small hill.
He checked his mirror, and passed the car.
He went up the hill, leaving the car behind,
and he was alone again on a straight road.
And then the world exploded underneath him!
It came with a sudden crash, like a shot from
a gun behind him.
A moment later, he realized what it was - he
was riding a flying machine on a back tyre
in pieces, fighting wildly to stay on and
to slow the Norton down from sixty-five to
zero.
The big bike flew from one side of the road
to the other, but as it went up the hill,
it began to go slower.
Then a car was coming and he was off the road,
and at last, the bike ran hard against a bank
and stopped.
Roy turned off the engine and sat back.
Then the car he had passed came up and stopped
beside him.
An unpleasant face stared at him from the
front passenger seat.
'Bad luck!'
The voice sounded pleased.
Somebody laughed.
Then the old car roared away and disappeared
over the hill.
Roy got off the bike.
He was shaking just a little.
He decided not to think about the guys in
the car for a while.
He wanted to calm down first.
He looked down the road, half a mile of it,
straight with no ditch, and he felt how lucky
he had been: A long straight road and no ditch,
man.
He turned and looked up the road.
There was a house near the top of the hill.
He half walked, half rode the bike to the
farm gate.
They would let him leave his bike there, surely.
He stopped by the back door and turned off
the engine.
A big man in jeans, with only socks on his
feet, came to the door.
Roy felt the farmer looking at him, deciding
about him while he explained.
'On your own?'
'Yes.'
Just a minute, the farmer said, and got his
boots.
They put the bike in one of the farm buildings,
and Roy felt better about it.
'Lucky it happened there,' the farmer said.
That's true, said Roy.
'And lucky it was the back wheel.'
'I used to have one of these things,' the
farmer said, and he reached over to hold the
bike.
He seemed to be looking back in time.
'It'll be safe here,' he said.
Roy took out the fish and gave it to him.
Well, he's a big one!' said farmer.
'We'll keep him for you.'
No, Roy said.
'Give him to the cook.
Do you think I'll get a ride this time of
day?'
Easy, the farmer said.
'One of those cattle trucks is what you need
- take you all the way to Westfield.'
The first two or three cars did not matter.
But then he knew he had a long walk in front
of him.
Most people did not even slow down before
they decided not to take him.
He was halfway up the second long hill, and
it was quite dark, when he heard the first
cattle truck.
He waited as the big truck came closer.
Then he saw the driver's face looking at him,
and he remembered it when the truck had gone.
It wasn't unfriendly, he thought - the guy
just didn't care.
He watched the truck go slowly up the hill.
He started to walk again.
He felt a kind of loneliness walking in the
dark.
It was the way the truck driver had looked
at him.
The guy just didn't care.
Or maybe he didn't want a stranger with him
all that way.
Maybe he just didn't want to talk.
More cars passed, but he didn't even try asking
for a ride any more.
He walked on, not caring, knowing how alone
in the world he was.
He had walked perhaps another five miles when
he heard his favourite sound.
A bike came up fast behind him, and went round
the next corner.
Roy heard it slow down, turn and come back.
The rider stopped and waited for Roy.
It was a big modern bike, Japanese, he guessed.
The rider sat looking back at him, crash helmet
shining.
Roy was next to the bike before he realized
that the rider was a girl - a tall, leggy
girl in jeans and boots, and perhaps there
was fair hair under the helmet.
Roy stared as they spoke.
'Which way you going, mister?'
'Auckland.'
'That makes two of us.
You have a crash?'
'Tyre went.'
'No fun.'
Roy felt her eyes watching him as she spoke.
'Well,' said, talking about it won't get us
home.'
Sure, said Roy.
His ears were getting hot under his crash
helmet.
He climbed up behind her and they were off.
She rode fast from the beginning.
This was a real bike and a real rider.
Roy felt good about it - good to be on wheels
again, good that somebody cared enough to
stop.
Close to his face the girl asked, 'What kind
of bike, mister?'
'Norton.
500cc.'
'Front wheel or back?'
'Back.'
Not so bad, she said.
'Better bade than front, any day.'
'Sure,' Roy said.
He wanted to talk to this girl, but he could
not get the words out.
They rode on in silence in the dark.
She knew about bikes all right.
'With a guy it's easy,' Roy thought.
'You have a crash, you get a ride, you climb
on the bike.
You don't even notice that he can ride it
well.
But this is a girl and she knows what she
is doing.
That doesn't mean you can't talk to her,'
he told himself.
'You've seen girls before, man.'
Her voice came back to him: 'Where have you
come from, mister?'
'Pukatea Valley.'
'Yes?
How was the fishing?'
Not bad, Roy said, before he had time to wonder
at her question.
'Nice water by the old bridge.
What were they taking?'
Black Gnat, he said, and there was more than
wonder.
He felt that hot pain behind his eyes.
'Wet or dry?'
'Wet,' said Roy, and his voice shook a little
with the wonder of it.
And in his heart he felt an ache that came
from a kind of longing.
This was the girl he had been longing for
all his life - a tall, leggy girl who rode
a 750cc Suzuki and knew about fly-fishing.
For a while, they rode and did not speak.
Then, back on straight road, the girl said,
close to his face, 'My brother caught a six-pound
fish under that bridge one year.'
'Really!'
Roy was beginning to understand.
'How long ago was that?'
'Maybe five years ago.
Ross played him for half an hour before he
pulled him in.'
'Sounds like he's a good fisherman, your brother,'
Roy said.
'He was,' she said, and that was all.
And Roy, guessing what she meant, knew it
was not the kind of thing you could shout
about above the noise of the wind and the
engine.
After a few miles the girl said, 'My name's
Kay, mister.'
Roy said his own name.
It sounded strange to him.
'Well, Roy, you going to buy me a cup of coffee
when we get to the next town?'
'Sure,' Roy said.
'Sure thing, Kay.'
They dropped their speed and rode into the
town.
It was quiet on a Sunday evening.
They found the place they wanted, and got
off the bike.
Her hair was long and fair and blown about
by the wind.
In the coffee shop he saw her face for the
first time, and he felt that kind of longing
from way back, and he sat down beside her,
knowing what it was.
'How long were you walking back there?'
Her voice was soft and pleasant after the
shouted conversation on the road.
'Perhaps five or six miles,' Roy said.
'Nobody was interested.'
'They never are.'
'It's not the kind of thing you worry about,'
he said.
'No.'
They sat drinking their coffee, watching and
listening, getting the idea of each other.
'You go fishing a lot?'
she said.
'Sure.
Fishing.
Moving around.'
'Always travel alone?'
'My friend got killed,' Roy said.
It came out like that.
There was not much else that he could say.
He felt a kind of softness in her eyes that
took him by the heart.
'What about you?' he said.
'What about me?'
'I mean, you can tell me about your brother.'
He saw her eyes - their softness, the quiet
hurt as his words hit her.
'Ross got killed in the army,' she said.
'It was his first week - just a stupid accident.
He was only twenty.
He fell off the back of a truck and hit his
head.
He used to do wild, crazy things all the time
- but then what killed him was just a stupid
accident...'
He played with his spoon in the coffee.
'What about your friend?'
she asked after a while.
'Plane,' Roy said.
'Another thing that just couldn't happen.'
He saw it in his mind - the broken plane,
that moment he could never forget for the
rest of his life.
This was something they both knew, he and
this girl: a death that you couldn't believe.
And that feeling was always with you, everywhere,
like a voice that whispers in your ear, 'There
will never be enough road any more, enough
water, enough air...'
But beyond the feelings of hurt, old and new,
he knew that they were telling each other
the truth about themselves, not hiding things.
Was he choosing the right words?
It didn't matter.
Now he asked, 'Where've you been today then,
on your big bike?'
'Tauranga.'
'Stay the weekend?'
'Down this morning.
It's only two hundred and sixty miles there
and back,' she said.
'My father's in a kind of hospital down there.
I don't stay because one visit each time is
all I can do.'
'I'm sorry,' Roy said.
It was all in her eyes.
In his mind, Roy saw a strong man broken - the
father who would never get old, never die.
How could you believe it, live with it?
Maybe he taught them to fish, Roy thought,
this girl and her brother, dead at twenty
from his accident.
Maybe he taught them all those good things
and they all had fun together, and then suddenly
she looked around and she was the only one
left.
Maybe that's why she rides the big bike.
The time was starting to get heavy now.
'What do you say we get on the road?'
Kay said.
'Sure.'
They went out and Roy felt the heaviness going.
It was all right if you knew when to get up
and go.
They put on their crash helmets and the tall
leggy girl started her bike.
Roy climbed on behind her, and they went away
laughing.
They rode gently out of the sleepy town; then
they reached the highway and the bike roared
away into the night.
Roy felt all right about riding on the back.
Sometimes, if you weren't sure about the rider,
you weren't happy when he went fast, but this
girl was okay.
They rode, not talking, enjoying the night
ride on their big fast machine.
Roy thought about the things they were passing
- the cattle in the fields, the night sounds
of the farms.
Lights appeared and cars sped past, and he
thought about all the people going places.
He felt Kay close to him, with her long friendly
shoulders and her fair hair flying back from
under her helmet.
He could go on and on.
He didn't care about the people who hated
you before they saw you, or enjoyed watching
you in trouble on the road, or let you walk
because they didn't want to think about you.
He felt that none of it could touch him now,
or ever, that all the hurt had gone, and the
shock from the deaths of friends and the bad
feelings that came from people's unkind words.
A notice warned of bends in the road, and
Kay cut their speed, and they rode the big
bike down into the first bend.
Cars came up from down below, their lights
showing the narrow road and the banks on each
side.
Most of the cars seemed to be in too much
of a hurry, Roy thought.
They reached the bottom of the narrow valley,
where he knew the river ran close to the road.
He thought about that clear mountain water
among the trees.
Then they started to climb.
They rode up the hill and into the first bend.
And death came down to meet them on the wrong
side of the road.
The lights of the car were right in front
of them.
They had nowhere to go, and not enough time
to hate the guy who was killing them.
Roy put his arms round Kay.
He felt his face against her shoulder, their
helmets close together.
Then they were off the road and into the ditch
as the car went past, moving too late to its
own side of the road.
They went on and on, fighting the ditch, crashing
into the bank, and then they were over the
bank and sailing, a moment's space before
the hurt that was coming.
They crashed down the bank, and Roy held tight
to Kay, and they were off the bike and dying
together, and the ground came up to knock
the life out of his body, and he reached for
Kay as he fell.
Impossibly, he was still alive, but as he
fell, crashed, broke, he didn't care - he
only reached for Kay, longed for her.
He came to rest; there was a taste of blood
and a whisper of pain through the shock, and
he felt cold water around him.
He lay in the icy water of the ditch, and
knew he was still alive.
Then he was moving along the ditch on hands
and knees, searching for Kay through the pain
and shock.
He pulled himself along the ditch until he
found her.
She was lying face down.
He touched her, and turned her over as gently
as he could.
Time had stopped.
It was like a bad dream, made of all the deaths
that had gone before.
He said her name, and it came thick and strange
through his painful lips.
She looked at him and he waited for an impossible
moment, and then she began to cry as the shock
hit her, and that was all the hope he needed.
He took off her helmet, and gently pushed
her hair back, and somewhere above them, he
heard voices and a crashing sound as help
came.
The pain in his legs began to come alive.
He put his arm around Kay, loving the life
that returned as she cried life and pain coming
together.
And that was all the hope he needed.
He guessed it must be all the hope in the
world.
Because, for all the time that it lasted,
they would have it together.
- THE END -