CHAPTER ONE
Before the War
In the last years of the nineteenth century,
no one believed that this world was being
watched closely by intelligences greater than
our own.
We had no idea that we were being studied
almost as carefully as a scientist studies
the small creatures in a drop of water.
With great confidence, people travelled around
this world and believed that they were in
control of their lives.
No one gave a thought to possible threats
from other planets.
At most, people believed there might be living
things on Mars, perhaps less developed than
us and ready to welcome visitors.
But across the great emptiness of space, more
intelligent minds than ours looked at this
Earth with jealous eyes, and slowly and surely
made their plans against us.
And early in the twentieth century, the great
shock came.
The planet Mars, I need not remind the reader,
goes around the sun at an average distance
of 224,000,000 kilometres, and receives from
the sun half of the light and heat that is
received by this world.
It must be, if scientific thinking is correct,
older than our world, and life on its surface
began a long time before this Earth cooled
down.
Because it is hardly one seventh of the size
of Earth, it cooled more quickly to the temperature
at which life could begin.
It has air and water and all that is necessary
to support living things.
But people are so blind that no writer, before
the end of the nineteenth century, suggested
that much more intelligent life had developed
there than on Earth.
It was also not generally understood that
because Mars is older and smaller than our
Earth, and further from the sun, it is nearer
life's end as well as further from its beginning.
Mars is getting colder, as one day our planet
must too.
Its physical condition is still largely a
mystery, but we know that even in the middle
of the day, in its warmest areas, the temperature
is lower than during our coldest winter.
Its air is much thinner than ours, its oceans
have become smaller until they cover only
a third of its surface, and from its far north
and south the ice is steadily moving forwards.
The end of all life, which is a distant possibility
for us, is an immediate problem for the Martians.
This has brightened their intelligence, increased
their abilities and hardened their hearts.
And looking across space, with instruments
and minds more powerful than we can dream
of, they see, at a distance of only 56,000,000
kilometres, a morning star of hope - our own
warmer planet with its green land and grey
seas, its cloudy atmosphere and its growing
population.
We, the people who live on this Earth, must
seem to them at least as different and less
developed as monkeys are to us.
And before we criticize them for thinking
in this way, we must remember how badly we
have treated not only the animals of this
planet, but also other people.
Can we really complain that the Martians treated
us in the same way?
It seems that the Martians calculated their
journey very cleverly - their mathematical
knowledge appears to be much more developed
than ours.
During 1894, a great light was seen on the
surface of the planet by a number of astronomers.
I now believe that this was a fire built to
make an enormous gun in a very deep pit.
From this gun, their shots were fired at us.
The attack came six years ago.
Towards midnight on 12 August, one astronomer
noticed a great cloud of hot gas on the surface
of the planet.
In fact, he compared it to the burning gases
that might rush out from a gun.
This, we now know, was a very accurate description.
However, the next day there was no report
in the newspapers except one small note in
the Daily Telegraph, and the world knew nothing
of one of the greatest dangers that ever threatened
Earth.
I do not think I would have known anything
about it myself if I had not met Ogilvy, the
well-known astronomer.
He was very excited at the news and invited
me to spend the night with him, watching the
red planet.
Despite everything that has happened since,
I still remember that night very clearly.
Looking through the telescope, I saw a circle
of deep blue with the little round planet
in the centre.
Because it was so small, I did not see the
Thing they were sending us, which was flying
quickly towards me across that great distance.
I never dreamed of it then, as I watched.
Nobody on Earth knew anything about the approaching
missile.
That night, too, there was another sudden
cloud of gas from the distant planet as a
second missile started on its way to Earth
from Mars, just under twenty-four hours after
the first one.
I saw a reddish flash at the edge, the slightest
bend in its shape, as the clock struck midnight.
I remember how I sat there in the blackness,
not suspecting the meaning of the tiny light
I had seen and all the trouble that it would
cause me.
I told Ogilvy, and he took my place and watched
the cloud of gas growing as it rose from the
surface of the planet.
He watched until one, and then we lit the
lamp and walked over to his house.
Hundreds of observers saw the flame that night
and the following night, at about midnight,
and again the night after that.
For ten nights they saw a flame each night.
No one on Earth has attempted to explain why
the shots ended after this.
It may be that the gases from the firing caused
the Martians inconvenience.
Thick clouds of smoke or dust, which looked
like little grey, moving spots through a powerful
telescope on Earth, spread through the clearness
of the planet's atmosphere and hid its more
familiar features.
Even the daily papers woke up to these events
at last, and there was much discussion of
their cause.
But no one suspected the truth, that the Martians
had fired missiles, which were now rushing
towards us at a speed of many kilometres a
second across the great emptiness of space.
It seems to me almost unbelievably wonderful
that, with that danger threatening us, people
could continue their ordinary business as
they did.
One night, when the first missile was probably
less than 15,000,000 kilometres away, I went
for a walk with my wife.
I pointed out Mars, a bright spot of light
rising in the sky, towards which so many telescopes
were pointing.
The night was warm.
Coming home, a group of party-goers from Chertsey
passed us, singing and playing music.
There were lights in the upper windows of
the houses as people went to bed.
From the distant railway station came the
sound of trains.
The world seemed so safe and peaceful.
CHAPTER TWO
The Falling Star
Only a few nights later, the first falling
star was seen towards the east.
Denning, our greatest astronomer, said that
the height of its first appearance was about
one hundred and fifty kilometres.
It seemed to him that it fell to Earth about
a hundred kilometres east of him.
I was at home at the time and writing in my
study with the curtains open.
If I had looked up I would have seen the strangest
thing that ever fell to Earth from space,
but I did not.
Many people in that part of England saw it,
and simply thought that another meteorite
had fallen.
Nobody went to look for the fallen star that
night.
But poor Ogilvy had seen it fall and so he
got up very early with the idea of finding
it.
This he did, soon after dawn.
An enormous hole had been made and the Earth
had been thrown violently in every direction,
forming piles that could be seen two kilometres
away.
The Thing itself lay almost completely buried
in the earth.
The uncovered part looked like an enormous
cylinder, about thirty metres across each
end.
It was covered with a thick burnt skin, which
softened its edges.
He approached it, surprised at the size and
even more surprised at the shape, since most
meteorites are fairly round.
It was, however, still very hot from its flight
through the air and he could not get close
to it.
He could hear movement from inside but thought
this was due to it cooling down.
He did not imagine that it might be hollow.
He remained standing on one side of the pit
that the Thing had made for itself, staring
at its strange appearance and thinking that
there might be some intelligent design in
its shape.
He was alone on the common.
Then suddenly, he noticed that some of the
burnt skin was falling off the round edge
at the end.
A large piece suddenly came off with a sharp
noise that brought his heart into his mouth.
For a minute he hardly realized what this
meant, and although the heat was great, he
climbed down into the pit to see the cylinder
more closely.
He realized that, very slowly, the round top
of the cylinder was turning.
Even then he hardly understood what was happening,
until he heard another sound and saw the black
mark jump forwards a little.
Then he suddenly understood.
The cylinder was artificial - hollow - with
an end that screwed out!
Something inside the cylinder was unscrewing
the top!
'Good heavens!' said Ogilvy.
'There's a man in it - men in it!
Half burnt to death!
Trying to escape!'
At once, thinking quickly, he connected the
Thing with the flash on Mars.
The thought of the creature trapped inside
was so terrible to him that he forgot the
heat, and went forwards to the cylinder to
help.
But luckily the heat stopped him before he
could get his hands on the metal.
He stood undecided for a moment, then climbed
out of the pit and started to run into Woking.
The time then was around six o'clock.
He met some local people who were up early,
but the story he told and his appearance were
so wild that they would not listen to him.
That quieted him a little, and when he saw
Henderson, the London journalist, in his garden,
he shouted over the fence and made himself
understood.
'Henderson,' he called, 'you saw that meteorite
last night?'
'Yes,' said Henderson.
'What about it?'
'It's out on Horsell Common now.'
'Fallen meteorite!' said Henderson.
'That's good.'
'But it's something more than a meteorite.
It's a cylinder - an artificial cylinder!
And there's something inside.'
'What did you say?' he asked.
He was deaf in one ear.
When Ogilvy told him all he had seen, Henderson
dropped his spade, put on his jacket and came
out into the road.
The two men hurried back at once to the common,
and found the cylinder still lying in the
same position.
But now the sounds inside had stopped, and
a thin circle of bright metal showed between
its top and body.
They listened, knocked on the burnt metal
with a rock and, getting no answer, they both
decided that the men inside were either unconscious
or dead.
Of course the two were quite unable to do
anything, so they went back to the town again
to get help.
Henderson went to the railway station at once,
to send a telegram to London.
By eight o'clock a number of boys and unemployed
men were already walking to the common to
see the 'dead men from Mars'.
That was the form the story took.
I heard it first from my newspaper boy at
about a quarter to nine and I went to the
common immediately.
When I got there, I found a little crowd of
perhaps twenty people surrounding the great
pit in which the cylinder lay.
Henderson and Ogilvy were not there.
I think they understood that nothing could
be done for the moment, and had gone away
to have breakfast at Henderson's house.
I climbed into the pit and thought I heard
a faint movement under my feet.
The top had certainly stopped turning.
At that time it was quite clear in my own
mind that the Thing had come from the planet
Mars, and I felt impatient to see it opened.
At about eleven, as nothing was happening,
I walked back, full of such thoughts, to my
home in Maybury.
By the afternoon the appearance of the common
had changed very much.
The early editions of the evening papers had
shocked London.
They printed stories like:
MESSAGE RECEIVED FROM MARS AMAZING STORY FROM
WOKING
There was now a large crowd of people standing
around.
Going to the edge of the pit, I found a group
of men in it - Henderson, Ogilvy, and a tall
fair-haired man I afterwards learnt was Stent,
the Astronomer Royal, with several workmen
holding spades.
Stent was giving directions.
A large part of the cylinder had now been
uncovered, although its lower end was still
hidden in the side of the pit.
As soon as Ogilvy saw me, he called me to
come down, and asked me if I would mind going
over to see Lord Hilton, who owned the land.
The growing crowd, he said, was now becoming
a serious problem, especially the boys.
He wanted a fence put up to keep the people
back.
I was very glad to do as he asked.
I failed to find Lord Hilton at his house,
but was told he was expected from London by
the six o'clock train.
As it was then about a quarter past five,
I went home, had some tea and walked up to
the station to meet him.
CHAPTER THREE
The Cylinder Opens
When I returned to the common, the sun was
setting.
Groups of people were hurrying from the direction
of Woking.
The crowd around the pit had increased to
a couple of hundred people, perhaps.
There were raised voices, and some sort of
struggle appeared to be going on around the
pit.
As I got nearer, I heard Stent's voice:
'Keep back!
Keep back!
'
A boy came running towards me.
'It's moving,' he said to me as he passed,
'- unscrewing and unscrewing.
I don't like it.
I'm going home.'
I went on to the crowd and pushed my way through.
Everyone seemed greatly excited.
I heard a peculiar humming sound from the
pit.
'Keep those fools back,' said Ogilvy.
'We don't know what's in the Thing, you know.'
I saw a young man - I believe he was a shop
assistant in Woking - standing on the cylinder
and trying to climb out of the pit again.
The crowd had pushed him in.
The end of the cylinder was being screwed
out from within.
Nearly half a meter of shining screw stuck
out.
Someone pushed against me, and I almost fell
down on top of the screw.
I turned, and as I did the screw came out
and the lid of the cylinder fell onto the
sand with a ringing sound.
I pressed back against the person behind me,
and turned my head towards the Thing again.
I had the sunset in my eyes and for a moment
the round hole seemed black.
I think everyone expected to see a man come
out - possibly something a little unlike us
on Earth, but more or less a man.
I know I did.
But, looking, I soon saw something grey moving
within the shadow, then two shining circles
- like eyes.
Then something like a little grey snake, about
the thickness of a walking-stick, came out
of the middle and moved through the air towards
me - and then another.
I suddenly felt very cold.
There was a loud scream from a woman behind.
I half-turned, still keeping my eyes on the
cylinder, from which other tentacles were
now coming out, and began pushing my way back
from the side of the pit.
I saw shock changing to horror on the faces
of the people around me, and there was a general
movement backwards.
I found myself alone, and saw the people on
the other side of the pit running off.
I looked again at the cylinder, and felt great
terror.
A big, greyish round creature, the size, perhaps,
of a bear, was rising slowly and painfully
out of the cylinder.
As it moved up and caught the light, it shone
like wet leather.
Two large dark- colored eyes were looking
at me steadily.
The head of the thing was rounded and had,
one could say, a face.
There was a mouth under the eyes, and its
lipless edge shone wetly.
The whole creature was breathing heavily.
One tentacle held onto the cylinder; another
moved in the air.
Suddenly, the creature disappeared.
It had fallen over the edge of the cylinder
and into the pit.
I heard it give a peculiar cry, and then another
of these creatures appeared in the deep shadow
of the door.
I turned and ran madly towards the first group
of trees, perhaps a hundred metres away.
I fell a number of times because I was running
with my head turned round.
I could not take my eyes away from these creatures.
The common was now covered with small groups
of people.
They were all very frightened, but still interested
in the strange happenings in the pit.
Then I saw a round object moving up and down.
It was the head of the shop assistant who
had fallen in, looking black against the hot
western sky.
He got his shoulder and knee up, but again
he seemed to slip back until only his head
was visible.
Then he disappeared, and I thought I heard
a faint scream.
For a moment I wanted to go back and help
him, but I was too afraid.
The sun went down before anything else happened.
The crowd around the pit seemed to grow as
new people arrived.
This gave people confidence and as darkness
fell, a slow, uncertain movement on the common
began.
Black figures in twos and threes moved forwards,
stopped, watched, and moved again, getting
closer and closer to the pit.
And then, coming from the direction of Horsell,
I noticed a little black group of men, the
first of whom was waving a white flag.
They were too far away for me to recognize
anyone there, but I learned afterwards that
Ogilvy, Stent and Henderson were with others
in this attempt at communication.
As the group moved forwards, a number of other
people started to follow them.
Suddenly, there was a flash of light and bright
greenish smoke came out of the pit in three
separate clouds, which moved up, one after
the other, into the still air.
The smoke (or flame, perhaps, would be a better
word for it) was so bright that the deep blue
sky overhead seemed to darken as these clouds
rose.
At the same time we could hear a faint sound,
which changed into a long, loud humming noise.
Slowly a dark shape rose out of the pit and
a beam of light seemed to flash out from it.
Then flashes of bright fire came from the
men, and I realized that the Martians were
using some kind of invisible ray.
Then, by the light of their own burning, I
saw each of the men falling, and their followers
turning to run.
I stood staring, watching as man after man
fell over.
As the unseen ray of light passed over them,
trees caught fire and even the bushes exploded
into flame.
And far away to the west I saw flashes of
trees and bushes and wooden buildings suddenly
set on fire.
This flaming death, this invisible sword of
heat, was sweeping round quickly and steadily.
I knew it was coming towards me because of
the flashing bushes it touched, but I was
too shocked to move.
All along a curving line beyond the pit, the
dark ground smoked.
Then the humming stopped and the black, rounded
object sank slowly out of sight into the pit.
All this happened so quickly that I stood
without moving, shocked by the flashes of
light.
It that death had swung round a full circle,
it would have killed me.
But it passed and let me live, and left the
night around me suddenly dark and unfamiliar.
There was nobody else around.
Overhead the stars were coming out, and in
the west the sky was still a pale, bright,
almost greenish blue.
The tops of the trees and the roofs of Horsell
were sharp and black against the western sky.
Areas of bush and a few trees still smoked,
and the houses towards Woking station were
sending up tongues of flame into the stillness
of the evening air.
I realized that I was helpless and alone on
this dark common.
Suddenly, like a thing falling on me from
above, came fear.
With an effort I turned and began an unsteady
run through the grass.
The fear I felt was panic - terror not only
of the Martians but of the dark and stillness
all around me.
I ran crying silently as a child might do.
After I had turned, I did not dare look back.
CHAPTER FOUR
Mars Attacks
I ran until I was totally exhausted and I
fell down beside the road.
That was near the bridge by the gas-works.
I remained there for some time.
Eventually I sat up, strangely puzzled.
For a moment, perhaps, I could not clearly
understand how I came there.
My terror had fallen from me like a piece
of clothing.
A few minutes earlier there had only been
three things in my mind: the great size of
the night and space and nature, my own weakness
and unhappiness, and the near approach of
death.
Now I was my normal self again - an ordinary
citizen.
The silent common, my escape, the flames,
seemed like a dream.
I asked myself if these things had really
happened.
I could not believe it.
I got up and walked up the steep slope to
the bridge.
My body seemed to have lost its strength.
The figure of a workman carrying a basket
appeared.
Beside him ran a little boy He passed me,
wishing me good-night.
I thought about speaking to him, but did not.
I answered his greeting and went on over the
bridge.
Two men and a woman were talking at the gate
of one of the houses.
I stopped.
'What news from the common?'
I said.
'Eh?' said one of the men, turning.
'What news from the common?'
I repeated.
'Haven't you just been there?'
the men asked.
'People seem fairly silly about the common,'
the woman said over the gate.
'What's it all about?'
'Haven't you heard of the men from Mars?'
I said.
'The creatures from Mars.'
'Quite enough,' said the woman.
'Thanks.'
And all three of them laughed.
I felt foolish and angry.
I tried but could not tell them what I had
seen.
They laughed again at my broken sentences.
'You'll hear more soon," I said, and went
on to my home.
My wife was shocked when she saw me, because
I looked so tired and dirty.
I went into the dining-room, sat down, and
told her the things that I had seen.
'There is one good thing,' I said, to calm
her fears.
'They are the slowest, fattest things I ever
saw crawl.
They may stay in the pit and kill people who
come near them, as they cannot get out of
it . . . but they are so horrible!'
'Don't, dear!' said my wife, putting her hand
on mine.
'Poor Ogilvy!'
I said.
'He may be lying dead there.'
My wife, at least, did not think my experience
unbelievable.
When I saw how white her face was, I began
to comfort her and myself by repeating all
that Ogilvy had told me about the impossibility
of Martians capturing the Earth.
On the surface of the Earth the force of gravity
is three times as great as on the surface
of Mars.
A Martian, therefore, would weigh three times
more than on Mars, although his strength would
be the same.
That was the general opinion.
Both The Times and the Daily Telegraph, for
example, said this very confidently the next
morning.
Both ignored, as I did, two obvious problems
with this theory.
The atmosphere of Earth, we now know, contains
much more oxygen than there is on Mars.
This certainly gave the Martians much greater
strength.
And we also learned that the Martians were
so mechanically clever that they did not need
to use their bodies very much.
But I did not consider these points at the
time, and so I thought the Martians had very
little chance of success.
With wine and food and the need to help my
wife feel less afraid, I slowly became braver
and felt safer.
I remember the dinner table that evening very
clearly even now: my dear wife's sweet, worried
face looking at me from under the pink lamp-shade,
the white cloth laid with silver and glass,
the glass of red wine in my hand.
I did not know it, but that was the last proper
dinner I would eat for many strange and terrible
days.
If, on that Friday night, you had drawn a
circle at a distance of five kilometres from
Horsell Common, I doubt if there would have
been one human being outside it, unless it
was a relation of Stent, whose emotions or
habits were affected by the new arrivals.
Many people had heard of the cylinder, of
course, and talked about it, but it did not
have as much effect as a political event.
Even within the five - kilometer circle, most
people were unaffected.
I have already described the behaviour of
the people to whom I spoke.
All over the district people were eating dinner.
Men were gardening, children were being put
to bed, young people were out walking together.
Maybe there was talk in the village streets,
a new topic in the pubs - and here and there
a messenger, or even an eye-witness of the
later events, caused some excitement.
However, for most of the time the daily routine
of work, food, drink and sleep went on as
it had done for countless years.
People came to the common and left it, but
all the time a crowd remained.
One or two adventurous people went into the
darkness and crawled quite near the Martians,
but they never returned, because now and again
a light-ray swept round the common, and the
Heat-Ray was ready to follow.
And all night the sound of hammering could
be heard as the Martians worked on the machines
they were making ready.
At about eleven, a company of soldiers came
through Horsell and spread out in a great
circle around the common.
Several officers had been on the common earlier
in the day and one was reported to be missing.
Another one arrived and was busy questioning
the crowd at midnight.
The army was certainly taking things seriously.
A few seconds after midnight the crowd in
the Chertsey Road, Woking, saw a star fall
from the sky into the woods to the north-west.
This was the second cylinder.
Saturday lives in my memory as a day of worry.
It was a lazy, hot day too.
I had only slept a little and I got up early.
I went into my garden and stood listening,
but towards the common there was nothing moving.
The milkman came as usual and I asked him
the latest news.
He told me that during the night the Martians
had been surrounded by soldiers and that field-guns
were expected.
'We have to try not to kill them,' he said,
'if it can possibly be avoided.'
After breakfast, instead of working, I decided
to walk down towards the common.
Under the railway bridge I found a group of
soldiers - engineers, I think, men wearing
small round caps, dirty red jackets and dark
trousers.
They told me that no one was allowed over
the bridge.
I talked with them for a time and told them
of my sight of the Martians on the previous
evening.
None had seen them, so they asked me many
questions.
An ordinary engineer is much better educated
than a common soldier, and they discussed,
with some intelligence, the odd conditions
of the possible fight.
After some time I left them and went on to
the railway station to get as many morning
papers as I could.
These contained only very inaccurate descriptions
of the killing of Stent, Henderson, Ogilvy
and the others.
I got back to lunch at about two, very tired
because, as I have said, the day was extremely
hot and dull.
To make myself feel better I took a cold bath
in the afternoon.
During that day the Martians did not show
themselves.
They were busy in the pit, and there was the
sound of hammering and a column of smoke.
'New attempts have been made to signal, but
without success,' was how the evening papers
later described it.
An engineer told me that this was done by
a man crawling forwards with a flag on a long
pole.
The Martians took as much notice of him as
we would of a cow.
At about three o'clock I heard the sound of
a gun, firing regularly, from the direction
of Chertsey.
I learned that they were shooting into the
wood in which the second cylinder had fallen.
An hour or two later a field-gun arrived for
use against the first cylinder.
At about six in the evening, as I had tea
with my wife in the garden, I heard an explosion
from the common, and immediately after that
the sound of gunfire.
Then came a violent crash quite close to us,
that shook the ground.
I rushed out onto the grass and saw the tops
of the trees around the Oriental College burst
into smoky red flame, and the tower of the
little church beside it slide down into ruins.
The roof of the college was in pieces.
Then one of our chimneys cracked and broken
bricks fell down onto the flower-bed by my
study window.
My wife and I stood amazed.
Then I realized that the Martians could hit
the top of Maybury Hill with their Heat-Ray
because they had cleared the college out of
the way.
After that I took my wife's arm and ran with
her out into the road.
Then I went back and fetched the servant.
'We can't stay here,' I said, and as I spoke
the firing started again for a moment on the
common.
'But where can we go?' said my wife in terror.
I thought, puzzled.
Then I remembered my cousins in Leatherhead.
'Leatherhead!'
I shouted above the sudden noise.
She looked away from me downhill.
Surprised people were coming out of their
houses.
'How will we get to Leatherhead?'
she asked.
Down the hill I saw some soldiers rush under
the railway bridge.
Three went through the open doors of the Oriental
College and two began running from house to
house.
The sun, shining through the smoke that rose
up from the tops of the trees, seemed blood-red
and threw an unfamiliar bright light on everything.
'Wait here,' I said.
'You are safe here.'
I ran at once towards the pub, whose owner
had a horse and cart.
I ran because I realized that soon everyone
on this side of the hill would be moving.
I found the pub's owner in his bar, with no
idea of what was going on.
I explained quickly that I had to leave my
home, and arranged to borrow the cart, promising
to bring it back before midnight.
At the time it did not seem to me so urgent
that he should leave his home.
I drove the cart down the road and, leaving
it with my wife and servant, rushed into the
house and packed a few valuables.
While I was doing this, a soldier ran past.
He was going from house to house, warning
people to leave.
I shouted after him, 'What news?'
He turned, stared, shouted something about
'crawling out in a thing like a dish cover',
and moved on to the gate of the next house.
I helped my servant into the back of the cart,
then jumped up into the driver's seat beside
my wife.
In another moment we were clear of the smoke
and the noise, and moving quickly down the
opposite side of Maybury Hill.
CHAPTER FIVE
Running Away
Leatherhead is about twenty kilometres from
Maybury.
We got there without any problems at about
nine o'clock, and the horse had an hour's
rest while I had supper with my cousins and
left my wife in their care.
My wife was strangely silent during the drive,
and seemed very worried.
If I had not made a promise to the pub owner,
she would, I think, have asked me to stay
in Leatherhead that night.
Her face, I remember, was very white as I
drove away.
My feelings were quite different.
I had been very excited all day and I was
not sorry that I had to return to Maybury.
I was even afraid that the last shots I had
heard might mean the end of our visitors from
Mars.
I wanted to be there at the death.
The night was unexpectedly dark, and it was
as hot and airless as the day.
Overhead the clouds were passing fast, mixed
here and there with clouds of black and red
smoke, although no wind moved the bushes around
me.
I heard a church strike midnight, and then
I saw Maybury Hill, with its tree-tops and
roofs black and sharp against the red sky.
At that moment a bright green light lit up
the road around me and showed the distant
woods to the north.
I saw a line of green fire pass through the
moving clouds and into the field to my left.
It was the third cylinder!
Just after this came the first lightning of
the storm, and the thunder burst like a gun
overhead.
The horse ran forwards in terror at high speed.
There is a gentle slope towards the foot of
Maybury Hill, and down this we went.
After the lightning had begun, it flashed
again and again, as quickly as I have ever
seen.
The thunder crashed almost all the time.
The flashing light was blinding and confusing,
and thin rain hit my face as I drove down
the slope.
I paid little attention to the road in front
of me, and then suddenly my attention was
caught by something.
At first I thought it was the wet roof of
a house, but the lightning flashes showed
that it was moving quickly down Maybury Hill.
Then there was a great flash like daylight
and this strange object could be seen clearly.
How can I describe this Thing that I saw?
It was an enormous tripod, higher than many
houses, stepping over the young trees.
It was a walking engine of shining metal.
Then suddenly, the trees in the wood ahead
of me were pushed to the side and a second
enormous tripod appeared, rushing, as it seemed,
straight towards me.
And I was driving fast to meet it.
At the sight of this second machine I panicked
completely.
I pulled my horse's head hard round to the
right.
The cart turned over on the horse and I was
thrown sideways.
I fell heavily into a shallow pool of water.
I crawled out almost immediately and lay,
my feet still in the water, under a bush.
The horse did not move (his neck was broken,
poor animal!) and by the lightning flashes
I saw the turned-over cart and one wheel still
spinning slowly.
Then the enormous machine walked past me and
went uphill.
As it passed it gave a deafening howl that
was louder than the thunder - 'Aloo!
Aloo!' - and a minute later it was with another
one, half a kilometer away, bending over something
in a field.
I have no doubt that this was the third of
the cylinders they had fired at us from Mars.
I was wet with rain above and pool-water below.
It was some time before my shock would let
me struggle up into a drier position, or think
of the great danger I was in.
I got to my feet at last and, keeping low,
managed to get into a wood near Maybury without
the machines seeing me.
Staying in the wood, I moved towards my own
house.
If I had really understood the meaning of
all the things I had seen, I would have gone
back to join my wife in Leatherhead immediately.
But that night it was all very strange and
I was physically exhausted, wet to the skin,
deafened and blinded by the storm.
All these things prevented me from making
a sensible decision.
I walked up the narrow road towards my house.
Near the top I stood on something soft and,
by a flash of lightning, saw the body of a
man.
I had never touched a dead body before, but
I forced myself to turn him over and feel
for his heart.
He certainly was dead.
It seemed that his neck had been broken.
Then the lightning flashed again and I saw
his face.
It was the owner of the pub, whose cart I
had taken.
I stepped over him nervously and moved on
up the hill.
Towards Maybury Bridge there were voices and
the sound of feet, but I did not have the
courage to shout or go to them.
I let myself into my house and locked the
door, walked to the bottom of the stairs and
sat down, shaking violently.
It was some time before I could get to my
feet again and put on some dry clothes.
After that I went upstairs to my study.
The window looks over the trees and the railway
towards Horsell Common.
In the hurry to leave it had been left open.
I stopped in the doorway, at a safe distance
from it.
The thunderstorm had passed.
The towers of the Oriental College and the
trees around it had gone.
Very far away, lit by red fire, the common
was visible.
Across the light, great black shapes moved
busily backwards and forwards.
I closed the door noiselessly and moved nearer
the window.
The view opened out until, on one side, it
reached to the houses around Woking Station,
and on the other, to the burnt woods of Byfleet.
Between them were areas of fire and smoking
ground.
The view reminded me, more than anything else,
of factories at night.
I turned my desk chair to the window and stared
out at the country and, in particular, at
the three enormous black Things that were
moving around the common.
They seemed very busy.
I began to ask myself what they could be.
Were they intelligent machines?
I felt this was impossible.
Or did a Martian sit inside each, controlling
it in the same way that a man's brain controls
his body?
The storm had left the sky clear, and over
the smoke of the burning land the tiny bright
light of Mars was dropping into the west,
when a soldier came quietly into my garden.
I got up and leant out of the window.
'Psst!'
I said, in a whisper.
He stopped for a moment, then walked across
to the house.
'Who's there?' he said, also whispering.
'Are you trying to hide?'
I asked.
'I am.'
'Come into the house,' I said.
I went down, opened the door and let him in.
I could not see his face.
He had no hat and his coat was unbuttoned.
'What's happened?'
I asked.
'We didn't have a chance.' he said.
'Not a chance.'
He followed me into the dining-room.
'Have a drink,' I said, pouring one for him.
He drank it.
Then suddenly he sat down at the table, put
his head on his arms and began to cry like
a little boy.
It was a long time before he was able to answer
my questions, and the answers he gave were
puzzled and came in broken sentences.
He was part of a field-gun team.
They were turning their gun to fire on one
of the tripods when it suddenly exploded.
He found himself lying under a group of burnt
dead men and horses.
His back was hurt by the fall of a horse and
he lay there for a long time.
He watched as the foot-soldiers rushed towards
the tripod.
They all went down in a second.
Then the tripod walked slowly over the common.
A kind of arm held a complicated metal case,
out of which the Heat-Ray flashed as it killed
anyone who was still moving.
Then the tripod turned and walked away towards
where the second cylinder lay.
At last the soldier was able to move, crawling
at first, and he got to Woking.
There were a few people still alive there;
most of them were very frightened, and many
of them had been burnt.
He hid behind a broken wall as one of the
Martian tripods returned.
He saw this one go after a man, catch him
in one of its steel arms and knock his head
against a tree.
After it got dark, the soldier finally ran
and managed to get across the railway.
That was the story I got from him, bit by
bit.
He grew calmer telling me.
He had eaten no food since midday, and I found
some meat and bread and brought it into the
room.
As we talked, the sky gradually became lighter.
I began to see his face, blackened and exhausted,
as no doubt mine was too.
When we had finished eating, we went quietly
upstairs to my study and I looked again out
of the open window.
In one night the valley had become a place
of death.
The fires had died down now, but the ruins
of broken and burnt-out houses and blackened
trees were clear in the cold light of the
dawn.
Destruction had never been so total in the
history of war.
And, shining in the morning light, three of
the tripods stood on the common, their tops
turning as they examined the damage they had
done.
CHAPTER SIX
The Death of Towns
As the dawn grew brighter, we moved back from
the window where we had watched and went very
quietly downstairs.
The soldier agreed with me that the house
was not a good place to stay in.
He suggested going towards London, where he
could rejoin his company.
My plan was to return at once to Leatherhead.
The strength of the Martians worried me so
much that I had decided to take my wife to
the south coast, and leave the country with
her immediately.
I had already decided that the area around
London would be the scene of a great battle
before the Martians could be destroyed.
Between us and Leatherhead, however, lay the
third cylinder.
If I had been alone, I think I would have
taken my chance and gone straight across country.
But the soldier persuaded me not to.
'It's no kindness to your wife,' he said,
'for you to get killed.'
In the end I agreed to go north with him under
cover of the woods.
After that I would leave him and turn off
to reach Leatherhead.
I wanted to start at once, but the soldier
had been in wars before and knew better than
that.
He made me find all the food and drink that
we could carry, and we filled our pockets.
Then we left the house and ran as quickly
as we could down the narrow road.
All the houses seemed empty.
In the road lay a pile of three burnt bodies
close together, killed by the Heat-Ray.
In fact, apart from ourselves, there did not
seem to be a living person on Maybury Hill.
We reached the woods at the foot of the hill
and moved through these towards the road.
As we ran, we heard the sound of horses and
saw through the trees three soldiers riding
towards Woking.
We shouted and they stopped while we hurried
towards them.
They were an officer and two men.
'You are the first people I've seen coming
this way this morning,' the officer said.
'What's happening?'
The soldier who had stayed with me stepped
up to him.
'My gun was destroyed last night, sir.
I've been hiding.
I'm trying to rejoin my company.
You'll come in sight of the Martians, I expect,
about a kilometer along this road.'
'What do they look like?' asked the officer.
'Big machines, sir.
Thirty metres high.
Three legs and a great big head, sir.'
'What nonsense!' said the officer.
'You'll see, sir.
They carry a kind of box that shoots fire
and strikes you dead.'
'What do you mean - a gun?'
'No, sir.'
And he began to describe the Heat-Ray.
Half-way through his report the officer interrupted
him and looked at me.
'Did you see it?' he said.
'It's perfectly true,' I replied.
'Well,' he said.
'I suppose it's my business to see it too.
Listen,' he said to my new friend, 'you'd
better go to Weybridge and report to the highest
officer.'
He thanked me and they rode away.
By Byfleet station we came out from the trees
and found the country calm and peaceful in
the morning sunlight.
It seemed like any other Sunday - except for
the empty houses, and the other ones where
people were packing.
However, Byfleet was very busy.
Soldiers were telling people to leave and
helping them to load carts in the main street.
Many people, though, did not realize how serious
the situation was.
I saw one old man with a big box and a number
of flower-pots, angrily arguing with a soldier
who wanted him to leave them behind.
'Do you know what's over there?'
I said, pointing towards the woods that hid
the Martians.
'Eh?' he said.
'I was explaining that these are valuable.'
'Death!'
I shouted.
'Death is coming!
Death!' and leaving him to think about that,
I hurried on to Weybridge.
We remained there until midday, and at that
time found ourselves at the place where the
River Wey joins the River Thames.
Here we found an excited crowd of people.
There was no great fear at this time, but
already there were more people than all the
boats could carry across the Thames.
Every now and then people looked nervously
at the fields beyond Chertsey, but everything
there was still.
Then came the sound of a gun and, almost immediately,
other guns across the river, unseen because
of the trees, began to fire.
Everyone stood still, stopped by the sudden
sound of battle, near us but invisible to
us.
Then we saw a cloud of smoke far away up the
river.
The ground moved and a heavy explosion shook
the air, smashing two or three windows in
the houses and leaving us shocked.
'Look!'
shouted a man.
'Over there!
Do you see them?'
Quickly, one after the other, one, two, three,
four of the Martian machines appeared, far
away over the low trees towards Chertsey.
Then, from a different direction, a fifth
one came towards us.
Their metal bodies shone in the sun as they
moved forwards to the guns.
One on the left, the furthest away, held a
large case high in the air, and the terrible
Heat-Ray shone towards Chertsey and struck
the town.
At the sight of these strange, quick and terrible
creatures, the crowd near the water's edge
seemed for a moment to be totally shocked.
There was no screaming or shouting, but a
silence.
Then came some quiet talk and the beginning
of movement.
A woman pushed at me with her hand and rushed
past me.
I turned, but I was not too frightened for
thought.
'Get under water!'
I shouted, but nobody listened.
I turned around again and ran towards the
approaching Martian, ran right down the stony
beach and dived into the water.
Others did the same.
The stones under my feet were muddy and slippery,
and the river was so low that I moved perhaps
seven metres before I could get under the
surface.
I could hear people jumping off boats into
the water.
But the Martian took no notice of us.
When I lifted my head it was looking towards
the guns that were still firing across the
river.
It was already raising the case which sent
the Heat-Ray when the first shell burst six
metres above its head.
I gave a cry of surprise.
Then two other shells burst at the same time
in the air near its body.
Its head twisted round in time to receive,
but not in time to avoid, the fourth shell.
This exploded right in its face.
Its head flashed and burst into a dozen broken
pieces of red flesh and shining metal.
'Hit!'
I shouted.
The headless machine marched on, swinging
from side to side.
It hit a church tower, knocking it down, then
moved on and fell into the river out of sight.
A violent explosion shook the air, and a column
of water, steam, mud and broken metal shot
far up into the sky.
In another moment a great wave of very hot
water came sweeping round the bend.
I saw people struggling towards the shore
and heard their screaming and shouting faintly
above the noise of the Martian's fall.
I rushed through the water until I could see
round the bend.
The Martian came into sight down the river,
most of it under the water.
Thick clouds of steam were pouring from the
wreckage, and through it I could see its long
legs and tentacles moving in the water.
My attention was caught by an angry noise.
A man, knee-deep in the water, shouted to
me and pointed, although I could not hear
what he said.
Looking back, I saw the other Martians walking
down the river-bank from the direction of
Chertsey.
The guns fired again, but with no effect.
At that moment I got under the water and,
holding my breath until movement was painful,
swam under the surface for as long as I could.
The river was rough around me and quickly
growing hotter.
When for a moment I raised my head to breathe
and throw the hair and water out of my eyes,
the steam was rising in a white fog that hid
the Martians completely.
The noise was deafening.
Then I saw them, enormous grey figures.
They had passed me and two were bending over
the fallen one.
The third and fourth stood beside him in the
water.
The cases that produced the Heat-Rays were
waved high and the beams flashed this way
and that.
The air was full of deafening and confusing
noises: the loud sounds of the Martians, the
crash of falling houses, the flash of fire
as trees and fences began to burn.
Thick black smoke was rising to mix with the
steam from the river.
Then suddenly the white flashes of the Heat-Ray
came towards me.
The houses fell as it touched them, and exploded
into flame.
The trees caught fire with a loud noise.
The Heat- Ray came down to the water's edge
less than fifty metres from where I stood.
It ran across the river and the water behind
it boiled.
I turned towards the shore.
In another moment a large wave of almost boiling
water rushed towards me.
I screamed and ran.
If my foot had slipped, it would have been
the end.
I fell in full view of the Martians on the
stony beach.
I expected only death.
I have a faknee-int memory of the foot of
a Martian coming down within twenty metres
of my head, going straight into the loose
stones.
Then I saw the four of them carrying the remains
of the fallen one between them, now clear
and then later faint through a curtain of
smoke, moving away from me across a great
space of river and fields.
And then, very slowly.
I realized that somehow I had escaped.
I saw an empty boat, very small and far away,
moving down the river and, taking off most
of my wet clothes, I swam to it.
I used my hands to keep it moving, down the
river towards Walton, going very slowly and
often looking behind me.
I was in some pain and very tired.
When the bridge at Walton was coming into
sight, I landed on the Middlesex bank and
lay down, very sick, in the long grass.
I do not remember the arrival of the curate,
so probably I slept for some time.
As I woke up, I noticed a seated figure with
his face staring at the sky, watching the
sunset.
I sat up, and at the sound of my movement
he looked at me.
'Have you any water?'
I asked.
He shook his head.
'You have been asking for water for the last
hour,' he said.
For a moment we were silent, staring at each
other.
He spoke suddenly, looking away from me.
'What does it mean? he said.
'What do these things mean?'
I gave no answer.
'Why are these things allowed?
What have we done - what has Weybridge done?
The morning service was over.
I was walking the roads to clear my brain,
and then - fire and death!
All our work - everything destroyed.
The church!
We rebuilt it only three years ago.
Gone!
Why?'
Another pause, and then he shouted, 'The smoke
of her burning goes up for ever and ever!'
His eyes were wide and he pointed a thin finger
in the direction of Weybridge.
It was clear to me that the great tragedy
in which he was involved - it seemed that
he had escaped from Weybridge - had driven
him to the edge of madness.
'Are we far from Sunbury?'
I said, very quietly.
'What can we do?' he asked.
'Are these creatures everywhere?
Has the Earth been given to them?'
'Are we far from Sunbury?'
'Only this morning I was in charge of the
church service -'
'Things have changed!'
I said, quietly.
'You must stay calm.
There is still hope.'
'Hope!'
'Yes, a lot of hope, despite all this destruction.
Listen!'
From beyond the low hills across the water
came the dull sound of the distant guns and
a far-away strange crying.
Then everything was still.
High in the west the moon hung pale above
the smoke and the hot, still beauty of the
sunset.
'We had better follow this path,' I said.
'To the north.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
In London
My younger brother was in London when the
Martians fell at Woking.
He was a medical student, working for an examination,
and he heard nothing of the arrival until
Saturday morning.
The morning papers on Saturday contained,
in addition to a great deal of information
about the planet Mars, one very short report.
The Martians, alarmed by the approach of a
crowd, had killed a number of people with
a quick-firing gun, the story said.
It ended with the words, 'Although they seem
frightening, the Martians have not moved from
the pit into which they have fallen, and don't
seem able to do so.'
Even the afternoon papers had nothing to tell
apart from the movement of soldiers around
the common, and the burning of the woods between
Woking and Weybridge.
Nothing more of the fighting was known that
night, the night of my drive to Leatherhead
and back.
My brother was not worried about us, as he
knew from the description in the papers chat
the cylinder was three kilometres from my
house.
That night he made up his mind to visit me,
in order to see the Things before they were
killed.
He sent a telegram, which never reached me.
On the Saturday evening, at Waterloo station,
he learned that an accident prevented trains
from reaching Woking.
He could not discover what kind of accident
it was.
In fact, the people in charge of the railway
did not clearly know at that time.
There was very little excitement at the station.
Few people connected the problem with the
Martians.
I have read, in another description of these
events, that on Sunday morning 'all London
was panicked by the news from Woking.'
In fact, this is simply not true.
Plenty of Londoners did not hear of the Martians
until Monday morning.
Some did, but they needed time to realize
what all the reports in the Sunday papers
actually meant.
But most people in London do not read Sunday
papers.
Besides this, Londoners are very used to feeling
safe, and exciting news is so normal in the
papers that they could read reports like this
without great fear:
At about seven o'clock last night the Martians
came out of the cylinder and, moving around
in metal machines, completely destroyed Woking
station and the houses around it, and killed
around 600 soldiers.
No details are known.
Machine guns are completely useless against
them, and field-guns have been put out of
action.
The Martians appear to be moving towards Chertsey.
People in West Surrey are very worried and
defenses have been built to slow the Martians'
movement towards London.
No one in London knew what the Martians looked
like, and there was still a fixed idea that
they must be slow: 'crawling', 'moving painfully'
- words like these were in all the earlier
reports.
But none of them were written by anyone who
had actually seen a Martian.
The Sunday papers printed separate editions
as further news came in.
But there was almost nothing to tell people
until the government announced that the people
of Walton and Weybridge, and all chat district,
were pouring along the roads towards London.
My brother went again to Waterloo station
to find out if the line to Woking was open.
There he heard that the Chertsey line was
also closed.
He learned that several unusual telegrams
had been received in the morning from Byfleet
and Chertsey stations, but that these had
suddenly stopped.
My brother could get very little exact information
out of them.
'There's fighting going on around Weybridge,'
was all the information they had.
Quite a number of people who had been expecting
friends to arrive by train were standing at
the station.
One man spoke to my brother.
'There are lots of people coming into Kingston
in carts and things, with boxes and cases,'
he said.
'They come from Weybridge and Walton, and
they said guns have been heard at Chertsey,
heavy firing, and that soldiers told them
to move out at once because the Martians are
corning.
What does it all mean?
The Martians can't get out of their pit, can
they?'
My brother could not tell him.
At about five o'clock the growing crowd in
the station was greatly excited by the opening
of the line between the South-Eastern and
South-Western stations, which is usually closed.
Then trains carrying large guns and many soldiers
passed through the station, moving towards
Kingston.
Soon after that the police arrived and began
to move the crowd out of the station, and
my brother went out into the street again.
On Waterloo Bridge a number of people were
watching an odd brown liquid that came down
the river from time to time.
The sun was just setting and the Houses of
Parliament stood against a peaceful sky.
There was talk of a floating body.
In Wellington Street my brother met two men
selling newspapers which had just been printed.
The advertising boards said, 'Terrible tragedy!
Fighting at Weybridge!
Defeat of the Martians!
London in danger!'
He bought a paper.
Then, and only then, he understood something
of the full power and terror of the Martians.
He learned that they were not just a few small
crawling creatures, but that they could control
enormous mechanical bodies.
They could move quickly and strike with such
power that even the biggest guns could not
stand against them.
They were described as, 'great machines like
spiders, nearly thirty metres high, as fast
as an express train, and able to shoot out
a beam of strong heat.'
Many field-guns, the report said, had been
hidden around the country near Horsell Common,
and especially between the Woking district
and London.
Five of the machines had been seen moving
towards the Thames and one, by a lucky chance,
had been destroyed.
In other cases the shells had missed, and
the guns had at once been destroyed by the
Heat-Rays.
Heavy losses of soldiers were mentioned, but
in general the report was optimistic.
The Martians had been defeated, my brother
read.
They had gone back to their cylinders again,
in the circle around Woking.
Guns, including some very large ones, were
moving in quickly.
One hundred and sixteen were now in position,
mainly covering London.
There had never been such a large or fast
movement of war equipment in England before.
No doubt, said the report, the situation was
strange and serious, but the public was asked
to avoid and discourage panic.
No doubt the Martians were very frightening,
but there could not be more than twenty of
them against our millions.
All down Wellington Street people could be
seen reading the paper.
Men came running from buses to get copies.
Certainly people were excited by the news,
whatever they had felt before.
A map shop in the Strand opened specially,
and a man in his
Sunday clothes could be seen inside quickly
fixing maps of Surrey to the shop window.
Going along the Strand to Trafalgar Square,
my brother saw some of the refugees from West
Surrey.
There was a man with his wife and two boys
and some pieces of furniture in a cart, and
close behind him came another one with five
or six well-dressed people and some boxes
and cases.
The faces of the people showed that they were
very tired.
Some distance behind them was a man on an
old-fashioned bicycle.
He was dirty and white-faced.
My brother turned towards Victoria station,
and met a number of people like these.
He had an idea that he might see me.
He noticed an unusual number of police controlling
the traffic.
Some of the refugees were exchanging news
with the people on the buses.
Most were excited by their strange experience.
My brother spoke to several of the refugees
but none could give him any news of Woking,
except one man who said that it had been totally
destroyed the previous night.
At that time there was a strong feeling on
the streets that the government should be
blamed because they had not destroyed the
Martians already.
At about eight o'clock the sound of tiring
could be heard clearly ail over the south
of London.
My brother walked from Westminster to his
room near Regent's Park.
He was now very worried about me.
There were one or two carts with refugees
going along Oxford Street, but the news was
spreading so slowly that Regent Street and
Portland Place were full of people taking
their usual Sunday night walk.
Along the edge of Regent's Park there were
as many romantic couples as there had ever
been.
The night was warm and still.
The sound of guns continued from time to time
and after midnight there seemed to be lightning
in the south.
My brother read and reread the paper, thinking
that the worst had happened to me.
He was restless, and after supper went out
again.
He returned and tried to concentrate on his
examination notes, but without success.
He went to bed a little after midnight and
was woken in the early hours of Monday morning
by the sound of knocking on doors, feet running
in the street, distant drumming and the ringing
of bells.
For a moment he lay in surprise.
Then he jumped out of bed and ran to the window.
Up and down the street other windows were
opening and people were shouting questions.
'They are coming!'
a policeman shouted back, banging on the door.
'The Martians are coming!'
Then he hurried to the next door.
The sound of drums came from the army base
in Albany Street and bells were ringing in
every church.
There was a noise of doors opening, and the
lights went on in window after window in the
houses across the street.
A closed carriage came up the street, quickly
followed by a number of other fast-moving
vehicles.
Most of them were going to Chalk Farm station,
where special trains were being loaded.
For a long time my brother stared out of the
window in total surprise, watching the policeman
banging at door after door.
Then he crossed the room and began to dress,
running with each piece of clothing to the
window in order to miss nothing of the growing
excitement.
And then men selling unusually early newspapers
came shouting into the street:
'London in danger!
Kingston and Richmond defenses broken!
Terrible killing in the Thames Valley!'
All around him - in the rooms below, in the
houses on each side and across the road, and
all across London - people were rubbing their
eyes and opening windows to stare out and
ask questions, and getting dressed quickly
as the first breath of the coming storm of
fear blew through the streets.
It was the beginning of the great panic.
London, which had gone to bed on Sunday night
not knowing much and caring even less, was
woken in the early hours of Monday morning
to a real sense of danger.
Unable to learn what was happening from his
window, my brother went down and out into
the street, just as the sky turned pink with
the dawn.
Every moment brought more and more fast-moving
people in vehicles.
'Black Smoke!' he heard people shouting.
'Black Smoke!'
As he stood at the door, not knowing what
to do, he saw another newspaper-seller approaching
him.
The man was running away with the others and
selling his papers for many times their normal
price as he ran - a strange mixture of profit
and panic.
And from this paper my brother read that terrible
report from the commander of the army:
The Martians are able to send out enormous
clouds of black smoke.
They have poisoned our gunners, destroyed
Richmond, Kingston and Wimbledon, and are
moving slowly towards London, destroying everything
on the way, It is impossible to stop them.
There is no safety from the Black Smoke except
by running away.
That was all, but it was enough.
All of the six million people who lived in
the great city were beginning to move.
Soon everybody would be trying to escape to
the north.
'Black Smoke!'
the voices shouted.
'Fire!'
The bells of the local church rang loudly,
a carelessly-driven cart smashed, and people
screamed and swore.
Yellow lights moved around in the houses.
And in the sky above them, the dawn was growing
brighter - clear and calm.
He heard people running in the rooms, and
up and down the stairs behind him.
His neighbour came to the door.
She was not properly dressed and her husband
followed her, shouting.
As my brother began to realize how serious
the situation was, he returned quickly to
his room, put all the money he had - about
ten pounds - into his pockets and went out
again into the streets.
CHAPTER EIGHT
The Black Smoke
While the curate had sat and talked so wildly
to me in the flat fields near Walton, and
while my brother was watching the refugees
pour across Westminster Bridge, the Martians
had started to attack again.
As it was reported later, most of them remained
busy with preparations in the pit on Horsell
Common until nine that night, doing something
that produced a great amount of Black Smoke.
But three certainly came out at about eight
o'clock.
They moved forwards slowly and carefully towards
Ripley and Weybridge, and so came in sight
of the waiting guns.
These Martians moved in a line, perhaps two
kilometres apart.
They communicated with each other by loud
howls.
It was this howling and the firing of the
guns at Ripley and Weybridge that we heard
at Walton.
The Ripley gunners had never been in action
before.
The guns fired one ineffective shell each,
then the soldiers ran away.
The Martian, without using his Heat-Ray, walked
calmly over their guns.
The Weybridge men, however, were better led
or were more experienced.
Hidden by a wood, it seems they were not noticed
by the Martian nearest to them.
They aimed their guns well and fired at a
distance of about one kilometer.
The shells exploded all round it and it was
seen to move forwards a few steps, and go
down.
The guns were reloaded quickly.
The fallen Martian used its voice, and immediately
a second one answered it, appearing over the
trees to the south.
It seemed that one of its three legs had been
broken.
All of the second shells missed the Martian
on the ground and, immediately.
The other Martians used their Heat-Rays on
the guns.
The shells blew up, the trees all around the
guns caught fire and only one or two of the
men escaped.
After this it seemed that the three Martians
spoke together, and those who were watching
them report that they stayed absolutely quiet
for the next half-hour.
The fallen Martian crawled slowly out of its
machine and began to repair its leg.
By about nine it had finished, and the machine
was seen to move again.
A few minutes later these three were joined
by four other Martians, each carrying a thick
black tube.
A similar tube was given to each of the three,
and the seven spread out at equal distances
along a curved line between Weybridge and
Ripley.
A dozen signal lights went on as soon as they
began to move, warning the waiting guns around
Esher.
At the same time four of the fighting-machines,
also carrying tubes, crossed the river, and
two of them, black against the western sky,
came into sight of myself and the curate as
we hurried along the road to the north.
When he saw them, the curate made a frightened
noise and began running, but I knew it was
no good running from a Martian and I crawled
into some bushes by the side of the road.
He looked back and turned to join me.
We heard the distant sound of a gun, then
another nearer, and then another.
And then the Martian closest to us raised
his tube and fired it towards the guns, with
a loud bang that made the ground shake.
The other one did the same.
There was no flash, no smoke, simply a loud
noise.
I was so excited by all this that I completely
forgot about my persona safety and raised
my head out of the bushes.
As I did, I heard another bang and something
flew fast over my head.
I expected at least to see smoke or fire,
but there was only the deep-blue sky above
and one single star.
There had been no explosion, no answer from
the guns.
Silence returned, and three minutes passed.
'What's happened?' said the curate, standing
up.
'I've no idea,' I answered.
I looked again at the Martian, and saw that
it was now moving east along the river bank.
Every moment I expected a hidden gun to fire
at it, but the evening calm was unbroken.
The figure of the Martian grew smaller as
it moved away, and soon it was hidden by the
mist and the coming night.
The curate and I climbed higher up the hill
and looked around.
Towards Sunbury there was something dark,
like a hill, hiding our view of the country
further away.
Then, far across the river, we saw another,
similar hill.
These hills grew lower and broader as we stared.
I had a sudden thought and looked to the north,
and there I saw a third of these cloudy black
hills.
Everything had become very still.
Far away to the north-east we heard the Martians
calling to each other, but our guns were silent.
At the time we could not understand these
things, but later I learnt the meaning of
these frightening black hills.
Each of the Martians, standing in the great
curve I have described, had used the tube
he carried to fire a large cylinder over whatever
hill, wood or other possible hiding-place
for guns might be in front of him.
Some fired only one of these, some two or
more.
These broke when they hit the ground - they
did not explode - and let out an enormous
amount of thick Black Smoke.
This rose up in a cloud shaped like a hill,
then sank and spread itself slowly over the
surrounding country.
And it was death to breathe that smoke.
It was heavy, this smoke, so when it began
to sink down it behaved like a liquid, running
down hills and into the valleys.
And where it met with water, or even mist
or wet grass, a chemical action took place
and it turned into a powder that sank slowly
and made room for more.
When the smoke had begun to settle, it stayed
quite close to the ground so that even fifteen
metres up in the air, on the roots and upper
floors of houses and in high trees, there
was a chance of escaping its poison.
A man later told me that he had watched from
a church roof as the smoke filled his village.
For a day and a half he stayed up there, tired,
hungry and burnt by the sun before it was
safe to come down.
But that was in a village where the Black
Smoke was allowed to remain until it sank
into the ground.
Usually, when it had done its work, the Martian
cleared the air by blowing steam at it.
They did this to the black clouds near us,
as we saw in the starlight from the upper
window of an empty house.
From there we could see the searchlights on
Richmond Hill and Kingston Hill moving in
the sky, and at about eleven the windows shook,
and we heard the sound of the large guns that
had been put in position there.
These continued for a quarter of an hour,
firing blindly at Martians too far away to
be seen.
Then the fourth cylinder fell - a bright green
star to the north-east.
So, doing it methodically, as a man might
kill insects, the Martians spread this strange
killing smoke over the country towards London.
The ends of the curve slowly moved apart,
until at least they formed a line about twelve
kilometres long.
All through the night their tubes moved forwards.
They never gave the guns any chance against
them.
Wherever there was a possibility of guns being
hidden, they fired a cylinder of Black Smoke
at them, and where the guns could be seen
they used the Heat-Ray.
By midnight the burning trees along the slopes
of Richmond Hill lit up clouds of Black Smoke
which covered the whole valley of the Thames,
and went as far as the eye could see.
They only used the Heat-Ray from time to time
that night, either because they had a limited
supply of material for its production or because
they did not want to destroy the country,
but only to defeat its people.
They certainly succeeded.
Sunday night was the end of organized opposition
to their movement.
After that no group of men would stand against
them, because this would mean almost certain
death.
You have to imagine what happened to the gunners
towards Esher, waiting so tensely in the evening
light, because none of them lived to tell
the story.
You can see the quiet expectation, the officers
watching, the gunners waiting with their horses,
the groups of local people standing as near
as they were allowed, the ambulances and hospital
tents with the burnt and wounded from Weybridge.
Then came the dull noise of the shots that
the Martians fired, and the cylinder flying
over the trees and houses and breaking in
the neighboring fields.
You can imagine, too, how they watched as
the blackness rose into the sky.
The men and horses near it were seen running,
screaming, falling down.
There were shouts of fear, the guns suddenly
left behind, men on the ground struggling
to breathe, and the fast spreading of the
dark smoke - a silent black cloud hiding its
dead.
Before dawn the Black Smoke was pouring through
the streets of Richmond.
The government, already falling apart, made
one last effort.
It told the people of London that they had
to run away.
CHAPTER NINE
Escape
You can understand the wave of fear that swept
through the greatest city in the world at
dawn on Monday morning.
People ran to the railway stations, to the
boats on the Thames, and hurried by even street
that went north or east.
By ten o'clock the police were finding it
hard to keep control.
All the railway lines north of the Thames
had been warned by midnight on Sunday, and
trains were being filled.
Passengers were fighting for standing room
in the carriages even at two o'clock in the
morning.
By three the crowds were so large around the
stations that people were being pushed over
and walked on.
Guns were fired and knives were used.
The police who had been sent to direct the
traffic, exhausted and angry, were fighting
with the people they had been called out to
protect.
And as time passed and the engine drivers
and firemen refused to return to London, the
people turned in growing crowds away from
the stations and onto the roads running north.
By midday a cloud of slowly sinking Black
Smoke had moved along the Thames, cutting
off all escape across the bridges.
Another cloud came over Ealing, and surrounded
a little island of people on Castle Hill,
alive but unable to escape.
After trying unsuccessfully to get onto a
train at Chalk Farm my brother came out into
the road, pushed through the hurrying lines
of vehicles, and had the luck to be at the
front of a crowd which was taking bicycles
from a shop.
He got his hands on one.
He put a hole in its front tire while he was
pulling it through the broken window, and
cut his wrist, but he managed to get away
on it.
The foot of Haverstock Hill was blocked by
fallen horses, but my brother got onto the
Belsize Road.
So he escaped from the worst of the panic
in London and reached Edgware at about seven.
A kilometer before the village the front wheel
of the bicycle broke.
He left it at the roadside and walked on.
People there were standing on the pavement,
looking in surprise at the growing crowds
of refugees.
He succeeded in getting some food at a pub.
My brother had some friends in Chelmsford,
and this perhaps made him take the road that
ran to the east.
He saw few other refugees until he met the
two ladies who later travelled with him.
He arrived just in time to save them.
He heard their screams and, hurrying round
the corner, saw a couple of men trying to
pull them out of the little cart which they
had been driving, while a third held onto
the frightened horse's head.
One of the ladies, a short woman dressed in
white, was screaming.
The other, younger one was hitting the man
who held her arm with a whip.
My brother shouted and ran towards them.
One of the men turned towards him.
Realizing from his face that a fight was unavoidable,
and being a good boxer, my brother hit him
hard and knocked him back onto the wheel of
the cart.
It was no time for fair fighting, and my brother
quieted him with a kick, then took hold of
the collar of the man who held the younger
lady's arm.
He heard the horse move forwards and then
the third man hit him between the eyes.
The man he held pulled himself free and ran
off down the road in the direction from which
he had come.
Still recovering, my brother found himself
facing the man who had held the horse's head,
and realized that the cart was moving away
along the road.
The man, who looked very well built, tried
to move in closer, but my brother hit him
in the face.
Then, realizing that he was alone, he ran
along the road after the cart, with the big
man behind him.
The man who had run away had now stopped and
turned and was following my brother at a greater
distance.
Suddenly, my brother fell.
The big man tripped over him, and when my
brother got to his feet he found himself facing
both of them.
He would have had very little chance if the
younger lady had not very bravely stopped
the cart and returned to help him.
It seemed that she had had a gun all the time,
but it had been under her seat when they were
attacked.
She fired from six metres away, narrowly missing
my brother.
The less brave of the two attackers ran away,
and the other one followed cursing him.
They both stopped further down the road, where
the third man lay unconscious.
'Take this!'
the younger lady said, and she gave my brother
the gun.
'Let's go back to the cart,' said my brother,
wiping the blood from his lip.
They walked to where the lady in white was
struggling to hold the frightened horse.
My brother looked back along the road.
The robbers had had enough and were moving
away.
'I'll sit here,' he said, 'if I may,' and
he got up on the front seat.
The younger lady sat beside him and made the
horse move.
My brother learned that the two women were
the wife and younger sister of a doctor living
in Stanmore, The doctor had heard about the
Martians at the railway station, on his way
home from seeing a patient, and had sent them
off, promising to follow after telling the
neighbour.
He said he would catch up with them by about
half-past four in the morning, but it was
now nearly nine and there was no sign of him.
They stopped and waited for a few hours, but
the doctor did not appear.
The younger woman suggested that they should
move on and catch a train at St Albans.
My brother, who had seen the situation at
the stations in London, thought that was hopeless.
He suggested that they should drive across
Essex to the sea at Harwich, and from there
get right out of the country.
Mrs Elphinstone - that was the name of the
woman in white - refused to listen to his
argument, and kept calling for 'George', but
her sister-in-law was very quiet and sensible
and agreed to my brother's suggestion.
So, intending to cross the Great North Road,
they went on towards Barnet.
As they got closer they saw- more and more
people, all tired and dirty.
They also noticed a long line of dust rising
among the houses in front of them.
There was a sharp bend in the road, less than
fifty metres from the crossroads.
When they came out of it Mrs Elphinstone said.
'Good heavens!
What is this you are driving us into'"
My brother stopped the horse.
The main road was a boiling stream of people,
a river of human beings rushing to the north.
A great cloud of dust, white under the strong
sun, made everything within five metres of
the ground grey and unclear.
More dust was raised all the time by the thick
crowd of men and women, horses and vehicles.
'Go on!
Go on!'
the voices said.
'They're coming.'
It seemed that the whole population of London
was moving north.
There were people of every class and profession,
but they were all dusty; their skins were
dry, their lips black and cracked, and all
of them looked very afraid.
My brother saw Miss Elphinstone covering her
eyes.
'Let's go back!' he shouted.
'We cannot cross this.'
They went back a hundred metres in the direction
they had come.
As they passed the bend in the road, my brother
saw a man lying not far away.
His face was white and shining.
It was clear that he was near death.
The two women sat in silence.
Beyond the bend my brother changed his mind.
He turned to Miss Elphinstone.
'We must go that way,' he said, and turned
the horse round again.
For the second time that day the girl showed
her courage.
My brother went into the crowd and stopped
a horse pulling a cart, while she drove in
front of it.
In another moment they were caught and swept
forwards with the stream of vehicles.
My brother, with red whip-marks on his face
and hands from the car's driver, got up into
the driving seat.
'Point the gun at the man behind,' he said,
giving it to her, 'it he pushes us too hard.
No - point it at his horse.'
Then they began to look for a chance of getting
to the right side of the road.
But as soon as they were in the stream of
vehicles, there was little they could do.
They were taken through Barnet and were more
than a kilometer beyond the centre of the
town before they could fight their way across
to the other side of the road.
They turned to the east and climbed a hill.
There they stopped for the rest of the afternoon,
because they were all exhausted.
They were beginning to feel very hungry and
the night was cold.
In the evening many people came hurrying along
the road near their stopping-place, escaping
from unknown dangers and going in the direction
from which my brother had come.
CHAPTER TEN
The Thunder Child
If the Martians had only wanted destruction,
they could have killed the whole population
of London on Monday, as it moved out slowly
through the neighboring countryside.
It one had flown over London that morning,
every road to the north or east would have
seemed black with moving refugees, everyone
a frightened and exhausted human being.
None of the wars of history had such an effect
- six million people, moving without weapons
or food or any real sense of direction.
It was the start of the death of the human
race.
And over the blue hills to the south of the
river, the Martians moved backwards and forwards,
calmly spreading their poison clouds over
one piece of country and then over another.
They destroyed any weapons they found and
wrecked the railways here and there.
They seemed in no hurry, and did not go beyond
the central part of London all that day.
It is possible that many people stayed in
their houses through Monday morning.
It is certain that many died at home, killed
by the Black Smoke.
Until about midday there were still many ships
on the Thames, attracted by the enormous sums
of money offered by refugees.
It is said that many who swam out to these
ships were pushed away and drowned.
At about one o'clock in the afternoon, the
thin remains of a cloud of Black Smoke was
seen coming through London's Blackfriars Bridge.
This caused a terrible panic and all the ships
and boats tried to leave at the same time.
Many became stuck together under Tower Bridge,
and the sailors had to fight against people
who tried to get on from the riverside.
People were actually climbing down onto the
boats from the bridge above.
When, an hour later, a Martian walked down
the river, there was nothing but broken pieces
of boats in the water.
I will tell you later about the falling of
the fifth cylinder.
The sixth one fell in Wimbledon.
My brother, watching beside the women in the
cart in the field, saw the green flash of
it far beyond the hills.
On Tuesday the three of them, still intending
to get out to sea, drove through the busy
country towards Colchester.
That day the refugees began to realize how
much they needed food.
As they grew hungry, they began to steal.
Farmers defended their animals and crops with
guns in their hands.
A number of people now, like my brother, were
moving to the east, and some were even so
desperate that they turned back towards London
to get food.
These were mainly people from the northern
suburbs who had only heard of, but not seen,
the Black Smoke.
My brother heard that about half the members
of the government had met in Birmingham, in
central England, and that enormous amounts
of explosive were being prepared to be used
in the Midlands.
He was told that the Midland Railway Company
had started running trains again, and was
taking people north from St Albans.
There was also a notice which said that within
twenty-four hours bread would be given to
the hungry people.
But this did not change their plans, and they
continued travelling east.
They heard no more about the bread than this
notice, and nobody else did either.
That night the seventh cylinder fell in London,
on Primrose Hill.
On Wednesday my brother and the two women
reached Chelmsford, and there a number of
people, calling themselves the Council of
Public Safety, took their horse for food.
Although the three of them were hungry themselves,
they decided to walk on.
After several more hours on the road, they
suddenly saw the sea and the most amazing
crowd of ships of all types that it is possible
to imagine.
After the sailors could no longer come up
the Thames, they went to the towns on the
Essex coast to take people onto their ships.
Close to the shore was a large number of fishing-boats
from various countries, and steamboats from
the Thames.
Beyond these were the larger ships - a great
number of coal ships, ships carrying goods,
and neat white and grey passenger ships from
Southampton and Hamburg.
About three kilometres out there was a warship.
This was the Thunder Child, the only one in
sight, but far away to the right a column
of smoke marked the position of other warships.
These waited in a long line, ready for action,
right across the mouth of the Thames, watching
the Martian attack but powerless to prevent
it.
At the sight of the sea Mrs Elphmstone panicked.
She had never been out of England before;
she would rather die than be friendless in
a foreign country.
She had been growing increasingly upset and
depressed during the two days' journey.
Her great idea was to return to Stanmore.
Things had always been safe in Stanmore.
They would find George in Stanmore.
It was very difficult to get her down to the
beach, where after some time my brother caught
the attention of some men from a steamboat.
They sent a small boat and agreed on a price
of thirty-six pounds for the three passengers.
The steamboat was going, these men said, to
the Belgian port of Ostend.
It was about two o'clock when my brother got
onto it with the two women.
There was food available, although the prices
were very high, and the three of them had
a meal.
There were already around forty passengers
on the boat, some of whom had spent their
last money getting a ticket, but the captain
stayed until five in the afternoon, picking
up passengers until the boat was dangerously
crowded.
He would probably have stayed longer it the
sound or guns had not begun at about that
time in the south.
The Thunder Child, too, fired a small gun
and sent up a string of flags.
Some smoke rose as its engines started.
At the same time, far away in the south-east,
the shapes of three warships appeared, beneath
clouds of smoke.
The little steamboat was already moving out
to sea, when a Martian appeared, small and
far away, moving along the muddy coast from
the south.
The captain swore at the top of his voice
at his own delay, and the ship increased speed.
It was the first Martian that my brother had
seen, and he stood, more amazed than frightened,
as it moved steadily towards the ships, walking
further and further into the water.
Then, far away, another appeared, stepping
over some small trees, and then another could
be seen even further away, crossing the flat
mud that lay between the sea and the sky.
Looking to the north-east, my brother saw
the long line of ships already moving away
from the approaching terror.
One ship was passing behind another; many
were turning.
Steamships whistled and sent up clouds of
steam, sails were let out and small boats
rushed here and there.
He was so interested in this that he did not
look out to sea.
And then a quick movement of the steamboat
(which had turned to avoid being hit) threw
him off the seat on which he had been standing.
There was shouting all around him.
a movement of feet and a cheer that seemed
to be answered.
He got to his feet and saw to the right, less
than a hundred metres away, the warship cutting
through the water at full speed, throwing
enormous waves out on either side.
Some water came over the side of the steamboat
and blinded my brother for a moment.
When his eyes were clear again, the warship
had passed and was rushing towards the land.
He looked past it at the Martians again and
saw the three of them now close together,
and standing so far out to sea that their
legs were almost completely under water.
It seemed to him that they were surprised
by this new enemy.
To their minds, perhaps, no other machine
could be as large as themselves.
The Thunder Child fired no gun, but simply
sailed at full speed towards them.
Probably because it did not fire, it managed
to get quite close.
They did not know what it was.
If the ship had fired one shell, they would
have sent it straight to the bottom with the
Heat-Ray.
Suddenly, the nearest Martian lowered his
tube and fired a cylinder at the Thunder Child.
This hit its left side and sent up a black
cloud that the ship moved away from.
To the watchers on the steamboat, low in the
water and with the sun in their eyes, it seemed
that the warship was already among the Martians.
They saw the three thin figures separating
and rising out of the water as they moved
back towards the shore, and one of them raised
the box that fired his Heat-Ray.
He held it pointing down, and a cloud of steam
came up from the water as it hit the ship.
A flame rose up through the steam and then
the Martian began to fall over.
In another moment it had hit the sea, and
a great amount of water and steam flew high
in the air.
The guns of the Thunder Child were heard going
off one after another, and one shot hit the
water close by the steamboat.
No one worried about that very much.
As the Martian fell, the captain shouted and
all the crowded passengers at the back of
the steamer joined in.
And then he shouted again.
Because rushing out beyond the smoke and steam
came something long and black with flames
coming from it.
The warship could stilt turn and its engines
worked.
It went straight towards a second Martian,
and was within a hundred metres of it when
the Heat-Rav hit it.
There was a violent bang, a blinding flash
and the warship blew up.
The Martian was thrown back by the violence
of the explosion, and in another moment the
burning wreckage, still moving forwards, had
broken the Martian like something made of
wood.
My brother shouted.
A boiling cloud of steam hid everything again.
'Two!'
shouted the captain.
Everyone was shouting and they could hear
shouts and cheers from the other ships and
the boats.
The steam stayed in the air for many minutes,
hiding the third Martian and the coast.
All this time the steamboat was moving steadily
out to sea and away from the fight, and when
at last the steam cleared, the black cloud
got in the way and they could see nothing
of either the Thunder Child or the third Martian.
But the other warships were now quite close
and moving in towards the shore.
The little ship my brother was on continued
to move out to sea, and the warships became
smaller in the distance.
Then suddenly, out of the golden sunset, came
the sound of guns and the sight of black shadows
moving.
Everyone moved to the side of the steamboat
and looked to the west, but smoke rose and
blocked the sun.
Nothing could be seen clearly.
The ship travelled on while the passengers
wondered.
The sun sank into grey clouds, the sky darkened
and an evening star came into sight.
Then the captain cried out and pointed.
Something rushed up into the sky, something
flat and broad and very large, and flew in
a great curve.
It grew smaller, sank slowly and disappeared
again into the night.
And as it flew, it rained down darkness on
the land.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Earth Under the Martians
In the last two chapters I have moved away
from my own adventures to tell of the experiences
of my brother.
All through this time I and the curate had
been hiding in the empty house where we went
to escape the Black Smoke.
We stayed there all Sunday night and all the
next day - the day of the panic - in a little
island of daylight, cut off by the Black Smoke
from the rest of the world.
We could only wait and be bored during those
two days.
I was very worried about my wife.
I thought of her in Leatherhead, frightened,
in danger, thinking of me already as a dead
man.
I knew my cousin was brave enough for any
emergency, but he was not the sort of man
to understand danger quickly and do something
about it.
These worries stayed on my mind and I grew
very tired of the curate's constant talking.
After trying and failing to keep him quiet,
I kept away from him in other rooms in the
house.
We were surrounded by the Black Smoke all
that day and the following morning.
There were signs of people in the next house
on Sunday evening - a face at a window and
moving lights, and later the closing of a
door.
But I do not know who these people were or
what happened to them.
We saw nothing of them the next day.
The Black Smoke moved slowly towards the river
all through Monday morning, slowly getting
nearer and nearer to us, coming at last along
the road outside the house that hid us.
A Martian walked across the fields at about
midday, killing the stuff with steam.
When we looked out I saw the country covered
with black dust, but we were no longer trapped.
As soon as I saw that escape was possible,
my dream of action returned.
But the curate did not want to leave.
'We are safe here - safe here,' he repeated.
I decided to leave him.
The soldier had taught me well and I looked
for food and drink and a spare shirt to take
with me.
When it was clear to the curate that I intended
to go alone, he suddenly decided to come.
Everything was quiet through the afternoon
and we started at about five o'clock along
the blackened road to Sunbury.
Here and there along the road, and in Sunbury
itself, were dead bodies of horses as well
as men, turned-over carts and luggage, all
covered thickly with black dust.
As we passed other small towns, we found them
unaffected by either Heat-Ray or Black Smoke,
and there were some people alive, although
none could give us news.
Here too, there were signs of quick departure.
I remember a pile of three broken bicycles,
flattened by the wheels of passing carts.
We crossed Richmond Bridge at about half-past
eight.
Once again, on the Surrey side, there was
black dust that had once been smoke, and some
dead bodies - a number of them near the approach
to the station.
Then suddenly, as we walked north, we saw
some people running.
The top of a Martian fighting-machine came
into sight over the house tops, less than
a hundred metres away from us.
We stood shocked by our danger, and if the
Martian had been looking down we would have
died immediately.
We were too frightened to go on and hid in
a hut in a garden.
There the curate lay down, crying silently
and refusing to move again.
But my fixed idea of reaching Leatherhead
would not let me rest, and in the evening
I went out again.
I left the curate in the hut, but he came
hurrying after me.
That second start was the most foolish thing
I ever did.
It was obvious that the Martians were all
around us.
As soon as the curate caught up with me, we
saw either the fighting-machine we had seen
before or another one, far away across the
fields.
Four or five little black figures hurried
in front of it, and in a moment it became
obvious that this Martian was hunting them.
In three steps it was among them, and they
ran away in all directions.
It did not use its Heat-Ray, but picked them
up one by one and threw them into a large
metal box which stuck out behind it.
For the first time, I realized that perhaps
the Martians had another purpose, apart from
destroying human beings.
We stood for a moment in terror, then ran
through a gate behind us into a garden and
hid in a corner until the stars were out.
It was nearly eleven o'clock before we felt
brave enough to go out again.
We kept away from the road, moving through
gardens and some areas full of trees.
When we got to Sheen, the curate said that
he felt unwell and we decided to try one of
the houses.
The one we chose was in a walled garden, and
in the kitchen we found some food.
There were two loaves of bread, a raw steak
and some cooked meat.
Under a shelf we found some bottled beer,
and there were two bags of green beans and
some lettuce.
In a cupboard there was some tinned soup and
fish and two tins of cake.
I am listing these exactly because we lived
on this food for the next fortnight.
We sat in the kitchen in the dark and had
a meal of cold food, and just before midnight
there was a blinding flash of green light
followed by the loudest bang I have ever heard.
There was a crash of glass, the sound of falling
walls, and then the ceiling fell down in pieces
on our heads.
I was knocked across the floor and my head
hit the oven.
I lay there unconscious for a long time, the
curate told me, and when I woke up he was
wiping my face with a wet handkerchief.
For some time I could not remember what had
happened.
'Are you better?' he asked.
At last I answered him.
I sat up.
'Don't move,' he said.
'The floor is covered with broken plates.
You can't possibly move without making a noise,
and I think they are outside.'
We both sat in complete silence, so we could
hardly hear each other breathing.
Outside and very near was the noise from a
machine, which started and stopped.
'What is it?'
I asked.
'A Martian!' said the curate.
Our situation was so strange and unbelievable
that for three or four hours, until the dawn
came, we hardly moved.
And then the light came, not through the window,
which was filled with earth from the garden,
but through a small hole that had been knocked
in the wall.
Through this we saw the body of a Martian,
watching a cylinder which was still red with
heat.
When we saw that, we moved as slowly as possible
out of the grey light of the kitchen and into
the darkness of the hall.
Suddenly, the truth came to me.
'The fifth cylinder!'
I whispered.
'It's hit this house and buried us under the
ruins!'
For a time the curate was silent, then he
said, 'God help us!'
For hours we lay there in the darkness, while
from outside came the sounds of hammering
and then, after some time, a sound like an
engine.
Towards the end of the day I found that I
was very hungry.
I told the curate that I was going to look
for food, and moved back into the kitchen
again.
He did not answer, but as soon as I began
eating I heard him crawling towards me.
After eating we went back to the hall, and
I fell asleep.
When I woke up and looked around I was alone.
I crawled back into the kitchen and saw him
lying down and looking out of the hole at
the Martians.
The noises still continued.
Through the hole I could see the top of a
tree, turned to gold by the evening sun.
I stepped carefully through the broken plates
that covered the floor.
I touched the curate's leg, and he moved so
suddenly that some bricks slid down outside
with a loud crash.
I took hold of his arm, afraid that he might
cry out, and for a long time we remained still.
Then I raised my head cautiously to see what
had happened.
The falling bricks had left another hole in
the wall of the building.
Through this I was able to see into what had
been, only the previous night, a quiet road.
Things had changed greatly.
The fifth cylinder had not fallen on our house,
but on top of the house next door.
The building had completely disappeared.
The cylinder had gone right through it and
made a large hole in the ground, much larger
than the pit I had looked into in Woking.
The earth all around had been thrown up over
the neighbouring houses.
Our house had fallen backwards.
The front part of it had been destroyed completely.
By chance the kitchen had escaped and now
stood buried under earth and bricks, covered
on every side except towards the cylinder.
We now lay on the very edge of the enormous
round pit that the Martians were making.
The cylinder was already open in the centre
of the pit, and on the furthest side one of
the great fighting-machines, empty now, stood
tall and unmoving against the evening sky.
However, at first I hardly noticed the pit
and the cylinder, because of the strange shining
machine that I saw working there, and the
odd creatures that were crawling slowly and
painfully across the earth near it.
This machine was shaped like a spider with
five legs and a great number of tentacles.
With these it was taking pieces of metal out
of the cylinder and laying them on the earth
behind it.
It was doing this so quickly and perfectly
that I did not see it as a machine at first.
The fighting-machines were extraordinary,
but could not compare to this building-machine.
People who have never seen these things can
hardly understand how alive they looked.
I had seen the Martians themselves once before,
but only for a short time, and then the sight
had almost made me sick.
Now I was more used to them, and was in a
good position with a lot of time to study
them properly.
They were the strangest creatures it is possible
to imagine.
They had large, round bodies - or perhaps
heads - about a metre and a half across.
Each body had a face in front of it.
This face had no nose - I do not think they
had any sense of smell - but it had a pair
of very large, dark eyes, and just beneath
these a kind of v-shaped mouth.
In the back of the head, or body - I do not
really know what to call it - there was a
flat surface like the skin of a drum, which
we now know worked as an ear.
Around the mouth were sixteen thin, whip-like
tentacles, arranged in two groups of eight.
These worked like hands.
As I watched the Martians, they seemed to
be trying to raise themselves on the hands,
but with their increased weight on Earth this
was impossible.
It may be that on Mars they moved around on
them quite easily.
Most of the space inside their bodies was
taken by the brain.
Besides this they had a heart, but they had
no stomach because they did not eat.
Instead, they took fresh blood from living
creatures and used a tube to put it straight
into their own bodies.
This idea seems horrible to us, but at the
same time I think we should remember how disgusting
our meat-eating habits would seem to an intelligent
rabbit.
In three other ways their bodies were different
from ours.
They did not sleep, and because they had very
simple bodies they never seemed to get tired.
On Earth they could not move without effort,
but even at the end of their time here they
remained active.
In twenty-four hours they did twenty-four
hours of work.
Also, strange as it may seem, the Martians
were absolutely without sex.
A young Martian, we now know, was born on
Earth during the war, and it was found growing
out of the body of its parent, just like some
young plants.
A final difference seems very unimportant.
Germs, which cause so much disease and pain
on Earth, have either never appeared on Mars
or they got rid of them a long time ago.
It is generally supposed that the Martians
communicated by sounds and by moving their
arms.
But no human being saw as much of them as
I did and lived to tell the story, and I can
say that I have seen four, five or six of
them slowly performing the most difficult
work without sound or any other signal.
I know a little of psychology and I am absolutely
certain that they exchanged thoughts.
While I was still watching their slow movements
in the sunlight, the curate pulled violently
at my arm.
I turned and saw an unhappy face and silent,
moving lips.
He wanted to see what was happening.
The hole was only big enough for one of us
to look through, so I had to stop watching
them for a time while he had his chance.
When I looked again, the busy building-machine
had already put together several of the pieces
of metal from inside the cylinder into a shape
that was very like its own.
Down on the left a busy little digging-machine
could be seen, sending out small clouds of
green smoke and working its way round the
pit, making it bigger and piling the earth
up over the top.
This was what had caused the regular heating
noise.
It whistled as it worked, and no Martian seemed
to be controlling it.
CHAPTER TWELVE
In the Ruined House
The arrival of a second fighting-machine made
us move back out of the kitchen into the hall,
because we were afraid that from that height
the Martian might see us through the hole.
At a later date we began to feel less in danger
of being seen because the sunlight outside
was very bright, but at first anything approaching
the house drove us back into the hall in fear.
However, despite the danger, we could not
prevent ourselves from going back to look
again and again.
In our desire to watch, we even fought each
other within a few centimeters of being seen.
We were very different people with different
habits of thought and action, and those differences
increased because we were living together
in this dangerous place.
The curate talked endlessly, and this prevented
me from forming a plan of action.
He had no self-control at all and sometimes
cried for hours at a time.
He ate more than I did, and did not seem to
understand that we had to stay in the house
until the Martians had finished their work
if we wanted to stay alive.
I tried threatening him, and in the end I
hit him.
That worked for some time.
The curate was watching through the hole when
the first men were brought there.
I was sitting near him, listening hard.
He made a sudden movement backwards and for
a moment I shared his panic.
Then curiosity gave me courage and I got up,
stepped across him and went to the hole.
At first I could see no reason for his behaviour.
The night was coming but the Martians had
lights on their machines.
The whole scene was one of moving lights and
shadows, difficult for the eyes.
The Martians at the bottom of the pit could
no longer be seen, because the earth around
it was now so high.
A fighting- machine stood in the corner of
the pit.
Then, through the noise of the machinery,
came the faint sound of human voices.
I watched the fighting-machine closely, sure
for the first time that it did actually contain
a Martian.
I could see the oily shine of its skin and
the brightness of its eyes.
And suddenly I heard a shout and saw a long
tentacle reaching over the shoulder of the
machine to the little cage on its back.
Then something - something struggling violently
- was lifted high against the sky and brought
down again.
I saw that it was a man.
He was fat, red- faced, middle-aged, well-dressed;
perhaps earlier he had been important.
He disappeared behind the pile of earth and
for a moment there was silence.
Then we heard him scream and the sound of
long and cheerful calling from the Martians.
I moved away from the hole, put my hands over
my ears and ran into the hall.
The curate, who had been lying silently with
his arms over his head, looked up as I passed,
cried out quite loudly and came running after
me.
That night, as we hid in the hall, I felt
a great need to do something but could think
of no plan of escape.
But afterwards, during the second day, I was
able to consider our position clearly.
The curate, I found, was quite unable to discuss
anything.
The death of the man outside had taken away
all his powers of thought.
He had almost sunk to the level of an animal.
I began to think that, although our position
was terrible, there was no reason yet to give
up hope.
The Martians might only stay in this pit for
a short time, then move on.
Or if they stayed permanently, they might
not think it necessary to watch it all the
time.
On the third day, if I remember correctly,
I saw a boy killed.
It was the only occasion on which I actually
saw the Martians feed.
After that I avoided the hole in the wall
for most of a day.
The Martians had made such an impression on
me that at first I did not think I could escape.
I did not think that they could be defeated
by human beings.
But on the fourth or fifth night I heard a
sound like heavy guns.
It was very late and the moon was shining
brightly.
The Martians had taken away the digging-machine
and apart from the fighting-machine on the
far side of the pit and a building- machine
that was busy out of my sight, the pit was
empty.
I heard a dog, and that familiar sound made
me listen.
Then I heard a noise exactly like the sound
of big guns.
I heard six bangs and then six more.
And that was all.
On the sixth day of our imprisonment I looked
out for the last time, and I soon found myself
alone.
Instead of staying close and trying to move
me away from the pit, the curate had gone
back into the hall.
I followed him quickly and quietly and in
the darkness I heard him drinking.
I put my hand out and my fingers closed around
a bottle of wine.
For a few minutes we fought together.
The bottle hit the floor and broke, and I
stopped fighting and got up.
We stood breathing heavily, staring at each
other.
In the end I moved between him and the food
and told him that I was going to take control.
I divided the food in the cupboard into separate
amounts to last us ten days.
I would not let him eat any more that day.
In the afternoon he tried to get some food.
I had been asleep but in a moment I was awake.
All day and all night we sat face to face.
I was tired but would not give up, and he
cried and complained about his immediate hunger.
The rest of the time he just talked to himself,
and I began to realize that he had gone completely
mad.
Through the eighth and ninth days his voice
grew louder.
He threatened me, begged me, and this was
mixed with a great deal of talk about his
service to God.
Then he slept for some time and began again
with even more strength, so loudly that I
had to try to stop him.
'Be still!'
I demanded.
He rose to his knees.
'I have been still too long,' he said, loud
enough for the Martians to hear, 'and now
I must tell the world.
This place will be destroyed because of the
bad things we have done!'
'Shut up!'
I said, getting to my feet.
'Please -'
'No!' he shouted, at the top of his voice.
'Speak!
The word of God is with me!'
In three steps he was at the door leading
to the kitchen.
I went after him, picking up the coal-hammer
as I entered the room.
Before he was half-way across the floor, I
was right behind him.
I swung the hammer and hit him on the back
of the head.
He fell forwards and lay flat on the floor.
I stepped over him and stood there breathing
hard.
He did not move.
Suddenly, I heard a noise outside and the
hole in the wall became dark.
I looked up and saw the lower part of a building-
machine coming slowly across it.
Then, through a sort of glass plate, I saw
the large, dark eyes of a Martian, and one
of its tentacles appeared, moving in through
the hole.
I turned, tripped over the curate and stopped
at the hall door.
The tentacle was now two metres or more into
the room, moving backwards and forwards with
strange, sudden movements.
I forced myself back into the hall.
I shook violently and could hardly stand straight.
Had the Martian seen me?
What was it doing now?
Then I heard the sound of a heavy body - I
knew whose it was - being dragged across the
floor of the kitchen towards the opening.
I could not stop myself - I moved to the door
and looked back into the kitchen.
In the light from outside, I saw the Martian
studying the curate's head.
I thought at once that it would know that
I was there from the mark of the hammer.
I shut the door and moved back into the hall
and tried to hide myself in the corner.
Then I heard a faint metallic sound as the
tentacle moved back across the kitchen floor.
I thought that it might not be long enough
to reach me.
I prayed.
Then I heard it touching the handle.
It had found the door.
The Martians understood doors!
It moved the handle up and down for a moment,
and then the door opened.
In the darkness I could just see the thing
moving towards me and examining the wall and
the floor.
It was like a black snake moving its head
from side to side.
Once, even, it touched my boot.
I almost screamed, but I bit my hand.
For a time it did not move, then it moved
back through the door.
I heard it go into the food cupboard, It moved
the tins and a bottle broke.
Then there was silence.
Had it gone?
At last I decided that it had.
The tentacle did not come into the hall again,
but I lay all the tenth day in the darkness,
too frightened even to move for a drink.
I did not enter the kitchen again for two
days.
When at last I did, I found that the food
cupboard was now empty.
The Martians had taken everything.
On that day and the next I had no food and
nothing to drink.
On the twelfth day my thirst was so bad that
I went into the kitchen and used the noisy
rainwater pump that stood by the sink.
I managed to get a couple of glasses of dirty
water.
This made me feel a lot better, and the noise
of the pump did not bring a tentacle in through
the opening.
On the thirteenth day I drank some more water,
and thought of impossible plans of escape.
Whenever I slept, I dreamed either of the
death of the curate or of wonderful dinners.
Then, early on the fifteenth day, I heard
the sound of a dog outside.
This greatly surprised me.
I went into the kitchen and saw its head looking
in through the hole.
I thought that if I could attract it in quietly,
I would be able, perhaps, to kill and eat
it.
It would be a good idea to kill it anyway,
in case its actions attracted the attention
of the Martians.
I moved forwards, saying, 'Good dog!'
very softly, but it suddenly pulled his head
back and disappeared.
I listened.
I heard the sound of some birds but that was
all.
For a long time I lay close to the opening
until, encouraged by the silence, I looked
out.
Except in the corner, where a number of birds
fought over some dead bodies, there was not
a living thing in the pit.
I stared around, hardly believing my eyes.
All the machinery had gone.
Slowly I made the opening larger and pushed
myself through it.
I could see in every direction except behind
me and there were no Martians in sight.
I hesitated, then with a rush of desperate
courage, and with my heart beating violently,
I climbed to the top of the pile of earth
in which I had been buried.
When I had last seen this part of Sheen, it
had been a street of comfortable white and
red houses.
Now the neighboring ones had all been destroyed.
Far away I saw a thin cat walking along a
wall, but there was no sign of people.
After my time in the darkness, the day seemed
very bright, the sky was shining blue.
A gentle wind moved the flowers.
And oh!
The sweetness of the air.
For some time I stood there, not worrying
about my safety.
At that moment, I felt the beginning of something
that soon grew quite clear in my mind, that
worried me for many days.
I was not the master now, but an animal among
the animals, under the power of the Martians.
The rule of man had ended.
But as soon as this feeling came, it left
me, and my main problem became hunger.
I climbed a wall and fell into a neighboring
garden.
Here I found some young vegetables, which
I took.
Then I started walking towards the river.
There were two ideas in my mind - to get more
food and to move, as quickly as possible,
away from the pit.
When I reached the Thames, I drank as much
water as I could.
I then walked up a hill to Putney Common.
Here I moved through areas which had been
totally destroyed and others which were totally
undamaged; houses with their curtains and
their doors closed.
I went into a couple of the houses, looking
for food, but all of it had already been taken.
I lay for the rest of the day in a garden,
too exhausted to go on.
All this time I saw no human beings and no
signs of the Martians.
I saw a couple of hungry-looking dogs, but
they hurried away from me.
I also saw some human bones, with all the
flesh eaten off.
After sunset I struggled on along the road
towards Putney, and in a garden I found some
potatoes, enough to stop my hunger.
From there I looked down on Putney and the
river.
The view of blackened trees and empty ruined
buildings made me very unhappy.
And over all - silence.
It filled me with terror to think how quickly
that great change had come.
Near the top of Putney Hill I came across
more human bones, eaten clean and left lying
around.
The Martians, it seemed, had killed and eaten
everyone around there, except for a few lucky
ones like myself.
They were now looking for food somewhere else.
Perhaps even now they were destroying Berlin
or Paris, or maybe they were moving north.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The Man on Putney Hill
I spent that night in the pub that stands
on the top of Putney Hill, sleeping in a made
bed for the first time since I had run away
to Leatherhead.
I broke into the house - and afterwards found
that the front door was unlocked.
I searched every room for food until, when
I was ready to give up, I found some bread
and two tins of fruit in one of the bedrooms.
The place had already been searched and emptied.
Later, in the bar, I found some sandwiches
that no one had noticed.
I ate some of these and put the rest in my
pockets.
I lit no lamps, afraid that a Martian might
come through that part of London looking for
food in the night.
Before I went to bed I was very restless and
went from window to window, looking out for
some sign of them.
I slept little.
As I lay in bed, I found myself thinking of
the killing of the curate.
I had no regrets about this, but in the stillness
of the night, with a sense that God was near,
I thought again of every part of our conversation
from the time we had first met.
We had been unable to co-operate.
If I had known, I would have left him at Walton,
but I had not been able to see ahead.
Nobody saw me kill him, but I have described
it here and the reader can make a judgement.
The morning was bright and fine and there
were little golden clouds in the eastern sky.
In the road that runs from the top of Putney
Hill to Wimbledon many things had been left
behind by the crowds that ran towards London
on the Sunday night after the fighting began.
There was a little two-wheeled cart with a
broken wheel.
It had the name of a shop written on it.
There was a hat lying in the mud, and a lot
of broken glass with blood on it.
I moved slowly because I was very tired and
my plans were uncertain.
I had an idea of going to Leatherhead, although
I knew there was little chance of finding
my wife there.
Certainly, unless they had been killed, she
and my cousins would have run away.
I came to the edge of Wimbledon Common and
stood there, under cover of some trees and
bushes.
It stretched far and wide and I hesitated
on the edge of that large open space.
Soon I had an odd feeling of being watched
and, turning suddenly, I saw something hiding
in some of the bushes.
I took a step towards it, and it rose up and
became a man armed with a sword.
I approached him slowly.
He stood silently, watching me but not moving.
As I came nearer, I saw that he was dressed
in clothes as dusty and dirty as my own.
His black hair fell over his eyes, and his
face was dark and dirty and thin, so at first
I did not recognize him.
'Stop!' he cried, when I was within ten metres
of him, and I stopped.
'Where have you come from?' he said.
I thought, watching him.
'I have come from Sheen,' I said.
'I was buried near the pit the Martians made
around their cylinder.
I have escaped.'
'There is no food around here,' he said.
'This is my country: all this hill down to
the river and up to the edge of the common.
There is only food for one.
Which way are you going?'
'I don't know,' I said.
He looked at me uncertainly, then his expression
suddenly changed.
He pointed at me.
'It's you,' he said,'- the man from Woking.
And you weren't killed at Weybridge?'
I recognized him at the same moment.
'You're the soldier who came into my garden.'
'What luck!' he said.
'We are lucky ones!'
He put out a hand and I took it.
'I hid,' he said.
'But they didn't kill everyone.
And after they went away, I went towards Walton
across the fields.
But - it's only been sixteen days and your
hair is grey.'
He looked over his shoulder suddenly.
'Only a bird,' he said.
'This is a bit open.
Let's crawl under those bushes and talk.'
'Have you seen any Martians?'
I asked.
'Since I got out-'
'They've gone away across London,' he said.
'I guess they've got a bigger camp there.
The night before last I saw some lights up
in the air.
I believe they've built a flying-machine and
are learning to fly'
I stopped, on hands and knees, because we
had come to the bushes.
'Fly!'
'Yes,' he said, 'fly!'
I crawled into an open space in the bushes
and sat down.
'If they manage to do that, we haven't got
a chance,' I said.
'They will simply go round the world.'
'They will.
But it will make things easier around here.
And besides ...' he looked at me.
'Don't you believe that we're beaten?
I do.'
I stared.
Strange as it may seem, I had not thought
of things this way, although it was perfectly
obvious.
I had still held onto some hope.
'It's finished,' he said.
'They've lost one - just one.
And they've taken over the capital of the
most powerful country in the world.
The death of that one at Weybridge was an
accident.
And these are only the first ones.
They keep coming.
These green stars - I've seen none for five
or six days, but I've no doubt they're falling
somewhere every night.
There's nothing we can do.
We're beaten!'
I did not answer.
I sat staring in front of me, trying without
success to find a way of arguing against him.
Suddenly, I remembered the night I had watched
through the telescope.
'After the tenth shot they fired no more - at
least until the first cylinder came.'
'How do you know?' said the soldier.
I explained.
'Something wrong with the gun?' he said.
'But even if there is, they'll get it right
again.'
We sat looking at each other.
'And what will they do with us?'
I said.
'That's what I've been thinking.' he said.
'It seems to me that at the moment they catch
us when they want food.
But they won't keep doing that.
As soon as they've destroyed all our guns
and ships and railways, they'll begin to catch
us one by one, picking the best and keeping
us in cages and things.
They haven't begun on us yet.
Don't you see that?'
'Not begun!'
I cried.
'Not begun.
And instead of rushing around blindly, we've
got to change to suit the new situation.
That's how I see it.'
'But if that's true,' I said, 'what is there
to live for?'
'There won't be anything important for a million
years or more - no music, no art and no nice
little visits to restaurants.
No entertainment.
But men like me are going to go on living
- so human beings can continue.
And if I'm not mistaken, you'll show how strong
you are too.
We aren't going to be killed.
And I don't intend to be caught, either, and
caged and fattened.
Ugh!'
'You don't mean -'
'I do.
I'm going on.
Under their feet.
I've thought about it.
We've got to learn while we've got a chance.
And we've got to live and stay independent
while we learn.
That's what has to be done.'
I stared, surprised and greatly affected by
the man's courage.
'Good God!'
I said.
'You are a brave man.'
And suddenly I held his hand.
'Go on,' I said.
'Well, people who intend to escape them must
get ready.
I'm getting ready.
But not all of us can live like animals, and
that's how we'll have to live.
That's why I watched you.
I had my doubts.
You're thinner.
I didn't know that it was you, you see.
All these - the sort of people that lived
in these houses, all those little office workers
that used to live down that way - they'd be
no good.
They haven't any spirit in them - no proud
dreams and no great ideas.
They just used to rush off to work - I've
seen hundreds of them, with a bit of breakfast
in their hand, running to catch their train,
frightened they'd be sacked if they didn't.
Well, the Martians will be a good thing for
them.
Nice big cages, fattening food, no worry.
After a week or two running around the fields
on empty stomachs they'll come and be caught
quite happily.'
He paused.
'The Martians will probably make pets of some
of them; train them to do tricks - who knows?
And some, maybe, they will train to hunt us.'
'No,' I cried, 'that's impossible!
No human being -'
'What's the good of going on with such lies?'
said the soldier.
'There are men who would do it cheerfully.
What nonsense to pretend there aren't!'
And I realized that I agreed with him.
I sat and thought about these things.
It was interesting that he, an ordinary soldier,
seemed to have a much better understanding
of the situation than I, a professional writer.
'What plans do you have?'
I said.
He hesitated.
'Well, we have to invent a life where people
can live and have children, and be safe enough
to bring the children up.
Yes - wait a bit, and I'll make it clearer
what I think ought to be done.
The ones the Martians capture will be like
farm animals; in a few years they'll be big,
beautiful, stupid - rubbish.
But we who stay free risk turning into wild
animals.
'You see, I intend to live underground.
I've been thinking about the drains.
Under London there are hundreds of kilometres
of them.
And we can dig passages between the drains
and buildings.
And then there are the railways, where they
go underground.
You begin to see?
And we'll get some people together - strong,
clean-minded men.
We're not going to accept any rubbish that
comes in.
Weak ones go out again.'
'As you intended me to go?'
'Well - I discussed it, didn't I?
'We won't argue about that.
Go on.'
'The people who stay will obey orders.
We want strong, good women too - mothers and
teachers.
No lazy ones with rolling eyes.
We can't have any weak or silly ones.
Life is real again, and the useless and bad
ones have to die.
They ought to die.
They ought to be willing to die.
It would be wrong of them to live and weaken
the others.
'But it's no good just staying alive.
That's just living like rats.
We have to save our knowledge, and add to
it.
That's why men like you are needed.
We must make great safe places deep underground,
and get all the books we can; not novels and
poetry, but ideas, science books.
We must go to the British Museum and choose
the best books in it.
Especially, we must keep our science - learn
more.'
The soldier paused and laid a brown hand on
my arm.
'In fact, it may not be so difficult to learn
how their fighting- machines work.
Think of four or five of them with men inside,
firing Heat-Rays back at the Martians!'
For some time the imagination of the soldier,
and the confidence and courage he showed,
persuaded me completely.
I believed in his idea of the future and in
the possibility of his plans.
We talked like this through the early morning,
and later came out of the bushes.
After checking the sky for Martians, we hurried
quickly to the house on Putney Hill where
he had his hiding-place.
There I saw the work he had spent a week on.
It was a passage about ten metres long, designed
to reach the main drain on Putney Hill.
For the first time I began to think that there
was some distance between his dreams and his
powers, because I could dig a hole like this
in a day.
But I believed in him enough to work with
him all that morning at his digging.
As we worked I thought about the job, and
soon some doubts began to come into my mind.
I thought about the distance to the drain
and the chances of missing it completely.
I also felt that it would be easier to get
into the drain and dig back towards the house.
And just as I was beginning to face these
things, the soldier stopped digging and looked
at me.
'We're working well,' he said.
'Let's stop.
I think it's time we looked around from the
top of the house.'
I wanted to continue, but a thought came to
me.
'Why were you walking around on the common,'
I asked, 'instead of being here?'
'Taking the air,' he said.
'It's safer by night.'
'But the work?'
'Oh, one can't always work,' he said, and
in a flash I understood the man clearly.
We went together to the roof and stood on
a ladder, looking out of the roof door.
No Martians could be seen.
We went back down into the house.
Neither of us wanted to start digging again,
and when he suggested a meal I was quite happy
to agree.
Afterwards we drank wine and played cards.
He won most of the games, and when we did
not want to play any more I went back up on
the roof.
I stayed there for a long time, looking north
over the city.
I began to feel that I had failed my wife,
and decided to leave this dreamer of great
things and to go on into London.
There, it seemed to me, I had the best chance
of learning what the Martians and human beings
were doing for death
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Dead London
After I had said goodbye to the soldier, I
went down the hill, along the High Street
and across the bridge to Fulham.
There was black dust on the road after the
bridge, and it grew thicker in Fulham.
The streets were horribly quiet.
I found some old bread in a baker's shop there.
After that, the streets became clear of powder
and I passed some white houses which were
on fire.
The noise of burning was actually better than
silence.
Beyond Fulham the streets were quiet again.
Here I found more black powder and some dead
bodies.
I saw about ten along Fulham Road.
They had been dead for many days, so I hurried
quickly past them.
The black powder covered them and softened
their shapes.
One or two had been partly eaten by dogs.
Where there was no black powder, it was curiously
like Sunday in the financial area of London,
with the closed shops, the houses locked up
and the curtains closed.
In some places thieves had been at work, but
usually only at the food and wine shops.
A jeweller's window had been broken open in
one place, but the thief had clearly been
chased away, because a number of gold chains
and a watch were lying on the pavement.
I did not take the trouble to touch them.
Further down the road, a woman in torn clothes
was sitting on a doorstep.
The hand that hung over her knee was cut,
and blood had fallen onto her dirty brown
dress.
A broken bottle of wine had formed a pool
on the pavement.
She seemed asleep, but she was dead.
The silence grew greater.
But it was not the stillness of death - it
was the stillness of expectation.
At any time the destruction that had already
happened to the north-western borders of the
city, that had destroyed Ealing, might strike
among these houses and leave them smoking
ruins.
It was an empty city waiting for death...
In South Kensington the streets were clear
of dead people and of black powder, and near
there I first heard the howling.
It started very quietly.
It was a sad movement between two notes, 'Ulla,
ulla, ulla, ulla,' continuing without stopping.
When I passed streets that ran to the north
it grew louder, and then houses and buildings
seemed to cut it off again.
It came most loudly down Exhibition Road.
I stopped, staring towards Kensington Gardens.
It seemed that all the empty houses had found
a voice for their fear and loneliness.
'Ulla, ulla, ulla,' cried that inhuman note
- great waves of sound sweeping down the broad,
sunlit road, between the tall buildings on
each side.
I turned to the north, towards the iron gates
of Hyde Park.
The voice grew stronger and stronger, although
I could see nothing above the roof-tops on
the north side of the park except some smoke
to the north-west.
'Ulla, ulla, ulla,' cried the voice, coming,
it seemed to me, from the district around
Regent's Park.
The howl affected my mind, and my mood changed.
I also found that I was very tired, and hungry
and thirsty again.
It was already past midday.
Why was I walking alone in this city of the
dead?
I thought of old friends that I had forgotten
for years.
I thought of the poisons in the chemists'
shops, the bottles in the wine shops...
I came into Oxford Street by Marble Arch,
and here again were black powder and several
bodies.
After a lot of trouble, I managed to break
into a pub and find some food and drink.
I was tired after eating and went into the
room behind the bar and slept on a black leather
sofa that I found there.
I awoke to find that sad howling still in
my ears: 'Ulla, ulla, ulla, ulla, ulla,' It
was now getting dark, and after I had found
some bread and cheese in the bar I walked
on through the silent squares to Baker Street
and so came at last to Regents Park.
And as I came out of the top of Baker Street,
I saw far away over the trees, in the clearness
of the sunset, the top of the Martian fighting-machine
from winch this howling came.
I was not frightened.
I watched it for some time, but it did not
move.
It appeared to be standing and calling, for
no reason that I could discover.
I tried to work out a plan of action.
That non-stop sound of 'Ulla, ulla, ulla,
ulla' confused my mind.
Perhaps I was too tired to be very afraid.
Certainly I was more curious to know the reason
for this howling.
I turned and went into Park Road, intending
to go round the edge of the park, with houses
between us to keep me safe, and get a view
of this unmoving, howling Martian from the
direction of St John's Wood.
I came to a destroyed building-machine halfway
to St John's Wood station.
At first I thought a house had fallen across
the road, but when I climbed up on the ruins
I saw, with a shock, this great machine lying,
with its tentacles bent and twisted, among
the ruins that it had made.
The front part of it was pushed in.
It seemed that it had been driven blindly
straight at the house, and had been turned
over when the house fell on it.
Wondering about all that I had seen, I moved
on towards Primrose Hill.
Far away, through a space in the trees, I
saw a second Martian fighting-machine, as
unmoving as the first, standing in the park
near the Zoo.
Then the sound of 'Ulla, ulla, ulla, ulla'
stopped.
The silence came suddenly.
And now night, the mother of fear and mystery,
was coming.
London around me looked like a city of ghosts.
My imagination heard a thousand noiseless
enemies moving.
Terror came to me.
In front of me the road became black and I
saw the twisted shape of a body lying across
the pavement.
I could not go on.
I turned down St John's Wood Road and ran
away from this terrible stillness.
I hid from the night and the silence until
long after midnight, in a garden hut in Harrow
Road.
But before dawn my courage returned, and while
the stars were still in the sky I turned again
towards Regent's Park.
I lost my way among the streets, and soon
saw down a long road, in the half-light of
the early dawn, the curve of Primrose Hill.
There, on the top, high against the early
morning stars, was a third Martian, standing
still like the others.
A mad idea came to me.
I would die and end it.
And I would save myself even the trouble of
killing myself.
I marched on without fear towards this great
machine, and then, as I came nearer and the
light grew, I saw that a number of black birds
were circling and gathering around the top
of it.
I began to feel very happy and I started running
along the road.
I got onto the grass before the sun rose.
Great piles of earth had formed around a pit
at the top of the hill - the final and largest
one the Martians had made - and from behind
these piles thin smoke rose against the sky.
Against the sky-line an eager dog ran and
disappeared.
The thought that had flashed into my mind
grew real, and believable.
I felt no fear, only a wild, shaking excitement,
as I ran up the hill towards the unmoving
Martian.
Out of the top of it hung long, brown pieces
of flesh, which the birds were tearing away.
In another moment I had climbed a pile of
earth and stood on its top, and the pit was
below me.
It was a large space, with enormous machines
here and there within it, great piles of material
and strange buildings.
And all around it, some in their overturned
war-machines and some in building-machines,
and ten of them lying in a row, were the Martians
- dead!
They had been killed by germs against which
their systems could not fight; killed, after
all man's machines had failed, by the smallest
things that God has put on this Earth.
It had happened in this way, and I and many
others did not see that it would happen because
terror and disaster had blinded our minds.
These germs of disease have killed people
and animals since the beginning of time, but
over these many years we have developed the
ability to fight against them.
But there are no germs on Mars, and as soon
as the Martians arrived, as soon as they drank
and fed, our tiny friends began to destroy
them.
By paying with a million lives, human beings
have bought their right to live on Earth.
It is our home and would be ours even if the
Martians were ten times as strong as they
are.
I stood staring into the pit, and my heart
grew wonderfully happy as the rising sun lit
up the world around me.
The pit was still in darkness.
Only the tops of the great engines, so unearthly
in their shape, could be seen in the morning
light.
I heard a large number of dogs fighting over
the bodies that lay in the darkness at the
bottom of the pit.
Across the pit, on its further edge, lay the
great flying-machine which they had been testing
in our heavier atmosphere when disease and
death stopped them.
Death had not come a day too soon.
At the sound of birds overhead I looked up
at the enormous fighting-machine that would
never fight again, at the pieces of red flesh
that dropped down onto the overturned seats
on the top of Primrose Hill.
I turned and looked down the slope of the
hill at those two other Martians that I had
seen the previous night.
They were surrounded by birds now.
One of them had died as it had been crying
to its friends.
Perhaps it was the last to die, and its voice
had gone on and on until its machinery stopped.
They stood now, harmless tripods of shining
metal, against the brightness of the rising
sun.
All around the pit, and saved from everlasting
destruction, lay the great city.
And as I looked at it, and realized that the
shadows had been rolled back, and that people
might still live in its streets, and that
this dear city of mine might be once more
alive and powerful again, I felt such emotion
that I was very close to tears.
The trouble had ended.
That same day the healing would begin.
People who were still alive would start to
return, and life would come back to the empty
streets.
The sound of tools would soon be heard in
all the burnt and broken houses.
At the thought, I lifted my hands towards
the sky and began thanking God.
In a year, I thought, we would rebuild all
that had been destroyed.
Then came the thought of myself, of my wife,
and the old life of hope and tender helpfulness
that had ended forever.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Wreckage
And now comes the strangest thing in my story.
But perhaps it is not totally strange.
I remember, clearly and in great detail, all
that I did that day until the time when I
stood crying on the top of Primrose Hill.
And then I forget.
I know nothing of the next three days.
I have learned since then that I was not the
first discoverer of the Martian defeat -several
wanderers like me had already known about
it on the previous night.
One man - the first - had even managed to
send a telegram to Paris.
From there the happy news had flashed all
over the world; a thousand cities, living
in great fear, suddenly- turned on all their
lights.
They knew of it in Dublin, Edinburgh, Manchester
and Birmingham at the time when I stood on
the edge of the pit.
Already men, crying with joy, as I have heard,
were getting onto trains to go to London.
Men on bicycles rode through the countryside
shouting the news to all.
And the food!
Across the Channel, across the Irish Sea,
across the Atlantic, corn, bread and meat
were coming to us.
All the ships in the world seemed to be coming
to London in those days.
But I have no memory of all of this.
For three days I walked aimlessly, a madman.
Then I found myself in a house of kind people,
who had found me.
They have told me since that I was singing
a crazy song about 'The Last Man Left Alive!
The Last Man Left Alive!'
Although they were troubled with their own
affairs, these people were very helpful to
me.
They gave me a place to stay and protected
me from myself.
Very gently, when my mind was working again,
they told me all they knew about what had
happened in Leatherhead.
Two days after I was imprisoned it had been
destroyed, with every person in it, by a Martian.
He had swept it all away for no reason at
all, it seemed.
I was a lonely man, and they were very kind
to me.
I was a sad one too, and they were patient
with me.
I stayed with them for four days after my
recovery.
All that time I felt a growing need to look
again at whatever remained of the little life
that had seemed so happy and bright in my
past.
My hosts tried to change my mind but at last,
promising faithfully to return to them, I
went out again into the streets that had lately
been so dark and strange and empty.
Already they were busy with returning people;
in places there were even shops open.
I remember how bright that day seemed as I
went sadly back to the little house in Woking
- how busy the streets were, and how full
of life.
But then I noticed how ill the people looked
and how many of them still wore old and dirty
clothes.
The churches were giving out bread sent to
us by the French government, and tired-looking
policemen stood at the corners of every street.
At the end of Waterloo Bridge I bought a copy
of the first newspaper to reappear.
I learned nothing new except that already
in one week the examination of the Martians'
machines had produced amazing results.
Among other things, the newspaper said that
the 'Secret of Flying' had been discovered.
I did not believe this at the time.
At Waterloo I found that free trains were
taking people to their homes.
The first rush had already ended and there
were few people on the train.
The city we went through was dirty with the
powder of the Black Smoke, despite two days
of thunderstorms and rain.
All down the line from there, the country
looked empty and unfamiliar.
Wimbledon particularly had suffered, and beyond
there I saw piles of earth around the sixth
cylinder.
A number of people were standing by it, and
some soldiers were busy in the middle.
Over it was a British flag, flying cheerfully
in the wind.
The line on the London side of Woking station
was still being repaired, so I got off the
train at Byfleet and took the road to Maybury,
past the place where I had seen the Martian
fighting- machine in the thunderstorm.
I was curious and I stopped to find the twisted
and broken dog-cart with the whitened bones
of the horse.
For a time I stood and looked at the remains...
Then I returned through the wood towards my
home.
A man standing at the open door of a house
greeted me by name as I passed.
I looked at my own house with a quick flash
of hope that died immediately.
The door had been broken, and it was opening
slowly as I approached.
It blew shut again.
The curtains of my study blew out of the open
window from which I and the soldier had watched
the dawn.
No one had closed it since then.
I went into the hall, and the house felt empty.
The stair carpet was discolored where I had
sat, wet to the skin from the thunderstorm
on that first terrible night.
Our muddy footsteps still went up the stairs.
I followed them to my study and found, lying
on my writing- table, the page of work I had
left on the afternoon of the opening of the
cylinder.
For some time I stood reading it.
I remembered how I could not concentrate that
morning, hardly a month before, and how I
had stopped work to get my newspaper from
the newsboy.
I remembered how I went to the garden gate
as he came past, and how I had listened to
his odd story of 'Men from Mars'.
I came down and went into the dining-room.
There were the remains of the meat and the
bread, now gone bad, where the soldier and
I had left them.
My home was a lonely place.
I realized the stupidity of the small hope
I had held on to for so long.
And then a strange thing happened.
'The house is deserted,' said a voice.
'No one has been here for ten days.
Don't stay here and make yourself unhappy.
No one escaped except you.'
I was shocked.
Had I spoken my thought aloud?
I turned, and the door to the garden was open
behind me.
I took a step towards it and stood looking
out.
And there, amazed and afraid, as I too stood
amazed and afraid, were my cousin and my wife
- my wife white and tearless.
She gave a faint cry.
'I came here,' she said.
'I knew-knew -' She put her hand to her throat
and started to fall.
I stepped forwards and caught her in my arms.
I can only regret now, as I finish my story,
how little I can help with the many questions
which are still unanswered.
In one area I shall certainly be criticized.
I know very little about medical matters,
but it seems to me most likely that the Martians
were killed by germs.
Certainly, in all the bodies of the Martians
that were examined after the war, no germs
were found except ones that came from Earth.
Besides this, we still know very little about
the Black Smoke, and the way that the Heat-Ray
worked remains a puzzle.
A question of more serious interest is the
possibility of another attack from the Martians.
I do not think that nearly enough attention
is being paid to this.
Every time the planet Mars comes near to us,
I worry that they might try again.
We should be prepared.
It should be possible to find the position
of the gun from which the shots came, to watch
this part of the planet carefully and be ready.
In that case, the cylinder could be destroyed
before it was cool enough for the Martians
to come out, or they could be killed by guns
as soon as the door opened.
It seems to me that they have lost a great
advantage in the failure of their first surprise.
Possibly they also believe this.
One astronomer has given excellent reasons
for supposing that the Martians have actually
landed on Venus.
Seven months ago, when these planets were
close together, faint, dark marks appeared
on photographs which suggested that a cylinder
had been fired from one to the other.
However, whether we expect another attack
or not, our views of the human future must
now be changed by these events.
We have learned that we cannot think of this
planet as a safe home for humans.
We can never know what unseen good or evil
might come to us suddenly out of space.
Perhaps this attack from Mars will be helpful
to us in the end.
It has taken away our confidence in the future,
which was making us soft; it has given great
help to science, and it has made us think
of human beings as one family.
Perhaps, across the great distances of space,
the Martians have watched what happened to
the ones that landed on Earth and learned
their lesson - and have found a safer home
on the planet Venus.
Even if that is true, for many years we will
continue to watch Mars carefully, and all
falling stars will make us afraid.
The war has broadened people's minds enormously.
Before it there was a general belief that
there was no life in space apart from on our
tiny planet.
If the Martians can reach Venus, there is
no reason to think that this is impossible
for us.
So when the slow cooling of the sun means
that we cannot continue to live on Earth,
it may be that life which began here can reach
out and continue there.
But that is a distant dream.
We may, on the other hand, still be destroyed
by the Martians.
The future may belong to them and not to us.
I must admit that the trouble and danger of
our time have left a continuing sense of doubt
and fear in my mind.
I sit in my study writing by lamplight, and
suddenly I see the valley below on fire again,
and feel that the house around me is empty
and lonely.
I go out into the Byfleet Road, and vehicles
pass me, a boy on a bicycle, children going
to school - and suddenly they become strange
and unreal, and I hurry on again with the
soldier through the hot, dangerous silence.
At night I see the black powder-darkening
the silent streets, and the twisted bodies
covered by it.
They stand up in front of me, torn and dog-bitten.
They talk and grow angry, paler, uglier, and
I wake, cold and shaking, in the darkness.
I go to London and see the busy crowds in
Fleet Street and the Strand, and it comes
to my mind that they are just the ghosts of
the past, walking the streets that I have
seen silent and empty, spirits in a dead city.
And it is strange, too, to stand on Primrose
Hill, as I did only a day before writing this
last chapter.
I saw the houses stretching away and disappearing
into the smoke and mist, people walking up
and down between the flower-beds, and the
sightseers around the Martian machine that
still stands there.
I heard the noise of playing children and
remembered the deep silence of the dawn of
that last great day...
And it is strangest of all to hold my wife's
hand again, and to think that I have thought
of her, and that she has thought of me, among
the dead.