ACT ONE
(The living room of Algernon Moncrieff's flat
in Mayfair, London.
Lane is arranging afternoon tea on a table.
Algernon enters)
Algernon: Lane, have you made the cucumber
sandwiches for Lady Bracknell's tea?
Lane: Yes, sir.
(Handing them to Algernon on a silver tray)
Algernon: (Looking carefully at them, taking
two and sitting down on the sofa) Oh, by the
way, Lane, I looked at your notebook.
I noticed that when Lord Shoreman and Mr Worthing
dined with me on Thursday night, eight bottles
of champagne were drunk.
Lane: Yes, sir; eight bottles.
Algernon: Why is it that, in a bachelor's
home, the servants always drink the champagne?
I just ask because I am interested, Lane.
Lane: I think that it is because the champagne
is better in a bachelor's home.
I have noticed that the champagne in married
people's homes is rarely very good.
Algernon: Good heavens!
Is marriage so depressing?
Lane: I believe marriage is very pleasant,
sir.
I haven't had much experience of it myself.
I have only been married once, and that was
because of a misunderstanding between myself
and a young person.
Algernon: (Lazily, without interest) I am
not very interested in your family life, Lane.
Lane: No, sir; it is not a very interesting
subject.
I never think of it myself.
Algernon: That is very understandable.
Well, thank you, Lane.
(Lane goes off)
Algernon: (To himself) Lane's views on marriage
seem very casual.
Really, if the servants don't set us a good
example, what on earth is the use of them?
They seem to have no morals.
(Lane enters)
Lane: Mr Ernest Worthing is here, sir.
(Jack enters.
Lane goes off)
Algernon: How are you, my dear Ernest?
What brings you to town?
Jack: Oh, pleasure brings me, pleasure, of
course!
What else should bring one anywhere?
You're eating as usual, I see, Algy!
Algernon: (Very formally) I believe it is
normal in good society to have some light
refreshment at five o'clock.
(In a normal voice) Where have you been since
last Thursday?
Jack: (Sitting down on the sofa) In the country.
Algernon: What on earth do you do in the country?
Jack: (Taking off his gloves) When one is
in town one entertains oneself.
When one is in the country one entertains
other people.
It is very boring.
Algernon: And who are the people you entertain?
Jack: Oh, neighbours, neighbours!
Algernon: Have you got nice neighbours in
your part of Shropshire?
Jack: No, they're all horrid.
I never speak to any of them.
Algernon: You must entertain them very much,
then!
(Going over to the table and taking a sandwich)
By the way, Shropshire is where you come from,
is it not?
Jack: Shropshire?
Yes, of course.
My dear fellow!
Why are all these cups here?
Why cucumber sandwiches?
Why are you being so extravagant?
Who is coming to tea?
Algernon: Oh, just Aunt Augusta and Gwendolen.
Jack: How perfectly delightful!
Algernon: Yes, but I am afraid Aunt Augusta
won't be happy that you're here.
Jack: And why is that?
Algernon: My dear fellow, the way that you
flirt with Gwendolen is perfectly disgraceful.
It is almost as bad as the way Gwendolen flirts
with you.
Jack: I am in love with Gwendolen.
I have come to town in order to propose marriage
to her.
Algernon: I thought you had come to town for
pleasure.
I call a marriage proposal business.
Jack: How very unromantic you are!
Algernon: I really don't think proposing is
romantic.
It is very romantic to be in love.
But there is nothing romantic about a proposal.
Someone might accept.
They usually do, I believe.
Then the exciting time is over.
The most important thing about romance is
the uncertainty.
If I ever marry, I'll certainly try to forget
that I am married.
Jack: I believe you, dear Algy.
The Divorce Court was especially invented
for people with memories like yours.
(Jack puts out his hand to take a cucumber
sandwich; Algernon immediately stops him)
Algernon: Oh, there is no point in thinking
about that.
Divorces are made in Heaven.
Please don't touch the cucumber sandwiches.
They were ordered specially for Aunt Augusta.
(Taking a sandwich himself and eating it)
Jack: Well, you have been eating them all
the time.
Algernon: That is different.
She is my aunt.
(Offering Jack a different plate) Have some
bread and butter.
The bread and butter is for Gwendolen.
Gwendolen loves bread and butter.
Jack: (Helping himself to bread and butter)
And very good bread and butter it is too.
Algernon: Well, my dear fellow, you don't
need to eat it all.
You are behaving as if you are married to
her already.
But you are not married to her and I don't
think you ever will be.
Jack: Why on earth do you say that?
Algernon: Well, firstly, girls never marry
the men they flirt with.
They don't think it's the right thing to do.
Jack: Oh, that is nonsense!
Algernon: It isn't.
It's true.
(Taking two more sandwiches) That's why one
sees such a large number of bachelors all
over the place.
And secondly, I don't give my consent.
Jack: Your consent!
Algernon: Gwendolen is my cousin.
And before I allow you to marry her, you will
have to clear up the matter of Cecily.
(Algernon rings a bell)
Jack: Cecily?
What on earth do you mean, Algy?
I don't know anyone called Cecily.
(Lane enters)
Algernon: Lane, bring me the cigarette case
which Mr Worthing left last time he dined
here.
Lane: Yes, sir.
(Lane goes off.
Algernon takes the last of the cucumber sandwiches)
Jack: Have you had my cigarette case all this
time?
I wish you had told me.
I have been writing letters to the police
about it.
I nearly offered a large reward.
Algernon: Well, I wish you would offer a large
reward.
I am very poor at the moment.
Jack: There is no point in offering a large
reward now that you've found it.
(Lane enters with the cigarette case on a
silver tray.
Algernon takes it immediately.
Lane goes off)
Algernon: I think that is mean of you, Ernest,
I must say.
(Opening the case and examining it) However,
it doesn't matter.
Now I look at the inscription inside, I see
that this isn't yours.
Jack: Of course it's mine.
(Moving towards Algernon) You have seen me
with it a hundred times, and you shouldn't
be reading what is written inside it.
It is very impolite to read a private cigarette
case.
Algernon: Oh!
It is ridiculous to have rules about what
one should read and what one shouldn't.
Most of modern culture depends on reading
what one shouldn't read.
Jack: I know that, and I am not going to discuss
modern culture.
I simply want my cigarette case back.
Algernon: Yes; but this isn't your cigarette
case.
This cigarette case is a present from someone
called Cecily.
And you said you don't know anyone called
Cecily.
Jack: Well, if you want to know, Cecily is
my aunt.
Algernon: Your aunt?
Jack: Yes.
She is a charming old lady.
Just give it back to me, Algy.
Algernon: (Going behind the sofa) But why
does she call herself 'little Cecily' if she
is your aunt?
(Reading) 'From little Cecily, with all her
love.'
Jack: (Going to the front of the sofa and
kneeling on it) My dear fellow, some aunts
are tall.
Some aunts are not tall.
My aunt should be allowed to decide her height
for herself.
You seem to think that every aunt should be
like your aunt, Lady Bracknell!
That is ridiculous.
Now, give me back my cigarette case.
(Following Algernon all around the room)
Algernon: Yes.
But why does your aunt call you her uncle?
(Reading) 'From little Cecily, with all her
love to her dear Uncle Jack.'
I don't object to an aunt being a small aunt.
But why does an aunt, whatever her size, call
her own nephew 'uncle'?
I don't understand.
And your name isn't Jack; it is Ernest.
Jack: It isn't Ernest; it's Jack.
Algernon: You have always told me that your
name is Ernest.
I have introduced you to everyone as Ernest.
You answer to the name Ernest.
You look as if your name is Ernest.
You are the most earnest-looking person I
have ever seen in my life.
It is perfectly ridiculous to tell me your
name isn't Ernest.
It is on your visiting cards.
Here is one of them.
(Taking it from a case) 'Mr Ernest Worthing,
B.4, The Albany, London.'
I'll keep this as proof that your name is
Ernest.
Don't ever try to deny it to me or to Gwendolen
or to anyone else.
(Putting the card in his pocket)
Jack: Well, my name is Ernest in town and
Jack in the country, and the cigarette case
was given to me in the country.
Algernon: That does not explain why your small
Aunt Cecily calls you her dear uncle.
My dear fellow, you had better tell me everything.
Go on!
I have always suspected that you were a secret
Bunburyist and now I am quite sure.
Jack: Bunburyist?
What on earth do you mean by a Bunburyist?
Algernon: I'll tell you the meaning of Bunburyist
when you tell me why you are Ernest in town
and Jack in the country.
Jack: Well, give me my cigarette case first.
Algernon: Here it is.
(Handing Jack the cigarette case) Now give
me your explanation and please make it unbelievable.
(Sitting on the sofa)
Jack: My dear fellow, there is nothing unbelievable
about my explanation.
In fact, it's perfectly ordinary.
I was brought up by an old gentleman called
Thomas Cardew.
He adopted me when I was a little boy and
he made me the guardian of his granddaughter,
Miss Cecily Cardew, in his will.
Cecily is my ward and calls me uncle because
she respects me, although you wouldn't understand
that!
You don't understand respect.
Cecily lives in my house in the country and
is looked after by her excellent governess,
Miss Prism.
Algernon: Where is your house in the country,
by the way?
Jack: That is nothing to do with you, my dear
fellow.
I am not going to invite you there... but
I will tell you honestly that the house is
not in Shropshire.
Algernon: I guessed that, my dear fellow!
I have Bunburyed all over Shropshire twice.
Now, go on.
Why are you Ernest in town and Jack in the
country?
Jack: My dear Algy, I don't know whether you
will understand.
You are not a very serious person.
I will try to explain it to you.
I am a responsible guardian and I have to
behave well all the time in the country.
It is my duty.
But it is not very good for my health or my
happiness.
So, when I want to leave the country and come
to town, I pretend to have a younger brother
called Ernest.
I tell everyone that he lives in The Albany
and that he gets into the most terrible trouble.
That, my dear Algy, is the truth.
Algernon: You are a Bunburyist!
I was right to say you were a Bunburyist.
You are one of the most advanced Bunburyists
I know.
Jack: What on earth do you mean?
Algernon: You have invented a younger brother
called Ernest so that you can come to town
as often as you like.
I have invented an invalid called Bunbury
so that I can go to the country as often as
I like.
When I pretend to visit him, I call it Bunburying.
And I call someone who visits imaginary people
a Bunburyist.
Bunbury is very valuable.
For example, if it wasn't for Bunbury's very
bad health, I wouldn't be able to dine with
you tonight.
I should be dining with Aunt Augusta.
Jack: I haven't asked you to dine with me
tonight.
Algernon: I know.
You are very careless about sending out invitations.
It is very foolish of you.
Nothing annoys people more than not receiving
invitations.
Jack: You ought to dine with your Aunt Augusta.
Algernon: I don't have any intention of dining
with Aunt Augusta.
Firstly, I dined there on Monday and once
a week is enough time to spend with one's
relations.
Secondly, Aunt Augusta will either give me
two women to talk to at dinner or none.
And thirdly, I know that tonight she will
make me sit next to Mary Farquhar, who always
flirts with her own husband across the dinner
table.
It is not very pleasant.
In fact, respectable women should not behave
like that... and more and more women are doing
it.
The number of women in London who flirt with
their own husbands is terrible.
It looks so bad.
Well, now I know that you are a Bunburyist,
I want to talk to you about Bunburying.
I want to tell you the rules.
Jack: I am not a Bunburyist.
If Gwendolen agrees to marry me, I am going
to kill my brother.
In fact, I think I will kill him anyway.
Cecily is a little too interested in him.
So I am going to get rid of Ernest.
And I think you should kill Mr... your invalid
friend with the ridiculous name.
Algernon: Nothing will make me kill Bunbury,
and, if you ever get married, you will be
glad to know Bunbury.
A man who marries without knowing Bunbury
will have a very boring marriage.
Jack: That is nonsense.
If I marry a charming girl like Gwendolen,
I certainly won't want to know Bunbury.
Algernon: Then your wife will want to know
him.
You don't understand that in married life
three is company and two is none.
Jack: Don't try to be cynical.
It's perfectly easy to be cynical.
Algernon: My dear fellow, it isn't easy to
be anything these days.
There is so much competition.
(There is the sound of a doorbell being rung
for a long time) Ah!
That must be Aunt Augusta.
Only relatives ring like that.
Now, I will take her out of the room for ten
minutes so that you can propose to Gwendolen.
So I can dine with you tonight, can't I?
Jack: I suppose so, if you want to.
Algernon: Good.
(Lane enters)
Lane: Lady Bracknell and Miss Fairfax are
here, sir.
(Algernon goes forward to meet them.
Lady Bracknell and Gwendolen enter)
Lady Bracknell: Good afternoon, dear Algernon.
I hope you are behaving very well.
Algernon: I'm feeling very well, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: Feeling very well is not the
same as behaving very well.
In fact, the two things rarely go together.
Algernon: (To Gwendolen) Good heavens, you
are smart!
Gwendolen: I am always smart!
Aren't I, Mr Worthing?
Jack: You're quite perfect, Miss Fairfax.
Gwendolen: Oh!
I hope I am not perfect.
There would be no room for development and
I intend to develop in every direction.
(Gwendolen and Jack sit down together in a
corner of the room)
Lady Bracknell: I am sorry if we are a little
late, Algernon, but I had to visit Lady Harbury.
I hadn't seen her since her poor husband died.
She has changed very much; she looks quite
twenty years younger.
And now I'll have a cup of tea and one of
those nice cucumber sandwiches you promised
me.
Algernon: Certainly, Aunt Augusta.
(Going over to the tea table)
Lady Bracknell: Will you come and sit here,
Gwendolen?
Gwendolen: Thanks, Mama, I'm quite comfortable
over here.
Algernon: (Picking up the empty plate of sandwiches
in horror) Good heavens!
Lane!
Why are there no cucumber sandwiches?
I ordered them specially.
Lane: (Seriously) There were no cucumbers
in the market this morning, sir.
I went there twice.
Algernon: No cucumbers?
Lane: No, sir.
Algernon: Thank you, Lane.
You may go.
Lane: Thank you, sir.
(Goes off)
Algernon: I am very upset that there were
no cucumbers, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: It doesn't matter, Algernon.
I had some crumpets with Lady Harbury.
Algernon: I hear that her hair has turned
quite blonde from grief.
Lady Bracknell: It certainly has changed its
colour.
I do not know why, of course.
(Algernon takes her a cup of tea) Thank you.
I've got quite a treat for you at dinner tonight,
Algernon.
I am going to seat you next to Mary Farquhar.
She is such a nice woman and she is so sweet
to her husband.
It's delightful to watch them.
Algernon: I am afraid, Aunt Augusta, I cannot
dine with you tonight after all.
Lady Bracknell: (Frowning) I hope you can,
Algernon.
There will be thirteen people at the dining
table if you aren't there.
That is unlucky.
Your uncle will have to eat upstairs.
Fortunately, he often has to do that.
Algernon: It is terribly disappointing to
me, but I've had a telegram to say that my
poor friend Bunbury is very ill again.
(Smiling quickly at Jack) They think I should
be with him.
Lady Bracknell: It is very strange.
Mr Bunbury seems to suffer from very bad health.
Algernon: Yes, indeed.
He is a permanent invalid.
Lady Bracknell: Well, Algernon, I think it's
about time that Mr Bunbury decides whether
he is going to live or die.
I don't sympathize with invalids.
Illness should not be encouraged in others.
One should be healthy.
Could you ask Mr Bunbury not to be ill on
Saturday?
I am holding a reception and I want you to
organize the music.
People talk during performances of music and
I want to encourage them to talk, particularly
since it is the end of the London season and
they have nearly run out of things to say.
Algernon: I'll speak to Bunbury, Aunt Augusta,
if he is still conscious.
I think I can promise you that he will be
well by Saturday.
Of course, the music is a problem.
You see, if one plays good music, people don't
listen and if one plays bad music, people
don't talk.
But I will show you the programme of music
I have chosen if you will come into the music
room for a moment.
Lady Bracknell: Thank you, Algernon.
It is very thoughtful of you.
(Lady Bracknell and Algernon go into the music
room, Gwendolen remains behind)
Jack: It's been a charming day, Miss Fairfax.
Gwendolen: Please don't talk about the weather,
Mr Worthing.
When people talk to me about the weather,
I always feel quite certain they mean something
else and I get nervous.
Jack: I do mean something else.
Gwendolen: I thought so.
In fact, I am never wrong.
Jack: I would like to talk to you about the
'something else' while Lady Bracknell is out
of the room.
Gwendolen: Then talk about it quickly.
Mama often comes back into a room suddenly.
Jack: (Nervously) Miss Fairfax, ever since
I met you, I have admired you more than any
girl...
I have met ever since...
I met you.
Gwendolen: Yes, I am quite well aware of that.
I was always fascinated by you - even before
I met you.
(Jack looks at her in amazement) We live in
an age of ideals - any expensive monthly magazine
will tell you that - and my ideal has always
been to love someone called Ernest.
When Algernon mentioned he had a friend called
Ernest, I knew I would love you.
Jack: Do you really love me, Gwendolen?
Gwendolen: Very much!
Jack: Darling!
You don't know how happy you have made me.
Gwendolen: My own Ernest!
Jack: But could you love me if my name wasn't
Ernest?
Gwendolen: But your name is Ernest.
Jack: Yes, I know it is.
But what if it was something else?
Couldn't you love me then?
Gwendolen: (Cleverly) Ah!
But you are called Ernest, so there is no
reason to think about you not being called
Ernest.
Jack: Personally, darling, I don't really
like the name Ernest...
I don't think the name suits me.
Gwendolen: It suits you perfectly.
It is a wonderful name.
It is musical.
Jack: Well, really, Gwendolen, I think there
are a lot of nicer names.
I think that Jack, for instance, is a charming
name.
Gwendolen: Jack...?
No, there is very little music in the name
Jack.
It does not excite me.
I have known several Jacks and they all were
very ordinary.
I feel pity for any woman who is married to
a man called Jack.
I think the only really good name is Ernest.
Jack: Gwendolen, I must get baptized at once...
I mean we must get married at once.
There is no time to lose.
Gwendolen: (Shocked) Married, Mr Worthing?
Jack: Well... you know that I love you and
you told me, Miss Fairfax, that you love me.
Gwendolen: I do love you.
But you haven't proposed to me yet.
Nothing has been said about marriage.
Jack: Well... may I propose to you now?
Gwendolen: I think that this would be an excellent
time to propose to me.
And I will tell you now that I will accept
you so that you aren't worried.
Jack: Gwendolen!
Gwendolen: Yes, Mr Worthing?
What are you going to say to me?
Jack: You know what I am going to say to you.
Gwendolen: Yes, but you haven't said it.
Jack: Gwendolen, will you marry me?
(Going down on his knees)
Gwendolen: Yes, of course I will.
You have taken a long time to ask.
I am afraid you have had very little experience
of proposing.
Jack: My dear, I have never loved anyone in
the world but you.
Gwendolen: Yes, but men often practise proposing.
My brother, Gerald, often proposes to people.
All my friends tell me.
What wonderful blue eyes you have, Ernest!
They are quite, quite blue.
I hope you will always look at me like that,
especially when there are other people in
the room.
(Lady Bracknell enters)
Lady Bracknell: Mr Worthing!
Get up from that position.
It is not respectable to behave like that.
Gwendolen: Mama!
(Jack tries to stand up but Gwendolen makes
him stay in a kneeling position) Please go
away.
Mr Worthing has not finished yet.
Lady Bracknell: Finished what, may I ask?
Gwendolen: I am engaged to be married to Mr
Worthing, Mama.
(Jack stands up)
Lady Bracknell: Pardon me, you are not engaged
to anyone, Gwendolen.
When you are engaged to someone, I, or your
father, will inform you of the fact.
An engagement should come as a surprise to
a young girl.
A pleasant surprise or an unpleasant surprise.
It is not something that she is allowed to
arrange for herself...
And now, I have a few questions to ask you,
Mr Worthing.
While I am asking these questions, you, Gwendolen,
will wait for me in the carriage.
Gwendolen: Mama!
Lady Bracknell: Wait in the carriage, Gwendolen!
(Gwendolen goes to the door.
She and Jack kiss their hands and pretend
to blow the kisses to each other behind Lady
Bracknell's back.
Lady Bracknell looks around for the cause
of the noise.
Finally she turns round and sees them.
Frowning) Gwendolen, I said wait for me in
the carriage!
Gwendolen: Yes, Mama.
(Going off, looking back at Jack)
Lady Bracknell: You can sit down, Mr Worthing.
(Looks in her pocket for a notebook and pencil)
Jack: Thank you, Lady Bracknell, I prefer
to stand.
Lady Bracknell: (Notebook and pencil in hand)
I must tell you that you are not on my list
of eligible young men, although I have the
same list as the Duchess of Bolton.
We work together during the season.
However, I am quite ready to add your name
to the list if your answers are satisfactory.
Do you smoke?
Jack: Well, yes, I do smoke.
Lady Bracknell: I am glad to hear it.
A man should always have an occupation.
There are far too many men in London who don't
have an occupation.
How old are you?
Jack: Twenty-nine.
Lady Bracknell: That's a very good age to
get married.
I have always believed that a man who wants
to get married should know everything or nothing.
Which do you know?
Jack: (After hesitating) I know nothing, Lady
Bracknell.
Lady Bracknell: I am pleased to hear it.
I approve of ignorance.
I don't approve of modern education.
Fortunately, in England at least, education
has no effect at all.
What is your income?
Jack: It's between seven and eight thousand
pounds a year.
Lady Bracknell: (Making a note in her book)
Do you earn this income from land that you
own or from investments?
Jack: From investments.
Lady Bracknell: That is satisfactory.
Owning land is neither profitable nor pleasurable
- it costs money to look after it when one
is alive and then there are taxes when one
is dead.
That's all I can say about land.
Jack: I have a country house with some land,
but I don't depend upon it for my income.
Lady Bracknell: A country house!
How many bedrooms?
Well, that doesn't matter.
I hope you have a house in town.
Gwendolen must have a house in town.
Jack: Well, I do have a town house in Belgrave
Square but it is rented to Lady Bloxham.
Lady Bracknell: Lady Bloxham?
I don't know her.
Jack: Oh, she doesn't go out very much; she's
very old.
Lady Bracknell: She's not necessarily respectable
even if she is old.
What number Belgrave Square?
Jack: 149.
Lady Bracknell: (Shaking her head disapprovingly)
But that is the unfashionable side of the
street.
However, that could easily be changed.
Jack: Do you mean the fashion or the side?
Lady Bracknell: (Very disapprovingly) Both,
if necessary.
Now, let us discuss less important details.
Are your parents living?
Jack: I have lost both my parents.
Lady Bracknell: To lose one parent, Mr Worthing,
is unfortunate; to lose both seems like carelessness.
Who was your father?
He must have been a wealthy man.
Was he a businessman or an aristocrat?
Jack: I am afraid I don't know.
Lady Bracknell, I said that I had lost my
parents.
In fact, my parents lost me...
I don't know who I am.
I was... well, I was found.
Lady Bracknell: Found?
Jack: The late Mr Thomas Cardew, a very kind
and charitable old gentleman, found me and
called me 'Worthing' because he had a train
ticket for Worthing in his pocket at the time.
Worthing is a seaside town.
Lady Bracknell: Where did the kind gentleman
who had a train ticket for this seaside town
find you?
Jack: (Seriously) In a handbag.
Lady Bracknell: A handbag?
Jack: (Very seriously) Yes, Lady Bracknell.
I was in a handbag - a large, black leather
handbag - an ordinary handbag with handles.
Lady Bracknell: Where did Mr Thomas Cardew
find this ordinary handbag?
Jack: In the cloakroom at Victoria Station,
here in London.
It was a mistake.
It was given to him instead of his own bag.
Lady Bracknell: In the cloakroom at Victoria
Station?
Jack: Yes.
Lady Bracknell: Mr Worthing, I am shocked
by what you have just told me.
I do not think it is right to be born in a
handbag, even if it has handles.
And I do not think it is right to be found
in a handbag in a cloakroom at a railway station.
It is not the way to become a respectable
gentleman with a good position in society.
Jack: What is your advice, Lady Bracknell?
I would, of course, do anything to make Gwendolen
happy.
Lady Bracknell: My advice to you, Mr Worthing,
is this - try to find some relations as soon
as possible.
And try to find at least one parent.
Jack: Well, I don't see how I could possibly
do that.
I can show you the handbag.
It is in a wardrobe at home.
I really think that should satisfy you, Lady
Bracknell.
Lady Bracknell: Me, sir!
It has nothing to do with me!
Do you really think that Lord Bracknell would
allow our only daughter to marry the son of
a cloakroom and form a relationship with a
piece of luggage?
Goodbye, Mr Worthing!
(Lady Bracknell leaves the room with great
dignity)
Jack: Goodbye!
(Algernon starts singing a Wedding March in
the music room.
Jack looks very angry and goes to the door)
Stop singing that awful tune, Algy!
(The singing stops and Algernon enters cheerfully)
Algernon: Didn't everything work out all right,
old fellow?
Did Gwendolen refuse to marry you?
Jack: Oh, Gwendolen was fine.
She believes we are engaged.
Her mother is awful.
I've never met such a monster.
Oh, I beg your pardon, Algy, I suppose I shouldn't
talk about your own aunt in that way in front
of you.
Algernon: My dear fellow, I love hearing people
being rude about my relations.
Relations are simply a boring group of people
who don't know how to live and don't know
when to die.
Jack: Oh, that is nonsense!
Algernon: It isn't!
Jack: Well, I won't argue about it.
You always want to argue about things.
Algernon: Things were made for arguing about.
Jack: If I believed that, I'd shoot myself...
(A pause) You don't think Gwendolen will become
like her mother in a hundred and fifty years,
do you, Algy?
Algernon: All women become like their mothers.
That is their tragedy.
No men become like theirs.
Jack: Have you said something clever?
Algernon: They were very fine sentences and
they are very true.
Jack: I'm tired of cleverness.
Everybody is clever nowadays.
You meet clever people everywhere.
I wish that there were a few fools left in
the world.
Algernon: There are.
Jack: I should like to meet them.
What do they talk about?
Algernon: The fools?
They talk about the clever people, of course.
Jack: What fools!
Algernon: By the way, did you tell Gwendolen
the truth about being Ernest in town and Jack
in the country?
Jack: My dear fellow, one does not tell the
truth to a nice, sweet girl.
You have extraordinary ideas about how to
behave to a woman!
Algernon: The only way to behave to a woman
is to flirt with her if she is pretty.
And if she isn't pretty, you must flirt with
someone else.
Jack: Oh, that is nonsense.
Algernon: What about your badly behaved brother
Ernest?
Did you tell her about him?
Jack: Oh, I shall have got rid of him before
the end of the week.
I'll say he died in Paris of a heart attack.
Lots of people die of a heart attack quite
suddenly, don't they?
Algernon: Yes, but it's hereditary, my dear
fellow.
It's the sort of thing that runs in families.
You had better say that he died of a bad cold.
Jack: Are you sure that a bad cold isn't hereditary?
Algernon: Of course it isn't.
Jack: Very well, then.
My poor brother Ernest will die suddenly,
in Paris, of a bad cold.
That gets rid of him.
Algernon: But you said that your ward...
Miss Cardew... was a little too interested
in your poor brother Ernest.
Won't she be very distressed?
Jack: Oh, that's not a problem.
Cecily is not a silly romantic girl, I am
pleased to say.
She eats big meals, goes for long walks and
doesn't pay attention to her lessons.
Algernon: I would like to meet Cecily.
Jack: I will make sure that you never meet
her.
She is extremely pretty and she is just eighteen.
Algernon: Have you told Gwendolen that you
have an extremely pretty ward who is just
eighteen?
Jack: Oh, one mustn't tell people everything
all at once.
Cecily and Gwendolen will be great friends,
I'm sure.
They will be calling each other sister half
an hour after they meet.
Algernon: Women only call each other sister
after they have called each other lots of
other things first.
Now, my dear fellow, if we want to get a good
table at the restaurant, we must go and change
our clothes now.
It's nearly seven.
I'm hungry.
Jack: (Irritably) I never knew a time when
you weren't hungry.
Algernon: What shall we do after dinner?
Go to a theatre?
Jack: Oh no!
One has to listen at the theatre.
I hate listening.
Algernon: Well, let us go to the Club.
Jack: Oh no!
One has to talk at the Club.
I hate talking.
Algernon: Well, we could go to the Empire
Music Hall at ten.
Jack: The Music Hall?
Oh no!
I hate looking at things.
Algernon: Well, what shall we do?
Jack: Nothing!
Algernon: Doing nothing is very hard work.
However, I don't mind very hard work if there
is nothing definite to do.
(Lane enters)
Lane: Miss Fairfax has returned, sir.
(Gwendolen enters.
Lane goes off)
Algernon: Gwendolen.
Hello!
Gwendolen: Algy, please go away.
I have something which I want to say to Mr
Worthing in private.
Algernon: Really, Gwendolen.
I don't think I can allow you to do that.
Gwendolen: Algy, you are not quite old enough
to say things like that.
(Algernon goes to the other side of the room
near the fireplace and stands with his back
to them)
Jack: My own darling!
Gwendolen: Ernest, we may never be married.
I saw the frown on Mama's face.
Few parents these days pay attention to what
their children say to them.
I was three years old the last time I had
any influence over my mother.
Ernest, she may stop us from getting married.
I may get married to someone else, I may get
married again and again - but nothing will
ever change my love for you.
Jack: Dear Gwendolen!
Gwendolen: Mama told me the romantic story
of your birth.
She is displeased about it, but I love it.
Your name - Ernest - fascinates me.
You are so simple and good-natured and that
makes you wonderfully complicated.
I've got your town address at The Albany.
What is your address in the country?
Jack: The Manor House, Woolton, Hertfordshire.
(Algernon, who has turned round and has been
carefully listening, smiles to himself and
writes the address on the cuff of his shirt.
Then he picks up a railway timetable from
a shelf)
Gwendolen: It may be necessary to do something
impetuous.
We will have to think carefully about this.
I will write to you every day.
Jack: My own one!
Gwendolen: How long will you be in town?
Jack: Till Monday.
Gwendolen: Good!
Algy, you may turn round now.
Algernon: Thanks, I have turned round already.
Gwendolen: You may also ring the bell for
Lane to take me to the door.
(Algernon rings the bell)
Jack: Let me take you to the door, my own
darling.
Gwendolen: Certainly.
Jack: (To Lane, who now enters) I will take
Miss Fairfax to the door.
Lane: Yes, sir.
(Jack and Gwendolen go off)
Algernon: Bring me a glass of wine, Lane.
Lane: Yes, sir.
Algernon: Tomorrow, Lane, I'm going Bunburying.
Algernon: I shall probably not be back till
Monday.
Pack my evening clothes, some casual clothes
and all my Bunbury suits...
Lane: Yes, sir.
(Handing Algernon his glass of wine)
Algernon: I hope that tomorrow is a fine day,
Lane.
Lane: It never is, sir.
Algernon: Lane, you are a pessimist.
Lane: I do my best, sir.
(Jack enters.
Lane goes off)
Jack: What a sensible, intelligent girl!
The only girl I've ever cared for in my life.
(Algernon is laughing loudly) What on earth
are you laughing at?
Algernon: Oh, I'm a bit worried about poor
Bunbury, that is all.
Jack: Your friend Bunbury will get you into
trouble one day, you know.
Algernon: I love trouble.
It's the only thing which is never serious.
Jack: Oh, that's nonsense, Algy.
You never talk anything but nonsense.
Algernon: Nobody ever does.
(Jack shakes his head at him and leaves the
room.
Algernon lights a cigarette, looks at his
shirt-cuff and smiles)
ACT TWO
(The garden at the Manor House in Woolton,
Hertfordshire, Jack Worthing's country home.
Miss Prism is sitting at a table.
Cecily is watering flowers)
Miss Prism: (Calling) Cecily, Cecily!
I think that watering flowers is a servant's
occupation rather than yours, especially at
a moment when the pleasures of education are
waiting for you.
Your German grammar book is on the table.
Please open it at page fifteen.
We will do yesterday's lesson again.
Cecily: (Coming over to the table very slowly)
But I don't like German.
It isn't a very pretty language.
I know that I look quite ugly after my German
lesson.
Miss Prism: Child, your guardian is anxious
that you improve yourself in every way.
As he was leaving for town yesterday, he reminded
me how important your German is.
Indeed he always reminds me how important
your German is when he is leaving for town.
Cecily: Dear Uncle Jack is so very serious!
Sometimes he is so serious that I think he
must be ill.
Miss Prism: (Sitting up very straight in her
chair) Your guardian's health is excellent
and his seriousness - indeed his earnestness
- is very admirable in such a young man.
I do not know anyone else who has such a good
sense of duty and responsibility.
Cecily: I suppose that is why he often seems
a little bored when we three are together.
Miss Prism: Cecily!
I am surprised at you.
Mr Worthing has many troubles in his life.
You must remember that he is always worried
about that unfortunate young man, his brother
Ernest.
Cecily: I wish Uncle Jack would allow that
unfortunate young man, his brother Ernest,
to come here sometimes.
We might have a good influence on him, Miss
Prism.
I am sure that you would.
You know German and geology and all kinds
of things that influence a man very much.
(Cecily begins to write in her diary)
Miss Prism: (Shaking her head) I do not think
that even I could have a good influence on
his character.
Mr Worthing himself says that his brother's
character is weak and indecisive.
Indeed, I wouldn't want to have a good influence
on him.
I do not approve of this modern desire to
turn bad people into good people at a moment's
notice.
I think he should suffer because of his misbehaviour.
You must put away your diary, Cecily.
I really don't understand why you keep a diary
at all.
Cecily: I keep a diary in order to write down
the wonderful secrets of my life.
If I didn't write them down, I should probably
forget all about them.
Miss Prism: Our memory is the diary that we
all have with us.
Cecily: Yes, but our memory usually remembers
things that have never happened and couldn't
possibly have happened.
I believe that memory is responsible for all
the three-volume novels people write.
Miss Prism: Do not be dismissive of the three-volume
novel, Cecily.
I wrote one myself a long time ago.
Cecily: Did you really, Miss Prism?
How wonderfully clever you are!
I hope it did not end happily!
I don't like novels that end happily.
They depress me so much.
Miss Prism: The good people ended happily.
The bad people ended unhappily.
That is fiction.
Cecily: I suppose so.
But it seems very unfair.
And was your novel ever published?
Miss Prism: I am sad to say it was not.
The manuscript, unfortunately, was lost.
Now, start work, child.
There is no point in thinking about these
things.
Cecily: (Smiling) But I see dear Canon Chasuble
coming towards us through the garden.
Miss Prism: (Standing up and going towards
Canon Chasuble) Canon Chasuble!
It is indeed a pleasure to see you.
Chasuble: And how are we today?
Miss Prism, you are, I hope, well?
Cecily: Miss Prism has just been complaining
of a slight headache.
I think that it would do her good to have
a short walk with you in the park, Canon Chasuble.
Miss Prism: Cecily, I have not mentioned anything
about a headache.
Cecily: No, dear Miss Prism, I know that,
but I felt that you had a headache.
Indeed, I was thinking about that, and not
about my German lesson, when Canon Chasuble
arrived.
Chasuble: I hope, Cecily, that you pay attention
to your lessons.
Cecily: Oh, I am afraid I do not!
Chasuble: That is strange.
If I were Miss Prism's pupil, I would always
pay attention.
Has Mr Worthing returned from town yet?
Miss Prism: We expect him on Monday afternoon.
Chasuble: Ah, yes, he usually likes to spend
his Sundays in London.
He is an earnest young man who does not always
look for pleasure as, I believe, his younger
brother does.
I will see you both at church later, shall
I?
Miss Prism: I think, dear Canon, I will have
a walk with you.
I find I have a headache after all and a walk
might do it good.
Canon Chasuble: It would be a pleasure, Miss
Prism, a pleasure.
Let us go to the end of the garden and back.
Miss Prism: That would be delightful.
Cecily, you will read your Political Economy
in my absence.
(Miss Prism goes down the garden with Canon
Chasuble)
Cecily: Oh horrid Political Economy!
Horrid German!
(Merriman enters with a visiting card on a
silver tray)
Merriman: Mr Ernest Worthing has just arrived
from the station.
He has brought his luggage with him.
Cecily: (Taking the card and reading it) 'Mr
Ernest Worthing, B.4, The Albany, London.'
He must be Uncle Jack's brother!
Have you told him Uncle Jack is in town?
Merriman: Yes, miss.
He seemed very disappointed.
I told him that you and Miss Prism were in
the garden.
He said he was anxious to speak to you privately
for a moment.
Cecily: Ask Mr Ernest Worthing to come here.
And you had better talk to the housekeeper
about a bedroom for him.
Merriman: Yes, miss.
(Merriman goes off)
Cecily: (To herself) I have never met a really
wicked person before.
I feel rather frightened.
I am so afraid that he will look just like
everyone else.
(Algernon enters looking very handsome and
fashionable) Oh dear, he does!
Algernon: (Raising his hat) You are my little
cousin, Cecily, I'm sure.
Cecily: You are making a strange mistake.
I am not little.
In fact, I believe I am quite tall for my
age.
(Algernon is rather surprised) But I am your
cousin, Cecily.
You, I see from your card, are Uncle Jack's
brother, my cousin Ernest, my wicked cousin
Ernest.
Algernon: Oh!
I am not really wicked at all, Cousin Cecily.
You mustn't think that I am wicked.
Cecily: If you are not wicked, then I think
you have been deceiving us all.
I hope that you have not been leading a double
life.
I hope you have not been pretending to be
wicked and being really good all the time.
That would be hypocrisy.
Algernon: (Looking at her in amazement) Oh!
Of course, I have been rather bad.
Cecily: I'm glad to hear it.
Algernon: In fact, I think that I have been
very wicked in my own way.
Cecily: I don't think you should be so proud
of that, though I'm sure it must have been
very pleasant.
Algernon: It is much pleasanter being here
with you.
Cecily: I can't understand why you are here
at all.
Uncle Jack won't be back from town till Monday
afternoon.
Algernon: That is a great disappointment to
me.
I have to leave for London by the first train
on Monday morning.
I have a business meeting that I am anxious...
to miss!
Cecily: Couldn't you miss it anywhere but
in London?
Algernon: No.
The appointment is in London.
Cecily: Well, of course, I know that it is
important not to attend a business meeting.
That is what makes life interesting.
But I think you should wait till Uncle Jack
arrives.
I know he wants to speak to you about your
emigration.
Algernon: He wants to speak to me about...
I don't understand!
Cecily: About your emigration.
He has gone to town to buy your clothes.
Algernon: I certainly wouldn't let Jack buy
my clothes.
He has no taste in ties at all.
Cecily: I don't think you will require ties.
Uncle Jack is sending you to Australia.
Algernon: Australia!
I'd rather die.
Cecily: Well, at dinner on Wednesday he said
that you would have to choose between this
world, the next world and Australia.
Algernon: Oh well!
I don't believe Australia and the next world
are very nice.
This world is good enough for me, Cousin Cecily.
Cecily: Ah, but are you good enough for it?
Algernon: I'm afraid I'm not.
That is why I want you to reform me.
Please will you do this, Cousin Cecily.
Cecily: I'm afraid I don't have time this
afternoon.
Algernon: Well, would you mind if I reformed
myself this afternoon?
Cecily: It is rather ambitious of you.
But I think you should try.
Algernon: I will.
I feel better already.
Cecily: You are looking a little worse.
Algernon: That is because I am hungry.
Cecily: How thoughtless of me.
I should have remembered that someone who
is going to reform himself needs regular meals.
Please come in.
Algernon: Thank you.
May I have a flower for my buttonhole first?
I never have any appetite unless I have a
flower for my buttonhole.
I'd like a pink rose.
Cecily: (Picking up scissors) Why?
(Cutting a flower)
Algernon: Because you are like a pink rose,
Cousin Cecily.
Cecily: I don't think that it is right for
you to talk to me like that.
Miss Prism doesn't say such things to me.
Algernon: Miss Prism must be a very short-sighted
old lady.
(Cecily puts the flower in his buttonhole)
You are the prettiest girl I have ever seen.
Cecily: Miss Prism says that good looks are
a trap.
Algernon: They are a trap that every sensible
man would like to be caught in.
Cecily: Oh, I don't think I would like to
catch a sensible man.
I wouldn't know what to talk to him about.
(They go into the house.
Miss Prism and Canon Chasuble enter)
Miss Prism: You are on your own too much,
Canon Chasuble.
You should get married.
Chasuble: The Early Church was very much against
marriage.
Miss Prism: That is obviously the reason why
the Early Church has not lasted to the present
day.
And you do not seem to realize, dear sir,
that a man who remains single becomes a permanent
temptation.
Chasuble: But isn't a man equally attractive
when he is married?
Miss Prism: No married man is ever attractive
except to his wife.
Chasuble: And often, I've been told, he is
not even attractive to her.
Miss Prism: That depends on the woman.
If she is a mature woman, she can be relied
upon.
You cannot rely upon a young woman.
But where is Cecily?
Chasuble: Perhaps she followed us.
(Jack enters from the back of the garden.
He is wearing black mourning clothes)
Miss Prism: Mr Worthing!
Chasuble: Mr Worthing!
Miss Prism: This is a surprise.
We did not expect you till Monday afternoon.
Jack: (Shaking Miss Prism's hand in a tragic
way) I have returned sooner than I expected
to.
Canon Chasuble, I hope you are well?
Chasuble: Dear Mr Worthing, I hope these black
clothes do not mean that something dreadful
has happened?
Jack: My brother.
Miss Prism: More shameful debts and bad behaviour?
Chasuble: Is he still leading his wicked life?
Jack: (Shaking his head) Dead!
Chasuble: Your brother Ernest is dead?
Jack: Quite dead.
Miss Prism: What a lesson for him!
I hope he will learn from this.
Chasuble: Mr Worthing, I offer you my sincere
condolences.
At least you know that you have always been
most generous and forgiving to him.
Jack: Poor Ernest!
He had many faults, but it is very, very sad.
Chasuble: Very sad indeed.
Were you with him at the end?
Jack: No.
He died abroad; in Paris, in fact.
I had a telegram last night from the manager
of the Grand Hotel in Paris.
Chasuble: Did the telegram mention the cause
of death?
Jack: A bad cold, it seems.
Miss Prism: As a man sows, so shall he reap.
Chasuble: Charity, dear Miss Prism, charity!
None of us are perfect.
I myself am particularly sensitive to draughts.
Will the funeral take place here?
Jack: No.
It seems he wanted to be buried in Paris.
Chasuble: In Paris!
(Shaking his head) I don't think he was being
very serious even at the end.
You will want me to mention this sad event
in church next Sunday.
(Jack presses Canon Chasuble's hand very hard
and looks very sad) My sermon on the mercy
of God can be used on any occasion, happy
or sad.
(They all sigh) I have preached it at baptisms,
weddings and funerals.
The last time I preached it was to the Society
for the Prevention of Discontent among the
Upper Classes.
The Bishop, who was present, liked it very
much.
Jack: Ah!
That reminds me.
You mentioned baptisms, I think, Canon Chasuble?
You know how to baptize people, I suppose?
(Canon Chasuble looks very surprised) I mean
you often baptize people, don't you?
Miss Prism: It is, I am sorry to say, one
of the canon's most frequent duties.
I have often spoken to the poorer classes
about it.
But they don't take any notice.
Chasuble: But is there any particular child
in whom you are interested, Mr Worthing?
Your brother was, I believe, unmarried?
Jack: Oh yes.
Miss Prism: (Bitterly) People who live just
for pleasure are usually unmarried.
Jack: But it is not for any child, dear canon.
No!
The fact is that I would like to be baptized
myself, this afternoon, if you have nothing
better to do.
Chasuble: But surely, Mr Worthing, you have
been baptized already?
Jack: I don't remember anything about it.
Of course, I don't know if you think I am
a little too old now.
Chasuble: Not at all.
At what time would you like the ceremony performed?
Jack: Oh, I'll come about five o'clock if
that would suit you.
Chasuble: Perfectly, perfectly!
In fact I have two similar ceremonies to perform
at that time - twins who were born in one
of the cottages on your estate.
Jack: Oh!
I don't think it would be much fun to be baptized
along with other babies.
It would be childish.
Would half-past five be all right?
Chasuble: Of course, of course!
(Taking out his watch from his pocket) And
now, dear Mr Worthing, I will not stay any
longer in this house of grief.
I ask you not to grieve too much.
Bitter trials are often blessings in disguise.
Miss Prism: This seems to me to be an extremely
obvious blessing.
(Cecily enters from the house)
Cecily: Uncle Jack!
Oh, I am pleased to see you.
But what horrible clothes you are wearing.
Please go and change them.
Miss Prism: Cecily!
Chasuble: My child!
My child!
(Cecily goes towards Jack, who kisses her
forehead in a tragic way)
Cecily: What is the matter, Uncle Jack?
Please look happy!
You look as if you have toothache, and I have
got such a surprise for you.
Who do you think is in the dining room?
Your brother!
Jack: Who?
Cecily: Your brother Ernest.
He arrived about half an hour ago.
Jack: What nonsense!
I haven't got a brother.
Cecily: Oh, don't say that.
He is still your brother even though he has
behaved badly in the past.
You mustn't be so heartless.
I'll tell him to come out.
And you will shake hands with him, won't you,
Uncle Jack?
(Cecily runs back into the house)
Chasuble: This is very happy news.
Miss Prism: Since we were just getting used
to his departure, his sudden return seems
very distressing.
Jack: My brother is in the dining room?
I don't know what it means.
I think it is perfectly ridiculous.
(Algernon and Cecily enter holding hands.
They come slowly towards Jack)
Good heavens!
(He waves his hand to try to make Algernon
go away)
Algernon: (Holding his hand out to Jack) Brother
Jack, I have come from town to tell you that
I am very sorry for all the trouble I have
given you and that I will behave myself better
in future.
(Jack glares at him and doesn't take his hand)
Cecily: Uncle Jack, are you going to refuse
to shake your brother's hand?
Jack: Nothing will make me shake his hand.
I think it is disgraceful that he has come
here.
He knows perfectly well why.
Cecily: Uncle Jack, do be nice.
There is some good in everyone.
Ernest has just been telling me about his
poor invalid friend, Mr Bunbury, whom he goes
to visit very often.
There must be much good in Ernest if he leaves
London to sit by the bed of an invalid.
Jack: Oh!
He has been talking about Bunbury, has he?
Cecily: Yes, he has told me all about poor
Mr Bunbury and his very bad health.
Jack: Bunbury!
Well, I don't want him to talk to you about
Bunbury or about anything else.
It makes me furious.
Algernon: Of course, I agree that I used to
behave very badly.
But I must say that I think Brother Jack's
coldness towards me is very unkind.
I expected a better welcome, especially since
it is the first time I have come here.
Cecily: Uncle Jack, if you don't shake hands
with Ernest, I will never forgive you.
Jack: You will never forgive me?
Cecily: Never, never, never!
Jack: Well, this is the last time I shall
ever do it.
(Shaking hands with Algernon and glaring at
him)
Chasuble: It is pleasant to see a perfect
reconciliation, is it not?
I think we should leave the brothers together.
Miss Prism: Cecily, you will come with us.
Cecily: Certainly, Miss Prism.
My task of reconciliation is over.
Chasuble: You have done something beautiful
today, dear child.
Miss Prism: We must not say these things too
soon.
Cecily: I feel very happy.
(They all go off except Jack and Algernon)
Jack: You young scoundrel, Algy, you must
get out of this place as soon as possible.
I don't allow any Bunburying here.
(Merriman enters)
Merriman: I have put Mr Ernest's things in
the room next to yours, sir.
Jack: What?
Merriman: Mr Ernest's luggage, sir.
I have unpacked it and put it in the room
next to your own.
Jack: His luggage?
Merriman: Yes, sir.
Three large suitcases, a small suitcase, two
hat boxes and a large picnic basket.
Algernon: I'm afraid I can only stay for a
week this time.
Jack: Merriman, order the carriage at once.
Mr Ernest has suddenly been called back to
town.
Merriman: Yes, sir.
(Merriman goes off)
Algernon: What a liar you are, Jack.
I have not been called back to town at all.
Jack: Yes, you have.
Algernon: I haven't heard anyone call me.
Jack: Your duty as a gentleman calls you back.
Algernon: My duty as a gentleman has never
interfered with my pleasure at all.
Jack: Yes, I quite understand that!
Algernon: Well, Cecily is a darling.
Jack: You are not to talk of Miss Cardew like
that.
I don't like it.
Algernon: Well, I don't like your clothes.
You look perfectly ridiculous in them.
Why don't you go upstairs and change?
It is perfectly childish to be wearing black
clothes for a man who is going to stay in
your house for a whole week as a guest.
Jack: You are certainly not staying with me
for a whole week.
You have got to leave... by the four o'clock
train.
Algernon: I certainly won't leave you while
you are in black clothes.
That would be very unfriendly.
Jack: Well, will you go if I change my clothes?
Algernon: Yes, if you are not too long.
I never saw anybody else who took so long
to get dressed, and with such uninteresting
results.
Jack: Well, at least that is better than always
being overdressed like you.
Algernon: If I am occasionally overdressed,
I make up for it by being extremely overeducated.
Jack: Your vanity is silly, your behaviour
is outrageous and your presence in my garden
is ridiculous.
However, you have got to catch the four o'clock
train and I hope you will have a pleasant
journey back to town.
This Bunburying has not been a success for
you.
(Jack goes into the house)
Algernon: (To himself) I think it has been
a great success.
I'm in love with Cecily and that is wonderful.
(Cecily enters at the back of the garden.
She picks up a can and starts watering the
flowers)
But I must see her before I go and make arrangements
for some more Bunburying.
Ah, there she is.
Cecily: Oh, I came back to water the roses.
I thought you were with Uncle Jack.
Algernon: He's gone to order the carriage
for me.
Cecily: Oh, is he going to take you for a
nice drive?
Algernon: He's going to send me away.
Cecily: Then we have to part?
Algernon: I am afraid so.
It's a very painful parting.
Cecily: It is always painful to part with
new friends.
It is easy to bear the absence of old friends,
but even a short parting from someone whom
one has just met is extremely painful.
Algernon: Thank you.
(Merriman enters)
Merriman: The carriage is at the door, sir.
(Algernon looks sadly at Cecily)
Cecily: It can wait, Merriman... for... five
minutes.
Merriman: Yes, miss.
(Merriman goes off)
Algernon: I hope, Cecily, I shall not offend
you if I tell you that you seem to me to be
perfect in every way.
Cecily: I think that it is very good that
you are so honest.
If you will allow me, I will copy your words
into my diary.
(Going over to a table and starting to write
in her diary)
Algernon: Do you really keep a diary?
I'd love to look at it.
May I look at it?
Cecily: Oh, no.
(Putting her hand over it) You see, it is
just a young girl's record of her thoughts
and impressions, and of course, it is going
to be published.
When it appears in the form of a book, I hope
you will buy a copy.
But please don't stop, Ernest.
I enjoy writing things down from dictation.
I have got to 'perfect in every way'.
You can go on.
I am quite ready to write down more.
Algernon: (Rather surprised, coughing) Ahem!
Ahem!
Cecily: Oh, don't cough, Ernest.
When one is dictating, one should speak clearly
and not cough.
Besides, I can't spell a cough.
(Writing as Algernon speaks)
Algernon: (Speaking very quickly) Cecily,
ever since I first looked at your wonderful
beauty, I have loved you wildly, passionately,
devotedly, hopelessly.
Cecily: I don't think that you should tell
me you love me wildly, passionately, devotedly,
hopelessly.
Hopelessly doesn't make much sense, does it?
Algernon: Cecily.
(Merriman enters)
Merriman: The carriage is waiting at the door,
sir.
Algernon: Tell it to come to the door next
week at the same time.
Merriman: (Looking at Cecily, who doesn't
say anything) Yes, sir.
(Merriman goes off)
Cecily: Uncle Jack would be very annoyed if
he knew you were staying till next week at
the same time.
Algernon: Oh, I don't care about Jack.
I don't care about anybody in the whole world
except you.
I love you, Cecily.
You will marry me, won't you?
Cecily: You silly boy!
Of course.
We have been engaged for the last three months.
Algernon: For the last three months?
Cecily: Yes, it will have been three months
on Thursday.
Algernon: But how did we become engaged?
Cecily: Well, ever since Uncle Jack told us
he had a very wicked younger brother, you,
of course, have been the main topic of conversation
between myself and Miss Prism.
And a man who is talked about all the time
is very attractive.
And I fell in love with you, which is probably
a bit silly of me.
Algernon: Darling!
And when did we become engaged?
Cecily: On the fourteenth of February.
I was unhappy that you didn't know I existed,
so I made up my mind to decide the matter,
one way or the other.
After thinking about it for a long time, I
decided to accept your proposal of marriage.
I decided that we were engaged.
And so the next day I bought this little ring
for you to give me and I promised you that
I would always wear it.
Algernon: Did I give you this?
It's very pretty, isn't it?
Cecily: Yes, you've got wonderfully good taste,
Ernest.
It's the excuse I've given you for leading
such a bad life.
And this is the box in which I keep all your
dear letters.
(Putting a box on the table.
Opening the box and bringing out a bundle
of letters tied up with a blue ribbon)
Algernon: (Sitting beside her) My letters!
But, my own sweet Cecily, I have never written
you any letters.
Cecily: You needn't remind me, Ernest.
I remember very well that I had to write your
letters for you.
I always wrote three times a week and sometimes
more often.
Algernon: Oh, do let me read them, Cecily.
Cecily: Oh, I couldn't possibly let you do
that.
They would make you far too conceited.
(Replacing the box) The three that you wrote
me after I had broken off the engagement are
so beautiful and so badly spelt that even
now they make me cry a little when I read
them.
Algernon: But was our engagement ever broken
off?
Cecily: Of course it was.
On the twenty-second of March.
You can see the diary entry if you like.
(Showing her diary) 'Today I broke off my
engagement with Ernest.
I feel it is better to do so.
The weather continues to be very pleasant.'
Algernon: But why on earth did you break it
off?
What had I done?
I had done nothing at all.
Cecily, I am very hurt indeed to hear that
you broke it off.
Particularly when the weather was so pleasant.
Cecily: It wouldn't have been a very serious
engagement if it hadn't been broken off at
least once.
But I forgave you before the end of the week.
Algernon: What a perfect angel you are, Cecily.
Cecily: You dear romantic boy.
(He kisses her)
Algernon: Do you promise that you'll never
break off our engagement again, Cecily?
Cecily: I don't think I could break it off
now that I have actually met you.
Besides, of course, there is your name.
Algernon: (Sounding nervous) Yes, of course.
Cecily: You must not laugh at me, darling,
but it had always been a dream of mine to
love someone called Ernest.
(Algernon stands up and then Cecily does also)
There is something about that name which inspires
confidence.
I pity any poor married woman whose husband
is not called Ernest.
Algernon: But, my dear child, couldn't you
love me if I had another name?
Cecily: But what name?
Algernon: Oh, any name you like - Algernon
- for instance...
Cecily: But I don't like the name Algernon.
Algernon: Well, my own dear, sweet, loving
little darling, I can't see why you don't
like the name Algernon.
It is not a bad name.
In fact, it is rather an aristocratic name.
Half the fellows who get into the Bankruptcy
Court are called Algernon.
But seriously, Cecily...
(Moving to her and making her sit down with
him) if my name was Algy, couldn't you love
me?
Cecily: (Standing up) I might respect you,
Ernest.
I might admire your character, but I would
not really want to spend very much time with
you.
Algernon: Ahem!
Cecily!
(Picking up his hat) The clergyman here is,
I suppose, a very experienced man?
Cecily: Oh, yes.
Canon Chasuble is a very learned man.
He has never written a single book, so you
can imagine how much he knows.
Algernon: I must see him at once about an
important baptism...
I mean... on important business.
Cecily: Oh!
Algernon: I shan't be away for more than half
an hour.
Cecily: We have been engaged since the fourteenth
of February and I only met you today for the
first time, so I think it is rather hard that
you should leave me for as long as half an
hour.
Couldn't you make it twenty minutes?
Algernon: I'll be back in no time.
(He kisses her and runs down the garden)
Cecily: What an impetuous boy he is!
I must write about his proposal in my diary.
(She sits down and writes in her diary)
(Merriman enters)
Merriman: A Miss Fairfax has just called to
see Mr Worthing.
She says it is on very important business.
Cecily: Isn't Mr Worthing in his library?
Merriman: Mr Worthing went to Canon Chasuble's
house some time ago.
Cecily: Please ask the lady to come out into
the garden and join me.
Mr Worthing is sure to be back soon.
And you can bring tea.
Merriman: Yes, miss.
(Merriman goes off)
Cecily: (To herself) Miss Fairfax!
I suppose she is one of the many good women
who help Uncle Jack with his charitable work
in London.
I don't really like women who are interested
in charitable work.
I think it is so presumptuous of them.
(Merriman enters)
Merriman: Miss Fairfax.
(Gwendolen enters.
Merriman goes off)
Cecily: (Standing up and going to meet her)
Let me introduce myself to you.
My name is Cecily Cardew.
Gwendolen: Cecily Cardew?
(Moving to her and shaking hands) What a very
sweet name!
I think we are going to be great friends.
I like you already more than I can say.
My first impressions of people are never wrong.
Cecily: How nice of you to like me so much
when we have known each other for such a short
time.
Please sit down.
Gwendolen: (Still standing up) I may call
you Cecily, may I not?
Cecily: Of course, with pleasure.
Gwendolen: And you will always call me Gwendolen,
won't you?
Cecily: If you wish.
Gwendolen: Then that is all quite settled,
is it not?
Cecily: I hope so.
(A pause.
Then they both sit down together)
Gwendolen: Perhaps this is a good opportunity
to tell you who I am.
My father is Lord Bracknell.
You have never heard of Papa, I suppose?
Cecily: I don't think so.
Gwendolen: Outside the family circle, Papa,
I am glad to say, is completely unknown.
I think that is quite right.
The home seems to me to be the proper place
for a man.
Certainly once a man begins to neglect his
duties at home, it makes him very attractive.
Cecily, Mama, whose views on education are
very strict, has brought me up to be extremely
short-sighted; it is part of her system.
So do you mind me looking at you through my
glasses?
Cecily: Oh!
Not at all, Gwendolen.
I like being looked at.
Gwendolen: (After looking at Cecily carefully
through a lorgnette) You are here on a short
visit, I suppose?
Cecily: Oh no!
I live here.
Gwendolen: (Severely) Really?
Your mother, or an elderly female relation,
lives here also?
Cecily: Oh no!
I have no mother, nor, in fact, any relations.
Gwendolen: Indeed?
Cecily: My dear guardian, with the help of
Miss Prism, has the difficult task of looking
after me.
Gwendolen: Your guardian?
Cecily: Yes, I am Mr Worthing's ward.
Gwendolen: Oh!
It is strange that he never mentioned to me
that he had a ward.
How secretive of him!
He is becoming more interesting every hour.
However, I am not sure that I am delighted
by this news.
(Standing up and going to Cecily) I have liked
you ever since I met you, Cecily.
But, now that I know you are Mr Worthing's
ward, I must say that I wish you were - well
- a bit older than you seem to be - and not
quite so pretty.
In fact, if I may speak candidly...
Cecily: Please do!
I think that when one has anything unpleasant
to say, one should always be quite candid.
Gwendolen: Well, to be quite candid, Cecily,
I wish that you were at least forty-two years
old and extremely plain.
Ernest has an honourable, truthful nature.
He would never be deceitful.
But the most honourable men can be influenced
by the beauty of others.
Modern history, and indeed ancient history,
give us many painful examples of what I refer
to.
Indeed, history would be quite unreadable
if it were not so.
Cecily: I beg your pardon, Gwendolen, did
you say 'Ernest'?
Gwendolen: Yes.
Cecily: Oh, but it is not Mr Ernest Worthing
who is my guardian.
It is his brother - his elder brother.
Gwendolen: (Sitting down again) Ernest never
mentioned to me that he had a brother.
Cecily: I am sorry to say that they have not
got on well with each other for a long time.
Gwendolen: Ah!
I see.
And now I think about it, I have never heard
any man mention his brother.
Most men don't seem to like the subject.
Cecily, you have lifted a weight from my mind.
I was becoming almost anxious.
It would have been awful if any cloud had
come across such a special friendship, would
it not?
Are you quite, quite sure that it is not Mr
Ernest Worthing who is your guardian?
Cecily: Quite sure.
(A pause) In fact, I am going to be his guardian.
Gwendolen: I beg your pardon?
Cecily: (Shyly) Dearest Gwendolen, there is
no reason why I should keep it a secret from
you.
It will be in the local newspaper next week.
Mr Ernest Worthing and I are engaged to be
married.
Gwendolen: (Politely, standing up) My darling
Cecily, I think that there must be some small
mistake.
Mr Ernest Worthing is engaged to me.
The announcement will appear in the newspapers
on Saturday at the latest.
Cecily: (Very politely, standing up) I am
afraid that you are mistaken.
Ernest proposed to me exactly ten minutes
ago.
(Showing her diary to Gwendolen)
Gwendolen: (Looking at the diary very carefully
through her lorgnette) It is very strange
because he asked me to be his wife yesterday
afternoon at half-past five.
Please check for yourself.
(Producing a diary of her own) I never travel
without my diary.
One should always have something exciting
to read on the train.
I am so sorry, dear Cecily, if it is any disappointment
to you, but I am afraid that I was his first
choice.
Cecily: It would make me very sad, dear Gwendolen,
to cause you any pain, but I feel I must point
out that since Ernest proposed to you he has
clearly changed his mind.
Gwendolen: (Thoughtfully) If the poor fellow
has been trapped into making a foolish promise,
it is my duty to rescue him at once - and
firmly.
Cecily: (Thoughtfully and sadly) If my dear
boy has got into an unfortunate entanglement,
I will never reproach him for it when we are
married.
Gwendolen: Are you calling me an entanglement,
Miss Cardew?
You are presumptuous.
On an occasion of this kind, it becomes more
than a duty to speak one's mind.
It becomes a pleasure.
Cecily: Do you suggest, Miss Fairfax, that
I trapped Ernest into an engagement?
How dare you!
This is no time to pretend to have good manners.
When I see a spade, I call it a spade.
Gwendolen: I am glad to say that I have never
seen a spade.
It is obvious we do not live in the same social
circle.
(Merriman enters, pushing a small trolley.
It holds a tablecloth, a teapot, some milk,
sugar, plates of cakes, muffins, teacake,
bread and butter, and some plates.
Cecily is about to reply but doesn't while
the servant is there)
Merriman: Shall I set the table for afternoon
tea here as usual, miss?
Cecily: (Sternly, in a calm voice) Yes, as
usual.
(Merriman begins to lay the cloth on the table.
There is a long pause.
Cecily and Gwendolen look angrily at each
other)
Gwendolen: Are there many interesting walks
near here, Miss Cardew?
Cecily: Oh, yes, a great many.
From the top of one of the hills one can see
five counties.
Gwendolen: Five counties!
I don't think I should like that; I hate crowds.
Cecily: (Sweetly) I suppose that is why you
live in town.
(Gwendolen doesn't answer and taps her foot
nervously on the ground)
Gwendolen: (Looking around) This is quite
a well-kept garden, Miss Cardew.
Cecily: I'm glad you like it, Miss Fairfax.
Gwendolen: I had no idea there were any flowers
in the country.
Cecily: Oh, flowers are as common here, Miss
Fairfax, as people are in London.
Gwendolen: Personally, I cannot imagine how
anyone manages to live in the country - if
anybody who is anybody does.
The country always bores me to death.
Cecily: Would you like some tea, Miss Fairfax?
Gwendolen: (Extremely politely) Yes, thank
you.
(To herself) Hateful girl!
But I want some tea!
Cecily: (Sweetly) Sugar?
Gwendolen: No, thank you.
Sugar is not fashionable anymore.
(Cecily looks angrily at her, picks up the
sugar tongs and puts four lumps of sugar into
the cup)
Cecily: (Severely) Cake or bread and butter?
Gwendolen: (In a bored way) Bread and butter,
please.
Cake is not seen in the best houses nowadays.
Cecily: (Cutting a very large slice of cake
and putting it on the tray which Merriman
is holding) Give that to Miss Fairfax.
(Merriman gives Gwendolen the cake and goes
off.
Gwendolen drinks some tea and makes a face.
She puts down her cup, reaches out her hand
for the bread and butter, looks at it and
finds that it is cake.
She stands up angrily)
Gwendolen: You have filled my tea with lumps
of sugar.
And, though I asked for bread and butter,
you have given me cake.
I am known to be sweet-tempered, but I warn
you, Miss Cardew, you may go too far.
Cecily: (Standing up) I would go any distance
to save my poor, innocent, trusting boy from
being trapped by a girl like you.
Gwendolen: I have distrusted you from the
moment I saw you.
I felt you were false and deceitful.
I am never wrong in such matters.
My first impressions of people are always
right.
Cecily: It seems to me that I am keeping you
from other appointments.
No doubt you have many other similar calls
to make in the area.
(Jack enters)
Gwendolen: (Seeing him) Ernest!
My own Ernest!
Jack: Gwendolen!
Darling!
(Offering to kiss her)
Gwendolen: (Drawing away from Jack) Wait a
moment!
May I ask if you are engaged to be married
to this young lady?
(Pointing to Cecily)
Jack: (Laughing) To dear little Cecily?
Of course not!
What could have put such an idea into your
pretty little head?
Gwendolen: Thank you.
You may kiss me.
(Offering her cheek)
Cecily: (Very sweetly) I knew there must be
some kind of misunderstanding, Miss Fairfax.
The gentleman whose arm is at present around
your waist is my guardian, Mr Jack Worthing.
Gwendolen: I beg your pardon?
Cecily: This is Uncle Jack,
Gwendolen: (Pulling away from Jack) Jack!
Oh!
(Algernon enters)
Cecily: Here is Ernest.
Algernon: (Going straight to Cecily without
noticing anyone else) My own love!
(Offering to kiss her)
Cecily: (Drawing away from Algernon) Wait
a moment, Ernest!
May I ask you - are you engaged to be married
to this young lady?
Algernon: (Looking around) To what young lady?
Good heavens!
Gwendolen!
Of course not!
What could have put such an idea into your
pretty little head?
Cecily: Thank you.
(Offering her cheek) You may kiss me.
(Algernon kisses her)
Gwendolen: I felt there was some slight error,
Miss Cardew.
The gentleman whose arm is at present around
your waist is my cousin, Mr Algernon Moncrieff.
Cecily: (Breaking away from Algernon) Algernon
Moncrieff!
Oh!
(The two girls move towards each other and
put their arms around each other's waists
as if for protection)
Are you called Algernon?
Algernon: I cannot deny it.
Cecily: Oh!
Gwendolen: Is your name really Jack?
Jack: (Standing rather proudly) I could deny
it if I liked.
I could deny anything if I liked.
But my name certainly is Jack.
It has been Jack for years.
Cecily: We have both been terribly deceived.
Gwendolen: My poor wounded Cecily!
Cecily: My poor wronged Gwendolen!
Gwendolen: (Slowly and seriously) Please will
you call me 'sister'.
(They embrace.
Jack and Algernon groan and walk up and down)
Cecily: (Rather brightly) There is just one
question I would like to ask my guardian.
Gwendolen: A very good idea!
Mr Worthing, there is just one question I
would like permission to ask you.
Where is your brother Ernest?
We are both engaged to be married to your
brother Ernest so it is important for us to
know where he is at present.
Jack: (Slowly and hesitantly) Gwendolen - Cecily
- it is very painful for me but I must speak
the truth.
It is the first time in my life that I have
been in such a painful position and I am quite
inexperienced at doing this.
However, I will tell you honestly that I have
no brother Ernest.
I have no brother at all.
I have never had a brother in my life and
I don't intend ever to have a brother in the
future.
Cecily: (Surprised) No brother at all?
Jack: (Cheerfully) None!
Gwendolen: (Severely) Did you ever have a
brother of any kind?
Jack: (Pleasantly) Never.
Not of any kind.
Gwendolen: I am afraid, Cecily, that neither
of us is engaged to be married to anyone.
Cecily: It is not a very pleasant position
for a young girl suddenly to find herself
in, is it?
Gwendolen: Let us go into the house.
They will not follow us into the house, will
they?
Cecily: No, men are so cowardly, aren't they?
(They go into the house, after looking scornfully
at the men)
Jack: I suppose that this awful business is
what you call Bunburying, is it?
Algernon: (Laughing) Yes, and it's the best
Bunburying I have ever done in my life.
Jack: Well, you have no right to Bunbury here.
Algernon: That is absurd.
One has a right to Bunbury wherever one chooses.
Every serious Bunburyist knows that.
Jack: What are you saying?
Serious Bunburyist?
Good heavens!
Algernon: Well, one must be serious about
something if one wants to enjoy one's life.
I am serious about Bunburying.
I have no idea what you are serious about
- I suppose you are serious about everything.
Jack: Well, the only satisfaction I get from
this awful business is that you won't be able
to Bunbury anymore.
Your friend, Bunbury, is quite finished.
You won't be able to run away from town to
the country quite so often now, Algy.
And that's a very good thing.
Algernon: Your brother isn't very well, is
he, Jack?
Dead, in fact.
You won't be able to run away to town from
the country quite so often now.
And that's a very good thing too.
Jack: And you have behaved very badly towards
Miss Cardew.
I must say that deceiving a sweet, simple
girl like Cecily is very wicked of you.
To say nothing of the fact that she is my
ward.
Algernon: I must say that deceiving a brilliant,
clever young lady like Miss Fairfax is very
wicked of you.
To say nothing of the fact that she is my
cousin.
Jack: I wanted to be engaged to Gwendolen,
that is all.
I love her.
Algernon: Well, I simply wanted to be engaged
to Cecily.
I adore her.
Jack: There is certainly no chance of you
marrying Miss Cardew.
Algernon: I don't think there is much chance
of you marrying Miss Fairfax, Jack.
(Sitting at the table and beginning to eat
muffins)
Jack: I can't understand how you can sit there
calmly eating muffins when we are in this
awful trouble.
You seem to me to be perfectly heartless.
Algernon: Well, I can't eat muffins in an
agitated manner.
The butter would probably get on my cuffs.
One should always eat muffins calmly.
It is the only way to eat them.
Jack: I think that it is perfectly heartless
to be eating muffins at all in the circumstances.
Algernon: When I am in trouble, eating is
the only thing which makes me feel better.
Indeed, when I am in very great trouble, I
refuse everything except food and drink.
At present, I am eating muffins because I
am unhappy.
Besides, I like muffins.
(Standing up)
Jack: (Standing up) Well, that is no reason
why you should eat them all.
(Taking the plate of muffins from Algernon)
Algernon: (Offering Jack teacake) Please will
you have teacake instead.
I don't like teacake.
Jack: Good heavens!
I think a man may eat his own muffins in his
own garden.
Algernon: But you just said that it was perfectly
heartless to eat muffins.
Jack: I said it was perfectly heartless of
you to eat muffins.
That is very different.
Algernon: Maybe.
But the muffins are the same.
(Taking the plate of muffins from Jack)
Jack: Algy, I wish you would go.
Algernon: You can't ask me to go without giving
me some dinner.
I never go without my dinner.
Besides I have just arranged with Canon Chasuble
to be baptized at a quarter to six.
I am going to be baptized with the name of
Ernest.
Jack: My dear fellow, no you aren't.
That is nonsense.
I arranged with Canon Chasuble to be baptized
myself at half-past five.
I will, of course, take the name Ernest.
Gwendolen would want me to.
We cannot both be baptized with the name Ernest.
It's absurd.
Besides, I have a right to be baptized if
I like.
There is no evidence that I have ever been
baptized.
I think it very likely that I never was and
so does Canon Chasuble.
It is different for you.
You have been baptized already.
Algernon: Yes, but that was years ago.
Jack: Yes, but you have been baptized.
That is the important thing.
Algernon: Yes indeed.
So I know my health can bear it.
I must say I think that it is rather dangerous
for you to be baptized now.
It might make you very unwell.
You can't have forgotten that a close relative
very nearly died in Paris this week of a bad
cold.
Jack: Yes, but you said yourself that a bad
cold was not hereditary.
Algernon: I know it didn't use to be - but
it probably is now.
Science is always making wonderful improvements.
Jack: (Picking up the muffin plate) Oh that
is nonsense.
You always talk nonsense.
Algernon: Jack - muffins again!
I wish you wouldn't.
There are only two left.
(Taking them) I told you I was particularly
fond of muffins.
Jack: But I hate teacake.
Algernon: Then why on earth do you serve teacake
to your guests?
I don't like your ideas of hospitality.
Jack: Algernon!
I have already told you to go.
I don't want you here.
Why don't you go?
Algernon: Because I haven't finished my tea
yet!
I have one muffin left.
(Jack groans and sits down.
Algernon continues eating)
ACT THREE
(The living room at the Manor House.
Gwendolen and Cecily are at the window looking
out into the garden)
Gwendolen: They have not followed us into
the house, as anyone else would have done.
They must be ashamed.
Cecily: They have been eating muffins.
That looks like repentance to me.
Gwendolen: (After a pause while she thinks
about what Cecily has said) They don't seem
to notice us at all.
Couldn't you cough?
Cecily: But I haven't got a cough.
Gwendolen: They're looking at us.
How dare they!
Cecily: They're coming towards us.
How presumptuous of them.
Gwendolen: Let us remain silent and dignified.
Cecily: Certainly.
It is the only thing to do now.
(Jack enters, followed by Algernon.
They are whistling the tune of a popular song)
Gwendolen: This dignified silence is rather
unpleasant.
Cecily: Yes, I agree.
It is.
Gwendolen: But we will not be the first to
speak.
Cecily: Certainly not.
Gwendolen: Mr Worthing, I have something to
ask you.
Your reply is extremely important.
Cecily: Gwendolen, I value your common sense.
Mr Moncrieff, I would be grateful if you would
answer the following question.
Why did you pretend to be my guardian's brother?
Algernon: In order that I might have the opportunity
of meeting you.
Cecily: (To Gwendolen) That seems a satisfactory
explanation, does it not?
Gwendolen: Yes, dear, if you can believe him.
Cecily: I don't believe him.
But it is a wonderful answer.
Gwendolen: That is true.
If you are talking about something very serious,
the style of what you say is much more important
than the sincerity.
Mr Worthing, why did you pretend to have a
brother?
Was it in order that you could come to town
as often as possible to see me?
Jack: Can you doubt that, Miss Fairfax?
Gwendolen: I have very strong doubts.
But I intend to ignore them.
(Going closer to Cecily) Their explanations
appear to be quite satisfactory, especially
Mr Worthing's.
His answer seems to me to be particularly
truthful.
Cecily: I am very happy with what Mr Moncrieff
said.
The sound of his voice alone makes me feel
certain that I should believe him.
Gwendolen: Then, do you think we should forgive
them?
Cecily: Yes...
I mean no.
Gwendolen: I agree!
I had forgotten something.
We have ideals which we must not ignore.
Which of us should tell them?
The task is not a pleasant one.
Cecily: Could we not both speak to them at
the same time?
Gwendolen: That is an excellent idea!
I nearly always speak at the same time as
other people.
Are you ready?
Cecily: Certainly.
(Gwendolen beats time with a finger as if
she is conducting an orchestra)
Gwendolen and Cecily: (Speaking together)
Your first names are a problem that cannot
be solved.
That is all!
Jack and Algernon: (Speaking together) Our
first names!
Is that all?
But we are going to be baptized later this
afternoon.
Gwendolen: (To Jack) Are you really prepared
to do this terrible thing for my sake?
Jack: I am.
Cecily: (To Algernon) Are you really prepared
to face this awful ordeal to please me?
Algernon: I am!
Gwendolen: How absurd to talk about the equality
of the sexes!
Men are infinitely better than us at self-sacrifice.
Jack: We are!
(Getting hold of Algernon's hand)
Cecily: They have moments of courage of which
we women know nothing.
Gwendolen: (To Jack) Darling!
Cecily: (To Algernon) Darling!
(They fall into each other's arms.
Merriman enters.
When he sees the situation, he coughs loudly)
Merriman: Ahem!
Ahem!
Lady Bracknell is here.
Jack: Good heavens!
(Lady Bracknell enters.
The couples separate very quickly.
Merriman goes off)
Lady Bracknell: Gwendolen!
What does this mean?
Gwendolen: It means that I am engaged to be
married to Mr Worthing, Mama.
Lady Bracknell: Come here.
Sit down.
Sit down immediately.
(To Jack) I learnt of Gwendolen's sudden departure
from her trusted maid, who gave me the information
after I had given her a small coin.
I followed her at once on the next train.
Her father does not know where she is and
I don't propose to tell him the truth.
In fact, I never tell him the truth about
anything.
I would consider it wrong to do so.
You must understand that all communication
between you and my daughter must stop immediately.
On this point, as indeed on all points, I
am firm.
Jack: I am engaged to be married to Gwendolen,
Lady Bracknell!
Lady Bracknell: You are not, sir.
And now...
Algernon...!
Algernon: Yes, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: Is this the house in which
your invalid friend Mr Bunbury lives?
Algernon: (Finding it difficult to speak)
Oh!
No!
Bunbury doesn't live here.
Bunbury is somewhere else at present.
In fact, Bunbury is dead.
Lady Bracknell: Dead!
When did Mr Bunbury die?
His death must have been extremely sudden.
Algernon: Oh!
I killed Bunbury this afternoon...
I mean poor Bunbury died this afternoon.
Lady Bracknell: What did he die of?
Algernon: Bunbury?
Oh he was quite exploded.
Lady Bracknell: Exploded?
Was he the victim of a terrorist plot?
I was not aware that Mr Bunbury was interested
in politics.
If so, he deserved his punishment.
Algernon: My dear Aunt Augusta, I mean that
he was found out!
What I mean is the doctors found out that
Bunbury could not live - so he died.
Lady Bracknell: He seems to have had great
confidence in his doctors' opinions.
I am glad, however, that he made up his mind
to do something definite and acted on proper
medical advice.
And now, Mr Worthing, may I ask: who is that
young person whose hand my nephew Algernon
is holding?
He is holding it, I may add, in a most unnecessary
way.
Jack: The lady is Miss Cecily Cardew, my ward.
(Lady Bracknell bows coldly to Cecily)
Algernon: I am engaged to be married to Cecily,
Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: I beg your pardon?
Cecily: Mr Moncrieff and I are engaged to
be married, Lady Bracknell.
Lady Bracknell: (Shivering, then moving over
to the sofa and sitting down) I do not know
whether there is anything very exciting about
the air in Hertfordshire, but the number of
engagements being made seems to be considerably
above the expected average.
I think that it would be a good idea for me
to make some preliminary enquiries.
Mr Worthing, is Miss Cardew connected with
any of the larger railway stations in London?
I am merely asking for information.
I did not know until yesterday that there
were families or persons who were related
to railway stations.
Jack: (Speaking in a cold, clear voice) Miss
Cardew is the granddaughter of the late Mr
Thomas Cardew of 149 Belgrave Square, London;
of Gervase Park, Dorking, Surrey; and also
of The Sporran, Fifeshire, Scotland.
Lady Bracknell: That sounds not unsatisfactory.
Three addresses always inspire confidence.
But I have no proof that they are real.
Jack: Miss Cardew's family lawyers are Markby,
Markby and Markby.
Lady Bracknell: Markby, Markby and Markby?
They are lawyers in the very highest position
of their profession.
Indeed I know that one of the Mr Markbys is
occasionally to be seen at dinner parties.
I am almost satisfied.
Jack: (Very irritably) How extremely kind
of you, Lady Bracknell!
I have also got, you will be pleased to hear,
certificates of Miss Cardew's birth, baptism
and confirmation of vaccinations for whooping
cough and the measles - both German and English.
Lady Bracknell: Ah!
A busy life, I see.
Though perhaps it has been too exciting for
a young girl.
I do not believe a young girl should have
too many experiences.
(Standing up and looking at her watch) Gwendolen!
We must leave.
We have not a moment to lose.
Since I am making enquiries, Mr Worthing,
I had better ask you if Miss Cardew has any
personal fortune.
Jack: Oh!
She has an investment of a hundred and thirty
thousand pounds in Government Stocks, so her
annual income is very large.
That is all.
Goodbye, Lady Bracknell.
So pleased to have seen you.
Lady Bracknell: (Sitting down again) Just
a moment, Mr Worthing.
A hundred and thirty thousand pounds!
And in Government Stocks!
Miss Cardew seems to me to be a very attractive
young lady, now that I look at her.
Few girls today have any good qualities which
last and improve with time.
We live in a time, sadly, when beauty is the
only important thing.
(To Cecily) Come here, dear.
(Cecily goes to her) You are a pretty child!
Your dress is not very fashionable and your
hair has not been styled very well.
But we can soon alter that.
An experienced French maid will produce a
very good result in a short time.
I remember recommending one to Lady Lancing
and after a few months her own husband did
not know her.
Jack: After a few months nobody knew her.
Lady Bracknell: (Glaring at Jack, then pretending
to smile at Cecily) Turn round, sweet child.
(Cecily turns completely round in a circle)
No, I want to see you from the side.
(Cecily turns round so that Lady Bracknell
can see her: face in profile from the side)
Yes, very good.
There is much about your situation which is
promising - you could fit well into good society.
Hold your chin a little higher, dear.
Chins are worn very high at present.
Algernon!
Algernon: Yes, Aunt Augusta!
Lady Bracknell: There is much about her situation
which is promising - she could fit well into
good society.
Algernon: Cecily is the sweetest, dearest,
prettiest girl in the whole world.
And I don't care about her fitting into good
society.
Lady Bracknell: Do not be dismissive of good
society, Algernon.
Only people who can't get into good society
speak like that.
(To Cecily) Dear child, of course Algernon
has no money.
He has nothing but his debts to bring to a
marriage.
But I do not approve of marrying for money.
When I married Lord Bracknell, I had no fortune
at all, but I didn't allow that to stand in
my way.
Well, I suppose I must give my consent to
this marriage.
Algernon: Thank you, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: Cecily, you may kiss me!
Cecily: (Kissing her) Thank you, Lady Bracknell.
Lady Bracknell: You may also call me Aunt
Augusta in future.
Cecily: Thank you, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: The marriage ought to take
place quite soon.
Algernon: Thank you, Aunt Augusta.
Cecily: Thank you, Aunt Augusta.
Lady Bracknell: I do not approve of long engagements.
They give people a chance to find out about
each other's character before marriage, which
I think is never advisable.
Jack: I beg your pardon, Lady Bracknell, but
their engagement is not acceptable.
I am Miss Cardew's guardian and she cannot
marry without my consent until she comes of
age.
I will not give my consent.
Lady Bracknell: Why, may I ask?
Algernon is an extremely eligible young man.
He has nothing, but he looks as if he has
everything.
What more can one want?
Jack: I am very sorry to have to say this
to you, Lady Bracknell, but the fact is that
I do not approve of his character.
I suspect that he is devious.
(Algernon and Cecily look at him, amazed and
indignant)
Lady Bracknell: Devious?
My nephew Algernon?
Impossible!
He was educated at Oxford University.
Jack: There can be no doubt about it.
This afternoon, while I was away in London,
he was allowed into this house because he
said he was my brother.
While pretending to be my brother, he drank,
I am informed by my servant, a complete bottle
of very good quality champagne which I was
keeping especially for myself.
He also succeeded in turning my ward against
me.
He then stayed to tea and ate every muffin
we had.
He behaved completely heartlessly.
And what is worse, he knew that I don't have
a brother, that I have never had a brother
and that I don't intend to ever have a brother
of any kind.
He knew because I told him so myself yesterday
afternoon.
Lady Bracknell: (Coughing) Ahem!
Mr Worthing, after thinking about this carefully,
I have decided to forget about the way my
nephew behaved towards you.
Jack: That is very good of you, Lady Bracknell.
I have decided, however, not to change my
mind.
I will not give my consent.
Lady Bracknell: (To Cecily) Come here, sweet
child.
(Cecily goes to her) How old are you, my dear?
Cecily: Well, I am really only eighteen, but
I always say I am twenty when I go to parties.
Lady Bracknell: You are perfectly right to
make a small alteration.
Indeed, no woman should ever be quite accurate
about her age.
It looks so devious.
(Speaking again, thoughtfully) Well, it will
not be very long before you come of age.
So I don't think your guardian's consent is
very important.
Jack: Excuse me for interrupting you again,
Lady Bracknell.
I must tell you that, according to her grandfather's
will, Miss Cardew does not come of age until
she is thirty-five.
Lady Bracknell: That does not seem to me to
be a problem.
Thirty-five is a very attractive age.
London society is full of women who have,
by their own free choice, remained thirty-five
for years.
Lady Dumbleton is an example.
She has been thirty-five ever since she reached
the age of forty, which was many years ago.
Our dear Cecily will be even more attractive
at the age of thirty-five than she is at present.
She will have even more money then than she
has now.
Cecily: Algy, could you wait for me till I
was thirty-five?
Algernon: Of course I could, Cecily.
You know I could.
Cecily: Yes, I believe that you could, but
I couldn't wait all that time.
I hate waiting even five minutes for anybody.
It always makes me rather cross.
I am not punctual myself but I do like other
people to be punctual.
Waiting, even to be married, is quite out
of the question.
Algernon: Then what are we going to do, Cecily?
Cecily: I don't know, Mr Moncrieff.
Lady Bracknell: My dear Mr Worthing, Miss
Cardew states that she cannot wait till she
is thirty-five - a remark that tells me she
has a rather impatient nature - however, I
beg of you to think again about your decision.
Jack: My dear Lady Bracknell, the decision
is entirely in your own hands.
When you consent to my marriage with Gwendolen,
I will gladly consent to your nephew's marriage
with my ward.
Lady Bracknell: (Standing and looking very
tall) You must know that your marriage with
my daughter is not possible.
Jack: Then none of us can look forward to
ever getting married.
Lady Bracknell: I cannot agree to Gwendolen
never getting married.
Algernon, of course, may choose for himself.
Come, dear, (Gwendolen stands up) we have
already missed five, if not six, trains.
(Canon Chasuble enters)
Chasuble: Everything is quite ready for the
baptisms.
Lady Bracknell: The baptisms?
Is it not a little early for baptisms?
First marriage, then children, then baptisms!
Chasuble: (Looking puzzled, and pointing at
Jack and Algernon) Both these gentlemen have
said they wish to be baptized immediately.
Lady Bracknell: Baptized?
At their age?
The idea is ridiculous and quite irreligious.
Algernon, I forbid you to be baptized.
My husband, Lord Bracknell, would be very
displeased to hear that you were wasting your
time and money like this.
Chasuble: Do I understand you correctly?
Is neither of you gentlemen to be baptized?
Jack: I don't think that baptism would be
much use to either of us at the moment, Canon
Chasuble.
Chasuble: I am very sorry to hear you say
so, Mr Worthing.
That sounds like the view of an irreligious
man.
I have written four unpublished sermons on
this subject.
However, since you have decided to ignore
religion for now, I will return to the church
where Miss Prism has been waiting for me for
an hour and a half.
Lady Bracknell: (Looking shocked and sitting
down again) Miss Prism?
Did I hear you say 'Miss Prism'?
Chasuble: Yes, Lady Bracknell.
I am going to the church to join her now.
Lady Bracknell: Please wait a moment, Canon
Chasuble.
This is something which may be important to
Lord Bracknell and myself.
Is this Miss Prism a rather ugly female who
is remotely connected with education?
Chasuble: (Rather indignantly) She is a very
respectable lady.
Lady Bracknell: It must be the same person.
May I ask what position she has in your household?
Chasuble: (Severely) I am celibate, madam.
Jack: Lady Bracknell, Miss Prism has been
Miss Cardew's valued governess and companion
for the last three years.
Lady Bracknell: I must see her at once.
Let her be sent for.
Chasuble: (Looking offstage) She's approaching.
She's nearly here.
(Miss Prism enters very quickly)
Miss Prism: I was told you were coming to
the church, dear canon.
I have been waiting there for an hour and
three-quarters.
(Seeing Lady Bracknell, who is glaring at
her, Miss Prism turns pale.
She looks round her as if she wants to escape)
Lady Bracknell: (In a severe voice, as if
she is a lawyer in a courtroom) Prism!
(Miss Prism lowers her head, looking ashamed)
Come here, Prism!
(Miss Prism approaches looking nervous) Prism!
Where is that baby?
(Everyone looks horrified.
The canon takes a step backwards.
Algernon and Jack pretend to be anxious to
stop Gwendolen and Cecily from hearing something
shocking) Prism, twenty-eight years ago, you
left Lord Bracknell's house, Number 104, Upper
Grosvenor Square, London, in charge of a pram
containing a baby boy.
You never returned.
A few weeks later, after a police investigation,
the pram was discovered at midnight in a remote
part of the city.
It contained the manuscript of a very bad
three-volume novel.
(Miss Prism looks indignant) But the baby
was not there.
(Everyone looks at Miss Prism) Prism, where
is that baby?
(There is a pause)
Miss Prism: Lady Bracknell, I am ashamed to
say I don't know.
I wish I did.
These are the facts.
On the morning of that day, a day I will remember
forever, I prepared as usual to take the baby
out in the pram.
I had with me a large old handbag in which
I had intended to put the manuscript of a
three-volume novel that I had written.
In a moment of forgetfulness, for which I
can never forgive myself, I put the manuscript
in the pram and the baby in the handbag.
Jack: (Who had been listening very carefully)
But where did you put the handbag?
Miss Prism: Do not ask me, Mr Worthing.
Jack: Miss Prism, this is very important to
me.
I must know where you put the handbag which
contained the baby.
Miss Prism: I left it in the cloakroom of
one of the larger railway stations in London.
Jack: Which railway station?
Miss Prism: (Looking very miserable) Victoria.
(Sitting down slowly on an armchair)
Jack: I must go to my bedroom for a moment.
Gwendolen, wait for me here.
Gwendolen: If you are not too long, I will
wait for you all my life.
(Jack leaves, very excited)
Chasuble: What do you think this means, Lady
Bracknell?
Lady Bracknell: I dare not guess, Canon Chasuble.
You must know that strange coincidences are
not supposed to happen in families with a
high position in society like ours.
They are not appropriate.
(Noises are heard above as if someone is throwing
boxes around.
Everyone looks up)
Cecily: Uncle Jack sounds very agitated.
Lady Bracknell: The noise is extremely unpleasant.
Chasuble: (Looking up) It has stopped now.
(The noises start again, sounding even louder)
Lady Bracknell: I wish he would stop.
Gwendolen: The suspense is terrible.
I hope it will last.
(Jack enters, with a black leather handbag
in his hand)
Jack: (Rushing over to Miss Prism) Is this
the handbag, Miss Prism?
Examine it carefully before you speak.
The happiness of more than one person depends
on your answer.
Miss Prism: (Calmly) It seems to be mine.
Yes, here is the damage which happened in
an accident on a bus.
Here is the stain caused by a drink which
exploded at Leamington.
And here, near the lock, are my initials.
I had forgotten that I had had them put there.
The bag is definitely mine.
I am delighted to have it returned to me so
unexpectedly.
It has been inconvenient not to have it all
these years.
Jack: (In a pathetic voice) Miss Prism, you
have had more returned to you than the handbag.
I was the baby you placed in it.
Miss Prism: (Amazed) You?
Jack: (Embracing her) Yes...
Mother!
Miss Prism: (Pulling away from him indignantly)
Mr Worthing, I am unmarried.
Jack: Unmarried!
That is a serious problem.
But who has the right to speak badly of someone
who has suffered?
Why should society treat men and women differently?
Mother, I forgive you.
(Trying to embrace her again)
Miss Prism: (Now even more indignant) Mr Worthing,
you are wrong.
(Pointing to Lady Bracknell) There is the
lady who can tell you who you really are.
Jack: (After a pause) Lady Bracknell, would
you kindly inform me who I am?
Lady Bracknell: I am afraid that my news may
not please you.
You are the son of my poor sister, Mrs Moncrieff,
and therefore Algernon's elder brother.
Jack: Algy's elder brother!
Then I have a brother after all.
I knew I had a brother!
I always said I had a brother!
Cecily - how could you ever have doubted that
I had a brother?
(Getting hold of Algernon and leading him
around the room) Canon Chasuble, here is my
unfortunate brother.
Miss Prism, my unfortunate brother.
Gwendolen, my unfortunate brother.
Algy, you will have to treat me with more
respect in the future.
You have never behaved to me like a younger
brother should.
Algernon: Well, I haven't done until today.
I did my best, though.
(They shake hands)
Gwendolen: (To Jack) My own - but my own - what?
What is your name, now that you are not Jack
Worthing?
Jack: Good heavens!
I had forgotten about my name.
I suppose that you won't change your mind
about your favourite name?
Gwendolen: Never!
Jack: Then the question must be cleared up
at once.
Aunt Augusta, had I been baptized?
Lady Bracknell: Your loving parents had done
everything for you, including baptism.
Jack: Then I was baptized!
That is clear.
Now what name was I given?
Let me know the worst!
Lady Bracknell: You were the elder son so
you were given your father's name.
Jack: (Irritably) Yes, but what was my father's
name?
Lady Bracknell: (Thoughtfully) I cannot at
present remember what the general's name was.
But I have no doubt that he had one.
Jack: Algy!
Can't you remember what our father's name
was?
Algernon: My dear fellow, we never even spoke
to each other.
He died before I was a year old.
Jack: His name will appear in the Army Lists
of that period, I suppose, Aunt Augusta?
Lady Bracknell: The general was a man of peace,
except in his domestic life.
So I have no doubt that his name will appear
in an Army List.
Jack: The Army Lists for the last forty years
are here.
I should have read them all!
(Rushes over to a bookcase and pulls lots
of books out) Mmm... generals...
Mallam, Maxbohm, Magley - what awful names
they have - Markby, Migsby, Mobbs, Moncrieff!
Lieutenant: 1840, Captain, Lieutenant-Colonel,
Colonel, General: 1869: names Ernest John.
(Putting down the book and speaking quite
calmly) I always told you, Gwendolen, that
my name was Ernest, didn't I?
Well, it is Ernest after all.
I mean it really is Ernest.
Lady Bracknell: Yes, I remember now that the
general called you Ernest.
I knew I had a reason for disliking that name.
Gwendolen: Ernest!
My own Ernest!
I felt from the first time I met you that
you could have no other name!
Jack: Gwendolen, it is terrible for a man
to find out suddenly that he has been speaking
the truth all his life.
Can you forgive me?
Gwendolen: I can.
Because I feel that you are going to change.
Jack: My own darling!
Chasuble: (To Miss Prism) Laetitia!
(Embracing her)
Miss Prism: (Enthusiastically) Frederick!
At last!
Algernon: Cecily!
(Embracing her) At last!
Jack: Gwendolen!
Lady Bracknell: My nephew, you seem to be
displaying signs of a lack of seriousness.
Jack: On the contrary, Aunt Augusta, I've
now realized for the first time in my life
the Importance of Being Earnest.