CHAPTER ONE
Death to the King
The news came one Saturday morning from a
young woman who sounded very upset and spoke
with a strong foreign accent.
"Yes, hello, police?
You must come.
He is dead!
His skin is cold and there is blood all over
the floor.
You must come here as soon as possible, please!"
Detective Inspector Evans had just arrived
at the office and was listening to a recording
of the telephone call.
There was always a lot of crime in London
on a Friday night, but he was not prepared
for what he was about to hear.
The operator was very calm and asked for the
woman's name and location.
She was calling from a mobile phone.
"My name is Helena Kowalska.
I have just come to work...
I am the cleaner at a nightclub called 'Lust'
in Charing Cross.
I am sorry, but my English is not very good.
When will you be here?"
"We'll send someone over as soon as we can,
Mrs Kowalska," the operator replied.
"Please stay where you are and let me take
some more information.
Do you know who the dead person is?"
"Of course!"
she exclaimed.
"It is the big boss.
He has shot himself.
The gun is still in his hand."
Inspector Evans could not believe his ears.
"The big boss?" he repeated after the recording
had ended.
"Does that mean what I think it means?"
Some people were nodding their heads in answer;
others shrugged.
Could Stanley Cooper really be dead?
Stanley Cooper was not only the owner of Lust,
but a notorious crime lord who ran a large
chain of bars and nightclubs in London's West
End.
He also owned a dog track in Walthamstow.
The Metropolitan Police called him the "King
of the Underworld" because they believed that
he and his gangsters were responsible for
much of the violence in the area.
Unfortunately for them, they had no solid
proof.
"The call came in less than twenty minutes
ago," said a deep female voice.
"The forensics team are already on their way
to examine the crime scene.
Evans, you should go and join them.
Something tells me that Cooper didn't kill
himself, and if I'm right, this is going to
be your case."
It was Superintendent Fisher, the officer
in charge of the station.
She was a very powerful woman, and everything
she said sounded like an order.
"Yes, ma'am," replied Inspector Evans.
"I'll take Sandra with me, if that's okay.
We've both been working on cases involving
Cooper's gang lately."
"That was going to be my next suggestion,
Evans," the superintendent growled.
"I want you to treat this death as suspicious
from the start.
Don't leave any stone unturned when you're
down there."
"Of course not, ma'am."
"Where is Checchino, anyway?
It's not like her to be late.
Find her and get going!"
"Right away, ma'am," the inspector said and
left the room.
Detective Inspector Sandra Checchino was sitting
in the staff kitchen when Inspector Evans
burst into the room.
"Ah, Sandra, there you are!"
She looked up from her large cup of coffee
in surprise.
"Oh, it looks like someone had a long night
last night!"
Evans said in a friendly tone.
Inspector Checchino smiled weakly.
"Yes, you could say that, Gary.
I just haven't had time to put on any make-up."
"Never mind, you look no worse without it,"
he joked.
"Anyway, you've just missed some important
news.
You'll never believe what happened last night!"
Inspector Checchino waited for him to continue.
"We've got to go and see our friend Stanley
Cooper!" he said.
"Oh, no, not again!"
she groaned and looked back down at her coffee.
"That man never cooperates.
He won't tell us anything.
What have he and his thugs done this time?"
"That's what we have to find out," DI Evans
replied mysteriously.
"But you are right about one thing: Cooper
definitely won't be telling us anything today,
that's for sure.
He's been found dead in his office at Lust.
It looks like suicide."
Inspector Checchino opened her eyes wide.
"Mamma mia!" she said in a parody of her Italian
relatives.
"Stanley Cooper's dead?
We should get going right away."
She quickly drank what was left of her coffee,
which was still rather hot, and walked out
of the kitchen with Inspector Evans.
The nightclub looked like a small building
from the outside.
The entrance was between two bars on a narrow
side street of Charing Cross Road.
Large, colourful posters on the door advertised
which disc jockeys were playing on which nights,
and red neon lights above the door spelt out
in elaborate letters the word "Lust".
"This would be a nice place for a first date,"
Inspector Evans said, smiling at Inspector
Checchino.
"Look, we missed DJs Mad Daddy and Divine
Lickz last night!"
"You and your jokes," she replied flatly.
"I think we're both a bit too old for places
like these, don't you?"
"I certainly am, but you're still young, free
and single, Sandra.
You'd quickly find yourself a date in a place
like this."
"Don't make me laugh.
I'm thirty-five next month.
And we meet enough thugs at work - I don't
want to date one as well."
"Lust is very exclusive," said Inspector Evans.
"Well, it is if you compare it to Cooper's
other bars, at least..."
The uniformed policeman who was guarding the
entrance smiled and let the pair inside.
They walked down the stairs, past the cloakroom
and into the bar area.
The air was heavy with the smell of alcohol,
and the floor was littered with empty bottles
and cigarette stubs.
It was quite sticky underfoot.
The large, pink leather sofas against the
walls looked very out of place in the daylight
that shone through the tall windows.
"Nice decor," Inspector Checchino whispered
sarcastically.
A young woman wearing jeans and a jumper was
sitting on one of the silver and red bar stools.
She did not notice the two police officers
entering the room, because she was busy talking
on her mobile phone in a loud voice.
"That must be the cleaner," said Inspector
Evans, who spoke a few words of Polish.
"We'll talk to her later.
Come on, let's go and see our man."
Although she was an experienced investigator,
Inspector Checchino always felt a sense of
dread before seeing dead bodies, and today
was no exception.
Her colleague, on the other hand, seemed to
be nothing but happy about Stanley Cooper's
death.
The forensics team were busy taking photographs
when Inspectors Evans and Checchino entered
the office.
"It's really true, then, the King has snuffed
it?"
Inspector Evans asked.
Near the back of the office, a man's head
appeared from behind the desk and grinned.
"A single shot to the brain," he said as he
stood up.
It was Vash Singh, one of the forensics experts.
His thick glasses made his eyes look as large
as saucers.
"There's no sign of a struggle at all," he
said.
"Just look around this room; you can see for
yourselves how tidy it is."
The office looked completely normal - apart
from the two legs that were sticking out from
behind the desk.
Inspector Evans walked up to look at the rest
of the body.
"Hmm, it's certainly less tidy at this end
of the room, that's for sure," he said solemnly.
Stanley Cooper's body was lying face up in
a pool of blood.
His mouth was open, and his arms were resting
on either side of his fat chest.
The inspector's eyes moved directly to the
gun in the man's left hand.
"So, what do you think, Vash?
Is it really possible that he shot himself?"
"I'd say so, Gary," he replied.
"It does look like suicide, but we still can't
rule out murder.
There'll have to be a full ballistic analysis.
We can only guess the facts until then."
"Does it look like the body's been moved at
all?"
Vash shook his head.
"There's a lot of blood here, but it's all
in one place," he said.
Inspector Checchino walked over from the doorway
and looked at the body.
The dead man had short, grey hair and a big
moustache that sat above his top lip like
a lazy caterpillar.
Even dead, he still has the same arrogant
expression on his face, she thought.
"Do you have any idea when this happened?"
she asked.
Vash pushed his glasses up his nose and explained
that the body had already been a little stiff
when they had arrived just after ten o'clock.
They had also measured the temperature.
"I'd say he died between 5 a.m. and 6 a.m.,"
he concluded.
"And you've found nothing unusual at all?"
she continued.
Vash shrugged.
"I wouldn't expect his arms to be in that
position if he shot himself," he said, "but
on the other hand, it's not impossible."
"Well, you've been trying to bring this man
to justice for a long time, Sandra," said
Inspector Evans.
"It looks to me like someone may have helped
you out."
"Maybe," she said quietly, staring at the
dead man's arms.
Then one of the other forensics experts said
that there was something interesting about
Cooper's shirt: she had noticed a small amount
of lipstick on the collar when she was taking
photographs of the body.
Inspector Checchino was examining a computer
monitor in the corner of the office.
It showed sixteen small pictures of the main
rooms in the nightclub from different angles,
including the office they were standing in.
It also showed two more pictures of the street
outside.
"There should be a lot of evidence on this,
Gary," she said, pointing at the security
camera footage.
Inspector Evans looked at the screen and scratched
his head.
"Hmm," he replied slowly.
"There might have been if someone hadn't switched
it off.
Look, it's not recording."
CHAPTER TWO
Find the Woman
"Sorry to keep you waiting, Mrs Kowalska,"
Inspector Evans began.
"Could you begin by telling us what the nightclub
was like when you came to work this morning?"
"Everything looked normal," she replied, looking
him in the eye.
"The doors were locked, and the lights were
off.
The sign outside was still turned on, but
that happens quite often."
"Is there an alarm system fitted here?" he
asked.
Inspector Checchino was noting down the information
and looked up at the cleaner when she did
not reply.
"Do you have an alarm?"
Evans repeated.
"Yes.
Sorry, I do not understand everything you
say," Helena said.
"The alarm was turned off when I arrived.
I thought that the big boss was here, or the
manager.
They sometimes stay in the office and play
poker until the morning."
"I see.
Can you tell me the manager's name, please?"
"Omar Omari," the cleaner smiled.
"He is such a charming man, Inspector.
He is always very friendly to me."
"How many other people work here at the club?"
"I'm not sure.
I do not know most of them personally," Helena
replied slowly.
"There is a list of names and telephone numbers
on the notice board.
I can give you a copy."
"That would be very helpful, thank you," he
said.
"It would also help us a great deal if you
could answer a few more questions."
The cleaner sighed a little and looked at
her watch.
"I must do some work," she complained.
"I have two more places to go to this morning."
"I'll try to be brief, Mrs Kowalska.
Have you heard of any arguments involving
Stanley Cooper recently?"
The young lady shook her head.
"I do not see the big boss often.
And when I do, he does not tell me anything
like that."
"I see, but maybe you've heard other people
talking about him?"
"You should talk to Omar," she replied.
"He knows much more about his private life.
In fact, he sometimes complains that he is
too - hmm, what is the word?
- too involved in it."
Inspector Evans paused and looked across at
his colleague.
"I didn't necessarily mean his private life,
Mrs Kowalska.
Do you know anything about any business deals,
for example?
Or have you heard any rumours involving other
gangs?"
"Gangs?"
she repeated, shocked.
"Oh no!
I am sorry, I really have nothing to do with
any of that.
I'm just the cleaner here."
The police had been knocking for five minutes
when Omar Omari finally opened the front door
to his apartment in North London.
His wild, curly hair was hanging over his
eyes, and he was only half dressed.
He did not seem at all surprised by the news
of his boss's death.
"So the dirty old swine is dead?" he laughed.
"He had that coming."
"Please take this seriously, Mr Omari," Inspector
Checchino said sternly.
"We're talking about a man's life - and possibly
a very serious crime."
"What do you mean by 'possibly'?" he asked.
"We're still trying to find out exactly what
happened last night," she said calmly.
"May we come inside?"
"Why, of course.
Do come on in, Officers," the man said with
exaggerated politeness.
"Take a seat in the lounge and I'll be right
with you."
The pair sat down on an old, blue futon that
was covered in large stains.
Omar came back a minute later wearing a white
T-shirt.
He was also carrying a rolled-up pair of socks
which he put on as the police began their
interview.
"Could you begin by telling us when you left
work last night, Mr Omari?"
Inspector Checchino asked in a tolerant voice.
"Yes, it was a really busy night and I stayed
until the end.
We had some great DJs playing - Mad Daddy
was there, you know - so it was an important
event for us all.
It went really well."
He brushed his hair away from his eyes and
looked at the two inspectors, who both seemed
to be expecting him to say more.
"Oh, I was there until about 4:30, I suppose,"
he finally answered.
Inspector Checchino wrote down the information.
"Did anybody see you leave?"
she asked.
"At that time in the morning?
No.
At least, nobody I know.
I got the night bus back up here."
"Hmm.
Well, what can you tell us about Stanley Cooper
- was he alone when you left the club?"
"No.
A man called Bruno Tartufo was in the office
with him all night," he explained.
"He's the boss's right-hand man.
They're almost always together, and he was
still there when I left."
"And apart from yourself, Mr Omari, how many
people have access to Mr Cooper's office?"
Inspector Checchino asked.
Omar did not flinch.
"I only go in there when I'm invited.
Normally I work in my own office across the
hall, but I know some people who don't have
to wait for an invitation, if you know what
I mean."
The young man grinned at the two inspectors
with perfect white teeth.
They looked back at him expressionlessly,
not understanding what was so amusing.
"Well, it's what they always say at the start
of a police investigation, isn't it?
Cherchez la femme!
And I can tell you right away that Cooper
had a young lady friend: a Miss Kim Watt.
She had him wrapped around her little finger"
"Kim Watt?"
repeated Inspector Checchino.
"Yes, Kim Watt the Kumquat, I call her - a
fruity little thing.
She manages Cooper's dog track in Walthamstow.
But I've seen her in Lust quite a lot lately,
too.
She always comes to the bar as soon as she
arrives and pours herself a gin and tonic,
the little madam."
"Did you see her at the club last night?"
Omar shook his head and brushed back his hair
again.
"Who else would Mr Cooper let into his office?"
asked the inspector, who suddenly felt there
was something strangely attractive about the
club manager.
"Just his idiot henchmen, I guess.
They do everything for Cooper, and they have
keys to all of his bars and clubs.
Faithful as dogs, they are - and just as stupid."
Inspector Evans laughed a little and took
down the men's names.
"Now then," he continued, "has anything happened
lately that could have made Stanley Cooper
someone's enemy?"
"Lots!"
Omar exclaimed.
"And you're asking the right person, let me
tell you!
He tried to get me involved in some of his
'business activities' outside the nightclub,
but I didn't want to have anything to do with
it."
"Is that what Helena Kowalska meant when she
said that you knew about his private life?"
Inspector Checchino wondered aloud.
"Ah, Helena," sighed Omar, "She doesn't know
the half of it.
But yes, I've told her some things in private.
The boss wanted me to 'take a message to a
client' in Walthamstow.
I'm not paid to go on dangerous missions like
that, though!"
"One last thing, Mr Omari," said Inspector
Evans towards the end of the interview.
"Do you know how to operate the security camera
system at Lust?"
"Of course," he replied.
"I'm the manager there, aren't I?
Actually, I don't have to do very much at
all.
It runs automatically, you see.
The cameras are connected to a computer that
saves the videos for a month, and then they're
deleted."
"Someone stopped the computer from recording
last night," the inspector explained.
"Have you any idea who that might have been?"
Omar blinked at him.
"No.
But it seems like a sensible thing to do if
you're going to commit a crime, doesn't it?"
he said dryly.
"Is it possible that there's another copy
of the videos somewhere?"
Inspector Evans continued.
"For example, is the footage sent to another
company, or to Mr Cooper's home computer?"
"Nope," said Omar simply.
"His house is the one place that is totally
secure.
Bad Manor Park.
I've heard that it's like Fort Knox there!"
"Bruno Tartufo!"
repeated Inspector Evans after they left the
apartment.
"This isn't the first time we've heard that
name lately."
The Metropolitan Police were trying to fight
the sale of cocaine in and around the West
End, and several unimportant members of a
drugs ring had mentioned Tartufo.
"Another fine Italian citizen in the city
of London," said Inspector Checchino ironically.
"We're not related, before you say anything."
Inspector Evans was more interested in finding
Tartufo than making jokes.
He radioed the station.
"I need addresses for Bruno Tartufo and Kim
Watt," he said.
"And make sure that the family liaison officer
reaches Stanley Cooper's daughter before the
Polish cleaner starts to gossip!"
Later that day, towards the midafternoon,
the two detectives drove to an elegant town
house in Chelsea.
It was the address of the third and last Kim
Watt in central London.
The first two had said that they did not know
anything about anyone called Stanley Cooper,
The pair had also tried to speak to Bruno
Tartufo, but there was nobody home, Inspector
Evans walked up the three white marble steps
leading to the large, black front door, rang
the bell and waited.
The voice that eventually came through the
intercom was as sweet as honey.
"Hello?" she asked, her voice almost seductive,
"Who's there?"
"Police, ma'am," replied the inspector with
a small smile, "Please open up!"
The first thing the police saw on the other
side of the door was a tall redhead with a
surprised expression on her face.
Her lips were painted bright red, Moments
later; a short man with a thin moustache entered
the hallway and stood next to her.
He looked at the police and put his arm around
the woman, "Miss Watt?"
Inspector Evans began, "Yes?"
"We've come to talk to you about Stanley Cooper,
May we come inside for a moment?"
"Hah!
You've caught him at last, have you?"
joked the small man in an unmistakably Italian
accent.
"Bruno, be quiet!"
Kim hissed,
"Ah, and you must be Mr Tartufo!"
the inspector smiled, "We have a lot to discuss."
CHAPTER THREE
A Headless Organization
After over an hour of interviews, Inspectors
Evans and Checchino left Kim Watt's house
in Chelsea and set off back to the station.
They talked about their impressions on the
way.
"I never thought the notorious Bruno Tartufo
would be such a short man!"
began Inspector Evans.
"Even you're taller than him, Sandra!"
She gave a little laugh, but kept her eyes
fixed on the road.
"Don't be fooled," she said, "small people
can be dangerous."
"I didn't like the way he was staring at Kim
whenever she spoke," her colleague continued.
"He was intimidating her.
Do you think she was telling the truth?"
"People like her are never honest about everything,
Gary," she replied, "but she did take the
news about Cooper very badly."
"For a few moments, maybe, then she was perfectly
normal again.
I know she says she was at the dog track in
Walthamstow all evening, but that closed just
after midnight, and she has no alibi for the
time of the shooting."
"Not many people will have an alibi that they
can prove, Gary.
After all, it was between five and six o'clock
in the morning.
I'm sure that you and I were asleep like most
other people in London, but nobody can prove
that either, can they?"
Inspector Evans turned to his colleague and
grinned.
"Only because you've turned me down so often,
Sandra.
I know better than to ask you out on a Friday
night now."
Inspector Checchino laughed in amusement.
"Oh, come off it!
You're a good friend, but we tried that once,
if you remember.
It would never work."
"I know, I know," he said.
"You can't blame me for trying, though."
There was a short pause in the conversation.
"What about Bruno?" he asked.
Inspector Checchino frowned.
"Hmm, yes, what about him?"
she agreed.
"He didn't appear at all shocked by the news.
And I find it very suspicious that he says
he left the nightclub at exactly 5 a.m., don't
you?"
The car came to a halt at some red traffic
lights, and she looked Inspector Evans in
the eye.
"Moments before Cooper was killed," he agreed,
scratching his chin.
"But Bruno says that his boss was expecting
a visitor and that he wanted to be alone when
that person arrived.
That's why he left the club at that time."
"So he says, yes," sighed Inspector Checchino.
"I don't believe that story for a second.
It's very convenient for Bruno, isn't it?"
Inspector Evans nodded slowly.
"It is, yes.
But it could be convenient for us that we
found him at Kim Watt's house today.
According to Omar, she was going out with
Cooper, wasn't she?
So, what do you think she was doing with Bruno
on a Saturday afternoon?"
Back at the police station, the two detectives
met Superintendent Fisher to discuss their
findings.
She listened to everything they had to say,
but she was not interested in the smaller
details: her favourite football club Arsenal
was playing at 5:30 p.m., and she was planning
to watch the game from start to finish.
"Let's be realistic," she said.
"Although it's very likely, we still don't
have any solid proof that Cooper didn't kill
himself.
And it won't be hard to find a lot of people
who had a good reason to want that man dead.
I'm sure even you two are pleased that he's
gone."
"You're right, ma'am," said Inspector Evans.
"And although we've collected some statements
from the people nearest to him today, it will
take a few days to compare what they've said
against whatever evidence there is."
"Right," she said.
"So let's call it a day and enjoy what's left
of the weekend."
Inspector Checchino remained quiet and followed
Inspector Evans out of the superintendent's
office.
On Monday morning, Inspector Checchino arrived
at work a good hour before Inspector Evans.
She had not been able to sleep well, and she
wanted to see what developments had taken
place over the weekend.
An incident room had been set up at the station
to collect all the information related to
Stanley Cooper's death.
The inspector was in there reading through
the reports when her colleague finally turned
up.
"So, have you heard?"
she asked her colleague, her face red with
anger.
"Good morning, Sandra!
Nice to see you, too," he said ironically.
"It's not like you to be here before me on
a Monday."
"Sorry.
Good morning, Gary," she smiled.
"Well, have you?"
"Obviously not.
What have you got for me?"
"To begin with, there was an arson attack
at Lust late last night.
The fire brigade think that someone broke
a window and set fire to a can of petrol.
You saw all the soft furniture in there: it
went up like a match.
The fire's destroyed everything inside."
"What?!
How did that happen?
Didn't we have an officer guarding the club
all weekend?"
"Only until the club manager locked up after
the forensics team had finished investigating
the scene," Inspector Checchino explained.
"That was on Saturday evening."
"I see," Inspector Evans said.
"And do you have any idea why someone might
want to burn down one of Cooper's clubs?"
"Well, it was too late to destroy the evidence.
My first thought was that Omar Omari might
have had something to do with it, but then
I read these."
She passed Inspector Evans a pile of paper.
"Three people in the north of the city have
reported the theft of their greyhounds.
Altogether we have six expensive racing dogs
to find."
"Why should we care about some kidnapped dogs?"
he asked.
Then he remembered.
"I suppose I don't need to ask what connects
these animals to Stanley Cooper, should I?"
"Probably not, no," said Inspector Checchino.
"The owners race them at Cooper's track in
Walthamstow.
And, as we learnt on Saturday, Kim Watt is
the manager there."
"What do we know about the owners - are they
friends?"
"One of them is Kim's brother.
The other two were close friends of Cooper's.
And when I say 'friends', I mean that both
were in his gang."
"Ah.
But why would someone target the dogs and
not the people?" asked DI Evans.
"Well, for a start, each greyhound is worth
at least 40,000 pound's.
And all six are meant to be racing at an event
tonight, so it will be very bad for business
if they aren't there."
"Sorry if I'm being a bit slow," he replied,
"but what do these dogs have to do with the
fire at Lust?
What's the connection?"
Inspector Checchino took the papers back and
put them on the desk.
"I think it was a symbolic act," she said.
"It's typical for gangs.
Just think about it: Lust was Cooper's most
prestigious nightclub, and it's where all
the best DJs went to play.
Whoever the killer was, he didn't only want
to kill the king, he wanted to destroy his
palace, too.
Kidnapping the dogs adds insult to injury
for Cooper's gang.
If we find the dogs, we will probably find
our killer,"
"You may have a good point there, Sandra.
But I need to wake up properly with a coffee
before looking at this more closely.
Can I get you one, too?"
Nobody knew exactly how many security cameras
there were in the city of London, but there
were a lot.
There were cameras on every main road and
in every underground station; they were also
installed on every bus to fight vandalism,
terrorism and other crimes.
A team of junior officers were watching the
camera footage from all of the night buses
that left Trafalgar Square for Finchley in
North London early on Saturday morning.
It was a boring job, but it was the only way
to find out if Omar Omari was telling the
truth: he had told the police that he could
not remember exactly which bus he had taken,
but that he normally got on the 134 or the
N13.
Meanwhile, Inspectors Evans and Checchino
were reviewing the videos from Lust.
There was a lot of footage on the hard disk
from Friday night.
Finally, they saw Bruno Tartufo leave the
building just before 5 a.m.
The recording was turned off five minutes
later.
"I don't believe it!"
cried Inspector Evans.
"He really did leave the club before Cooper
was shot!"
"Hmm...," his colleague said quietly, "but
did he return?"
They repeated the last ten minutes of footage
in Cooper's office.
It was a strange feeling to watch the monitor.
Inspector Checchino thought it was as if one
of the dead had come back to life and was
walking around the room.
The two detectives watched Cooper point to
the door, at which point the short Italian
man turned and left the room.
Cooper then took out his mobile phone and
made a call that lasted only a few seconds.
He was smiling.
After he put his phone back into his pocket,
he waddled up to the computer in the corner,
looked up at the camera, and the screen went
black.
"He turned off the recording himself!"
she exclaimed in surprise.
"Why would he do that?"
"I'd say it's fairly obvious that he was about
to do something that he wanted to keep secret,"
replied Inspector Evans dryly.
"What do you mean?"
"Well, it could have been anything.
A secret business deal, a meeting with an
important drug trafficker... maybe even a
meeting with a mystery lady friend?"
Inspector Checchino laughed.
"A mystery woman?
Do you really think that someone as unattractive
and disgusting as Stanley Cooper could manage
two women?"
He was about to reply when one of the junior
officers shouted across the room: "I've found
him!"
She had identified the bus that Omar Omari
got onto after work on Saturday morning.
The club manager had been correct that it
was the 134 to Finchley, but he had got the
time wrong.
According to the clock on the screen, it was
already 5:30 a.m. when he left Trafalgar Square.
"A whole hour later?"
Inspector Checchino thought aloud.
"A lot can happen in sixty minutes..."
CHAPTER FOUR
A Smoking Gun
Inspector Checchino was more patient than
Inspector Evans.
She told him that it would be a bad idea to
rush to visit Omar Omari again.
They should wait until there was some solid
proof that he had returned to the scene, she
said.
"Why do you and Fisher always talk about waiting?"
he complained.
"We should bring him in for questioning before
he disappears!"
In the end, the pair spent most of Monday
interviewing the other people who worked at
Lust, but it proved to be pointless.
Everyone had gone home before the manager
left, and nobody could remember anything unusual.
Two other officers had spoken with the staff
at Cooper's bars and his other clubs.
Most of them had very little to say.
They all respected their boss a great deal,
it seemed - or they were still afraid of him,
even though he was dead.
The only noteworthy report came from one of
the women
seen her boss smoking outside a bar in Soho
at around 3:30 a.m.
Kim had forgotten to mention this fact when
the inspectors had visited her in Chelsea.
According to her own statement, she had stayed
at work until shortly after 1 a.m. and then
driven back home.
"We should go and speak to her again right
away!"
Inspector Evans said when he heard the report.
"You wanted to do the same with Omar Omari
a few hours ago, Gary," sighed Inspector Checchino.
"We can't go around accusing everyone of lying
to us."
"Well, one of them is hiding something," he
growled.
"At least one of them."
Their conversation was interrupted when the
telephone on Inspector Evans' desk rang.
It was Vash Singh calling from the forensics
department.
He said that he had some important news for
the investigators.
The two detectives always enjoyed talking
to Vash, who could explain things in a lively
and interesting way.
When they walked into his office this time,
Vash was holding a plastic skull in one hand
and a pencil in the other.
"You should have been an actor," said Inspector
Evans.
"You'd make a good Hamlet."
"Just take a seat and listen to what I have
to tell you," he smiled.
"First of all, we can definitely rule out
suicide now.
Look, the bullet must have gone in at this
angle."
He was pointing the pencil at the left temple,
but it was nowhere near square against the
skull.
"How can you be sure it was murder?" asked
Inspector Checchino.
"Stanley Cooper was left-handed, and the revolver
in his hand was six inches long.
Just look at the trajectory."
Inspector Evans put his hands in the position
that Vash was describing.
"You're right," he agreed.
"I wouldn't try to commit suicide like this.
It's too difficult."
He turned to Inspector Checchino, who was
staring at the skull.
"I'd either put the gun inside my mouth or
hold it here, just above my ear, wouldn't
you?"
Inspector Checchino sighed a little.
"I haven't really thought about how I would
shoot myself, Gary, but you're both right,
yes."
"So," Vash continued, "now you probably think
that someone was standing in front of him,
and not to his side?"
Inspectors Evans and Checchino both nodded.
"You're wrong!"
Vash exclaimed.
"Neither Cooper nor the killer were standing
up.
We found no traces of blood near head height
in the room, and none on the desk either.
But there is something very revealing about
the few small spots on the back wall of the
office."
He showed the inspectors a photograph of the
bloodstains.
"Take a look.
The stains on this picture suggest that Cooper's
head was about two feet above the ground when
he was shot."
"So he was kneeling?"
the inspector asked.
"Someone made him beg for his life?"
"No, the blood is too low down for that as
well," Vash explained.
"I think he was lying down, which would also
explain the position of the body."
Inspector Evans remembered seeing Cooper's
body on the office floor in Lust.
It was true that he did not appear to have
fallen to the ground: both of his arms were
resting on either side of his chest.
"Do you mean the killer was lying on top of
him?" he asked.
"That would explain the lipstick on his shirt
as well, don't you think?"
Vash suggested.
"Cherchez la femme!"
The inspectors exchanged looks.
"Did anyone ever find Cooper's mobile phone?"
asked Inspector Checchino.
"We know that he made a call shortly before
he was shot, but we have no idea whose number
he dialled.
We asked his telephone company, and they said
that it belongs to a pay-as-you-go phone that
hasn't been registered."
Vash shook his head.
"We didn't find anything else in the office
that could help you," he explained.
"Apart from one thing, that is.
You haven't asked about the really important
clue that we're quite excited about."
"What's that?"
the two inspectors asked simultaneously.
"Whoever shot Stanley Cooper wanted it to
look like a suicide, so they left the gun
and the shell casing on the scene.
Of course there is no licence for the gun,
but the bullet was quite rare.
The ballistics expert says that fewer than
five percent of revolvers use this type.
Interestingly, they're more popular in Eastern
Europe.
There's a large factory near Warsaw."
"He was killed by a Polish bullet?" asked
Inspector Evans, surprised.
"Not necessarily, no.
The same bullets are available in Britain
as well, but they're not used very much."
"The cleaner is Polish," the inspector continued,
ignoring what Vash was saying.
"I bet she knows some people in Cooper's gangs,
too.
I thought it was strange that someone who
visits a place like Lust so often knew so
little about the people there."
Inspector Checchino smiled at Vash and turned
to her colleague with an irritated look.
"Will you stop accusing everyone, Gary!"
she complained.
"First it was Bruno, then Omar, then Kim,
and now you want to accuse Helena Kowalska!"
"I want to speak to them all again," he replied
stubbornly.
"We should start with the women.
After all, that lipstick on his collar must
have come from somewhere."
"But it could have been there for days," Inspector
Checchino said.
"I don't think Stanley Cooper was the most
hygienic man to walk this planet..."
Kim Watt was alone when the detectives arrived
at her house early that evening.
She opened the door with the same surprised
look on her face that they had seen on their
previous visit.
"Do you mind if we ask you a few more questions
about Friday night, Miss Watt?" asked Inspector
Evans.
"Of course not!
Please come in," she said.
She led them through the hall-way to the large
kitchen at the back of the house and offered
them a seat at the table.
"Would you like some tea, Officers?"
she asked politely.
"Oh, that would be great, thank you!" said
Inspector Evans happily.
Inspector Checchino was slightly irritated
by the woman trying to be the perfect hostess
and kicked her colleague's leg under the table.
"Miss Watt," she began, coming straight to
the point, "we have received a report that
you were in central London after 3 a.m. on
the night that Stanley Cooper was shot.
Is there a reason why you failed to tell us
this on Saturday?"
Kim put down the kettle and turned to the
two inspectors.
She was biting her lip nervously and did not
say a word.
"I've got nothing to hide," she said after
a long pause.
"Please just tell us the truth," said Inspector
Evans, who thought that the woman seemed much
more natural than she did when they had first
met.
"You have to understand that this is something
I just couldn't tell you the other day.
Not with Bruno right beside me..."
She stopped speaking and took a cigarette
out of the box that was lying next to the
sink.
"I did go into town after work, it's true.
I was going to go to Lust, but Omar told me
not to, because a lot of the people there
know Bruno.
And Bruno himself was there all night on Friday.
So I went to a salsa bar that I like instead.
It's only a few minutes away from Charing
Cross, and I waited there until Omar finished
work."
"Do you remember what time that was?" asked
the inspector.
"Oh, about 4 a.m.," Kim Watt replied.
There was another awkward pause in the conversation.
Inspector Evans cleared his throat.
"We know that Mr Omari left Trafalgar Square
at 5:30 a.m. on the 134 bus to Finchley, Miss
Watt," he said.
"Can you tell us where you and he were before
that time?"
The woman began to blush.
Her pale cheeks were soon almost as red as
her flame-coloured hair.
"We...
we visited a hotel where one of Omar's friends
works as a night manager.
There are always some empty rooms, and he
lets us use one from time to time, It's just
a bit of fun!"
CHAPTER FIVE
The Fight for Justice
Superintendent Fisher entered the incident
room on Tuesday after she walked past and
saw that Inspectors Evans and Checchino were
laughing inside.
"What's so funny, you two?"
she asked impatiently.
"It's been over three days now and you've
found more questions than answers!"
The two detectives tried to look serious,
but Inspector Evans burst out laughing again.
"Sorry ma'am," he said.
"It's a private joke."
The superintendent noticed Inspector Checchino
lifting her hand from Inspector Evans' shoulder.
"Never mind that," she answered.
"You need to get to the bottom of this case
before these gangs get out of control."
There had been more violence on Monday night.
Bruno Tartufo had attacked two of Cooper's
henchmen, and they were in hospital.
"We're doing our best, ma'am," said Inspector
Checchino.
"We found out today that both the bar manager
and the woman that Cooper was seeing have
a solid alibi.
They were recorded entering and leaving a
hotel."
"Who are your other suspects?" asked Superintendent
Fisher.
"For a moment we thought the cleaner might
have been involved," explained Inspector Evans,
smiling slightly.
"She has keys to the nightclub, and she's
polish."
"Polish?"
"Well, like the bullets that Vash told us
about," Inspector Evans continued, "But we
looked into her background today, and it's
true that she and her family have nothing
to do with any gangsters as far as we can
tell."
Inspector Checchino was trying to give the
impression that they had more to work with.
"There's still a big question mark over Bruno
Tartufo," she said, "He was the last person
on the scene, and nobody can prove his alibi."
"And we are watching him very closely," added
Inspector Evans, "He's going to be at Cooper's
funeral with the rest of the gang at four
o'clock today."
"Fine," the superintendent replied shortly,
"Just make sure that nobody sees members of
the police attending the funeral of one of
London's biggest criminals!"
"Any news about the search warrant, ma'am?"
asked Inspector Checchino, "Do we have permission
to go to Bruno's house yet?"
"Yes, we should have it ready before the end
of the afternoon."
With that, Superintendent Fisher turned around
and left the incident room.
Inspectors Evans and Checchino drove to the
crematorium in an unmarked car and waited
outside the gates.
They arrived half an hour early so that they
could watch the crowd.
Some mourners were already there; many others
soon turned up and formed a long line of black
suits and overcoats outside the building.
"I don't like these places at all, Gary,"
said Inspector Checchino quietly when the
hearse drove up to the door of the crematorium.
"Nobody likes funerals," he smiled.
"But I think we can be pleased that Stanley
Cooper has danced his last dance, don't you?"
"I suppose so," she said quietly.
"Come on, Sandra, just think about it.
You always said he was a monster.
Secretly we both know that he deserved whatever
happened on Friday night.
Remember all those drug-related killings last
year?
Only someone as evil as him could have ordered
so many executions.
Omari was right: he had it coming."
Inspector Checchino was silent and watched
six fat men lift the coffin onto their shoulders.
"He was behind so many other crimes as well,
and we all knew it.
How many cases have we worked on over the
past few years?"
"...And he always got away," she said, speaking
over her colleague.
This conversation was practically a routine,
but the tense was now new.
Stanley Cooper was history.
"If we're lucky, his gang will be powerless
soon," he continued.
"I..."
"I feel sick," she said suddenly, interrupting
him.
Inspector Evans looked across at her in surprise
as she opened the door and stepped out of
the vehicle.
"I just need some fresh air," she said, looking
back into the car.
"The air conditioning in there is making me
nauseous!"
The inspector watched her walk along the grass
with one eye fixed on her long, slim legs.
After a moment, he thought he saw two people
in the crowd staring at Sandra, too.
They looked as if they could have been Bruno
Tartufo's brothers.
"I think you've got a couple of admirers here,"
Inspector Evans said when Inspector Checchino
finally returned and got into the car.
"What are you talking about?"
"There were two men staring at you.
Didn't you see?"
"Oh...
no, not really.
This place is full of criminals today, though,
Gary.
I'm sure we've met them all before at one
time or another."
They sat and waited for the funeral to end.
Inspector Evans wanted to see whether any
fights would break out between the mourners,
or whether any more gangsters would come to
cause trouble.
After twenty minutes of near silence, a call
came through on the radio.
It was a sergeant at the station who had just
made an arrest.
"We've caught the person who set fire to Lust,
sir!"
she said in excitement.
"It was Bruno Tartufo's younger brother, Alessio.
He says that Cooper's gang has divided into
two groups: one led by Bruno and the other
by a thug in Walthamstow.
This second gang forced him to destroy the
club in order to save his family.
He's been very helpful so far because he wants
us to protect him."
"Protect him?
What do you mean, we should protect him?"
"From the other gang, sir, but from his brother,
too.
He says that lately Bruno has been a dangerous
man to be around.
He's also told us who kidnapped those dogs.
Apparently Bruno is keeping them in his cellar
as some kind of trophy, but he wants to either
sell them or shoot them.
He sees himself as the next big cheese!"
"Let's get going!" said Inspector Checchino.
"We should go to Tartufo's house before he
gets back from this funeral."
Bruno Tartufo owned a large house in Chelsea
that was twice as large as Kim Watt's.
The two detectives did not yet have a search
warrant, but they had a good reason to believe
that a crime was taking place in the cellar.
It meant they could go inside.
The old Italian woman who let them in did
not ask many questions.
When she said that she did not have a key
to the cellar, Inspector Evans kicked open
the door without thinking twice.
Immediately, six brown dogs ran up the stairs
and jumped all over him.
One even started to lick his face as if it
were a giant ice cream.
During the chaos that followed, Inspector
Checchino carefully stepped downstairs into
the darkness of the cellar.
It was her only chance, and she decided to
take it.
She slowly pulled out a small box from her
coat pocket and placed it on a table at the
far end of the room.
It contained around two dozen bullets that
she had bought undercover on the black market.
As she turned around to leave the cellar,
a hand came out of the shadows and landed
on her shoulder.
"Sandra," said a concerned voice, "what the
hell are you doing?!"
She looked up at Inspector Evans, who was
shaking his head in disbelief.
He had a bad feeling about what she was about
to say.
"I was just taking a look at these bullets,"
she began.
"Don't lie to me!
I saw you put them there."
Inspector Checchino paused and looked around
the room.
"Gary, we've been trying all year to bring
Cooper to justice, but he always got away.
You know how he operated.
He always had a puppet in place to take the
blame for what he did.
And Bruno is no better - he would kill his
own mother."
"I can't believe this!" he hissed.
"That's not how justice works!"
"Justice?
Let me tell you about justice, Gary.
I'm sure you don't remember a young man who
committed suicide in Camberwell twelve months
ago," she began.
"No, I can't say that I do.
There are a lot of suicides in London."
"You're right, there are.
But this wasn't really a suicide.
Everyone just assumed that it was..."
"How can you know that?" he asked.
"Who are you talking about?"
"It was a university student," Inspector Checchino
said flatly.
"Matthew Puglisi."
Inspector Evans looked her in the eye.
He moved his hand down from her shoulder to
her hand and squeezed it.
"He wasn't just a student, was he?" he asked
calmly.
"No, Gary," she said and looked down at the
floor, "He... he was my nephew.
He was killed one year ago on Friday night."
Inspector Checchino looked back up at Inspector
Evans with tears in her eyes.
"He was my nephew, and he told me that he
was in trouble with some drug dealers at a
nightclub in Charing Cross.
I think you can guess which one.
He'd even received some death threats, but
he was too afraid to talk to the police - apart
from me, that is."
"Are you serious?
You were behind the whole thing?"
She thought of the two men at the funeral.
They were her cousins, and they had helped
to arrange her meeting with Cooper.
"Yes, Gary, just little old me.
Cooper let me into the club because he thought
he was going to get some information about
his enemies...
it was easy.
A little charm and a little lipstick go a
long way.
And I thought it would be easy to blame Tartufo.
You know it would."
"Sandra, you must realize that I can't let
it go," he said.
"You can do whatever you want," she replied
quietly.
She was now the one squeezing his hand.
Inspector Evans took a deep breath and sighed.
Inspector Checchino was his friend, but a
murder was a murder.
"We can't all go out there and take an eye
for an eye!" he cried.
"We have Alessio Tartufo now.
He will tell us everything we need so that
we can arrest his brother.
As for you, what can I say?"
"I'm sure you'll do whatever you think is
right, Gary."
He growled and went back upstairs, leaving
Inspector Checchino in
the dark.