CHAPTER ONE
The Time Traveller
The Time Traveller (it will be convenient
to call him this) was talking to us about
geometry.
His grey eyes shone and his usually pale face
was red and excited.
The fire burned brightly and there was that
relaxed after-dinner feeling when thoughts
run freely.
'You must listen carefully.
I shall have to destroy one or two ideas that
almost everyone accepts - for example, the
geometry that they taught you at school.
You know, of course, that a mathematical line,
a line with no thickness, doesn't really exist.
They taught you that?
A mathematical model, which only has length,
width and thickness, doesn't really exist
either.
It's just an idea.'
'That's all right,' said the Psychologist.
'But if you make that model out of a material,'
said Filby, a red-haired man who liked an
argument, 'it exists.
All things exist.'
'Most people think so.
But wait a moment.
Imagine a thing that doesn't last for any
time.
Can it have a real existence?'
Filby looked thoughtful.
'Clearly,' the Time Traveller said, 'a real
body must have length, width, thickness (the
dimensions of space) - and also exist in time.
But through a natural human weakness, we usually
forget the fourth of these.'
'That,' said a very young man, 'is very clear.'
'Well, I don't mind telling you that I have
been at work on this geometry of four dimensions
for some time.
Some of my results are interesting.
Here is a record of the weather.
This line shows the changes in temperature.
Yesterday it was quite high, last night it
fell, then this morning it rose again.
Surely that line is not in any of the dimensions
of space that we generally understand?
It is along the time-dimension.'
'But,' said the Medical Man, looking hard
at the fire,' if time is really only a fourth
dimension of space, why can't we move about
in it as we move in the other dimensions?'
The Time Traveller smiled.
'Are you so sure we can move freely in space?
We can go right and left, backwards and forwards
freely enough.
But up and down?
That isn't so easy.'
'Well, we can move a little up and down,'
said the Medical Man.
'But we can't move at all in time.
We are always in the present moment.'
'That is at the centre of my great discovery.
Why can a modern man not hope that one day
he might travel in time?'
'It doesn't make sense,' said Filby.
'Possibly not,' said the Time Traveller.
'But now you begin to see the reason for my
work on the geometry of four dimensions.
Long ago I had an idea for a machine that
can travel in any direction of space and time,
as the driver wants.'
Filby started to laugh.
'But I have proved this by experiment,' said
the Time Traveller.
'It would be very useful for the historian,'
the Psychologist suggested.
'He could travel back and see how things really
happened!'
'Then there is the future,' said the Very
Young Man.
'Just think!
You could put all your money in the bank,
leave it to grow and hurry on ahead!'
'To discover a society,' I said,' that doesn't
use money.'
'Of all the crazy ideas!'
began the Psychologist.
'It seemed so to me, and I never talked about
it until-'
'An experiment!'
I cried.
'You are going to prove that?'
'Let's see what you can do,' said the Psychologist,
'though I think it's all rubbish.'
The Time Traveller smiled at us.
Then, with his hands deep inside his trouser
pockets, he walked slowly out of the room
and we heard him going down to the laboratory.
The Psychologist looked at us.
'I wonder what he's got?'
'A trick probably,' said the Medical Man,
and Filby tried to tell us about a trick he
had seen once, but before he had really started
his story the Time Traveller came back.
He held something in his hand.
It was made of shiny metal and was not much
larger than a small clock.
And now I must be exact, because unless you
believe his explanation it is impossible to
explain what happened next.
He took one of the small tables in the room
and put it in front of the fire.
On this he placed the machine.
Then he placed a chair next to it and sat
down.
The only other object on the table was a small
lamp, the light of which fell on the model.
I sat in a low chair nearest the fire and
I pulled this forwards so I was almost between
the Time Traveller and the fire.
Filby sat behind him, looking over his shoulder.
The Medical Man watched him from the right;
the Psychologist from the left.
The Very Young Man stood behind the Psychologist.
We were all wide awake.
I cannot believe that a trick was played on
us under these conditions.
'This little thing,' said the Time Traveller,
resting his elbows on the table and pressing
his hands together above the machine, 'is
only a model.
It is my plan for a machine to travel through
time.
You will notice that it looks a little rough,
and this bar has an odd shining appearance
- it looks quite unreal.'
He pointed to this part with his finger.
'Also, here is one little white lever, and
here is another.'
The Medical Man got out of his chair and looked
closely into the thing.
'It's beautifully made,' he said.
'It took two years to make,' said the Time
Traveller.
Then, when we had all had a close look, he
said, 'Now I want you to understand clearly
that this lever sends the machine flying into
the future, and this other one sends it into
the past.
'Soon, I'm going to press the lever and the
machine will disappear into future time.
Have a good look at the thing.
Look at the table too, and satisfy yourself
that there can be no tricks.
I don't want to waste this model and then
be told I'm dishonest.'
There was a minute's pause perhaps.
The Psychologist opened his mouth to speak
to me but closed it again.
Then the Time Traveller put out his finger
towards the lever.
'No,' he said suddenly, pulling his finger
away again.
'Lend me your hand.'
And turning to the Psychologist, he took that
person's hand in his own and told him to put
out his first finger and touch the lever.
So the Psychologist himself sent the model
time machine on its endless journey.
We all saw the lever turn.
I am completely certain there was no trick.
There was a breath of wind and the lamp flame
jumped.
The machine suddenly turned round, looked
unclear, was seen like a ghost for a second
and was gone - disappeared!
Except for the lamp, the table was empty.
Everyone was silent for a minute.
Then the Psychologist recovered from his surprise
and looked under the table.
The Time Traveller laughed cheerfully.
'Well?' he said.
We all stared.
'My friend,' said the Medical Man quietly,
'are you serious about this?
Do you really believe that machine has travelled
in time?'
'Certainly,' said the Time Traveller.
'And I have a big machine nearly finished
in there' - he pointed to the laboratory - 'and
when that is put together I intend to go on
a journey myself.'
'You mean to say that that machine has travelled
into the future?' said Filby.
'Into the future or the past - I'm not completely
sure which.'
After some time the Psychologist said, 'It
has gone into the past if it has gone anywhere.'
'Why?' said the Time Traveller.
'Because I'm quite sure that it hasn't moved
in space, and if it travelled into the future
it would still be here all this time.
It would have to travel through the time that
is passing as we stand here.'
'But,' I said, 'if it travelled into the past,
why wasn't it here when we first came into
this room, and last Thursday when we were
here - and the Thursday before that?'
'Let's be fair - these are serious questions,'
said Filby, turning towards the Time Traveller.
'That can be explained,' the Time Traveller
said to the Psychologist.
'It's there but can't be seen.'
'Of course,' said the Psychologist.
'That's simple enough.
Why didn't I think of it?
We can't see it, in the same way that we can't
see a bullet flying through the air.
If it is travelling through time fifty times
or a hundred times faster than we are, we
can see only one-fiftieth or one-hundredth
of it.'
We sat and stared at the empty table for a
minute or two.
Then the Time Traveller asked us what we thought
of it all.
'It sounds believable enough tonight,' said
the Medical Man, 'but it will seem different
in the morning.'
'Would you like to see the Time Machine itself?'
asked the Time Traveller.
And then, taking the lamp in his hand, he
led the way to the laboratory.
I remember clearly how we all followed him,
and how in the laboratory we saw a larger
copy of the little machine.
It was almost complete, but two bars lay unfinished
on the table and I picked one up for a better
look.
'Now listen,' said the Medical Man,' are you
really serious?'
'In that machine,' said the Time Traveller,
holding the lamp high, 'I intend to travel
in time.
Is that clear?
I was never more serious in my life.'
None of us knew what to say.
I looked at Filby over the shoulder of the
Medical Man and he smiled at me.
CHAPTER TWO
The Traveller Returns
I think at that time none of us really believed
in the Time Machine.
The fact is, the Time Traveller was one of
those men who are too clever to be believed.
You never felt that you knew everything about
him.
You always thought that something was hidden,
that he was playing a trick on you.
If Filby showed us the model and explained
things in the Time Traveller's words, we would
believe him more easily.
We would understand his reasons - because
anyone could understand Filby.
But the Time Traveller had a strong imagination
and we didn't really believe him.
The next Thursday I went to Richmond again
and, arriving late, found four or five men
already in the sitting room.
The Medical Man was standing in front of the
fire with a sheet of paper in one hand and
his watch in the other.
I looked around for the Time Traveller.
'It's half-past seven now,' said the Medical
Man.
'I suppose we'd better have dinner?'
'Where's our host?'
I asked.
'You have just come?
It's rather odd.
He has been delayed.
He asks me in this note to start dinner at
seven if he's not back.
He says he will explain when he comes.'
'It seems a pity to let the dinner spoil,'
said the editor of a well-known daily paper,
and so the Medical Man rang the bell.
Only the Psychologist, the Medical Man and
myself had attended the first dinner.
The other men were the Editor, a journalist
and another - a quiet, shy man with a beard
- who I didn't know.
There was some discussion at the dinner table
about the Time Traveller's absence and I suggested
time travelling, in a half-joking way.
The Editor wanted that to be explained to
him and the Psychologist gave a very dull
description of the 'clever trick' we had seen
a week before.
He was in the middle of this when the door
opened slowly and without noise.
I was facing it and saw him first.
'Well!'
I said.
'At last!'
The door opened wider and the Time Traveller
stood in front of us.
I gave a cry of surprise.
'Oh, my friend!
What's the matter?'
cried the Medical Man, who saw him next.
The others turned towards the door.
He looked very strange.
His coat was dusty and dirty, his hair untidy
and, it seemed to me, greyer - either with
dust or because its colour had gone.
His face was very pale and his chin had a
cut on it.
For a moment he stopped at the door; the light
seemed too strong for his eyes.
Then he came into the room.
He walked slowly, with a bad limp.
He did not say a word, but came painfully
to the table and moved a hand towards the
wine.
The Editor filled a glass and pushed it towards
him.
He drank it and it seemed to do him good because
he looked round the table and smiled a little.
'What have you been doing?' said the Medical
Man.
The Time Traveller did not seem to hear.
'Don't let me worry you,' he said in a tired
voice.
'I'm all right.'
He stopped, held out his glass for more, and
drank it down.
'That's good,' he said.
His eyes grew brighter, and a faint colour
came to his face.
Then he spoke again.
'I'm going to wash and dress, and then I'll
come down and explain things'...
Save me some of that meat.
I'm hungry.'
The Editor began a question.
'I'll tell you soon,' said the Time Traveller.
'I'm feeling strange!
I'll be all right in a minute.'
He put down his glass and walked towards the
door to the stairs.
Standing up in my place, I saw his feet as
he went out.
He had nothing on them except a pair of socks
with holes in them.
They were covered with dried blood.
Then the door closed behind him.
For a minute, perhaps, my mind was empty.
'Strange Behaviour of a Famous Scientist,'
I heard the Editor say, thinking of his newspaper.
'What's happened to him?' said the Journalist.
'I don't understand.'
I thought of the Time Traveller walking painfully
upstairs.
I don't think anyone else had noticed his
limp.
The Medical Man recovered from his surprise
first, and rang the bell for a hot plate.
The Editor picked up his knife and fork and
the Silent Man did the same.
The dinner started again.
Conversation was slow for a minute or two
because we were so surprised.
Then the Editor said, 'Does our friend have
another job, or just a strong imagination?'
'I feel sure it's this business of the Time
Machine,' I said, and continued the Psychologist's
story of our earlier meeting.
The new guests were very surprised and the
Editor said, 'What is this time travelling?
A man couldn't cover himself with dust by
doing something impossible, could he?'
The Journalist, too, refused to believe it,
and started to make a joke of the whole thing.
'Our Special Reporter in the Day after Tomorrow
reports,' he was saying - or shouting - when
the Time Traveller came back.
He was dressed in ordinary evening clothes
and nothing except his tired look reminded
me of the change that had shocked me.
'Well,' said the Editor, laughing, 'these
men say you have been travelling into the
middle of next week.'
The Time Traveller sat down without a word.
He smiled quietly, in his usual way.
'Where's my meat?' he said.
'How nice it is to stick a fork into meat
again.'
'Story!'
cried the Editor.
'Later,' said the Time Traveller.
'I want something to eat first.
I won't say a word until I get some food into
my stomach.
Thanks.
And the salt.'
'One word,' I said.
'Have you been time travelling?'
'Yes,' said the Time Traveller, with his mouth
full.
'I'd give a pound a line for the story in
your own words,' said the Editor.
The Time Traveller pushed his glass towards
the Silent Man, who was staring at his face.
He jumped a little, then poured him some wine.
The rest of the dinner was uncomfortable.
The Journalist tried to relax us by telling
funny stories.
The Medical Man smoked a cigarette and watched
the Time Traveller closely.
The Silent Man seemed nervous, and drank a
lot of wine.
At last the Time Traveller pushed his plate
away and looked round at us.
'I suppose I must apologise,' he said.
'I was so hungry.
I've had a most interesting time.'
He put out his hand for a cigarette.
'But come into the smoking room.
The story is too long to tell over dirty plates.'
And he led the way.
'You have told these men about the machine?'
he said to me, sitting back in his chair and
naming the three new guests.
'But the thing's just a trick,' said the Editor.
'I can't argue tonight.
I don't mind telling the story, but I can't
argue.
I will,' he continued, 'tell you the story
of what has happened to me, if you like, but
you mustn't interrupt.
Most of it will sound like lies, but it is
true - every word of it.
I was in the laboratory earlier, and since
then ... I have lived eight days... days like
no human being ever lived before!
I am very tired, but I shan't sleep until
I have told this thing to you.
But no interruptions!
Is it agreed?'
We all agreed and the Time Traveller began
his story as I have written it down.
He sat back in his chair at first and spoke
slowly.
Afterwards he got more excited.
As I write it down I feel the limits of pen
and ink, and my own limits.
You will read, I expect, with enough attention,
but you cannot see the speaker's white, honest
face in the bright circle of the little lamp,
or hear his voice.
Most of us listeners were in shadow.
At first each looked at the others.
After a time we stopped doing that and looked
only at the Time Traveller's face.
CHAPTER THREE
Forwards in Time
'I told some of you last Thursday how the
Time Machine works, and showed you the actual
thing itself, incomplete in the laboratory.
It is there now, a little damaged by travel,
but not in bad condition.
I expected to finish it on Friday, but when
I had put most of it together, I found that
one piece was too short.
I had to make this again, and the thing wasn't
complete until this morning.
So at ten o'clock today, the first of all
Time Machines began its journey.
'I checked everything, then got into the seat.
I felt a little frightened, but interested
in what was going to happen next.
I took the starting lever in one hand and
the stopping one in the other.
Then I pressed the first and almost immediately
the second.
I felt that I was falling but, looking around,
I saw the laboratory exactly as before.
Had anything happened?
For a moment I thought that my mind had tricked
me.
Then I noticed the clock.
A moment before, it had showed a minute or
two past ten.
Now it was nearly half-past three.
'I took a breath, held the starting lever
with both hands and pushed it harder.
The laboratory became unclear and went dark.
Mrs Watchett, my cook, came in and walked,
without seeing me, towards the garden door.
I suppose it took her a minute or two to cross
the room, but she seemed to move at high speed.
I pressed the lever over to its furthest position.
'The night came, and in another moment came
tomorrow.
The laboratory grew faint and unclear.
Tomorrow night became black, then day again,
night again, day again - faster and faster.
A low and changing sound filled my ears, and
my mind became confused.
'As my speed increased, night followed day
faster and faster.
The faint picture of the laboratory seemed
soon to move away from me.
I saw the sun jumping quickly across the sky,
once every minute, each minute being a day.
I supposed that the laboratory had been destroyed
and I had come into the open air.
The quick changes of darkness and light were
very painful to my eyes.
Then, in the short dark times, I saw the moon
turning quickly through her quarters from
new to full.
'Soon, as I continued, still increasing speed,
the change from night to day became one continuous
greyness.
The sky turned a wonderful deep blue.
The jumping sun became a line of fire, the
moon a fainter line that changed in width.
'The land was difficult to see clearly.
I was still on the hillside where this house
now stands.
I saw trees growing and changing.
They changed from green to brown and back
to green again, grew tall, died and fell.
I saw enormous buildings rise up, then disappear
like dreams.
The speed dials on the machine went round
faster and faster.
The line of the sun moved up and down, from
summer to winter, in a minute or less.
Minute by minute white snow spread across
the world and disappeared, and was followed
by the green of spring.
'The unpleasant feelings at the beginning
now changed into a kind of crazy excitement.
I noticed a strange movement of the machine
from side to side, which I couldn't explain,
but my mind was too confused to pay any attention
to it.
So with a kind of madness growing in me, I
threw myself into the future.
At first I didn't think of stopping.
But then a new feeling grew in my mind - a
sense of fear mixed with the need to know.
'What strange changes had happened to people?
What wonderful improvements to our simple
way of life might appear when I looked more
closely into that world?
I saw large and wonderful buildings growing
in front of me, bigger than ours.
I saw a stronger green colour move up the
hillside, and stay there without any interruption
by snow.
Although I was travelling so quickly, the
world still seemed beautiful, and so my mind
turned to stopping the machine.
'My greatest fear was that there would already
be something in the space when I, or the machine,
stopped.
While I travelled at high speed through time,
this didn't matter much - I seemed to move
like a gas through other things.
But when I stopped, I would put myself into
whatever lay in my way.
Such close contact with the other thing might
cause a great explosion.
I had thought of this possibility again and
again while I was making the machine, but
then I had cheerfully accepted it as one of
the necessary dangers that a man must face.
I wasn't as cheerful now, when I couldn't
escape it.
'The strangeness of everything, the movement
of the machine and the feeling of continual
falling had made me very nervous.
I told myself that I could never stop.
Then, becoming suddenly angry, I decided to
stop immediately.
Like a fool in a hurry, I pulled over the
lever.
The machine turned over and I was thrown through
the air.
'There was the sound of thunder in my ears.
For a moment I forgot what was happening,
then I found myself sitting on soft grass
in front of the machine.
Heavy rain was falling.
Everything still seemed grey, but soon I noticed
that the confusion in my ears was gone.
I looked around me.
I was on a small lawn, surrounded by bushes.
Their purple flowers were dropping under the
beating of the heavy rain.
In a moment I was wet to the skin.
"A fine welcome," I thought, "to a man who
has travelled so many years to see you."
'Soon I stood up and looked around me.
Through the heavy rain I could see an enormous
figure cut, perhaps, out of white stone.
But the rest of the world was unclear.
'As the rain became lighter, I saw the white
figure more clearly.
It was very large - a tree touched its shoulder.
It was shaped a little like a sphinx with
spread wings, and seemed to be flying.
The pedestal seemed to be made of metal, and
had turned green with age.
I stood looking at the figure for some time.
When, at last, I took my eyes from it for
a moment, I saw that the rain was stopping
and the sky was growing lighter.
'Then I suddenly realised the full danger
of my journey.
What might appear when the rain stopped?
What might people be like?
Had they perhaps changed into something inhuman
and very strong?
I might seem like an old-world wild animal,
but more frightening because I looked like
them - a horrible creature to be speedily
killed.
'Already I saw the shapes of enormous buildings,
and a wooded hillside growing clearer through
the dying storm.
I turned quickly to the Time Machine and tried
hard to turn it the right way up.
As I did so, the grey rain suddenly stopped
and the sun shone through the clouds.
My fear grew stronger and I fought hard with
the machine.
It moved under my attack and turned over.
It hit my chin violently.
One hand on the seat, the other on the lever,
I stood breathing heavily, ready to climb
inside it again.
'But now I had a way of escaping, my confidence
recovered.
I looked with more interest and less fear
at this world of the future.
In a round opening, high up in the wall of
the nearest building, I saw a group of figures
wearing soft robes.
They had seen me, and their faces were turned
towards me.
'Then I heard voices coming nearer.
Through the bushes I saw the heads and shoulders
of running men.
One of these appeared on a path leading straight
to the lawn where I stood.
He was quite thin, just over a metre high,
wearing only a long purple shirt tied at the
waist with a leather belt.
Noticing that, I realised for the first time
how warm the air was.
'He seemed to be very beautiful, but also
very weak.
At the sight of him, my confidence returned.
I took my hands from the machine.
CHAPTER FOUR
The People of the Future
'In another moment we were standing face to
face, I and this weak creature from the future.
He came straight up to me and laughed into
my eyes.
I noticed immediately that he had no fear
in him.
Then he turned to the two others who were
following him.
He spoke to them in a strange and very sweet-sounding
language.
'There were more coming, and soon a little
group of perhaps eight or ten of these beautiful
people were around me.
One of them spoke to me.
I don't know why, but I thought that my voice
was too strong and deep for them.
So I shook my head and, pointing to my ears,
shook it again.
He came a step forwards, stopped and then
touched my hand.
Then I felt other soft little hands on my
back and shoulders.
They wanted to make sure that I was real.
'There was nothing at all frightening in this.
In fact, these pretty little people had a
relaxed and childlike gentleness that made
me confident.
And also, they looked so weak that I could
imagine myself throwing the whole group of
them to the ground.
'But I made a sudden movement to warn them
when I saw their little pink hands touching
the Time Machine.
Fortunately then, when it wasn't too late,
I thought of the danger that I had forgotten.
Reaching over the bars of the machine, I took
out the little levers that would make it move.
I put these in my pocket.
Then I turned again to the little people to
see how I could communicate.
'Looking closer at their faces, I saw some
strange differences in their sweet prettiness.
They all had the same wavy hair, and this
came to a sharp end at the neck and below
the ears.
There was none growing on their faces, and
their ears were very small.
Their mouths were small, too, with bright
red, rather thin lips.
Their little chins came to a point and their
eyes were large and gentle.
Perhaps my sense of my own importance is too
great, but I felt even then that they showed
very little interest in me.
'Because they didn't try to speak to me, but
simply stood smiling and speaking softly to
each other, I began the conversation.
I pointed to the Time Machine and to myself.
Then, after thinking for a moment how to describe
time, I pointed to the sun.
At once a pretty little figure dressed in
purple and white did the same, and then made
the sound of thunder.
'For a moment I was very surprised, though
the meaning of his movement was clear enough.
The question had come into my mind suddenly:
were these people fools?
You couldn't really understand how I felt.
I had always expected that people living about
800,000 years in the future would have much
greater knowledge than us in science, art
- everything.
'But one of them had asked me a very simple
question, which showed him to be on the level
of intelligence of one of our five- year-old
children.
He had asked me, in fact, if I had come from
the sun in a thunderstorm!
'This made me think again about their clothes,
their weak arms and legs and pretty faces.
A feeling of sadness came into my mind.
For a moment I felt that I had built the Time
Machine for no reason at all.
'I said yes, pointed to the sun, and made
a sound like thunder.
This was so real that it frightened them - they
all stood back a step or two and bent their
heads down.
Then one came laughing towards me, carrying
some beautiful flowers which were new to me.
He put these around my neck.
'The idea made them all happy.
Soon they were running around for flowers
and throwing them on me until I was almost
covered with them.
You cannot imagine what wonderful flowers
countless years of work had produced.
'Then someone suggested that their new toy
should be shown to others in the nearest building,
and so I was led past the sphinx made of white
stone, which had seemed to watch me all the
time with a smile at my surprise.
As I went with them, the memory of my hopes
for a future full of highly intelligent people
came to my mind, and made me smile.
'The building had a very large entrance, and
was really enormous.
I was worried about the growing crowd of little-
people, and the shadows beyond the big open
doors.
Around me I saw many bushes and flowers.
It was clear that no gardener was looking
after them, but they still looked beautiful.
The Time Machine was left on the lawn.
'Several more brightly-dressed people met
me in the doorway and we walked through into
a large hall.
The roof was in shadow and the windows, partly
made of coloured glass, let in a soft light.
The floor was made of large pieces of a very
hard white metal, lower in places where people
had clearly walked across it for hundreds
of years.
'Along the length of the room were many tables
made of shiny stone, perhaps half a metre
above the floor, and on these were piles of
fruit.
Some I recognised as larger apples and oranges,
but mostly they were strange.
'The people with me sat down around a table
and made signs for me to do the same.
They immediately began to eat the fruit with
their hands.
I was happy to follow their example because
I felt thirsty and hungry.
As I did so, I took some time to look around
the hall and noticed that the glass windows
were broken in many places and the curtains
were thick with dust.
The general effect, though, was very attractive.
'There were, perhaps, a couple of hundred
people eating in the hall, and most of them
were watching me with interest, their little
eyes shining over the fruit they were eating.
All of them were wearing the same soft but
strong material.
'Fruit, I later learned, was all that they
ate.
These people of the future didn't eat meat,
and while I was with them, although I missed
it, I could only eat fruit too.
In fact, I discovered later that horses, cows
and sheep, and dogs, had disappeared from
Earth.
But the fruits were very pleasant.
'When I had filled my stomach, I tried to
learn some of the language of these new people.
The fruits seemed an easy thing to start with,
and holding one of these up, I began using
questioning sounds and movements.
I had great difficulty making them understand.
At first they stared in surprise and laughed,
but soon a fair-haired little female seemed
to realise what I wanted and repeated a name.
'They had to talk for some time to explain
things to each other, and when I first tried
to make the sounds of their language they
were very amused.
I felt like a teacher among children, but
soon I at least knew a number of names for
things and even the verb "to eat".
'It was slow work, though, and the little
people soon got tired and wanted to get away
from my questions, so I decided to let them
give short lessons when they wanted to.
And they were very short lessons because I
have never met people who are lazier or more
easily tired.
They used to come to me with happy cries of
surprise, like children, but like children
they soon stopped examining me and went away
to find another toy.
'When the dinner ended, I noted the disappearance
of almost all the creatures who had surrounded
me at first.
It is odd, too, how quickly I stopped caring
about these little people.
I was continually meeting more of them.
They followed me a little distance, talked
and laughed around me, smiled in a friendly
way, then left me alone.
CHAPTER FIVE
Life in the Future
The evening was calm as I came out of the
great hall, and the land was lit by the colour
of the sun as it went down.
The big building was on the side of a wide
river valley, but the Thames had moved a kilometre
or two from its present position.
I decided to climb to the top of a hill from
where I could see more of our world in the
year 802,701.That was the date the little
dials of my machine had showed.
'As I walked, I looked for anything that could
explain the bad condition of things.
A little way up the hill, for example, was
a great pile of stones held together by pieces
of metal.
These were the ruins of a great building,
although I couldn't imagine what its use had
been.
'Looking round with a sudden thought, I realised
that there were no small houses.
Here and there among the trees and bushes
were palace-like buildings, but the single
house, and possibly even the family, had disappeared.
'And then came another thought.
I looked at the small group of figures who
were following me.
I saw that all had the same type of clothes,
the same soft hairless faces and the same
girlish arms and legs.
'It may seem odd, perhaps, that I hadn't noticed
this before.
But everything was so strange.
Now, I saw the fact clearly enough.
These people of the future were all very similar
in clothes, and in all other ways the differences
between men and women had almost disappeared.
And the children seemed to my eyes to be just
smaller adults.
'Seeing how safely and comfortably these people
lived, I felt that this close similarity of
the sexes was understandable.
If there are enough people, it becomes a problem
rather than an advantage to have a lot of
children.
If violence conies only rarely and children
are safe, there is less need for men to be
strong and protect their families.
This, I must remind you, was my feeling at
the time.
Later, I discovered how wrong I was.
'I continued, and because I could walk better
than the people of the future, I found myself
alone for the first time.
At the top of the hill I found a seat of a
yellow metal that I didn't recognise.
I sat down on it and looked at the wide view
of our world under the sunset of that long
day.
It was as beautiful as I have ever seen.
The west was burning gold, mixed with some
purple and red.
Below was the valley of the Thames, in which
the river lay like a line of shining metal.
'As I watched, I began to try to understand
the things I had seen.
(Afterwards I realised I had only learned
half the truth.)
It seemed to me that people were now past
their best.
The sunset made me think about the sunset
of our people.
For the first time I began to understand an
odd result of the social changes we are trying
to make at the moment.
Strength comes because we need to be strong;
weakness comes when we feel safe.
The work of improving the conditions of life,
of making life safer and safer, had continued
until nothing more could be done.
The result was what I saw!
'The science of our time has attacked only
a few human diseases, but it moves forwards.
Farming today is still at an early stage.
We improve our plants and animals very slowly
- a new and better apple, a prettier and larger
flower, a cow that gives more milk.
One day the whole world will be better organised,
and better.
'I knew that this change had been made, and
made well, in the space of time across which
my machine had jumped.
The air was free of unpleasant insects, the
earth was free of useless plants.
Everywhere there were fruits and sweet and
pleasant flowers.
Beautiful birds flew here and there.
And I saw no diseases during my stay.
'Social changes, too, had been made.
I saw people living in fine buildings, beautifully
dressed, but I hadn't yet found them doing
any work.
There were no signs of economic activity.
The shop, the advertisement, buying and selling
- all of these things are so important to
us, and all of them were gone.
It was natural in the evening that I had the
idea of a social heaven.
'But this change in conditions has to produce
changes in people.
What is the cause of human intelligence and
energy?
Difficulties make people strong and clever
and help them to work together.
And the family, with its protective love and
selfishness, is there for the care of children.
The love of parents helps to keep the young
out of danger.
Now, where were these dangers?
'I thought of the physical smallness of the
people, their low intelligence and those big
ruined buildings.
It strengthened my belief that humans, who
had always fought against nature, had finally
won - because after the fight comes quietness.
People had been strong, energetic and intelligent,
and had used this energy to change their living
conditions.
And now they too had changed because of the
new conditions.
'No doubt the beauty of the buildings was
the result of the last waves of the now purposeless
energy of people.
After that, they began to lead quieter lives.
Even artistic activity would finally disappear
- had almost disappeared in the time I saw.
The people liked to cover themselves in flowers,
to dance and to sing in the sunlight.
That was all they did.
'As I stood there in the growing dark, I thought
that I had understood the whole secret of
these pleasant people.
Possibly their population control had worked
too well, and their numbers had fallen instead
of staying the same.
That would explain the empty ruins.
My explanation was very simple, and believable
enough - as most wrong ideas are!
CHAPTER SIX
Lost in Time
'As I stood there thinking about this too
perfect success of humans, the full moon came
up in the north-east.
The little figures stopped moving around below
me and the night began to feel cold.
I decided to go down and find a place to sleep.
'I looked for the building I knew.
Then my eye moved to the white sphinx on the
pedestal.
There were the bushes and there was the little
lawn.
I looked at it again.
A strange doubt made me feel cold.
"No," I said to myself, "that isn't the lawn."
'But it was the lawn, because the white face
of the sphinx was towards it.
Can you imagine how I felt as I realised this?
But you can't.
The Time Machine had gone!
'At once I understood the possibility of losing
my own time, of being left helpless in this
strange new world.
I ran with great jumps down the hillside.
Once I fell and cut my face.
I did nothing to stop the blood, but jumped
up and continued running.
All the time I was saying to myself, "They
have just pushed it under the bushes out of
the way."
'But I knew that I was wrong.
I suppose I covered the whole distance to
the small lawn, three kilometres perhaps,
in ten minutes.
I shouted but nobody answered.
Nobody seemed to be moving in that moonlit
world.
'When I reached the lawn, I found that my
worst fears were true.
The Time Machine was nowhere to be seen.
I felt faint and cold.
I ran round the lawn quickly, checking every
corner, then stopped suddenly.
Above me was the white sphinx.
It seemed to smile with pleasure at my problems.
'It is possible that the little people had
put the machine in a safe place for me, but
I didn't feel that they were either strong
enough or caring enough to move it.
This is what worried me, the feeling of a
new power that had moved the machine.
But where could it be?
'I think I went a little mad.
I remember running violently in and out of
the moonlit bushes all around the sphinx and
frightening a small white animal that I didn't
recognise.
Then, crying and shouting, I went down to
the great building of stone.
The big hall was dark, silent and empty.
I lit a match and continued past the dusty
curtains.
'There I found a second great hall, where
about twenty of the little people were sleeping.
I have no doubt they found my second appearance
strange, as I came suddenly out of the quiet
darkness with mad noises and the sudden light
of a match.
Perhaps they had forgotten about matches.
"Where is my Time Machine?"
I began, shaking them with my hands.
'This behaviour was very strange to them.
Some laughed, but most looked very frightened.
When I saw them standing round me, I realised
that it was foolish to try and frighten them.
Judging by their daylight behaviour, I thought
that fear must be forgotten.
'I threw down the match and, knocking one
of the people over as I went, I ran across
the big dining-hall again, out under the moonlight.
I heard cries of terror and their little feet
running this way and that.
I don't remember everything I did as the moon
moved slowly up the sky I know that I ran
here and there screaming, then lay on the
ground near the sphinx and cried.
After that I slept, and when I woke up again
it was light.
'I sat up in the freshness of the morning,
trying to remember how I had got there.
Then things became clear in my mind.
I understood the wild stupidity of my madness
overnight and I could reason with myself.
"Suppose the worst," I said.
"Suppose the machine is really lost - perhaps
destroyed?
I should be calm and patient, learn the ways
of the people, learn what has happened and
how to get materials and tools - then, in
the end, perhaps, I can make another machine."
That would be my only hope, perhaps, but better
than giving up.
And it was a beautiful and interesting world.
'But probably the machine had only been taken
away.
I must be calm, find its hiding-place and
get it back by force and cleverness.
I stood up and looked around me, wondering
where I could wash.
I felt tired and dirty and rather surprised
by my emotional state the night before.
'I made a careful examination of the ground
around the little lawn.
I wasted some time in useless questions, asked,
as well as I could, to the little people that
passed.
They all failed to understand what I meant.
Some simply said nothing; others thought it
was a joke and laughed at me.
'The grass told me more.
I found a line in it.
There were other signs around, with strange
narrow footprints.
This made me look again at the pedestal.
It was made, as I think I have said, of metal.
It was highly decorated with metal panels
on either side.
'I went and knocked at these.
The pedestal was hollow.
There was no way to pull to open the panels,
but perhaps if they were doors they opened
from inside.
One thing was clear enough to my mind: it
wasn't difficult to work out that the Time
Machine was inside that pedestal.
But how had it got there?
'I saw the heads of two people dressed in
orange coming through the bushes towards me.
They came and, pointing to the pedestal, I
tried to make them understand my wish to open
it.
But at my first move to do this they behaved
very oddly.
I don't know how to describe their faces to
you.
They looked insulted.
'I tried a sweet-looking man in white next,
with exactly the same result.
He made me feel ashamed of myself.
But as you know, I wanted the Time Machine
and I tried him again.
As he turned away, like the others, I lost
my temper.
In three steps I was after him, took him by
the loose part of his robe round the neck
and began pulling him towards the pedestal.
Then I saw the fear on his face and I let
him go.
'But I wasn't beaten yet.
I hit the metal panels with my hands.
I thought I heard something move inside - to
be exact, I thought I heard a sound like a
laugh - but perhaps I was mistaken.
Then I got a big stone from the river and
hit the metal until I had flattened part of
the decoration.
The little people could hear the noise a kilometre
way in all directions, but they did nothing.
'I saw a crowd of them on the hillside, looking
at me in a frightened way.
At last, hot and tired, I sat down to watch
the place.
But I was too impatient to watch for long.
I could work at a problem for years, but I
was unable to wait, inactive, for twenty-
four hours.
'I got up after a time and began walking aimlessly
through the bushes towards the hill again.
"Patience," I said to myself.
"If you want your machine again, you must
leave that pedestal alone.
If they intend to take your machine away,
it won't help if you destroy their metal panels.
If they don't, you will get it back when you
can ask for it.
"Face this world.
Learn its ways, watch it, be careful of guessing
its meaning too quickly.
In the end you will find an answer to it all."
Then suddenly the humour of the situation
came into my mind: the thought of the years
I had spent in study and work to get into
the future age, and now my impatience to get
out of it.
I had put myself into the most hopeless situation
a man could ever imagine.
I couldn't help laughing at myself.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Ghosts
'Going through the big palace, it seemed to
me that the little people were staying away
from me.
Perhaps it was my imagination, or because
I had hit the metal panels.
I was careful, though, to show no worry and
not try to catch any of them, and after a
day or two the situation got back to normal.
'I decided to put any thought of my Time Machine
and the mystery of the metal doors as much
as possible in a corner of my memory.
I hoped that in the end, growing knowledge
would lead me back to them in a natural way.
But you can understand why I stayed within
a circle of a few kilometres around my point
of arrival.
'As far as I could see, all the world seemed
to be like the Thames valley.
From every hill I saw the same large numbers
of fine buildings, all very different in material
and style, and the same kinds of trees and
bushes.
I soon noticed, though, a number of wells
in the ground.
Several of these, it seemed to me, were very
deep.
One lay by a path up the hill, which I had
followed during my first walk.
Like the others, it had a top made of metal,
interestingly decorated and protected by a
little roof from the rain.
'Sitting by the side of these wells, and looking
down into the darkness, I could see no sign
of water or any reflection when I lit a match.
But in all of them I heard a certain sound
like the beating of a big engine.
I also discovered, from the flames of my matches,
that air was going down into them.
I threw a piece of paper down into one and,
instead of falling slowly, it was at once
pulled quickly out of sight.
I couldn't imagine what these wells were for.
'And I must say now that I learned very little
about many parts of the life of these people.
Let me describe my difficulties.
I went into several big palaces, but they
were just living places, great dining-halls
and sleeping apartments.
I could find no machines of any kind, but
these people were dressed in fine cloth that
didn't seem very old, and their shoes, though
undecorated, were very well made.
'But the people didn't seem to make things
themselves.
There were no shops, no factories, no signs
that they brought things in from other places.
They spent all their time playing gently,
swimming in the river, falling in love in
a half-playful way, eating fruit and sleeping.
I couldn't see how or where things were produced.
'But something had taken the Time Machine
into the pedestal.
Why?
I couldn't imagine.
Suppose you found something written in English,
with here and there some words that were completely
unknown to you.
Well, on the third day of my visit, that was
how I felt about the world of 802,701.
'That day I made a friend - a kind of friend.
As I was watching some of the little people
playing in a shallow part of the river, one
of them was suddenly pulled away by the water.
The river there could run quite quickly, but
not too quickly for a swimmer of normal ability.
It will give you an idea, therefore, of the
weakness of these people, when I tell you
that none tried to help the one that was in
such danger.
'When I realised this, I quickly took off
my clothes and, walking into the water at
a place lower down, I caught her and brought
her safely to land.
'She soon began to feel better and I saw that
she was all right before I left her.
I had such a low opinion of her people by
then that I didn't expect any thanks from
her.
I was wrong about that, though.
'This happened in the morning.
In the afternoon I met my little woman as
I was returning from a long walk, and she
greeted me with cries of happiness and gave
me some flowers.
Perhaps because I had been very lonely I did
my best to show I was happy with the gift.
We were soon sitting together and deep in
a conversation, mainly of smiles.
'The woman's friendliness affected me exactly
as a child's would.
We passed each other flowers and she kissed
my hands.
I did the same to hers.
Then I tried to talk, and found that her name
was Weena.
That was the beginning of a strange friendship,
which continued for a week and ended ... as
I will tell you!
'She was exactly like a child.
She wanted to be with me always.
She wanted to follow me everywhere, and on
my next journey around the area I walked fast
and tried to leave her behind.
She gave up at last, calling after me rather
sadly.
But the problems of the world had to be solved
and I hadn't, I said to myself, come into
the future to start a relationship.
'She was, though, a very great comfort.
When it was too late, only when it was too
late, I clearly understood how badly she felt
when I left her, and what she meant to me.
By seeming fond of me, and by showing in her
weak way that she cared for me, the little
person soon gave my returns to the place of
the white sphinx almost the feeling of coming
home.
I used to watch for her when I came over the
hill.
'From her, too, I learned that fear had not
yet left the world.
She was fearless enough in the daylight, but
she hated the dark shadows.
Darkness to her was the one thing to be frightened
of.
It was a very strong emotion, and I started
thinking and watching.
'I discovered then, among other things, that
these people got together in the great houses
after dark and slept in groups.
I never found one outside, alone.
And if I entered the room without a light,
I made them very afraid.
But I was such a fool that I missed the lesson
of that fear, and although it made Weena unhappy
I slept away from the others.
'It worried her greatly, but in the end her
feelings for me won.
For five of the nights of our friendship,
including the last night of all, she slept
with her head on my arm.
But my story is running away from me as I
speak of her.
'On the night before I met her I was woken
very early in the morning.
I had slept badly, dreaming that I was under
water, and that fish were touching my face.
I woke suddenly and with the odd feeling that
a greyish animal had just rushed out of the
room.
'I tried to go to sleep again, but I felt
uncomfortable.
It was that grey hour when things are just
appearing from the darkness, but are still
unreal.
I got up, went down into the great hall and
out onto the stones in front of the palace.
I thought I would go and watch the sun come
up.
'The moon was going down, and the dying moonlight
and the first light of day were mixed in a
pale half-light.
The bushes were inky black, the ground a dark
grey, and up on the hillside I thought I could
see ghosts.
Three times I saw white figures and twice
I thought I saw a single white animal running
quickly on two legs.
'Near the ruins I saw a group of them carrying
a dark body.
They moved quickly and it seemed that they
disappeared among the bushes.
The light was still unclear, you must understand.
I was experiencing that cold, uncertain, early-morning
feeling you may know, and I doubted my eyes.
'As the eastern sky grew brighter, and the
light of day brought stronger colours to the
world again, I watched the hillside closely.
But I saw no more white figures.
I thought about them all morning - or at least
until I had to get Weena out of the river.
I connected them in some way with the white
animal I had touched in my first mad search
for the Time Machine.
It was more pleasant to think about Weena,
but these ghosts would soon take much stronger
control of my mind.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Morlocks
'I think I said how much hotter the weather
of this Golden Age was than our own.
I can't explain this.
It is usual to think that the sun will continue
cooling in the future.
But people forget that the Earth must also,
in the end, fall back closer and closer to
the sun.
'Well, one very hot morning - my fourth, I
think - as I was trying to get away from the
heat and the strong light in a large ruin
near the great house, a strange thing happened.
Climbing among those piles of stones, I found
a narrow room, whose end and side windows
were closed by falling stones.
After the light outside, it seemed very dark
to me.
I entered it, feeling my way with my hands.
'Suddenly, I stopped and held my breath.
A pair of eyes, made bright by the reflection
of the daylight outside, was watching me out
of the darkness.
'I felt the old natural fear of wild animals
as I looked into those angry eyes.
I was afraid to turn.
Then I thought how safely people appeared
to be living.
And then I remembered their strange terror
of the dark.
'Trying to control my fear, I took a step
forwards and spoke.
My voice was strong but shaking.
I put out my hand and touched something soft.
'At once the eyes moved to the side and something
white ran past me.
I turned, as my heart beat even faster, and
saw an odd- looking figure, its head held
down in a strange way, running across the
sunlit space behind me.
It ran into a large stone, fell to one side
and in a moment was hidden in a black shadow
under another pile of stones.
'It went too fast for me to see clearly, but
I know it was a dull white and had strange
large greyish-red eyes.
Also, there was fair hair on its head and
down its back.
I can't say whether it ran on four legs or
only with its arms held very low.
After a few seconds I followed it into the
second pile of ruins.
'I couldn't find it at first, but after some
time in the deep darkness I saw one of those
round well-like openings that I have told
you about, half-closed by a large fallen stone.
A sudden thought came to me.
Had the thing disappeared down the well?
'I lit a match and, looking down, saw a small
white moving creature with large bright eyes.
It stared at me as it climbed down.
Now I saw for the first time a kind of metal
ladder down the side of the well.
Then the light burned my fingers and fell
out of my hand, going out as it dropped.
I lit another but the horrible little creature
had disappeared.
'I don't know how long I sat staring down
that well.
Time passed before I could make myself believe
that I had seen something human.
But slowly I began to understand the truth:
that humans hadn't stayed as one species,
but had become two different animals.
My pleasant children of the Upper-world weren't
alone.
'And what, I wondered, was this creature of
the dark doing in my idea of a perfectly organised
society?
What was its relationship with the calm laziness
of the beautiful Upper-world people?
And what was hidden down there?
I sat on the edge of the well telling myself
that there was nothing to fear and that I
must go down to find the answer.
But I was very afraid to go!
As I sat there, two of the Upper-world people
came running across the daylight into the
shadow.
The male followed the female, throwing flowers
at her as he ran.
'They seemed upset to find me looking down
the well.
I understood that it was bad behaviour to
look down these holes, because when I pointed
to this one and tried to make a question about
it in their language, they grew even more
upset and turned away.
But they were interested in my matches and
I struck some to amuse them.
I asked them again about the well, and again
I failed.
So I soon left them, intending to go back
to Weena and see what she could tell me.
'But my mind was already working.
I now had an idea of the importance of these
wells, of the mystery of the ghosts, of the
meaning of the metal panels and what had happened
to the Time Machine!
And I also had the beginnings of a solution
to the economic mystery that had worried me.
'Here was my new idea.
Clearly, this second human species lived underground.
There were three things especially which made
me think this.
First, there was the white skin common to
most animals that live largely in the dark.
Then there were those large eyes, like those
of a cat.
Finally, its confusion in the sunshine, how
it ran into the stones, the strange way it
held its head - all these things made me believe
that its eyes weren't used to the light.
'Under my feet, then, there must be many tunnels,
where these people lived.
The wells, which carried air to them, were
all along the hillsides - everywhere, in fact,
except along the river valley.
Their great number showed how many tunnels
there were.
It seemed natural, too, to believe that the
underground people made things for the comfort
of the daylight people.
The idea was so sensible that I accepted it
at once, and then thought about how humans
had turned into two species.
'Starting with the problems of our own age,
it seemed clear to me that the widening of
the social difference between the worker and
the manager explained the whole situation.
Even now we can see the beginnings of this.
We have begun to make use of underground space
- we have railways, underground workrooms
and restaurants, and these are becoming more
common.
It was clear, I thought, that workers had
begun to go underground into larger and larger
factories, spending more and more of their
time there, until, in the end...
'Also, the increasing difference between the
social classes made marriage between them
less and less frequent.
So above the ground now were the Haves, looking
for pleasure and comfort and beauty, and below
ground the Have-nots, the workers, changed
by the demands of their jobs.
'When they were there, they had to pay rent,
and not a little of it, for the air coming
to their homes.
If they refused, they would die.
If they couldn't live in this way, they would
also die.
In the end, everyone living underground would
be used to the conditions of their life, and
as happy in their way as the Upper- world
people were.
'This, I must warn you, was my explanation
at the time.
It may be completely wrong but I still think
it is the best one.
But I think this way of life had worked better
in the past.
The Upper- world people had become too safe,
and so had become smaller, weaker and less
intelligent.
'I didn't yet know what had happened to the
underground people.
But I could imagine that the changes to the
Morlocks - that, I discovered later, was their
name - were even greater than the changes
to the Eloi, the ones I already knew.
'Then came worrying doubts.
Why had the Morlocks taken my Time Machine?
I felt sure they had taken it.
Why, too, if the Eloi were in control, could
they not get my machine back for me?
And why were they so terribly afraid of the
dark?
As I have said, I questioned Weena about this
Under-world, but I learned nothing from her.
'At first she didn't understand my questions
and later she refused to answer them.
The whole subject seemed too unpleasant.
And when I asked her again, perhaps a little
loudly, she began to cry.
They were the only tears, except my own, that
I ever saw in that Golden Age.
'When I saw those tears, I stopped worrying
about the Morlocks.
I lit a match and very soon she was smiling
again.
CHAPTER NINE
Underground
'It may seem odd to you, but it was two days
before I could find out more about the Morlocks.
I felt a strange fear of those pale bodies.
They were just the same colour as the things
one sees in jars in a museum and they were
horribly cold when you touched them.
I knew I could only get to the Time Machine
by going underground.
But I couldn't do it.
I was so alone, and even the idea of climbing
down into the darkness of the well frightened
me.
'The next night I did not sleep well.
Probably my health had suffered a little.
I was confused and unhappy.
Once or twice I had a feeling of great fear
for which I could see no definite reason.
I remember walking noiselessly into the great
hall where the little people were sleeping
- that night Weena was among them - and feeling
more comfortable in their company.
I realised that the moon was in its last quarter
and the nights were growing darker, and that
there might be more appearances of those unpleasant
creatures from below.
And on both these days I had the restless
feeling of someone who is trying to escape
a duty.
I felt that I could only get the Time Machine
back if I understood these underground mysteries.
But I wasn't brave enough to solve the mysteries,
and I never quite felt safe.
'These worries drove me further and further
in my walks around the country.
Going south-west towards the higher country,
I saw, far away, an enormous building.
It was larger than the largest of the palaces
or ruins I knew, and the front was pale green.
The difference in appearance suggested a difference
in use, and I thought about going to look
around.
But it was growing late so I decided to wait
until the following day, and I returned to
Weena's welcome.
'But the next morning I realised that my interest
in the Green Palace was just helping me to
delay an experience I was afraid of.
I decided that I would go down without wasting
any more time, and walked in the early morning
towards a well near the ruins.
'Little Weena danced beside me to the well,
but when she saw me bend over the opening
and look down, she seemed upset.
"Goodbye, little Weena," I said, kissing her,
and then I began to feel over the edge for
the metal steps.
'At first she watched me with surprise.
Then she gave a most heartbreaking cry and,
running to me, began to pull at me with her
little hands.
I think her fear made me braver.
I shook her off and in another moment I was
inside the well.
I saw her frightened face over the top and
smiled to make her feel better.
'I had to climb down a well perhaps two hundred
metres deep.
There were metal bars all the way down, but
these were made for a person much smaller
and lighter than I was and I was quickly tired
by the climb.
And not simply tired!
One of the bars bent suddenly under my weight
and almost threw me off into the blackness
below.
For the moment I hung by one hand, and after
that I didn't dare to rest again.
'Although my arms and back were very painful,
I continued climbing down as quickly as possible.
Looking up, I saw the opening, a small blue
circle, where Weena's head was round and black.
The noise of a machine grew louder.
Everything except that little circle above
was very dark, and when I looked up again
she had disappeared.
'I was in great discomfort and thought of
going up again.
But I continued to climb down.
At last, with great happiness, I saw, half
a metre to the right of me, a thin opening
in the wall.
Fulling myself in, I found it was the start
of a narrow tunnel in which I could lie down
and rest.
It was not too soon.
'I lay there, I don't know how long, until
I felt a soft hand touching my face.
Quickly getting to my feet in the darkness,
I pulled out my matches.
I struck one and saw three white figures moving
quickly back, away from the light.
Their eyes, unusually large from living in
darkness, were like those of deep-water fish,
and reflected the light in the same way.
I have no doubt they could see me and they
didn't seem to have any fear of me, only of
the light.
'The thought of running away was still in
my mind, but I told myself that the job had
to be done.
As I felt my way along the tunnel, the noise
of machinery grew louder.
Soon I came to a large open space and, striking
another match, saw that I had entered an enormous
underground room.
It stretched into total darkness beyond my
light.
'Great shapes like large machines rose out
of the darkness, and made strange shadows
in which I could see the shapes of Morlocks
hiding.
The air wasn't very fresh and there was a
faint smell of fresh blood.
Some way down the central path was a little
table of white metal, covered with food.
So the Morlocks, at least, were meat-eaters!
'Even at the time, I remember wondering what
large animal still lived to produce the red
piece of meat that I saw.
Then the match burned down to my fingers and
fell, a moving red spot in the darkness.
'I have thought since then how very badly-prepared
I was for such an experience.
When I had started building the Time Machine,
I had had the stupid idea that the people
of the future would certainly be far ahead
of us in all their inventions.
I had come without weapons, without medicine,
without tobacco, even without enough matches.
'I didn't even think of bringing a camera,
so I couldn't take a picture of that Under-world,
to examine later.
I stood there with only the weapons that nature
had given me - hands, feet and teeth - and
the four matches that I had left.
I was afraid to push my way in among all this
machinery in the dark, and then I discovered
that I had almost finished my matches.
I had never thought that there was any need
to save them and I had wasted almost half
the box surprising the Eloi.
Now I had four left, and while I stood in
the dark a hand touched mine and cold fingers
began feeling my face.
'I thought I could hear the breathing of a
crowd of those horrible little creatures around
me.
I felt the box of matches in my hand being
gently pulled away, and other hands behind
me pulling at my clothes.
I shouted as loudly as I could.
'They jumped back, and then I could feel them
coming towards me again.
They took hold of me more strongly, whispering
odd sounds to each other.
I shook violently and shouted again.
This time they weren't so worried, and they
made a strange laughing noise as they came
back at me.
T was horribly frightened.
I decided to strike another match and escape
under the protection of its light.
I did so and, keeping the flame burning with
a piece of paper from my pocket, I moved quickly
into the narrow tunnel.
But I had just entered this when my light
was blown out, and in the blackness I could
hear the Morlocks hurrying after me.
'In a moment I was held by several hands,
trying to pull me back.
I struck another light and waved it in their
faces.
You can't imagine how horribly inhuman they
looked in their blindness and surprise.
But I didn't stay.
I moved back again and when my second match
went out, I struck my third.
It had almost burned down when I reached the
opening into the well.
'I lay down on the edge and felt for the metal
bars.
As I did so, my feet were held from behind
and I was violently pulled backwards.
I lit my last match... and it went out.
But I had my hand on the bars now and, kicking
violently, I got myself free of the hands
of the Morlocks and quickly climbed up the
well.
They stayed, afraid of the light, all except
one little one who followed me for some way,
and almost got my shoe as a prize.
'That climb never seemed to end.
In the last eight or ten metres of it, a terrible
feeling of sickness came over me.
I had the greatest difficulty holding the
bars.
Several times I thought that I might fall.
At last, though, I got over the top of the
well, and walked shakily out of the ruin into
the blinding sunlight.
'I fell on my face.
Even the earth felt sweet and clean.
Then I remember Weena kissing my hands and
ears, and the voices of others among the Eloi.
Then, for a time, I remember nothing.
CHAPTER TEN
A Place to Live
'Now I seemed in a worse position than before.
Until then, except during my night of madness
over the disappearance of the Time Machine,
I had felt that in the end I would escape.
But that hope was shaken by these new discoveries.
I had been worried by the thought of unknown
forces which I could beat when I understood
them.
The situation was different now.
There was something sickening about the Morlocks
- something inhuman.
Before, I had felt like a man who had fallen
into a hole: my worry was how to get out of
it.
Now I felt like an animal which had been caught,
whose enemy would come to him soon.
'That enemy was the darkness of the new moon.
Weena had put this fear into my head by some
things she said, which at first I didn't understand,
about the Dark Nights.
Now I could guess what the coming Dark Nights
might mean.
The moon was getting smaller and each night
there was a longer time of darkness.
And I now understood a little of the Eloi's
fear of the dark.
I wondered what terrible things the Morlocks
did under the new moon.
'The Eloi had probably been the managers and
the Morlocks their servants, but that situation
had changed a long time before.
The two species were moving towards, or had
already arrived at, a completely new relationship.
The Eloi were still allowed to own the world,
because the Morlocks, underground for so long,
now found the daylight impossible.
And the Morlocks made their clothes, I thought,
and did other necessary things for them, perhaps
because an old habit of service had continued.
'But clearly, the end of the Eloi's power
was coming closer.
And suddenly I thought of the meat I had seen
in the Underworld.
I tried to remember its shape.
I had a feeling it was something familiar,
but I hadn't recognised it at the time.
'The little people could do nothing about
their fear, but I was made differently.
I came out of our age, this best time for
humans, when fear doesn't make us helpless.
I at least could defend myself.
Without further delay I decided to make myself
weapons and a safe place where I could sleep.
From there, I could face this strange world
with some of that confidence.
I had been slow to realise what creatures
could harm me night after night.
I felt I could never sleep again until my
bed was safe from them.
I shook with fear to think how they had already
examined me.
'I walked during the afternoon along the valley
of the Thames, but found nowhere that seemed
safe.
All the buildings and trees seemed easy for
such good climbers as the Morlocks to get
into, judging by their skill at entering and
leaving their wells.
Then the Green Palace came into my mind.
In the evening, carrying Weena like a child
on my shoulders, I went up into the hills
towards the south-west.
The distance, I had thought, was eleven or
twelve kilometres, but it was probably nearer
thirty.
'I had first seen the place on a wet afternoon
when things in the distance seemed nearer.
In addition, the heel of one of my shoes was
loose, so I couldn't walk well.
And it was already long past sunset when I
came in sight of the palace, dark against
the pale yellow of the sky.
'Weena had been very pleased when I began
to carry her, but later she wanted me to put
her down.
She ran along by my side, occasionally going
off to pick flowers to put in my pockets.
Weena had been unsure of the purpose of pockets,
but had decided that they should be filled
and decorated with flowers.
And that reminds me!
While changing my jacket I found...'
The Time Traveller paused, put his hand into
his pocket and silently placed two dead flowers
on the little table.
Then he went back to his story.
'As the quiet of evening spread over the world
and we moved over the top of the hill towards
Wimbledon, Weena grew tired and wanted to
return to the house of grey stone.
But I pointed to the Green Palace, and tried
to make her understand that we were looking
for a safe place there.
'You know that quietness that comes before
dark?
In that calm my senses seemed to sharpen.
I thought that I could almost see the tunnels
in the ground under my feet - that I could
see the Morlocks going here and there and
waiting for the dark.
In my excitement I imagined that they would
see my arrival in their homes as an act of
war.
'So we continued and the evening turned into
night.
The ground grew difficult to see and the trees
turned black.
Weena's fears and her tiredness grew.
I took her in my arms and talked to her.
Then, as the darkness grew deeper, she put
her arms round my neck.
Closing her eyes, she tightly pressed her
face against my shoulder.
'So we went down a long hillside into a valley,
and there in the poor light I almost fell
into a little river.
I walked across this and went up the opposite
side.
I had seen nothing of the Morlocks, but it
was still early in the night.
The darker hours before the moon came up hadn't
yet arrived.
'From the top of the next hill I saw a thick
wood spreading wide and black in front of
me.
I stopped at this.
I could see no end to it, either to the right
or the left.
Feeling tired - my feet, especially, were
very painful - I carefully lowered Weena from
my shoulder as I stopped, and sat down on
the grass.
I could no longer see the Green Palace, and
I wasn't sure of my direction.
'I looked into the thickness of the wood and
thought of what it might hide.
In there, we might be out of sight of the
stars.
Even if there were no other waiting danger,
there would still be many things to fall over
and walk into.
I was very tired, too, after the excitement
of the day, so I decided that I wouldn't face
it, but would spend the night on the open
hill.
'Weena, I was glad to find, was asleep.
I put my jacket round her and sat down beside
her to wait for the moon to rise.
The hillside was quiet and empty, but from
the black of the wood came, now and then,
the sound of living things.
Above me the stars shone, because the night
was very clear, and I felt a sense of friendly
comfort from their lights.
All the familiar old ones had moved in the
sky, rearranged in new groups during countless
human lifetimes.
'As I looked at all these stars, I suddenly
felt that my problems were smaller.
I thought of their distance, and their slow
movements out of the unknown past into the
unknown future.
And in my time travelling forwards, all the
activity, the traditions, the organisations,
the nations, languages, literature, hopes,
even the memory of humans as I knew them,
had totally disappeared.
Instead, there were these weak people who
had forgotten their great history, and the
white Things of which I was so afraid.
'Then I thought of the great fear between
the two species.
I thought about the meat that I had seen.
And for the first time I understood what it
might be.
But the thought was too horrible!
I looked at little Weena sleeping beside me,
her face white under the stars, and put the
thought from my mind.
'Through that long night I kept my mind off
the Morlocks as well as I could.
I passed the time by trying to find signs
of the old groups of stars in the sky.
No doubt I slept a little.
Then, as time passed, there came a soft light
in the eastern sky and the old moon came up,
thin and pointed and white.
And close behind, and stronger, came the light
from the sun.
'No Morlocks had come near us.
In fact, I had seen none on the hills that
night.
And in the confidence of the new day it almost
seemed to me that I had been wrong to be afraid.
I stood up and found my foot with the loose
heel was painful, so I sat down again, took
off my shoes and threw them away.
'I woke Weena and we went down into the wood,
now green and pleasant instead of black and
unwelcoming.
We found some fruit there to eat for breakfast.
We soon met other Eloi, laughing and dancing
in the sunlight.
And then I thought again of the meat that
I had seen.
I felt sure now what it was and with all my
heart I pitied them.
'Clearly, at some time in the past, the Morlocks
hadn't been able to find enough food.
Possibly they had lived on rats and similar
animals.
Now the Eloi were like fat cows, which the
Morlocks kept and hunted.
And there was Weena dancing at my side!
'I tried to think more scientifically, and
less emotionally.
Perhaps this was a punishment for human selfishness.
Some people had been happy to live from the
work of others.
They had said this was necessary, and in time
it had become equally necessary for the workers
to eat them.
But this attitude was impossible.
It didn't matter how unintelligent they were,
the Eloi still looked human.
I understood their situation and I felt their
fear.
'I had at that time no clear ideas about what
I should do.
I thought I could find a safe place and make
myself some weapons out of metal or stone.
Next I hoped to find a way of making fire,
so I would have the weapon of a torch.
I knew that nothing would work better against
these Morlocks.
Then I wanted to find a way of breaking open
the metal panels under the white sphinx.
'I felt that if I could enter those doors
and carry a light in front of me I would discover
the Time Machine and escape.
I couldn't imagine that the Morlocks were
strong enough to move it far away.
I had decided to bring Weena with me to our
own time.
And thinking about plans like these, we walked
towards the building which I had chosen as
our home.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
The Green Palace
I found the Green Palace, when we came to
it at about midday, to be empty and falling
into ruin.
The glass in its windows was broken and large
pieces of green material had fallen off the
walls onto the ground.
It stood high on a grassy hill and, looking
towards the north-east before I entered it,
I was surprised to see a large river where
I thought Wandsworth and Battersea had been
in the past.
I thought then of what had happened or might
be happening to the living things in the sea.
'Along the front of the palace I saw writing
in an unknown language.
I thought, rather foolishly, that Weena might
help to understand this, but I only learned
that the idea of writing had never entered
her head.
She always seemed to me, I imagine, more human
than she was, perhaps because her love was
so human.
Inside the large door - which was open and
broken - we found, instead of the usual hall,
a long room lit by many side windows.
At first look I was reminded of a museum.
The floor was thick with dust, and an interesting
collection of strange objects was covered
in grey dust too.
Then I noticed, in the centre of the room,
the bones of a large animal.
They lay on the floor in the thick dust, and
in one place, where the rainwater had come
through the roof, some had almost been destroyed.
'This made me feel sure that I was in a museum.
Going towards the side I found shelves and
on them I found the old familiar glass cases
of our time.
They had kept the air out; the objects inside
were still in good condition.
'I continued walking and found another short
room running across the end of the first.
This appeared to be full of rocks, in which
I had little interest, so we didn't stop.
The next room appeared to be about natural
history, but everything had changed so much
that it was unrecognisable.
A few blackened things which had been animals
many years before, a brown dust of dead plants,
that was all!
I was sorry about that, because I wanted to
know how people had learned to control nature.
'Then we came to an enormous room, which was
very badly- lit.
Every few metres, white glass balls hung from
the ceiling - many of them broken - which
suggested that the place had had electric
lighting.
On either side of me were large machines,
all in bad condition and many broken down,
but some still quite complete.
I wanted to stay among these because I could
only make guesses at what they were for.
I thought that if I could learn to understand
them, I would have powers that might be useful
against the Morlocks.
'Suddenly Weena came very close to my side,
so suddenly that she surprised me.
I woke out of my dream and then noticed that
the floor of the room went downhill.
I had come in at an end that was above ground,
and had a few tail thin windows.
As you went down the room, the ground came
up against these windows, until finally there
was only a narrow line of daylight at the
top.
'I had moved slowly, thinking about the machines,
and had been too interested in them to notice
that it was getting dark.
Then Weena's increasing nervousness made me
realise that the room ran down into thick
darkness.
I stopped and, as I looked around me, I saw
that the dust was thinner there.
Further away towards the darkness, it appeared
to be broken by a number of small, narrow
footprints.
'I felt that I was wasting my time looking
at this machinery.
I remembered that it was already late in the
afternoon and that I still had no weapon,
no safe place and no way of making a fire.
And then down at the far end of the room I
heard the sound of footsteps and the same
strange noises I had heard down the well.
'I took Weena's hand.
Then, getting a sudden idea, I left her and
turned to a machine on which there was a long
metal bar.
Climbing up, and taking this in my hands,
I put all my weight on it sideways.
It broke after a few seconds, and I rejoined
Weena with a weapon in my hand.
It was heavy enough, I thought, to break the
head of any Morlock I might meet.
And I wanted very much to kill a Morlock or
two.
I wanted to go straight down the room and
kill the ones I heard.
I didn't do this, though, partly because I
also wanted to stay with Weena - and to get
back to my Time Machine.
'Well, with the metal bar in one hand and
Weena in the other, I went out of that room
and into another even larger one, which was
full of old books.
These had fallen to pieces and none of the
words could be read.
I'm not a great writer, so didn't spend too
long thinking about this waste of time and
energy, but I did think sadly of my own seventeen
papers on scientific subjects.
'Then, going up the wide stairs, we came to
a room that had perhaps been a science room.
And here I had some hopes of finding something
useful.
Except at one end where the roof had fallen
down, this room was in good condition.
I went quickly to every unbroken case.
At last, in one of them, I found a box of
matches.
Very excited, I tried them.
They were dry and perfectly good.
'I turned to Weena.
"Dance," I said to her in her own language,
because now I really had a weapon against
the horrible creatures that we were afraid
of.
And so, in that broken-down museum, on the
thick, soft carpet of dust, to Weena's great
happiness, I danced a slow dance, singing
a song as well as I could.
Partly the dance was from different countries,
partly it was my own invention - because I
am naturally inventive, as you know.
'It was strange that this box of matches had
lasted for so many years, but it was very
fortunate for me.
And I also found something even less likely
- a jar containing a number of candles.
I broke it open, put these in my pocket and
left that room very happy.
'I can't tell you all the story of that long
afternoon.
I would have to think hard to remember what
I saw in the correct order.
I remember a long room filled with guns, and
although some were still in good condition,
I could find no bullets.
In another place was a large collection of
stone and metal gods - Polynesian, Mexican,
Greek, Roman, from every country on Earth,
I think.
And here I couldn't help writing my name on
the nose of a stone god from South America
that I really liked.
'As evening came, my interest level fell.
I went through room after room: dusty, silent,
often ruined.
Some things were just piles of broken material;
some were in better condition.
In the end we came to a little open square.
It had grass and three fruit trees, so we
rested there.
'Towards sunset I began to think about our
situation.
Night was getting closer and my safe hiding
place still had to be found.
But that worried me very little now.
I had with me, perhaps, the best of all defences
against the Morlocks - I had matches.
I had the candles in my pocket too, if more
light were needed.
'It seemed to me that we should spend the
night in the open, protected by a fire.
In the morning I could try to get the Time
Machine.
To do that, at that time, I had only my metal
bar.
But now, with my growing knowledge, I felt
very differently about those metal panels.
I had never thought they were very strong,
and I hoped that the metal bar would be heavy
enough to do the job.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Fear of Fire
'When we came out of the palace, the sun hadn't
completely gone down.
I wanted to get through the woods before it
was dark, and to reach the white sphinx early
the next morning.
My plan was to go as far as possible that
night and then build a fire and sleep in the
protection of its light.
So as we went along I collected sticks and
dry grass, and soon had my arms full.
'Because of this, we walked more slowly than
I had expected, and also Weena was tired.
And I began to suffer from sleepiness too,
so it was night before we reached the wood.
On a bushy hill at the edge of it, Weena wanted
to stop, afraid of the darkness in front of
us.
But a strong feeling of danger, that I failed
to see as a warning, made me continue.
I had been without sleep for a night and two
days, and felt ill and bad-tempered.
I felt sleep coming on me, and the Morlocks
with it.
'Then, among the black bushes behind us, and
dark against their blackness, I saw three
figures close to the ground.
There was long grass all around us and I didn't
feel safe from them.
The forest, I thought, was about a kilometre
across.
If we could get through it to the open hillside,
that, it seemed to me, was a much safer resting-place.
'I thought that with my matches and my candles
I could keep my way lit through the woods.
But I knew that I wouldn't be able to hold
my firewood too.
So, rather unwillingly, I put it down.
Then it came into my head that I would surprise
the Morlocks behind us by lighting it.
I soon discovered how stupid this was, but
at the time it seemed a good way of protecting
our backs.
'I don't know if you have ever thought what
an unusual thing fire must be where there
are no people and where the climate is cool.
The sun's heat is not often strong enough
to burn plants, even when it shines through
a drop of water, as sometimes happens in hotter
places.
Lightning may start small fires, but they
don't usually spread very far.
In this future time, the way to make fire
had been forgotten in the world.
The red tongues climbing my pile of wood were
completely new and strange to Weena.
'She wanted to run to them and play with them.
She almost threw herself on the fire, but
I held her back.
Then I picked her up and, although she fought
against me, I walked forwards into the wood.
For a short distance the light from my fire
showed us the way.
Looking back, I could see, through the many
trees, that from my pile of sticks the fire
had spread to some bushes.
Now a curved red line was coming slowly up
the grass of the hill.
'I laughed at that, and turned again to the
dark trees in front of us.
It was very black and Weena held on to me
in fear, but there was still, as my eyes got
used to the darkness, enough light for me
to walk around the trees.
Above us it was simply black, except where
a piece of blue sky shone down on us here
and there.
I struck none of my matches because I had
no hand free.
With my left arm I carried my little friend;
in my right hand I had my metal bar.
'For some time I heard nothing except the
breaking of dry- wood under my feet, the low
sound of the wind above, my own breathing
and the beat of my heart.
Then I seemed to hear soft footsteps around
me.
I kept moving.
The footsteps grew louder and then I heard
the same strange sounds and voices I had heard
in the Under-world.
There seemed to be several of the Morlocks
and they were getting closer.
In fact, in another minute I felt one of them
pull at my coat, then something on my arm.
Weena shook violently and then stopped moving.
'It was time for a match.
But to get one I had to put her down.
I did so and, as I searched in my pocket,
a fight began in the darkness around my knees,
with no sounds from her and some strange bird-like
noises from the Morlocks.
Soft little hands, too, were moving over my
coat and back, even touching my neck.
Then the match caught fire and I saw the white
backs of the Morlocks running away through
the trees.
I quickly took a candle from my pocket and
prepared to light it.
'Then I looked at Weena.
She was lying with her face to the ground,
holding my feet and not moving.
With a sudden feeling of fear I bent down
to her.
She seemed almost unable to breathe.
I lit the candle and placed it on the ground,
and as the flame grew it chased away the Morlocks
and the shadows.
I bent down and lifted her.
The wood behind us seemed full of the movement
and voices of the Morlocks.
'She seemed to have fainted.
I put her carefully on my shoulder and stood
up.
and then there came a horrible thought.
While lighting my match and helping Weena,
I had turned myself around several times and
now I had no idea which direction to go in.
I might be facing back towards the Green Palace.
'Now I was cold with fear.
I had to think quickly what to do.
I decided to build a fire and stay where we
were.
I put Weena, still not moving, down against
a tree.
Very quickly, because my candle was burning
low, I began collecting sticks and leaves.
Here and there, out of the darkness around
me, the Morlocks' eyes shone like jewels.
'The candle burned down and went out.
I lit a match and as I did so, I saw two white
shapes that were moving towards Weena.
When the light shone, they ran quickly to
get away.
One was so blinded by the light that he came
straight towards me and I felt a bone break
when I hit him with my hand.
He cried out in pain, walked with difficulty
for a short distance and fell down.
I lit another candle and continued building
my fire.
'After some time, I noticed how dry some of
the leaves were above me; since my arrival
a week before, no rain had fallen.
So instead of looking around among the trees
for fallen sticks, I began jumping up and
pulling down branches.
Very soon I had a smoky fire of green wood
and dry sticks, and could put out my candle.
Then I turned to the place where Weena sat
beside my metal bar.
I did what I could to make her wake up, but
she seemed almost dead.
I couldn't even decide whether or not she
was breathing.
'Now the smoke of the fire surrounded me and
suddenly I felt terribly tired.
My fire wouldn't need any more wood for an
hour or two, so I sat down.
The wood was full of quiet noises that I couldn't
understand.
I seemed just to close my eyes for a minute.
But then everything was dark and the Morlocks
had their hands on me.
'Throwing off their fingers, I quickly felt
in my pocket for the matchbox and - it had
gone!
Then they took hold of me again.
In a moment I realised what had happened.
I had slept and my fire had gone out.
I felt the fear of death.
The forest seemed full of the smell of burning
wood.
I was caught by the neck, by the hair, by
the arms, and pulled down.
It was unbelievably horrible in the darkness
to feel all these soft creatures lying on
top of me.
There were too many of them, and I fell to
the ground.
'I felt little teeth biting at my neck.
I turned over and as I did so, my hand touched
my metal bar.
It gave me strength.
I fought hard to get back on my feet, shaking
off the human rats.
Holding the bar against my body, I pushed
where I thought their faces might be.
I could feel the softness of bodies and my
hits, and for a moment I was free.
'I felt the strange happiness that so often
seems to come with hard fighting.
I knew that both I and Weena were finished,
but I decided to make the Morlocks pay for
their meat.
I stood with my back to a tree, moving the
metal bar from side to side in front of me.
'The whole wood was full of the movement and
cries of the Morlocks.
A minute passed.
Their voices seemed to rise to a greater level
of excitement and their movements grew faster.
But no more came within reach.
I stood staring into the blackness.
'Then suddenly hope came.
Were the Morlocks afraid?
And soon after that, I noticed a strange thing.
The darkness seemed to grow lighter.
I began to see the Morlocks around me - three
half-dead at my feet.
Then I recognised, with great surprise, that
the others were running from behind me and
away through the wood in front.
And their backs seemed 110 longer white, but
reddish.
'As I stood there, my mouth open in surprise,
I saw a little cloud of smoke move across
a small area of starlight between the branches
and disappear.
And then I understood the smell of burning
wood and the quiet voices growing now into
a great noise.
I understood the smoke and the reason for
the Morlocks' speed.
'Stepping out from behind my tree and looking
back, I saw, through the nearer trees, the
flames of the burning forest.
It was my first fire coming after me.
I looked for Weena, but she was gone.
The sounds of the fire behind me, the crashing
noise as each new tree caught fire, left little
time to think.
With my metal bar still in my hand, I followed
in the Morlocks' path.
'It was a hard race.
Once the flames moved forwards so quickly
on my right as I ran that they got ahead of
me and I had to move away to my left.
But at last I came out of the trees into a
small open space, and as I did so, a Morlock
rushed towards me.
He ran blindly past me and straight into the
fire!
'And then I saw the most strange and horrible
thing, I think, of all that I saw in that
future age.
This whole space was as bright as day with
the light of the fire.
In the centre was a small hill, surrounded
by burned bushes.
Beyond that was another arm of the burning
forest, with yellow tongues of flame already
coming from it, completely surrounding the
space with a ring of fire.
On the hillside were thirty or forty Morlocks,
blinded by the light and the heat, running
here and there against each other in their
fear.
'At first I didn't understand their blindness
and struck angrily at them with my bar, in
terror, as they came close to me.
I killed one and hurt another.
But when I had watched the movements of one
of them under the bushes against the red sky,
and heard their cries, I understood their
total helplessness and pain in the strong
light and I hit no more of them.
'But now and then one ran straight towards
me, frightening me so much that I got out
of his way.
At one time the flames became a little less
bright and I was afraid the awful creatures
would be able to see me.
I was even thinking of beginning the fight
by killing some of them before this happened,
but the fire started up again and I stopped
myself.
I walked around the hill among them and kept
out of their way, looking for a sign of Weena.
But Weena was gone.
'At last I sat down on the top of the little
hill and watched this strange group of blind
creatures feeling their way here and there.
They made inhuman noises to each other, as
the heat from the fire affected them.
The smoke rushed up and blew across the sky,
and through the occasional spaces in it, the
little stars shone.
Two or three Morlocks ran into me and I fought
them off with my hands, shaking as I did so.
'For most of that night I felt that I was
having a bad dream.
I bit myself and screamed to make myself wake
up.
I hit the ground with my hands and got up
and sat down again.
I walked around, and again sat down.
Then I started calling to God to let me wake.
'Three times I saw Morlocks put their heads
down in great pain and rush into the flames.
But at last, above the dying red of the fire,
above the great clouds of black smoke and
the whitening and blackening trees, and the
decreasing numbers of Morlocks, came the white
light of the day.
'I looked again for signs of Weena, but there
were none.
It was clear that they had left her poor little
body in the burning forest.
I can't describe how glad I was that it hadn't
been eaten.
As I thought of that, I wanted to kill the
helpless Morlocks around me, but I managed
to control myself.
'The hill, as I have said, was a kind of island
in the forest.
From the top of it, I could now see the Green
Palace through the thin smoke, and from that
I could work out my direction to the white
sphinx.
And so, leaving the last of the Morlocks running
and crying, I tied some grass around my feet
and limped across smoking grass and burnt
wood, still hot inside, towards the hiding-place
of the Time Machine.
'I walked slowly, because I was very tired
and my feet were painful.
I was so sorry about the death of little Weena.
It seemed such a terrible thing.
Now, back in my own room, it feels more like
the sadness of a dream than a real sadness.
But that morning I felt very lonely again
- terribly alone.
I began to think of this house, of this fireside,
of some of you, and with these thoughts came
a great need to return.
'But as I walked over the smoking ground under
the bright morning sky, I made a discovery.
In my trouser pocket there were soil some
loose matches.
The box had broken open before it was lost.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
A Fight for the Time Machine
'At about eight or nine in the morning I came
to the same seat of yellow metal from which
I had looked at the world on the evening of
my arrival.
I thought of my first ideas about this future
world on that evening, and I couldn't stop
myself laughing at my confidence.
'I was sad to think how short the dream of
human intelligence had been.
It had tried to make a comfortable, fair and
safe society.
It had succeeded - and had then led to this.
We forget the law of nature - that change,
danger and trouble make us think harder.
Nature never asks the brain to work until
habit and feeling are- useless.
There is no intelligence where there is no
change and no need of change.
'So as I see it, the Upper-world people had
moved towards their weak prettiness, and the
Under-world to hard work.
But it seemed that as time passed, the Upper-world
had stopped feeding the Under-world.
And when other meat failed them, the people
of the Under-world had started to eat what
hadn't been allowed before.
That is how I understood the situation in
my last view of the world of 802,701.
'Although I was unhappy, this seat, the peaceful
view and the warm sunlight were very pleasant
after the hard work, excitement and terror
of the past few days.
I was very tired and sleepy, and so I spread
myself out on the grass and slept.
'I woke up a little before sunset and stretching
myself, I walked down the hill towards the
white sphinx.
And now a most unexpected thing happened.
As I came to the pedestal, I found that the
metal doors were open.
I stopped in front of them, not sure about
entering.
Inside was a small room, and on a higher place
in the corner of this was the Time Machine.
I had the small levers in my pocket.
So here, after all my thought about breaking
in, was an easy solution.
I threw my metal bar away, almost sorry not
to use it.
'A sudden thought came into my head as I bent
towards the door.
This time, at least, I understood the thinking
of the Morlocks.
Trying not to laugh, I stepped through the
door and up to the Time Machine.
I was surprised to find it had been carefully
oiled and cleaned.
I have thought since then that the Morlocks
had even partly taken it to pieces while trying
in their slow way to understand it.
'Now as I stood and examined it, finding pleasure
in just touching it, it happened.
I had expected it.
The metal panels suddenly closed with a loud
noise.
I was in the dark and couldn't get out.
This is what the Morlocks thought, I was certain.
I smiled.
'I could already hear them laughing softly
as they came towards me.
Very calmly I tried to strike a match.
I only had to fix the levers and leave then
like a ghost.
But i had forgotten one little thing.
Those matches could only be lit by striking
them against the box.
'You can imagine how all my calm disappeared.
The little creatures were close to me.
One touched me.
I struck at them with the levers and began
to get into the seat of the machine.
Then one hand touched me and then another.
After that I simply had to fight against their
fingers for my levers and at the same time
feel for the places where these fitted.
'One lever, in fact, almost got away from
me.
As it left my hand, I had to hit in the dark
with my head - I could hear the Morlocks head
ring - to get it back.
This was an even more dangerous fight than
the fight in the forest, I think.
'But at last the lever was fixed and I pulled
it.
The little hands fell away from me.
The darkness soon changed to the same grey
light that I have already described.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
The Death of the World
'I have already told you of the sickness and
confusion that comes with time travelling.
And this time I wasn't sitting safely in the
seat.
For some time I held onto the machine as it
moved from side to side, not thinking about
my journey.
'When I looked at the dials again I was very
surprised to find where I had arrived.
One dial shows days, another thousands of
days, another millions of days, and another
thousands of millions.
Instead of pushing the levers backwards, I
had pulled them forwards, and when I looked
at the dials I found that the thousands hand
was moving round as fast as the seconds hand
of a watch - into the future.
'As I continued travelling, the appearance
of things changed in a strange way.
First the greyness grew darker.
Then the times of each day and night grew
longer and longer.
At first this seemed strange because I was
still travelling at high speed.
But then I understood that the world had slowed
down, and now each movement of the sun across
the sky lasted for years.
'At last an unchanging half-light covered
the world.
The sun's line of light had disappeared, because
it simply came up and went down in the west
and grew wider and redder.
The moon had totally disappeared.
The movement of the stars had grown slower
and slower.
Finally, some time before I stopped, a large,
red sun stopped moving.
At one time it had become brighter for a short
time, but it quickly lost its light again.
'I understood that the Earth had stopped turning
and was resting with one side facing the sun,
just as in our own time the moon faces the
Earth.
Very nervously, because I remembered my first
fall, I began to slow the machine down.
The hands on the dials moved slower and slower
until the thousands dial seemed to stop and
the daily one could be seen again.
I slowed down more, until I could begin to
see an empty beach.
'I stopped very gently and sat in the Time
Machine, looking round.
The sky was no longer blue.
To the north-east it was inky black, and out
of the darkness the pale white stars shone
clearly and brightly.
Overhead it was deep red and starless, and
to the south-east it grew brighter to the
point where half of the sun could be seen
above the line of the land.
The rocks around me were of a dull reddish
colour.
Some very green plants covered every part
of their south-eastern side, and these were
the only living things that I could see.
'The machine was standing on a beach.
The sea was to the south-west.
There were no waves, because there was no
wind.
The sea moved very slowly up and down like
gentle breathing.
And along the edge of the water was a thick
line of salt - pink against the brightly-coloured
sky.
I noticed that I was breathing very fist.
This reminded me of my only experience of
climbing mountains, and I knew that the air
was thinner than it is now.
'Far away up the empty beach I heard a scream
and saw a thing like an enormous insect go
flying up into the sky.
It circled and disappeared over some low hills
beyond.
The sound of its voice was so sad that I shook
and sat myself more safely on the machine.
'Looking round me again, I saw that, quite
near, a large red rock - I had thought it
was a rock - was moving slowly towards me.
Then I saw that the thing was really a large
crab-like creature.
Can you imagine a crab as large as that table,
with its many legs moving slowly and uncertainly
and its eyes looking at you?
'As I stared at this horrible creature, I
felt something on my face.
I tried to brush it away with my hand, but
in a moment it returned and almost immediately
I felt another by my ear.
I struck at this and found something like
a long string.
It was pulled quickly out of my hand.
With a great feeling of fear, I turned and
saw that another enormous crab was standing
just behind me.
Its horrible eyes were moving, its mouth was
open with hunger and it was going to attack
me.
'In a moment my hand was on the lever and
I had put a month between myself and these
creatures.
But I was still on the same beach and I saw
them clearly now when I stopped.
Large numbers of them seemed to be moving
here and there, in the dull light, among the
strong green plants.
'I can't make you understand the feeling of
great emptiness that hung over the world.
The red eastern sky, the darkness to the north,
the salt Dead Sea, the thin air, all had a
horrible effect.
I moved a hundred years further into the future,
and there was the same red sun - a little
larger, a little darker - the same dying sea,
the same cold air, and the same crowd of crabs
moving slowly in and out of the green plants
and the red rocks.
And in the west I saw a curved pale line like
a large new moon.
'So I travelled, stopping now and again, in
great steps of a thousand years or more, wanting
to know what happened to the Earth.
I watched, with a strange interest, the sun
grow larger and duller in the western sky,
and the life of the old Earth die away.
At last, more than thirty million years from
now, the enormous red sun covered almost a
tenth of the darkening sky.
'Then I stopped again and the hundreds of
crabs had disappeared.
Now the red beach, except for its green plants,
seemed lifeless.
A strong cold attacked me and snow fell from
time to time.
There was ice along the edge of the sea, with
large pieces further out, but most of that
salt ocean - all bloody under the sky - was
still unfrozen.
'I looked around me to see if any animals
were still alive, but I saw nothing moving,
on the land or in the sky or sea.
A low island of sand had appeared in the sea
and the water had moved back from the beach.
I thought I saw a black object moving around
on this, but it stopped moving when I looked
at it, and I decided that it was just a rock.
The stars in the sky were very bright.
'Suddenly I noticed that the shape of the
sun in the west had changed and that something
was moving into its circle.
For a minute, perhaps, I stared in shock at
this and then I realised that either the moon
or Mercury was passing across the sun.
'It became darker and darker, a cold wind
began to blow from the east and the snow fell
more and more heavily.
Except for these lifeless sounds the world
was silent.
Silent?
It would be hard to describe the quietness
of it all.
All the everyday sounds of people, and of
sheep, birds and insects - all that had ended.
As the darkness grew, the snow fell more heavily
and it turned colder.
The soft wind grew stronger.
In another moment only the pale stars could
be seen.
Everything else was darkness.
The sky was completely black.
'This great darkness was horrible to me.
I shook, and began to feel very sick.
Then, like a red-hot curve in the sky, the
edge of the sun appeared.
I got off the machine to recover.
I felt unable to face the return journey.
As I stood there, I saw again the moving thing
on the island - there was no mistake now that
it was a moving thing - against the red water
of the sea.
It was round, the size of a football perhaps,
and long arms hung down from it.
'Then I felt that I was fainting.
But a terrible fear of lying helpless in that
awful half-darkness gave me strength while
I climbed back into the seat.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Coming Home
'So I came back.
I think I fainted in the machine.
When I felt better the change from day to
night had started again, the sun was golden
and the sky was blue.
I breathed more freely.
The shape of the land moved here and there.
At last I saw again the shadows of houses,
the signs of humans.
These, too, changed and passed, and others
came.
Soon I began to recognise our own smaller
and familiar buildings, and the hand of the
thousands dial returned to its starting point.
Then the old walls of the laboratory came
round me.
Very gently now, I slowed the machine down.
'I think I have told you that when I started,
before my speed became very high, Mrs Watchett,
my cook, had walked across the room.
She moved, as it seemed to me, very quickly.
As I returned, I passed again across that
minute and now all her movements appeared
to be the exact opposite of the ones she had
made before.
And just before that, I seemed to see you,
Hillyer, for a moment.'
The Time Traveller looked at me as he spoke.
'Then I stopped the machine, got off" it very
shakily and sat down on my chair.
For several minutes I shook violently.
Then I became calmer.
Around me was my old laboratory again, exactly
as it had been.
But not exactly!
The machine had started from the south-east
corner.
It had stopped again in the north-west.
This gives you the exact distance from my
little lawn to the pedestal of the white sphinx
into which the Morlocks had carried it.
'For a time my brain went dead.
Then I got up and came through here, limping
because my heel was still painful.
I saw the newspaper on the table by the door.
I found the date really was today and, looking
at the clock, I saw that the time was almost
eight o'clock.
I heard your voices and the sound of plates.
I smelled well-cooked meat and opened the
door to the dining- room.
You know the rest.'
He looked at the Medical Man.
'No.
I can't expect you to believe it.
Accept it as a lie - or as a guess at the
future.
Say I dreamed it in the laboratory.
But as a story, what do you think of it?'
He picked up his pipe and began, in his usual
way, to play with it in his hands.
I took my eyes off his face and looked around
at the others.
The Medical Man was staring at our host.
The Editor was looking hard at the end of
his cigarette - his sixth.
The Journalist searched in his pocket for
his watch.
The others, as I remember, did not move.
The Editor stood up and shook his head.
'What a pity that you are not a writer of
stories!' he said, putting his hand on the
Time Traveller's shoulder.
'You don't believe it?'
'Well-'
'I thought not.'
The Time Traveller turned to us.
'Where are the matches?' he said.
He lit his pipe, blowing smoke.
'To tell you the truth, I can't really believe
it myself...
But...'
His eye fell with a questioning look on the
dead white flowers on the little table.
Then he turned over the hand holding his pipe.
I saw he was looking at some red marks.
The Medical Man rose, came to the lamp and
examined the flowers.
'This one is odd,' he said.
The Psychologist bent forwards to see, holding
out his hand for one of them.
'It's strange,' said the Medical Man, 'but
I certainly don't know what type of flowers
these are.
Can I have them?'
The Time Traveller thought for a few seconds.
Then he suddenly said,' Certainly not.'
'Where did you really get them?' said the
Medical Man.
The Time Traveller put his hand to his head.
I thought he was trying to remember something.
'They were put into my pocket by Weena.'
He stared round the room.
'I'm beginning to forget it all.
Did I ever make a Time Machine, or a model
of a Time Machine?
Or is it only a dream?
I must look at that machine.
If there is one!'
He picked up the lamp quickly and carried
it through the door.
We followed him.
There in the lamplight was the machine, with
brown spots and mud on it, bits of grass on
the lower parts and one side bent.
The Time Traveller put the lamp down on the
table and touched the damaged side.
'It's all right now,' he said.
'My story was true.
I am sorry I brought you out here in the cold.'
He picked up the lamp and in total silence
we returned to the smoking room.
He came into the hall with us and helped the
Editor on with his coat.
The Medical Man looked into his face and,
after a few seconds, told him he was suffering
from too much work.
The Time Traveller laughed loudly.
I remember him standing at the open door,
shouting good night.
I walked some distance with the Editor.
He thought the story was 'a colourful lie'.
I was unable to make up my mind.
It was so strange, and the telling was so
believable and serious.
I lay awake most of the night thinking about
it.
The next day, I went to see the Time Traveller
again.
I was told he was in the laboratory.
I went there but it was empty.
I stared for a minute at the Time Machine
and put out a hand and touched the lever.
It shook like a branch in the wind.
Its movements surprised me greatly, and I
had a strange memory of childhood days, when
I was not allowed to touch things.
I went back into the smoking room and found
the Time Traveller there.
He had a small camera under one arm and a
bag under the other.
He laughed when he saw me.
'I'm very busy,' he said,' with that thing
in there.'
'But is it not a joke?'
I said.
'Do you really travel through time?'
'Really and truly I do.'
And he looked straight into my eyes.
'I only want half an hour,' he said.
'I know why you came and it is very good of
you.
There are some magazines here.
If you will stay for lunch I shall prove this
time-travelling to you completely.
I shall even bring back some things for you
to look at.
Will you forgive me if I leave you now?'
I agreed, not really understanding the full
meaning of his words, and he left the room.
I heard the door of the laboratory shut, sat
down in a chair and picked up the daily paper.
What was he going to do before lunch-time?
Then suddenly I was reminded by an advertisement
that I had promised to meet a friend at two.
I looked at my watch and saw that there was
just enough time.
I got up and went to tell the Time Traveller.
As I took hold of the handle of the laboratory
door I heard a shout, then strange noises.
A sudden wind blew round me as I opened the
door, and from inside came the sound of broken
glass falling on the floor.
The Time Traveller was not there.
I seemed to see a ghostly, unclear figure
sitting in a moving machine for a moment,
but all of this disappeared.
The Time Machine had gone.
The window was broken.
I was surprised and unable to understand.
As I stood staring, the door into the garden
opened and a servant appeared.
We looked at each other.
Then ideas began to come.
'Has Mr gone out that way?'
I said.
'No, sir.
No one has come out this way.'
And then I understood.
I stayed there, waiting for the Time Traveller;
waiting for the second, perhaps stranger story,
and the objects and photographs he would bring
with him.
But I am beginning to fear that I must wait
a lifetime.
The Time Traveller disappeared three years
ago.
And as everyone knows now, he has never returned.