CHAPTER ONE
The Strange Man's Arrival
The stranger came early one winter's day in
February, through a biting wind and the last
snowfall of the year. He walked over the hill
from Bramblehurst Station, and carried a little
black bag in his thickly gloved hand. He was
wrapped up from head to foot, and the edge
of his soft grey hat hid every part of his
face except the shiny point of his nose; the
snow had piled itself against his shoulders
and chest. He almost fell into the Coach and
Horses, more dead than alive, and threw his
bag down. 'A fire,' he cried, 'in the name
of human kindness! A room and a fire!' He
stamped his feet, shook the snow from his
coat and followed Mrs Hall, the innkeeper's
wife, into her parlour. There he arranged
to take a room in the inn and gave her two
pounds.
Mrs Hall lit the fire and left him there while
she went to prepare him a meal with her own
hands. To have a guest at Iping in the winter
time was an unusual piece of good fortune,
and she was determined to show that she deserved
it.
She put some meat on the fire to cook, told
Millie, the servant, to get the room ready
for the stranger, and carried the cloth, plates
and glasses into the parlour, and began to
lay the table. Although the fire was burning
brightly, she was surprised to see that her
visitor still wore his hat and coat, and stood
with his back to her, looking out of the window
at the falling snow in the yard.
His gloved hands were held behind him, and
he seemed to be thinking deeply. She noticed
that some melted snow was falling onto the
floor from his shoulders.
'Can I take your hat and coat, sir,' she said,
'and dry them in the kitchen?'
'No,' he replied, without turning.
She was not sure that she had heard him, and
was about to repeat the question.
He turned his head and looked at her over
his shoulder. 'I would rather keep them on,'
he said firmly; and she noticed that he wore
big blue glasses, and had a bushy beard over
his coat collar that almost hid his face.
'Very well, sir,' she said. 'As you like.
Very soon the room will be warmer.'
He made no answer, and turned his face away
from her again, and Mrs Hall, feeling that
her talk was unwelcome, finished laying the
table quickly, and hurried out of the room.
When she returned he was still standing there
like a man of stone, his collar turned up,
the edge of his hat turned down, almost hiding
his face and ears. She put down the eggs and
meat noisily, and called rather than said
to him:
'Your lunch is served, sir.'
'Thank you,' he answered. He did not move
until she was closing the door. Then he turned
round and walked eagerly up to the table.
Mrs Hall filled the butter dish in the kitchen,
and took it to the parlour.
She knocked and entered at once. As she did
so her visitor moved quickly, so that she
only saw something white disappearing behind
the table. He seemed to be picking up something
from the floor. She put down the butter dish
on the table, and noticed that the visitor's
hat and coat were hanging over a chair in
front of the fire.
'I suppose I may have them to dry now?' she
said, in a voice that could not be refused.
'Leave the hat,' said her visitor, and turning,
she saw he had raised his head and was looking
at her.
For a moment she stood looking at him, too
surprised to speak.
He held his napkin over the lower part of
his face, so that his mouth and jaws were
completely hidden. But it was not that which
surprised Mrs Hall. It was the fact that the
top of his head above his blue glasses was
covered by a white bandage, and that another
covered his ears, leaving nothing of his face
to be seen except his pink, pointed nose.
It was bright pink, and shining, just as it
had been at first. He wore a dark brown jacket,
with a high black collar turned up about his
neck. His thick black hair stuck out below
and between the bandages. This bandaged head
was so unlike what she had expected that for
a moment she stood staring at it.
He did not remove the napkin, but remained
holding it, as she saw now, with a brown-gloved
hand, and looking at her from behind his dark
glasses.
'Leave the hat,' he said, through the white
cloth.
She began to feel less afraid. She put the
hat on the chair again by the fire.
'I didn't know, sir,' she began, 'that-' and
she stopped.
'Thank you,' he said shortly, looking from
her to the door, and then at her again.
'I'll have it nicely dried, sir, at once,'
she said, and carried his coat out of the
room. She looked at his bandaged head and
dark glasses again as she was going out of
the door; but he was still holding his napkin
in front of his face. She was shaking a little
as she closed the door behind her. 'My goodness!'
she whispered. She went straight to the kitchen,
and did not even think of asking Millie what
she was doing now.
The visitor sat and listened to her footsteps.
He looked out of the window before he removed
his napkin from his face and began his meal
again. He took a mouthful, looked again at
the window, then rose and, taking the napkin
in his hand, walked across the room and pulled
down the blind. This darkened the room. He
returned more happily to the table and his
meal.
'The poor man's had an accident, or an operation
or something,' said Mrs Hall. 'What a shock
those bandages gave me.'
She put some more coal on the fire, and hung
the traveller's coat to dry. 'And the glasses!
Why, he doesn't look human at all. And holding
that napkin over his mouth all the time. Talking
through it!... Perhaps his mouth was hurt
too.'
She turned round, suddenly remembering something.
'Oh dear!' she said, 'Haven't you done those
potatoes yet, Millie?'
When Mrs Hall went to clear away the stranger's
lunch, her idea that his mouth must also have
been damaged in an accident was strengthened,
for though he was smoking a pipe, all the
time that she was in the room he kept the
lower part of his face covered. He sat in
the corner with his back to the window, and
spoke now, having eaten and drunk and being
comfortably warmed through, less impatiently
than before. The light of the fire shone red
in his glasses.
'I have some boxes,' he said, 'at Bramblehurst
Station. How can they be brought here?'
Mrs Hall answered his question, and then said,
'It's a steep road by the hill, sir. That's
where a carriage was turned over, a year ago
and more. A gentleman was killed. Accidents,
sir, happen in a moment, don't they?'
'They do.'
'But people take long enough to get well,
sir, don't they? There was my sister's son,
Tom, who cut his arm with a scythe - he fell
on it out in the fields. He was three months
tied up, sir. You'd hardly believe it. I've
been afraid of scythes ever since, sir.'
'I can quite understand that,' said the visitor.
'We were afraid that he'd have to have an
operation, he was so bad, sir.'
The visitor laughed suddenly.
'Was he?'
'He was, sir. And it wasn't funny for those
who had to nurse him as I did, my sister being
so busy with her little ones. There were bandages
to do, sir, and bandages to undo. So that
if I may say, sir-'
'Will you get me some matches?' said the visitor
quite suddenly. 'My pipe is out.'
Mrs Hall stopped. It was certainly rude of
him after she had told him so much. But she
remembered the two pounds, and went for the
matches.
'Thanks,' he said shortly, as she put them
down, and turned his back upon her and looked
out of the window again. Clearly he did not
like talking about bandages.
The visitor remained in the room until four
o'clock, without giving Mrs Hall an excuse
for a visit. He was very quiet during that
time: perhaps he sat in the growing darkness
smoking by the firelight - perhaps he slept.
Once or twice a listener might have heard
him: for five minutes he could be heard walking
up and down the room. He seemed to be talking
to himself. Then he sat down again in the
armchair.
CHAPTER TWO
Mr Henfrey Has a Shock
At four o'clock, when it was fairly dark,
and Mrs Hall was trying to find the courage
to go in and ask her visitor if he would like
some tea, Teddy Henfrey, the clock-mender,
came into the bar.
'Good evening, Mrs Hall,' said he, 'this is
terrible snowy weather for thin boots!'
Mrs Hall agreed, and then noticed he had his
bag with him. Now you're here, Mr Teddy,'
said she, 'I'd be glad if you'd look at the
old clock. It's going, and it strikes loud
and clear, but the hour hand does nothing
except point to six.'
And, leading the way, she went across to the
parlour door and knocked.
As she opened the door, she saw her visitor
seated in the armchair in front of the fire,
asleep, it seemed, with his bandaged head
leaning on one side. The only light in the
room was from the fire. Everything seemed
hidden in shadows. But for a second it seemed
to her that the man she was looking at had
a great, wide-open mouth, a mouth that swallowed
the whole of the lower part of his face. It
was too ugly to believe, the white head, the
staring glasses - and then a great hole. He
moved, sat up straight and put up his hand.
She opened the door wide, so that the room
was lighter, and she saw him more clearly,
with the napkin held to his face, just as
she had seen him hold it before. The shadows,
she thought, had tricked her.
'Would you mind, sir, if this man came to
look at the clock, sir?' she said.
'Look at the clock?' he said, staring round
sleepily and speaking over his hand; and then,
more fully awake, 'Certainly.'
Mrs Hall went away to get a lamp, and he rose
and stretched himself. Then came the light,
and at the door Mr Teddy Henfrey was met by
this bandaged person. He was, he said later,
'quite shocked'.
'Good afternoon,' said the stranger, staring
at him - as Mr Henfrey said - 'like a fish'.
'I hope,' said Mr Henfrey, 'that you don't
mind.'
'Not at all,' said the stranger. 'Though I
understood,' he said, turning to Mrs Hall,
'that this room was to be mine for my own
use.'
'I thought, sir,' said Mrs Hall, 'you'd like
the clock-'
'Certainly,' said the stranger, 'certainly;
but at other times I would like to be left
alone.'
He turned round with his back to the fireplace,
and put his hands behind his back. 'And soon,'
he said, 'when the clock is mended, I think
I should like to have some tea. But not until
then.'
Mrs Hall was about to leave the room - she
did not try to talk this time - when her visitor
asked her if she had done anything about his
boxes at Bramblehurst. She told him that the
carrier could bring them over the next day.
'You are certain that is the earliest?' he
asked. She was quite sure.
'I should explain,' he added, 'but I was really
too cold and tired to do so before, that I
am a scientist.'
'Indeed, sir,' said Mrs Hall, respectfully.
'And I need things from the boxes for my work.'
'Of course, sir.'
'My reason for coming to Iping,' he went on
slowly, 'was a desire to be alone. I do not
wish to be disturbed in my work. Besides my
work, an accident-'
'I thought so,' said Mrs Hall to herself.
'-makes it necessary for me to be quiet. My
eyes are sometimes so weak and painful that
I have to shut myself up in the dark for several
hours and lock myself in. Sometimes - now
and then. Not at present, certainly. At such
times the least thing, even a stranger coming
into the room, gives me great pain. It's important
that this should be understood.'
'Certainly, sir,' said Mrs Hall. 'And if I
might ask-'
'That, I think, is all,' said the stranger
quietly. Mrs Hall said no more.
After Mrs Hall had left the room, he remained
standing in front of the fire and watched
the clock being mended. Mr Henfrey worked
with the lamp close to him, and the green
shade threw a bright light onto his hands
and onto the frame and wheels, and left the
rest of the room in shadow. He took longer
than he needed to remove the works, hoping
to have some talk with the stranger. But the
stranger stood there, perfectly silent and
still. So still that it frightened Henfrey.
He felt alone in the room and looked up, and
there, grey and shadowy, were the bandaged
head and large dark glasses staring straight
in front of them. It was so strange to Henfrey
that for a minute they stood staring at each
other. Then Henfrey looked down again. He
would have liked to say something. Should
he say that the weather was very cold for
the time of the year?
'The weather-' he began.
'Why don't you finish and go?' said the stiff
figure, angrily. 'All you've got to do is
to fix the hour hand. You're simply wasting
time.'
'Certainly, sir - one minute more. I forgot...'
And Mr Henfrey finished and left the room.
'Really!' said Mr Henfrey to himself, walking
down the village street through the falling
snow. 'A man must mend a clock sometimes,
surely.' And then, 'Can't a man look at you?
Ugly!'
And yet again, 'It seems he can't. If you
were wanted by the police, you couldn't be
more wrapped and bandaged.'
At the street corner he saw Hall, who had
recently married the lady of the inn. 'Hello,
Teddy,' said Hall, as he passed.
'You've got a strange visitor!' said Teddy.
Hall stopped. 'What did you say?' he asked.
'A strange man is staying at the inn,' said
Teddy. And he described Mrs Hall's guest.
'It looks strange, doesn't it? I'd like to
see a man's face if I had him staying in my
house. But women are so foolish with strangers.
He's taken your rooms, and he hasn't even
given a name.'
'Is that so?' said Hall, rather stupidly.
'Yes,' said Teddy. 'And he's got a lot of
boxes coming tomorrow, so he says.'
Teddy walked on, easier in his mind.
And after the stranger had gone to bed, which
he did at about half past nine, Mr Hall went
into the parlour and looked very hard at the
furniture, just to show that the stranger
wasn't master there. When he went to bed,
he told Mrs Hall to look very closely at the
stranger's boxes when they came next day.
'You mind your own business, Hall,' said Mrs
Hall, 'and I'll mind mine.'
But in the middle of the night she woke up
dreaming of great white heads that came after
her, at the end of long necks, and with big
black eyes. But being a sensible woman, she
turned over and went to sleep again.
CHAPTER THREE
The Thousand and One Bottles
That was how, on the ninth day of February,
the stranger came to Iping village. Next day
his boxes arrived. There were two trunks,
indeed, such as any man might have, but also
there was a box of books - big, fat books,
of which some were in handwriting you couldn't
read - and 12 or more boxes and cases full
of glass bottles, or so it seemed to Hall,
as he pulled at the paper packing material.
The stranger, covered up in hat, coat and
gloves, came out impatiently to meet the carriage,
while Hall was talking to Fearenside, the
carrier, before helping to bring the boxes
in. The stranger did not notice Fearenside's
dog, who was smelling at Hall's legs.
'Come along with those boxes,' he said. 'I've
been waiting long enough.' And he came down
the steps, as if to pick up the smaller case.
As soon as Fearenside's dog caught sight of
him, however, it began to growl, and when
he ran down the steps it went straight for
his hand. Hall cried out and jumped back,
for he was not very brave with dogs, and Fearenside
shouted, 'Lie down!' and reached for his whip.
They saw that the dog's teeth had missed the
stranger's hand, heard a kick, saw the dog
jump and bite the stranger's leg, and heard
the sound of his trousers tearing. Then Fearenside's
whip cut into his dog, who, crying with pain,
ran under the wheels of the carriage. It was
all done in a quick half minute. No one spoke,
everyone shouted. The stranger looked at his
torn glove and at his leg, then turned and
ran up the steps into the inn. They heard
him go across the passage and up the stairs
to his bedroom.
'Come here, you!' said Fearenside to his dog,
climbing off the carriage with his whip in
his hand, while the dog watched him through
the wheel. 'Come here!' he repeated. 'You'd
better!'
Hall stood staring. 'He was bitten,' he said.
'I'd better go and see him.' And he went to
find the stranger. He met his wife in the
passage. 'The carrier's dog bit him,' he told
her.
He went straight upstairs, pushed open the
stranger's door and went in.
The blind was down and the room dark. He caught
sight of a strange thing, a handless arm that
seemed to be waving towards him, and a face
of three large dark spots on white. Then he
was struck in the chest and thrown out of
the room, and the door was shut in his face
and locked. All this happened so fast that
it gave him no time to see anything clearly.
A waving of shapes, a blow and a noise like
a gun. There he stood in the dark little passage,
wondering what he had seen.
After a few minutes he came back to the little
group that had formed outside the inn. There
was Fearenside telling the story all over
again for the second time; there was Mrs Hall
saying his dog had no right to bite her guests;
there was Huxter, the shopkeeper from over
the road, asking questions; Sandy Wadgers
looking serious and women and children, all
talking.
Mr Hall, staring at them from the steps and
listening, found it hard to believe that he
had seen anything very strange happen upstairs.
'He wants no help, he says,' he said in answer
to his wife's question. 'We'd better take
his luggage in.'
'He ought to have his leg looked at immediately,'
said Mr Huxter.
'I'd shoot the dog, that's what I'd do,' said
a lady in the group.
Suddenly the dog began growling again.
'Come along,' cried an angry voice in the
doorway, and there stood the stranger, with
his coat collar turned up and the edge of
his hat bent down.
'The sooner you get those things in, the better
I'll be pleased.' His trousers and gloves
had been changed.
'Were you hurt, sir?' said Fearenside. 'I'm
very sorry the dog-'
'Not at all,' said the stranger. 'It didn't
even break the skin. Hurry up with those things.'
As soon as the first box was carried into
the parlour, the stranger began to unpack
it eagerly, and from it he brought out bottles
- little fat bottles, small thin bottles,
blue bottles, bottles with round bodies and
thin necks, large green glass bottles, large
white glass bottles, wine bottles, bottles,
bottles, bottles - and put them in rows on
the table under the window, round the floor,
on the shelf - everywhere. Case after case
was full of bottles; he emptied six of the
cases and piled the packing material high
on the floor and table.
As soon as the cases were empty, the stranger
went to the window and set to work, not troubling
in the least about the paper, the fire which
had gone out, the box of books outside or
the boxes and other things that had gone upstairs.
When Mrs Hall took his dinner in to him, he
did not hear her until she had cleared away
most of the paper and had put the food on
the table.
Then he half turned his head, and turned it
away again. But she saw he had taken off his
glasses; they were beside him on the table,
and he seemed to her to have no eyes. He put
on his glasses again, and then turned and
faced her. She was about to complain about
the paper on the floor, but he spoke first.
'I wish you wouldn't come in without knocking,'
he said, angrily as usual.
'I knocked, but-'
'But in my work I cannot have any - I must
ask you-'
'Certainly, sir. You can turn the key if you
want to, you know. Any time.'
'A very good idea,' said the stranger.
'This paper, sir. If I might say-'
'Don't. If the paper is a problem, put it
on the bill.'
He was so strange, standing there, with his
bottles and his bad temper, that Mrs Hall
was quite afraid. But she was a strong-minded
woman. 'Then I should like to know, sir, what
you consider -'
'A shilling - put a shilling on my bill. Surely
a shilling's enough?'
'Very well,' said Mrs Hall, taking up the
tablecloth and beginning to spread it over
the table.
'If you're satisfied, of course-'
He turned his back on her and sat down.
All afternoon he worked with the door locked,
and almost in silence. But once there was
a noise of bottles ringing together, as though
the table had been hit, and the crash of glass
thrown down, and then came the sound of quick
walking up and down the room. Fearing something
was the matter, she went to the door and listened,
not wanting to knock.
'I can't go on,' he was shouting; 'I can't
go on! Three hundred thousand, four hundred
thousand! It may take me all my life!... Patience!
Patience, indeed!... Fool! Fool!'
There was a noise of boots on the brick floor
of the bar, and Mrs Hall could not stay to
hear any more. When she returned, the room
was silent again except for the faint sound
of his chair and now and then of a bottle.
It was all over; the stranger had returned
to his work.
Later, when she took in his tea, she saw broken
glass in the corner of the room. She pointed
at it.
'Put it on the bill,' he said. 'In God's name
don't worry me! If there's damage done, put
it on the bill.' And he went on with his writing.
'I'll tell you something,' said Fearenside.
It was late in the afternoon, and they were
in a little inn outside Iping.
'Well?' said Teddy Henfrey.
'This man you're speaking of, that my dog
bit. Well - he's black. At least his legs
are. I saw through the tear in his trousers
and the tear in his glove. You'd have expected
a sort of pink to show, wouldn't you? Well
- there was just blackness. I tell you he's
as black as my hat.'
'Good heavens!' said Henfrey. 'It's a very
strange case indeed. Why, his nose is as pink
as paint!'
'That's true,' said Fearenside. 'I know that.
And I tell you what I'm thinking. That man's
black here and white there - in pieces. And
he daren't show it. He's a kind of half-breed.
I've heard of such things before. And it's
common with horses, as anyone can see.'
CHAPTER FOUR
Mr Cuss Talks to the Stranger
The stranger rarely left the inn by day, but
in the evening he would go out, wrapped up
to the eyes, whether the weather was cold
or not, and he chose the loneliest paths.
His glasses and bandaged face under his great
black hat would appear suddenly out of the
darkness to one or two workmen going home,
and one night Teddy Henfrey, coming out of
the Dog and Duck, was frightened by the stranger's
white, round head (he was walking hat in hand)
lit by the sudden light of the open inn door.
It seemed doubtful whether the stranger hated
boys more than they hated him, but there was
certainly hatred enough on both sides.
Of course they talked about him in Iping,
and were unable to decide what his business
was. Mrs Hall said he 'discovered things',
that he had had an accident, and that he did
not like people to see the ugly marks on his
body. Some said that he was a criminal hiding
from the police, and others that he was part
white and part black, and 'if he chose to
show himself at fairs he would make a great
deal of money'. A few thought that he was
simply and harmlessly mad. And in the end
some of the women began to think that he was
a spirit or a magician.
No one liked him, for he was always angry
and never friendly. They drew to one side
as he passed down the village street, and
when he had gone by young men would put their
coat collars up and turn the edges of their
hats down, and follow him for a joke.
Cuss, the doctor, was interested in the bandages
and bottles. All through April and May he
wanted to talk to the stranger, and at last
he could bear it no longer and went to visit
him. He was surprised to find that Mr Hall
did not know his guest's name.
'He gave a name,' said Mrs Hall - this was
untrue - 'but I didn't hear it properly.'
She thought it seemed silly not to know the
man's name.
Cuss could hear swearing inside the parlour.
He knocked at the door and entered.
'Please forgive me for breaking in on you,'
said Cuss, and then the door closed and shut
out Mrs Hall.
She could hear the sound of voices for the
next ten minutes, then a cry of surprise,
a moving of feet, a chair being knocked over,
a laugh, quick steps to the door, and Cuss
appeared, his face white, his eyes staring
over his shoulder. He left the door open behind
him and, without looking at her, went across
the hall and down the steps, and she heard
his feet hurrying along the road. He carried
his hat in his hand. She stood behind the
bar, looking at the open door of the parlour.
Then she heard the stranger laughing quietly,
and his footsteps came across the room. She
could not see his face from where she stood.
The parlour door shut loudly, and the place
was silent again.
Cuss went straight up the village to Bunting,
the vicar.
'Am I mad?' Cuss began, as he entered the
little study. 'Do I look like a madman?'
'What's happened?' asked the vicar.
'That man at the inn...'
'Well?'
'Give me something to drink,' said Cuss, and
he sat down.
When his nerves had been steadied by a glass
of wine he said, 'As I went in, he put his
hands in his pockets and then he sat down
in his chair. I told him I'd heard he took
an interest in scientific things. He said,
"Yes." I tried to talk to him. He got quite
angry... Well, he told me that he had had
a piece of paper. It was important, most important,
most valuable. A list of... "Was it medicine?"
I asked. "Why do you want to know?" was his
answer. In any case, this paper was of great
value. He had read it, put it down on the
table and looked away. Then the wind had lifted
it and blown it into the fire. He saw it go
up the chimney. Just as he told me that, he
lifted his arm. The sleeve was empty. I could
see right up it. What can keep a sleeve up
and open if there's nothing in it?
"How can you move an empty sleeve like that?"
I asked.
"Empty sleeve?" he said.
"Yes," I said, "an empty sleeve."
"It's an empty sleeve, is it? You saw it was
an empty sleeve?" He stood up. I stood up
too. He came towards me in three very slow
steps, and stood quite close.
"You said it was an empty sleeve?" he said.
"Certainly," I said.
Then very quietly he pulled his sleeve out
of his pocket again, and raised his arm towards
me, as though he would show it to me again.
He did it very, very slowly. I looked at it,
holding my breath. "Well?" I said, clearing
my throat; "there's nothing in it."
'I was beginning to feel frightened. I could
see right down it. He put it out straight
towards me, slowly, slowly - just like that
- until it was 6 inches from my face. Just
imagine seeing an empty sleeve come at you
like that! And then-'
'Well?'
'Something - it felt exactly like a finger
and a thumb - pulled my nose.'
Bunting began to laugh.
'There wasn't anything there!' said Cuss,
his voice rising to a shout at the "there".
'You may laugh if you like, but I tell you
I was so shocked that I hit his sleeve hard
and turned round and ran out of the room I
left him-'
Cuss stopped. It was easy to see that he was
afraid. He turned round in a helpless way,
and took a second glass of wine. 'When I hit
his sleeve,' he said, 'I tell you, it felt
exactly like hitting an arm. And there wasn't
an arm! There wasn't any arm at all!'
Mr Bunting thought it over. 'It's a very strange
story,' he said. He looked very serious. 'It
really is a very strange story indeed.'
CHAPTER FIVE
The Robbery at the Vicarage
The robbery at the Vicarage happened in the
early hours of Whit Monday, the day when Iping
held its spring fair. Mrs Bunting, it seems,
woke up suddenly in the stillness that comes
before the sunrise, with a strong feeling
that the door of their bedroom had opened
and closed. She did not wake her husband at
first, but sat up in bed listening. She then
clearly heard the sound of bare feet coming
out of the next room and walking along the
passage towards the stairs. As soon as she
felt sure of this, she woke her husband as
quietly as she could. He did not light the
lamp, but put on his glasses and a pair of
soft shoes, and went out of the bedroom to
listen. He heard quite clearly someone moving
in the study downstairs, and then the sound
of a violent sneeze.
At that he returned to his bedroom, armed
himself with the poker, and went downstairs
as silently as he could. Mrs Bunting stood
at the top of the stairs.
It was about four o'clock, and the last darkness
of the night had passed. There was a faint
light in the passage; the study door stood
half open. Everything was quiet and still,
except the sound of the stairs under Mr Buntings
feet, and the slight movements in the study.
He heard a drawer being opened, and a sound
of papers. Then came some swearing, and a
match was struck, and the study was full of
yellow light. Mr Bunting was now in the hall,
and through the half-open door he could see
the desk, an open drawer, and a lamp burning
on the desk. But he could not see the thief.
He stood there considering what to do, and
Mrs Bunting, her face white with fear, walked
slowly downstairs after him.
They heard the noise of coins, and knew that
the thief had found the housekeeping money
- two pounds and ten shillings in gold and
silver. That sound made Mr Bunting very angry.
Holding the poker firmly, he ran into the
room, closely followed by Mrs Bunting.
'Come on, my dear,' and then Mr Bunting stopped.
The room was perfectly empty.
But they knew that they had heard someone
moving in the room. They stood still for half
a minute. Then Mrs Bunting went across the
room and looked behind the curtain, while
Mr Bunting looked under the desk and up the
chimney, and pushed the poker up into the
darkness. Then they stood still looking at
each other questioningly.
'I was quite sure -' said Mrs Bunting.
'The lamp!' said Mr Bunting. 'Who lit the
lamp?'
'The drawer!' said Mrs Bunting. 'And the money's
gone!'
She went quickly to the doorway.
'Who in the world -'
There was a loud sneeze in the passage. They
rushed out, and as they did so the kitchen
door closed!
'Bring the lamp!' said Mr Bunting, and led
the way.
As he opened the kitchen door, he saw the
back door opening. The garden beyond was lit
by the first, faint light of sunrise. He was
certain that nothing went out of the door.
It stood open for a moment, and then closed
with a loud bang. They searched outside for
a minute or more before they came back into
the kitchen.
The place was empty. They locked the back
door and examined the kitchen and all the
rooms thoroughly. There was no one to be found
in the house, though they searched upstairs
and down.
When daylight came, the vicar and his wife
were still searching by the unnecessary light
of the dying lamp.
'Of all the surprising events, this is -' began
the vicar for the twentieth time.
'My dear,' said Mrs Bunting, 'there's the
servant coming down. Just wait here until
she has gone into the kitchen, and then go
upstairs.'
CHAPTER SIX
The Furniture That Went Mad
When Mr Hall came downstairs in the early
hours of Whit Monday, he noticed that the
stranger's door was open and the front door
unlocked. He remembered holding the lamp while
Mrs Hall locked it the night before. At the
sight of the front door he stopped; then he
went upstairs again. He knocked at the stranger's
door. There was no answer. He knocked again;
then pushed the door wide open and entered.
It was as he expected. The bed, the room too,
was empty. And what was still more strange,
on the bed and chair were scattered the clothes,
the only clothes so far as he knew, and the
bandages of their guest. His big hat was hanging
on the bedpost.
As Mr Hall stood there he heard his wife's
voice coming from the kitchen.
He turned and hurried down to her.
'Jenny,' he said, 'he's not in his room and
the front door is unlocked.'
At first Mrs Hall did not understand, but
as soon as she did she determined to see the
empty room for herself. Hall went first. 'If
he's not there, his clothes are. And what
is he doing without his clothes?'
As they came out of the kitchen they both
thought they heard the front door open and
shut but, seeing it closed and seeing nothing
there, neither said a word to the other about
it at the time. Mrs Hall passed her husband
in the passage, and ran on first upstairs.
Someone on the staircase sneezed. Mr Hall,
following six steps behind, thought that he
heard her sneeze; she, going first, thought
that he was sneezing. She threw open the door
and stood looking round the room. 'What a
strange thing!' she said.
She heard a cough close behind her, as it
seemed, and, turning, was surprised to see
her husband some distance away on the top
stair. But in another moment he was beside
her. She put her hand under the bedcovers.
'Cold,' she said. 'He's been up an hour or
more.'
At that point, a most unexpected thing happened.
The bedcovers pulled themselves together into
a pile, and then jumped violently off the
bed. It was just as if a hand had thrown them
to one side. Then the stranger's hat jumped
off the bedpost, flew through the air, and
came straight at Mrs Hall's face. Next, a
piece of soap flew from the washstand. Finally
the chair threw the stranger's coat and trousers
carelessly onto the floor, laughed in a voice
very like the stranger's, turned itself round
so that its four legs pointed at Mrs Hall,
seemed to take aim at her for a moment, and
then moved quickly towards her. She cried
out and turned, and the chair legs landed
gently but firmly against her back and pushed
her and Mr Hall out of the room. The door
shut loudly and was locked. The chair and
the bed seemed to be dancing for a moment,
and then suddenly everything was still.
Mrs Hall was left almost fainting in Mr Hall's
arms in the passage. It was with the greatest
difficulty that Mr Hall and Millie, now dressed,
succeeded in getting her downstairs.
'Spirits,' said Mrs Hall. 'I know it's spirits.
I've read about them in the papers. Tables
and chairs dancing.'
'Lock him out,' she went on. 'Don't let him
come in again. I half guessed... I might have
known. With those eyes and that bandaged head,
and never going to church on Sunday. And all
those bottles - more than it's right for anyone
to have. He's put the spirits into the furniture...
My good old furniture! My poor dear mother
used to sit in that chair when I was a little
girl. And now it rises against me!'
They sent Millie across the street through
the golden five o'clock sunshine to wake up
Mr Sandy Wadgers, who was clever and might
be able to help them.
'Magic,' said Mr Wadgers and came to the inn
greatly troubled. They wanted him to lead
the way upstairs to the room, but he didn't
seem to be in any hurry. He preferred to talk
in the passage. Then Mr Huxter came and joined
in the talk. There was a great deal of talking,
but nothing was done.
'Let's have the facts first,' said Mr Sandy
Wadgers. 'Let's be sure we'd be acting perfectly
right in breaking that door open.'
And suddenly the door of the room upstairs
opened by itself, and they saw coming down
the stairs the wrapped-up figure of the stranger
staring more blackly than ever through those
large glasses. He came down stiffly and slowly,
staring all the time; he walked across the
passage, staring, and then stopped.
He entered the parlour, and suddenly and angrily
shut the door in their faces.
Not a word was spoken until the noise of the
door had died away. They looked at one another.
'Well, I've never seen anything like it!'
said Mr Wadgers, more troubled than ever.
'If I were you, I'd go in and ask him about
it,' Mr Wadgers advised Mr Hall. 'I'd demand
an explanation.'
It took some time to persuade Mr Hall to do
it. At last he knocked, opened the door, and
got as far as:
'Excuse me-'
'Go to the devil!' said the stranger, 'and
shut that door after you.'
And that was all.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Stranger Shows His Face
It was half past five when the stranger went
into the little parlour of the Coach and Horses,
and there he remained until nearly midday,
with the blinds down and the door shut, and
nobody went near him.
All that time he could have eaten nothing.
Three times he rang his bell, the third time
loud and long, but no one answered him. 'Telling
us to go to the devil, indeed!' said Mrs Hall.
Soon came the story of the robbery at the
Vicarage, and that started them thinking.
Hall went off with Wadgers to find Mr Shuckleforth,
the lawyer, and take his advice. No one went
upstairs, and no one knew what the stranger
was doing. Now and then he walked rapidly
up and down, and they heard him swearing,
tearing paper, breaking bottles.
The little group grew bigger. Mrs Huxter came
over; some young fellows joined them. There
was a stream of unanswered questions. Young
Archie Harker tried to look under the closed
curtains. He could see nothing, but he was
soon joined by other boys.
And inside in the darkness of the parlour,
the stranger, hungry and afraid, hidden in
his uncomfortable hot clothes, stared through
his dark glasses at his paper, or shook his
dirty little bottles or swore at the boys
outside the windows. In the corner by the
fireplace lay the pieces of several broken
bottles, and the sharp smell of a strange
gas filled the air.
At about midday he suddenly opened his parlour
door and stood looking at the three or four
people in the bar. 'Mrs Hall,' he said. Somebody
went and called for her.
She soon appeared, a little short of breath,
and so even more angry. Hall was still out.
She had had time to think now, and had brought
the stranger's unpaid bill.
'Why wasn't my breakfast laid?' he asked.
'Why haven't you prepared my meals and answered
my bell? Do you think I can live without eating?'
'Why isn't my bill paid?' said Mrs Hall. 'That's
what I want to know.'
'I told you three days ago I was expecting
some money-'
'I told you three days ago I wasn't going
to wait. You can't complain if your breakfast
waits a bit, when my bill's been waiting for
five days, can you?'
The stranger swore in answer.
'And I'd thank you, sir, if you'd keep your
swearing to yourself sir,' said Mrs Hall.
'Look here, my good woman-' he began.
'Don't call me your good woman,' said Mrs
Hall.
'I've told you my money hasn't come.'
'Money, indeed!' said Mrs Hall.
'Still, in my pocket-'
'You told me three days ago that you hadn't
anything but a pound's worth of silver on
you.'
'Well, I've found some more.'
'And where did you find that?' said Mrs Hall.
He stamped his foot. 'What do you mean?' he
said.
'I mean where did you find it?' said Mrs Hall.
'And before I take any money, or get any breakfasts,
or do any such things, you must tell me one
or two things that I don't understand, and
that nobody understands, and that everybody
is very anxious to understand. I want to know
what you have been doing to my chair upstairs,
and I want to know why you went out of your
bedroom and how you got in again. Those who
stay here come in by the doors - that's the
rule of this house, and you didn't do that,
and what I want to know is how you did come
in. And I want to know-'
Suddenly the stranger raised his gloved hands,
stamped his toot, and said 'Stop!' so loudly
that he silenced her at once.
'You don't understand,' he said, 'who I am
or what I am. I'll show you. By heaven! I'll
show you.' He put his open hand over his face
and then took it away. His face became a black
hole. Here,' he said. He stepped forward and
handed Mrs Hall something which she, staring
at his face, took without thinking. Then,
when she saw what it was, she screamed loudly
and dropped it. The nose - it was the stranger's
nose, pink and shining! - rolled on the floor.
Then he removed his glasses, and everyone
in the bar breathed deeply. He took off his
hat, and tore at his beard and bandages.
It was worse than anything they had ever seen.
Mrs Hall, open-mouthed with terror, ran to
the door of the house.
Everyone began to move. They had expected
burns, wounds, something ugly, but they saw
- nothing! The bandages and false hair flew
across the passage into the bar. Everyone
fell over everyone else down the steps. For
the man who stood there shouting was a man
up to the shoulders, and then - nothing!
People down in the village heard shouts and
saw the people rushing out of the inn. They
saw Mrs Hall fall down, and Mr Henfrey jump,
so as not to fall over her, and then they
heard the frightful cries of Millie, who,
running quickly from the kitchen at the noise,
had come on the headless stranger from behind.
Then her cries stopped suddenly.
Everyone in the village street, old and young,
about forty or more of them, collected in
a crowd around the inn door.
'What was he doing?'
'Ran at them with a knife.'
'I heard the girl.'
'No head, I tell you.'
'Nonsense.'
'Took off his bandages.'
Everyone spoke at once. Suddenly Mr Hall appeared,
very red and determined, then Mr Bobby Jaffers,
the village policeman and then the serious
Mr Wadgers.
Mr Hall marched up the steps, walked straight
to the door of the parlour and found it open.
'Policeman,' he said, 'do your duty.'
Jaffers marched in, Hall next, Wadgers last.
They saw the headless figure facing them,
with a half-eaten piece of bread in one gloved
hand and a piece of cheese in the other.
'That's him,' said Hall.
'What the devil's this?' came in an angry
voice from above the collar of the strange
figure.
'Well, Mister,' said Jaffers, 'I've got to
arrest you, head or no head.'
'Keep off!' said the stranger, jumping back.
He took off his glove and with it struck Jaffers
in the face. In another moment Jaffers had
seized him by the handless wrist, and caught
his invisible throat. He got a hard kick that
made him shout with pain, but he kept his
hold. A chair stood in the way, and fell with
a crash as they came down together.
'Get hold of his feet,' said Jaffers between
his teeth to the other men.
When he tried to obey this order, Mr Hall
received a great kick in the chest that finished
him for a time; and Mr Wadgers, seeing that
the headless stranger had rolled over and
got on top of Jaffers, went backwards towards
the door, and so fell against Mr Huxter and
another man coming to help the policeman.
Four bottles fell and broke on the floor,
filling the room with a powerful smell.
'I give in,' said the stranger, though he
had thrown Jaffers down; and in another moment
he stood up, shaking, breathless. A strange
thing, he looked, without head or hands. His
voice seemed to come out of nothing. Jaffers
also got up.
The stranger ran his arm down his coat, and
the buttons to which his empty sleeve pointed
became undone. Then he bent down and seemed
to touch his shoes.
'Why!' said Huxter suddenly, 'That's not a
man at all. It's just empty clothes. Look!
You can see down his collar and his shirt.
I could put my arm-'
He stretched out his hand; it seemed to meet
something in the air, and he pulled it back
with a sharp cry of surprise.
I wish you'd keep your fingers out of my eye,'
shouted the voice in anger. 'The fact is,
I'm all here - head, hands, legs, and all
the rest of it, but it happens I'm invisible.
But that's no reason why you should put your
fingers in my eye, is it?'
The suit of clothes, now all unbuttoned, stood
up.
Several other men had now come into the room,
so that it was crowded.
'Invisible, eh?' said Huxter. 'Who ever heard
of such a-'
'It's strange, perhaps, but it's not a crime.
Why am I attacked by a policeman in this way?'
'Ah! That's different,' said Jaffers. 'I can't
see you, but I have orders to arrest you,
not because you can't be seen, but because
a house has been robbed.'
'Well?'
'And it looks as if-'
'Nonsense,' said the Invisible Man.
'I hope so, sir. But I've got my orders.'
Suddenly the man sat down, and before anyone
could think of stopping him, he had thrown
off all his clothes - all except his shirt.
'Here, stop that,' said Jaffers suddenly.
'Hold him,' he cried. 'If he gets his shirt
of-'
'Hold him,' shouted everyone, and there was
a rush at the white shirt, which was now all
that could be seen of the stranger.
The shirt sleeve struck a blow in Hall's face
that sent him backward into old Toothsome,
the gravedigger, and in another moment the
shirt was lifted up, just like a shirt that
is being pulled over a man's head. Jaffers
tore at it but only helped to pull it off.
He was struck in the mouth out of the air,
and lifted his stick and hit Teddy Henfrey
hard on the top of his head.
'Look out!' cried everybody, hitting everywhere
at nothing. 'Hold him! Shut the door! Don't
let him go! I've got something! Here he is!'
Everybody was being hit at once, falling on
one another. Sandy Wadgers opened the door
and they fell out. The hitting went on. One
man had a tooth broken, another a swollen
ear. Jaffers was struck under the jaw. He
caught at something hard that stood between
him and Huxter. Then the whole mass of struggling,
excited men fell out into the crowded hall.
The battle moved quickly to the house door.
There were excited cries of 'Hold him!'
'Invisible!', and a young man, a stranger
to the place, rushed in, caught something,
missed his hold, and fell over another man's
body. Halfway across the road a woman fainted
as something pushed past her, a dog ran growling
into Huxter's yard, and with that the Invisible
Man was gone.
For a moment people stood, not knowing what
to do. And then they ran, scattered as the
wind scatters dead leaves.
But Jaffers lay quite still, face upward and
knees bent.
CHAPTER EIGHT
On the Road
Mr Thomas Marvel, a tramp, had removed his
boots and was sitting by the roadside airing
his feet and looking sadly at his toes. They
were the best boots he had worn for a long
time, but he hated them for their ugliness
and their size. 'The ugliest boots in the
whole world, I should think,' he said.
'They're boots, anyway,' said a Voice.
'Yes,' Mr Marvel agreed. 'They were given
to me. Too large. I'm tired of them. That's
why I've been begging for boots, boots, boots
everywhere, but no one has any to give away.'
'Hm,' said the Voice.
'No. I've been begging for boots round here
for ten years. I've got all my boots around
here, and now look at them - they're the best
they can find for me.'
He turned his head over his shoulder to look
at the boots of the speaker - but they weren't
there. There were neither boots nor legs - nothing.
'Where are you?' he asked. He saw the road,
the open country, but no sign of any man except
himself. 'Am I mad? I must be seeing things.'
'No, you aren't,' said the Voice. 'Don't be
frightened.'
'Frightened, frightened!' said Mr Marvel.
'Come here. Where are you?'
'Don't be frightened,' said the Voice.
'You'll be frightened soon. Let me get hold
of you. Are you buried?'
There was no answer. Mr Marvel began to put
on his coat.
'I could have sworn I heard a voice.'
'So you did.'
'It's there again,' said Mr Marvel, closing
his eyes and running his hand across his forehead.
'I must have gone mad.'
'Don't be a fool,' said the Voice. 'You think
I'm just in your imagination - just in your
mind?'
'What else can you be?' said Mr Marvel, rubbing
the back of his neck.
'Very well,' said the Voice, 'I'm going to
throw stones at you until you think differently.'
'But where are you?'
The Voice made no answer. A stone came whistling
through the empty air and just missed Mr Marvel's
shoulder. He turned round and saw a stone
jump up into the air, hang there for moment,
and fall at his feet. Another came and hit
his bare toes which made Mr Marvel cry aloud.
Then he started to run, fell over something
unseen, and came to rest sitting by the road.
'Now,' said the Voice, 'am I just in your
mind?'
Mr Marvel struggled to his feet, and was immediately
rolled over again. He lay quiet for a moment.
'If you struggle anymore,' said the Voice,
'I'll throw this stone at your head.'
'I'm finished,' said Mr Thomas Marvel, sitting
up and taking his wounded toe in his hand.
'I don't understand it. Stones throwing themselves.
Stones talking. I'm finished.'
'It's very simple,' said the Voice. 'I'm an
invisible man.'
'Tell me something I don't know,' said Mr
Marvel, white with the pain. 'Where you're
hidden - how you do it - I don't know.'
'I'm invisible,' said the Voice. 'That's what
I want you to understand.
'Anyone can see that. There's no need for
you to be so angry. Now then. Give us an idea.
Where are you hidden?'
'I'm invisible. That's the point. And what
I want you to understand is this-'
'But where are you?' interrupted Mr Marvel.
'Here - six yards in front of you.'
'Oh, no! I'm not blind. You'll be telling
me next you're just thin air.'
'Yes. I am - thin air. You're looking through
me.'
'What! Isn't there anything in you?'
'I am just a human being - solid, needing
food and drink, needing clothes, too... But
I'm invisible. You see? Invisible. Simple
idea. Invisible.'
'What, are you real?'
'Yes, real.'
'Let me feel your hand,' said Marvel, 'if
you are real.'
He felt with his fingers the hand that had
closed round his wrist and his touch went
up the arm, found a chest, and touched a bearded
face.
Mr Marvel's own face showed shock and surprise.
'Of course, all this isn't half so strange
as you think,' said the Invisible Man.
'It's quite strange enough for me,' said Mr
Marvel. 'How do you manage it? How is it done?'
'It's a very long story. And besides-'
'I tell you, the whole business is - I can't
understand,' said Mr Marvel.
'What I want to say now is this: I need help.
I need help immediately. I came on you suddenly.
I was wandering around helpless, without clothes.
And I saw you-'
'Oh, Lord!' said Mr Marvel.
'I came up behind you, stopped, went on, then
stopped again. "Here," I said to myself, "is
the man for me." So I turned and came back
to you. You. And-'
'Oh, Lord!' said Mr Marvel. 'May I ask: What
does it feel like? And what kind of help do
you need? Invisible!'
'I want you to help me get clothes and shelter,
and then other things. I've left those things
long enough. If you won't - well!... But you
will - you must.'
'Look here,' said Mr Marvel. 'Don't knock
me about any more. And let me go. I must get
my breath back. And you've very nearly broken
my toe. It's all so unreasonable. Empty earth,
empty sky. Nothing visible for miles except
Nature. And then comes a voice. A voice out
of heaven! And stones. And a hand. Lord!'
'Pull yourself together,' said the Voice,
'for you have to do the work I want you to
do.'
Mr Marvel's mouth opened wide, and his eyes
were round.
'I've chosen you,' said the Voice. 'You are
the only man except some of those fools down
there who knows there is such a thing as an
Invisible Man. You have to be my helper. Help
me - and I will do great things for you. An
Invisible Man is a man of great power.' He
stopped for a moment to sneeze loudly.
'But if you trick me,' he said, 'if you fail
to do as I tell you-'
He paused and took hold of Mr Marvel's shoulder.
Mr Marvel gave a cry of terror at the touch.
'I don't want to trick you,' he said, moving
away from the fingers. 'Don't think that,
whatever you do. All I want to do help you
- just tell me what I have got to do. Whatever
you want done, I shall be pleased to do it.'
At about four o'clock, a stranger entered
the village from the direction of the hills.
He was a short, fat person in a dirty old
hat and he seemed to be very much out of breath.
There was fear in his face, and he seemed
to be talking to himself. Some of the village
men noticed him. Mr Huxter saw him go up the
steps of the inn, and turn towards the parlour.
Mr Huxter heard voices from the parlour telling
the man that he must not go in.
'That room's private!' said Mr Hall, and the
stranger shut the door and went into the bar.
A few minutes later he came out again, rubbing
his mouth as if he had been having a drink.
He stood looking around him for a few moments,
and then walked towards the gates of the yard,
where the parlour window was. He leant against
one of the gateposts and took out a short
pipe. Although he seemed calm, his hands were
trembling.
Suddenly he put the pipe back in his pocket
and disappeared into the yard. Immediately
Mr Huxter, guessing that the man was a thief,
ran out of his shop to stop him. As he did
so, Mr Marvel reappeared, carrying some clothes
tied together in one hand and three books
in the other. As soon as he saw Huxter he
turned and began to run towards the hill road.
'Stop thief!' cried Huxter, and set off after
him.
Mr Huxter had hardly gone any distance at
all when something seized his leg and sent
him flying through the air. He saw the ground
suddenly move towards his face, and then - nothing.
CHAPTER NINE
In the Coach and Horses
At the time when Mr Marvel went into the inn,
Mr Cuss and Mr Bunting were in the parlour,
searching the stranger's property in the hope
of finding something to explain the events
of the morning. Jaffers had recovered from
his fall and had gone home. Mrs Hall had tidied
the stranger's clothes and put them away.
And under the window where the stranger did
his work, Mr Cuss found three big books.
'Now,' said Cuss, 'we shall learn something.'
But when they opened the books they could
read nothing Cuss turned the pages.
'Dear me,' he said, 'I can't understand.'
'No pictures, nothing to show-?' asked Mr
Bunting.
'See for yourself,' said Mr Cuss, 'it's all
Greek or Russian or some other language.'
The door opened suddenly. Both men looked
round. It was Mr Marvel. He held the door
open for a moment.
'I beg your pardon,' he said.
'Please shut that door,' said Mr Cuss, and
Mr Marvel went out. 'My nerves - my nerves
are in pieces today,' said Mr Cuss. 'It made
me jump when the door opened like that.'
Mr Bunting smiled. 'Now let us look at the
books again. It's true that strange things
have been happening in the village. But of
course I can't believe in an invisible man.
I can't.'
'No. Though I tell you I saw right down his
sleeve.'
'But are you sure?' said Mr Bunting. 'Are
you quite sure?'
'Quite. I've said so. There's no doubt at
all. Now let's look at these books.'
They turned over the pages, unable to read
a word of their strange language. Suddenly
Mr Bunting felt something take hold of the
back of his neck. He was unable to lift his
head.
'Don't move, little men, or I'll knock your
brains out.'
Mr Bunting looked at Cuss, whose face had
turned white with fear.
'I am sorry to be rough,' said the Voice.
'Since when did you learn to look through
other men's possessions?'
Two noses struck the table. 'To come unasked
into a stranger's private room! Listen. I
am a strong man. I could kill you both and
escape unseen, if I wanted to. If I let you
go, you must promise to do as I tell you.'
'Yes,' said Mr Bunting.
Then the hands let their necks go and the
two men sat up, now very red in the face.
'Don't move,' said the Voice. 'Here's the
poker, you see.' They saw the poker dance
in the air. It touched Mr Bunting's nose.
'Now, where are my clothes? Just now, though
the days are quite warm enough for an invisible
man to run about without anything on, the
evenings are cold. I want some clothes. And
I must also have those three books.'
CHAPTER TEN
The Invisible Man Loses His Temper
While these things were going on in the parlour,
and while Mr Huxter was watching Mr Marvel
as he leaned smoking his pipe against the
gate, Mr Hall and Teddy Henfrey stood talking
nearby.
Suddenly there came a loud knock on the door
of the parlour, a cry, and then - silence.
'Hel-lo!' said Teddy Henfrey. 'Hel-lo!' from
the bar. Mr Hall and Teddy looked at the door.
'Something's wrong,' said Hall.
For a long time they listened. Strange noises
were coming from behind the closed door, as
if something was falling about. Then a sharp
cry.
'No! No, you don't.' Then silence.
'What's that?' exclaimed Henfrey in a low
voice.
'Is everything all right there?' called Hall.
'Quite ri-ight,' came Mr Bunting's voice,
'qui-ite! Don't come in!'
They stood listening.
'I can't', they heard Mr Bunting say. 'I tell
you, sir, I will not.'
'Who's that speaking now?' asked Henfrey.
'Mr Cuss, I suppose,' said Hall. 'Can you
hear anything?'
Silence.
'Someone is throwing the table around,' said
Hall.
Mrs Hall appeared behind the bar. When they
told her, she would not believe anything strange
was happening. Perhaps they were moving the
chairs and table.
'Didn't I hear the window?' said Henfrey.
'What window?' asked Mrs Hall.
'The parlour window,' said Henfrey.
Everyone stood listening. Mrs Hall, looking
straight in front of her, saw, without seeing,
the bright shape of the inn door, the white
road, and Huxter's shop-front shining in the
June sun. Suddenly Huxter's door opened, and
Huxter appeared, his eyes staring with excitement,
his arms waving in the air.
'Stop thief!' cried Huxter, and he ran towards
the yard gates and disappeared.
At the same time a noise came from the parlour,
and there was the sound of windows being closed.
Hall, Henfrey, and everyone in the bar rushed
out into the street. They saw someone run
round the corner towards the hill road, and
Mr Huxter jump into the air and fall on his
face and shoulder. Hall and two workmen ran
down the street and saw Mr Marvel disappearing
past the church wall.
But Hall had hardly run 12 yards when he gave
a loud shout and fell on his side, pulling
one of the workmen with him. The second workman
came up, and he too was knocked down. They
came the rush of the village crowd. The first
man was surprised to see Huxter and Hall on
the ground. Suddenly something happened to
his feet, and he was lying on his back, the
crowd was falling over him, and he was being
sworn at by a number of angry people.
When Hall, Henfrey and the workmen ran out
of the house Mrs Hall had remained in the
bar. Suddenly the parlour door was opened,
Mr Cuss appeared and, without looking at her,
rushed down the steps towards the corner of
the street.
'Hold him!' he cried. 'Don't let him drop
those books and clothes! You can see him so
long as he holds them.'
He knew nothing of Marvel; for the Invisible
Man had handed over the books and clothes
to him in the yard. The face of Mr Cuss was
angry and determined, but there was something
wrong with his clothes: he was wearing a tablecloth.
'Hold him!' he shouted. 'He's got my trousers
- and all the vicar's clothes!'
Coming round the corner to join the crowd,
he was knocked off his feet and lay kicking
on the ground. Somebody stepped on his finger.
He struggled to his feet, something knocked
against him and threw him on his knees again,
and he saw that everyone was running back
to the village. He rose again, and was hit
behind the ear. He set off straight back to
the village inn as fast as he could run, and
on his way jumped over the body of Huxter,
who was now sitting up.
Behind him, as he was halfway up the inn steps,
he heard a sudden cry of anger above the noise,
and the sound of someone being struck in the
face. He knew the voice as that of the Invisible
Man.
In another moment Mr Cuss was back in the
parlour.
'He's coming back, Bunting!' he said, rushing
in. 'Save yourself!'
Mr Bunting was standing in the window, trying
to dress himself in the curtains and a newspaper.
'Who's coming?' he said, so surprised that
his dress nearly fell off him.
'The Invisible Man!' said Cuss, and rushed
to the window. 'We'd better move - quick.
He's fighting like a madman!' In another moment
he was out in the yard.
Mr Bunting heard a frightful struggle in the
passage of the inn, and decided to leave.
He climbed out of the window, and ran up the
village street as fast as his fat little legs
could carry him.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Mr Marvel Tries to Say No
Mr Marvel was walking painfully through the
thick woods on the road to Bramblehurst. He
looked very unhappy and was carrying three
books and some clothes wrapped in a blue tablecloth.
A Voice went with him and he was held tightly
by unseen hands.
'If you try to escape again,' said the Voice,
'I will kill you.'
'I didn't try to escape,' said Mr Marvel.
The Voice swore a few times and then stopped.
Mr Marvel, who was not used to so much work,
was very tired. There was silence for a time.
Then, 'I shall have to make use of you. You
are a poor creature, but I must.'
'Yes, I am,' said Marvel.
'You are,' said the Voice.
'I'm not strong,' said Marvel. Then after
a short silence he repeated, 'I'm not strong.
I've got a weak heart. I can't do what you
want.'
'I'll make you,' said the Voice.
'I wish I was dead,' said Marvel.
'Go on! Walk! Move!' said the Voice.
'It's cruel,' said Marvel.
'Be quiet,' said the Voice. 'I'll see that
you're all right. But be quiet. I want to
think.'
Soon they saw the lights of a village.
'I shall keep my hand on your shoulder,' said
the Voice. 'Go straight through the village,
and don't try to say anything to anybody.'
CHAPTER TWELVE
At Port Stowe
At ten o'clock the next morning Mr Marvel,
dirty, tired, and worried, sat outside a little
inn at Port Stowe. Beside him were the books,
but now they were tied up with string. He
had left the clothes in the woods beyond Bramblehurst.
Mr Marvel sat on a wooden seat and, although
no one took any notice of him, he seemed excited.
When he had been sitting for nearly an hour
an old sailor, with a newspaper in his hand,
came out of the inn and sat down beside him.
'Pleasant day,' said the sailor.
Mr Marvel looked around him with eyes that
were full of terror. 'Very,' he replied.
The sailor looked around him as if he had
nothing to do, and then at Mr Marvel's dusty
clothes and the books beside him. He had heard
the sound of money being dropped into a pocket,
and thought that Mr Marvel did not look like
a man who would carry much money.
'Books?' he said suddenly.
Mr Marvel jumped and looked at them. 'Oh,
yes,' he said. 'Yes, they're books.'
'There are some strange things in books,'
said the sailor.
'There are,' said Mr Marvel.
'And some strange things out of them,' said
the sailor.
'True,' said Mr Marvel.
'There are some strange things in newspapers,
for example,' said the sailor.
'There are.'
'In this newspaper,' said the sailor.
'Ah!' said Mr Marvel.
'There's a story,' said the sailor, 'there's
a story about an Invisible Man.' And he told
Mr Marvel as much of the story as the newspaper
contained. 'I don't like it,' he said. 'He
might be anywhere, might be here at this moment
listening to us. And just think, if he wanted
to steal or kill, what is there to stop him?'
Mr Marvel seemed to be listening for the least
sound.
'Ah - and - well-' he said. And lowering his
voice, 'I know something about this Invisible
Man.'
'Oh,' said the sailor, 'you?'
'Yes,' said Mr Marvel, 'me.'
The sailor did not seem to believe Mr Marvel.
'It happened like this,' Mr Marvel began,
and then his expression changed suddenly.
'Ow!' he said. He rose stiffly from his seat,
as if in pain.
'What's the matter?' said the sailor.
'I - I think I must be going,' said Mr Marvel.
'But you were just going to tell me about
this Invisible Man,' said the sailor.
Mr Marvel seemed to think carefully.
'A lie,' said a Voice.
'It's a lie,' said Mr Marvel.
'But it's in the paper,' said the sailor.
'Yes,' said Mr Marvel loudly, 'but it's a
lie. I know the man who started it. There
isn't any Invisible Man at all.'
'But this paper? Do you mean to say-?'
'Not a word of truth in it,' said Mr Marvel
firmly.
The sailor stared, the paper in his hand.
Mr Marvel turned round.
'Wait a bit,' said the sailor, rising and
speaking slowly. 'Do you mean to say-?'
'I do,' said Mr Marvel.
'Then why did you let me go on and tell you
all this, then? What do you mean by letting
a man make a fool of himself like that for,
eh?'
'Come along,' said a Voice, and Mr Marvel
was suddenly turned round and he started marching
off in a strange, jumpy manner.
'Silly devil,' said the sailor, legs wide
apart, watching the little man go. 'I'll show
you, you silly fool! It's here in the paper!'
And there was another strange thing he was
soon to hear about, that had happened quite
close to him. And that was a 'hand full of
money' travelling by itself along by the wall.
A sailor friend had seen this strange sight
that very morning. He had tried to take the
money and had been knocked down by an unseen
hand, and when he had got to his feet the
money had disappeared.
The story of the flying money was true. And
all round that neighbourhood, even from the
bank, from shops and inns, money had quietly
walked away. And it had found its way into
Mr Marvel's pocket, so the sailor had heard.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The Man in a Hurry
In the early evening time, Dr Kemp was sitting
in his study on the hill above Burdock. It
was a pleasant little upstairs room, with
three windows - north, west, and south - with
bookshelves crowded with books and with a
broad writing table. Dr Kemp was a tall, thin
man of about thirty-five, with fair hair.
He was writing.
His eye, soon wandering from his work, caught
the sunset behind the hill opposite his house.
For a minute, perhaps, he sat, pen in mouth,
admiring the rich golden colour, and then
he saw the little figure of a man running
over the hill towards him. He was a shortest
little man, in a dirty old hat, and he was
running fast.
Dr Kemp got up, went to the window, and stared
at the hillside and the dark little figure
running down it. 'He seems to be in a hurry,'
said Dr Kemp to himself.
Then the running man was hidden behind some
houses; he came into sight and disappeared
again - still running.
But those who were nearer to him saw the terror
in his face. He looked neither to the right
nor left, but his wide eyes stared straight
down the hill to where the lamps were being
lit and there were people crowding together
in the street. Everybody he passed stopped
and began staring up and down the road, and
asking one another, half afraid, why the man
was running so hard.
And then, far up the hill, a dog playing in
the road growled and ran under a gate, and
something - a wind - a noise of feet, a sound
like heavy breathing - rushed by.
People cried out. People jumped off the footpath.
They shouted as the thing rushed past them
down the hill, and they were still shouting
in the street before Marvel was halfway there.
They were running into houses with the news
and shutting the doors behind them. He heard
it, and ran even faster. Fear came hurrying
by, rushed ahead of him, and in a moment had
seized the town.
'The Invisible Man is coming! The Invisible
Man!'
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
In the Happy Cricketers
At the bottom of the hill was an inn called
the Happy Cricketers. Inside, the barman leant
his fat red arms on the table and talked about
horses with a cabman, while a black-bearded
man who spoke like an American talked to a
policeman.
'What's the shouting about?' said the cabman,
trying to see up the hill over the dirty yellow
curtains in the low window of the inn. Somebody
ran past outside.
'Fire, perhaps,' said the barman.
The door was pushed open, and Marvel, crying,
his hat gone, the neck of his coat torn open,
rushed in and tried to shut the door. It was
held half open by a door-stop.
'Coming!' he cried, his voice cracked with
terror. 'He's coming. The Invisible Man! After
me. Help! Help! Help!'
'Shut the doors,' said the policeman. 'Who's
coming? What's the matter?' He went to the
door and removed the door-stop, and the door
shut with a bang. The man with the beard closed
the other door.
'Let me hide,' said Marvel, with tears running
down his face. 'Let me hide. Lock me in somewhere.
I tell you he's after me. I escaped. He said
he'd kill me, and he will.'
'You're safe,' said the man with the black
beard. 'The door's shut. What's it all about?'
'Let me hide,' said Marvel, and cried aloud
as a blow suddenly made the locked door shake.
The blow was followed by a hurried knocking
and a shouting outside.
'Hello,' cried the policeman, 'who's there?'
'He'll kill me,' shouted Mr Marvel, 'he's
got a knife or something. Don't open the door.
Please don't open the door. Where shall I
hide?'
'Is this the Invisible Man, then?' asked the
black-bearded man, with one hand behind him.
'I think it's about time we saw him.' The
window of the inn was suddenly broken in,
and there were shouts, and people running
about in the street. The policeman had been
standing on a chair, looking out of the window
to see who was at the door. He got down. 'That's
who it is' he said. The barman stood in front
of the parlour door, where Mr Marvel was now
locked in, and stared at the broken window.
Then he came round to the two other men.
Everything was suddenly quiet. 'I wish I had
my stick,' said the policeman. 'If we open
the door, he'll come in. Nothing can stop
him.'
'Don't be in too much of a hurry about that
door,' said the cabman anxiously.
'Unlock it,' said the man with the black beard,
'and if he comes...' He showed them the revolver
in his hand.
'That won't do,' said the policeman; 'that's
murder.'
'I know what country I'm in,' said the man
with the beard 'I'm going to shoot at his
legs. Unlock it.'
'Not with that thing going off behind me,'
said the barman.
'Very well,' said the man with the black beard.
He stepped forward with his gun ready, and
unlocked the door himself. Barman, cabman
and policeman turned around.
'Come in,' said the bearded man in a low voice,
standing back and facing the door with his
gun behind him. No one came in and the door
remained closed.
'Are all the doors of the house shut?' asked
Marvel, five minutes later. 'He's going round
to the back.'
'There's the yard door,' said the barman,
'and the private door. The yard door-'
He rushed out of the bar.
In a minute he appeared again with a long
sharp knife in his hand. 'The yard door was
open,' he said.
'He may be in the house now,' said the cabman.
The man with the beard put the gun back in
his pocket. As he did so, the door opened,
something rushed past them, and the parlour
door burst open. They heard Marvel cry out
and ran to his rescue. The bearded man's revolver
went off, and the mirror at the back of the
parlour came crashing down on the floor.
As the barman came into the room, he saw Marvel
struggling against the door that led to the
yard and kitchen. The door flew open and Marvel
was dragged into the kitchen.
The policeman, who had been trying to pass
the barman rushed in, followed by the cabman,
caught hold of the invisible hand that held
Marvel, was hit in the face and fell down.
Then the cabman took hold of something.
'I've got him,' said the cabman.
'Here he is!' said the barman.
Mr Marvel suddenly dropped to the ground,
and made an attempt to hide behind the legs
of the fighting men. The struggle went backwards
and forwards near the door. The voice of the
Invisible Man was heard for the first time,
as the policeman stepped on his foot. Then
he cried out, and his arms flew out. The cabman
was suddenly knocked to the ground by a kick
in the stomach. The door into the bar parlour
from the kitchen shut with a bang as Mr Marvel
escaped through it. The men in the kitchen
found themselves struggling with empty air.
'Where's he gone?' cried the man with the
beard. 'Out?'
'This way,' said the policeman, stepping into
the yard and stopping.
A large stone flew by his head and fell on
the kitchen table.
'I'll show him,' shouted the man with the
black beard and he fired five rapid shots
in the direction the stone had come from.
As he fired, the man with the beard moved
his hand slightly, so that his shots went
from one side to the other of the narrow yard.
A silence followed. 'Come along,' he said,
'and feel around for his body.'
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Dr Kemp's Visitor
Dr Kemp was writing in his study when he heard
the shots. Crack, crack, crack, they came,
one after the other.
'Hello!' said Dr Kemp to himself, putting
his pen into his mouth again and listening.
'Who's letting off guns in Burdock? What are
they doing now?'
He went to the south window, threw it up and,
leaning out, stared down on the town. 'It
looks like a crowd down by the Happy Cricketers,'
he said to himself. Then his eyes wandered
over the town to far away where the ships'
lights shone. The moon in its first quarter
hung over the hill to the west, and the stars
were clear and bright.
Five minutes later, Dr Kemp pulled down the
window again, and returned to his writing
desk.
It must have been about an hour after this
that the front-door bell rang. He sat listening.
He heard the servant go to the door, and waited
for the sound of her feet on the staircase,
but she did not come.
'What was that about?' Dr Kemp asked himself.
He tried to go on with his work, failed, and
went downstairs. He rang the bell and called
to the servant as she appeared in the hall.
'Was that a letter?' he asked.
'Only the bell ringing, sir, and no one there,'
she answered.
'I'm restless tonight,' he said to himself.
He went back to his study.
Soon afterwards he was hard at work again,
and his room was silent except for the sounds
of the clock and his pen moving over the paper.
It was two o'clock before he had finished
his work for the night. He rose and went upstairs
to bed. When he had taken off his coat and
shirt, he felt thirsty. He took a lamp and
went down to the dining room in search of
a drink.
Dr Kemp's scientific work had trained him
to notice things quickly. As he crossed the
hall, he saw a dark spot on the floor near
the stairs. He went on upstairs, and then
he asked himself what the dark spot on the
floor might be. He went back to the hall,
and, bending down, touched the spot. It looked
and felt like drying blood.
He returned upstairs, looking around him and
thinking about the blood spot. Then suddenly
he saw something which made him stop. There
was blood on the handle of his door.
He looked at his own hand. It was quite clean.
Then he remembered that the door of his room
had been open when he came down from his study,
and that he had not touched the handle at
all. He went straight into his bedroom, his
face quite calm - perhaps a little more determined
than usual... He looked at the bed. There
was a pool of blood, and the sheet was torn.
He had not noticed this when he had been in
the room before. The other side of the bed
looked as if someone had been lying on it.
Then he seemed to hear a low voice say, 'Help
me! - Kemp!' But Dr Kemp did not believe in
'voices'.
He stood staring at the sheets. Was it really
a voice? He looked around him again, and noticed
nothing. But he clearly heard something move
across the room. A strange feeling came over
him. He closed the door of the room and came
forward. Suddenly, with a shock, he saw a
bloody bandage hanging in the air between
him and the bed.
He stared at it in surprise. It was an empty
bandage - a bandage properly tied, but quite
empty. He would have moved forward to take
hold of it, but a touch stopped him and a
voice spoke quite close to him.
'Kemp!' said the Voice.
'Eh!' said Kemp, with his mouth open.
Said the Voice, 'I'm an invisible man.'
Kemp made no answer for a moment or two, but
simply stared at the bandage. 'The Invisible
Man?' he said at last.
'I'm an invisible man,' repeated the Voice.
'I thought it was a lie,' he said. 'Have you
got a bandage on?' he asked.
'Yes,' said the Invisible Man.
'Oh!' said Kemp, and then, 'I say! But this
is nonsense. It's some trick.' He stepped
forward suddenly, stretched out his hand towards
the bandage and met invisible fingers.
'Keep steady, Kemp, in God's name! I want
help badly. Stop!' The hand seized his arm.
He struck at it. 'Kemp!' cried the Voice.
'Kemp, keep still!'
A desire to free himself took hold of Kemp.
But the hand held his shoulder, and he was
suddenly pushed and fell backwards upon the
bed. He opened his mouth to shout, and the
corner of the sheet was pushed between his
teeth. The Invisible Man held him down, but
his arms were free, and he hit back fiercely.
'Listen to reason, will you?' said the Invisible
Man. 'By heaven, you'll make me mad! Stop
struggling and lie still! Lie still!'
Kemp struggled for another moment, and then
lay still.
'Let me get up,' he said. 'I'll stay where
I am. And let me sit quiet for a minute.'
He sat up and felt his neck.
'I'm just an ordinary man - a man you used
to know - made invisible. Do you remember
Griffin?'
'Griffin?' repeated Kemp.
'Griffin,' answered the Voice. 'A younger
student than you.'
'What has this to do with Griffin?'
'I am Griffin.'
Kemp laughed. 'It's too much of a shock,'
he said. 'But what devil's work can make a
man invisible?'
'It's no devil's work. It's honest and simple
enough.'
'It's terrible!' said Kemp. 'How on earth-?'
'I'm wounded and in pain, and tired... Great
God! Kemp, you are a man. Keep calm. Give
me some food and drink, and let me sit down
here.'
Kemp stared at the bandage as it moved across
the room, then saw a chair slide along the
floor and come to rest near the bed. It made
a noise, and the seat sank slightly. He rubbed
his eyes and felt his neck again.
'This beats magic,' he said, and laughed stupidly.
'That's better. Thank heaven, you're becoming
sensible!'
'Or silly,' said Kemp, and rubbed his eyes
again.
'Give me something to drink. I'm nearly dead.'
'It didn't feel like that. Where are you?
If I get up, shall I run into you? There!
All right. A drink... Here. Where shall I
give it you?'
Kemp felt the glass taken out of his hand.
He let it go into the air. It came to rest
just in front of the chair seat. He stared
at it. 'This... I don't believe it... I must
be mad.'
'Nonsense!' said the Voice. 'Listen to me.
I'm hungry, and the night is cold to a man
with no clothes on.'
'Food?' offered Kemp.
The glass emptied itself.
'Yes,' said the Invisible Man, putting it
down. 'Can you give me something to wear?'
Kemp found some clothes. 'These?' he asked.
They were taken from him. They hung in the
air, buttoned themselves and sat down in the
chair.
'The maddest thing I've ever seen in my life,'
said Kemp.
'Some food?'
Kemp went to the kitchen for some bread and
some meat, returned and put them on a table
in front of his guest.
'Never mind about a knife,' said the Invisible
Man: and a piece of meat hung in the air and
disappeared with a sound of eating.
'I always like to have clothes on when I eat,'
said the Voice.
'Is your arm all right?'
'Not very painful.'
'It's all mad, as mad as can be.'
'Quite reasonable,' said the Invisible Man.
'But how's it done?' began Kemp. 'What were
the shots?' he asked. 'How did the shooting
begin?'
'There was a man - I tried to make him help
me! - who tried to steal my money. And he
has stolen it.'
'Is he invisible too?'
'No.'
'Well?'
'Can't I have some more to eat before I tell
you all about it? I'm hungry - in pain. And
you want me to tell stories!'
Kemp got up. 'You didn't do any shooting?'
he asked.
'Not me,' said his visitor. 'Some fool fired,
a man I'd never seen before. A lot of them
got frightened. They all got frightened of
me. I say - I want more to eat than this,
Kemp.'
'I'll see whether there's anything more to
eat downstairs,' said Kemp. 'Not much, I'm
afraid.'
Kemp found some more food. And when his guest
had eaten he told him to try to get some sleep.
Though the Invisible Man was wounded and tired,
he refused to accept Kemp's word that no one
would try to seize him. He examined the two
windows of the bedroom, pulled up the blinds
and opened the windows to see whether it was
possible to get out that way, as Kemp had
told him. Outside the night was very quiet
and still, and the new moon was setting over
the hill. Then he examined the key of the
bedroom door. At last he was satisfied. He
stood by the fireside and Kemp heard his breathing
relax.
'I'm sorry,' said the Invisible Man, 'if I
cannot tell you all that I've done tonight,
but I'm so tired. It's foolish, no doubt.
It's horrible! But, believe me, Kemp, in spite
of your arguments, it's quite a possible thing.
I've made a discovery. I intended to keep
it secret. I can't. I must have someone to
help me. And you... We can do such great things
together... But tomorrow. Now, Kemp, I feel
as though I must sleep or die.'
They said goodnight to each other, and Kemp
stayed in his room, thinking. He picked up
a newspaper and found that it was full of
reports of the Invisible Man. As he read,
he began to feel afraid of what his guest
might do if he was allowed to stay free. He
wrote a note and addressed it to 'Colonel
Adye, Port Burdock'
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
How to Become Invisible
The next morning Kemp heard a loud noise and
went to see his guest.
'What's the matter?' asked Kemp, when the
Invisible Man let him in.
'Nothing,' was the answer.
'But, good heavens! What was that crash?'
'I lost my temper,' said the Invisible Man.
'I forgot this arm; and it's sore.'
'You're rather in the habit of losing your
temper.'
'I am.'
'Your story is in the papers,' Kemp said.
The Invisible Man swore.
'Come and have some breakfast,' said Kemp,
leading the way. 'Before we can do anything
else,' he went on, 'I must understand a little
more about you.' He had sat down, with the
air of a man who means to talk seriously.
'It's simple enough,' said Griffin.
'No doubt it's simple enough to you, but-'
Kemp laughed.
'Well, yes, to me it seemed strange at first,
no doubt. But we can still do great things!
I found the secret first at Chesilstowe College.'
'Chesilstowe?'
'I went there after I left London. You know
I have always been interested in light.'
'Ah!'
'I said: "I will give my life to this. This
is worth my trouble." You know what fools
we are at twenty-two.'
'Fools then and fools now,' said Kemp.
As though just knowing could satisfy a man!
I saw a way to change the human body, or any
other kind of body...' And then the strange
man, or rather the clothes of a man, sitting
opposite Kemp, explained how a student of
science had disappeared.
'If you take a small piece of glass and crush
it into powder, the powder is white and solid
like salt. You can't see through it. Human
flesh, white paper, cloth, hair, are really
made of a kind of powder. The tiny grains
of powder break up the light which shines
on them, so that it can't shine through them,
and that is why we can see flesh and paper.
Now, if you could smooth the broken grains
of powder so that they would not break up
the light, they would no longer look solid.
The light would shine through them, just as
now the sun is shining through me. You can
try it with a piece of white paper and a drop
of oil. Pour a little oil on the paper and
things will begin to show through it. If the
oil is good enough and the paper is bad enough,
you will be able to see through the paper
to the print on the other side. That is because
the oil is smooth and it smooths out the rough
surfaces of each little grain of the powder.
'Well, I found something which would do to
human flesh what the oil does to the paper,
and would do it so perfectly that there is
no tiny part of my body which holds up the
light. It is as if you had taken powdered
glass and turned it back into the unbroken
glass of that window.'
The explanation, as always between two scientists,
led to all kinds of questions. Kemp was so
surprised at the story that he nearly forgot
that his friend was invisible.
'Yes,' said the Voice, 'I had found it all.
The way was open - and then - then after years
of care and working in secret - then I knew
that I could do nothing. I knew, and I was
helpless. And that was after three years of
secrecy and hard work.'
'Why could you do nothing?' asked Kemp.
'I had no money,' said the Invisible Man,
and went to stare out of the window.
He turned round. 'I robbed the old man - robbed
my father. The money was not his, and he shot
himself.'
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
The Experiment
For a moment Kemp sat in silence, staring
at the back of the headless figure at the
window. Then he rose, took the Invisible Man's
arm and turned him away from the view.
'You're tired,' he said, 'and while I'm sitting
down, you walk around. Have my chair.'
He got up and stood between Griffin and the
nearest window.
For a time Griffin sat silently, and then
he went on with his story.
'I'd already left the College,' he said, 'when
that happened. It was last December. I had
taken a room in London, in a big house in
Great Portland Street.
'It was all like a dream, that short visit
to my father in my old home. When I returned
to my room it seemed like waking from a dream
to reality. Here were the things I knew and
loved. Here was the equipment; the experiments
were arranged and waiting. And now there was
hardly any difficulty left, beyond the planning
of details.
'I will tell you, Kemp, sooner or later, all
the complicated details. We need not talk
about that now. For the most part, except
for certain words I chose to remember, they
are written in those books that that tramp
has hidden, in a way that only I can understand.
We must hunt him down.
'First I tried some white wool. It was the
strangest thing in the world to see it lose
its substance, like smoke, and disappear.
I could hardly believe I had done it. I put
my hand into the emptiness and there was the
thing as solid as ever. I felt it, and threw
it on the floor. I had a little trouble finding
it again.
'And then I heard a noise behind me and, turning,
saw a white cat, very dirty, outside the window.
A thought came into my head. "Everything is
ready for you," I said, and went to the window,
opened it, and called softly. She came in.
The poor creature was thirsty and I gave her
some milk. After that she went smelling round
the room, plainly with the idea of making
herself at home. The invisible wool upset
her a bit; you should have seen her attack
it! But I made her comfortable on my bed.'
'And then you made the cat invisible?'
'Yes: it took four hours.'
'You don't mean to say there's an Invisible
Cat in the world?' said Kemp.
'If it hasn't been killed,' said the Invisible
Man. 'Why not?'
'Why not?' repeated Kemp. 'Go on.'
He was silent for a few minutes and then continued.
'My only clear thought,' he said, 'was that
the thing had to be completed. And it had
to be done soon, for I had little money left.
After a time I ate some food and went to sleep
in my clothes on my bed.
'I was woken by a loud knock at the door.
It was the owner of my room. He said I had
been hurting a cat in the night, he was sure.
He wanted to know all about it. I told him
there had been no cat in my room. Then the
noise of my experiments could be heard all
over the house, he said. That was true, certainly.
He came into the room, asked me what I was
doing, and said it had always been a respectable
house. In the end I got angry, pushed him
out and shut the door. He made some noise
outside, but I didn't listen. After a time
he went away.
'But I didn't know what he planned to do,
nor even what he had the power to do. To move
to new rooms would have meant I delay - I
had twenty pounds left in the world, most
of it in a bank. If he brought the police,
my room might be searched. What could I do?
Disappear! Of course. It was all done that
evening and night.
'There was some pain at first. I felt sick.
At times I cried out. I talked aloud to myself.
But I did not give up. I shall never forget
seeing my hands. They became white as white
paper and then slowly, became like glass.
And then - they had disappeared. At first
I was weak as a little child, walking on legs
I could not see.
'I slept during the morning, pulling a sheet
over my eyes to shut out the light, and I
was woken again by a knocking. My strength
had returned. I sat up and listened and heard
talking. Soon the knocking was repeated and
voices called. To gain time I answered them.
My window opened on to a roof. I stepped through
it, closed it, stood outside and watched.
The old man and his two sons came into the
room.
'You may imagine their surprise at finding
the room empty. One of the younger men rushed
to the window at once, threw it open and stared
out. His eyes and his thick-lipped, bearded
face came close to my own. He looked right
through me. So did the others. The old man
went and looked under the bed.
'While they were all talking together, I came
back into the room, slipped past them, and
went down the stairs. In one room I found
a box of matches, and when they had come down
I returned to my own room and set fire to
the papers, the bedcovers and the furniture.'
'You set the house on fire?'
'Set the house on fire! Yes. It was the only
way to hide my tracks.'
For the next hour he went on with his story,
and Kemp listened. It was the story of how
the Invisible Man had got some clothes, how
he lived by getting food and drink wherever
he could, of the shelter he found and the
beds he slept in, until he came to Iping.
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
The Plan That Failed
'But now,' said Kemp, looking out of the window,
'what are we to do?'
He moved nearer to his guest so that he did
not see the three men who were coming up the
hill road - too slowly, as it seemed to Kemp.
'What were you planning to do, when you were
going to Port Burdock? Did you have a plan?'
'I was going to leave the country. But I have
rather changed that plan since seeing you.
I thought it would be wise, now the weather
is hot, to make for the south. Especially
as my secret was known, and everyone would
be watching for a man all wrapped up like
me. You have regular boats from here to France.
My idea was to get on board one. Then I could
go by train into Spain, or else to Algiers.
It wouldn't be difficult. There a man could
be invisible all the time, but still live
and do things. I was using that tramp as a
moneybox and carrier until I decided how to
get my books and things sent over to join
me.'
'That's clear.'
'And then he tried to rob me! He has hidden
my books, Kemp. Hidden my books! If I can
get hold of him, I'll -'
'You'd better get the books from him first.'
'But where is he? Do you know?'
'He's in the town police station, locked up,
at his own request, in the strongest room
in the place.'
'The rat!' said the Invisible Man.
'But that delays your plans a little.'
'We must get those books; those books are
necessary.'
'Certainly,' said Kemp, a little anxiously,
unsure if he heard footsteps outside. 'Certainly
we must get those books. But that won't be
difficult, if he doesn't know they're for
you.'
'No,' said the Invisible Man, thoughtfully.
Kemp tried to think of something to keep the
conversation going, but the Invisible Man
continued himself.
'Coming into your house, Kemp,' he said, 'changes
all my plans. For you are a man who can understand.
You are a scientist. You have told no one
I am here?'
'Not a soul.'
'If we are to make any use of being invisible,
we must start by killing.'
'Killing?' repeated Kemp. 'I'm listening to
your plan; but I'm not agreeing. Why killing?'
'The point is this: they know as well as we
do that there is an Invisible Man - and that
Invisible Man, Kemp, must now start to rule
by terror. Yes; I mean it. To rule by terror.
He must take a town like your Burdock and
put the fear of God into it. He must give
orders. He can do that in many ways. And he
must kill everybody who disobeys his orders,
and everybody who works against him.'
'Really!' said Kemp, no longer listening to
Griffin, but to the sound of his front door
opening and closing.
The Invisible Man had also heard the sound.
'Listen!' he said. 'What is that downstairs?'
'Nothing,' said Kemp; and suddenly he began
to speak loud and fast. 'I don't agree to
this, Griffin,' he said. 'Understand me, I
don't agree to this. Why do you wish to be
alone? Why not tell everyone? Think how much
better it would be. You might have a million
helpers.'
The Invisible Man raised his hand. 'There
are footsteps coming upstairs,' he said.
'Nonsense,' said Kemp.
'Let me see,' said the Invisible Man, and
went to the door and listened.
And then things happened very quickly. Suddenly
the clothes sat down and opened as the unseen
man began to undress.
Kemp opened the door.
As he opened it, there came sounds of hurrying
feet and voices downstairs.
With a quick movement Kemp pushed the Invisible
Man back, jumped aside, and shut the door
behind him. The key was outside and ready.
In another moment Griffin would have been
locked in the room, except for one little
thing: the key fell noisily on the floor.
Kemp's face became white. He tried to hold
the door handle with both hands. For a moment
he pulled at it. Then the door opened slightly,
but he got it closed again. The second time
it was opened a foot, and the clothes came
into the opening. Kemp's throat was seized
by invisible fingers, and he let go of the
handle in order to defend himself. He was
forced back and thrown heavily to the floor.
Halfway up the stairs was Colonel Adye, the
chief of the Burdock police. He was staring
at the sudden appearance of Kemp, followed
by the clothes, which danced in the air. He
saw Kemp fall and then struggle to his feet.
He saw Kemp rush forward, and go down again.
Then suddenly he was struck. By nothing! A
great weight, if seemed, jumped on him, and
he was thrown down the staircase. An invisible
foot stepped on his back, faint steps passed
downstairs. He heard the two police officers
in the hall shout and run, and the sound of
the front door of the house as it shut.
He rolled over and sat up staring. He saw
Kemp coming down the staircase, his face white
and bleeding.
'My God!' cried Kemp, 'I couldn't stop him!
He's gone!'
CHAPTER NINETEEN
The Hunt for the Invisible Man
Kemp took some time to explain to Colonel
Adye what had happened.
'He's mad,' said Kemp. 'And evil. He thinks
of nothing but his own advantage, his own
safety. I've listened this morning to a terrible
story of cruelty and pride. He has wounded
men. He'll kill them unless we can prevent
him. He plans to rule by terror.
'Nothing can stop him. He's loose outside
there now - and he's mad!'
'He must be caught,' said Adye. 'That's certain.'
'But how?' cried Kemp, and suddenly became
full of ideas. You must begin immediately,
you must set every man to work; you must prevent
him leaving this place. If he gets away, he
may go through the country, killing as he
goes. The only thing that may keep him here
is the thought of finding some books which
he values very much. I will tell you about
them. There is a man in your police station
- Marvel.'
'I know,' said Adye, 'I know. Those books
- yes. But the Invisible Man-'
'Says he hasn't got them. But he thinks Marvel
has. Now listen! You must prevent him from
eating or sleeping - day and night the country
must be on the watch for him. Food must be
locked up, all food, so that he will have
to break into a house or shop to get it. The
houses everywhere must be shut against him;
for 20 miles round Port Burdock, the whole
country must begin hunting and keep on hunting.
I tell you, Adye, he's dangerous. Unless he
is caught, it's terrible to think of the things
that may happen.'
'Come along,' said Colonel Adye. 'Tell me
as we go. What else is there we can do?'
In another moment Adye was leading the way
downstairs. They found the front door open
and the policemen standing outside staring
at empty air.
'He's got away, sir,' said one.
'We must tell the police station at once,'
said Adye. 'One of you must go down and report
and then come up and meet us - quickly. And
now, Kemp, what else?'
'Dogs,' said Kemp. 'Get dogs. They don't see
him, but they smell him. Get dogs.'
'Good,' said Adye. 'We have no suitable dogs,
but the prison officers over at Halstead know
a man with bloodhounds. What else?'
'Remember,' said Kemp, 'his food shows. You
can see it for some time after he has eaten
it, so he has to hide. You must keep on searching
in every quiet corner. And put away all weapons
and everything that might be a weapon. He
can't carry such things for long. You must
hide anything he can pick up and strike men
with.'
'Good again,' said Adye. 'We'll find him yet!'
'And the roads-' said Kemp, and hesitated.
'Yes?' said Adye.
'Broken glass,' said Kemp. 'It's cruel, I
know. But think of what he may do!'
Adye drew the air in between his teeth sharply.
'It's cruel. I don't perhaps think we should.
But I'll have some broken glass ready. If
he is killed, it will be only what he deserves.
'The man is mad, I tell you,' said Kemp. 'He
will do anything. We must catch him by any
possible means. He has cut himself off from
the human race.'
CHAPTER TWENTY
The Wicksteed Murder
The Invisible Man seems to have rushed out
of Kemp's house in blind anger. A little child
playing near Kemp's gateway was violently
picked up and thrown to one side - so that
his leg was broken - and then for some hours
the Invisible Man disappeared completely.
No one knows where he went or what he did.
But we can think of him hurrying through the
hot June morning, up the hill and onto the
open land behind Port Burdock, and hiding
at last in the woods.
There he hid for two hours, while a growing
crowd of men was hunting him across the country
with dogs, and searching for him in every
direction. In the morning he had still been
just a story, a terror; in the afternoon,
mainly because of Kemp's story, he was shown
to be a real enemy who had to be caught and
held by force, and the countryside began organising
itself very quickly. Before two o'clock, he
might still have escaped from the area by
hoarding a train, but after two that became
impossible: every passenger train between
Southampton, Winchester, Brighton and Horsham
travelled with locked doors, and the goods
trains were almost entirely stopped. And in
a great circle of 20 miles round Port Burdock,
men armed with guns and sticks were soon setting
out in groups of three and four, with dogs,
to search the roads and fields.
Police on horseback followed the country roads,
stopping at every house and warning people
to lock their doors and not to go out unless
they were armed. All the schools had closed
before three o'clock, and the frightened children,
keeping together in groups, hurried home.
A notice written by Kemp was put up everywhere,
telling people clearly what must be done - that
the Invisible Man must have neither food nor
sleep, that a continuous watch must be kept
for signs of him. Before night the whole country
was on guard and also before night came news
of the murder of Mr Wicksteed.
Somewhere on the road the Invisible Man must
have picked up an iron bar. Mr Wicksteed,
a quiet, harmless man on his way home from
work, had, no doubt, seen an iron bar walking
by itself, and had turned to follow it. Perhaps
the Invisible Man imagined he was one of the
hunters. We only know that he stopped quiet
little Mr Wicksteed, attacked him, broke his
arm, knocked him down and beat his head to
pieces.
Then there is the story of a voice heard by
some men in a held, laughing and crying. Across
the field it went and was lost. The Invisible
Man must have seen the use Kemp had made of
his story. He must have found all the houses
shut and locked, and seen the groups of men
with dogs watching. He knew that he was a
hunted man. In the night he must have eaten
and slept, for on the last morning he was
himself again and ready for his struggle against
the world.
CHAPTER TWENTY ONE
The Attack on Kemp's House
Kemp was reading a strange letter, written
in pencil on a dirty sheet of paper.
You have been very clever, though what you
gain by it I cannot think. You are against
me. For a whole day you have hunted me - you
have tried to rob me of a night's rest. But
I have had food, I have slept, and we are
only beginning. We are only beginning. There
is nothing to be done but to start the Terror.
This is the first day of the Terror. Port
Burdock is no longer under the Queen. Tell
your police, and the rest of them; it is under
me - the Terror! I am Invisible Man the First.
We shall begin with the death of a man named
Kemp. He will die today. He may hide himself
away, and collect guards around him; Death,
the unseen Death, is coming. The game begins.
Death starts. If you help him, my people,
Death may fall on you too. Today Kemp is to
die.
Kemp read this letter twice. 'That's his voice!'
he said, 'and he means it.'
He got up slowly, leaving his lunch unfinished
- the letter had come by the one o'clock post
- and went into his study. He rang the bell
for his servant, and told her to go round
the house immediately, and see that all the
windows were shut. He closed the study windows
himself. From a locked drawer in his bedroom
he took a little revolver, examined it carefully,
and put it into his pocket. He wrote a number
of short notes, one to Colonel Adye, and gave
them to his servant to take.
'There is no danger to you,' he said. He thought
for a time and then returned to his meal.
Finally he struck the table. 'We will have
him!' he said. 'He'll go too far.'
He went up to his room, carefully shutting
every door after him. 'It's a game,' he said,
'a strange game - but I shall win, Mr Griffin,'
he said.
He stood at the window staring at the hot
hillside. 'He must get food every day. Did
he really sleep last night? Out in the open
somewhere? I wish we could get some good cold,
wet weather instead of the heat. He may be
watching me now.'
He went close to the window. Something hit
the wall above the window.
'I'm getting worried,' said Kemp. But it was
five minutes before he went to the window
again. 'It must have been a bird,' he said.
Soon he heard the front-door bell ringing
and hurried downstairs. He unchained and unlocked
the door, and opened it without showing himself.
It was Adye.
'Your servant's been attacked, Kemp,' he said
round the door.
'What!' exclaimed Kemp.
'She had that note of yours taken away from
her. He's very near. Let me in.'
Kemp opened the door a few inches, and Adye
came in. He stood in the hall, looking at
Kemp locking the door.
Kemp swore. 'What a fool I was!' he said.
'I might have known. Already!'
'What's the matter?' said Adye.
'Look here!' said Kemp, and led the way towards
his study. He handed Adye the Invisible Man's
letter.
Adye read it, 'And you-?' said Adye.
The sound of a breaking window came from upstairs.
Adye saw the little revolver half out of Kemp's
pocket. 'It's a window upstairs!' said Kemp,
and led the way up. There came a second noise
while they were still on the staircase. When
they reached the study they found two of the
three windows broken, the floor covered with
broken glass, and one big stone lying on the
writing table. The two men stopped in the
doorway. Kemp swore again, and as he did so
the third window broke with a crack like a
gunshot, and the broken glass fell into the
room.
'What's this for?' said Adye.
'It's beginning,' said Kemp.
'There's no way of climbing up here?'
'Not even for a cat,' said Kemp.
Stones came flying in and then it sounded
as if someone was banging on the windows downstairs.
The two men stood outside the study, not knowing
what to do.
'I know!' said Adye. 'Let me have a stick
or something, and I'll go down to the station
and get the man with the bloodhounds. They'll
find him.'
Another window broke.
'You haven't got a revolver?' asked Adye.
Kemp's hand went to his pocket. Then he paused.
'I haven't one - at least, none that I want
to part with.'
'I'll bring it back,' said Adye. 'You'll be
safe here.'
Kemp gave him the weapon.
'Now for the door,' said Adye.
As they stood waiting in the hall, they heard
one of the bedroom windows crack. Kemp went
to the door and began to turn the key as silently
as he could. His face was a little paler than
usual.
'You must step straight out,' he said.
In another moment Adye was on the doorstep
and the door was shut. He waited for a moment,
feeling more comfortable with his back against
the door. Then he marched down the steps.
He crossed the grass and had almost reached
the gate when something moved near him.
'Stop a bit,' said a Voice, and Adye stopped,
with his hand on the revolver.
'Well?' said Adye.
'Please go back to the house,' said the Voice.
'No,' said Adye. He thought of trying a shot
in the direction of the Voice.
'What are you going to do?' said the Voice.
'What I do is my own business,' said Adye.
The words were still on his lips when an arm
came round his neck, he felt a knee in his
back, and his head was forced backward. He
fired the gun wildly, and in another moment
he was struck in the mouth and the weapon
was taken from his hand. He tried to struggle,
and was thrown on his back.
'You devil!' said Adye.
The Voice laughed. 'I would kill you now if
it wasn't a waste of a shot,' it said. Adye
saw the revolver in the air, 6 feet off, pointing
at him.
'Well?' said Adye, sitting up.
'Get up,' said the Voice.
Adye stood up.
'Stand still,' said the Voice, and then firmly.
'Don't try any tricks. Remember I can see
your face, if you can't see mine. You've got
to go back to the house.'
'He won't let me in,' said Adye.
'That's a pity,' said the Invisible Man. 'It
isn't you I want to kill.'
Adye glanced away from the revolver and saw
the sea far off, very blue and dark under
the bright sun. He saw the smooth green hill,
the white rocks of the coast, and the spreading
town, and suddenly he knew that life was very
sweet. His eyes came back to this little metal
thing hanging between heaven and earth, six
feet away. 'What must I do?' he asked.
'What must I do?' asked the Invisible Man.
'If I let you go, you'll get help. The only
thing is for you to go back to the house.'
'I'll try. If he lets me in, will you promise
not to charge the door?'
'I don't want to fight you,' said the Voice.
Kemp had hurried upstairs after letting Adye
out, and now, looking through a broken window,
he saw Adye stand talking with the unseen
enemy. 'Why doesn't he fire?' said Kemp to
himself. Then the revolver moved a little.
'That's strange!' he said. 'Adye has given
up the revolver.'
'Promise not to charge the door,' Adye was
saying. 'Give me a chance.'
'Just go back to the house. I tell you I'll
promise nothing.'
Adye seemed to decide suddenly. He turned
towards the house, and walked slowly with
his hands behind him. Kemp watched him. The
revolver appeared, a small dark object, following
Adye. Then things happened very quickly. Adye
jumped at the small object, missed it, threw
up his hands and fell forward on his face.
A little ball of blue smoke rose into the
air! Kemp did not hear the sound of the shot.
Adye raised himself on one arm, fell forward,
and lay still.
For a time Kemp remained looking at Adye as
he lay peacefully on the grass. The day was
very hot and still. Nothing seemed to move.
Adye lay on the grass near the gate. The curtains
of all the houses down the hill road were
drawn, but in one little green garden hut
was a white figure, rather like an old man
asleep. Kemp's eyes returned to Adye - the
game was not beginning well!
Then came a ringing and a knocking at the
front door, but nobody opened it. Silence
followed. Kemp sat listening and then began
to look carefully out of the three windows,
one after another. He went to the stairs and
stood listening anxiously. What was his enemy
doing?
Suddenly there was a banging from below. He
waited and went down the stairs again. The
house was filled with the sound of heavy blows
and breaking wood. He went into the kitchen.
The door was being broken down with an axe.
Kemp went back into the passage, trying to
think. In a moment the Invisible Man would
be in the kitchen. This door would not keep
him a moment, and then the front-door bell
rang again and Kemp heard voices. It was the
policemen with the servant. He ran into the
hall, opened the door, and three people fell
into the house in a pile. Kemp shut the door
again.
'The Invisible Man!' said Kemp. 'He has a
revolver - with two shots left. He's killed
Adye. At least, he's shot him. Didn't you
see him on the grass? He's lying there.'
'Who?' said one of the policemen.
'Adye,' said Kemp.
'We came round the back way,' said the girl.
'What's that banging?' asked one of the policemen.
'He's in the kitchen - or will be. He's found
an axe-'
Suddenly the house was full of the sound of
the Invisible Man's blows on the kitchen door.
The girl stared towards the kitchen and stepped
into the dining room. Kemp tried to explain
in broken sentences. They heard the kitchen
door breaking open.
'This way,' cried Kemp, and he pushed the
policemen into the dining room doorway.
'The pokers,' said Kemp, and rushed to the
fire.
He handed a poker to each of the policemen.
He suddenly threw himself backwards. 'Whup!'
said one policeman, jumped to one side and
caught the axe on his poker.
The revolver cracked and shot a hole in a
picture. The second policeman brought his
poker down on the little weapon and sent it
to the floor.
The axe went back into the passage. They could
hear the Invisible Man breathing.
'Stand away, you two,' he said. 'I want that
man Kemp.'
'We want you,' said the first policeman, taking
a quick step forward and striking with his
poker at the Voice. The Invisible Man must
have stepped back and fallen over a chair.
Then, as the policeman went after him, the
Invisible Man returned and struck him down.
But the second policeman, aiming behind the
axe with his poker, hit something soft that
cracked. There was a sharp cry of pain, and
then the axe fell to the ground. The policeman
struck again at emptiness and hit nothing;
he put his foot on the axe and struck again.
Then he stood, holding the poker, listening
for the slightest movement.
He heard a window open, and a quick rush of
feet outside. His companion rolled over and
sat up, with blood running down between his
eye and ear.
'Where is he?' asked the man on the floor.
'I don't know. I've hit him. He's standing
somewhere in the hall unless he's slipped
past you. Dr Kemp - sir!'
'Dr Kemp,' cried the policeman again.
The second policeman began struggling to his
feet. He stood up. Suddenly the faint sound
of bare feet could be heard. 'Whup!' cried
the first policeman, and threw his poker.
He started to go after the Invisible Man.
Then he changed his mind and stepped into
the dining room.
'Dr Kemp-' he began.
The dining-room window was wide open, and
neither servant nor Kemp was to be seen.
CHAPTER TWENTY TWO
The Hunter Hunted
Kemp had set off running, running to save
his life as he had seen Mr Marvel run down
the hill road. Never, he thought, had he seemed
to run so slowly.
People looked at him. They saw fear in his
face.
Now he was rushing to the town below, where
people were standing or walking in groups.
He slowed down and then heard rapid footsteps
behind.
'The Invisible Man,' he cried. He thought
of going into the police station, but changed
his mind, turned down a side street and then
into a yard, into a little house and so back
into the main road.
A crowd had collected in the street; there
was a noise of running feet. A big man, a
few yards away, was swinging a heavy spade,
striking at something. Another man came out
of a shop with a thick stick in his hand.
'Spread out! Spread out!' cried someone. Kemp
stopped and looked round, breathing heavily.
'He's close!' he cried. 'Form a line across-'
He was hit hard under the ear and tried to
turn round towards his unseen enemy. Then
he was hit again under the jaw, and fell to
the ground. In another moment a knee was digging
into his chest and hands held his throat,
but one hand was weaker than the other; then
the spade of the big man came through the
air above him, and struck something. He felt
warm blood on his face. The hold on his throat
was loosened and Kemp rolled on top of his
enemy.
'I've got him!' cried Kemp. 'Help! Help - hold
him! He's down! Hold his feet!'
In another second there was a rush of people
to the struggle. There was no shouting after
Kemp's cry - only a sound of blows and feet
and heavy breathing.
Then the Invisible Man got to his feet. Kemp
still held his legs. Then someone got hold
of his neck and pulled him back. Down went
the pile of struggling, kicking men again.
Then suddenly came a wild cry that died away
into silence.
'Get back!' cried Kemp. 'He's hurt, I tell
you. Stand back.'
A doctor was feeling the unseen body.
'The mouth is all wet,' he said.
He stood up quickly, and then knelt down on
the ground by the side of the unseen thing.
More people joined the pushing crowd. Men
were coming out of the houses. The doors of
the inn stood wide open. Very little was said.
Kemp felt around him; his hands seemed to
pass through empty air. 'He's not breathing,'
he said, and then, 'I cannot feel his heart.
His side - ugh!'
An old woman, looking under the arm of the
big man with the spade, cried out. 'Look there!'
she said, and pointed. And looking where she
pointed, everyone saw a shadowy, cloudy body.
At first, they could see through it, but it
was becoming more solid every moment.
'Hello!' cried the policeman. 'Here are his
feet showing!'
And so, slowly, beginning at his hands and
feet, and spreading slowly to the centre of
his body, that strange change continued. It
was like the slow movement of a poison. They
saw the glassy bones, then the flesh and skin,
misty at first but slowly growing thicker
and harder and more solid. Soon they could
see his chest and his shoulders, and the faint
shape of his face.
When at last the crowd made way for Kemp to
stand back, there lay the bare and broken
body of a young man of about thirty. His hair
was white - not grey with age, but white as
snow - and his eyes were bright like jewels.
His expression was one of anger and fear.
'Cover his face!' cried a man. 'In God's name,
cover that face!'
Someone brought a sheet. They covered him,
and carried him into the inn. And there it
was, on a bed in an ill-lighted bedroom, among
a crowd of excited people, that Griffin, the
first of all men to make himself invisible,
ended his strange and terrible life.