CHAPTER ONE
Control!
'Golf Bravo Alpha.
You are cleared for take-off.'
Eighteen-year-old Swiss-Italian, Francesca
Bartolli, sat in the small single-engined
Cessna 152 and stared through the window at
the runway ahead.
A white dotted line stretched down the middle
of the concrete far into the distance.
Had the moment finally arrived?
Was she really going to pilot a plane at last?
'Well?' said a voice in her headphones.
'What are you waiting for?'
It was Doug, the flying instructor, in the
seat beside her.
Francesca felt hot.
The sun was shining brightly through the windscreen,
turning the plane's small cockpit into an
oven.
And the headphones were tight and painful
on her ears.
'You mean you want me to...' she began.
'Push the throttle in smoothly and hold the
control column steady,' the instructor said.
'When I tell you, just pull back gently.
I'll do all the rest.'
'OK,' Francesca answered in a shaky voice.
Doug called the control tower for permission
to take off, but Francesca didn't take in
what he said.
Now that the moment had finally arrived, she
suddenly wondered if it was really what she
wanted.
The instructor's voice became firmer.
'Right, let's go!' he said.
Francesca didn't hesitate now.
Setting her mouth with new determination,
she stretched out her right arm and pushed
carefully on the throttle.
Immediately, the engine roared and the little
aircraft seemed to sit up.
The next moment it was being pulled forward
as if on a huge elastic band.
Within a couple of seconds, they were already
racing along the runway.
The white dotted lines began disappearing
quickly below the nose of the plane.
'Keep your eye on the airspeed dial,' she
heard the instructor say in her headphones
again, above the roar of the engine.
'When the needle reaches 60, pull back gently.'
Francesca didn't answer.
There was so much to look at, so much going
on.
It seemed somehow crazy, this race down the
runway.
She watched the needle going round the dial:
40... 45...
The white dotted lines on the runway flashed
below the plane.
Her head felt as if it was bursting.
All of a sudden, the needle was at 60.
'Right, pull back!' came Doug's voice.
But already Francesca was pulling back on
the control column.
It was much lighter than she expected, just
like pulling your hand slowly through cream.
Straightaway the nose of the aircraft lifted
and the runway disappeared from view.
The next moment she felt the plane rise into
the air.
'OK, hold it there!' said Doug.
Francesca felt a strange smile pull at the
sides of her mouth.
She couldn't help it.
They were flying!
'That's enough!
Keep the nose down.
Don't climb too fast.
Keep your eye on that airspeed dial.
Climb at 80.
80s the perfect climb.'
Francesca wanted to look around.
Already the airfield was beginning to slip
away below, and new fields were coming into
view, but Francesca had to keep her eye on
the airspeed dial.
The needle was dropping.
70... 65...
'Nose down!
Keep it down!'
Francesca pushed the control column forward
quickly.
The engine roared and the plane began bouncing
up and down.
She pulled back, trying to correct the movement,
but then the wings began rolling.
She felt a bit desperate; everything was going
wrong.
'OK,' said Doug, 'I have control.'
He reached out to the control column in front
of him and the plane began flying steadily.
Francesca felt her face burn red with shame.
'I'm sorry,' she said.
'I didn't mean...'
She couldn't even finish.
'Don't worry about it,' Doug answered.
'Everyone finds it difficult at first.'
She glanced across at the man.
He was smiling at her.
'Just relax,' he said.
'I'll take us up a bit higher, then we can
level out and you can try again.'
Francesca watched as the instructor settled
the plane into a proper climb, then looked
out through the side window.
A sick feeling was rising up inside her.
Was flying really going to be so much harder
than she'd imagined?
She'd been looking forward to this moment
for so long, dreamed of piloting a plane for
so many years - surely it wasn't going to
be a disappointment after all?
'You OK?'
Doug called.
Francesca didn't look round.
She was determined not to let the man see
her nerves.
'Yes, fine,' she answered.
She looked down.
She saw a farm pass beneath them; the buildings
getting smaller even as she looked.
Then there was a road.
Already the cars on it looked like toys that
she might reach out and pick up in her hand.
Next a wood slid below, and the silvery S-shape
of a river, then the sharp brown line of a
railway.
At last, when Francesca felt in control of
herself again, she began looking round the
cockpit.
She stared at all the dials and switches in
front of her.
Would they ever make sense to her?
She must have shaken her head slightly.
'Confusing?'
the instructor's voice came.
She could see him smiling again.
'Yes,' she answered.
'Yes, they are.'
'You'll get used to them.
Just remember where the airspeed dial is - that's
the most important.
Speed through the air.
That's what keeps you flying.'
Francesca nodded and looked for the airspeed
dial again.
There it was in the top left-hand corner,
the needle pointing directly to 80.
The instructor made another quick call to
the control tower, so sudden and rapid that
Francesca didn't catch it.
Then he glanced across at her once more.
'So, how long have you been in England?' he
asked.
'Six months,' Francesca answered.
The man nodded.
'They did a good job at the language centre,'
he said.
'Your English is very impressive.'
'Thank you,' Francesca answered.
'I did ten years of English at school, so
it wasn't starting from zero.'
'And you didn't fancy university?'
the instructor asked.
'Came straight here to England when you left
school?'
'Yes,' Francesca replied.
'My parents tried to make me do a degree,
but all I've ever wanted is to learn to fly
and become a commercial pilot.
In the end, my father said, "Well, if I don't
have to pay for university, I suppose I can
pay for a language school and some flying
lessons."
And as English is the language of aviation,
England's the best place to learn to fly.'
Doug replied with a nod.
'So, what will you do after this?
You realise the commercial pilot's course
is ten times the cost of the private pilot's
licence you're doing with me?'
'Yes, I know,' Francesca answered.
'But I'm working as an au pair for the family
I live with here.
And then when I go back to Switzerland I'll
get a job and give extra English classes in
the evening.
I'm hoping I can make plenty of money like
that.'
Francesca saw Doug glance across at her.
For a moment a smile played around his lips
again as if an idea had occurred to him, but
then he said very simply, 'You are a very
determined young lady, Francesca.'
Francesca looked back into the man's dark
sunglasses, but couldn't see his eyes.
'I am,' she said quietly.
'Yes, I am.'
Doug turned his attention back to the controls.
Francesca watched him push the control column
forward very slowly.
As the nose of the plane dropped, suddenly
the horizon came into view through the windscreen.
Francesca felt their speed increasing rapidly,
and when she looked at the airspeed dial,
she saw it was already pointing to 120.
A few moments later, Doug reached for the
throttle and the speed dropped back a little.
'Right,' he said.
'We're flying straight and level now.
You take control again and see if you can
keep the plane steady like this.'
Very firmly, Francesca took hold of the controls
once more.
For two or three seconds as she took over,
the plane started bouncing around again.
'Gently!'
Doug called.
'You don't need to hold the controls so tightly.
Imagine you're with your boyfriend,' he added
with a little laugh.
Francesca gave a small frown, but concentrated
on the control column.
She relaxed her grip slightly.
The plane seemed to respond.
Slowly, she moved the control column around
with tiny actions.
It was strange.
The plane seemed to fly itself somehow, as
if it were an animal, a horse perhaps, which
was just beginning to trust its rider.
'That's better!'
Doug called.
'That's the idea.'
Francesca felt her confidence returning.
Gradually, she increased the movements she
made, watching and feeling how the plane responded.
Slowly, a strange feeling came over her.
She felt as though she wasn't sitting in the
cockpit holding the control column, but instead
had her arms stretched out, like a child pretending
to have wings.
And as she imagined this - seeing herself
as the pilot of her dreams - the wings of
the plane seemed to melt into her own.
It felt like a miracle.
She was flying all alone.
All of a sudden she glanced across the cockpit.
Doug was staring at her, and nodding his head
very slowly.
'Very good,' he said.
'I'm full of admiration.'
CHAPTER TWO
The price of dreams
Two hours later, Francesca was on the bus
home, heading back to Norwich.
As the bus found its way slowly through the
streets, Francesca looked out of the window
at the dull buildings and relived her first
flight.
It was hard to believe that she'd really been
piloting a plane up in the sky only a short
time before.
It felt almost like a dream.
But she had, and the lesson had gone well.
No, that wasn't true, she told herself - the
lesson had gone brilliantly, and she hadn't
just made that up herself.
The instructor had said so.
He had told her she was a 'natural'.
Francesca felt wonderfully happy.
She thought back over the day and her arrival
at the airfield.
She'd imagined Fastwings to be a busy little
flying school with several other students,
but when she'd arrived and discovered hers
was the only lesson that day, it had made
her feel uncomfortable.
So had Doug's welcome when she'd walked through
the Fastwings office door.
'Well, this is a pleasant surprise,' he'd
said.
'These lessons might be rather more fun than
I'd imagined.'
Francesca tried to decide what she thought
of Doug.
She felt confused.
He was about thirty-five or forty, quite tall
and good-looking.
However, that first remark of his was just
the sort of thing she'd hoped she wouldn't
hear in England.
And there was something in his eyes she didn't
like.
But then that had passed, and she had the
flying lesson to concentrate on.
There was no doubt he was a very good pilot
and he'd made her feel good about her flying.
It was just the way he looked at her and his
odd remarks that made her feel uncomfortable.
She was used to such comments from Italian
men, who were always trying to show off in
front of women.
But Doug was English and she thought Englishmen
might be different.
What had he said about handling the control
column like her boyfriend?
Did it mean what she thought?
Francesca felt her heart drop all of a sudden
as the image of Andrea came crashing back
into her head.
Dear Andrea.
The break-up of their relationship was almost
too painful a memory: the last three months
in Ticino, before she came over to England,
had been so emotional.
Andrea had been her first - well, her only
real boyfriend.
They'd begun going out together when Francesca
was only fifteen.
And she'd loved him deeply.
Dear Andrea, funny, handsome, sexy Andrea
- the boy she'd given herself to - the boy
she'd imagined marrying and having children
with.
But Andrea hadn't wanted her to come to Britain.
He hadn't wanted Francesca to learn to fly.
He'd always said her plan to become an airline
pilot was ridiculous, an embarrassment to
him, something he couldn't possibly ever accept.
And he'd meant it.
Whenever Francesca had raised the subject,
he'd become angry, once even marching out
of a cafe in front of all her friends with
a cry of 'Stupid, selfish dreamer!'
Well, who was the selfish one?
What kind of love was it that wanted to cut
your wings?
And what was wrong with having a dream?
In the end, Francesca had decided their relationship
would never work.
But making that decision, and finishing things
with Andrea, had almost broken her heart.
She'd made up her mind then that nothing,
and no one, would ever stand in the way of
her flying dream.
She wasn't interested in a relationship with
anyone.
The sight of a familiar pub brought Francesca
back to the present.
The next bus stop was hers.
She hurried off the bus and turned in the
direction of home.
She had a job as an au pair with the Thompson
family, looking after the two children, Sam
and Emma.
That afternoon Mrs Thompson was picking the
children up from school, so Francesca only
had to prepare their dinner, and get them
ready for bed.
After that, she was free - well, free only
to continue studying all the instruction books
necessary for the pilot's licence exams: aviation
law, radio procedures, the weather, all the
technical matters...
the amount was terrifying.
A pretty scarf in a shop window caught her
eye.
She hesitated.
To her surprise, it wasn't very expensive:
only 11.99 pounds.
Not very much to spend, she said to herself.
A moment later she dragged herself away from
the shop window.
She couldn't afford it.
If she wanted to achieve her ambition, there
could be no luxuries.
She had to save and save and save!
Everything now was a question of money.
Flying was so hugely expensive!
Lessons were more than 140 pounds an hour
and the minimum required for the private pilot's
licence was forty-five hours.
She'd arranged with Doug to have two one-hour
lessons a week over the following six months,
on Tuesday and Thursday afternoons - the days
Mrs Thompson only worked in the mornings.
But, in order to get a discount, she'd paid
Doug in advance for the whole course, including
examinations, and equipment - and the total
was over 7000 pounds!
And if she needed more than forty- five hours
for the private pilot's licence, she would
have to pay extra.
Even though her father had agreed to pay 5000
pounds now and then help fund the commercial
pilot training, the amounts required were
frightening.
As an au pair, although her room and food
were paid for, she only received 50 pounds
a week - less than half-an-hour's flying lesson.
Mrs Thompson was waiting for her when she
got home.
'So, how was it?'
she asked.
Francesca couldn't help grinning.
'Fantastic!'
she said.
'I'm so excited.
The instructor said I was very good.'
'Wonderful,' Mrs Thompson replied.
'But now you need to call your mother.
She telephoned ten minutes ago, terrified
that you might have had an accident.'
Francesca shook her head in despair.
Her mother's fears were yet another stress
she had to handle.
Francesca went upstairs, opened up her laptop
to make a Skype call, then listened to the
familiar sound as the number rang in Ticino.
After only a couple of seconds, her mother's
anxious face appeared on the screen.
A rush of Italian followed.
'Francesca!
Francesca, my darling, is that you?
Are you all right?
Why didn't you phone?
Your father and I have been worried sick!'
said her mother.
'Mamma!'
Francesca said, when she finally managed to
get in a word.
'Calm down!
I've only just got home.
Everything's fine.'
'Oh, thank God for that!'
her mother replied.
'I haven't been able to do anything all day,
imagining you crashing the stupid plane.
Please say you didn't enjoy it and that you've
decided to come home.'
Francesca closed her eyes.
After a couple of seconds she took a deep
breath.
'No, Mamma,' she said.
'It was brilliant.
Mamma, you must try not to worry.
The instructor called me "a natural".
It was even better than I'd dreamed!'
CHAPTER THREE
A different kind of fun
'Right,' Doug said, looking across the cockpit
at Francesca, 'I think it's about time we
had a bit of fun.'
'What do you mean?'
Francesca answered.
'Well, there are all kinds of fun,' Doug replied
with a strange smile.
'But the fun I'm referring to is stalling.'
Francesca felt confused.
'I'm sorry, I don't understand,' she said.
She wasn't certain whether he was making a
joke, but in any case the word 'stalling'
was a new one for her.
'A stall,' Doug replied, becoming more serious,
'is when the plane stops flying - usually
when it isn't going fast enough for the wings
to do their job.
In other words, when a plane is in danger
of falling out of the sky!'
It was a fortnight later - two weeks after
Francesca's first lesson.
She'd had three more lessons since and things
couldn't be going better.
In the second lesson she'd had further practice
at flying straight and level.
Then she'd gone on to 'turns': 'banking' the
plane - rolling the plane to the left and
right; and also 'the climb', which had seemed
so difficult in her first lesson.
Doug kept telling her how pleased he was with
her.
He had even said if she continued at the same
rate of progress, he could imagine her taking
her first solo flight in a couple of weeks'
time - after perhaps only ten hours - much
faster than the average student.
But now Francesca felt a tiny stab of fear.
Doug still had this slightly cruel look on
his face.
She was beginning to think he quite enjoyed
it when she was frightened.
Francesca tried to focus on the lesson again.
'So, what are we going to do then?'
she asked as lightly as she could.
'Well,' Doug replied, 'we're going to fly
the plane up to 4000 feet, check there's no
one else about, and then you're going to cut
the power until the plane stops flying.'
Doug paused, the sunglasses he always wore
flashing in the sunlight.
'What happens then?'
Francesca asked, trying to disguise the slight
tremble in her voice.
'Well, then, I hope you're going to get the
plane flying again.'
Doug paused and smiled.
'Otherwise we'll make a horrible mess in a
field!'
Fifteen minutes later, they took off and began
climbing into the grey sky.
It was a dull day, not the bright clear weather
that Francesca had experienced for her other
lessons.
When they reached 4000 feet Francesca set
the plane up for straight and level flight,
but it was much more difficult than in her
last lessons.
The grey of the land and the grey of the sky
meant there was almost no horizon - no guide
for keeping level.
She started to feel nervous.
They flew on for five minutes until they were
out over farmland to the west of the city.
Then, after glancing around out of the cockpit
window, Doug spoke again.
'Right,' he said.
'First, check your safety harness.'
Francesca pulled against the harness, but
she was held so tight against the seat she
could barely move.
'Good,' Doug went on, once he'd checked his
own harness.
'Right, now we look around: to the right...
and the left...
now a quick look behind... and most important
of all, down below...
Anything about?'
Francesca searched the sky, but couldn't see
any other aircraft.
'No,' she answered.
'OK, now listen carefully,' Doug continued.
'In a moment you're going to pull out the
throttle so there's no power, and pull back
on the control column to keep the nose up
in the air.
At some point you'll feel the plane tremble
and the controls will go soft like jelly.
And the stall-warning alarm behind us will
sound - it's like a trumpet sound.
Then, all of a sudden the nose will drop.
When that happens, push the control column
forward - this is very important.
Don't pull it back, which seems the natural
thing to do - push forward so that you're
heading towards the ground.
If you don't do that, the plane won't start
flying again.
After a few seconds like that, the plane will
pick up flying speed and you can pull out
of the dive and add the power again.'
He looked across at Francesca.
'OK, do you understand?'
Francesca repeated the instructions back.
Her heart was beating a little faster, unsure
of exactly what lay ahead.
'Ready?'
Doug asked.
Francesca nodded.
'Right,' he said.
'Now, pull out the throttle.'
Francesca obeyed.
Almost immediately the power died away and
the nose began to drop.
'Pull back!' Doug called.
Francesca did as he said.
The control column was firm, much firmer than
she'd felt before.
'Harder!'
Doug shouted.
'Pull back!
Keep the nose up!'
It required all Francesca's strength to keep
pulling back.
She felt herself becoming more and more anxious.
It was partly because of the way the plane
was behaving, but partly Doug's shouting as
well.
Her heart was racing.
'Keep pulling back!' he called.
'Harder!
Come on!'
Suddenly the stall-warning alarm sounded - a
long steady noise that didn't stop.
For a moment the plane trembled, then all
at once, the wings seemed to fold.
For the next couple of seconds Francesca didn't
know what was happening.
Her stomach seemed to fall out of her body.
Suddenly she found she was staring at the
ground and the earth was racing up to meet
them.
A scream became trapped in her throat; she
was paralysed with fear.
The thought rushed through her head that she
was going to die, that this was it, that the
flying idea had been a terrible mistake.
She didn't know what to do.
The next moment she realised Doug had taken
over the controls.
Still with the scream caught in her throat,
she saw him take his control column firmly
in both hands and push forward, increasing
the angle of their dive, then slowly pull
back.
After a few seconds he had brought back the
power and they were flying straight and level
again.
For a short while Francesca felt nothing but
relief.
Then she felt her face burning with shame.
Doug was watching her closely.
'You OK?'
'F... fine,' Francesca stammered.
She felt angry all of a sudden.
'I... it just took me by surprise, that's
all,' she said.
Doug smiled.
'Yes,' he replied quietly.
'It's a bit of a shock the first time.
Just a matter of letting yourself go,' he
added lightly.
'Like some other kind of fun I can think of.
In time you might actually get to like it.'
As he said so, he looked across again and
rested a hand on Francesca's knee.
For a moment she didn't realise what had happened.
Then she threw him a look of astonishment.
A couple of seconds later he withdrew his
hand.
They flew on in silence and neither referred
to what had happened.
CHAPTER FOUR
Have no fear!
That night Francesca couldn't sleep, her mind
was so full of unpleasant thoughts.
The incident that afternoon had reminded her
of the manager of a cafe where she'd worked
for the summer a couple of years before.
With a feeling of sickness, she remembered
the horrible man purposely pushing past her
as she worked behind the counter, pressing
himself against her and pretending it was
an accident.
Although it had happened four or five times,
she'd done nothing and said nothing, instead
deciding the best thing was simply to change
jobs.
But the incident had both embarrassed and
angered her.
Now the memory of Doug's words and his hand
on her knee gave her the same miserable feeling.
Had she misunderstood what he was saying?
Had his hand simply been a friendly gesture
to reassure her?
Or was it something else?
Was he trying to suggest something to her?
After half an hour like this, she finally
sat up, switched on the bedside light, and
decided to think logically about what had
happened.
Taking her iPod from the drawer, she put on
the headphones, selected some gentle music,
and slowly felt herself calm down.
Then she thought back to that afternoon's
incident.
Had it really happened?
Yes, of course, it had.
Was it an accident?
No, of course, it wasn't.
But that didn't necessarily mean Doug had
a sexual motive.
Stalling the aircraft had seriously alarmed
her and he might have been genuinely trying
to reassure her.
But was it acceptable for a man to put his
hand on her knee like that?
She wished desperately there was another woman
taking lessons for her to talk to, but there
wasn't.
There seemed to be only two other students,
in fact - both men, and she had yet to see
either of them.
When Francesca had asked where the other students
were, Doug had simply said, 'Well, times are
hard, didn't you know?'
And then, 'Why?
What's the problem?'
Francesca tried to think what she knew about
Doug already.
She was sure he was married.
Once when she was waiting in the office, Doug
had taken a phone call, discussing the time
he'd be home that evening.
Francesca remembered that as he'd put down
the phone he'd made one of those typically
British comments she couldn't be certain was
a joke - something about 'the joys of marriage'.
She guessed, too, that he had children: a
picture frame on his desk contained a photo
of two pretty young girls - twins of six or
seven, she thought.
But did it make any difference whether he
was married with children?
Her experience at the cafe had taught her
that it didn't.
That dirty old man had a wife and three horrible
teenage boys, who used to sit around the cafe,
grinning at her in almost as disgusting a
manner as the old man's.
For a moment or two she considered searching
for Doug Barker on the Internet and seeing
what she could discover about him, then decided
it was ridiculous.
She switched off her iPod, turned out the
light and determined to get some rest.
It was half an hour more before sleep finally
came.
***
By the time of her next lesson, two days later,
the whole 'hand-on-the-knee' business seemed
like a crazy dream and her spirits lifted
again.
Flying was the important thing.
She had to concentrate on that.
She was a little late when she arrived at
the airfield that afternoon.
Doug was in the hangar where the planes were
kept, checking the Cessnas engine.
'So, you've come after all,' he said, without
looking round.
'I was afraid the last lesson might have frightened
you off.'
Francesca hesitated for a moment, wondering
exactly what he meant, then she answered,
'Not at all.
My bus was held up in the traffic, that's
all.'
Doug turned to look at her and smiled.
'Good,' he said.
'It would be a terrible shame after such a
promising beginning.'
To Francesca's relief, Doug seemed to be in
a very business-like mood that day.
They dragged the plane outside and began by
checking round the aircraft.
Although she'd helped with the checks in her
previous lessons, Doug hadn't spent very long
explaining all the procedures.
This time he did.
Francesca was impressed at how careful it
all was: walking round the plane, examining
all the moving parts, looking at the tyres,
pushing and pulling at everything that could
be pushed or pulled, checking the lights and
oil.
Then Doug got out a small glass bottle shaped
like a test tube and pressed it up into a
small hole under the wing.
It half filled with fuel.
'Smell!' he said, holding the test tube out
to Francesca.
Francesca frowned.
'Why?'
she asked.
'Because if it doesn't smell like fuel, then
it may be water,' he explained.
'The fuel tanks are in the wings and if the
aircraft has been standing outside for a time,
rain might get in.
We do this before the first flight of the
day.
Look at the test tube.
What can you see?'
'Nothing special,' Francesca answered, 'just
clear liquid.'
'Then that's fine,' Doug went on.
'If there was water mixed in, the water would
sink to the bottom and you might see a line
dividing it from the fuel above.'
The checks went on for more than twenty minutes,
then Doug turned to her.
'Right,' he said, 'in future you'll do all
the checks on your own.
As the pilot of the plane it's your responsibility
to make sure it's safe to fly.
Understand?'
Francesca nodded.
'OK,' he said, 'let's go flying.'
Soon they were high up above the ground, heading
in the direction of the coast.
The sky was especially beautiful that day:
a clear blue, but dotted with clean white
clouds like exploding balls of paint.
Francesca began to relax.
Up in the sky her fears about Doug seemed
quite ridiculous.
Clearly, she had got everything out of proportion.
This time they practised descending: losing
height steadily using the power of the engine,
holding the plane at the same angle and trying
to keep the same speed.
For the first few minutes, Francesca struggled,
then, with her confidence returning, she began
to learn the technique.
After three or four attempts, she realised
that a smile of success had returned to her
face.
Noticing this, Doug spoke.
'So, how about another go at stalling?'
he said.
Francesca felt herself tense up again immediately.
Would this be another opportunity for him
to touch her knee?
She was determined not to show her fears.
'Good,' she answered.
'I want to get that right.'
Doug gave a short laugh.
'OK, take us up to 4000 feet again and let's
see what happens.'
Feeling her heart start to race, Francesca
put the plane into a climb.
Once they'd reached height, they checked their
safety harnesses and Francesca looked carefully
all around outside the plane.
Then, at Doug's instruction, she killed the
power and prepared for the stall.
'Pull back... pull back... that's the idea.'
Doug's words were more familiar this time.
So, too, was the plane's behaviour.
After what seemed like an age, the plane began
trembling just as before, then it suddenly
collapsed forward.
This time Francesca was ready for it.
As the nose fell towards the ground, she pushed
the control column forward and slowly increased
the power.
The plane responded immediately, the wings
grabbing at the sky, as if it were a climber
pulling itself back up a mountain.
Francesca breathed a sigh of relief.
She hadn't panicked, she had overcome her
fears.
And Doug hadn't touched her.
Everything was all right.
Doug was looking at her.
'You're a quick learner, Francesca,' he said.
Then he added with a short laugh, 'Just a
pity you don't need calming down.'
CHAPTER FIVE
Getting to know you
Ninety minutes later, Francesca was hurrying
down the road to the airfield gates.
The lesson had finished late and now she was
in danger of missing her bus.
She broke into a run.
If she missed the bus, she wouldn't be back
in time to get the children's dinner.
But despite running the rest of the way, she
saw the bus disappearing round the bend just
as she reached the gates.
Miserably, she sank down onto the grass by
the entrance.
The next bus wasn't for another hour.
She could ring Mrs Thompson, but she didn't
want to let her down.
She was just on the point of calling a taxi
and facing up to all that expense when she
saw a grey Audi approaching.
The next moment it pulled up beside her.
It was Doug.
He lowered the window and leant across.
'Waiting for a pick-up?' he asked.
Francesca's heart missed a beat.
Suddenly, she wasn't sure of her English.
Didn't 'pick-up' have a double meaning?
'I missed my bus,' she answered flatly.
'Jump in,' he went on.
'I'll give you a lift.'
The passenger door opened.
Francesca stood there looking at it stupidly.
Half a dozen conflicting thoughts were rushing
round her head, some saying: 'Don't get in,
don't be crazy,' while others were saying:
'Don't be ridiculous, you've just been alone
in a plane with him!
What's the difference?'
'What's the problem?'
Doug asked.
Taking a deep breath, Francesca stepped forward,
climbed inside the car and pulled the door
closed.
All of sudden she felt trapped.
The car pulled away.
Soon they were driving towards the city centre.
Francesca tried to calm herself.
After a short time, Doug glanced across.
'So, tell me more about yourself,' he said.
'I think we ought to know a little about each
other, don't you - especially if we're spending
all this time alone together.'
Francesca felt her whole body tense up.
'You know most things about me already,' she
murmured.
'No, I don't,' Doug answered.
'I'm interested.
A beautiful girl like you, giving up everything
in Switzerland and coming over here to learn
to fly.
Most girls your age are probably chatting
on Facebook and discussing boyfriends.'
'I'm not fifteen years old,' Francesca replied
sharply.
'Oh, I can see that,' Doug answered, looking
across.
'No, I simply meant you're pretty unusual.
Not many of my students come for their flying
lessons by bus, you know.'
Francesca kept her eyes firmly on the road
ahead.
'It must have meant a lot of sacrifices,'
Doug said.
Feeling she had to reply, Francesca answered,
'Not many.'
'Come on,' Doug continued, 'What about holidays,
clothes, all that sort of thing?
And no doubt you've left behind at least one
boy with an aching heart.'
Francesca felt sick.
She was urging the car on, willing it to get
to the city quickly.
'Why do you keep asking about boyfriends?'
she said, trying to keep control of her voice.
This seemed to amuse Doug even more.
'I just thought it might be quite lonely for
you here all on your own.'
He looked across at her and smiled.
Francesca took a moment to reply.
'Look,' she said, unable to hide her temper.
'I don't think my private life is any of your
business.
But if you must know - yes, I'm on my own
and I'm very happy like that.
All I want to do is get my pilot's licence.
Just now I'm not interested in anything else.'
'An excellent philosophy,' Doug said.
He turned towards her, that familiar smile
playing around his lips again.
'Apologies for asking.'
Francesca didn't look back.
Her blood was still boiling.
After a couple of seconds, Doug looked away
again.
They drove on in silence for a couple of minutes.
Then, all of a sudden, Doug turned onto a
quieter road.
Francesca tensed up again.
It wasn't the route the bus took.
'Where are we going?'
she asked.
'I thought you lived in Eaton,' Doug said.
'This is a short cut.'
Francesca shivered.
A horrible scene began playing out in her
mind: Doug driving her to some secret place,
locking the car doors so she was trapped inside,
then forcing himself on her.
Her heart raced crazily.
Surely it would be madness for him to try
anything?
She took a deep breath.
Doug glanced round.
'Are you all right?' he asked.
'You look very pale.'
'I'm fine,' Francesca answered weakly.
Doug watched her for a second or two longer,
looking unconvinced.
He didn't say anything for a time.
They drove on.
After a couple of turns, Francesca suddenly
recognised a church on the left-hand side.
She breathed a sigh of relief.
Perhaps Doug had taken a short cut after all.
'What's the name of your road?'
Doug asked.
Francesca hesitated.
'If you just drop me here, I'll be fine,'
she said quickly.
'Don't be silly,' Doug answered.
'Considering how much you're paying me, taking
you back home for once is the least I can
do.'
Francesca couldn't see a way out.
'It's Brabazon Road,' she said quietly.
Doug nodded.
After several more turns, they swung into
Francesca's road.
'What number?'
Doug asked.
'Really, just here would be great,' Francesca
protested.
'I run a door-to-door service,' Doug answered
firmly.
Francesca swallowed hard.
'It's the big house on the left, just after
the second tree,' she said.
A couple of moments later they pulled up at
the entrance to her driveway.
Francesca felt relief flood through her.
'Thank you very much,' she said, feeling she
should try to be polite.
'My pleasure,' Doug said, smiling.
Francesca had her hand on the door.
The next moment Doug suddenly leant across
her.
Terrified, Francesca pressed herself back
into the seat.
What was happening?
Doug gave a short laugh.
'Take it easy!
I'm only opening the door for you.'
He stretched right across her and reached
to the door.
'Handle's a bit awkward, you see.'
The door swung open.
Francesca climbed out.
'Thank you again,' she said very quietly.
Doug pulled the door shut and drove off without
replying.
CHAPTER SIX
If only...
That evening, once Sam and Emma, the Thompsons
children, had gone to bed and Francesca had
cleared up in the kitchen, she went back up
to her room to make her daily Skype call to
her parents.
As usual, she kept it cheerful and positive.
She told them happily of all the progress
she'd made and related a couple of Doug's
comments praising her flying skills.
She then concentrated on news about Sam and
Emma, which was what her mother was most interested
in.
With her family duty done, Francesca then
decided to email Antonella, her best friend
back home.
Although her message was definitely still
positive, she finished, 'The only problem
is that the instructor, Doug, makes me feel
really uncomfortable.
Although he's a good pilot, he makes these
weird remarks and I keep thinking he's about
to make some sort of sexual move.
He definitely touched my knee!
He seems to be laughing at me half the time
and he really scares me.
I just don't like him.'
Once she'd finished her email, Francesca read
it through.
She stared for a long time at the lines she'd
written about Doug.
Finally, with a little cry of annoyance, she
deleted everything she'd said about him, and
pressed 'Send' before she could change her
mind.
She was about to shut down the laptop, when
she found herself opening up the Internet
again and typing in the address of the Fastwings
website.
The familiar front page opened up: the picture
of her Cessna, G-AZBA, Doug in flying jacket
and sunglasses, leaning up against the engine.
A couple of bubbles of text near the bottom
caught her eye - recommendations from previous
students: 'Superb instruction from beginning
to end.
I never expected it to be so much fun!'
And another: 'As a one-man show, Fastwings
can keep costs to a minimum.
Getting my licence was cheaper than I imagined!'
Francesca thought about the comments.
It was that second one, emphasising how cheap
it was, which had made her pick Fastwings.
She wished now she'd chosen another flying
school.
She'd considered others at the time - there
was even another one at Norwich.
She typed that in now: Flying Start.
A fresh page appeared.
She remembered it immediately: the rather
unappealing picture of a young student sitting
in the cockpit beside his instructor.
The instructor looked very formal in his white
shirt and tie - another reason why Francesca
had chosen Fastwings.
Doug had seemed so much more casual.
Francesca tried to see into the Flying Start
instructor's eyes.
He looked very correct, certainly not someone
who might try to take advantage of her.
An idea flashed through her mind.
Could she switch schools, ask for her money
back from Fastwings, then sign up at Flying
Start?
She wouldn't have to begin all over again,
she would be able to continue from the point
she'd already reached.
But almost as quickly as the idea had come,
it died.
How could she ask Doug for her money back?
What could she give as a reason?
Francesca closed down her computer quickly,
angry with herself now.
What was she thinking?
Doug hadn't done anything.
Well, he'd possibly touched her on the knee,
but nothing more.
Nothing had happened!
She'd let her imagination run wild in the
car with him.
What was wrong with her?
Perhaps living here in England all on her
own was too much for her.
Perhaps she was too young.
Feeling furious with herself, Francesca marched
through into the bathroom, tore off her clothes
and stood under the shower.
Finally, after a couple of minutes under the
steady stream of water, she began to calm
down.
***
Francesca was determined to focus on her flying
when she arrived at the airfield for her next
lesson.
She knocked on the office door and was surprised
when a woman's voice told her to come in.
When she entered, she found a dark-haired
woman of about forty, sitting on the sofa.
She looked tired and fed up.
Two little girls were kneeling at her feet,
drawing in colouring books on the low table
in front of her.
Francesca recognised them from the photo on
Doug's desk.
'You must be Francesca,' the woman said immediately.
Francesca realised it was Doug's wife.
'Mrs Barker?'
she said.
'That's right,' the woman replied.
'I've heard all about you.
Doug's star pupil!'
She didn't wait for a response, but began
gathering her things together.
'Don't worry, we're not staying.
We just came to bring Doug his phone.
He left it on the dining table.
He's always forgetting things, poor man.'
Francesca didn't know how to react.
The woman sounded bitter and sarcastic.
Sometimes the English way of saying the opposite
of what was meant left her completely confused.
But she didn't need to think of an answer
because the next moment Doug came in.
'Don't bother with the introductions,' Mrs
Barker said, 'we've already done all that.
Besides, we're going.
How much did you manage to get?'
A brief discussion followed which Francesca
understood was something to do with money.
Doug then took out his wallet and handed across
a couple of notes, which his wife immediately
put in her bag.
All of a sudden, Doug marched across the room.
'I told you not to do that!' he shouted, pulling
up one of the girls roughly by the arm.
'I told you not to get your pens all over
the floor!'
The girl's face immediately twisted in fear
and alarm.
The next moment she began to cry.
She ran over to her mother's side.
'Oh, brilliant work, Doug!'
his wife said sharply.
'Well, it serves her right.
She should bloody well listen when I give
her orders,' Doug said angrily.
A short argument followed.
Eventually, Doug's wife gathered the children
together and they made for the door.
Doug meanwhile sank down into a chair and
watched the scene moodily.
A moment or two later, with barely a word
of goodbye, the small group hurried away.
When they'd gone, Doug twisted his face into
a frown.
'See what I mean about the joys of marriage?'
he said.
Francesca didn't respond.
At last Doug pulled himself upright.
'OK, "landings" today, wasn't it?
Perhaps you could do me a favour and fly us
straight into the ground.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
An unhappy client
For the next half hour, Francesca listened
while Doug explained in detail the principles
of landing.
It seemed the general idea was to bring the
plane slowly down, by carefully controlling
the power.
The most difficult part was the final moments.
When the plane was six or seven metres above
the ground, you had to 'flare' - to pull back
gently on the control column so that the main
wheels touched the ground before the nose
wheel.
At that point you had to hold steady, letting
the speed die away, so that the plane would
gently sink down.
'It's not as easy as it sounds,' Doug added.
'Some students get it almost immediately;
some take a long time.
Judging when to flare - when to pull back
- is the biggest problem.
You have to wait until the ground seems to
be rushing up to meet you... that's the moment
to flare.'
By the time they got up in the air, Francesca
was quite nervous.
She was trying to concentrate on flying, but
she couldn't stop thinking about the scene
with Mrs Barker and Doug's treatment of his
daughter.
It had shocked her tremendously - the anger
and violence hidden just beneath the surface.
She wondered if this was Doug's true nature.
The more she got to know him, the less she
liked him.
They climbed to 1000 feet and flew down the
western side of the airfield, parallel to
the runway.
It was windier than usual and Francesca found
it difficult to control the plane; she couldn't
seem to find the right power to keep the plane
straight and level.
Soon they were turning back towards the airfield.
The runway lay ahead in the distance.
Doug began a steady stream of instructions.
'OK, reduce power,' he said.
'Hold her steady at 80.
Not too slow... keep your speed up.'
Francesca looked along the nose.
The runway was creeping towards them, growing
bigger all the time, but it was a little over
to the left.
'Keep the plane in line with the runway!'
Doug called.
'You're not on the centre line.'
Francesca tried to correct their direction,
but when she did so, the nose came up.
'Watch your speed!'
Doug shouted.
'You're down to 65!'
Francesca pushed in the throttle, but it was
too much.
Instantly, the plane rose upwards.
Francesca pushed the control column forward,
then at last regained control.
'Are you OK?'
Doug asked, glancing across.
'I'm fine,' Francesca answered quickly.
'Right, try and keep her like this then,'
he said.
Francesca's eyes flashed between the dials
inside the cockpit and the runway visible
above the nose.
The plane slipped slowly down towards the
ground.
The runway was getting closer and closer,
the black and white stripes at its end like
a set of piano keys.
'Aim just beyond the piano keys,' Doug said,
more gently now.
'That's good.
Hold it there.
Now watch for the ground rush.'
Francesca froze.
What did it mean?
What was the 'ground rush'?
The runway already looked huge.
She waited.
Should she pull back now?
Surely they would hit the ground at any moment!
She pulled back on the control column and
at the same time reduced the power.
As the nose lifted, the runway disappeared
from sight.
They seemed to be flying on blindly, the plane
hanging in the air only a couple of metres
above the ground.
They held like that for an age, speed dropping,
like a boat sinking in the water.
Then, suddenly, there was a terrific bang.
For a second, Francesca thought they'd crashed.
Then she realised the main wheels had hit
the ground.
'OK, push the control column forward slowly
to bring down the nose wheel,' Doug called.
Francesca obeyed automatically.
She watched the nose slowly drop, then felt
the front wheel touch the ground.
The plane rolled steadily forward, eventually
coming to a stop.
'All right, take her off the runway,' Doug
instructed.
'Then let's have a talk.'
Francesca did as she was told.
She felt suddenly hot and embarrassed; the
headphones were tight on her ears.
'OK, stop here,' Doug said.
Francesca brought the plane to a stop.
She felt afraid of what Doug was going to
say; the landing had been so heavy.
'Have I damaged the plane?'
she began.
'There was so much to think about.
I didn't expect -'
'Don't worry about it,' Doug interrupted.
He turned towards Francesca and looked at
her closely.
'Heavy landings are quite normal at this stage.
But you're not concentrating today.
There's something on your mind.'
Francesca blinked.
Was it really so obvious?
She didn't know what to say.
'I...
I didn't sleep well last night.
Maybe that's it,' she said a bit desperately.
Doug raised his eyebrows.
He kept his eyes on her.
'I hope you're happy with the lessons,' he
went on quietly.
Francesca felt completely frozen: the harness
trapping her back against the seat, the cockpit
tinier than ever.
'Of course,' she lied.
Doug continued to watch her.
Then, keeping his eyes on her all the time,
he stretched out his hand and placed it on
top of hers where she was resting it on her
knees.
'Good,' he said, squeezing her hand very gently.
'Because I'm very happy with you.'
Francesca didn't move.
Doug's words seemed to hang in the cockpit.
She felt suddenly sick.
The image of a huge fleshy spider resting
on the back of her hand flashed into her mind.
After a moment or two more, Doug took his
hand away.
'Right, turn the aircraft round and take her
back to the runway,' he said.
'Let's see if we can get these landings sorted
out today.'
Francesca was still frozen.
Although Doug had removed his hand, it still
felt as though there was a spider resting
on hers.
She had to look to check there wasn't one
there.
'OK, let's go,' Doug said.
Francesca tried to refocus on flying.
She reached forward to the throttle and pushed
it in to increase the power.
The plane leapt forward fast, too fast.
Immediately, she pulled at the control column.
'Whoah!'
Doug called.
'We don't want to take off!'
Using his controls, he brought the plane to
a stop.
Francesca closed her eyes.
She felt her arms shaking slightly as she
held the control column.
She was sure it must be noticeable.
All of a sudden she felt a hand on her leg.
Francesca's eyes shot open.
She looked down to see the man squeezing the
top of her leg gently.
'Take your hand off me!'
she shouted.
Doug smiled at her across the cockpit.
'Whatever you say,' he said casually and slowly
removed his hand.
'Shame,' he added more quietly.
'I guess we'd better concentrate on these
landings.'
All of a sudden Francesca knew she couldn't
go on.
'I want to stop.
I want to stop the lesson,' Francesca said
quickly.
'I don't feel very well.'
Doug looked across and raised his eyebrows.
For a moment she thought he was going to lean
across and try to kiss her, and she froze.
Then, with heavy sarcasm, he said.
'As you wish.
Don't want an unhappy client, do we?'
Francesca didn't reply.
Doug took over the controls and took the plane
back towards the hangar without speaking.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Coffee break
When Francesca marched out of the Fastwings
office that afternoon, she had just missed
one bus into the city and it was almost a
two-hour wait till the next.
She didn't care.
It was just a relief to be out of the place
and away from Doug.
For fifteen minutes she walked as fast as
she could, going wherever her footsteps took
her, dragging her hand through her hair, as
if by doing so she might empty her head of
the memory of Doug's hand on hers - the imaginary
spider.
When she had at last calmed down, she found
she had walked right round to the other side
of the airfield.
As she was walking back towards the airfield
gates, a sign on the hangar she was passing
caught her eye.
'Flying Start: Pilot Training,' it read - it
was the other flying school she'd been looking
at online the night before.
A small door was cut into the hangar wall.
Perhaps if it hadn't been open, Francesca
wouldn't have thought to go and look any closer.
But as it was, she wandered across and looked
through the doorway.
There was little light inside, but she could
make out the shape of several aircraft in
the darkness.
Without thinking, Francesca stepped inside
and began making her way around the planes.
They were parked tightly together, wings almost
touching.
Slowly, she made her way among them, studying
them as if she were looking at pictures in
an art gallery.
Towards the back she saw an ancient yellow
plane, but behind that, the shape of an expensive
executive jet caught her eye.
She went over to look at it more closely,
admiring the smart green and gold paintwork,
and the eager hungry shape of its nose.
'Beautiful, isn't she?'
a voice behind her said.
Francesca swung round.
A young man of about twenty-five, with longish
brown hair and wearing blue work clothes,
approached.
He bent his head to pass under a wing, wiping
his hands on an oily cloth.
'I'm sorry,' Francesca began.
'I didn't realise there was anyone here,'
she added, noticing now a light aircraft behind
him, its engine cover open.
'The door was open, so I...'
'No problem,' the man replied.
'As long as you weren't planning to steal
one!'
Then, pointing at the jet, he went on, 'Yes,
she belongs to Harry Moore - you know, the
furniture man.
Uses it to pop around Europe and check that
everyone's making him lots of money.'
Francesca smiled.
She had no idea who Harry Moore was.
But this young man had a friendly and amusing
way of speaking.
And he looked funny.
He had a big nose and there was a big black
mark down the side of it, where he must have
rubbed oil from his hand.
'Anyway,' he went on, 'can I help?
You're not interested in flying lessons, are
you?'
Francesca felt embarrassed.
'Well, umm... actually I'm already having
lessons.
To be honest I'm just - how do you say?
- killing time.'
She was about to explain about the bus when
the man broke in.
'Oh, hold on a minute.
You must be Doug's Swiss-Italian, is that
right?' he asked, then cut himself short.
'Oh dear, that doesn't sound very good, does
it?
I'm really sorry; I just heard someone say
Doug had a foreign student taking flying lessons.
You're quite famous, you know.'
Francesca wasn't sure she liked this idea.
But there was something light and easy about
the man's way of speaking, and he'd made a
funny face at his mistake which relaxed her
immediately.
After all the tension of the afternoon it
was a wonderful relief.
'Do you work for Flying Start?'
she asked.
'Yes,' the man answered.
'I'm the office manager.'
He smiled.
'Big title, small job - I answer the phone
and help maintain the aircraft and so on.
Tom Brennan's the name,' he said.
As he did so, he put out his hand, then realising
it was covered in oil, took it back, smiling.
'Sorry, probably not such a good idea.'
Francesca laughed.
'No problem.
And I'm Francesca Bartolli,' she said.
'Nice to meet you,' he said.
Francesca smiled.
'Good to meet you, too,' she said.
They looked at each other for a second or
two, uncertain how to continue, then Tom went
on.
'I don't suppose you fancy a cup of coffee,
do you?
I'm just about to make one.'
Francesca hesitated.
'Aren't you busy?'
she asked.
'I was about to have a break anyway,' Tom
said.
'I'll just go and wash my hands.'
Tom led the way round the planes and out of
the hangar into a small office.
Over to one side there was a small sofa and
a table covered in flying magazines.
Leaving her there, Tom went off to the washroom.
A few minutes later, he reappeared, carrying
two cups of steaming coffee.
'There,' he said.
'Not exactly cafe latte, but at least it's
hot and wet.'
When she tasted the coffee, Francesca realised
the man hadn't been joking - it was awful.
But she didn't care; it was just such a relaxing
atmosphere after being with Doug.
'It's drinkable,' she said with a smile.
Tom laughed and sat down beside the desk.
'So,' he began, 'how are your lessons going?'
'Not too badly, I think,' Francesca answered.
'I didn't do very well today though.
I made quite a mess of my first landing.'
Tom grinned.
'You're alive, aren't you?
You know the definition of a good landing?'
he asked.
'One that you are able to walk away from.'
Francesca laughed.
Tom went on.
'So, why do you want to learn to fly?' he
asked lightly.
'I want to be a commercial pilot,' Francesca
answered.
Tom sat up in surprise.
'Wow!' he said.
'Good for you!
I'm impressed.
So why are you learning here?
Not enough flat land back home in Switzerland?'
Francesca laughed again and explained all
about it.
Tom listened carefully.
Soon Francesca realised she'd told him all
about her family and home and then they'd
moved on to discuss all things Swiss and Italian:
the people and food, even the Italian language.
Twenty minutes had passed before she knew
it.
'And what about you?'
Francesca asked the moment there was a break
in the conversation.
'I suppose you got your pilot's licence years
ago.'
'Actually, no,' Tom replied.
'My father was a pilot in the Royal Air Force
- and thought I'd be brilliant, but to be
perfectly honest, I didn't enjoy it much.
Got in a total panic and scared the instructor
out of his pants.
I'm happier on the ground.
But I still think planes are very beautiful.'
'Yes, I know what you mean.
My friends all thought I was crazy when I
said that,' she replied, happy to have found
someone who felt the same.
They fell silent for a moment and she suddenly
began to wonder if she'd stayed too long.
'I'm sorry,' she said.
'I ought to go and let you get on with your
work.'
Tom gave a small smile.
'Yes, I suppose so,' he said uncertainly.
'The boss will be back soon.'
Francesca felt awkward.
They both stood up, a bit embarrassed.
As Francesca got to her feet, she noticed
the drawing of a bird - an owl - on a notepad
on the desk.
It was beautiful: detailed and delicate.
Tom saw her looking at it.
'The head's not quite right,' he said.
'I've got to do that bit again.'
'You drew it?'
Francesca asked.
'But it's lovely!'
she went on, genuinely impressed.
'It must have taken ages.'
'About half an hour,' Tom replied.
'Sometimes there isn't a lot to do in the
office,' he added with a laugh.
Francesca studied it carefully.
'It's fantastic,' she said at last.
'Do you draw other things as well as birds?'
'Well, people sometimes,' he answered.
'But mostly birds and planes.
Anything that flies, I suppose.'
'You've got a real talent,' Francesca said.
Tom looked a bit embarrassed.
Then, all of a sudden, he tore off the sheet
with the bird and handed it to Francesca.
'Here,' he said.
'A small gift.'
Francesca protested only briefly before accepting
the drawing.
Tom showed her out of the hangar.
'Well, good luck with your flying lessons,'
he said once they were outside.
'Doug's certainly a brilliant pilot, or so
I've heard.'
Francesca's heart sank.
For the last half-hour, she'd forgotten all
about Doug.
She didn't say anything.
'Drop in again next time you're here,' Tom
said suddenly.
'I'm nearly always around if you fancy another
coffee.'
Francesca smiled and put out her hand.
Their eyes met for a second.
She wondered if she would see Tom again.
Then she set off down the path towards the
airfield gates.
When she'd gone ten metres or so, she couldn't
help glancing round.
Tom was still standing in the doorway.
With a little wave, he immediately disappeared
back into the office.
CHAPTER NINE
A difficult phone call
As soon as she'd put Sam and Emma to bed that
evening, Francesca hurried up the stairs to
her room, turned on her laptop, and opened
up the Flying Start website.
Reading through all the details now, she couldn't
understand why she'd ever chosen Fastwings.
Flying Start had more aircraft, more instructors,
and offered several more courses.
Besides that, now she examined the website
more closely, the whole place seemed more
attractive.
In a section called 'Gallery' there was a
huge display of photos: aircraft in flight,
aircraft on the ground, sunlit landscapes
taken from the air, the same scenes repeated
with snow on the ground.
Francesca looked at them, feeling increasingly
annoyed, unable to believe that she'd ignored
them before.
There was another section called 'Staff.
This time she checked the photos more carefully:
there seemed to be three main instructors
- two youngish men: Nick Downing and Brian
Hamilton, and a much older man, George Scott.
Next, there was a photo of Tom.
Francesca looked at it for a long time.
It was unmistakeably him - the nose was so
recognisable.
He was standing beside one of the aircraft,
smiling shyly.
He looked kind and honest, his eyes wide and
warm.
Had she really seen the photograph before?
She couldn't remember it and felt slightly
ashamed at the thought.
She glanced at the drawing of the owl that
she'd already put on the noticeboard above
her desk.
If only she had taken up lessons at Flying
Start!
But she'd paid for the whole private pilot's
licence course with Doug; she was committed
to lessons with him.
The memory of his hand on her hand and leg
came flooding back.
She could feel it even now - like a huge great
tarantula creeping up her body.
It made her feel sick; it made her want to
scream!
Quite why she didn't close down the laptop
at that moment, she never fully understood.
Later, she wished she had just shut it down
and gone to bed.
But after hesitating for a few seconds, she
did a search for Doug by typing in his name.
Instantly, half a dozen 'Doug Barkers' appeared
with Facebook entries.
She quickly checked the photos one by one,
but they were clearly not the Doug she knew.
Next she tried 'Doug Barker Flying Instructor'.
This time the results were different.
An entry half the way down the page caught
her eye.
'Flying instructor wins damages' it read.
It appeared to be from a newspaper, The Southampton
Herald.
With a feeling of sickness about what she
might discover, Francesca opened the page
and saw a photo of the Doug Barker she knew
only too well.
He was standing beside an aircraft, hand on
its nose.
Below the photograph, was a report.
With increasing horror, Francesca read:
A Southampton flying instructor yesterday
won damages against a woman who had accused
him of sexual harassment.
The woman, who remains unnamed, had accused
Doug Barker, 37, of making sexual advances
to her while she was receiving flying lessons
from him.
The woman yesterday admitted in court that
she was unable to provide evidence and all
charges against Mr Barker were dropped.
The judge ordered the woman to pay Barker
2500 pounds in damages...
It was a very long time before Francesca got
to sleep that night.
At ten o'clock the next morning, Francesca,
sat down at the desk in her room, and picked
up her mobile phone.
After closing her eyes for a second or two,
she searched down through the numbers until
she found the one for Fastwings.
Then, before she could change her mind, she
pressed the Call button.
The number rang for a very long time.
Half of Francesca was praying that it wouldn't
be answered, but just as she was about to
give up, she heard Doug's voice.
'Fastwings,' was all he said.
Francesca decided she must sound firm.
Taking a deep breath, she said, 'Hello, it's
Francesca here...
Francesca Bartolli.'
Doug gave a short cruel laugh.
'Ah, Francesca Bartolli,' he responded sarcastically.
'For a moment, I thought it might be the other
Francesca I teach.'
Francesca didn't respond.
She hated Doug now; hated him with all her
heart.
'So, what can I do for Francesca?' he asked.
Francesca took another deep breath.
'I'm ringing,' she said, 'because I've decided
I must cancel.'
There was a slight pause.
Then Doug spoke again.
'I see,' he said carefully.
'When would you like your lesson instead?'
Francesca put a hand to her head.
'No,' she said more quietly.
'I mean I want to cancel the course.
I've decided not to continue the flying lessons.'
There was a long silence after that.
Francesca's hand trembled as she waited for
Doug's response.
The silence went on and on.
Finally, Francesca decided something must
be wrong.
'Are you still there?'
she asked.
'Oh yes, I'm here,' Doug replied.
He didn't say anything more.
Francesca felt a tight ball in her throat.
At last Doug broke the silence.
'What's the problem, Francesca?' he asked.
'Just because I put my hand on you a couple
of times to calm you down...
Is that really so terrible?'
'It wasn't to calm me down,' she replied quickly.
'What was it then?'
Doug asked.
'You know very well,' she protested.
'But it's not only that - it's...'
She stopped.
Francesca didn't know what to say.
She didn't want to say anything about what
she'd read the previous night.
She bit her lip.
'What exactly are you accusing me of, Francesca?'
Doug asked quietly.
Francesca searched for words.
She'd prepared in advance what she was going
to say, but now the memory of that newspaper
article had wiped all the words from her head.
'I...
I just want to stop,' Francesca said, her
nerve failing her.
'I can't explain.
I'm sorry.
It was a mistake.'
After another pause, Doug spoke again.
'I see,' he said.
'So you're not going to have lessons somewhere
else then?'
Francesca hesitated.
Although she'd expected the question, now
she realised she had made the mistake of not
deciding firmly on the answer.
'I haven't made any plans,' she said.
'I'm not sure.
I may go back to Switzerland.'
It came out before she knew she was going
to say it.
'What a pity,' Doug replied, with a hint of
sarcasm.
'Yes,' Francesca said.
There was another silence.
'Well, don't expect any of your money back,'
Doug said finally.
'What do you mean?'
Francesca asked.
'You can't keep my money!'
There was a pause.
Then Doug spoke again.
'I don't know about that, Francesca.
You see, the way I understand it, we had a
contract - a contract for a whole flying course,
and now you're trying to break the contract.
I think I can do whatever I like and you don't
have a leg to stand on.'
Francesca felt panic rising suddenly in her
throat.
'I...
I don't understand.
What do you mean, "a leg to stand on"?'
'I mean, you can't do anything about it, Francesca,'
Doug answered slowly.
'If I decide not to give you any money back,
then that's your hard luck.'
Francesca didn't know what to do.
She could hardly breathe.
'But you can't do that!'
she said.
'Listen, Ms Bartolli,' Doug replied with exaggerated
politeness.
'You've called to tell me you want to break
your contract and as good as accused me of
trying to rape you!
How do expect me to react?
Who exactly do you think you are?
It seems to me you've got a pretty big idea
of yourself!'
Francesca felt tears coming and it made her
furious.
She never cried.
She didn't know what to do, what to say.
Suddenly she felt completely out of her depth.
'Please,' she said desperately, hating herself
for being weak.
'Don't do this to me!'
There was another pause.
'Well, I'll have to think about it.
You say you're going back to Switzerland?'
Francesca fought against the tears.
'Probably,' she muttered.
'Because if you decide to join another flying
school here, I will be very, very angry,'
he went on.
Francesca felt the tears rising up through
her body and all of a sudden, just as they
burst, she shouted out down the phone.
'Oh, stop it, please!
Just leave me alone!'
Then, without knowing she was about to say
it, she added, 'I wish I'd never come here.
I hate it here in England.
I just want to go home!'
With that, she ended the call and in a sudden
fit of despair, threw the phone hard down
onto her bed.
It bounced once, and crashed against the wall.
As the flood of tears streamed from her eyes,
Francesca saw that the phone had broken open
and the battery had fallen onto the floor.
She threw herself onto the bed and covered
her head with the pillow.
CHAPTER TEN
A fresh start
'I don't understand why you have to leave,'
Sam said bitterly, kicking his heels against
the park bench.
'I don't want you to go back to Switzerland.'
Francesca gave a deep sigh.
It was over a week later and she was sitting
in the park near the Thompson's house, watching
the children play in the warm May sunshine.
After playing on the swings for a good while,
Sam had come over and sunk down beside Francesca,
exhausted.
'I'm sorry, Sam,' Francesca began.
'It's very difficult to explain, but I've
had to change my plans.'
'But why?'
the little boy asked.
'Because... because things haven't worked
out the way I'd hoped,' Francesca answered.
'But you said you were going to be a pilot,'
Sam said with a frown.
'You said you were going to fly planes!'
Francesca dropped her head.
Mrs Thompson had warned Francesca how upset
the children would be.
Sam was such a sweet little boy and she loved
him dearly, but she wished he would stop.
Making the decision to go home to Switzerland
had been terrible enough.
Now, if the children were going to question
her in this way, it would be unbearable.
Francesca had told Mrs Thompson of her decision
the day after the phone call to Doug.
Mrs Thompson had been quite disappointed herself.
'Oh no, not really?'
she'd said.
'But I thought you were enjoying it here.
And you seemed to be doing so well with the
flying lessons!'
Francesca hadn't known what to say.
For some reason she didn't want to tell Mrs
Thompson about Doug's behaviour or what she'd
read.
She didn't want to tell anyone.
She couldn't properly understand it herself,
but she felt strangely ashamed - as though
she was partly responsible for what had happened.
Instead, she told Mrs Thompson that taking
flying lessons in a foreign language had proved
to be more difficult than she'd realised at
the beginning.
Francesca guessed that Mrs Thompson hadn't
really believed it.
But the woman was sensitive enough not to
press Francesca for any further explanation.
She simply said how sorry she was, and how
sorry the children would be to see her go.
Francesca's departure was set for a month's
time - the period of notice she was obliged
to give according to her contract.
Doug's threat not to return the money for
the unused lessons had also dominated Francesca's
thoughts all week.
As each day passed her anxiety grew, until
finally Mrs Thompson asked what was worrying
her so much.
Francesca explained what Doug had said about
her breaking the contract and losing her money.
Mrs Thompson was shocked and that night told
her husband, who was a solicitor.
Mr Thompson took one look at the paperwork
Francesca had received from Fastwings, and
said, 'The man's talking rubbish!
What's the telephone number of this place?'
Francesca didn't hear the phone call, but
a short while later Mr Thompson appeared saying,
'What a thoroughly unpleasant man.
I think you're better off having nothing more
to do with him!'
Two days later, a cheque had arrived in the
post.
The sound of someone calling her name brought
Francesca back to the present and made her
look up.
A cyclist had stopped about ten metres away
and was calling across.
'Francesca?
Yes, it is!'
Francesca stared for a moment, still lost
in her thoughts, then realised who it was.
The man was already wheeling his bike towards
her.
'Do you remember me?
Tom Brennan... from Flying Start?'
Francesca blinked a couple of times.
'But, of course I do,' she answered.
'Nice to see you again,' she said, genuinely
pleased to see a friendly face.
'Great to see you, too,' Tom said.
'How are you?
How are things?'
Francesca paused for a moment before replying,
wondering what to tell him.
But there was no point in going into the whole
business with Doug.
'I'm fine,' she said, as Sam went running
off back to the swings.
Then, she went on quickly: 'How about you?'
'Oh, same as ever,' Tom answered.
He went on immediately: 'Seeing you here is
really funny because I was thinking about
you only yesterday.'
Francesca frowned, not quite sure what was
coming next.
'Yeah, you see I noticed there was a new film
out at the cinema, a film about Amelia Earhart,
you know-'
Francesca interrupted him: 'Yes, the first
woman to fly across the Atlantic.'
'That's right,' he went on.
'Anyway, I just thought...'
He seemed to lose confidence all of a sudden.
'Well, I just wondered if you'd like to see
it... if you're not busy, that is.'
Francesca's heart gave a little leap, excited
at the thought.
But then, just as quickly, her heart fell.
She was leaving for Switzerland in less than
a month.
What was the point of getting to know him
better?
It was just stupid and unfair.
Tom misunderstood Francesca's silence.
'Sorry,' Tom went on, rubbing the side of
his nose all of a sudden.
'I just thought that as it was a film about
flying and a famous woman pilot, you might
-'
'Oh, I'd love to it see it,' Francesca said
looking him directly in the eyes, 'and I really
appreciate you asking, but there's something
you should know.'
'You've got a boyfriend...'
Tom said.
Francesca took a breath.
'No, no, it's not that.
The fact is I'm going back to Switzerland
in three weeks' time.'
'What!'
Tom said.
'Yes, I decided...'
Francesca paused.
'Why?'
Tom asked, concerned.
'What's happened?'
Francesca thought about the excuse she'd given
Mrs Thompson.
But for some reason the words seemed to stick
in her throat.
Tom broke in, embarrassed.
'I'm sorry.
It's none of my business, but I'd heard you
were doing brilliantly at Fastwings,' Tom
said.
'You were getting on well with Doug-'
'I wasn't,' Francesca cut in.
'Sorry?'
'I wasn't getting on with him at all,' Francesca
answered, strangely relieved to have told
him the truth.
'Why?'
Tom answered, clearly very surprised.
'I don't want to go into the reasons,' Francesca
said quickly.
'I just don't like him, that's all.
He wasn't very nice to me and I don't like
the way he treats his children either.
He frightens me, actually.'
'Oh...'
Tom answered, trying to absorb what he'd just
heard.
'I must say I'd heard Doug could be quite
a hard instructor.
And I think he's going through a bit of a
bad time just now,' he added.
'All the same...'
'What do you mean?'
Francesca asked.
'What kind of bad time?'
'Oh, I don't know,' Tom answered.
'Financial problems, I think.
Apparently he borrowed a lot of money to set
up Fastwings.
And personal things, as well.
There's a rumour his marriage is on the rocks,
actually.'
Francesca was silent for a moment.
The idea of the man's private life collapsing
would only make him more unstable and it frightened
her more than ever.
'But anyway, that's no reason for you to stop
your lessons,' Tom went on, interrupting her
thoughts.
'You've come this far - you simply mustn't
give up.
Come and have a try at Flying Start.
We'd love to have you.'
'I'm sorry, Tom,' Francesca said.
'Something's happened.
I've lost my confidence, I think...'
'What!
I can't believe that,' Tom protested.
'I can't carry on, Tom,' she said.
'I feel a complete mess.
Besides, Doug would be furious if he knew
I was starting lessons with you.'
'Well, that's his problem.
Anyway, you don't have to tell him you're
flying with us,' Tom answered.
'He'll kill me if he finds out,' Francesca
murmured.
'Rubbish,' Tom answered.
'Anyway, I'm not going to let you run off
to Switzerland.
Make a fresh start!
I absolutely insist.
When are you free next?'
CHAPTER ELEVEN
A gentle touch
That night, lying there in the darkness, Francesca
replayed her meeting with Tom over and over
in her mind.
It was amazing to her how quickly and dramatically
her mood could change.
All the previous week she'd been down in the
deepest depths of misery, her dream of becoming
a pilot completely ruined.
Then, all of a sudden, after meeting Tom in
the park, she was sailing up through the clouds,
floating through the air like a bubble of
soap.
It made her want to laugh; she actually lay
there on the pillow with a smile on her lips.
Life could begin again!
The dream was not dead.
As she finally drifted closer to sleep, the
memory of Tom's face formed in her mind.
She liked his big nose.
It made her smile once again to remember the
way he kept holding it between his thumb and
finger, as if hoping to find that it might
have reduced in size.
***
It was a long wait till her next free afternoon,
but the following Tuesday, she was waiting
at her window when Tom's small red car pulled
into the Thompson's driveway.
Telling herself not to rush and seem too eager,
she waited until she saw him climb out of
the car and approach the front door.
Then she ran down the stairs and opened the
door.
'Hi,' he said cheerfully, touching his nose
as he did so.
Francesca couldn't prevent a small laugh.
Tom looked puzzled.
'What's funny?' he asked.
'Nothing.
I'm sorry, I'm just excited,' Francesca replied.
They stood there, looking at one another for
a moment or two, both a little embarrassed,
then Tom laughed as well.
'Right, we'd better go!'
They climbed in the car and set off, still
laughing, like over-excited children.
Soon, they were speeding towards the airfield.
Tom proved to be a terrible driver - either
that or his nerves had got the better of him.
They seemed to approach traffic lights and
roundabouts at great speed, then need to brake
very hard.
At the same time, Tom chatted away happily,
telling Francesca all about Flying Start and
its history, about the aircraft and about
George, the instructor who would take her
flying that afternoon.
Francesca could hardly take a word in.
She was so excited, so relieved that her life
was moving forward again.
She sat back with her head close to the open
window and let the wind blow through her hair.
She felt as though she'd been reborn.
After twenty minutes they arrived at the airfield.
When they went into the Flying Start office,
two middle-aged men were sitting at a small
round table, examining a map.
Tom introduced them: Mike, another student
like herself, and John, his instructor.
Francesca then noticed a silver-haired man
of about sixty-five sitting on the sofa, reading
the newspaper and drinking coffee.
For a second or two, Francesca wondered what
he was doing there, but then the man got to
his feet and stretched out his hand.
'Something tells me you must be Francesca,'
he said.
'My name's George Scott.
I believe we're going flying together.'
The moment she shook his hand, Francesca felt
herself relax.
'If you're Italian, you must like coffee,'
he said.
'I love coffee,' Francesca replied, a little
puzzled by the man's remark.
George's eyes twinkled with amusement.
'In that case,' he went on, looking down at
the cup he was holding, 'don't drink any of
this stuff - unless you've got a death wish,
that is.'
***
Half an hour later, after doing all the usual
checks, Francesca watched from the left-hand
seat of the Flying Start Cessna 152, as George
climbed painfully into the plane.
'I'm getting too old for this,' George said.
'You know the worst thing about flying a light
aircraft?' he went on, pulling himself up
and round into the seat.
'No,' Francesca answered.
'It's getting inside the bloody plane,' George
went on.
He finally managed to drag his second leg
inside the door, then spent another exhausting
minute putting on his safety harness.
Once that was done, he turned to Francesca.
'Right, take her away, Ms Bartolli.
Wake me when we get to 1000 feet.'
Francesca laughed, but George was almost true
to his word.
For the next fifteen minutes, Francesca was
totally in control and George sat beside her
without saying a thing.
She took the plane round to the waiting point
before the start of the runway, performed
all the aircraft checks, then called to the
control tower to line up on the runway.
With a wave of his hand, George then indicated
that she should pull forward onto the runway.
Once the control tower had cleared her for
take-off, Francesca turned to him.
'Shall I take off?'
she asked.
'Can't think of another way to get to 1000
feet, can you?'
George replied, his eyes twinkling with good
humour again.
Francesca laughed, and pushed in the throttle.
The little plane seemed to sit up suddenly,
then pulled itself down the runway, gathering
speed all the time.
Checking the airspeed dial, Francesca watched
as the needle reached 60, then she pulled
back gently on the control column.
Out of the corner of her eye, she was aware
of George sitting up more alertly, his hands
loose on his knees, ready if necessary to
reach out to the controls.
They climbed steadily to height.
When Francesca glanced across, she saw George
searching the sky around them, checking for
danger.
She realised now that his casual act was exactly
that.
Every moment they'd been in the air he'd been
ready to take control.
It comforted her tremendously.
While he left her to fly the plane, she felt
confident that he would react quickly the
moment there was a problem.
'Very nice,' he said at last.
'You've got a very gentle touch.
Now, do you fancy having another go at landing?
I think you said that was the point you reached
at Fastwings.'
Francesca nodded.
'OK,' she answered, trying to sound positive.
They flew back along the side of the airfield.
A minute later, Francesca looked over her
shoulder and saw the end of the runway about
forty-five degrees behind.
Careful not to lose any height, she turned
the plane through ninety degrees, then reduced
the power a little.
Slowly, they began to lose height.
Half a minute later, with the end of the runway
almost directly opposite the left-hand window,
she turned again so the runway was directly
ahead.
With her hand on the throttle, Francesca let
the plane slip slowly down through the air.
It was like being on a very gentle children's
slide.
Beside her, Francesca could see George sitting
relaxed.
The runway seemed to rise up to meet them.
She tried to picture the moment to pull back
on the control column, the rush as the ground
seemed to swallow them up.
'Wait...' she murmured to herself, 'Wait...'
All of a sudden the runway seemed to open
out as if it were a sheet being unfolded in
front of her.
She pulled back and held steady.
'Now, hold on!'
she said under her breath.
The plane sank gently down, then a moment
later there was a small bump as the main wheels
met the ground.
Carefully, she pushed the control column forward
to bring the nose wheel down and they rolled
along the runway.
As they did so, Francesca felt the blood begin
flowing back to her fingers.
She hadn't realised she had been so tense.
'That, Ms Bartolli,' George said, looking
across at her, 'was a landing I would have
been proud of myself.'
He stretched out his hand.
Smiling with delight, Francesca shook it.
Tom was waiting when they pulled up outside
the hangar.
'How did it go?' he asked anxiously, as they
climbed out of the plane.
'Bloody awful,' George answered, his eyes
twinkling once more.
'Don't know where to start.'
'Really?'
Tom said, his face screwing up.
Francesca went up to him.
'It was wonderful,' she said.
'Thank you, Tom,' she added.
'I'm so very glad you spotted me that afternoon
in the park.'
CHAPTER TWELVE
Alone at last
That night Francesca had to babysit, but the
following evening Tom picked her up at seven
thirty and they headed out to the cinema.
Tom was very gentlemanly, hurrying to open
the car door for her, insisting on paying
for the tickets, and buying popcorn.
Francesca loved it.
Her old boyfriend, Andrea, had always said
such old-fashioned manners were 'uncool',
but Francesca enjoyed Tom's attention.
She felt very special, and it made her feel
attractive; she realised now how much Andrea
had taken her for granted.
Francesca loved the film.
Amelia Earhart had been one of her childhood
heroes and she was an interesting character
in herself, quite apart from her flying achievements.
As they left the cinema, Francesca felt so
happy she reached out and took Tom's hand.
Squeezing it excitedly, she said,
'Come on, let's go and get a drink.'
Tom's reaction to the gesture was one of almost
complete astonishment, but he certainly didn't
protest.
Francesca was almost as astonished as Tom
at what she'd done - all the emotions of the
last week had left her head spinning.
When they'd found a pub and settled in a quiet
corner, they chatted about the film for a
time.
Then Francesca said, 'Do you know, my last
boyfriend would never have taken me to a film
like that.'
'Why ever not?'
Tom asked.
'He could never understand why I loved planes
so much,' Francesca answered.
'He seemed to find it embarrassing.
I think he believed a girl who liked aircraft
must be strange in the head.
He hated it whenever I said I wanted to become
a pilot.'
Tom shook his head.
'That's crazy,' he said.
'I think it's a brilliant idea.'
Francesca nodded, delighted to find someone
who thought as she did.
'Anyway,' she went on, 'I want to know more
about you.
You've hardly told me a thing about yourself.'
Tom gave a weak smile.
'What do you want to know?' he asked.
'Well, what are you interested in for a start?'
Francesca replied.
Tom hesitated.
'Well, painting and drawing, above all.
Like I said before, mostly anything that flies.'
'Would you show me your pictures some time?'
Tom looked uncomfortable.
'They're nothing special.
"Traditional and unimaginative" was how they've
been described,' he said.
'What do you mean?'
Francesca asked.
'I went to art college after I left school,'
Tom replied, then went on quite bitterly.
'They didn't much like the sort of thing I
do and I didn't like their ideas, so we had
a bit of an argument.
I left after a couple of terms.'
'That sounds like a true artist,' Francesca
replied.
'Good for you!'
Tom looked surprised.
'That's not what my father said,' Tom added.
'He called it "dropping out".'
'Well, if that bird you drew is anything to
go by, it was the art college that lost out.'
'That's not quite how my father sees it,'
Tom muttered.
'I've never been quite the son he wanted,
I guess.'
Sensing it was a bit of a delicate area, Francesca
asked him about other things and soon the
subject was forgotten.
Tom relaxed again.
Three-quarters of an hour passed before they
knew it; all of a sudden the pub was closing.
They drove back to the Thompsons, both curiously
silent, a little uncertain of what lay ahead.
When they reached the house, Tom pulled up
beside the pavement.
With the engine still running, he turned towards
Francesca.
'Thank you for a wonderful evening,' he said.
'I've enjoyed it so much.'
'No, Tom, I've got to thank you,' Francesca
replied.
'It was really lovely.'
They looked at each other a bit awkwardly.
After a moment Tom spoke again.
'So, I'll see you up at the airfield next
Tuesday?'
'You bet,' Francesca replied.
The awkwardness grew again.
This time Francesca reached out her hand.
'Tom,' she said, touching him on the arm.
'I didn't thank you properly yesterday afternoon
for persuading me to join Flying Start.'
'Of course, you did,' Tom protested.
'No, Tom, really,' Francesca insisted.
'Three days ago I was more depressed than
I can tell you.
I was about to go back to Switzerland and
drop the whole idea of flying, a dream I've
had since I was just a child.
And then meeting you in the park...
well, you rescued me, don't you understand?'
Tom blinked in confusion.
'Really?' he asked.
'Really,' Francesca replied.
With that, she leant across the car very quickly
and kissed Tom on the cheek.
'Thank you,' she said, then climbed hurriedly
out of the car.
Later that night, she lay in bed thinking
over her evening with Tom.
It occurred to her that kissing him like that
wasn't exactly the act of someone determined
to avoid a relationship, but she didn't really
care.
There was something about his shyness that
she liked and the way he seemed so proud to
be with her.
When she'd got out of the car after the kiss,
he'd looked as wide-eyed as a young boy with
a brilliant birthday gift.
The memory left her with a smile as she drifted
off to sleep.
***
Francesca didn't have any time off in the
next few days, so she didn't see Tom again
until the next Tuesday afternoon.
Of course, they phoned and texted one another
a number of times.
When she arrived at the airfield, however,
George was keen to get going quickly, so there
was no time to talk.
Once Francesca had checked the aircraft, she
climbed inside and started up the engine.
A couple of minutes later, George pulled himself
slowly into the right-hand seat.
'OK,' he said, once they were settled.
'Today I want three more landings exactly
like the one you did last Thursday.
Do you think you can manage that?'
They approached the runway, then waited for
another plane to land.
As it got nearer, Francesca recognised the
Fastwings Cessna and her heart missed a beat.
Although she knew Doug couldn't possibly see
her, she felt herself slide lower in the seat
as he flew past.
When his plane had cleared the runway, they
moved forward themselves and quickly took
off.
A couple of minutes later they were at 1000
feet and turning round on the familiar route
to land back at the airfield.
Francesca's first landing was good - not as
good as the one on Thursday, but in Georges
words, 'quite acceptable'.
The second was brilliant.
As she brought the plane down, she knew even
before the wheels touched the ground, that
they would just kiss the runway as softly
as a pair of lips.
George was impressed.
'Very good,' he said.
'Now, pull up just there on the left.'
Francesca frowned, but did as George instructed.
She felt a little disappointed.
'I thought you said we were going to do three
landings,' she said, bringing the plane to
a stop.
'I'm not,' George replied.
'But you are.'
George was already opening the door before
she'd understood what he meant.
'You mean I'm going on my own?'
she said.
'We call it "going solo",' George answered.
'Now listen.
Just take the aircraft round to the start
of the runway, radio the control tower for
permission to take off, and take her up.
Do exactly what you've just done.
Just one landing, then bring her back to the
hangar.
All right?'
Francesca was too taken aback to protest.
She nodded silently.
George was already climbing out of the plane.
She couldn't believe what was happening.
She'd imagined that flying solo would be months
ahead, after dozens and dozens of landings.
'You'll find she'll climb much quicker with
only one person,' George said, already standing
down on the ground.
Again, Francesca nodded.
'Away you go then,' George said.
He gave an encouraging thumbs-up sign, then
shut the door.
The next moment he was moving away below the
wing, and heading for the grass.
All of a sudden, Francesca found herself on
her own.
She blinked a couple of times, trying to focus.
The cockpit seemed terribly empty without
George close at her side.
She hesitated.
'Well, this is what you wanted, isn't it?'
she thought, suddenly angry with herself.
With that, she sat up, reached for the throttle
and released the brakes.
The plane edged forward.
Through the side window she saw George making
his way across the grass; he didn't turn and
wave.
Francesca took the plane up to the waiting
point before the runway and stopped.
Clearing her throat, she called the control
tower.
'Golf Lima Yankee is ready for take-off,'
she said, surprised at the firmness of her
voice.
'Golf Lima Yankee, you are cleared for take-off,'
came the reply.
Francesca steered the plane round onto the
piano keys and stopped again, the runway stretching
ahead.
'This is it,' she thought.
'This is the last chance to turn back.'
She only hesitated to check all the dials
and controls.
Then, emptying her mind of all other thoughts,
she pushed in the throttle.
The plane sat up eagerly and moved forward.
This time the speed picked up much faster.
Soon they were at 55, and then before she
knew it the nose was lifting up and they were
in the air.
'Keep the nose down,' she kept telling herself.
'Don't try to climb too fast!'
George was absolutely right.
Without his extra weight, the plane was up
to 1000 feet in half the time it had previously
taken.
Steadily, Francesca turned the aircraft.
As she did so, a wonderful feeling ran through
her.
This was it!
She was solo!
All those hours of work and saving had finally
paid off.
A smile began to creep across her face; but
the moment she felt it, she wiped it away.
'Francesca,' she said, 'you are up here all
alone.
Now you've got to get down by yourself.'
She had to concentrate very hard.
Everything happened twice as fast as usual.
Before she knew it she was already making
the preparations for landing, watching for
the moment to swing onto the final approach.
When she did, a new sense of confidence ran
through her.
Slowly the plane slipped through the sky,
gradually losing height.
'Remember that picture,' she told herself.
'You're going down a slide; at the end you'll
step off.'
Down and down she slid.
She concentrated very hard.
'Not too soon,' she said out loud.
'Remember to hold off!'
Afterwards, she couldn't remember those last
few moments.
She must have been so focused, so concentrated
on the job.
All she knew was that, quite suddenly, she
was down and the plane was running along the
runway.
As she drove the plane back towards the hangar,
a huge sense of achievement ran through her,
greater than she'd ever felt before in her
life.
She had flown a plane solo; no one would be
able to take that from her as long as she
lived.
A new smile began to spread across her face.
This time she didn't stop it.
Tom came running towards her before she'd
even brought the plane to a stop.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
A declaration of war
Francesca couldn't remember ever having been
happier than she was that evening.
When she got home, the first thing she did
was make a Skype call to her family.
Her mother's reaction made her laugh.
'Oh no, Francesca!
Please don't say that!'
her mother cried.
'Please don't tell me you've been up there
all alone.
Whatever was your stupid instructor thinking
of!'
'But Mamma, you have to go solo some time!'
Francesca answered.
'Well, why didn't he warn you?
Why didn't he tell you beforehand?'
Francesca's mother protested.
'Oh, Mamma, think about it!'
Francesca replied.
'If your instructor warned you in advance,
it would be disastrous.
Can you imagine how nervous you'd get?'
'Well, please don't do it again, that's all,'
her mother said.
'But of course I will, Mamma,' Francesca answered.
'That's the whole point!'
When Francesca finally returned downstairs,
the Thompsons produced a bottle of champagne
to celebrate.
Francesca had an extraordinary sensation at
that moment - as though she was walking on
air.
If someone had asked her, she half imagined
she might be able to fly herself.
That evening Tom came round and took her out
for a meal to celebrate.
This time Francesca insisted on sharing the
cost.
The restaurant - Italian, of course - was
beside the river, and they sat outside in
the evening sunshine, overlooking the water.
When the meal was finished, they went for
a walk along the river bank until they came
to a bench.
They sat there for a time, chatting quietly,
all the time watching a couple of white swans
in the water in front of them, the birds circling
elegantly in the water, as if admiring one
another.
Francesca couldn't think of a more perfect
English setting.
Sunshine sparkled on the water, setting a
million diamonds dancing on the surface of
the river.
When Tom drove her home, they sat in the car
for a long time, with the engine running.
At last, with her heart bursting with all
the magic of the day, Francesca could stop
herself no longer.
'Tom,' she said suddenly, 'you know, if you
don't kiss me, I'm going to be very upset.'
Tom looked at her in astonishment.
Then, very slowly, not quite believing his
luck, he leant across and softly kissed her
on the lips.
They broke apart, looking at one another as
if seeing each other properly for the first
time, then kissed again.
After a minute or two like this, Tom pulled
away.
'I can't believe this is happening,' he said
quietly.
Francesca looked at with him amusement.
'You'd better kiss me again in that case,'
she said.
***
It was about ten o'clock the following morning
when Francesca's mobile rang.
Since she was expecting a call from Tom, she
didn't even bother to glance at the screen.
'Hello,' she said happily.
'Why did you lie to me?'
a man's voice asked roughly.
Francesca was so shocked, that for a second
or two, she didn't realise who it was.
Then she felt her stomach drop.
'I asked you why you lied to me,' Doug repeated
even more brutally.
'Why couldn't you find the courage to tell
me what you were planning?'
Francesca was still too astonished to react
sensibly.
She suddenly felt a terrible sense of disappointment.
Had everything that previous day been just
a dream?
All her happiness had been swept away in a
flash.
'I asked you a question!'
Doug was almost shouting.
'I don't know what you mean,' Francesca managed
to say at last.
'I-'
Doug cut her short.
'Don't play that game with me,' he growled.
'Do you think I'm stupid?
I know very well you've joined Flying Start.
I heard you on the radio yesterday making
your calls to the control tower.
Did you really imagine I wouldn't find out?
What was it - first solo?'
Doug sounded almost mad.
Francesca still couldn't quite believe what
she was hearing, but the man was just getting
started.
'You tricked me!' he went on bitterly.
'You told me you were going back to Switzerland
just so you could get your money back.
And all the time you were planning to switch
to that useless lot at Flying Start.'
'I wasn't!'
Francesca broke in.
'I don't believe you,' Doug answered.
'It's true,' Francesca protested.
'I was going home.
I only changed my mind because...'
'Because what?'
Doug said bitterly.
'I trust you're not going to give me any of
that rubbish about touching you up.'
'It wasn't rubbish,' Francesca said, starting
to fight back.
'Oh yes?
Perhaps you'd like to prove it then,' Doug
said, almost spitting out the words.
'But it's the truth!'
Francesca responded.
She was suddenly filled with panic, thinking
of that other woman's experience when she'd
made accusations against Doug.
'You know it's the truth!'
she went on more desperately.
'Right from the very first day you were making
horrible remarks and asking me about my boyfriend,
then trying to scare me so you could put your
horrible hands all over me.
Just because I'm young and foreign it doesn't
mean you can do as you please.
Did you really imagine that I might be interested
in you?
I think you're disgusting.
If you were the last man on earth, I wouldn't
look at you twice!'
Doug didn't respond for a moment, then he
burst out suddenly.
'How dare you!' he shouted.
'You're going to regret what you just said!
Do you hear me?'
Francesca was shocked into silence.
'I said, "Do you hear me?"'
Doug repeated.
Francesca didn't know what to say.
Finally, it was all too much.
A rush of Italian spilled from her mouth - words
she didn't normally use - then she ended the
call.
With that she collapsed down onto the chair
beside her.
For some time afterwards she stared at the
phone, not believing what had just happened.
Her heart was beating very fast and her hand
was shaking.
She couldn't seem to get her breath.
Then a dreadful feeling began to sweep over
her.
Something terrible had just taken place, something
that couldn't be reversed.
What had happened was like a declaration of
war.
From now on she wouldn't be able to relax
for a minute.
Doug was a madman.
There was no telling what he might do next.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Learning a lesson
Francesca didn't tell Tom - or anyone else,
for that matter - about Doug's phone call.
She didn't want to talk about it, or even
think about it.
In that way she could try and pretend it had
never happened.
Nevertheless, when she arrived at the airfield
for her next lesson on Thursday afternoon,
Tom immediately spotted there was something
wrong.
Although she might have been able to disguise
her voice on the phone, it was more difficult
to hide it from her appearance.
She'd hardly slept all night and she felt
terrible.
He jumped up the moment she came into the
office and hurried over to her.
'Are you OK?' he asked, looking concerned.
'Why, don't I look it?'
Francesca answered sharply.
Tom seemed hurt.
Frowning a little, he immediately said, 'You
look absolutely great.
I'm sorry, I just thought you seemed a bit
worried when you came in, that's all.'
'I guess I'll have to do better then,' Francesca
answered.
Then, doubly ashamed for treating Tom so unfairly,
she said.
'Sorry.
I've just had a bad morning with the children.
I didn't mean to be so horrible.'
Tom look relieved.
They kissed briefly, then Francesca looked
around.
'Where's George?'
she asked.
'He's on his way,' Tom answered.
'He phoned a short while ago to say he's stuck
in traffic.'
Tom paused.
'But I've just heard some interesting news,'
he said.
'What's that?'
Francesca asked.
Tom gave something of a strange look.
'Well, I've just been talking to a guy who
keeps his aircraft in the same hangar as Doug's,'
he said.
'Why?
What's happened?'
Francesca asked impatiently.
Tom raised his eyebrows.
'Well, according to this guy, Doug spent the
night sleeping in the Fastwings office!'
'What!'
Francesca said.
'That's what the guy said,' Tom went on.
'Apparently, when he came in this morning,
he found Doug in a sleeping bag on the sofa
in his office.
It seems his wife has thrown him out and he's
sleeping there until he can make other arrangements.'
Francesca was too shocked to speak for a moment.
Sitting down, she tried to think it through.
It certainly helped to explain the madness
of the phone call she'd received from Doug.
Perhaps he was having some kind of mental
breakdown?
But how would that affect her?
Did it make things better or worse for her?
'I must say I've never liked Doug very much,'
Tom went on, 'but I wouldn't wish a family
break-up on anyone.
You met his wife and kids, didn't you?'
'Yes,' Francesca answered distantly.
Then, after a moment or two, she added, 'Do
you know what it's all about?'
Tom shook his head.
'No, that's all Doug told this guy.
I don't suppose it's the sort of thing you
want to talk about very much.'
Francesca didn't comment.
A picture had come into her mind: Doug having
been thrown out of his home, sitting in his
office, on his mobile phone to her, bitter
and furious, striking out at anyone who had
upset him.
She had no idea where he was when he'd phoned
her, of course, but the picture stuck in her
mind.
He seemed suddenly more dangerous, more unpredictable
than ever.
She was just about to tell Tom about Doug's
phone call, when George came in.
'You two look a bit suspicious,' he said.
'What's up?'
Tom retold the story.
When he'd finished, George simply said, 'Sorry,
I don't have much sympathy.
From what I've heard he's a bit of a womaniser.
No doubt his wife's had enough of him.
He probably deserves all he gets.'
He smiled at Francesca.
'Pleased you moved to us?'
Francesca nodded, at the same time wondering
exactly what George meant about Doug being
a womaniser.
But there was no time to ask.
'Right, let's get flying,' George said.
'This afternoon you're going to fly me down
to Beccles.
There's a nice little grass airfield there
where you can practise some more solo landings.
How does that sound?'
Francesca found it difficult to concentrate
at first when they climbed into the Cessna.
Her mind was still focused on the news about
Doug.
Besides, as they approached the runway she
kept thinking that he might have just picked
up her call to the control tower and would
know she was at the airfield now.
She tried to tell herself that it made no
difference, that there was nothing he could
do.
But she still felt very nervous.
It wasn't until they'd taken off that she
began to relax.
'That's better,' George commented.
'I was beginning to think you were a different
person from the girl who went solo last week.'
They flew on over farmland: large fields of
corn, and grassy fields with cattle in.
The cows looked tiny, like small beetles creeping
across a green sheet.
Every now and again a small wood, or the grounds
of a big house, provided some contrast.
After about twenty minutes, a small group
of hangars appeared under the nose of the
aircraft, and then the broad line of a pale
green runway cut through the grass.
George announced their arrival over the radio
and told Francesca to fly round to make their
approach from the west.
She did as instructed.
Beccles was a much smaller airfield than Norwich
and the runway looked impossibly short.
'Just keep your eyes on the piano keys,' George
told her.
'And use the throttle to control the height.'
They came in a bit too fast.
The plane flew on far beyond the piano keys
and landed with a heavy bump.
But the aircraft quickly slowed to a stop
on the grass runway.
George told her to take the plane over to
a small group of hangars.
When they'd stopped, George turned to her.
'Right, I'm going to have a cup of tea with
my friend, Stan, in the office here.
And while I'm doing that, I want you to do
three landings.
When you've finished, don't forget to come
and pick me up.'
After George had climbed out and hurried off,
Francesca tried to refocus her thoughts.
She felt more worried this time, much more
so than when George had sent her off on her
first solo.
She wondered whether he would have been happy
for her to fly if he knew all the things that
were occupying her mind.
Perhaps she should have told him, confessed
that she hadn't really slept.
Francesca went back to the start of the runway
and a minute later she was speeding over the
grass and pulling back gently on the control
column, up in the air once more.
Almost immediately, as she began climbing
to height, she felt her brain begin to clear.
It was as if a screen in her head was being
wiped clean; suddenly all her fears and concerns
about Doug disappeared.
There was only Francesca and her plane.
She flew round in a tight circle, glancing
happily down at the hangars where she'd just
left George, then concentrated on turning
for the landing run.
With each landing, her technique improved
and her confidence grew.
After the third landing, she took the plane
over to where George was already waiting on
the grass.
'Well done,' he said simply, as he climbed
into the plane.
'Now, take me home, please.
It's beginning to get cold.'
What George had said was true: it was beginning
to feel colder.
The wind was picking up slightly and there
was a chill in the air.
Francesca shivered suddenly.
They took off and began climbing to height.
Then, when they'd reached about 500 feet,
George slowly stretched forward and pulled
out the throttle.
'You have engine failure,' he said.
For a moment or two Francesca didn't know
what was happening.
The power died instantly, and with it, all
the speed.
An unnatural silence filled the cabin.
Francesca felt panic flood through her body.
The next second the stall-warning alarm sounded.
At the last moment, just as George was about
to take over, Francesca reacted.
She pushed the control column forward and
dropped the nose.
Almost immediately, the stall-warning alarm
fell silent, the speed picked up again and
the frightening sense that they were about
to drop out of the sky died.
But still there was no power.
'Where are you going to land?'
George asked calmly.
'The airfield?'
Francesca replied.
'No,' George said firmly.
'Never try to turn back!'
Francesca searched the horizon ahead for an
open field.
Some way in front, beside some trees, there
was a long green field.
'That one over there, then!'
she shouted.
'Which one?'
George asked.
'The one on the right!'
They continued slipping down.
350 feet, 300; all of a sudden they were down
to 200.
At last George reached for the throttle.
The power recovered at once and the speed
picked up.
Francesca pulled back on the control column
in relief, her blood flowing freely once again.
When they'd regained some height, George looked
across at her.
'I thought you'd done an "engine-failure-on-take-off"
when you were with Fastwings?'
'No,' Francesca answered.
George shook his head in disgust.
'That man Barker is worse than I thought.
Well, let it be a lesson to you,' he went
on, more seriously than she'd ever heard him
before.
'An engine can fail at any time, especially
during take-off.
If it fails, you've got to act quickly.
Drop the nose and look for somewhere to land.
And keep up your speed.
If you don't, we won't need to bury you - you'll
make your own hole in the ground.'
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Nowhere to hide
The following week, at about ten o'clock in
the morning, Francesca was returning to the
house after taking the children to school.
She was nearly home when she noticed the grey
Audi on the other side of Brabazon Road.
It was just one of many other cars, but Francesca
immediately thought of Doug's.
His was a grey Audi, she was certain, but
was it the same model?
She felt her whole body tense up and tried
not to look.
As she turned into the drive of the Thompsons'
house, she couldn't stop herself glancing
across at the car.
Was there someone sitting in the driving seat?
The sun was reflecting on the glass and it
wasn't easy to see inside.
She looked at the number plate.
She only dared look for half a second, and
she could only take in the first three letters.
With a horrible feeling growing in her throat,
Francesca let herself into the house and hurried
upstairs to her room.
Keeping back in the shadow, she slowly approached
the window and looked out.
The car was still there, half-visible behind
a tree, like a wolf hiding in the wood, a
grey creature creeping about, ready to leap.
She watched for at least a minute, unconsciously
holding her breath.
Then the car suddenly pulled away and raced
off up the road.
For the rest of the day Francesca couldn't
get the memory of the car out of her head.
She couldn't be sure it was Doug's.
On one hand, she knew very well that plenty
of people drove grey Audis, but on the other
hand it seemed too much of a coincidence that
a car just like Doug's should be parked opposite
her house.
But if it was him, what on earth was he doing?
The idea that he might be following her filled
her with sudden terror.
She felt sick as she remembered the day he
had given her a lift home.
Of course, he knew where she lived.
Francesca's anxiety grew all day.
She tried to occupy her thoughts by keeping
busy: cleaning the house with extra thoroughness
and making a cake.
But several times she went back to her bedroom
window to see if the car had returned.
And when she went to fetch the children from
school, she couldn't get rid of the feeling
that Doug might be there, hiding behind a
tree, or creeping along behind her.
That evening Tom had invited Francesca for
a meal at his flat.
It was the first time she'd seen where he
lived, and she could tell immediately that
he'd gone to a lot of trouble in order to
impress her.
He'd obviously been busy tidying because everywhere
smelt of cleaning products, and there were
flowers and candles on the table.
The evening started well.
The flat was full of Tom's drawings and paintings,
and just as Francesca had guessed, they were
brilliant - detailed drawings of birds like
owls and hawks, aircraft painted against beautiful
skies, and then a whole series of pencil drawings
of a young girl, Tom's niece apparently.
The expressions on the child's face were so
real that Francesca thought the girl might
suddenly come to life and step out of the
picture.
'Have you ever tried to sell your work?'
Francesca asked.
'I didn't think it was good enough,' Tom answered.
Francesca shook her head in astonishment.
'Tom, you must,' she said.
Then she added more quietly, 'Would you do
a drawing of me some time?
I could send it to my family - they'd love
it.
I'll pay you, of course.'
'I'd love to,' Tom replied, delighted.
'But if you try and give me any money, I'll
be very upset.'
Tom had made a great effort with the meal,
too.
For the first course, he'd made a tomato salad
- using the very best 'buffalo' mozzarella
cheese, and then for the main course, a mushroom
risotto, which was delicious.
Francesca could see Tom felt very proud that
the meal had turned out so well, and she liked
him even more for all the attention he gave.
The more she got to know him, the more she
felt that this was the sort of person he was
- an artist - and he'd spent his whole life
trying to be someone different.
Perhaps his father was to blame, wanting Tom
to be a copy of himself.
But despite all Tom's efforts, Francesca couldn't
fully relax.
She kept thinking about the grey Audi.
Should she tell Tom about it or not?
Would he think she was crazy?
After the meal, Tom made some coffee and they
went over to his sofa.
Francesca knew that Tom was hoping that the
evening would end romantically.
'I was just thinking,' she said, unable to
stop herself at last.
'Do you know what kind of car Doug drives?'
Tom frowned in disappointment.
'An Audi, I think.
Why?'
'No reason,' Francesca answered quickly.
'I just thought I might have seen his car
in our road today, that's all.'
'But what would Doug be doing there?'
Tom asked innocently.
'I don't know,' Francesca answered.
'That's why I wanted to check on his car.
Do you know what the number plate is?'
Tom looked at her in confusion.
Francesca shook her head.
'No, of course you wouldn't.
That was a bit of a stupid question.'
With that she changed the subject.
Doing so made her even angrier with herself
than she was already.
She knew that she ought to tell Tom the true
reason for her concern; this was the perfect
moment to get the whole business out in the
open.
But for some reason she couldn't.
The more time went on, the more difficult
it was.
After a while, Francesca asked Tom to take
her home, complaining of a headache.
Francesca could see that it hurt him badly
and was a blow to his confidence, but he was
too much of gentleman to say anything.
Francesca was silent on the way home, full
of anger with herself for spoiling the evening.
If only she'd never begun lessons with Fastwings!
If only she'd never met Doug!
Tom kissed her sweetly when he dropped her
home, but Francesca ran inside before he could
see the tears rolling down her cheeks.
She couldn't believe what was happening to
her.
This was the second time she'd cried in less
than a month.
***
The following Tuesday George sent Francesca
off on her first 'landaway'.
'What's that?'
Francesca asked.
'You go off on your own to land at another
airfield, and then, with a bit of luck, you
come back,' George replied cheerfully.
'I want you to fly down to Beccles just like
we did last week.
Go into the office, get Stan to sign your
logbook, then fly straight back here.
Sound simple enough?'
Francesca couldn't wait to get into the air.
The last three days had been a nightmare of
anxiety - checking the street for signs of
Doug, trying to decide what to do.
When she'd arrived at the airfield earlier,
she'd resisted the temptation to go straight
to look for Doug's car and check the number
plate.
She would try to do it after her lesson, but
now she needed to concentrate on flying.
Soon, she thought, she would be up in the
air and all those fears would melt away.
But as she approached the runway, she felt
as tense as ever.
Was Doug at the airfield now?
Was he listening in to the radio calls?
Did he know she was there?
Once shed taken off, however, as if by magic,
her anxiety began to slip away.
She climbed steadily to 3000 feet, then turned
south-east and headed for Beccles.
It was a beautiful day, the colours of the
sky and fields below intensely clear and bright.
Looking down the length of the wings, she
had the sensation once more that they might
be her arms.
She moved the control column left and right
very gently and watched with delight how the
wings responded.
It gave her a huge sense of freedom.
She was untouchable up there in the sky, completely
out of reach!
The landing at Beccles went well, and Stan
was friendly when she went to get her logbook
signed.
She loved the little airfield with its grass
runway and handful of light aircraft.
It made her feel connected to all the aviators
of the past, taking to the skies in wooden
aircraft and open cockpits.
Refusing a cup of tea and saying she ought
to head home, Francesca climbed back into
the plane and very soon took off.
As she turned towards Norwich, she radioed
back to Stan below and said a cheerful goodbye.
It was about five minutes later, when she'd
reached 3000 feet, that an odd sensation came
to her.
Performing her regular check of the sky around,
she caught sight of something over her shoulder.
Immediately, she looked behind.
A plane - another Cessna - was flying very
close to her, perhaps ten metres below and
as many metres behind.
The shock almost made her let go of the control
column.
It was Doug in the Fastwings Cessna.
She glanced behind again and saw him quite
clearly; he was looking out of the cockpit
window and staring directly at her.
Francesca wanted to scream.
A terrible panic rushed up through her body,
paralysing her for a minute.
Suddenly, she didn't know how to fly the plane,
or what any of the controls were for.
She didn't want to look round, and yet she
couldn't stop herself.
But every time she did, Doug was still there,
his sunglasses staring blindly back.
She felt helpless, with no idea what to do.
All of a sudden she realised he must have
followed her to Beccles, then circled somewhere
overhead until he heard her make her take-off
calls.
Then he'd come swooping down out of the sky,
just like a hawk.
But what did he want?
Was he just trying to scare her or would he
try to make her crash?
She flew on, her hands shaking on the control
column, trying to imagine what would happen
next.
And then, just as suddenly as he'd appeared
on her shoulder, he was gone.
The next time she looked round, there was
no sign of the aircraft anywhere.
She searched the sky, but the plane had simply
disappeared.
When she finally landed back at Norwich, George
and Tom were both waiting for her.
'How was it then?'
Tom asked.
'Fine.
Just fine,' Francesca answered weakly.
'You look a bit pale,' he went on anxiously.
'Do you feel all right?'
Francesca didn't say anything.
Without another word, she hurried through
to the toilets at the back of the hangar and
was violently sick.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
The stalker
Francesca was watching television that evening,
when she heard a text arrive on her phone.
Thinking it would be Tom, she immediately
opened the message.
'Sorry if I frightened you!'
she read.
'For a moment I was afraid you might crash!
Best of luck with the rest of your lessons.
Doug'
Francesca didn't know what to do with herself
for the rest of the evening.
She wanted to scream out loud.
The man was hunting her, following her around,
keeping at a safe distance, but making sure
she knew he was there all the time.
There was a word for what he was doing - the
man was stalking her; he was a stalker.
It was the same word in Italian.
She felt a great knot of anger growing in
her chest.
What did he want?
Somehow it seemed to her that Doug was no
longer interested in her for sex, it was as
though things had gone beyond that desire.
Now what he wanted was to make her suffer
as much as he could.
Wasn't that the point of the message?
'Sorry if I frightened you' meant just the
opposite.
He wasn't wishing her good luck with her lessons.
Doug was determined to scare her to death.
Lying in bed that night, Francesca tried to
decide what she could do.
The idea of going to the police was out of
the question.
What would she tell them?
That the man had put his hand on her knee
and touched her a couple of times?
What else had he done?
He didn't even have her money any more.
There had been a couple of angry phone calls,
she 'thought she'd seen his car outside the
house, and now he'd flown up alongside her.
Even the text message could be read as nothing
more than cheerful good wishes.
The police would laugh at her, and yet she
knew Doug was stalking her.
So, what about telling someone else: for instance,
telling Tom or Mrs Thompson what was going
on?
How would that help?
What could they do?
What if she told Tom the whole story?
How would he react?
She knew he'd do everything he could - she
could picture him bravely marching up to the
Fastwings hangar and getting into a fight
with Doug.
Although she liked the idea of a courageous
Tom coming to her rescue, it wasn't something
she could ever accept.
Francesca always fought her own battles and
she didn't let others take her place.
By the time she finally fell asleep, Francesca
had decided that if she was going to stay
in England, the only thing to do was to go
and see Doug herself.
***
The next morning, once she'd taken the children
to school, Francesca took the bus straight
up to the airfield.
She didn't tell Tom she was coming - indeed,
she didn't even call in at the Flying Start
office.
Instead she went straight to Fastwings.
Outside the entrance, she paused for a moment
or two and tried to calm her nerves.
Then, before she could change her mind, she
went directly inside and down the small corridor
to the Fastwings office.
As soon as she reached it, she could see through
the glass door that Doug wasn't there.
A strange sense of anti-climax ran through
her.
Having prepared herself so bravely for meeting
up with him, it seemed doubly cruel that it
should all be for nothing.
She didn't know what to do.
She couldn't wait long: she had jobs to do
at home for Mrs Thompson that morning.
She was still trying to decide how long to
wait, when a strange feeling made her turn
round.
Doug was standing there, only a couple of
metres behind her.
He was holding a large hammer.
Francesca felt very frightened.
'Well, well, this is a surprise,' Doug said,
with a look of slight amusement.
Then, seeing Francesca's expression, he gave
a small wave with the hammer.
'It's all right, just a problem with the hangar
door.
Nothing for you to worry about,' he said.
'Just yet...' he added, giving a short laugh.
Francesca tried not to lose her nerve.
'I'd like to talk to you for a minute,' she
said.
'Of course, come into the office.
Is it just you or have you got your lawyer
with you?' he asked with heavy sarcasm.
Francesca ignored the remark.
She didn't want to go inside, but there seemed
little choice.
Swallowing hard, she followed Doug through
into the office.
As she did so, she caught a faint smell of
alcohol in the atmosphere.
Had he been drinking?
The thought frightened her even more.
He dropped the hammer on his desk and gestured
to her to sit down.
Francesca wanted to remain standing, but Doug
was already sitting behind his desk with his
feet on the table.
She sat on the edge of the sofa opposite,
trying not to look directly at him.
There was a weird look in his eyes.
'So, have you got fed up with Flying Start?'
Doug asked with a curling lip.
'Or has lover boy tried to push his luck too
far?' he added, then smiled with satisfaction
at Francesca's shock.
Francesca was taken completely off guard.
How had he found out about her and Tom?
Had someone told him?
'Oh yes,' Doug went on, 'I know all about
you and Tom Brennan.
You should find somewhere more private, Francesca.
Really - climbing all over one another in
his Ford Focus!
I thought you'd have more style than that.
And with a loser like him!
Honestly, Francesca!'
He grinned once again.
'Anyway, I didn't mean to spoil your visit
with cheap insults about your boyfriend.
Perhaps you've come to apologise?'
Francesca felt sick for a moment.
When she'd decided to come and see Doug, she'd
imagined the meeting quite differently.
She'd imagined marching into his office and
making her speech confidently, without fear,
in a sensible adult manner.
But Doug had caught her by surprise.
He must have been in Brabazon Road one night
when Tom had taken her home.
He must have been spying on them for ages.
The idea filled her with fresh anger.
'Me?
Apologise!
I shall never apologise to you,' she began,
trying to keep control of her voice.
'I came to tell you to leave me alone.'
Doug gave a small frown.
'I'm sorry, Francesca,' he said, 'I don't
think I quite understand.'
Francesca closed her eyes.
How had it come to this?
Did she really deserve this misery?
All she wanted was to learn to fly.
'You're stalking me,' she said quietly.
'I know you are.
You've been following me in your car; now
you're following me in your plane.'
Doug gave a look of astonishment.
It was pure acting, Francesca knew it was.
Even Doug seemed to know it wasn't convincing.
Pushing back against his chair, he put his
hands together behind his head.
'I'm sorry, Francesca, but I can't believe
what I'm hearing,' he said.
'Are you really accusing me of stalking you,
just because I happened to be flying over
Beccles at the same time as you a couple of
days ago?
Do we men have to keep out of the air every
time Francesca Bartolli takes to the skies?'
Francesca tried to keep herself calm.
'But you were!
You were stalking me!'
she exclaimed.
'I've seen your car outside my house in Brabazon
Road and you've just admitted seeing Tom and
me in his car!
You're following me around and spying on me!
Why are you doing this?
What do you want from me?'
Doug watched Francesca for a little while,
all the time the same cruel smile playing
at his lips.
Then, with the amusement dying on his face,
he slowly took his feet from the desk and
sat forward with a cold bitter expression.
'I don't want anything from you, Francesca,'
he said.
'OK, it might have been nice if you'd been
more...
how shall I put it... friendly?
Indeed, I might have reduced your flying fees
even more if you had!'
He gave a strange laugh at the idea for a
moment, and Francesca wondered again if he'd
been drinking.
Then he immediately grew serious again.
'But that time has long gone, my dear.
Now I get a kick from just seeing the terror
on your face.'
He paused, watching Francesca with cold lifeless
eyes.
Francesca was reminded of a snake.
'So you admit that you've been stalking me!'
she said desperately.
Doug continued staring at her.
'I admit nothing.
If you think I've been stalking you, then
prove it,' he said, his voice getting louder.
'Now, get out of my office before I call the
police.
I haven't got time for this!'
As he said that, Doug picked up the hammer
he had left on the desk and smashed it down
as hard as possible on the wood.
There was a tremendous crash and part of the
desk cracked, sending a tray spinning to the
floor.
'Didn't you hear me?'
Doug shouted, his eyes wild with madness.
'I told you to get out!
Don't you understand the English language?'
Francesca froze.
The man was completely out of control.
He was drunk.
She rushed for the door.
As she left the office, she looked back to
see Doug getting up from his chair, the hammer
still gripped tightly in his hand.
She ran down the corridor and out into the
open air in genuine fear of her life.
She didn't stop shaking until she was safely
on the bus home.
There, as she sat hiding her face in her hands,
a little old lady asked her if she was feeling
all right.
'Yes, I think so,' Francesca answered.
Then, realising it was a bit of an odd reply,
she added, 'I nearly got myself killed a minute
ago - when I was crossing the road.'
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
A matter of practice
For the next four days, apart from taking
the children to and from school, Francesca
didn't leave the house.
She simply didn't feel safe.
Saying she had a bad headache, she even cancelled
her next flying lesson on Thursday afternoon.
At the weekend Tom invited her out twice,
but she refused both times.
She sat miserably in her room, unable to concentrate
on anything and trying not to go to the window
to look out.
By Monday morning she'd almost made a final
decision to go back to Switzerland - one hundred
percent definitely this time.
How her relationship with Tom could survive
after that she couldn't imagine.
Whatever the case, she decided to ring Flying
Start that morning and cancel her lesson the
next day.
Listening to the number ring, she half hoped
somebody other than Tom would answer, but
of course it was him.
'Hello,' he said brightly.
'Flying Start.'
'Tom,' she said quietly, 'it's Francesca.
Tom,' she went on before he could say anything,
'I'm just ringing to say I still don't think
I'm well enough for tomorrow's lesson.'
Tom's voice dropped immediately.
'Oh no, poor you!
Really?
Is your headache still bad?'
Francesca felt like a complete fraud.
She knew she had to talk to him.
She was about to say something when Tom interrupted.
'I was so much hoping you'd be OK - and I
heard a bit of news this morning that I thought
would interest you.'
'What?'
Francesca asked.
'Fastwings has gone out of business,' Tom
said.
Francesca wasn't sure she understood.
'What do you mean?'
she asked.
'I mean Doug's finished, that's what I mean,'
Tom replied.
'Apparently there's a notice on his office
door this morning saying "Fastwings regrets
to announce that, with immediate effect, it
has stopped trading".
What's more, I've heard his Cessna is up for
sale on the Internet.'
Tom finally came to the end of his speech.
All the while he'd been speaking Francesca
had been trying to absorb the news and what
it meant for her.
Did it mean there was a chance she would be
able to continue with her flying lessons?
Did it mean she could stay in England after
all?
'Francesca?
Are you still there?'
Tom asked.
'Yes... yes, of course,' Francesca answered.
'But I was just thinking...
I suppose that means Doug won't be up at the
airfield any more.'
'I can't see why he should be,' Tom replied.
Anyway, apparently he's left Norwich and run
off up north.
But you won't be sorry about that, will you?'
'No, no I won't,' Francesca answered.
It seemed to her as if ice was melting around
her.
For days her body had felt frozen.
Now the sun had come out again; there was
life!
'Anyway,' Tom went on, 'Thank God you got
out in time.
I mean, if you were still having lessons with
him, you might have lost all your money.'
'Really?'
Francesca said.
'Yes, sure.
You could have lost the lot!'
Tom continued.
'Come to think of it, I guess losing your
business can't have helped him much.'
'Yes,' Francesca answered.
She'd been thinking the same herself; perhaps
that was why he seemed to hate her so much.
'Anyway,' Tom said, breaking into her thoughts.
Are you sure you won't be well enough for
the lesson tomorrow?'
'What do you mean?'
she asked.
'Your headache,' Tom said, sounding a little
confused.
'Oh, that,' Francesca answered, even more
ashamed now about her excuse.
'On second thoughts, perhaps it would do it
good if I got out for a while.'
'Brilliant,' Tom said.
'In that case, is there any chance I could
see you tonight?'
Francesca felt a smile breaking out on her
face.
'All right, I don't see why not,' she said
happily.
'That would be great.'
***
The next afternoon, Francesca was 3000 feet
above the East Anglian fields, flying with
George again.
They'd been practising advanced turns, first
putting the aircraft into a tight 43-degree
turn, and then even tighter, so that the plane
was over on its side at 60 degrees or more.
Francesca's head was spinning.
Pulling back on the control column and holding
the nose level on the horizon had made her
feel quite dizzy.
Francesca was feeling a little dizzy too with
everything that was happening in the rest
of her life.
Knowing that Doug wasn't in Norwich any more,
meant life could return to normal.
She was still afraid though that it might
all be a dream and she would turn a corner
and find the grey Audi waiting there.
But no one had seen any sign of Doug at the
airfield and she began to believe it at last.
And then there was Tom.
In the few days since his phone call, things
had become much more serious in their relationship.
Perhaps the thought of returning to Switzerland
and breaking up with him had concentrated
her mind.
Whatever it was, Francesca had come to see
very clearly that she wasn't just fond of
Tom.
She was most definitely in love.
'I think it's about time we did a PFL,' George
said, interrupting her thoughts.
'What's that?'
Francesca asked.
'A PFL?'
George replied.
'A PFL is a practice forced landing - a bit
like we did last time - engine failure, but
this time from higher up.
I pull out the throttle, you choose a field
in which to land, then we can glide down doing
all the engine checks and emergency calls.'
'And do we actually land?'
Francesca asked.
'Not unless you want to pay the farmer for
damage to his field,' George said, smiling.
'But we do go down to about 200 feet - low
enough to see if we'd survive the landing.'
'Sounds fun,' Francesca answered, who was
growing in confidence with each flying-hour
that passed.
They flew on for a couple of minutes, then
George reached forward slowly and pulled out
the throttle.
Instantly, the engine noise died and Francesca
felt the plane slow.
'You have engine failure, Ms Bartolli,' George
said quietly.
This time Francesca reacted quickly.
Pushing the control column forward, she put
the aircraft into a gentle glide and felt
the speed pick up again.
'Good,' George said calmly.
'Now, where are you going to land?'
Francesca looked down to the ground far below.
There was a wood away to the left, then, nearer
to the plane, a series of fields.
The biggest was a large brown one, just below
the nose.
'That one,' Francesca replied, pointing with
her free hand.
'Mmm, I find ploughed fields a bit bumpy to
land on,' George said quietly.
'Don't you think a grassy one would be better?'
Francesca immediately felt foolish.
Brown meant ploughed; green meant grass.
She couldn't believe she had made such a basic
mistake.
'Come on, make a decision quickly,' George
said cheerfully.
'You've already lost 300 feet in height.'
Francesca looked down in desperation.
Almost directly below there was a long thin
green field.
'That one, then!'
she said, pointing again.
George glanced down.
'Your decision,' he said.
'Now, you need to land into the wind.
Which way is the wind blowing?'
Francesca panicked.
'I can't remember,' she said.
'Well, look for some smoke!'
George called.
Francesca searched the sky.
Far away to the right she spotted the chimney
of a factory.
The smoke was blowing towards them.
That meant, to land in the field below, Francesca
had to fly round in a circle.
Still disturbed by her mistake, she began
to turn.
'2300 feet,' George said.
'Right, don't forget your emergency calls!'
Francesca's mind went blank.
She couldn't remember a word of what she'd
learnt.
The panicky feeling in her chest got worse.
The plane was sinking fast.
'I can't remember,' she said.
George reminded her.
'Mayday, mayday, mayday,' he said.
'And don't forget this is only a practice,
so don't press the radio button!'
Francesca swallowed hard.
'Mayday!
Mayday!
Mayday!'
she called, then came to a stop.
What was she meant to say next?
She remembered she had to say the details
of the plane and half a dozen other things,
but everything became confused in her head.
'Sorry,' she said, hopelessly.
'All right, forget the calls,' George said,
trying to calm her.
'It's more important to land the plane safely.
You're down to 1500 feet.
You'll have to do a tight turn or you won't
make it to the field.'
Francesca tried to concentrate, but now everything
seemed to be going wrong.
Unconsciously, she'd been pulling back on
the control column, so the plane was flying
dangerously slowly.
All of a sudden the stall-warning alarm sounded.
Francesca froze.
This time, George didn't wait.
'All right, I have control,' he said.
At once he reached for his control column
and pushed it forward, at the same time increasing
the power.
The plane picked up speed immediately and
after a few moments George took it into a
steady climb.
Francesca felt herself going red.
'I'm sorry,' she said.
'That was terrible, wasn't it?'
George gave a tiny nod of the head.
'Don't worry,' he said.
'Everyone makes a mess of it the first time.'
Then he looked across and smiled.
'Besides, in forty years of flying I haven't
had an engine failure once.'
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
Tempting fate
Whenever Francesca either saw Tom or telephoned
him over the next couple of weeks, she couldn't
resist the temptation of asking if there was
any news of Doug.
There was none.
No one seemed to have any idea where he was.
A rumour went round the airfield that he'd
gone abroad, but no one could confirm it.
Whatever the case, the door to the Fastwings
office remained firmly shut and there was
no sign of his grey Audi.
Then, one evening when Francesca was at Tom's
flat, he announced that he had some further
news.
'I heard something else about Doug this morning,
but I'm not sure you'll want to know,' he
said.
Francesca felt herself tense up immediately.
'You'd better tell me,' she said quietly.
'Well,' Tom went on a little anxiously, 'it
seems that before he came here, when he was
an instructor down at Southampton, he was
accused of sexually harassing one of his female
students.
The woman brought charges against him, but
the case was dropped because she didn't have
any proof and Doug won damages.
But I can't believe a woman would go to the
lengths of bringing charges against someone
unless there was some truth in it.
And I think you said you always felt very
uncomfortable with him - I just thought that
might explain why.'
Francesca had remained silent throughout Tom's
speech and she didn't say anything now.
She just didn't want to think about Doug.
'Sorry, perhaps it was a mistake to tell you,'
Tom said, confused.
'No, it's all right,' she said at last.
'But I knew the story already.'
Tom looked very surprised.
'You knew it?' he said.
Francesca gave a sigh.
She didn't understand why she was still so
unwilling to talk about it, but she was.
With difficulty, she began, 'About a month
ago, I searched for Doug on the Internet and
I found a newspaper report about him.
It's one of the reasons why I decided to leave
Fastwings.'
'I'm not surprised,' Tom said quickly.
'I hope he didn't try anything like that with
you.'
Francesca bit her lip.
'Well, actually, he did,' she said.
'That's the other reason I had to leave.'
'What?!'
Tom cried.
Francesca felt sick again.
'He used to keep putting his hand on my leg
and touching me,' she said.
'It was horrible - and he kept saying things,
making sort of sexual suggestions.
It was disgusting...'
Just as Francesca had guessed, Tom was furious
and over the next five minutes Francesca was
forced to relate all that had happened in
the flying lessons.
The memory of it all only brought Francesca's
misery back, and, on the point of tears, she
said she wanted to think about something else.
At least Tom had the sensitivity not to press
her any further.
Saying how sorry he was, and all the things
he would do if he ever saw Doug again, he
finished with a shake of his head.
'What I don't understand is how he ever got
an instructor's licence,' he said.
'Yes,' Francesca murmured.
'Well, at least it's all over and you're safe
now.'
Francesca didn't say anything.
For some reason, she hadn't been able to bring
herself to tell Tom about any of Doug's threats.
***
Francesca's next few lessons were much more
successful.
She managed some difficult crosswind landings
very well and her confidence returned.
So the lesson after that George made her try
another PFL.
This time Francesca was much more focused,
choosing a landing field quickly, noting the
direction of the wind and turning the plane
well.
The emergency calls didn't go so well, but
more importantly, as they glided down, it
soon became clear that the field Francesca
had selected was not a good choice.
A telephone line stretched from one side of
the field to the other.
If she'd attempted to land she would have
hit the wire for certain, and probably buried
the plane deep in the earth.
Nevertheless, when they'd returned to Norwich
and were back in the Flying Start office,
George announced that the following Tuesday
he wanted Francesca to do her 'cross country
flight'.
'What does that mean?'
Francesca asked.
'It means you fly solo, landing at two different
airfields before you return here.'
George grinned.
'This is the last big flight before you do
your final flying exam.'
***
Francesca couldn't believe how much planning
was involved in such a flight.
George had told her she was to fly to Leicester,
then Peterborough and finally back to Norwich.
So she examined maps, learning the route and
areas to be avoided, then studied information
about the airfields.
There were other things to consider, too:
the fuel she needed to take, the radio calls
she'd have to make.
When she went to bed the night before the
flight, her brain was full of a million facts
and figures all competing for a place in her
head.
Francesca woke on the Tuesday morning with
an uncomfortable feeling.
It was a curious sensation: nothing precise,
just the sort of feeling that a bad dream
sometimes leaves, a sort of shadow cast over
the day.
She got up and pulled open the curtains, determined
to forget the feeling.
The weather was quite windy, but bright and
clear, which meant good visibility.
That was a relief: nothing would have been
worse than discovering the flight was off.
Mrs Thompson had given her the whole day off
and Tom had promised to come and pick her
up, so at ten-thirty, Francesca was waiting
at her window, ready to leave.
It was then that she saw the grey Audi.
It crept slowly past the entrance to the drive,
disappeared, then reappeared on the other
side of the road half a minute later and stopped.
Francesca's heart sank.
Doug was back.
She was certain of it.
She drew back from the window and collapsed
onto the bed.
Her hands tore at her hair in misery.
'Why!
Why!
Why!'
she thought, 'Why can't he leave me alone!'
She sat there, trying to fight her fears,
trying to fight against the feeling that her
heart was going to explode.
Then the next moment, full of anger, she jumped
up, determined to settle matters with the
man once and for all.
She raced down the stairs, pulled open the
front door angrily, and marched out into the
drive.
But the Audi was no longer there.
It had disappeared completely.
A couple of seconds later, Tom's car pulled
into the drive and stopped.
'Today's the day!' he said cheerfully, climbing
out of the driver's door.
Then, seeing Francesca's face, he asked, 'Hey,
are you all right?'
Francesca stood still on the spot.
A sentence about Doug being back formed in
her mouth, but wouldn't come out.
Somehow, it seemed as long as she didn't say
it, it wouldn't be true.
'Fine,' she answered quietly.
On the way to the airfield, her spirits began
to rise.
Perhaps she'd got it wrong after all.
She couldn't actually be certain it was Doug's
car - maybe it was someone else's car.
Just a simple mistake.
She rested her head back and tried to relax.
George was already waiting in the office when
they arrived.
He gave a slight frown as Francesca walked
in.
'Everything all right?' he asked, looking
at her closely.
'Of course,' Francesca answered.
George didn't seem convinced.
'Sure?' he asked.
'Well, a bit nervous, I guess,' Francesca
said.
George nodded, apparently satisfied with the
response.
'Well, that'll keep you focused,' he said.
'Right, I've printed out the weather report
for you, so Tom and I will leave you to get
down to the final planning now.'
Francesca tried to settle at the desk.
She stared at the weather report George had
given her, but none of the lines and numbers
printed there meant anything to her.
All she could see was Doug's car, creeping
along the road.
The panicky feeling rose in her chest again
as she tried to get the picture out of her
head.
Today of all days, she told herself, she really
couldn't afford to have anything else in her
mind except the cross-country flight.
It would need all of her concentration - not
simply flying the plane, but all the other
tasks, too.
Fifteen minutes later, George came back.
'How's it going?' he asked.
Francesca showed him her flight plan - all
the rows of figures she'd prepared.
George studied it for a short time, then looked
at her.
'Not bad,' he said.
'Except for one small point.
Which way is the wind blowing today?'
'West to east,' Francesca replied.
'You've calculated everything east to west.
Following this flight plan, you'd end up in
the middle of the North Sea.'
He gave her a friendly smile and left.
Francesca buried her head in her hands.
Twenty minutes later, after Francesca had
corrected her error, and George had approved
the plan, they left the office.
The Flying Start Cessna was already outside
the hangar, its blue and white paintwork shining
brightly in the sun.
Tom was cleaning the windscreen.
Francesca walked around the plane, looking
over the body, the tyres and the lights, doing
an oil-check.
The fuel didn't need checking for water since
the plane had already been flown that morning,
but it needed filling up.
She and Tom dragged the aircraft over to the
fuel tank.
'For the flight you're doing, you'll need
it filled right up to maximum.'
Tom said.
'If you operate the pump, I'll take the fuel-line.'
'It's OK, I'll do it,' Francesca said.
Taking the end of the fuel-line, she climbed
up onto the wing, and opened the fuel-cap.
Soon, with Tom at the pump, fuel was pouring
into the tank.
When it was full, Francesca took the line
and climbed up onto the other wing.
'Stop,' she called, when the fuel reached
the maximum point.
Tom gave a small frown.
'That's funny,' he said.
'Why?'
Francesca asked.
'I thought she'd take a couple more litres
than that.'
He thought for a minute.
'Oh well, I suppose I must have noted down
the wrong figures after the last flight yesterday.
Not to worry.'
Francesca double-checked the levels, then
climbed down.
'Right.
Are you all ready?'
Tom said cheerfully.
'I think so,' Francesca answered.
'Good luck, then,' Tom replied.
He leant across and gave Francesca a brief
kiss on the cheek.
'See you in about five hours' time,' he whispered
in her ear.
Francesca didn't say anything.
For some reason it felt too much like tempting
fate.
CHAPTER NINETEEN
One chance
Francesca climbed into the cockpit, settled
into the seat and did up her safety harness.
Then she arranged the flight plan on her knee
and put the map on the other seat.
Satisfied with all that, she called to Tom
to stand clear, and started the engine.
When that was running smoothly, she put on
the headphones and tuned in the radio to Norwich
Control Tower.
'Norwich Tower, this is Golf Lima Yankee,'
she called.
The tower called back.
Francesca announced that she was going to
go round to the runway, then she released
the brakes and the aircraft began to move
forward.
Tom gave her a firm thumbs-up sign, and watched
as she began to move away.
As she went round past the hangars, Francesca's
confidence began to grow again.
Even if it was Doug she'd seen that morning,
she was safe now - he couldn't reach her.
With the Fastwings Cessna out of action, locked
away in the hangar, he couldn't come swooping
out of the sky as he had done previously.
She could forget about Doug.
Focusing her mind on the flight ahead, she
stopped before the start of the runway, and
began the power checks.
First she ran the engine up to full power,
then let it drop back to almost nothing, making
sure that it didn't cut out.
Happy with that, she checked all the controls,
moving the control column around, noting that
there was full and free movement.
Then she made the next radio call.
'Norwich Tower, Golf Lima Yankee is ready
to line up runway zero nine.'
'Golf Lima Yankee,' the call came back, 'You
are cleared for take-off runway zero nine.'
Francesca felt her heart beating faster.
She released the brakes and, using the throttle
carefully, powered the small aircraft onto
the piano keys at the start of the runway.
Then she waited there for a moment.
This was the critical time.
When she pushed in the throttle she would
begin the take-off run, and then would come
the point of no return.
If she was going to change her mind, it had
to be now.
She hesitated for perhaps three seconds, then
actually spoke out loud in English, 'Come
on!
Don't be such a coward!'
The next moment she'd pushed in the throttle
and already the little Cessna had started
moving.
The speed picked up fast.
Francesca's eyes moved quickly between the
dials and the runway ahead.
A faint smile spread across her face, then
before she realised she'd made the decision,
she had already pulled back on the control
column and the plane was in the air.
Holding the nose down, she put the aircraft
into a climb.
Soon the first five hundred feet were passed,
and the airfield was left behind.
She was out over fields, climbing steadily
towards the clouds high up above.
And as she flew, she began to feel that familiar
sense of release - that sensation she had
whenever she was in the air now.
It was one of complete freedom, a kind of
divorce from ordinary life, a belief that
she was part of a completely different world
from that of the Earth.
At 1000 feet, she began to turn the plane
until she was flying in the correct direction
towards Leicester.
Looking down, she checked for the things she
should see: a railway line entering a large
wood.
It was there.
She was exactly on course.
She wasn't even a minute into the flight when
the radio call came.
'Golf Lima Yankee.
This is Norwich Tower.'
'Golf Lima Yankee,' she called back.
'Golf Lima Yankee.
Return to Norwich immediately!'
Francesca couldn't believe her ears.
Forgetting her radio language she asked, 'What
was that?'
The call was returned instantly.
'Golf Lima Yankee, you must return to the
airfield immediately.
We have been informed that there is water
in your fuel and you are in serious danger
of engine failure!'
Francesca felt her blood run cold.
'Pardon?'
she said faintly.
'Golf Lima Yankee, you are in danger of engine
failure.
Return to Norwich immediately.
Do you understand?'
Weakly, Francesca answered.
'Yes, I understand.'
With staring eyes, she began to turn the plane
round.
A hand seemed to be gripping her throat.
She could hardly breathe.
Of course, it was Doug.
He had somehow put water in the fuel tank.
If it reached the engine, the engine was certain
to stop.
Another call came through.
'Golf Lima Yankee, please state your height
and position.'
Francesca stared at the map, at the dials,
down at the ground.
For a moment, she was in total confusion.
Then she called back.
'Norwich Tower,' she said slowly.
'Golf Lima Yankee is at 3000 feet, overhead
Branton Wood, heading zero eight zero.'
'Very good, Golf Lima Yankee,' the tower answered.
'Emergency Services are standing by at Norwich.
You have priority for landing.'
Francesca had no time to take in what had
happened, for almost at the same moment, the
engine coughed like an old man, went back
to full power for a second or two, then stopped
completely.
Francesca froze.
She couldn't move, she couldn't speak.
Then it hit her.
This was real.
She had to act.
She blinked a couple of times as if suddenly
waking up, then a new Francesca seemed to
slip into the seat.
Immediately she pushed the control column
forward and put the plane into a glide.
And then she was looking down through the
left-hand window to the earth beneath.
Fortunately, she had just left the woodland
behind and there was a choice of fields below.
A large green rectangular one caught her eye,
but a thin wavy line through the middle of
it suggested a small stream.
A little way ahead, Francesca spotted another
field, paler green this time - it would have
to be that one.
She tried to work out which way she would
land.
She'd taken off to the west, now she was flying
back in the opposite direction, so she must
be flying east.
If she was going to land into the wind, it
meant turning 180 degrees.
She would have to make a wide circle round,
but make sure she didn't come in short.
If she did, there were trees and a ploughed
field - she would crash into these.
'Norwich Tower.
Mayday!
Golf Lima Yankee has engine failure,' she
called.
'Attempting forced landing just east of Branton
Wood.'
'Golf Lima Yankee,' the call came back, 'Emergency
call understood.
Forced landing east of Branton Wood.
Good luck.'
Francesca didn't answer.
Already the plane was down to 1500 feet.
She was over the middle of the field she had
chosen - now she had to fly on and circle
round to come into land.
Another cough from the engine caught her by
surprise.
Somehow, it must have restarted.
Maybe she would be able to fly on, after all;
perhaps there was hope!
But as suddenly as the engine had restarted,
it stopped again.
Francesca swore.
It would have been better if it hadn't restarted
at all.
She had to concentrate.
Concentrate like never before.
1000 feet.
She should begin the turn.
There were trees beneath, and a road.
She could see a small white car racing along.
Francesca imagined the driver happily speeding
on, completely unaware of the drama taking
place overhead.
Now five hundred feet.
So, turn towards the field now.
Keep up speed.
Oh, God, Francesca thought, I'll never make
it, it's too far ahead.
She dropped the nose.
The ground was getting closer with every second.
And the trees.
Unconsciously her hand went to the throttle
to get more power, before she remembered there
was no power, the engine had failed.
'Stupid!'
she shouted out loud.
She looked ahead, down the nose.
The field was approaching.
There was nothing for it.
This was it.
One chance to land.
One chance to live!
'Here we go!
Come on, Francesca!'
she said.
She thought of her family: of her mother and
father and sister, and Tom.
This is for you, she thought.
All of a sudden the ground was rushing past.
The pale green suddenly formed into a line
of balls; she pulled back on the control column.
The plane hung in the air for a moment or
two, then dropped.
With a heavy bump, it came down to the ground,
all three wheels hitting the earth at the
same time.
Just before it stopped, the plane suddenly
dug into the earth and dropped forward onto
its nose.
Francesca was thrown tight against the safety
harness, then back against the seat.
It took her four or five seconds to realise
she wasn't moving any more.
She looked around, unable to understand what
she was seeing.
Then she realised that lettuces were pressed
up all around the window.
She had landed in a lettuce field.
Through her headphones, she heard a call.
'Golf Lima Yankee?'
'Norwich Tower, this is Golf Lima Yankee,'
she said.
'I am safely down on the ground.'
The next moment she burst into tears of relief.
CHAPTER TWENTY
A final test
Three hours later, having left the Cessna
in the temporary care of a very surprised
farmer, Francesca was taken by police back
to the airfield at Norwich.
'So, you're telling me Doug put water in my
fuel and then he was the one who telephoned
the control tower?'
Francesca said.
She was back in the Flying Start office with
Tom and George, gripping a cup of coffee tightly.
'Yes,' Tom answered miserably.
'I should have known there was something up
when we couldn't get those other two litres
of fuel in the tank.
I don't know what to say Francesca; it's my
fault.'
'Rubbish,' George broke in.
'There's only one person to blame, and it's
not you.
Just get on with the story.'
Tom hesitated for a moment, then continued.
'Well, it seems Doug was sitting in his car
up here at the airfield, when he saw you going
past, and suddenly he realised the seriousness
of what he'd done.
He claims he never imagined you'd even get
as far as the runway - that the engine would
cut out long before take-off and he just wanted
to scare you.
But when you went past it was like waking
from a dream; he realised you might actually
die and that he would be responsible for murder.
Apparently, he called the control tower from
his mobile just as you were taking off.'
Francesca shook her head in disbelief, and
gripped her cup of coffee even tighter.
'And then he gave himself up to the police,'
she said quietly.
'Yes,' Tom replied.
'Once he'd called the control tower, he phoned
the police himself and just sat in his car
until they arrived.
He made no attempt to get away.'
Francesca shivered.
'The poor guy,' she said quietly.
'He really must be ill.'
'Insane, more like it,' George broke in.
'They should lock him up and throw away the
key.'
Francesca smiled, touched by the anger that
her instructor was showing.
George reminded her of her grandfather, who,
although the kindest and gentlest of men,
would be furious at any mistreatment of a
family member.
She tried to change the subject.
'So, why didn't the engine stop immediately?'
'Ah,' said George, 'that's the remarkable
thing.'
He sat up.
'The point is this: at some time today after
its first flight, the stupid fool got to the
aircraft and poured a couple of litres of
water into one of the tanks.
Now, as you know, fuel floats on water, so
with the tank up on the wing, the water would
feed very quickly into the engine.
However, there would have already been some
fuel in the system, so clearly in driving
round and taking off, you used up that fuel,
and only a minute later the water got in.
Then, the engine stopped!'
Francesca half understood.
If she was totally honest, she wasn't fully
listening.
Every now and then, the true horror of what
had happened hit her again.
She'd been closer to death than at any time
before in her life - at that moment, she might
be lying dead in a field inside a broken plane.
She shivered once again.
'I just hope the bloody fool hasn't put you
off flying,' George went on.
'Most experienced pilots wouldn't have made
a better forced landing than you did.
You've got a brilliant flying future ahead
of you.'
In spite of everything, Francesca felt a glow
of warmth at George's remark.
But then, all of a sudden, she imagined her
next flight - later that week, next week,
whenever it might be - and she felt a sense
of panic.
Something told her she wouldn't be able to
do it.
The longer she waited, the worse it would
be.
The thought of what Doug had done would stick
in her mind like a seed and grow there, filling
her head with fear.
Afraid her hand would begin to tremble, she
quickly put down her cup of coffee.
And then it came to her.
If she were ever going to fly again, it had
to be as soon as possible.
She sat up and turned to George.
'George,' she began, 'would you consider allowing
me to take the other Cessna for a flight?'
'Of course,' George replied.
'When?'
'Now,' Francesca answered.
'What!'
George exclaimed.
'Now.
This minute,' Francesca said firmly.
'I know that if I don't go today, I'll never
get in the pilot's seat again; I'll completely
lose my nerve.'
George shook his head immediately.
'No, Francesca, I'm sorry, but it's quite
out of the question.
You've just had a terrible experience; you're
not thinking straight, you're far too emotional.
Look at you, you're shaking.'
Francesca looked at George desperately.
'Just one short flight,' she said.
'Take off and land, like my first solo.
If I don't, I'll never fly again.'
'Well, I'll come with you,' George said.
'No, it has to be solo,' Francesca insisted.
George closed his eyes, then opened them.
He looked across at Tom.
'You tell her, Tom.
You're her boyfriend.
Perhaps you can make her see some sense.'
Francesca turned to Tom.
He was looking down, his head in his hands.
Now, he looked up.
Francesca watched him.
For a moment, he reminded her of Andrea with
his head held high like that.
'I think you should let her go, George,' he
said quietly.
'I think you should let her decide.'
George stared at Tom in shock.
Then, after thinking for a while longer, he
finally gave a tiny nod of his head.
***
Less than half an hour later, Francesca was
approaching the runway for the second time
that day, in the other Flying Start Cessna,
G-ABJN.
She felt perfectly calm.
She stopped the plane before the runway, turned
into the wind, and did the power checks.
Then she called the control tower.
'Norwich Tower.
Golf Juliet November is ready to line up runway
zero nine.'
'Golf Juliet November, please wait.'
Francesca did as instructed, guessing that
another aircraft must be coming in.
As she waited, she thought about Tom, about
what he'd just done.
George must have been quite certain that Tom
would say this flight was a crazy idea.
But he hadn't.
He'd taken Francesca's side.
He'd put his confidence in her and given her
her freedom.
That was the kind of love she wanted.
He was the sort of person she could love.
A small two-engined plane flew past in front
of her.
She watched it land, first one of the main
wheels, then the other, finally, the nose
wheel - a good crosswind landing.
Then came her call on the radio.
'Golf Juliet November, line up runway zero
nine.'
Francesca released the brakes and moved the
plane forward, then swung round onto the piano
keys and stopped.
Only then did nerves grip her stomach.
Did she really want to do this?
Perhaps it wasn't such a good idea after all.
In the distance the other plane had disappeared
from the runway.
She waited.
Then came the call.
'Golf Juliet November.
You are cleared for take-off.'
Sitting there alone in the plane, she was
suddenly overcome with fear as the memory
of the forced landing came back to her.
She had nearly died!
What was she thinking of, going up there again?
Down here on the ground she was safe.
The seconds passed.
She had to do something.
She could head back to the hangar or go ahead
and take off.
She stared through the windscreen down the
runway, the white dotted line stretching away
into the unknown.
'Like the rest of my life,' she thought to
herself all of a sudden.
Where would she be in one year's time?
Would she have passed her private pilot's
exams and be studying for her commercial licence?
Would she still be living in England?
Would she still be with Tom?
And what about in five years' time?
She had her whole life ahead of her.
The mystery of the future suddenly filled
her with excitement.
Without delaying a second longer, she steadily
pushed in the throttle.
The little plane began running forward immediately,
quickly picking up speed.
This was it.
She pulled back on the control column and
felt the plane slowly lift into flight.