The Girl with Green Eyes
'Of course,' the man in the brown hat said,
'there are good policemen and there are bad
policemen, you know.'
'You're right,' the young man said. 'Yes.
That's very true. Isn't it, Julie?' He looked
at the young woman next to him.
Julie didn't answer and looked bored. She
closed her eyes.
'Julie's my wife,' the young man told the
man in the brown hat. 'She doesn't like trains.
She always feels ill on trains.'
'Oh yes?' the man in the brown hat said. 'Now
my wife - she doesn't like buses. She nearly
had an accident on a bus once. It was last
year... No, no, it wasn't. It was two years
ago. I remember now. It was in Manchester.'
He told a long, boring story about his wife
and a bus in Manchester.
It was a hot day and the train was slow. There
were seven people in the carriage. There was
the man in the brown hat; the young man and
his wife, Julie; a mother and two children;
and a tall dark man in an expensive suit.
The young man's name was Bill. He had short
brown hair and a happy smile. His wife, Julie,
had long red hair and very green eyes - the
colour of sea water. They were very beautiful
eyes.
The man in the brown hat talked and talked.
He had a big red face and a loud voice. He
talked to Bill because Bill liked to talk
too. The man in the brown hat laughed a lot,
and when he laughed, Bill laughed too. Bill
liked talking and laughing with people.
The two children were hot and bored. They
didn't want to sit down. They wanted to be
noisy and run up and down the train.
'Now sit down and be quiet,' their mother
said. She was a small woman with a tired face
and a tired voice.
'I don't want to sit down,' the little boy
said. 'I'm thirsty.'
'Here. Have an orange,' his mother said. She
took an orange out of her bag and gave it
to him.
'I want an orange too, the little girl said
loudly.
'All right. Here you are,' said her mother.
'Eat it nicely, now.'
The children ate their oranges and were quiet
for a minute.
Then the little boy said, 'I want a drink.
I'm thirsty.'
The tall dark man took out his newspaper and
began to read. Julie opened her eyes and looked
at the back page of his newspaper. She read
about the weather in Budapest and about the
football in Liverpool. She wasn't interested
in Budapest and she didn't like football,
but she didn't want to listen to Bill and
the man in the brown hat. 'Talk, talk, talk,'
she thought. 'Bill never stops talking.'
Then suddenly she saw the tall man's eyes
over the top of his newspaper. She could not
see his mouth, but there was a smile in his
eyes. Quickly, she looked down at the newspaper
and read about the weather in Budapest again.
The train stopped at Dawlish station and people
got on and got off. There was a lot of noise.
'Is this our station?' the little girl asked.
She went to the window and looked out.
'No, it isn't. Now sit down,' her mother said.
'We're going to Penzance,' the little girl
told Bill. 'For our holidays.'
'Yes,' her mother said. 'My sister's got a
little hotel by the sea. We're staying there.
It's cheap, you see.'
'Yes,' the man in the brown hat said. 'It's
a nice town. I know a man there. He's got
a restaurant in King Street. A lot of holiday
people go there. He makes a lot of money in
the summer.' He laughed loudly. 'Yes,' he
said again. 'You can have a nice holiday in
Penzance.'
'We're going to St Austell,' Bill. said. 'Me
and Julie. It's our first holiday. Julie wanted
to go to Spain, but I like St Austell. I always
go there for my holidays. It's nice in August.
You can have a good time there too.'
Julie looked out of the window. 'Where is
Budapest?' she thought. 'I want to go there.
I want to go to Vienna, to Paris, to Rome,
to Athens.' Her green eyes were bored and
angry. Through the window she watched the
little villages and hills of England.
The man in the brown hat looked at Julie.
'You're right,' he said to Bill. 'You can
have a good time on holiday in England. We
always go to Brighton, me and the wife. But
the weather! We went one year, and it rained
every day. Morning, afternoon, and night.
It's true. It never stopped raining.' He laughed
loudly. 'We nearly went home after the first
week.'
Bill laughed too. 'What did you do all day,
then?' he asked.
Julie read about the weather in Budapest for
the third time. Then she looked at the tall
man's hands. They were long, brown hands,
very clean. 'Nice hands,' she thought. He
wore a very expensive Japanese watch. 'Japan,'
she thought. 'I'd like to go to Japan.' She
looked up and saw the man's eyes again over
the top of his newspaper. This time she did
not look away. Green eyes looked into dark
brown eyes for a long, slow minute.
After Newton Abbot station the guard came
into the carriage to look at their tickets.
'Now then,' he said, 'where are we all going?'
'This train's late,' the man in the brown
hat said. 'Twenty minutes late, by my watch.'
'Ten minutes,' the guard said. 'That's all.'
He smiled at Julie.
The tall dark man put his newspaper down,
found his ticket, and gave it to the guard.
The guard looked at it.
'You're all right, sir,' he said. 'The boat
doesn't leave Plymouth before six o'clock.
You've got lots of time.'
The tall man smiled, put his ticket back in
his pocket and opened his newspaper again.
Julie didn't look at him. 'A boat,' she thought.
'He's taking a boat from Plymouth. Where's
he going?' She looked at him again with her
long green eyes.
He read his newspaper and didn't look at her.
But his eyes smiled.
The train stopped at Totnes station and more
people got on and off.
'Everybody's going on holiday,' Bill said.
He laughed. 'It's going to be wonderful. No
work for two weeks. It's a nice, quiet town,
St Austell. We can stay in bed in the mornings,
and sit and talk in the afternoons, and have
a drink or two in the evenings. Eh, Julie?'
He looked at his wife. 'Are you all right,
Julie?'
'Yes, Bill,' she said quietly. 'I'm OK.' She
looked out of the window again. The train
went more quickly now, and it began to rain.
Bill and the man in the brown hat talked and
talked. Bill told a long story about two men
and a dog, and the man in the brown hat laughed
very loudly.
'That's a good story,' he said. 'I like that.
You tell it very well. Do you know the story
about...' And he told Bill a story about a
Frenchman and a bicycle.
'Why do people laugh at these stories?' Julie
thought. 'They're so boring!'
But Bill liked it. Then he told a story about
an old woman and a cat, and the man in the
brown hat laughed again. 'That's good, too.
I don't know. How do you remember them all?'
'Because', Julie thought, 'he tells them every
day.'
'I don't understand,' the little girl said
suddenly. She looked at Bill. 'Why did the
cat die?'
'Shhh. Be quiet,' her mother said. 'Come and
eat your sandwiches now.'
That's all right,' Bill said. 'I like children.'
The man in the brown hat looked at the children's
sandwiches. 'Mmm, I'm hungry, too,' he said.
'You can get sandwiches in the restaurant
on this train.' He looked at Bill 'Let's go
down to the restaurant, eh? I need a drink
too.'
Bill laughed. 'You're right. It's thirsty
work, telling stories.'
The two men stood up and left the carriage.
The little girl ate her sandwich and looked
at Julie. 'But why did the cat die?' she asked.
'I don't know,' Julie said. 'Perhaps it wanted
to die.'
The little girl came and sat next to Julie.
'I like your hair,' she said. 'It's beautiful.'
Julie looked down at her and smiled.
For some minutes it was quiet in the carriage.
Then the tall dark man opened his bag and
took out a book. He put it on the seat next
to him, and looked at Julie with a smile.
Julie looked back at him, and then down at
the book. Famous towns of Italy, she read.
Venice, Florence, Rome, Naples. She looked
away again, out of the window at the rain.
Two weeks in St Austell,' she thought. 'With
Bill - In the rain.'
After half an hour the two men came back to
the carriage. 'There are a lot of people on
this train,' Bill said. 'Do you want a sandwich,
Julie?'
'No,' she said. 'I'm not hungry. You eat them.'
The train was nearly at Plymouth. Doors opened
and people began to move. 'A lot of people
get on here,' the man in the brown hat said.
The tall dark man stood up and put his book
and his newspaper in his bag. Then he picked
up his bag and left the carriage. The train
stopped at the station. A lot of people got
on the train, and two women and an old man
came into the carriage. They had a lot of
bags with them. Bill and the man in the brown
hat stood up and helped them. One of the women
had a big bag of apples. The bag broke and
the apples went all over the carriage.
'Oh damn!' she said.
Everybody laughed, and helped her to find
the apples. The train moved away from Plymouth
station. After a minute or two everybody sat
down and the woman gave some apples to the
children.
'Where's Julie?' Bill said suddenly. 'She's
not here.'
'Perhaps she went to the restaurant,' the
man in the brown hat said.
'But she wasn't hungry,' Bill said. 'She told
me.'
The little girl looked at Bill. 'She got off
the train at Plymouth,' she said. 'With the
tall dark man. I saw them.'
'Of course she didn't!' Bill said. 'She's
on this train. She didn't get off.'
'Yes, she did,' the children's mother said
suddenly. 'I saw her too. The tall man waited
for her on the platform.'
'He waited for her?' Bill's mouth was open.
'But... But he read his newspaper all the
time. He didn't talk to Julie. And she never
talked to him. They didn't say a word.'
'People don't always need words, young man,'
the children's mother said.
'But she's my wife!' Bill's face was red and
angry. 'She can't do that!' he said loudly.
He stood up. 'I'm going to stop the train,'
Everybody looked at him and the two children
laughed.
'No,' the man in the brown hat said, 'no,
you don't want to do that. Sit down and eat
your sandwiches, my friend.'
'But I don't understand. Why did she go? What
am I going to do?' Bill's face was very unhappy.
After a second or two he sat down again. 'What
am I going to do?' he said again.
'Nothing,' the man in the brown hat said.
He ate his sandwich slowly. 'Go and have your
holiday in St Austell. You can have a good
time there. Forget about Julie. Those green
eyes, now.' He took out a second sandwich
and began to eat it. 'I knew a woman once
with green eyes. She gave me a very bad time.
No, you want to forget about Julie.'
South for the Winter
I never stay in one country for a long time.
It gets boring. I like to move on, see new
places, meet different people. It's a good
life, most of the time. When I need money,
I get a job. I can do most things - hotel
and restaurant work, building work, picking
fruit. In Europe you can pick fruit most of
the year. You need to be in the right country
at the right time, of course. It's not easy
work, but the money's not bad.
I like to go south in the winter. Life is
easier in the sun, and northern Europe can
get very cold in the winter. Last year, 1989
it was, I was in Venice for October. I did
some work in a hotel for three weeks, then
I began slowly to move south. I always go
by train when I can. I like trains. You can
walk about on a train, and you meet a lot
of people.
I left Venice and went on to Trieste. There
I got a cheap ticket for the slow train to
Sofia, in Bulgaria. This train goes all down
through Yugoslavia, and takes a long time
- a day and a half. But that didn't matter
to me.
The train left Trieste at nine o'clock on
a Thursday morning. There weren't many people
on it at first, but at Zagreb more people
got on. Two girls went along the corridor,
past my carriage. They looked through the
door, but they didn't come in. Then an old
woman came in, sat down and went to sleep.
The two girls came back along the corridor
and looked into the carriage again. The train
left Zagreb and I looked out of the window
for about ten minutes, then I went to sleep
too.
When I opened my eyes again, the two girls
were in the carriage. They looked friendly,
so I said, 'Hullo.'
'Hi!' they said.
'You're American,' I said. 'Or Canadian. Right?'
'American,' the taller girl said. She smiled.
'And you're twenty-three, your name's Tom
Walsh, you've got blue eyes, and your mum
lives in Burnham-on-Sea, UK. Right?'
'How did you know all that?' I asked.
The second girl laughed. 'She looked at your
passport. It's in your coat pocket.'
'Oh. Right.' My coat was on the seat next
to me. I took my passport out of my pocket
and put it back in my bag. 'Who are you, then?'
I asked.
They told me. Melanie and Carol from Los Angeles,
USA. They liked Europe, they said. They knew
a lot of places - Britain, Holland, Denmark,
Germany, France, Spain, Italy, Yugoslavia,
Bulgaria, Greece...
'I'm going to Bulgaria now,' I said. For about
a month. Then I'm going south for the winter,
Cyprus, or perhaps North Africa.'
'Oh yes?' they said. 'We love Bulgaria. Sofia's
a great town. Wonderful.'
'What do you do about money?' I asked,
'Well, you know,' Carol smiled. 'Sometimes
we get a little job. This and that. But what
about you?'
'Yeah, come on,' Melanie said. 'Tell us about
you - Tom Walsh with the blue eyes and the
mum in Burnham-on-Sea. What are you doing
with your life, hey?'
So I told them. They were nice girls. They
were older than me, perhaps twenty-seven or
twenty-eight, but I liked them. We talked
and laughed for hours. I told them a lot of
stories about my life. Some of the stories
were true, some weren't. But the girls laughed,
and said I was a great guy. I asked them about
Bulgaria, because I didn't know the country.
They knew Sofia well, they said.
'Hey, Carol,' Melanie said. 'We're staying
in Bela Palanka for a day or two. But let's
go over to Sofia this weekend and meet Tom
there. We can meet him on Saturday night at
the Hotel Marmara.'
'Yeah! It's a good hotel,' Carol told me.
'Cheap, but good. What do you think, Tom?'
'Great!' I said. 'Let's do that.'
The train was very slow. We got to Belgrade
at six o'clock in the evening, and a lot of
people got off. There were only me and the
girls in the carriage then. The guard came
and looked at our tickets, and went away again.
Carol looked at Melanie. 'Hey, Mel,' she said.
'Why don't you and Tom go along to the restaurant?
I'm not hungry, and I want to sleep for an
hour.'
'Er... Food's very expensive on the train,'
I said. 'I haven't got much money just now.
I'm going to get a job in Sofia.'
'Oh Tom!' Melanie said. 'Why didn't you tell
us? Look, you're a nice guy, right? We're
OK for money this week. We can buy you a meal.'
'Of course we can,' Carol said. 'And look,
in Sofia, we can take you to the best restaurant
in town. It's a great place. We love it.'
What could I say? I was hungry. They had money,
I didn't. So Melanie and I went to the restaurant
and had a meal. When we came back, Carol was
still alone in the carriage. Melanie put her
feet on the seat and went to sleep.
At Nis some more people got on the train,
and two old men came into our carriage. They
looked at Melanie's feet on the seat, and
talked in loud voices. Carol laughed, and
Melanie opened her eyes and sat up.
'Are we nearly there?' she asked Carol, and
looked out of the window.
'Yeah. About half an hour, I think.'
'Why are you getting off at Bela Palanka?'
I asked. 'What are you going to do there?'
Melanie smiled. 'Find a cheap hotel, meet
people, take a look at the town... you know.'
'Just for a day or two,' Carol said.
'But there's nothing there!'
'Oh well, you never know,' Melanie laughed.
'See you in Sofia, right? On Saturday night.'
'The Hotel Marmara, OK? Eight o'clock,' Carol
said. 'Don't forget now!'
'OK. Great,' I said. 'See you there.'
The train came into Bela Palanka and stopped.
The two girls got off and stood on the platform.
They smiled at me through the window. 'Saturday.
Eight o'clock,' Melanie shouted.
'OK,' I called. They couldn't hear me because
of the noise in the station. They smiled again,
picked up their bags and walked away. Nice
girls. I'm going to have a great time in Sofia,
I thought.
The train left Yugoslavia and crossed into
Bulgaria at two o'clock in the morning. Then
the train stopped at some village - I don't
remember the name. I ate an apple and looked
out of the window.
Suddenly there were a lot of policemen on
the train. Everybody in the carriage sat up
and began to talk.
'What's happening?' I said in Italian to the
old man next to me.
'I don't know,' he said in bad Italian. 'Perhaps
they're looking for somebody. Look. The police
are taking some people off the train.'
Then two policemen came into our carriage,
a tall thin one and a short fat one. They
looked at everybody carefully... and then
they looked at me again.
'Come with us, please,' the fat policeman
said in English.
'What? Me?' I said. 'Why? What's the matter?'
'And bring your bag with you,' the tall policeman
said.
I began to ask a question, but policemen never
like questions from young men with long hair.
So I stayed quiet, picked up my bag, and went
with them.
In the station building there were a lot more
policemen, and some people from the train.
They were all young people, I saw. Some were
afraid, some were bored. The police looked
in everybody's bags, and then the people went
back to the train.
My two policemen took me to a table. 'Your
passport, please,' the fat policeman said,
'and open your bag.'
They looked at my passport and I opened my
bag. There was a young policewoman with red
hair at the next table. She had a nice face,
so I smiled at her and she smiled back.
'Aaah!' the tall policeman said suddenly.
All my dirty shirts and clothes were out on
the table. The policeman picked up my bag
and turned it over. On to the table, out of
my bag, fell packet after packet of US American
dollars. Nice, new dollars. Fifty-dollar notes
in big packets. A lot of money.
My mouth opened, and stayed open. I couldn't
find my voice. I was suddenly a very interesting
person, and a lot of police ran up to our
table and stood behind me.
'50,000... 100,000... 150,000... There's 200,000
dollars here,' the tall policeman said. 'What
an interesting bag, Mr Tom Walsh!'
I found my voice again quickly. 'But it's
not my bag!' I shouted.
There was a big, happy smile on that policeman's
face. 'Well,' he said, 'it's got your name
on it. Look!'
So I looked, and of course there was my name,
and yes of course, it was my bag. So how did
200,000 US dollars get into my bag?
'You cannot bring US dollars into this country,'
the fat policeman said. He had very short
grey hair and little black eyes. He didn't
smile once.
'But I didn't bring them,' I said quickly.
'They're not my dollars. I never saw them
before in my life, and-'
There was a lot of noise in the station. I
looked out of the window and saw my train.
Slowly, it began to move.
'Hey! I shouted. 'That's my train-'
The tall policeman laughed. It was a great
day for him. 'Oh no,' he said. 'You're not
getting back on that train. You're staying
here with us, in our beautiful country.' He
smiled, happily.
So I never got to Sofia on Saturday. I was
very unhappy about that. I wanted to have
a little talk with Melanie and Carol, ask
them one or two questions, you know. You're
a nice guy, Tom. See you in Sofia, OK? Take
you to the best restaurant in town. Yeah.
Great.
And I never got down to Cyprus or North Africa
that winter. Oh well, I live and learn. It's
not an easy life, in prison. But it's warm
in winter, and the food's not bad. And I'm
meeting some interesting people. There's a
man from Georgia, USSR - Boris, his name is.
He comes from a place by the Black Sea. He's
a great guy. When we get out of here, he and
I are going down to Australia... Brisbane
perhaps, or Sydney. Get a job on a ship, start
a new life. Yeah, next year's going to be
OK.
Mr Harris and the Night Train
Mr Harris liked trains. He was afraid of aeroplanes,
and didn't like buses. But trains - they were
big and noisy and exciting. When he was a
boy often, he liked trains. Now he was a man
of fifty, and he still liked trains.
So he was a happy man on the night of the
14th of September. He was on the night train
from Helsinki to Oulu in Finland, and he had
ten hours in front of him.
'I've got a book and my newspaper,' he thought.
'And there's a good restaurant on the train.
And then I've got two weeks' holiday with
my Finnish friends in Oulu.'
There weren't many people on the train, and
nobody came into Mr Harris's carriage. He
was happy about that. Most people on the train
slept through the night, but Mr Harris liked
to look out of the window, and to read and
think.
After dinner in the restaurant Mr Harris came
back to his carriage, and sat in his seat
next to the window. For an hour or two he
watched the trees and lakes of Finland out
of the window. Then it began to get dark,
so he opened his book and began to read.
At midnight the train stopped at the small
station of Otava. Mr Harris looked out of
the window, but he saw nobody. The train moved
away from the station, into the black night
again. Then the door of Mr Harris's carriage
opened, and two people came in. A young man
and a young woman.
The young woman was angry. She closed the
door and shouted at the man: 'Carl! You can't
do this to me!' The young man laughed loudly
and sat down.
Mr Harris was a small, quiet man. He wore
quiet clothes, and he had a quiet voice. He
did not like noisy people and loud voices.
So he was not pleased. 'Young people are always
noisy,' he thought. 'Why can't they talk quietly?'
He put his book down and closed his eyes.
But he could not sleep because the two young
people didn't stop talking.
The young woman sat down and said in a quieter
voice: 'Carl, you're my brother and I love
you, but please listen to me. You can't take
my diamond necklace. Give it back to me now.
Please!'
Carl smiled. 'No, Elena,' he said. 'I'm going
back to Russia soon, and I'm taking your diamonds
with me.' He took off his hat and put it on
the seat. 'Elena, listen. You have a rich
husband, but I - I have no money. I have nothing!
How can I live without money? You can't give
me money, so I need your diamonds, little
sister.'
Mr Harris looked at the young woman. She was
small, with black hair and dark eyes. Her
face was white and afraid. Mr Harris began
to feel sorry for Elena. She and her brother
didn't look at him once. 'Can't they see me?'
he thought.
'Carl,' Elena said. Her voice was very quiet
now, and Mr Harris listened carefully. 'You
came to dinner at our house tonight, and you
went to my room and took my diamond necklace.
How could you do that to me? My husband gave
the diamonds to me. They were his mother's
diamonds before that. He's going to be very,
very angry - and I'm afraid of him.'
Her brother laughed. He put his hand in his
pocket, then took it out again and opened
it slowly. The diamond necklace in his hand
was very beautiful. Mr Harris stared at it.
For a minute or two nobody moved and it was
quiet in the carriage. There was only the
noise of the train, and it went quickly on
through the dark cold night.
Mr Harris opened his book again, but he didn't
read it. He watched Carl's face, with its
hungry eyes and its cold smile.
'What beautiful, beautiful diamonds!' Carl
said. 'I can get a lot of money for these.'
'Give them back to me, Carl,' Elena whispered,
'My husband's going to kill me. You're my
brother... Please help me. Please!'
Carl laughed again, and Mr Harris wanted to
hit him. 'Go home, little sister,' Carl said.
'I'm not going to give the diamonds back to
you. Go home to your angry husband.'
Suddenly there was a knife in the young woman's
hand. A long, bright knife. Mr Harris watched
with his mouth open. He couldn't speak or
move.
'Give the diamonds back to me!' Elena cried.
'Or I'm going to kill you!' Her hand on the
knife was white.
Carl laughed and laughed. 'What a sister!'
he said. 'What a kind, sweet sister! No, they're
my diamonds now. Put your knife away, little
sister.'
But the knife in the white hand moved quickly:
up, then down. There was a long, terrible
cry, and Carl's body fell slowly on to the
seat. The colour of the seat began to change
to red, and the diamond necklace fell from
Carl's hand on to the floor.
Elena's face was white. 'Oh no!' she whispered.
'Carl! Come back... come back! I didn't want
to kill you!' But Carl didn't answer, and
the red blood ran slowly over the floor. Elena
put her head in her hands, and again in the
carriage there was a long, terrible cry.
Mr Harris's face was white too. He opened
his mouth, but he couldn't speak. He stood
up, and carefully moved to the door. The young
woman was quiet now. She didn't move or look
up at Mr Harris.
In the corridor, Mr Harris ran. The guard
was at the hack of the train and Mr Harris
got there in half a minute.
'Quickly!' Mr Harris said. 'Come quickly!
An accident... a young woman... oh dear! Her
brother is... is dead!'
The guard ran with Mr Harris back to the carriage.
Mr Harris opened the door and they went inside.
There was no dead body of a young man. There
was no young woman... no blood, no knife,
no diamond necklace. Only Mr Harris's bags
and his hat and coat.
The guard looked at Mr Harris, and Mr Harris
looked at him.
'But...' Mr Harris began. 'But they were here!
I saw them! She... the young woman... She
had a knife and she... she killed her brother.'
'A knife, you say?' the guard asked.
'Yes,' Mr Harris said quickly. 'A long knife,
and her brother took her diamonds, so she-'
'Ah! Diamonds! the guard said. 'Was the young
woman's name Elena?' he asked.
'Yes, it was!' Mr Harris said. 'How do you
know that? Do you... Do you know her?'
'Yes - and no,' the guard said slowly. He
thought for a minute, then looked at Mr Harris.
'Elena di Saronelli,' he said. 'She had dark
eyes and black hair. Very beautiful. She was
half-Italian, half-Finnish. Her brother was
a half- brother. They had the same father,
but his mother was Russian, I think.'
'Was? Had?' Mr Harris stared at the guard.
'But she... Elena... she's alive! And where
is she?'
'Oh no,' said the guard. 'Elena di Saronelli
died about eighty years ago. After she killed
her brother with a knife, she jumped off the
train, and died at once. It was near here,
I think.' He looked out of the window, into
the night.
Mr Harris's face was very white again. 'Eighty
years ago!' he whispered. 'What are you saying?
Were she and her brother... But I saw them!'
'Yes, that's right,' the guard said. 'You
saw them, but they're not alive. They're ghosts.
They often come on the night train at this
time in September. I never see them, but somebody
saw them last year. A man and his wife. They
were very unhappy about it. But what can I
do? I can't stop Elena and Carl coming on
the train.'
The guard looked at Mr Harris's white face.
'You need a drink,' he said. 'Come and have
a vodka with me.'
Mr Harris didn't usually drink vodka, but
he felt afraid. When he closed his eyes, he
could see again Elena's long knife and could
hear her terrible cry. So he went with the
guard to the back of the train.
After the vodka, Mr Harris felt better. He
didn't want to sleep, and the guard was happy
to talk. So Mr Harris stayed with the guard
and didn't go back to his carriage.
'Yes,' the guard said, 'it's a famous story.
I don't remember it all. It happened a long
time ago, of course. Elena's father was a
famous man here in Finland. He was very rich
once, but he had three or four wives and about
eight children. And he liked the good things
of life. So there wasn't much money for the
children. Carl, the oldest son, was a bad
man, people say. He wanted an easy life, and
money in his hand all the time.'
The train hurried on to Oulu through the black
night, and the guard drank some more vodka.
'Now, Elena,' he said. 'She didn't have an
easy life with those three difficult men - her
father, her brother, her husband. One year
she visited her mother's family in Italy,
and there she met her husband, di Saronelli.
He was rich, but he wasn't a kind man. They
came back to Finland, and Carl often visited
their house. He wanted money from his sister's
rich husband. Elena loved her brother, and
gave him some money. But di Saronelli didn't
like Carl and was angry with Elena. He stopped
giving her money, and after that... well,
you know the story now.'
'Yes,' Mr Harris said. 'Poor, unhappy Elena.'
Mr Harris stayed with his friends in Oulu
for two weeks. They were quiet weeks, and
Mr Harris had a good holiday. But he took
the bus back to Helsinki. The bus was slow,
and there were a lot of people on it, but
Mr Harris was very happy. He didn't want to
take the night train across Finland again.