CHAPTER ONE
A Gentleman from La Mancha
In the Spanish village of La Mancha, there
lived a gentleman who loved to read.
His favorite stories were of knights and their
code of chivalry: full of dragons, magic swords,
enchanted forests, and damsels in distress.
This gentleman was not a wealthy man, but
rather a hidalgo.
A hidalgo was a landowner who was richer than
a peasant, but poorer than a nobleman.
His name was Senor Quixano.
Senor Quixano lived modestly with his housekeeper
and his young niece.
He was a tall, thin man in his fifties.
He was a strong and healthy man, who went
hunting every morning.
However, he started to read adventure stories
all the time.
His best friends, the local priest and the
village barber, were worried.
Their friend suddenly began spending night
and day in his chair, reading adventure books
through crazed, bloodshot eyes.
Soon he started thinking these stories were
true.
Finally he went completely crazy.
Waking up in his reading chair one morning,
Senor Quixano announced, "I'm going to become
a knight-errant!"
"A what?" asked his concerned niece.
"A knight-errant is a righter of wrongs, a
friend to the unfortunate, a rescuer of fair
maidens, and a killer of dragons!"
"But Uncle," she cried, "there are no dragons
in Spain!
And who are these maidens who need rescuing?"
The old man went to the attic of his house
and found a rusty old suit of armor.
He put the suit on and felt ready for action.
In a bold voice, he announced, "Now, to my
faithful steed.
This "steed" was really a worn-out nag.
But to his delusional eyes, it was a valiant
war horse.
"I name you Rocinante, Queen of the hacks!
And I will call myself.
He took a moment to think of the perfect name.
"Don Quixote!"
"Now I must dedicate my life to a lady!'
"Do you know a lady?"
sobbed the man's niece, frightened by his
insane ramblings.
"All knights know a lady," the man replied.
"When I conquer a giant or capture a villain,
I'll parade them in front of her to prove
my love and loyalty."
Then he remembered stories he had heard of
a beautiful peasant girl from the nearby village
of El Toboso.
Having lost his grip on reality, he decided
that she was a lonely princess.
"What's her name?"
demanded his niece, hoping to bring him to
his senses.
Quickly, he invented a name.
"All of the sweetest ladies are named Dulcinea.
Her name is Dulcinea del Toboso, and to her
I dedicate my life!
Don't try to stop me.
I must go!"
Then he picked up his sword, a cracked old
lance, and a leather shield and marched out
to the stable.
A few minutes later, he rode out in search
of his first knightly adventure.
Don Quixote soon realized that he had not
been knighted.
"I must find a lord or lady to dub me a knight,"
he said.
"I don't want to be called a fraud!"
All day Don Quixote rode the scorching plain
searching for adventure, but nothing happened.
By sunset, he and Rocinante were hungry and
tired.
In the fading light, the armored man saw an
inn and rode toward it.
"Perhaps we'll find shelter at that castle,"
he said to his horse.
The inn was of the common shabby type found
along the highways of Spain.
In front of the inn were two dirty-faced peasant
girls, who watched in shock as this man in
rusty armor approached them.
"Good evening, fair maidens," he said.
"I am the knight, Don Quixote de La Mancha.
Please summon a trumpeter to announce my arrival."
In his eyes, this old inn was a great castle
with tall silver towers.
Don Quixote became annoyed when the girls
just giggled.
But at this moment, a pig-handler stepped
out of the inn and blew his horn to round
up his grunting animals for the night.
Don Quixote mistook the sound of the horn
for a chorus of pipes and trumpets.
Then the innkeeper came to the knight.
"If you're looking for a bed for the night,
I'm sorry to tell you that we're all full."
"Sire, are you the master of this castle?"
asked Don Quixote politely.
Looking at this man in his rusty armor, the
innkeeper realized that he was obviously crazy.
The innkeeper decided to have some fun with
this loon.
"All of the royal apartments in my castle
are full."
"That's okay," replied Don Quixote.
"A good knight has no need for comfort.
I'll be happy to sleep on the ground with
a rock for a pillow."
"You're a knight, aren't you?"
the innkeeper asked mischievously.
"I am an apprentice knight," replied Don Quixote.
"I seek a kind lord who will dub me a knight
with his sword."
"I see," said the innkeeper, "but I'm busy
now caring for my other guests.
I'll be back to you when I get a chance."
"Thank you, my lord," replied Don Quixote.
After some rest, Don Quixote grew impatient
and sent for the innkeeper.
When the innkeeper stumbled out, Don Quixote
said, "Lord, I can wait no longer.
Please tell me what good deed I must do to
earn my knighthood."
The innkeeper said, "If you want me to knight
you, stay here and guard my courtyard tonight."
With that, he turned and stomped off to the
kitchen.
Don Quixote picked up his weapons and walked
to the middle of the courtyard, next to a
water trough.
Inside, the innkeeper told his guests about
the madman who thought he was a knight in
the courtyard.
A few hours later, a muleteer approached the
trough with his animals.
"Stand back, foolish knight!"
shouted Don Quixote.
"I will defend this magic well to the death!"
"But my mules need water," cried the peasant
as he pushed past Don Quixote.
Swinging his lance, Don Quixote hit the man
on the head and knocked him out.
"I have done my first good deed!"
exclaimed Don Quixote.
"When this man awakes, I must send him to
my lady Dulcinea to pay his respects."
Alarmed by the noise, the other muleteers
rushed out of the inn and attacked Don Quixote.
"A swarm of evil knights attacks me!"
cried Don Quixote as he blocked their flying
stones with his shield.
The innkeeper realized that he needed to get
rid of this dangerous screwball.
"Dear knight," he said to Don Quixote, "forgive
these evil knights and put down your weapons.
You have proved your courage.
I will dub you a knight without delay.
Kneel down."
Obediently, Don Quixote knelt amid the straw
and dung of the yard.
"I hereby appoint you to the order of righteous
knights," cried the innkeeper, smacking Don
Quixote across the back with his own sword.
Don Quixote jumped to his feet excitedly,
"My lord, I owe you everything!"
"Yes, yes," replied the innkeeper.
"Now you must go off on your good-deed doing
and wrong-righting."
"At once!"
cried Don Quixote, who hurried to the stable,
mounted Rocinante, and rode out into the dawn
of La Mancha.
Shortly after, Don Quixote spotted a group
of silk merchants coming toward him on the
road.
"Here is an opportunity for gallantry."
Riding in front of the group, he blocked the
road.
"Halt, cretins!
None shall be allowed to pass without proclaiming
that my lady, Dulcinea del Toboso, is the
most beautiful maiden in the world!"
The traders stopped and looked at each other.
It was obvious to them that they were in the
presence of a madman.
"I want to see her first before I can proclaim
her beauty.
How do we know that she's not just some old
sloppy chops?" said the joker of the group.
"Sloppy chops?"
screamed Don Quixote.
"Prepare to do battle, you impudent knave!"
Don Quixote raised his lance and charged the
group.
But Rocinante was not accustomed to speed
and stumbled.
Don Quixote was thrown through the air and
landed in a ditch with a crash.
The merchants went away, laughing loudly.
Hours later, a passing farmer heard a whimper.
He found Don Quixote in the ditch, covered
in mud.
The farmer recognized him as Senor Qixano
from the village.
He hurriedly picked up Don Quixote and carried
him home.
There the knight was tucked safely into his
own bed.
CHAPTER TWO
Knight & Squire
For two weeks Don Quixote rested in his house,
making everyone think he had regained his
sanity.
But he had secretly sold some of his land
to finance his next adventure.
He was also looking for a squire to accompany
him.
The only man Don Quixote found who would work
for him was a fat little farmer named Sancho
Panza.
He was a total dunce.
"This squire job sounds like hard work," said
Sancho.
"I'd rather be at home with my family, munching
on a big plate of pork."
Sancho Panza loved wine, food, and afternoon
naps more than anything else.
"But squires always receive great prizes of
gold and land from the knights they serve,"
promised Don Quixote.
"If you serve me, you'll surely end up as
the governor of some rich island."
"My own island!"
Sancho repeated, licking his lips.
"Okay, I'll grab my bags and saddle up my
donkey."
Then the two left in the middle of the night
without telling anyone.
By dawn, the two men were in the middle of
a wide plain.
Squinting in the glare of the brilliant sun,
Don Quixote saw thirty or forty windmills
in the fields before them.
"Sancho, fortune is smiling upon us!" he called.
"Does that mean it's time for breakfast?"
replied Sancho.
"This is no time for eating, you pig.
Look at those giants over there.
I'll kill every one of them.
Our great service will be remembered for centuries!"
"What giants?"
cried Sancho Panza.
"Over there!
The ones with the long arms!"
"But Master, those are windmills."
"Don't contradict me," scolded Don Quixote.
"I know an army of giants when I see them!"
Don Quixote spurred Rocinante into a gallop
and raised his lance.
"Giants!
Prepare to fight!" he shouted.
Charging into the nearest tower, he thrust
the shaft of his lance into a sweeping sail.
The weapon shattered, and the knight was picked
up off his horse and tossed into the air.
He landed with a great "BOOM!"
fifty meters away in a large puff of white
dust.
Trotting over on his donkey, Sancho Panza
said, "I told you they were windmills."
"You fool!" said Don Quixote.
"When I charged those giants, an evil wizard
flew by on an invisible horse and cast a spell
that changed them into windmills!
To rob me of my glory!"
"I see," said Sancho, believing every word
as he helped his master to his feet.
"Don't worry, my squire.
I'll find this wizard and destroy him!"
The next morning, they began traveling again
with-out breakfast, to Sancho's dismay.
An hour later, they saw a large cloud of dust
in the distance.
"It must be two bloodthirsty armies in battle!"
exclaimed Don Quixote.
Then he quickly described both of the armies,
including the names of their generals and
fiercest knights which he made up.
"How do we know that this isn't just a trick
by those evil wizards?"
"Can't you hear thousands of marching feet?"
yelled Don Quixote, who raised his broken
lance and charged them.
"They're not soldiers," cried Sancho, "It's
just a large flock of sheep!"
The knight began skewering the poor sheep
on the end of his lance.
As soon as the shepherds saw him killing their
animals, they began pelting him with stones.
A rock smashed the side of Don Quixote's face
and knocked him off Rocinante.
"Those evil wizards!"
cried Don Quixote, spitting out a mouthful
of blood and the chips of broken teeth.
"They've done it again!"
In a nearby meadow, the knight and the squire
found a place to rest for the night.
"I'll have dinner ready in a minute," said
Sancho.
"Oh, Squire, how can you think of eating in
the moment of my greatest despair?"
"There's nothing more important to me than
eating," Sancho said, devouring raw onion
and salami.
"What are you so sad about anyway?"
Holding his throbbing head, the knight answered,
"The loss of half my ear and four teeth saddens
me."
"I'm not surprised.
There will be nothing left of you in a week
or two.
I've never seen a man more miserable.
We should call you the Knight of the Long
Face.
Your chin is almost scraping the ground."
"Yes, my squire, that's an excellent name
for such an unhappy knight as myself.
The two realized that they were thirsty.
An hour later, they located a stream in the
forest.
As the sun began to set, they heard a terrible
sound coming from within the depths of the
forest.
"This is an enchanted forest ruled by a terrible
ogre.
I will find and destroy him with my lightning
lance.
If I'm not back in three days, go to my lady
Dulcinea and tell her I died valiantly in
her honor."
Sancho Panza was afraid to be left alone,
so he slipped off his donkey and sneaked under
Rocinante's hind legs.
There he tied a loop of rope to hold her still.
When Don Quixote tried to spur the nag on,
she could not move.
"What magic is this?"
boomed Don Quixote.
"My steed is held still."
"Oh, it must be that evil wizard again," lied
Sancho.
"Perhaps it would be better to destroy the
ogre in the morning."
"Yes, I will break this spell in the morning,"
agreed Don Quixote.
The two men spent the rest of the night trembling
in the forest for fear of the terrible noise
coming from down the river.
At dawn, Sancho slipped the rope from Rocinante's
hind legs.
When Don Quixote mounted her, she could walk.
"I'm free!"
exclaimed the knight happily.
Then they set off to search for the ogre.
But when they found the source of the terrible
crashing sound, it wasn't an ogre but an old
water machine, clanking away under the power
of a water- fail.
Sancho Panza began laughing at Don Quixote's
newest folly.
"We just spent the night trembling in fear
of this!" he laughed.
The Knight of the Long Face was even more
miserable after this failed adventure.
But late that afternoon, he saw something
that lifted his spirits.
"Look, Sancho, do you see that knight riding
toward us?"
"I see a man on a donkey," replied Sancho.
"That knight is Horatio the Brave, and his
helmet is the most valuable on Earth."
"I think that's a barber's wash basin on his
head."
"No, it's a solid gold battle helmet.
I will challenge him and win it!"
Don Quixote shouted, "Surrender your helmet,
Horatio, or I'll spear you with my lance!"
"I have no helmet," cried the man.
"I'm just a barber.
This brass basin is for my work.
I put it on my head because it was raining."
"Do you expect me to believe that?"
scoffed Don Quixote, drawing his sword.
Don Quixote snatched the basin from the man
and placed it on his head.
"The visor is missing, and someone has tried
to melt the gold off.
But I shall wear it with pride."
Sancho tried not to giggle at the sight of
Don Quixote with the wash basin on his head.
Later they came to a line of a dozen men with
heavy chains around their necks and hands.
Four soldiers herded them, cursing and lashing
them with whips.
"Prisoners," said Sancho, "off to row the
king's boat."
"I don't believe it," said Don Quixote.
"These unfortunate men are being held against
their will.
It is my duty to rescue them."
"Master," said Sancho with alarm, "these men
are terrible criminals.
They must pay for their crimes!"
"Move aside!"
commanded one of the soldiers.
"These men are vulnerable and needy," said
Don Quixote.
"As a knight-errant, I offer them protection!"
"This crazy old fool is out of his mind,"
laughed the sergeant.
"He's got a wash basin on his head!"
As the other soldiers laughed, Don Quixote
smashed the sergeant over the head with his
lance and knocked him unconscious.
The other soldiers attacked him, but the convicts
attacked them faster.
One of the convicts stole the keys from the
sergeant's pocket and unlocked the other criminals.
The convicts overtook the soldiers easily.
"My friends," cried Don Quixote, "I have given
you freedom.
All I ask in return is that you go to the
village of El Toboso and testify of my courage
to my mistress."
"He's as crazy as a coconut!"
yelled one of the convicts.
"Grab him!"
The convicts attacked Don Quixote and Sancho
Panza and beat them.
They robbed their saddlebags and cracked Don
Quixote's basin on a rock before running away.
Sancho Panza cried, "Now we're going to be
in big trouble.
We'll be wanted men.
The Holy Brotherhood Police will be after
us!"
CHAPTER THREE
The Giant Killer
To escape from the Holy Brotherhood, Don Quixote
and Sancho Panza fled into the mountains.
They traveled high up to desolate lonely country
of the Sierra Moreno range.
"All great men go through a period of despair
when they question everything they believe
in," Don Quixote said.
He turned to his hungry squire, "I am sending
you to El Toboso, with a message of my love
for Dulcinea.
She must tell me whether she can return my
love or not.
I will stay here and whip myself until you
return."
All Sancho could think about was the feast
he was going to eat as soon as he got back
to a village.
"Ride quickly, Sancho Panza," commanded Don
Quixote as he took off his armor.
Then he smashed himself in the chest with
a large rock and began to beat himself on
the back with a tree branch.
Riding away from the strange scene.
Sancho called to his master, "Don't overdo
it, or there'll be nothing left of you before
I can return."
Halfway to the village, Sancho stopped at
an inn for the feast he had been waiting for.
As he approached the door after his big meal,
he came face to face with Don Quixote's old
friends, the priest and the barber.
"Hey, you work for our troubled friend, Senor
Quixano, don't you?"
the priest said to Sancho.
"It's true.
I am his squire."
"How can you believe his nonsense?
Don't you realize he has lost his mind?"
"There have been some strange things happening,"
replied Sancho.
"Where is he now?"
demanded the barber.
"He's in the mountains, waiting for me to
return with an answer from his mistress, the
lady Dulcinea del Toboso."
"Her answer to what?" asked the priest.
"Something about love," answered Sancho.
"Take us to him.
We have to bring him back to the village with
us," said the priest.
"I will, but I warn you he'll never come back
with you."
"Hmm," said the barber, "I have a plan.
I'll be back in a minute."
Shortly after, the barber came back with two
dresses from the innkeeper's wife.
The three traveled back to the mountains.
That night, they camped and discussed the
details of their plan.
In the morning, Sancho went off to find Don
Quixote and tell him about the ladies in need
of help.
Meanwhile, the priest and the barber put on
the dresses and began cooking bacon over the
fire for their breakfast.
As they ate and talked, they saw a beautiful
woman passing by.
"We must show ourselves at once,'" said the
priest.
They stepped out to meet her.
The girl screamed when she saw them, and tried
to run away.
"Do not fear us," shouted the priest, "I am
a man of God!"
"If you're a priest, why are you wearing that
dress?"
she questioned.
"It's a long story," he replied.
"By the way, why are you wandering these hills?"
asked the barber.
The beautiful young girl then told her sad
story.
"My name is Dorotea.
I am the daughter of a wealthy farmer.
I was to be married to the Duke's son, Ferdinando.
But he left me for another woman.
I was so broken-hearted that I came here to
cry away the rest of my days."
Then the priest had an idea.
"Perhaps a truly beautiful lady such as yourself
could convince Don Quixote to come back to
our village, rather than an old priest and
barber dressed like women."
Dorotea agreed to their plan and put on one
of the dresses.
When Sancho returned, he led them to Don Quixote,
who was still lashing himself with the branch
of an old olive tree.
Immediately, Dorotea fell to her knees.
"Please, brave knight, a terrible giant is
attacking my father's kingdom.
You must help us!"
"Of course I will help you!
Sancho, prepare my horse.
We leave at once.
I cannot refuse a princess in distress."
Later the group arrived at the inn where Sancho
had first met the barber and the priest.
The innkeeper ran out to greet them and was
met by the priest.
The priest handed him ten gold pieces and
said, "My friend in the iron suit is mad.
He thinks he's a knight and this is a castle.
I ask you only to play along for the night
and let us stay until morning."
"Yes, my wife heard something about a lunatic
roaming the valley," said the innkeeper.
"I heard the Holy Brotherhood is searching
for him.
You may stay, but your crazy friend will have
to stay in the hayloft where I keep my wine,
so he won't bother anyone."
The priest and barber agreed.
Long past midnight, after everyone had gone
to bed, the priest awoke to the loud sound
of gushing liquid, as if a river had burst
into the inn.
Suddenly, Sancho Panza stumbled into the room,
covered in blood.
"My master is fighting a giant upstairs!
It's a bloodbath up there!"
The priest helped him up and tasted some of
the redness on his fingers.
"Sancho, this isn't blood, you simpleton.
It's wine!"
Sprinting up the stairs, the priest shuddered
when he saw what had happened.
There was Don Quixote, swinging his sword
and stabbing the huge pigskin sacks full of
wine hung from the ceiling.
"Ah ha!" cried Don Quixote as the wine splashed
out over him, blinding his eyes.
"Another fatal wound.
Soon there will be no more blood left in your
body.
Victory will be mine!"
The innkeeper raced upstairs screaming, "Oh
no, you're a madman.
My best wine is all gone.
My wife has sent for the Holy Brotherhood.
You'll pay for all of this damage!"
As the officers of the Holy Brotherhood arrived
to arrest Don Quixote, the priest came and
took one of the officers aside for a moment.
He explained that Don Quixote was crazy and
needed to be taken home for medical attention.
The priest also told the officer to have his
men put some chalk on their faces.
Soon after, Dorotea came to Don Quixote.
"Brave knight, you have slain the giant and
saved my father's kingdom.
I thank you."
"It was my pleasure, dear princess,' said
Don Quixote.
Suddenly the knight was surrounded by eight
ghostly figures with white faces.
One of them stepped forward and said,
"We are demons, sent by the evil wizard to
take you back to your village!
Get into this cage!"
Don Quixote tried to fight, but the eight
men seized him and locked him into the cage.
Don Quixote struggled to break free from the
cage until his strength was gone.
Then he fell asleep.
CHAPTER FOUR
New Quest
Don Quixote stayed in bed for several weeks.
His niece and housekeeper watched him closely,
hoping his knightly madness was finished.
One day, the barber and the priest visited
him.
"I'm fully recovered and ready to get back
to my old life," said Don Quixote.
"So old friend," asked the priest, "what do
you think our king should do about this Turkish
sultan who has threatened to attack our shores?"
"I would hold a jousting contest to find the
bravest knight in all of Spain," said Don
Quixote.
"Then I would send that single courageous
knight to conquer the sultan's armies."
Don Quixote sat up in bed, demonstrating the
sword thrusts to destroy the sultan's forces.
"Oh dear," said the barber to the priest,
"it seems as if our friend's sanity has not
returned.
We may have to employ more shocking tactics
to bring his mind back."
Suddenly Sancho squeezed into the room with
a grin on his face and gave the old knight
some good news.
"Last night I was at a party to welcome back
young Carrasco, who has been studying at Salamanca
University.
Before I could say 'hello', he told me he
had read about all of our adventures," said
Sancho.
"Somebody wrote a book called Don Quixote,
and it's the biggest bestseller in all of
Spain!"
"Bring him to me, my squire.
I must meet this young man," said Don Quixote.
A few minutes later, Sancho returned, leading
a young man with a chubby face and a mischievous
expression into the room.
Before Don Quixote could speak, the youth
fell onto his knees and said, "Oh, great knight,
I'm humbled to be in your excellent presence!"
Carrasco kept talking, trying to control his
giggles.
"In all the history of chivalry, no one can
find a braver, more extraordinary knight than
Don Quixote.
The book is beloved by every man and woman
in every social class.
The author is even talking about writing part
two!"
"Well then," cried Don Quixote, hopping out
of bed, "it's time to get back in the saddle.
My public needs me!"
Seven days later, Don Quixote and Sancho Panza
saddled their mounts and prepared to ride.
Carrasco was there to wish them farewell.
Suddenly the housekeeper and niece burst out
of the house and cried, "What's going on here?
Where's the priest?
He must stop this madness!"
Carrasco whispered to them, "Don't worry.
The priest and I have a plan to bring him
home.
You'll see in a day or two."
Then Don Quixote shouted farewell, and they
rode off.
"So what's our first move?" asked Sancho after
they had been riding for an hour.
"We are riding to El Toboso where you will
guide me to the palace of my mistress."
"Oh no," fretted Sancho.
"I'm not sure I can remember where she lives."
Later they found themselves riding around
the dark streets of El Toboso, hopelessly
lost.
Sancho convinced Don Quixote that they should
wait until morning to find Dulcinea.
After eating breakfast at their campsite,
Sancho rode off, trying to figure out what
to do.
As he was trying to think of a solution, Sancho
saw three peasant girls riding across the
plain on donkeys.
He had an idea.
He turned around and rode back to camp.
"Master, I have great news," he cried.
"Will she allow me to visit?"
Don Quixote asked hopefully.
"Polish your suit.
She couldn't wait for your visit.
She's riding here with two of her maids."
Don Quixote ran around in a panic.
Sancho helped him into his armor, and minutes
later they were riding through the trees.
"Where is she?"
cried Don Quixote.
"Over there," said Sancho, pointing to the
peasant girls who were riding past.
"All I see are three ugly girls on donkeys,"
said Don Quixote.
"But sir, those are the prettiest women I
have ever seen."
Don Quixote walked up to them and asked the
one in the middle, "Are you my mistress, Princess?
Are you Dulcinea, the sweetest rose in Spain?"
The girl let out a big laugh, "Sorry, Granddad,
I can't waste time talking with lunatics."
Then she kicked Sancho so hard he almost fell
off his donkey.
The girls rode off, leaving Don Quixote in
a cloud of dust.
"The evil wizard has changed my love into
a disgusting country wench!"
cried Don Quixote.
"It's terrible," cried Sancho, clapping his
hands with glee because his plan was working
so well.
"Now I am truly the Knight of the Long Face.
This evil wizard has struck me in my weakest
spot!
I must find a way to break his spell and restore
her beauty!"
Don Quixote spent the rest of that day crying
in the woods, reciting poetry about lost love.
Sancho contented himself with two salamis
and a leather cask of wine.
Suddenly Don Quixote hissed, "I hear two men
approaching in the forest."
"Where?" asked Sancho.
"On the other side of those bushes."
Then the two sat and listened.
"My lady, Casilda, is the most lovely woman
in Spain!" said the voice.
"And she has sent me, the Knight of the Forest,
on my mission to destroy all knights who would
disagree."
"This knight lies," whispered Don Quixote.
"You are mistaken!"
shouted Don Quixote, stepping out of the bushes
to face the knight.
"I must tell you that my Dulcinea is the most
beautiful woman on Earth."
"Then we must do battle," the other knight
replied coolly.
"We will joust at dawn," replied Don Quixote.
"Yes, but there is one condition.
The loser must return to his village and swear
to stay there and not enter any combat for
one year."
"I accept," answered Don Quixote.
The next morning at dawn, the knights met
on opposite sides of a clearing.
To the left of the Knight of the Forest was
his squire, a hunchback with a large purple
nose.
Without warning, the Knight of the Forest
spurred his steed into a gallop and charged
Don Quixote with his lance.
Don Quixote immediately raised his lance.
At the last moment, the Knight of the Forest's
horse neighed and refused to take another
step.
Don Quixote charged with all his might and
knocked the other knight out of his saddle.
Don Quixote quickly jumped down from Rocinante,
drawing his sword and holding it to the downed
knight's neck.
"Do you surrender?"
Don Quixote demanded.
"Yes," cried the Knight of the Forest, "I'm
finished."
Then Don Quixote commanded Sancho to remove
the knight's helmet.
"Well," cried Sancho, "this knight looks like
that youth Carrasco!"
"Yes, he does," agreed Don Quixote.
"The power of this evil wizard to change people's
faces is amazing."
"No, I really am Carrasco," sobbed the student.
"It would be safer to kill him now," said
Sancho.
Don Quixote raised his sword to strike, but
the hunchback rushed over and flung off his
robe.
It was Don Quixote's friend, the barber.
"Put your sword away," he said.
"Amazing," said Don Quixote, "This evil wizard
never stops."
The barber dragged Carrasco away toward their
campsite, cursing him for not being better
in a joust.
The next morning found Don Quixote and Sancho
Panza riding through a wheat field.
The victory over the Knight of the Forest
left Don Quixote feeling unstoppable.
He didn't suspect for a moment that it had
been a plot hatched by the priest to bring
him back to the village.
Stepping onto the road, the knight and his
squire came upon a royal cart.
Raising his lance, Don Quixote blocked the
cart and said, "Halt, or I'll slice you in
two.
I demand to know what you have in this cart."
"A lion," called one of the cart drivers,
"A gift to our king from an African prince."
"Dangerous?"
asked Don Quixote.
"It's thirsty for blood.
It's even more dangerous because it's hungry.
So clear off, old man, before you get hurt."
"I am Don Quixote," proclaimed the knight.
"And I'm not afraid of any pussy cats!"
Then he swung his lance below the driver's
nose.
"Open the cage!"
Sancho and the driver's mate quickly ran up
a nearby hill, while Don Quixote positioned
himself in front of the lion's cage, and the
driver prepared to pull a rope that would
open it.
"Will you reconsider?" asked the driver.
"Don Quixote does not fear danger!"
shouted the knight.
"Pull!"
The door crashed open, and a gigantic lion
stuck his head into the air.
His jaws were black and covered with thick
drool, his teeth yellow and curved like knives.
The lion's eyes blazed as if on fire.
"I'm waiting for you, King of the jungle,"
Don Quixote cried fearlessly.
"Are you afraid to come out?"
The lion stared at the old knight for a moment,
and then yawned and went to sleep.
"This lion is a coward!"
shouted Don Quixote.
"Driver, rattle his cage.
Make him roar!"
"I will not!"
replied the driver, dropping the rope that
closed the lion's cage.
"You are the bravest man in Spain.
No one else would go up against a man-killer."
"Will you swear to our king?" asked Don Quixote.
"He will receive a full report of your bravery,"
replied the driver.
Don Quixote signaled to Sancho and the driver's
mate that it was safe to return.
"From this day on," announced Don Quixote,
"I wish to be known as the Knight of the Lions.
Men will tell tales of this adventure hundreds
of years to come!"
CHAPTER FIVE
The Final Adventures
Sancho grumbled and sulked for three days
as Don Quixote led them through the forest.
Their food was almost gone, and the squire
had to go to sleep hungry, under a damp blanket
worrying about wolves and other predators.
Don Quixote was proud of their sufferings,
often reminding Sancho that "a hard life makes
a brave heart."
On the fourth day, at sunset, they came across
a group of riders.
Among them was a lady dressed in green velvet.
She sat atop a majestic white stallion and
held a falcon on her arm.
"A huntress," gasped Don Quixote.
"Perhaps even a princess.
She'll certainly want to be introduced to
me."
"She probably just wants us to mind our own
business," Sancho replied with a grin.
Ignoring his squire, the knight commanded
him, "Ride over there and introduce me."
Sancho groaned and spurred his donkey in the
group's direction.
"My lady," he called.
"My master, the Knight of the Lions, formerly
known as the Knight of the Long Face, wishes
to
"Wait," interrupted the lady, "Did you say
the Knight of the Long Face?"
"Yes, and I'm his squire, Sancho..."
"Panza?"
interrupted the lady again with a smile.
"Yes," gulped Sancho.
"Do you know about us?"
"Of course," she replied.
"I've read the book of your adventures.
It's my husband's and my favorite book!"
"Shall I bring him over then?" asked Sancho.
"You must do more than that," said the lady.
"You and your master must come to our nearby
castle as distinguished guests of my husband,
the Duke."
The Duchess giggled when Sancho accepted her
invitation.
In truth, she and her husband thought the
book Don Quixote was the finest comedy ever
written.
She and her husband were great jokers, and
she figured they would be able to have some
fun with the crazy knight and his dim-witted
sidekick.
The group with Don Quixote and Sancho soon
crossed a drawbridge and found themselves
inside a vast, opulent castle.
Two trumpeters sounded the knight's arrival,
and a group of maidens surrounded them, fanning
jars of perfume.
That night, the knight and his squire ate
the best meal of their lives while chatting
with their hosts.
The Duke and Duchess listened with great interest
about all of their recent adventures.
But their greatest interest was in hearing
news of Dulcinea.
When they asked about Dulcinea, the knight
replied sadly, "My beautiful lady has been
transformed into a vulgar, donkey-riding trollop
by an evil wizard."
"How terrible!"
gasped the Duchess, barely able to contain
her laughter.
The next day, the Duke and Duchess convinced
Don Quixote to accompany them on a wild boar
hunt in the forest.
But they had made secret plans to play a big
joke on the knight and his squire.
While they were hunting, there was a sudden
noise coming through the trees.
"My men must have found a boar.
It's coming toward us.
Beware its tusks!" said the Duchess.
But when the trees parted, there was no wild
boar.
Rather, a black stallion came prancing and
kicking before them.
On its back rode a man, covered in twigs,
leaves, and ivy.
"I am the forest sprite!"
the strange figure wearing a green mask with
horns on top of his head shouted.
"The demons of the forest have sent me with
a message for the knight-errant, Don Quixote
de La Mancha!"
"I am Don Quixote," replied the knight.
"To free your lady from their spell," the
sprite continued, "you must do two things.
First of all, your squire must lash himself."
"How many times?"
screamed Sancho.
"Three thousand, three hundred times."
Sancho gasped in disbelief.
"But first, you must ride a flying horse through
the air and over the mountains.
This horse waits for you at the Duke's castle.
If you are brave enough to perform these two
tasks, your beloved Dulcinea will be set free,"
said the forest sprite.
Then the creature turned and rode away.
"It's a miracle!"
cried the Duchess, "We must return to the
castle at once!"
"Yes, but first, Sancho, fetch me a whip,"
shouted Don Quixote.
"You can begin lashing yourself while we ride!"
The terrified squire had already ridden away
from the knight's grasp.
Back at the castle, the servants were rushing
around, shouting alarm from the towers.
There was a giant wooden horse in the middle
of the courtyard.
The servants told the Duke it had suddenly
and mysteriously dropped from the sky.
Meanwhile, Don Quixote and Sancho were arguing
about the lashes the squire must suffer to
free Dulcinea.
"I won't do it," cried the squire.
"For the sake of my lady, I beg you," sobbed
the knight.
The Duchess approached them.
"You two must cease your squabbling," she
said, leading them into the courtyard.
She was enjoying every moment of this grand
practical joke she had planned with her husband.
Don Quixote stared up at the wooden horse
in amazement.
"What a creature!
It must be twenty feet tall!"
Sancho's knees knocked together in fear.
There was a rope ladder on the side which
they climbed up.
Seeing them mount the wooden horse, the Duke
and Duchess could hardly control their laughter.
When the two seated themselves on top of the
horse, Sancho found there was nothing to hold
on to.
So he grabbed onto Don Quixote's trouser belt
with both hands.
"There is a carving in the wood here!"
exclaimed Don Quixote.
"It says we have to blindfold ourselves.
Anyone who rides this magic horse without
a blindfold will be struck dead!"
"I've got a handkerchief!" said Sancho.
He pulled out his handkerchief, tore it in
two, and gave half to his master.
The two fixed the smelly halves of handkerchief
around their faces.
From a balcony, the Duchess and Duke squealed
with pleasure at the sight of the two fools
on the horse.
Once their eyes were covered, a servant tapped
on the horse, and the servants inside lifted
it three feet off the ground and rocked it
from side to side.
"We're up in the clouds, Sancho," cried Don
Quixote,
"I'm feeling airsick," moaned Sancho.
On a balcony across from the knight and squire,
four maidens were pumping a pair of bellows
and dousing them with cups of water.
"Hold on, Sancho.
We're flying through a rainstorm!"
called Don Quixote.
At this point, the Duke and Duchess were laughing
their socks off.
But they were also beginning to feel guilty
for playing such a prank on the good knight.
The Duke signaled to his butler for the grand
finale.
A servant lit the horse's tail on fire.
There was a "POP" and a "FIZZ" as hundreds
of fireworks hidden inside the tail exploded.
Sancho wrapped his arms around the knight
and howled, "Save me, Master.
I promise I'll suffer the lashing!"
"All of them?" asked Don Quixote.
"Every one!"
cried Sancho.
Then Don Quixote beat the top of the horse
with his fist.
But this only made the men inside rock it
harder.
Finally, they tilted it too far, and the wooden
horse crashed to the ground.
Sancho and the knight were thrown to safety,
landing on the soft grass of the castle lawn.
Quickly the servants carried the horse away.
By the time Don Quixote and Sancho tore the
rags from their eyes, they were facing the
Duchess who leaned over them, acting concerned.
"Welcome back," she said softly, "You've been
gone for hours.
We were so worried.
How was the ride?"
Sancho and Don Quixote rested for a few days.
Then the knight announced it was time for
them to leave.
"But what about Sancho's lashing?"
asked the Duchess, who didn't want to miss
out on the spectacle.
"He'll have to carry out the lashes while
we travel.
Life at court is softening my sword arm.
It is time for us to go.
I thank you for your hospitality."
Don Quixote and Sancho Panza rode away toward
the sea and the city of Barcelona.
The next morning, Don Quixote told Sancho,
"I want to see you do some whipping right
now."
"Don't rush me," cried Sancho, jumping to
his feet.
"And I prefer to perform my lashing in private."
"I don't care how you do it, but I want to
hear each lash so I know you're not shirking."
"Fine," snapped Sancho, "I'll get started."
He grabbed the whip and stomped off into the
trees.
Then he unbuttoned his shirt and cracked the
whip against the trunk of the tree.
"Ow!" he yelled.
"That one almost drew blood!"
A few days later, when Don Quixote and Sancho
rode into Barcelona, word had already spread
of their arrival.
The streets were filled with citizens trying
to get a glimpse of the crazy yet noble knight.
People threw flowers and cheered.
The leader of their escort allowed Don Quixote
and Sancho to stay in his luxurious villa
in the middle of the city.
For two weeks they lived like kings.
They were paid daily visits by generals, admirals,
and high-ranking public officials.
Each morning, Don Quixote would take Rocinante
for a trot along the beach.
Then one day, as he was on his morning jaunt,
he saw a figure approaching him from down
the beach.
The figure was a knight, wearing a full suit
of armor with his visor lowered.
When Don Quixote neared the knight, he could
see a white crescent emblem on his chest.
"Halt, the Knight of the Lions!"
called the Knight of the White Moon.
"I have a challenge for you."
"Don Quixote is always ready for a challenge,"
the old hidalgo answered bravely.
"Then we will joust," said the strange knight,
raising a shiny new lance.
"Name your terms," called Don Quixote.
"If you win, this fine horse and my new lance
are yours.
If I am the victor, you must retire from your
career as a knight-errant."
"Retire?"
cried Don Quixote.
"But that is impossible."
"We young knights are tired of you getting
all of the public's attention.
We want you to return to your village for
a year and live a peaceful life."
"I accept your terms!"
snapped Don Quixote.
Then both knights turned away from each other
and checked their weapons.
When they turned, the Knight of the White
Moon spurred his horse into a gallop and thrust
his lance toward Don Quixote.
He held his lance with such precision that
the elderly knight didn't have a chance and
was thrown from his saddle.
He landed in the shallow water and sand of
the beach.
In a flash, the Knight of the White Moon dismounted
and pressed his sword to Don Quixote's neck.
"You are vanquished.
Do you concede?"
demanded the Knight of the White Moon.
"But it means the end of my life," sobbed
Don Quixote.
"Without chivalry, I am nothing."
"You gave your word," snarled the victor.
"I will retire," coughed Don Quixote, "as
I promised."
The knight's tears of defeat mixed with the
salt water of the waves.
"This is the darkest day of all my adventures,"
he moaned.
But the Knight of the White Moon showed no
mercy and rode off on his stallion.
The broken hidalgo sat, sobbing in the surf.
Later, Don Quixote hobbled back to town.
He never realized that the Knight of the White
Moon was actually the youth, Carrasco.
In the months since he had been defeated as
the Knight of the Forest, he had studied jousting
and horsemanship.
He was determined to have his revenge on Don
Quixote and to return the crazy hidalgo to
his friends in the village.
When Sancho heard of Don Quixote's defeat
and retirement, he sobbed.
"You can't quit, Sire. Old dogs don't learn
new tricks."
"I promised.
Now help me take off my armor.
I no longer need it."
As the two began their three-day journey home,
they lamented their fate.
One night, the two men made camp by a stream.
Sancho had been trying to lift the broken-hearted
knight's spirits all day.
"Can I do anything to make you feel better?"
he asked.
"If I knew my lady was safe," said Don Quixote,
"I might be able to smile again."
So Sancho wandered off into the nearby woods
and lashed a tree letting out blood-chilling
cries with each crack of the whip.
When Sancho had lashed all the bark off the
tree, Don Quixote told him he had finished
a thousand lashes and he stopped for the day.
"I am proud of you," Don Quixote told him
warmly.
"If you can manage a thousand per night, Dulcinea
will be free by the time we reach our village."
They rode hard each day, passing by many sights
of past adventures.
Each night, Sancho found a suitable tree to
whip and rack up another thousand lashes.
On the fourth morning, he completed the final
two hundred and forty-eight lashes.
Don Quixote shook his hand and promised to
double his salary if they ever went questing
again.
When Don Quixote rode into the courtyard of
his home, the housekeeper dropped her basket
of laundry in the dust.
"Master, you're back in one piece," she cried.
"I am weak," whispered Don Quixote, "Sancho,
help me to my room."
Back in his bed, the old hidalgo slipped into
a sleep that lasted for six days.
The fever he had gotten grew stronger each
day.
He cried and moaned in his sleep, as if being
haunted by nightmares.
Meanwhile, his friends waited patiently by
his bedside.
After a week, he opened his eyes to see the
priest and the barber sitting at the end of
his bed.
"I am back," muttered the old knight.
"Don Quixote!"
they shouted, rushing to his side.
"My name is Alonso Quixano," said the man
in the bed.
"I was mad, but now my mind is restored."
"Is it true?
Are all your thoughts of chivalry and wizards
really gone from your head?" asked the priest.
"They are all gone," he replied softly.
"I am sane enough to know that I am dying."
The news that the hidalgo was on his deathbed
raced around the village.
Sancho came running in from the fields where
he had been at work.
He was shown into the room and knelt down
at his former master's side.
"Perhaps you were a little crazy," Sancho
sobbed, "but if you were still a knight, you
would not die."
"Your friend who was a knight," replied the
hidalgo, "is no longer here.
You must forget him."
"I cannot," sobbed the squire.
Sancho tried to convince his old friend not
to give up the ghost.
But the old hidalgo was overcome with fever.
Sancho waited at his bedside for three days
until finally, the old knight slipped away.
This was the end of the brave knight, Don
Quixote de La Mancha.
In his madness, he accomplished feats that
ordinary men can only dream of.
The stories of his amazing adventures have
been told for more than four hundred years.
Rest in peace, noble Don Quixote.
May the questing be grand and the adventures
bring you glory...