CHAPTER ONE
A Short History
Back in England's oldest times, people lived
in big groups called tribes.
They were farmers - they grew their food,
and kept animals for meat and eggs.
They lived in villages, in wooden or mud houses,
and there was often fighting between the different
tribes.
Life was simple but dangerous.
Then in AD 43, forty thousand Roman soldiers
invaded England from the area of Europe that
is now Italy.
The Roman army was very well-organized and
had good weapons.
The soldiers built a wall around themselves
every night so they were safe.
They moved across the country, fighting and
winning battles against the different tribes,
and after four years they controlled the south
of England.
The Romans had to fight for many years before
they controlled all of England.
They made many changes in the country, such
as building towns and cities, and good roads.
They brought a new language to England - Latin
- and made laws, so people knew what they
could and could not do.
The religion of Christianity came to England
in Roman times too.
The Romans never took control of Scotland,
which is north of England, and Scottish tribes
came to fight against them in the north of
England again and again.
Because of this, in the second century AD,
the Romans built a wall to stop the Scottish
tribes coming to England.
This wall between England and Scotland was
one hundred and twenty kilometers long, and
was called Hadrian's Wall.
For English people in towns and cities, life
in Roman times was good.
Towns now had clean water and sewers (pipes
taking away dirty water), and there were strong
walls around them, so people felt safe.
People came to the towns to buy and sell things,
and food became more interesting and enjoyable.
To relax, people could go to special bath
houses, where they met their friends, kept
clean and exercised.
But after AD 250, Roman soldiers began to
leave England.
They had to fight in other parts of the world,
and it was too expensive and difficult for
them to keep England safe.
By AD 411, all the Roman soldiers had left
England.
Then the Anglo-Saxons, from Germany, the Netherlands
and Denmark, began to arrive.
The Anglo-Saxons had come to England several
times before, but the Romans had always defeated
them.
Now, with the Romans gone, the English could
not win battles against the Anglo-Saxons,
and many Anglo-Saxons came to live in England.
The Anglo-Saxons did not like the Romans'
towns, so they did not use them, and the towns
stayed empty.
The AngloSaxons built their own villages near
rivers or the sea and made wooden houses.
In their villages, they grew crops - plants
they could use for food.
They also kept pigs, sheep and cows, and caught
fish and other animals.
By AD 600 in England, the AngloSaxons had
made seven kingdoms - different parts of the
country, each controlled by its own king.
The four main kingdoms were Northumbria, Mercia,
East Anglia and Wessex.
The three minor kingdoms were Essex, Kent
and Sussex.
In each of these kingdoms, the king had nobles
- important men who fought for him.
The other people in the kingdom were either
peasants or slaves.
Peasants were poor people who had some land,
but had to give money to the nobles.
Slaves had nothing and had to work for other
people for no money at all.
People bought and sold slaves like animals.
The Anglo-Saxons stayed in England, but in
AD 793 a new group of people invaded the country.
The Vikings, from Norway, Sweden and Denmark,
wanted good farming land.
They came to England in strong wooden ships,
and soon they took control of many parts of
the country.
But the Anglo-Saxon king of Wessex, Alfred
the Great, won a big battle against the Vikings.
After this, part of England, called Danelaw,
was given to the Vikings, but the Vikings
had to promise not to invade other parts of
the country.
After Alfred the Great died, the Viking and
Anglo-Saxon parts of England came together,
and England was now ruled as one country with
one king.
The Vikings and the Anglo-Saxons continued
to fight a lot, and for a while England had
Viking kings, but by 1042, the Anglo-Saxon
King Edward ruled England.
With Edward as the king, London became the
most important city in England.
Edward had many nobles, and he let them become
very powerful.
He had no children, so when he died, one of
his nobles, Harold, became the king.
But Edward's cousin William, a Norman (from
the north of France), believed that he should
be the king of England.
In October 1066, William brought a big Norman
army from France to England.
The Normans fought against Harold and his
soldiers at the Battle of Hastings.
Harold was killed, and William the Conqueror,
as he was called, became the king of England.
William the Conqueror made many important
changes in England.
A lot of castles were built.
One of these was the Tower of London, which
you can visit today.
William the Conqueror brought the feudal system
to England.
In the feudal system, the richest and most
important person was the king.
Below the king were the nobles, then the knights
and then the serfs, who were the poorest people
in the land.
The king owned everything in the country,
but he gave a castle and land to his nobles,
and they paid him money.
The nobles gave land to the knights, who had
to fight battles for the nobles and the king.
The knights gave some land to the serfs, who
had to work for the knights and give them
food from the land.
William the Conqueror wanted to know exactly
what he had in England.
He sent people all around the country, asking
many questions, and they made a big book called
the Domesday Book.
The book showed how much farming land there
was in England and how many animals.
We know a lot about life in Norman England
because of the Domesday Book.
The time from William the Conqueror's rule
until the fifteenth century in England is
often called the Middle Ages.
In the Middle Ages, most people lived in villages.
The people of the village had to work for
the nobles, and give them crops and animals.
The nobles lived very well, in big houses
and with expensive food, but most people were
very poor.
Religion was very important in the Middle
Ages, and the Catholic Church became very
powerful.
From 1095 to 1291, soldiers went to other
countries to fight religious battles.
There was more fighting in the fourteenth
and fifteenth centuries, as France and England
fought the Hundred Years War, hoping to win
land from each other.
Many of the battles of the Hundred Years War
were fought by knights.
As well as fighting battles for nobles and
for the king, knights also fought as a sport
in competitions called jousting tournaments.
Young men who wanted to become knights had
to spend many years learning all the things
that a knight could do.
In 1348, a terrible illness called The Black
Death came to England.
Only about four million people lived in England
at that time, but in two years, nearly one-and-a-half
million of them died.
From 1455-1485, there were terrible battles
between people who wanted the kings of the
country to be from different families, and
many more people died.
Finally, in 1485, Henry Tudor became the first
Tudor king of England, King Henry the Seventh.
Some of the Tudor kings and queens are now
very famous in England's history.
Henry the Eighth, who became the king in 1509,
lived some of the time at the Tower of London,
but he had other beautiful palaces in and
around London, including the Palace of Westminster
and Hampton Court.
He and the people around him lived very well.
They wore the best clothes and ate wonderful
food, and at the palaces there was always
dancing, sport, poetry and music.
Henry enjoyed life, and he drank and ate too
much.
When he became the king, he was a sporty,
good-looking young man, but later he became
so fat he could not walk!
England was a Catholic country, but Henry
the Eighth wanted England to leave the Catholic
Church, so he started a new church.
It was a Protestant church (a Christian church,
but for people who believe in a different
kind of Christianity) called the Church of
England, and he controlled it.
Anyone who disagreed with the new church was
executed - killed for their crime.
When Henry the Eighth was ruling England,
more than seventy thousand people were killed
because of crimes, or because they disagreed
with the king about religion or other important
things.
Six years after Henry the Eighth died, his
oldest daughter Mary - the daughter he had
with his first wife, Catherine of Aragon - became
Queen Mary the First of England.
She was a Catholic and wanted England to be
a Catholic country again, but many people
had left the Catholic Church and had become
Protestants.
Mary executed hundreds of Protestants who
refused to become Catholic again.
But in 1558, Mary died, and her half-sister
Elizabeth - the daughter Henry had with his
second wife Anne Boleyn - became the queen.
Queen Elizabeth the First was a Protestant,
but she did not make Catholics follow her
religion, and she soon became one of the best
loved of England's kings and queens.
The second half of the sixteenth century,
which was known as the Elizabethan period,
was a very important time for English literature.
Many people liked to go to the theatre, and
William Shakespeare wrote a lot of plays and
poetry at this time.
Ships also began to travel to other parts
of the world.
Sir Walter Raleigh sailed to America, and
Sir Francis Drake became the first Englishman
to sail around the world.
But life in England was also very difficult
for many people in the Elizabethan period.
There was less work in farming now, and a
lot of people were very poor.
There was a lot of crime, but no police, and
when people were caught for crimes, they were
often executed.
Alter Queen Elizabeth the First died in 1603,
kings and queens called the Stuarts came to
power in England.
The Stuarts were from Scotland, and for the
first time, they ruled both England and Scotland.
The second of the Stuart kings was Charles
the First.
He argued with Parliament because he spent
a lot of money fighting wars in Europe, and
in 1642, he started a civil war.
For seven years, the King's men and Parliaments
men fought against each other, and thousands
died.
But with Oliver Cromwell as leader, Parliaments
army became very strong and fought very well,
and in 1649, they won the war.
Charles the First was executed, and for eleven
years England had no king or queen.
The country was ruled by Cromwell and Parliament.
Cromwell was a Puritan - a Protestant who
believed in a simple, hard-working life - and
when he ruled, there was no sport or dancing
in England, and theatres were closed.
When Cromwell died, England was ready to have
a king again, and the Stuarts came to power
once more.
There were some difficult times for England
in the second half of the seventeenth century.
In 1665, another terrible illness came to
London and killed nearly seventy thousand
people, and a year later, large parts of London
were burnt down in the Great Fire of London.
There were many other changes at this time
too.
England now traded - bought and sold things
- with many other countries, so English people
could get different foods like tomatoes, chocolate,
coffee and tea for the first time.
People continued to work on the land, but
now there were other jobs, in cloth-making
or glass-making, and in the coal or iron industries.
London was rebuilt with wider roads and many
beautiful new buildings, and scientists like
Sir Isaac Newton began to do important work
and learn many interesting things.
England started its first colonies too.
These were other parts of the world, like
America, which were ruled by England.
For the first time in the seventeenth century,
people from England went to live and work
in these places.
There was one more important change as England
entered the eighteenth century.
In 1707, the Act of Union brought England,
Wales and Scotland together with one parliament
as Great Britain.
The eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries
were called the Georgian period because Britain's
kings were George the First, Second, Third
and Fourth.
But during this time, kings became much less
powerful, and Parliament really began to rule
the country.
An industrial revolution began in Britain
too: machines were built, and they were used
in many different industries.
People could now make many things very quickly,
and because of this towns began to grow.
In 1783, Britain lost the American War of
Independence, so America was no longer ruled
by Britain and became independent.
Britain did not have its old American colonies
anymore, but it now found new ones.
In that same year, France gave its colonies
in Canada to Britain, and by the end of the
eighteenth century, Britain had won many battles
in India, which soon became an important part
of the British Empire.
This was a great time for exploration: travelling
to different places to find new things.
The famous sailor Captain Cook visited many
new lands and was the first European to go
to Australia and New Zealand.
In 1801, Ireland and Britain came together
as the United Kingdom (UK) with one parliament.
(Today, Northern Ireland is the only part
of Ireland which belongs to the UK.)
The ruler of this new UK, from 1837 until
1901, was Queen Victoria.
Victoria ruled for longer than any other English
or British king or queen, and she was much
loved by many of her people.
In the Victorian period, the British
Empire became bigger and more important, and
the industrial revolution continued.
The country was growing, but at first this
made life difficult for many people.
More and more factories were built in the
UK, and factory work was very hard and very
dangerous.
Towns got bigger and bigger, but people put
their rubbish and dirty water in the streets,
so there was a lot of illness.
But soon important new changes started to
happen.
Towns became cleaner, and in 1880, all children
aged 5-10 began to go to school.
People had electric lights and telephones
for the first time, and because the railways
grew, they could now travel around the country
easily.
By 1901, when Queen Victoria died, the modern
United Kingdom was arriving.
CHAPTER TWO
England in the Modern UK
In the early 1900s, the UK was one of the
most powerful countries in the world, with
a big empire.
The industrial revolution was changing many
peoples lives, and steamships and cars were
widely used for the first time.
Rich people lived very well, with beautiful
houses and servants, but poor people had few
clothes and little to eat, and their children
were often ill.
Life was difficult for women in the UK at
this time too.
People expected women to stay at home with
their families, and they could not get well-paid
jobs.
It was very difficult for women to go to university,
and they could not vote.
In 1903, a group of women called the suffragettes,
led by Emmeline Pankhurst, organized meetings
and marches, asking for Parliament to give
women the vote.
In 1914, the UK and its allies, France and
Russia, went to war with Germany and Austria-Hungary.
Many young men chose to fight.
They believed the war would be very short,
but it went on for four years, and nearly
three quarters of a million soldiers from
the UK were killed.
While the men were fighting, women had to
do the men's jobs at home.
Women soon showed that they could work in
farming, factories and even in the coal industry.
After helping their country to win the First
World War, workers and women in England wanted
better lives.
Men got their jobs at home back from the women,
so most women were no longer working, but
in 1918, women over thirty were given the
vote for the first time.
From 1929, women, like men, could vote from
the age of twenty-one.
A new political party for working people - the
Labour Party - became important in politics
at this time, and in 1926, half a million
workers went on strike to fight against low
pay and long working hours.
But life became even more difficult for workers
in 1929, when the world went into an economic
depression.
Prices fell, there was less trade, and many
shops and factories closed.
By 1931, nearly three million people in the
UK had lost their jobs.
The First World War was fought mainly in battles
on fields in France, but almost everyone in
the UK had a difficult life because of the
Second World War (1939-45).
Many children had to leave their homes and
go to live in the countryside.
This was because at the end of 1940 and the
beginning of 1941, the Germans dropped many
bombs on London and other cities.
This was called the Blitz.
Many people lost their homes and their families,
and everyone had to live on rations - they
could only buy fixed amounts of many kinds
of food.
'When we heard the air raid warning in the
middle of the night, everyone woke up and
got into the shelters.
The Second World War ended in 1945, and big
changes were made by a new Labour government.
Most importantly, the UK now had a National
Health Service, so anyone who was ill could
see a doctor or go to hospital without paying.
The government also now gave money to help
people who were ill or old, or had lost their
jobs.
Because of the Education Act of 1944, there
were also free places in schools for children
up to the age of fifteen.
Another change after the Second World War
was that more women went to work.
They had shown that they could do men's jobs,
and many of them had done important war work.
In some homes, nothing was different for women,
but over the next fifty years, women in the
UK slowly saw changes for themselves in education,
work and at home.
Their lives would never be the same again.
After the Second World War, many of the UK's
colonies wanted to rule themselves.
The south of Ireland had already become independent
from the UK in 1921, so the country had now
become the United Kingdom of Great Britain
and Northern Ireland.
People from the colonies had fought for the
UK during the war, and they felt they had
won their freedom.
In 1947, India, once a very important part
of the Empire, became independent.
In the next twenty years, most of the other
colonies also did the same.
They became independent, but joined the Commonwealth,
an organization of the governments of the
UK's old colonies.
The UK needed more workers to help rebuild
the country after the war, so the government
invited other Europeans and people from the
colonies of the old Empire to move there.
Hoping to find good new jobs, many people
came, mainly from Europe, India, Pakistan
and the West Indies.
In 1945, there were only a few thousand non-white
people in the UK, but by 1970, there were
1.4 million.
Sadly, there were often problems in later
years when some of the people born in the
UK felt that immigrants and their families
were taking too many jobs.
There is some racism - when people do not
like others because they have a different
colour skin - in the UK today.
But most people do not like racism and want
all people in the UK to live together happily.
In 1952, Elizabeth the Second became the new
queen of the UK, and millions of people watched
her coronation on TV.
The first TVs were made in the 1920s, but
many English people bought TVs for the first
time for the coronation, and in the 1950s,
TV started to become an important part of
life in England.
There were many changes in the UK in the second
half of the twentieth century.
Many of the country's traditional industries,
for example iron, cloth, coal and shipbuilding,
began to have problems, and people working
in those industries lost their jobs.
New industries became more important, for
example banking and pharmaceuticals (drugs
and medicines).
England today is a very different place than
it was one hundred years ago.
Today, England is one of the most multicultural
countries in the world, and many people from
the West Indies, Africa, India, China, South-East
Asia and eastern Europe live here.
More than two hundred and fifty different
languages are spoken in London!
Probably because of this, there are also many
religions in England.
England is a Christian country, but different
religions are freely followed, and there are
many Hindu, Jewish, Muslim, Sikh and Buddhist
people here.
Society has changed in England too.
One hundred years ago, most people married
in their early twenties or younger and then
had children, but today many more people live
alone, and most do not get married or have
children until they are in their thirties
or older.
England's place in the world, as part of the
UK, is also very different.
The UK does not have an empire now, but it
is an important country in Europe and became
a member of the European Union (then called
the EEC) in 1973.
The UK works very closely with the United
States of America (USA), and it also continues
to be a member of the Commonwealth, together
with fifty-two other countries from around
the world.
Members of the Commonwealth meet every two
years to decide how they can best work together.
CHAPTER THREE
Traditions
Because England is such an old country, it
has many traditions.
Some of these have come from important or
interesting moments in history.
Some have come from other parts of the world.
Others have come from England's many kings
or queens, or from its long religious history.
There are special days and festivals throughout
the year in England, but only a few are bank
holidays - days when people do not have to
work.
Christmas is one of the most important religious
festivals in England.
Christmas Day, 25th December, and the next
day, Boxing Day, are always bank holidays,
and most people spend this time with family
or friends.
Traditionally, people eat turkey on Christmas
Day, with Brussels sprouts and cranberry sauce;
and for dessert there is usually Christmas
pudding, a type of cake made with dried fruit.
Not long before Christmas, people decorate42
their houses and send cards to people they
know.
On Christmas Day, there are presents from
friends and family, and, for the children,
from Father Christmas (or Santa Claus).
Children believe that Father Christmas brings
the presents on 24th December, Christmas Eve,
and leaves them to be opened on the morning
of Christmas Day.
New Year's Eve is also important in England.
Many people go to the Houses of Parliament
in London to hear Big Ben (the bell inside
the big clock tower) strike midnight and to
see the wonderful fireworks near the River
Thames.
Other people meet up with friends and family,
and make New Year's Resolutions: they decide
what things they will do (or not do!) in the
next year.
On Valentine's Day, 14th February, people
give cards or presents to the people they
love, but April Fool's Day, on 1st April,
is a very different kind of celebration.
On that day, people play jokes on their friends
and family, and call them an 'April Fool!'.
People think April Fool's Day started because,
before 1562, 1st April was the first day of
the year.
In 1562, this was changed, so 1st January
became the first day of the year.
But many people were slow to remember the
change, so they were laughed at for celebrating
New Year's Day on 1st April.
There is often special food for festivals
in England.
Shrove Tuesday, in February, comes the day
before the start of Lent, the forty days before
Easter.
In the past, people stopped eating the most
important foods - butter, eggs and flour - during
Lent.
So on Shrove Tuesday, they made pancakes with
these foods, and ate butter, eggs and flour
for the last time.
People continue to eat pancakes today, and
there are many pancake races around the country:
people have to run, throwing pancakes up and
down in a frying pan!
Today, many people try to give something up
for Lent too - often sweets, cakes or chocolate!
After Lent comes Easter, another religious
festival, and for people who go to church,
a very important time of year.
Easter comes in the spring, and many people
give each other Easter eggs and Easter bunnies
(little rabbits) made from chocolate.
For children, there are often Easter Egg Hunts,
when little eggs are hidden in the house or
garden.
People also eat hot cross buns at Easter - warm
sweet bread with dried fruit inside and a
cross on top.
May Day in England is on the first day of
May, and there is a bank holiday on or very
near that day.
This is usually the start of warmer weather
in England, and sometimes people celebrate
with Maypole dancing - dancing around a big
pole with ribbons.
Halloween, on 31st October, has become a popular
festival in modern times.
On this night, children dress up as witches,
ghosts and other frightening things, and go
from house to house, calling 'Trick or Treat'.
The neighbours give them sweets and other
nice things, but if they have nothing to give,
the children play a trick, or joke, on them.
A strange festival is held on 5th November.
On that day in 1605, a man called Guy Fawkes
and a group of friends tried to blow up the
Houses of Parliament.
They wanted to do this because King James
and his nobles were not treating the Catholics
in the country well.
But the king's soldiers found Guy Fawkes in
the Houses of Parliament and stopped him and
his friends.
Now on 5th November every year, there are
bonfires and fireworks all over England on
'Guy Fawkes Night'.
Another day that is important because of something
in history is Remembrance Day, on 11th November.
At eleven o'clock in the morning on that day,
at exactly the time when the First World War
ended in 1918, many people are silent for
two minutes.
They remember the many men and women who have
lost their lives in wars.
Many people wear paper poppies - red flowers
- on their coats at this time too.
Poppies grew on the battlefields of France
after the First World War ended, so they make
people remember the terrible days of the war.
Because kings and queens have always been
so important in England's history, there are
many royal traditions.
One important tradition is the State Opening
of Parliament.
On this day, the Queen goes from her home
at Buckingham Palace to the Houses of Parliament
in a gold carriage and then reads 'the Queen's
speech'.
This tells people what the government wants
to do in the next year.
Another important yearly royal tradition is
called 'Trooping the Colour'.
To celebrate the Queen's birthday, more than
a thousand soldiers and musicians march from
Buckingham Palace to Whitehall and back again,
and the Queen goes past them in her carriage.
On most days at Buckingham Palace, you can
also see the 'Changing of the Guard'.
This is when one group of soldiers who were
guarding the Queen leave the palace, and another
group arrives.
The soldiers who guard the Queen wear red
coats and tall hats, made from real bearskin.
They can march in front of the palace, but
when they are standing, they must not move.
There are many important traditions in sport
in England.
One famous example is the Oxford and Cambridge
boat race.
Oxford and Cambridge are the two oldest universities
in England, and because both universities
are in cities with rivers, Oxford and Cambridge
students have always enjoyed rowing.
In rowing, two, four or eight people move
a boat through water with long wooden sticks
called oars.
They sit with their backs towards the front
of the boat, so there is often a person called
a cox at the back, telling them where to go.
In 1829, students from Oxford and Cambridge
decided to have a rowing race, and since then
there has been a race on the Thames every
year in spring.
The Oxford and Cambridge boat race: Oxford
in dark blue, Cambridge in light blue
What is traditional English food and drink?
Fish and chips are probably England's most
famous dish.
Fish and chips first became popular in the
1860s, when the railways opened and trains
began to bring fish from the east coast of
England to the cities.
Fish and chips are usually eaten as takeaway
food (food that is not eaten in a cafe or
restaurant), with the fish wrapped in paper,
and the chips covered in salt and vinegar.
Today, Indian and Chinese takeaways are just
as popular as fish and chips.
England is also famous for its breakfasts.
Very few people eat a full English breakfast
every day, but you can usually get one in
hotels or cafes.
The English breakfast is toast, eggs and sausages,
often with tomatoes, beans, hash browns (potato
cakes) and mushrooms too!
Bangers (sausages) and mash (a mixture of
potatoes with butter and milk) is another
traditional dish in England.
The sausages are often called bangers because
in times of war, when food was rationed, there
was usually a lot of water in the sausages.
When they were fried, they often blew up!
The traditional Sunday lunch is a roast dinner,
with roast beef, roast potatoes and Yorkshire
pudding (a cooked mixture of eggs, flour and
milk).
However, many English people now eat fewer
traditional dishes, and English people now
eat lots of different kinds of food from all
around the world.
But some traditional English food continues
to be very popular.
English farmers make wonderful cheeses like
red leicester, cheddar and Stilton, and at
farmers' markets all around the country people
can buy fantastic meat, fish, fruit, vegetables
and bread.
Tea, of course, is one of the most important
drinks in England, and in cafes and at home
many people like to have afternoon tea, which
is tea with cakes and sandwiches.
English people also like to go to the pub
to have a drink and perhaps to eat.
These are places where people come together
to talk, play games, or watch football or
rugby matches.
In different areas of England there are some
very strange traditions.
At many fairs, you can see Morris dancing
(people in costumes dancing to music with
sticks, swords and handkerchiefs).
In the Lake District, people have a 'gurning'
competition every year.
Gurning is trying to make a very strange face,
for example by lifting the bottom of your
mouth up above the top of it!
And in a village near Gloucester there is
a cheese rolling competition, in which people
run after a cheese which is moving like a
wheel down a very big hill!
CHAPTER FOUR
Cities and Sights
England has fifty cities and many smaller
towns, and there are lots of things to see
and do there.
The biggest city, and England's capital, is
London.
Nearly eight million people live in London
- more than in any other European city.
The country's government is there, and for
people in many different jobs, London is the
most important place to be for work.
For visitors, too, London has many of England's
most interesting sights and is one of the
most important places to visit.
London has many areas, which are often very
different, even if they are very close!
Whitehall and Westminster are the areas where
you can see some of London's most famous sights.
Here, next to the River Thames, are Big Ben
and the Houses of Parliament.
At one time, England's kings and queens lived
in these buildings, and they were called the
Palace of Westminster, but today Parliament
meets here.
Near the Houses of Parliament is Downing Street,
where the UK's prime minister - the leader
- lives, and where the government meets.
Also near here is Westminster Abbey, a large
and very important church where England's
kings and queens have had their coronations
since the time of William the Conqueror.
Following the Thames to the north, and then
towards the east from Whitehall and Westminster,
you come to the West End.
Here you can find theatres, restaurants, cinemas
and clubs.
Covent Garden, where there was once a big
market, is now a great place to go shopping,
or to have a coffee and watch the street entertainers
- actors, musicians, dancers and others who
do small shows outside.
Further east is a small area called the City
of London, which was the most important part
of London in the Middle Ages.
It is now one of the great financial centers
of the world - a place where money comes in
and out, and where England's big banks work
from.
Also here is St Paul's Cathedral, which was
built by the great architect Sir Christopher
Wren, and the Tower of London, a castle from
the eleventh century.
London is also famous for its large and beautiful
parks.
Just minutes from the West End, people can
walk, exercise and relax in the large green
areas of Hyde Park, Green Park and St James's
Park.
Many people visit London for its museums and
art galleries, and most of these are free.
The Tate Modern is the worlds largest modern
art gallery, and at the British Museum, there
are several kilometers of rooms, with more
than seventy thousand things to see.
Many visitors to London like to take a ride
on the London Eye, the largest Ferris wheel
in Europe.
From the top of the Eye, at one hundred and
thirty- five meters, you can see many of London's
most famous buildings.
Not far from London, you can visit three interesting
and important royal places - Windsor Castle,
which continues to be used by the royal family
today, Hampton Court Palace and Kew Gardens.
It is less than 100 kilometers from London
to Oxford, one of England's most beautiful
cities and home to its oldest university.
Here you can walk around the fantastic old
buildings of colleges like Christ Church and
Magdalen, many of them more than five hundred
years old.
Oxford also has England's oldest museum, the
Ashmolean, as well as parks, gardens and lovely
river walks.
Oxford is near a famous area of England called
the Cotswolds.
Close to the green hills there are beautiful
villages, with pretty houses made from gold-coloured
stone and fine old churches.
Many visitors come to this area, and there
are tourist shops and afternoon tea rooms
in a lot of bigger villages.
Oxford is not very far from Stratford-upon-Avon,
famous as the home town of William Shakespeare,
the great writer.
In this pretty river town, you can visit Shakespeare's
old house and also see a play at the theatre
of the Royal Shakespeare Company.
At Warwick, just a few kilometers away, is
one of the greatest medieval castles in England.
With its great towers and walls, dark dungeons
and beautiful gardens, Warwick Castle is one
of the most impressive in England.
The University of Cambridge is almost as old
as Oxford's, and the two cities are like each
other in many ways.
Like Oxford, Cambridge is a city of old colleges,
many from the late thirteenth and early fourteenth
centuries.
With its gardens, green spaces and river,
Cambridge is a lovely city to walk around.
Two of the most famous places in Cambridge
are King's College, with its beautiful chapel
(a small church), and the Backs, an area of
green land around the River Cam from where
you can see many of the colleges.
Moving north, England's second biggest city
is Birmingham, which was an important center
during the industrial revolution.
Today, Birmingham is a very multicultural
city and is home to the National Exhibition
Centre (NEC), where many big shows and events
are held.
Many people come to Birmingham to visit its
big, modern shopping center, the Bull Ring,
but few tourists spend a lot of time here.
Further north of Birmingham, Stoke-on-Trent
has been famous since the seventeenth century
for its pottery industry - the industry of
making objects such as cups, plates and bowls.
Here you can visit the pottery factories and
buy pottery cheaply from the factory shops.
York is one of the most interesting cities
of the north of England.
It was a Roman city, and for many years it
was an important place for religion and politics
in England.
During medieval times - the Middle Ages - there
was a strong wool trade in York, and because
of this, many other traders came to live here.
The city feels very medieval even today, with
its narrow streets and old walls.
Many tourists come to visit the city and to
see York Minster, the city's old cathedral
(a large and important church), with its beautiful
windows.
York was an important city when the railways
were first built in England, and now it is
home to the National Railway Museum.
Twenty-five kilometers from York is Castle
Howard, one of the best of England's stately
homes (big country houses).
Stately homes were built for the most important
families of England, who normally had homes
in London too.
These homes were places where the king or
queen could visit and where important people
could have meetings about politics or government.
Two very exciting cities in the north of England
are Liverpool and Manchester.
Liverpool, which is on the sea, became important
in the eighteenth century because of trade
with America.
Many immigrants from the West Indies, China
and Ireland arrived in Liverpool when they
came to England, so Liverpool was one of England's
first multicultural cities.
But by the 1970s and 1980s, ships were no
longer coming to Liverpool.
The city's old buildings stayed empty, and
it became very poor.
Since 2004, a lot of money has been spent
in Liverpool, and Albert Dock, where ships
used to arrive, is now an exciting new area
with restaurants, museums, shops and art galleries.
Liverpool was home to The Beatles, and many
people come here to do 'Beatles Tours' and
to visit the clubs where the famous band played
or see the homes where John, Paul, George
and Ringo lived.
In Liverpool, you can also see some wonderful
art at the Walker Art Gallery or Tate Liverpool,
visit the two cathedrals, or take a boat across
the River Mersey and look back at the famous
sights of this great city.
Just fifty kilometers east of Liverpool is
another big city, Manchester.
Manchester has some of the most exciting modern
buildings in England.
Its cafes, clubs and nightlife make it one
of the best cities in the country for many
young people.
But like Liverpool, Manchester had a difficult
time in the second half of the twentieth century.
Once the most important city in the world
for cotton, Manchester's old industries were
coming to an end by the 1950s, and many people
lost their jobs.
But new industries began to grow, and at the
start of the twenty-first century, parts of
the city were rebuilt, making Manchester an
exciting city once more.
Blackpool is very different from Liverpool
and Manchester.
With its long beaches, hotels and piers, Blackpool
is a popular holiday town.
Here you can eat fish and chips, go to amusement
arcades and see the coloured lights on Blackpool
Tower.
Some of the most interesting sights of England
are in the far north of the country.
Durham Cathedral, almost nine hundred years
old, is here, and also the Angel of the North,
the biggest sculpture in England.
The sculpture - of an angel with very wide
wings - was built on an old coal mine by Antony
Gormley, the same artist who made Another
Place (see the fact box opposite).
He wanted people to remember that for two
hundred years, mining was one of the biggest
industries in this area.
People pass the Angel of the North as they
drive to Newcastle-upon-Tyne.
Like Manchester and Liverpool, Newcastle is
another industrial city that now has museums,
art galleries and an exciting nightlife.
Near Newcastle is the end of Hadrians Wall,
parts of which can be seen very clearly.
Today, the border with Scotland is further
north than it was when the Romans built Hadrians
Wall.
Just a few kilometers from today's border
is another interesting sight, Holy Island,
or Lindisfarne.
You cannot get to the island at high tide
- when the sea comes in closest to the land
- but at other times you can walk or drive
across to it and see the castle that was built
here in the sixteenth century.
Back in the south of England, and west of
London, there are more sights and interesting
cities to see.
Bath, so-called because of its famous Roman
baths, is a lovely little city.
The old Roman baths are some of the best-kept
in Europe, and in the eighteenth century,
many rich and important people came here to
'take the waters'.
Big, fine houses were built for them, and
so Bath has many Georgian streets and buildings,
with pretty parks too.
Just a few kilometers further west from Bath,
but very different, is the big, busy city
of Bristol.
Bristol, once a very big port, now has a strong
electronics industry and is important in the
creative media - film, TV, radio and fashion.
It is also the biggest cultural center in
the area, with a busy nightlife.
As in many other cities in England, the old
docks - the area where the ships used to come
in - have now been changed into an area for
restaurants, shops and museums.
One of the most famous sights of Bristol is
the Clifton Suspension Bridge, which was made
by the great engineer Isambard Kingdom Brunei.
Many visitors to Bristol make the short journey
south to Glastonbury.
Here you can visit Glastonbury Abbey, which
was built in the seventh century.
Glastonbury is also famous for the music festival
held there most years in June.
It is the biggest music festival in the country.
Stonehenge, east of Glastonbury, is one of
the wonders of the world.
The big stone circles here were made between
3000 BC and 1600 BC - they are as old as Egypt's
pyramids!
One of the most interesting things about Stonehenge
is that some of the stones are very heavy
- up to forty tones - but they came from hundreds
of kilometers away, in Wales.
People believe they were probably brought
and pulled to Stonehenge in simple boats.
But no one is sure how they got to Stonehenge.
On the longest day of the year, the sun rises
across the stone circles.
Because of this, many people think the circles
were perhaps some kind of ancient calendar.
In the county of Cornwall, in the far south-west
of England, you can visit the Eden Project.
Here you can see plants and trees from many
different places, and the largest non-wild
rainforest in the world.
Brighton, on the south coast, became an important
town in the mid eighteenth century, when people
began to enjoy swimming in the sea.
The Prince of Wales (later King George the
Fourth) started to come to Brighton in the
1780s, and in 1815, the Royal Pavilion was
built for him.
The Royal Pavilion, which has a strange mixture
of Indian and Chinese building styles, is
one of the most interesting buildings in Brighton
today.
Like Bath, Brighton has some beautiful Georgian
buildings, but it is a fun town too.
Here you can walk on the pier, beside the
sea, or through the Lanes - narrow streets
that were once part of the old fishing village
of Brighton, and which are now busy with shops
and restaurants.
North-east of Brighton, on the road to Dover,
Canterbury is a place full of history.
It was an important Roman town, and in AD
602, the first cathedral in England was built
here.
The cathedral was rebuilt in 1070 and continues
to be very important today: the Archbishop
of Canterbury is the head of the Church of
England.
As you can see, there are lots of exciting
places to visit in England!
CHAPTER FIVE
Nature and the Environment
England has some exciting and beautiful cities,
and many interesting sights.
But for a lot of people, the best thing about
England is its countryside.
Mostly, England is a place of green hills,
but it also has lakes, rivers, a long coastline
that is very different in different parts
of the country and, in the north, mountains.
Because there are so many different kinds
of environments in England, there is a lot
of wildlife too.
Around the coast you can see seals, sharks,
dolphins and otters; and rabbits, foxes, squirrels
and deer are just some of the animals that
move around the countryside freely.
Nearly two hundred and thirty different kinds
of birds live in England, and another two
hundred visit for part of the year.
There are also many different kinds of trees,
plants and wild flowers growing in the English
countryside.
The weather in England is temperate - almost
never very, very hot, or very, very cold - with
lots of rain all year.
It is usually warmest between June and September,
but the weather in any month can be very different
from year to year.
England has ten national parks beautiful areas
of countryside where is the special laws keep
the land and a wildlife safe.
The biggest of these is the Lake District,
in the north-west of England.
The Lake District has the highest mountains
in the country, with sixteen big lakes lying
below them.
With its beautiful scenery, the Lake District
is not surprisingly a very popular place for
tourists.
Most visitors come to walk in the mountains,
to go on boats on the lakes and to enjoy the
area's pretty stone-built villages.
There is also a lot of wildlife in the Lake
District, and it is the only place in the
country where golden eagles - birds of prey
- live.
In the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries,
many poets began to write about the Lake District.
The most famous of these was William Wordsworth,
who lived there for sixty years.
The poems and books that he wrote about the
Lake District made many people come and visit
the area for the first time.
Another famous writer from the Lake District
is Beatrix Potter, whose children's books
about Peter Rabbit and his friends are famous
around the world.
Today, a lot of tourists visit the house near
Hawkshead where she wrote many of her books.
There are four other national parks in the
north of England.
The Peak District, the Yorkshire Dales and
the Northumberland National Park are all part
of the Pennines, an area of low mountains
in the middle of the north of England.
The Pennine Way, a walking trail 429 kilometers
long, goes along these mountains, which make
a kind of natural border between east and
west.
East of the Pennines is the north of England's
other national park, the North York Moors,
between York in the south and Middlesbrough
in the north.
In all these northern national parks, you
can find deep valleys covered with forests,
high moorland and wonderful caves (natural
holes in the rock in the hillside), and they
are great places for walking, cycling or horse-riding.
People who have read Wuthering Heights, Jane
Eyre, The Tenant of Wildfell Hall or any of
the other books by Charlotte, Emily and Anne
Bronte, probably feel that they already know
the countryside of the Pennines.
The Bronte sisters lived in Haworth in Yorkshire,
and they describe the windy, heather-covered
moorland of this area in many of their books.
The history of the New Forest, about one hundred
kilometers south-west of London, begins more
than nine hundred years ago.
William the Conqueror wanted this area to
be kept for hunting, and he and his nobles
enjoyed looking for deer and other animals
here.
Parts of the New Forest, which is now a national
park, have probably not changed very much
since these times.
Today, cows walk freely around this area,
with its ancient trees and open land covered
with heather.
Visitors here can also see beautiful wild
flowers, deer and big birds of prey.
But most famous are the ponies - about three
thousand of them - that live in the New Forest,
as they have for many years.
You can often see them walking around the
villages of the New Forest, and you must be
ready to stop your car when one decides to
cross the road!
Between Exeter and Plymouth, the national
park of Dartmoor in Devon is the biggest and
wildest area of open countryside in the south
of England.
A lot of Dartmoor is moorland and covered
in heather, but Dartmoor is also famous for
its many tors - hills with rocks at the top.
Sheep, cows and ponies walk freely around
on Dartmoor, and many birds live here too.
North of Dartmoor is the national park of
Exmoor, a beautiful area of moorland, forests,
valleys and farmland, which goes across the
counties of Somerset and Devon, right up to
the coast.
Here you can see otters in nearly every river,
wild red deer, bats and some very special
butterflies.
Devon is not only famous for Dartmoor and
Exmoor.
The counties of Devon and Cornwall are very
popular with tourists because of their lovely
countryside and because they get more hours
of sunlight than anywhere else in England.
Away from the coast, the green fields are
full of wild flowers in the summer, and narrow
little roads with tall hedges at the side
go from one pretty village to the next.
By the sea, there are golden beaches and little
rocky coves, and on the north coast, the big
waves in places like Newquay make surfing
a very popular sport.
Off the coasts of Devon and Cornwall, you
can see basking sharks and porpoises, and
on Lundy Island there are puffins in April
and May.
Another beautiful area to visit in this part
of England are the Scilly Isles, about one
hundred small islands forty-five kilometers
away from Land's End, in England's far south-west
corner.
Each island is very different, and people
live on only five of them.
Along England's south coast, big white cliffs
- large rocks next to the sea - look out onto
the English Channel.
The rocks in the cliffs on part of this coast,
which is called the Jurassic Coast and goes
from East Devon to Dorset, are one hundred
and eighty five million years old.
Here you can easily find wonderful fossils
- rocks with the shape of animals and plants
from ancient times.
You can see lots of fossils here because of
erosion - the rock is very soft, and every
day the sea breaks bits of the rock away from
the cliffs.
Erosion has made parts of this coast very
beautiful: the perfect little cove at Lulworth
in Dorset and the famous arch of Durdle Door
were both made by erosion.
England's newest national park is the South
Downs, which comes down to the sea near Brighton.
You can walk through the beautiful green hills
of the South Downs on the South Downs Way,
a special walking trail which ends at the
enormous white cliffs of Beachy Head on the
south coast.
Most of the North Sea coast of England (on
the east side of the country) is very flat
and sandy, with a lot of saltmarsh - wet,
muddy areas with grass growing on them.
There are many sea birds here and also, at
Blakeney Point in Norfolk, several hundred
seals.
This is the best place in England to see seals,
and many people take special boat trips to
visit them.
The national park of the Norfolk Broads is
also in this area.
Here, three rivers go across flat land to
the sea, and are so wide in places, they are
almost like lakes.
Many people like to visit this area by boat
or by bike, enjoying the wonderful birdlife.
England has a lot of beautiful countryside,
but there are many problems for the environment.
Factories, vehicles and modern farming can
make the air, rivers and the sea dirty, and
this is bad for plants and wildlife.
Many animals also lose their homes when forests
are cut down or land is taken for building
houses on.
People believe that global warming (the Earth
getting hotter because of dangerous gases
in the air) is bringing new problems to the
countryside too.
It is because of these dangers to the environment
that the national parks of England were made,
and there are many organizations that work
to keep wildlife and the English countryside
safe.
The UK government is also working with governments
from other countries to try to find ways to
fight global warming.
English people hope that they, and the tourists
who come to their country, will always be
able to enjoy the wonderful natural environment.
CHAPTER SIX
Daily Life
For most English teenagers, daily life is
mainly about school.
Education is free for all children aged five
to sixteen.
It is also compulsory - everyone must have
an education.
As well as state schools, which are run by
the government, there are also independent
schools, which families have to pay for.
About six percent of children in England go
to independent schools.
Some families also home-school: they teach
their children at home.
Children start their compulsory education
in primary school when they are four or five
years old, and at age eleven, they move to
secondary school.
The school year is from September to July,
with two-week holidays at Christmas and in
the spring, and a longer six-week holiday
in the summer.
Between each of these holidays, there is a
one-week break called Half Term, so the school
year has got three terms.
Most state schools follow the national curriculum,
which tells teachers what subjects to teach.
At the end of Year 11, when students are about
sixteen, they take exams called GCSEs in many
different subjects.
Some of these subjects, such as math's and
English, are compulsory, but students can
also choose some subjects.
After their exams, some students leave education,
and others go to technical colleges, where
they learn how to do the jobs they are interested
in.
Others stay at school and study for one or
two more years to do exams called AS-levels
and A-levels, this time in only three or four
subjects.
Some students who do well in their A-levels
will go on to study at university for another
three to six years.
Most jobs in England today are in the service
industry - in places like hotels, restaurants,
shops, computer companies and banks.
Many English people work very hard.
The working day is usually from nine o'clock
until five o'clock, with an hour at lunchtime,
five days a week, but often people work much
longer hours.
It can be very difficult for young people
to find a job, even if they have studied at
university.
Some do more training, learning how to do
new things.
Others take unpaid work, so they can get experience.
In the evenings and at the weekends, many
English people enjoy watching or playing sport,
watching TV, playing computer games, or reading
books or newspapers.
Sometimes they go out to the cinema or to
a restaurant, or to see their favourite band
play music.
Sometimes they just go shopping or spend time
with their friends.
Children and teenagers often go to weekly
clubs, for example Scouts, martial arts, dance,
drama or music.
Most teenagers also have a mobile phone, so
that they can talk to their friends or send
them text messages, and an MP3 player for
listening to music.
There are lots of things to do at the weekends
and on holidays in England.
Many families go out together to museums,
beaches or theme parks, or for walks or cycle
rides in the countryside.
People also invite friends to their houses
for meals, a cup of tea, or to watch a sports
match on TV.
Life in England is very different if you live
in the city or in the countryside.
In the city, public transport is usually very
good, and there are many buses and trains.
London also has an underground train system,
called the Tube, and you can travel around
Manchester by tram.
But in the countryside, people often have
to walk and drive a lot.
Most people who live in cities have homes
in the suburbs - the areas around a city.
Cities often also have big estates.
These are places built mainly for people to
live in, with lots of houses or flats, and
usually some shops and a park.
There are lots of different kinds of homes
for people to live in in England.
Some houses are more than six hundred years
old, others are very modern; some people live
in houses with several different rooms and
a garden, others live in small apartments
called flats.
In the past, people in England used to buy
their own homes, but houses and flats have
now become very expensive.
For young people with little money, it is
now very difficult to buy a home, and more
people now rent: they pay money to someone
to live in their house or flat.
Most English people usually eat at home because
eating out - eating in a restaurant or cafe
- is expensive.
Breakfast is often toast or cereal, and while
some people have a big meal at midday, others
just have a sandwich for lunch and then eat
their main meal in the evening.
This meal can be called supper, dinner or
tea.
But for some families, 'tea is a cup of tea
with a biscuit or a piece of cake!
Many people now buy their food and all the
other shopping they need from big supermarkets,
which are on the outside of almost every town
and city.
These supermarkets are often open all day
and in the evening, and some now stay open
all night too.
Other shops usually open at nine o'clock and
close at half-past five or six, with shorter
opening hours on Sundays.
Life in England is busier than ever today.
Travel around any English city at rush hour
- when people are going to or from work - and
it seems that no one has time for anything.
But over a morning coffee or the important
afternoon cup of tea, most English people
can always find the time to talk about sport
or the weather, or think of something to laugh
about.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Sports
Sport is very important in England, and people
enjoy going to big sports events or watching
them on TV and playing sport in their free
time.
Some of the most popular world sports - football,
rugby, cricket, golf and tennis - first started
in England, and people from all around the
world come here for some of its great sports
events.
In 2012, the Olympics were held in England,
and millions of people from around the world
came to London to watch the many different
sports of the Olympics and the Paralympics.
New sports stadiums were built, including
the main Olympic stadium, a basketball arena
and a velopark, for cycling.
It was the first time the Olympics had come
to England since 1948 and was a very exciting
year for the country.
The most popular sport in England is football,
and there are professional matches every week
from August until May.
Many thousands of people also play in parks,
at local clubs, and at schools or universities.
Football has been played in England for hundreds
of years, and the best football teams, for
example Manchester United, Liverpool, Chelsea
and Arsenal, are famous around the world.
The most important day in England's football
calendar is the Football Association (FA)
Cup Final day in May at London's Wembley Stadium.
Many people believe that England's best ever
footballer was Bobby Charlton, who started
playing for Manchester United in 1953 and
scored 249 goals over the next twenty years.
In 1958, Charlton was in an aeroplane with
the Manchester United team when it crashed,
killing eight players.
Bobby Charlton was not killed in the crash,
and he went on to play in the 1966 World Cup,
which England won.
It was the first and only time that England
has won the World Cup.
Cricket was first played in England in the
sixteenth century, and by the eighteenth century,
it had become the country's national sport.
Every summer, teams from other countries play
five-day Test matches against the English
national team.
Cricket is also played on village greens - small
fields in villages - around the country in
the summer months.
Because cricket matches are so long, a new
kind of match called the Twenty20 was introduced
in 2003.
Twenty20 matches are only three hours long,
so people can watch them in one day.
Rugby is another sport that began in England,
and it is named after the school where it
was first played Rugby School in Warwickshire.
Rugby is like football, but players can hold
the ball and tackle each other pull each other
to the ground - to get the ball.
Rugby is not as popular as football, but after
England won the World Cup in 2003, more people
began to watch and play the sport.
In England, there are two kinds of rugby,
each very different: Rugby League and Rugby
Union.
For two weeks around the end of Traditionally,
when people June, England becomes tennis-mad!
This is the time of the Wimbledon they eat
strawberries and cream.
Championships, the most famous tennis tournament
in the world.
Few people watch tennis on TV for the rest
of the year, but during Wimbledon, matches
are shown on TV every afternoon and evening.
England's most famous tennis player was Fred
Perry, who won the Wimbledon Championship
every year for three years, from 1934 to 1936.
Since that time, no English player has won
the Men's Championship.
Horse-racing is another very popular sport
in England.
There are races every day of the year, and
people enjoy making bets on which horse will
win.
The Derby at Epsom, which continues to be
held today, was the first derby ever, and
derbies - races on flat ground for three-year-old
horses - are now held around the world.
Other important dates in horseracing are the
Grand National in Liverpool in April - one
of the most difficult horse races in the world
- and Royal Ascot, five days of horse racing
in Berkshire in June.
The Queen always goes to Ascot, so it is an
important event in England, and visitors wear
their best clothes and hats.
Another important day for sport in England
is the London Marathon in April.
More than thirty thousand people run in the
London Marathon, which has been held since
1981.
The fastest people finish the forty-two kilometer
run in just over two hours, but for many runners
the most important thing is making money for
charity.
Watersports are popular in England, and many
people, especially on the south coast, enjoy
sailing.
There are good waves for surfing at many of
the beaches in the south-west, and canoeing
is also popular on England's many rivers and
canals.
Two of England's most famous sportspeople
do a watersport - Steve Redgrave, who won
gold medals for rowing at every Olympic Games
between 1984 and 2000, and Ellen MacArthur,
who broke the world record for sailing around
the world alone in the fastest time on 7th
February 2005.
Golf is also a very popular sport for English
people.
There are many golf courses in England, and
every July the Open Championship, one of the
four biggest tournaments in the world, is
held in England or Scotland.
Motor-racing is also well-liked, and many
people go to a course called Silverstone in
Northamptonshire every year to watch the British
Grand Prix.
At school, children play football, rugby,
netball and cricket, and do athletics in the
summer.
There are public swimming pools and gyms in
most towns, and many people also enjoy cycling
and walking.
Other outdoor activities like mountaineering
- climbing and walking in the hills and mountains
- are also very popular in England.
English people love sport.
For some time, they have not won many big
events in the sports that first came from
their country many years before.
But sport continues to be a very important
part of life in England.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Entertainment
England is famous around the world for its
great culture and entertainment.
Some of the worlds greatest writers, best
films, and most famous actors and directors
have come from England, and there are several
hundred theatres and concert halls showing
wonderful plays, music and dance.
Literature is a very important part of England's
history, and all around the country you can
visit the homes of some of the many great
English writers.
The most famous of these is, of course, William
Shakespeare, but many others have written
great works of literature too.
In the late seventeenth century, there were
some fine poets, for example John Milton,
who wrote Paradise Lost.
Novels only began to be widely written in
the eighteenth century, and one of the earliest
of these was Daniel Defoe's Robinson Crusoe,
published in 1719, which continues to be very
popular today.
The first half of the nineteenth century was
famous for the Romantic poetry of writers
like Wordsworth, Coleridge, Byron, Shelley
and Keats.
Jane Austen was another great writer of this
time.
In books like Emma, Pride and Prejudice and
Persuasion, Austen wrote about how women saw
society, marriage and happiness.
Famous Victorian writers included Charles
Dickens, the Bronte sisters and George Eliot.
In Victorian times, people began for the first
time to write literature just for children,
and one of the best-known of these new children's
books was Lewis Carroll's Alice's Adventures
in Wonderland, which continues to be read
by many children even today.
Another writer from around this time whose
work is much-loved now is Arthur Conan Doyle,
who was Scottish.
He wrote stories about Sherlock Holmes, a
London detective, between 1880 and 1907.
Sherlock Holmes had a brilliant mind and was
able to find the answers to the strangest
mysteries.
The stories of these mysteries were told to
the reader by Sherlock Holmes's great friend
Dr Watson.
An important English writer at the beginning
of the twentieth century was Thomas Hardy.
Tess of the d'Urbervilles, Far From the Madding
Crowd and Hardy's other novels were often
terribly sad stories about people in an imaginary
county called Wessex.
Rudyard Kipling was also popular at this time
and from 1910, a new kind of 'modernist' literature
became important.
One of the first modernist writers was Joseph
Conrad, who was Polish, but lived in England,
and between the two wars there was a lot of
other new literature, from writers like Virginia
Woolf, Evelyn Waugh and DH Lawrence.
After the Second World War, two of England's
most important writers were George Orwell,
who wrote Nineteen Eighty-Four and Animal
Farm, and Agatha Christie, who wrote sixty-six
detective novels, including the adventures
of Miss Marple and Hercule Poirot.
Modern fantasy literature - writing about
magic, monsters and other imaginary things
- became popular at this time too, when The
Lord of the Rings, by JRR Tolkien, was published
in 1949.
Two of the most famous writers of the last
fifty years are children's writers.
Roald Dahl, who was born in Wales to Norwegian
parents, wrote books such as Charlie and the
Chocolate Factory and Matilda, many of which
also became great films and theatre shows.
JK Rowling's Harry Potter series - a group
of seven fantasy books for children - has
sold hundreds of millions of copies, and people
can now read them in sixty-seven different
languages.
Many of these works of literature have become
famous plays, and for many people an important
part of any visit to England is a trip to
the theatre.
There are several hundred theatres in England,
around the country, but the most famous are
the theatres of the West End in London.
In the West End, there is a theatre on nearly
every street, showing the latest plays and
musicals, and many of the best actors from
all around the world come to perform here.
Some of the most famous shows in the West
End have been musicals, such as Cats and Phantom
of the Opera by Andrew Lloyd Webber, but in
London and around the country, you can also
see many different kinds of shows, including
more serious plays, new works and comedy.
One of the oldest theatres in London is the
Old Vic, which first began to show plays in
1818.
England also has the National Theatre, on
London's South Bank near the London Eye, which
opened in 1976.
Across the Thames are the Royal Ballet and
the Royal Opera House at Covent Garden, and
the English National Opera at the Coliseum,
the largest theatre in London.
Outside London, England's most famous theatre
is the theatre of the Royal Shakespeare Company
in Stratford-upon-Avon, where Shakespeare's
plays are performed throughout the year.
In the summer, you can also see Shakespeare's
plays at the Globe Theatre in London, a round
theatre with no roof, like the one where these
famous plays were first performed more than
four hundred years ago.
England is important for its music too.
George Frideric Handel, Edward Elgar and Gustav
Holst are three of the country's most famous
classical music composers, and at places like
the Royal Festival Hall and the Barbican Centre
in London, you can hear many different kinds
of classical music, played by some of the
finest orchestras in the world.
There is also a lot of good classical music
outside London: the Birmingham Symphony Orchestra
is one of the best in Europe, and at many
stately homes and castles around the country
there are outdoor concerts in the summer.
But it is for its pop music that England is
best known.
Together with the USA, the UK brought rock
'n' roll to the world in the 1950s, and The
Beatles, who became popular in the 1960s,
is one of the most famous bands in the world.
During the 1960s, the Rolling Stones, Cliff
Richard and The Shadows, The Who, The Kinks,
The Animals and many other bands became important
in England, and they started to become famous
in the USA too.
For a while, the USA began to follow the UK
in music and in fashion.
In the 1970s, music changed.
First there was glam rock from artists like
David Bowie and Elton John, who coloured their
hair, and wore strange and wonderful clothes
and shoes.
Then came punk rock - short, fast songs, often
with a political message, sung by bands like
the Clash.
In the 1980s, world music, heavy metal (loud,
hard music) and indie rock were popular, and
England's dance music culture also began.
But in the late 1990s, some artists turned
against the many fashions in music of the
'80s and early '90s, and Britpop arrived - bands
such as Blur, Oasis and Radiohead that followed
the British guitar music of the 1960s and
'70s.
Several of these bands became famous around
Europe and in the USA.
Today, you can see bands play in clubs in
almost every big city, and there are also
music festivals around the country where people
camp and watch music in big fields.
The most famous of these is at Glastonbury.
Art-lovers can find a lot to enjoy in England
too.
Two of England's most famous artists were
the landscape painters John Constable and
JMW Turner, and many of their pictures can
be seen at the Tate Britain gallery in London.
London also has the Tate Modern, of course,
and there are also great exhibitions at the
Royal Academy of Arts, and a lot of Western
European art at the National Gallery in Trafalgar
Square.
In the 1990s, a group of artists called the
Young British Artists (YBAs) became very popular
in England.
One of the most famous YBAs was Damien Hirst,
who made a lot of art works with dead animals.
Some people love his work, and others hate
it!
Most towns in England have a cinema, and watching
films is a very popular activity for English
people.
England has made some of the world's greatest
films, and some of the most famous actors
and directors are English.
The film industry only really started in England
in the 1930s, when some famous films like
The 39 Steps were made.
But it was in the 1950s and 1960s that British
cinema became really important.
At this time, Hammer Horror films like The
Curse of Frankenstein and Dracula were made
- and Ealing Comedies like Kind Hearts and
Coronets and Whisky Galore.
The first Carry On film was made in 1958,
and by 1992, there were thirty-one.
The Carry On films were comedies that made
jokes about English life.
They were not thought of as important films,
but were loved by many English people.
The James Bond films were another series that
became very famous in England.
The stories were adventures about James Bond,
a secret service agent - someone who worked
secretly for the government, looking for enemies
of the country.
The first Bond film, Dr No, was made in 1962,
and the films became famous for their music,
Bond's cars and clever equipment, and for
James Bond himself - a character played by
several different actors.
A famous English actor of the 1960s was Julie
Andrews, who appeared in two famous musical
films, The Sound of Music and Mary Poppins.
But many people believe that the greatest
actor of the twentieth century was Laurence
Olivier.
Olivier, who worked in theatre and film from
the 1920s until the 1980s, made nearly sixty
films, including Rebecca and Wuthering Heights.
Also very famous, but as a director not an
actor, was Alfred Hitchcock.
He made many great mystery films in England
and in Hollywood, where he later went to live.
From the 1990s, romantic comedies like Four
Weddings and a Funeral and Notting Hill were
made, and the Merchant Ivory films of classic
novels like Howard's End.
Since then, some of England's most successful
films have been Love Actually, Slumdog Millionaire
and the Harry Potter series.
But England's most popular kind of entertainment
is television.
Public television first began in England in
1936, and the British Broadcasting Corporation
(the BBC) is the world's oldest and largest
broadcaster Today there are five main channels
in England, and there are also hundreds more
channels on cable and satellite TV.
There are hundreds of radio stations too.
On English TV, there are many different kinds
of programmers, but some of the most popular
ones are sitcoms (situation comedies) - comedies
about people in their home or where they work.
One of the most famous of these was Fawlty
Towers, with the actor John Cleese.
Many people also enjoy soap operas - dramas
which continue from one programme to the next,
for example Eastenders, Coronation Street,
Emmerdale and Hollyoaks.
Another very popular drama series in England
in the 1990s was Inspector Morse, about a
detective in Oxford.
Many people also enjoy reality programmes
- programmes about ordinary people's lives.
One of the most famous of these is Big Brother,
a programme in which a group of people live
together in a house and are filmed twenty-four
hours a day.
Some of the Big Brother programmes have been
watched by up to six million people in the
UK: England has great music, art, history
and literature, but sometimes people are most
interested in day-to-day life!
CHAPTER NINE
English Heroes
Who are England's heroes - the important people
who will never be forgotten?
One of the greatest must be William Shakespeare,
who wrote many beautiful poems and about thirty-seven
plays, including A Midsummer Night's Dream,
Romeo and Juliet, Hamlet and Macbeth.
The people in his plays always seem very real,
and he wrote about their feelings and problems
in words that continue to sound new and interesting
today.
Another hero of England from the world of
literature is Charles Dickens.
Dickens wrote some of the best novels of Victorian
times, including Oliver Twist, David Copperfield,
Bleak House and Little Dorrit.
Dickens used his books to show how terrible
life was for poor people in England at the
time of the industrial revolution.
But England has scientific heroes as well
as heroes from the world of literature.
One of the greatest of these was Sir Isaac
Newton.
Born in Lincolnshire in 1643, Newton studied
at the University of Cambridge.
He was able to understand and explain many
things about the world around us for the first
time, and his book Mathematical Principles
of Natural Philosophy was very important in
the history of science.
Newton helped people to understand about light
and colour, and he was also the first person
to explain gravity - the force that pulls
things towards the ground.
Charles Darwin also did scientific work in
England.
He was born into a rich family, and in 1831
he left England to travel around the world.
Darwin studied the animals and plants that
he saw on his trip, and was interested in
the differences between them.
When he came home, he began to work on a new
idea: the theory of evolution.
This was the idea that only the strongest
animals and plants lived and reproduced - had
babies or grew seeds.
And so, Darwin believed, each kind of animal
and plant was slowly changing.
In 1859, Darwin published his ideas in the
book On the Origin of Species.
One very real hero of England was Horatio
Nelson, who was leader of the Royal Navy from
1794 to 1805.
Nelson, who lost one eye and one arm in battle,
was a great leader, and with him, Britain
won many battles against France during the
Napoleonic Wars.
At the Battle of Trafalgar, Nelson helped
to stop the French from invading Britain,
but he was then killed.
A very large statue of him stands forty-six
meters high in Trafalgar Square and is one
of London's best-loved sights.
Two other important English seamen were Sir
Francis Drake and Captain Cook.
Sir Francis Drake helped to lead England against
the Spanish Armada in 1588, and Captain Cook
was the first European to reach the east coast
of Australia, in 1770.
Winston Churchill, prime minister from 1940
until 1945, was another English hero for many
people during World War Two.
Churchill was a strong leader, and many people
believe that the speeches and radio broadcasts
he made during the war helped the UK to win
the war.
He was prime minister again from 1951 to 1955,
and when he died in 1965, the Queen gave him
a state funeral - a special funeral that is
normally only for kings and queens.
Another famous politician was Margaret Thatcher.
Thatcher was prime minister from 1979 to 1990
- longer than any other person in the twentieth
century - and she was also the first woman
prime minister of the UK.
One of England's most famous heroes is not
actually real.
Stories about Robin Hood have been popular
since the Middle Ages, and in modern times
many films, plays and TV programmes have been
made about him.
In these old stories, Robin Hood is a great
fighter and an outlaw - someone who does not
follow the law.
Living in Sherwood Forest at a time when the
king of England is a dishonest man, he takes
money from the rich to give it to the poor.
Florence Nightingale was famous for helping
people too - but she was a real person.
Florence Nightingale is thought of by many
as the first real nurse.
In 1854, during the Crimean War, she went
to work in a hospital for soldiers.
She thought that it was dirty and badly organized,
so she quickly started to make important changes.
Because of her, the hospital became cleaner,
the soldiers were given good food and taken
care of better, and soon fewer people were
dying.
When she came back to England, Florence Nightingale
started the first proper nursing school at
St Thomas' Hospital.
England also has heroes of the stage and screen.
One of the first of these was Charlie Chaplin,
a comedy actor and director who was famous
for his many silent films in the years before
films with sound were made.
Chaplin's best-known character was 'The Tramp',
a funny little man with a hat, a moustache
and a stick.
Before the end of the First World War, Chaplin
was the most famous film actor in the world.
But probably the greatest stage heroes of
England are The Beatles.
John Lennon, Paul McCartney, George Harrison
and Ringo Starr had their first hit, Love
Me Do, in 1962, and by 1964, they had become
famous around the world.
There was international 'Beatlemania: people
screamed and shouted when the band came on
stage, and the world watched everything they
did.
The Beatles were the first English band to
become successful in the USA.
They made more than two hundred songs and
are the best-selling band in history.
Two more musical heroes of England, famous
in a quieter way, are the composers George
Frideric Handel and Sir Edward Elgar.
Handel was German, but came to live in London
in 1712 and became British in 1727.
He is one of the greatest composers in history
and is best known for wonderful works like
Water Music and The Messiah, written in 1742.
Elgar's most famous works are the Enigma Variations,
written in 1899, The Dream of Gerontius and
the Pomp and Circumstance Marches.
What about modern-day English heroes?
For many football lovers, David Beckham is
a hero.
He was captain of the England football team
from 2000 until 2006 and, along with his wife
Victoria, who was once in the band the Spice
Girls, Beckham is a very famous celebrity.
Princess Diana is also, for many people, an
English hero.
Diana was the first wife of Charles, the Prince
of Wales, and when they married in 1981, people
believed that she would one day be the queen.
But they were not happy together, and in 1996
Charles and Diana ended their marriage.
A year later, Diana was killed in a car accident
in Paris.
Many people loved her for her work with international
charities and because she showed great kindness
to children, ill people and those with difficult
lives.
When she died, thousands of people brought
flowers to her London home, and two-and-a-half
billion people watched her funeral on TV.
CHAPTER TEN
Looking Forward
All through England's history, small inventions
- new things that people make - have brought
big changes to peoples lives.
When William Caxton made the first English
printing press in 1476, the country changed
in many ways.
Now people could get more books, more cheaply,
and so they could get information about lots
of different things.
Because of this, information also became more
standardized: it was written down in the same
way each time, which was important in areas
like science.
The printing press changed the English language
too.
At that time, people in different parts of
the country used very different words, but
William Caxton only printed books in standardized
English.
The spinning Jenny, invented in 1764 by James
Hargreaves, brought more important changes
to England.
With the spinning Jenny, people working in
their homes in England could spin cotton more
quickly and so make much more.
Other machines followed, and when steam power
was introduced, cloth making became a proper
industry.
Cloth-makers did not work at home anymore;
they used big machines in factories in the
cities.
This was the beginning of the industrial revolution,
and in twenty- first century England, people
are in the middle of another revolution, or
great change, again started by several small
inventions.
One of the most important of these was the
invention by the Englishman Tim Berners-Lee,
in 1990, of the World Wide Web.
The World Wide Web has made it easier than
ever for people to get information.
Its invention is part of the digital revolution,
which has given us mobile phones, computers,
MP3 players, digital TV and much, much more.
The digital revolution is changing many things
about life in England.
We can now talk on the telephone almost anywhere,
send messages quickly around the world and
see people who are thousands of kilometers
away through our computers.
Because of this, people can study or work
from home more easily, and work with people
in different countries.
We can shop and meet people on the Internet,
read books on our computers and watch hundreds
of different TV channels.
And the machines we use every day, like radios,
washing machines and cameras, are becoming
better and cheaper all the time.
But the digital revolution is also bringing
new problems.
Many people feel that modern technology makes
life busier and sometimes more difficult.
We can work wherever we are now, so for some
people there is less time to think or to relax.
Is it good for children to play computer games
and watch TV so much?
And are we forgetting how to meet people and
make real friends because we talk to people
through computers so much now?
These are all difficult questions for England's
future, and there are other questions we are
trying to answer now too.
For a long time, we have known that there
are big environmental problems in the world.
Factories, cars, and burning coal, oil or
gas for fuel all make our air dirty, giving
us global warming.
So now we need to find ways to help the environment.
Many English homes and companies are already
getting their electricity from solar (sun)
or wind power, and the government is giving
money to people who use these renewable energies
- ones that can be used again and again.
In the future, we will probably use less and
less coal, oil and gas.
Many English people have been recycling more
and more of their rubbish, and by 2011, they
were recycling forty percent of their rubbish.
In the future, many people also believe that
we will use electric cars more and other energy-saving
technologies.
The digital and environmental revolutions
are changing England.
England in 2100 will be a very different place
to the England we now know.
Will England have a king or queen?
Will there continue to be big differences
between rich and poor people?
How many different languages will people speak?
And will England have won the Football World
Cup again?
We cannot know.
But we can probably hope that people will
continue to watch Shakespeare's plays, climb
the mountains of the Lake District and visit
the sights of London.
And perhaps they will still say that England
is a wonderful, exciting place.