Juanantes Dios Rodrigues was a poor farmer.
He was a good man, a good husband.
He worked hard and lived a simple life.
One night Juanantes took a bottle of whiskey
to the field behind his house.
He didn't usually drink alcohol.
He hated the taste, although people said it
was better than most other pleasures in life.
Some people had even found the "good light"
after drinking alcohol.
A person who experienced the "good light"
was able to leave this earth and, for a short
time, stay between two worlds, in a place
where death couldn't touch them.
This light meant good health, long life, happiness,
good business.
Everyone searched for this light.
But Juanantes didn't drink - until that night.
There was no reason for his drinking - nothing
to celebrate, no anger to drown, or sadness
to forget.
But he couldn't fight his desire on that night.
When he had finished the bottle, he heard
a voice.
The voice commanded him to go to the top of
a mountain called the Hill of Sand on the
first Tuesday of the ninth month, at midnight.
There he would find a large fire in the forest.
He would see a bag by the fire.
He had to approach the fire and pick up the
bag before the fire burned it.
Inside the bag there would be treasure and
something else, a mandate.
He had to do exactly what the mandate ordered
him to do.
On the first Tuesday of the ninth month his
wife, Cardenala, went with him to the Hill
of Sand.
They left at midnight, as the voice had instructed,
and walked through the forest.
They were afraid but excited at the same time.
The noises of the night were all around them.
Eyes shone in the dark, watching them.
Juanantes had told Cardenala about the voice
during a moment of weakness, as he lay there
recovering from his night of drinking.
He knew now, as she pushed him forward in
the darkness, that it had been a mistake to
tell Cardenala.
Since he had told her about the voice, he
had had no peace.
He couldn't work.
His farm and his animals had suffered.
Cardenala wouldn't leave him alone, day or
night.
Even in silence they knew each others thoughts.
To him the mysterious voice he had heard was
like an evil curse.
But not to Cardenala.
To her it was a way of escaping from their
poverty, the way to the "good light."
Juanantes wanted the treasure but at the same
time he feared it.
He wasn't sure he should do what the voice
had commanded.
But Cardenala's desire infected him.
She decided for both of them.
They would go to the Hill of Sand.
They would do exactly what the voice had told
them to do.
They would find the treasure.
She planned.
She worried.
If the bag contained money, how would they
spend it?
If it contained jewels, who could they sell
them to?
She woke him up with her fears.
"The police might ask questions.
If there's gold in the bag, what will we do?"
The more she pushed, the more full of doubt
he became.
"I may be poor, but at least I'm happy," he
told her.
She called him a coward and threatened to
go alone.
So they went together on that dark night.
At one point Cardenala wanted to turn back.
She suddenly had a black thought.
She could see danger waiting for them.
She called to Juanantes, but it was too late.
He didn't hear her.
He didn't answer.
He didn't even turn his head.
There was no moon.
Cardenala could only see his white hat in
the darkness.
He walked on without stopping, without thinking.
He wasn't cautious or indecisive now.
There was another Juanantes inside his skin,
fingers holding tightly onto his machete,
eyes staring.
What had caused this change in him?
What was driving him forward?
At last they came to the fire, an enormous,
blinding fire.
Juanantes waited for a moment, silent, thinking.
Should they turn around?
Could they escape this?
Forget it had ever happened?
Cardenala said nothing.
Then Juanantes rushed forward and saw, where
the voice had told him it would be, an old
cloth bag.
He quickly took the bag, almost burning his
face in the flames, and returned to Cardenala.
Suddenly ambitious again and filled with curiosity
about what was in the bag, he took Cardenala's
hand and they ran from the place.
They could see nothing in the darkness.
They felt the outside of the bag.
Bones?
And something heavier, with a weight like
metal.
Juanantes opened it and felt inside.
It was impossible to see but yes, there 'were
the bones of a man, a machete, and in a smaller
bag, a bottle of whiskey and some gold coins.
Was this the treasure of the dead?
It was all a mystery.
He found a metal box and opened it.
Inside he could feel some kind of paper - a
document.
This must be the mandate.
The events of later that night have never
been fully understood.
In the early hours, when it was still dark,
as Cardenala lay sleeping in their bedroom,
Juanantes opened the metal box and read the
mandate.
The mandate told him to kill a man, Prudencio
Salvatierra.
Kill?
Juanantes shook with fear.
He left quietly and went to a bar to have
a drink.
He needed a drink now, to calm himself.
He needed to think.
He was lifting his glass to his mouth when
he heard someone say the name of Prudencio
Salvatierra.
The sound of that name filled him with hatred.
His glass crashed to the floor.
He couldn't see.
He couldn't think.
He wanted this man's blood.
He had to spill this man's blood!
He pulled out his machete and rushed toward
Prudencio Salvatierra.
"Fight or be killed like a dog!" he shouted.
Prudencio pulled out his machete.
"Who are you?
What do you want with me?"
Juanantes attacked him.
There were screams.
People were running.
Tables and chairs were knocked over as people
crowded around to watch.
Juanantes was wild, with the strength of ten
men.
His machete came down again and again on Prudencio
Salvatierra until the bar was red with his
blood.
Prudencio had no chance.
Within minutes he lay dead, his body in pieces.
Later, Juanantes was questioned again and
again by the judge.
Why had he fought with Prudencio Salvatierra?
Juanantes could give no answer.
There was no logic.
No, they had never met before.
No, he was not an enemy - until that night.
Until the moment when Juanantes heard his
name, the name he recognized, the name that
was written in the mandate.
Juanantes was found guilty of murder and sent
to prison for ten years.
Cardenala found employment as a servant near
the prison, so that she could visit Juanantes
every Sunday.
After many Sundays they began to talk of when
Juanantes would be freed.
"What are you going to do?" asked Cardenala.
Juanantes heard her words again and again
in his mind.
What are you going to do?
What are you...?
Not we.
He looked hard at Cardenala, as a policeman
looks at a suspect, searching for signs.
Was she planning to stay in the city?
Was there another man?
"Tell me, Cardenala.
Aren't you coming back with me?"
"No."
Her quiet answer, her guilt, hit him.
For a moment he couldn't speak.
"All right.
All right.
But I must go back to our village.
You know that, don't you?"
"Yes, I know.
But I don't care what you say.
I'm not going with you.
I went to see the priest.
He told me it was the work of the devil.
I'm not going to fall into that trap again."
"The priest?
Why did you go to the priest?" he asked her.
"My boss wanted me to.
He was worried about me.
He's very kind to me."
Juanantes knew it then.
He knew that he was losing Cardenala.
Prison was bad, like a kind of death.
Four walls.
Always the same four walls.
The desperate faces.
The waiting.
The long, lonely nights.
But losing Cardenala?
No.
Impossible.
There was nothing he could do, though.
When the evil light has fallen on a man, everything
goes wrong.
He would have to go back to their village
alone.
The following Sunday Cardenala came to visit
as usual.
"You've come," he said.
"Of course I've come.
What do you mean?"
"Well, I thought..."
"You thought!
You thought!
You think too much!"
laughed Cardenala.
In her mouth a new gold tooth shone.
"And this tooth?" asked Juanantes.
"Oh, my boss paid for it."
"Your boss again.
And you paid him back?"
"Of course.
Stop questioning me!"
Juanantes asked again.
"Are you coming back with me?"
"No, Juanantes."
Short and sharp.
It cut his heart.
"Well, at least..."
He stopped.
His voice left him.
"At least this way I know," he finally managed
to say.
"These things happen to people who have swallowed
the evil light."
His sad eyes grew hard as he watched Cardenala's
face.
On his last day he gathered his few remaining
possessions - a few clothes, old and full
of holes now, and the torn pieces of a picture
of Cardenala.
He had torn the picture up, put it back together,
torn it up, so many times.
But still he saved the pieces.
He went to a hotel to stay that night and
filled in the form at reception with his full
name, Juanantes Dios Rodriguez.
Then he left with no explanation.
Why?
The keys!
Those large, heavy room keys reminded him
of his prison cell, of hundreds of cells.
He wandered around without sleeping or eating
until his stomach ached with hunger.
But he couldn't sit in the cafe, where people
stood in line like prisoners.
So he walked along the dusty road toward the
mountains.
He knew something still had to be done.
He had killed Prudencio Salvatierra ten long
years ago.
Now he had to obey the mandate's final order.
He went to where he had been living with Cardenala.
Nothing had changed.
Everything was as it had always been.
The trees, the rocks.
It even seemed that the same old dogs still,
now, after ten years, slept in the sun.
Juanantes felt full of sorrow.
But he wasn't doing anything.
He wasn't living.
And so, without further thought, he called
on the wise old man, Tata Guamarachito, for
help.
"It's no good being in this condition," the
old man told Juanantes.
"You're good for nothing.
Nothing goes right.
I know why you're suffering.
As a young man the same thing happened to
me.
Yes, I can help you.
I can help you understand what you're dealing
with.
I can advise you about what you have to do."
"But I don't want to do what the mandate ordered!"
shouted Juanantes.
"I have no enemies."
"It's not necessary to have an enemy."
"Yes, but to bury the evil light, this evil
light, which by accident or pure bad luck
I've fallen into, I know that I have to write
a mandate, an order to kill someone.
I have to put that into the metal box.
But I keep telling you: I have no one to kill!
It's hopeless anyway.
The evil light has entered my body, like sand.
I cough.
I even cough blood!
It's in me.
It got into me in prison.
I..."
As he was speaking he lost control and fell,
coughing, to the ground.
But the old man was still not persuaded.
"How do you know it's the evil light?" he
asked calmly.
Juanantes told him that pieces of the evil
light were everywhere.
He saw them clearly, dancing around him, causing
him to cough, giving him night fevers.
"Then get away from them," was the old man's
advice.
But Juanantes asked again, with anger now,
"How can I do this if I have no enemies?"
"Calm down.
I'm only trying to help.
And don't blame yourself so much.
You've paid your debt in prison for killing
Salvatierra.
You killed fairly.
The two of you faced each other as men, with
machetes.
Salvatierra died and you lived.
If you hadn't followed the mandate to kill
someone, you would have been killed yourself.
Because it was written.'
But Juanantes was still unhappy.
"It would be better if I were dead."
"Don't talk like that.
In my experience it's never better to be dead
than alive."
"What has to be done then?
What must I do?"
"You must light the fire of evil light and
write your own mandate to put into the metal
box by the fire."
"But I've told you.
I can't write this mandate."
"Juanantes, if you let me, I'll show you a
way to break the chain of death, the chain
which has caught you."
"No, Tata.
If I break the chain of death, it will only
bring me more tragedy.
More sorrow!
I..."
The old man interrupted.
" The evil light that's around you is responsible
for many deaths.
It's time to put an end to it.
I've told you that I can show you how to break
this chain.
Be brave.
Believe in me.
Write your own mandate.
Use your own words.
The words of Juanantes Dios Rodriguez, a man
of honor.
Then we'll do together what has to be done."
They arranged to meet in nine weeks, when
the night would be at its blackest.
On that night they waited, hidden behind some
trees.
They heard the sound of a horse coming, slowly,
cautiously.
Juanantes lit the fire.
The horse and rider slowly approached the
fire.
The rider got down, with his gun in his hand.
A moment passed.
There was silence.
Then the rider rushed toward the fire, took
the bag which Tata Guamarachito and Juanantes
had left there, jumped onto his horse, and
rode away into the night.
"See how simple it was," said Tata Guamarachito,
throwing his arm around Juanantes's shoulder.
"Look at you!
Already the evil light is leaving you.
The sadness is lifting.
But have you broken the chain of death?
The bones, your machete - the same machete
you used to kill Salvatierra - the bottle
of whiskey, the gold, were all there in the
bag.
But you didn't order anyone to be killed.
So what did you order instead?
What did you write on that piece of paper,
with your signature, which you put in the
metal box?"
"That one thing I can't tell you.
It's my secret."
"But you didn't order anyone to be killed?"
"No.
I told you, I couldn't.
I have no enemies."
"Then what was your order?"
"I repeat, Tata, that's my secret."
"All right.
I respect that."
"Please forgive me, Tata."
"There's no need.
Men with secrets are always interesting to
me.
But let me tell you.
You're breaking a chain, a chain that has
caused many deaths and destroyed many lives.
I'm..."
Tata Guamarachito coughed, the heavy cough
of a smoker.
"I'm close to 100 years old.
But when I was your age...
How old are you?
About thirty?
When I was your age, I fell into the evil
light.
I was ordered to kill a man, Belisario Consuegra,
a man I had never met.
A man I had never seen.
But one day, I was at a market buying a horse
and I heard someone shouting, 'Belisario!
Belisario Consuegra!'
My blood turned cold.
I couldn't see or hear.
I took out my machete, found him, and ordered
him to defend himself or be killed like an
animal.
He fought.
But I killed him.
I cut him into pieces.
The smell of his blood made me crazy."
"But did you bury your evil light with a mandate?"
"Yes, Juanantes.
There was a man, a Mexican, my enemy.
My mandate was found by Placido Salgaespera,
and Salgaespera killed the Mexican with his
machete.
Salgaespera's mandate was then found by Remigio
Huertas, who killed Salgaespera's enemy, and
it has continued in this way.
Say that you've broken the chain, Juanantes.
Tell me this."
But Juanantes only sat silently watching the
sunrise.
He always watched the sunrise, but had never
liked the morning.
Now, however, freed from the evil light, it
seemed to be the most beautiful dawn he could
ever experience.
Suddenly he wanted Cardenala.
He wanted her so badly.
But he stopped these thoughts as soon as they
began.
Why should he want her?
He knew now that Cardenala was part of the
evil light which had brought him to this place.
Because of her, Prudencio Salvatierra now
lay cold in the ground.
When the sun had fully risen, he offered Tata
Guamarachito payment for his services.
The old man wouldn't accept money.
"I want only to know your secret.
The mandate that the horseman read."
But without speaking, Juanantes walked away.
He was going down the mountain when he suddenly
changed his mind, turned, and started back
toward Tata Guamarachito.
Walking, then running, shouting, "Tata!
Wait!
I will!
I will share my secret with you!"
When he reached the place where they had sat,
he bent down and whispered in the old man's
ear.
"Is that true?
Was that really your mandate?" asked the old
man, smiling, trying to hold back his tears
of joy.
"Yes.
Yes.
That she too would be torn up when the picture
was torn up.
Now I know, Tata, that when I tore up Cardenala's
picture in prison it began to free me, to
free me from her evil power.
Woman, when she goes bad, is the worst of
all evil lights.
Because of this, my mandate ordered the unknown
rider to take the picture of the first person
with an untrue heart that he found, the first
unfaithful friend or lover, and tear it into
pieces.
There are many ways of destroying someone."