CHAPTER ONE
Our Heroine's Adventures Begin
If you had known Catherine Morland as a young
child, you would never have imagined that
one day she would be the heroine of a novel
filled with adventure, mystery and romance.
Her father was a respected clergyman, neither
rich nor poor, and her mother was a strong,
sensible mother of ten children.
The Morlands were often described as a fine
family, but that was because there were so
many of them, not because any of them were
handsome, beautiful or noticeably talented.
For the first ten years of her life, Catherine
was as ordinary as the rest of the Morlands.
She was thin and clumsy, with dull skin and
hair.
She spent her time throwing a ball, riding
a horse or chasing her brothers and sisters
while avoiding any lady-like activities like
arranging flowers, nursing a poor injured
pet or watering a pretty rose bush.
And certainly Catherine's education could
not be described as appropriate for a heroine.
In fact, she had an obvious dislike for the
classroom and never could learn or understand
anything before she was taught; occasionally
she even seemed rather stupid.
Her mother wanted her to learn music and Catherine
was sure that she would like to play the piano,
so at eight years old she began lessons.
But she soon gave up, and the day on which
the music teacher was dismissed was one of
the happiest days of her young life.
Her drawing ability was also disappointing;
although she enjoyed drawing animals, all
her pictures, from chickens to horses, looked
very similar.
Whatastrange, incomprehensible character!
Incomprehensible because, in spite of such
clear signs of a difficult nature, Catherine
was seldom unpleasant; she rarely quarrelled
and was very kind to her six younger brothers
and sisters and quite friendly with the three
older ones.
But it still must be admitted that she was
untidy, noisy and wild and loved nothing better
than rolling down her favourite hill at the
back of the house.
At fifteen, Catherine's appearance began to
improve; her skin was brighter, her hair was
shinier and nicely styled, her eyes shone
and her figure was pleasing.
Her love of dirt was replaced by an interest
in the latest fashions and in the possibility
of going to a ball.
She was quite thrilled one day to hear her
father remark on her personal improvement:
'Catherine is almost pretty today.'
To be almost pretty is a great prize to a
girl who has been plain for fifteen years.
Catherine had never been interested in books
full of facts and useful knowledge, but from
the age of fifteen she began to read the type
of books which heroines must read: stories
of romance, adventure and fantasy, set in
mysterious foreign places.
These supplied her memory with useful instructions
about life, death, and especially love.
And although she could not write poetry or
play the piano or paint a picture - achievements
we might expect in a heroine - she began,
nevertheless, to admire those skills in others.
At the beginning of our story, Catherine was
seventeen and eager for life.
But the world around Fullerton, the village
in Wiltshire where the Morlands lived, did
not offer the kind of adventure and romance
that a heroine needs.
Luckily for Catherine, Mr Allen, the gentleman
who owned most of the property around Fullerton,
was required by his doctor to go to the city
of Bath for a healthy rest.
His wife, a good-natured woman with no children
of her own, was very fond of Catherine.
She understood that a young lady of seventeen
is ready to take her place in society, so
she invited our heroine to accompany her and
Mr Allen to Bath for the season.
When the time came for Catherine's first trip
away from home without her family, you can
imagine the excitement and anxiety in the
Morland household.
Would Mrs Morland warn her daughter about
the evils of city life and the dangers of
mixing with the wrong sort of gentleman?
Would her father generously hand her a blank
cheque to cover every need?
Would the sister closest to her in age insist
that she write to her every day and tell her
every detail of her life in Bath?
Well, no.
This, after all, was an ordinary family from
rural England.
Mrs Morland simply said: 'Catherine, please
remember to wear your warm scarf around your
throat when you are out in the evening.'
Mr Morland gave Catherine a small purse with
ten pounds and promised more if it was needed.
Catherine's sister, Sarah, shouted goodbye
as she ran out to meet a friend.
In fact, the family had not realised that
Catherine was going to be a heroine.
They cheerfully but quietly sent her off without
any dramatic speeches, tears or warnings.
The trip to Bath was both calm and safe.
The carriage was not stopped by robbers or
by stormy weather; nor were the passengers
lucky enough to meet a hero before arriving
at their destination.
But when they arrived in Bath, Catherine felt
happy immediately.
Her eyes were here, there, everywhere as the
carriage drove through the pretty streets.
Soon Mr and Mrs Allen and Catherine were settled
in comfortable lodgings in Pulteney Street.
And what do we know about Mrs Allen, Catherine's
close companion and chaperone for the coming
weeks?
She was the type of woman who amazes us by
finding a husband.
Why would any sensible gentleman, like Mr
Allen, want a wife without beauty, intelligence,
achievements or a pretty manner?
Well, she was generally quiet, did not concern
herself with his business and agreed with
his opinions on every topic.
In addition to these qualities, Mrs Allen
had two special interests that kept her busy
and made her a suitable person to introduce
a young lady into society.
First, she loved going out and never chose
to stay quietly at home.
Second, she found endless pleasure in fashion;
she would not consider taking Catherine to
any of the stylish Rooms in Bath until they
had both bought new dresses in the latest
style.
When they were ready to attend their first
ball, Mrs Allen declared that Catherine looked
exactly as she should.
Such admiration was always very welcome when
it came, but Catherine did not depend on it.
Nevertheless, on this evening it made her
confident enough to face any crowd of strangers.
When they entered the ballroom, Mr Allen escaped
to a side-room to play cards with a group
of husbands.
Meanwhile, the two ladies looked around a
very full ballroom and, with Catherine holding
her chaperone's arm rather desperately, they
struggled through the crowd.
They finally found a place on a balcony at
the top of the long room with a good view
of the company below them.
It was a splendid sight and Catherine began,
for the first time that evening, to feel that
she was really at a ball.
She hoped to dance, but did not know anyone
in the room, and Mrs Allen did not see anyone
she knew either.
'Surely I should see a familiar face soon.
I wish I could find a partner for you,' remarked
Mrs Allen.
Catherine had no time to worry about dancing
because before long everyone began to move
towards the tea tables.
But Catherine and Mrs Allen were at a distinct
disadvantage without a party of friends to
join or a polite gentleman to assist them.
After being pushed and squeezed by the crowd,
they finally found two empty places at the
end of a long table where a large group was
already seated.
The two ladies were ignored and left with
no one to speak to except one another.
'Well, I am very pleased that I have not damaged
my new dress in this terrible crowd, I assure
you.
It would have been shocking to have it torn,
wouldn't it?' said Mrs Allen.
'I must say that I have not seen one dress
in the whole room that I prefer to mine.'
'It is very uncomfortable with no friends
here, don't you think?'
whispered Catherine.
'What shall we do?
The gentlemen and ladies at this table do
not look happy with us here.
We seem to be forcing ourselves into their
party.'
'Yes, it is very disagreeable,' said Mrs Allen.
'My good friends the Skinners would rescue
us if they were here now.'
'Shouldn't we leave?
There are no cups or plates for us here, you
see,' Catherine said with a worried frown.
'I think we should sit still,' said Mrs Allen.
'We shall be pushed and pulled in every direction
if we try to find another place in this crowd.
My dress could easily be damaged.'
'Mrs Allen, are you sure there is nobody that
you know in this great assembly of people?
You must know somebody.'
'Oh, if only I could see a familiar face,'
Mrs Allen said.
'Oh, look!
There goes a strange-looking woman.
What an odd, old-fashioned dress!
Look at the back of it.
How awful!'
After some time the two ladies received a
polite offer of tea from one of their neighbours
at the table.
They accepted gratefully and enjoyed a little
light conversation with the gentleman, but
that soon ended and no one else spoke to them
during the entire evening.
When the dancing came to an end, Mr Allen
found Catherine and his wife.
'Well, Miss Morland,' he said, 'I hope you
have had an agreeable ball.'
'Very agreeable indeed,' Catherine replied
politely, trying unsuccessfully to hide a
great yawn.
As the ballroom began to empty and the crowd
grew smaller, our heroine had a better opportunity
to be admired.
In her hearing, two gentlemen commented on
her to one another: 'There is a pretty girl.
Where was she all evening?'
Such words had a strong effect; Catherine
immediately thought that the evening had been
very pleasant.
Perhaps an experienced heroine would expect
more, but Catherine left the ball perfectly
satisfied with her share of public attention.
CHAPTER TWO
Extremely Agreeable Introductions
Every morning now brought its regular duties
for Catherine and Mrs Allen: visiting shops,
exploring Bath, attending the Pump Room, where
they walked up and down for an hour, looking
at everybody and speaking to no one.
Mrs Allen repeated her usual disappointment
every morning: 'Oh, my dear, I would very
much like to find someone I know in this crowd!'
Then on Friday evening when they arrived in
the Lower Rooms, Catherine's fortunes improved.
Mr King, whose job was to act as host, introduced
Catherine to a young gentleman as her dance
partner.
Mr Henry Tilney was about twenty-five years
old, rather tall, with a pleasing, if not
quite handsome, face and, in general, an intelligent
and energetic manner.
He spoke politely and Catherine felt lucky
to have him as a partner.
When the two young people retired to the tea
table, Catherine discovered that Mr Tilney
was very entertaining company.
After some polite conversation, he said in
a dramatic whisper, 'Miss Morland, I must
apologise.
I have not asked you how long you have been
in Bath; if you have been here before; whether
you have been in the Upper Rooms, to the theatre,
to a concert.
Forgive me and allow me to begin my list of
questions immediately.'
Then Mr Tilney, with a bow and in an exaggerated,
extremely polite voice asked, 'Have you been
in Bath long, madam?'
'About a week, sir,' answered Catherine, trying
not to laugh.
'A week!
Really!'
replied Mr Tilney with excessive surprise.
'Why should you be so surprised, sir?' asked
Catherine.
She too was now speaking like an actor in
the theatre.
'That is a good question!' said Tilney in
his normal voice, 'But reacting to your answers
with appropriate emotions and gestures is
my duty.
Now let us continue.
Were you ever here before, madam?'
'Never, sir,' replied Catherine, enjoying
the game.
'How interesting!'
cried Mr Tilney, continuing with his actor's
voice.
'Have you been to the Upper Rooms?
The theatre?
The concert hall?
And are you totally pleased with Bath?'
Catherine smiled at her companion and said,
'Yes, I have been everywhere, and I like the
city very much.'
She turned her head away, not knowing whether
she should laugh or not.
'Miss Morland, will you be writing unkind
things about me in your journal?
I predict you will say: "Friday, went to the
Lower Rooms and had to dance with a silly
man who bothered me with his strange conversation,
delivered in a funny voice.'"
'I would never say such a thing,' objected
Catherine.
'May I tell you what you ought to say?' asked
Mr Tilney.
'Please, sir.'
"'I danced with a very agreeable young man.
We enjoyed a great deal of pleasant conversation
and he seemed a most extraordinary and intelligent
person.
I hope I get to know him better."
That, madam, is what I wish you to write in
your journal.'
'But perhaps I do not have a journal.'
'Not have a journal!
How will you re-live every dance, every flattering
word, every admiring glance?
My dear madam, I think writing a journal is
delightful and so particularly suited to the
talents of young ladies, whose usual writing
style is perfectly faultless except in two
areas: a lack of subject, and no attention
to the essential rules that govern the English
language.'
'You do not have a very high opinion of ladies'
talents.'
'Actually, I believe that in every area where
good taste is the basis for success, high
achievement is quite fairly divided between
the sexes,' finished Mr Tilney.
But then this interesting discussion was interrupted
by Mrs Allen.
'My dear Catherine, can you look at my dress?
Have I torn it?
It cost me more than any other dress in my
wardrobe.'
'Madam, I can see why it was so expensive,'
said Mr Tilney.
'Miss Morland's dress, on the other hand,
is pretty but the fabric is too delicate.
It will not wash well.'
Catherine began laughing and said, 'Sir, how
can you be so...'
She almost said, 'strange'.
But Mrs Allen was delighted to talk about
her favourite subject, and Mr Tilney was polite
enough to continue chatting about fabrics
and current fashions for another five minutes.
When Mr Tilney and Catherine returned to the
dance floor, he noticed a troubled look on
his partner's face.
'What are you thinking of so seriously?' he
asked.
Catherine blushed; she had been wondering
if Mr Tilney had been too obviously teasing
Mrs Allen.
But she said, 'I was not thinking of anything.'
'You would not look so serious if something
had not upset you.
I would prefer to be told at once that you
choose not to tell me what you are thinking.'
'Well, then, I choose not to tell you,' replied
Catherine with clear determination.
'Thank you,' said her dance partner.
'Now I can tease you about your serious, secret
thoughts and opinions whenever we meet.
Nothing brings people closer than a bit of
teasing.'
They danced again, and when the assembly closed,
Catherine, at least, hoped that there would
be many more opportunities to continue their
friendship.
She did not intend to dream of Henry Tilney
that night.
As a famous writer has insisted, a young lady
must not dream about a gentleman or fall in
love with him before the gentleman declares
his love for her.
As Catherine's host and protector, Mr Allen
enquired about her dance partner.
Discovering that Henry Tilney was a clergyman
from a very respectable family in Gloucestershire
allowed him to feel satisfied that he had
done his duty.
With more than usual eagerness, Catherine
hurried to the Pump Room the next day.
She felt sure that she would see Mr Tilney
there and she was ready to meet him with a
smile.
But unfortunately no smile was required.
It seemed that every other creature in Bath
arrived in the room during the fashionable
hours; only Henry Tilney remained absent.
Mrs Allen once again repeated her usual complaint:
'How pleasant Bath would be if we had some
acquaintances here!'
This wish had been repeated by Mrs Allen so
often that it is not surprising that on this
morning she had her reward.
When she and Catherine sat down, the woman
to their right stared at them for a few seconds
before crying, 'Madam, if my eyes do not deceive
me, your name is Allen.'
Looking closely at the woman next to her,
Mrs Allen cried in delight, 'Mrs Thorpe, my
old school friend - it is you, isn't it?'
The two ladies had not been in contact for
more than fifteen years, and now their joy
in meeting again was enormous.
They chatted excitedly, talking both at the
same time, and each much more interested in
giving than receiving information.
Although Mrs Thorpe was a widow, and not a
very rich one, she had one great advantage
over Mrs Allen: she had three sons and three
daughters.
Mrs Allen had no children to talk about, but
as she listened to all the news about the
Thorpe children, she enjoyed noticing that
her old friend's costume was quite inferior
to anything in her own wardrobe.
'Look!
Here are my dear girls,' cried Mrs Thorpe,
pointing at three smart-looking females moving
towards them.
'The tallest, the most beautiful and most
elegant is Isabella, my eldest.'
After Mrs Allen was introduced, she presented
Catherine Morland to the Thorpe ladies.
'Miss Morland!
You are the picture of your brother!'
the Thorpes cried.
They quickly explained that their brother,
John, was at Oxford University and was a great
friend of James Morland, Catherine's brother,
who was studying to be a clergyman like his
father.
Catherine remembered that James had recently
visited a college friend and his family near
London.
And this was the family.
How lovely!
Soon the eldest Thorpe girl, Isabella, invited
Catherine to take her arm and walk round the
room with her.
Catherine was so delighted that she almost
forgot Henry Tilney while she was talking
to Miss Thorpe.
Friendship is certainly the finest medicine
for the pain of disappointed love.
Because Miss Isabella Thorpe was four years
older, Catherine felt that she could learn
a lot about society from her new friend.
When they parted, she watched Isabella as
she walked away.
She admired the older girl's graceful walk,
her lovely figure, her fashionable dress,
and she felt extremely lucky to have found
such a charming companion.
That evening at the theatre and the next morning
in the warm sunshine in the Crescent, Catherine
enjoyed the sweet pleasure of her new and
agreeable friendship with Isabella.
She was so much happier than she had been
in her first week in Bath, but she desired
another meeting with Mr Henry Tilney and could
find him nowhere.
He must have left Bath, although he had not
mentioned his departure on Friday evening.
Of course this sort of mysterious behaviour
is always attractive in a hero, and it made
our heroine anxious to know more about him.
Isabella loved to hear anything with even
a hint of romance, and wanted to know everything
about Henry Tilney; therefore, he became a
regular topic of conversation for the two
young ladies.
Catherine re-lived every moment that she had
spent with the young gentleman, and Isabella
analysed the situation and gave advice from
her superior experience and wisdom.
'He must be a charming young man, and I am
sure he found you equally charming.
He must have important business in Gloucestershire
and will soon return to Bath.
And he is a clergyman!
I have a particular liking for clergymen,'
Isabella said in a rather dreamy voice.
Not being experienced in the etiquette of
romance, Catherine did not demand to know
the cause of Isabella's emotional response
to clergymen.
Perhaps as a good friend she should have insisted
that her friend tell her more about her 'particular
liking'.
The friendship between the two girls nevertheless
continued to grow and to become more and more
affectionate.
Even if the weather was very poor, the two
young ladies walked through mud and rain to
sit together and read novels.
Yes, novels!
To many people, novels are considered to be
nothing more than foolish nonsense.
But why?
Novels may not be as serious as books about
history or science or even art, but novels
have humour, mystery, culture and elegance.
Do not, therefore, say, 'Oh!
It is only a novel!'
Read novels and learn everything about human
nature in the most delightful language and
through the most entertaining plots.
Our two young ladies, you will see, had already
learned this lesson.
Listen to their conversation in the Pump Room
after a friendship of only eight or nine days.
'My dear Catherine,' Isabella began, 'I saw
the prettiest hat you can imagine in the shop
in Milsom Street; I must say that I longed
to have it.
But, Catherine, what have you been doing all
morning?
Have you read more Udolpho?'
'Oh, yes!' cried Catherine.
'I am at the part with the black veil.'
'You are desperate to know what is behind
the veil, aren't you?'
'Do not tell me!
I know it must be Laurentina's bones.
Oh, I love Udolpho!
I assure you that only a meeting with you
could persuade me to come away from it.'
'How charming of you.
When you finish Udolpho, I have a list of
ten or twelve other Gothic novels that I am
certain you will love,' Isabella said.
'But are they all frightening and full of
dark secrets and mysterious accidents?'
hoped Catherine.
'Of course,' Isabella assured her.
'My friend Miss Andrews has recommended them
to me.
Miss Andrews is as beautiful as an angel,
and I often scold men terribly for not admiring
her!'
'Scold them!
Do you really scold them for not admiring
her?' asked Catherine, who was quite shocked
by Isabella.
'Yes, in fact, I told Captain Hunt at a ball
this winter that even if he teased me all
evening, I would not dance with him unless
he admitted that Miss Andrews was beautiful.
I am determined to show men that we ladies
are capable of real friendship.
For example, if I heard anybody say anything
negative about you, I would quickly lose my
temper.
Of course, that will not happen, because you
will always be a great favourite with the
men.'
'How can you say that?'
Catherine cried, blushing bright red.
'Dear Catherine, Miss Andrews is really quite
dull compared to you.
I saw a young man watching you yesterday,
and I am sure he is in love with you.
Don't look embarrassed.
I understand perfectly that your heart is
attached to another man, who shall remain
nameless.'
'But I may never see Mr Tilney again,' said
Catherine rather desperately.
'Don't say that I have lost my heart to him.
I will not think about him; instead, I shall
worry about the black veil.'
'Well, my dear, we will change the subject.
Have you decided what you will wear tonight?
I am determined to dress exactly like you.
The men take notice of that sometimes, you
know.'
'Does it mean anything?' asked Catherine innocently.
'Mean anything!
I make it a rule to ignore what men notice
or what they say.
They are often very bold if you do not treat
them with spirit and make them keep their
distance.'
'Are they bold?
Men always behave very politely to me,' said
Catherine, feeling quite confused.
'Oh, men think they are so important!
But, listen, I have meant to ask you something:
do you prefer men with dark or fair hair?'
'I have not really thought about it,' answered
Catherine, 'but perhaps neither.
Something between the two: a medium brown.'
'That sounds like your description of Mr Tilney's
hair, and he has dark brown eyes, if I remember
correctly.
I actually prefer fair hair and blue eyes
better than any other, but do not reveal my
preference if you know anyone like that.'
'Why would I do that?'
Catherine asked, feeling more confused than
ever.
'Catherine, let us drop the subject for now.
Let us move to the other end of the room.
I believe there are two bold young men near
us who have been staring at me for more than
half an hour.'
The young ladies walked to the book at the
front of the room.
'Watch those two young men, dear Catherine.
I hope they are not following us.
I refuse to take any notice of them.'
'There is nothing to worry about, dear Isabella,'
Catherine assured her friend.
'They have left the Pump Room.'
'Which way did they go?' asked Isabella in
a rush.
'One was very good-looking.'
'They went towards the church.'
'Well, I am very glad that I have got rid
of them!'
insisted Isabella.
'Now please accompany me to the hat shop.'
'That would be lovely,' agreed Catherine,
'but we may see those two young men if we
go in that direction.'
'I will not take any notice of them.
If I did, it would spoil them and make them
believe they were important.'
Catherine did not know how to argue against
this logic, so she and her friend walked as
quickly as possible towards the hat shop,
following in the steps of the two young men.
CHAPTER THREE
A Complicated Social Life
The young ladies' progress was stopped at
the busiest crossroads in Bath.
Every day parties of ladies out on important
tasks like buying cakes, trying on hats, or
even (as in the present case) searching the
roads for two young men, were held up by the
traffic at this corner.
'We shall be kept here for a terribly long
time,' Isabella complained.
'Look at this carriage coming towards us.
What dangerous driving!'
But Isabella's attitude changed when she looked
again.
'How delightful!
It is Mr Morland and my brother!'
'Good heavens!
It is James!'
uttered Catherine when she saw her blond,
blue-eyed brother.
John Thorpe and James Morland got out of their
carriage, and although Catherine was totally
surprised by the arrival of her brother, she
greeted him with the most sincere pleasure.
James could not say much to his sister for
the moment because Miss Thorpe clearly intended
to gain his attention with her flirtatious
eyes and sweet smiles.
James responded to Isabella with a mixture
of joy and embarrassment which, if she had
been more of an expert in matters of the heart,
might have given Catherine a clue to the reason
for her brother's visit.
John Thorpe, a rather fat young man of medium
height with a plain face and ungraceful style,
immediately claimed everyone's attention.
Looking at his watch, he shouted, 'Twenty-five
miles from Tetbury to Bath in two and a half
hours!
We left Tetbury as the town clock struck eleven.'
'You have lost an hour, John,' James Morland
corrected him.
We left the inn at Tetbury at ten o'clock.'
'Miss Morland, your brother is dreaming.
My horse could never take over three hours
for such a journey.
And have you noticed my carriage?
I just gave fifty pounds for it to a friend
at Oxford.
Now, lead the way to Mother's lodgings, Isabella.'
Isabella was so happy to take James's arm
and when they passed the two offensive young
men from the Pump Room, she only looked back
at them three times.
Mr Thorpe accompanied Catherine, and no sooner
had they begun their walk than he started
to talk about his superior carriage again.
'Do you like an open carriage, Miss Morland?'
'Very much, but I have few opportunities of
being in one.'
'I shall drive you to Lansdown Hill tomorrow,
and I shall take you out in my carriage every
day that I am in Bath.'
Catherine was not sure if this was an appropriate
arrangement, but she said, 'Thank you, but
won't your horse need a rest?'
'Never!
That horse has only covered twenty-five miles
today.
Too much rest ruins a good horse.
I am an expert on horses and tomorrow you
and I will drive to Lansdown, Miss Morland.'
Isabella was listening to her brother and
turned and said, 'And what about me?'
'Isabella, I did not come to Bath to drive
my sisters around, especially not those two
ugly younger ones.
Anyway, Morland must take care of you.'
And turning towards Catherine, he said, 'Miss
Morland, let us be dance partners this evening.
It is always good to get these annoying arrangements
out of the way.'
After getting her agreement, Mr Thorpe seemed
to give up chatting with Catherine.
Instead, he made comments to her about the
appearance of every woman they passed.
Some he said were pretty, some fat, some old,
some almost handsome.
Although Catherine was very inexperienced,
she doubted if Mr Thorpe was behaving very
politely, so she tried to change the direction
of his comments.
'Have you ever read Udolpho, Mr Thorpe?'
'Lord, no!
There has not been a good novel since Tom
Jones.'
'You might like Udolpho; it is so interesting,'
said Catherine.
'No, if I read any, it will be one of Mrs
Radcliff's; she knows something about real
life,' said Mr Thorpe confidently.
Catherine did not want to embarrass Mr Thorpe,
but she had to say, 'Udolpho was written by
Mrs Radcliff.'
'Was it?
Oh, yes,' Mr Thorpe replied.
'I was thinking of that other stupid book
by that woman who married a foreigner.
Keep away from anything she has written.'
Once again Catherine felt that she had misunderstood
the reasoning behind someone's opinions.
When James Morland visited his sister and
Mr and Mrs Allen at their lodgings later that
afternoon, he asked, 'Well, Catherine, how
do you like my friend Thorpe?'
If John Thorpe had had no connection to her
brother or to her new friend, and if there
had been no invitations for carriage rides
and dance partners, Catherine would have said,
'I do not like him at all.'
But under the present circumstances, she said,
'I like him very much; he seems very agreeable.'
'He is a good-natured fellow.
Perhaps a little too full of opinions sometimes,
but you girls like that in a gentleman, don't
you?
And how do you like the rest of the family?'
'Oh, very much, especially Isabella,' Catherine
said happily.
'I am very glad to hear you say that,' said
James.
'She has so much good sense and is so friendly
and kind.
Since I met her, I have wanted you to meet
her and now I learn that she already has a
very high opinion of you.
I am sure you may be very proud of receiving
praise from a girl like Miss Thorpe.
And I am sure she is greatly admired in a
place like Bath, isn't she?'
'I believe so,' agreed Catherine.
'Mr Allen thinks that she is the prettiest
girl in the city.'
'I do not know any man who is a better judge
of beauty than Mr Allen.
And, dear Catherine, are you pleased to be
here?'
'James, I have never been so happy,' admitted
Catherine.
'Everything is so exciting, and now I am even
more delighted.
How good it is of you to come so far to see
me.'
The Morland children had been taught not to
lie, so James chose his next words carefully.
He simply said, 'My sweet Catherine, I love
you dearly.'
The Thorpes and the Allens, with Catherine
and James Morland, met that evening in the
Upper Rooms.
Isabella was all smiles when she saw Catherine,
and the two girls followed their chaperones
into the ballroom, whispering to each other
and exchanging affectionate glances.
James was engaged to dance with Miss Thorpe,
and invited her to join the sets of dancers
when the music began.
Catherine, who you will remember was also
engaged to dance, could not see her partner
anywhere.
'Mr Morland, I cannot possibly begin to dance
while my dear friend is without a partner.
We will wait here with her until my brother
returns,' explained Isabella.
Catherine felt very grateful for this kindness,
and she continued to chat with Isabella for
another three minutes.
But after turning to James Morland on her
left, Isabella whispered, 'My dear Catherine,
your brother is so impatient to begin.
I know you will forgive me for going away,
and I am sure John will return in a moment,
and then you can come and find me.'
Catherine was too polite to oppose her friend's
plan as she watched the couple hurry on to
the dance floor, but she was upset and rather
cross.
Not only did she want to dance, but she also
did not want to be pointed out as a young
lady in need of a dance partner.
Nevertheless, such things happen in a heroine's
life; Catherine suffered, but she made no
comment about the disappointment caused by
John Thorpe's rude behaviour.
After another ten minutes, Catherine was shaken
from this angry state by the sight of Mr Henry
Tilney, who was walking towards her party
with a young woman on his arm.
Fortunately he had not seen her yet so she
was able, like a true heroine, to hide her
blush and sudden smile.
Mr Tilney looked as handsome and as full of
life as Catherine remembered as he chatted
with the stylish, good-looking young woman
at his side.
Instead of turning pale and filling her head
with tragic thoughts of a possible Mrs Henry
Tilney, Catherine correctly guessed that the
young lady was the sister who Mr Tilney had
mentioned to her and Mrs Allen on Friday.
One of the ladies in the Tilneys' party, a
Mrs Hughes, was an acquaintance of Mrs Thorpe's,
and as she spoke to Isabella's mother, Mr
Tilney saw Catherine and smiled at her in
recognition.
Catherine returned his smile very prettily
and said, 'How nice to see you again, sir.
I was afraid you had left Bath.'
'Thank you, Miss Morland, for your fears.
I had to leave Bath the morning after I had
the pleasure of meeting you.'
'Well, sir, I hope you are happy to be back
again.
I find Bath an exciting place at this time
of year,' responded Catherine.
After a few enjoyable moments of conversation,
Mr Tilney asked Catherine to dance with him.
This delightful invitation produced terrible
anxiety in our heroine; and in giving her
refusal, she expressed her genuine sorrow,
explaining that she was already engaged to
dance with another gentleman.
Just then John Thorpe inconveniently wandered
over to the group and claimed Catherine as
his partner.
As they danced, Mr Thorpe's conversation about
buying a good hunting dog allowed Catherine
to keep watch on the part of the room where
she had left Mr Tilney.
She also looked around for Isabella, wanting
to point out Henry Tilney to her dear friend,
but she seemed cruelly separated from friends
and acquaintances.
As Mr Thorpe continued his one-sided conversation,
Catherine began to realise a useful lesson:
it is not always best to arrange your dance
partners before going to a ball.
But luckily Catherine's thoughts were interrupted
by a light touch on her shoulder from Mrs
Hughes.
'I beg your pardon, Miss Morland,' Mrs Hughes
began.
'Would you allow Miss Tilney and her partner
to join your set?'
Catherine could not have been more pleased.
She now had the opportunity to chat with Henry's
sister, and she welcomed the young lady very
warmly and politely.
Miss Tilney was attractive in every way; she
was not as fashionable as Miss Isabella Thorpe,
but she was more naturally elegant.
She was polite to everyone and was capable
of being young, beautiful and at a ball without
flirting with every man near her, and without
becoming over-excited or over-dramatic about
insignificant flattery.
At the conclusion of the two dances, Catherine
found her arm immediately seized by her dear
Isabella, who in an excited voice cried, 'At
last I have got you.
Why didn't you and John join our set?
I have been quite miserable without you.
I kept telling your brother to search for
you, but he was extremely lazy and would not
leave my side.
Isn't that right, Mr Morland?
I have been scolding him all evening.
You would be amazed.'
Catherine pulled Isabella away from James
and whispered urgently, 'Do you see that young
lady with the white ribbons in her hair?
It is Mr Tilney's sister.'
'Oh!
Let me get a good look at her!'
cried Isabella.
'I have never seen anyone half as beautiful!
So wonderfully dressed!
But where is her famous brother?
I am dying to see him.'
'What is all this whispering about?' asked
James.
'Men are so much more curious than women,'
teased Isabella.
'This is not about you and we will not tell
you anything about it.'
'And is that likely to satisfy me?'
James asked with a smile.
'Please don't listen,' Isabella smiled back.
'Perhaps we are talking about you and you
may hear something disagreeable.'
This flirtatious chat continued between Isabella
and James for so long that the original topic
seemed entirely forgotten.
Although Catherine felt a sense of relief
to have the subject of Henry Tilney dropped,
she was a bit disturbed by Isabella's apparent
lack of interest in her news.
When the music began again, James started
to lead Isabella to the dance floor.
'Catherine, tell your brother we must change
partners after two dances together,' Isabella
cried.
'My dear Miss Thorpe,' objected James politely,
'in these public assemblies, we are not required
to change partners.'
'You men,' cried Isabella, 'always insist
that you are correct about everything!
Catherine, tell your brother that everyone,
including you, would be shocked if we danced
together again.'
'I do not see why anyone would be shocked,'
Catherine said innocently, 'but if you think
it is wrong, you should, of course, change
partners.'
'You see, James, your sister is on my side,
but you will not listen to her!
Well remember, sir, it is not my fault if
all the old ladies start gossiping about us.'
And off she went to dance again with Mr James
Morland.
Meanwhile, John Thorpe had disappeared again
and Catherine had to return to her seat beside
Mrs Allen and Mrs Thorpe.
'Oh, my dear, did you see Mr Tilney just now?
He was tired of sitting and went off to find
a dance partner,' reported Mrs Allen.
'I thought perhaps he would ask you to dance,
if he saw you.'
'Where can he be?' said Catherine desperately.
She looked round and saw him leading a young
lady to the dance floor.
Catherine had missed the most desirable opportunity
of the evening and was not in a friendly mood
when John Thorpe came up to her and said,
'Well, Miss Morland, I suppose you and I should
have another dance together.'
'No, thank you,' Catherine said rather coolly.
'I do not intend to dance again this evening.'
'Oh, really?
Well, let us walk around the room and examine
everyone.
We could start with my two younger sisters
and their partners.
Did you ever see such silly, unattractive
girls?'
Catherine did not enjoy Mr Thorpe's comments
and again excused herself from joining him.
She sat with the older ladies and found the
rest of the evening very dull.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Shift in Our Heroine's Affections
Catherine's reaction to her disappointing
evening in the Upper Rooms was to go to bed
and sleep for nine uninterrupted hours.
She awoke the next morning perfectly rested,
in excellent spirits and with fresh hopes
and schemes.
She wanted to get to know Miss Tilney better,
and with that in mind, she planned to go in
the early afternoon to the Pump Room, where
any new arrival in Bath was likely to be.
And so our heroine happily sat with Mrs Allen
that morning, reading her book and smiling
at her companion's comments about everything
that crossed her mind, from a stain on the
carpet to the noise of a carriage in the street.
Then at about half past twelve, an extremely
loud knock on the door made both ladies look
up suddenly.
Before the servant could announce him, Mr
John Thorpe came running up the stairs and
into Mrs Allen's sitting-room.
'Well, Miss Morland, here we are.
Isabella and your brother are waiting outside
in their carriage and are in a great hurry
to get going.
Good morning, Mrs Allen.
A terribly good ball last night, wasn't it?
Have you seen my fine carriage outside?
Far superior to the rented carriage Morland
is driving.'
'Mr Thorpe, what is happening?' asked Catherine.
'Miss Morland, what a silly girl you are.
You agreed to go for a drive this morning.
We are all going up Claverton Hill.'
'I remember that you mentioned a carriage
ride, but really I did not expect you,' Catherine
explained.
'Not expect me!
I wonder how you would have complained if
I had not come for you!'
shouted John Thorpe.
Catherine did not know what to do and so looked
to Mrs Allen for guidance.
She wondered if it was proper to go for a
drive in Mr Thorpe's carriage without a chaperone.
Would Mrs Allen approve since James and Isabella
were going too?
'Well, madam, shall I go or not?' asked Catherine.
'Do as you please, my dear,' replied Mrs Allen
calmly.
She did not seem to understand any of Catherine's
anxiety.
A drive in an open carriage with Isabella
and James following behind in a second carriage
was almost as exciting as the possibility
of another meeting with Miss Tilney, and,
with Mrs Allen's permission, Catherine was
ready to go in two minutes.
As she and Mr Thorpe hurried out of the house,
they were greeted by Isabella.
'Catherine!
My dearest creature!
What a delightful ball we had last night.
I have a thousand things to discuss with you.
But now I am anxious to begin our adventure.'
John Thorpe helped Catherine into his carriage,
saying, 'Don't be frightened, Miss Morland,
if my horse shows a bit of spirit.
You are in no danger; I am an excellent horseman!'
With this warning, Catherine was surprised
when the horse started and continued in the
quietest manner imaginable.
A silence of several minutes was broken when
Mr Thorpe suddenly asked, 'Old Allen is one
of the richest men in Wiltshire, isn't he?'
'Oh, do you mean Mr Allen?' asked Catherine,
not understanding how this topic of conversation
had come up.
'Yes, I believe he is very rich.'
'And no children at all?'
'No, not any.'
'And he is a relative of yours, isn't he?'
'Oh, no.
We are not related,'
'But you spend a lot of time with them.'
'Yes, very much.'
After that short exchange, Mr Thorpe talked
about more topics that interested him: his
horse, the value of his carriage, his skill
as a horseman, the expensive wine he served
in his Oxford apartment.
Catherine had been brought up in a family
of plain people who were not in the habit
of telling lies or exaggerating their own
importance.
Mr Thorpe, on the other hand, was obviously
accustomed to a type of conversation which
always began and ended with praise for himself.
Catherine had little idea of how such young
men ought to behave, but she could not rid
herself of the conviction that Mr Thorpe was
not an agreeable person.
It was a difficult and bold conclusion to
come to, since he was her brother's friend
and dear Isabella's brother; but in spite
of this, when she was in John Thorpe's company
Catherine was quickly bored and felt exhausted
by his lack of interest in anything but himself.
After what seemed like hours to Catherine,
the carriages finally returned to Mrs Allen's
door.
'Past three o'clock!'
cried Isabella.
'It is impossible!
I cannot believe my watch.
No two and a half hours have ever gone by
so rapidly and so nicely.
Don't you agree, dear Catherine?'
Our heroine could not tell a lie even to please
Isabella; but she was spared the need to disagree
with her friend because Isabella did not wait
for her answer.
'I have a thousand things to talk to you about,
but now I have to go home,' complained Isabella.
And with the gestures of a tragic actress
mixed with her satisfied smile and laughing
eyes, Isabella called goodbye to Catherine
and left her.
Catherine found Mrs Allen in her sitting-room.
'Well, my dear, I hope your afternoon was
as pleasant as mine,' began Mrs Allen.
'I went to the Pump Room as soon as you were
gone and met Mrs Thorpe there.
Then we met Mrs Hughes and Mr Tilney and his
sister in the Crescent.
They are very agreeable people, and Miss Tilney
was wearing a particularly pretty dress.
Very expensive, I imagine.
Of course the family is very wealthy according
to Mrs Hughes.'
'Did you learn anything else about the Tilneys?'
'Quite a lot!
They are a very good, very rich family.
The mother, Mrs Tilney, was Miss Drummond
before her marriage and was at school with
Mrs Hughes.
She brought a large fortune to her marriage
to General Tilney.'
'And are General and Mrs Tilney in Bath?'
asked Catherine, hungry for more information.
'Let me think,' said Mrs Allen.
'I believe Mrs Tilney is dead, because Mrs
Hughes told me there was a beautiful set of
pearls that Mr Drummond gave his daughter
on her wedding day, and that Miss Tilney has
them now.
They were given to her when her mother died.
I think that is what Mrs Hughes said.'
'And is Mr Tilney, my dance partner, the only
son?'
'I am not sure about that, my dear.
I think he is, but anyway he is a very fine
young man according to Mrs Hughes, and he
has a good future ahead of him.'
Catherine deeply regretted having missed such
a meeting with both brother and sister, especially
since it had been replaced by a rather unpleasant
drive with a rather disagreeable companion.
That evening the Allens, Thorpes and Morlands
met at the theatre, and finally Isabella had
an opportunity to communicate with Catherine
about the thousands of things she had been
wishing to discuss with her dear friend.
'Now, Mr Morland,' Isabella began, turning
to James Morland on her left, 'I shall not
speak another word to you all the rest of
the evening, so do not expect it.'
Then turning to Catherine on her right, she
continued, 'My sweetest Catherine, how lovely
you look!
You are sure to attract every man in Bath.
My brother is already in love with you, and
Mr Tilney must have returned to Bath just
to see you.
Look around and tell me if he is here.
I assure you that I can hardly breathe until
I have a look at him.'
'I am sorry,' said Catherine, 'I cannot see
him anywhere.'
'How horrible!
Am I never to make his acquaintance?
Do you like my dress?
I think it suits me, don't you?
Do you know that I am becoming quite sick
of Bath; your brother and I were discussing
it this morning.
It is enjoyable to be here for a few weeks,
but we both prefer the country.
I imagine that you have some clever comment
to make about the ridiculous fact that James
and I can find nothing to disagree about.'
'No, it does not sound ridiculous to me.'
'Oh, you would probably like to say that we
seem made for each other, or some nonsense
of that kind.'
'No, you misjudge me, Isabella.
I would never make such an improper remark,'
protested Catherine.
Isabella smiled and gave Catherine a look
which seemed very significant.
Then she turned to her left and talked to
James for the rest of the evening.
The next afternoon, Catherine had a similar
experience in the Pump Room when she joined
her brother James and Isabella Thorpe for
a walk around the room.
Catherine soon realised that she had no part
in either her friend's or her brother's conversation.
The two of them constantly laughed and teased
each other or playfully argued about some
insignificant topic.
They often asked for Catherine's opinion,
but they never seemed to hear anything she
tried to add to the discussion.
Thankfully Catherine was rescued from this
situation when she saw Mrs Hughes and Miss
Tilney enter the Pump Room.
Miss Tilney greeted her very warmly and she
and Catherine enjoyed a pleasant conversation,
marked by a simple, honest style on both sides.
'Your brother dances very well!'
Catherine said innocently.
'And he is so interesting to talk to.'
This surprisingly direct statement amused
Miss Tilney.
'Henry!'
she replied with a smile.
'Yes, we have often said that he dances very
well.
And he loves conversation.'
'He must have thought it very odd the other
evening when he invited me to dance and I
refused.
But I really had been engaged the whole day
to dance with Mr Thorpe.'
Miss Tilney smiled and remained silent.
'I was so surprised to see Mr Tilney.
I thought he might have left Bath for good.'
'No, when you first met him, Henry was here
for a few days to find lodgings for us,' Miss
Tilney explained.
'Oh, I see now.
I think the young lady he danced with on Monday
was very glad to have such a good partner.
Did you think she was very pretty?' asked
Catherine.
'Not very,' answered Miss Tilney, who was
enjoying her companion's questions.
'I suppose your brother never comes to the
Pump Room.'
'He does sometimes.
But this morning he has gone riding with our
father.'
When the two ladies parted, Catherine was
not conscious of having revealed anything
about herself, but Miss Tilney was certain
that she had discovered something important
about her new acquaintance's feelings.
There was a ball the next evening and Catherine
dressed carefully, hoping that she would meet
Miss Tilney and her brother there.
But before the Tilneys arrived, Catherine
had to work hard at avoiding the attentions
of Mr John Thorpe.
She hid herself from his view as much as possible,
and when he spoke to her she pretended not
to hear him.
When the dancing began, Isabella whispered,
'Don't be shocked, my dear Catherine, but
I am going to dance with your brother again.
I hope you and John will join us when he returns.'
Catherine started to say something to her
friend, but Isabella hurried to the dance
floor.
Catherine could see John Thorpe approaching,
and she worried that all was lost; she might
have to dance with him again.
But what luck!
Mr Tilney appeared and immediately asked her
to dance.
Not only had she had a lucky escape from John
Thorpe, but it seemed that Mr Tilney had sought
her out on purpose!
They joined a set and took their positions
for the dance.
However, Catherine's happiness was disturbed
by the arrival of John Thorpe behind her.
'Hello, Miss Morland!'
Mr Thorpe shouted.
'I thought we would be dancing together this
evening.'
'Mr Thorpe, you did not ask me to dance,'
replied Catherine.
'That is a good joke.
I asked you as soon as I came into the room.
This is a low trick to play on a fellow.
I told my friends that I was going to dance
with the prettiest girl in the room, and now
you have abandoned me.
And who is this partner of yours?'
'He is Mr Henry Tilney,' answered Catherine
quietly.
'I do not know him.
A good-looking man.
Does he need a horse?
I can get a good one for him from Sam Fletcher.
He sold me my last horse, a really good hunter.'
The dance was beginning now and Mr Thorpe
was forced to leave the floor.
When Mr Tilney came close to Catherine, he
said, 'I was getting very impatient with that
gentleman, taking your attention from me.
We have agreed to be faithful to each other
as dance partners for the evening; and a man
who tries to claim the attention of another
man's partner is breaking what I consider
an important contract.
Neither person should look around and wonder
about the advantages of having a different
partner.
Don't you agree?'
'Yes, of course I agree,' answered Catherine
enthusiastically.
'May I come to the conclusion then that if
the gentleman who spoke to you just now were
to return, or if any other gentleman wanted
to talk to you, you would excuse yourself
and concentrate your attention on me, your
partner?'
'Well, it would be honest to say that I do
not want to talk to any other gentleman this
evening,' Catherine said prettily.
'I am very satisfied with that guarantee,
and I shall continue with courage.
Do you find Bath as agreeable as when I had
the honour of asking that question before?'
'Yes, quite.
Even more so than before.'
'More so!
Be careful.
The fashionable young ladies always get tired
of Bath at the end of six weeks.'
'Well, other people must judge for themselves,
but I do not think I would be tired of Bath
at the end of six months,' insisted Catherine.
'I do not think I could ever be tired of Bath.'
As the dance progressed, Catherine noticed
a handsome older man with a rather noble attitude
standing in the crowd and staring at her.
Then she saw him whisper something to Henry
Tilney, and both men looked at her again before
the older man withdrew from the dance floor.
Henry politely approached Catherine and said,
'That gentleman is General Tilney, my father,
and he was asking me who you are.'
Later that evening, Catherine had a very welcome
opportunity for a chat with Henry Tilney and
his sister.
They discovered that all three of them had
a special liking for country walks.
'Shall we have a walk together one morning?'
suggested Miss Tilney.
'I would like that better than anything in
the world,' Catherine said enthusiastically.
'Shall we go tomorrow?'
The three young people agreed, unless there
was rain, to go out for a walk together at
twelve o'clock the next day.
And so, although she had seen hardly anything
of her good friend Isabella during the entire
evening, Catherine travelled home in the carriage
with Mr and Mrs Allen in such good spirits
that she danced in her seat all the way.
At breakfast the next morning, Catherine looked
out at a disappointing sky full of clouds.
Then at eleven o'clock, when she was watching
the weather with great attention, a few drops
of rain hit the sitting-room window.
'Oh, Mrs Allen, do you think the rain will
stop before midday?'
'Perhaps it may, my dear,' answered Mrs Allen,
'but then the streets will be very dirty and
muddy.'
'I do not mind dirt and mud.
I would still be happy to go for a walk.
But, oh dear, now I see four raised umbrellas,
but I will not give up until half past twelve,'
Catherine said.
'That is just the time of day for the weather
to change.
Oh why can't we have the kind of beautiful
weather they had in Udolpho!'
Then just as the clock struck the half hour,
the sky really did begin to clear and the
rain stopped.
In ten more minutes, the sun was shining and
it promised to be a fine, bright afternoon.
Catherine continued to sit at the window,
hoping that the Tilneys would appear for their
country walk.
But instead of the Tilneys, she was surprised
by the arrival of Isabella and John Thorpe,
and her own brother, James.
'Be hasty, Miss Morland,' shouted Mr Thorpe
as he entered Mrs Allen's sitting-room.
'The carriages are waiting and we are all
going to Clifton to dine and then on to Blaize
Castle.'
'Thank you, but I cannot go.
I am waiting for my friends, Mr and Miss Tilney.
I am engaged to go for a walk in the country
with them.
They promised to come at twelve, but it rained;
now, with this fine weather, I expect them
here soon.'
'No, they will not be coming,' insisted Mr
Thorpe.
'I saw them in a carriage and heard them say
that they were going as far as Wicks Rocks.
Anyway, it is much too dirty for a country
walk.'
'Oh, that is disappointing,' said Catherine.
'But what about this castle?
Is it really old?
Is it like the castle in Udolpho?'
'It is almost exactly the same,' said Mr Thorpe.
'Then shall I go, Mrs Allen?
What do you think?'
Catherine asked.
'Well, my dear, I suppose you should go,'
said Mrs Allen, and in two minutes the four
young people had begun their journey.
Catherine felt upset that she had not heard
anything from the Tilneys, but she had to
admit that she was excited about seeing a
real castle.
The carriages went down Pulteney Street and
through Laura Place, and John Thorpe once
again talked about his horse and his skills
as a driver.
Then near Argyle Street, Mr Thorpe said, 'Who
is that girl on the pavement who was staring
at you as we passed her?'
Catherine looked back and saw Miss Tilney,
walking along the pavement, holding her brother's
arm, and both of them were looking directly
at her.
'Stop, stop, Mr Thorpe,' Catherine cried impatiently.
'It is Miss Tilney and her brother!
How could you tell me that they had gone out
of town?
Stop, stop, I must speak to them.'
But John Thorpe did not stop.
In fact, he laughed and encouraged his horse
to go faster, and in another minute the Tilneys
were out of sight.
Now the carriage was moving so quickly that
Catherine could not possibly escape from it,
and she felt extremely angry.
'Why did you lie to me, Mr Thorpe?
And why didn't you stop when I asked you to?
They must think that I am very rude.'
Their drive, even after they had stopped talking
about the Tilneys, was not very agreeable.
Catherine obviously would have preferred a
country walk with the Tilneys, but at least
she had a real castle to look forward to.
When they could see the town of Keynsham,
James Morland shouted at Mr Thorpe and the
two carriages came to a stop.
'We had better go back, Thorpe,' James began.
'Isabella agrees.
We left too late to visit Blaize Castle today.'
'It does not matter to me,' said Mr Thorpe,
turning his carriage around for the drive
back to Bath.
As they started again, he said to Catherine,
'Your brother is a fool not to have his own
horse and carriage.
If he had a good horse like mine, we could
easily have reached the castle today.'
'But he could not afford to keep a horse and
carriage,' objected Catherine.
'And why can't he afford it?'
'He does not have money for those things,'
replied Catherine.
'Well, I think it is a bad practice for people
who are rolling in money to be too mean to
have a good horse and carriage.'
Catherine did not understand what Mr Thorpe
was talking about, and she had become less
and less willing to listen to anything he
had to say.
They returned to Pulteney Street without her
speaking twenty words.
When she entered Mr and Mrs Allen's house,
a servant told Catherine that a young lady
and gentleman had called for her a few minutes
after she had set off with Mr Thorpe.
Thinking about this upsetting news, our heroine
walked slowly upstairs to her room, but was
stopped by Mr Allen.
'Dear Catherine, I am glad your brother was
sensible enough to bring you home in good
time.
It was a strange, wild scheme.'
That night our heroine went to bed feeling
confused and unhappy, unable to sleep because
she was busy re-living the terrible events
of the day.
CHAPTER FIVE
Seeds of Misunderstanding
'Mrs Allen,' said Catherine the next morning,
'will there be any harm in my visiting Miss
Tilney today?
I will not be calm until I have explained
everything that happened yesterday.'
With Mrs Allen's permission and advice on
which dress to wear, our heroine anxiously
hurried to the Tilneys' lodgings in Milsom
Street.
The door was opened by a servant, who said
he would check if Miss Tilney was at home.
When he returned to Catherine, the servant
said, 'Miss Tilney has gone out.'
Something made Catherine think that Miss Tilney
was in the house but was too offended to see
her.
When she got to the bottom of the street she
looked back and saw Miss Tilney and General
Tilney himself coming out of the house.
Catherine's first reaction was to feel angry,
but then she remembered how her own actions
might have been misinterpreted and was determined
not to judge Miss Tilney unfairly.
Catherine was in a rather thoughtful mood
all day, but was persuaded to go to the theatre
that night with the Allens and the Thorpes.
The comedy, one that she had been looking
forward to seeing, almost immediately lifted
her mood.
But at the beginning of the fifth act, Catherine
saw Mr Henry Tilney and his father join a
group of people in the opposite box and all
her anxiety and distress returned.
She lost interest in the play and watched
Mr Tilney.
Finally he looked towards her and bowed; but
what a cold bow it was!
He did not smile and immediately turned his
eyes back towards the stage.
Catherine's heart raced and she felt miserable
and eager for an opportunity to explain herself
to him.
The play came to its conclusion, the curtain
fell and Catherine's wish came true: Henry
Tilney came round to the Allens' box.
He greeted the Allens very politely, but Catherine
did not wait for him to speak to her.
'Oh!
Mr Tilney, I have been quite wild to speak
to you to make my apologies.
You must have thought me so rude yesterday,
but really it was not my fault - was it, Mrs
Allen?
Mr John Thorpe told me that you and your sister
had gone out in your carriage.
What could I do?
But I would have ten thousand times preferred
to be with you, wouldn't I, Mrs Allen?'
'Yes, my dear, but calm down.
You will damage my dress,' said Mrs Allen.
'I begged Mr Thorpe to stop his carriage and
let me out when I saw you,' Catherine rushed
on, 'but he would not even slow down.
If he had, I would have jumped out of the
carriage and run after you.'
No man could choose not to accept Catherine's
sincere apology and explanation, and Henry
Tilney smiled politely and told her that she
must say no more about it.
'My sister would also like to apologise to
you, Miss Morland, for her own behaviour this
morning,' Mr Tilney added.
'That is not necessary.
It is understandable that she did not want
to see me after yesterday's disaster.'
'But Eleanor did not choose to ignore you.
My father wanted her to accompany him on his
walk.
He is not a patient man and told the servant
to send you away, so I would like to apologise
for her.
And now may I join you for a few minutes?
What did you think of tonight's play?'
Catherine chatted with Mr Tilney for some
time and they made plans to take their country
walk as soon as possible, which made Catherine
believe that she was one of the happiest creatures
in all the world.
But a new mystery appeared while the two young
people were together.
Catherine observed with some surprise that
John Thorpe was in the opposite box talking
to General Tilney and looking over at her
from time to time.
'Does Mr Thorpe know your father well?'
Catherine asked.
'I did not know that they were acquaintances,
but my father is a military man and has a
wide circle of friends.'
On Sunday afternoon in the Crescent, Catherine
met Henry and Eleanor Tilney by chance and
they decided to go for their country walk
the next morning.
At almost the same time, the Thorpes and James
Morland were looking for Catherine to tell
her about their plans for another carriage
ride into the country, also on Monday morning.
'My dear,' Isabella began when they found
Catherine, 'we are going on our trip to Clifton
tomorrow morning.
You must be ready early so that we have time
to see and do everything.'
'I am very sorry, but I cannot go with you
tomorrow.
I am engaged to go for a walk with Eleanor
Tilney and her brother.'
'But we cannot go without you,' complained
Isabella.
'Explain that you had forgotten you were engaged
to go with us.'
'Don't try to persuade me, Isabella.
I will not break my engagement with the Tilneys.'
But the discussion did not end there.
'My dearest, sweetest Catherine, you cannot
refuse such a small request from me, a friend
who loves you so dearly,' Isabella tried.
'You cannot possibly love Miss Tilney more
than you love me.
You can go for your country walk another day.'
But Catherine would not change her plans.
'Well, I cannot help feeling jealous when
I see that you prefer strangers over me,'
answered Isabella, as she wiped away a tear
from her cheek.
It seemed to Catherine that Isabella was actually
behaving quite selfishly and not considering
her feelings at all.
'I am sorry, but I will not change my plans,'
Catherine insisted.
'Very well, then that is the end of our party
tomorrow.
If Catherine does not go, I cannot,' said
Isabella through her tears.
'It would be very improper.'
'Why can't Mr Thorpe invite one of his younger
sisters?
I imagine they would like to go for a carriage
ride,' suggested Catherine.
Mr Thorpe, who had left the group for a few
minutes, heard this suggestion and shouted,
'Thank you very much, but I did not come to
Bath to drive those silly girls around.
And anyway, I have solved the problem, and
now we may all four go tomorrow with no worries.
I have spoken to Miss Tilney and made your
excuses.
You can go out with them another day.'
'No!
I cannot believe you would do such a thing,'
cried Catherine.
'I have done it.
I told her you had sent me to say that having
just remembered a prior engagement of going
to Clifton with us tomorrow, you could not
walk with her until Tuesday.
She said Tuesday was convenient for her, so
there is an end to our argument.
That was a good idea of mine, wasn't it?'
'No, it was not!
I must run after Miss Tilney and explain everything.
You had no business inventing a message from
me and trying to trick me into doing what
I thought was wrong.'
As Catherine rushed off to find Miss Tilney,
her mind was greatly troubled.
She did not like disappointing and displeasing
her brother and Isabella, but she would not
break a promise that had already been made,
and she would not fail to keep an engagement
with Miss Tilney and her brother for the second
time.
She saw the Tilneys and their father as they
entered their lodgings and hurried after them.
'Miss Tilney!'
Catherine shouted.
'I told them that I could not go with them.
I ran here to explain everything to you.'
Although Catherine's speech was not completely
clear, the Tilneys understood her and everyone
was on friendly terms again.
Eleanor introduced Catherine to General Tilney,
who welcomed her into their house very politely
and invited her to join them for dinner one
evening if the Allens could spare her.
After sitting with the three of them for a
quarter of an hour, General Tilney accompanied
Catherine to the street and said goodbye in
the most graceful, friendly manner.
At Pulteney Street, Catherine wondered if
she had been unkind to Isabella and James,
and mentioned their plan to Mr Allen.
'Were you thinking of going with them?' asked
Mr Allen.
'No, sir.
I had just agreed to go for a walk with Miss
Tilney, so I could not go with them, could
I?'
'No, certainly not, and I am glad you would
not consider it.
I do not approve of young men and women who
are not related driving around the country
in open carriages, going to inns and public
places together!
It is not proper, and I am surprised that
Mrs Thorpe allows it.'
'I wish Mrs Allen had stopped me on the other
occasion,' said Catherine quietly.
'No harm has been done,' Mr Allen replied,
'but I would advise you, my dear, not to go
out with Mr Thorpe anymore.'
Monday dawned clear and bright and Catherine
was rewarded with a perfect walk in the country
with the pleasantest companions: Eleanor and
Henry Tilney.
The conversation covered every imaginable
topic, ranging from the novels of Mrs Radcliff,
which all three were fans of, to an analysis
of the current government.
Catherine listened with great attention after
the talk moved away from the Gothic novels
that she loved so much.
She was very impressed with how much both
Eleanor and Henry knew about history, art,
nature and even politics.
You may remember that she had never been a
very willing student, and this fact actually
made her very good company for such clever
conversationalists as the Tilneys.
Obvious admiration for a young man's superior
knowledge is always a great advantage in an
attractive young woman.
The whole walk was delightful, and although
it ended too soon for Catherine, she was very
pleased by its conclusion.
When they returned to Pulteney Street, Miss
Tilney asked Mrs Allen if they might invite
Catherine to join them for dinner on the day
after next.
No difficulty was made on Mrs Allen's side,
and Catherine's only problem was to hide her
excessive pleasure at receiving this kind
invitation.
The morning had been so charming, so enjoyable
that Catherine had not thought about James
or Isabella, but was reminded of them in the
afternoon when she happened to meet Miss Anne
Thorpe in Bond Street.
'Good afternoon, Anne,' Catherine began.
'Did your sister and brother go for their
drive to Clifton this morning?'
'Yes, my other sister, Maria, went with them.
I think you had a lucky escape.
It must have been a very boring, dull drive,
but Maria was excited about going.
I decided immediately that I did not want
to go with them.'
Catherine doubted that Anne wanted to be left
behind, but she was happy to know that the
trip had not been cancelled because of her
refusal to join it.
Before leaving she asked, 'And did Maria enjoy
seeing Blaize Castle?'
'Oh, they did not see any castles.
They had lunch at the York Hotel in Clifton,
and after a walk they had tea there too, before
returning to Bath.'
The next morning Catherine hurried to the
Thorpes' lodgings, wanting to be certain that
she was on good terms with Isabella again.
But Isabella seemed to have forgotten that
there had been any disagreement between them
as she rushed into the sitting-room to greet
her dear friend.
'Darling Catherine, from the beginning you
understood more about me than I understood
about myself.
You have seen through everything.'
Catherine could not reply because she did
not understand what Isabella was talking about.
'My sweetest, my most precious friend,' continued
the older girl, 'you can see that I am amazingly
excited.
Let us sit down and talk about what you have
already guessed.
You clever creature!
Your brother is the most charming man on earth.
I only wish that I deserved him.
But what do you think your excellent father
and mother will say when he speaks to them?
Oh, I am so worried that they will not accept
me for their dear son.'
Finally Catherine began to understand what
Isabella was talking about.
'Isabella, are you telling me that you and
James are in love?'
And soon Catherine had heard the whole story.
The young couple had spoken of their love
for each other during yesterday's carriage
ride.
Now Catherine was thrilled to think that her
dear friend, Isabella, would one day be her
sister-in-law.
'Catherine, you will mean so much more to
me than either Anne or Maria; I feel that
I will be much more attached to the Morland
family than to my own,' Isabella insisted.
This idea astonished Catherine, and she honestly
thought it was inappropriate, but she was
delighted to hear Isabella's story of how
the engagement had happened.
'I remember the first time I met your dear
brother,' continued Isabella.
'With me, the first moment settles everything.
When he visited us in London, I lost my heart
to him immediately.
I remember I was wearing my yellow silk dress,
and when I came into the sitting-room, I thought
I had never seen anybody so handsome as dear
James.'
Here Catherine secretly thought about the
power of love because, although she was very
fond of her brother, she had never once thought
that he was handsome.
'Catherine, your brother caused me many sleepless
nights.
I was sure he would fall in love with someone
else.
He is such a wonderful man.
I knew you understood what was in my heart,
especially when I told you that I had a particular
liking for clergymen.
I was sure that my secret would be safe with
you.'
Once again Catherine was surprised by what
Isabella thought she knew, but she saw no
reason to change her friend's mind about the
situation.
She learned that her brother was already on
his way to Fullerton to ask for his parents'
permission to become engaged to Miss Isabella
Thorpe.
'Will they accept me, dear Catherine?
My fortune is very small and your brother
could marry anyone he chose.'
Again Catherine thought about the strength
of love and said, 'Isabella, you are too humble.
The difference between your fortunes will
not affect anything.'
'Catherine, not everyone would have such a
generous heart as yours.
I just wish that the situations were reversed.
If I had command of millions and ruled the
world, your brother would be my only choice.
I need very little in life, and where people
are attached by love, poverty itself is not
a problem.'
Catherine liked this idea; it sounded like
something from one of her novels.
'I will not think of a wedding or a house
or anything of that sort until we have your
father's answer,' continued Isabella.
'Your dear brother said that he will send
me news tomorrow, but I know I will not have
courage enough to open his letter.'
The two friends spent every moment together
that day and the next, talking of nothing
except how happy they would be as sisters.
Finally, after much anxiety, the post was
delivered on the second day and Isabella opened
her letter from Fullerton.
James wrote:
I have gained the approval of my kind parents,
and they promise that everything in their
power will be done to guarantee my happiness.
The brightest look spread across Isabella's
face and she said that she was the happiest
woman on earth.
The entire Thorpe family were now very happy
and wanted to hear about the details of Mr
Morland's promise: What would his income be?
Would he be given property by his family?
What kind of ring would Isabella receive?
What would their carriage and their house
be like?
Where would they live?
Mr John Thorpe had business in London and
now that Isabella had her letter, he prepared
to depart.
'Well, Miss Morland,' he said, finding Catherine
alone in the sitting-room, 'I have come to
say goodbye for the present time.'
'Goodbye, sir.
I hope you have a safe journey.'
'What do you think of this marrying idea,
Miss Morland?'
'I am sure marriage is a very good thing,'
replied Catherine.
'Do you?
I am glad you are not an enemy to marriage.
By the way, do you know that old song that
says, "One wedding brings another"?
Perhaps we may find out if that old song has
some truth in it at Isabella's wedding.'
'May we?' asked Catherine, feeling quite confused.
'But I never sing, so I would not know.
Well, I wish you a good journey.
I dine with Miss Tilney today, so I must rush
home.'
'Don't hurry away.
I will be gone from Bath for a fortnight and
it will seem a long time.
When will we be together again?'
'Well, we will see you when you return.
Goodbye for now,' said Catherine, trying to
get away.
'That is very kind of you, Miss Morland.
You are probably the nicest person I know.
You have so many good qualities.'
'Sir, there are much nicer, better people
than me.
Good morning to you.
I must get home.'
'But Miss Morland, may I visit Fullerton one
day soon?'
'My father and mother would be pleased to
meet you.'
'And I hope, Miss Morland, that you would
be pleased to see me there.'
'It is always nice to have company at our
house.'
'I agree with you - give me some cheerful
company and I am very happy.
I believe you and I agree about most things.'
'That idea has never occurred to me,' said
Catherine.
'In fact, I do not know my own mind about
most things.'
'I am the same,' cried Mr Thorpe.
'I have a simple idea about most things.
Let me have a girl I like and a comfortable
house and I would be satisfied.
Fortune is nothing.
I am sure of a good income of my own, so my
wife does not need to have a penny.'
'I am in agreement with you there, sir.
If there is a good fortune on one side, there
can be no need for any on the other.
I hate the idea of one great fortune marrying
another.
And I think it is very wicked of people to
marry for money.
Goodbye.
We shall be glad to see you in Fullerton one
day.'
And having said that, Catherine hurried out
of the Thorpes' house without another thought
about John Thorpe.
She was concentrating on getting ready for
her dinner with Miss Tilney.
Mr Thorpe felt very satisfied; he believed
that Miss Morland had clearly encouraged his
attentions and he intended to pursue her confidently
and without hesitation.
CHAPTER SIX
A Friend's True Nature Revealed?
Catherine went to the Tilneys' lodgings with
high hopes of a particularly pleasurable evening,
and of course this could only lead to disappointment.
Although General Tilney was extremely polite
to her, Eleanor Tilney welcomed her warmly
and Henry Tilney was as charming as usual,
the happiness that Catherine had expected
was not achieved.
Somehow the evening did not have the spirit,
or perhaps the magic, that Catherine had wished
for.
On leaving the party, Catherine's conclusion
was that nobody was to blame, and that the
evening was just one of those unfortunate
failures that happen occasionally.
But when she described the evening to Isabella,
her reaction was very different.
'I blame it on pride.
Rude, unbearable pride!
The people in that family think they are very
grand.
I have never heard of such unfriendly behaviour
as Miss Tilney's.
Hardly even to speak to you, a guest!'
'But, Isabella, you are misinterpreting my
words.
Miss Tilney was not rude; she was very polite,
very proper and correct.'
'Please don't defend her.
Or her brother!
He had appeared so attached to you and then
he hardly looked at you when you were a guest
in their house!
How rude!'
'No, Isabella.
That is not what I said.
I simply meant that he did not seem in good
spirits.'
'I hate this type of inconstant behaviour
in anyone.
Never think of him again; he does not deserve
your attention.'
'I do not suppose that he ever thinks of me,'
said Catherine.
'Do you see how different he is from your
brother and from mine?
I really believe that John has the most faithful
heart.'
'But General Tilney, I assure you, could not
have treated me with more attention or with
greater politeness.
It seemed that his only care was to make me
happy.'
'Oh, I do not suspect him of pride.
John thinks very highly of him, and I trust
my brother's judgement.'
'Well, we will meet again this evening at
the Rooms, so I will wait until then to judge
their behaviour towards me.'
'And must I go?' asked Isabella.
'Of course, I can refuse you nothing, but
you know that my heart is elsewhere.
And you know that it is completely out of
the question for me to think of dancing, so
please do not suggest it, although I know
that Charles Hodges will beg me to dance with
him.'
Isabella's opinion of the Tilneys did not
influence Catherine's view of them.
She was certain that they had not meant to
be quiet or proud when she dined with them,
and that evening she was proved right.
Both Miss Tilney and her brother were dearly
happy to see her and treated her very kindly
throughout the evening, and once again she
enjoyed her usual happiness as Henry's dance
partner.
At the end of the first dance, a tall, handsome
young man approached Eleanor and Henry Tilney,
and Catherine learned that this was their
older brother, Captain Tilney.
After a short, polite conversation, the older
brother asked if they knew the pretty young
woman sitting with some of the older ladies.
Catherine explained that it was her good friend
Isabella Thorpe.
'Could you please introduce me to her?' asked
Captain Tilney.
'I would like to invite her to dance.'
'I am afraid that she would not dance this
evening for any reason in the world, although
I think it is very kind of you to think she
might wish for a partner,' said Catherine.
When Catherine and Henry were returning to
the dance floor, Henry said, 'Thank you for
thinking that my brother was being kind in
wanting to dance with Miss Thorpe.
You allow the rest of the world to have motives
that are as good and generous as your own.'
Catherine was lost in thought about Henry's
comment when she heard Isabella's voice.
She looked up and saw her with Captain Tilney,
standing in the set opposite her and Henry.
Isabella raised her eyebrows for a second
and then smiled.
'How could this happen?'
Catherine said to Henry.
'Isabella was so determined not to dance.'
'And has Isabella never changed her mind before?'
'But what about your brother?
Why did he invite her to dance after what
I said?' asked Catherine, feeling very confused.
'My brother makes his own decisions, but his
behaviour does not surprise me.
She is very pretty and that would have been
enough reason for him to have asked her.'
Catherine had no opportunity to speak to Isabella
until the dance had finished and they were
walking round the room arm in arm.
'Dear Catherine, I know you are surprised
that I danced, and now I am exhausted.
But he is very amusing, I must admit, although
I would have preferred to sit still all evening.'
'Why didn't you?' asked Catherine, thinking
of her brother.
'That would have made me look quite spoiled,
and you know how I hate that kind of behaviour.
I refused him as long as possible, but he
would not give up.
He said that he would dance with me or with
no one.
Such nonsense!
Since there would be no peace until I danced
with him, and knowing that your dear brother
would not want me to sit throughout the evening,
I had to accept his invitation.
He is such a smart-looking young fellow.
Did you see that every eye was upon us?'
'He is a very handsome man,' Catherine agreed
quietly.
'Oh, yes, I suppose he is very good-looking,
but too proud.
I scolded him about that several times in
my way.'
Catherine was with Isabella in the sitting-room
of the Thorpes' lodgings when her brother
James's second letter arrived from Fullerton;
it contained a summary of his father's kind
arrangements for James and his wife's future
happiness.
As a clergyman, he would be given his father's
living with the salary that went with it,
and he would receive a future inheritance
of equal value, then doubling his yearly salary.
James wrote how grateful he was to his parents
and explained the necessity of waiting between
two and three years before he would have his
parish and he and Isabella could marry, which
is what he had expected.
Catherine followed her brother's lead and,
feeling very satisfied with her parents' generosity
and good wishes for the young couple, congratulated
Isabella on having everything so pleasantly
settled.
'It is very charming, I am sure,' said Isabella
softly.
'Mr Morland has behaved generously, without
doubt,' added Mrs Thorpe, looking anxiously
at her daughter.
'I am sure that he would do more if he could.
I am certain that if his fortunes change,
he will do more for you and his son in the
future.
A clergyman's salary is a small amount to
begin on, but you are very modest in your
needs, dear Isabella.'
'Well, as you know, I never think of myself,'
Isabella began, 'but I do not want to injure
my dear James.
Such a small income is hardly enough to pay
for the essential requirements of life.
For myself, that is unimportant; I never think
of myself.
Anyway, Mr Morland has a right to do what
he likes with his own money.'
Catherine felt hurt by what Isabella was implying
and said, 'I am sure that my father has promised
as much as he can afford.'
Isabella quickly tried to cover up her true
feelings.
'My dear Catherine, you know me well enough
to know that I hate money and would be happy
with very little, but two or three years is
a long time to wait until your brother and
I can marry.'
The Allens now began the sixth of their eight
weeks in Bath, and Catherine was looking forward
to more opportunities to spend time with both
Eleanor and Henry Tilney.
But on her next visit to Miss Tilney at Milsom
Street, she was disappointed to learn that
the family would be leaving Bath at the end
of the following week.
'I am afraid my father has missed some of
his friends who did not come to Bath this
year,' explained Miss Tilney.
Catherine was very upset by this news and
wanted to ask Miss Tilney to promise to write,
but before she could make her request, General
Tilney entered the room.
'Well, Miss Morland,' he said to Catherine,
'have you agreed?
We leave Bath a week from Saturday, and if
you will accompany us to Northanger Abbey,
none of us will have any reason to miss this
place.
We cannot offer you all of the excitement
of a place like Bath, but we will do everything
we can to make your stay agreeable.'
Northanger Abbey!
These were thrilling words to Catherine, and
it was such a flattering invitation.
To have her company so warmly requested!
She thought her heart might burst if she tried
to speak.
A visit to Northanger Abbey held so much promise:
a continued friendship with Eleanor, whom
she greatly admired, and the possibility of
a romance, but that was something she dared
not mention to anyone.
And in addition to all that, she would be
staying in an ancient abbey and would be able
to explore every damp cellar, every hidden
room, every ruined passage.
The decayed walls would speak to her and tell
her the stories hidden there.
With a mind so full of excitement about her
stay at Northanger Abbey, Catherine was hardly
aware that two or three days passed without
her seeing Isabella for more than a few minutes
at a time.
But one afternoon Isabella sought her out
in the Pump Room and asked her to sit with
her on her favourite bench between two doors,
where they could see everybody who entered
the room before they were seen.
As the two friends chatted, Catherine noticed
that Isabella's eyes continually turned towards
the entrance as if she were waiting for someone.
Catherine decided to tease her friend a little
and said, 'Don't worry, Isabella.
James will be here soon.'
'Catherine, my dear creature, do not think
that I always want to keep James at my elbow.
It would be awful to always be together.
And so you are going to Northanger Abbey.
I am very glad for you.
I understand that it is one of the finest
old places in England, and you must write
and tell me all about it.'
'I will do my best.
But who are you looking for?
Are you expecting your sisters?'
'I am not looking for anybody.
My eyes must be somewhere, and you know my
eyes wander when my thoughts are a hundred
miles away.
Tilney says it is always the case with certain
types of minds.
But forget about that.
I have something important to tell you.
I have just had a letter from John, and I
am sure you can guess what he has written
about.'
'No, I cannot.
Why could I?' asked Catherine innocently.
'Catherine, don't be naive.
You know that he is head over heels in love
with you.'
'With me?
Dear Isabella, why would you say such a thing?'
'My sweet Catherine, be honest, and don't
pretend you are not aware of his feelings.
John says in his letter that just before he
left Bath he made it clear that he intended
to propose marriage to you very soon, and
that you encouraged him quite openly.'
'Isabella, I am completely astonished by what
you say.
I had no idea that your brother was in love
with me, and I certainly did not encourage
him in any way.
I sincerely swear that no talk of his proposing
marriage to me ever passed between us.
He must have misunderstood me in some way
because I never thought nor wished for anything
of this kind from him.
Please explain to him as properly as possible
that I did not intend to deceive him in any
way, but if I could think of one man more
than any other, he is not that person.
Please don't be angry with me, Isabella, because
we shall, of course, still be sisters-in-law.'
'Yes, yes,' Isabella said blushing, 'but there
are more ways than one of our becoming sisters.
But what am I talking about?
My mind is wandering again.
So you are determined not to accept a proposal
from John?'
'I cannot return his love, and I certainly
never meant to encourage him,' insisted Catherine.
'I must say, Catherine, that I agree with
you.
What would you and he live on?
He has very little money, and it is no good
saying that people can live on love because
it is just not possible.
I think John cannot have received my last
letter.'
'And so you do understand what I have said?
I did not mean to encourage your brother.'
'Of course I understand,' said Isabella.
'A little harmless flirtation often leads
one person to assume they know another's mind.
I assure you that I am the last person in
the world to judge you severely in such matters.
Circumstances change; what one means one day,
one may not mean the next.'
'But my opinion of your brother did not change.
You are describing something that did not
happen.'
Without listening to Catherine, Isabella continued
with her own thoughts.
'Nobody should rush into an engagement before
knowing what they are doing.
And young men change their opinions so easily.
Why should a brother's happiness be more important
to me than my friend's?
My advice to you, Catherine, is not to be
in a hurry.
Tilney says people often deceive themselves
about the state of their own heart, and I
believe that he is right.
Oh, look, here he comes, but he will not see
us here.'
But Captain Tilney walked directly to their
bench and took the seat next to Isabella.
The two of them began whispering together,
making Catherine very uncomfortable and very
jealous for her brother.
Finally she stood and said, 'Isabella, I would
like to join Mrs Allen.
Will you walk with me?'
'You go without me,' Isabella said.
'I must wait here for my sisters.'
Catherine could do nothing to persuade Isabella
to leave the bench, and so she found Mrs Allen
and left the Pump Room.
It seemed to her that Captain Tilney was falling
in love with Isabella and that her friend
was unconsciously encouraging him.
It had to be an unconscious flirtation because
Isabella was engaged to James, but Catherine
was left confused and worried by her conversations
with Isabella that day.
Why had she talked so much about money?
Why had she been so obviously pleased at seeing
Captain Tilney?
And how did John Thorpe come to the conclusion
that she had encouraged him to fall in love
with her?
A few days passed and Catherine, although
not allowing herself to suspect Isabella of
improper behaviour, could not help noticing
that her friend seemed an altered creature.
When she was with Catherine and James in the
Allens' or Thorpes' lodgings, she seemed a
bit dreamy and not quite as full of spirit
and energy as before.
That alone would not have troubled Catherine,
but when she saw Isabella in the public rooms,
she had to admit that she became much livelier
and flirtatious when Captain Tilney was in
the room.
Catherine could see that James was confused
and hurt by his fiancee's behaviour, and she
thought that Captain Tilney too was being
treated badly by Isabella.
Surely Isabella had not told him that she
was an engaged woman; otherwise, he would
not have flattered her with so much attention.
Catherine worried so much about the situation
that she finally decided to speak to Henry
Tilney about it, describing what she had observed
and ending by saying, 'I am certain that your
brother must be unaware that Miss Thorpe is
engaged to be married to my brother, James.'
'My brother does know that,' replied Mr Tilney.
'Does he?' asked Catherine.
'Then why does he pursue Isabella as if she
was unattached?
He will have his heart broken if he falls
in love with her.'
'I am sure that my brother can look after
his own heart,' Henry said with a smile.
'I have told him that Miss Thorpe is engaged,
but he is his own master and will do as he
pleases.'
'But he is giving great pain and anxiety to
my brother.'
'Are you sure that this distress is caused
by Frederick?
Is it his attentions to Miss Thorpe, or Miss
Thorpe's reaction to them that gives pain
to your brother?'
'Is it not the same thing?'
'I think your brother would understand the
difference.
No man is offended by another man's admiration
of the woman he loves; it is the woman only
who can turn it into a tragedy.'
'Should I warn James?
Or can you speak to your brother and advise
him to leave Bath?'
'I do not believe that any one of the three
people involved in this situation would thank
us for our advice.
If your brother and Miss Thorpe love each
other, as you are certain they do, they will
never tease each other beyond what is acceptable
to them both.
Don't worry.
Frederick will not stay long in Bath, and
then your brother and his fiancee will laugh
about poor Captain Tilney's attachment to
the beautiful Isabella.'
Catherine could not argue against Henry's
analysis of the situation, and she decided
to stop worrying about it.
That evening Isabella and James were at the
Allens' lodgings to say goodbye to Catherine,
and with relief she saw only affectionate
behaviour between them.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Disappointment at First Sight
The next morning Catherine was at the Tilneys'
lodgings, ready to begin her journey to Northanger
Abbey.
She was unusually nervous, wanting to do exactly
what was right to maintain her new friends'
high opinion of her.
But she had no need to worry.
Miss Tilney's good manners and Henry's smile
soon drove away any anxious feelings, and
General Tilney welcomed her very warmly and
looked after her every need.
Even Captain Tilney appeared in the sitting-room
to wish them all a safe journey, although
Catherine heard him whisper to Eleanor, 'How
glad I shall be when you are all on your way
home.'
Catherine joined Eleanor and a servant inside
one carriage; Henry and General Tilney were
in the front carriage, with Henry driving.
Finally the journey of thirty miles from Bath
to Northanger Abbey began.
Our heroine relaxed and enjoyed Eleanor's
company as she observed a road that was entirely
new to her.
She looked back at Bath without regret, excited
about being with Eleanor and Henry, and about
spending time in a real abbey.
After two hours, which flew by for Catherine,
the carriages stopped for lunch.
Catherine could not help noticing the General's
habit of giving orders and dominating every
conversation.
He gave his opinion about the journey, about
the inn at which they had stopped, the service
of the waiters, the quality of the food, and
even about the weather.
Eleanor and Henry spoke very little when their
father was part of the group, and Catherine
felt a sense of relief when it was time to
return to the carriages and get away from
General Tilney.
But the General delighted her with a surprising
suggestion.
'The day is very fine, Miss Morland, and I
think you would see more of this beautiful
countryside if you took my place with Henry
at the top of the front carriage.'
And so Catherine found herself sitting beside
Henry, as happy as any girl who ever existed.
And Henry drove so well!
He did not swear or congratulate himself on
his ability with horses, and he seemed to
enjoy making conversation with Catherine.
Sitting beside him in his carriage was almost
as good as dancing with him.
'My sister is very happy that you are coming
to Northanger Abbey as her guest.
She does not have a true friend in the neighbourhood
and is looking forward to this time with you.'
'But you are with her most of the time, aren't
you?'
'Northanger is my home for about half of my
time.
I have my own house in Woodston, which is
nearly twenty miles from my father's house,
and I must spend some of my time there in
my parish.
Of course I am always sorry to leave Eleanor.'
'And the Abbey?
You must be very fond of the Abbey.'
Henry smiled and said, 'You seem to have formed
a very positive view of Northanger Abbey.'
'Yes, I think I have.
It is a fine old place, isn't it?
Like the kind of places one reads about in
Mrs Radcliffe's novels?'
'And are you prepared to meet the type of
frightening experiences that may occur in
such houses?
Do you have a brave heart?
Are your nerves strong enough for secret rooms
and hidden staircases?'
said Henry in a low, quiet voice.
'Oh, yes!' cried Catherine.
'But I will not be easily frightened with
so many people in the house.
We are not returning to it after it has stood
empty for years and no one expects us.
I have read about that kind of thing happening
in novels, and then mysterious and scary things
occur.'
'No, that is certainly not the case at Northanger.
We shall not have to feel our way along a
dark hall with only the dying coals of a distant
fire to light our way.
Nor will we have to make our beds on the floor
of a room without windows, doors or furniture.
I am sure you have read about such circumstances
too in one of your favourite novels,' suggested
Henry.
'Of course, as is the custom in old houses,'
he continued in his dramatically low voice,
'you will be in a separate part of the house,
away from the rest of the family.
And when we go to our warm, familiar rooms
at the end of the evening, Dorothy, our ancient
servant, will lead you up a different staircase,
and then along several dark passages, into
an apartment that has not been used since
a very old aunt died in it more than twenty
years ago.
Will that frighten you?
'Will you be content in your large room with
very high ceilings and very little light?
The walls in this room are hidden behind dark,
heavy tapestries and the bed is covered in
material appropriate for a funeral.
Will your blood run cold when you enter?
Will you be happy to spend the night there
alone, with nobody close enough to hear you
if you shout, or even scream?'
'But that will not happen to me, I am sure,'
said Catherine in a trembling voice.
'You are describing what happens in novels.'
'But what are they based on?
Think about the furniture you will find in
your apartment.
Not tables, wardrobes or drawers, but in a
dark corner you might see a broken violin
or a tall black cupboard from several centuries
ago, and over the fireplace an oil painting
of a handsome military man, whose eyes seem
to follow you round the room.
'And Dorothy, before leaving you, tells you
that you will be alone in this part of the
house, with only the ghosts of the past to
keep you company.
With these parting words, she disappears down
the dark hall, and you listen until you can
no longer hear her footsteps.
You hurry to the door, wanting to lock it,
but there is no lock or key.'
'Oh, Mr Tilney, how frightening!
It is like a scene from Udolpho!
But it cannot really happen to me.
I am sure your housekeeper is not really Dorothy,
and there are no ghosts at Northanger Abbey,
are there?
What else might happen?'
'I think you will feel frightened on your
first night, but nothing unusual will happen
to you.
Not on that night.
You will go to bed and get a few hours of
disturbed sleep.
But on your third night, there will probably
be a violent storm.
The thunder will be so loud and so frequent
that the whole abbey will shake.
A terrible wind will accompany the noise,
and when the lightning flashes, you will see
movement behind the heavy tapestries.
Because you are naturally curious, you will
get out of bed to investigate and behind a
tear in one of the tapestries, you will discover
a small, secret door.
With your lamp in your hand, you will pass
into a small dark room.'
'No, I could not go into the room!
I would be too frightened!'
'But you would enter because Dorothy has told
you about a secret underground passage between
your apartment and the church of St Anthony,
less than two miles away.
Could you resist such an adventure?
No!
You will go into the small, dark room, which
leads to several more tiny rooms.
You will see a sharp knife in one room, drops
of blood in another and, in a third, chains
and a whip.
'Finally you find a large, old-fashioned cupboard,
and when you unlock its doors, you find drawers,
one of which contains many mysterious sheets
of paper.
You hurry back to your room with this treasure
and begin to read:
You have found the diary of Matilda, a poor,
unfortunate girl.
Have pity on me and...
Your lamp suddenly goes out and leaves you
in total darkness.'
'Oh, no!'
cries Catherine.
'And then what?
Please, go on!'
But Henry could not continue telling the story
without smiling, and Catherine at last understood
that he was amusing himself by frightening
her.
Catherine felt ashamed of desperately wanting
to hear more of the story, and told herself
to remember where she was.
'Mr Tilney, you are a good story-teller, but
you have not alarmed me.
Your sister would never put me in a room like
the one you have described.
I am not afraid of anything at Northanger
Abbey,' insisted our heroine.
Just then the Abbey came into view and Catherine
found that she was more than a little disappointed.
Parts of the building were very low and she
could not even see an ancient chimney.
But it was a real abbey, and she was delighted
to be there, even when she saw that the hallway
and informal sitting-room were very modern
and decorated with elegant furniture.
She had to admit that this was not what she
had wished for.
She had dreamed of entering a scene from Udolpho,
but instead found herself in a richly decorated,
beautiful, comfortable home.
Soon she was taken to her own room by Eleanor,
who asked her to be ready for dinner in twenty-five
minutes.
This room was nothing like the one that Henry
had described.
There was pretty paper on the walls and a
lovely carpet on the floor.
Everything, in fact, was very handsome, comfortable
and even cheerful.
She was determined to change her clothes quickly
and be early for dinner because she did not
want to risk upsetting General Tilney.
But suddenly she noticed a large wooden chest
at one side of the fireplace and she forgot
about the General and the need to hurry.
'This is very strange!
I did not expect such a sight as this!
What an enormous chest!
Why is it hidden in this corner, almost out
of sight?
I should not, but I will look inside.
I must do it now while there is still light
outside.
If I wait until evening my candle may go out.'
Without hesitating, Catherine tried to open
the old oak chest, but had trouble with the
lock, which was made of ancient looking, dull
silver.
The handles at each end were broken, perhaps
by some awful violence, and in the centre
of the lid there was a silver plate with some
mysterious writing which she could not understand.
Could it say Tilney in a foreign alphabet,
or did the chest not originally belong to
the family?
By what strange events could it have become
theirs?
Catherine's curiosity grew by the second and
she became more and more determined to open
the chest.
With trembling hands, she had just managed
to turn the lock and lift the heavy lid a
few centimetres when a servant knocked on
the door.
Catherine dropped the lid immediately and
it came down with a tremendous bang.
'Miss Tilney has sent me, miss.
Do you need any help with dressing for dinner?'
asked the servant.
This kind offer brought Catherine to her senses
and reminded her of what she should be doing
at that moment.
She dismissed the servant and rapidly changed
her dress, although her eyes kept returning
to the chest.
She was ready so quickly that she believed
she had time to examine the chest again.
She hurried to the corner and, with all her
strength, threw back the lid.
She was astonished to discover a beautiful,
new white blanket, folded neatly and resting
at the bottom of the chest, and nothing more.
Catherine was staring at the blanket when
Miss Tilney, hoping that her friend would
be ready for dinner, entered the room.
'It is an odd old chest, isn't it?' said Miss
Tilney, as Catherine hastily closed the chest
and turned away from her friend's eyes.
Our heroine was blushing and feeling ashamed
of her wild imagination.
'It is impossible to say how long that chest
has been in our family,' continued Miss Tilney.
'I do not know why it was put in this room,
but I have left it here because it is handy
for blankets and sheets.
And in that corner it is out of the way.'
Catherine could not speak, but made herself
calm down and hurry down the stairs with Eleanor
to join Henry and General Tilney in the dining-room.
The General insisted on punctuality and was
looking at his watch as the two young ladies
entered the room.
He violently pulled the bell beside the fireplace
and shouted, 'Dinner to be on the table immediately!'
Catherine felt extremely nervous as she took
her place at the table, worried about offending
the General and cursing her own interest in
old chests.
The General scolded his daughter for making
their guest hurry down the stairs, and then
recovered his politeness.
Catherine was distressed at having caused
Eleanor any discomfort, but the General was
so kind and attentive towards her that, with
this and a healthy appetite, Catherine soon
recovered her peace of mind and began to enjoy
being at Northanger Abbey; she actually felt
a very positive sense of happiness.
The dining-room was large and elegant, with
a very grand table and a number of servants
attending to the diners' needs.
'This is a beautiful room,' Catherine commented.
'It is a good size,' agreed the General.
'I believe that a large dining-room is necessary
in a house like this.
But I suppose you are used to much grander
dining-rooms at home and at Mr Allen's house.'
'No, not at all,' was Catherine's honest answer.
'I have never seen such a large dining-room
in my entire life.'
The General's mood brightened when he heard
this, but he politely said, 'I am sure that
there is more comfort in a smaller dining-room.
I am sure that Mr Allen's house has everything
in the correct size for perfect happiness.'
Before the party retired for the night, a
violent storm started outside, and as Catherine
reached the door to her room, she listened
to the wind and rain with sensations of wonder.
The night made her think of the horrible scenes
which Mrs Radcliffe's buildings had witnessed.
She knew that in a house like Northanger Abbey,
which was so modern in many ways and so securely
guarded, she had nothing to fear, and so,
after noticing that Eleanor's apartment was
very close to hers, she entered her room with
a reasonably strong heart and steady nerves.
Catherine looked across the room and saw the
window curtains move, and so she forced herself
to step boldly forward, and while softly whistling
a little tune, she courageously looked behind
each curtain and found nothing unusual.
Then she glanced at the chest beside the fireplace
and laughed at herself for worrying about
anything in this very pleasant room.
'I will take my time getting ready for bed,
and I will not worry if the fire goes out.'
Catherine felt satisfied with her own determination
to be brave and normal.
She happily prepared herself for bed and watched
the fire die away, but just as she was ready
to climb into bed she spied a tall, old-fashioned
black cupboard, which she had not noticed
earlier and which looked like the cupboard
Henry had described in his fictional room.
Had he, in fact, been talking about this particular
cupboard?
Catherine took her candle and examined it
closely.
It was very handsome, black with gold handles,
and very old.
The key was in the door, inviting her to look
inside.
So, placing the candle very cautiously on
a chair, she seized the key and tried with
all her strength to turn it, but it would
not move.
Alarmed, but not discouraged, she tried it
another way and the key turned in the lock,
but the door would not open.
She paused a moment, listening to the wind
roaring down the chimney and the rain beating
against the windows, and everything seemed
to warn her not to open this mysterious cupboard.
But Catherine knew she would not be able to
sleep until she had seen what was hidden within.
She tried the key again, moving it in different
directions until the door suddenly opened;
Catherine's heart leapt at such a thrilling
victory.
Now she saw a variety of drawers of different
sizes, and she bravely began to open them
and examine the interiors; each was equally
empty!
But Catherine had read enough novels to know
that such cupboards often had secret, hidden
sections, and so her search continued, and
she was successful.
By opening a door behind the first set of
drawers, Catherine discovered a roll of papers
that had been pushed back into the furthest
part of the cupboard.
Her heart trembled, her knees shook and her
cheek grew pale.
With an unsteady hand she seized the precious
treasure and was determined to read every
line before she attempted to rest.
Could it be the diary of Matilda, the young
woman Henry had told her about?
But then something horrible happened: Catherine's
candle was blown out by the wind from the
chimney, and she was left in total darkness.
She heard footsteps outside her room and a
door banged shut.
By now there was a cold sweat on Catherine's
forehead and she was trembling from head to
foot; the papers fell from her hand as she
jumped into her bed and hid beneath the blankets.
To close her eyes in sleep was impossible;
her thoughts were going in every direction:
Had Henry intended her to find Matilda's diary?
How long had it been hidden in the cupboard?
Would she be the first person to discover
its secrets?
She was determined to read the diary, which
she was sure she had found, as soon as there
was enough sunlight to see.
Hour after hour passed and Catherine could
do nothing but listen to the terrible storm,
which seemed to be warning her of hidden dangers,
and pray that morning would come quickly.
A servant entered Catherine's bedroom at eight
o'clock the next morning and opened the curtains.
As soon as she was alone again, Catherine
leapt from her bed and gathered up the sheets
of paper she had left on the floor.
Then she jumped back into bed to enjoy the
luxury of discovering Matilda's secrets while
resting on her pillow.
Her greedy eyes glanced rapidly over one of
the pages.
She was surprised by what she found and quickly
looked at several more pages.
All of them contained household lists of laundry
items: shirts, socks, underwear, gloves, ties;
or lists of household purchases: writing paper,
pens, hair powder, shoes and string.
These lists and nothing more were the secret
documents that had filled her with excitement
and robbed her of half her night's rest!
She blushed to think that she had learned
nothing from her experience with the chest
beside the fireplace.
How could she imagine that she would find
a family secret in a guest bedroom?
Catherine hurried to get ready for breakfast,
hoping that Henry Tilney would never know
that she had spent her first day at Northanger
Abbey behaving like a fool.
CHAPTER EIGHT
A Gothic Interpretation of Reality
Catherine was extremely impressed by the elegant
breakfast table, and she made a pretty comment
about the beautiful plates and cups.
'I am pleased that you approve of my choice,'
General Tilney responded.
'These dishes were manufactured in this county,
and I believe the set is as fine as anything
from the continent.
In fact, I hope that soon I will have the
opportunity of selecting another set of dishes
from the same company, although this time
not for my own dining-room.'
Catherine was probably the only one of the
party who did not understand what the General
was hinting at.
Soon after breakfast Henry left them for a
three-day visit to Woodston, where he had
parish work to do.
As the other three watched him go, Catherine
asked his father, 'Is Woodston a pretty place?'
'Over the last few years, I have tried to
make the house and gardens a suitable place
for my son,' General Tilney explained.
'It is a family living, and I want Henry to
be happy there.
Of course, his clergyman's salary is not important,
although he could easily live on it.
What is important for any son is to have a
job, to be employed in worthwhile work.
Even Frederick, my eldest son, who will inherit
one of the largest pieces of private property
in the country, has his profession.
I am sure that your father, Miss Morland,
would agree with me.'
Catherine could not answer for her father,
but she was very impressed with everything
General Tilney had just said.
'Now, last night you mentioned that you would
like to see the rest of Northanger Abbey.
It would be my privilege to show you the house
and the gardens if you can be ready to go
out in five minutes.
I will wait for you young ladies at the front
door.'
Catherine would have preferred to go around
the house with only Eleanor, and her disappointment
showed on her face.
'I hope you do not mind joining my father,'
said Eleanor, almost apologetically.
'He always walks out at this time of day.'
Catherine thought it was odd that the General
always took his walk so early.
Neither her father nor Mr Allen did so.
It made her wonder about her host.
She certainly wanted to see the house, but
she had to admit that she was not very interested
in seeing the gardens.
Nevertheless, when Catherine was outside,
being guided around the exterior of the Abbey,
she was more impressed than she could ever
have predicted.
She admired the size, the design, the beauty
of the buildings, as well as the wonderful
gardens.
General Tilney considered her reaction and
all of her comments both pleasing and appropriate,
especially when she made it clear that nothing
in Fullerton, not even on Mr Allen's land,
could compare to what she was seeing at Northanger
Abbey.
Finally the General said, 'Here is a handy
door.
I think you young ladies are probably ready
to go inside and get warm.'
'But I will take our guest down this narrow
path,' said Eleanor.
'It is my favourite walk.
Will you join us, Father?'
'No, Eleanor, it is cold and damp along that
path.
I will go across the park and meet you later,
but don't show our guest around the inside
of the house until I join you.'
As the young ladies walked along, Miss Tilney
said, 'This was my mother's favourite walk
and brings back memories of her.'
'I am surprised, then, that the General would
not enter it.
Your mother's death must have caused great
grief and distress.'
'Yes, and it causes more pain every year.
I was only thirteen when she died, too young
to understand that I had lost a constant friend
whose love and advice I could rely on.'
Catherine wanted to know more about Mrs Tilney
and eagerly asked many questions: 'Was your
mother a charming woman?
Is there a picture of her in the Abbey?
Did this dark path reflect something sad in
her?'
As Catherine listened to Eleanor's answers,
she came to the conclusion that General and
Mrs Tilney had had an unhappy marriage.
He did not love her favourite path, so how
could he have loved her?
And there was something in his handsome face
that told Catherine he had not behaved well
to his wife.
'Is the picture of her in your father's room?'
was Catherine's final question.
'No,' answered Eleanor quietly.
'My father was never satisfied with the picture
and would not hang it in the sitting-room
or in his apartment.
After Mother's death, I found it and hung
it in my bedroom.
I will show it to you if you would like to
see it.'
Catherine believed this was one more proof
that the General did not love his wife and
must have been extremely cruel to her!
She knew this kind of selfish, unfeeling man
from her novels, and as he led her around
the house, she came to the conclusion that
General Tilney was the type of man that Mrs
Radcliffe often wrote about - someone with
dark, dangerous secrets, a man who lived by
his own rules.
The General proudly pointed out the many modern
improvements he had made to Northanger Abbey
as they walked through the living rooms, the
kitchens, the offices and the storerooms.
Everything had been done to make the house
both comfortable and efficient to run.
But Catherine wondered if there was anything
left of the original fifteenth-century building.
Had every ancient treasure been swept away
for the sake of domestic economy?
They finally returned to the chief staircase
and walked up to examine three large guest
rooms which had been decorated in the last
five years.
'We hope to have other guests from Fullerton
staying here in the future,' said the General,
and Catherine was pleased by this kind thought
for her family.
At the end of this grand hall, they reached
a set of large doors which Eleanor began to
open.
'No, Eleanor.
Miss Morland has seen enough.
There is nothing else worthy of her notice.
We will retire to the library for a cup of
tea after so much exercise.'
Catherine watched as the heavy doors were
closed and believed that the General had excluded
her from the most interesting part of the
house.
When she was alone with Eleanor, Catherine
learned that the room in which Mrs Tilney
had died was behind those doors.
She imagined that the General's guilt, not
grief, kept him away from that room.
'Has the room been kept as it was when your
mother died?' asked Catherine eagerly.
'Yes,' answered Eleanor, 'even after nine
years it is still exactly as she left it.'
'I suppose that you were with her when she
died?'
'No,' said Eleanor sadly, 'I was unfortunately
away from home.
Her illness was sudden and short.
It had ended before I could return.'
Horrible pictures came into Catherine's head.
Could Henry's father have caused his wife's
death?
That evening ended quietly and as the young
ladies retired, General Tilney said that he
had to spend several hours in his office looking
over some important papers.
Catherine would not let herself believe that
the General had business to take care of;
she thought there was a deeper reason for
his late hours, something that could only
be done when the rest of the household was
asleep.
Catherine analysed what she believed were
the facts: Mrs Tilney's illness was very sudden;
her daughter was away from home at the time,
and probably her sons were too; General Tilney
was a jealous and cruel man.
What was her conclusion?
Perhaps Mrs Tilney was alive, shut up for
unknown reasons, and receiving a nightly supply
of coarse food from a husband who had never
loved her.
The poor woman must be a prisoner in the oldest
part of the Abbey, the part that Catherine
was not permitted to see.
She worried that her conclusions were too
bold, but then she persuaded herself that
all the evidence supported her opinion.
Catherine was determined to find out more
about the tragic life of Mrs Tilney, and she
watched for an opportunity to visit the mysterious
rooms that the General did not want her to
see.
Unfortunately Sunday was a busy day and Catherine
had to accompany the Tilneys to church.
She sat with the family in their usual seats
near the front of the church and stared directly
at a very elegant monument which had been
built in memory of Mrs Tilney, although Catherine
did not accept this as proof of the poor woman's
death.
Our heroine's eyes filled with tears as she
read the words recorded on the monument, which
described Mrs Tilney as a wonderful mother,
a loyal friend, a generous neighbour, and,
especially, as a loving and much-loved wife.
She looked to her left and was not surprised
to see that General Tilney remained unmoved;
this unemotional attitude, and the proud look
on his face, strengthened Catherine's belief
that he had in some way been his wife's destroyer.
She knew this type of man.
She could remember dozens of such cruel animals
from her novels - men who went from one crime
to another, murdering whoever they chose,
without any feelings of guilt or regret.
On the next day, Catherine had some time alone.
Henry would not return until Tuesday, and
both General Tilney and Eleanor were busy
with their household duties, giving Catherine
time to carry out her plan.
She would go through the forbidden doors alone
and search for proof of the General's cruelty.
She was sure she would find something: perhaps
the veil Mrs Tilney had worn to cover her
desperate sadness or the last few paragraphs
in her journal, which she had written in a
trembling hand.
Catherine knew the way and walked quickly
and quietly through the heavy doors and on
to Mrs Tilney's room.
She turned the key, opened the door and was
in the room.
But it was several minutes before she could
take another step.
What kind of horrible scene did she face?
What surprise took her breath away?
It was a clean, beautiful, modern, lady's
bedroom.
It was filled with handsome furniture, and
the bright afternoon sun poured through two
large windows which looked out on the most
attractive flower gardens.
Catherine's common sense told her that this
had been a cheerful place; she was filled
with shame.
How could she have assumed so much?
She was sick of exploring and analysing; she
only wanted to return quickly and safely to
her own bedroom and to keep all her suspicions
to herself.
But just as she stepped towards the door,
she heard footsteps, and as she entered the
hall again, she found herself face to face
with Henry Tilney.
'Mr Tilney!'
Catherine cried.
'Why did you come up that staircase?'
'I always use that staircase.
It is the easiest route from the stables to
my apartment.
And why shouldn't I use it?
But may I ask why you were using that staircase?
It does not connect with the passage to your
room.'
'I have been to see your mother's room,' Catherine
explained, blushing deeply.
'Really?
Is there anything extraordinary to see there?'
'No, nothing at all,' said Catherine.
Then she quickly added, 'I thought you were
not coming back until tomorrow.'
'I finished my business earlier than expected.
You look pale.
Did I alarm you by running so fast up those
stairs?'
'Oh, no.
And did you have good weather for your ride?'
'Well, yes.
But has Eleanor ignored you and left you to
find your way into all the rooms in the house
by yourself?'
'Oh, no, don't say that.
She showed me most of the house on Saturday,
and we were coming into these rooms, but then,'
whispered Catherine, 'then your father stopped
us.'
'Have you looked into all of the rooms in
this part of the house?'
'No, I only wanted to see...
Isn't it late?
I must hurry and get dressed for dinner,'
said Catherine nervously.
'It is only a quarter past four,' said Henry
as they walked along the passage.
For the first time in their acquaintance,
Catherine wished to leave him, but he continued
chatting.
'My mother's room is very attractive, isn't
it?
Large and cheerful, with such a wonderful
view.
I am surprised that Eleanor does not use it
for herself.
She sent you to look at it, I suppose.'
'No,' said Catherine without adding any explanation.
'So it was your own decision to visit my mother's
room.
Since there is nothing out of the ordinary
there, I assume you went there to honour my
mother's memory.
I am sure that Eleanor has told you that the
world never saw a better woman... but I still
cannot understand the reason for your visit.
What else did my sister say to make you curious
about Mother's room?'
Slowly and with some hesitation, Catherine
said, 'She said that her dying was very sudden,
and that none of you were at home at the time,
and I thought, perhaps, your father had not
been very fond of her.'
'And from this little information, you have
come to the conclusion that my mother was
badly treated in some way?'
He continued, with cold eyes fixed on Catherine,
'My mother's illness, which ended in her death,
was sudden, but she had suffered from the
same illness for years.
Her doctors, very respected, capable medical
men, were called and looked after her until
she died on the fifth day.
Frederick and I were at home and visited her
repeatedly; she received every possible attention
which we could offer.'
'But was your father,' said Catherine, 'equally
attentive during her illness?
Was he full of grief and sorrow when she died?'
'Miss Morland, you have misjudged my father.
He loved my mother as well as he could, and
although I know that he was not the easiest
man to live with, he valued her highly and
sincerely, and he was truly, if not permanently,
affected by her death.'
'I am very glad to hear that,' Catherine began.
'It would have been very shocking otherwise!'
'If I understand what you are implying, you
had come to a conclusion that is too horrible
for me to put into words.
What have you been basing your wild suspicions
on?
Do we not live in a civilised society where
laws and customs guide us?
Do you not know us well enough to accept us
as part of that society?
We are not characters in a Gothic novel, Miss
Morland.'
They had reached the end of the passage, and
with tears of shame our heroine ran off to
her own room.
She hid there, considering every disappointment
that she now might have to face.
She was terribly humbled and she cried bitter
tears.
Would General Tilney learn what she had imagined?
Would she lose Eleanor's friendship and possibly
Henry's love?
She hated herself more than she could express,
but when the clock struck five, she knew that
she had to appear for dinner although both
her heart and spirit were broken.
Henry was more polite than ever, seeming to
know that Catherine was in need of a kind
word and careful attention.
Gradually Catherine began to feel better,
and she started to hope that her foolishness
had not cost her all of Henry's friendship.
She had arrived at Northanger Abbey hoping
to be frightened, and she had willingly turned
what she saw and heard into a tragedy which
could be traced back to the pages of the Gothic
novels she loved to read.
Charming as Mrs Radcliffe's books were, it
was not in them perhaps that human nature,
at least in the middle counties of England,
could be looked for and understood.
Maybe Mrs Radcliffe and her fellow novelists
understood the character of the people beside
the lakes and in the pine forests of the continent,
but in the central part of England murders
were uncommon, servants were not slaves, and
neither poison nor sleeping pills could be
bought at a local chemist's, like potatoes
at a grocer's.
She now believed that there was a mixture
of good and evil in the English character
rather than the black and white described
in her Gothic novels.
With these thoughts in mind, Catherine decided
that she would use her good sense in the future,
and because of Henry's continued kindness
and his unwillingness to refer to what had
happened, she was able to be happy again.
She listened to Henry with the greatest attention,
knowing that she would be improved by what
she learned from him.
She still trembled when she glanced at the
chest or the black cupboard in her bedroom,
but she admitted that these reminders of her
past foolishness were probably good for her.
CHAPTER NINE
Distressing Letters
When Catherine was completely calm again at
Northanger Abbey, she began to wonder why
she had not heard anything from Isabella.
She was impatient for news from Bath, and
she wanted to know that her friend and her
brother, James, continued on the best possible
terms.
Isabella had promised to write and had assured
Catherine that she was always strict about
carrying out her promises.
This, Catherine thought, made it very strange
that she had not received a letter from Isabella.
Then, on her tenth morning at the Abbey, Catherine
found a letter beside her place at the breakfast
table.
She opened it and found that it was from James:
Dear Catherine,
This is not a letter that I want to write,
but I think it is my duty to tell you that
everything is at an end between Miss Thorpe
and me.
I left her and Bath yesterday, and will never
see either of them again.
You will learn the details from a different
source, but I hope you will trust that my
only mistake was to believe that my love was
returned.
Thank God I learned the truth in time.
She has made me miserable forever.
I hope that your visit to Northanger Abbey
finishes before Captain Tilney and Isabella
announce their engagement.
I have been a fool, believing her words rather
than the evidence in front of my eyes.
I wish that I had never met her.
Dearest Catherine, be careful how you give
your heart.
Catherine sat at the breakfast table with
tears running down her cheeks, and with Eleanor
and Henry wondering how they could help her.
Fortunately, General Tilney was hidden behind
his newspaper and took no notice of his guest
that morning.
Unable to eat, Catherine hurried off to the
sitting-room to be alone as soon as it was
politely possible.
Eleanor and Henry recognised that their friend
was distressed and were very concerned for
her, and so, after half an hour, they quietly
approached her.
'I hope you have not had bad news from Fullerton.
Is your family all well?'
Eleanor asked gently.
'They are all well, thank you.
The letter was from my brother at Oxford.'
Everyone was quiet for a few minutes, but
then Catherine cried, 'I do not think I shall
ever wish for a letter again!
Poor James is so unhappy, and you will soon
know why.'
'I am sure he is glad to have such a kind,
affectionate sister.
You will be a comfort to him if he is in any
distress,' replied Henry kindly.
'I have one favour to beg,' Catherine said
in a troubled voice.
'If your brother, Captain Tilney, is coming
here, could you please give me notice so that
I may go away.'
'Frederick?
Has this anything to do with your friend,
Miss Thorpe?'
asked Henry.
'How quickly you have guessed,' cried Catherine.
'And now I understand why she has not written
to me, but please read what my brother has
written.'
Both Henry and Eleanor read James Morland's
letter, and Henry said, 'I am very sorry that
anyone you love is unhappy, but I cannot believe
that Frederick ever intended to propose marriage
to Miss Thorpe.'
Then Eleanor asked, 'What can you tell me
about Miss Thorpe's family?
Does she have any fortune?'
'Her mother seems a good sort of person, and
her father is dead.
They are not a wealthy family, and I believe
Isabella has no fortune at all, but that would
not matter to your family.
Your father told me the other day that he
only valued money because it allowed him to
guarantee the happiness of his children.'
Henry and Eleanor exchanged a look.
Then Eleanor said, 'I can imagine Frederick
flirting with a girl like Miss Thorpe, but
he would not respect her for treating her
own fiance so badly.
He has never found a woman good enough to
love, and this situation would not make him
love Miss Thorpe.'
'You might be wrong this time, my dear sister,'
said Henry.
'Surely Miss Thorpe would not break off her
engagement to Mr Morland before securing a
promise from the other gentleman.
You may delight in such a sister-in-law: open,
honest, lively, with strong affections and
nothing artificial about her emotions.'
'That kind of sister-in-law would be delightful,'
said Eleanor, smiling at her brother.
'But perhaps,' observed Catherine, 'although
she has behaved so badly to my family, she
may behave better to yours.
Now that she has got the man she really likes
and wanted, she may learn to be faithful.'
'I trust she will be faithful to our brother,'
replied Henry, 'unless she meets someone with
more charm, or even a better fortune.
I think that is Frederick's only chance of
escape.'
'You are right.
I think ambition was her only motive when
falling in love.
I remember when she found out what my father
would do for her and James, she was so obviously
disappointed.
I have never been so deceived by anyone in
my entire life, but that does not compare
to poor James's feelings towards her.'
'We must pity your brother at present,' Henry
said, 'but we must not underestimate your
loss.
You no longer have a close friend to open
your heart to, to depend on, to learn from.
You will feel the loss greatly, won't you?'
Catherine thought for a moment and then said,
'No, to tell the truth, I am hurt and cannot
still love her.
I will never hear from her or see her again,
but I do not feel such grief as I would have
thought.'
To Catherine's surprise, this conversation
greatly lifted her spirits.
From this time, the subject of the affair
between Isabella Thorpe and Captain Frederick
Tilney was frequently discussed and analysed
by the three young people at Northanger Abbey.
Catherine learned, with some surprise, that
Eleanor and Henry were in perfect agreement
about one thing: their father may not approve
of Isabella's behaviour, but his greatest
objection to her as a wife for his elder son
would be that she was not socially well connected
and she had no money.
Such thoughts made Catherine think with some
alarm about herself.
She was as socially insignificant and as poor
as Isabella, and if the heir to the Tilney
fortune could not propose to a woman without
money, would his younger brother ever gain
his father's permission to marry someone like
her?
This worried Catherine, but she thought about
General Tilney's generous attitude towards
her and the special attention she always received
from him.
Added to this, more than once she had heard
him dismiss the idea that money was the most
important thing in the world.
During one of their discussions, Catherine
said, 'Mr Tilney, shouldn't you tell your
father how Isabella has behaved towards my
brother?
Then he will be able to judge her by her character
rather than by her situation in life.'
'No,' replied Henry.
'Frederick must tell his own story if he asks
my father for permission to marry Miss Thorpe.
But I must emphasise to you that I do not
believe that will ever happen.'
The household went about its business with
no news from Captain Tilney, and so the General,
who knew nothing about his elder son's connection
to Miss Thorpe, was able to spend his time
and energy making Catherine's time at Northanger
pass pleasantly.
He often expressed his anxiety about this
task, worrying that she would be bored with
the quiet life they led.
He wished that there were more young people
in the area, or more types of entertainment.
He talked about hosting a large dinner party
or even a ball, but it was a dead time of
year and many of their friends were not at
present in the neighbourhood.
His worries ended one morning, at last, when
he told Henry that he would bring Eleanor
and Miss Morland to dinner at his son's house
the next time Henry was at Woodston.
'And when do you think, sir, I may look forward
to this pleasure?' asked Henry.
'I am going to Woodston on Monday and will
have business there for at least two or three
days.'
'Well, we will take our chances on one of
those days,' General Tilney answered.
'There is no need to make a firm date.
We do not expect anything fancy, just whatever
you have in the house will be enough.
We know that a single man cannot be expected
to produce anything grand.
What about Wednesday?
Yes, you may expect us early on Wednesday.'
A ball itself could not have pleased Catherine
more than a visit to Henry's house in Woodston,
and her heart was full of joy with the idea
of becoming acquainted with the place.
Nevertheless she was both surprised and a
little sad when Henry found her and Eleanor
in the sitting-room an hour later and said,
'I am here, young ladies, to say that our
pleasures in this world must always be paid
for.
Look at me at this moment.
Because I look forward to seeing you both
in my own house on Wednesday, I must leave
now, two days before I had intended to go,
and I would much rather stay.'
'But must you go?'
Catherine asked with a very sad face.
'Yes, I must!
My old cook will be frightened half to death
about preparing a dinner for my father.
She will need as much time as possible to
prepare everything.'
'But the General told you not to give yourself
any trouble,' said Catherine.
Henry only smiled, and as he left he said,
'I wish I could reason like you.'
Catherine always doubted her judgement and
agreed with Henry's, so she had to think about
this.
How could people understand each other if
they said one thing so positively and meant
something else?
Only Henry and Eleanor could interpret what
their father's words really meant.
The hours from Saturday to Wednesday passed
very slowly for Catherine.
Everything was quieter, even rather dull,
without Henry.
Then she worried that Captain Tilney might
arrive, and she could not imagine acting politely
towards him.
She thought a lot about her brother, and felt
sad at having lost Isabella's friendship.
Her only feeling towards Northanger Abbey
itself was now one of embarrassment, and the
idea of a country parish with a comfortable
house was much more attractive to her.
Finally Wednesday arrived and by ten o'clock
the carriage left the Abbey with General Tilney,
Eleanor and Catherine inside, and after an
agreeable drive of about twenty miles they
entered Woodston, a large village in pleasant
countryside.
Catherine looked around and believed that
she preferred it to any place she had ever
seen.
They drove through the village, looking at
the neat houses, charming shops and tidy gardens
until they reached Henry's house at the far
end of the main street.
It was a newly built, large stone house, and
as they drove up to the door, Henry, with
three or four energetic dogs, waited at the
door to welcome them.
When they were inside, the General, who seemed
to think that Catherine would be disappointed
by the house, began to defend it.
'We are not calling it a good house.
It does not compare to Northanger or to Fullerton,
but we feel that it is decent, and not inferior
to the houses round here.
I believe that there are very few clergymen
in England with a house half so good.'
When the party entered the sitting-room, which
was still without furniture, Catherine was
delighted and her comments satisfied even
the General.
'What a prettily shaped room!'
she cried.
'It is the nicest room I have ever seen.
And it has a beautiful view.
You must decorate it soon, Mr Tilney, and
enjoy it.'
'I believe it needs a lady's touch,' said
the General with a satisfied smile.
'Well, if it were my house, I would always
sit in this room,' Catherine declared.
Henry entertained his guests with a wander
round his garden, a look at the stables, and
then a walk through the village.
At four they returned to the house for a delicious
meal of many courses, which the General seemed
extremely pleased by.
At six o'clock, after General Tilney had had
his coffee, the carriage was waiting at the
front door for the return trip to Northanger
Abbey.
Catherine felt certain that she could not
possibly misinterpret the General's behaviour
that day.
It seemed clear that he expected her to become
his daughter-in-law; she only wished that
she could feel as confident about his son's
plans.
The next morning brought the following unexpected
letter from Isabella:
Bath, April
My dearest Catherine,
I was delighted to receive your two kind letters
and I have a thousand apologies to make for
not answering them sooner.
I am quite ashamed at being so idle, but in
this horrible place, one can find time for
nothing.
Thank God we leave here tomorrow, so please
direct your next letter to me at my home,
and write to me soon!
I have not found any pleasure in Bath since
you left.
There is so much dust in the air, and everyone
that I care about has left.
I believe that if I could see you, I could
put up with everything else because you are
more precious to me than anybody can imagine.
I am worried about your dear brother, who
I have not heard from since his return to
Oxford.
I fear that there has been some misunderstanding
between us, and I am confident that you will
make my position plain to him: he is the only
man I ever did or ever could love.
I trust you to make that perfectly clear to
him.
The spring fashions are in the shops, and
the hats are simply the most awful you can
imagine.
I hope you are having a nice time at Northanger
Abbey, but I am afraid you never think of
me.
I will not say anything against the family
you are with, although I could if I wanted
to be spiteful or ungenerous.
I have learned that young men change their
minds from one day to the next, and I am happy
to say that the young man whom I dislike more
than all others has left Bath.
You will guess that I mean Captain Tilney,
who, as you remember, was constantly following
me and teasing me in the most flirtatious
manner.
But I know men too well to be fooled by him.
He returned to his duties in the army two
days ago, and I hope that I will never be
bothered by him again.
In the last two days he was in Bath he was
always flirting with Charlotte Davis, a rather
plain girl.
I refused to take any notice of him when I
saw him on the street after that.
What a contrast there is between him and your
brother!
Please send me news of dear James.
He seemed so unhappy when he left Bath, perhaps
he had a cold or something else that made
him feel unwell.
I would write to him myself but I have lost
his address in Oxford and I worry that he
misinterpreted my behaviour in some way.
Ask him to write to me and we will sort everything
out.
I have not been going out in the evenings,
except that I went to the theatre last night
with the Hodges, after they teased me about
staying in night after night.
I had to show them that I was not staying
in because Captain Tilney had gone.
I went out to show everyone that I have a
good spirit of my own.
Do you remember Anne Mitchell?
She was wearing a hat like the one I bought
with you, but it did not suit her.
I suppose it went with my odd face, at least
Tilney told me so at the time and said every
eye was looking at me.
But, of course, he is the last man whose opinion
I would take any notice of.
I wear purple all the time now.
I know it is not the best colour for me, but
it is your dear brother's favourite colour.
Lose no time, my dearest, sweetest Catherine,
in writing to him and to me.
Your friend forever...
How could anyone be so false, so dishonest?
Not even kind-hearted Catherine could be fooled
by so many lies and so much self-interest.
In fact, Catherine was ashamed of Isabella
and ashamed of ever having loved her.
Her excuses for her treatment of James were
empty, and Catherine could not believe that
she had been asked to write to her brother
on Isabella's behalf.
He had suffered enough and would never hear
Isabella's name mentioned by his sister.
Never again!
When Henry returned from Woodston, Catherine
told him and Eleanor about the letter.
'Your own brother has had a lucky escape,'
Catherine said sincerely.
'And for me, I wish that I had never met Isabella
Thorpe.
I can see that she never had any true feelings
for either James or for me.'
'It will soon seem that you never had met,'
Henry said.
'But please explain one more thing for me,'
Catherine replied.
'She was obviously pursuing your brother but
did not succeed.
But I do not understand Captain Tilney's behaviour
in this affair.
Why did he flirt with her and make her quarrel
with my brother, and then walk away from her?'
'I cannot explain my brother's motives, but
like Miss Thorpe, he thinks very highly of
himself.
Until this time, he has not been hurt by his
flirtations,' explained Henry.
'I believe that he never really cared for
your friend.'
'Well, I disapprove of this sort of behaviour,'
Catherine said quite angrily, 'and I must
say that I do not like Captain Tilney at all.
I suppose that no great harm has been done
to me or to my brother, but what would have
happened if Isabella had lost her heart to
him?'
'But we must first assume that Isabella had
a heart to lose, which would make her a different
young woman, and so she would have received
very different treatment from my brother,'
replied Henry.
'It is good that you defend your brother,'
said Catherine.
'And you must defend your brother's position
and understand that he should not feel sad
about losing Miss Thorpe.
He has had a lucky escape.
Your own sense of what is right and wrong
is so strong that you have not even thought
of revenge against your friend.
I admire you very much for that.'
Henry's admiration was enough to make Catherine
feel better in any situation.
She was determined not to think that Captain
Tilney was completely evil; she decided she
would never answer Isabella's letter, and
she tried not to think about what had happened
in Bath between those two ever again.
CHAPTER TEN
A Perfect Visit Ends in Disaster
A few days later, the General announced that
he had to go to London on business for a week.
As he was leaving, he said, 'Miss Morland,
more than anything, I regret that I will be
robbed of your charming company for a whole
week.
I have instructed Eleanor and Henry to look
after you, and I hope you will tell them if
there is anything they can do to make your
stay more amusing or more comfortable.'
The General's departure gave Catherine her
first understanding of the principle that
a loss may sometimes be a gain.
The three young people had much more fun without
General Tilney in control of their lives.
Every meal was a scene of enjoyment and ease,
and every day was spent as the three wished.
These delightful days made our heroine love
the place and the people more and more.
Catherine was now in the fourth week of her
visit and had never been happier.
But the fact that she had been there for almost
a month made her wonder whether it was polite
to stay any longer, or whether she should
suggest choosing a date for her return to
Fullerton.
Although it was an unpleasant subject, Catherine
took the first opportunity to speak to Eleanor
about it.
'Dear Eleanor, I think I must return home
soon.'
'Oh, Catherine,' Eleanor began with feeling,
'I had hoped for the pleasure of your company
for a much longer time.
If your parents knew how much we enjoyed having
you here, do you think they might allow you
to stay a bit longer?'
'Oh, my parents are in no hurry to have me
at home.
They are always satisfied if I am happy.'
'Then why are you in such a hurry to leave
us?' asked Eleanor with a worried look on
her face.
'But I have been here so long!'
Catherine cried.
'If you have grown tired of being here, I
cannot urge you to stay,' Eleanor said sadly.
'Oh, no, you misunderstand me!
For my own pleasure, I would be very happy
to stay another four weeks, but I do not wish
to become a nuisance.'
'Catherine, it is settled then.
You must not think of leaving us.
Henry and I will be very sad to lose you,
so you must stay as long as possible.'
Eleanor's desire for her to stay longer at
Northanger Abbey was so sincere that it confirmed
Catherine's secret belief that the Tilneys
hoped she would belong to their family one
day.
Henry's obligations at Woodston took him away
during his father's absence, but Catherine
continued to be happy because it gave her
time to get to know Eleanor better and to
enjoy her company.
On the evening of Henry's departure, the young
ladies were still sitting and chatting at
the dinner table at eleven o'clock, a rather
late hour at the Abbey.
Then as they walked to their bedrooms, they
heard a carriage arrive outside, and in the
next moment they heard the loud noise of the
doorbell.
'Who could that be at this late hour?'
wondered Eleanor.
'It must be Frederick.
I will say good night, dear Catherine, and
go downstairs to welcome him.'
Catherine went into her room, thinking about
meeting Captain Tilney the next morning at
breakfast.
She hoped that he would not mention Isabella's
name, or the part he had played in her brother's
unhappiness.
She thought she could be polite to him as
long as no one talked about Bath.
Half an hour later, Catherine heard someone
come up the stairs and then her door opened
very gently.
Eleanor came into her room, looking pale and
quite nervous.
Catherine worried that Captain Tilney was
in some kind of trouble and made Eleanor sit
down.
After a minute or two of silence, Miss Tilney
said, 'My dear Catherine, I have come to you
with bad news.
And I do not know how to tell you about it.
Oh, how shall I tell you?'
'Has something happened to Henry?
Is there a messenger from Woodston downstairs?'
'No, it is not anyone from Woodston.
My father himself has arrived.'
Eleanor's voice shook and she looked at the
carpet when she said, 'my father'.
Catherine was disappointed to know that General
Tilney had returned early, but she waited
for Eleanor to explain more.
'You are so good and kind, a friend who will
understand how difficult this is for me, especially
after we had happily agreed that you would
stay for another four weeks.
I am an unwilling messenger who has to tell
you that we must part.
My father has remembered that we accepted
an invitation to go to Lord Longtown's house,
near Hereford, for a fortnight.
We leave on Monday.
Explanation and apology are equally impossible.
My heart is too heavy to attempt either.'
'My dear Eleanor, don't be distressed.
I am very, very sorry that we must part so
soon, but I am not offended.
An earlier engagement must take priority,
and I can finish my visit later, or you can
come to me at Fullerton after Hereford.'
'It will not be in my power to do that,' Eleanor
said quietly.
'Come to Fullerton when you can, then.'
Eleanor did not respond to this suggestion,
and Catherine continued, 'Monday is very soon.
And are you all going?
Don't worry, Eleanor, I can be ready to go
on Monday morning.
We can be together until it is time for you
to depart.
It will not bother my parents if I show up
unannounced on Monday evening.
The General will send a servant with me, I
imagine, for half the trip, and then I will
be at Salisbury and only nine miles from home.'
'Catherine, I wish I could tell you that those
were the arrangements.
But - what can I say?
You must leave us tomorrow morning; the carriage
has been ordered to be waiting for you at
seven o'clock and no servant will accompany
you.'
Catherine sank into a chair, unable to breathe
or to speak.
'Dear Catherine,' Eleanor continued, 'I could
hardly believe my senses when I was told.
No disappointment or anger on your part could
be greater than my own.
What will your father and mother say after
we took you away from the Allens, your true
friends, and brought you here, so far from
your home?
And now you are cruelly driven out of the
house without the smallest consideration for
your comfort or safety.
Dear, dear Catherine, I had to deliver the
message, but you know that I have no real
power in this house.
I think you know who is responsible for this
insult.'
'Have I offended the General?'
Catherine asked weakly.
'I can think of nothing that you have done
to offend him, but I have never seen him so
angry.'
Catherine struggled to speak for Eleanor's
sake.
'I am very sorry if I have upset him; it is
the last thing I would do on purpose.
But don't be unhappy, Eleanor.
You must go to Hereford and keep your engagement.
I am only sorry that the trip was not remembered
sooner so I could have written home.
But it will not matter to my family.
They will be happy to see me.'
'But you should not have to make the journey
alone!'
'The journey is nothing.
It is less than seventy miles.
Don't think about that.
I can be ready at seven.
Please ask your servant to call me in time.'
After Eleanor left, Catherine burst into tears.
She was being thrown out!
With no reasonable explanation nor apology
from General Tilney, she was being rudely
sent home.
She could not even say goodbye to Henry, and
what about her hopes?
Would she ever see him again?
How could a man who had been so polite and
kind to her, who had treated her fondly throughout
her time at Northanger Abbey, now act so rudely
towards her?
She must have offended him in some way and
given him reasons for treating her so badly.
Seven o'clock!
He wanted her out of the house before he left
his bedroom in the morning.
Catherine spent another sleepless night at
Northanger Abbey, but this time she was not
frightened by imagined ghosts and mysterious
chests and cupboards.
This time her anxiety had a basis in fact,
and neither the wind nor the darkness bothered
her.
Instead, she lay awake wondering how things
had gone so badly wrong.
By the time Eleanor came to her room at six
in the morning Catherine had finished her
packing, and she was almost dressed and ready
to depart.
Both young women remained silent, neither
knowing how to improve the situation.
At the breakfast table, Catherine could not
eat, but she thought about breakfast the day
before.
Happy, happy breakfast!
Henry had been there and the three of them
had chatted, enjoying everything present,
and fearing nothing in the future except Henry's
visit to Woodston for a few days.
Henry had sat beside her and helped her to
food, and so Catherine now lost herself in
this memory.
Then she heard the carriage arrive outside
and remembered what was happening.
Eleanor now felt the need to speak and hurried
to say, 'You must write to me, Catherine,
as soon as possible.
You must tell me you are safe at home and
have found your family well.
I will not expect more.
Please send a letter to me at Lord Longtown's,
but address it to his daughter, my friend
Alice.'
'No, Eleanor,' Catherine answered quietly,
'if you are not allowed to receive a letter
from me, I think I had better not write.
I will have no trouble getting home safely.'
'I am not surprised by your feelings, dear
Catherine, and will not urge you to do something
you are unhappy about,' Eleanor answered sadly,
with tears in her eyes.
'Oh, Eleanor, I will write to you.
Please don't worry.'
'Thank you, Catherine, and there is one more
thing.
You have been so long away from home that
I wonder if you have any money left for the
journey.'
Catherine quickly looked into her purse and
said, 'I had not thought about money, but
you are right.
I cannot pay for the journey to Fullerton.'
Eleanor gave Catherine money from her own
purse.
Soon the carriage was announced to be ready;
and Catherine and Eleanor's silent, sad looks
expressed more than any words could.
They hurried to the door, and Catherine was
soon climbing into the carriage.
But she could not leave until she had asked
Eleanor with trembling lips to give her kind
regards to her absent friend.
But by almost mentioning his name, Catherine's
tears began again and she found her seat and
covered her face with her handkerchief.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Reliable Family Life
Catherine felt too unhappy to be frightened
by the journey to Fullerton, and began it
without worrying about its length or about
being alone.
Leaning back in the corner of the carriage,
crying and feeling cruelly treated, she had
gone a number of miles beyond the walls of
Northanger Abbey before she raised her head
and looked out of the window.
She recognised the road as the same one that
had taken her to Woodston only ten days earlier,
and she suffered even more as she thought
about the difference between that trip and
this one.
Every mile, as it brought her nearer Woodston,
added to her grief.
When the carriage passed the road that led
directly to Woodston, Catherine thought of
Henry and the day that she had spent at his
house there.
It had been one of the happiest days of her
life.
On that occasion the General had given her
the impression that he actually wished for
Henry to marry her.
Yes, only ten days ago she had felt so happy
about the future, and now, what had she done
or not done to deserve such a change in the
General's opinion of her?
The only offence against General Tilney that
Catherine could accuse herself of was her
shocking suspicions about what had happened
to his wife.
But Catherine trusted that her secret was
safe with Henry; he would not have betrayed
her.
It was impossible for the General to know
that she once wondered if he might have murdered
his wife or made her a prisoner in her own
home.
Of course if he did know about her suspicions,
he would have a good reason to ask her to
leave, but she believed in Henry and was certain
that her secret was safe with him.
But more than anything, Catherine was anxious
about Henry's feelings when he returned to
the Abbey and found that she had been sent
away.
Would he accept his father's reasons for throwing
her out?
Or would he regret that she was gone and hate
his father for sending her home?
Would he argue with his father or remain obedient
and talk only to Eleanor about his true feelings?
While thinking over many questions and struggling
with doubts about herself, Catherine hardly
noticed the hours and miles flying by.
How would she explain to her family the circumstances
surrounding her sudden return to Fullerton?
Would there be any pleasure in returning home
with such a story to tell?
How could she make it clear to them that Henry
and Eleanor were the finest, most interesting
and most reliable friends she had ever known?
How could she separate them from General Tilney
in her family's opinion?
It would break her heart if her family judged
her friends unfairly.
Finally, after a journey which had taken more
than eleven hours without accident or alarm,
Catherine reached Fullerton just after six
thirty in the evening.
We would expect a heroine to return to her
native village after achieving great things,
with many stories of success to be proud of.
But this homecoming was very different from
what you or she might have hoped for.
Our heroine was returning home disappointed,
alone and without hope or joy.
Therefore, her carriage passed quickly through
the village and Catherine hurried into her
house, unwilling to meet the questioning eyes
of friends and neighbours.
But you must remember that the Morland family
would not have high expectations of any great
achievements or successes for Catherine.
Instead, although they would be surprised
by her unexpected arrival, they would simply
be very happy to have her at home again.
The two youngest children, a boy and girl
of six and four years old, looked out when
they heard the carriage stop at their gate,
expecting, as usual, to see a brother or sister
arrive home.
But when they saw that it was Catherine returning
after an absence of eleven weeks, they jumped
for joy, shouted for their parents and ran
out to greet their older sister.
The warm, affectionate welcome that Catherine
received from her parents and brothers and
sisters awakened the best feelings in her
heart, and she found her troubled spirit calmed;
she even, at first, felt happy!
But Mrs Morland noticed that the poor traveller
looked pale and tired, and soon had the family
seated round the tea-table.
With cups of tea and sandwiches in front of
them, everyone was eager to hear about Catherine's
adventures and to find out why she had come
home without warning.
Quite slowly, and with much hesitation, Catherine
tried to explain what had happened the night
before, and although her parents were usually
unwilling to criticise other people, they
felt unable to pardon this insult to their
daughter.
They believed that General Tilney had acted
neither honourably nor kindly as a gentleman
or as a parent.
What could have made him treat a guest so
badly?
Like Catherine, they could see no reason for
his rude behaviour, especially after he had
treated her so well for the past four weeks.
Finally, Mrs Morland ended the conversation
by saying, 'It is a strange business and General
Tilney must be a strange man, but you are
home now, safe and secure.
It is not worth troubling yourself any further
about that man's reasons.'
'But why couldn't he send Catherine home in
the proper manner if he had to leave for Hereford?'
asked Sarah, the eldest of Catherine's sisters.
'I do not think we will discover his reasons,'
answered Mrs Morland.
'I feel sorry for his own children, who must
have a difficult time with him as their father.
But you managed well on your long trip, Catherine,
and I am very proud of you.
I believe you have grown up quite a lot in
the last eleven weeks.
I am glad I did not know of your journey while
it was happening, but now it has ended perhaps
there is no great harm done.
You are not the same little girl that we said
goodbye to eleven weeks ago.
You have grown up and can take care of yourself
now.'
Catherine hoped that her mother was right
about that, but her spirits were quite worn
down and she longed to be silent and alone.
She was happy to agree to her mother's suggestion
that she should go to bed early and gain the
benefit of a good night's rest.
Her parents knew she was tired and disappointed,
but they had not guessed that she was also
suffering from a broken heart.
Perhaps it is odd that with a young daughter
of seventeen just returning from her first
adventure away from home, they had not thought
of that.
As soon as breakfast had ended the next morning,
Catherine sat down to write the promised letter
to her friend at Northanger Abbey.
She regretted the cold manner in which she
had left Eleanor Tilney, and the fact that
she had never valued her kindness and character
enough.
But most of all, she worried about leaving
Eleanor to deal with General Tilney and his
difficult nature.
She wanted her letter to say how grateful
she was without reminding Eleanor of how the
visit had ended.
She wanted to be careful without being cold,
honest without placing blame.
She did not want to cause Eleanor any pain,
and she did not want to embarrass herself
in case Henry saw the letter.
In the end, Catherine wrote a very short note
in which she expressed her grateful thanks
and her affectionate good wishes for Eleanor
and her brother, and in which she returned
the money Eleanor had given her for her journey.
'This is a very strange friendship,' said
Mrs Morland when Catherine had finished her
letter.
'Soon made and soon ended.
I am sorry that you were disappointed, because
Mrs Allen had only good things to say about
the Tilney children.
And you were so unlucky with your friend Isabella
too.
And poor James!
Well, we must live and learn; I hope your
next new friends will be more worth keeping.'
Catherine's cheeks went red as she warmly
answered, 'No friend can be more worth keeping
than Eleanor.'
'If that is true, Catherine, I hope that you
and she will meet again some time in the next
few years.
It is very likely to happen - imagine what
a pleasure it will be to see her again.'
But Catherine was not thinking only of Eleanor
as she listened to her mother's kind, but
painful words.
What would happen to Henry Tilney if she did
not meet him for a few years?
Her eyes filled with tears as she imagined
such a meeting.
He might have forgotten her and have met another
young woman who attracted him.
The next time she saw him, he might be a married
man with a family of his own - he might not
even recognise her!
Mrs Morland was disturbed by her daughter's
tears and proposed a visit to Mrs Allen.
And so mother and daughter began the walk
to their neighbour's house, which was less
than a quarter of a mile distant.
As they walked, Mrs Morland gave Catherine
her opinion of James's broken engagement.
'Of course we are sorry for James, but it
is good that the engagement has ended, and
there is no harm done in the end.
We did not know Miss Thorpe, and she had no
personal fortune.
And now, after such improper behaviour, we
have a very poor opinion of her.
James will recover, and I am sure that he
will use better judgement next time.'
Her mother's thoughts made Catherine reflect
on the changes in her own circumstances.
Three months ago she had been full of happy
expectations and had run between her home
and the Allens' house ten times a day with
a light heart and an independent spirit, looking
forward to new pleasures and without a care
in the world.
She could picture herself three months ago,
and now what a different young woman she was!
The Allens were surprised, but very glad,
to see Catherine, and they too were very angry
and displeased on learning how she had been
treated by General Tilney.
'Catherine surprised us yesterday evening,'
reported Mrs Morland.
'She travelled all the way in a carriage by
herself and knew nothing about her journey
until late Saturday night.
General Tilney returned home with the strange
idea that he was tired of having her in his
house.
He must be a very odd man, very unfriendly
certainly, but we are so glad to have Catherine
with us again.
And it is a great comfort to find that she
is not a poor helpless creature, but can manage
very well for herself.'
Mrs Allen was shocked.
She filled every pause in the conversation
by saying, 'I really have no patience with
the General.'
But she did not allow for many pauses.
'Bath is a nice place, Catherine, after all,'
she said brightly.
'I did not like the idea of leaving.
Did I tell you that I tore my blue dress?
I had it mended before we left Bath and you
cannot see the tear.
And Mrs Thorpe was such a comfort to us, wasn't
she?
You know, you and I were quite lonely at first.'
'Yes, but that did not last long,' Catherine
replied brightly, enjoying thoughts of Bath
and happier days.
'Very true.
Then we met Mrs Thorpe and were always busy.
My dear, do you think these silk gloves still
look well?
I wore them for the first time in Bath.
Do you remember that evening?'
'Oh, yes, perfectly,' answered Catherine.
'It was very agreeable, wasn't it?
Mr Tilney drank tea with us that evening,
and I thought he was an excellent addition
to our little society.
He is a kind gentleman, isn't he?
I think you probably danced with him that
evening.
I am not certain, but I was wearing my most
expensive dress, do you remember?
And Mr Tilney admired it very much.'
Catherine felt too emotional to answer, but
Mrs Allen continued, 'I really have no patience
with the General.
He seemed such an admirable gentleman when
we met him.
Do you know, Catherine, that his lodgings
were rented by another family the day after
he and his children left?
But no wonder - it was such a desirable address.'
As they walked home again, Mrs Morland said,
'You must be grateful for your old friends.
They have loved you and been concerned for
your happiness for many years.
Having the affection and good opinion of friends
like Mr and Mrs Allen is much more important
than your recent unhappy experience.'
Catherine knew that these were wise words,
but at that moment they meant little to her.
Her present happiness did not depend on old
friends, but on the behaviour of her newest
friends.
Mrs Morland continued encouraging her daughter
to forget about the people she had met at
Bath as they walked towards home.
Catherine listened politely to her mother,
but she was silently reflecting that now Henry
must have arrived at Northanger; now he must
have heard about her departure; and now, perhaps,
the family were leaving the Abbey for Hereford.
The following day, Mrs Morland sat with Catherine
and Sarah, her two eldest daughters, as they
worked at their various jobs.
Catherine had never been hard-working, nor
had she liked sitting indoors for very long,
but Mrs Morland noticed that her bad habits
had become even worse.
The seventeen-year-old could not sit still,
nor concentrate on a piece of work for even
ten minutes at a time.
She regularly stood up and walked around the
room or wandered into the garden.
Sitting quietly seemed impossible.
But worst of all to her mother was Catherine's
lack of energy and spirit.
She knew her daughter had never been a good
worker, but silence and sadness were unusual
for her.
What had happened to her old, cheerful personality?
For two days Mrs Morland allowed this behaviour
to pass without a hint of criticism, but when
a third night's rest still had not returned
Catherine to her old self, she decided to
have a serious talk with her daughter.
'My dear Catherine, I am afraid you have become
too grand for your own family.
Should your father mend his own shirts?
Look how steadily your sister is working,
while your head is still in Bath.
You must remember that there is a time for
everything.
Now is not the time for balls and theatre;
now is the time for you to be useful to me
and to your family.'
Catherine picked up her sewing basket and
sadly replied, 'I do not think about Bath.
At least, not very much.'
'Then you must still be upset about General
Tilney, and that is very silly of you.
You probably will never see him again.
You should not worry about things you cannot
change.'
After a short silence, she continued, 'I hope
you have not found your home disappointing
because it is not as elegant as Northanger
Abbey.
That would be turning your visit into something
evil.
Wherever you are, but especially in your own
home, you should learn to be content.
I was not happy to hear you at breakfast talking
so much about the French bread and the beautiful
plates at Northanger.'
'I am sure I do not care about any of that,'
said Catherine quietly.
'I have a book,' Mrs Morland said, 'with a
very clever essay about young ladies who have
been spoiled by making friends with people
who are much grander than their own families.
I will find it for you later.
I am sure it will do you good.'
Catherine tried to get on with her work, but
after a few minutes Mrs Morland saw her staring
out of the window again.
She came to the conclusion that her daughter
was suffering, and she hastily left the room
to find her book of clever essays.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Happily Ever After...
Eventually
It took at least fifteen minutes for Mrs Morland
to find her book of essays, and then she had
a few other tasks to complete before she could
return to her daughter.
And when she was able to return, she was surprised
to find a visitor there, someone whom she
had never seen before.
With a look of much respect, the young man
immediately rose, and Catherine introduced
Mr Henry Tilney to her mother.
Mr Tilney quickly began to apologise to Mrs
Morland.
'I am sorry to arrive here without an invitation.
I know that you cannot welcome a visitor from
Northanger Abbey after what happened to Miss
Morland there, but I was impatient to know
that she had arrived home safely.'
Mrs Morland had never blamed Henry or his
sister for their father's rude behaviour,
and now she was very pleased by this young
man's appearance and by his sincere apology.
'Thank you, Mr Tilney, for your kind treatment
of Catherine.
I believe you have nothing to apologise for.
You, and any friends of our children, are
always welcome to visit us at Fullerton.'
Then she continued with a list of polite questions
about Mr Tilney's journey, the weather and
the condition of the roads.
Meanwhile Catherine remained silent, but her
mother could see from her bright eyes and
rosy cheeks that she was very pleased by Mr
Tilney's presence, and Mrs Morland slipped
the book of essays into a convenient drawer
for a future hour.
Eventually Mrs Morland exhausted her supply
of polite questions, and Henry turned to Catherine
for the first time since her mother's entrance
and asked, 'Are Mr and Mrs Allen now at Fullerton?'
Catherine struggled to calm her nerves and
answer sensibly, but finally made it clear
that the Allens were at home.
'I would like to pay my respects to them,'
Mr Tilney said.
His face was now almost as red as Catherine's.
'I wonder if you would be kind enough to show
me the way to their house, Miss Morland?'
'You can see it from that window,' interrupted
Sarah, who continued to sew quietly but was
keeping an eye on what was happening.
Mr Tilney bowed politely, but Mrs Morland
gave her younger daughter a silencing nod.
They both understood that seeing the Allens
was not the primary purpose of Mr Tilney's
invitation.
Mrs Morland thought that he might want to
explain his father's behaviour to Catherine
in private, and she did not intend to put
any barriers in the way of that conversation;
she encouraged Catherine to walk to the Allens'
house with Mr Tilney.
Mrs Morland was correct: Henry Tilney did
want to explain his father's rudeness - a
difficult task for a son - but that was not
his primary reason for wanting to talk to
Catherine.
Above all, he wanted to explain himself, and
before they reached the Allens' house he had
done that extremely well.
In fact it was a speech that Catherine thought
could not be repeated too often.
Henry assured her of his affection, and asked
if he could hope that she also loved him - something
that you will have no doubts about by this
time.
Henry was sincerely and completely attached
to our heroine; he was delighted by her character
and truly loved spending all his time with
her.
But you must understand that his love and
affection for Catherine had its origin in
something quite simple; he had recognised
that she seemed to admire everything about
him, and for this he was very grateful.
So on this basis, although Henry would not
have been able to explain his reasons to himself,
he proposed marriage to Miss Catherine Morland.
The visit to Mr and Mrs Allen's house was
very short.
Both Catherine and Henry were thinking of
something much more important than chatting
about Bath.
Henry was polite, Catherine scarcely said
a word, and soon the young couple were happily
walking along the path together again, with
nothing to do except think of their future
life together.
Can you imagine the joy that filled our heroine's
heart?
She floated along beside Mr Tilney in a cloud
of happiness, as he talked about this and
that.
But she listened carefully when her dear Henry
said that he did not have his father's permission
to approach her.
On his return from Woodston, two days earlier,
he had been met near the Abbey by his impatient
father.
In very angry terms the General had insisted
that Henry should never think of Miss Catherine
Morland again.
This information shocked Catherine, but more
important was the fact that Henry wanted to
marry her.
Knowing that she was loved gave her the courage
to try to understand the motives for General
Tilney's actions and for his disapproval of
her.
As Henry's story unfolded, her curiosity turned
to delight.
His father had found no reason to criticise
Catherine's behaviour or her character; he
was, instead, disappointed by his own actions
and ashamed of having been misled by Mr John
Thorpe.
Catherine, it seemed, was guilty of only one
thing in the General's opinion: she was less
rich than he had supposed her to be.
The General had been deceived by John Thorpe
at their first meeting, at the theatre in
Bath.
On that occasion, Henry had been talking to
Catherine and the General had asked Mr Thorpe
if he knew the young lady.
John Thorpe had a misleading, and even dangerous,
habit of exaggerating the importance and wealth
of his friends and acquaintances; he seemed
to think that this made him more important
in the eyes of the world.
When he had become friends with James Morland,
he had reported to his family that he had
met a young man from a very grand family;
then, introducing James to Isabella, he had
doubled the amount of his friend's living,
multiplied his private fortune by three or
four times, invented a rich aunt for him,
and forgot about half of James's brothers
and sisters.
John Thorpe had continued with this practice
of exaggeration when telling General Tilney
about the Morland family.
He had invented a large private income for
Catherine, whom he himself had decided to
marry, as well as the promise that she would
one day receive an enormous inheritance from
the Allens.
With this information, which he had no reason
to doubt, General Tilney had decided to welcome
Miss Morland to Northanger Abbey and to encourage
his son to consider Miss Catherine Morland
as a possible bride.
Henry and Eleanor knew nothing about their
father's conversation with John Thorpe; they
were astonished by the kind, friendly attention
he showed towards Catherine, and the clear
signals he gave Henry that he approved of
her as his son's future wife.
But on his visit to London, the General had
met Mr John Thorpe again.
The younger man was by that time suffering
from what he considered to be ill treatment
by both James and Catherine Morland: she had
refused his proposal of marriage and James
would not accept Isabella's apologies.
Now he was eager to change the General's good
opinion of the whole Morland family.
This time he gave a more accurate account
of how many Morland children there were and
the amount of money and possessions the parents
had; in fact, he mentioned too many of one
and too few of the other.
And the Allens?
Their entire fortune would be inherited by
one of Mr Allen's nephews.
Angry with almost everyone in the world except
himself, the General had returned to the Abbey,
where you have seen how he behaved towards
our heroine.
Having heard all this, Catherine forgave herself
for thinking that General Tilney could either
have murdered or imprisoned his wife.
Now she understood how cruel he could be in
reality.
Poor Henry was blushing with shame while telling
Catherine this story.
He had had an angry conversation with his
father at Northanger Abbey, and had shocked
the General by refusing to agree with his
judgement of Catherine.
He felt tied to Catherine as much by honour
as affection; he would not dismiss her from
his heart or from his life.
He refused to accompany Eleanor and his father
to Herefordshire, and declared his intention
of asking Miss Morland to marry him.
General Tilney had been angrier than he had
ever been with his son, and the two had parted
without speaking to each other again.
Henry had returned to Woodston, and had begun
his journey to Fullerton on the following
afternoon.
Mr and Mrs Morland were quite astonished to
be asked by Mr Henry Tilney for permission
to marry their daughter.
They had not suspected a connection between
the two young people, but they believed Catherine
was worth loving and they soon happily accepted
the situation.
They had no reason to object to the marriage,
not having heard anything negative about Henry
and liking his pleasing manners and good sense.
Mrs Morland's only additional comment was,
'I am sure Catherine will make a poor housekeeper,
but practice is a good teacher.'
Nevertheless, even with everyone celebrating
the proposal, Mr and Mrs Morland could not
approve of the engagement.
They had mild tempers, but their principles
were strong; they did not expect heartfelt
approval from the General, but they required
his agreement, at least.
They assured the pair that they would be happy
for them to marry when that agreement was
obtained, but not before, and they trusted
that it would not be denied for long.
There need be no expectation of money from
the father, since his son's present income
already made him independent and comfortable,
their daughter could not hope for more.
The young people were not surprised by this
decision.
They were, of course, upset, but they parted
from each other with the hope that the General's
opinion could be changed very soon.
Henry returned to what was now his only home,
at Woodston, to look after his parish and
to make improvements to his house for his
future wife; Catherine remained at Fullerton
to cry rather dramatically and to look forward
to regular letters from Henry.
We need not enquire whether the difficulties
of absence were made easier by such secret
communication.
Mr and Mrs Morland never did - they had been
too kind to demand promises and whenever Catherine
received a letter, which happened quite often,
they always looked the other way.
As we approach the last of these pages, you
will have guessed that a happy ending is promised
very soon.
The only doubt can be the way in which perfect
happiness was achieved.
What circumstance could possibly change the
General's opinion of a marriage between his
son and Miss Morland?
The answer was another marriage.
In the course of the summer, Eleanor Tilney
married a young man with a large fortune and
a very respectable position in society.
Such an addition to his own importance threw
the General into a good mood for months, and
Eleanor insisted that he must forgive Henry
and accept Catherine as his future daughter-in-law.
Everyone who knows Eleanor Tilney will, I
am sure, congratulate her and wish her well
in the home and with the man of her choice,
away from the strict discipline of Northanger
Abbey.
My own joy on the occasion is very sincere.
I know of no one who, after all her suffering,
deserves happiness more.
And her husband was a young man who truly
deserved her: he was not only rich and important,
but also affectionate and charming.
Eleanor had known him for years, but General
Tilney had approved of him as little as he
approved of Catherine, and for the same reason:
he came from a respectable family with no
money.
But then this young man inherited an enormous
fortune as well as a title, and the General's
opinion changed immediately.
Suddenly he too could see that Eleanor's future
husband was the most charming young man in
the world.
And I should add that this was the same gentleman
whose careless servant left the laundry lists
in a drawer at Northanger Abbey and involved
our heroine in one of her most alarming adventures.
Eleanor and her delightful, rich husband used
their influence to persuade the General that
Henry should be allowed to marry Catherine
Morland.
In fact, they explained that Catherine was
not, in fact, poor and would have an income
of her own of three thousand pounds a year,
and that her father was much wealthier than
John Thorpe had reported during his second
meeting with General Tilney.
As a result of this happy news, the General
soon permitted his son to return to Northanger
Abbey and wrote to Mr Morland, politely giving
his agreement to the marriage of his younger
son and the Morlands' eldest daughter.
The event which the General's letter permitted
soon followed: Henry and Catherine were married,
the church bells rang and everybody celebrated.
The wedding took place less than twelve months
after the young couple had met, so the General's
cruelty did not hurt them very much or for
very long.
To begin perfect happiness at twenty-six and
eighteen is to do quite well.
I should add, moreover, that perhaps the General
added to this happiness by delaying the marriage
and giving them time to improve their knowledge
of each other and to strengthen their attachment.
I leave it for you to make a final judgement
on this question: Is the purpose of this story
to recommend parental cruelty, or to reward
a son's disobedience?