Being Frank
It wasn't easy, being Frank.
That's what everybody called him, when they
weren't calling him a dirty old tramp or a
scrounger or a layabout.
Frank, they called him.
Only the people at the hostel and at the Social
Security bothered with his full name: Francis
Rossetti Hyslop.
Rossetti, he seemed to remember, not after
the painter but after his sister the poet,
Christina.
Most often, a person - a person in authority
- would read that name from the piece of paper
they were holding and then look up at Frank,
not quite in disbelief, but certainly wondering
how he'd come so low.
He couldn't tell them that he was climbing
higher all the time.
That he preferred to live out of doors.
That his face was weatherbeaten, not dirty.
That a plastic bag was a convenient place
to keep his possessions.
He just nodded and shuffled his feet instead,
the shuffle which had become his trademark.
'Here he comes,' his companions would cry.
'Here comes The Shuffler!'
Alias Frank, alias Francis Rossetti Hyslop.
He spent much of the spring and autumn in
Edinburgh.
Some said he was mad, leaving in the summer
months.
That, after all, was when the pickings were
richest.
But he didn't like to bother the tourists,
and besides, summer was for travelling.
He usually walked north, through Fife and
into Kinross or Perthshire, setting up camp
by the side of a loch or up in the hills.
And when he got bored, he'd move on.
He was seldom moved on by gamekeepers or the
police.
Some of them he knew of old, of course.
But others he encountered seemed to regard
him more and more as some rare species, or,
as one had actually said, a 'national monument'.
It was true, of course.
Tramp meant to walk and that's what tramps
used to do.
The term 'gentleman of the road' used to be
accurate.
But the tramp was being replaced by the beggar:
young, fit men who didn't move from the city
and who were unrelenting in their search for
spare change.
That had never been Frank's way.
He had his regulars of course, and often he
only had to sit on a bench in The Meadows,
a huge grassy plain bordered by tree-lined
paths, and wait for the money to appear in
his lap.
That's where he was when he heard the two
men talking.
It was a bright day, a lunchtime and there
were few spaces to be had on the meagre supply
of Meadows benches.
Frank was sitting on one, arms folded, eyes
closed, his legs stretched out in front of
him with one foot crossed over the other.
His three carrier bags were on the ground
beside him, and his hat lay across his legs
- not because he was hot especially, but because
you never knew who might drop a coin in while
you were dozing, or pretending to doze.
Maybe his was the only bench free.
Maybe that's why the men sat down beside him.
Well, 'beside him' was an exaggeration.
They squeezed themselves onto the furthest
edge of the bench, as far from him as possible.
They couldn't be comfortable, squashed up
like that and the thought brought a moment's
smile to Frank's face.
But then they started to talk, not in a whisper
but with voices lowered.
The wind, though, swept every word into Frank's
right ear.
He tried not to tense as he listened, but
it was difficult.
Tried not to move, but his nerves were jangling.
'It's war,' one said.
'A council of war.'
War?
He remembered reading in a newspaper recently
about terrorists.
Threats.
A politician had said something about vigilance.
Or was it vigilantes?
A council of war: it sounded ominous.
Maybe they were teasing him, trying to scare
him from the bench so that they could have
it for themselves.
But he didn't think so.
They were speaking in undertones; they didn't
think he could hear.
Or maybe they simply knew that it didn't matter
whether an old tramp heard them or not.
Who would believe him?
This was especially true in Frank's case.
Frank believed that there was a worldwide
conspiracy.
He didn't know who was behind it, but he could
see its tentacles stretching out across the
globe.
Everything was connected, that was the secret.
Wars were connected by arms manufacturers,
the same arms manufacturers who made the guns
used in robberies, who made the guns used
by crazy people in America when they went
on the rampage in a shopping-centre or hamburger
restaurant.
So already you had a connection between hamburgers
and dictators.
Start from there and the thing just grew and
grew.
And because Frank had worked this out, he
wondered from time to time if they were after
him.
The dictators, the arms industry, or maybe
even the people who made the buns for the
hamburger chains.
Because he knew.
He wasn't crazy; he was sure of that.
'If I was,' he told one of his regulars, 'I
wouldn't wonder if I was or not, would I?'
And she'd nodded, agreeing with him.
She was a student at the university.
A lot of students became regulars.
They lived in Tollcross, Marchmont, Morningside,
and had to pass through The Meadows on their
way to the university buildings in George
Square.
She was studying psychology, and she told
Frank something.
'You've got what they call an active fantasy
life.'
Yes, he knew that.
He made up lots of things, told himself stories.
They whiled away the time.
He pretended he'd been an RAF pilot, a spy,
minor royalty, a slave-trader in Africa, a
poet in Paris.
But he knew he was making all these stories
up, just as he knew that there really was
a conspiracy.
And these two men were part of it.
'Rhodes,' one of them was saying now.
A council of war in Rhodes.
So there was a Greek connection, too.
Well, that made sense.
He remembered stories about the generals and
their junta.
The terrorists were using Greece as their
base.
And Edinburgh was called the 'Athens of the
north'.
Yes!
Of course!
That's why they were basing themselves in
Edinburgh too.
A symbolic gesture.
Had to be.
But who would believe him?
That was the problem, being Frank.
He'd told so many stories in the past, given
the police so much information about the conspiracy,
that now they just laughed at him and sent
him on his way.
Some of them thought he was looking for a
night in the cells and once or twice they'd
even obliged, despite his protests.
No, he didn't want to spend another night
locked up.
There was only one thing for it.
He'd follow the men and see what he could
find.
Then he'd wait until tomorrow.
They were talking about tomorrow, too, as
if it was the start of their campaign.
Well, tomorrow was Sunday and with a bit of
luck if Frank hung around The Meadows, he'd
bump into another of his regulars, one who
might know exactly what to do.
Sunday morning was damp, blustery.
Not the sort of day for a constitutional.
This was fine by John Rebus: it meant there'd
be fewer people about on Bruntsfield Links.
Fewer men chipping golf-balls towards his
head with a wavering cry of 'Fore!'
Talk about crazy golf!
He knew the Links had been used for this purpose
for years and years, but all the same there
were so many paths cutting through that it
was a miracle no one had been killed.
He walked one circuit of the Links, then headed
as usual across Melville Drive and into The
Meadows.
Sometimes he'd stop to watch a kickabout.
Other times, he kept his head down and just
walked, hoping for inspiration.
Sunday was too close to Monday for his liking
and Monday always meant a backlog of work.
Thinking about it never did any good, of course,
but he found himself thinking of little else.
'Mr Rebus!'
But then The Meadows offered other distractions,
too.
'Mr Rebus!'
'Hello, Frank.'
'Sit yourself down.'
Rebus lowered himself onto the bench.
'You look excited about something.'
Frank nodded briskly.
Though he was seated, he shuffled his feet
on the earth, making little dance movements.
Then he looked around him, as though seeking
interlopers.
Oh no, thought Rebus, here we go again.
'War,' Frank whispered.
'I heard two men talking about it.'
Rebus sighed.
Talking to Frank was like reading one of the
Sunday rags - except sometimes the stories
be told were more believable.
Today didn't sound like one of those days.
'Talking about war?
Which war?'
'Terrorism, Mr Rebus.
Has to be.
They've had a council of war at Rhodes.
That's in Greece.'
'They were Greek, were they?'
Frank wrinkled his face.
'I don't think so.
I can give you a description of them though.
They were both wearing suits.
One was short and bald, the other one was
young, taller, with black hair.'
'You don't often see international terrorists
wearing suits these days, do you?'
Rebus commented.
Actually, he thought to himself, that's a
lie: they're becoming more smartly dressed
all the time.
In any case, Frank had an answer ready.
'Need a disguise though, don't they?
I followed them.'
'Did you?'
A kickabout was starting nearby.
Rebus concentrated on the kick-off.
He liked Frank, but there were times...
'They went to a bed and breakfast near the
Links.'
'Did they now?'
Rebus nodded slowly.
'And they said it was starting today.
Today, Mr Rebus.'
'They don't hang about, do they?
Anything else?'
Frank frowned, thinking.
'Something about lavatories, or laboratories.
Must have been laboratories, mustn't it?
And money, they talked about that.
Money they needed to set it up.
That's about it.'
'Well, thanks for letting me know, Frank.
I'll keep my ears open, see if I can hear
any whispers.
But listen, don't go following people in future.
It could be dangerous, understand?'
Frank appeared to consider this.
'I see what you mean,' he said at last, 'but
I'm tougher than I look, Mr Rebus.'
Rebus was standing now.
'Well, I'd better be getting along.'
He slipped his hands into his pockets.
The right hand emerged again holding a pound
note.
'Here you go, Frank.'
He began to hand the money over, then withdrew
it again.
Frank knew what was coming and grinned.
'Just one question,' Rebus said, as he always
did.
'Where do you go in the winter?'
It was a question a lot of his cronies asked
him.
'Thought you were dead,' they'd say each spring
as he came walking back into their lives.
His reply to Rebus was the same as ever: 'Ah,
that would be telling, Mr Rebus.
That's my secret.'
The money passed from one hand to the other
and Rebus sauntered off towards Jawbone Walk,
kicking a stone in front of him.
Jawbone because of the whale's jawbone which
made an arch at one end of the path.
Frank knew that.
Frank knew lots of things.
But he knew, too, that Rebus hadn't believed
him.
Well, more fool him.
For over a year now they'd played this little
game: where did Frank go in the winter?
Frank wasn't sure himself why he didn't just
say, I go to my sister's place in Dunbar.
Maybe because it was the truth.
Maybe because it was a secret.
Rebus looked to him like a man with secrets,
too.
Maybe one day Rebus would set out for a walk
and never return home, would just keep on
walking the way Frank himself had done.
What was it the girl student had said?
'Sometimes I think we're all gentlemen of
the road.
It's just that most of us haven't got the
courage to take that first step.'
Nonsense: that first step was the easiest.
It was the hundredth, the thousandth, the
millionth that was hard.
But not as hard as going back, never as hard
as that.
Rebus had counted the steps up to his second-floor
flat many, many times.
It always added up to the same number.
So how come with the passing years there seemed
to be more?
Maybe it was the height of each step that
was changing.
Own up, John.
For once, own up: it's you that's changing.
You're growing older and stiffer.
You never used to pause on the first-floor
landing, never used to linger outside Mrs
Cochrane's door, breathing in that smell unique
to blackcurrant bushes and cat-pee.
How could one cat produce that amount of odour?
Rebus had seen it many a time: a fat, smug-looking
creature with hard eyes.
He'd caught it on his own landing, turning
guiltily to look at him before sprinting for
the next floor up.
But it was inside Mrs Cochrane's door just
now.
He could hear it mewling, clawing at the carpet,
desperate to be outside.
He wondered.
Maybe Mrs Cochrane was ill?
He'd noticed that recently her brass nameplate
had become tarnished.
She wasn't bothering to polish it any more.
How old was she anyway?
She seemed to have come with the tenement,
almost as if they'd constructed the thing
around her.
Mr and Mrs Costello on the top floor had been
here nigh-on twenty-five years, but they said
she'd been here when they arrived.
Same brass nameplate on her door.
Different cat, of course, and a husband, too.
Well, he'd been dead by the time Rebus and
his wife - now ex-wife - had moved here, what,
was it ten years ago now?
Getting old, John.
Getting old.
He clamped his left hand onto the bannister
and somehow managed the last flight of steps
to his door.
He started a crossword in one of the newspapers,
put some jazz on the hi-fi, drank a pot of
tea.
Just another Sunday.
Day of rest.
But he kept catching glimpses of the week
ahead.
No good.
He made another pot of tea and this time added
a dollop of J&B to the mixture in his mug.
Better.
And then, naturally, the doorbell rang.
Jehovah's Witnesses.
Well, Rebus had an answer ready for them.
A friend in the know had said that Roman Catholics
are taught how to counter the persuasive arguments
of the JWs.
Just tell them you're a Catholic and they'll
go away.
'I'm Catholic,' he said.
They didn't go away.
There were two of them, dressed in dark suits.
The younger one stood a little behind the
older one.
This didn't matter, since he was a good foot
taller than his elder.
He was holding a briefcase.
The chief, however, held only a piece of paper.
He was frowning, glancing towards this.
He looked at Rebus, sizing him up, then back
to the paper.
He didn't appear to have heard what Rebus
said.
'I'm Catholic,' Rebus repeated, but hollowly.
The man shook his head.
Maybe they were foreign missionaries, come
to convert the heathen.
He consulted his scrap of paper again.
'I think this is the wrong address,' he said.
'There isn't a Mr Bakewell here?'
'Bakewell?'
Rebus started to relax.
A simple mistake; they weren't JWs.
They weren't salesmen or cowboy builders or
tinkers.
Simply, they'd got the wrong flat.
'No,' he said.
'No Mr Bakewell here.
And his tart's not here either.'
Oh, they laughed at that.
Laughed louder than Rebus had expected.
They were still laughing as they made their
apologies and started back downstairs.
Rebus watched them until they were out of
sight.
He'd stopped laughing almost before they'd
begun.
He checked that his keys were in his pocket,
then slammed shut his door - but with himself
still out on the landing.
Their footsteps sent sibilant echoes up towards
the skylight.
What was it about them?
If pressed, he couldn't have said.
There was just something.
The way the smaller, older man had seemed
to weigh him up in a moment, then mentioned
Bakewell.
The way the younger man had laughed so heartily,
as if it were such a release.
A release of what?
Tension, obviously.
The footsteps had stopped.
Outside Mrs Cochrane's door.
Yes, that was the ting-ting-ting of her antiquated
doorbell, the kind you pulled, tightening
and releasing the spring on a bell inside
the door.
The door which was now being pulled open.
The older man spoke.
'Mrs Cochrane?'
Well, they'd got that name right.
But then it was on her nameplate, wasn't it?
Anyone could have guessed at it.
'Aye.'
Mrs Cochrane, Rebus knew, was not unique in
making this sound not only questioning but
like a whole sentence.
Yes, I'm Mrs Cochrane, and who might you be
and what do you want?
'Councillor Waugh.'
Councillor!
No, no, there was no problem: Rebus had paid
his Poll Tax, always put his bin-bags out
the night before, never earlier.
They might be after Bakewell, but Rebus was
in the clear.
'It's about the roadworks.'
'Roadworks?'
echoed Mrs Cochrane.
Roadworks?
thought Rebus.
'Yes, roadworks.
Digging up the roads.
You made a complaint about the roads.
I've come to talk to you about it.'
'Roadworks?
Here, you mean?'
He was patient, Rebus had to grant him that.
'That's right, Mrs Cochrane.
The road outside.'
There was a bit more of this, then they all
went indoors to talk over Mrs Cochrane's grievances'.
Rebus opened his own door and went in, too.
Then, realising, he slapped his hand against
his head.
These were the two men Shuffling Frank had
been talking about!
Of course they were, only Frank had misheard:
council of war was Councillor Waugh; Rhodes
was roads.
What else had Frank said?
Something about money: well, that might be
the money for the repairs.
That it was all planned to start on Sunday:
and here they were, on Sunday, ready to talk
to the residents about roadworks.
What roadworks?
The road outside was clear, and Rebus hadn't
heard any gossip concerning work about to
start.
Something else Frank had heard them say.
Lavatories or laboratories.
Of course, his own cherished conspiracy theory
had made him plump for 'laboratories', but
what if he'd misheard again?
Where did lavatories fit into the scheme?
And if, as seemed certain, these were the
two men, what was a local councillor doing
staying at a bed and breakfast?
Maybe he owned it, of course.
Maybe it was run by his wife.
Rebus was a couple of paces further down his
hall when it hit him.
He stopped dead.
Slow, John, slow.
Blame the whisky, maybe.
And Jesus, wasn't it so obvious when you thought
of it?
He went back to his door opened it quietly,
and slipped out onto the landing.
There was no such thing as silent movement
on an Edinburgh stairwell.
The sound of shoe on stone, a sound like sandpaper
at work, was magnified and distorted, bouncing
off the walls upwards and downwards.
Rebus slipped off his shoes and left them
on his landing, then started downstairs.
He listened outside Mrs Cochrane's door.
Muffled voices from the living-room.
The layout of her flat was the same as Rebus's
own: a long hallway off which were half a
dozen doors, the last of which - actually
around a corner - led to the living-room.
He crouched down and pushed open the letterbox.
The cat was just inside the door and it swiped
at him with its paw.
He let the hinge fall back.
Then he tried the doorhandle, which turned.
The door opened.
The cat swept past him and down the stairs.
Rebus began to feel that the odds were going
his way.
The door was open just wide enough to allow
him to squeeze inside.
Open it an inch or two further, he knew, and
it creaked with the almightiest groan.
He tiptoed into the hallway.
Councillor Waugh's voice boomed from the living-room.
'Bowel trouble.
Terrible in a man so young.'
Yes, he'd no doubt be explaining why his assistant
was taking so long in the lavatory: that was
the excuse they always made.
Well, either that or a drink of water.
Rebus passed the toilet.
The door wasn't locked and the tiny closet
was empty.
He pushed open the next door along - Mrs Cochrane's
bedroom.
The young man was closing the wardrobe doors.
'Well,' said Rebus, 'I hope you didn't think
that was the toilet.'
The man jerked around.
Rebus filled the doorway.
There was no way past him; the only way to
get out was to go through him, and that's
what the man tried, charging at the doorway,
head low.
Rebus stood back a little, giving himself
room and time, and brought his knee up hard,
aiming for the bridge of the nose but finding
mouth instead.
Well, it was an imprecise science, wasn't
it?
The man flew backwards like a discarded ragdoll
and fell onto the bed.
Flat out, to Rebus's satisfaction.
They'd heard the noise of course, and the
'councillor' was already on his way.
But he, too, would need to get past Rebus
to reach the front door.
He stopped short.
Rebus nodded slowly.
'Very wise,' he said.
'Your colleague's going to need some new teeth
when he wakes up.
I'm a police officer by the way.
And you, "councillor", are under arrest.'
'Arresting the councillor?'
This from Mrs Cochrane, who had appeared in
the hall.
'He's no more a councillor than I am, Mrs
Cochrane.
He's a conman.
His partner's been raking through your bedroom.'
'What?'
She went to look.
'Bakewell,' Rebus said, smiling.
They would try the same ruse at every door
where they didn't fancy their chances.
Sorry, wrong address, and on to the next potential
sucker until they found someone old enough
or gullible enough.
Rebus was trying to remember if Mrs Cochrane
had a telephone.
Yes, there was one in her living-room, wasn't
there?
He gestured to his prisoner.
'Let's go back into the living-room,' he said.
Rebus could call the station from there...
Mrs Cochrane was back beside him.
'Blood on my good quilt,' she muttered.
Then she saw that Rebus was in his stocking-soles.
'You'll get chilblains, son,' she said.
'Mark my words.
You should take better care of yourself.
Living on your own like that.
You need somebody to look after you.
Mark my words.
He told me he was a councillor.
Would you credit it?
And me been wanting to talk to them for ages
about the dogs' mess on the Links.'
'Hello, Shuffler.'
'Mr Rebus!
Day off is it?
Don't usually see you around here during the
week.'
Frank was back on his bench, a newspaper spread
out on his lap.
One of yesterday's papers.
It contained a story about some black magic
conspiracy in the United States.
Wealthy people, it was reckoned, influential
people, taking part in orgies and rituals.
Yes, and the arms manufacturers would be there,
too.
That's how they got to know the politicians
and the bankers.
It all connected.
'No, I'm off to work in a minute.
Just thought I'd stop by.
Here.'
He was holding out a ten-pound note.
Frank looked at it suspiciously, moved his
hand towards it, and took it.
What?
Didn't Rebus even want to ask him the question?
'You were right,' Rebus was saying.
'What you told me about those two men, dead
right.
Well, nearly dead right.
Keep your ears open, Frank.
And in future, I'll try to keep my ears open
when you talk to me.'
And then he turned and was walking away, back
across the grass towards Marchmont.
Frank stared at the money.
Ten pounds.
Enough to finance another long walk.
He needed a long walk to clear his head.
Now that they'd had the council of war at
Rhodes, the laboratories would be making potions
for satanic rituals.
They'd put the politicians in a trance, and...
No, no, it didn't bear thinking about.
'Mr Rebus!' he called.
'Mr Rebus!
I go to my sister's!
She lives in Dunbar!
That's where I go in the winter!'
But if the distant figure heard him, it made
no sign.
Just kept on walking.
Frank shuffled his feet.
Ten pounds would buy a transistor radio, or
a pair of shoes, a jacket, or a new hat, maybe
a little camping stove.
That was the problem with having money: you
ended up with decisions to make.
And if you bought anything, where would you
put it?
He'd need either to ditch something, or to
start on another carrier-bag.
That was the problem, being Frank.