The woods were already filled with shadows
one June evening, just before eight o'clock,
although a bright sun, low in the west, still
shone through the trees.
A little girl was driving home her cow, a
slow-moving, annoying creature, but also a
good companion among the shadowy trees.
Their way home was deep in the woods, but
their feet knew the path very well, so the
darkness did not matter.
It often took a long time to find the cow
before Sylvia could bring her home.
The cow seemed to enjoy hiding among the bushes.
She wore a loud bell around her neck, but
the clever creature had discovered that the
bell did not ring if she stood very still.
Luckily, the cow gave good milk and lots of
it, so her owners did not mind about her hiding.
And Sylvia had all the time in the world,
and very little to do in that time except
chase the cow.
The cow had now decided she wanted to go home,
and stepped along the path more quickly.
Sylvia wondered what her grandmother would
say, because they were very late.
It was a long time since she had left home
at half-past five.
But Mrs Tilley had chased the cow herself
on many summer evenings and knew how difficult
the old cow could be.
She also knew that Sylvia loved being outside
in the woods and fields.
It was a great change for a little girl who
had lived for eight years in a crowded noisy
town full of factories.
Old Mrs Tilley had chosen Sylvia from her
daughter's houseful of children, to come and
live with her at the farm.
Sylvia was 'afraid of people', her mother
said, but Mrs Tilley just laughed.
'I guess she won't be troubled much with people
up at the old place!'
So the old grandmother took Sylvia away.
And when at last they reached the door of
the lonely farmhouse, and the cat came to
walk around their legs purring loudly, Sylvia
whispered that this was a beautiful place
to live in, and she would never wish to go
home.
That was a year ago, and now the girl and
the cow followed the shadowy path through
the woods.
The cow stopped to drink in a little river,
and Sylvia stood still and waited, letting
her feet cool themselves in the shallow water.
Up above her, in the great branches of the
tall trees, the leaves moved gently in a little
wind, and the birds were singing, preparing
for the night.
Sylvia herself felt sleepy, but it was not
far to the house now, and the air was soft
and sweet.
She felt that she belonged in this quiet world
of gray shadows and moving leaves, and her
life in the noisy town seemed far away.
Suddenly the little woods-girl heard a clear
whistle not far away.
Not a bird's whistle, which is a friendly
sound, but a boy's whistle - loud and strong
and full of fight.
Frightened, Sylvia tried to hide behind some
bushes, but she was just too late.
The enemy had discovered her, and called out
in a friendly voice, 'Hallo, little girl,
how far is it to the road?'
'A good long way,' answered Sylvia in a frightened
little whisper.
She was not brave enough to look at the tall
young man, who carried a gun over his shoulder,
but she came out from behind her bush and
again followed the cow.
The young man walked along beside her.
'I have been hunting for some birds,' the
stranger said, 'and I have lost my way, and
need a friend very much.
Don't be afraid,' he added gently.
'Speak up, and tell me what your name is.
And do you think I can spend the night at
your house, and go out hunting early in the
morning?'
Sylvia was more frightened than ever.
What would her grandmother say about this?
She did not know what to do and looked down
at the ground.
In the end she managed to whisper, 'Sylvy',
when the young man again asked her name.
Mrs Tilley was at the door when the three
companions arrived.
The cow gave a loud moo to explain matters.
'Yes, you ought to be sorry!'
Mrs Tilley said to the cow.
'Where was she hidin' herself this time, Sylvy?'
But Sylvia kept silent, not knowing how to
explain the stranger.
The young man put his gun by the door, and
dropped his hunting bag next to it.
He said good evening to Mrs Tilley, told his
story, and asked for a night's rest at the
farm.
'Put me anywhere you like,' he said.
'I must be off early in the morning, before
day; but I am very hungry indeed.
You can give me some milk, that's clear.'
'Oh yes, we can give you milk,' said Mrs Tilley.
'And you're welcome to what we've got.
I'll milk the cow right now, an' you make
yourself at home.
There's plenty o' comfortable places to sleep
round the farm,' she added kindly.
'Now step round an' put out a plate for the
gentleman, Sylvy!'
Sylvia disappeared at once, pleased to have
something to do, and she was hungry herself.
The young man was surprised to find this clean
and comfortable little house in the New England
wilderness.
He had stayed in very different kinds of homes,
where the chickens lived in the same room
as the family.
He listened with interest to the old woman
talking, he watched Sylvia's pale face and
shining gray eyes, and he said it was the
best supper that he had eaten in a month.
Afterward, the new friends sat in the doorway
together while the moon came up.
'I've buried four children,' Mrs Tilley told
the young man.
'Sylvy's mother and one son are all the children
that I have now.
Dan, my boy, was a great hunter, he was always
out in the woods.
Sylvy is like him, she knows all the woods
an' fields, every tree an' bush.
The wild creatures think she's one o' them.
The squirrels will come and eat right out
o' her hands, and all kinds o' birds.
She knows all o' them.
Just like Dan.
He's been gone for years,' she said sadly.
'Dan an' his father, they didn't get along.'
There was some family sadness hidden in those
words, but the young man did not hear it;
he was too interested in something else.
'So Sylvy knows all about birds, does she?'
he said.
He looked round at the little girl who sat,
shy and sleepy, in the moonlight.
'I've been collecting birds myself, ever since
I was a boy.'
(Mrs Tilley smiled.)
'But there are two or three unusual ones that
I haven't found yet.'
'Do you put them in cages?'
asked Mrs Tilley.
'Oh no, they're stuffed.
And I've shot or caught every one myself.
I saw a white heron two days ago, and I've
been following it.
The little white heron, it is,' and he turned
to look at Sylvia, hoping that she had seen
it.
'A strange tall white bird with soft feathers
and long thin legs.
Its nest is made of sticks, often in the top
of a high tree.'
Sylvia's heart gave a wild beat.
She knew that strange white bird, and had
once got close to where it stood in the green
marsh grass, over at the other side of the
woods.
'I'd like to find that heron's nest more than
anything,' the young man said.
'I'd give ten dollars to anybody who could
show it to me,' he added, 'and I plan to spend
the rest of my vacation hunting for it.'
Mrs Tilley listened to all this with amused
interest, but Sylvia was watching the moonlight
dancing in the trees.
It was impossible to decide, during that night,
how many wonderful things those ten dollars
could buy.
***
The next day the young hunter walked around
the woods, and Sylvia went with him.
She had lost her fear of the young man, who
was friendly and kind.
He told her many things about the birds and
where they lived and what they did.
And he gave her a pocket-knife, which was
a wonderful thing to her.
She liked him very much indeed, but she did
not like the shooting.
She could not understand why he killed the
birds that he seemed to love so much.
But as the day passed, Sylvia still watched
the young man, and the woman's heart, asleep
in the child, slowly began to learn the dream
of love.
Together they stepped softly through the woodlands.
They stopped to listen to a bird's song, then
went forward, carefully moving branches to
one side.
They spoke little, and only in whispers; the
young man going first and Sylvia following,
with her gray eyes dark with excitement.
She was sad because they did not find the
white heron, the bird that the young man wanted
so much.
But Sylvia only followed where he went; she
could never speak first.
It was hard enough for her to whisper 'yes'
or 'no' to answer questions.
At last evening came, and they found and drove
the cow home together.
And Sylvia smiled happily when they came to
the place where she heard the whistle and
was afraid only the night before.
***
Half a mile from home, at the far edge of
the woods, on high ground, a great pine-tree
stood.
It was the last tree of an older forest, and
around it a new wood of younger trees had
grown.
But the old pine-tree's head stood high above
them all, and was seen from miles away across
land and sea.
Sylvia knew this tree well.
She believed that at the top it was possible
to see the Atlantic Ocean.
The little girl had never seen the sea, but
she had often dreamed about it.
Now, she had a new idea, which filled her
with excitement.
From the top of this great tree she could
see all the world.
So couldn't she also see where the white heron
flew, where it came from, and where it went
to?
She would see where it flew into the trees,
and she would remember the place, and find
the hidden nest.
What an adventure it would be!
And how wonderful, later in the morning, when
she could tell her great secret!
The young hunter and the old grandmother slept
deeply that night, but Sylvia lay awake, waiting
for the short summer night to pass, and her
great adventure to begin.
Before daylight, she quietly left the house
and followed the path through the woods.
The birds were making their first sleepy little
calls, but Sylvia was thinking only about
the great change that had come into her dull
little life.
Ah, Sylvy, Sylvy, do not forget that the birds
and animals of the forest were your first
friends!
Now she came to the great pine-tree, and small
and foolish Sylvia began to climb.
First, she must climb the white oak tree next
to the pine-tree.
She had often climbed this tree, and knew
that one of its high branches went into the
pine-tree, and she could move from one tree
to the other.
She made that dangerous crossing safely, and
now began to climb the pine-tree itself, using
all her fingers and toes to hold on.
The way was harder than she thought; she must
reach far and hold fast.
A red squirrel, coming down the tree, stopped
in great surprise when it saw her, and then
ran away along a branch.
Bravely, she climbed upward.
Light was just appearing in the eastern sky,
and the small song-birds began to sing their
welcome to the new day.
Higher and higher Sylvia climbed.
Her fingers ached from holding on, and the
roughness of the branches hurt her feet.
But on she went.
Perhaps the old pine-tree welcomed this stranger
among its branches, and loved the brave, beating
heart of the gray-eyed child.
At last, Sylvia's face appeared like a pale
star, and she stood, tired and aching, but
bright with victory, high in the tree-top.
Yes, there was the sea in the east, with the
sun making a golden path across it.
And in the west, the woods and farms, the
green fields and white villages, reached miles
into the distance.
Truly, it was a great and beautiful world.
The birds sang louder and louder, and the
sun grew brighter.
Sylvia could see the white sails of ships
out at sea, and the purple-pink clouds began
to turn white.
Where was the white heron's nest in this sea
of green branches?
Now look down, Sylvy, to where the green marsh
lies between the trees.
There, where you saw the white heron once,
you will see him again.
Look, look!
Something white is flying upward from the
dead hemlock-tree by the green marsh.
It comes higher and higher, and flies past
the great pine-tree, its white wings beating
slowly.
Now it lands on a branch nearby, and cries
back to his mate on the nest below and cleans
his feathers for the new day.
The child watches, her heart full of happiness.
She knows the wild white heron's secret now.
In a minute he flies away, back down to his
home in the green world below.
Then Sylvia begins the dangerous climb down,
careful not to look down, and ready to cry
sometimes because her fingers ache and her
feet hurt.
But she wonders over and over again what the
young man will say to her when she tells him
how to find his way straight to the heron's
nest.
'Sylvy, Sylvy!'
called the busy old grandmother again and
again, but Sylvia's small bed was empty.
The visitor woke up, and hurried to get ready
for his day in the woods.
He was sure from the shy little girl's face
that she knew where the white heron was.
Here she is now, paler than ever, her dress
dirty from the pine-tree.
The grandmother and the hunter stand at the
door together and question her, and the great
moment has come to speak of the dead hemlock-tree
by the green marsh.
But Sylvia does not speak after all, although
the young man's kind eyes are looking straight
into her own.
He can make them rich with money; he has promised
it, and they are poor now.
She wants so much to make him happy, and he
waits to hear the story that she can tell.
No, she must keep silent!
Why, suddenly, is it forbidden to speak?
It is the first time in her young life that
the great world has put out a hand to her
- and must she push it away, because of a
bird?
The sound of the great pine-tree's branches
is in her ears, she remembers how the white
heron came flying through the golden air and
how they watched the sea and the morning together,
and Sylvia cannot speak; she cannot tell the
heron's secret and give its life away.
***
The pain in that loyal heart was great when
the young man went away disappointed later
in the day.
The promise and the dream of love had gone
for ever.
For a long time she heard again his whistle
as she came home with the cow, and she even
forgot her sadness at the sound of his gun
and the song-birds falling silent to the ground.
Were the birds better friends than their hunter
- who can tell?
But remember, you wild creatures of the woodland,
what this child has lost!
Bring your love and trust and tell your secrets
to this lonely country child!