CHAPTER ONE
A Mountain Home
It was a hot morning in June in the Alps.
Heidi walked behind her aunt named Dete.
They were walking through the
village and up the mountain.
Heidi was very hot because she
was wearing all her clothes.
She had to carry them to her new
home. She was only six years old.
As Heidi and her aunt hurried out of
the village, a villager stopped to talk.
"Dete, is this the orphan your sister left
when she died? Where are you taking her?"
"Yes, this is Heidi. I'm taking
her to live with her grandfather.
I'm starting a job in the city. So
I can't take care of her any more."
"Poor Heidi," said the villager. "No one
else will talk to that grumpy old man.
While Dete was talking with the villager,
Heidi met a boy named Peter. He was the
village goat herder. Every morning, Peter
came to the village to get the goats.
He was going to take them up the mountain. Heidi
followed him up the mountain. She couldn't keep
up with him because of her heavy clothes. So
she took off all of them except her underwear.
Then she danced behind Peter. He thought she
was funny. The two children began laughing.
Dete caught up with them.
"Where are your clothes?" she asked.
"I don't need them!" Heidi said.
"I want to run free like the goats!"
Aunt Dete scolded Heidi and sent Peter to get
her clothes. They walked for another hour.
Near the mountaintop was Grandfather's hut.
The old man was sitting in front of the house.
Heidi ran up to him and held out her hand.
"Hello, Grandfather," she said. He
held her hand and stared at her.
"Good morning, Uncle," said Dete.
Heidi must stay with you now."
She explained why she couldn't
take care of the child any more.
The old man was angry. "You
can just get out of here!"
he yelled at Dete. Aunt Dete said
goodbye to Heidi very quickly and left.
Heidi looked around her new home.
"Where can I sleep?" asked Heidi.
"Anywhere you want," answered Grandfather.
Heidi saw a ladder behind the bed.
She climbed the ladder up to the loft.
The loft was filled with fresh hay.
''I'll sleep up here," said Heidi happily.
Heidi followed Grandfather everywhere. She
watched as he made a new chair for her.
When the sun was setting, Heidi heard a whistle.
It was Peter bringing the goats home. Grandfather
had two goats. Their names were Daisy
and Dusky. Heidi liked them at once.
The next morning, Peter's whistle woke Heidi.
She got ready to go with Peter. She was excited.
The mountain was very beautiful.
Heidi picked flowers and chased
the goats. Peter told her all of the goats' names.
Heidi was sad when she heard that
a little goat had lost its mother.
She promised to take special care of that goat.
By now, the sun was setting.
It spread a golden glow across
the tops of the mountains.
"Peter!" cried Heidi. "The mountains are on fire!"
"Don't worry," replied Peter. "That happens
every day. It means it's time to go home."
Heidi went up the mountain with
Peter every day during the summer.
She grew to be healthy and strong. She was
as free as a bird. But when the fall came,
Grandfather made her stay at home. He was afraid
the strong winds would blow her off the mountain.
She spent the days helping him make cheese.
Then came the winter and lots of snow.
Peter went to school in the winter.
One day, he came to the hut. He told Heidi
that his grandmother would like to meet her.
She wanted to go.
But Grandfather said the snow was too deep.
A few days later, the snow
finally stopped. The sun came out,
and Grandfather said she could go out.
He put Heidi on his sled. The sled
raced down the mountain very fast.
Grandfather stopped the sled
in front of Peter's small hut.
Heidi met an old woman that was sewing.
"Hello, Grannie," said Heidi.
Grannie smiled and felt Heidi's
hand. Grannie was blind.
"Why can't you see?" asked Heidi.
"I can't see," Grannie said
kindly, "but I can hear."
Heidi spent the rest of the winter with Grannie.
Sometimes Grandfather came and fixed
the windows and chairs in Grannie's hut.
CHAPTER TWO
Heidi Goes to Frankfurt
It was near the end of Heidi's
second happy winter with Grandfather.
One day, the village pastor came to the hut.
He was angry at Grandfather
because Heidi wasn't in school.
"Heidi doesn't need school," argued Grandfather.
"She'll grow up here with the goats and the
birds. They won't teach her any bad ideas!"
"She must learn to read and
write!" the pastor argued back.
But he couldn't change Grandfather's mind.
The next day, Aunt Dete came to the hut.
"I have a wonderful opportunity for
Heidi," she said. "Heidi is going
to live with a wealthy family in Frankfurt.
She'll be a companion to their little girl."
"Heidi is happy here!" Grandfather said
rudely. "She doesn't need to go to Frankfurt!"
Aunt Dete said, "This is a chance for
Heidi to go to school and church."
"Fine!" yelled Grandfather. "Then
take her, and don't ever come back!"
Heidi didn't want to leave Grandfather
to go to Frankfurt. But Aunt Dete lied
to her that they would be back in a day or two.
"You can even bring fresh bread for Grannie,"
said Aunt Dete. This idea pleased Heidi.
Grannie had trouble eating black, hard bread.
They left so quickly that Heidi
couldn't even say goodbye to Peter.
Dete took Heidi to a large house in Frankfurt. A
rich man named Mr Sesemann owned the house. His
daughter Klara had to stay in a wheelchair.
Her mother had died a long time ago.
Now Ms Rottenmeier was looking
after her. Ms Rottenmeier took
a look at Heidi. She did not
like her old clothes and hat.
She didn't even like Heidi's name.
"Is 'Heidi' a real name?" Ms Rottenmeier asked.
"Her mother named her
Adelheid," Aunt Dete explained.
"Then we shall call her
Adelheid," said Ms Rottenmeier.
Later, when Ms Rottenmeier was away, Klara
said, "I'll call you Heidi if you want."
"It doesn't matter," said Heidi. "I'll be
going home tomorrow with some fresh bread."
"No," said Klara. "You came
here to keep me company."
At the dinner table, Heidi was happy
to find fresh bread on her plate.
She put it in her pocket. A servant,
Sebastian, brought a dish of food for Heidi.
She didn't know what to do with it.
She had never eaten this way before.
Then Ms Rottenmeier told Heidi how she
should behave at the table for a long time.
But while she was talking, Heidi fell asleep.
When Heidi awoke, she didn't know where she was.
She remembered that she was
in Frankfurt. She was afraid.
A few days later, Heidi went for
a walk while Klara was resting.
Sebastian told her to look at the
whole city from the church tower.
When she climbed up to the top of the
tower, all she could see was buildings.
There were no mountains and trees. The church
keeper could see that she was disappointed.
So he showed her a basket of kittens.
"You can have them," he said.
"I'll deliver them to your house."
"Oh yes," said Heidi. "But
can I have two of them now?"
The keeper gave Heidi two kittens.
When she got home, everyone was waiting
for her. Ms Rottenmeier was angry.
"Who said you could leave the house?" she asked.
"Meow," a sound came from Heidi's pocket. Ms
Rottenmeier screamed. She was afraid of cats.
The next morning, there was a knock at the
door. Sebastian came back with a big basket.
Klara opened it, and kittens ran everywhere.
One kitten climbed up Ms Rottenmeier's skirt.
"Sebastian!" she screamed. "Get
rid of these little monsters!"
That evening, Ms Rottenmeier
decided to punish Heidi.
She said, "I'm going to lock
you in the cold basement."
But Klara said, "Please, wait until
my father gets home. Let him decide
what to do."
Ms Rottenmeier agreed.
For the next few days, Heidi didn't get into
any trouble. But she was becoming very homesick.
CHAPTER THREE
Homesick
Mr Sesemann came home from his business trip
with many gifts. He was happy to see Klara.
He was also happy to meet Heidi. He could
see that Heidi and Klara liked each other.
But Ms Rottenmeier said terrible
things about Heidi to Klara's father.
"I think that little girl is crazy," she said.
"You should see the trouble she's caused here."
Mr Sesemann asked Klara about Heidi.
"What happened while I was away?"
Klara told him about the kittens and
other things. Mr Sesemann laughed.
He went to Ms Rottenmeier and said,
"Heidi will stay. She is good for Klara."
A few days later, Mr
Sesemann left on another business travel. But
his mother, Grandmamma Sesemann, came to visit.
Her face seemed very kind to Heidi.
Heidi liked Grandmamma very much.
One day, Grandmamma showed Heidi a book.
She wanted to help Heidi with her reading.
In the book there was a picture
of a boy with goats on a mountain.
The picture reminded Heidi of Peter, so she began
to cry. She was very homesick. Grandmamma told
Heidi she could have the book when she learned to
read. From then on, Heidi tried very hard to read.
That night, she prayed to God
to help her read and go home.
After a week, Grandmamma heard Heidi reading to
Klara. She gladly gave Heidi the picture book.
It was time for Grandmamma to leave the house.
After she left, something strange
started happening at night.
Every morning, the front door was wide open.
Sebastian locked the door tight every evening.
But in the morning, it was open. It was a mystery.
One night, Sebastian and another
servant stayed up to watch the door.
Then the wind blew the candle out. The house
was totally dark, and the door was open.
Sebastian saw a small person
in white run up the stairs.
He thought it was a ghost. He told
everyone there was a ghost in the house.
Two days later, Mr Sesemann came home. He and his
friend, Dr. Classen, stayed up to watch the door.
Late that night, they heard the door opening.
There was a small person in white clothes.
It was Heidi.
"What are you doing? asked Mr Sesemann.
Heidi looked confused.
''I don't know," she answered. "Every
night I dream I'm back with Grandfather."
"She's been sleepwalking," said Dr. Classen.
"She must be very homesick. The
only cure is to send her home."
The next day, Mr Sesemann prepared to send Heidi
home. Klara was very upset when she learned Heidi
was leaving. But her father promised her she
could visit Heidi with Grandmamma very soon.
CHAPTER FOUR
Heidi Returns
Sebastian and Heidi traveled to her village. All
of the villagers were surprised that Heidi came
back to live with her grandfather. The first
place Heidi ran to was Peter and Grannie's
hut. Heidi cried and sat on Grannie's lap.
She gave Grannie a basket of fresh bread.
Then she climbed the mountain
to see her grandfather.
He was sitting outside the hut, just
like the first time she saw him.
"Grandfather!" Heidi cried.
She threw her arms around him. Grandfather
cried for the first time in many years.
"So you've come back," he said.
That night, Heidi slept in
her old bed in the loft.
It was the best night of sleep
she'd had in a long time.
The next day, Grandfather woke Heidi.
"Put your best clothes on," he
said. "We're going to church."
They went to church in the village.
Grandfather spoke to the pastor.
"I've decided to move to the village for
the winter. Heidi will go to school."
The villagers were surprised to see Grandfather
and the pastor talking like friends.
On the way home, Grandfather told Heidi,
"I never thought I would be this happy again.
It was a good day when God sent you to me.'
That fall, Peter often asked Heidi to herd
the goats with him. But she told him she was
too busy. She was cleaning the hut. She was also
waiting for her friends from Frankfurt to visit.
One day, she looked down the mountain and saw
somebody coming. It was Dr. Classen.
Grandfather and Heidi greeted him.
"Where are Grandmamma and Klara?" Heidi asked.
"I'm alone," he said.
"Klara has been sick. She can't travel until
springtime, when the weather is warmer."
Heidi was sad, but she was
glad to see Dr. Classen.
Grandfather gave Dr. Classen a mug of
fresh goat's milk and some golden cheese.
"This will be a good place for
Klara to get well," said the doctor.
That winter, Heidi and Grandfather moved down to
the village. Grandfather rented a small hut there.
Heidi missed the mountains. But
she was very happy to go to school.
She studied her lessons very hard.
But Peter rarely went to school.
One day, Heidi asked him, "Why
weren't you at school again today?"
"I couldn't stop the sled," lied
Peter. "It went straight through
the village. I couldn't get off! Then
it was too late to go to school!"
"If you do that again," said Grandfather,
"you're going to get in big trouble with me!"
When Heidi and Peter came to
visit Grannie, she was very sick.
Grannie couldn't get out of bed. Heidi read
to her to cheer her up. She thought Peter
should learn to read. Then he could read
to Grannie, and maybe she would get well.
The next day at school, Heidi said to Peter,
"You must learn to read. So
then you can read to Grannie."
"I can't do it," Peter replied.
"I'm going to teach you," said Heidi.
Reading was very difficult for Peter. But Heidi
made him learn the ABC's with a book from Klara.
Then he began to read a few words. A few
weeks later, he could read to Grannie.
The whole village heard that Heidi got
Peter to read. Everyone was very impressed.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Mountain Miracle
When spring came, the
mountains turned green again.
Then Grandfather and Heidi moved
back up to their hut on the mountain.
One day, Peter brought Heidi
a letter. It was from Klara.
"Klara and Grandmamma will be
here in six weeks!" cried Heidi.
She was very excited. But Peter
was not. He was angry and jealous.
One morning in June, Heidi saw them
coming up. One man was pushing Klara
in her wheelchair. Another man carried their
things. Grandmamma rode behind them on a horse.
Klara and Grandmamma were amazed at
the beauty of Heidi's mountain home.
"Oh, Heidi," cried Klara. "If only I
could run over the hills with you!"
"Don't worry," said Heidi.
"I'll push you everywhere."
Then Grandfather served everyone big
mugs of goat's milk and toasted cheese.
They ate happily outside in
the gentle breeze and sunshine.
When Klara saw Heidi's bed
in the hayloft, she said,
"It must be wonderful to look at
the stars while you go to sleep."
Grandfather asked Grandmamma,
"Why don't you let Klara stay here
with us while you stay in the village?"
Grandmamma agreed.
"I think it will be very good
for Klara's health to stay here."
As the days passed, Grandfather
grew to like Klara very much.
He told Peter to feed the goats the best grass.
They made extra-good milk
that would make Klara strong.
While Klara stayed with them for two
weeks, Grandfather helped her stand.
Standing made her legs and feet hurt very much.
But each day, she tried to stand a little longer.
Heidi begged Grandfather to carry
Klara up to the top of the mountain.
That was the place where
the was the most beautiful.
But Grandfather said he would do that
only if Klara could stand on her own.
Heidi was excited and told
Peter. But this made Peter angry.
He wanted Klara to go away.
The next morning, Peter went up to the hut.
He saw the empty wheelchair outside. He kicked
the wheelchair with anger. The wheelchair
went rolling down the side of the mountain.
Peter was so afraid. He ran
away without taking the goats.
Grandfather and Heidi came outside
and found out the wheelchair was
gone. They looked everywhere for the wheelchair.
Grandfather saw it down below the mountain.
The wheelchair was in pieces. It was destroyed.
"It must have been the wind,"
said Heidi. Klara began to cry.
"Now I'll never be able to go up the mountain."
"That's okay," said Grandfather. "I'll
carry you up. By the way, where is Peter?"
Grandfather picked up Klara,
and they walked up the mountain.
The goats followed them.
When Grandfather saw Peter, he
scolded him for forgetting the goats.
"Did you see Klara's
wheelchair?" asked Grandfather.
Peter just shook his head to say, "No."
Grandfather left the children on top
of the mountain and went back home.
After lunch, Heidi wanted to take Klara
higher to see the prettiest flowers.
"Peter and I can carry you," Heidi said.
They pulled Klara to her feet. But
suddenly, she began to take a step.
"I'm walking!" she shouted.
When Grandfather came to get them
later, he was happy to see Klara walk.
Klara practiced walking for the next week.
When Grandmamma came up the mountain,
Klara surprised her. She cried with
joy when she saw Klara walking.
"Thank you so much!" she said to Grandfather.
"Your kindness and care have done this for her."
"And God's sun and the mountain
air," Grandfather replied.
Then Grandmamma decided to send
a letter to Klara's father.
She wanted him to come early
and join them for the surprise.
Mr Sesemann had almost arrived at the hut. He
expected to meet Klara and Heidi in a moment.
Klara was waiting at the
hut with a surprise for him.
They saw him getting close to the hut.
Then Klara stood up and walked to him.
Mr Sesemann was surprised
and cried, "It's a miracle!"
Mr Sesemann thanked Grandfather
and Heidi for helping Klara.
Grandmamma saw Peter hiding behind the hut.
"Young man," she said, "why
are you so afraid of us?"
"I think Peter was the wind that blew Klara's
wheelchair down the mountain," said Grandfather.
Grandmamma took Peter aside.
"What you did was very bad. But
I understand how you feel," she
said. "I hope you will always
remember us." Peter became happy.
Later, Mr Sesemann asked Grandfather if
there was any way he could repay him.
Grandfather thought for a while.
Then he said, "Will you promise
to take care of Heidi when I die?"
Mr Sesemann promised he would,
and the men shook hands.
It was time for the Sesemanns
to leave. Klara was sad.
But Heidi said to her, "Don't worry. Soon it will
be summer again. Then you
can come back and see us."
Heidi stood on the mountain
and watched her friends leave.
She waved until she couldn't see them any more.
Shortly after, Dr. Classen
came to live in the village.
He bought a hut and shared it with Grandfather
and Heidi in the winter. He told Grandfather
that he thought of Heidi as his own child.
He promised to always take care of her.
Heidi spent another happy winter in the village.
All around were people who cared for her.