CHAPTER ONE
Tavioka Island
Iveri sat at the back of the boat and steered
it slowly over the water.
His day's work on Papaya Island was finished.
If he went fast, Iveri could get home to Tavioka
Island in fifteen minutes.
But he wasn't in a hurry today.
It was a warm and sunny afternoon.
Iveri stopped the boat and turned off the
motor.
He threw the anchor into the water.
The anchor hit the sand below and the boat
rocked gently in one place.
Iveri sat in the bottom of the boat and lay
back with his hands behind his head.
Today was a special day for Iveri.
It was the day a family from New Zealand was
coming to stay on Tavioka.
Iveri knew all about tourists.
He had started work at the Papaya Island Resort
when he left school.
He took the tourists horse riding along the
beaches and into the centre of the island.
Sometimes he and some other Fijian boys played
music in a band while the tourists at the
resort ate their dinner.
When he finished work each day, he left the
tourists on Papaya.
But today was different.
Now the first tourists were going to stay
on Tavioka.
They were going to stay with Iveri's family.
He wasn't very happy about that.
The boat rocked and Iveri's eyes closed.
He was tired.
Then he remembered that his mother had told
him not to be late.
'The Robinsons have two children,' she'd said.
'Please be nice to them.'
Iveri sat up and pulled up the anchor.
He started the boat's motor and steered towards
Tavioka again.
When Iveri got closer to home he saw two people
- girls on the beach near his village.
They weren't looking towards him.
He turned off the motor and let the boat drift
along the shore away from the young people.
They still didn't notice him.
The girls had blond hair.
They both wore T-shirts and long shorts.
One was shouting at the other.
The other one had her head down and was kicking
the sand with her toe.
Iveri thought, it's going to be an interesting
week!
The boat was drifting too far from shore.
Iveri started the motor and steered closer.
The girls turned and looked at him as he came
into the shallow water.
He dropped the anchor, climbed out of the
boat and walked towards them.
'Hello!
Bula!' he said.
Then he stopped and looked closely at the
girls.
The one in the red T-shirt who had been shouting
was a girl.
But the other one in the green T-shirt was
a boy.
Iveri smiled.
The boy's hair was almost as long as the girl's
hair.
They were twins.
Michelle didn't like the way the tall Fijian
boy stared at her.
Maybe he's never seen twins before, she thought.
'Bula to you,' she said, but she wasn't very
friendly.
She wasn't feeling very happy.
She hadn't wanted to come to Fiji.
'I've seen enough Pacific islands in my life!'
she'd said to her brother Peter before they
came.
'It's okay for you.
You do anything Mum wants.'
Michelle had wanted to go skiing in Europe.
She certainly didn't want to stay in a Fijian
village.
But their parents wanted a different holiday
this year.
'At least we could have gone to Papaya Island
Resort instead of this place,' Michelle had
said to Peter.
'There are lots of things to do there.'
Peter was quite happy to come to the village.
The family's holidays were usually too busy
for him.
Michelle asked Iveri, 'Do you live here?'
'Yes,' he replied.
'Tavioka is my home.'
He put out his hand to Michelle.
'My name is Iveri.
Your family is staying with mine.'
Michelle shook his hand.
'I'm Michelle Robinson,' she said.
She pointed at her brother.
'And that's Peter.'
Peter said, 'Hello!
Bula!'
Iveri shook his hand.
Michelle said, 'Our mother said your father
is the chief here.'
'Yes, I am the chief's son,' said Iveri.
'I must go home.
My mother wants me.'
He began to walk up the path from the beach.
Michelle and Peter walked with him.
Three small children with big smiles were
playing with a dog beside the path.
They called out, 'Bula!' to Iveri.
'So, if you're the chief's son, does that
mean you'll be chief one day?'
Michelle asked.
'Oh no, I'll never be chief.
My father has brothers and I am my father's
youngest son.
When my father dies, the clan will choose
another chief.
The clan won't choose me.'
Peter said, 'We met your mother.
She's very happy about our family coming to
Tavioka.'
'Yes, she is,' said Iveri.
'My mother works at the resort over on Papaya.
She likes tourists.'
Maybe she won't like tourists after living
with Michelle for a week, thought Peter.
CHAPTER TWO
A village welcome
They were at the village now.
It was quite small.
Most houses were made of cement and painted
bright colours like blue, green or pink.
More children looked out of windows and doors
at them.
'Bula!'
Women sat in doorways and said, 'Bula!'
when they passed.
Michelle and Peter had already seen the house
they were going to sleep in.
It was a cement house next to Iveri's family
bure, a house made of wood and grass.
The Robinsons' house had two rooms.
One was for Tom and Nicola, the twins' parents,
and the other was for Michelle and Peter.
The rooms had beds and cupboards in them and
a chair or two.
The floors were covered with grass mats.
There was no electricity on Tavioka, so they
were going to use oil lamps at night.
Nicola told Michelle and Peter that it was
an adventure.
Michelle thought it wasn't her kind of adventure!
Tom and Nicola were standing with Iveri's
mother, Tema, on the rara, the village green
in the centre of the village.
Tema was a big woman.
She was wearing a long yellow dress with white
flowers on it.
Tema said, 'Iveri, I see you have met the
children.
Tom, Nicola, here is my youngest son, Iveri.'
Iveri shook hands with Tom and Nicola and
said, 'Nice to meet you.
Welcome.'
'We hope you like it here,' Tema said to the
Robinsons.
'There are a lot of things to see on Tavioka
- the beach, the reef, the river, the hills.
If you need anything, please ask.'
A noise made them all look around.
A man had begun to hit a wooden drum in the
centre of the rara.
Tema continued, 'Iveri, now it is time for
sevusevu.'
'Sevusevu?' said Michelle.
Peter said, 'The ceremony to welcome us to
the village.'
Everyone smiled at him.
Peter thinks he knows everything, Michelle
thought.
Mum thinks he can't do anything wrong.
The man kept hitting the drum.
People came from their houses.
Some women were carrying plates of food.
Tema said, 'We will all eat.
Our men have been working very hard.'
She pointed behind them.
'They are building a new church.
Our old church is too small.'
A small man with white hair came out of the
church.
He walked slowly.
His face was tired.
'Here is my husband, Ratu Loti,' said Tema.
'Ratu means "chief",' Peter explained quietly
to Michelle.
Ratu Loti shook everyone's hands.
Tom gave him a small paper bag and said, 'This
is a gift from us to you - kava powder.'
'Vinaka,' said the Ratu.
'Thank you.'
The women put mats on the grass and put the
plates of food on the mats.
The women and children and young people sat
down.
'You can sit with me,' Tema said to the Robinsons.
The men of the village sat together in a circle.
Ratu Loti began to speak.
He spoke in Fijian for a long time.
Other men spoke.
They were welcoming the Robinsons to Tavioka.
Then Tema said to Tom, 'You must speak now.'
Everyone looked at Tom.
He smiled and said, 'Thank you for welcoming
us to your village.
Nicola, Peter, Michelle and I are very happy
to be here on Tavioka Island.
We've been to a lot of places in the Pacific
- I do a lot of work in the islands with my
building company - but we've never really
seen the way people live outside the resorts.
I think we're going to enjoy staying here
and learning about your life.
We hope that Tema's homestay business will
help everyone here.'
One of the men opened the paper bag and put
the powder into a bowl.
Then he picked up a bucket, poured water from
the bucket into the bowl and mixed the water
with the powder.
'He is making kava,' Iveri said quietly to
Michelle and Peter.
The man took the bowl around the circle of
men.
He gave Ratu Loti a cup made from half a coconut.
Ratu Loti clapped once and then drank some
kava from the coconut cup.
He passed the cup to the man next to him and
then clapped three times.
The bowl and cup went slowly around the circle
of men, then someone passed it to Tom.
He clapped, drank, passed it to Nicola, and
then clapped three times.
Nicola did the same.
Then Peter drank, and passed the cup to Michelle.
She looked at the kava in the cup.
It was brown.
'What's it like?'
Michelle quietly asked Peter before she drank.
'It's okay,' he said.
Michelle drank.
It had a taste like pepper.
Her tongue and mouth were burning.
Peter laughed.
Nicola said, 'Clap, Michelle!'
She put the cup down, clapped and got up from
the mat.
Nicola said, 'Michelle!'
but Michelle didn't stop.
'I need water to wash away that taste!'
she said.
Iveri watched Michelle run away from the ceremony.
'Where is your sister going?' he asked Peter.
Peter laughed.
'I don't think she likes kava.'
'Oh, well.
The food is good,' Iveri said.
He gave Peter some small cakes.
The boys talked a little about life in the
village and life in New Zealand.
Iveri was sixteen - a year older than the
twins.
'I wish I was still at school.
I left last year,' Iveri said.
'I really wanted to go to a good school in
Suva but we are a very poor village.
I had to leave school and get a job.'
After the meal Iveri said, 'I have to help
my uncle in his garden now.'
He said goodbye to Peter and went to look
for his uncle.
He was surprised that Uncle Vili hadn't been
at sevusevu.
Maybe he was late coming home from work on
Papaya Island.
Uncle Vili was a gardener at the resort.
Iveri went to his uncle's house.
Uncle Vili lived alone.
He wasn't there.
Iveri took a machete and a sack and walked
out of the village to the hills behind it.
The plantations, the villagers' gardens, were
there.
He cut bananas and coconuts down from trees
with the machete.
He dug tavioka and dalo from the ground.
He put everything in the sack and carried
it back to his uncle's.
When he got home, he found Uncle Vili, Tema
and Ratu Loti sitting together outside the
bure.
They were drinking tea.
'Uncle, I've been to your plantation.
I got some fruit and vegetables for you.
I put them in your kitchen,' said Iveri.
'I will bring you some later, Tema,' said
Uncle Vili.
'You will need a lot of food for these tourists.'
'Thank you,' Tema smiled.
'Eroni is bringing me some fish too.'
Eroni was one of Iveri's brothers.
He was a fisherman.
He and his wife and children lived close by.
'You work very hard already, Tema,' Uncle
Vili continued.
'These tourists will be too much work for
you.'
'I told her that too,' said Ratu Loti.
'We had to build new houses, a special toilet
and a new shower room.'
'Loti,' said Tema.
'The houses weren't new.
They were houses that belonged to our family
already.
We just made them better.'
Her face was sad.
They were the houses of Iveri's oldest brothers.
Aseri lived in Suva and Simoni lived in Australia,
playing rugby.
'And Simoni sent us money for the toilet and
shower.'
Uncle Vili shook his head.
'These people will be trouble.
They should stay in the resorts with the other
tourists.'
'The village will get all the money from the
homestay business,' said Tema.
'It will be good for all of us.'
Ratu Loti smiled at Tema.
'We will see, my dear.'
Tema told Iveri, 'Time for a wash.
Remember you're taking the Robinsons to the
meke on Papaya tonight.'
Iveri went to have a shower in the new shower
room.
It was nicer than washing in the water trough
behind the bure.
But there was someone already in the room.
He could hear a beautiful voice singing in
the shower.
Michelle or her mother, he thought.
He washed in the water trough then he saw
Peter come out of the shower room.
Peter looked at him uncertainly.
Iveri said, 'Good singing!'
Peter smiled and said, 'Thanks, Iveri.
I love music.
I'm really looking forward to the concert
tonight.'
'Yes, you'll enjoy the meke,' said Iveri.
After dinner, Iveri took the tourists to Papaya
Island Resort in Ratu Loti's boat.
Uncle Vili came too.
Uncle Vili sat with Tom and Nicola.
'You will like the resort,' he told them.
'There are many things to do there.'
There was singing and dancing at the meke.
A man played a wooden drum.
Iveri and his band played and sang.
Peter and his parents smiled and clapped.
Michelle didn't smile once.
After the meke, Iveri showed the family around
the resort.
It was a beautiful place with a lot of shops
and many things to do.
He heard Michelle say, 'I'd love to stay here.
It's nicer than the village.'
Nicola said, 'Sh!' angrily.
It was time to go back to Tavioka.
The Robinsons waited on the wharf while Iveri
looked for his uncle.
He found Uncle Vili sitting with two men outside
a bure in the resort.
They were drinking kava.
One of the men was a tall thin tourist.
He was bald and was wearing a red shirt with
white flowers on it and blue shorts.
His legs were white and hairy.
The other man was a Fijian called Sami.
Iveri said, 'Bula!' to the men.
'We are ready to return to Tavioka, Uncle.'
'Go without me, Iveri.
I will stay on Papaya tonight.'
Iveri walked away.
He was surprised to see Sami there.
Sami was a bad person.
He had once lived on Tavioka but the Ratu
had made him leave the island.
He had gone to Suva and got into trouble there.
What was Sami doing on Papaya?
And why was he drinking with Uncle Vili?
CHAPTER THREE
Nothing happens on Sunday
After breakfast, the Robinsons went to church
with Ratu Loti, Tema and Iveri.
They wore their best clothes.
Michelle wore her new silver flip-flops.
They all had to leave their shoes at the church
door.
Peter loved the church.
He sang all the songs.
The words were Fijian, but that wasn't a problem
for Peter.
He just sang, 'La, la, la!'
The Fijians all turned to look at him.
Michelle wanted him to stop.
She kicked him.
When church was over Michelle hurried outside.
She looked for her flip-flops, but they were
gone.
'What's wrong, Michelle?'
Tom asked.
'I can't find my flip-flops.'
'You must be looking in the wrong place,'
he said.
'No, I'm not,' she said.
'I put them by the door.'
'That's strange,' said Tom.
Then he said, 'Hey, where are my shoes?'
He began to look among all the shoes.
'I can't see your mother's shoes, or Peter's.'
Tema came up and asked, 'What's wrong, Tom?'
'Michelle can't find her flip-flops and I
can't find my shoes.
Nicola's and Peter's shoes have gone too.'
Most of the villagers had taken their shoes.
There were only a few shoes and flip-flops
left outside the church.
'Somebody has taken our shoes,' said Michelle
angrily.
Tema said, 'Sorry!
It must be a mistake.'
'How can somebody take four pairs of shoes
by mistake?'
Michelle shouted.
Tom and Nicola both said, 'Michelle!'
and Peter said, 'Be quiet, Michelle.
Maybe someone needs shoes more than we need
them.'
Michelle marched off angrily and sat in her
room.
Why did we come to this silly village?
she thought.
I want to go and stay at the resort.
After lunch, Ratu Loti asked Iveri to take
the twins to the river.
'The river is a wonderful place,' he said.
'I am too old to swim now, but when I was
a young man I went there every day.'
Iveri wanted to visit friends.
But he was a good son and always did what
Ratu Loti asked him.
Michelle liked the idea.
Swimming was something she was good at.
She went to change her clothes.
'I'm not a very strong swimmer,' said Peter.
'That's okay, it's an easy place to swim,'
said Iveri, and Peter went to change too.
When the twins returned, Iveri said, 'Let's
go!'
The young people walked through the village
towards the plantations.
'I didn't know there was a river on Tavioka,'
said Peter.
'I thought you knew everything,' said Michelle.
'Shut up!' said Peter.
Iveri didn't want them to fight.
'It's only a small river,' he said.
They walked between thick fruit trees towards
the hills.
Then they came to the river.
Peter and Michelle followed Iveri across the
river where it was very shallow.
The water moved fast over the rocks.
One of Peter's flip-flops fell off and was
carried away by the river.
'Oh no,' said Peter.
'I'll have no shoes left!'
When they were across the river, Iveri led
them along the bank to a sandy area.
'The river is deep here and it moves fast,'
he said.
'If you jump in here you will drift a long
way.
It's fun!'
He jumped into the water.
The river carried him downstream, away from
the twins.
Michelle jumped straight in after him.
Peter sat on the bank with his legs in the
water.
Iveri and Michelle swam back up the river.
'Come on, Peter!' said Iveri.
Peter shook his head.
'I don't really like swimming in rivers or
the sea,' he said.
'I like to see the bottom.'
'Just get wet,' said Michelle.
Iveri watched as Peter slowly walked off the
bank and into the water.
He sat down and let the water cover him to
his neck.
'It's nice,' he said.
When Iveri and Michelle were tired, they sat
with Peter in the water.
'You two are very different,' said Iveri.
'You look the same but you're not like twins
at all!'
Michelle looked angry but Peter laughed.
'Did you think twins didn't fight?
We're just like any brother and sister, you
know.'
'Bula!'
called a voice behind them.
It was Uncle Vili.
He was carrying his machete and a sack over
his shoulder.
He smiled.
'It's nice to be a tourist,' he said to the
twins.
'No work.'
He walked past them.
Iveri showed Peter and Michelle that the riverbank
was made of clay.
'The women in the village make pots from it,'
he said.
'I know something you can do with clay,' said
Michelle.
She dug some clay out of the bank with her
fingers.
Then she put the clay on Peter's nose.
Iveri laughed at the look on Peter's face.
He stopped laughing when Michelle put clay
on his nose.
Then he took some clay and tried to catch
Michelle.
The three of them had a clay fight.
It was good fun, and they got clay all over
them.
Afterwards they washed it off in the water.
The sun was going down when Iveri took the
twins back to the village.
Michelle suddenly stopped.
She pointed at something on the path.
'What's that?'
she asked.
Iveri said, 'It's a toad.
They live near the river.'
'Yuck!
They're ugly,' said Michelle.
'Let's go!'
'Can we come here again, Iveri?'
Peter asked.
'I have to work at Papaya Island Resort most
days,' Iveri said.
'But you two can come here any time.'
Michelle and Peter were tired and went to
bed early.
It was very dark on the island at night.
There was lamplight, but when the lights went
out there was only the light from the moon
and stars.
Peter woke when something fell onto his bed.
He put his hand out and touched it.
It was wet and moved.
He felt something else jump onto the bed.
He got out of bed quickly and looked for the
lamp.
Something moved near his foot.
He lit the lamp.
The room was full of big toads.
Their eyes stared at him.
A fat toad jumped onto Michelle's bed and
she woke up.
When she saw the toad on her bed, she began
to scream.
There were screams coming from Nicola and
Tom's room too.
That's Mum, Peter thought.
Then there was the sound of feet outside and
Iveri called, 'What's wrong?'
Peter stepped over the toads and opened the
door.
Iveri and Tema were there.
'Look!'
Peter said.
They looked inside.
Michelle stopped screaming.
'Where did the toads come from?'
Tema asked.
'Look.
Someone has cut the flyscreen,' Iveri said.
There was a big hole in the flyscreen.
A sack was lying in the corner of the room.
More toads were coming out of it.
Tom and Nicola came to the door.
'Tema, our room is full of toads,' said Tom.
Then he saw that Peter and Michelle's was
too.
Iveri and Peter went to look at the flyscreen
in Tom and Nicola's room.
It had been cut too.
'Who did this?'
Tema asked.
'Maybe someone in the village doesn't like
tourists,' said Tom.
'No!' said Tema.
'They are just toads.
We won't leave because of a few toads,' Nicola
said bravely.
Tema tried to smile.
Iveri said, 'Help me get the toads out of
the rooms, Peter.
They won't hurt you.'
First Peter took some photographs.
He wished he'd taken a picture of Michelle's
face!
It was fun getting the toads out of the rooms.
Peter chased them and Iveri caught them and
put them back in the sack.
'I'll take them to the river before work tomorrow,'
he said.
Peter and Michelle went back to bed but Michelle
made Peter keep the lamp on.
'I hope there aren't any snakes on Tavioka,'
she said.
CHAPTER FOUR
Out on the reef
Iveri took the toads away from the village
early in the morning and let them go near
the river.
When he arrived home, the Robinsons were eating
breakfast outside their house.
Ratu Loti was sitting with them.
'Uncle Vili will take your mother to work
on Papaya,' said the Ratu.
'This morning I want you to take our visitors
out in the new boat.
Show them the reef.'
'That will be fun,' said Tom.
Iveri heard Michelle say to Peter, 'How many
coral reefs have we looked at?
I'd rather dive on one!'
Iveri said, 'I can take you diving one day.'
Michelle smiled at him.
'Thanks.'
'Vinaka,' Peter said.
'That means, "thank you".'
Michelle gave Peter a hard push.
'You think you know everything,' she said.
She walked away from the boys.
Iveri shook his head.
He was glad she wasn't his sister!
Tema was ready for work.
She gave the Robinsons a basket of food to
eat on the boat.
'I will walk to the beach with you, Iveri.
Your Uncle Vili will be waiting to take me
to Papaya.'
Iveri led the way to the beach.
The 'new' boat was an old one Ratu Loti had
bought from Papaya Island Resort.
He and Iveri had painted it blue and white.
It was a special boat for looking at the coral
reef.
When you looked through the glass boxes in
the floor, you could see the reef under you.
Uncle Vili was waiting for Tema.
He helped her into his boat.
'Bula!' he said to the Robinsons with a big
smile.
'Where are you taking our friends today, Iveri?'
'To the reef near Papaya.'
'Show them the Tavioka reef too.
But be careful!
No more surprises for the Robinsons!' said
Uncle Vili.
He laughed.
Iveri thought, My mother must have told him
about the toads.
Uncle Vili started his boat's motor.
Tema waved to them as the boat moved off towards
Papaya Island.
Iveri helped the Robinsons into the boat.
It had long blue seats along each side and
a seat for Iveri in the back.
Tom and Michelle sat on one side and Nicola
and Peter sat on the other.
The two glass boxes were in the middle of
the boat.
There were wooden covers over the boxes.
Iveri started the motor and steered the boat
away from the shore.
Children on the beach waved to them.
It was a beautiful day.
The sun was hot.
Everyone wore hats.
Tom said, 'Where are the lifejackets, Iveri?'
Iveri said, 'We don't have any!'
Tom wasn't happy about that.
'You should have lifejackets.
We could have an accident.'
'I'll be very careful, Mr Robinson,' said
Iveri.
'And I will ask the Ratu to buy some lifejackets.
Perhaps we can get some from the resort.'
There were other boats out on the reef.
Most were from the resort.
The tourists from the resort went diving and
looked at the coral.
In some places, the reef was in shallow water.
Iveri had to be careful not to steer the boat
near those waters.
In other places, the reef lay down deep.
He steered through the reef for a while and
then he said, 'This is a good place.'
He turned off the motor and threw out the
anchor.
'Won't the anchor hurt the coral?'
Nicola asked.
'No,' said Iveri.
'I am careful.
The anchor is in the sand.'
Peter said, 'It's very deep out here.'
'You'll be okay,' said Tom.
Iveri took the wooden covers off the boxes.
'Look down!' he said.
'You'll see the coral and a lot of fish.'
The bright colours below them were amazing.
The coral was blue, pink and red.
'Wow!
Look at the blue starfish,' said Peter.
'I wish I was down there with the fish,' said
Michelle.
They drifted on the water and watched the
fish swimming through the coral reef.
Some were blue and others were yellow.
Some were black and white.
Nicola said, 'Some of the coral is brown,
Iveri.
Is it dead?'
Iveri told them that too many people dived
on the reef and that pollution from the resort
was killing the coral.
'There is no pollution on Tavioka,' he said.
'Shall I show you the reef there?'
'Okay,' said Nicola.
Iveri pulled up the anchor, started the motor
and steered towards Tavioka.
No one noticed a white boat begin to follow
Iveri's boat.
It was just another tourist boat out on the
reef.
They passed Iveri's brother Eroni, the fisherman
in his fishing boat.
He waved to them.
He was going home to Tavioka with a basket
full of fish.
'Fish for dinner,' said Iveri.
'Again,' said Michelle very quietly.
Then they were alone on the deep blue sea.
The boat was moving fast.
Iveri wanted to get to the reef and then home
again before he had to go to work at two o'clock.
Iveri heard the sound of another motor.
He looked behind him.
A white boat was coming quickly towards them.
Tom looked at the white boat and shouted,
'What's that fool doing?'
Nicola screamed, 'He's going to hit us!'
The white boat was almost on top of them.
Iveri saw the driver.
He was a Fijian and he was wearing sunglasses.
He steered right at them.
He wasn't going to stop.
Iveri tried to move out of the way but his
boat was heavy and slow.
The white boat hit them.
There was a loud noise and Iveri's boat rocked
wildly.
Peter was scared and tried to stand up.
'Sit down, Peter,' his father shouted.
The white boat had turned and was coming towards
them again.
'Peter, sit down!'
Nicola screamed.
The boat hit them for the second time.
Peter fell into the water.
The white boat circled their boat once, then
went off very fast.
Iveri stopped the motor.
Nicola was screaming.
She and Iveri stared over the side of the
boat.
There was no sign of Peter in the water.
Michelle dived into the water.
Tom followed her in.
Iveri didn't know what to do.
Should he go into the water too?
Or should he stay with Peter's mother?
He put his hand on Nicola's.
'Mrs Robinson, they will find Peter.'
'He'll drown,' cried Nicola.
'He'll be okay.'
Iveri hoped he was right.
Then they heard a shout.
It was Michelle.
'I've got him!'
she called.
Nicola and Iveri watched Michelle pull Peter
through the water, holding him under the arms.
Tom swam beside her.
'His eyes are closed!' said Nicola.
'He's okay!'
Tom called.
'His eyes are closed because he's scared.'
Tom got back into the boat and took Peter
from Michelle.
Nicola covered Peter's face with kisses.
Iveri helped Michelle back onto the boat.
'You are very brave,' he said.
Peter opened his eyes.
'Thanks, Michelle,' he said.
'I wish I could swim like you.
I wish I was brave like you.'
Michelle's face went red.
'You're okay, Peter.
I couldn't let you drown.'
Tom and Nicola told Michelle that she was
wonderful.
Iveri thought she was too.
CHAPTER FIVE
A strange meeting
There was a small hole in the side of the
boat but it was above the water level, and
the motor still worked.
The Robinsons were very quiet as Iveri took
them home.
Tom sat close to Michelle and Nicola held
Peter's hand.
Peter was still shaking.
Iveri was quiet too, but his thoughts were
very busy.
The man in the white boat had been wearing
sunglasses but Iveri knew him.
It was Sami.
Iveri heard Nicola say to her husband, 'Perhaps
we should leave Tavioka, Tom.
Too many strange things have happened and
Peter nearly drowned.'
Tom said, 'I think we'll have to tell the
police.
There may be a police station on Papaya.'
When they arrived at Tavioka, the Robinsons
walked to the village together.
Michelle turned and said, 'It'll be okay,
Iveri.'
Iveri tried to smile, but he was unhappy.
Poor Peter!
And he was worried about his mother.
Tema hoped a lot of tourists were going to
come to stay on Tavioka.
She didn't want to work in the resort.
She wanted to stay at home and look after
Ratu Loti.
Iveri looked for his father and found him
at the church.
He told him what had happened.
Ratu Loti shook his head.
'My son,' he said.
'This homestay business is a lot of trouble.
Tonight I will talk to your mother about it.
And I will send someone to look for Sami.
He must explain.'
When Iveri got back from work that evening,
he found Tema, Ratu Loti and Uncle Vili sitting
on the mats inside the bure.
'Where are the Robinsons?' he asked.
'They have already gone to their rooms,' said
the Ratu.
'The boy isn't very well.'
'I think they will leave soon,' said Tema.
Uncle Vili said, 'I told you tourists should
stay in resorts.
They should stay with other tourists.'
'But the only way for people to understand
Fijians is to live in a village,' said Tema.
'And their money will come right into the
village this way.'
Uncle Vili looked at Ratu Loti and said, 'I
have a better idea, Tema.
The resort developers are always looking for
land.
They want to build more resorts.
I think we should lease some land to a developer.
Maybe some land near Baka Bay.
We will get a lot of money.
Our people can work in the resort.
But we can keep the village for Fijians.'
Ratu Loti listened carefully to his brother.
'There are many things to think about,' he
said.
'First we will see what the Robinsons want
to do.
They were talking about going to the police
tomorrow.'
In Nicola and Tom's room, the Robinsons talked.
Nicola said, 'I really think we should leave.
It's not safe here.'
Peter was lying on his parents' bed.
'That's not fair!' he said.
'I love it here.
And it wasn't Iveri's fault that I fell in.'
Nicola said, 'I think we've learnt enough
about village life now.
We could go and stay in Papaya Island Resort.
Michelle liked it there - didn't you, Michelle?'
Michelle was quiet for a minute.
Then she said, 'Someone wants us to leave
here.
I don't think we should go.
Ratu Loti will find them soon.
Then things will be okay.'
Nicola said, 'I don't know.'
Tom said, 'Ratu Loti said he was going to
find the driver of the white boat.
Maybe we should give him a day to do that.'
Peter and Michelle went to their room.
'I thought you wanted to stay at the resort,'
said Peter.
'I did.
But I've changed my mind.
I like the people here.
I want Iveri to take me diving.
And I want to swim in the river again.'
'I don't think I want to go near water again
for a while,' said Peter.
'I was very scared.'
They lay in the dark, talking quietly.
They were friends again.
'I'm tired,' said Ratu Loti.
Uncle Vili went home, and Tema and the Ratu
went to bed.
Iveri stayed up.
He was thinking.
Why did Uncle Vili want the Ratu to lease
some Tavioka land to a developer?
Uncle Vili had never wanted any tourists to
come to the island.
Iveri needed to talk to his uncle.
His uncle hadn't really explained his reasons.
Why was a resort better than Tema's homestay
business?
The light from the moon was bright as Iveri
walked to his uncle's house.
The house was dark.
Iveri called out, 'Uncle!'
but there was no answer.
He went inside and called his uncle again.
His foot kicked against something on the floor.
He picked it up.
It was a small shoe.
He took it outside the house and looked at
it in the moonlight.
It was one of Michelle's silver flip-flops.
Had Uncle Vili taken the Robinsons' shoes?
Why?
Iveri thought hard.
Did Uncle Vili want to make trouble?
Was he trying to end the homestay business?
Iveri remembered that he had seen Uncle Vili
and Sami together at the resort.
Were they working together?
Iveri took the flip-flop home and hid it there.
Then he walked through the quiet village to
the beach.
He got into his own boat, pulled up the anchor
and began to row across the water.
He didn't want to start the motor yet.
It was a windy night and it was hard to row.
When his arms were tired, Iveri stopped rowing
and started the boat's motor.
On Papaya, he anchored the boat away from
the wharf.
He walked through the shallow water to the
shore.
He looked for the bure where he had seen Uncle
Vili on Saturday night.
He moved from bure to bure.
It was easy to see in the moonlight.
When he found the bure, there was a light
on inside.
He watched and waited.
The door opened and Iveri saw Uncle Vili come
outside.
The bald white man followed him.
The man shook Uncle Vili's hand and gave him
something.
Quickly and quietly, Iveri went closer.
He wanted to see what it was.
Uncle Vili had some small pieces of paper
in his hand.
Was it money?
The bald man called someone.
Sami appeared with a bag.
Uncle Vili began to put the paper into the
bag.
Then the wind blew and a piece of paper flew
into the air.
It was money.
Sami began to chase it at the same time as
Iveri ran forward out of the shadows to pick
it up.
Sami saw him and shouted, 'Stop!'
Iveri didn't look behind him.
He held the money in his hand and ran straight
for the beach.
He wished he was as fast as his brother Simoni,
the rugby player.
He heard feet coming fast behind him.
CHAPTER SIX
Night on the beach
Peter woke in the middle of the night.
The wind was loud outside and he could hear
a tree branch hitting the roof.
He sat up and said softly, 'Michelle?'
'Are you awake too?'
she asked.
'The wind woke me,' said Peter.
'What time is it?'
'Just after two.
I can't sleep,' said Michelle.
'I've been thinking about all the things that
have happened.
Someone doesn't want the homestay business
on Tavioka.
Who?'
'I don't know,' said Peter.
'But someone must have a reason.'
It was hot in the room.
Michelle said, 'Let's go for a walk.'
All the houses in the village were dark, but
the moonlight was bright.
There were a lot of coconuts on the ground
because of the wind.
The twins walked to the beach.
There were more coconuts there.
Peter picked one up.
It was heavy.
He rolled it along the hard wet sand.
Then Michelle picked up a coconut and rolled
it at Peter's.
It was fun.
Suddenly they heard a boat's motor out to
sea.
It was coming towards them fast.
In the shallow water, the driver threw out
the anchor and ran up onto the beach.
It was Iveri.
He said, 'What are you doing here?'
at the same time as Peter said, 'Hey, Iveri,
what's happening?'
'Someone's coming after me,' Iveri said.
'I'm going to hide behind the bushes.
Don't tell him where I am.'
He ran off.
They could hear another boat coming.
Iveri's footprints were clear in the moonlight.
Peter said to Michelle, 'Quick.
Let's roll coconuts over the footprints.'
So they took a coconut each and rolled them
on the sand.
They jumped all over the footprints too.
Soon no one could see where Iveri had been.
The second boat came quickly towards the beach.
The driver stopped his motor and jumped out
into the water.
He saw the twins on the beach and came up
to them.
It was a Fijian man.
He was tall and heavy and he wasn't smiling.
Peter stood next to Michelle.
He wanted to look after her.
The man pointed at Iveri's boat and said,
'Did you see a boy in that?'
'No,' Peter said.
'You're the first person we've seen.'
'I don't believe you,' said the man.
His face was angry.
'There's no boy here,' said Michelle.
'Are you hiding him?'
the man asked.
He came closer.
He put his big brown hand on Michelle's arm.
'If you are hiding him, I'll hurt you.'
'No, you won't,' said Peter and moved the
man's hand off Michelle's arm.
'I know you!
You're the man who tried to drown me.
I'll tell Ratu Loti.'
The man marched back to his boat.
He sat in it for a minute, then started the
motor and steered away.
When he was gone, Iveri came out from behind
the bushes.
'Vinaka!
Thank you!' he said.
Michelle said, 'Peter was very brave.
That was the man in the boat yesterday.'
'He's Sami,' said Iveri.
'Come back to my bure.
I have something to show you.'
They walked through the village.
When they got to Iveri's bure, he said, 'Wait!'
and went inside.
He came back out with something in his hand.
'Can we go to your room?' he asked them.
'But we must be quiet.'
Michelle lit the lamp inside their room.
Iveri showed them two things.
One was Michelle's silver flip-flop, and the
other was the money.
He told them the story of the night's adventures.
Michelle's eyes shone brightly in the lamplight.
'I think the bald man is a developer.
I think he's paying Uncle Vili to stop the
homestay business,' said Iveri.
'When are you going to tell the Ratu, Iveri?'
Peter asked.
Iveri shook his head.
'I don't know what to do, Peter.
My father will be so unhappy.
How could his brother do this thing?'
'Your Uncle Vili was very nice to us,' said
Michelle.
'And he is very nice to your mother.
I'm surprised that he could do such bad things.
The developer must be giving him a lot of
money.'
'My uncle has no wife or family,' said Iveri.
'He wanted to marry my mother when they were
young.
My mother chose the Ratu.
It made Uncle Vili very unhappy.
But he stayed on Tavioka and has been a good
brother and a kind uncle.
Now my father is old and not very strong.
My uncle wants to be chief when the Ratu dies.'
Peter said, 'Will you tell the Ratu in the
morning?
He needs to know what's happening.'
'Yes,' said Iveri.
'I'll tell him in the morning.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
Enter Mr Brown
Peter was tired in the morning and wanted
to sleep longer.
Nicola wanted to read a book.
So Michelle and her father went for a walk
on the island without them.
They watched children washing in water troughs
outside their houses.
They visited the village shop and bought a
clay pot for Nicola.
Michelle took Tom to the river and showed
him the place where she and Peter had swum
with Iveri.
Everywhere they went people called, 'Bula!'
and smiled big, happy smiles.
'It's a lovely place,' said Tom.
'It's hard to believe someone wants us to
leave.'
Michelle wanted to tell her father about Uncle
Vili, Sami and the developer.
But she didn't want him to go to Ratu Loti
before Iveri could tell his father the story.
She just said, 'The Ratu will find the bad
person soon, Dad.
I know it.'
When they got back, Peter was awake.
He and Nicola were sitting in the sun outside
the house.
'Have you seen Iveri this morning?'
Michelle asked Peter.
'No,' he said.
'Mum and I went for a little walk but we didn't
see him.'
'Maybe he went to work,' said Michelle.
Tom and Nicola were talking.
Nicola called the twins over.
'We've decided to stay here for the week.'
'Thank you,' said Peter.
'Vinaka!' said Michelle.
Later, Tema returned from Papaya Island Resort.
She almost cried when Tom told her the family
was staying.
She made them a picnic and they took it to
the beach.
They sat under a coconut tree and watched
the boats out to sea.
A white boat was coming towards Tavioka.
'Isn't that the boat that hit us yesterday?'
said Peter.
The Fijian, Sami, was steering.
The bald man was sitting next to him.
Sami stopped the boat close to the shore.
The bald man climbed out.
He was wearing a purple shirt and white shorts.
'It can't be,' Tom said.
'It's Jasper Brown!'
'Isn't he the man who got you to build him
a big hotel in Nadi?' said Nicola.
Peter said, 'And the hotel burnt down before
you got paid?'
'Yes.
That was Jasper Brown,' said Tom.
He put down the banana he had been eating.
'Dad,' Michelle said, 'there's something we
have to tell you.'
Tom didn't listen.
He marched down the beach towards the men.
Nicola and the twins followed.
'Hey!' said Tom.
'I want to talk to you!'
Sami walked towards Tom.
'What were you doing in that boat yesterday?'
Tom shouted.
'Tom!'
cried the bald man.
'Tom Robinson!
What a surprise!'
He walked forward with his hand out.
Tom looked at him.
'Brown,' he said.
He slowly shook Mr Brown's hand.
'Is that man with you?' he asked.
Mr Brown walked away from Sami.
Tom followed him.
Nicola went over to Sami and started talking
to him angrily.
Michelle went close to Tom and Mr Brown.
She wanted to hear what they said.
'Sami's helping me here in Fiji,' said Mr
Brown.
'He told me about yesterday.
He made a mistake.
He thought the Fijian boy was someone else.'
'What?
Does he always hit other boats like that?
He's dangerous!' said Tom.
'He could have killed us all!
I'm going to the police.'
'He's very sorry,' said Mr Brown.
'Dad,' said Michelle.
'Later, Michelle.'
Tom kept talking to Mr Brown.
'What are you doing here on Tavioka?'
'I have business with the Ratu,' said Mr Brown.
'Bula!'
Uncle Vili appeared along the path.
'Good morning, Mr Brown.
Come with me.
I will take you to the Ratu now.'
'We'll meet again, Tom,' said Mr Brown.
'Perhaps,' said Tom.
Sami hurried after Uncle Vili and Mr Brown.
He looked behind him at Nicola.
His face was scared.
'What did you say to him, Nicola?'
Tom asked.
'I told him I'd find his mother and tell her
what he did,' said Nicola.
Peter and Michelle looked at each other and
smiled.
Their mother wasn't a big woman, but she could
scare people when she was angry.
Tom gave Nicola a kiss.
'Let's forget about Brown and Sami and finish
our picnic.'
They ate their food and later Michelle and
her parents went swimming.
Peter sat in the shallow water and watched
them.
They were still on the beach when Iveri came
back from Papaya.
'I couldn't tell the Ratu this morning,' said
Iveri to Peter and Michelle.
'My mother was crying about the homestay business.
I'm going to tell him now.'
The twins told Iveri about Mr Brown and Sami.
He listened, then said, 'I have to go,' and
ran along the path to the village.
When Iveri got to the rara, he found everyone
there.
There was a sevusevu ceremony.
Mr Brown had given Ratu Loti a bag of kava
and the Ratu was welcoming him into the village.
Iveri didn't think the Ratu was happy, but
Uncle Vili was sitting proudly with Mr Brown.
Iveri looked for Sami but couldn't see him.
After the ceremony, Mr Brown walked around
the village with Uncle Vili.
He talked to everyone and went everywhere.
Iveri watched them.
Later, when Iveri went back to his family's
bure, Tema told him Mr Brown was coming for
dinner.
Iveri said, 'Where is my father?
I must talk to him.'
Tema said, 'He is very tired.
He is sleeping.'
Tema made a fine meal for dinner that night.
Everyone sat on mats on the floor.
The Robinsons weren't happy to be eating with
Mr Brown, but they did it for Tema.
Everyone ate with their hands, but Mr Brown
asked for a fork and spoon.
Mr Brown and Uncle Vili talked and laughed.
After dinner, the Robinsons said goodnight
and left.
Mr Brown stayed and talked.
He talked about the resort business in Fiji.
He told the Ratu that there were a lot of
jobs in the resorts for villages that leased
land to developers.
The Ratu listened.
Iveri listened too.
Tema went into her kitchen.
Later Uncle Vili said, 'I will take Mr Brown
back to Papaya now.'
Sami still had not appeared.
Where is he?
Thought Iveri.
Uncle Vili didn't take Mr Brown back to the
boat.
He took him to see Tom instead.
Iveri followed them, and watched from the
shadows.
Mr Brown knocked softly on the Robinsons'
door.
Tom opened the door.
The smile on his face disappeared.
'Oh, it's you,' he said.
'What do you want, Brown?'
'Tom,' said Mr Brown, 'listen to me.
I want to lease a large piece of land here
on Tavioka.
Some people I know plan to build a big resort
here.
We'll need a good builder.
Why don't you help me?
You'll make a lot of money.
Vili says the Ratu likes you.
You could tell him that a resort will be good
for the village.'
Iveri stood very still.
He liked Tom Robinson.
He wanted him to say no.
Tom said, 'I quite like Tavioka without a
resort.'
Mr Brown laughed.
'Money, Tom.
Money.
We could make a lot of money.'
'Mm.
I'll think about it.
But I still remember the Nadi hotel,' said
Tom.
'That was an accident!'
'Goodnight, Brown.
My wife is waiting for me.'
Tom went inside and closed the door behind
him.
Mr Brown stood at the closed door, and Iveri
heard him quietly say, 'Fool.'
Uncle Vili and Mr Brown walked away towards
the beach.
Iveri wished Tom had just said no.
Any resort that Mr Brown built was not going
to be good for Tavioka.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Answers
Early the next morning, before work, Iveri
talked to the Ratu.
He told his father that Uncle Vili was working
for Mr Brown.
He showed him the banknote and Michelle's
flip-flop.
Ratu Loti put his head in his hands.
'Oh, Vili...
He should have been the Ratu after me.
The clan liked him.
Now he will have to leave us.
He could have had everything.
Now he will have nothing.'
Ratu Loti asked Iveri not to tell Tema.
'I must speak to Vili first.'
Iveri and Tema went to Papaya Island together.
On the way, Tema talked about Mr Brown.
'Why did your uncle bring him to Tavioka?'
she asked.
'I don't want the Ratu to listen to him.'
'He won't,' said Iveri.
The Robinsons ate breakfast outside again.
The Ratu was very quiet and sad.
He sat in the sun with his eyes closed.
Then he said, 'I'm going to see the men at
the church now.
Tema and Iveri have gone to work.
I've asked another of my brothers, Josefa,
to take you for a walk today.
Josefa will take you across the hills.'
The family went to put their walking shoes
on.
'I think Iveri has told him about Uncle Vili,'
Peter said to Michelle quietly.
'I think you're right,' said Michelle.
'What will he do?'
Their parents were talking about Mr Brown.
'If you help that man I'll never talk to you
again,' said Nicola.
'I know his kind of resort.
The villagers work hard for very little money.
There'll be false sevusevu ceremonies and
false mekes.'
'I was never going to help him, Nicola,' said
Tom.
'Why didn't you say no last night?'
Nicola asked.
'It's better not to answer a question like
that straight away.
I've seen an angry Jasper Brown before.'
Michelle said, 'Dad, we've been trying to
tell you about Mr Brown.'
She and Peter told their parents about Mr
Brown giving Uncle Vili money.
They told them about Michelle's flip-flop.
'Right,' said Tom.
'I'll talk to the Ratu.'
He got up to go to the church to find Ratu
Loti.
Just then, Mr Brown appeared with Uncle Vili.
'Tom!' he said.
Today he was wearing a pink shirt and black
shorts.
He was smiling.
The Robinsons didn't smile back.
Tom walked towards him.
'Do you want my answer, Brown?'
'That's why I'm here,' said Mr Brown.
'I know what you've done,' said Tom.
'You've tried to stop Tema's homestay business.
Your man nearly drowned my son.
I know that was part of your plan.'
He went very close to Mr Brown and spoke very
quietly.
'I'll never help you put a resort onto this
island.'
Mr Brown's smile disappeared.
Tom continued, 'I have some of my own ideas
about helping the village.
I'm going to talk to the Ratu about them today.'
Mr Brown's face was as pink as his shirt.
'You're a fool, Robinson.'
He stared at the family one by one.
'You'll be very sorry.'
He marched away.
Uncle Vili put his head down and followed
quickly.
Tom said, 'I'll be back soon.'
He hurried away to the church.
When he returned, Josefa had arrived to take
them for the walk across the hills.
Tom said, 'We'll talk later.'
They followed Josefa quietly.
There was a lot to think about.
When Iveri and Tema returned to Tavioka at
the end of the day, the Ratu was sitting outside
with Tom Robinson.
They were drinking tea.
'Have you seen Vili?'
the Ratu asked.
His face was tired.
'Was he on Papaya today?'
'I saw him,' said Tema.
'He was with Sami.'
'Mm,' said the Ratu.
'Come and sit with us, Tema.
You too, Iveri.'
He told them that Tom wanted to help the village.
'Yes,' said Tom.
'I will help you with the homestay business,
Tema.
I know a lot of people who will come here
to stay.
I will help you build some bathrooms.
I can bring electricity to the village.'
They talked for a long time.
They made a lot of plans.
Tema was very happy.
The Ratu's face was still sad.
Tema made a big meal for dinner.
Nicola helped her.
The women talked and laughed happily.
Uncle Vili still didn't appear.
It was a warm night.
After dinner, Iveri and the twins went for
a walk on the beach.
Then Iveri said, 'I must go.
I have work again tomorrow.'
'You work too hard, Iveri,' said Michelle.
Iveri laughed.
'Horse-riding with the tourists?
It's not so hard.
Tomorrow after work, we'll meet some of my
friends.
We'll have a game of football on the beach.'
That night, Michelle dreamt that she was in
Austria.
She'd been skiing and was very tired.
She was sitting by a wood fire.
It was warm, and she watched the orange light.
It was so real.
She could even smell the smoke from the fire.
She was getting too hot.
She fought to wake up - it wasn't a dream.
There was a fire in the room, and smoke was
everywhere.
'Peter!'
she called.
He didn't answer.
Michelle couldn't see through the smoke.
She remembered the lessons about fire she'd
learnt at school - Get down low.
Go!
She lay down on the floor and moved towards
the wall.
She found the wall and then the window.
She pushed the flyscreen and climbed out of
the window.
'Help!'
she cried, but her voice was weak.
Suddenly someone came out of the darkness
and climbed quickly in the window.
Michelle couldn't see who it was.
She banged on her parents' door and called,
'Fire!
Our room's on fire!'
Tom and Nicola came running out.
Nicola screamed, 'Where's Peter?'
'He's in the room.
I couldn't get to him.'
Michelle was crying now.
Tom ran to the twins' room.
Just then, the door opened and out of the
smoke came Uncle Vili and Peter.
Uncle Vili was helping Peter to walk.
Both of them were coughing from the smoke.
Uncle Vili gave Peter to Tom, then fell onto
the ground and lay there.
Nicola knelt beside Vili.
'He's been burnt,' she said.
Suddenly Tema was there, and Ratu Loti too.
'Vili!'
cried the Ratu.
'No!'
Uncle Vili opened his eyes and looked at the
Ratu.
'Is the boy okay?'
Tom was sitting on the ground with Peter now.
Peter was still coughing, but he wasn't hurt.
Tom said, 'Yes, Peter's okay.
We've been very lucky.'
The Ratu looked down at Uncle Vili.
'Tell me you didn't do this too?' he asked.
'No,' said Uncle Vili.
'I didn't.'
Tears ran down his face.
He took his brother's hand.
'I told Mr Brown I wasn't going to work for
him anymore.
I gave him back his money.
He said I was going to be sorry.'
Uncle Vili stopped for a moment, then went
on.
'I think Sami started the fire.
I saw him earlier.
He was walking through the village with a
lamp.
Then I saw him later, and he didn't have the
lamp then.
I called to him but he began to run.
Then I saw the smoke from the fire.'
'Thank you for getting Peter out,' said Tom.
'You saved his life.'
Other villagers appeared out of the night.
People began to fight the fire with water
and wet sacks.
'They've got him,' someone shouted.
Two Fijian men were coming forward, holding
Sami between them.
One was Eroni, Iveri's brother, and the other
was Ratu Loti's brother, Josefa.
'We found him running to the beach,' said
Eroni.
'We knew the Ratu wanted to find him.'
'He has a lot of questions to answer,' said
the Ratu.
Tom said, 'We need to get Vili to a doctor.'
The Ratu said, 'There's a doctor at the resort
on Papaya.
We'll take him there.'
'What about Sami?' said Tema.
'We'll take him too.
The police will want to talk to him.'
Tom said, 'The police need to find Mr Brown
too.'
'Yes, they do,' said the Ratu.
'Come, Eroni.
You too, Iveri.
We will go to Papaya now.'
Some villagers carried Uncle Vili gently to
the beach.
Sami was led away.
The fire was put out.
'What will happen now?'
Michelle asked.
Tom said, 'Sami and Brown should go to prison.
There'll be no resort on Tavioka.'
'What about Uncle Vili?'
Peter asked.
'He saved my life.'
Tema said, 'The Ratu loves his brother.
Vili knows he did wrong and is very sorry.
I don't think the clan will send him away
now.
When he's better he can come home and help
me with the homestay business.'
Later that week the Tavioka villagers stood
on the beach.
They had just sung a goodbye song for the
Robinsons.
Iveri, Tema and Ratu Loti watched the Robinsons'
boat leave Tavioka Island.
Tema waved for a long time.
Iveri's family was sad to say goodbye to the
Robinsons, but they knew they were going to
see them again.
Tom was coming back with some men to rebuild
the visitors' house and to bring electricity
to the village.
More tourists were going to come to Tavioka
when Tom and Nicola and the twins told everyone
about the beauty of this place and its people.
Tema turned to Iveri and said, 'You will soon
follow our friends, my son.
The Robinsons are going to send for you when
school in New Zealand begins again.'
Iveri smiled.
Peter had told Tom and Nicola about Iveri's
wish that he still went to school.
So Tom and Nicola had talked to Tema and the
Ratu about Iveri.
Then they'd asked Iveri to come and live with
them while he went to school in New Zealand.
'Living with the Robinsons is going to be
an adventure,' he said to his mother, 'but
I'll always come back to my island home.'