CHAPTER ONE
Buzz, buzz, buzz.
Angus groaned and hugged the pillow closer
to him.
Maybe if he pretended to be asleep the noise
would just go away.
Buzz, buzz.
It stopped.
But there was someone hammering on the wall.
Or, no, it seemed to be closer.
It seemed to be coming from inside his head.
Buzz, buzz, buzz.
Angus groaned again, stretched out his arm
and pulled the ringing phone to his ear.
"Good morning, Angus," he heard Ross's voice
say, "Or should that be 'Good afternoon'?
How're you feeling?"
"I'm dying.
Leave me alone," was Angus's mumbled reply.
"Nah, that wouldn't be much fun."
Ross sounded like he was enjoying himself.
Angus turned over, wincing as the sunlight
hit his eyes.
"What are you doing up so early?
Why are you so cheerful?"
"I'm not cheerful, it's just Schadenfreude.
And it's not early, it's 1 o'clock and I've
been up since eight.
Some of us have real jobs,
you know."
"Uh-huh," was Angus's response.
"So, you had a good time last night, then?
Susie and you seemed to be having a good chat
when I left."
"Oh?"
The mention of Susie's name had finally woken
Angus up.
"In fact, I was wondering if you know where
she is?
A body's been found and everyone has to get
to Arthur's Seat now."
Angus pulled himself into a sitting position,
and rubbed his eyes while he tried to understand
the implications of Ross's question.
It
took a moment but then he felt himself blush
to his ears.
"No, no!
I've no idea where she is," he protested.
"Wh-why?
Can you not get hold of her?"
"No, she's not answering her phone, so I put
two and two together..."
Ross still sounded amused, but became serious,
"But she really needs
to come to work, the boss is not pleased,
so if you hear from her..."
"Of course.
You said Arthur's Seat and a body?"
"That's right.
I'm heading over there now."
"OK, well I hope you find Susie soon."
"Right you are, bye."
Angus sat a moment, the phone quiet in his
hand.
A body on Arthur's Seat, now that didn't happen
every day of the week, maybe he'd walk up
there himself, see what was going on.
He might see Susie... and some fresh air would
help his sore head.
But first things first: he needed a cup of
tea.
Thirty-five minutes later, Angus stumbled
out of the front door of the Marchmont tenement
he had lived in for a little over a year and
began to walk in the direction of Newington.
It was warmer than he had expected and he
was soon regretting the jacket he'd grabbed
on his way out.
He quickly forgot about that as he turned
into Holyrood Park Road and saw the police
vans parked at the end, sirens off but blue
lights flashing.
He was surprised that they were still there,
as he had taken a long time to get ready.
It must be very serious.
As he neared the entrance to Holyrood Park,
he could see a police-tape barrier strung
across the road and pavement.
A group of students
from the nearby university accommodation were
smoking and texting; a couple of joggers had
also paused and were chatting to an elderly
couple; off to the side was a young woman.
She stood out with her amazing, fiery-red
hair which was blowing across her face in
the breeze.
It contrasted perfectly with her green dress,
and Angus was momentarily distracted by this
vision.
He quickly turned his attention, however,
to the men and women on the other side of
the plastic barrier: police officers, forensic
scientists and other miscellaneous people
who had a job to do at a crime scene.
He caught sight of Ross standing near a van,
talking to his superior.
Looking around, he saw Susie approach them
- so Ross had managed to find her.
He watched as she greeted Ross and their
chief, who didn't look very pleased.
He gestured towards the crowd of people and
Susie started walking in their direction.
As he waited for her to cross the 100 yards
or so to where he and the others were standing,
his attention was again diverted, this time
to
two paramedics carrying down a covered body
and a police officer pulling at the lead of
a dog.
The animal, a Border Collie, was tugging at
its restraint and barking quite fiercely.
The uniformed officer was clearly having some
trouble keeping the dog under control.
"Thank you everyone, there's nothing to see
here.
Please be on your way and clear the area,
so that we can get on with our investigation."
Susie seemed less than happy to have this
task and stood with arms crossed as the collection
of people moved off a few more yards.
Job done, she turned to Angus.
"Afternoon.
What you doing here then?"
The tone was neutral but there was a hint
of a smile on her face.
"Well, Ross woke me up and so I thought I
might as well come and have a look..."
Angus smiled and trailed to a halt.
"Um, so how are you?"
"Couldn't be better."
Angus nodded at the sarcasm and asked: "What
happened here anyway?"
"Now Angus, you know I can't tell you anything.
You'll just have to read about it in the paper.
Besides, I'd better be getting on.
See you
later."
"Yes, fine.
Take care."
Angus watched as Susie started to walk away.
Behind her he could see the struggling officer
and dog, which was still pulling at its lead.
Angus imagined it desperately trying to return
to its master's side, the story of Greyfriar's
Bobby, the dog who wouldn't leave his master's
grave, coming to mind...
And at that moment, the collie finally broke
free of the young officer and went tearing
off, dodging
parked cars and outstretched arms, before
vanishing into the undergrowth.
There were shouts and arm-waving from the
police officers but nothing more of interest
to see.
Angus turned his back on the scene, and
wondered what he should do now.
It was a lovely day and he was in no hurry
to return to his messy flat; he'd go for a
walk and clear the cobwebs.
Removing the too-warm jacket, he meandered
off, with only one more glance at the action
behind him, the mound of the Crags and
Arthur's Seat bathed in the soft April sunlight.
CHAPTER TWO
Edinburgh had been Angus Fleming's home for
eleven years now, but he hadn't lost the feeling
of wonder at walking through its winding
streets with their grey-yellow sandstone buildings,
small gardens and multitude of chimneys.
He had arrived here as a naive 18-year-old
and the move from a small Hebridean island
to this elegant and eerie city had been a
shock to the system.
In time, however, the streets,
at least in the area around the university,
had become as familiar to him as the paths
he'd played on as a child growing up on Harris.
Today, he wasn't concentrating on the buildings
but was instead thinking about recent events.
Nine months earlier his first novel, a crime
story, had been published and had been an
instant success.
After years of uncertainty about his future,
it had come as a complete surprise and still
hadn't really sunk in.
He'd just returned from a few weeks of PR
stuff in England - the party the night before
had been in
celebration of that - and now he had some
time to recover from it all.
His publisher wanted him to start work on
the next book, but he didn't fee under any
pressure to get started.
Plus he had no idea what it should be about.
Pushing those thoughts to one side, he remembered
how touched he was that his friends, Ross
especially, had organized a party for him.
He
smiled to himself; everyone had been so complimentary
and Susie in particular had looked at him
differently.
Or, at least, so it had seemed to him.
He just hoped he hadn't made a fool of himself
- the end of the evening was a bit of a blur.
Sighing, he stopped to work out where he was.
Out of the corner of his eye, he caught sight
of a black shape.
It disappeared as he turned
around.
Was he still hungover?
No, there it was again: two dark eyes, a pink
tongue and a quizzical expression.
The lead hanging from its collar confirmed
Angus's suspicion.
The runaway dog.
Now, would it let him catch it?
Angus stood, eyes fixed on the dog; the dog
stared back; they both seemed to be thinking.
Then Angus raised his eyebrows, he'd had a
brainwave.
The dog sat down, intrigued by Angus's actions.
He had lifted up his jacket and was patting
the pockets, muttering to himself, "I'm sure
it's still here.
What did I do with it?"
before smiling, "Aha!"
He pulled out a crumpled crisp bag, opened
it and lay it flat on
the ground, the flattened contents letting
off an appetizing aroma of salt and vinegar.
He took a step back and waited.
The dog looked at the crisp bag, looked at
him, looked back at the bag, and after a brief
hesitation moved forward to lick up the tasty
mixture, tail wagging.
Angus saw his chance and picked up the end
of the lead.
The dog raised its head again but with a seemingly
defeated air, finished off the crisps before
letting Angus quietly lead him down the
road.
CHAPTER THREE
Walking back the way he had come, Angus could
see police officers clustered around the police
station on St Leonard's Street.
Ross and
Susie were there, too.
They spotted him with the dog and a small
group came to meet him a few steps away from
the station.
The dog started whining, then began barking
again.
"How'd you find her?
We've been looking everywhere!" asked a young
officer, taking the lead from Angus.
The dog pulled on it.
"Well, I was just walking through Dumbiedykes,
when I..."
Angus didn't get any further, because everyone
turned to watch as a car drew up.
An elegant woman, her face set tight in disbelief,
got out.
Susie muttered, "That must be the wife."
Beside them the dog's barking grew louder
and it pulled at the lead.
Taking the officer by surprise, it once again
got free and ran in the
direction of the woman.
She turned and was greeted by outstretched
paws, a wagging tail and silence...
Angus frowned slightly but before he could
articulate his thoughts - the quietness of
the dog around somebody it knew - the others
were
patting him on the back, "Well done Angus"
and wandering off, back to their duties.
"I'll give you a call later, thanks for your
help," Ross shouted over his shoulder and
was gone.
Angus stuck his hands, now free of a lead,
in his pockets, his jacket slung over the
crook of his arm, shrugged and turned towards
home.
He was hungry so he popped into a cafe for
something to eat before walking over the Meadows.
As he crossed the grass on his way to Jawbone
Walk, he spotted the red haired girl from
earlier.
The intensity of the colour combined with
the emerald green dress she was wearing made
her unmistakeable.
She was standing at the edge of the path talking
to a young man.
Something in her body language - her shoulders
hunched, one arm held
tight around herself - said here was someone
who was unhappy.
There was something else about her posture
that reminded Angus of something but he couldn't
pinpoint what.
As he walked past them he caught bits of what
they were saying.
From her:
"... can't believe he's gone.
What am I going to do?"
And him:
"You're well rid of ..."
When he was safely past them, Angus stopped
and turned back, but they had also started
walking, going up the hill towards George
IV
Bridge, her long red hair moving in rhythm
to her step.
CHAPTER FOUR
Angus found the events of the day difficult
to put out his mind.
Who was the murdered man?
Was the girl with red hair connected to him?
But until he saw Ross and Susie, he'd have
to leave his questions unanswered.
And even when he saw them, he knew there was
little they'd be allowed to tell him.
Instead, he decided to try and do some writing,
get back into a routine after weeks of being
on the road.
But his heart wasn't in it, and
he spent the following two days staring at
a blank computer screen, pacing his flat and
trying to persuade his brain to cooperate.
It ignored all his entreaties and so Angus
contemplated the pile of ironing instead,
pondered about dinner, wondered at the football
results
and dreamt about Susie's blue eyes and dimply
smile.
The only break from this mental torture had
been popping out to buy some milk and the
evening newspaper.
This could at least satisfy some
of his curiosity regarding the dead man: news
of the murder had been made public and the
local paper provided some basic details about
the victim.
He was the owner of a small gallery in Stockbridge,
married with no children.
The police had released his name, Geoffrey
Brodie, and were
asking for witnesses to come forward with
any information about the night of the murder.
Having read these few facts, Angus was about
to Google the name when his phone beeped.
Ross hadn't been in touch since Angus had
returned
the dog - no doubt working day and night on
the case - so Angus was surprised but happy
to read his text message:
"Drink?
Blind Poet?
In 20 mins?"
Angus tapped in "Great!
CU at the pub!"
while he looked for his keys and jacket, all
thought of Geoffrey Brodie suddenly forgotten.
He was
about to leave when he had a thought: maybe
Susie would be there...
There was a sudden panic as he quickly shaved,
dug out a crumpled but clean T-shirt and dragged
a comb through his hair.
Ten minutes later he ran out the door.
Arriving late, cheeks pink and out of breath,
he found Ross alone except for a half-finished
beer.
They exchanged greetings, Angus got
himself a pint and sat down.
"How's it going?"
"Well, could be better.
It's been mad at the station, as you can imagine.
It's not been going well, though we think
we've got a lead now.
But all these people keep calling with information
that turns out to be completely bogus."
"Umm," Angus said sympathetically, "So, what's
the theory?"
"I can't say much.
But, well, let's put it this way: Brodie seems
to have had some very shady friends."
"What kind of thing?
Handling stolen goods?
Drugs?"
Ross gave a non-committal shrug.
Angus was quiet a moment: "So, do you think
a deal went wrong, or something, and ended
badly for him?"
"Something like that."
Angus nodded, the germ of an idea had been
planted, perhaps the start of a new story?
His mind wandered as he supped his pint and
looked
unseeingly at the familiar poster-covered
walls of their favourite pub.
His daydreaming was interrupted by Ross getting
up to greet Susie, who had just walked in
the door.
Angus's heart began beating just that
little bit faster.
"You made it then.
Angus is in his own world again, so I could
use the company."
Ross grinned, "Same as usual?"
Susie just nodded as she sat down with a sigh.
"Hi, Susie, lo-long day?"
Angus stammered.
"Urn, yeah.
It's been non-stop."
She did look tired, but Angus would never
have let on he thought this.
They were silent while they waited
for Ross to return with her drink.
"Thanks," was her reply, when Ross brought
over her G&T.
She took a sip and finally smiled: "That's
better!
So, Angus, how are you?
What have you been up to?..."
With that the conversation started up again.
A few hours later, as they stood on Buccleuch
Street, ready to go home, Angus remembered
the
girl: "Ross, mate, I meant to tell you, there
was this girl - had amazing red hair - standing
watching at Arthur's Seat the other day.
And, well, I saw her again and overheard her
talking.
Something about it being good he was gone.
Do you think she had anything to do with
the murder?"
Ross thought a moment but then shook his head,
"I doubt it, she could have been talking about
anything.
But I'll get someone to look into
it, just in case."
"OK.
'Night then.
'Night Susie."
"'Night."
"'Night Angus, sleep tight..."
Susie answered with a giggle and a wave.
Angus went home, feeling happy to be back
in Edinburgh and to already have a vague idea
for his next book.
CHAPTER FIVE
In the cold light of day, the story idea still
seemed to have potential, but Angus knew he
would need to do some research before he could
start building on it.
He jotted down a few notes but quickly turned
his attention to Google and Wikipedia, surfing
for anything he could find on gallery owners,
contemporary painting and the Edinburgh art
scene.
As a child he'd loved reading, losing himself
in new worlds which couldn't have been more
different from the reality of his island life.
He'd also written short stories and poems,
but it was only when he started writing his
first novel that he felt he'd finally found
something he was good at.
Nevertheless, the amount of research involved
had surprised him but had also thankfully
turned out to be a
pleasant, if sometimes frustrating, task.
At the moment, though, he could relax and
enjoy it.
After hour or two's work, while taking a break
from the computer, Angus remembered a
university friend, who conveniently worked
in a local gallery run by a Kathleen Reid.
She could perhaps help with some general information
about what was involved in running a gallery,
and also might have some gossip about Geoffrey
Brodie, who Angus still couldn't get out of
his mind.
He sent her a message on Facebook to ask if
they could meet.
She clearly had time to kill, as an answer
arrived only half an hour later.
By 12.30 Angus and Amy were sitting on a bench
with take-away rolls from the deli, a few
tulips swaying in the breeze beside them.
"So, what is it you'd like to know?"
Amy asked as she tucked into her panini.
"I've got an idea for a story and it's revolves
around a gallery owner from Edinburgh..."
"Is this to do with Brodie?"
"Um, yes, in a way.
He's the spark for the whole thing.
Why, did you know him?"
"Only by reputation: Kathleen knows - knew
- him and I've often heard her talk about
him.
From what I can gather, he was a terrible
flirt
with a penchant for young female artists.
He'd offer them his support and, as his gallery
was successful, it was good to have him on
your side.
In return...
well, who knows what he expected in return,
but I wouldn't have wanted to be in his debt."
"But his wife...
Did she know?"
"Must have done.
But she had a good life with him, could swan
about the city and jet off to Paris for the
weekend, so why would she rock
the boat?"
They were quiet for a moment, eating their
lunch; Angus turned over this new information.
He wondered if this was common knowledge ...
maybe he should give Ross a call and tell
him, though he probably knew about it already.
"Was there anyone in particular he was meant
to be involved with?"
"I don't know.
There seem to have been several over the years.
Can you use that for your story?"
Amy looked at him hopefully.
"Ah, yes, possibly.
It's still in the very early stages, and I'm
not sure what direction it might take, so
everything could be useful.
Thanks."
"Not at all," she replied, satisfied, "Glad
I could help.
But I've got to be getting back.
Catch up again soon?"
Angus nodded and watched Amy as she walked
back towards her work.
He found his phone and called Ross.
He repeated the gossip Amy had
passed on, but Ross didn't seem that interested.
"We think we've got our man.
Found a connection between Brodie and a guy
we've been watching for years, deals in stolen
art, but has never
been convicted.
He's being brought in for questioning."
The call ended, but Angus stayed sitting,
people watching and enjoying the spring sunshine.
A group of art students walked past and he
was
reminded of the red-headed girl in the green
dress: who was she?
And was she connected to Brodie?
Why did he even assume she was an artist?
And what about Brodie's wife, would she really
just sit back and let her husband have affairs?
The police may well have found the
murderer, but Angus couldn't help wanting
to know more about the people connected to
the dead art dealer.
Perhaps a visit to Brodie's gallery would
provide some of the answers.
CHAPTER SIX
As the sun burned through the morning haar,
Angus set off on foot in the direction of
Stockbridge, the arty area of the New Town.
Brodie's
gallery was located in Raeburn Terrace, the
main street running through Stockbridge.
It would be a fairly long walk but a pleasant
one, taking him through the Old Town and into
the Georgian terraces of the New.
With any luck the mist would lift enough to
allow a view over
to Fife and the hills to the north of the
city.
Angus found walking helped the creative process.
Today though, he simply let his mind wander;
it was too glorious a day to think about
work.
And in no time, it seemed, he'd arrived at
the gallery, 'Brodie's' written in chic silver
lettering above the door.
Looking through the
window, Angus could see the cliched interior
of a gallery: white walls, pale wooden floors,
minimal furniture.
Some brightly-coloured canvases were hung
on the walls and a roughly-hewn sculpture
sat in the corner.
Stopping to compose himself, he was surprised
to see the crisp-loving Border Collie tied
up to some railings: Brodie's wife must be
here.
As he turned towards the door, he almost collided
with two large men striding out of the door,
their leather jackets and aggressive
demeanour not what you'd expect in an Edinburgh
gallery.
Slightly flustered, he watched them walk away
before entering the gallery.
He stopped in front of the first picture and
stared at it, but
didn't really see it.
He was wondering who the men were and what
they wanted.
Slowly, he forced himself to focus; he'd tie
himself in knots if he weren't careful, always
imagining the worst.
Calm again he concentrated on what he was
looking at: a landscape of a sunny beach,
the sea gently lapping at the shore.
Adopting the manner associated with people
looking at paintings, he moved slowly and
quietly around the room, head tilted slightly
so as
to better enjoy the pictures.
As he walked past, he noticed that a door
at the back of the gallery - probably to an
office or a storeroom - was slightly ajar.
However, he couldn't hear anything, so continued.
Back at the front door he started again, this
time
reading the captions and moving more randomly
here and there.
It didn't take long to realize the paintings
were all by the same person, a woman called
Katrina McPhair.
Finding a leaflet on the desk at
the front, he read a short biography of her.
She was from Inverness, in her late 20s, had
studied in Edinburgh and was a fan of the
Colourist movement, something which was evident
in her paintings: bold colours, vivid landscapes
and still-lifes, an enthusiasm for all
things Scottish.
There was no photo of her, but Angus couldn't
help wondering if this was the girl with the
red hair.
Deep in thought, he was startled by a voice:
"Hello, I'm sorry, I didn't hear you come
in."
He recognized the tall woman as Mrs Brodie.
She was expensively dressed and could have
been anything between 40 and 60.
She looked poised
and steady, but a slight redness around the
eyes and nose belied this.
She also didn't look too happy to have a visitor.
"Hello, the paintings caught my eye so I came
in for a closer look."
He stopped and waited for a reply.
Mrs Brodie turned to look at the painting
nearest them, a brief appearance of pain on
her face.
"Is... is everything all right?
You look...
I'm sorry..."
Angus reached out a hand towards her.
He suddenly felt very guilty for intruding
on this woman's grief and misfortune.
He was ashamed of letting his curiosity get
the better of him, but didn't know how to
put it right.
She had now completely turned away from him,
her hands held up to cover her face, clearly
trying not to cry.
"Should I go?
I should go."
Angus took a step towards the door.
"No, no, please stay.
I'm sorry.
I just need a moment.
Please have a look around."
With her head bowed, she walked back to the
small office.
Angus hovered, unsure of what to do but, as
she had left the door open, he took
a few steps towards it.
He could see her sitting at a small table
and on the counter beside her a kettle and
some mugs.
"Would you like me to make a cup of tea?"
He asked hesitantly and received a nod in
reply.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Shortly after, they were sitting opposite
each other, cups of tea on the table.
Mrs Brodie had recomposed herself.
Angus introduced
himself: "I'm Angus."
"Eleanor Brodie.
Did you know my husband?"
"No, I didn't."
"Well, that's no great loss."
She sounded bitter.
"He's gone and now I have to clear up his
mess.
It appears the successful gallery owner
wasn't so canny after all.
Seems he wasn't just cheating on me..."
Angus raised his eyebrows slightly but didn't
say anything.
Mrs Brodie didn't appear to notice.
"I thought Geoffrey had saved, but it
turns out he owes thousands of pounds.
And to whom?
Some thug!
God!
I don't know what I'm going to do."
The muscles in her jaw tightened as she said
this.
She glanced at him quickly before continuing.
"I don't why I'm telling you this.
I
don't even know you."
She stiffened a moment, her gaze once more
directed at him: "You're not from the press,
are you?
You look familiar."
Angus blushed, "No, I'm not a journalist,
Mrs Brodie.
But I've written a book, maybe..."
She interrupted him, "Of course, you're the
crime writer.
What exactly are you doing here?
What do you want?"
Her tone was accusatory.
Angus squirmed in his seat, feeling deeply
ashamed.
The words came tumbling out as he tried to
explain.
"I'm sorry.
I really didn't mean to pry.
I heard about what happened and I'm trying
to write a new story and it seemed like a
good idea,
you know, and I saw the dog run away and then
stumbled across her and brought her back,
and then I saw her, and...
I'm sorry."
"It was you who found Jessie?"
Angus nodded.
They sat in silence while Eleanor Brodie thought
about this piece of information.
At last, she spoke, "You're going to use my
husband's death in a story?"
"No, not exactly, I'm not sure."
Angus took a deep breath, "I'm not explaining
myself very well, I'm sorry.
I'm...
I'm here because I'm
nosy, I really am sorry, it was very thoughtless
of me.
The story is just a vague idea at the moment,
I don't know how it'll turn out, what it'll
be about."
Mrs Brodie didn't answer and Angus wondered
how he could make the situation better.
"Is there anything else I can do for you?"
he asked,
as Mrs Brodie stood up to clear the table.
She placed the mugs in the sink and turned
to face him, hands tightly gripping the edge
of the sink.
She looked exhausted.
"You seem to be good with dogs... you could
take Jessie for a while.
I can't look after her at the moment.
You can come round to the house
to collect some food and things for her."
All Angus could do was agree.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Back at his flat, Jessie exploring her temporary
home, Angus thought back over the afternoon.
It occurred to him that he should check if
it was OK for him to have the dog, seeing
as it was involved in a police investigation.
And he wanted to fill Ross in anyway, so he
dialled his number.
Ross sounded angry and began talking before
Angus could really speak.
Apparently the main suspect, the guy who had
been questioned, had an
airtight alibi, so he was free, and the police
were back to square one.
They had done some research regarding Brodie's
indiscretions - something which had been brought
up by more than one acquaintance of the
deceased, and had a new suspect.
Some officers were on their way at that moment
to bring her in for questioning.
Angus felt himself go cold, "Wh-who are you
bringing in?"
"The wife," was the grim reply.
"Are you sure?"
"Not yet but she had a motive and knew where
her husband was going.
We just need to establish her whereabouts
more exactly at the time of
the murder.
Why?"
Angus told Ross about his meeting with Eleanor
Brodie, ending with his question about Jessie.
"Well, it's a bit irregular, but I'll ask
the chief and let you know.
And I know she seems respectable and he was
a scumbag but that
doesn't mean she didn't do it.
I've got to go but I'll get back to you shortly.
In the meantime, keep the dog with you and
take care of her."
With that they hung up and Angus went to find
Jessie.
Sitting down beside her on the living room
floor, he couldn't help but feel
sorry for Mrs Brodie.
He also felt a shiver at the idea that he
may have just had tea with a murderer.
CHAPTER NINE
Angus had a restless night.
He couldn't stop thinking about the case.
What had started as a bit of harmless nosiness
- just research for a
story - had turned into something more serious:
he'd had tea with a suspected murderer and
was looking after her dog.
He knew he should disentangle himself but
was finding the whole situation quite thrilling.
It was a puzzle and he liked puzzles.
Though he
didn't have access to all the information
the police did, he still wanted to solve the
mystery of the red-haired girl, even if it
was only for his own satisfaction.
He struggled with his conscience telling him
to leave well alone and only finally fell
asleep, having decided to put off the decision
until the morning.
It was another sunny day, white clouds dotted
a blue sky, as Angus got up and went to get
showered.
With the water beating down on him, he
reached a decision: he'd stop meddling in
the case.
He had wanted to relax after all his PR stuff
and that was what he'd do, no more research
and asking questions.
With the decision made, he hurried to get
dressed - he wanted to be outside and making
the most of the
lovely weather.
He had a quick breakfast and then left the
flat, Jessie following behind him.
It felt a bit tactless to take her to Arthur's
Seat, so the
Meadows would have to do for a morning walk.
With one of the many paperpacks beside his
bed stuffed into his pocket - in this case,
one that Susie had recommended - they set
off along the quiet street.
The park looked lovely in the early-morning
light.
The cherry trees which lined Middle Meadow
Walk had only just blossomed and a glorious
haze of pink set against sharp green leaves
and the blue sky created a gorgeous canopy
over his head.
He turned off the path in the direction of
the tennis courts.
Arriving at the triangle of grass at the east
end of the park, he let Jessie off her lead
and found a stick to throw to her.
She brought
it back so obediently to him that he sat down
on a bench and started to read his book, only
looking up when she reappeared.
Time passed and he was so absorbed in the
novel, everything to do with the case forgotten,
that he didn't immediately notice that Jessie
hadn't come back.
When he did, he stood up to get a better look
but couldn't see her.
Panic mounted as he pictured her running out
into the road behind him.
He rushed towards the centre of the grass,
hoping to see around the hedge that bordered
the tennis courts while also
looking over his shoulder for any signs of
a black and white shape on the road.
With a sigh of relief he spotted her wagging
tail after only a few steps.
He found her being petted by a red headed
girl he recognized at
once: it was the girl from Arthur's Seat,
and possibly, if he was right, the artist
in Brodie's gallery.
Should he speak to her?
"Hello, hi there," he said to the figure crouched
down beside Jessie.
She looked up, startled, and blushing slightly
stood up.
He understood at once what had struck him
about her before: she was pregnant,
perhaps five or six months along.
"I'm sorry, is she your dog?
I thought I recognized her ..." she trailed
off.
"Uh, yes, well no, I'm just looking after
her for someone."
There was a moment's awkward silence and she
looked as if she was about to go: "I think
I've seen you before.
At Arthur's Seat when the
body was found," Angus voiced the first thing
that came to mind, wanting to see how she
would react.
And was both pleased and disappointed to see
the colour drain from her face and her air
of discomfort be replaced by one of anxiety.
"No, I think you must be mistaken.
I really must be going now."
And with that she turned and was halfway up
the path before Angus could do
anything.
He knelt beside Jessie, stroking her soft
ears while his mind went over what had just
happened.
For a dog that so disliked strangers,
Jessie had been incredibly calm and quiet
with the woman.
She must know her, but what did that prove?
Suddenly, he realised that he just had to
find out who she was, and all his intentions
of doing the right thing went straight out
the
window.
Attaching Jessie's lead to her collar, they
set off in the direction the woman had gone
in.
Rounding a corner, he saw her and then continued
to follow her as she walked along Bucchleuch
Terrace and over George Square.
He almost
lost sight of her as she weaved around the
students that were going to and from classes.
At Bristo Square, she turned right and, disappearing
under the overpass at Potterrow and going
against the stream of law students, hurried
down the cobbled lane to Chamber's Street.
Nearly colliding with a skateboarder, he reached
the street corner and didn't know at first
which way she had gone.
Standing on tiptoe,
trying to get a better look, he finally thought
he saw someone with red hair going through
the revolving door of the museum.
Apologizing to Jessie as he tied her up outside,
he also entered the light-filled Victorian
atrium and stopped again.
The place was
packed: tourists, pensioners meeting for lunch,
school kids crowded round the fountains with
the goldfish and museum wardens directing
people to different parts of the collection.
She could have gone anywhere - Angus would
just have to take his chances, maybe he'd
be lucky.
Climbing the stairs to the second floor, he
walked into the calm and quiet of the Asian
collections: ceramics, glassware and textiles
were
all neatly displayed behind glass in metal-framed
cabinets.
The museum was a maze and it wasn't long before
Angus was lost in its charm, his hope of finding
the girl fading.
He became absorbed in
the artefacts around him and nearly jumped
out of his skin when someone said:
"Why are you following me?"
It was the girl with red hair and, though
she spoke quietly, she was clearly angry.
Angus again said the first thing that came
to mind:
"Are you Katrina McPhair?"
"Why do you want to know?"
Angus took that as a yes.
"I saw you at Arthur's Seat when they found...
when they brought down the body."
The girl didn't react, so Angus
continued: "He was - or still is - exhibiting
your paintings.
So you must have known him.
And I think you knew him very well, is that
right?"
"Who are you?
What has this got to do with you?"
"Nothing, it's got nothing to do with me,"
Angus admitted.
"I was just intrigued."
He was aware of how lame this sounded and
waited for her reply.
She looked him up and down and must have decided
he looked harmless as her
posture relaxed a little.
"Yes, I knew him, knew him well," she touched
her rounded stomach and her look confirmed
what Angus had suspected - Brodie was the
father.
"But I didn't kill him, if that's what you
think.
I was angry but I would never have done that.
I loved him," she added softly, eyes on the
ground.
Then she looked up at him, expression firm
once again, "So, leave me alone!
I don't ever want to see you again."
Angus nodded shamefacedly, and waited until
she had left before slowly making his way
to the exit to collect Jessie and go home.
He believed her and only wondered what that
meant for Eleanor Brodie.
CHAPTER TEN
He heard nothing from Ross or Susie for a
few days and didn't want to bother them by
calling.
He had to make do with the newspaper and
whatever they printed but, besides learning
more about Brodie in his obituary, there was
very little new information.
He tidied his flat, walked Jessie and spent
as much time outside as he could.
Coming out of the cinema one afternoon - a
sudden shower
having forced him to take cover - he turned
on his phone to find Ross had tried to call.
Dialling his number, he was surprised when
Susie answered:
"Hi, Angus, Ross is just at the bar.
We're at the Peartree House.
Do you want to come and join us?"
"Hi, Susie, does that mean you've solved the
case, then?"
"Yes!
We're celebrating, or rather recovering from
the whole thing.
So, are you going to come or not?
I haven't seen you for a few days."
Angus's smile widened at her use of the first
person singular and assured her that he was
on his way.
But could she say first who they'd
charged with the crime?
"Well, you know I can't do that, but I suppose
there's no harm in you guessing..."
"Was it Eleanor Brodie?"
"Yup.
But you'll have to wait for the papers to
find out more.
Now, get a move on, your beer won't wait forever!"
Angus laughed and
hurried off towards the pub and his friends.