CHAPTER ONE
The Plan
India was a wild, strange, and dangerous place
when I worked there as a journalist many years
ago.
It was even wilder, stranger, and more dangerous
than it is today.
It was the kind of place where you never knew
what was going to happen next.
It was a place where people lived by laws
that nobody could understand, and where you
could be suddenly rich or suddenly poor and
then suddenly rich again.
You could be a beggar one day, a prince the
next, and then a beggar again.
All sorts of strange people came from England
to try and make money there, and they found
very unusual ways to make it.
There was enormous wealth in India, and if
you could find a way to get some of it you
could live very well.
If you couldn't find a way, you would live
very badly indeed; begging is not fun.
At the time that my story begins, I wasn't
a beggar, but I was certainly not a prince.
I was traveling to Mhow from Ajmir on the
train, and because of lack of funds, I had
to travel in third class, which is not very
nice.
There are no cushions on the seats, and the
passengers carry their food in bundles and
pots and drink water from the roadside.
In summer, when it is really hot, third-class
passengers are sometimes carried out of the
carriages dead.
I was the only person in the carriage until
we reached Nasirabad, when a huge Englishman
in shirt sleeves came in and began to talk
to me.
He was also a traveler, and we shared stories
of our past adventures.
He then wondered how he could send a telegram
to his friend, who was in Ajmir, because he
only had enough money for his dinner.
I had no money at all, and although I would
be paid when I reached Mhow there was no telegraph
office there, so I was not able to help him.
"Did you say that you would be traveling back
along this line soon?" asked my big friend.
"In about ten days," I replied.
"Can't you make it eight?
My business is urgent."
"I can send your telegram for you in ten days'
time if that will help you," I said.
My fellow-passenger thought about it for a
moment.
"My friend is traveling from Delhi to Bombay
on the twenty-third, so I don't think the
telegram will reach him in time, but perhaps
there is another way.
He will pass through Marwar Junction early
in the morning of the twenty-fourth, and you
might be returning through there at about
that time.
Do you think you could be there to give him
a message?
If I don't tell him where I am, he won't know
where to go."
I thought that this might just be possible.
"All you have to say to him is, 'He has gone
south for the week.'
He'll know what that means.
He's a big man with a red beard, and he'll
be asleep in a second-class carriage.
Just wake him up and tell him the message."
I said that I would do it if I could, and
then he told me that he was on his way to
Degumber because he had heard that the Raja
had done something bad.
His plan was to blackmail the Raja by pretending
to be a journalist and threatening to publish
the story in his newspaper.
People like him generally lived a hard life
and died suddenly.
I kept my promise and was at Marwar Junction
on the twenty-fourth.
I found the red-bearded man in a second-class
carriage, woke him up, and told him the message.
"I am to tell you that he has gone south for
the week."
The red-bearded man rubbed his eyes.
"That's just like him.
Did he say I was to give you anything?
I won't."
I told him that he did not have to give me
anything, and I watched the train pull away
from the station.
I didn't want the two men to get into trouble
in Degumber, so I described them to the authorities.
This prevented them from entering Degumber
at all.
I got a job at the newspaper office, where
we reported all the important events from
Europe as well as India.
Kings died, wars began and ended, politicians
made speeches, and ladies had afternoon teas.
During the hot summer, the only things that
happen in India happen in the hill towns,
where it is cooler, and nobody comes into
the office where I work.
One hot summer Saturday night, I was in the
office alone, waiting for a telegram about
a sick king so that the paper could be up-to-date
with the news before it was printed.
It was a very black night with a westerly
wind blowing in hot air from the desert.
I was surprised to see two men wearing white
clothes come into the office, and when they
saw me, they laughed.
One was the man I had met on the train, and
the other was the red-bearded man to whom
I had given a message.
I asked them what they wanted.
"We'd like to talk to you for half an hour,"
said the red-bearded man, "and ask you for
some advice.
We think you owe it to us because you stopped
us from going to Degumber."
I invited them to sit down, and they introduced
themselves.
"This is Peachey Carnehan," said the red-bearded
man, pointing to the other, "and I am Daniel
Dravot, and we have been most things in our
lives, including soldiers, sailors, proof-readers,
photographers, street preachers, journalists,
engine drivers, and so on, but we think India
is not big enough for us."
They were certainly too big for the office.
Dravot's red beard filled half of it, and
Carnehan's shoulders filled the other half.
"We don't like all the laws that the government
makes," said Carnehan, "so we are going away
to be kings, and we have signed a contract
that we will not drink alcohol or go near
any women until we are kings.
It is alcohol and women that give us most
trouble and stop us from getting ahead."
I thought they had been out in the heat and
were affected by the sun, but they were serious,
and Carnehan continued to tell me their plan.
"There's a place to the north of India called
Kafiristan, where no Englishman has ever been
and where the people are always fighting each
other.
We will teach one of the tribes to have a
proper army and then overthrow the king and
take his place and establish a dynasty."
"You'll never get there," I said.
"No Englishman has ever crossed Afghanistan
because of its wild mountains and even wilder
people."
Despite my warning, they wanted to look at
maps, so I gave them some, as well as an encyclopedia
and some other books so that they could read
about Kafiristan.
I sat and smoked and watched them for a while
and then went home, leaving them with the
books.
"Come to the market tomorrow," they said as
I left, "and we will say goodbye to you then."
"You will never get past the border," I repeated.
"Stay here, and I will try to find you some
work."
"No, we are going," said Carnehan, and he
showed me the contract they had made as proof
that they were serious.
CHAPTER TWO
To Kafiristan and Back
I went to the market the next day.
It was a place where all the nationalities
of Central Asia come, as well as people from
all over India, and where you could buy ponies,
precious stones, cats, sheep, and hundreds
of other things, many of which don't even
have names in English.
A priest approached me, carrying a child's
toy, and his servant walked behind him, carrying
a heavy basket full of children's toys.
Everybody laughed at them, and a horse trader
told me they were mad.
"He is going to Kabul to sell the toys to
the Amir, but I think that he will have his
head cut off."
"God protects the mad," said an Uzbek, "and
they always bring good luck."
The Uzbek shouted to the mad priest, "Where
do you come from?"
"I come from Roum, blown by the breath of
a hundred devils across the sea!
Listen all you liars and thieves.
Who will take me north to help me sell these
magic toys to the Amir?
God will protect you if you protect me."
A trader from Eusufzai told him there was
a caravan leaving from Peshawar in twenty
days and that he was welcome to join it.
The priest and his servant leapt onto their
camels.
As they left, the priest turned to me and
invited me to come a little way along the
road with him, promising to give me a ring
that would make me the King of Kafiristan.
Suddenly, I understood, and I followed the
priest and his servant out of the market.
When we reached the open road, the priest
spoke to me in English.
It was Dravot.
Carnehan was his servant, and they had twenty
of the best rifles that money could buy, with
ammunition for them, hidden under their basket
of toys.
They both shook hands with me and said goodbye,
and I watched the camels go down the road.
I was certain that I would never see them
again because their plan was insane and full
of danger.
Two years passed.
Lots of things happened in those two years,
and all of the important ones were recorded
in our newspaper.
Kings died, but the daily work in our office
remained the same.
On another one of those hot dark nights, I
was again sitting alone in the office, waiting
for some news to come by telegram when a strange
creature crept into my room.
It was a man, but his head was sunk between
his shoulders, and he shuffled along like
a bear.
He was dressed in rags, but he called out
my name and told me that he had returned.
"Give me a drink!" he croaked.
"Don't you know me?
I am Peachey Carnehan, and I was the King
of Kafiristan, together with Daniel Dravot,
and you have been sitting here all that time!"
I was more than astonished and said so.
"We were real kings, with crowns on our heads!
Poor Daniel, he would not take advice, though
I begged him."
I gave him a whiskey and told him to stay
calm and tell me his story slowly.
"I'm not mad," he said, "but you need to look
into my eyes, or I will forget."
I saw his hands and they were like bird claws,
with a strange scar on the back of each.
Then I looked into his eyes.
"You left the market on your camels, with
Dravot dressed as a mad priest, and you were
his servant.
Can you remember that?"
I asked.
"Yes, and we joined a caravan, but we left
it before Jagdallak, because we heard that
the roads to Kafiristan were good from there.
We dressed in all sorts of strange clothes.
Dravot burned off half his beard and shaved
his head into strange patterns.
We went into the mountains, which were tall
and black and they always fought each other."
I looked at him strangely and said to him
slowly, "Here, have another glass of whiskey."
He continued, "After a while, our camels could
go no further.
We killed the camels, but first we unloaded
the guns and ammunition, and when two men
came along with four mules, we killed one
of the men.
The other one ran away, leaving us the four
mules, so we put the rifles on the mules and
went further into the mountains.
Dravot sang as he went along, but I was afraid
and begged him to stop.
Dravot wouldn't stop, saying that if a king
could not sing, it was not worth being a king.
"We marched through the mountains with our
mules and our guns for ten cold days, and
then we came to a wide valley.
The mules were almost dead, so we killed them
and sat on the boxes of guns.
Ten men came running into the valley, carrying
bows and arrows and chasing twenty men with
bows and arrows.
We could see that this was an opportunity
to start the business of becoming kings.
We took out our rifles and began to shoot
at the twenty men and killed most of them.
Then the ten men fired an arrow at us, but
Dravot fired a bullet over their heads, and
they all fell down.
Dravot walked over to them and began to kick
them, and then he shook hands with them in
a friendly way.
He made them carry the boxes of guns across
the valley and up a hill to their village,
as if he were already their king.
"In the village, there were some very large
carved rocks, and Dravot stood in front of
the biggest one, opened his mouth, and pointed
down it.
One of the men offered him some food, but
he refused.
Another man offered him food, but he refused
again.
Then the oldest and most important looking
man in the village offered him some food,
and he accepted it.
"That's how we came to our first village,
as if we had tumbled out of the sky, but later
we tumbled from one of those rope bridges,
and you can't laugh much after that."
"Have some more whiskey," I said to him, "and
tell me how you became kings."
CHAPTER THREE
Carnehan Tells How He Became a King
"Dravot sat by the large rock every day, and
the people in the village came to worship
him.
Then some other people came into the valley.
Dravot and I shot them before they knew what
was happening.
We ran down into the valley and up the other
side and found another village, and all the
people there were afraid of us.
Dravot made the two villages work together
in the valley digging up the land, and we
began to learn some of their language.
We chose twenty good men and showed them how
to use a rifle and make a military formation.
They were our army.
"Then we went into the next valley and found
another village, which was very poor because
the land was too rocky, so we took the people
from there and gave them some land in the
good valley.
We found another valley, but the army was
afraid to go there, so Dravot shot one of
them, and the others were suddenly more courageous.
We made friends with the people, and Dravot
left me there while he searched for more villages.
"A big chief came across the mountains to
us because he had heard that there was a new
chief in the area.
I shot one of his men as they were approaching
and told the big chief to come forward alone
and shake hands, or they would all die.
The big chief obeyed.
I asked him if he had an enemy, and when he
said that he did we trained some of his men,
and together we marched to a plain on top
of a hill where the enemy was, and we shot
some people there and made the others our
friends.
I sent a message to Dravot because I was worried
that our kingdom was becoming too big to look
after by myself, but it was two months before
he returned.
When he did, he had an army of hundreds of
men with him and was wearing a golden crown.
"He was very excited because the people all
thought that he was a god, descended from
Alexander the Great and Queen Semiramis, and
they thought I was his younger brother and
also a god.
He opened a bag and gave me a golden crown
as well.
It was very heavy, but I wore it for a while
because it made me look so grand.
He brought one of the chiefs to me and asked
me to shake hands with him.
Dravot had given him the name of Billy Fish.
I shook hands with him and nearly fell over;
he had given me the secret Freemason's handshake!
'"Does he know the secret words, too?'
I asked.
Dravot assured me that he did, that all the
priests and chiefs knew them, and that they
had made Freemason marks in the rocks, but
that they did not know the Third Degree.
Dravot could hardly believe it himself, but
he declared that he would make himself Grand
Master, as well as king and a god, because
it would help him to run the country more
easily.
I agreed, and we ordered the women to make
lots of Freemason aprons for the men to wear.
"Then we held a meeting, where we told all
the people that we were gods and descendents
of Alexander, as well as Grand Masters, and
that we had come to make Kafiristan a place
where everyone could live happily and in peace.
One of the old priests saw the Freemason marks
on our aprons, which made him shout and try
to push over one of the large rocks.
It was very frightening because I thought
he was going to reveal that we were frauds.
But when he and his friends pushed over the
stone and cleaned the bottom of it, we could
see the ancient Freemason mark on the stone.
It was exactly like the one on our aprons.
The old priest fell to the ground and kissed
Dravot's feet.
It was a miracle, or, as Dravot said, luck.
"After that day, we had no trouble convincing
the villages to stop fighting each other and
to form an army to protect themselves against
people from places further away.
We worked very hard for the next six months,
teaching the people about farming and helping
them to build rope bridges across the deep
ravines.
We trained the army, which became quite large,
and settled complaints and disputes with the
help of Billy Fish and some other chiefs.
"Then we took some of the gold and valuable
gems that were in the country, and I took
them to the Ghorband country, where we bought
a hundred more rifles and ammunition and gave
them to the army.
I was very busy training the army, and Dravot
did most of the other work of kingship.
He was becoming so excited that he started
talking about establishing an empire rather
than just a kingdom.
He reckoned that there were about two million
people in his kingdom, and he could have an
army of two hundred and fifty thousand fighting
men, who would help England protect India
if the Russians ever decided to attack.
"He was sure that Queen Victoria would be
grateful.
His plans became grander and grander, and
he decided that he needed more men to help
him run the country, insisting that they had
to be clever and wise and have skills that
I did not possess.
I was angry when he said this because I knew
he thought I was not wise or clever enough
to help him.
However, he told me that I was still a king
and that half the kingdom was mine, and that
the men he needed had to be cleverer than
either of us because the kingdom was now so
large.
Then he told me something else that he wanted
to do, but this time I could not agree with
him at all."
CHAPTER FOUR
Kings, Gods, and Men
"'Winter is coming,' said Dravot, 'and nothing
much will happen then because it is too cold,
so I am going to get a wife, and I think you
should, too.'
"'I don't think it is a good idea,' I replied.
'We still have a lot to do.
Remember all the trouble that women have brought
us in the past.
We made a contract!'
"'But the contract was only until we became
kings, and we have been kings for many months
now.
We should both have nice, young, healthy girls
to keep us warm in winter, and we can take
any one of them that we choose, perhaps even
more than one, because we are kings.'
"'I'm staying away from women until we are
a lot more settled than we are now!
I haven't forgotten the trouble they made
for me when we were living in Mogul Street
in Bengal.'
"'But this will not be a Bengali woman.
This will be a queen.'
"I warned him that it could only lead to trouble.
'Don't do it, Daniel.'
"'I will do it,' he said, and walked away
from me.
The sun shone on his red beard and on his
crown, and he looked as if he was on fire.
"Getting a wife was not as easy as Dravot
thought.
He asked the chiefs about it, but they did
not give any advice, until Billy Fish said
he had better ask the girls which of them
wanted to be the queen, but this made Dravot
angry.
He thought that a king should not ask a girl
to be queen but that the chiefs should find
one for him.
He shouted at the chiefs about all the things
he had done for them and walked away.
"I asked Billy Fish what the problem was,
and he told me that no girl would marry a
god or a devil because they thought they would
die if they did.
I tried to explain this to Dravot, but he
would not listen and ordered the chiefs to
give him a wife the next day.
I was awake very early the next morning, and
when I went out I saw the chiefs and priests
standing around whispering to each other,
and they looked at me out of the corners of
their eyes.
"'What's the matter?'
I asked Billy Fish.
"'I can't really say, but if the king would
give up this idea of marriage it would be
better for him and also for us.'
"I knew that Dravot would not change his mind.
I told Billy Fish that we were not gods but
only men.
He said that it would be better to let the
people believe that we were gods.
Nevertheless, he told me that he had twenty
men who would be loyal to the two kings no
matter what happened.
"Winter was already beginning, and there was
a little snow on the ground when Dravot arrived
for the wedding.
I urged him once more to drop the plan and
warned him that there would be trouble, but
he would not take any notice.
"'There will be no trouble, Peachey,' he said,
'for they are my people, and they love me
more than they love their fathers.
Where's the girl?
Let the emperor see if his wife suits him!'
All the chiefs and priests were there, and
a group of priests brought a girl to Dravot.
"She was beautifully dressed and wore a large
number of jewels.
The priests blew the trumpets loudly enough
to wake the dead.
The girl looked back at the priests as she
came toward Dravot, her face as white as death.
"'She'll do,' said Dravot.
'Come and kiss me, girl.
You don't need to be afraid.'
He put his arms around her, and she closed
her eyes and put her face into his red beard.
'She's bitten me!'
exclaimed Dravot, putting his hand on his
neck where her teeth had broken the skin.
His hand had blood on it, and the priests
began to howl.
'Not a god, not a devil, but just a man!'
"Billy Fish pushed us both to where his loyal
twenty soldiers were, just as the army attacked.
The loyal twenty tried to protect us, but
the army had too many people in it now, and
we had to run.
Dravot blamed me for not keeping the army
under control and called me every bad name
under the sun.
"'We cannot escape,' said Billy Fish, 'because
the priests will be telling everybody in the
valley that you are not gods or devils but
just men.
I am a dead man.'
"He fell to the ground and began to pray.
We got away from the village, but only six
of the twenty men were still alive.
It was very steep country, and when we came
to a village, the people there began to shoot
at us because they had already received the
priests' message.
A bullet hit Dravot in the leg, and this woke
him up.
"'It is my fault, Billy Fish.
You get away from here and save yourself!
And you go, too, Carnehan.
They may not kill you.'
"But Billy Fish would not leave us, and I
would not leave Dravot, either.
We told the last six men that they could run,
and they did.
Then Dravot, Billy Fish, and I walked to the
village, where trumpets, drums, and horns
were making a lot of noise.
It was very cold up there, and I have a lump
of that cold in the back of my head right
now."
I realized that Carnehan's story was almost
at an end.
"What happened after that?"
I asked him.
"They took the three of us without making
a sound.
I shot a few of them, but they did not care.
The others closed in around us, and I could
smell them.
They cut Billy Fish's throat as if he were
a pig.
Then they took the king and made him walk
to the middle of one of his rope bridges.
They cut the ropes of the bridge, and the
king fell into the ravine, and I saw his body
on the rocks below, with the golden crown
next to it.
"They took me to some trees and nailed me
to the trees with wooden nails through my
hands and feet, but I didn't die.
They took me down the next day and let me
go.
Sir, you knew Daniel Dravot," he cried out.
"Would you like to see him now?"
He reached into his loose clothes and brought
out a bag, from which he pulled a red-bearded
head and a golden crown which he placed gently
on the head.
I shuddered, for it was strange to see the
head of a man you had once spoken to when
he was alive.
"I must go now," Carnehan said quietly.
I gave him a bottle of whiskey and a little
money, put him in my carriage, and drove him
to a hospital.
The next day, he died, and nobody ever saw
the head of the king or his crown again.