Escape
'I'm innocent! Why don't they believe me?'
'Five years! I must stay in this
prison for five years! All I do
is read. This is no life. I must get out of here.'
Suddenly the door opens.
'Ah, Brown. How are you today?
You like your book, I see.'
'It's a very beautiful day. Oh, I
forget - you can't go out. Ha, ha, ha!'
'Why do you hate me? You don't know
me. Why do you say these things?'
'You're a thief. Everybody hates thieves.'
'I'm not a thief. I'm an innocent man.'
'You're not innocent. Why are you in prison?
Can you answer that? Now, eat and be quiet.'
'I'm not hungry!'
Crash!
'Now, don't get angry, Brown.'
'- he guard's right - it is a
beautiful day. I must escape. But how?'
'I want to be like that bird.
He's free. He does what he likes.'
'Wait a minute. I've got an
idea. I can be like that bird.'
'There's a photograph. It's in one of these books,
and it shows the country near
the prison. Where is it?'
'Yes! It's here. Here's the
prison. And over here...'
'OK. Tomorrow I'm leaving.'
Slam!
The next day.
'Good morning, Brown. It's another beautiful
day. But you're in here. Ha, ha, ha!'
Clink!
The guard does not believe his eyes.
'No! It can't be! Quick -
sound the alarm. It's Brown...'
Ring! Ring!
'... He's not here!'
'Look everywhere. You must catch Brown.
Find him and bring him to me. Do you hear?'
'Yes, sir. Right away sir.
'This is Brown's cell. I want someone in it
tonight. You or Brown. Do you understand?'
'Yes, sir.'
Ring!
'I'm not happy and he's in trouble.'
'He's not happy and I'm in trouble.'
But Brown is not free.
'The guard never looks up here.'
'Now I must get out of here.'
'After him!'
'I must be quick. I'm not going back
to prison. They must kill me first.'
'Be careful, Brown. Don't fall now.'
'I'm nearly there. But this isn't easy.'
'Don't be afraid, Brown... OK, here I go.'
Brown is high above the guards. He runs and jumps.
'We must stop him.'
'Where is he?'
'Can you see him?'
'Look everywhere and find him - fast.'
'Oh, it's a long way down.'
'Help!'
'Ouch! That hurts.'
'There's a ditch. I can get there.'
'What's that? Is it him?
Turn your light that way.'
'Can they see me? Am I safe?'
The guards do not see Brown.
He is safe - for now.'
'Perhaps it's an animal.
I don't think it's Brown.'
'My foot hurts. I've got water in my shoes.
I'm tired. But I'm not going back to prison.'
'The wood isn't far. It's safe
there. They can't catch me now.'
Brown runs and runs until... he
can't run anymore. Suddenly...
'Dogs. I can hear dogs.'
'Go on!'
'Where's Brown?'
'Get him!'
'Oh, no. The dogs are looking for me!'
Splash! Splash!
'How can I hide? Perhaps...'
A minute later.
'Where is he? The dogs don't know.
Perhaps he's this way. Come with me.'
Brown is very tired.
'I want to sleep, but I can't now. I must go on.'
'It's getting dark. I can stop soon.'
'Ah this nice.'
'I need that bicycle. I am not a thief but...'
'Stop! That's my bicycle.'
'Sorry. I need it. Bye!'
Brown cycles for hours.
'Watch out! You...! The bicycle doesn't work now.
I must stop. Where can I find somewhere to sleep?'
Moo! Moo!
'Shush. I'm not going to hurt you. I only need to
sleep. Can I sleep here, please? I don't snore.'
Brown shuts his eyes - and sleeps.
'He does snore!'
There is a noise. Brown opens his eyes.
'What's that?'
'Come on then, Daisy. On your feet, Clover.'
'Good, I'm safe. The farmer's going away.'
'These are prison clothes. I
need some different clothes.'
'Hey! What are you doing? Those aren't
your clothes! Come back here. Thief! Stop!'
Bang! Bang!
'Get out of my way. Guards, dogs,
and now farmers' wives. What next?'
'I hear something. I'm very close now. That
plane's coming in to land.
The airport's over there.'
Brown arrives at the airport.
'The fence is high, but I can climb it.'
'Ow!'
Buzz!
An electric fence. I can't
climb it. What do I do now?'
'I can climb this tree and get over
that fence. But I must be careful.'
'Ten more minutes and I'm free. All I need is a
big plane. There are a lot of
planes. Which one do I want?'
'That's the one. There's lots of room for me.'
Screech!
'I need to eat. Pizza, I think!
And some milk. Are you hungry?'
'Of course I am. I need three big pizzas. It's
five hours before we land again, you know.'
'Quick, we've only got half
an hour. What's that noise?'
'My stomach, I think. I'm very hungry.'
'I can get in here.'
'What a lot of boxes! They
can't all go in that plane.'
'I'm free. I'm like that bird now.'
'Wait!'
'He's in there!'
Some time later.
'Another beautiful day, Brown.
But not for you. Ha, ha, ha!'
'You can't escape, Brown. Nobody escapes from me.'
'Brown lies on the cold floor. He is hurt.'
'The guard's wrong. I must
escape. I can't stay in here.'
'You can't keep me in here. I'm
innocent. You wait and see...'
'Perhaps things aren't all bad. I'm alive. The sun
shines. I hear the birds sing. I have my books.
Other people have a worse life than I
have...'
Brown looks out of his window for a long time.
Brown sees something move. It is a mole.
'Wait a minute! That mole's
making a tunnel. I've got an idea.