Introduction
Moreland Road is a street in the city of Bath,
England.
One Friday evening in March, at six o'clock,
people were coming home from work as usual.
The schoolchildren were already at home.
A woman's voice was coming from number 12.
'Jason, are you doing your homework?
You've got to do it before you go out to see
Maria
tonight.'
But there was no answer.
Jason was listening to music and couldn't
hear his mum.
At number 48 David Sen wasn't home yet, but
his wife was.
Thirty-two-year-old Nina Sen was tired after
a long week of work at the bank.
She had some news for her husband, but she
wasn't sure how to tell him.
Across the street was number 75.
Maggie was in the living room, sitting on
the sofa.
She was thinking about something.
It was a nice
something, because she had a smile on her
face.
And then there was Sam Davies, from number
56.
He was walking slowly home, looking a bit
worried.
Actually, he always looked worried.
Money was his problem.
He never had enough for everything.
How was he going to tell his wife that they
couldn't have a holiday this year?
So, just another ordinary Friday...
CHAPTER ONE
Jason's future
'Jason!
Did you hear me?
Are you working?'
Jason's mum heard nothing from his room.
She decided to go and see what was happening.
She stood outside the door of his bedroom
for a minute and then she walked in.
Jason was sitting on the floor and looking
at some photos.
'What are you doing, Jason?'
she asked.
Jason turned off his music and looked up.
'Do you remember this?'
He gave her a photo.
'It's me when I was five, and Maria.
She was really pretty - well, she still is.
It was my
birthday party, wasn't it?'
'Yes, I think so,' his mum said.
'It was the last birthday before Dad left,'
Jason said.
'I remember it very well.'
'The party, or the day Dad left?' asked his
mum.
'Both,' said Jason.
'In my mind, they both happened on the same
day.'
'They didn't, but it all happened a long time
ago,' his mum replied.
She walked to the window so Jason couldn't
see her face.
Simon, her husband, left their house in Moreland
Road early one morning twelve years ago.
He wrote her a letter and put it on the kitchen
table.
And then he left.
For twelve years she didn't hear from him.
No letters, no birthday cards for Jason.
Then, last week, there was a phone call.
'Why did you go?' she asked Simon again and
again.
He wanted to meet her.
'No,' she said, but she wanted to say yes.
Jason's mum turned away from the window.
'Jason, what about your homework?'
she said.
'Why are you looking at old photos?'
'I want to find all the ones I've got of Maria.
I want to take them with me to London, you
know, when I go to art school.'
He smiled at a
funny photo of Maria, aged eleven.
'It's a bit early to think about all that,
Jason,' his mum said.
'You're not going until the autumn.
And you don't know if you're going to
get a place at the art school.'
'I will, I'm sure I will.
When I went to visit them two weeks ago they
said, "We think your work's very good.
We really like your ideas."'
'I know, but... anyway, where are you going
with Maria tonight?' asked his mum.
'Broad Street Bar.
There's a great reggae band on,' said Jason.
'Have you told her about going away to art
school in September?' asked his mum.
'Yeah.
She's fine about it, I think,' he replied.
'I can come home at the weekends.'
'You won't...' his mother began and then stopped.
'I know what you're thinking,' said Jason.
'But we're different.
We'll always be together.'
His mother left the room and went downstairs.
'Maybe Jason and Maria are different,' she
thought.
'They've known each other since they
started primary school.
But I thought Simon and I were different,
and look what happened.'
'Mum.'
Jason came into the kitchen.
'I'm going round to Maria's now.
I'll have something to eat at her house.
OK?'
'Have you finished your work?' asked his mum.
'Yes.
Stop asking me.
See you later - about twelve.
OK?'
And Jason left the house before his mum had
time to say anything else.
Five
minutes later the phone rang.
Jason's mum jumped out of her chair, looked
at the phone and thought 'Simon.'
She answered it.
'Hello,' she said in a very quiet voice.
'Oh, hi, Mrs Campbell.
Is Jason there?'
'Maria!'
Jason's mum almost shouted her name.
'No, sorry, he's left.
He's on his way to your house.'
'Oh no!' said Maria.
'Is there a problem?'
Jason's mum asked.
'No...
Yes, I can't go out with him tonight.
But it's OK, I'll tell him when he arrives
here,' answered Maria.
'Bye.'
Jason's mum sat down.
She drank a little red wine.
She thought about the phone call from Maria.
She thought that Maria's voice was a bit
strange.
She hoped nothing was wrong.
CHAPTER TWO
Nina's new job
Nina Sen's work at the bank was over for the
week.
She was at home at 48, Moreland Road with
her six-year-old son, Max.
He was eating
sausages and chips.
'I got 100 percent in maths today,' he said.
'Did you?
That's great!'
Nina answered.
'You're good with numbers - just like me.'
'Is Dad at work?' asked Max.
'Yes, but he'll be home soon.
He's got the evening off,' Nina replied.
David Sen worked as the top cook at Julie's,
an expensive French
restaurant.
He worked long hours and very often he didn't
get home until late.
'Oh good!
Mum, can my friend Adam come to football with
us tomorrow?' asked Max.
'Of course he can.
Do you want to watch a bit of TV after dinner?'
Nina wanted some time to think before David
came home.
But she didn't get much time, because ten
minutes later she heard David come in.
'Hi, Nina.'
David kissed her.
'Where's Max?'
'Watching TV,' said Nina.
'How was the restaurant today?'
'Good.
You know Dan?' asked David.
'The new assistant in the kitchen?
Well, one of my cooks was ill today so Dan
did some cooking.
And he
was great.
He has a French grandmother and he can remember
some of the food she made.
So he's got lots of ideas for the new menu.'
'Daddy, Daddy!'
Max shouted, running into the room.
'Hello, tiger,' said David.
'Let's go and read a story, and then you can
tell me all about your day.'
Father and son left the kitchen.
Nina could hear Max's excited voice.
He was really happy to see his father.
'I'm lucky,' thought Nina.
'Why do I want to change things?'
She cooked dinner for herself and David.
'Are you ready to eat?' asked Nina when David
came back to the kitchen.
'There's something I want to talk to you about.'
'Mmm.
I'm not sure I like the sound of that.
Is it something important?' he asked.
'The director from head office came to the
bank today.
He told me I was the manager of the month,'
Nina said.
'Well done!
Does that mean you'll get more money?'
David laughed.
'In a way, yes.
He asked me to be the manager in Newcastle.
That's a really big bank, about five times
the size of the one here.'
Nina
stopped and looked at David's face.
'So yes, more money.'
'Ah,' was David's only answer.
Then a few seconds later, 'And what did you
say?'
'I said I was interested,' Nina answered.
'I also said I wanted to talk to you.
What do you think?'
'First thought,' said David, who stood up
to get a glass of water, 'well done you.
You work hard and I'm pleased for you.
Second thought -
what about my job?
Third thought - Newcastle is so far away from
here.'
'I thought all that too,' said Nina.
She went across the kitchen and stood with
her arms around David.
'And what about Max?
He loves his school and his friends.
And there's my mum and dad to think about,'
continued David.
'I know they live
in Exeter, but it's only a hundred kilometres
from Bath and we see them quite often.'
'They could come with us.
I'm sure they'll be happy in Newcastle.
Your mum was born near there, wasn't she?'
Nina was trying to think of
some more good reasons.
She really wanted this new job.
'Yes, but they have all their friends around
them now, and they love living in Exeter,'
David answered.
'It's a big thing to move at their
age.'
'Forget them for a minute.
What about you?' asked Nina.
'Well, you know I love working at Julie's,'
David replied.
'We've got a good name since that newspaper
wrote about us.
It's an exciting
time, and I don't really want to leave.
Of course, I'm sorry the restaurant isn't
mine, but we haven't got the money to buy
it, so...'
'I really want to say yes, David,' Nina said.
'I think this is just the beginning.
Maybe I could become manager for a big area
in a few
years and after that.
Well, who knows?
Then we could buy two restaurants and...'
'Slow down,' said David with a smile.
'We haven't decided yet.
When does the job start?'
'In three months,' replied Nina.
'David, we're still young.
It could be exciting to start again in a new
city.'
'True,' replied David slowly.
'When do you have to give the bank an answer?'
'Well, they want me to decide by the beginning
of next week,' Nina said.
'Say yes, then,' said David quickly.
'What?'
Nina looked at David.
She couldn't believe it.
'Well, we can't buy Julie's - that's what
I'd really like,' David answered.
'But I can get another job in a good restaurant
in Newcastle.
And your work is important.
I know you love it.'
'Oh, David, you're wonderful.
I'm so pleased I married you!'
Nina laughed.
'I'm going to write to head office and tell
them before you
change your mind.'
David pulled Nina close and kissed her.
'I hope we've done the right thing,' he said.
'Anyway, now I'm going to have a long hot
bath and
think about it.
And then I must phone Mum and Dad - I haven't
spoken to them all week.'
'Don't tell them yet about Newcastle,' said
Nina.
'Let's keep it to ourselves for the weekend.'
Nina sat at the table and wrote.
Then she walked down Moreland Road with her
letter and put it in the post box on the corner.
She heard a
soft 'plop' sound as it fell onto the other
letters in the box.
'We've decided what to do and nothing can
change that now,' she thought.
CHAPTER THREE
Dinner at Maggie's
Maggie was sitting on the sofa.
She had a photo in her hand.
She was thinking about her holiday in Chile
last month.
She and her friend
Belen went to Chile for three weeks, walking
in the Andes mountains.
It was a wonderful time.
'Well, actually, I don't think the holiday
was as wonderful for Belen as it was for me,'
Maggie thought.
She looked at the photo and saw a happy group
of young people.
They looked happy because the day's walking
was finished.
They were also happy because that was the
day they saw the beautiful bird.
A
condor, the famous bird of the Andes, flew
high above them in the sky that day and stayed
with them for hours.
Maggie was sad to see it fly away at the end
of the day.
'It was a very important bird for the Inca
people, you know,' said Xavier, their group
leader.
'On lots of old Inca buildings you can see
an unusual cross.
It's unusual because it has three levels.
Like this.'
And Xavier drew the cross on the ground.
He continued, 'For the Incas, each level was
a different world - the lower world, this
world and the higher world.
And there was an animal
for each world.
The higher world had the condor.
So you see, these birds were very special,
very important for the Inca people.'
The group were interested in Xavier's stories.
Belen was more interested in Xavier.
From day one Maggie knew that Belen liked
Xavier.
Well, he was great-looking and friendly with
everyone.
Belen talked to Maggie a lot about Xavier.
What he said to her, how she felt.
'This is exactly what she was like when we
were at school together,' thought Maggie.
'I hope I don't have to listen to this all
holiday.'
At the end of the first week, Maggie went
for a walk after dinner without the others.
She didn't go far.
She just wanted to be quiet and
on her own with the stars in the dark sky.
She stood looking up and then she knew that
someone was behind her.
She turned round and saw Xavier.
'Are you OK, Maggie?' he asked.
'Fine,' she replied.
'It's beautiful here, isn't it?
I love the mountains.
It's so different from where I come from.'
'I was born near here, so I love it too,'
Xavier said.
They sat and talked for a long time.
She learnt about his life and about the life
of ordinary people in Chile.
From that day, she and Xavier had a special
friendship.
They often talked together after dinner, and
something more than a friendship
began.
And of course Belen saw it.
'It's OK, Maggie, really,' said Belen.
'I don't mind.'
But Maggie felt she did mind, and sometimes
she saw Belen looking at her rather
coldly.
But at the end of the holiday things were
OK between the two friends.
And Belen actually said she wanted to go on
holiday with Maggie
again.
Maggie got up slowly from the sofa.
She enjoyed dreaming about her time in Chile,
but she had to make dinner.
Belen was coming tonight.
She walked into the kitchen and started cooking
the meat for the lasagne.
'Oh, I forgot to buy the tomatoes,' she thought.
She took her money and left the house.
She walked quickly to the shop at the end
of her
street.
In her house the phone rang and, of course,
nobody answered it.
Then the answerphone started: 'Hi, this is
Maggie.
Sorry, I'm not here to
take your call but please leave your name
and number, and I'll call you back later.
Thanks.'
There was a small noise at the other end of
the phone - someone was getting ready to speak.
But the person didn't leave a message or their
name and number.
Maggie came back with the tomatoes.
She saw the message light on the phone.
'Probably Belen,' she thought.
'Maybe she's going to be late.'
Maggie played the message, but there was nothing
to listen to.
'Strange,' she thought.
She went into the kitchen and finished the
lasagne.
Then she took a glass of red wine into the
living room.
She picked up the phone.
'Telephone number 07788536782 called today
at 19:00 hours,' she heard.
Maggie wrote the number down and thought,
'I don't know anyone with that mobile number.
'
But then she heard someone at the front door.
It was Belen.
'Hi, Maggie,' said Belen and gave her a kiss.
'Mmm, something smells good.'
They walked into the living room and Maggie
gave Belen a glass of wine.
'It's good to see you,' said Maggie.
'You look great.
I love your hair.'
'Thanks.
And how's the lovely Xavier?'
asked Belen.
'Have you heard from him?'
'Yeah, I have,' said Maggie.
'I got an email last week.
He was in an Internet cafe in Santiago.'
'Great!
I thought it was just a holiday romance.
But I'm really pleased for you...
No, really I am,' said Belen quickly when
she saw
Maggie looking carefully at her.
'He says he's coming to England very soon
- maybe next week,' said Maggie.
'Really!
So soon?
It must be love!' said Belen with a smile.
'Well, I don't know about that.'
Maggie laughed.
'He doesn't say anything about love.
Just that he's coming and that he's written
me a
letter to tell me everything.'
'Everything about what?'
Belen asked.
'I don't know.
It's a bit of a strange email.
Look, you can read it.'
Maggie gave the email to Belen.
She read:
Hi condor-girl
I'm coming to England very soon.
I need to get away from Chile for a bit.
Have written to tell you everything.
Can't say much now.
Looking
forward to seeing you a lot.
Much love
Xavier
CHAPTER FOUR
Sam has money problems
Sam arrived at his house, number 56.
The lights were on in every room, and he could
see his sixteen-year-old daughter, Emma, sitting
at
her computer in her bedroom.
Sam went inside the house and put his bag
down.
'Wonderful,' he thought.
'No more work until Monday.'
Sam worked for the town's
newspaper - the Bath Chronicle.
He was a reporter, but not a very important
one.
He quite liked his job, but he didn't get
a lot of money for it.
When he started work at the newspaper twenty
years ago, he had big ideas.
He wanted to work there for a few years, and
then move
to London to work for one of the big newspapers.
But time moved on and he didn't.
Sam still wrote about the ordinary lives of
people in Bath and sometimes... sometimes
a big story.
Then all the people on the paper had to
work together and it felt good again - for
a short time.
'Hannah, where are you?'
called Sam.
'Upstairs with Alicia,' a voice replied.
Sam went upstairs and found his wife, Hannah,
in the bathroom.
Two-year-old Alicia was playing in the bath
with about ten yellow plastic
ducks.
'Hello, my favourite two girls,' said Sam
and kissed them both.
'I heard that, Dad,' called Emma from her
bedroom.
'What about me?
I thought I was your favourite.'
'That was yesterday - when you made me a cup
of tea,' said Sam and walked into his older
daughter's room.
Emma was looking at something on
the Internet.
'I'm trying to find something about Chile
for my geography teacher,' said Emma and turned
to give her father a kiss.
'Go and ask Maggie.
She's just come back from Chile,' replied
her father.
'No, it's OK.
I'll find it on the Internet.
It's quicker.
Anyway, she probably doesn't know much about
the Mapuche Indians.
Dad, you know
I really like geography, don't you?' asked
Emma.
'Yes,' replied her father.
'Well, our teacher wants to take us to Norway
after school finishes in the summer.
She told us about it today.
It sounds wonderful.
Can I
go?'
Emma looked at her father.
He could see how excited she was.
'It'll be expensive, won't it?' asked Sam.
'I'm not sure,' replied Emma, but she knew
it wasn't cheap.
'There's the money I got for my birthday.
We can use that.'
'Yes, but that's not enough for a holiday
to Norway.
I'll talk to your mum about it,' said Sam,
and he left the room - again thinking
about money.
Sam went into his other daughter's bedroom.
Hannah was sitting on the bed.
Alicia was nearly asleep so Sam kissed her
goodnight.
'How much does Emma need for Norway?' he asked
Hannah as they walked downstairs.
'A lot - about 700 pounds, I think.
And she has to tell her teacher on Monday
if she's going,' replied Hannah.
'She really wants to, Sam.'
'I know.
I'll try to find the money from somewhere.'
Sam walked into the back garden for a cigarette.
Hannah sat down at the kitchen table
to read the newspaper.
Hannah looked up when Sam came back in and
said, 'I could get a job, Sam.
But I really want to stay at home with Alicia
for a bit longer.'
'I know, and that's fine,' said Sam.
'I'll ask Jeremy to lend us some money.
I don't like doing it, but I've done it before.'
His older brother, Jeremy, had a good job.
He worked in the world of computers where
nobody thought about not having enough money.
Jeremy
was strong - some people thought he was hard,
not strong.
Every job he got was better than the last
one.
He wasn't happy if life was too quiet and
easy.
He was a doer, not a thinker.
His wife was the same.
They both worked and played really hard.
'It's good that they don't
have any children because there isn't enough
time for them in their lives,' thought Sam.
Jeremy didn't understand how expensive children
were.
And Sam hated asking his brother for money.
He could tell that Jeremy felt sorry for his
younger brother.
'Why don't you get a better job, Sam?'
Jeremy always asked.
'You're intelligent, you could do anything.'
'I like my job,' replied Sam.
'I don't want to work anywhere else.'
That wasn't really true, but he could never
let Jeremy know that.
And this was the same conversation Sam and
Jeremy had on the phone that Friday evening.
But then it changed...
'I'm sorry, Sam, but I'm not going to lend
you the money,' said Jeremy.
'Pardon?' said Sam.
'No, no money this time.
You need to think about your job.
Get a job with more money.
You've got to change, Sam.
Every time you need
money, you come to me.
Well, I think it's too easy.'
Jeremy stopped.
Sam put the phone down.
His head was hurting.
He couldn't believe it.
His own brother didn't want to help him.
His own brother talked to
him like that, and made him feel small and
dirty.
Sam went back into the kitchen.
'What did he say?' asked Hannah.
'Fine,' said Sam.
'He'll lend us the money, so Emma can go to
Norway.'
'I know it's difficult for you to ask, so
thank you, my love,' said Hannah and kissed
him.
Sam didn't look at Hannah and went to find
Emma.
CHAPTER FIVE
Jason and Maria
Maria opened the front door of her house and
let Jason in.
'Hi,' said Jason and kissed Maria.
She took his head in her hands and looked
at him for a few seconds.
'What are you looking at?
Have I got something on my face?' asked Jason,
and he kissed her again.
'No, I just wanted to look at you - you've
got a lovely face,' replied Maria and walked
into the living room.
'Are you OK?' asked Jason, following her.
'I haven't seen much of you this week.'
'I'm fine,' replied Maria.
Then she turned and looked at Jason.
She saw someone who was her best friend.
She saw a person she loved, but
she knew that she was going to change everything.
'Jason, sit down.
I need to talk to you,' said Maria.
She took his hand.
'There isn't an easy way to say this, but
I've met someone else.'
'What do you mean - met someone else?'
For a moment Jason didn't understand.
Then his face went white.
'When I was on holiday with my family in France
at New Year I met a man and...' (this was
the difficult bit to say) 'and I think I love
him.'
'You said you love me,' said Jason in a loud
voice.
'I did.
I do.
I do love you, but maybe like a brother.
I feel a different love for Francois.'
Maria looked at Jason.
'Oh Jason, I'm sorry.
I didn't want this to happen.'
'You don't love him,' said Jason.
'It was just a holiday romance.
How can you fall in love with someone else?
Have you heard from him
since the holiday?
Have you seen him?
Does he say that he loves you?'
'Yes, he loves me too,' Maria answered.
'We've emailed each other every day, and he
came to London last week for a few days.
I saw him
then when I stayed at my sister's.'
'You told me your sister wanted to spend some
time with you,' said Jason.
'So that wasn't true, was it?'
Jason looked at Maria.
He couldn't believe what was happening.
'When we finish school in the summer, I'm
going to Paris to study.
Francois is studying there at the moment,'
Maria said, not looking at
Jason.
'You've thought of everything, haven't you?
When did you decide all this?'
Jason asked.
Maria didn't reply.
Jason got up, put on his coat and said, 'I'm
going.
I can't stay here.
It hurts just to look at you.'
'Will you be all right?' asked Maria.
'I don't know.
And anyway it's not your problem now, is it?'
replied Jason angrily.
'Jason, please don't,' said Maria.
'Don't go.
We need to talk some more.'
But Jason was already running out of the front
door.
He ran and ran until he couldn't run any more.
He wasn't angry any more, but just so sad.
He started to walk slowly home.
He hoped his
mother was out - he didn't want to talk to
anyone.
When he got to his house, he saw the lights
were on.
He tried to open the door quietly, but he
couldn't.
'Is that you, Jason?'
called his mother from the living room.
'Yes,' he replied.
She came to the door of the living room.
'Why are you back so early?'
'I'll tell you tomorrow,' replied Jason.
'I'm going to my room now.'
'Please can you come into the living room
for a moment,' his mother said.
'Do I have to?' asked Jason.
'Yes,' his mother replied.
Jason followed his mother into the living
room and saw a man sitting on the sofa.
'Jason,' said his mother.
'This is your father, Simon.'
Jason looked at the man and said nothing.
Simon said nothing, but couldn't look at Jason.
After a minute or two Jason said coldly, 'So
where have you been for the last twelve years?'
His father replied, 'It's difficult, but let
me try and tell you what happened.'
But Jason didn't want to hear any more things
that evening.
For the second time that day he ran out of
a house.
He went to the river and
sat looking at the water.
He felt lost.
Everything was different.
Maria loved someone else.
A strange man - someone he called 'Dad' twelve
years ago - was sitting in his house.
Jason felt he was going mad.
The weather was cold and it was raining, but
he just sat looking at the river.
For a moment he thought about jumping into
the water and
letting it take him away.
'Who will be sorry?
Nobody,' he thought.
But, deep inside, he didn't really believe
that.
He put his hand into his pocket and found
some cigarettes.
He lit one, stood up and turned away from
the river.
For hours he walked the
streets of Bath.
The rain was still falling and he was wet
through.
At about three o'clock in the morning he was
outside the city's mail depot.
There was a lot happening.
Big vans were arriving with bags of letters.
Jason was happy to stand outside the gate
and watch the
bags going into the building.
He stopped thinking about his problems for
a bit and time passed.
One of the men shouted to him, 'Hey mate,
you all right?
Want a job or something?'
Jason didn't answer.
A voice called out from inside the building,
'Harry, tea's ready.
Leave those bags and come and get it.'
The big gate opened to let the next van in.
And Jason just followed.
The man at the gate didn't see him behind
the van - he was too busy
reading his newspaper.
The driver got out of the van and went inside.
Then there was nobody but Jason.
He wanted to get out of the rain, so he got
into the van and sat down between the bags
of letters.
It was dry and comfortable.
He smoked his last cigarette and then closed
his eyes.
He woke up a short time later when he heard
the sound of people laughing in the building.
For a moment he didn't know where he was.
Then
he remembered.
He knew he must go home and talk to his mother.
Then there was his father.
Jason was angry with him, but he did want
to know why he was back.
'And I don't want anyone to find me in this
van,' he thought.
He jumped out and waited in the dark for the
gate to
open again.
When it did, he ran out.
A voice called out behind him, 'Hey, you!
Stop!'
But he didn't.
He ran on.
His head was hurting and his clothes felt
wet and
uncomfortable.
There was only one thing in his life that
made him feel good - going away to art school
in the autumn.
It was really important that he
heard from the London art school soon.
CHAPTER SIX
Nina and David talk
David lay in the bath.
He thought about Nina's new job, and about
all of them moving to Newcastle.
He loved working at Julie's and he was
sorry to leave it.
And Max liked his school.
But Nina was important too.
David knew she was wonderful at her job.
He got out of the bath and put on his jeans
and a blue sweater.
He went into Max's bedroom.
His son was asleep.
David sat on his bed for a
few minutes.
Then he gave him a kiss, turned off the light
and left the room.
'Just going to phone Mum and Dad,' David called
to Nina.
'OK.
Remember, don't tell them about my new job,'
said Nina.
'No, I won't,' replied David.
David phoned his father.
'Hi, Dad.
Are you OK?'
'Fine,' replied his father.
'Your mother and I had a lovely walk by the
sea this afternoon.
Anyway, it's good you phoned.
We wanted to
tell you there's something in the post for
you.
For your birthday on Tuesday.
It'll be a surprise, I know, but I hope it's
a good surprise.'
'That sounds interesting,' said David.
'Are you going to tell me anything more about
it?'
'No, you'll have to wait.
Let me just get your mother.
I know she wants to speak to you,' his father
said.
'Joan!'
his father shouted to his mother.
'It's David on the phone.'
'Coming.'
David heard his mother's voice.
And then he heard her say in a quiet voice
to his father, 'Have you told him?' and the
answer,
'No.'
'Hello, David,' said his mother.
'Are we going to see you soon?
Can you come down next weekend?'
'Yes, on Sunday,' said David.
'We can't on Saturday because I'm working,
but Sunday will be fine.'
'Oh good,' replied his mother happily.
'We want to see our lovely grandson again.
We're lucky that you live near so we can see
him quite
often.'
David said something, but all the time he
was thinking, 'How can we tell them that we're
taking him away to Newcastle?'
'I'll give the phone back to your father now.
I know he wants to tell you something about
the garden,' his mother said.
'See you all next
Sunday.'
'Bye, Mum,' David said.
He then listened to his father talking about
some ideas he had for his garden.
David could hear how excited he
was.
His father was only really happy when he was
outside and doing things.
At the end of the conversation his father
said again, 'I hope our surprise for your
birthday is what you want.'
'I'll ring you as soon as I get it,' replied
David.
'Bye for now, Dad.'
David put the phone down and walked into the
living room.
'Everything OK?' asked Nina.
'Yes, fine,' said David.
'I said we'll go down to see them next Sunday
for the day.
That's OK, isn't it?'
'Sure.'
Nina saw the look on David's face.
'Mum said how she loved having Max so near,'
said David, 'and I felt bad.
They're getting older and they'll be so sad
when we tell them
about Newcastle.'
'Oh, David, I know, but they'll want us to
do the right thing for us - as a family,'
replied Nina.
'But now I really don't know if it is the
right thing any more,' said David quietly.
They talked for hours and the questions were
always the same: 'Is it right for us to go
to Newcastle?', 'Do we ask your parents to
go with
us?', 'Do we forget about the new job and
stay in Bath?'
And then there was a new idea: maybe David
and Max could stay in Bath and Nina could
go to Newcastle for the week and come home
every
weekend.
But how could David look after Max and work
in the restaurant?
In the end they agreed.
It was the same as their earlier decision.
Newcastle in June for all the family.
'It'll be OK, won't it?' asked Nina.
'I hope so, love,' replied David.
'I really hope so.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
Maggie's visitor
Belen gave Xavier's email back to Maggie.
'That's very strange,' she said.
'Maybe he's done something wrong - perhaps
the police are after him or something.'
'No, not Xavier,' said Maggie.
'Why not, Maggie?'
answered Belen.
'I mean, we were only in Chile for three weeks.
How well do we know him?
Have you had any other emails
or letters from him?'
'Yes, an earlier email, but it didn't say
anything about coming to England,' replied
Maggie.
'Oh well, there's nothing you can do - just
wait for the letter and hope it's nothing
bad,' said Belen.
'I've just remembered something.
Do you mind if I make a quick call?' asked
Maggie.
'Someone phoned me just before you arrived,
but they
didn't leave a message.'
'Go ahead,' said Belen.
'I'll go into the kitchen.'
'No, no problem,' answered Maggie.
'Stay.
I won't be a minute.
Then we can eat.'
Maggie rang the mobile number.
'Hello,' said a foreign voice.
It was a man.
'Oh hello,' said Maggie.
'You called this number earlier - Bath 726549.
Who are you?'
'I'm sorry,' answered the man.
'It was a wrong number.'
'Oh, OK.
Bye then,' said Maggie and put the phone down.
'Wrong number.'
Maggie turned to Belen.
'Someone with a Spanish-sounding voice, I
think.'
'From Chile, perhaps?' asked Belen.
'Maybe,' said Maggie.
'Anyway, it's not important.
Let's go into the kitchen and have dinner.'
Maggie and Belen ate the lasagne.
They looked at photos from their holiday and
laughed at some of the things they remembered.
There was a noise from the living room and
they both jumped.
'It's OK.'
Maggie laughed.
'It's only the window.
When it's windy, it always makes a noise.'
But then there was another, different noise.
Someone was at the front door.
'What a bad time to call,' said Maggie.
She walked to the front door.
When she opened it, she saw a man.
'Yes?'
she asked.
'Can I help you?'
'Are you Maggie Cox?' asked the man.
'Yes,' answered Maggie.
'And who...'
But she didn't finish her question.
The man came into the house and closed the
door behind him.
'Excuse me!' said Maggie angrily.
'What are you doing?
Who are you?'
Belen heard her shouting and came out of the
kitchen.
'Sit down, both of you,' said the man quietly.
'I don't want to hurt you.'
Belen and Maggie sat together on the sofa.
'I'm looking for a friend of yours - Xavier
Santos,' said the man.
'He's not here,' said Maggie and Belen at
the same time.
'Who are you?' asked Maggie.
'Let's just say I'm a friend of the Santos
family,' answered the man.
'I know he's in England, and I want to talk
to him.'
'I haven't heard from him since we got back
from Chile,' said Maggie quickly.
'Really?' said the man.
He walked round the room and looked at everything
- postcards from friends on holiday, the phone
bill that was on
top of the TV.
Then Maggie remembered Xavier's email - it
was on the table next to her.
It was too late to move it.
The man saw it.
'So this is from another Xavier, is it?
Where's the letter he talks about in the email?'
asked the man.
'I haven't had it yet,' said Maggie.
She was afraid and she could feel Belen was
too.
She didn't understand what the man was doing
in her
house.
'How did you know where I live?' asked Maggie.
'I found your address in Xavier's home,' said
the man.
'And your photo.
Did you have a good time in my country, Maggie?'
Maggie didn't answer the question.
She asked, but half of her didn't want to
know, 'Why are you looking for Xavier?'
'He's got something that I want,' said the
man.
'But maybe he gave it to you to bring back
to England.'
The man walked up to Maggie and
stood very close.
'He didn't give me anything,' said Maggie.
'Maybe he didn't, but I know that Xavier will
come here soon.
And when he does, I'll be ready for him.'
The man looked hard at Maggie.
'You did a bad thing, Maggie, when you chose
Xavier,' said the man.
'He's not right for a nice girl like you.'
He moved away.
'Remember, Maggie, I'll come back.'
Belen and Maggie jumped up when the man left.
'You must phone the police, Maggie,' said
Belen.
'This is terrible.
You must come home with
me.
You're not safe here.'
Maggie phoned and told the police everything.
She told them, 'I'm not going to stay here.
I'm going to stay with a friend tonight.
You can
call me on my mobile, 04776 567831.'
The police asked her to go to the police station
the next day.
Maggie put some things in a bag, ready to
leave with Belen.
'I'm so stupid,' said Maggie.
'I thought Xavier was really nice.
I believed he loved me, but he was just playing.'
Maggie and Belen called a taxi and left Moreland
Road half an hour later.
CHAPTER EIGHT
What Sam didn't know
'How am I going to find 700 pounds?'
thought Sam that Friday evening.
'And why didn't I tell Hannah about Jeremy?'
But it was too late now.
Emma was going to Norway.
'That's so great, Dad!
Thank you,' she said and kissed him.
It made Sam happy to see
her so excited.
'I know what I'll do,' thought Sam sadly.
'On Monday morning I'll take some of the jewellery
my mother gave me before she died.
There's a
jeweller's shop on the way to work.
I'm sure they'll be interested in buying diamond
rings.'
Sam didn't want to sell the jewellery.
He knew his mother wanted Emma to have it.
'Maybe my brother is right,' he thought.
'I do need a job with better money.
I don't know how much longer we can go on
like this.'
That Friday morning, six hundred kilometres
away in the city of Edinburgh, something important
happened that could change Sam's life.
But
Sam knew nothing about it.
Two people, a man and a woman, arrived at
the offices of lawyers Barrett, Grabbe and
Lennox.
A man took the two visitors upstairs to the
office of Frank Barrett.
It was a very old-fashioned place with big,
dark wood furniture.
There were hundreds of law books all around
the room.
'Good morning,' said Mr Barrett to the visitors.
'It's Paul and Sonia Cooper, isn't it?
Please sit down.'
'Thank you,' said Sonia and sat down next
to her brother, Paul.
'I'm sorry about your father,' said Mr Barrett.
'We looked after his business for years here.'
'Thank you,' said Paul.
'He was ninety-one when he died.
But now we need to know what he decided to
do with his money and things.'
'Paul!' said Sonia.
'That sounds terrible!'
'It's OK,' said Mr Barrett.
'Let me tell you what he wrote in his will.'
Mr Barrett didn't always enjoy reading a will
to a family.
Sometimes there were surprises in it that
they didn't like.
'I leave my house and all that is in the house
to my two children, Paul and Sonia.
My money I give to my grandchildren, Robert,
Amy and
Charlie.'
Paul and Sonia looked pleased.
He continued, 'But not all of it.'
Their smiles became smaller.
'I want to leave some of my money to a special
person who was a good friend to me in my life
- Samuel Davies.
'About thirty years ago, when my wife died,
Sam lived next door to me.
He was a young man, but he spent many hours
with me at that time.
He visited me most days and listened to me
when I talked about my wife.
He was a true friend.
I have never forgotten how kind he was.
I want to say thank you to him and to give
him 50,000 pounds.'
A few minutes later, Mr Barrett finished reading
and the office was quiet.
Then Paul Cooper said, 'Samuel Davies is a
lucky man - 50,000
pounds is a lot of money, just for talking
to Dad.'
And Sonia said, 'I don't remember him.
Well, that's what Dad wanted to do, and it's
his money, so that's that.
We can't change anything.
But how much will there be for the grandchildren
- Paul's children?'
'I'm not sure yet.
We'll have to wait and see,' said Mr Barrett.
'We have to let Samuel Davies know.
It could take quite a long time - you
know, the address your father gave us could
be wrong now.
But I'll write to you as soon as I know.'
'But if you don't find him, what happens to
the money?' asked Sonia.
'Oh, I'm sure we'll find him.
It could take months, but we usually find
people in the end,' replied Mr Barrett.
Paul and Sonia left the lawyer's office quietly.
Mr Barrett gave some papers to his secretary
and she wrote a letter to Samuel Davies.
At
lunchtime she took the letter to the post
office.
As she put it in the post box, she thought,
'Lucky Samuel Davies.
What's he going to do with 50,000 pounds?'
Back in Bath that Friday evening, of course
Sam had no idea about Mr Cooper and his money.
He went to bed unhappy.
Was it right to sell
his mother's jewellery?
And what job could a man his age get that
paid more money?
CHAPTER NINE
Fire!
At three-thirty on the morning of Saturday
15th March, a small fire started in a van
at the back of the mail depot in Bath.
Nobody saw it
at first because everyone was inside the building.
Then someone smelled something and shouted,
'Fire!'
Another person ran outside and saw what was
happening.
Someone else phoned the fire
service.
They tried to put out the fire, but they couldn't.
The fire service arrived very quickly and
put out the fire.
But two big bags of letters were lost.
In those bags were four very important
letters for some people in Moreland Road.
St Martin's School of Art
Charing Cross Road
London W1 8XA
Jason Campbell
12 Moreland Road
Bath BA6 5LZ
13th March
Dear Jason
Thank you for coming to see us last week.
We really like your work and we think that
you are the kind of student who will do well
here at
our college.
We are very happy to offer you a place here
from September.
As you know, there are many students who want
to come to this art school.
So
it is important that you reply to us.
Please tick (V) the box below and return the
letter to the above address by 25th March.
We look forward to hearing from you soon.
Yours sincerely
Neil Parker (Course Tutor)
( ) Yes, I can take a place on the art course,
starting in September.
( ) No, I cannot take a place on the art course,
120 Wharf Road
Exeter
13th March
Dear David
First of all, Happy Birthday!
We hope you have a really lovely day.
We've been thinking about our future and we
want to do something with our money.
We have enough for ourselves, so we've decided
to spend
some.
We know how hard you work at Julie's and we
know that you've always wanted it to be yours.
So we've bought it for you.
We met Jean-Pierre last month and agreed a
price.
Yesterday we heard that it's now ours - well,
yours actually.
We both know that you're going to make the
restaurant better than ever.
Can we come to dinner on your first big night?
Lots of love to our wonderful son
Mum and Dad
Santiago, 6th March
Dear Maggie
Hope you got my email.
And I hope this letter won't make you angry.
I'm coming to England because I must leave
Chile.
I haven't done anything wrong, but my brother
has.
He's in with some bad people.
My
brother has disappeared - nobody knows where
he is.
His 'friends' think I've got some of his papers,
but I haven't.
So I want to come to England and get away
from all these problems.
Maybe I can get a job and stay there for a
bit.
Also I want to see you.
I think we're at the beginning of an exciting
time together.
I'll be with you very soon.
Until then please believe me that I HAVE DONE
NOTHING WRONG.
Please email me and tell me I can come.
Lots of love and kisses
Xavier
Barrett, Grabbe and Lennox
34 Queen Street
Edinburgh EH2 3XJ
Samuel Davies
56 Moreland Street
Bath
BA6 5LX
14th March
Dear Mr Davies
We are writing about Mr Thomas Cooper, who
has sadly died.
Mr Cooper has remembered you in his will and
we would be grateful if you could
write to this office as soon as possible.
Yours sincerely
Frank Barrett
Conclusion
And what happened to Jason, David and Nina,
Maggie and the Davies family?
Jason went away for two weeks to stay with
his grandmother.
She looked after him and he began to feel
better about himself.
When he got
back to Bath he was sad that there was still
no letter from the art school in London.
He phoned the school, but it was too late.
The school said he could have a place the
next year.
For a year, Jason stayed in Bath and did lots
of different jobs.
Simon, his father, came
to the house sometimes and Jason began, slowly
and carefully, to get to know him.
Nina's letter to the head office of the bank
arrived safely.
David never got the letter from his parents,
but his mum and dad phoned him
on his birthday and he learnt about the restaurant.
It was the best birthday present in the world.
Nina decided to work in Newcastle and come
home at the weekends.
They were lucky because David's niece came
to study at Bath University.
She stayed with them and looked after
Max.
But it wasn't easy for the family.
David wanted Nina to come home and work with
him in the restaurant, but she stayed at the
bank in Newcastle for eighteen months.
Then she took the job of area manager in Bristol
- a city twenty-five kilometres from Bath.
Maggie never heard from the Chilean visitor
again.
She never heard from Xavier again either,
and he never arrived in England.
Maggie was
very sad.
She really thought that she and Xavier were
great together.
It was hard for her.
She wanted to believe that he was a good person,
but all her friends told her to forget him.
Sometimes she thought about going back to
Chile to find him.
But in the end, she
didn't.
She decided that probably it was just a holiday
romance for him after all.
Sam sold his mother's jewellery and gave Emma
the money.
After a few days, he had another conversation
with his brother.
Then he decided
to leave his job at the newspaper and write
a book.
He worked at home so he could look after Alicia
too.
At first, it was strange for him, but slowly
he began to enjoy his new life.
It was exciting to write and Alicia was an
easy child.
Hannah got a good job in a shop, which
she enjoyed.
They were still short of money, but one day
about three months later he got a letter from
Barrett, Grabbe and Lennox.
Life began to look a lot better for Sam and
his family.