CHAPTER ONE
A man with a dream
On a warm, sunny day in June 1957, six
young men stood in Rosebery Street,
Liverpool, and began to play a song.
The band was called The Quarrymen.
They were not famous, and in
1957, they were not very good!
The singer had brown eyes and brown
hair, and his name was John Lennon.
He sang song after song, the
band played, and people danced.
Nobody in the street that
day knew the singer's name.
But he was a man with a dream.
'One day, I'm going to be famous,' he often said.
And he was right.
The Quarrymen slowly became The
Beatles, and seven years later,
they were the world's most famous band.
Before he died, John Lennon wrote and
sang some of the best songs of our time.
But John Lennon was more
than a singer and songwriter.
He talked about love and peace, and
millions of young people listened to him.
He wanted to change the world.
And when a man called Mark Chapman killed him,
far from his Liverpool home,
thousands of people stood and cried.
So how did John Lennon and his band become famous?
Why did people all around the world listen to him?
And why did one man want to
kill him?
CHAPTER TWO
Liverpool boy
John Winston Lennon was born in a
Liverpool hospital on 9 October 1940.
Britain was at war, and John's father Alf worked
on ships, so he was away most of the time.
His mother Julia wanted to leave Alf, and
when John was five, they asked him a question:
did he want to live with his father or his mother?
John did not know.
He cried and went to his father at first, but
when his mother walked away, he ran after her.
He did not see Alf again for nineteen years.
Life was not easy for Julia,
so when John was seven,
he began to live with his mother's sister
- his aunt Mimi - in Woolton, Liverpool.
Mimi loved John, and her husband
George always had time for him.
George read books to John at night,
and John learned to read with him.
They often walked around Woolton, too.
There was a big house called
Strawberry Field near Mimi's house,
and John liked to visit the gardens there.
Years later, Strawberry Fields Forever
became one of his most famous songs.
John visited his mother Julia a lot.
She had two daughters now,
but she loved John very much.
Julia had lots of photos of him in the house,
and she often played a record called My Son John.
Julia listened to the radio all the time, too,
so John heard the new music
from the USA - rock and roll.
Julia sang and played the banjo and, when John
was about eight, he got his first harmonica.
He soon learned to play it very well.
Some of John's friends had pianos at home,
so he learned to play the piano, too.
Then Julia taught him the banjo.
Music was easy for John, and at first,
he was a good student at school, too.
But John could not see
well, and he needed glasses.
Children laughed at his glasses,
so he stopped wearing them.
Because of this, and because he was
not very interested in schoolwork,
he did not do well at high school.
But at home, John did a lot of writing and
beautiful art, and he read lots and lots of books.
These were happy years for John.
He liked to go to the cinema with his
cousins Stanley Parkes and Liela Harvey.
When Stanley's family moved to Scotland, John
and Liela often went there for the summer.
John played his harmonica for hours and hours
on the long drive to Scotland from Liverpool!
One summer, when John was away in
Scotland, Mimi's husband George died.
George was like a second father to John
- but John never cried in front of Mimi.
In 1950s Liverpool, boys did not cry.
At this time, John was becoming
more and more interested in music.
In 1956, a young American rock and roll singer
called Elvis Presley became very famous.
He was an amazing dancer, and
his music was new and exciting.
Elvis had seven songs in the
UK music charts that year.
Suddenly, young people like John wanted to sing
like Elvis, dress like him, and be in a band.
So Julia took John into town
and bought him a guitar.
That summer, John began a skiffle
band with two friends from school.
They were called The Quarrymen, because
their school was called Quarry Bank.
Skiffle was like American
country music, but faster.
Soon, there were six boys in John's band.
They played songs by skiffle
musicians like Lonnie Donegan.
That autumn, The Quarrymen began to do
little concerts, like Saturday night dances.
John was the singer, and
he played the guitar, too.
He always played very hard on his
guitar strings, so he often broke them.
It was John's last year at school,
and he needed to work hard.
Mimi was not happy about the band,
or about his pictures and writing.
Sometimes, she went into his room and took them.
'You're going to be sorry when I'm famous,'
he often told her.
CHAPTER THREE
The Beatles are born
On Saturday 6 July 1957, The Quarry men
played two concerts in Woolton, Liverpool.
A fifteen-year-old boy called Paul
McCartney was in the crowd that day.
He was a friend of one of The Quarrymen,
and he met the band and talked to
John before the second concert.
That day changed their lives.
When Paul met The Quarrymen
between their concerts,
he took one of their guitars and
began playing a rock and roll song.
He was amazing!
John could play the first
four strings of his guitar,
like a four-string banjo, but
Paul could play all six strings.
Paul soon became one of The Quarrymen,
and John quickly learned to play
all six strings on the guitar.
When John left school that summer, he nearly
went and worked on ships like his father.
But with help from a teacher, he got
into the Liverpool College of Art.
Seventeen-year-old John was good at art,
but he did not listen to the teachers.
He often brought his guitar to college,
and he dressed like a rock and roll singer.
Sometimes, John did not go to college.
He met Paul in a cafe and they
talked about books and music.
You could hear great music in the
cafes of Liverpool at that time.
John and Paul listened to American rock
and roll singers like Little Richard and
Buddy Holly, and they learned to play their songs.
Paul liked to write music, and in
1958, John began to write songs, too.
His first song was a love
song called Hello Little Girl.
Early in 1958, John met
Paul's friend George Harrison.
George was three years younger than John,
but he was amazing on the guitar
- so he became a Quarryman, too.
The Quarrymen often met and
played music in Julia's house.
She was always happy when they came,
and she liked to listen to their music.
In July 1958, something changed John's life.
His mother died in a car accident.
John loved his mother very much, but
he never cried in front of his friends.
It was a hard time for John,
but students at his art college,
like Cynthia Powell and Stuart
Sutcliffe, helped him a lot.
Cynthia was John's girlfriend, and
Stuart Sutcliffe was his best friend.
One day, Stuart bought a bass guitar.
He played that bass guitar for hours
every day because he wanted to be in
John's band, but he was not very good.
Stuart was an artist, not a musician.
Many different people played with The
Quarrymen, but slowly the band became John,
Paul, and George on guitars, and
later, Stuart on the bass guitar.
Paul, George, and Stuart were not from Quarry
Bank High School, so the band changed their name.
The Quarrymen became The
Beatals, then The Silver Beetles.
They played in cafes and music
clubs like the Casbah Coffee Club,
but they did not get a lot
of money for their concerts.
There were lots of young bands in Liverpool
- and The Silver Beetles were not the best!
John and Stuart often went to a
cafe called the Jacaranda Club.
The cafe manager, Allan Williams,
knew a lot of bands, and in 1960,
he found work for them in Scotland
with a singer called Johnny Gentle.
The band were very excited about
their first tour, but it was not easy.
They ate and stayed in some very bad
places because they did not have any money.
In the end, Stuart's mother bought
train tickets home for them.
Later, Williams found work for them
in Hamburg, Germany - for more money.
For the first time, they had a drummer.
His name was Pete Best.
They had a new name, too:
The Beatles.
Williams drove them to Germany, and when they
stopped in the Netherlands, John took a harmonica
from a music shop and did not pay for it.
Many years later, John Lennon
fans went to the Netherlands,
found the shop, and paid for that harmonica.
From August to November 1960, The Beatles
played at two different nightclubs in Hamburg.
They stayed in some very bad rooms,
and they played for five, six, or
seven hours every night of the week.
At one of the clubs, they
performed with a Liverpool band,
and they became friends with
the drummer - Ringo Starr.
The bands finished work at 3 a.m., and
then they all went out for breakfast!
The clubs were in the worst streets of Hamburg.
Every night, people threw bottles and chairs
- and sometimes knives - across the room.
It was very, very hard for The
Beatles, but they did not stop playing.
'One day we're going to be famous,'
they thought.
CHAPTER FOUR
Beatlemania
In December 1960, The
Beatles were back in England.
There were only four of them now, because
Stuart Sutcliffe stayed in Hamburg.
Nobody in Liverpool remembered the band.
But when they began to play at a concert
there one night, everyone became very excited.
They moved nearer to the front,
and some people began to scream!
The Beatles' music was
different now, after Hamburg.
It was not skiffle or rock and roll - it was
something new and exciting, and people loved it.
Everyone began to talk about The Beatles.
In April 1961, John, Paul,
George, and Pete played most
nights in clubs all around Liverpool
- and the clubs sold every ticket!
That spring, The Beatles went
back to Hamburg for four months,
and they recorded songs there with
a singer called Tony Sheridan.
Then, in November, they played in a
Liverpool club called the Cavern Club.
It was not a big club, and it
was hot, dark, smoky, and noisy.
But some of the best bands in Liverpool
- and in Britain - played there.
A young man called Brian Epstein
saw The Beatles at the Cavern Club.
Epstein did not often listen to bands, and
he was not a band manager before he met John,
Paul, George, and Pete - he had a record shop.
But he knew a lot about music,
and he loved The Beatles.
He came back and watched the band
many times in the next few weeks.
The Beatles liked him, and
he soon became their manager.
Epstein quickly changed The
Beatles' hair and clothes.
They wore suits now, so they looked different
from most bands, and people remembered them.
Epstein looked for a record
company for The Beatles, too.
Bands become famous because record
companies make and sell their records,
so this was important for The Beatles.
But for a long time, no record
companies were interested.
Then, someone from Decca Records
saw the band and liked them,
so The Beatles performed for the
record company on New Year's Day, 1962.
But they did not play well that day, and
Decca did not want to make their records.
In August 1962, Ringo Starr became The Beatles'
new drummer, and Pete Best left the band.
John married his girlfriend
Cynthia Powell that month, too.
But he did not see his new wife very much:
The Beatles had concerts every night!
That summer, they began to play
at the Cavern Club all the time.
Slowly, more people became
interested in Liverpool music.
TV and magazine reporters from
Europe and the USA visited
the club, and they began to talk
about Liverpool music, or 'Liverpop'.
After a lot of work, Brian Epstein now
had a record company for The Beatles.
Parlophone (EMI) began to record their songs.
In October 1962, The Beatles' first record,
the song Love Me Do, was number
17 in the British music charts.
It was an exciting time for the band.
In February 1963, The Beatles
had their first number one hit
with a John Lennon song, Please Please Me.
Later, there was an album called Please Please Me,
too, and The Beatles recorded
all fourteen songs in one day!
John Lennon was ill that day, and the band
played for ten hours, but he sang amazingly.
Three more of The Beatles'
songs were number one in 1963.
The band became famous because of their
records, and it happened very fast.
In October, they came to London and were on TV.
Fifteen million people watched them on TV, and
thousands of fans waited outside the TV studio.
People screamed and stopped cars in the street.
One reporter called it 'Beatlemania'.
People cried and screamed
at every Beatles concert.
Fans waited outside their hotels, too -
sometimes all night in the cold and rain.
In The Beatles' first film,
A Hard Day's Night, John,
Paul, George, and Ringo run away from their fans.
In Britain, that was their life.
People loved The Beatles
because their songs were great,
and you could easily remember and sing them.
The Beatles were young like their
fans, and they looked good, too.
But The Beatles became famous
because they worked very hard.
They played or recorded seven days a week,
and John and Paul wrote new songs
at night in their hotel rooms.
Between 1960 and 1964, The Beatles performed for
about 1,200 hours - most bands do
not play that much in their lives!
In November 1964, The Beatles
did a big concert in Liverpool.
Thousands of fans were in the streets, and
more people stood in windows and on roofs.
'We want The Beatles!'
people cried, and the noise was amazing.
These four young men from Liverpool were now
Britain's most famous faces.
CHAPTER FIVE
World-famous
In the autumn of 1963, a famous American magazine
laughed at British Beatles fans
for their crying and screaming.
But soon, Beatlemania arrived in the USA.
In February 1964, The Beatles' song I Want to Hold
Your Hand was number one in the American charts.
That month, when The Beatles went to the USA,
five thousand fans waited for
their plane at New York's John F.
Kennedy airport.
On 9 February, 73 million
people watched The Beatles
on the famous Ed Sullivan Show on American TV.
In the New York studio, people screamed
when The Beatles began to play.
Outside, thousands of fans stood
on Broadway and 53rd Street.
No one could get through the streets.
American stars like Elvis
Presley were famous in Britain.
Now, suddenly, Americans loved a British band.
Later, British bands and singers like the Rolling
Stones and Elton John became famous in the USA,
too - but it all began with The
Beatles, that night in New York City.
The Beatles played two concerts on their
first visit to the USA - in Washington, D.C.
and New York City.
But they came back again in
August 1964 for a one-month,
thirty-concert tour of Canada and the USA.
On 23 August 1964, The Beatles performed
at the Hollywood Bowl in Los Angeles.
After the concert, they met some
of Hollywood's rich and famous.
When John was a boy, he watched these film
stars in the Woolton cinema with his cousins.
Now they wanted to meet him!
In the next two years, The Beatles
went on tours to many countries,
and there was Beatlemania around the world.
People nearly died in crowds in the Philippines.
In New Zealand, hundreds of fans stopped The
Beatles' car, and they could not get out.
In Tokyo, the band could not leave their hotel
because there were thousands of fans outside.
So John, Paul, George, and Ringo sat
in their hotel room and made a picture.
Years later, somebody bought it for $155,000!
On their third American tour in 1965, The Beatles
visited Elvis at his house in Los Angeles.
They sat and talked about music, then
they began to play guitar with him.
It was amazing for John,
because Elvis was his hero.
Friends watched while the two greatest names in
music - The Beatles and Elvis - played together!
When The Beatles were not on tour,
they recorded music in London.
Between 1963 and 1965, they made six albums,
and lots of their songs, like Can't Buy Me Love,
A Ticket to Ride, and We Can Work it Out,
were number one in Britain and the USA.
Thousands of people bought the records,
and fans could buy Beatles T-shirts,
guitars, magazines, and lots more things, too.
The Beatles became very rich, and John Lennon
bought a big house and a very expensive car.
The money was great, but
some things were not easy.
The Beatles could not go out for dinner or
go to the shops because fans ran after them,
and they quickly became tired of this.
And they were not happy with their
concerts because people screamed,
and nobody could hear their music.
Some of John and Paul's songs at this
time, like Help, were not happy ones.
Because people loved The Beatles,
they watched them on TV and read
about them in magazines all the time.
But sometimes The Beatles did not
think carefully before they spoke.
In July 1966, John said something to a magazine
reporter, and American fans became
very angry when they read about it.
On The Beatles' fourth tour of the USA,
people broke Beatles records in the
street and protested outside the concerts.
Some people wrote angry letters, too.
'You're going to die,' some of them
said, and Brian Epstein was afraid.
'Is somebody going to shoot John
Lennon?' he thought.
CHAPTER SIX
Family man
In April 1964, a man walked into
Brian Epstein's office and said,
'I'm John Lennon's father.' When John
saw Alf Lennon, he was not happy.
He thought, 'Do I want to meet my
father again after nineteen years?
Why did he go away all those years ago?
Why did he not visit or write?'
John could not forget these things.
He met his father sometimes after that,
but they never became good friends.
John's family life was not easy.
He and Cynthia had a son now, called Julian.
John wanted to be a good father to Julian,
but he did not have much time with his family.
The Beatles were always on tour, or
at the recording studios in London,
so Cynthia and Julian often
did not see John for weeks.
And when he was at home, he worked very hard.
He wrote songs all the time,
and he wrote two books, too.
In the winter of 1966, John met a
Japanese artist called Yoko Ono in London.
They soon became very good friends.
Yoko was seven years older than
John, but she was very like him.
She was an artist and musician, too,
and like John, Yoko had a young
child - a daughter called Kyoko.
John and Cynthia soon broke up, and
after that he was with Yoko all the time.
They made art together, and Yoko came to the
studio when The Beatles recorded their music.
On 20 March 1969, Yoko and
John got married in Gibraltar.
Yoko Ono became Yoko Ono Lennon, and John
later changed his name to John Ono Lennon.
That summer, they bought a beautiful
house called Tittenhurst Park.
Everything in the rooms was white, and they
had a beautiful garden and a recording studio.
Yoko and John were happy there, and they
recorded some amazing songs in the studio.
Julian often came to the house,
and he played with Kyoko.
John and Yoko loved to do
things with the children.
One year, they all went on holiday to Scotland,
because John remembered happy summers
there with his cousins.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Going solo
On 29 August 1966, The Beatles performed
at Candlestick Park, San Francisco.
Twenty-five thousand fans listened to
The Beatles that cold summer evening,
but it was the band's last big concert.
The Beatles did not need to
do concerts and tours now.
They could work in a studio,
and sell millions of records.
They were afraid of the crowds at
concerts, too - some fans got too excited.
A year after the San Francisco
concert, Brian Epstein died.
He was only thirty-two years old.
Epstein was an amazing manager,
and a great friend, too.
It was very hard for The Beatles because
they were musicians, not managers.
They did not manage the band
well after Epstein died.
They began a company called Apple,
but the company lost a lot of money,
and things were not easy between
John, Paul, George, and Ringo.
On a cold winter's day in January 1969, The
Beatles played together for the last time.
They performed for a film on a roof in London.
People stood in the street and listened.
Office workers looked out of windows.
Taxi drivers stopped their cars.
They could not see the people on the
roof, but everybody knew their songs.
In the end, the police came onto the roof
and stopped them, because of the noise!
A year later, the band began to break up.
Many of their fans could not understand it.
But The Beatles all wanted to do different things
now, and they wanted to write different music.
In 1970, all four Beatles made solo albums.
After that, the four of them
never played together again.
John Lennon made eight solo
albums - most of them in the USA.
When John wrote songs for The
Beatles, they were usually about love.
But the songs on his solo albums were often
about the world around him, or about his life.
Some of them are very sad.
His second album, called Imagine, became one
of the most important albums of all time.
1971 was an important year for John and Yoko:
they moved to the USA.
They found a house in Greenwich Village, in
Manhattan, and they were very happy there.
New York in the 1970s was the
most exciting city in the world.
John and Yoko's door was always open,
and they met lots of interesting people.
They knew many of the best artists,
writers, and musicians of their time.
John and Yoko went around the city on bicycles,
and John loved his life there.
CHAPTER EIGHT
War and peace
The day after John and Yoko got married
in 1969, they went to Amsterdam.
It was an interesting week
for a new husband and wife.
For seven days, they sat on their hotel
bed and talked to reporters about peace.
They called their war protest a 'bed-in',
and it was on TV around the world.
At the time, there were wars in many countries,
like Northern Ireland, Nigeria, and Mozambique.
One of the worst wars was in Vietnam:
half a million Americans went and fought
there, and every day, hundreds of people died.
Many people wanted to stop the war.
The second bed-in protest was
in Montreal, Canada in May 1969.
One day, John recorded a song
called Give Peace a Chance.
There were many people in their room that
day - reporters, musicians, and friends.
John played the guitar and sang,
and everyone became the band.
They hit the tables with
their hands and sang with him.
It became the most famous song
of the Vietnam War protest.
On 15 November that year, hundreds of
thousands of people sang Give Peace a
Chance outside the White House in Washington, D.C.
Later that year, John recorded a song
called Happy Christmas (War is Over),
and John and Yoko paid for posters
in ten cities around the world.
The posters said 'WAR IS OVER (if you
want it)' in many different languages.
This was John and Yoko's message to the world.
After John and Yoko moved to the
USA, John talked about peace on TV,
and he went to many protests about
wars and spoke to the crowds.
Millions of young Americans listened to
him, and the government was not happy.
The FBI (government police) began to watch
John, and they listened to his telephone.
In 1972, the government wrote him a letter.
You must leave the country, the letter said.
Yoko and John wanted to stay in the USA, so
they talked to a lawyer called Leon Wildes.
Wildes was not very interested
in John's war protests
or his music, but he worked
very hard for John and Yoko.
It took four years, but in the end, John
Lennon could live freely in the USA.
John liked the work of Gandhi
and Martin Luther King.
These men changed the world, but they did not do
it with guns - they changed it
with love, protests, and peace.
Before John Lennon, rock stars and film
stars did not usually talk about peace,
or changing the world.
Today, people like Bono, Angelina Jolie,
and George Clooney work hard for peace,
and they help thousands of people
around the world.
CHAPTER NINE
A quiet life
9 October 1975 was a very
important day for John and Yoko.
Their son Sean Taro Lennon was born
- on John's thirty-fifth birthday.
When John's first son Julian was born, he did not
see him very much because he was in The Beatles.
This time, he wanted to be a better
father, so he stopped making music.
John became a 'house husband'.
Yoko worked, and John stayed
at home all day with Sean.
They often went out for lunch or dinner, or
shopping, and they played with their cats.
John did everything for Sean,
and he sang to him at night.
Julian sometimes visited them in the USA, too.
Mimi never came to New York,
but John often asked her.
She was afraid of the USA
because many Americans had guns.
John and Yoko now lived in a famous
New York building called The Dakota.
From their windows, you could see the
trees and gardens of Central Park.
John and Yoko took Sean to
Central Park all the time.
New Yorkers often saw them when they walked there.
'Hey, John.
How are you?' people called.
But fans did not run after him.
John loved that.
John did not make any albums for five years,
but he bought records and listened to the
latest music - from glam rock to punk.
He worked on his third book, too, and wrote
lots of letters - to friends, family, and fans.
He did some art, and he made nice dinners at home.
And he learned some Japanese, because
John, Yoko, and Sean went to Japan in 1977.
They stayed there all summer, and John and
Sean met Yoko's family for the first time.
The Lennon's usually lived
in their home in The Dakota,
but they had a beautiful house
near the sea on Long Island, too.
John learned to sail there, and he loved it.
In June 1980, John sailed from Rhode
Island to Bermuda with some friends.
At first, everything went well.
But then some very bad Atlantic weather hit them.
Some of John's friends became ill, so
for hours, John did all the sailing.
He was afraid, but he stood out
there in the rain and sang songs.
Sean and Yoko met John and his friends
when they arrived in Hamilton, Bermuda,
and John stayed there with Sean for two months.
He began to work on a new album, and he wrote
some great songs, like Woman and Beautiful Boy.
Then, one day, he saw a beautiful
flower in the gardens in Hamilton.
It was called 'Double Fantasy',
and John loved the name.
When he went back to New York, John wanted
to record an album called Double Fantasy.
John was excited about music again,
and he began to record new songs.
One day that autumn, John and Yoko
were in the recording studio all night.
In the morning, they heard
John's first new record,
the song (Just Like) Starting Over, on the radio.
They were very happy, and they danced
around the room!
CHAPTER TEN
Dead heroes
On 9 October 1980, Sean and John had
their fifth and fortieth birthdays.
Fans waited outside The Dakota, and at 5 p.m.,
they looked up and saw planes in the sky.
The planes wrote a message:
'Happy Birthday John and Sean - love Yoko.'
Eight thousand kilometres away in Hawaii,
it was eleven o'clock in the morning,
and a man called Mark David Chapman
could hear something in his head:
'Kill someone famous!'
Two weeks after John's birthday,
Chapman bought a gun, got a plane to
New York City and visited The Dakota.
But he could not buy bullets for his
gun in New York City, so he left.
On 5 December, John talked to a reporter from a
music magazine about the film star James Dean.
James Dean died very young, and
he became a hero for young people.
'I don't want to be a dead hero,' John said.
The next day, Mark Chapman
came back to New York City.
This time, he had bullets.
On Monday 8 December 1980, John and
Yoko left The Dakota at around 5 p.m.
Chapman came up to them.
He had John's new Double Fantasy
album, and John wrote on it for him.
John and Yoko worked in the recording
studio that evening, and John phoned Mimi.
At about 10.45 p.m., John and Yoko came back home.
Their driver often drove the car into
The Dakota, but it was a nice evening,
so this time he stopped outside in the street.
John and Yoko got out of the ear.
Chapman was in the street
near the door of The Dakota.
He took out his gun and
shot John Lennon four times.
Then he sat and waited for the police.
An ambulance arrived very quickly,
and took John to Roosevelt Hospital,
but he was dead when he arrived there.
Soon, TV across the USA and the world told people:
'John Lennon is dead.'
Crowds of people came to The Dakota.
'He's not dead!
It's not true!'
one girl cried.
But it was.
The next Sunday in Liverpool, thousands
of people stood in the streets.
They remembered their city's dead
hero, and they listened to his songs.
Across the Atlantic in New York City's Central
Park, a crowd of 150,000 people stood in the cold.
Some quietly cried.
Some sang John Lennon's songs.
They had photos of John and big messages.
'Why?' read one message.
'We'll never forget you,' read another.
And they did not.
New York City was John's second
home, and now there is a place
in Central Park called Strawberry
Fields, like John's famous song.
It is a quiet place, and
people sit there and think.
There is a memorial at Strawberry Fields,
too - a circle with the word 'Imagine' in it.
People leave flowers on the circle, and
sometimes people leave their guitars.
Every year on 8 December,
people meet in Central Park.
They remember John's life,
and they sing his songs.
Thousands came in 2010, thirty years
after he died.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Remembering John Lennon
There are many John Lennon statues and
John Lennon memorials around the world.
One of the best statues is near
the old Cavern Club in Liverpool.
It is John when he was a young Beatle.
He is standing next to a building with his hands
in his pockets - a young man with a big dream.
The year after John died,
George Harrison wrote a song about his old
friend, and George, Paul, and Ringo recorded it.
Later, Paul McCartney remembered
John in his song Here Today.
There were songs by bands and singers like
the Cranberries, Queen, and Elton John, too.
Paul, George, and Ringo all became solo
musicians after The Beatles broke up,
and they all performed at
concerts around the world.
Paul McCartney became one of the
greatest British singers of his time.
George Harrison died in 2001, but Paul
and Ringo never stopped performing.
Julian and Sean Lennon became
musicians like their father.
They want to make the world a better place,
and they do a lot of important work
and help many different people.
Yoko Ono finished John Lennon's last album
after he died, and his last book, too.
She became an important artist,
musician, and peace worker.
She never left The Dakota:
she stayed there because she wanted to
remember all the good times there with him.
After John died, many fans wanted to
buy some of his things, like letters,
or albums with his writing on them.
In 1982, someone bought his car for $2.23 million!
But most people want to
remember the man and his music.
There are lots of books, magazines,
and films about John Lennon, and two hundred
thousand people buy his albums every year.
When many people think about John
Lennon, they remember his song Imagine.
It became one of the most
important songs of all time,
but it was John Lennon's
message to the world, too.
Imagine is a song about living together -
in a world without hungry people and war.
In the video for Imagine, John is
sitting at a white piano in a white room,
but the shutters on the windows are closed.
Then Yoko opens the shutters, the summer
sun comes into the room, and John sings.
He sings of his dream, and it is a beautiful one:
a dream of a better world for everyone.