CHAPTER ONE
Young Davy
Davy Crockett was born on August 17, 1787,
in Greene County, Tennessee. In 1787 America
was a new nation. Most of the territory was
a wilderness.
Davy Crockett was born in the wilderness.
His father, John Crockett, was an Irish immigrant.
He fought in the American Revolution. He was
a very courageous man.
Davy had a difficult childhood. His family
was poor. When he was twelve years old, his
father said, "Davy, our family doesn't have
any money. You must go to work as a cattle
herder."
"All right, father," said Davy. "I'm happy
to help the family!"
Davy travelled four hundred miles on foot.
He took cattle from Tennessee to other places.
When he finished his work, he was far from
home. He was lost! Davy walked 400 miles.
When he returned home, he was very tired.
Davy gave his father the money he made. His
father was happy and said, "Thank you, Davy!
Now we have some money for the winter months."
"I can do it again to help the family," Davy
answered.
The years passed. Davy went to school when
he had time. He spent most of his time hunting
in the forest. He was the best shooter and
hunter in Tennessee. He entered many shooting
competitions and won them all. He called his
rifle "Old Betsy."
For years Davy hunted bears and other wild
animals. He was a trapper. Once he hunted
one hundred bears in six months!
It was dangerous to hunt bears hut Davy was
very courageous and strong. He knew the forest
well. The Indians were his good friends. He
ran fast and was a strong fighter. He fought
with the wild cats of the mountains.
Some people said that one day Davy saw a racoon
in a tree. He wanted to shoot it but the racoon
saw him and said, "Wait a minute! Are you
Davy Crockett?"
Davy answered, "Yes, I am!"
The racoon answered, "Then don't shoot! I'll
come down from the tree." And the racoon came
down from the tree!
CHAPTER TWO
The Creek Ware
Everyone liked Davy Crockett. He was always
happy, with a big smile. He was honest and
always helped others.
Davy was a tall man. He wore a coonskin cap,
buckskin trousers and a buckskin jacket. He
always carried his long rifle, "Old Betsy."
In 1806 Davy married Polly Finley.
She was a school teacher.
They had two sons and a daughter: John, Joseph
and Judith. After a few years, the Crockett
family moved into the Tennessee hills. The
Tennessee hills were near hostile Indian country.
In 1812 the war between the United States
and Britain began. The Mohawk and Creek Indians
fought with the British against the Americans.
The American General Andrew Jackson organized
a small army. He wanted to fight the Creek
Indians and the British.
Davy fought with this army. He was a scout
because he knew the territory well. His work
as a scout was very important. Davy travelled
across Tennessee, the Mississippi Territory,
Florida and Louisiana with General Jackson's
army. The Battle of New Orleans was a big
victory for General Jackson and the Americans.
The war ended in 1814.
The British lost the war. The Indians lost
their territories and went away. New American
families settled in the Tennessee hills.
At the end of the war Davy returned home to
his family. Unfortunately, his wife Polly
died. Life was again difficult for Davy. He
worked as a trapper and took care of his three
children.
After some time, Davy met Meg Mackinack. Meg's
father was an American trapper. Her mother
was a Cherokee Indian. Davy fell in love and
married her. They had twins. Davy named the
twins George and Washington, in honour of
America's first president. There were now
five children in the Crockett family!
CHAPTER THREE
Davy Enters Politics
Davy and his big family wanted to live in
Lawrenceburg, Tennessee. Davy bought a covered
wagon. He and his family put all of their
things inside the wagon: chairs, tables, beds,
clothing and many other things. Four strong
horses pulled the big wagon. Davy and his
wife sat in the front. The five children were
inside the wagon.
After travelling in the forests and mountains,
they arrived in Lawrenceburg. This was their
new home. Davy opened a mill. He was a hard
worker. His neighbours liked him. Everybody
in Lawrenceburg liked him.
He became a representative of the town government.
He was very popular. People liked listening
to his stories about hunting bears and about
the War of 1812. They admired his honesty
and courage.
Davy was different from other politicians.
His speeches were never boring. His message
was clear. He spoke to the people in simple
language. He dressed like them too. He always
wore his coonskin cap and his buckskin trousers
and jacket.
One day at an important meeting he didn't
know what to say. So he looked at the people
and said, "Today, I am like a man trying to
drink water from an empty barrel! I'll tell
you a funny story and then we can go home!"
Davy soon became a representative of the government
of Tennessee. Now he was in politics. He helped
his people in many ways.
At first, many politicians laughed at Davy
because he never wore a suit. After some time,
these politicians admired and respected him.
Davy was an honest man. Everyone believed
what he said.
His buckskin jacket had two big pockets. In
his right pocket Davy had a bottle of whisky.
When he met his friends, he gave them some
whisky! In those days, it was common to give
some whisky to friends.
CHAPTER FOUR
Congressman Crockett
Davy often went to Nashville, the capital
of Tennessee. In Nashville, he worked for
the Tennessee Government. One day, while Davy
was working for the Tennessee Government,
a big flood destroyed his mill. This was terrible!
He was very unhappy because he lost a lot
of money.
When he returned to Lawrenceburg, he started
a new type of work. This time he made barrels!
He sold these barrels in New Orleans, Louisiana.
New Orleans was about 400 miles away.
To go to New Orleans, he travelled on the
Mississippi River. He had a big boat to carry
the barrels. It was difficult to travel on
the Mississippi River. There were many dangers.
One day his boat had a bad accident. It began
to sink. Davy almost drowned. He lost his
boat and his barrels but he didn't lose his
life!
In 1827 there was a big election in Tennessee.
Davy Crockett became a United States Congressman!
This was a great honour for him. In the United
States Congress, he represented the people
of Tennessee. He travelled to Washington D.
C., the capital of the United States.
Davy was very happy to be a Congressman. He
wanted to help his people. There were Congressmen
who wanted to take land away from the Fox
Indians of Tennessee. Davy protected these
Indians. He fought against dishonest Congressmen.
"The Fox Indians cannot live without their
land!" Davy shouted. "I must defend all the
American people of Tennessee: the whites and
the Indians!"
After months of hard work, Davy was not able
to help the Fox Indians. The U. S. Congress
made a law that took away land from the Indians.
Davy was very angry. He hated injustice. In
1835 he left the U. S. Congress!
CHAPTER FIVE
Texas!
In 1835 the Crockett family left Tennessee.
They put all their things in a big covered
wagon and they travelled for many days. They
finally arrived in Texas.
At that time, Texas belonged to Mexico. At
first, the Mexican Government was happy with
the American settlers. They cultivated the
land.
Many settlers went to Texas because land was
very cheap. With a little money, a settler
bought a lot of land. More and more Americans
went to Texas. There were about 20,000 American
settlers in eastern Texas. There were only
5,000 Mexicans! The Mexican Government did
not like this. There were too many Americans!
Mexico decided to close its borders. The American
settlers were very angry.
In 1834, the Mexican General Santa Anna became
the dictator of Mexico. He was a cruel man.
He sent his soldiers to the Mexican border.
He did not want American settlers to enter
Mexico.
By 1834, there were more than 30,000 Americans
living in Texas. They wanted Texas to be an
independent American state! They did not want
to live under a cruel Mexican dictator.
Davy and his family now lived in Texas. They
were happy in their new home. They wanted
the independence of Texas, too.
One day Davy heard that the Mexicans wanted
to attack Fort Alamo. The Alamo was a Spanish
church and fort near San Antonio, in western
Texas. There were Texans and American soldiers
at Fort Alamo. There were also women and children
at the fort. War was in the air! Davy knew
he must fight for the independence of Texas.
CHAPTER SIX
Fort Alamo
Davy asked other American settlers to go to
the Alamo with him. Few men wanted to fight.
But this did not stop Davy! He and 15 men
decided to go to the Alamo. They were ready
to fight the Mexicans.
There were 112 men at the Alamo. Colonel William
Travis of the U.S. Army was the commander.
William Travis was a young colonel. He was
only 27 years old. He was a lawyer. He entered
the U.S. Army to fight for the independence
of Texas. One day, Colonel Jim Bowie and 30
men arrived at the fort. Jim Bowie was a tall,
strong man. He was a hunter and trapper.
"Good evening, Colonel Travis," said Colonel
Bowie. "I have a message for you from General
Sam Houston. Here is the letter."
Colonel Travis opened it. He read it aloud:
You must destroy the Alamo and come with my
army! General Santa Anna will attack the Alamo
soon.
Gen. Sam Houston
"What!" said Colonel Travis. "I don't want
to destroy the Alamo. I want to defend it."
Colonel Bowie said, "We cannot defend the
Alamo. We must have more men."
In February 1836, Davy Crockett and his men
arrived at the fort. Colonel Travis was happy
to see them. He asked Davy and his men to
defend the Alamo.
"We don't have many men," said Colonel Travis.
"We must ask for more soldiers. I am sending
a messenger to General Fannin. He can send
us more soldiers."
Davy said, "My men and I want to defend the
Alamo. We are hunters and trappers. Our long
rifles can shoot at a great distance."
Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie became good friends.
Together they repaired the walls of the fort.
They cleaned the rifles and the cannons. They
were ready for the battle.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Red Flag
One morning a messenger arrived. "I have a
message from General Fannin: He is very sorry.
He cannot send any soldiers. You must leave
the Alamo now. General Santa Anna is near.
You are all in danger."
"We don't want to leave the Alamo," said Jim
Bowie. "We want to fight for the independence
of Texas. How many soldiers has General Santa
Anna got?"
"He's got about 4,000 soldiers!" said the
messenger.
Colonel Bowie looked at Colonel Travis. "We
must speak to our men," said Colonel Travis.
"Yes," said Bowie, "we must speak to them."
Colonel Travis called his 187 men. He said
sadly, "General Santa Anna is coming to attack
us. He has about 4,000 soldiers and lots of
ammunition. We have only 187 men and little
ammunition. We have little food and water.
Remember, there are women and children in
the fort."
Then he marked a line on the ground with his
sword. "Those who want to fight for the independence
of Texas, cross this line! The others can
leave the fort and go home."
There was a very long silence. Davy thought
about his wife and his five children. Then
he thought about the independence of Texas
and the American settlers. He thought about
a new American state: Texas!
All the men crossed the line. These men wanted
to defend the Alamo. These men wanted an independent
Texas.
On February 23, 1836, General Santa Anna and
his army arrived. He sent a messenger to the
Alamo. He wanted the people in the Alamo to
leave. The men in the Alamo answered with
a cannon shot! They did not want to leave.
They did not want to return to the United
States. General Santa Anna was furious. He
showed a red flag. The red flag meant: No
Prisoners! He wanted to kill everyone in the
fort!
On February 24, 1836, General Santa Anna's
army attacked the Alamo. The Mexicans had
an enormous cannon. It shot a cannon ball
that damaged a wall of the fort.
Davy said, "We must destroy that cannon. It
can destroy the walls of our fort."
That night, Davy and Jim Bowie left the fort.
They went to the Mexican camp. Everyone in
the camp was sleeping. Davy and Jim silently
passed behind the two Mexican guards. They
put mud and stones in the enormous cannon.
Then they returned to the Alamo.
The next morning, the Mexican army used the
cannon. It exploded! The Mexicans were very
surprised. Their enormous cannon was destroyed.
The men in the Alamo killed many Mexican soldiers.
The Mexican army attacked many times during
the day. But the Texans and the American army
defended the Alamo.
CHAPTER EIGHT
The Massacre
The days passed. The battle continued. There
was little food and ammunition. The men in
the Alamo fought courageously. Nothing stopped
them!
After twelve days of fighting, General Santa
Anna sent all of his army to attack the fort.
On March 6, at 5 a.m., the Mexican bugles
played the "Deguello." The "Deguello" was
a war song. It meant "Death for everyone."
The women and children at the fort were tired
and afraid. The situation was desperate.
The men at the Alamo heard the "Deguello."
They understood the message. General Santa
Anna's army attacked the fort from all sides.
It was a terrible battle. Everyone was shooting.
Cannon balls were flying. A lot of men were
injured. Some men were killed. Davy and the
other men defended the fort. They sent back
the Mexicans twice.
The third time, the Mexicans entered the fort.
They killed many people: men, women and children.
It was a massacre!
Jim Bowie was a great fighter. He was a strong
man and he was never afraid. He fought with
his famous Bowie knife. He killed many Mexican
soldiers. At the end of the day, three Mexican
soldiers killed Jim Bowie.
Davy and the other men fought until the end.
They killed many enemy soldiers. It was a
desperate battle. Four Mexican soldiers killed
Davy with a long knife. The tall, courageous
trapper fell to the ground!
Only two women and two children were alive
after the massacre. But General Santa Anna
did not kill them. These women and children
returned home.
The Mexicans burnt the bodies of the dead
people. It was a big victory for General Santa
Anna. He lost 1,544 men at the Alamo.
On April 21, 1836, General Sam Houston and
his army attacked General Santa Anna. General
Houston made General Santa Anna prisoner.
Santa Anna then signed a treaty. This treaty
said that Texas was independent! Everyone
remembered
Davy Crockett, Jim Bowie, Colonel Travis and
the other men. They died for the independence
of Texas. Texas became a state of the United
States in 1845.
All through his life, Davy Crockett did what
he believed was right. With his honesty and
determination, he became a national hero.
Davy Crockett was the perfect example of the
American free spirit. In his life story Davy
wrote, "I leave this rule for others when
I'm dead:
Always be sure you're right-then go ahead!"
- THE END -