CHAPTER ONE
The Minstrel
One cold winter evening King Arthur and his
knights were sitting at the Round
Table in the castle of Camelot.
Suddenly a tall young man
came into the great hall.
He had dark hair and dark, sad eyes.
His clothes were old but clean.
He had a harp under his arm.
'Welcome to Camelot, young man,' said King Arthur.
'Are you a minstrel?'
'Yes, your majesty, I am,' said the young man.
'Where are you from?' asked King Arthur.
'I'm from Cornwall,' answered the minstrel.
'Well,' said King Arthur, 'we
like minstrels and their stories.
Tell us a good story about brave
knights and lovely ladies.'
'Do you know the story of Sir Tristan
of Lyonesse?' asked one of the knights.
'Yes, I do,' answered the minstrel.
'Sir Tristan is a brave knight,
but his story is very sad.'
'Sit down and tell us,' said King Arthur.
Everyone in the hall was interested in
the story of Sir Tristan of Lyonesse.
The minstrel sat on a stool and started
telling his story to the king and his knights.
Sometimes he spoke and sometimes
he sang and played his harp.
This is the story he told:
For many years there were wars
between Cornwall and Ireland.
The Irish often sailed across the
sea to Cornwall and attacked it.
There were terrible battles and many people died.
King Mark of Cornwall wanted
peace but the Irish did not.
He didn't know what to do.
One day he asked his cousin King
Rivalin of Lyonesse for help.
'Help me fight the Irish and you can marry my
beautiful sister,' said King Mark to his cousin.
'The Irish are my enemies too,' said King Rivalin.
'I'll help you fight them.
Together we can win, and I'll
marry your beautiful sister.'
King Rivalin and King Mark fought together
and won the war against the Irish.
King Rivalin married King Mark's sister and
they returned to his castle in Lyonesse.
They loved each other and
were very happy together.
But their happiness did not continue for long.
A year later King Rivalin was killed in battle.
At the same time the queen had
a son, but she died soon after.
Before dying she called her servant, Rual.
'Rual, I'm dying,' said
the young, beautiful queen.
'Take my child and call him Tristan.
His name means sadness.
It comes from the French word "triste".
Look after him and love him like a son.
And when he is a man he must go and
meet my brother, King Mark of Cornwall.
He will help him.'
Rual and his wife loved little
Tristan and they looked after him.
He became a strong, brave boy.
He learned to use a sword, a
spear, and to ride a horse.
He also learned to play the
harp and speak other languages.
When Tristan became a man he left Lyonesse and
went to Cornwall to meet his uncle, King Mark.
The king lived in a big castle in Tintagel.
Tristan entered the great hall of the
castle and saw his uncle for the first time.
'Your majesty, I'm your
nephew Tristan from Lyonesse.'
'My nephew, Tristan - my sister's son!'
said King Mark, looking at the tall young man.
'Welcome to Tintagel! This is your new home.
I'm very happy you're here.
My knights and I will teach you many
things and you'll become a great knight.'
Everyone welcomed Tristan to the castle.
He was happy with his uncle,
who loved him like a son.
He became a famous knight
and fought in many battles.
The people of Cornwall knew about
his great courage and liked him.
But some of the knights and nobles were jealous of
him because he was King Mark's favourite knight.
One day Sir Morholt from
Ireland came to Tintagel Castle.
He was a gigantic man with a
dark face and strong hands.
'King Gurman of Ireland sent me
here,' he said in a loud voice.
'He wants a tribute from you, King Mark.'
'A tribute?' said King Mark, surprised.
'Yes, a tribute!'
said Sir Morholt.
'If you send a tribute, King
Gurman won't attack Cornwall.'
'What is the tribute?' asked King Mark.
'You must send him thirty noble
boys who will become his servants.'
'What!'
cried King Mark.
'Thirty of our noble boys! This is terrible!'
'You must do what King Gurman wants,' said Sir
Morholt, 'or one of your knights can fight me.
If your knight wins you don't have
to send the tribute to the king.
But no one will fight me! I'm the strongest
knight in the world and everyone's afraid of me.'
Everyone was silent, but
Tristan's face was red with anger.
'I will fight you, Sir Morholt!'
said Tristan.
'I'm not afraid of you!'
Everyone was surprised and looked at Tristan.
'No, Tristan, don't fight him - he's
too big and strong,' said King Mark.
'You can't win! He'll kill you.'
'No, Uncle Mark,' said Tristan, 'I'm a
knight of Cornwall and I must fight him.'
Sir Morholt looked at the young man
in front of him and started laughing.
Tristan was much shorter and
thinner than the Irish giant.
'I'll meet you in a week on the small island
opposite the castle,' said Sir Morholt.
'Come alone, early in the morning!'
'I'll be there!'
said Tristan, looking at Sir Morholt's
cold eyes.
CHAPTER TWO
Sir Morholt
A week later Sir Morholt came to
the island early in the morning.
He pulled his boat onto the beach.
Then Tristan came to the island
but he pushed his boat away.
'Why did you push your boat
away?' asked Sir Morholt.
'You'll need it when you
decide to run away from me.'
Tristan looked at him bravely and said, 'I
won't run away because I'm not afraid of you.
Remember, only one man will
leave this island alive!'
Sir Morholt laughed and raised his big sword.
Tristan did the same and they started fighting.
Tristan was young and light and he moved quickly.
Sir Morholt was slow and
heavy, but he was very strong.
Tristan jumped here and there,
and soon Sir Morholt was tired.
But he continued fighting.
The fight went on for many hours.
Suddenly Sir Morholt wounded
Tristan's leg with his big sword.
'There's poison on my sword,'
said Sir Morholt, laughing.
'If you don't find someone to cure
your wound you'll be very ill.
And only a few people in the world can cure it.'
Tristan was very angry and raised his heavy sword.
He cut through Sir Morholt's
helmet and wounded his head.
A small piece of Tristan's sword broke
and remained in Sir Morholt's head.
The Irish giant fell to the
ground - he was almost dead.
That evening some of Sir
Morholt's men came to the island.
They were surprised to see
him on the ground, wounded.
They put him on their boat and sailed
back to Ireland, where he died.
His sister was the Queen of Ireland, and she
was very sad because she loved her brother.
She took the small piece of sword from Sir
Morholt's head and put it in
a small blue box in her room.
'One day I'll find the man who
killed my brother,' she thought.
Tristan returned to Tintagel Castle
but his wound made him very ill.
King Mark called the best doctors of
Cornwall but they could not help him.
'Tristan must go to Ireland to cure
his wound,' said an old doctor,
'because the poison comes from there.
The Queen of Ireland knows
everything about poisons and herbs.
She can help him.'
'Then Tristan must go to Ireland
immediately,' said King Mark.
'Get a ship ready!'
Tristan went to Ireland dressed as a
minstrel and called himself Tantris.
He did not want anyone to
know that he was Sir Tristan.
He played the harp and sang beautifully,
and the Irish liked his songs.
One day King Gurman heard about the
minstrel and called him to his castle.
King Gurman and his Queen had only one
child - a lovely daughter called Isolde.
She was the most beautiful girl in the world, with
long blonde hair, blue eyes and a lovely smile.
Everyone talked about her beauty.
The King wanted Isolde to play the harp,
but there were no good teachers in Ireland.
Tantris entered the great hall
of the castle with his harp.
He walked slowly because his leg hurt.
'Are you the famous minstrel
Tantris?' asked King Gurman.
'Yes, I'm the minstrel,' said Tristan.
'What's wrong with your leg?' asked the King.
'I wounded it during a
terrible battle,' said Tristan.
'People say you play the harp
beautifully,' said King Gurman.
'Play something for me.'
Tristan played the harp and sang a
lovely song, and the king was pleased.
'Can you teach my daughter Isolde
to play the harp?' asked the King.
'Of course I can,' said Tristan happily.
'Very well,' said the King.
'The Queen will cure your
wound with her special herbs.
And you will teach Isolde to play the harp.
You can live here at the castle.'
'Thank you, your majesty,' said Tristan, smiling.
'I'm glad everyone thinks I'm
a minstrel,' thought Tristan.
'Now my leg will get better and
I'll soon go back to Cornwall.'
Tristan's leg slowly got better.
Every morning he taught Isolde
to play the harp and sing.
Isolde learned quickly and
the King was very happy.
During the harp lessons Tristan often thought,
'Isolde is very beautiful!'
CHAPTER THREE
The Dragon
Tristan stayed in Ireland at King Gurman's castle
and taught Isolde to play the harp and sing.
He and Isolde became good friends and
often laughed and talked together.
Isolde became a good singer and harp player.
She played the harp and sang songs
for her parents and other nobles.
After a year Tristan returned to Cornwall.
King Mark was very happy to see his nephew.
Every day Tristan told his uncle
about Isolde's great beauty.
'Isolde is the most beautiful girl in
the world, and she is gentle and kind.
Her hair is the colour of gold and
her eyes are the colour of the sea.
She plays the harp well and
sings with a sweet voice.'
King Mark listened to Tristan and said,
'Isolde is King Gurman's only daughter
and she is beautiful and kind.
If I marry her there will be
peace between our two countries.'
The king's knights and nobles agreed
with him, but there was one problem.
'We agree with you,' said one noble,
'but how can you marry Princess Isolde?
The king and queen of Ireland hate us
because Sir Morholt was killed here.'
'He's right,' said another noble.
King Mark was silent for a moment and
then said, 'I want to marry Isolde.
I'll have the most beautiful wife in the world
and there will be peace between our countries.
We must find a way!'
He looked at Tristan but he didn't say anything.
Tristan knew what his uncle wanted.
'Uncle Mark,' said Tristan, 'I
know this is a dangerous adventure.
When the Queen of Ireland discovers
who I am, she'll be very angry.
She hates the knight who
killed her brother Morholt.
But I'm not afraid.
I'll bring Isolde to you, Uncle
Mark, and you can marry her.'
'You're brave and loyal, Tristan,' said King Mark.
'Be very careful.'
Tristan sailed to Ireland on
a small ship with thirty men.
They arrived in Ireland on a stormy night.
'I must think of a plan,' thought Tristan.
'I must bring Isolde to King Mark.'
At that time a terrible green
dragon lived in Ireland.
It killed a lot of people and burned
houses and trees with its fire.
No one could kill it.
King Gurman was worried
and didn't know what to do.
One day he said to his nobles, 'The man who kills
the terrible green dragon will
marry my lovely daughter Isolde!'
Everyone in Ireland was talking about
this, and Tristan heard about it too.
He was excited because he
wanted to kill the dragon.
He had a heavy sword, a
long lance and a big shield.
He rode to the valley of the dragon and saw the
dead bodies of other knights who tried to kill it.
Suddenly Tristan saw the angry dragon.
It was a terrible green monster with long
white teeth, angry red eyes and a long tail.
Fire and smoke came out of its mouth.
'What an ugly creature!'
thought Tristan.
He attacked the dragon with his lance and sword.
They fought for more than an hour, and in the
end Tristan killed it with his long lance.
The dragon's last breath was hot and poisonous.
Tristan soon felt very bad.
He went to the dead dragon
and opened its big mouth,
Then he cut out its tongue and put it in his bag.
'This tongue will show that I
killed the dragon,' he thought.
The poison made him ill and he fell to the ground.
Later that day one of the king's nobles called
Seneschal came to the valley of the dragon.
He liked Isolde very much
and he wanted to marry her.
But he was a coward and was afraid of the dragon.
When Seneschal saw the dead dragon he
thought, 'This is wonderful - someone
already killed the dragon! I can tell
the King I killed it and then I can
marry Isolde! But first I must cut off
the dead dragon's head to show the King.'
He cut off the head and took it to the King.
'Your majesty,' he said, 'I killed the
green dragon! Look, here is its head.
Now I can marry your daughter, Princess Isolde.'
The King knew Seneschal was a
coward and he did not believe him.
But the head of the dragon was in front of him.
When Isolde heard this she
started crying and could not stop.
'What's wrong, Isolde?' asked the Queen.
'Oh, mother,' said Isolde crying, 'I don't
like Seneschal and I don't want to marry him!'
'Don't cry, my dear,' said the Queen.
'I don't believe Seneschal killed the dragon.
Come with me quickly.'
That evening they went to the valley and found
the dead dragon and Tristan on the ground.
'Look!'
cried Isolde.
'It's Tantris the minstrel.
But he's dressed like a knight.
I don't understand.'
Tristan heard Isolde's sweet
voice and slowly moved his head.
'Are you Tantris?' asked the Queen.
He opened his eyes and said, 'Yes, I am.'
'Why are you in Ireland?' asked the Queen.
'I came to Ireland with some merchants,' he said.
'Did you kill the dragon?' asked the Queen.
'I knew there was a terrible dragon in your
country and I decided to kill it,' said Tristan.
The Queen listened and smiled.
'Tantris, you did a great
thing and helped our country.
The King will be very pleased.
But you aren't well because
the dragon poisoned you.
Come with us to the castle and I'll cure
you again with my herbs.'
CHAPTER FOUR
Seneschal
Once again the Irish Queen cured Tristan
with her magic herbs and Isolde helped her.
After a week he got better and went
to the great hall to see King Gurman.
There was a big dinner in honour of
Seneschal, who wanted to marry Isolde.
King Gurman, the Queen, Isolde, knights, nobles
and their ladies were sitting at a long table.
Seneschal talked to his friends and told
them about his fight with the dragon.
'It was a long, terrible fight,' he
said loudly, 'but I was never afraid.
I got very near to the green
monster and looked at his red eyes.
I saw his long, white teeth and
felt his hot breath in my face.
I knew I had to kill him, and in the
end I did! Then I cut his head off.'
The King was silent but the Queen was not.
She looked at Seneschal and said,
'You didn't kill the dragon.
You found the dead dragon and cut his head off!'
'What!'
said Seneschal, angrily.
'I killed the dragon with my lance after a long
fight,' said Tristan, getting up from his chair.
'You're a liar and a coward!'
Seneschal got up from his chair and
said, 'Everyone knows I'm a brave man.
I brought the King the head of the dragon.'
'Look in the dragon's mouth,' said the Queen.
Seneschal opened the dragon's mouth
and cried, 'The tongue's gone!'
'Yes,' said Tristan.
Everyone was surprised and looked at Tristan.
He opened his bag and pulled
out the dragon's tongue.
'Oh!'
everyone said when they saw the long green tongue.
'Liar! Coward!'
everyone shouted at Seneschal.
'No,' cried Seneschal angrily, 'you're
a liar and a thief! I killed the dragon
and you took its tongue! Fight me in battle
and we'll see who marries Princess Isolde!'
'Very well,' said Tristan, 'I'll
fight you, Seneschal, and I'll win!'
'Very well, there will be a tournament in three
days,' said King Gurman, 'and everyone is invited.
The winner will marry my daughter, Isolde.'
Everyone started talking about the tournament and
there was a lot of excitement in the great hall.
'Who do you think will win?' asked one noble.
'I don't know, but they're both young
and strong,' answered his friend.
'It will be a great fight,' said a young knight.
'And the winner will have a
beautiful prize: Princess Isolde!'
said a noble lady.
On the morning of the tournament
Tristan went to prepare his horse.
Isolde brought some of the Queen's herbs
to Tristan's room, but he wasn't there.
His big sword was on the
table and she looked at it.
'How strange,' she thought, 'a small
piece of the sword is missing.'
She immediately thought of the blue box with the
small piece of sword from
her uncle Morholt's head.
'Oh no,' she thought, 'is this
the sword that killed my uncle?'
She ran to her mother's room and got the blue box.
She opened it slowly and saw
the small piece of sword inside.
Then she looked at Tristan's sword and said,
'The piece comes from the same
sword! I must tell my mother.'
She went to her mother and said,
'Come with me to Tantris's room.'
When they got there she said,
'The minstrel Tantris is not a
minstrel! He's Sir Tristan of Lyonesse, who
killed uncle Morholt! Look at his sword.'
She showed her mother Tristan's sword
and the small piece in the blue box.
'You're right, Isolde!'
said the Queen, surprised.
'This is the sword that killed Morholt.'
Isolde's face was red with anger.
'Now I'm going to kill Tristan with this sword!'
'No, Isolde!'
cried the Queen.
'What are you saying? Tristan fought
against Morholt in a fair battle.
He's a brave knight and a good man.
Let's talk to him.'
When Tristan returned to his room the Queen and
Isolde confronted him, and he told them the truth.
'Yes, I'm Sir Tristan of Lyonesse.
My uncle is King Mark of Cornwall,
a rich and important king.
He sent me here because he wants to marry
Isolde and bring peace to our countries.'
The Queen listened to Tristan and said, 'You came
to Ireland for a good reason - we want peace too.
A marriage between our families is a good idea.'
'But mother!'
said Isolde.
'Tristan killed my uncle Morholt!'
'Morholt was my brother, and I loved
him very much,' said the Queen.
'But we must forget the bad things of the
past and build a future for our countries.'
'You're a good Queen,' said Tristan.
Isolde was silent.
Then the Queen looked at her daughter and smiled.
'My dear Isolde, King Mark is a great king and
you'll be his queen - the Queen of Cornwall.
You'll be happy with him.'
'But he's much older than I am,' said Isolde.
'King Mark isn't an old man,' said Tristan.
'He's tall and good-looking, and
he's not a coward like Seneschal.
He's a brave man.'
'Did you hear that, Isolde?' asked the Queen.
Isolde looked at her mother and
asked, 'Will I love him, mother?'
'Yes, Isolde, you'll love him,' she
answered quietly and looked away.
Isolde smiled.
'But now Tristan must win the
tournament,' said the Queen.
'If he doesn't, you must marry Seneschal.'
'I'll fight and win!'
said Tristan.
'Please win, Tristan!'
said Isolde.
'I don't want to marry Seneschal - he's
a coward and a liar.'
CHAPTER FIVE
The Green Bottle
The tournament started early in the afternoon,
and hundreds of people were there to watch it.
King Gurman, the Queen and
Isolde sat in the first seats.
Isolde was very anxious.
Both men wore heavy armour.
Seneschal rode a black horse
and Tristan rode a white one.
Senescal fought bravely because
he wanted to marry Isolde so much,
but in the end Tristan killed Senescal.
He was the winner.
'Hurrah for Sir Tristan!'
cheered the people.
'Hurrah!'
Now Tristan could take Isolde
to his uncle, King Mark.
The Queen loved Isolde and wanted
her to be happy with King Mark.
'Isolde must fall in love with King
Mark,' she thought, 'then she'll be happy.
I must prepare the best love
potion in the world for them.
When they drink this love potion
they will always love each other.'
She quickly went to her herb garden and
took the magic herbs for the love potion.
Then she went to her secret room
in the castle and made the potion.
When it was ready she called Lady
Bragnae, who was Isolde's maid and friend.
'Listen carefully, Lady Bragnae,' said the Queen.
'You'll go with Isolde to Cornwall.
The ship leaves tomorrow.'
'Yes, my Queen,' said Lady Bragnae,
'I'm happy to go with Isolde.'
'On the day of her marriage you must give this
green bottle to Isolde and
King Mark,' said the Queen.
'Tell them to drink this excellent
wine - a good luck present from me.
Remember, Bragnae, they both must drink it.
This is the strongest love potion in the world.
When they drink it they
will always love each other.
Their love will be the greatest in
the world and it will never die.
Do you understand?'
'Yes, I do,' said Lady Bragnae.
She left the Queen's room with
the green bottle in her hands.
The next day Tristan's ship
left Ireland for Cornwall.
The sea voyage took many days.
There was stormy weather at sea and
Isolde sat in her cabin all day.
Sometimes she was sad because she
thought about her mother and father.
Tristan often visited her and
told her stories of old Cornwall.
He also told her the story of King Arthur
and the Knights of the Round Table.
Isolde liked listening to his stories.
During the stormy weather Lady Bragnae was
often ill and stayed in bed in her cabin.
One evening Tristan and Isolde played
the harp and sang together all evening.
Tristan was thirsty.
'Do you have anything to drink in the cabin?'
'Lady Bragnae brought a bottle of wine,' said
Isolde, pointing to a green bottle on a shelf.
'Would you like some?'
'Hmm...
yes, I would,' said Tristan.
Isolde took two gold cups and
they drank the wine together.
They did not know that it
was the Queen's love potion!
The green bottle was soon empty.
Tristan and Isolde talked and laughed together,
but something strange was happening to them.
They started looking into each
other's eyes and feeling strange.
What was this new feeling? They were in love!
That evening the sea became calm
and Bragnae soon felt better.
She went to find Isolde and immediately
saw the empty bottle and the two gold cups.
But Bragnae had a cold heart and did
not say anything to Tristan and Isolde.
'This is terrible!'
she thought.
'They both drank the potion and
they will be unhappy lovers until
they die! But they must never know the truth.
Oh, why did this happen?'
That night when Isolde was sleeping Bragnae took
the empty green bottle and threw it into the sea.
The next morning Tristan went
to visit Isolde in her cabin.
'Isolde,' said Tristan, 'something strange
happened to me last night and now...
I'm in love with you!'
'Oh, Tristan, 'said Isolde, smiling, 'the same
thing happened to me - I'm in love with you too.'
They looked at each other and embraced and kissed.
'Our love is impossible, Tristan
- I must marry King Mark.'
'Yes, I know,' said Tristan sadly.
'King Mark is my uncle and
I love him like a father.
But I love you more than anyone or
anything in the world, my sweet Isolde.'
'We must enjoy these few wonderful
days at sea together,' said Isolde.
'These are the only days we have,' said Tristan.
'When we get to Cornwall our
happiness will end, but not our love.'
'No, our love will never end,'
said Isolde, touching his hand.
'Never ever.'
CHAPTER SIX
Queen Isolde of Cornwall
Tristan's ship arrived in Cornwall at Tintagel,
and before getting off Tristan and
Isolde said goodbye to each other.
'You'll always be my only love,
sweet Isolde,' said Tristan.
'My heart will always be yours.'
'And you'll always be the only person
in my heart, Tristan,' said Isolde.
They embraced for the last time.
When King Mark met Isolde he was amazed
by her beauty and her sweet voice.
He loved her immediately.
She became King Mark's wife
and the Queen of Cornwall.
There was a great celebration with
music and dancing that lasted many days.
The people of Cornwall liked their new queen.
King Mark was very happy with Isolde but
she was not, because she loved only Tristan.
A year later, in the spring,
Isolde decided to go hunting
in the forest with Lady Bragnae and other nobles.
King Mark called Tristan and said,
'Isolde and Lady Bragnae want to
go hunting in the forest today.
I don't want them to go
alone because it's dangerous.
Go with them, and look after them.
I trust only you, Tristan.'
Tristan's heart jumped when
he heard Isolde's name.
'Very well, uncle Mark,' he said.
'I'll go hunting with them.'
During the hunt Lady Bragnae and the
others took different paths in the forest.
Soon Isolde and Tristan were alone.
They stopped near a small river.
They were still in love.
'I'm happy we're alone, dear
Isolde,' said Tristan quietly.
'I am too, Tristan,' said Isolde,
looking into Tristan's eyes.
'But our love's wrong...'
'I know, it's wrong and impossible,' said Tristan,
'but you're in my heart
and you'll always be there.
My love for you is stronger
than my loyalty to the King...'
Isolde could not speak - they embraced
and stayed near the river until sunset.
After that day they met at the
river in the forest many times.
One day some of King Mark's nobles saw them.
They were jealous of Tristan because
he was the best knight in Cornwall.
They decided to tell King Mark.
'Don't trust Sir Tristan and
Queen Isolde,' said one noble.
'I saw them sitting together
at the river in the forest.'
'My nephew and my wife are good friends
and nothing more,' said King Mark angrily.
'I trust them both!'
'They are more than good friends,
King Mark,' said another noble.
'Don't say these bad things
about my wife and my nephew!'
cried King Mark angrily.
Tristan and Isolde continued seeing each other
in the forest and one day Sir Melot saw them.
He was a bad man and hated Tristan.
He immediately went to tell King Mark.
'I saw Sir Tristan and Queen Isolde
together again in the forest,' he said.
'I don't believe you!'
said King Mark.
'You're a liar.'
'Then come with me quickly and
you'll see them too,' he said.
King Mark got on his horse and
followed Sir Melot to the forest.
They hid behind some trees and saw Tristan
and Isolde sitting near the stream.
Tristan was touching Isolde's long blonde hair.
Now King Mark believed Sir
Melot and he was very angry.
That evening he called all of his
nobles and explained everything to them.
'Sir Tristan is a traitor!'
cried King Mark.
'I loved him like a son and
taught him everything he knows.
I trusted him and I trusted Queen
Isolde - but now he must die!'
King Mark had tears in his eyes.
'No,' said the oldest noble.
'We don't like Sir Tristan
but he is a brave knight.
We may need him for future battles.
He's the best knight we have, and the people
of Cornwall love him - he's their hero.
If you kill him the people will be angry.
Send him away, and if we need him
for future battles we'll call him.'
'You're right,' said King Mark.
'He must leave Cornwall immediately and never see
Isolde again! The Queen is young
and she'll forget Tristan soon.'
King Mark sent Tristan away from
Cornwall and Isolde was very sad.
She stayed in her room and cried
because she could not forget Tristan.
Tristan left Cornwall and he was very unhappy.
He did not want to be a knight any
more because he did not have a king.
Now he was alone in the world.
He decided to became a minstrel
and went from village to village.
He played the harp and sang the
story of his love for Isolde.
***
This was the end of the minstrel's story.
He stopped singing and playing, and suddenly there
was silence in the great hall of King
Arthur's castle.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Sir Tristan of Lyonesse
King Arthur looked at him and said, 'Minstrel,
why do you know the story of Tristan and Isolde?
The minstrel got up from his stool and
said, 'Because I am Tristan of Lyonesse!'
Everyone in the great hail was very surprised.
King Arthur stood up and said, 'Welcome to
Camelot, Sir Tristan, and welcome to the
Round Table! Many years ago Merlin the magician
said, "One day Sir Tristan will be a knight of
the Round Table." He was right! Look, there's
a seat with your name, next to Sir Lancelot.
Sit down, Sir Tristan! Today's
an important day for us because
we have another brave knight at the Round Table.'
'This is a great honour for
me,' said Tristan, sitting down.
'Thank you, King Arthur.'
The other knights cheered and welcomed him.
Sir Tristan became an important
knight of the Round Table,
and the other knights liked him
because he was brave, kind and loyal.
Only the bravest knights
could sit at the Round Table.
He fought for King Arthur in many wars and
battles, and had many adventures in the kingdom.
But he was always sad because
he could not forget Isolde.
He thought about her all the time, day and night.
The years passed and one day
he went to Brittany in France,
where he met the daughter of the Duke of Arundel.
Her name was Isolde too -
Isolde of the White Hands.
She was a pretty, young
girl and Tristan liked her.
'Why do I like Isolde of the
White Hands?' he thought.
'Do I like her smile or her voice? Do I like
her lovely white hands or do I like her name?
Do I love her?'
Tristan could not answer these
questions, but he decided to marry her.
Isolde of the White Hands was a good, loving
wife and Tristan was a kind, loyal husband.
But he was not happy because he
could not forget Queen Isolde.
She was his first and only love.
Isolde of the White Hands
knew this and she was jealous.
'Why can't Tristan love me like
he loves her?' she thought.
One day Tristan fought in a battle
to help his wife's brother, Kahedin.
It was a long, terrible battle and
Tristan was wounded with a poisoned spear.
His wound made him very ill.
He could not walk and stayed in bed a long time.
But he did not get better - he got worse.
'I'm very ill,' said Tristan to Kahedin,
'and I think I'm going to die soon.'
'No, Tristan!'
said Kahedin.
'Don't say that! You helped me during
the battle and now I want to help you.
Tell me what I can do, my friend.'
'Only Queen Isolde of Cornwall
can cure my wound because the
spear was poisoned,' said Tristan weakly.
'She learned the secrets of the
magic herbs from her mother.'
'Then I'll sail to Tintagel immediately,
and ask Queen Isolde to come
here and cure you,' said Kahedin.
'Oh, Kahedin, thank you!'
said Tristan.
'If Isolde comes with you, raise
the white sail on your ship.
But if she doesn't, then raise the black sail.'
'Very well,' said Kahedin.
'I'm leaving this evening.
Isolde of the White Hands heard this
conversation and she was angry and jealous.
Kahedin sailed to Cornwall and told King
Mark and Queen Isolde about Tristan's wound.
'I must go and cure his wound with
my magic herbs,' said Queen Isolde.
'I'm the only person who can save his life!'
King Mark looked at his wife and said,
'Time is helping me to forget many things.
I think I can trust you now, Isolde.
Go and cure Tristan's wound.'
'Yes, my King,' said Queen Isolde
quietly, 'you can trust me.'
Isolde left Cornwall with Kahedin the same
day with some bottles of herbs and potions.
When the ship arrived near Tristan's
castle Kahedin raised the white sail.
Tristan was very weak and could not get
up from bed and look out of the window.
He called his wife and said,
'Go and look out of the window.
Kahedin's ship will be here soon.
Can you see it?'
Isolde of the White Hands went to the window
and saw Kahedin's ship with its big white sail.
'Oh, no,' she thought, 'the sail's
white - Queen Isolde is here!'
She was very jealous.
'Yes, Tristan,' said Isolde of the
White Hands, 'Kahedin's ship is here.'
'What colour is the sail?' asked Tristan weakly.
'The sail is...
black!'
answered Isolde of the White Hands.
'Oh, no, Isolde, my love,' said
Tristan sadly, 'you didn't come to me.
I won't see your beautiful face again.
Dearest Isolde, dearest Isolde...'
and then he closed his eyes and died.
Queen Isolde came to Tristan's
room and saw his dead body.
She sat down on the bed and
looked at him for the last time.
Her sadness was very great and her heart broke.
She died next to him.
'What did I do! My terrible
jealousy killed them both!'
said Isolde of the White Hands, and she
was very sorry - but it was too late.
Tristan and Isolde were
buried together in one grave.
And over the grave Isolde of the White Hands
planted two rose trees, a red one and a white one.
They grew together with red and white roses.
And this is the end of the great love story of Sir
Tristan of Lyonesse and Queen Isolde of Cornwall.