The Virgin and the Gipsy
Lucille and Yvette Saywell were sisters.
When Lucille was nine years old and Yvette was
seven, a shocking thing happened in their family.
Their mother, Cynthia, left their father
and ran away with a young, poor man.
The sisters' father, Arthur Saywell, was a vicar.
He was a handsome man and a good husband.
The vicar's neighbours were very surprised.
Why had the vicar's wife left him?
Lucille and Yvette did not know
why their mother had gone away.
Perhaps she did not love them.
Perhaps they had not been good daughters.
The vicar was offered a job
as rector of Papplewick,
a small village in the north of England.
So the family went to live in the rectory,
which stood just outside the village.
The rectory was an ugly stone house, with
the River Papple running just beside it.
The rector's mother, and his sister Aunt Cissie,
came to live with the rector
and his two daughters.
The rector's mother - or Granny, as the girls
called her - was over seventy years old.
The rector was very upset that his wife had left.
So Granny never spoke about Cynthia to her son.
But, secretly, the old woman was
pleased that Cynthia had run away.
Granny was now the most
important person in the house.
She controlled everybody else so
that they did what she wanted.
She liked controlling the family very much.
If Cynthia came back, everything would change.
And Granny did not want that to happen.
Lucille and Yvette remembered their
first home in the south, very clearly.
They also remembered their mother.
She had been like the sun.
She was beautiful and bright, but also dangerous.
She had brought light and life to the
house, but she had also been selfish.
As Granny grew older, she became almost blind.
She could not read and somebody had to lead
her about because she could see very little.
She did not get out of her bed until midday, but
she controlled all the other people in the house.
The rector especially loved
his younger daughter, Yvette.
Yvette was like her mother in many ways.
She was beautiful but careless.
The rector spoiled Yvette.
And he let her do everything that she wanted.
So, as Yvette grew up, she did not care
very much about other people's feelings.
The rector's sister, Aunt
Cissie, was almost fifty.
She spent all her time taking care of Granny.
Cissie did not complain,
but inside she felt angry.
She had no life of her own and no future.
She had no time for herself.
And she had nothing to look forward to.
Yvette was young and beautiful.
She never tried to understand
Aunt Cissie's feelings.
So Aunt Cissie was jealous
of Yvette and hated her.
When they had finished their education in England,
Lucille and Yvette were sent to a
school in Switzerland for a year.
They returned to the rectory at Papplewick when
Lucille was twenty-one and Yvette was nineteen.
They were tall, attractive young
girls with fresh, bright faces.
Their hair was cut short in the modern style.
It was a summer day and Yvette and
Lucille were coming back to England.
They were crossing the
Channel by boat from France.
The girls were not looking
forward to living at the rectory.
'Papplewick is such a boring place,' said Yvette.
'There are no interesting young
men living near the village.'
'Yes, there are!' said Lucille.
'The Framley family lives in the village
and Bob Framley is a nice young man.
And you know that Gerry Somercotes adores you.'
'But men who adore me are
very boring,' said Yvette.
'I would like to fall deeply in love.'
'I wouldn't,' said Lucille.
'I would hate to fall in love.
Perhaps you would hate it too, if it happened.'
'But won't you hate to go back
to Papplewick?' said Yvette.
'Not really,' said Lucille.
'But I suppose that we'll get rather bored there.
I wish that Daddy would buy a car.
We'll have to ride our bicycles everywhere.'
As the ship came closer to
the south coast of England,
Yvette and Lucille watched the cliffs of Dover.
The walls of rock were usually
white when the sun shone.
But today, the sky was grey and dull,
and the cliffs were grey and dull too.
The two girls looked tall and confident.
But they were just young girls
who knew nothing about life.
They were like ships that were moving from a
safe harbour onto the wide and dangerous sea.
As soon as they went inside the rectory,
Lucille and Yvette felt depressed.
The hard stonewalls seemed ugly and unclean.
The furniture seemed ugly and unclean too.
Nothing was fresh.
The food they ate was terrible.
Granny was given special things to eat.
And grey-faced Aunt Cissie ate very
little - only one boiled potato at dinner.
She never ate meat.
Cissie hated food and eating.
Granny was now over eighty years old.
It was easy for her to control her son.
When Arthur Saywell's marriage went wrong,
he had realized that life outside the
family could be difficult and dangerous.
Only life inside the family was safe.
So he stayed close to the family and his mother
- the most important person in the house.
The countryside round the village
of Papplewick was dark and dull,
with steep hills and deep, narrow valleys.
All the houses in the village were made of stone.
Life in Papplewick was as dull as stone too.
Lucille got a job in the city as a secretary.
She travelled to and from
the city every day, by train.
Both girls helped the poorer
people in the village.
But Yvette left the rectory whenever she could.
Sometimes she had tea with the wives
of men who worked in the factories.
She liked talking to the working men.
Their world was very different
from her own life in the rectory.
The months passed.
Yvette went to lots of parties and dances.
Sometimes friends came in their
cars and took her to the city.
But she never seemed to be really happy.
At home, she was often angry,
and she was rude to Aunt Cissie.
The girls hated inviting
their friends to the rectory.
There were only four rooms
downstairs - the kitchen,
the dining room, the rector's
study and the drawing room.
The drawing room was the only room
where a good hot fire was lit.
So Granny always sat in the drawing-room.
Whenever the girls brought their friends to the
rectory, Granny was sitting in the drawing-room.
The girls never felt comfortable and they
could not relax when Granny was there.
Granny liked meeting people.
She wanted to be introduced
to all the girls' friends.
She wanted to know who the young people were.
She wanted to know where they came
from and every detail of their lives.
When Granny had this information,
she took control of the conversation.
One afternoon, Lottie, Ella and Bob Framley -
some of Yvette's friends - came to the house.
A young man called Leo Wetherell came too.
Granny had not met Leo before, so
Yvette had to introduce him to her.
'Granny, this is Mr Wetherell.'
'Mr What-did-you-say?' shouted Granny.
'You must excuse me, I'm a little deaf.
I can't hear properly.'
She held her hand towards Leo Wetherell
and stared at him with her blind old eyes.
Leo felt very uncomfortable.
'We want to go on a picnic tomorrow,' said Ella.
'We're going to Bonsall Head, in Leo's car.'
There was a wonderful view from the top
of Bonsall Head, from this high hill,
you could see across the
countryside for miles around.
'Did you say Bonsall Head?' asked Granny.
'Yes.'
There was a silence.
'Did you say that you were
going in a car?' asked Granny.
'Yes,' said Yvette.
'In Mr Wetherell's car.'
'I hope that he's a good driver,' said Granny.
'The road to Bonsall Head is very dangerous.'
'Leo is a very good driver,' said Yvette.
'Not a very good driver?' said Granny.
'He is a very good driver!' shouted Yvette.
Then Aunt Cissie came into the room.
Following her was the maid, who brought
tea and a plate of little cakes.
Several minutes later, Lucille
returned from her job in the town.
She was very tired and had
black marks under her eyes.
When she saw all the people in the drawing
room, she gave a little cry of surprise.
'You've never spoken about Mr Wetherell
to me, have you, Lucille?' said Granny.
'I don't remember,' said Lucille.
'You can't have talked about him,' said Granny.
'I've never heard his name before.'
Yvette was eating the little cakes.
Without thinking about anyone else,
she took another cake from the plate.
Aunt Cissie felt very angry with Yvette.
She picked up her own plate, which had one
small cake on it, and offered it to Yvette.
'Would you like my cake too?' she asked in a
voice that was polite, but cold with anger.
'Oh, thanks!' said Yvette carelessly,
taking Aunt Cissie's cake as well.
Now she had two cakes on her plate.
Aunt Cissie's face showed her
feelings - feelings of hate.
But Yvette did not notice that anything was wrong.
Lucille and Yvette felt very
tired when their friends left.
The conversation between their friends
and Granny had been very difficult.
Yvette looked at her grandmother.
Granny looked like a kind, weak
old lady, but she was very strong.
She wanted to control other people by
knowing everything about their lives.
She was like a fat old toad that
Yvette had seen in the garden one day.
The toad had sat by a bee-hive.
It had caught and eaten the bees
as they came out of the hive.
Next day, the weather was dull and grey.
The roads were wet and slippery because
it had rained for several weeks.
But the young people still wanted
to drive up to Bonsall Head.
There were two men in the group
- Leo Wetherell and Bob Framley.
And there were four girls - Lottie and Ella
Framley, who were sisters, and Lucille and Yvette.
The young people all got into Leo's car.
As he drove through the quiet villages,
they all talked and sang songs.
The car went along the road through dark trees,
and then began the long slow
climb up to Bonsall Head.
At the top of the hill, there were
no trees, there was only grass.
On each side of the road there
were low walls made of stone.
Above the hills, the sky was dull and grey.
'Shall we stay here for a moment?'
said Leo, stopping the car.
'Oh, yes!' cried the girls.
Leo turned off the engine and
they all got out of the car.
The view from the top of the Head was wonderful.
All around, they could see hills and deep valleys.
And towards the north, they saw a
train moving slowly in the distance.
'Come on!' said Leo.
'Let's drive down to Amberdale and have some tea.'
The friends got back into the car
and drove along the top of the Head.
They were so high that it was
like being on top of the world.
Up here, it was cold and windy.
The young people were silent,
looking out across the stone walls.
Suddenly, ahead of them on the road, they
saw a horse pulling a small green cart.
The cart was driven by a man, and an
old woman was walking by its side.
Because the road was narrow,
the car could not pass.
Leo sounded the horn sharply and
the man on the cart looked round.
But the old woman walked on
and did not turn her head.
Yvette's heart gave a jump.
The man on the cart was a gipsy.
He wore a dark green cap and a big red and
yellow silk handkerchief around his neck.
He sat on the cart in a comfortable, relaxed way.
'Get out of the way!' shouted Leo angrily.
The man pulled the horse's
reins and the cart stopped.
But it was still in the middle of
the road and the car could not pass.
So Leo had to stop the car too.
'Would the pretty young ladies like to have
their fortunes told?' said the gipsy, laughing.
'Would they like to know what will
happen to them in the future?'
The gipsy was very handsome, with black hair
and a black moustache above very white teeth.
His dark watchful eyes looked
at Yvette's soft young face.
She looked into his eyes and felt
a strange feeling of excitement.
It was like a little flame in her heart.
'He's very strong,' she thought.
'He's stronger than I am!'
'Oh, yes!' cried the girls.
'Let's have our fortunes told!'
'But what about the time?' cried Leo.
'It's getting late.'
'It doesn't matter about the time,' said Lucille.
The gipsy jumped down lightly from the cart.
He seemed a little over thirty
years old and he was well dressed.
Beneath his black and green coat,
he wore a dark green jumper, tight
black trousers and black boots.
Now the young people saw that there was
an old quarry on one side of the road.
Many years ago, men had cut rock out of the
ground and an opening had been made in the hill.
There were three caravans in the quarry.
The wall of rock rose high above the
caravans, curving round towards the road.
Grass grew between the rough stones on the ground.
The quarry was a good place
for the gipsies winter camp.
The old gipsy woman went into one of the caravans.
Two black-haired children
looked out of the open door.
The gipsy gave a call and an old man
came to take the horse from the cart.
Then the gipsy went up the
steps into the nearest caravan.
At the same moment, a tall and handsome
gipsy woman came down the steps.
She had big gold rings in her ears and a
pink headscarf over her black wavy hair.
She wore a large green skirt.
Her face was long and her eyes were
bright and fierce, like a wolf.
'Which beautiful young lady wants to
hear her fortune?' the woman asked.
'If she shows me her little
hand, I can read her future.'
The woman's eyes looked sharply from face to face.
Yvette, Lucille, Lottie and Ella all wanted
the gipsy woman to tell them their fortunes.
They agreed a price and the woman pulled
two wooden stools from under a caravan.
The first girl, Lottie, sat down and the
gipsy woman looked closely at her hand.
She told Lottie about her future life.
Yvette was the last girl to have her fortune told.
The gipsy woman stared into the girl's face.
'I don't think that I want my
fortune told,' Yvette said nervously.
'Are you afraid?' asked the woman.
'Do you have a secret? Would you like to go
into the caravan, where nobody can hear?'
'Yes!' said Yvette.
'I'll go into the caravan.'
The gipsy woman called something to her husband.
The gipsy man appeared at
the top of the caravan steps.
He was holding a small,
black-haired baby in his arms.
He came down the steps,
looking at Yvette as he passed.
Yvette followed the woman
up the steps of the caravan.
At the top, she turned towards her friends.
'I won't be long,' she said.
Yvette's coat had soft, grey
animal's fur around the collar.
The collar was open, showing the white skin
of her throat and her pale green dress.
She knew that the gipsy man was looking
at her as she entered his house.
Yvette's friends waited for a long time.
It was getting dark and cold.
At last, the caravan door
opened and Yvette came out.
The gipsy woman followed her.
'Was I away a long time?' asked
Yvette, not looking at anybody.
'I hope that you weren't bored!
Wouldn't tea be nice! Shall we go?'
'You get in the car,' said Bob Framley.
'I'll pay.'
He gave some money to the gipsy woman.
As Yvette got into the car, she also
put some money into the woman's hand.
Leo started the engine and
switched on the car's lights.
'Goodnight!' called Yvette.
As Leo turned the car onto the
road, Lucille spoke to her sister.
'Yvette, tell us what the
gipsy woman said to you.'
'Oh, nothing exciting,' said Yvette.
'Just the usual things.
My future will include a dark man who means
good luck, and a fair one who means bad luck.
Someone in the family will die.
I'll marry when I'm twenty-three.
I'll have lots of money
and love, and two children.
That's all!'
At the rectory a few days later, there was a
big quarrel between Yvette and Aunt Cissie.
The quarrel was about Aunt Cissie's Window Fund.
Aunt Cissie had been collecting money to pay
for a new, decorated glass window in the church.
This window was to remember the men from
the village who had died in the war.
Aunt Cissie had asked Lucille and Yvette
to collect money for the Window Fund too.
She gave each of them a special moneybox.
The quarrel started when Aunt Cissie asked
the girls for the money from their boxes.
There was very little money in
Yvette's box, only fifteen shillings.
'But some money must be missing.
Where is the rest of it?' asked Aunt Cissie.
'Oh,' said Yvette carelessly.
'I borrowed it.'
Aunt Cissie was very angry with Yvette.
Yvette's father, the rector, was angry too.
'If you needed money, why
didn't you tell me?' he said.
'I - I thought that it didn't
matter,' said Yvette nervously.
'I needed to buy some things for myself.
I can pay it back.'
'And what have you spent the
money on?' her father asked.
'I can't remember,' said Yvette.
'I gave some of it away.'
Yvette's face was very pale.
The rector was afraid that Yvette
was becoming like his wife, Cynthia.
She had behaved in the same
careless way as Yvette.
Now Yvette looked at him in the
same way that Cynthia had done.
Arthur Saywell felt guilty and afraid.
'You must give the money back to
the Window Fund,' he said coldly.
'I'll lend you some money now
so that you can pay it back.
In the future, if you can't trust yourself,
don't touch money which isn't yours.
You have not been honest.
Dishonesty is a terrible thing.'
Yvette felt very bad.
She knew that she had done wrong.
She had been dishonest.
She had taken money, which was
not hers, and she had spent it.
Why had she touched the money?
The rector paid the missing money to Aunt Cissie.
But Aunt Cissie could not forgive Yvette.
One night, when Yvette had gone
to bed, her door opened softly.
Aunt Cissie stood in the doorway of the
bedroom, pushing her grey-green face forward.
Terrified, Yvette sat up in her bed.
'Liar! Thief! Selfish little creature!'
said Aunt Cissie in a voice full of hate.
'You're a selfish, greedy little thief!'
Yvette opened her mouth to scream.
But Aunt Cissie shut the door and disappeared.
Yvette jumped out of bed
and locked the bedroom door.
She slowly got back into the bed
and lay there, almost mad with fear.
'I wish that I were a gipsy,' she said to herself.
'I want to live in a camp, or a caravan.
I never want to go into a house again.
I hate this house.
There's no fresh air here.
I want to live my life freely.
I want to live in the fresh air, like a gipsy.'
Then Yvette thought about the gipsy
woman who had told her fortune.
She remembered the woman's words:
'There's a dark man who never lived in a house.
He loves you.
Other people are treading on your heart.
They will tread on your heart
until you think that it's dead.
But the dark man will blow the spark
of life into fire again - a good fire.'
Yvette hated the cold rectory.
She liked the big dark gipsy woman
who had gold rings in her ears.
She liked the woman's strong hands.
And the gipsy man!
Yvette remembered the way that he had
looked at her, and her body shook.
She had given two pounds from the
Window Fund to the gipsy woman.
She never told her father or Aunt Cissie this.
For several days, the weather was cold and wet.
One afternoon, Lucille had a half
day's holiday from her job in the city.
The rector was writing in his study.
Granny, Lucille and Yvette
were in the drawing room.
The girls were making a blue dress for Yvette.
Granny was resting on the couch.
Yvette was sitting at the table, sewing her dress.
The room was very untidy.
There were small pieces of
blue material everywhere
and the scissors were lying on the floor.
Yvette had placed a mirror
on the top of the piano.
But she had placed it in such a
careless way that it could easily fall.
Aunt Cissie came into the room.
'This room is in a terrible mess!' she said.
'You'll have to clear these things away, Yvette.'
'I'll clear everything away before
we have tea,' Yvette replied.
She got up and pulled the
half-made blue dress over her head.
But as she did so, she knocked the mirror off
the top of the piano and it fell to the floor.
Luckily the mirror did not break.
But everybody got a terrible shock.
'Oh! She's smashed the mirror!' cried Aunt Cissie.
'It's broken!'
'Smashed a mirror! Which mirror! Who's
smashed it?' said Granny sharply.
'I haven't smashed anything,' said Yvette calmly.
'It's all right.
Anyway, it's my own mirror.
I brought it from our home at the vicarage.'
'Don't break it in this house,
wherever it came from,' said Granny.
'It's very unlucky to break a mirror.
I don't want any bad luck brought to this house.'
'Oh, I'm not superstitious,' said Yvette.
'I don't believe that breaking
a mirror will bring bad luck.'
'Yvette, will you please tidy this mess and
put your things away,' said Aunt Cissie.
'It's really terrible to live with people who are
always making a fuss about small
things!' cried Yvette angrily.
'Which people are you talking
about?' said Aunt Cissie.
'You know who I'm talking about,' said Yvette.
'I'm talking about the
people in this awful house.'
'Well,' said Granny.
'Thank goodness that there's nobody evil
or mad, like your mother, in our family.'
For a second, there was a terrible silence.
Then Lucille stood up quickly.
'You shut up!' she shouted at Granny.
Aunt Cissie angrily jumped towards Lucille
and began to push her out of the room.
'Go to your bedroom!' she cried.
'Stay in your room until
you've apologized to Granny.
Say that you're sorry, then you can leave!'
'I shall not apologize!' shouted
Lucille, and she left the room.
Yvette stood in the centre of the drawing room.
She was still wearing the half-made blue dress.
She was shocked by what
Lucille had said to Granny.
But she was also very angry with Granny.
The rector came in.
'What's wrong?' he asked.
'Oh, nothing!' said Yvette carelessly.
'Lucille told Granny to shut up
when she was saying something.'
'Lucille must learn to control
her nerves,' said Granny.
'The mirror fell down, and it worried me.
Yvette said something about superstitions
and the people in this awful house.
I said that the people in this
house weren't evil or mad.
Then Lucille told me to shut up.
But it's only because of her nerves.'
Yvette was shocked.
Granny was not telling the rector the truth.
Granny had said that the
girls' mother was evil and mad.
Aunt Cissie came back into the room.
'I've told Lucille not to come out of her
room, until she apologizes,' she said.
'I don't want an apology,' said the old lady.
'Lucille's nerves made her behave like that.'
Yvette's body was shaking inside as she collected
her thread, scissors and other sewing things.
She went up the stairs to see Lucille.
Halfway up the stairs, there was a window.
Yvette always looked out of this window,
hoping to see someone on the road.
The rectory was beside the River Papple.
The road curved round the bouse, down to the
bridge over the river, and on up to the village.
A horse, pulling a green cart,
was coming down the road.
It was driven by a man who was
sitting on the front of the cart.
He was wearing a green cap.
It was the gipsy.
At of the cart, there were metal
pots and pans and long brushes.
The gipsy crossed the bridge, and passed
along the road by the rectory wall.
He looked up at the old stone house
and saw Yvette standing at the window.
He nodded his head to her.
Yvette was still wearing the blue
dress, but it had no sleeves.
Because she was a little cold, Yvette
rubbed her hands along her pale arms.
The gipsy stopped at the white gate of the
rectory, and jumped down from the cart.
He took some brushes and other things from the
back of the cart and turned towards the house.
He looked up at Yvette as he opened the gate.
Yvette hurried to the bathroom
and put on her other dress.
Then she went downstairs to the drawing room.
The maid arrived there at the same time.
'Aunt Cissie,' Yvette said.
'There's a man selling brushes at the door.
Shall I go and see him?'
'What kind of a man is he?' asked Aunt Cissie.
'A man with a cart,' said Yvette.
'A gipsy,' said the maid,
coming into the drawing-room.
Aunt Cissie stood up.
She wanted to see the gipsy herself.
The gipsy stood at the door,
holding his brushes in one hand.
From his other hand, shining metal objects were
hanging - a saucepan, a candlestick and plates.
He looked at Aunt Cissie with his large dark eyes.
'Do you want to buy anything today,
lady?' he asked in a soft, quiet voice.
Aunt Cissie saw that he was very
handsome, so she did not close the door.
'This candlestick is lovely,' said Yvette.
'Did you make it?'
'Yes, lady!'
The gipsy looked at Yvette and his
eyes showed his feelings for her.
She knew that he wanted her.
He desired her.
It made her feel weak.
Aunt Cissie went to show the rector the
candlestick and Yvette was
left alone with the gipsy.
'How is your wife?' she asked.
The man looked at Yvette and smiled.
'She's all right,' he said.
'When are you coming to the quarry
again?' he asked in a low voice.
'Oh, I don't know,' said Yvette carelessly.
'Come on a Friday, when I'm there,' he said.
Yvette looked over the
gipsy's shoulder at the road.
She pretended that she had not heard his words.
Aunt Cissie returned with
money to buy the candlestick.
Yvette turned away and went upstairs.
She stood beside the window on the
stairs and looked onto the road.
She did not want the gipsy to see her.
She wanted to know if he had any power over her.
Did he control her feelings and her mind?
She watched the gipsy walk through
the white gate to the cart.
He put his brushes and pans
away and jumped onto the cart.
Then he was gone.
'No, he hasn't any power over me!' said Yvette.
And she went to see Lucille.
'Granny is sorry about what happened,' she said.
'Don't be angry.
Let's go down to dinner.
Come on, Lucille!'
When Friday came, Yvette thought all day
about the quarry high up on Bonsall Head.
She wanted to be there, among
the caravans with the gipsies.
But she did not go.
She stayed at home and sewed her
blue dress for a party the next day.
She danced with Leo Wetherell at the party.
'Why don't we get engaged, Yvette?' asked Leo.
Leo was an ordinary young man.
But he was pleasant and kind, and he was rich.
Yvette quite liked him.
But she did not want to get engaged to him.
What a silly idea! She did not
think about Leo's feelings at all.
'Get engaged!' she said.
'But that's impossible.'
'Since those gipsies told your fortune, I've
felt that I am the only one for you,' said Leo.
'And you are the only one for me.'
'Really!' said Yvette, very surprised.
'Really!'
'You felt the same thing, didn't you?' he said.
'Do you feel the same about
me, as I feel about you?'
'What? Do you think that I
want to get engaged?' she said.
'No.
How could I dream of such an impossible thing?'
The musicians began to play again
and people stood up to dance.
Leo looked at Yvette.
'I won't dance anymore,' she said.
'But do go and ask somebody
else to dance with you.'
Leo stood up angrily and walked away from her.
Yvette watched the young men dancing.
Then suddenly a picture of
the gipsy came into her mind.
She saw his face, his straight
nose, his smiling lips.
She saw his black eyes, which seemed to look
deep into a dark, secret place inside her.
The gipsy was so different
from the young men around her.
Yvette did not want any of them.
When Leo smiled at her, his smile did
not make a flame burn in her heart.
The next week, it rained again.
But when Friday came, it was sunny and cold.
Yvette told her family that she was
going for a ride on her bicycle.
But she did not tell them that she
was going to visit the gipsies camp.
It was February and the sun was not strong
enough to melt the ice on the ground.
But the sun made Yvette think of spring.
Her body was warm from cycling,
but her hands were very cold.
She was not wearing gloves.
The horse and cart were not in the camp.
The gipsy man was sitting on
the ground, making a metal bowl.
He was not wearing a coat or a cap.
The sun shone on his black hair and green jumper.
An old woman was cooking some
food in an iron pot over the fire.
Three small children were playing near her.
The man looked up as Yvette got off her bicycle.
'How are you all?' she asked politely.
'All right.
Do you want to sit down for a minute?' he said,
pulling a wooden stool from under a caravan.
Yvette went to the fire to
warm her hands near the flames.
'Are you cooking dinner?' she asked the old woman.
'Yes,' the woman replied.
'Dinner for him.
And for the children.'
She pointed at the three
black-eyed, black-haired children.
They were staring at Yvette.
The gipsies, their caravans and
everything in the camp was clean and tidy.
'Are they your children?'
Yvette asked the gipsy man.
He looked straight into her eyes, and nodded.
'Where's your wife?'
'She's taken the cart, to try and sell things.
I don't go selling things.
I make them, but I don't go selling them.
Not often.'
Yvette sat down on the stool.
'You said that you would be
here on a Friday,' she said.
'And the weather was fine today.
So I came this way.'
'It's a very fine day!' said the gipsy.
'Do you want some dinner? There's
meat with some beans in it.'
'Yes, please.
I'll have just a little,' said Yvette.
'Do you want to come up into the
caravan and wash your hands?'
'No, thank you,' she said.
'They're clean.'
They ate the food, sitting round the fire.
The children sat on the ground, eating beans
and meat with a spoon or their fingers.
The gipsy man was silent.
Then the old woman made some coffee.
Yvette took off her hat and shook her
short, brown hair in the sunshine.
'How many children do you
have?' Yvette asked suddenly.
'Five, I think,' replied the gipsy
slowly, looking up into her eyes.
He held a cup of coffee
towards her and she took it.
She knew that he was sitting
there silently, like a shadow.
Yvette's hair fell across her face
as she put her lips to the hot cup.
She felt very weak, as if the
gipsy had complete power over her.
And as he drank his own coffee, he looked at her.
'Do you want to go to my caravan
now, and wash your hands?' he said.
'Yes, I think so,' she said.
He got up quietly.
Then he spoke a few words to the old woman
and climbed up the steps to his caravan.
Yvette stood still at the bottom of the steps.
Suddenly they heard the sound of a car.
A big, powerful car passed
the quarry, then stopped.
The gipsy came down the
steps of the caravan again.
'Put on your hat,' he said to Yvette.
Yvette went back to the stool by the fire.
The gipsy picked up his tools and
began working on the metal bowl again.
'May we warm our hands at
the camp fire?' said a voice.
A small woman came towards the fire.
She was wearing a fur coat, but
her body was shaking with the cold.
A large, fair-haired man was following her.
He was tall and strong, with
a body like an athlete's.
The woman sat at the fire and held
her hands towards the warm flames.
The gipsy was still making his metal bowl.
The big blond man went over to him.
'We're on our honeymoon,'
the woman said to Yvette.
'But it's a honeymoon before we're married!'
'Really!' said Yvette.
She was surprised.
'Yes! Have you heard of Simon
Fawcett?' the woman asked.
She was talking about a rich,
well-known engineer in northern England.
'Well, I'm Mrs Fawcett.
My husband is divorcing me.
As soon as the divorce is complete, I'm
going to marry this man - Major Eastwood.'
She turned round and looked at the large
blond man who was talking to the gipsy.
Then she looked at the gipsy.
Her big brown eyes shone.
'He's a handsome man!' she said.
'Yes, quite handsome!' said Yvette.
'Are you cycling?' asked the woman,
looking at Yvette's bicycle by the caravan.
'Yes.
I'm going down to Papplewick,' replied Yvette.
'My father is the rector of Papplewick.'
Major Eastwood came and stood by the fire.
'We were talking about the war,' he said.
'I thought that I remembered that man's face.
He served in my regiment.
He took care of the horses.
He was excellent.'
'Why don't you come with us in our
car?' said the woman to Yvette.
'We live in Scoresby.
That's near Papplewick.
We can tie your bicycle onto the back of the car.'
'Thank you.
I think that I will,' said Yvette.
'It's going to snow,' said the woman,
looking up at the cold, grey sky.
She closed the collar of her
fur coat around her neck.
'Are you going back in the car?'
the gipsy asked, looking at Yvette.
'Yes,' she replied.
'The weather changes very quickly.'
Yvette did not know what the gipsy was thinking.
But she was not very interested.
She was more interested in Mrs Fawcett.
This woman had left her rich husband
and had run away with Major Eastwood,
a poor man who was five or
six years younger than her.
'Well, goodbye!' said Mrs Fawcett to the gipsy.
'Thank you for the warm fire.'
'Fire is free for everyone,' said the gipsy.
'Goodbye!' said Yvette.
'I hope that it doesn't snow.'
'We don't worry about a
little snow,' said the gipsy.
And Yvette followed the woman
in the fur coat to the car.
Yvette was excited about her new friends.
She called them the Eastwoods.
They were renting a small cottage near the hills.
Mrs Eastwood was thirty-six.
She had two children, who were
both more than twelve years old.
She had left them with her husband.
But Mr Fawcett had agreed that the children could
live with their mother when
the divorce was complete.
The Eastwoods were a strange couple.
Mrs Eastwood was a tiny woman,
with big eyes and curly black hair.
Major Charles Eastwood
looked completely different.
He was a big young man with bright
blond hair and light grey eyes.
He looked like a great, pale bird of winter.
The Eastwoods invited Yvette
for a meal at their cottage.
Yvette thought that they were very
unusual and interesting people.
She told Lucille about her new friends, but she
did not tell the rector, Granny, or Aunt Cissie.
She knew that they would
ask her a lot of questions.
'But I don't want you to visit
us if your father doesn't know
about our friendship,' said Mrs Eastwood.
'I'm sure that he won't worry,' said Yvette.
Yvette talked about many
things with the Eastwoods.
On one visit, they talked about love and marriage.
'Don't you want to fall in love and
get married?' asked Mrs Eastwood.
'No, not really,' said Yvette.
'But don't you know what love is?'
said Mrs Eastwood in surprise.
'Is there no man who makes you feel different?'
'I don't think so,' said Yvette.
'Except - yes! There is one man
who makes me feel different.
The gipsy.'
'What gipsy?'
'The one who was a soldier and cared for the
horses in Major Eastwood's regiment in the war.'
'You're not in love with him!' said
Mrs Eastwood in a shocked voice.
'Well!' said Yvette.
'I don't know.
He's the only man who makes me feel different.
He really is!
He looked at me in a different
way from any other man.
He looked as if he really
desired me - really wanted me.'
'What a horrible man!' cried Mrs Eastwood.
'Do you think that he shouldn't
look at me?' asked Yvette.
'No! He certainly should not!' cried Mrs Eastwood.
'But it was rather wonderful.
It really was!' said Yvette.
'And nothing like that has happened in my life.'
'I think,' said the Major, 'that desire
for a woman is the most wonderful thing.'
'Do you think that the gipsy
is special?' asked Yvette.
'If I were you, I should know,' said the Major.
'But she can't possibly marry him and live in a
caravan!' said Mrs Eastwood in a shocked voice.
'I never said that she should
marry him,' said Major Eastwood.
'And she shouldn't have a love
affair,' said Mrs Eastwood.
Major Eastwood thought for several moments.
'That gipsy was the best man that we
had who worked with horses,' he said.
'He became ill and almost died.
I almost died too.
I was buried for twenty hours under snow.
I was only found by accident.'
'Oh,' said Yvette.
'Life is so terrible.'
Yvette had thought that her father would not
worry about her friendship with the Eastwoods.
But when the rector heard
about them, he was very angry.
'I've heard that your new friends
are the half-divorced Mrs Fawcett
and her boyfriend, Eastwood,' he said.
'They're very nice,' said Yvette.
'They'll be married in about a month.
I like them very much.
They both seem such honest people.'
'You've got a strange idea
about honesty,' said the rector.
'Eastwood is a young man who lives
with a woman older than himself.
He lives on her money.
The woman has left her home and her children!
And you seem to know them very well.
Where did you meet them?'
'I was riding my bicycle,' said Yvette.
'I met them on the road.
They came along in their
car and we started to talk.'
'And how many times have you visited them?'
'I've been to their cottage in Scoresby twice.'
The rector looked at Yvette with hate in his eyes.
He remembered his wife Cynthia.
Cynthia had behaved like Mrs Eastwood.
Cynthia had left him and run
away with a younger, poor man.
His daughter liked the Eastwoods.
She did not think that their behaviour was wrong.
Was Yvette becoming like Cynthia?
'Yvette, why do you make friends with
people like the Eastwoods?' he said.
'Aren't there enough good people in the world
for you? You must stop this kind of behaviour.
Or you will have to live with mad, bad people.'
Yvette's face became pale.
She felt cold with fear.
'But why?' she said.
'What have I done? Is it a very bad
thing, to be friends with the Eastwoods?'
'Don't say anymore,' said the rector.
'I'll kill you, before you go down
the same bad road as your mother.'
Yvette looked at her father.
The skin of his face was pale yellow, and
his eyes were mad with fear, anger and hate.
Yvette felt very cold and lonely.
There was a terrible silence.
'Are you saying that I can't be a friend
of the Eastwoods?' she asked again.
'You can be their friend, if
you wish,' said the rector.
'But if you are, you cannot be with your
Granny, your Aunt Cissie, and Lucille.
You have to choose between
clean people like your Granny,
and people who are unclean
in their bodies and minds.'
There was another silence.
'All right,' said Yvette at last.
'I'll write to the Eastwoods.
I'll say that you don't want me to know them.'
She walked quietly out of the room
and wrote a note to Mrs Eastwood.
Dear Mrs Eastwood,
Daddy isn't happy that I'm visiting you.
So you'll understand that I
can no longer come to Scoresby.
I'm very sorry.
After she had sent the note, Yvette felt empty.
Her life was dull.
Her home was cold and loveless.
She thought about the gipsy again.
She wanted him to hold her in his arms
and keep her safe from her father.
Her feelings for her father had changed.
She still liked him, but she no longer loved him.
His words had hurt her very much.
And she began to hate Granny.
Whenever she saw the fat, blind old woman sitting
in the drawing room, she thought of a great toad.
After she had sent the note,
Yvette saw the gipsy twice.
Once he came to the house with things to sell.
She stood by the window on
the stairs and watched him.
But she did not go downstairs and talk to him.
The second time that Yvette saw
the gipsy, she met him by accident.
It was March, and the weather was sunny.
Brightly coloured spring flowers were growing
in the woods and on the hills and fields.
Yvette was cycling along the road.
She saw the gipsy coming out of a stone cottage.
His horse and the green cart
were standing in the road.
He returned to the cart with some of his brushes.
Yvette got off her bicycle.
As soon as she saw him, she loved him.
She knew that she loved the way that he moved.
She loved his face as he
turned, silently, towards her.
She felt that she knew him
better than she knew anybody.
She knew him better than her sister, Lucille.
She felt that she belonged to the gipsy forever.
'Have you made anything new?' she asked,
looking at the things on his cart.
'I don't think so,' he said.
When the gipsy looked at her,
there was still desire in his eyes.
But now the desire was less strong.
'The old gipsy dreamed
something about you,' he said.
'Did she?' cried Yvette, very interested.
'What did she tell you?'
'She said, "Be braver in your body,
or your luck will leave you." And then she
said, "Listen for the voice of water."'
'What does that mean?' asked Yvette in surprise.
'I asked her that question,' the gipsy said.
'She says that she doesn't know.'
Then he was silent, as he looked at her soft face.
'All right,' she said.
'I don't understand the words now, but
perhaps I'll understand them in the future.'
She looked at him with clear, shining eyes.
'Aren't you coming to the quarry again?' he said.
'Perhaps I'll come, sometime,' she said.
'It's spring!' he said, smiling
and looking round at the sun.
'We're going to pack up our
camp soon, and go away.'
'All right,' Yvette said.
'Perhaps I will visit before you go.
I'll come and say goodbye to your wife,
and the old woman who sent me the message.'
But Yvette did not visit the
gipsies camp at the quarry.
She went out with her friends to parties,
and she danced with Leo Wetherell.
She wanted to go and say goodbye to the gipsies.
But she did not.
It was Friday afternoon.
The weather was fine, and the sun shone brightly
on the yellow flowers in the rectory garden.
The River Papple was very full of water.
The water rushed quickly and
noisily under the stone bridge.
It was unusual for the river
to have so much water in it.
Yvette felt very lazy.
She did not want to do anything.
She walked in the garden by the river.
The rector had gone out, and Lucille was at work.
Granny was inside the house with Aunt Cissie.
Yvette sat on a wooden seat, which
was only a few feet above the river.
She thought about the gipsies.
'The gipsies camp is a better home for me,
than here in the rectory,' she thought.
Yvette looked again at the river.
The brown water was rushing past
the garden extremely quickly.
She remembered the message from the old
gipsy: 'Listen for the voice of water.'
Yvette heard a voice calling her name.
Aunt Cissie was standing by a door
of the house, waving her hand.
'Yvette! I'm going to the
village!' Cissie shouted.
'I won't be away for long.
Don't forget that Granny is alone.'
'All right!' Yvette shouted back.
The sun was beginning to go down.
It was past five o'clock.
Yvette would have to go
back into the rectory soon.
Once again, she would have to be in
those horrible rooms with Granny.
She walked by the river.
She did not want to go inside the ugly house.
Suddenly she heard the sharp noise
of a horse and cart on the road.
And somebody was shouting.
It was the gipsy.
He was waving his hands at
her wildly, and shouting.
Yvette turned and looked behind her.
At that moment, she heard a sound like
the roar of a great and dangerous animal.
A huge wall of water was coming around the
bend of the river and rushing down towards her.
The gipsy was shouting and
running across the garden.
He pulled her arm and screamed, 'Run!'
The huge wave of water swept Yvette off her feet.
The gipsy pulled her towards the house.
He was trying to take her to the
steps that led up to the front door.
But before they reached the steps, another
wave hit them and covered their heads.
The water was as cold as ice.
The gipsy pulled Yvette up again.
'Go to the steps!' he shouted in Yvette's
ear, pushing her in front of him.
At last, they reached the steps of the house.
Another wall of water came roaring
to the house, and the walls shook.
The gipsy pushed open the door
and they were swept inside.
The water filled the hall.
Suddenly they saw Granny
come out of the drawing room.
She felt the water all around her legs,
and opened her mouth in a cry of fear.
Yvette climbed up the stairs.
Water poured from her hair and clothes.
The gipsy followed her, his
wet black hair over his eyes.
From the top of the stairs, they stared at the
flood, which rushed through the hall below them.
Yvette saw Granny's body in the water.
Her old face was purple and
her mouth opened and closed.
But no sound came out.
She was trying to hold onto
the stairs with one hand.
Yvette saw the old woman's gold
wedding ring shining on her finger.
Another wave of water struck the house
and there was a strange cracking noise.
Yvette reached the door of her bedroom.
The water moved below them like a wild brown sea.
They felt the house begin to move.
'The house is going to fall!' shouted the gipsy.
'Where is the chimney? The chimney is strong.
It won't fall.
We must get near the chimney.
Then we'll be safe.'
'Come in here! In here!' said Yvette.
The chimney was in one wall of Yvette's bedroom.
They went into the room and the
gipsy looked out of the window.
Outside, between the house and the
hill, there was a sea of water.
Broken trees and other things were being
swept around in the wild brown flood.
There was a terrible noise
from somewhere in the house.
Walls were falling.
'It's all right,' said the gipsy.
'This room is safe.'
He pointed to the chimney.
'Look, the chimney is strong.
It's like a tower.
But we must get warm.
Take off your wet clothes and get into the bed.
I'll rub you with a towel so that you can get dry.
I'll dry myself too.'
The gipsy pulled off his wet clothes.
He took a towel and began to
rub his cold wet body quickly.
Yvette took off her dress.
Her body was shaking.
The gipsy went to the door and looked out.
The sky was quite dark now.
The end of the house that was
nearest to the river had gone.
The water had swept the walls away.
The stairs had disappeared too.
'It's all right! The water isn't
rising any higher,' said the gipsy.
'Get into the bed.
Lie under the blankets.'
Yvette pulled the sheets
and blankets over her head.
Her body was shaking with cold.
Suddenly she uncovered her
head and looked at the gipsy.
'M-make me warm!' she cried.
Her teeth were snapping
together between each word.
'I w-will d-die from the c-cold.'
The gipsy nodded his head
and held her in his arms.
His body was shaking too.
He held her body tightly against his own body.
Slowly, they began to feel warm again.
At last, they slept.
The next day, the sun was
shining in a beautiful blue sky.
The bridge had broken and disappeared.
But the water had stopped rising.
Most of the rectory had
been destroyed in the flood.
The south-west corner of the house was
now a great pile of mud and stones.
By midday, men from Papplewick
village arrived at the rectory.
They used ladders to get
across the river to the house.
In the kitchen, they found Granny's body
among the mud, trees and broken furniture.
Then more villagers came running down the hill.
They had a message from the old gipsy.
He had said that his son had
been near the rector's house.
He had seen Yvette at the top of the house.
Everyone began to search for Yvette.
The men put a long ladder up
to the window of her bedroom.
A policeman from Papplewick climbed up the
ladder and broke the glass of the window.
He saw Yvette lying in the bed, asleep.
The noise of the breaking glass woke her.
She sat up suddenly, holding a blanket around her.
The policeman shouted to the people
below, 'Miss Yvette's in bed!'
'Don't be frightened, miss,' he said to Yvette.
'Don't worry anymore.
You're safe now.'
Yvette did not understand.
Was the policeman talking about the gipsy?
Where was her gipsy?
What had happened to him?
He had gone!
And a policeman was looking into the room!
'If you get dressed, miss, we'll take you
down to safe ground,' said the policeman.
'You can't stay here.
The house will probably fall.'
The policeman turned his head away and waited.
Yvette took some clothes from
a cupboard and put them on.
The gipsy's wet clothes
were no longer on the floor.
There was just a wet mark on the carpet.
Yvette called to the policeman.
'We must get out of the house as
soon as possible, miss,' he said.
'The house may fall.'
'Really!' said Yvette calmly.
'Is it as bad as that?'
She heard shouts from outside.
She went to the window and looked out.
There, below, was her father.
The rector's arms were wide open and
tears were running down his face.
'I'm all right, Daddy,' Yvette said calmly.
And tears began to run down her own face.
'Don't cry, miss, don't cry!' said the policeman.
'The rector has lost his mother, but
he's very thankful that you're alive.'
'Is Granny drowned?' asked Yvette.
'I'm afraid that she is dead,
poor lady!' said the policeman.
'Can you go down the ladder, miss?'
Yvette looked at the ladder.
It did not look safe.
But then she remembered the words of
the old gipsy: 'Be braver in the body.'
'Oh, yes!' she said.
At the bottom of the ladder,
she ran into her father's arms.
Later, a car took Yvette and her
father to the Framleys house.
Lucille and Aunt Cissie were waiting there.
Lucille cried when she saw
that her sister was safe.
Even Aunt Cissie was happy that Yvette was safe.
'I can't cry about Granny, now that
Yvette is alive!' Aunt Cissie said.
The flood had happened because of a great
reservoir, live miles from the rectory.
The reservoir contained a huge amount of water.
But the wall of the reservoir had
become weak and had suddenly burst.
The water had rushed through the broken wall,
and down to the village, in a great flood.
Yvette did not tell anyone that
the gipsy had been in her bedroom.
She only said that he had
taken her inside the house.
She said that she had climbed up the stairs alone.
But Yvette knew that the gipsy had escaped.
The old gipsy had come to the
village to get the horse and cart.
He had said that his son was safe.
'We should thank the gipsy who
saved Yvette's life,' said Lucille.
The rector and his daughters went to the quarry.
But it was empty.
The gipsies had packed up their camp and left.
That night, Yvette lay in her bed and
thought about everything that had happened.
There was a deep pain in her heart.
'Oh, I love him! I love him! I
love him!' she said to herself.
Sometime later, Yvette received a short letter.
Dear Miss,
I saw in the paper that you were all right.
So was I.
I hope that I'll see you again one day.
I came that day to say goodbye,
but the water gave me no time.
Your servant,
Joe Boswell
For the first time, Yvette
realized that the gipsy had a name.