THE HARE AND THE TORTOISE
"Look at me!" said the Hare to the other animals.
"Just look how fast I can run."
The Hare ran across a field as fast as he could.
All the animals agreed that yes the Hare was very fast.
The Hare ran back.
"See," he shouted.
"I'm not even out of breath."
"Yeah, that was fast," said a Fox.
"So who wants a race?" said the Hare.
"Anybody think they could beat me?"
None of the animals spoke.
"See," said the Hare.
"You're all too scared to even try."
"I'll have a go," said the Tortoise.
The Hare laughed.
"You? The slowest creature in the whole world? I'm not
wasting my time racing a Tortoise."
"What's the matter?" said the Tortoise.
"Scared I might beat you?"
Some of the animals laughed at that so the Hare said, "Alright then, Tortoise. Let's have a race...right
now...then we'll see who's laughing."
"Not today," said the Tortoise.
"We'll race next week. Got to do a bit of training first."
Next morning the animals watched the Tortoise do his
"training".
First he did some gentle stretching exercises to warm
himself up... and then he started to run.
"Has he started running yet?" asked the Fox.
"Hard to tell with Tortoises," said the Badger.
"He's definitely moving."
"Is he?" said the Fox.
"Tortoise, are you sure about this?" said the Crow.
"I mean the Hare IS very fast and you…well…"
"Don't worry," said the Tortoise.
"This is just day one. I'll speed up. You'll see."
On the day of the race crowds of animals came to watch.
The Tortoise slowly made his way to the starting line and
then suddenly...
...the Hare arrived at top speed wearing a brand-new track
suit and four expensive-looking trainers.
"The race starts here," said the Fox pointing to a line on
the ground.
"And ends at that tree on the other side of the field. First
one to touch the tree is the winner."
"Right, let's get on with it," said the Hare.
"Ready Tortoise? Ready to see some real speed?"
"I'm ready," said the Tortoise.
"Ready, steady...go!" said the Fox and the race began.
The Hare roared off then stopped and looked back.
The Tortoise was still crossing the starting line.
The Hare ran back to the Tortoise.
"Didn't you hear him say go? You can start, you know."
"I have started," said the Tortoise.
"Look," said the Hare.
"You're going so slowly I'm going to have a rest. Might even
have a little sleep. I'll finish the race when I wake up and still beat you by miles."
The Hare lay down in the sun and fell asleep.
The Tortoise kept going.
Slowly, steadily he moved across the field and by evening
time he was getting close to the finishing tree.
Still the Hare slept on and now the animals started to get
excited.
"You know what? I think he might win," said a Rabbit.
"I can't believe it," said the Badger.
"The Tortoise might actually win."
The animals started to get excited and as the Tortoise got
close to the finishing tree they started to cheer.
"Come on Tortoise," they shouted.
"Nearly there. Keep going old friend. Keep going."
But the noise of the cheering crowd woke up the Hare.
He looked across the field, saw the Tortoise about to reach
the tree and in a flash he was running.
The Tortoise heard the Hare thundering up behind him but he
kept going...and going...and suddenly he was there.
Just in time the Tortoise touched the tree with his nose.
He'd done it.
The Tortoise had beaten the Hare fair and square.
"There you go," said the Badger.
"Slow and steady's sometimes better than fast and flashy."
"Not fair," said the Hare.
"I was asleep. We have to run the race again. It's not
fair."
But no-one was listening to the Hare.
THE FROGS AND THE OX
"Mum! Mum! Come quickly!" called the little frog, hopping
and skipping with excitement...
"Come and see the monster!" He called.
"It's got two big spikes sticking out of its head and a
funny brush thing at the other end and it goes "OARRR AGH!"
And it kicks frogs."
"Not now dear," said the little frog's mother.
"Come on mum! Please!"
Mother frog looked more closely at the little one.
"You're Stanley, aren't you?"
"No mum, I'm Zebadee."
"Are you really? You all look so alike."
She had 247 children, and it is hard to remember that many names, so she called everyone Stanley to give her memory a
rest.
"Mu-ummm…" cried Zebedee,
"I haven't finished breakfast, dear."
The little frog hesitated.
"Can I have some then?"
"No, Stanley," she said.
"You're not a tadpole any more. Go and find your own slugs -
and stop jiggling about, you're giving me a headache."
"I'm not jiggling about, I'm hopping about."
"Well stop it. It looks like exercise, and I can't be having with that sort of thing. How would it be if I were to flip
and flop about like you, doing exercise?"
The little frog thought about it.
"You wouldn't be so podgy," he said.
"Exactly!" said his mother.
"You don't get a jelly-belly like mine by exercising. I get all the exercise I need chewing. Now, what's all the fuss
about?"
"It's an Ox! And it's really gross and his shoes have split
down the middle."
"There are no such things as monsters, Stanley, and no
creature in the pond is bigger than me."
"But it is bigger than you, mum. Lot's bigger. I promise."
"Right!" said his mum.
"We'll see about that! I'll go with you, and if you are
telling fibs you'll have no worms for a week."
The damp hollow she sat in was home to a good assortment of
slugs.
But she had eaten too many of them.
The big jelly-belly she was so proud of made it difficult to
get about.
Now she could only half-hop, and flop, and then stop.
Hop, flop and stop, until she was all tired out and could go
no further.
"Stop, Stanley!"
"You've only moved half a metre, mum."
"Far enough," she wheezed.
She took a deep breath – and then she took a deep breath –
and then she took a deep breath.
"Is the ox as big as this?" she asked.
She sounded odd, because it's hard to speak, blown up like a
beach ball.
"Much bigger than that," said the little frog.
So she sucked in more air, and sucked in more air, and
sucked in more air.
"No, mum – it's still bigger…"
So she took in another breath, and …and…she shot into the air like an escaped balloon that zips around the room making
rude noises because you let go of the end.
"YAAAAAH!" she yelled, looping-the-loop and fizzing off in all directions before crashing - with a spectacular splash -
right in front of the ox!
The ox looked bored with the whole thing.
Water dribbled from his mouth.
"Stanley!" she called back to the little frog a field and a
half away.
"Let that be a lesson to you!"
But the lesson was hers really.
THE FOX AND THE CROW
"One morning a Fox was walking through the woods looking for something tasty to eat for his breakfast when his nose
picked up a scent - a scent of something very interesting. He stood still and sniffed the air."
"Cheese," he said.
"I smell cheese. Now why would there be cheese in the middle
of a wood like this?"
"The Fox didn't have to wait long to find out because there sitting on a branch high up in a tree sat a crow and in the
crow's beak was the biggest piece of cheese he'd ever seen."
"Now the Fox loved cheese more than anything in the whole world and he decided that come what may he would have that
piece of cheese for himself."
"Morning Mr Crow," he said.
"Why don't you come down and have a little chat."
"The Crow didn't reply. He just sat on his branch and looked
down at the Fox."
"He must think I'm stupid," thought the Crow to himself.
"That fox is after my cheese. If I fly down there he'll jump on me and gobble me up first and then the cheese. Foxes
can't climb trees so I'll just sit up here and enjoy my piece of cheese."
"The Crow was just about to swallow his lump of cheese when
the Fox said."
"That cheese looks a bit mouldy to me. I wouldn't eat it if I were you. Mouldy cheese is very very dangerous. You could
easily get ill from bad cheese. If I were you I'd be on the safe side and just drop that cheese right now."
"Oh no," thought the Crow.
"I'm not falling for that. There's nothing wrong with this cheese. I found it fresh this morning. It smells wonderful
and I'm going to eat it right now."
"The Crow looked straight at the Fox and waggled his piece
of cheese as if to say "Look what I've got!
Aren't I the lucky one!""
"Right," thought the Fox.
"This Crow isn't quite as stupid as he looks. I'm going to
have to try something else."
"You know, Mr Crow," said the Fox, "you really do have the
most lovely feathers."
"The Crow smiled to himself. He was rather proud of his sleek black feathers. The Fox was right. They were rather
lovely."
"And your head," said the Fox.
"Your head is very fine indeed. Makes you look fierce...but
wise at the same time."
"Right again," thought the Crow.
"That Fox knows what he's talking about because I do look
fierce... and I am very very wise."
"And I bet you've got the most beautiful singing voice too,"
said the Fox.
"I can tell just by looking at you. I mean all crows are
good singers..."
"The Crow nodded."
"And I bet you're the best singer out of all the crows."
"The Crow nodded again."
"See, I can tell you're a great singer just by looking at you. Oh how I'd love to hear you sing. Just once. That's all
I ask. Just one little song would make me so happy."
"The Crow's mind was racing as the Fox started to walk
away."
"Oh well I see I'm not in luck today," sighed the Fox.
"Suppose I'll just have to go and listen to a boring old sky
lark...or nightingale..."
"The crow thought to himself. "The Fox is right.
I'm a wonderful singer.
Much better than those boring nightingales...and
larks...very over-rated...
I shall sing.
I shall sing for the Fox right now.""
"As the crow opened his beak and started to sing...the piece
of cheese fell to the ground."
"The Fox licked his lips. "Thank you Mr Crow," he said. "You
can stop singing now.
That horrible sound's spoiling my breakfast.""
"But you said you loved to hear a crow sing."
"Never believe what people tell you when they're trying to steal your cheese," said the Fox...and he winked at the crow
as he gobbled up the last little bit.
THE MONKEY AS KING
"There was a huge competition in the Indian jungle – and the
prize was – "To be King of the Beasts!"
It was very exciting!
To be King of all the Beasts was a grand thing – when you were King you got to wear a shiny crown and all the animals
had to call you "Sire".
Of course, lots of animals entered the competition.
Each animal got to say their piece on a big stage while the
other animals judged."
"The first up on stage was Fox. Fox was a very clever animal. He spoke very well about the rights of the people
and the duties of the King; but he used such long words like "fiscal" and "jurisdiction" that most of the animals got bored and fell asleep."
"And," said Fox, "never forget that there are many new traps
around in the jungle. Traps laid by Man to catch animals! Of course, there never was a trap made that could catch a fox. So this is my promise to you. If I am made King, I will educate each and every animal in avoiding these traps. Thank you."
"Fox went off the stage and was met by Monkey."
"Oooh-ooh-ooh! That was a fine and educated speech you just
made!" said Monkey."
"Well, thank you Monkey," replied Fox, pleased."
"Yes – very clever you are," Monkey carried on.
"But that is not what the animals want in a king. Watch
this!"
"And he bounded on to the stage."
"Thank you! Thank you!" he shouted.
"It's great to be here! You know - that Fox is a clever fellow. But – poor Fox - he's got no nose. How does he
smell, I hear you ask? He smells...AWFUL!"
"Oooh-ooh-ooh! Do you want to see me dance?" cried Monkey."
"YEH!" roared the audience."
"And monkey danced. He frolicked and he pranced and he
capered and he danced! And what faces he pulled!"
"Monkey was funny. The audience laughed and roared and held their sides. And that is how Monkey became King of the
Beasts."
"Oooh-ooh-ooh! Well, Fox!" he smirked, as he paraded up and
down in his gold crown.
"Funny beats clever!"
"PA!" said Fox, angrily.
"We'll see about that!"
"The next day, Fox saw Monkey lolling around in his throne
with his golden crown upon his head."
"No hard feelings…Sire," he said.
"You won, fair and square. And I want to give you a present
fit for a clever king."
"Oooh-ooh-ooh!" said Monkey.
"Being King is boring work! Where's your present?"
"It's a little way into the forest. Come with me!"
"So Monkey and Fox set off into the forest together."
"Oooh-ooh-ooh! Where is it? Where is it?" said Monkey,
getting excited."
"There it is, Sire," said sly Fox, pointing at a big, ripe
banana on the jungle floor."
"YUM YUM!" cried Monkey, and dived off to pick it up."
"Later that day, the animals were running around in
confusion."
"Where's the King?" they cried.
"Has anyone seen the King?"
"At last they found him. He was sitting – in a TRAP!"
"Monkey held out his arms through the bars. "Oooh-ooh-ooh!
When I went to pick up a banana – this trap fell over me!
Please get me out!""
"But none of the animals knew anything about traps - except
for Fox."
"Fox sat down and curled his long red tail around him."
"Fox! Fox!" cried Monkey.
"Please help me!"
"The Fox turned to look at the animals."
"Should a King be clever?" asked Fox"
"Yes!" the animals cried."
"Does an animal that is clever fall in to a trap?" asked
Fox."
"The animals were silent. They looked at Monkey."
"You are a very foolish monkey," said Fox.
"I will get you out of the trap, but you must give up your crown. The King of the Beasts should be an animal that is
smarter than to fall into traps. Don't you think?"
"And all the other animals agreed."
THE BUNDLE OF STICKS
"Mrs Mckenzie had six strong sons. They were Peter, Paul and
Patrick, Philip, Frankie and Fred. The only trouble was they couldn't stop arguing with each other!"
"When Mrs Mckenzie wanted a well dug – do you think six strong sons could do that? "We'll dig a hole here!" said
Peter. "No – over here!" said Patrick."
"And each of the six strong sons grabbed a spade and started digging different holes in different parts of the garden!
"That's no use at all," she sighed."
"Mrs Mckenzie asked her six strong sons to row her across the river to see her friend. "We'll do it!" cried Peter and
Paul. They leapt into the boat and sat down facing the front and picked up oars. "No we will!" shouted Patrick and Philip. And they sat down facing backwards and picked up the
oars."
"And though they pulled at the oars until the sweat dripped off them – they were rowing the boat in opposite directions
and the boat went absolutely nowhere! "Oh that's no use at all," she sighed."
"One day there was a notice in the paper. "Grand Competition to build the biggest barn in the county!" it read. "£600
prize!"
"I'll win that!" said Peter.
"No I'll win it!" said Paul.
Patrick, Philip, Frankie and Fred all disagreed…and they all
fell to arguing."
"Suddenly, Mrs Mckenzie jumped to her feet. "Quiet!" she said. Then she climbed up on her chair. "Quiet!" she
shouted. Then she climbed up right on top of the table. "WILL YOU BE QUIET!" she roared. Six sons went very, very quiet. They looked up at their mother in astonishment."
"That's better," Mrs Mckenzie said.
"Now, you! Fetch me one of those big bundles of sticks that
we keep for the fire." "Yes Mum!" said Peter."
"He ran out the door and came back with sticks tied together in abundle as fat as your arm. "Here you are Mum," he
panted. Mrs Mckenzie folded her arms. "Now, my fine strong son, break that bundle in two!""
"Peter smirked at his brothers. "Easy!" he boasted, and he took the bundle in both hands. He bent the bundle and he
bowed the bundle but he could not break the bundle. "Well?" said Mrs Mckenzie, tapping her foot."
"Peter hung his head in shame. "I can't do it!"
"Pass the bundle to Paul," said Mrs Mckenzie.
"Ha, ha, ha! Watch this, ha, ha!" sneered Paul.
He bent the bundle and he bowed the bundle but he could not
break the bundle.
And neither could Patrick, Philip, Frankie or Fred."
"Give it to me!" said Mrs Mckenzie.
She took the bundle of sticks and untied the string."
"She gave one stick to each of her sons. "Can you break that?" she asked. CRACK! Went the sticks as the six strong
sons easily broke them."
"And what have you broken?" asked Mrs Mckenzie.
"Er...a stick?" asked Peter, looking down at his hands."
"Yes," Mrs Mckenzie nodded.
"But between you, you have broken the bundle of sticks." The
six strong sons looked at each other."
"One of you wasn't strong enough," explained Mrs Mckenzie,
"but when you all worked together…"
"We were much stronger!" cried Peter, Paul, Patrick, Philip,
Frankie and Fred."
"And so they were."
"And do you know that when they went to the competition, the
six strong sons of Mrs Mckenzie all worked together to build the biggest barn in the county and they won that prize money. All together."
THE GNAT AND THE LION
"Far, far away in a hot land called Africa, lived a Gnat and
a Lion."
"These two creatures were complete opposites. One was weak and one was strong. One was huge and one was tiny. One was
fierce and one was timid. They met one dark night, and this is what happened."
"The Gnat had gone to sleep. He had made himself a swinging
hammock on a blade of grass and he was snoring gently."
"The Lion was awake. He was hunting - and his roar could be
heard in the distance."
"It woke the Gnat."
"What is that?" he asked."
"The Lion roared again. The sound was even louder."
"It's getting closer," thought the Gnat, holding his
breath."
"A minute later the Lion came into view."
"When the Gnat saw who it was he felt relieved."
"Oh!" he said.
"It's only you."
"This annoyed the Lion."
"Only me!" he murmured silkily, narrowing his yellow eyes.
Are you aware I am the King of the Beasts."
"When Lions narrow their eyes and murmur silkily, they are
at their most dangerous. But the Gnat wasn't worried."
"He opened his tiny mouth and yawned."
"You may be the King of the Beasts," he said, "but I can
outwit you anytime."
"The Lion snorted."
"Ha!" he said.
"I could flatten you with one swipe of my paw."
"The Gnat stood up on his spindly legs."
"Go on then," he said."
"The lion raised his paw above his head and brought it down
as hard as he could."
"The Gnat jumped out of the way."
"Missed," he said."
"Humming a little tune he began buzzing round the Lions
head."
"Zzzz, Zzzz, Zzzz, Diddly, Diddly, Dee. Zzzz, Zzzz, Zzzz,
Try And Catch Me."
"The Lion was furious. He twisted his head this way and that. He snapped, he snarled, he swirled his tail, he swiped
with his paws."
"But the Gnat was too nimble."
"A thought came into the Lion's head."
"If I keep perfectly still, the Gnat will settle down, and I
can pounce."
"But the Gnat didn't settle down. He acted quickly."
"He flew straight up the lions nose!"
"And began to bite."
"Roaring with pain the Lion shook his head. He stuffed his
claws up his nose."
"The Gnat pulled the hairs inside the Lion's nostrils."
"Make me the King of the Beasts," he called."
"Never," roared the Lion."
"The Gnat bit him again. The Lion's nose began to swell. He
could hardly breath."
"Say it," said the Gnat.
"Say - The Gnat is the King of the Beasts."
"The Lion could bear it no longer."
"The Gnat is King of the beasts," he muttered."
"His face hurt. His nose was running. His eyes were watering. Without saying another word the once proud Lion
turned and disappeared into the long grass."
"The Gnat was full of glee."
"I am the smartest creature that ever lived," he boasted."
"He began looking for a new place to make his home. He
wanted something soft and comfortable."
"Ahead, draped over a bush was what looked like a white,
lacy shawl."
"That's perfect," said the Gnat.
And he wrapped himself in it."
"At first, the Gnat didn't notice a small creature moving swiftly towards him, climbing delicately over the lacy
threads. When he did, it was too late."
"Hello, Gnat," said the Spider."
"The Gnat tried to fly away, but he was stuck."
"You can't harm me," he said, "I'm the new King of the
Beasts."
"We'll see about that," said the Spider."
"And he ate the Gnat for his supper."
THE NORTH WIND AND THE SUN
"It was a fine but very cold winter's day as the Sun shone
down on the snow-covered earth below."
"What a beautiful sight," it thought.
"And look at the little white sails of the ships on the blue
sea. I want to take my time travelling across the sky today. After all, what's the rush?"
"Suddenly, a freezing cold blast of air screeched past – and
nearly blew the Sun along with it."
"Out of my way, Sun," roared the Wind.
"See those ships? I'm going to blow them right off course.
They won't know what's hit them…"
"The Wind blew and blew – it blew so hard that the ship's sails ripped apart. All the Sun could do was watch as the
sailors shivered in the icy blast, shook their fists and cried out in anger."
"Not again, Wind," sighed the Sun.
"Why do you have to cause misery and chaos all the time?"
"Because I like showing just how strong I am," replied the
Wind.
"You sit in the sky and do nothing except shine, but I am
full of force and energy."
"Hmmm…" said the Sun, looking thoughtful.
"I have an idea. Let's have a contest to see which of us is
the stronger."
"I know who will win," said the Wind.
"We shall see," replied the Sun.
"Do you see that man down there?"
"The Wind looked where the Sun was pointing. A young man was walking along a windy road through the mountains. It was so
cold, he was wearing a heavy winter coat to keep warm."
"Let's see which one of us is strong enough to take his coat
off him," suggested the Sun."
"Easy, I can do that in no time," boasted the Wind.
"Go on then," said the Sun.
I'll watch you from behind a cloud."
"The Wind blew and blew. It blew so hard that the birds had
to cling to the trees to stop being swept away."
"The man shivered and did up the top button of his coat as the snow swirled in the air. The Wind kept on blowing – but
the more it did so, the tighter the man pulled his coat around him to keep warm."
"I give up," gasped the Wind at last.
"I've got no more puff left."
"Now it's my turn," said the Sun as it emerged from the
cloud."
"The Sun gently breathed in the cold air. The stronger it
breathed in, the larger and rounder it seemed to glow."
"On the white earth below the air was becoming warmer. The Wind watched in awe as the snow began to melt. Icicles were
dripping and even the thick ice on the lakes was starting to thaw and crack."
"The man looked round in wonder at the melting landscape. It had been such a long, cold winter that it was a joy to feel
the warmth of the Sun on his face. He undid his top button, then a second…"
"What a lovely day it's turning out to be," the man thought.
"It's too warm for this heavy winter coat. Everything is so bright and beautiful, I just want to enjoy the Sun and rest
a while – I might even have a little nap."
"The Wind was beside itself with annoyance as the man sat under the shade of a large rock and took off his coat. It
was so annoyed it kept making little angry puffs."
"Your icy blasts hardened his heart and made him
determination to keep his coat on," said the Sun.
"But my glowing rays opened his heart - and his coat
buttons. Look, I've cheered up those poor sailors too."
"The sailors on the broken ships were cheering and waving up at the Sun. "Now they can mend their sails – and I shall
carry on shining until their ships can sail again," said the Sun."
"Down below on the Earth, the young man looked up at the Sun
as if he had heard him speak."
"That Wind – it was strong. But the Sun is stronger still," he murmured to himself, before nodding off for a restful
sleep."
THE FOX AND THE GRAPES
"One hot day at the end of summer a fox trotted along the dusty path to a farm, listening out for other creatures and
sniffing the air, as foxes do."
"It was getting late, and after a long day the sun looked a little red in the face and had dropped out of sight behind a
bush."
"It was the time of day that the fox liked best. The farmer's work was finished. He had taken off his muddy boots
and gone inside for tea. The fox only showed himself when the farmer had left his boots outside. Then, if he came running after the fox with his gun - as farmers do - he would first have to sit on the step, put his boots back on again, and the fox would have plenty of time to run away."
"The fox is certainly very clever, and handsome too, but no
one knows this better than the fox himself."
"He would look at his reflection for hours admiring his beautiful red coat with its snow white bib. He would look at
his smart black legs, which matched his sleek black ears. And his
sleek black ears matched his shiny black nose, which looked
exactly like a small polished pebble."
"But best of all, he thought, was his glorious bushy tail,
like a big, soft paintbrush dipped in whitewash."
"The farmer locked in the hens at night, and the rabbits and geese, and he shooed the ducks onto their little island in
the middle of the duck pond so that the clever fox could not get them. He knew the fox hated swimming."
"But the fox did not only eat chickens and rabbits and ducks and geese, though he would put them all on the menu given
half a chance. If he couldn't get into the hen house, and he couldn't swim to the duck island, and if the geese made a fuss and rattled their beaks at him - as geese do - then there was always something else to eat."
"There were slugs and grasshoppers and mice and worms and frogs and eggs and big meaty bones the farmer put out with
the rubbish."
"And tonight there was fruit!"
"The fox looked up at a huge bunch of juicy grapes hanging
above his head. He was very thirsty. He could imagine the
sweet, delicious juice running down his chin."
"But he couldn't reach them. He was clever, though, wasn't he? Everyone said so, and the fox was used to getting what
he wanted – so he would take a run at it, and…jump!"
"Missed!"
"He jumped again…And again. He leaped and hopped and bounced and somersaulted. But the juicy grapes were always just out
of reach."
"The fox stopped at last, hot and panting."
"Haaa well!" he said to himself.
"The grapes don't look that juicy and I just know they will be as bitter as lemons. Phooey! Who wants to eat sour
grapes!"
"And the fox walked slowly along the dusty path back to his den with his nose in the air and his tail between his legs -
as hungry, disappointed foxes do."
"Sometimes, when we can't get what we want, we pretend we
never wanted it anyway."
THE DOG, THE COCKEREL AND THE FOX
"Dog lived in the farmyard and it was her job to let
everyone know when someone was at the gate."
"And she did her job very well."
"Cockerel lived in the farmyard too and it was his job to
wake everyone up in the morning!"
"He was an excellent alarm clock."
"One day Dog said to Cockerel "Let's go for an adventure in
the big wide world.""
""I'm not sure that's a good idea," Cockerel replied, "I've heard that there's a fox nearby whose favourite food is
cockerel pie!""
""Well if a fox tries to bake you in a pie!" said Dog, "I'll
soon sort him out…GRRRRR GRRRR!""
""In that case, I'll come
with you!" said Cockerel."
"So off they went."
"The big wide world was wide indeed…with sky at the top and hills underneath and a squiggly path that seemed to go on
forever."
"The two friends journeyed along the path, then, just as the
sun slipped behind the hills they came to a wood."
""It'll be dark soon," said Cockerel. "Let's find a place to
sleep.""
""This tree looks perfect," woofed Dog, "it's big and it's
hollow, so I can curl up inside and keep guard!""
""And there's a wide branch where I can roost!" said
Cockerel."
"Dog curled up in the hollow tree and Cockerel roosted on
the branch."
"Suddenly they heard a sound."
""What was that?" said Cockerel."
""Just an owl," woofed Dog."
""Oh, thank goodness," said Cockerel, "I thought it was a
fox coming to gobble me up!""
""Yes," said Cockerel, "foxes are slinky and sneaky and sly
and their favourite food is cockerel pie!""
""I'll protect you!" said Dog, "A fox can't find you on that
branch anyway, not unless you
cock-a-doodle-doo.""
""That's true!" said Cockerel. "Goodnight, Dog!""
""Goodnight, Cockerel - and remember not to
cock-a-doodle-doo in the morning, or the fox might hear
you!""
"Cockerel slept happily after that."
"But in the morning when the sun came up, he thought he was still on the farm. So he let out a loud COCK-A-DOODLE-DOO.
Which woke up Fox."
""Ooops!" clucked Cockerel, "Now I've gone and done it!""
""Good morning, Cockerel," growled Fox."
""Good morning!"
Cockerel replied nervously."
"Fox narrowed his eyes, "I haven't seen you in this wood
before!""
""I only arrived last night," clucked Cockerel nervously."
""Why don't you invite me up, it would be rude not to," said
Fox."
""I haven't tidied up yet!" said Cockerel, "Pop back
later!""
""I don't mind if your branch is untidy!" said Fox."
"Cockerel sighed, "Come on up then," he said slyly. "Go round to the door at the bottom of the tree and my porter
will let you in!""
"Fox grinned to himself a sneaky grin…a thread of drool hung from his chin. He went to the hollow in the tree…where Dog
was waiting patiently."
""Hey, Mr Fox, you wanted to trick me and gobble me up, but
I tricked you instead!" clucked Cockerel."
"Fox ran off as fast as he could… and he's never been seen
in that part of the wood again."
""That was an adventure!"
Dog yapped."
"And home they went to tell the tale of how the Fox's plan
had failed."
THE MILLER, HIS SON AND THE DONKEY
"Fetch our old donkey," the miller said to his son one day.
"We're taking him to market. We need money and we've nothing
else to sell."
"The son ran to the stable where the donkey was kept. He
threw a halter over its neck. And the donkey wasn't
happy!!!"
"Grumpy old thing!" said the son, as he led the donkey out
of the stable."
"I'm not sorry we're selling you!"
"I'm not sorry either," brayed the donkey.
"When was the last time you gave me a carrot!"
"We won't ride him," said the miller.
"It'll be easier to sell him if he's not tired."
"They led the donkey down the street towards the town."
"Hey, you," a man shouted suddenly."
"Why don't you ride the donkey?"
"That's what it's for!" another man hollered."
"The crowd began to laugh."
"The miller hated to be laughed at. "Get up, son," he said.
The son climbed up on to the donkey's back."
"At least it's the smaller one," the donkey grumbled as he
felt the son's weight on his back.
"Something to be grateful for, I suppose."
"But they hadn't travelled far before they passed three
merchants, whispering and shaking their heads."
"What is the world coming to?" the miller heard one of them
say.
"Get down, young man. Let your master ride the donkey."
"The miller thought he'd better do as they said. "Hop down,
lad, and help me up," he said to his son."
"So the son climbed down and helped his father clamber up."
"Ee-aw!" grumbled the donkey, as the miller landed on his
back.
"What a lump. Worse than a sack of potatoes."
"His back was hard and bony. The miller wasn't sorry when they reached the gates of the town. A group of girls were
standing there, bags and baskets in their hands."
"The miller pulled on the donkey's halter. "Whoa!" he said.
"Let the ladies through first."
"Cor, look at that poor boy," one of the girls said, seeing
the son lead the donkey, his father on top.
"His master should let him ride too."
"Lazy thing."
"The miller was a bit cross, but he liked to please. "Get up
behind me, son," he said."
"What! Both of you at once!" the donkey screeched.
"I'm an old donkey. Ee-aw!"
"Look at that poor creature," a woman said as the donkey
crawled slowly along the road, head drooping.
"Two of them on his back."
"And one of them so big!" said her friend."
"They should be carrying it!"
"Yes, they are right," thought the miller, and climbed down.
"Get down, son. We'll carry him between us." They tied the
donkey's legs to a pole, the donkey slung between them."
"Now they know what it's like to be a donkey - carrying great loads all day," he thought as the miller and his son
stumbled down the street."
"The townspeople had never seen such a sight before. They ran out of their houses to watch. "Don't they look silly",
they laughed."
"The donkey hated to be laughed at. He pushed and he pulled,
trying to free himself."
"Slowly the ropes that bound him began to loosen. "One –
more – heave," he gasped as they stumbled up to the bridge."
"And with a final tug and a kick he was free. Over the bridge he tumbled. Down, down, down he fell. Splash! Into
the river below."
"He thrashed and he brayed."
"But there was nothing he could do."
"Ee-aw. Ee-aw," he cried.
Ee— aw!"
"The miller watched helplessly as his donkey was swept
away."
"Silly me," he said as he and his son trudged homewards.
"By trying to please everyone I have lost my donkey - and
now I have nothing left to sell."
THE WOLF AND THE HERON
"Wolf loved food. He ate breakfast then he ate two more breakfasts, which took him up to his midday snack. This was
followed by three helpings of lunch, tea, dinner, supper and a midnight feast – with barely a burp between them."
"When Wolf went to bed he stared up at the moon and stars
and wondered what they would taste like."
"Absolutely scrumptious," he decided.
Then Wolf would fall asleep and dream of all the food he'd
eat next day."
"One morning Wolf found an enormous, glittering fish in the shallow waters at the edge of the river. So, Wolf gobbled up
the fish as quickly as a great woolly cloud gobbles up the moon. Wolf was about to pat his stomach when he realized something was wrong."
"Ack eurk ach! There's a bone stuck in my throat!" Wolf spluttered and slapped the back of his neck with his
enormous paws.
He coughed, shook his head and waggled his ears but nothing
he did made any difference – the bone was stuck fast."
"I wont be able to eat ever again!" Wolf moaned.
"No more food for me - and the bone hurts, it's like having tummy ache and stubbed toes all at once inside my neck!
Please, will someone help me!" and he whined and stumbled frantically along the riverbank.
Then he noticed…"
"Oh – look at that bird!
Look at that beak!" he croaked."
"Are you looking at me?" asked a Heron as the Wolf's
whiskers tickled his wing."
"Yes," said Wolf and smiled the best smile he'd ever smiled
so that sunlight went "ting" on his teeth.
"I was just thinking what a beautiful bird you are and how pointy and useful that beak of yours is. I wonder if you
could help me?"
"Go on," said the Heron, "I am rather handsome."
"Well, Heron, there's a bone stuck in my throat and it hurts. Worse than that, I can't eat because of it." And
Wolf's stomach rumbled so loudly a nearby family of ducks thought it was thunder and hurried into the rushes.
Wolf lifted up his paw and whined."
"Please, wonderful Heron, kind Heron, use your beak to get
it out."
"Um, well, to tell you the truth, Wolf, I am having a little
rest right now," said the Heron."
"Listen, Heron, my friend, I'll give you a present if you
remove the bone - as a reward."
"Sounds good to me," said the Heron.
"I can always have a rest later. Open your mouth as wide as
you can and I'll have a look."
"Ahhhh," went the Wolf and in went the Heron's head, sliding
carefully between the rows of sharp teeth."
"It was dark in the Wolf's throat but Heron found the bone
and tapped and tweaked and tugged."
"Got it!" Heron said, gently drawing out the bone and
setting it down beside the Wolf.
"Now, what about my reward?"
"Wolf grinned an unpleasant grin that showed all his teeth.
"See these?"
Wolf said, tapping a tune on them with the tip of a long
pointed claw."
"Yes, I had a good look at them a moment ago when my head
was in your mouth," said the trusting Heron."
"Well, snarled Wolf, "I didn't bite your head off, did I?"
"Heron checked his neck. "No you didn't," he replied."
"Well, that's your reward." And Wolf snapped slinked away to
get his next meal."
THE DONKEY IN THE LION'S SKIN
"There was once a foolish donkey who wished he was something
else."
"If only I was a giraffe," he would say, "then I could look over the tops of trees...if only I was an elephant then I
could remember where I left things...if only I was a cheetah then I could run like the wind...or fierce as a rhinoceros..."
"...or cunning as a crocodile..."
"...or strong as a hippo."
"Anything was better than being a donkey. Everyone laughed
at donkeys and he didn't like it one little bit."
"One day, when he was walking through the forest the donkey saw something draped over the branch of a tree. When he got
closer he could see it was a lion costume."
"I'd look good in that," he thought."
"So he put it on."
"It covered him from head to foot."
"The donkey found a pool and looked at his reflection."
"I look magnificent," he said."
"He paraded up and down looking at his reflection from every
angle."
"The massive head of the lion covered his donkey's head and
the lion's golden mane flowed round his neck."
"I look like a lion and I feel like a lion," he said.
"No-one will laugh at me now. I am King of the beasts!"
"The donkey couldn't wait to show himself to other animals. He walked up to a giraffe who was eating leaves from the top
of a tall tree. She stopped when she saw the donkey and bent her long legs in a curtsy."
"Your Majesty," she said, in a fearful voice."
"Greetings, giraffe," said the donkey in a deep, lion-like
voice.
"Won't you join me in a stroll?"
"I can't today," said the giraffe, "I have to get tea for my
children."
"And she ran away as quickly as she could."
"The donkey smiled to himself."
"He saw a hippo in the river."
"The hippo bowed his head when he saw the donkey."
"Your Majesty," he said, in hushed tones."
"Greetings hippo," said the donkey.
"Won't you join me in a stroll?"
"I can't today," said the hippo.
"I have to call on a friend who is sick."
"And he sank out of sight."
"Inside the lion costume the donkey was grinning all over
his face."
"He tripped over a crocodile sunbathing on a rock."
"Your Majesty!" said the crocodile, smiling with his teeth
on the outside of his lips."
"Greetings crocodile," said the donkey.
"Won't you…"
"But the crocodile had slipped into the water and
disappeared."
"The donkey was jubilant."
"He wanted to leap up and down with delight. What a marvellous thing it was to be a lion. A lion was admired and
feared by all the other animals. He felt like a king."
"Just then a wily fox came into view. When he saw the donkey
he turned to run."
"The donkey could contain his delight no longer. "I'm a
lion," he thought. "I look like a lion, I act like a lion.
I feel like a lion.
I BET I EVEN SOUND LIKE A LION.""
"And the foolish donkey lifted his head and roared."
"Hee-Haw, Hee-Haw, Hee-Haw!"
"The fox stopped in his tracks. He knew that sound. He grabbed the lion's mane and pulled. The lion costume came
off in his hands. The donkey stood there, trembling. The fox began to laugh."
"So did the crocodile."
"So did the giraffe."
"And so did the hippo."
"If only I had kept my mouth shut," thought the donkey."
"The other animals put their arms round him."
"Don't worry," they said, "we like you just as you are."
"And they all hurried away before the real lion came along."
THE ANT AND THE GRASSHOPPER
"One hot summer's day a Grasshopper sat on a blade of grass
enjoying the sunshine."
"What a fine day," he said.
"The sun's shining and I've got as much grass as I can eat."
"The Grasshopper spent the whole morning stuffing his face
until he couldn't eat another thing."
"Right," he said.
"Now I'll make some music."
"He rubbed his back legs against his wings and made a loud
buzzing sound."
"Lovely," said the Grasshopper.
"Nothing better than the sound of a happy Grasshopper."
"Give it a rest," said a passing Ant."
"What?" said the Grasshopper."
"I'm trying to work here," said the Ant.
"You're giving me a headache."
"You don't like my music?" said the Grasshopper."
"Not my kind of thing," said the Ant.
"Anyway ain't got time to stand around talking about music.
Got stuff to do."
"Stuff?" said the Grasshopper.
"What stuff have you got to do on a lovely sunny morning
like this?"
"Gotta get this food shifted," said the Ant."
"The Grasshopper noticed that the Ant was dragging along a
huge ear of corn."
"That looks like hard work, mate," said the Grasshopper."
"Tell me about it," said the Ant."
"What you doing with it?" said the Grasshopper."
"Taking it to our nest," said the Ant."
"What're you doing that for?"
"Food for the winter," said the Ant."
"Gotta get ready for the winter."
"Why?" said the Grasshopper."
"Winter won't come for ages. Won't be winter till...the
winter. It's summer now. Why worry about the winter?"
"We always worry about the winter." said the Ant.
"We spend all summer gathering up food for the winter. It's
what we Ants do."
"It's not what Grasshoppers do," said the Grasshopper.
"We Grasshoppers know how to enjoy the summer. Eat...sleep...make some cool music...It's a fine life. We
Grasshoppers know how to live, see."
"Right," said the Ant.
"I'll leave you to it."
"Don't go Ant, mate," said the Grasshopper.
"Stick around. Pass the day with me."
"Sorry." said the Ant.
"Like I said, I got stuff to do."
"The Ant dragged his ear of corn and struggled off across
the field."
"Please yourself," called the Grasshopper.
"I'm not bothered. I got stuff to do too. Got all this grass to eat. Got the sun to enjoy. Not gonna waste a lovely day
like this talking to Ants."
"Have you ever seen a more silly creature than an Ant?"
shouted the grasshopper."
"It was winter. The Grasshopper was cold. Too cold to hop.
Too cold to make his music. And he was hungry."
"He'd spent all day looking for something to eat. Suddenly
he saw the Ant."
"Hello Ant," he shivered.
"Remember me?"
"Yep," said the Ant."
"Cold," isn't it," said the Grasshopper."
"Nice and warm in our nest," said the Ant."
"Not so much to eat now is there," said the Grasshopper"
"We've got plenty," said the Ant. "Our store rooms are full
of seeds and corn.
Got loads of food.
Enough to see us safely through to Spring."
"Loads of food, eh?" said the Grasshopper.
"Look...mate...I don't suppose I could...? I don't suppose
you'd be able to give me...?"
"You said you'd never seen a more silly creature than an
Ant," said the Ant."
"I didn't mean that," said the Grasshopper.
"That was just a joke. Oh come on. Just a couple of ears of
corn. You can spare it. I've got nothing."
"Sorry...mate," said the Ant.
"If you save up on the days when you have plenty then
there'll never be a day when you have nothing."
"The Ant hurried down into his warm nest knowing that he'd
never ever see that Grasshopper again."
THE VAIN AND THE GRASSHOPPER
"One day a king was sitting in his garden watching a pair of
peacocks walking proudly across the lawn."
"See how beautiful those birds are," he said to the Queen.
"Our peacocks with their blue and green feathers and long
shiny tails are the most beautiful birds in the whole
world."
"Just then a swan flew over the garden and landed gracefully
on the King's lake."
"No," said the Queen.
"I think the swan with its long neck and silky white wings
is the most beautiful bird in the world."
"Peacock!" said the King"
"Wrong" said the Queen. "Swan!"
"The King didn't like being told he was wrong so he decided to hold a competition. All the birds were ordered to come to
the palace garden on Saturday afternoon."
"There the King and Queen and their friends would decide
which one was the most beautiful."
"There's no point," said the Queen.
"The swan is bound to win."
"Peacock!" said the King as he sent out his orders."
"The birds were very excited when they heard about the competition and there was much polishing of beaks and
combing of feathers as they all made themselves look beautiful for the great competition."
"All that is except for the jackdaws."
"No point," said the Chief Jackdaw.
"We're not going to win this. Everyone knows that we
jackdaws aren't beautiful."
"I'm not bad looking," said a young jackdaw.
"I might be in with a chance."
"Don't make me laugh. Look at yourself. Your feathers are all grey and black, your beak's too long for your head and
you look like you haven't had a bath in a month."
"You're a scruffy little jackdaw like us. We're clever and cunning and cheeky but none of us is ever going to win a
beauty competition."
"The young Jackdaw was upset."
"Right," he said.
"I'll show "em."
"Next day the young jackdaw flew to the King's garden where he found two long green and blue peacock feathers lying in
the grass."
"He picked them up in his beak and carried them back to his
nest."
"Then, down by the King's lake, he found three beautiful
white swan's feathers and carried them off too."
"Soon he had lots of brightly coloured feathers from all sorts of birds and he started to work. First he stuck bright
red and green parrot feathers onto his wings. Then on his tail he tied the beautiful long peacock feathers."
"For his head he made a hat from the silky white feathers of the swan and when his outfit was finished he looked at
himself and said, "Who's scruffy now?""
"On the day of the competition the King and Queen and their friends sat in the garden as the birds paraded past. Last to
appear was a strange brightly-coloured bird that no-one had ever seen before."
"What on earth is that?" said the King"
"I don't know," said the Queen, "I've never seen anything
like it before but it's very very beautiful."
"Yes it is," said the King."
"Yes I am," said the young jackdaw walking up and down in
front of the crowd and showing off his fine colours."
"There was no doubt about it. The King announced that this
new bird was the winner."
"The peacock and the swan both looked very cross as the young jackdaw bowed to the cheering crowd. Then something
terrible happened. His hat fell off."
"Just a minute," said the swan.
"Aren't those my feathers?"
"And those wings," said the parrot looking closely at the
jackdaw.
"Didn't they used to belong to me?"
"And that tail," said the peacock.
"I'd know that tail anywhere."
"Soon the young jackdaw was surrounded by birds pecking at his beautiful costume. They pulled away their lovely
coloured feathers until his costume had all gone."
"It's just a jackdaw," said the King."
"A scruffy little jackdaw," said the Queen."
"The young jackdaw walked back to his nest very slowly."
"I just wanted to be special," he said."
"You don't become special just by putting on fine clothes,"
said the Chief Jackdaw."
"I know that. I know that now," said the young jackdaw."
"But the other jackdaws weren't listening to him. They'd
already flown away and left him all alone."
THE FROGS WHO WANTED A KING
"The Frogs should have been happy. It was summer, they had plenty to eat and nothing much to do except mess about in
the cool clear water of their pool. They should have been very happy indeed...but they weren't."
"Being a frog's a bit boring actually," said a frog."
"Yeah. It's just eating and swimming basically," said
another."
"What's the point? Why are we here? Why can't life be more
exciting?"
"If only we had a leader," said a fat bullfrog.
"If we had a leader he'd tell us what to do."
"That's right," said another Frog.
"If we had a leader he'd organise... parties and...plays
and... picnics and errr..."
"Of course what we really need... ...in an ideal world,"
said the bullfrog, "is a King."
"The frogs all gasped. A king! Imagine! Their very own king with a crown on his head, giving orders and telling them all
what to do."
"So how do we get a king?" said the little frog."
"To get a King," said the bullfrog, "you need to go to the
top."
"The Frogs knew what the bullfrog meant. The king of all the gods was called Jupiter. If you needed to go to the top you
couldn't go any higher than Jupiter."
"Later that afternoon the frogs watched as the bullfrog then
climbed up onto a rock and cleared his throat."
"Excuse me," he shouted in his loudest voice.
"Excuse me, Jupiter... ...we were wondering if we could have
a King? Please," said the bullfrog."
"Jupiter was very busy and didn't want to be bothered but he knew that if he didn't give those frogs something they'd
keep croaking on and on and on...so he said:"
"Alright! Enough! You want a King? Well have this one!"
"Into the pond fell a huge log of wood."
"Wow!" said the little frog.
"Look how big our King is!"
"He's enormous," said the bullfrog."
"All day the frogs swam around their enormous King and
waited for him to speak but the new King didn't say a word."
"He's a bit quiet in't he?" said the little frog "...for a
King."
"Yeah," they all agreed.
"He's a bit quiet."
"Days went past and the new king never said a word. In fact he didn't even move and after a while the frogs stopped
thinking of him as a king and started using him as a diving platform and sunbathing area."
"I don't think this King is much good to be honest," said
one of the younger frogs."
"Yes," said somebody else.
"Tell Jupiter that frogs deserve a proper king who'll move
about and be powerful and strong and frightening and..."
"Now Jupiter was listening to all this and these noisy ungrateful frogs were making him very angry indeed. He
lifted his right hand."
"You want a frightening king do you frogs?" he said.
"Well try this one for size."
"From out of the sky came a huge white stork, the biggest bird they'd ever seen. The frogs ran in terror as the stork
started gobbling them up in his huge beak."
"Please, Lord Jupiter," said the bullfrog.
"Save us. Take away this terrible King."
"Do you see now?" said Jupiter.
"Better to have no king at all than a cruel one. "
"But the frogs weren't listening... ...they'd all
disappeared."
THE CAT AND THE MICE
"On the kitchen table was a smelly cheese. The smell wafted through the kitchen. The smell spiralled down the hole in
the skirting board. The smell drifted into the noses of three little mice."
"I love ch...ch...cheese!" whined Mini-Mouse, hungrily."
"So do I!" squeaked Mildred-Mouse."
"Mighty-Mouse narrowed his eyes, "Mission required to steal
cheese!" he said."
"In the kitchen lived a cat."
"I'm a Terrible-Tiger-Cat!" said the cat, prowling across
the floor."
"And this Terrible-Tiger-Cat had the important job of
guarding the cheese from pesky mice."
"Under the skirting boards, the smell of cheese was too much
for the mice."
"Right!" said Mighty-Mouse."
"Right," said Mighty-Mouse, "Mini-Mouse you go on my right side, Mildred-Mouse goes on my left and we'll rush out,
steal the cheese and get back quick. OK?"
"What makes you think this plan will work?" said
Mildred-Mouse."
"Trust me!" said Mighty-Mouse confidently.
"We have the element of surprise! Let's GO!"
"Under the kitchen table sat the Terrible-Tiger-Cat. He watched as three little mice shot out of the hole in the
skirting board."
"Mice? I'll catch "em!
I'll snatch "em!"
"The Terrible-Tiger-Cat opened his terrible mouth and showed
his terrible teeth."
"Wait for me!" yelled Mighty-Mouse."
"In the hole under the skirting boards, three little mice
panted for breath."
"N...n...now what?" asked Mini-Mouse."
"NOW," said Mildred-Mouse, with grim determination.
"We forget the cheese! We don't need it!"
"And she marched off, leaving Mighty-Mouse looking
embarrassed."
"In the kitchen, the Terrible-Tiger-Cat waited. There was no
sign of mice. The Terrible-Tiger-Cat was bored."
"Mice? I'll catch "em!
I'll snatch "em!...if I can thee "em!
"Humm… maybe if I wasn't here, the mice would come out!
Maybe, if I pretend to not be here…"
"Terrible-Tiger-Cat looked up at a sack that hung from the wall. The sack was grey. Terrible-Tiger-Cat looked at his
fur. His fur was grey also."
"Now," he said thoughtfully.
"If I take this sack down from the wall… and if I climb up and hang myself there instead…I would look like a sack and
not like a cat! Clever, eh?"
"So Terrible-Tiger-Cat hung himself from the wall and
waited."
"Down the hole Mini-Mouse groaned."
"The smell of ch...cheese is killing me! If I could have one
taste…"
"Get back here!" said Mildred, grabbing Mini-Mouse's tail
and pulling him back.
"B...b...but NO CAT!" said Mini-Mouse excitedly."
"Humm," said Mildred.
"NEVER trust a cat!"
"She poked her snout out cautiously."
"Mildred looked up at the sack hanging on the wall. The sack
with the two bright eyes."
"No cat?" Mildred smiled wryly.
"THEN WHAT'S THAT HANGING ON THE WALL?"
"And the Terrible-Tiger-Cat replied, "Waaaoow!
I'm only an old sack!""
"C...c...cat!" stuttered Mini-Mouse."
"Abandon plan!" said Mighty-Mouse."
"Come on!" laughed Mildred, "Let's get back to the
mousehole."
"And there was silence in the kitchen."
"Ooopth!" said the Terrible-Tiger-Cat.
"I wonder what gave me away?"
THE LION AND THE MOUSE
"A Mouse was scurrying through the forest when he saw a Lion sleeping under a tree. The Mouse stopped and said to the
Lion. "You may be very big but I'm not scared of you.""
"The Mouse climbed up the Lion's tail and sat down on its
back leg."
"Oh no, Mr Lion, you don't frighten me one little bit."
"Still the Lion didn't move so the Mouse walked along the
Lion's side and climbed up towards his head."
"All the animals in the forest are scared of you, Mr Lion, but not us mice "cos mice are the bravest creatures in the
world."
"Again the Lion didn't move so the mouse climbed up the lions face and shouted in his ear. "Why should we be scared
of lazy lions who spend all day snoring under trees?""
"The Mouse was enjoying himself and feeling very brave when he noticed that the Lion's eye was open and looking straight
at him."
"Quick as a flash the Lion grabbed the little Mouse in his
paw."
"What were you saying?" said the Lion."
"Nothing," said the little Mouse."
"Something about brave mice and lazy lions"
"That wasn't me," said the Mouse.
"I'd never say that. I think lions are..."
"Quiet," said the Lion.
"I'm going to eat you. What do you think about that? "
"Don't think that's a good idea," said the Mouse."
"Why's that?" said the Lion."
"Because…"
"Because what?" said the Lion."
"Because…" And suddenly an idea flashed into the Mouse's
tiny head.
"Because one day I could help you."
"The Lion roared with laughter. "You?
How could a tiny Mouse help a huge Lion like me..?"
"I don't know," said the Mouse.
"Maybe I could..."
"Yes?" said the Lion."
"Maybe I could…"
"Yes?"
"The Mouse couldn't think of a single way in which a tiny Mouse could help a Lion. He shut his eyes and waited to be
eaten."
"But the Lion didn't eat the Mouse. He just laughed and
gently put the Mouse down on the ground."
"That's the funniest thing I've ever heard," said the Lion.
"A tiny Mouse helping a huge Lion like me. I'm not going to eat you after all, little Mouse. You're too funny to eat.
I'm going to let you go."
"Oh, thank you," said the mouse.
"I think that's a very wise decision. I meant what I said. I
will help you Mr Lion. One day. Just you wait and see."
"The Lion laughed again: "Off you go little one," he roared,
"before I die laughing.""
"The Mouse ran away feeling very lucky."
"But the very next day he was scurrying through the forest
when he heard more roaring."
"This time though, it wasn't a roar of laughter but a roar of pain and fear. The Mouse crept closer to the terrible
sound and saw the same Lion all tangled up in a hunter's net. The more he struggled the more tangled up he became."
"He was just about to run away when the Mouse remembered how the Lion could have eaten him but let him go. And then the
Mouse remembered saying:"
"I will help you, Mr Lion. One day. Just you wait and see."
"Suddenly the Mouse was chewing at the ropes and gnawing as fast as he could. His teeth were tiny but razor sharp and
soon he had cut the ropes and the Lion was free."
"The Mouse looked at the Lion. The Lion looked at the
Mouse."
"Yesterday I laughed when you said you would help me. I'm not laughing now. You are a very brave little Mouse. Just
goes to show you don't have to be big to be a big friend. Thank you."
"That's
alright," said the Mouse.
"You get into trouble again just give me a shout, OK?"
"OK," said the Lion and he turned and walked away."
"The Mouse watched him go. He smiled to himself and now
somehow he didn't feel quite so little."
THE CAGED BIRD AND THE BAT
"In a village far, far away there once lived a pretty little
songbird."
"She was in fact a very grumpy, bad-tempered little songbird. You see, she'd been caught and trapped by a young
woodsman named Fergus Fowler and he had locked her in a cage outside his cottage window."
"So there she sat looking out through the bars, longing to
be free, mumbling and grumbling all through the day."
"That nasty, horrible, grubby little good for nothing…with his muddy knees and dirty feet and his hooks and his nets
and his traps…going about catching us happy folk…"
"But oh when she sang! You've never heard such a beautiful sound. She would sing of the fields and the flowers, of the
wind ruffling her feathers and the sun warming her wings. She would sing of the sound of waterfalls and cool mountain streams tinkling and splashing over pebbles."
"It was a magical song that you
wished to hear from the first light of dawn till last thing
at night…"
"But that is something our little songbird…never…ever…did. Not a peep, not a whistle, not a single twitter tweet would
she utter during daytime hours."
"I have my reasons," said the songbird smugly to herself.
"Oh no…no I'll not do that again…I've learned that sure
enough."
"Now Fergus Fowler wasn't such a bad young lad. He was a kind, sensitive boy and he was a really terrible hunter and
if he did by some extraordinary good luck actually catch a guinea-fowl or field mouse he always set it free."
"He couldn't bear to see it suffer."
"The only creature that Fergus Fowler had ever actually
trapped and kept and loved very much was the songbird."
"What a wonderful song," he said… "Now you can sing for me every day!" But the little songbird hadn't sung from that
day to this."
"I might be a useless hunter," Fergus mumbled to the little bird, feeding her some of his bread, "but you're a bit of a
useless songbird too. You're very sweet and pretty, but you never, EVER sing!"
"Which was true as far as he knew because it was only when the moon was up and the owls awake, when Fergus Fowler was
sound asleep in his bed that the little songbird opened her tiny beak…and sang."
"She would sing her beautiful tunes all through the long night hours while Fergus snored inside. But each day at
dawn, as the sun rose over the meadows, the little songbird would fall silent and pretend to be asleep."
"Late that night, while Fergus was sound asleep, the little songbird began her song. A tiny bat flew past and hearing
the beautiful sound he clung to the bars of the cage and asked:"
"Little songbird, you sing such lovely songs, but why do you only sing at night and never during the day like all the
other birds in the forest?"
"Oh I have a clever plan," tweeted the bird.
"You see, the last time I sang during the day a trapper caught me in his nets and locked me in this cage. So I'll
not make that mistake again!"
"But the Bat replied, "Well it's no use your doing that now
when you're a prisoner.
If only you'd done that before you were caught, you might
still have been free.""
"And the cheeky bat flew off into the night."
THE FOX AND THE GOAT
"One day a rather clever Fox went out for a stroll. The sun was shining, clouds bumped along in the sky and - well,
better than that the great cloud shadows raced across the fields."
"Whoo hooo!" barked the Fox as he chased after them.
"What fun! It's a very good day to be a Fox."
"The not-quite-looking-where-he-was-going Fox laughed and - whoops! Splish! Splosh! Fox fell into a well that he just
hadn't noticed."
"That's all right! I'll jump back out again. Look at me, I can leap over hedges and fences and sleeping dogs! I'm the
best jumper there ever was!" said the rather hopeful Fox."
"However, the walls of the well were much too high. They were also slippery with moss. So, a rather soggy Fox
doggy-paddled to and fro and tried to come up with another plan. After he had swum one hundred times around the well, and back again, the rather tired Fox had to admit he was trapped."
"I never thought I'd end up down here," he sighed.
"No more racing in the sunlight and chasing shadows for me!" And a rather sad Fox floated quietly in a patch of water
that reflected the sky.
Just then a goat's head appeared over the edge of the well."
"Hello," she bleated.
"I thought I heard a voice. What are you doing?"
"Hello," said the rather quick-thinking Fox.
"Actually, I'm having a wonderful time. This is the best
water in the whole wide world."
"Drinking it makes you happy, paddling in it makes you
healthy and it tastes delicious! It's wonderful!"
"Fox smiled and dipped his face into the water and blew
bubbles. Then drank and drank and drank."
"Oh, where are my manners," Fox said as the Goat leaned down, stretched her neck, stuck out her tongue and tried her
hardest to reach the water."
"Would you like some?"
"Yes, please," said the Goat."
"Well jump straight in and help yourself. I'll move over
here so there's room for two."
"I am very thirsty," said the Goat.
"I've just eaten thistles!" And in she leapt."
"Slurp, gargle, gulp," went the goat.
"This water is perfect – cool and sweet and delicious. Thank
you for letting me share it. Now I'll be off, there are lots of thistles waiting to be munched." Then the Goat looked up and frowned.
"Excuse me for asking, Fox, but how do we get out of here?"
"The Fox pretended to think about it for a minute, then
clicked his paws."
"I know, lean up against the side of the well and I'll climb
up your back, onto your shoulders then step on your head and I'll be out."
"Ohhhh what a good idea! You are clever," said the goat, standing on her hind legs and leaning against the mossy well
wall.
"There you are, my friend – a goat ladder!"
"Upsadaisy!" the Fox giggled as he scrambled out of the
well.
Then he shook his coat.
Water flew off him and the warm sunlight made his fur steam.
"Hello sky!" he cried and chased his tail before running off
across the wide, green field."
"Hello?" bleated the Goat.
"What about me? How do I get out?"
"Fox shouted back over his shoulder, "You should have
thought about that before you jumped in!""
"Wait!" wailed the goat."
"It was good to see you but I wouldn't want to be you!" the rather clever Fox sang, as he followed a cloud shadow over
the hill."
THE LION AND THE ELEPHANT
"It was nearly morning and the Lion had just gone to bed."
"He pulled the grass duvet over his head and closed his
eyes."
"He was just about to fall asleep when a noise sounded
across the plain."
"COCK-A-DOODLE-DOO!"
"It was the Cockerel crowing."
"The Lion put his paws over his ears."
"Go away," he cried, "go away!"
"But the Cockerel didn't want to go away. He wanted to tell
the world what a beautiful morning it was."
"The Lion kept his head under the duvet."
"That noise is driving me mad," he said.
It was the same every morning.
The sun came up and the Cockerel crowed.
And each time he heard it the Lion hated it more.
It made him feel afraid."
"Why is it," he asked himself, "that someone like me, who is brave and strong and fearless should be afraid of the sound
of a harmless cockerel?"
"He decided to talk to the other animals."
"Monkeys," he asked, "does the sound of the Cockerel make
you feel afraid?"
"No," said the monkeys together.
"We're not afraid of anything."
"Hippopotamus," asked the Lion, "you are big and strong like
me. Is there anything that frightens you?"
"The hippopotamus was bathing in the river. He blew a stream
of bubbles out of his nose."
"Nothing frightens me," he said."
"Not even the sound of a cockerel crowing."
"Especially not the sound of a cockerel crowing."
"Ashamed of his weakness the Lion turned away. A crocodile
was sunbathing near by."
"Are you afraid of anything, Crocodile?" the Lion asked."
"The crocodile thought for a moment."
"Jam sandwiches!" he answered."
"The Lion thought this was a strange thing for the crocodile
to be afraid about, but he didn't argue."
"Just then an elephant lumbered out of the forest."
"If anyone can answer my question, he can," thought the
Lion."
"Elephant, can I speak to you?" he asked."
"Not today, Lion," said the Elephant, shaking his head.
"I have a problem."
"Is it a serious problem?" asked the Lion."
"It is to me," said the Elephant.
And he shook his head so hard the Lion thought the
elephant's ears would come off."
"I've got a serious problem too," said the Lion."
"Well, you tell me your serious problem and I'll tell you
mine," said the Elephant."
"So the Lion told the Elephant all about how afraid he was
of the crowing of the cock."
"I sympathise with you, Lion," said the Elephant.
And he gave his head another massive shake."
"Do you see a small insect buzzing around?" he continued."
"The Lion could just make out a gnat near the Elephant's
head."
"If that insect flies inside my ears," continued the
Elephant, "I am positive I am done for."
"You mean you are afraid of a tiny gnat?" queried the Lion."
"Yes," said the Elephant."
"The Lion thought about this for a minute. It was hard to believe that such a strong, wise and clever animal could be
afraid of so small a thing."
"Now the Lion felt sorry for the Elephant."
"Your fear is worse than mine," he told him.
"I am sorry now I troubled you at all."
"I'm glad you did," said the Elephant."
"The next morning when the Cock crowed the Lion turned over
in bed and went back to sleep."
"It's just a noise," he told himself, "it can't possibly
hurt me."
"And he was right."
THE CROW AND THE PITCHER
"This is the story of a pitcher and a crow, and a pitcher is
a jug, in case you didn't know."
"Old Mr Crow was a big black bird with a big black beak and
he lived at the top of a tree."
"He was a clever old creature."
"There's no problem you can't fix if you only take the time
to think about it!" he would say."
"And over the years, Old Mr Crow had managed to solve lots of problems…just through taking the time to settle his
feathers and think."
"When he wanted to feast on a juicy clam that was hiding inside its tightly shut shell, Mr Crow solved the problem by
dropping the shell from a great height so it hit the ground and burst open. "This clam sure tastes delicious!" he cawed."
"Go, go Mr Crow, you're the smartest bird we know!" chirped
the Sparrow Sisters."
"Walnuts were even trickier for a crow to crack open, but Mr Crow solved that problem too. "I'll let the cars that drive
by do the work for me," he cawed. Then he plucked a walnut from the tree and dropped it in the road, just by the crossing. A car drove over it and cracked the walnut open. When the traffic lights turned red and the traffic stopped Mr Crow hopped into the road and pecked up the tasty nut."
"Go, go Mr Crow, you're so clever don't you know!" chirped
the Sparrow Sisters."
"Then one day Mr Crow came across a problem he thought he
couldn't solve."
"The weather had been hot and dry for weeks and all the water had dried up in the pond. Mr Crow was very thirsty. He
flew for miles looking for water but wherever he went the streams and ponds were dry."
"Then, as he was flying by a farm house, he noticed a pitcher in the garden. "Maybe that pitcher will have water
in it," he thought."
"So he flew down to look. There was a little bit of water at
the bottom, not much, but enough for a crow. Mr Crow put his beak in eagerly…but the pitcher was tall and the water was shallow and his beak couldn't reach."
"I can see the water, but I can't drink it!" he said to
himself.
"And without the water I will die of thirst. This is a
problem!"
"Mr Crow settled his feathers and thought for a while…and as he was thinking, his black beady eyes spotted a small
stone…"Hmm," he thought, "I wonder if that stone can help me solve my problem?""
"Then he had an idea…he picked the stone up in his beak and he dropped it in the pitcher…this made the water in the
pitcher rise, just a little."
"I need more stones," thought Mr Crow.
He flew around the yard searching for stones and, one by
one, he dropped them into the pitcher.
Each time the water rose a little but each time he dipped
his beak in but it wouldn't reach the water."
"Mr Crow worked all day…flying backwards and forwards picking up stones and dropping them in… then at last, as the
sun was setting, he looked into the pitcher and saw that he had almost filled it with stones. Now the water had risen high enough for his beak to reach."
"Go, go Mr Crow, you're so clever don't you know!" chirped
the Sparrow Sisters"
"A problem's not a problem if you take the time to think,"
said Old Mr Crow as he settled down to drink."
THE FOX AND THE STORK
"A rather large bird was wandering round the wood, looking a
bit lost. It had long legs, a long thin neck and a very long bill for eating, that clattered away as it searched for nice things to eat."
"Hey there, big bird!" cried the little birds in the trees
above.
"You're new round these parts, aren't you?"
"Indeed I am," replied Stork.
"And I'd like to make some friends."
"I'll be your friend," purred a soft voice from behind a
bush.
Out slunk Fox with his shiny red coat and soft paws."
"Oooo, we wouldn't make friends with old Foxy if we were
you," chorused the birds.
"He's a bit of a joker."
"Oh, ignore them", Fox purred reassuringly.
"Please, allow me to show you round the woods…"
"Fox and Stork were soon laughing and chatting as if they'd
known each other forever…"
"What do you like to eat, Stork?" asked Fox.
"Frogs, fish, insects and earthworms are my favourites,"
replied Stork."
"Mine too – oh, leaving aside frogs," said Fox.
"I eat nuts and berries too – and I'm very partial to the
occasional little bird."
"Boo, hiss!" cried the birds from above."
"Only joking," said Fox rather too quickly.
"Would you like to come around my house tomorrow for supper,
Stork?"
"It's a trick, it's a trick!" chorused the birds."
"Thank you, Fox, I'd love to!"
"That night, Stork flew over to Fox's house."
"Come in!" cried Fox as he showed Stork into the dining
room.
"I hope you like fish soup with mashed earthworms."
"Stork was expecting to see two bowls full of lovely steaming soup – but instead, two flat plates covered in a
thin layer of liquid lay on the table."
"Stork tried her hardest to eat the soup with her bill, but
it was impossible."
"Fox meanwhile was already licking his bowl clean. "Oh,
dear, is there a problem?" he asked with a smirk."
"Not at all," replied Stork.
"It's just – well, I had rather a large tea before I came
and my tummy's full."
"Tea – I like the sound of that," purred Fox.
"Well, why don't you come to my home tomorrow and join me?"
suggested Stork.
"I shall look forward to it," replied Fox."
"Stork flew home that night with a heavy heart. "We warned
you, we warned you!" chorused the birds."
"I know, my so-called friend tricked me," replied Stork.
"But I may yet have the last laugh."
"The next day, Fox set off for Stork's house. "Shame on
you!" cried the birds as he slunk under their tree."
"Stork can take a joke," Fox replied.
"And after all, she's invited me over for tea."
"Hee, hee!" sniggered the birds."
"Come in!" said Stork to Fox.
"I've cooked roast rabbit on a bed of grass with berry and
nut sauce."
"Mmm, my favourite," said Fox as Stork carried in a tray."
"He stared at the tall jar Stork had placed in front of him.
It was long and thin and the food lay right at the bottom."
"Fox watched in frustration as Stork stuck her long bill into her jar and gobbled up the meal. "Oh dear," said Stork.
"Is there a problem?"
"None at all," growled Fox.
He stuck his nose as far down the jar as he could, but he
still couldn't reach his dinner."
"And now there really was a problem. "Yowl!
The jar's stuck to my face!" came Fox's muffled cries."
"Hee hee! Serves you right, Foxy," chorused the birds who
were watching on the window sill.
For once, Fox couldn't answer back."
"I'll pull it off with my wings," offered Stork kindly."
"Hmmm, I guess I deserved that after the joke I played on
you," said Fox sheepishly.
"Never mind," said Stork.
"I've got plenty of food in the kitchen. This time we'll have it on proper plates – and our little feathered friends
can have some too."
"Wee, hee!" cried the birds."
TWO TRAVELLERS AND A BEAR
"One cold winter's day two friends set off to travel to the town. They talked and laughed as they strode along. It was
cold and snow was falling but the two men hardly noticed - they were enjoying each other's company so much. What a pleasant fellow he is, each of them thought. I'm glad that we are travelling together."
"The road to the town lay through a forest. It was late by the time the men reached it. "We should turn back," one of
them said to the other nervously. "It'll soon be dark and there are bears in that forest.""
"His friend was just as scared as he was. But didn't want
his friend to know. So he laughed. "Pah!
Bears.
That's nothing to be afraid of.
I fought a bear once – and he ran away.""
"The other man felt ashamed of himself. I am a coward, but
he is brave, he thought. "Then we'll go on," he said."
"It was very dark in that forest. The trees grew close together. It was hard to see the road clearly. It was hard
to see anything at all!"
"But the man wasn't afraid any more. He listened as his friend told him all about his fight with the bear. "It was
very big," he boasted. "Twice as big as me.
But I picked up a stick and fought it off.""
"All of a sudden there was an enormous crash. And out of the
bushes lumbered - a bear. The men had never seen such a huge bear. When it saw the men it licked its lips. "At last!" it said, standing up on its hind legs and growling. "Dinner!""
"With a cry of fright, the friend ran to the nearest tree and hauled himself up onto a branch. "Aren't you going to
fight it?" the man cried."
"Fight it! You must be mad," said his friend.
"It will kill us." The man ran up to the tree where his
friend crouched, trembling.
"There's room for us both in that tree," he cried.
"Help me up.""
"But his friend pushed him away.
"No there isn't. Find somewhere else to hide," he said."
"What shall I do?" the man thought.
The bear was so close now he could have stretched out a hand
and touched it.
"If I try to run it will run faster. If I fight it, it will
kill me. It is bigger and stronger than me.""
"He flung himself to the ground and lay there, as still as
he could.
"Perhaps it will leave me alone," he thought, "if it thinks
I am dead.""
"The bear was very hungry.
It hadn't eaten for a long time.
But it was puzzled when it saw the man drop to the ground.
"Is he dead?" it wondered.
"Let me see.""
"It bent down, so close that the man could feel its fur
brush his cheek.
Then it put out a paw and prodded him.
The man lay still, his heart pounding.
"Any minute now," he thought, "that bear will tear me to
pieces." But the bear got up.
"He hasn't moved. He must be dead," it thought.
"And I don't like dead meat." And it ambled away sadly into
the forest."
"The man got up and dusted himself down. He didn't look at his friend. He was very angry with him. He had pretended to
be brave, but he was a coward. He had left him to face the bear on his own."
"I saw the bear whisper in your ear," the friend said
climbing down from the tree.
"What did he say?"
"He said a man who leaves his friend to face danger isn't a true friend." And with that he turned away, leaving the
other to make his own way home."
THE GOOSE THAT LAID THE GOLDEN EGGS
"There once was a very poor farmer. So poor he lived in an old tumbledown pigsty in the middle of nowhere with only
acorns and the odd goose egg to eat and a bale of straw for his bed. His name was Attacus Greeb."
"Now Attacus Greeb hadn't always been poor. He'd inherited a large and prosperous farm from his father and he'd owned
land as far as the eye could see. But Attacus Greeb was a lazy man. He didn't like work."
"I'm far too good to be milking cows," he said.
"I should be Lord of the Manor with servants and footmen…and
heaps of silver and gold."
"So over the years, instead of working for a living he'd
simply sold off his possessions."
"He'd sold almost everything his father had given him - his house, his land, his horses, his pigs, his cattle and all he
was left with was one single goose who lived with him."
"Oh what is to become of me?" wailed Attacus late one night.
"I have no house, no food and no money and nothing left to sell…I shall surely starve!" And then he looked at his
goose."
"It's no good honking at me goosey it's off with you to the market tomorrow – you haven't laid an egg in weeks and your
feathers will fetch me a fair few guineas." And off he went to sleep."
"The next morning Attacus Greeb awoke to a glittering dawn. It was so light and bright he had to shield his eyes. But it
wasn't the sunlight shining, he could hardly believe what he saw, it was a gigantic, glorious…Golden Egg! "You clever girl!
Ha!
H!a Ho!
Ho!
We'll be rich!
Rich beyond our dreams!""
"So off he went to market pushing the egg in an old wheelbarrow… and back he came with a barrowful of meat to
cook, chicken feed for his goose and a huge bag of coins."
"Oh how I wish I had money to buy a horse-drawn carriage,"
he said patting his full tummy that night.
"That's what I need to be happy."
"Well, the very next morning the same thing happened…there was another shiny golden egg lying beside the goose. So off
went Attacus to market and with the money he got he bought a smart black carriage and six sleek horses."
"And every day the same thing happened and every day Attacus
Greeb counted his money and wished for more and more."
"But as fast as the little goose could lay a golden egg Attacus Greeb wanted more. "Why can't you lay more eggs each
day?
We need more, we need more I say!""
"Soon the farmer became a very rich man indeed – but as he
grew rich, he grew greedy – and still he wanted more."
"And then he had an idea."
"How I wish I could have all the golden eggs at once," he thought, "instead of just one a day. Then I would surely be
happy."
"So the next morning he ordered his cook to kill the goose and open it up so he could take out all the eggs at once –
but, of course, to his horror there was nothing inside the poor goose…and there would be no golden eggs again."
"And Attacus Greeb ended up back in his tumble-down pigsty -
just where he belonged!"
"Those who have plenty want more and so lose all they have."
THE KID AND THE WOLF
"Once there was a billy goat kid who lived with his mother
on a farm."
"Each morning he and the other goats were herded into a
meadow."
"And each evening they were driven home again."
"At the edge of the field was a wood. The grass grew thick and sweet there because the goats never went near it. The
kid looked at it
longingly. "Don't go there," the other goats warned him. "A
big bad wolf lives in that wood."
"Yes, mind you stay close by me," said his mother."
"At first the kid did stay close by his mother. But with each day that passed his horns grew bigger. "I am not a
little kid any more," he thought. "I can look after myself.
Anyway, I don't believe a wolf lives in that wood.
The goats are just a bunch of scaredy-cats!"
He trotted over to where the juiciest grass grew.
The goats shook their heads when they saw where the kid
was."
"Baaa. Silly young thing," they said."
"The little kid was very happy. He tore up the long stalks of sweet grass. He was so busy eating that he didn't hear
his mother call him. He didn't even notice the dogs rounding up the goats to drive them home. "Oh, I do hope my little goat is safe," his mother said as they were herded out of the field."
"At last the kid had had enough. He lifted up his head. The
goats had gone. He was all alone."
"Long shadows crept towards him. It was growing dark. The
kid did not feel so big and brave any more."
"Mother," he bleated, running up and down the field.
"Where are you? I want to go home."
"But his Mother didn't hear him. She was far away, down the
lane."
"But someone heard him. Big yellow eyes followed the kid, as
he ran up and down the field. It was the wolf."
"He couldn't believe his luck."
"It's time for my dinner and that kid will do nicely," he
smiled."
"Well, we did warn him."
"And with a single bound he was out of the wood. The kid
tried to run away, but the wolf put out a paw."
"Whoa!" he growled.
"Not so fast!"
"He smacked his lips."
"If only I had listened to Mother," thought the kid.
"What shall I do? How can I stop the wolf from eating me?
Help! Help!" He bleated, as loudly as he could.
But the dogs and goats couldn't hear him."
"The wolf growled, showing sharp yellow teeth. Then the kid had an idea. "If I can get the wolf to sing, maybe Mother
will hear him and save me," he thought."
"Mr Wolf," he squeaked.
"I'm sure you have a beautiful voice. Will you sing for me?
And I will dance for you. I like dancing."
"The wolf considered. "Why not?" he thought. "A little music
before dinner.""
"He opened his mouth to sing."
"Eeurgh what is that," the rabbits said darting back into
their burrows."
"What a horrible noise!" said the moles digging themselves
hurriedly down into the earth."
"But in the pasture the little kid pranced and frolicked, kicking up his little legs as if he was having the most
wonderful time. "Oh wolf, he gasped.
"How beautifully you sing.""
"You really think so?" simpered the Wolf, and howled even
louder. No one had ever told him he sang beautifully
before."
"Down the lane the dogs and goats also heard the wolf. They stopped and looked at each other. "It's the wolf!" one of
the dogs cried. "Oh, please – save my little goat!" cried the kid's mother."
"The dogs tore back into the field barking loudly."
"The wolf turned his head and saw them. He leapt for the
trees just as one of the dogs was about to seize his tail."
"Why did I let that kid flatter me?" he growled to himself
as soon as he got his breath back.
"Am I daft? I should have eaten him at once!"
THE OLD LION AND THE FOX
"It isn't easy being old," said Lion one day as he looked in
the mirror."
"Look at my fangs, they're all worn down and my claws are
short and stubby!"
"I'm so hungry, I could eat a herd of wildebeests," Lion grizzled, "but I'm not very good at hunting these days, I'm
too slow! I need to think of an easy way to catch my dinner."
"Then he had an idea."
"If I can't get to my dinner, I'll make my dinner come to me! I'll pretend that I'm sick and all the animals will feel
sorry for me… they'll come to visit and as soon as they do I'll gobble them up!"
"Lion put his plan to work straight away. He settled himself in his den, put on his poorly face and let out a sorrowful
growl."
"Oh woe is me, oh woe is me, I'm feeling sick as sick can
be!" he groaned."
"Bird came flitting by…"
"Oooh poor lion, you look very skinny!" she said."
"That's because I'm poorly and I haven't felt like eating!"
lion fibbed."
"Let me check your temperature," chirped bird and she hopped
inside lion's jaws with her thermometer."
"Then Lion nabbed her – grrr, grrr, snap…and put her in his
dinner sack."
"Bird's aren't very filling," said Lion, "let's see what
else I can catch."
"He put on his poorly face again and let out another
sorrowful growl."
"Oh woe is me, oh woe is me, I'm feeling sick as sick can
be!"
"Monkey jumped down from a tree to help."
"What's wrong with you Lion?" he asked."
"I feel weak and wobbly!" Lion fibbed."
"Well you are looking a bit skinny… let me look at your
tongue," said monkey kindly.
He peered inside lion's jaws…"
"Then Lion nabbed him – grrr snap… and put him in his dinner
sack."
"There isn't much meat on a monkey," grizzled Lion, "I'll
have to keep trying."
"I need one more creature…something bigger I hope."
"He let out another sad roar."
"Oh woe is me, oh woe is me, I'm feeling poorly as can be!"
"That's a shame," said Fox, appearing at the door of Lion's
den."
"I think I might have a thorn in my throat," grizzled Lion.
"Maybe you can pull it out."
"Fox looked at all the footprints outside Lion's den - they
were leading inside, but they didn't come out again."
"She spotted Lion's dinner sack too… it was wriggling."
"Hmmm," she thought!
"Lion is up to something, I'd better be careful."
"I'll pull out the thorn in your throat," Fox told Lion, "but it's a tricky job, I want you to close your eyes and
keep very still."
"Lion closed his eyes tight, opened his jaws and got ready
to snap."
"He waited and he waited then suddenly Fox shouted."
"You can open your eyes now Lion."
"Lion opened his eyes just in time to see Fox running off
with his precious dinner sack."
"Drat, thought Lion, there goes my dinner!"
"When Fox reached the wood she opened Lion's dinner sack and
set the creatures free."
"I'll set you free this once, gruffed Fox. But never fall for Lion's bluffs, "cos if you do not use your brains,
you'll end up in his sack again!"
THE EAGLE AND THE JACKDAW
"Oh my, look at that bird!" a Jackdaw exclaimed to her
husband one day.
High above the nest a great eagle was soaring."
"Oh isn't he magnificent," she sighed watching him circle
and swoop.
She leant over the nest to take a better look.
Perched next to her was her husband who pushed back his
shades and looked out to see what the fuss was all about."
"Hmm. He's just an eagle," he grumbled.
"I'm as fine a bird as him!" The nest was full of things
he'd collected.
Rings, bottle tops, feathers."
"The jackdaw smiled, looking at the glittering heap. "Mrs
Jackdaw," he said to his wife. "You are a lucky bird.
Look at all the beautiful things I've brought you.""
"Humph!" grumbled the jackdaw's wife.
"What use is it? You can't eat feathers and bottle tops! If
only you brought back something useful for a change."
"The jackdaw was very cross. He stared at the eagle as it swooped downwards. Suddenly he heard a bleat. The eagle had
seized a lamb that had got separated from the flock in the pasture below."
"The lamb bleated and struggled. But it was no use. The eagle had him firmly gripped in his talons. Up and up he
flew again, higher and higher, the lamb swinging from his claws."
"The jackdaw had had enough. "I'll show her," he muttered to
himself. "I'm just as big and strong as that eagle.
She'll see."
He hopped out of the nest."
"Then flapping his wings he flew down to a bush."
"His eyes gleamed as they lit on the farmer's prize ram. "Won't she be surprised when I bring that ram back for tea?"
he chuckled. And putting on his fiercest expression down he plopped, onto the ram's back."
"Up we go!" he cawed happily, flapping his wings and rising
up into the air again.
But all that was swinging from his claws was a bit of wool.
He dropped down again and tugged a bit harder."
"But he couldn't budge the ram. Up and down the jackdaw jumped, furiously flapping his wings and tugging at the
ram's woolly coat."
"But he couldn't lift the ram."
"Silly old bird," said Mrs Jackdaw, who was watching.
"He thinks he's an eagle!"
"The jackdaw pulled and he tugged, but the more he tugged and the more he pulled the more his claws got caught in the
ram's woolly coat until he could hardly move at all."
"Leaning by the gate, a shepherd had been watching. He ran up to the ram. "Silly old bird," the shepherd said taking
out a pair of scissors to clip his wings. "I'm taking you home with me.
Can't have you messing with my flock.""
"When he got home that night the shepherd put the jackdaw down on the table. "Come and see what I've brought you," he
said to his children."
"The children crowded round the table."
"What sort of bird is it, Father?" one of them asked.
"Well I call it a jackdaw, but he thinks he's an eagle," the
shepherd chuckled.
He gave the jackdaw a stern look.
"Perhaps you've learned your lesson now," he said.
The jackdaw hung his head."
"Up in the jackdaw's nest, his wife stretched out happily. "I've seen the last of him," she said. "And good riddance
too.
Useless bird.
Fancy thinking he was an eagle!""
THE WOLF IN SHEEP'S CLOTHING
"Mr Wolf dreamt of eating a nice woolly sheep for his
supper…but he just couldn't catch one."
"He spent his time spying on the sheep in Farmer Foggarty's field… and thinking of wily ways to catch them. But his wily
ways never seemed to work."
"One time he'd waited behind a rock for hours just so he could pounce on a juicy sheep…but when he heard the sound of
hooves and he leapt out of his hiding place…it was not a sheep he pounced on… …but an angry bull."
"It looked like Mr Wolf was never going to get a Sheepie
Supper."
"Then one day when he was visiting his Auntie Marge he
noticed a large sheep skin rug on the floor."
"Ha, he thought, I will borrow Auntie Marge's rug and disguise myself as a sheep, then I can easily get into
Farmer Foggarty's sheep pen; and once I'm in there, gnash, gobble, gnash, gobble…I will have my sheepie supper!"
"As soon as he arrived home with the sheepskin rug he
dressed himself up and then practised talking in Sheep
language."
"It was tricky at first, baaa…grrr! baaa…grrrr… but he soon
got the hang of it Baaa! Baaa! Baaa!"
"Then he set off to Farmer Foggarty's field to join the
sheep. On the way he checked his reflection in the pond."
"I look cute, he said. Baaaa-ootiful!"
"Farmer Foggarty's sheep were grazing happily when Mr Wolf slyly slipped amongst the flock. He nibbled some grass just
like they did. But it tasted yucky."
"So far his plan was working; the sheep didn't seem to notice him, even though he was larger than they were; they
all just kept nibbling the grass."
"I'll wait til sunset when the farmer puts the sheep in the pen and when I'm tucked up tight with them, gnash, gobble,
gnash, gobble, I'll have a delicious sheepie supper."
"When sunset came, the farmer and his dog herded the sheep into their pen and in went Mr Wolf as well. His disguise had
worked."
"Oh yeah, oh yeah, I'm going to get me some juicy sheep!
said Mr Wolf to himself."
"Mummy, said one of the lambs, that
sheep smells a bit funny!"
"Don't be rude, said the lamb's mother."
"Ha ha, thought Mr Wolf, because you're so rude little
lambie, you will be the first to be gobbled."
"Sheep are woolly, sheep are yummy, Sheep are best in my
tummy!"
"He flashed his claws and opened his jaws and was just about
to pounce when…Farmer Foggarty appeared."
"He was ready for his supper too. He wasn't having Bolognese. He wasn't having beans and mashed potatoes in a
heap. He was having SHEEP!"
"The farmer looked at the herd carefully, he spotted the biggest, juiciest looking sheep and he hooked it with his
shepherd's hook. It was Mr Wolf."
"Drat, thought Mr Wolf. I thought I was going to get my
Sheepie Supper, but it looks like I'm the sheepie supper!"
"With a lightning fast wriggle he freed himself from the
farmer's hook…and off he shot as fast as his legs could go."
"Excellent work, said Farmer Foggarty to his sheep, we
fooled that wily Mr Wolf! Now I'm off to have my egg and
chips!"
THE GOATHERD
AND THE WILD GOATS
"Wild goats live in wild, rocky places where it is hot during the day and cold during the night. They eat dry
leaves and thistles and bits of twig. Sometimes they go hungry."
"Sherpa, the leader of the wild goats was a magnificent creature. He had a noble head, a long beard and two
extraordinary horns. The horns were so unusual they curled upwards and then downwards and ended up pointing in different directions from each other."
"Sherpa wasn't only magnificent, he was also wise."
"I've had a brilliant idea," he said to the rest of the herd
one day."
"He pointed to some other goats, in a field further down the
valley, eating a big pile of fragrant hay."
"They are tame goats," said Sherpa, "and they are looked after by a man called a Goatherd. They have plenty to eat
and a warm place to sleep. Not like us! We are often hungry and cold."
"The wild goats stopped clambering over rocks to listen."
"My idea," Sherpa went on, "is to hop over the fence and
join them. Then we would be looked after too!"
"The other goats liked the sound of this."
"So, later that day, when the goatherd was changing his socks, the wild goats hopped into the field with the tame
goats and pretended they had been there all the time."
"That night it started to snow."
"The goatherd rounded up his goats and counted them."
"That's funny," he said.
"There are twice as many now, than there were before."
"He was pleased. More goats meant more milk and cheese to
sell in the market."
"The goatherd looked after his new goats well."
"He gave them the best food and the warmest beds."
"He brushed their coats and polished their hooves and combed
their beards."
"He spoiled them."
"If they are happy they'll stay with me," he said to
himself."
"But the goatherd didn't look after his own goats."
"He turned them out in the snow and gave them less to eat."
"He no longer brushed and polished and combed them."
"He treated them unfairly."
"But, the wild goats couldn't believe their luck."
"This is the life," they said to each other."
"Their leader, Sherpa, wasn't so sure. He was beginning to
have doubts."
"I'm not happy about this," he said.
"Why is the goatherd treating his own goats so badly?"
"Who cares about them," said one goat, unkindly."
"As long as we are all right," said another."
"Sherpa told them off."
"Think carefully," he said.
"What happens if some newer goats come along. Will the
goatherter start treating us badly?"
"The more Sherpa thought about it, the more certain he was
he was right."
"We have to leave at the first opportunity," he told his
herd."
"Spring came and the snow disappeared. The wild goats went back into the field. But Sherpa hadn't forgotten what he had
said."
"One afternoon, when the goatherd was dozing in the sun,
Sherpa ordered the wild goats to play leapfrog."
"They made a lot of noise, running and jumping and getting in each others way. And by the time the goatherd could work
out what was happening, the wild goats had not only leapfrogged over each other they also leapfrogged over the fence."
"The goatherd was furious."
"Rascals!" he yelled.
"Is this how you repay my kindness?"
"Sherpas answer came from half way down the valley:"
"You should have treated all your goats the same," he called
back."
"That would have been real kindness."
"The tame goats, left behind in the field, nodded their
heads sadly."
"They had to agree."
THE DOG IN THE MANGER
"It had been another busy day at the farm. Dog yawned. It was hot, hot, hot! And Dog was tired. He looked around for
somewhere to snooze. The barn was shady and quiet."
"And in the barn there was a manger, and it was full of hay to feed the cows. Ah, yes! The manger was just the right
place for a dog to sleep. It was soft and smelled of fresh hay and it was cool in the barn after the heat of the sun."
"Dog climbed into the manger and turned around – once…twice…
three times – and curled himself into a nest of hay with his nose by his tail."
"At that moment, who should come into the barn but Bull and
all the cows?"
"Time for some dinner, my dears?" said Bull, stepping aside
to allow his wives to go into the barn first."
"Oh, thank you dear!" replied Queeny-cow, daintily strolling
in at the head of the herd.
"You are such a gentleman! A nice munch of cool hay would be
very nice – OH!"
"She stopped when she saw Dog. All the cows stopped when they saw Dog. Dog didn't open his eyes, but his ears pricked
up like satellite dishes."
"Oh dear, said Queeny-cow, as Bull came up beside her.
"There appears to be a dog in the manger!""
"A dog? A dog?" blustered Bull.
"What would a dog be doing in the manger? Dogs don't eat
hay! I say! I say, Dog! What are you doing in our manger?"
"Sleeping," grunted Dog.
"Go away!"
"Well!" said Queeny-cow in a sulky voice.
"That's no way to behave in front of ladies!"
"You are not ladies – you are cattle," said Dog.
"That's what you are."
"Well!" squeaked Queeny-cow, offended.
"I have never been spoken to in that way!"
"Hrmph!" snorted Bull.
"I must ask you to not speak to my wife that way. She's very delicate, you know! My dear," he said to Queeny-cow, "Leave
this to me!"
"Sir!" he continued, lowering his head and displaying his
very fine horns, "I must ask you to leave the manger NOW!"
"Or else?" asked Dog.
He rose up on stiff legs, lowered his head and bared his
teeth.
"OR ELSE?" he barked."
"Bull looked at the fierce dog and backed away in sudden
confusion."
"Alright! Alright! K..K..Keep your hair on!"
"Attack him!" Queeny-cow encouraged.
"Don't be cowed!"
"I am cowed!" squeaked Bull, backing away towards the door.
"I have just remembered what my dear old mother always used
to say to me! She said "Let sleeping dog's lie!"
Goodbye!"
"And Bull lumbered out of the barn."
"Well!" said Queeny-cow.
"So much for him - we'll do this my way!" she said, turning
smartly and wandering out of the door."
"Delusional!" muttered Dog, watching the cows nudging out of
the barn door.
"Daft!" snorted Dog, turning around three times in the hay.
"Dippy!" decided Dog, curling himself into a nest of hay
with a groan of contentment and shutting his eyes."
"DOG!" roared a man's voice."
"Farmer John stormed furiously in through the barn door."
"DOG!" he shouted angrily.
"Get out of that manger at once, you selfish animal! There are silly cows milling everywhere they shouldn't be! I've
got cows in my kitchen! I've got cows in my car! And I've got a Bull hiding under my bed! Stop being a dog in a manger and go and round up the sheep!"
"Dog jumped down from the hay and skulked out of the barn
with his tail between his legs."
"Drat!" he sighed.
"It's a dog's life!"
ANDROCLES AND THE LION
"Once there was a slave called Androcles who belonged to a very cruel master. Androcles worked all day long in his
master's fields and was never paid a single penny. He was always tired and hungry and one night Androcles decided to escape."
"He waited until his master was fast asleep then he crept out of the house...and silently made his way into the
forest...and started running."
"Androcles knew that if he was caught he'd be punished so he ran all night and in the morning he lay down to rest. He'd
just fallen asleep when he was woken by a terrible roaring sound."
"Androcles jumped to his feet and standing right in front of him was a huge Lion. He was about to run away when he
noticed the lion was holding out his paw...and...he wasn't really roaring...he was crying because a huge thorn was sticking out of his paw."
"Ouch! No wonder you're crying," said Androcles to the lion.
"I'd like to help you but if I come any closer you'll
probably eat me."
"But the lion had such a sad look in its eye that before Androcles had time to think he'd stepped forward and pulled
out the thorn."
"The lion opened his mouth and let out a terrible cry..."
"...and for a moment Androcles thought he was going to be eaten but instead of biting Androcles the lion gently licked
his face."
"Androcles fetched some water from a stream and washed the
Lion's bleeding paw."
"You'll be alright now," said Androcles."
"The lion licked Androcles one last time as if to say "thank
you" then limped off into the forest. Then Androcles heard a voice"
"That's him. Quickly...tie him up."
"Androcles knew that voice. It was his master. Six men
grabbed Androcles and tied him up with ropes."
"Thought you would escape did you?" said the master.
"Nobody escapes from me."
"Now Androcles was in really big trouble. The men took
Androcles to the city and threw him in prison."
"Next day a prison guard brought Androcles some food."
"Do you hear that roaring Androcles? We haven't fed that lion since we caught him. But he's going to have plenty to
eat tomorrow when we put you in his cage."
"Next morning Androcles was taken to a huge arena like a football stadium. The Emperor and thousands of his people
had come to see a man being eaten by a lion."
"In the centre of the arena was a cage and in the cage was a
huge, very hungry lion."
"The crowd clapped and cheered as the guards pushed
Androcles into the cage and slammed the door shut."
"Everyone went very still as the lion leapt towards Androcles. But then something odd happened. The lion stopped
and stood very still."
"He knew this man. He'd seen him somewhere before. Then he
remembered the thorn that had stuck in his paw."
"Are you going to eat me then old friend?" said
Androcles."
"But the lion just purred and licked the slave's face."
"At first the crowd were angry. This wasn't supposed to happen. They hadn't paid good money to see a lion lick a
man's face."
"But the Emperor stood up and said, "This is the most
amazing thing I've ever seen.""
"and he started to clap..."
"...and the people thought, "If the Emperor's clapping then
maybe I should clap too.""
"Soon clapping and cheering rang round the arena. Androcles was taken to the palace and when the Emperor heard the story
of the lion and the thorn he announced that both Androcles and the lion should be given their freedom."
"Androcles, you helped the lion so the lion helped you" said
the Emperor."
"See how one good deed leads to another. You're a free man
now."
"Androcles and the lion walked out of the city together;
both free."
THE DOG AND HIS REFLECTION
"When Patch was young he was a good dog. He was warm and soft and had the sweetest breath, and he licked the tip of
your nose if you let him."
"And because he was so good he was allowed to stay in the
farm kitchen. The other farm dogs lived outside in a
kennel."
"But just because a dog is warm and soft and good when he's a puppy, and licks the tip of your nose if you let him, it
doesn't mean he will grow up like that."
"Once, when Patch was a fully grown up dog he pulled the cloth off the table and all the family's dinner crashed to
the floor."
"He had eaten it all up before the farmer's wife came
running in."
"Bad dog!" scolded the farmer's wife."
"He barked at the children and bit their legs when they rode
their bikes."
"Bad dog!" cried the children."
"He pulled up all the flowers outside the kitchen door, dug five holes in the lawn and did his business in the farmer's
hat."
"Bad dog!" yelled the farmer."
"So Patch was sent outside with the other dogs. And because people only said "bad dog!" to him, everyone forgot he'd
once been called Patch. Now he was called simply, "Bad Dog"."
"At feeding time every dog had their own bowl of biscuits and scraps from the table, but Bad Dog would get to them
first."
"He would growl and snarl and turn up his lips to show how
sharp his teeth were."
"The other dogs had to wait, licking their mouths until Bad Dog had finished eating. When he had eaten all the meat and
the gravy, and all the dog biscuits from the bowls, all that was left was dry bread and carrots and broccoli, and lots of other things that farmers eat but dogs don't."
"But then one day he went too far."
"The smell of roast meat was wafting out from the kitchen. Bad Dog ran in, snatched the huge bone with the meat still
on and ran off with it."
"Bad Dog," screamed the farmer, running after him.
"Come back with that meat now, or you'll never come back
again!"
"Bad Dog took no notice. This was a whole big bone with the meat still on, not scraps, and he wanted it more than
anything."
"So Bad Dog ran away with it."
"He ran for a long time until at last he came to a little bridge. This would be a good place to stop and eat his
stolen dinner."
"He looked over the side of the bridge."
"And had such a shock!"
"Below him in the still water was another dog. A big, fierce, ugly dog - and this dog had a bone with all the meat
on too!"
"Bad Dog had to have it. Two joints of meat! His lips turned back in a snarl, and so did the lips of the other dog. He
opened his mouth to growl…And so did the other dog!"
"And the bone fell from Bad Dog's jaws into the water and
was taken away by the stream."
"It had been his own reflection in the still water he had
seen, and now instead of two bones he had nothing."
"Bad Dog felt sad. He had lost everything that was
important."
"From now on,"
he said to himself, "I shall try and be better. I shall be good instead of bad and nice instead of nasty. Then one
day... ...everyone will love me again."
"And that is what happened."
"If you are too greedy, he realised, it's easy to end up
with nothing."
THE HERON AND THE FISH
"The heron walked like a king along the grassy river bank."
"The otter curtseyed as the heron passed."
"The water vole bent his knee as the heron passed."
"The kingfisher bowed so low as the heron passed that she turned completely upside down on the branch she was clinging
to."
"But the otter was not being polite."
"The water vole was not being reverent. The kingfisher was not being respectful. They were making fun of the heron,
though he didn't know it."
"They thought he had far too good an opinion of himself."
"They laughed at him behind his back."
"Herons are only birds. They are not Princes or Prime Ministers, Presidents or pop-stars. They are definitely not
Kings, even if they walk like Kings on
grassy river banks. In other words, they are nothing
special."
"They just think they are."
"They parade along in a very high-minded fashion with their
noses in the air."
"Or they would do if they had noses."
"They have long beaks instead."
"Everything about the heron is long – he has a long beak, long neck, long body and long legs. The heron has especially
long legs. And although the heron walks along the grassy river bank on his especially long legs, he only stands on one of them, so he has a spare."
"There is one good thing to be said of herons: they have great patience. When fishing he can stand quite still for
hours waiting for their supper."
"He was quite snappy if the otter and the water vole and the kingfisher were there before him because they made such a
kafuffle."
"They were always doing things, these lesser creatures. They
chattered. They swam. They dug holes in the river bank. They did high dives and low belly-flops; all splashy, noisy, annoying things!"
"They
played games, when all he wanted was peace and quiet."
"Then one day he came to the river later than usual. The others had already finished for the day. The otter was
curled up on the grassy bank. The water vole was cleaning his fur. The kingfisher was pecking at something in his feathers."
"At last," thought the heron.
"I shall have the river to myself."
"He waded out to his favourite spot of clear water, pulled up his spare leg so that he was standing on only one, and
began being patient."
"It didn't take long for a minnow to swim by. The heron
watched it go past."
"You missed a fish, oh great one," said the otter."
"It wasn't worth my attention," said the heron."
"Then a stickleback swam by, and kept swimming by and the
heron still didn't move."
"You missed a nice little snack there, majesty," said the
water vole."
"Nice for you," said the heron.
"Little for me."
"Other fish swam by, each larger than the one before, but
the heron gave them hardly a glance."
"Then a very fine perch came by, a prize fit for a King –
but not for a heron."
"You missed a big one there, Highness," said the
kingfisher."
"Only a salmon is good enough for me!" claimed the heron."
"But not another fish came by that day; not a minnow, not a
stickleback, and especially not a perch."
"The heron could have eaten his fill if he'd been satisfied
with what was on offer."
"Instead he went hungry…"
"…Except for one tiny snail."
"So, don't be too hard to please or you might end up with
nothing."
THE EAGLE AND THE TORTOISE
"In a tumbledown cottage deep in the countryside lived Old Mrs Mumbles. Every morning, she opened the kitchen door…and
threw the remains of last night's dinner onto the grass."
"Three, two, one…bet I get there first!" cried Racy Rabbit."
"All the animals that lived in the garden charged towards
the food – all except Tod the very slow tortoise."
"Wait for me…!" he croaked.
But it was no good – Racy Rabbit, Fox and the birds were greedily tucking into vegetable peelings and left over
stew…and by the time Tod arrived, there was nothing left."
"It's not faaaaaair, he moaned. "I've only got short little
legs and my shell is really heavy.
I'm so slow I always get there last."
"Never mind, Tod," squeaked his friend, Milly Mouse.
"Look, I've saved you a nice piece of lettuce."
"As Tod chomped away, he spotted a great Eagle soaring on
the light breeze way up high."
"I wish I could fly like that eagle," he sighed.
"Just imagine how fast and free I would be!"
"The next day, Tod poked his head from his shell – and nearly jumped out of it in surprise. For the eagle was
standing on the grass, looking right at him."
"Us eagles have very good eyesight you know", she said in a
rather raspy voice.
"I read your lips yesterday. And I have come to grant you
your wish. I shall teach you to fly in the sky."
"Ohhh! Thank you, Eagle!" cried Tod.
"I'll give you anything you want in return."
"Anything?" asked the Eagle with a glint in her eye."
"Yes, anything," replied Tod."
"Tod gasped with excitement as the Eagle carried him high into the sky. Mountains and oceans and forests and castles
were spread out below as far as he could see."
"I can fly!" cried Tod with delight."
"Now, there's just the small matter of my payment," said the
Eagle."
"I'm rather partial to small, cuddly creatures for my tea,
so I'd like that little mouse you were talking to."
"What?! But you can't eat Milly – she's my best friend,"
protested Tod.
"But you promised to give me whatever I wanted," said the
Eagle."
"Er, yes I know - but not Milly, pleeeease…" pleaded Tod."
"There was a horrible silence. Todd shivered in the cold wind and looked down. It was an awfully long way to the
ground…"
"Very well then," said the Eagle.
"You wanted to fly – so let's see how you manage by
yourself." And with that, she shook Tod off her back."
"Heeeeeeelp!" cried Tod as he fell through the air.
"You forgot to tell me how to do it!!!"
"It's easy, just flap!" cried the now distant Eagle."
"Tod flapped and flapped his little legs, but it was no use.
Down he dropped like a very heavy stone."
"I don't think I like flying after all…" he gasped.
"I'd much rather be back on the ground. The problem is, the
ground's getting very close…very fast…!"
"As the garden rushed up to meet him, Tod shut his eyes…then
ever so slowly…opened them again…"
"He had landed in a giant pile of lettuce leaves. "We thought we'd give you a soft landing just in case your
flying lesson went horribly wrong," giggled Racy Rabbit."
"Lucky for you, Old Mrs Mumbles had a big party last night,
and threw out loads of left overs!" added Milly."
"That night, the animals celebrated with a feast. "Thanks for saving my life, guys," said Tod as he chomped on
lettuce. "You know, I much prefer being slow and steady to flying all fast and whizzy.
I even like my shell a bit more.""
"He pulled his little friend under his shell, and they
munched to their hearts" content till the sun came out
again."
THE TOWN MOUSE AND THE COUNTRY MOUSE
"Town Mouse was very fond of his own appearance."
"I shall visit my friend Country Mouse," he announced one morning, waxing his whiskers with a dab of butter and
admiring his reflection in the teapot.
"And he shall see what a very fine mouse I am!" And with a hop and a skip he straightened his bow tie and scurried off
to catch the 10.17 packing crate bound for Paddington station."
"Meanwhile, deep in the trunk of an old chestnut tree, Country Mouse was busy dusting and tidying, cleaning and
sweeping and cooking an extra special hotpot of beans and corn to welcome his cousin from the city. He had been collecting food all week to celebrate."
"There was a loud rap at the door and Country Mouse took off
his apron and scampered over to greet his friend."
"There on the doorstep stood Town Mouse looking very smart indeed in his pin-stripe suit and bowler hat. He handed
Country Mouse his gloves and bag, looked down his long nose and said, "What a very small house you have dear cousin… no chandeliers, no Persian rugs… no velvet cushion to rest upon?""
"Country Mouse smiled, he was very fond of Town Mouse and he ignored his snooty remarks - he knew that he didn't mean to
be rude."
"Come and sit down, dear cousin. You must be tired and hungry from your journey," he said pulling out a little
acorn stool for him to sit on."
"What no napkins?…no silver service?" sniffed Town Mouse.
"No scented bowl to wash my paws?"
"Country Mouse smiled again and served up the hot soup and
barleyseed bread."
"What is this food?" scoffed Town Mouse.
"No caviar, no steak tartare?"
"No pickled herring and horseradish sauce?! Come, my friend,
this instant! We're off to the city and I shall show you how to live!""
"It was late that night when they arrived at Town Mouse's House and as they crept along the hall to the grand dining
room Country Mouse felt the soft wool carpet under his tired little paws and the warm glow of the fire and he remembered the cold, bitter wind that blew through his country tree cottage."
"And how his little eyes beamed and his whiskers twitched at the sight of the left over feast that was laid out on the
table for them to gobble up!"
"There were soufflés and sandwiches, savoury flans and pastries. There were jellies and trifles and fresh cream
cakes and a MOUNTAIN of meringues…"
"Couthin…I'b neber seen such a banquet as thith!" cried
Country Mouse."
"But this is how you could feast EVERY night my friend!"
laughed Town Mouse."
"The two little mice had a very merry time…"
"Then all of a sudden there was a thunderous ROAR!"
"Wwwwwwwhat's that terrible noise Cousin?!" stammered
Country Mouse."
"H-h-h-h-hoover?!" cried the terrified little mouse."
"Yes…oh and the Humans"…"
"And just at that moment the door burst open and in marched
a team of kitchen staff with brooms and mops."
"WHAT EEZ ZEES?!" shouted the French Chef…"MEESES! Quick
hoover zem up!"
"Yikes!" squeaked Country Mouse as they scampered down the
table leg and through a crack in the floorboards.
"I'm off!" he cried as he scurried off under the door."
"So soon?" called Town Mouse.
"No fabulous food? No smart city life?"
"No, no, dear cousin," called Country Mouse over his
shoulder.
"And no loud scary monsters to gobble me up! It's the simple, safe life at home for me…not the rich, dangerous
high life!"
BELLING THE CAT
"The mice who lived on a farm were very happy because the farmer's cat which was supposed to hunt and kill mice was
old and lazy and spent most of his time sleeping in the sunshine."
"Can't be bothered with catching mice any more," said the
old cat.
"All that lurking about and pouncing. Got better things to
do...like sleeping."
"So the mice ran about safely all over the farm and had
plenty to eat...until one day an awful thing happened."
"The farmer came into the farmyard carrying a wooden box. He
put it on the floor and...out of the box walked a cat; a new young cat with black sleek fur and long sharp claws. The cat looked around the farmyard and she sniffed the air."
"Huh, she's nothing to be scared of," said a young mouse.
"She's only a cat. Only a lazy old cat."
"But an old mouse wasn't so sure. The new cat didn't look
old...or lazy. This cat looked young and keen and...hungry."
"Just be careful," said the old mouse.
"Just keep your eyes open and be very careful."
"That night the new cat prowled the farmyard. She walked silently in the darkness; invisible in her black coat. She
watched and she waited; listening for the tiniest sound."
"In the morning when the mice met for breakfast in the barn
there didn't seem to be quite so many of them."
"Where is everyone this morning?" said the young mouse."
"I wonder," said the old mouse looking at the new cat who was sitting outside the farmhouse with a big smile on her
face."
"Each night more mice disappeared… and the new cat seemed to
be getting fatter."
"Soon the mice were really scared. Finally the old mouse
called a meeting."
"We have to do something," he said.
"If we can't get rid of this cat she'll end up eating us
all. We need a plan."
"The problem," said the old mouse, "is that you can't hear the cat coming. She moves silently in the darkness. You
don't know she's there...until it's too late."
"That's it!" said the young mouse.
"We get a bell and tie it round the cat's neck. The bell will ring every time the cat moves and we'll know where she
is so she'll never catch us."
"The mice all looked at each other."
"Not bad," said someone."
"Actually, that's brilliant!" said someone else."
"The mice leapt into action. One group found a little bell that had fallen off the back of the farmhouse door and
another found some string which had been holding up a scarecrow's trousers."
"See," said the young mouse.
"We have everything we need for my brilliant plan. That cat
has eaten her last mouse. All our troubles are over."
"The mice all cheered and patted the young mice on the back. The young mouse had saved everyone from being eaten and
suddenly he was a hero...for about ten seconds."
"Just one question," said the old mouse.
"Who's going to tie the bell on the cat?"
"The mice all went silent then looked at the young mouse. The young mouse looked at the floor. He didn't want that
job. Nobody wanted that job."
"Oh dear," said the old mouse.
"It's easy to say something but often harder to actually do
it."
THE TOO FAT FOX
"A bitter wind blew the last leaves from the trees as Fox
made his way across the fields in search of food."
"The lake had been frozen for weeks and the livestock were tucked up safe and warm in the farmer's winter barns. Fox
couldn't remember when he had last eaten. His skinny ribs stuck through his patchy, moth-eaten coat, his teeth chattered and the hard frosty ground hurt his paws as he walked."
"Not a chicken, not a bird, not a puny little rabbit…not a scrap of food for a fox to eat…I shall surely die of cold
and hunger," he muttered miserably as he huddled up against a gnarled old tree trunk for shelter."
"Earlier that morning, not far from where our Fox was crouching, Mrs Tom Cobbler was busy fussing around her
husband and shooing him out of the farmhouse."
"Here's yer shopping list Mr Tom Cobbler - one nice, juicy leg of pork, 2 kilos of potatoes, half a bag of carrots, 2
onions and some big, firm cooking apples for our Sunday lunch. Now don't you go forgetting anything Mr Tom Cobbler. You're the most forgetful man I ever knew!" and she waved a dishcloth at him."
"Yars, Mrs Tom Cobbler…er I mean… no dear, I won't forget." And he stuffed the shopping list in his trouser pocket and
walked off to market."
"It was a long, cold walk to market and it was a long, hard walk back with his rucksack full of his wife's Sunday
shopping."
"Mr Tom Cobbler decided to sit down for a moment's rest beside a tree. (The very tree our Mr Fox was going to huddle
close too later on.)"
"After his rest and before he set off down the lane he looked about for a place to hide his shopping bag and saw a
hollow in the tree trunk."
"Ah, that'll do, he said. "That'll keep it safe from foxes – that hole's far too small for a plump ol" fox to climb
through." And off he tramped up the hill towards the farmyard."
"Well…what a nice surprise for our Mr Fox crouching beside that very same tree later that morning. His sly foxy nose
began to twitch…and he sniffed the cold wintry air…there was a whiff of FOOD nearby! And it seemed to be coming from the hollow of the very tree he sat against."
"And because he was so very starved and thin – our TOO THIN MR FOX was able to slip easily through into the hole. And
what did he find inside? That's right! All Mrs Tom Cobbler's Sunday dinner!"
"And what did he do with it? That's right! He gobbled it all
up, lickity-quick."
"And he felt very full indeed…SO full in fact that our TOO THIN FOX had become TOO FAT FOX in a matter of ten minutes
flat! Too fat in fact to fit back through the hole."
"So our Mr Fox had to wait and wait for days and days until his plump little tummy turned thin once more…and he could
climb back out through the hole of the tree again and off in search of food."
"Which just goes to show – that if you wait long enough –
the problem
might go away."
"And what happened to old Mr Tom Cobbler that day?"
"Well, Mrs Tom Cobbler wasn't happy at all that he'd lost the Sunday roast - so he had turnip soup and potato peel pie
instead!"
THE RAT AND THE ELEPHANT
"A Rat was walking through the city. He was a very proud Rat
who believed that he was the most frightening animal alive."
"Oh, yes!" said the Rat to himself.
"Everyone's scared of me."
"Scary Rat coming through. Out of my way."
"The Rat turned a corner and saw a crowd of people standing
by the side of the road."
"Brilliant," thought the rat.
"I do like a crowd."
"He jumped out into the middle of the road right in front of the crowd and waited for the first scream... but there
wasn't one. Everybody was staring up the road. Nobody even noticed the Rat."
"Look everybody," said the Rat.
"Over here. Rat. See."
"Nothing happened. The people were all too busy looking up
the road."
"This is ridiculous," said the Rat.
"Are you all blind? Can't you see me?"
"Then the Rat saw what the people were looking at."
"An elephant was coming down the road. Sitting on the
elephant's back and stroking a large white cat rode the
King."
"Wow," said a man.
"Just look at the size of that elephant!"
"Never mind the elephant," said the Rat.
"What about me. Look at me. I'm a scary rat."
"Yes look at its wonderful long trunk," said a woman."
"That's just its nose," said the Rat.
"I've got a nose."
"And its huge ears," said a little girl."
"I've got ears," said the Rat, jumping up and down."
"But nobody was listening. They were too busy admiring the
enormous elephant."
"That is the most wonderful creature in the whole world,"
they all said."
"No...no!" said the Rat.
"There's nothing wonderful about elephants. How many legs have they got? Four like me. How many eyes have they got?
Two like me. What colour are they? Grey like me. See, I'm exactly the same as an elephant except an elephant's really slow and boring and I'm truly the most fierce and terrifying creature in the world."
"But nobody noticed the Rat... ...apart from the King's
Cat."
"Look at me...look at me. I'm exactly like an elephant "cept
better.
Elephant's are rubbish.
I am the most fierce and..."
"The Rat didn't finish what he was saying because..."
"...in an instant the white cat had run down the elephant's
trunk and was staring the Rat in the face."
"Exactly like an elephant, eh?" said the Cat looking down at
the Rat."
"Well maybe not exactly," said the Rat looking nervously at
the cat's sharp claws.
"Obviously my nose isn't quite as long...my ears are a bit
smaller...and I haven't got a king riding on my back…"
"Suddenly the Cat's paw flashed out and pinned the Rat to
the ground. The Rat couldn't move."
"Think I could do this to an elephant?" said the Cat."
"Um...not sure," said the Rat."
"The Cat scooped up the Rat and held him up to her mouth."
"Think I could do this to an elephant?" said the Cat."
"No, maybe not," said the Rat shaking in fear."
"Think I could eat an elephant in two seconds flat?" asked
the Cat."
"Nope," whispered the Rat."
"Look what I've found," said the Cat to the people putting
the terrified Rat back down on the ground."
"The Rat was shaking and looked so small and scared that
people weren't at all frightened of him."
"What is it?" said a man."
"Sort of mouse I think," said his wife.
"Funny little mouse thing probably."
"As he slunk away the Rat heard the Cat say "A rat and an elephant may be the same colour but that doesn't make them
the same size.
You remember that...
Mr Rat.""
"And the Rat did remember that. For ever."
THE ANT AND THE DOVE
"It was another hot, dry day in the forest…"
"Ant had been wandering over crinkly, dry leaves for days in
search of a nice, cool drink…"
"All I need is a drop of rain falling from a leaf – or a tiny pool of dew on a flower petal – or even a muddy
puddle…" he thought.
But it was so hot all the dew and puddles in the forest had
dried up."
"I'm so thirsty, that I have no choice," Ant sighed at last.
"I shall have to go in search of the Roaring River."
"Ant had been warned about the Roaring River. "It roars and it swirls and if you go too close, it will sweep you away,"
a wise owl had told him."
"But Ant was desperate. "The river has more drops of water than all the rain clouds in the world," he thought. "It's my
only hope of staying alive.""
"So Ant headed off. He plodded on and on through the trees,
until finally, he heard rushing water ahead…"
"Before him lay the Roaring River – as vast as a sea, or so it seemed to tiny Ant. The fast flowing waters looked
frightening – but Ant was too thirsty to feel fear…"
"He clambered down the river bank and bent his weary head
into the water to drink it up."
"The cool, sparkling water was so refreshing that Ant didn't
hear a roaring wave coming towards him…"
"Suddenly, he was flat on his back - his little legs in the air, being swept away by the water! "Help!" he cried.
"Someone save me, please!""
"All of a sudden, a green leaf dropped onto the water by his side with a plop. "Quick, climb on!" cried a gentle cooing
voice."
"Ant didn't have time to see who the voice belonged to. He just did what it told him…then he opened his eyes and looked
up."
"Perching on the branch of a tree above was a pure white
Dove."
"Stay calm, little Ant - and wait for the gentle breeze to
blow the leaf to the river bank," she cooed."
"Sure enough, the leaf carried Ant to safety. He looked up – but the Dove had disappeared. "I can't leave without
thanking her," he thought. "So I shall wait until she returns.""
"Ant waited and waited. Then, just as he was about to fall asleep, he heard strange noises. They were coming closer and
closer…"
"Two men emerged from the forest and stopped under the Dove's tree. One was carrying a bucket – the other a large,
golden cage. "This is the tree – the home of the most beautiful dove in the land," said the man with the cage. "I hope that glue in your bucket is sticky enough…""
"Indeed it is," said the second as he covered the branch
with a thick, green paste.
"When the Dove lands, its feet will stick to the branch – then we can put it in the cage and take it to the King. All
we have to do is hide and wait…"
"Ant was horrified. "I can't let this happen!" he thought. "But what can a tiny creature like me do against two such
giants of men?""
"Ant looked up as he heard the flapping of wings. The Dove had returned and was about to land on the sticky branch…!
"If I'm going to act, I must use the only weapon I have…" thought Ant. "And I must do it RIGHT NOW!""
"So he jumped onto the men's feet – and bit as hard as he
could…time and time again…"
"Yow!!!" they cried out in pain and took to their heels
through the forest."
"Thank you for saving me from a life in a cage," cooed the
Dove to Ant."
"And thank you for saving me from the giant wave," replied
Ant."
THE BOY WHO CRIED WOLF
"A young boy got a job with a shepherd."
"Just keep your eyes open and look out for wolves" said the
shepherd.
"Wolves always try to eat my sheep. If you see one, ring
this bell and shout out "Wolf..!
Wolf..!"
Then we'll come running with our guns.
Can you do that, boy?"
"Don't you worry Mr Shepherd," said the boy.
"Your sheep are safe with me.""
"The boy took the sheep up into the hills and sat down with
his bell."
"Don't worry sheep," he said.
"I'm here now. I'm in charge. You'll be safe with me."
"All morning the boy sat in the grass looking for wolves. "I
expect they're hiding," he said to the sheep."
"That night the boy took the sheep back to the village. The shepherd counted his sheep and was very pleased. "Well
done," he said. "All safe.
Same again tomorrow?""
"Yes sir!" said the boy."
"The next day was exactly the same as the first day. The boy took the sheep to the hills and sat down with his bell
looking for wolves."
"There weren't any."
"The boy noticed that the day felt very long. There was no-one to talk to...except sheep...and the sheep never
talked back...they just ate grass...all day..."
"By the fifth day the boy was very bored with his job. He
looked up at the mountains. Not a wolf in sight."
"He looked down at the bell and he thought: "Maybe I could
just pretend there's a wolf.""
"So he picked up his bell... ...and rang it, shouting "Wolf...wolf... ...hurry...come quickly...there's a big old
wolf coming!""
"Soon he could hear the sound of men running up the hill.
"Where is it?" said the shepherd. "Gone," said the boy."
"He just ran off." "Well done boy," said the shepherd.
"You saved my sheep." The other men all patted the boy on the head and said how brave he'd been and what a good job
he'd done.
The boy felt so proud and pleased with himself that he
almost forgot that he'd made the whole thing up."
"A few days later he was bored again. "The only good day I had in this job was when I pretended there was a wolf," he
told the sheep. "And I rang my bell and all the men came and told me what a good job I'd done.
It was brilliant.""
"He looked at his bell. And that's when he decided to do it
again."
"He rang, he shouted and again the men came running. "Where
is it?" said the shepherd. "Gone," said the boy. "Ran away."
This time the men didn't say "well done" and pat him on the
head.
This time they looked at the boy like they didn't believe
him.
"There was a wolf, honest," he said.
The men just walked back to the village without speaking."
"Now the boy felt really sorry for himself. "They know I
rang my bell when there was no wolf.""
"Then out of the corner of his eye he saw a movement - a big
grey thing was coming down the hillside heading straight for the sheep."
"The boy rang his bell and he shouted. "Wolf...wolf...come
quickly... ...there's a wolf!""
"Down in the village the men heard the bell ring and just
carried on working."
"Little fool," said the Shepherd.
"Does he really think we'll fall for that again?"
"The boy kept ringing his bell. There were tears in his eyes as he watched the wolf make a meal of one of the shepherd's
fattest sheep."
"I rang my bell but nobody came," the boy told the shepherd
that evening."
"The shepherd nodded "Nobody believes a liar...even when
he's speaking the truth."