Dunstan Thwaite looked at the railway crossing
and decided that it was time for John Dunn
to die.
It was a very suitable place for a murder.
There were trees all around, and they hid
the trains which came so fast along the railway
line.
The nearest house was Thwaite's own, and this
was also hidden by the trees.
People and traffic did not use the crossing
very often, and the big gates were kept locked.
There was a small gate used by passengers
going to the station, but at night it was
always quiet.
Thwaite was a worried man.
He had to use sleeping powders to help him
sleep.
But after tonight, things were going to be
different.
The time had come to stop the blackmail.
The time had come for John Dunn to die.
It all began five years earlier...
Thwaite worked in the offices of a large company,
and his only money was the money that the
company paid him.
It was not much, but it was enough.
Then he met the beautiful Miss Hilda Lorraine
and asked her to marry him.
She came from an important family who were
supposed to be very rich, but in fact they
had less money than Thwaite had thought.
He learned that he would have to pay for the
wedding himself.
And he did not have enough money for the expensive
kind of wedding that Miss Lorraine wanted.
So Thwaite stole a thousand pounds, by changing
the figures in the company's books.
He planned to put the money back after he
was married, but someone discovered that it
was missing.
Thwaite kept quiet.
Another man was thought to be the thief, and
he lost his job.
Thwaite still said nothing.
But John Dunn worked in the same office.
He worked closely with Thwaite and guessed
Thwaite's crime.
He searched through the company's books until
he found what he was looking for.
Then he went to Thwaite.
'Sorry to have to ask you, Mr Thwaite,' he
said.
'I need a hundred pounds... for my son.
He's in a bit of trouble, you see...'
'But you don't have a son,' said Thwaite.
Dunn just smiled.
It wasn't a very nice smile.
'A hundred pounds,' he said again.
And then Thwaite knew that he was being blackmailed.
He paid Dunn one hundred pounds, and Dunn
said nothing more for a year.
During that time, Thwaite got married.
Then the day came when Dunn asked him for
more money.
'Two hundred and fifty pounds,' he said to
Thwaite.
'I can't pay-' began Thwaite.
But he did.
Either he paid or he went to prison.
It went on for five years, and each time Dunn
wanted more money.
Thwaite found it difficult to live on the
money that he was left with.
His wife liked expensive things.
An expensive house, an expensive car, visits
to expensive restaurants.
She also discovered that some of the money
her husband was paid each year seemed to disappear.
He tried to lie about it, but he knew that
she thought he was paying to keep another
woman.
Oh, how he hated John Dunn!
Something must happen!
And then he remembered the railway crossing.
It was not a new idea.
Weeks before, he had thought about what could
happen there.
The idea came when the doctor gave him some
powders to help him sleep.
He thought about giving Dunn enough of them
to kill him, but then he got a better idea.
Although he was afraid, Thwaite slowly realized
that murder was the only answer to his problem.
Then Dunn asked for more money.
'Five hundred pounds, Mr Thwaite,' Dunn told
him.
'Five hundred!' said Thwaite.
'Why not ask for the moon?
You'll get neither one nor the other.'
'Five hundred,' repeated Dunn, calmly.
It was then that Thwaite decided to murder
the other man.
He pretended to think about the money for
a moment, then he said, 'Come to my house
tomorrow night and we'll talk.'
He remembered his wife was going to be away
in London all night.
'And bring those papers from the office which
you want me to look at.'
'All right,' said Dunn.
The following evening, Thwaite put two hundred
pounds in his pocket.
Then he put half of one of his sleeping powders
into a whisky bottle.
There was only enough whisky for two glasses,
but there was an unopened bottle next to it.
Next he put a hammer into one pocket of his
overcoat, and a torch into the other pocket.
The coat was outside the door of his study.
Lastly, he moved the hands on his watch and
on the study clock forward by ten minutes.
Those extra ten minutes would give him his
alibi.
Thwaite knew that he must be extra careful.
He knew that people at the office thought
there was some secret between him and Dunn.
A secret that Thwaite didn't want anyone to
know.
'If Dunn is killed,' he thought, 'they'll
wonder if it was really an accident, or if
I murdered him.'
But if his plan went well, the police would
believe that he hadn't left the house.
Thwaite sat down to wait for John Dunn.
He thought about what he was going to do.
Murder!
He could almost see his hand holding the hammer
above Dunn; could hear the awful sound of
it crashing down on to the man's head.
He could see Dunn's dead body!
Dead all except the eyes, which looked at
Thwaite... followed him everywhere he went...
He tried to calm himself.
He remembered why he was doing this.
When Dunn was dead, his problems were over.
Half an hour later, Dunn arrived.
Jane opened the door.
Jane was the servant who lived in the house
with Thwaite and his wife.
She brought Dunn into the study.
Thwaite smiled in a friendly way.
'Oh, good.
You've brought those papers for me to see,
Dunn.
Thank you.'
After Jane left, the two men looked at each
other.
'Give me the papers,' Thwaite said.
'I'll look at them now that you've brought
them.'
Fifteen minutes later, he gave the papers
back to Dunn and sat back in his chair.
'Now, about that other matter.'
He got up.
'But why not have a drink first?'
'No, thank you,' said Dunn.
He looked afraid.
'What are you afraid of?' said Thwaite.
He gave Dunn the opened whisky bottle and
two glasses.
'We can both drink the same whisky, if you
like.
Here, you do it.'
After a moment, Dunn put whisky into each
glass, then he waited until Thwaite drank
before he drank his own.
Thwaite watched him.
How long before the other man began to feel
sleepy?
Thwaite needed all of one sleeping powder
to make him sleep, but Dunn did not usually
take them.
'Listen, Dunn,' said Thwaite, 'I haven't got
five hundred pounds, but I can give you this.'
He took the money from his pocket and put
it on the table.
Dunn counted it.
'Two hundred?' he said, with a laugh.
'Are you trying to be funny?'
'I'm not saying it will be the last,' said
Thwaite.
'Take it now and be pleased that you've got
it.'
Dunn shook his head.
'Five hundred, Mr Thwaite.'
'I've told you, I can't do it,' said Thwaite.
'And I won't do it.
You can tell everyone what I did - I don't
care anymore.
It's been five years, and I've done a lot
of good work for the company during that time.
I saved them a lot more than a thousand pounds.
I'll sell this house and pay them back.
I'll take my punishment, then I'll go and
live in another country and give myself a
new name.'
'And your wife?' said Dunn.
'My wife will leave the country first,' Thwaite
told him.
'She'll wait for me to come out of prison.
It won't be more than two or three years.
So you can take the two hundred pounds, or
you can do your worst!'
The powder in the whisky was beginning to
make Dunn sleepy.
He looked stupidly at Thwaite, and Thwaite
began to worry.
Had he given the other man too much?
He looked at the clock.
There was not much time left.
'Will you take it, or leave it?' asked Thwaite.
'Five hundred,' said Dunn, in a heavy voice.
'I want five hundred.'
'You can go and do your worst,' said Thwaite.
Dunn held out a shaking hand.
'Come on, pay me.'
Thwaite began to worry again.
'Are you feeling all right, Dunn?
Have some more whisky.'
He opened the other bottle and put some whisky
in Dunn's glass.
Dunn drank it, and it seemed to make him feel
better.
'That was strange,' he said.
'I didn't feel very well, but I feel a little
better now.'
'If you're going to catch your train, you
must go,' said Thwaite.
'Tell me tomorrow what you finally decide
to do.
Take the two hundred with you.'
Dunn thought for a moment, then picked up
the money.
He looked at his watch, then looked at the
study clock.
'Your clock is wrong,' he said.
'I have ten more minutes.'
'Wrong?'
said Thwaite.
He looked at his own watch.
'It's your watch that's wrong.
Look at mine.'
Dunn looked and seemed unable to understand
it.
He stood up... and almost fell back again.
Thwaite hid a smile.
This was how he wanted Dunn to be.
'You're not feeling well,' he said.
'I'll take you to the station.
Wait until I get my coat.'
Now that the time was here, Thwaite felt cool
and calm.
He put on his coat, feeling the hammer in
the pocket, then went back into the study.
'We'll go out this way,' he said.
There was a side door from the study into
the garden.
Thwaite closed it silently and it locked automatically
behind him.
It was his plan to return that way, go in
quietly again, and then to change the clock
and his watch back to the right time.
Then he would shout 'Goodnight', and close
the front door very loudly, pretending that
somebody had left just then.
Next, he would call Jane and ask for some
coffee, making sure that she saw the clock.
Then, if the police asked her later, Jane
could say that Thwaite did not leave the house
and that Dunn went to catch his train at the
right time.
It was a dry night, but very dark.
A train carrying freight went slowly by.
Thwaite smiled to himself.
There were plenty of freight trains at that
time of the night.
He needed one of them to hide his crime for
him.
He planned to hit Dunn on the head with the
hammer, then put his body on the railway line.
A freight train would do the rest.
Slowly, the two men walked on, Thwaite holding
Dunn's arm.
A light wind moved among the trees.
Thwaite gently pushed the half-asleep Dunn
forwards.
He put his hand into his pocket for the hammer...
And stopped.
His keys!
They were still inside the house, and he could
not get back in without them!
He would have to ring the front door bell.
His alibi was destroyed!
It was a bad mistake.
Everything was wrong now.
He couldn't go on with the murder.
'Most murderers make mistakes,' thought Thwaite,
trying to calm himself.
'I've been the same.'
But he was shaking with fear as he thought
about the mistake.
Suddenly, he could not walk another step with
Dunn.
'Goodnight,' he said to the other man.
And before they reached the crossing, he turned
and walked back to the house.
For ten minutes, Thwaite walked up and down
outside until he began to feel calm again.
Then he rang the bell.
A few moments later, Jane opened the door.
'Thank you, Jane,' he said.
'I went to see Mr Dunn over the crossing,
and I forgot my keys.'
He went to bed a happier man.
He was not a murderer.
When he was eating his breakfast the next
morning, he decided what to do.
'I'll tell them at the office that I stole
the thousand pounds,' he said to himself.
'I'll take my punishment, and then I can have
some peace again.'
It suddenly seemed so easy.
Until Jane came in.
'Have you heard the news, sir?'
she said.
'Mr Dunn was killed by a train on the crossing
last night.
A man who was working on the railway line
found him this morning.'
Thwaite slowly went white.
Jane was looking at him strangely.
What was she thinking?
What story did he tell her the night before?
He couldn't remember!
'Dunn killed!' he said.
'How terrible, Jane!
I'll go down.'
The body was in a small railway building,
near the line.
There was a policeman outside.
'A sad accident, Mr Thwaite,' the policeman
said.
'You knew the man, didn't you, sir?'
'He worked in my office,' replied Thwaite.
'He was with me last night, discussing business.
I suppose this happened on his way home.
It's terrible!'
'It's very sad, sir,' said the policeman.
'But accidents will happen.'
'I know that,' said Thwaite.
'But I wish he hadn't drunk so much of my
whisky.
I was going to walk with him to the station.'
The policeman looked closely at Thwaite.
'And did you, sir?'
'No,' said Thwaite.
'The cold night air seemed to make him feel
better.
I turned back before the crossing.'
The policeman said no more, but later that
day two more policemen came to the office.
'Have they talked to Jane?' wondered Thwaite.
Again he told them, 'I left Dunn before we
reached the railway crossing.'
They wrote down what he said to them, then
went away.
Next day, they came back.
There were things that Thwaite could not explain
to them.
Why did the whisky bottle contain what was
left of a sleeping powder?
Why was the study clock wrong by ten minutes?
(At dinner-time earlier on the same evening,
Jane had noticed that it was right.)
And why was a hammer found in his overcoat
pocket?
Then the police found papers in Dunn's house.
The handwriting on them was Dunn's.
It told the story of Thwaite and the thousand
pounds, and it told how Thwaite was a thief.
The police then discovered that money taken
from Thwaite's bank account over the last
five years always appeared a few days later
in Dunn's bank book.
Lastly, the time of death was known to be
10.30 pm because Dunn's blood was found on
the train that went through the railway crossing
at that time.
It was also seven minutes before Jane opened
the front door to let Thwaite back in.
At first, Thwaite had no answers to all their
questions.
Finally, on his last morning, he told them
the true story.
Then he went to his death bravely.
- THE END -