In law, the third party is a person involved
in a situation in addition to the two main
people involved.
A third party quite often appears in cases
of divorce, for example.
However, all threesomes are different.
And in some of them it is not always clear
which of the three people actually is the
third party...
The two men met by arrangement in the bar
of Buswell's Hotel, at half past eleven.
'I think we'll recognize each other all right,'
the older man had said.
'I expect she's told you what I look like.'
He was tall, his face pinkish-brown from the
sun, his fair hair turning grey.
The man he met was thinner, wearing glasses
and a black winter coat - a smaller man, whose
name was Lairdman.
'Well, we're neither of us late,' Boland said
a little nervously.
'Fergus Boland.
How are you?'
They shook hands.
Boland took out his wallet.
'I'll have a whiskey myself.
What'll I get you?'
'Oh, just a lemonade for me, Fergus, this
time of day.'
Boland ordered the drinks and they stood by
the bar.
Boland held out a packet of cigarettes.
'Do you smoke?'
Lairdman shook his head.
He placed an elbow tidily on the bar.
'Sorry about this,' he said.
They were alone except for the barman, who
put their two glasses in front of them.
Boland paid him.
'I mean I'm really sorry,' Lairdman went on,
'doing this to anyone.'
'Good luck,' Boland said, raising his glass.
He had softened the colour of the whiskey
by adding twice as much water.
'You never drink this early in the day, I
suppose?' he said, carefully polite.
'Well, that's very sensible, I always think.'
'I thought it might not be an occasion for
drinking.'
'I couldn't talk to you without a drink inside
me, Lairdman.'
'I'm sorry about that.'
'You've stolen my wife from me.
It's not an everyday event.'
'I'm sorry-'
'It'd be better if you didn't keep saying
that.'
Lairdman made no protest at Boland's sharpness.
'The whole thing's awkward, I must confess.
I didn't sleep at all last night.'
'You're from Dublin, she tells me,' Boland
said, still politely.
'You're in the wood business.
There's money in that, no doubt.'
Lairdman was offended.
She'd described her husband as clumsy, but
had added he wouldn't hurt a fly.
Already, five minutes into the difficult meeting,
Lairdman wasn't so sure.
'I don't like Dublin,' Boland continued.
'To be honest, I never have.
I'm a small-town man, but of course you'll
know that.'
He imagined his wife telling her lover about
the narrowness of his experience.
She liked to tell people things; she talked
a lot.
'I want to thank you,' Lairdman said, 'for
taking all this so well.
Annabella has told me.'
'I don't see that I have any choice.'
Lairdman's lips were very thin, his mouth
a line that smiled without any obvious effort.
I wonder why he doesn't have a funny little
moustache, like so many Dubliners, thought
Boland.
'I thought you might hit me when we met,'
Lairdman said.
'But Annabella said you weren't like that
at all.'
'No, I'm not.'
'That's what I mean by taking it well.'
'All I want to know is what your plans are.'
'Plans?'
'I'm just asking if you're thinking of marrying
her, and what your arrangements are.
I mean, have you a place that's suitable for
her?
I'll have another whiskey,' he said to the
barman.
'We were hoping that - if you agree - she
would move into my place more or less at once.
It's suitable all right - a seven- room flat
in Wellington Road.
But in time we'll get a house.'
'Thanks,' Boland said to the barman, paying
him.
'It was my turn to pay,' Lairdman protested,
just a little late.
She wouldn't care for meanness, Boland thought,
when it began to have an effect on her, which
it would, in time.
'But marriage?'
Boland said.
'It isn't easy, you know, to marry another
man's wife in Ireland.'
'Annabella and I would naturally like to be
married one day.'
'That's what I wanted to ask you about.
How are you thinking of getting a divorce?
She doesn't really know much about it - we
talked about it for a long time.'
'Thank you for that.
And for suggesting we should meet.'
'You two have given me good reasons for a
divorce, Lairdman, but it's no damn use to
me.
A divorce will take years.'
'It wouldn't take so long if you had an address
in England.
Then we could get a divorce over there.'
'But I haven't an address in England.'
'It's only a thought, Fergus.'
'So she wasn't exaggerating when she said
you wanted to marry her?'
'I don't think I've ever known Annabella exaggerate,'
Lairdman replied stiffly.
Then you don't know the most important thing
about her, Boland thought - that is, she can't
help telling lies, which you and I might politely
describe as exaggerating.
'I'm surprised you never got married,' he
said.
He really was surprised, because in his experience
self-confident little men like Lairdman very
often had a good-looking woman in their life.
'I've known your wife a long time,' Lairdman
said softly, trying not to let his smile show.
'As soon as I first saw Annabella, I knew
she was the only woman I'd ever want to marry.'
Boland stared into his whiskey.
He had to be careful about what he said.
If he became angry for a moment, he was quite
likely to ruin everything.
The last thing he wanted was for the man to
change his mind.
He lit a cigarette, again offering the packet
to Lairdman, who again shook his head.
In a friendly, conversational way Boland said,
'Lairdman's an interesting name.'
'It's not Irish - French maybe, or part of
it anyway.'
When she had said her lover's name was Lairdman,
Boland had remembered it from his schooldays,
and in Buswell's bar, he had immediately recognized
the face.
At school, Lairdman had been famous for an
unexpected reason: his head had been held
down a toilet while his hair was scrubbed
with a toilet brush.
The boys who had done this were older and
bigger than him.
Called Roche and Dead Smith, they took pleasure
in punishing small boys whose faces and habits
they found annoying.
'I think we were at school together,' Boland
said.
Lairdman almost gave a jump, and this time
it was Boland who tried not to smile.
Clearly, this had come as a shock to Lairdman.
'I don't remember a Boland,' Lairdman said.
'I'd have been a little older than you.
I hated the damn place.'
'Oh, I quite liked it,' Lairdman said.
'You day boys went home in the evenings and
at weekends, we boarders had to stay there
all the time.'
'I suppose that made a difference.'
'Of course it did.'
For the first, time Boland felt annoyed.
Not only was her lover mean, he was stupid
as well.
If he had any common sense at all, he'd realize
he'd be mad to buy a house for Annabella,
because no one could ever be sure she would
do what she had promised.
'I've always thought, actually, it gave an
excellent education,' Lairdman was saying.
The awful little Frenchman who couldn't make
himself understood.
The history teacher who gave the class a history
book to read while he wrote letters.
The mathematics man who couldn't solve the
problems he presented.
The head teacher who enjoyed causing as much
physical pain as possible.
'Oh, a great place,' Boland agreed.
'A fine school.'
'I'm sorry I don't remember you.'
'I wouldn't expect you to.'
'We'll probably send our children there.
If we have boys.'
'Your children?'
'You wouldn't mind?
Oh dear, no, why should you?
I'm sorry, that was a silly thing to say.'
'I'm having another whiskey,' Boland said.
'How about you?'
'No, I'm OK, thanks.'
This time Lairdman didn't mention, even too
late, that he should pay.
Boland lit another cigarette.
So she hadn't told Lairdman?
She had let the poor man imagine that in no
time at all the seven-room flat wouldn't be
big enough for all the children they were
going to have.
Boland could almost hear her telling Lairdman
that her husband was to blame for their childless
marriage.
In fact, she'd discovered before they got
married that she couldn't have children; in
a quarrel long after the wedding she confessed
that she'd known and hadn't told him.
'Naturally,' Lairdman continued, 'we'd like
to have a family.'
'You would, of course.'
'I'm sorry that side of things didn't go right
for you.'
'I was sorry myself.'
'The thing is, Fergus, is it OK about the
divorce?'
'Are you saying I should agree to be the guilty
party?'
'It is what men in your situation usually
do, actually.
But if you don't like the idea of it-'
'Don't worry, I'll agree to be the guilty
party.'
'You're being great, Fergus.'
His wife used to say, 'I think I'll go up
and stay with Phyllis,' saying it more often
as time went by.
Phyllis was a woman she knew in Dublin.
But of course, Phyllis had just been a name
she'd used, a friend who would tell lies for
her if necessary.
'Phone me,' he used to say, and obediently
his wife phoned him, telling how Dublin looked
and how Phyllis was.
No doubt, she'd been sitting on the edge of
a bed in the seven-room flat in Wellington
Road.
'It's really good of you to come all this
way,' Lairdman said, sounding eager to end
the meeting.
'I'll ring Annabella this afternoon and tell
her all about it.
You won't mind that, Fergus?'
'Not at all.'
Boland had often interrupted such a telephone
conversation.
He would come home and find her sitting on
the stairs, talking on the phone.
As soon as he came through the door, she'd
wave a greeting and start to whisper secretively
into the phone.
The trouble with Annabella was that sooner
or later everything in the world bored her.
'Now I want to hear every single thing that's
happened since the moment you left home this
morning,' she would soon say to Lairdman.
And the poor man would begin a long story
about catching the bus and arriving at work
and having a cake with his coffee.
Later, in a quarrel, she would throw it all
back at him.
'Who could possibly want to know about your
damn cake?' she'd scream wildly at him, her
fingers spread out in the air so that her
blood-red nail varnish would dry evenly.
'I'll be able to say,' Lairdman was saying,
almost proudly, 'that neither of us got angry.
She'll be pleased about that.'
Boland couldn't imagine his wife being pleased,
since she hardly ever was.
He wondered what it was that she liked about
Lairdman.
When he'd asked her, she'd said her lover
was amusing, that he had what she called a
fantastic sense of fun.
'I wonder what became of Roche and Dead Smith,'
he said.
He didn't know why he said it, why he couldn't
accept that the business between them was
over.
He should have shaken hands with Lairdman
and left it at that, perhaps saying there
were no hard feelings.
He would never have to see the man again;
once in a while, he would simply feel sorry
for him.
'I don't remember either of them,' said Lairdman,
shaking his head.
'I'll say goodbye, Fergus.
I'm grateful, I really am.'
'They were the boys who had the bright idea
of washing your hair in a toilet bowl.'
Boland had said to himself over and over again
that Lairdman was welcome to her.
He looked ahead to an easy life, living alone.
The house she had filled with her moods and
her lies for the last twelve years would be
as silent as a peaceful sleep.
He would clear out the memories of her, because
naturally she wouldn't do that herself - the
old fashion magazines, the empty medicine
bottles, the clothes she had no further use
for, the curtains torn to pieces by her cats.
He would cook his own meals, and Mrs Couglan
would still come to clean every morning.
Mrs Couglan wouldn't exactly be sorry to see
her go, either.
'I don't know why you keep going on about
your schooldays,' Lairdman said.
'Let me get you a real drink before you go.
Two big ones,' Boland called to the barman.
'No, really,' Lairdman protested.
'Really now.'
He had put on his coat and a pair of black
leather gloves.
'Oh, go on, man.
We're both in need of it.'
Finger by finger Lairdman took one of the
gloves off again, and unwillingly picked up
the new glass.
They drank.
'I only mentioned the school,' Boland said,
'because that was the other thing that you
and I shared.'
'As I said, I think we'd maybe send the children
there.'
'You don't remember it?'
Boland asked.
'What's that?'
'The toilet thing.'
'Look here, Boland-'
'I've offended you.
I didn't mean that at all.'
'Of course you haven't offended me.
It's just that I see no reason to keep going
on about things like that.'
'We'll talk of something else.'
'Actually, I'm getting late.'
The second glove was pulled on again, the
coat buttons were checked to see that all
was well for the street.
The glove was removed again when Lairdman
remembered there'd have to be a handshake.
'Thanks for everything,' he said.
For the second time, Boland surprised himself
by being unable to let the matter rest.
'You mention your children,' he heard himself
saying.
'Would these be your and Annabella's children?'
Lairdman's mouth dropped open and he stared
at Boland.
'What other children are there?' he asked,
shaking his head in a puzzled way.
'She can't have children, Lairdman.'
'Oh now, look here-'
'That's a medical fact.
The unfortunate woman is incapable of being
a mother.'
'I think you're drunk.
One whiskey after another you've had.
Annabella's told me a thing or two about you,
you know.'
'She hasn't told you about the cats she's
going to bring with her.
She hasn't told you she can't have children.
She hasn't told you she gets so bored that
her face turns white with anger.
It's best not to be near her then, Lairdman.
Take my advice on that.'
'She's told me you can't stay sober.'
'Except for occasions like this, I hardly
ever drink.
I drink a lot less than Annabella does, I
can promise you.'
'You've been unable to give Annabella children.
She's sorry for you, she doesn't blame you.'
'Annabella was never sorry for anyone in her
life.'
'Now look here, Boland-'
'Look nowhere, man.
I've had twelve years of the woman.
I'm ready to let you take my place.
But there's no need for this talk of divorce,
I'm just telling you that.
She'll come and live with you in your seven-room
flat; she'll live in any house you like to
buy, but if you wait forever, you won't find
children coming along.
All you'll have is two cats that want to bite
the legs off you.'
'You're being most unpleasant, Boland.'
'I'm telling you the truth.'
'You seem to have forgotten that Annabella
and myself have talked about all this.
She knew there'd be bitterness.
Well, I understand that.
I've said I'm sorry.'
'You're a mean little wooden man, Lairdman.
Your head belongs in a toilet bowl.
Were you all wet when they let go of you?
I'd love to have seen it, Lairdman.'
'Will you keep your damn voice down?
And stop trying to quarrel with me!
I won't stand here and listen to this.'
'I think Dead Smith went on to become a-'
'I don't care what he became.'
Suddenly Lairdman was gone.
Boland didn't even turn his head.
After a moment he lit a fresh cigarette.
For half an hour, he remained alone, where
his wife's lover had left him, thinking about
his schooldays and Lairdman.
He had lunch in the dining room of the hotel,
ordering soup and fish.
He imagined himself, one day in the future,
entering the silence of his house.
He'd actually been born in it.
Opposite O'Connor's garage, it was the last
one in the town, yellow-painted and ordinary,
but a house he loved.
'Did you say the fish, sir?'
the waitress enquired.
'Yes, I did.'
He'd got married in Dublin, as Annabella's
family lived there.
His friends and neighbours had been delighted
when he brought her to live among them.
They stopped him in the street and told him
how lucky he was.
But those same people would be delighted when
she left.
The terrible bitterness that filled her, because
of not being able to have children, eventually
turned her beauty into a kind of madness.
That's what had happened, nothing else.
Slowly he ate his fish.
Nobody would mention it much; they'd know
what had happened and they'd say to one another
that one day, probably, he'd marry again.
He wondered if he would.
He ordered a slice of apple cake with cream,
and later coffee came.
He was glad it was all over.
Now he had accepted the truth; it had been
necessary to hear it from someone other than
his wife.
When first she'd told him, he'd wondered if
it was all just another of her lies.
He paid his bill and went out to the car park.
It was because there hadn't been enough for
her to do, he thought, as he drove out of
Dublin through the heavy city traffic.
A childless woman in a small town had all
the time in the world.
She had changed the furniture around, and
had chosen the wallpaper that her cats had
later damaged.
But she hadn't joined any clubs or made any
friends.
He'd driven her to Dublin as often as he could,
before she'd started going there alone to
visit Phyllis.
For years, he'd known she wasn't happy, but
until she told him, he'd never suspected she
had become involved with a man.
Lairdman would have telephoned her by now,
perhaps to say, 'Why don't you drive up this
afternoon?'
Maybe all day she had been packing, knowing
the meeting at Buswell's was nothing to worry
about.
The little white Volkswagen he'd bought her
might be on the road to Dublin already.
He was on the open road now, looking out for
the Volkswagen coming towards him.
If she passed him, would she greet him with
a touch on the horn?
Or would he greet her?
He didn't know if he would.
Better to wait.
But over the next fifty miles or so, there
was no sign of his wife's car.
And of course, he told himself, there was
no reason why there should be.
It was only his own idea that she might depart
that afternoon, and surely, she'd need more
than a day to pack all her things.
The more he thought about it, the less likely
it was that she would be capable of completing
the move alone.
He turned the radio on, and heard a song called
'Dancing in the dark'.
It reminded him of the world he supposed his
wife and Lairdman belonged to, the excitement
of secret love, dancing close together in
the darkness.
'Poor Annabella,' he said aloud, while the
music still played.
Poor girl, to have married a small town businessman
like himself.
It was lucky, really, that she had met self-confident
little Lairdman.
He imagined them in each other's arms, and
then their shared smile before they held each
other close again.
As the dull third party, he had no further
part to play.
But as Boland reached the first few houses
on this side of his hometown, he knew none
of that was right.
The little white car had not carried her to
Lairdman today.
It would not do so tomorrow or the next day.
It would not do so next month, or after Christmas,
or in February, or in spring.
It would never do so.
It hadn't mattered reminding Lairdman of what
he had suffered as a schoolboy; it hadn't
mattered telling him she was in the habit
of lying, or even calling him mean.
That kind of unpleasant talk was more or less
expected in the situation they found themselves
in, and might simply be the result of a few
whiskeys.
But something had driven Boland to go further.
Little men like Lairdman always wanted children.
'That's a total lie,' she'd have said already
on the telephone, and Lairdman would have
pretended to believe her.
But pretending wasn't going to be enough for
either of them.
Boland turned the radio off.
He stopped the car outside Donovan's pub and
sat there for a moment, before going in.
At the bar, he greeted men he knew, and stood
drinking with them, listening to talk of horses
and politicians.
They left after a few more drinks, but Boland
stayed there for a long time, wondering why
he hadn't been able to let Lairdman take her
from him.
- THE END -