CHAPTER ONE
Delivery
In her house outside the town, Mrs Kennedy
writes her diary, paints the views from her
windows, and finds no comfort in the world.
Every week Charlie Blue delivers a box of
groceries to her door, but she never appears.
It is now one year since the accident...
On Thursdays, after the last delivery of the
long day, which was to the mad Kennedy woman,
Charlie Blue was allowed to keep the van for
the night.
He could drive home to his mother, proud behind
the wheel of the yellow van, waving to any
of the boys from his schooldays he might happen
to see in their long gardens, playing with
their children or cutting their midsummer
grass.
The arrangement suited his mother.
She would have the dinner ready for him and
then, after watching their favourite TV programme
Coronation Street together, he would drive
her into town to Horan's Hotel for her weekly
game of cards.
Tommy Horan also owned the grocery store and
she thought he was a great man, a generous
man to let her son have the van so that she
could get to her game of cards.
Charlie said nothing, but knew Tommy Horan
to be a bit of a bollocks, selling his tired
vegetables and soft tomatoes and eggs that
were no longer fresh.
He said nothing because his mother could become
as nasty as her twelve-year-old dog, which
she allowed to sit on her knees while she
fed it with the better bits of meat from her
dinner plate.
There was a light shower of rain as Charlie
was driving to Mrs Kennedy's.
The sun appeared strongly again from behind
the clouds, the road shone blackly, and the
smells of fresh-cut grass and warm earth rose
from the fields and came in through the open
window of the van.
With one hand, Charlie took out a cigarette
from a packet and lit it with his Horan's
Hotel cigarette lighter.
He felt lucky.
Lucky to have his driver's licence, lucky
to have his mother still alive, lucky to be
working for Tommy Horan, even if he was an
old bollocks.
August 20
A month already.
A day just as lovely as that day, the clouds
low over the hills.
Light seed balls blowing across the land like
a first snow.
And I hate this beauty because Bobby cannot
see it.
I paint it but I hate it.
With their sharp wings, the birds cut open
the sky and I am delighted to see it bleed.
From my window, I can see the gate and the
red wallflowers, staining the stones with
their blood.
At night, the screams of hunted animals comfort
me.
I am not the only one in pain.
In the morning, I cannot bear to dress, and
prefer to wear only shadows.
I go to each of my fifteen windows and decide
which view to paint today.
I might eat, if my body lets me, and then
I move to my chosen window and start to paint.
Charlie drove carefully around the last bend
before the Kennedy house.
It was a year to the day, he realized, since
poor old Foley lost control of his tractor
on this very bend and killed Mrs Kennedy's
young son.
Bobby was his name, only four or five years
of age.
He and his mother were planting flowers at
the foot of the big stone pillars either side
of the gate, when around the corner came Foley,
shouting about the brakes.
The front of the tractor was already too close
to the pillar on the left, throwing up grass
and earth into the sky.
Mikey Tuohy, who saw the whole thing from
his field above the road, told the police
in detail what happened.
His story earned him free beer in the pub
for a long time afterwards.
He said the screams of the mother nearly stopped
his heart.
She picked up the boy's body before Tuohy
could get there, and she ran all the way up
the long driveway to the big house, screaming
the whole time as the boy's head dropped lifelessly
against her arm and shoulder.
Poor old Foley sat on the grass and put his
head in his hands and didn't even recognize
Tuohy when he reached him.
Tuohy said Foley shouldn't have been allowed
on the road, not even on a bike, because the
old boy was half-blind.
September 3
Horan's got somebody new to deliver the groceries.
I recognized him: Charles Cullen.
He knocked and stood at the door and stared
out for a long time, out beyond the fields.
At what, I don't know.
He stretched his arms out wide like Christ
on the cross, to take the whole world to his
heart, perhaps.
Then he yawned and knocked again.
He lifted his T-shirt and scratched his stomach.
With his toe he pushed the box nearer the
wall, and left slowly, looking back occasionally
at the door.
While I was emptying the box afterwards I
discovered a box of chocolates I hadn't asked
for.
I must remember not to pay for that.
Now, at the end of summer, the land is bled
dry and colours are slowly returning to brown.
The cooler air moves against my skin like
long grass.
When the night enters the house, I look for
Bobby.
I want to run a bath and pour warm water over
his small, smooth back.
I want to turn back his soft sheet and lift
him into bed and bring the edge of the sheet
to his chin.
I want to kiss his eyelids as he sleeps.
Instead, the darkness tears at my own.
Once, last autumn, as darkness was falling,
Charlie saw an owl standing on the right-pillar
of Mrs Kennedy's gate.
It didn't move as Charlie edged the van past
the ruined left pillar and wall, and then
past the gate still on its side since the
accident.
At first, he thought it was a shadow.
He had stopped by the pillar and quietly rolled
down the window, when the top of the fat,
dark shape turned towards him.
From the centre of two wide circles two eyes
stared evenly at him, daring him to move,
and then with two or three movements of its
surprisingly wide wings it slowly, coldly,
flew off low over the field towards the trees.
Charlie remembered feeling uncomfortable,
judged in some way.
October 9
Charles still brings the groceries.
For the same reason, I both hate and love
him being at my door each week.
He reminds me of a better life.
I so clearly remember Charles in my class,
tall and clumsy at his desk.
I had to let him stand in the end.
He was freer that way.
And the day I decided, he had a gift, it comes
back so clearly.
(I hate the way I can remember every detail
of my life before Bobby and Bobby's death!)
He brought his finished painting up to my
desk and at first, I was disappointed.
'A Beach in Summer' it was called, but everything
in Charles's painting was a different shade
of blue, not just the sea: blue sand, blue
hills, blue boat, and what I thought was a
blue sun.
I asked Charles why he hadn't used other colours,
and he said in that frightened way he had,
'Well, Miss, it's a beach at night-time, you
see.'
Charlie Blue they called him after that.
Maybe he still paints.
I hope so.
When the police arrived, Mrs Kennedy wouldn't
let them into the house, Tuohy said.
Nor the priest either.
In the end, the police had to break a window
and get in that way.
They found her upstairs washing the child
in the bath.
The bloodstained water went everywhere, over
the walls and the mirror, wetting the priest
and the doctor as they forced the dead boy
out of her arms.
Dr Murphy phoned his wife, who came over and
stayed in the house.
Mrs Kennedy didn't come out of the bathroom
until the next morning.
She came downstairs still covered in blood
and told Mrs Murphy to kindly leave her house.
Hasn't been seen outside her house and garden
since the child was buried.
From the high field Tuohy says he sometimes
sees her sitting all day at one of her windows.
Or walking naked to the woodpile or throwing
bits of food out for her cats.
As Charlie drove the van up the driveway,
he looked around for her, as he always did.
He threw the end of his cigarette out of the
window, thinking to himself that he had only
two cigarettes left and that the old bollocks
wouldn't be paying him until tomorrow evening.
He'd better save them.
He looked up at the high field behind Mrs
Kennedy's and guessed that Tuohy was probably
spending a lot more time up there than he
needed to.
December 25
I found a Christmas cake I hadn't ordered
in the box of groceries yesterday.
Sometimes a man comes to the gate and stands
there, staring up at the house.
Who is he?
I wonder.
He was there last week and again today.
I feel Bobby's presence strongly today.
I fetched the Christmas tree from the cellar
and put it in the front room, with coloured
lights and pretty glass balls on it.
I write in its red and blue and green light.
I have wrapped his favourite toys and placed
them under the tree.
I close my eyes and he is there, lying on
the carpet by the tree, opening his presents,
turning his blond head around to smile up
at me, not minding a bit that they're the
same presents as last year.
I drink my wine and eat a piece of Christmas
cake.
Too rich for you, Bobby, too rich.
Charlie couldn't imagine his former art teacher
naked.
Every other woman in town had spent time naked
in his dreams, even Mrs Simpson in the post
office.
Mrs Kennedy was older than her but not by
a million years, she could only be forty or
so, and she had had a good shape back then
during his time at school, even if it was
hidden by long dresses and colourful baggy
jackets.
He had liked her.
She hadn't laughed at him for being stupid.
She had put up a painting he had done of a
beach at nighttime, right up beside the board
where everybody could see it.
That was good.
It was worth being called Charlie Blue for
that.
February 18
This week Charlie hid a couple of oranges
in the box.
I love him for these small presents, the only
kisses I receive.
Today the stranger walked up the driveway
to the door.
I saw him clearly through the glass, tall,
blond-haired, blue-eyed.
Serious.
He just stood there for a long time, unmoving.
One of the cats scratched at the kitchen window
and I looked away for a moment.
When I looked back, he was gone.
Snow fell again today but a hard sun drove
it into the hungry grass.
Charlie felt sorry for the thin grey mother
cat.
She came up to him as he pulled back the side
door of the van.
He reached down to scratch her head and she
replied by rubbing her whole body against
the leg of his jeans.
It's not much of a life for you, Charlie said,
not like you used to have, anyway.
He was halfway to the front door when he saw
last week's box exactly where he had left
it.
A busy line of black ants led from the box
to a hole in the front wall of the house.
Confused, he walked up and down for a while,
looking at the front door and windows.
He put the box he was carrying back into the
van, lifted his T-shirt and scratched his
stomach.
Near the corner of the house, he saw a torn
egg-box and a pile of clean chicken bones.
April 28
I feel so heavy.
As the world outside grows lighter and fills
with hope, I become heavier.
My paintings are still in winter, almost colourless.
I paint from one window now, from Bobby's
room, which gives the best view of the gate.
My handsome stranger is making good progress.
He began by laying out the stones in rows
and writing numbers on them.
Sometimes he stood up and looked back up at
me, serious as always, his blond hair not
quite visible from where I sit.
The wall is finished.
All that remains are the pillar and the gate.
Charlie smoked a cigarette, then knocked on
the door for the first time since he began
deliveries to Mrs Kennedy nearly a year before.
Just leave the box by the door and she'll
bring the groceries in herself, Horan had
said.
But Charlie couldn't just drop the new box
down beside the old one and let the ants run
all over it.
When he knocked, the door opened.
It hadn't been properly shut.
'Mrs Kennedy?' he called into the shadowy
hall.
May 21
Charlie still leaves his small offerings.
Yesterday it was a packet of sweets.
I cannot eat them but I feel grateful and
that feeds me.
I heard the owl call again last night.
Closer this time.
In my head I could see his long brown body
diving from the sky, the terrified movements
of the small animal he caught, the slow beat
of his wings as he rose into the nighttime
trees.
The pillar is almost finished.
The gate lies on its side on the grass, ready
to be put back in place.
Charlie felt cold.
These thick-walled country houses were impossible
to heat, from a single wood fire, anyway.
His eyes got used to the darkness.
'Mrs Kennedy?' he called again.
He went into the front room.
There was a painting she had been working
on, and others standing against a wall, which
was papered in a flower pattern.
An untidy pile of silver knives and forks
on the carpet.
He closed the door and moved towards the back
of the house, where the kitchen was, he supposed.
This door was open.
He switched on the light.
There was a fridge in the corner, still working.
Three bananas blackened in a glass bowl.
He could see that rats had been here; they
had eaten into the bread and the butter and
there were even tooth marks in a piece of
pink soap in a dish.
Charlie went back out into the hall and stood
at the bottom of the stairs.
He felt colder than ever.
'Mrs Kennedy?' he called and started up the
stairs.
June 20
The days are like children, unwilling to come
in from their play, and tonight the sky is
a gentle purple, as smooth and as tight as
the skin of an aubergine.
I have washed all my brushes for the last
time.
Each one left its own history of colour on
my hands.
I emptied the wooden knife-and-fork box and
put them into it, along with all my paints.
My present to you, Charlie Blue.
Tomorrow I will walk through the gate.
The smell of paint-cleaner hangs in the air.
While Charlie waited for O'Reilly the policeman
and Dr Murphy to finish inside, he smoked
his last cigarette, leaning against the side
of the van, looking out over the trees to
the distant, darkening hills.
A yellow light came from the open doorway
and upstairs window of the house.
He had just finished his cigarette when O'Reilly
came out and handed him a small wooden box,
told him to go on home, that the ambulance
could take over an hour to get there from
Ballinasloe and that there was no point in
waiting.
O'Reilly would see him tomorrow.
Ambulances never hurry for the already dead.
Charlie drove back into town and parked outside
Horan's Hotel.
The bollocks could keep his van.
Through the hotel window, he could see his
mother at her card game, the dog at her feet.
She must have asked a neighbour to bring her
into town.
The dog sensed his presence, looked out but
did not move.
He reached into the van and took out Mrs Kennedy's
box of brushes and paints from the passenger
seat.
Shutting the door with his shoulder, he put
her present under his arm and walked on, out
past the last lights of the town and into
the blue shadows of the moonlit countryside,
feeling nervous but welcomed, like a stranger
at home in what was once a foreign land.
- THE END -