CHAPTER ONE
The Fisherman and the Giant
Once there was a poor fisherman. He never caught
many fish and so he had no money. On some days he
did not catch any fish. He couldn't buy food for
his wife and three children. They only ate fish!
Usually he caught very small fish,
but one day he caught a dead horse.
'Today is a bad day,' he thought.
Angrily, he began to fish again. This
time he caught a bag of old cups.
Sadly, he threw them back in the water.
'What can I do?' he said. 'I am a poor man. I want
to sell fish. I want to buy food for my children.'
He tried again. This time he caught an old jar.
It looked green, but then he looked
again. It was dirty. So he washed it
and it was gold. There were some words on
the top of the jar, but he couldn't read.
The fisherman jumped up happily.
'I can sell this now,' he said.
'Today is a good day.'
He looked at the jar carefully. 'Perhaps
there is something inside,' he thought.
'I'll open it.' So he opened the jar
and looked inside. Suddenly white smoke
came out of the jar and a great giant appeared.
The fisherman was very afraid. The giant spoke.
'Now, fisherman. I am going to kill you.'
'Why?' cried the fisherman. 'What did I do?'
'You opened the jar. For that I am going
to kill you. How do you want to die?
I can kill you with my hands, or
I can throw you into the sea.'
'But why do you have to kill me?'
'I will tell you,' said the giant. 'One day,
the King of the Giants was very angry with me.
I took his youngest and loveliest daughter
for a walk by the sea and he didn't like it.
So he put me in this jar. I could not get out
because he wrote his name on the top of the jar.
I could hear him from inside the jar.
"Because you love the sea, you dog," he cried,
"you can live in it!" And
he threw me in the water.
'I was in the jar for days and weeks. "One day
somebody will open this bottle," I thought.
"And I will make them into a great king or queen."
But after a hundred years, nobody
opened the bottle. So I thought,
"I will make them into a king or queen but not a
great king or queen." After 200 years, I thought,
"Where is this person? Now I will make them
rich, but I will not make them a king or queen."
After 300 years, I was very angry." When
somebody opens the jar, I will kill them,"
I thought. You are that person,
Fisherman. How do you want to die?'
'I have one question,' said the
fisherman. 'Will you answer it?'
'I will,' said the giant, 'but ask quickly.'
'Were you in that jar?'
'Yes, I was,' answered the giant. 'You saw me.'
'But you are so big. Your
hand is as big as the jar.
Think before you speak. Is
there nothing inside your head?'
The giant was not very clever. 'I
will show you,' he said angrily.
Suddenly he disappeared into white smoke
again, and the smoke went inside the jar.
'You see!' he called from inside. The
fisherman quickly put the top back on the jar.
'Hah! Now, Giant,' he said. 'I will
throw the jar back into the sea.
Perhaps somebody will find
you in another 300 years.'
'Please open the jar,' called the
Giant. 'I will make you a rich man.'
'No. You will kill me,' answered the fisherman.
'No, I won't,' said the giant. 'I
won't. I'll make you very, very rich.'
The fisherman thought for a minute. 'All right,
then,' he said, and opened the jar. White smoke
came out of the jar and the giant appeared
again. He quickly threw the jar into the sea.
'Thank you,' he said to the fisherman.
'I will not forget this. Come with me.'
The fisherman followed the giant round the
city walls and over a mountain. There they
came to a great blue and gold sea.
In the water there were many fish.
'Now, catch something. I will watch
you,' said the giant. In no time,
the fisherman caught three fish - three
beautiful red, white and gold fish.
'Take these fish to your king,' said the giant.
'He will give you a lot of money for them.'
The giant disappeared, and blue and
gold smoke went into the ground.
When the king saw the fish,
he said to the fisherman,
'Those are beautiful fish! I
will give you gold for them.'
Then he said to his servant, 'Take these
fish to the cook. We will eat them today.'
The fisherman took his gold home to his
family. They ate a wonderful dinner of bread,
meat, fruit, vegetables and no fish. For the
first time in their lives, they were not hungry.
The king's cook put the fish over the fire.
They started to cook. Suddenly, the smoke from
the fire went blue and gold and a strange woman
appeared in the kitchen. She spoke to the fish.
'Fish, fish! Are you doing your work?' The
fish did not answer. Then their heads went up,
and they said, 'We are, and we are happy.' The
strange woman pushed the fish into the fire.
The smoke from the fire went blue and
gold and the woman disappeared into it.
The king and his servant came into the kitchen.
'I am waiting for the fish. Where are they?'
he said to the cook. He saw that the fish were in
the fire and he could not eat them. The cook told
him about the strange woman. The king wanted
to see the woman so he sent for the fisherman.
'Bring me three more fish!' he said.
When the fisherman came back with three more fish,
the king gave him more gold. The
cook put the fish over the fire.
This time the smoke from the fire went red
and gold and a big man with red hair appeared.
'Fish, fish! Are you doing your work?'
The fish answered, 'We are, we are! And we
are happy!' And the same thing happened.
The man pushed the fish into the fire and
disappeared into the red and gold smoke.
The king did not speak for a minute. This
was magic! Then he turned to the fisherman.
'Where do you get these fish?' he asked.
'I get them from a sea of blue
and gold water over the mountain.'
'Do you know this sea?'
the king asked his servant.
'No. I often go across the mountain,
but there is no blue and gold sea.'
'Will you take us there?'
the king asked the fisherman.
The king and his men followed
the fisherman over the mountain
to the sea of blue and gold and there they saw the
wonderful fish. The fish were jewels in the water.
'Wait here,' said the king. He took
two men and went round the sea.
There they came to a great house of red stone. All
round the house were gardens of wonderful flowers.
There was no answer at the door. But it
was open so the king went in. He saw many
beautiful rooms but no people. He came
into a very large room with high windows.
Somebody spoke: 'When will I
die? I don't want to live.'
The king saw a young man
at the other end of the room. He was
on the floor with a coat over his feet.
'I know you are a king,' said the
young man, 'but I cannot stand up.'
The king took away the coat and saw
that his feet were fine white stone.
'What is this?' cried the king. 'Why do you
have stone feet? Why do the fish talk? Why
does a man with red hair appear from nowhere
in my kitchen? What is happening? Tell me.'
'I will tell you,' said the young
man. 'Please sit down and listen.
There was once a great city in this
place. My father was king of that city,
and I was a prince. Then my father died and
I was the king. I married a beautiful woman.
She was my queen but she did not love me. She
loved a servant. When I learnt about him, I wanted
to kill that servant. We had a fight. I hurt him
but I didn't kill him. He could not use his legs.
'My wife was very angry. She can do magic
and she changed my feet to white stone.
Then I could not use my legs. That was not the
end of it. Three mountains and a blue and gold sea
appeared in place of the city. She changed
the men and women of the city into fish.
'There is a little house of white
stone in the garden of this house.
The servant lives there. He cannot
walk. My wife visits him every day.'
The king went into the garden and thought for some
time. Then he went to the house of white stone.
He found the servant inside and killed him. He
put the servant under the bed and then climbed
onto it. He pulled the servant's jacket over
his face. Sometime later, the queen came in.
'Are you happy, my dearest servant?' she asked.
'No,' said the king. 'I cannot sleep.
Somebody is crying. The young king
is crying because of his stone feet.'
The queen went to the young king and threw some
magic water over his feet. He stood up and walked.
Then she came back to the house of white
stone. 'And I cannot sleep,' the king said,
'because the men and women of the city cry
at night. They do not want to be fish.'
So the queen went to the blue and gold sea. She
said some magic words. A great city appeared all
round her. Men and women ran happily through
the streets and in and out of the houses.
Then the queen came back to
the house of white stone.
'Are you happy now, my dear servant?' she asked.
'Yes, my love,' he said. 'Come near
me.' She came near him. 'Come nearer.
I want to put my arms round you.' She came
nearer his bed. He put his arms round her.
In one hand he had a knife, and he killed her.
He went back to the young king. 'Your queen
is dead. The city and its people are living.'
The older king and the young
king were friends after that.
One city helped the other city.
But nobody ate fish again.
The fisherman and his family were happy. The
two kings sent them gold and beautiful things.
They were never hungry again.
- THE END -