CHAPTER ONE
Arlo's War
The snake's world was a silent one.
Its world was a box with a glass front.
It was staring at its next meal.
Its meal, a rat, was staring back.
The rat sat frozen with fear in the corner
of the large box.
It heard a soft shaking sound and answered
with a few high sounds of terror.
The snake was hungry and moved quickly.
It was a big North American diamond-backed
rattlesnake, almost two meters long with enough
poison in its bite to kill several men.
The rat was soon dead and the snake stretched
its jaws to begin the business of swallowing
its meal.
Arlo Penton sat and watched through the glass
as Susie ate her rat.
The sight made him feel a little uncomfortable
- it always did - but that, he thought, was
the way of Nature.
And he did admire snakes.
He admired their smooth beauty and their beautiful
patterned skins.
But most of all he admired their deafness.
Arlo had discovered some years before that
snakes were completely deaf.
They depended mostly on their highly developed
sense of smell, and their tongues could actually
taste smells from the air.
As well as this, their expressionless eyes
could see the heat given off by the bodies
of other animals.
Arlo watched with feelings of deep respect
as the rat slowly disappeared down Susie's
throat.
The snake lived in a world without annoying
continuous noise.
A silent world.
To Arlo, snakes stood for beauty and perfection.
He loved to watch them and admire them.
If only his own world could be as silent as
theirs!
That was why he had caught Susie.
More correctly, he had Chico - a local gardener
- catch her for him.
Susie had been caught in the rocky dry land
that bordered Tucson, Arizona, where Arlo
lived.
Chico was most casual in the way he touched
dangerous snakes.
Sometimes he would even eat them.
'They're good to eat and they're free,' he
would say.
This disgusted Arlo, not because he didn't
like the idea of snakes being used as food,
but because he thought it failed to give the
snake enough respect.
Nevertheless, he was glad Chico had found
Susie.
She was a beauty.
Arlo liked living at the edge of town.
He had to drive to work and it took him over
an hour each way.
It was noisy and hot, but at least he had
quiet when he got home.
Quiet was very important to Arlo.
As a young man he had been a soldier and had
fought in a war.
His mind had been damaged by the noise of
loud and terrible explosions and he had to
be sent to a hospital at home to recover.
He had met his wife, Maria, there.
She was one of the nurses who had looked after
him.
He still hated noise.
'Everybody talks about pollution,' Arlo would
say to anybody who would listen.
'The way we poison our environment with this
and that, yet the one thing which really poisons
the quality of our lives is noise.
Everywhere you go you hear people making noise,
noise, noise.
Where can you hear the birds sing these days?
Not in the city, my friend.
All you hear is traffic, loud radios and people
with noisy machinery.
Twenty-four hours a day it's noise, noise,
noise.
It's enough to drive you crazy.'
Too much noise took Arlo back, in his mind,
to the war with its loud explosions that had
brought death and suffering.
Maria had saved him from madness.
Maria and his work and his pills.
To look at, Arlo was like many other fifty-nine-year-old
men: he was of average height and his once-dark
hair was now grey.
He was neither fat nor thin and dressed casually
- usually in black trousers, a blue shirt
and his favourite cowboy hat.
His thin face had taken on a more troubled
look since Maria had died of cancer one year
before.
She had helped him through the bad times and
made sure he took the pills he needed to keep
him calm.
But now Maria was gone.
They had no children.
Most of Arlo's time was now given to his work.
Even when he was at home he would be thinking
about work, putting new ideas down onto his
computer.
His work was his life.
Arlo had a job in a company called Teckno-Toys,
which made electronic toys for children.
He was the company's chief designer of radio-controlled
toys, such as cars and aeroplanes.
These toys were so clever and amazing that
many fathers bought them at Christmas for
their children, only to play with them themselves.
The cries of Aw, Dad, can I have a go now?'
were often heard in many homes where Dad had
bought one of Arlo's marvelous toys.
His toys were indeed wonderful.
The cars were tough but fast, while the aeroplanes
were like magical birds that would fly up
or down and turn in the air whenever you told
them to.
They could be guided from great distances
with the powerful electronic controls that
Arlo designed.
What Arlo liked best about his work was the
electrical side.
He would leave the design of the toy's body
to others, but design the electronic controls
himself.
By the time the toy was finished it would
be the best that money could buy.
Arlo had a garage full of small model planes,
boats and cars he had made.
He often used them to help test out new designs
at home - that was why he had been allowed
to keep them.
The Teckno-Toys factory was quite separate
from the place where Arlo worked.
He needed quiet so that he could concentrate
and did not want loud upsetting noises to
remind him of the war.
He could never do this next to a noisy factory.
He did his work in an old large house in the
centre of the city called The Havens, which
was owned by the company.
The house was unusual in having its own spacious
grounds that protected it from the loud noises
of the city.
Arlo worked there with a few other favoured
employees.
They would send their designs to the factory,
which would build the models then return them
to Arlo and his colleagues to be checked.
This arrangement suited Arlo: he had a quiet
place to work in, while Teckno-Toys got top-quality
new toys that were sure to sell well.
Keeping Arlo happy at The Havens had been
worth it to them.
So far.
Arlo had made enough money from his work to
buy a spacious house outside the city and
away from the noisy traffic.
He built a large wooden tower in the garden
so that he could control his models from great
distances.
He loved that.
But he missed Maria and his sleep was sometimes
troubled, especially when he forgot to take
his pills.
But, at least he had his work to take his
mind off the war.
Work was all he had left.
Bernie Dimaggio, Vice President of Teckno-Toys,
held a towel as he watched his boss on her
exercise cycle.
She often spoke to him while doing her early
morning exercises in the private gym she had
next to her office.
She got off the machine and he handed her
the towel.
'He's not going to like it, Miss De Cruz.
You know how he feels about the place!'
Bernie's suntan could not hide the way his
face turned red as he spoke
'You seem to forget who you are talking to,
Mr Dimaggio, I am now the head of Teckno-Toys.
My father was old-fashioned in his ways.
He made this company but if we are to become
the market leader we must change with the
times.'
'But Miss De Cruz...' began Bernie.
'Enough, Mr Dimaggio.
You may be Vice President and your concern
for one of our... er... senior employees is
understandable.
But we have a business to run.
We have to progress; we have money to consider.
We can't afford not to sell a valuable property
like The Havens just because an old man close
to retirement likes a bit of quiet, not when
we need the money for building up the factory.
It's just not good business sense, Mr Dimaggio,
and we both know it.'
'But Arlo has been working at The Havens for
twenty years!
He couldn't work anywhere else now.
You knew him when you were just a kid, Miss
De Cruz...'
'I'm not a 'kid' any more, Mr Dimaggio, in
case you haven't noticed.
And I have a business to run.
The property will be sold.
If Mr Penton wants to continue to work for
Teckno-Toys, he will have to work at the factory,
like the rest of us.
Or he can go.
I trust you will let him know of this development
at the appropriate time.'
'You mean after he's completed the designs
for the new season's models?'
'Exactly.
No sense in upsetting him just now.
Not while he's doing useful work.
It's not good business, Mr Dimaggio, you ought
to know that,' said Eva De Cruz firmly.
Bernie Dimaggio had been with the company
since Eva De Cruz had been a child.
He had seen the business grow as Eva grew.
It was a successful business, though not yet
the biggest of its kind.
He looked at his new boss, the twenty-five-year-old
daughter of Diego De Cruz, his former boss
and friend.
Eva had studied at the best business school
and she wanted to show the world that she
was going to be better than her father had
ever been.
Better and richer.
After Diego's wife, Eva's mother, had died
fifteen years before, Diego De Cruz had put
all of his energies into the business.
The education of his daughter and only child
was left to private boarding schools, where
she had lived for most of the time.
She had been educated from a distance, like
one of Diego's toys.
And Eva was the result.
Everything about her was businesslike, from
her usual dark blue suit to her electronic
organizer.
Bernie sometimes wondered if her brain had
become electronic, too.
And what would happen to Arlo once he was
told about the sale of The Havens?
Both he and Diego had been in the army with
Arlo during the war and had become friends.
After the war they had given Arlo work he
could do in peace.
They wanted to help him put his broken mind
back together.
Diego had promised Arlo that there would always
be a peaceful place for him to work at Teckno-Toys.
What would this news do to him?
'Couldn't you find somewhere else quiet for
him, Miss De Cruz,' Bernie asked, 'where he
can carry on his work?
Diego...
I mean, your father...
promised Arlo somewhere quiet a long time
ago!'
'That was then, this is now.
We can't afford to treat him any differently
from the rest of us, Mr Dimaggio,' she said
after drying her face with the towel and throwing
it back to him.
'Now excuse me, but I have another appointment
in twenty minutes.'
Eva left him with the damp towel.
Bernie was close to retirement age himself.
He felt sorry for Arlo.
Diego would have done something to help, but
not Eva.
He might lose his own job if he didn't do
as she told him.
Bernie felt older and weaker as he walked
out of the gym.
While Eva and Bernie were talking, Arlo was
getting into his car to go to work.
He had forgotten to take his pill again.
His face was already sweating.
It was a bright sunny morning and the roads
would be hot.
He was glad he had completed the new designs
and was looking forward to handing them in
personally, as usual, to Bernie Dimaggio.
They lay on the seat next to him as he drove
to the city center.
The road was already busy with the morning
rush of traffic.
Arlo had to stop at a set of traffic lights.
The car next to him was a sports car with
an open top.
The man at the wheel was young and wore dark
glasses.
He was listening to loud rock music and was
nodding his head to the rhythm as he listened.
Arlo could not understand how anybody could
listen to such a loud noise without damaging
their ears.
He could feel the noise hitting his own head
in solid waves.
It was painful.
He shouted to the man to turn the sound down.
The man saw him and laughed, then turned the
sound up even more.
Fortunately, the lights changed at that moment
and they both drove away.
Arlo let the sports car speed ahead, taking
its noise with it.
Everything seemed to be noisy on that journey.
Other cars had noisy radios.
Arlo swore at the Tucson rock music radio
station as he passed it by.
Then he heard some loud machines at some new
building works.
Car horns sounded at every pause in the stream
of traffic, and everywhere people seemed to
be shouting, shouting, shouting.
At last, the turning for The Havens came into
view.
He could hardly wait to enter the peaceful
building!
As he drove through the private grounds all
the awful noises disappeared into the distance.
When Arlo stopped the car his body was shaking
and covered in sweat.
Echoes of loud noises were still in his head,
some of them terrible memories of the war.
He took a few deep breaths to calm himself,
then picked up his designs and walked into
the big house.
It was nine o'clock at The Havens.
Bernie Dimaggio was early.
He was waiting in the office as Arlo walked
in.
He noticed that Arlo was holding the envelope
containing the new designs.
He also noticed how upset Arlo looked.
'Hi Arlo!
Hey, are you OK?
You don't look so good, if you don't mind
me saying so.
Are you still sleeping OK?
Hey, if you need anything just say the word.'
Arlo smiled.
Bernie was always concerned about him when
it was time to hand in his designs.
Did he think he would finally go crazy before
completing them?
Probably.
Bernie had always been a worrier.
Arlo looked into the familiar suntanned face
and answered, 'I'm fine, Bernie.
At least, I would be if I walked around with
my ears closed.
I swear this town is getting noisier every
day.'
'Oh no,' thought Bernie.
'I hope he's not going to give me another
long talk about noise pollution!'
Bernie decided to change the subject quickly.
'You have the designs I see, Arlo.
All ready for production?'
Arlo handed over the envelope, giving it a
firm tap with his hand on the way.
'You bet, Bernie.
This one is going to be a winner, I'm telling
you.
The kids are going to love it!
It's easy to control, yet it's as quiet as
a baby asleep in its mother's arms!'
'Everything's checked?' asked Bernie.
'Checked and double-checked,' Arlo answered.
'You ought to know me by now.'
Bernie did know.
If Arlo said something was ready, it was ready.
He put the designs in his briefcase and began
to walk towards the door as he thanked Arlo.
Then he stopped and turned to him, pulling
another smaller envelope from his jacket pocket.
'Oh, I almost forgot... said Bernie, though
he had done no such thing.
'Here's some mail from the factory for you.'
'What is it?'
Arlo asked as he took the envelope.
Bernie looked at his watch.
He wasn't brave enough to face Arlo's reaction
to the sale of The Havens.
'Hey, I've got to go to a meeting right now.
See you later, OK?'
'OK,' said Arlo as Bernie smiled nervously
and left.
'He sure was in a rush,' he thought.
'Maybe the noise has been getting to that
guy, too.
I wouldn't be surprised.
Nothing surprises me anymore.'
Arlo sat down with a sigh and opened the envelope.
Eva De Cruz tested her coffee.
It was black with no sugar, just as she liked
it.
As she sat at her office desk she thought
that things, on the whole, could be a lot
worse.
It had been a month since the old man had
left them.
She had expected him to make a lot more fuss
about the whole business.
She knew he would never work in the factory
grounds, not with his unreasonable attitude
towards perfectly normal noise levels.
All the other designers had agreed to the
new arrangements.
She couldn't change the world just because
one employee had had some unfortunate experiences
in the war.
That wasn't her problem.
Besides, The Havens had been knocked down
by the new owners.
They had already started to build a new radio
station on the grounds.
It was going to be the biggest rock music
radio station in Arizona.
Teckno-Toys had made a lot of money out of
the sale.
And if the old man didn't like it... well,
that was just too bad.
Eva De Cruz had known Arlo for most of her
life.
She had even played with some of the toys
he had designed while they were in the testing
stage.
She had loved the toys but the man who designed
them was, to her, just a strange old man who
hated noises.
She had never been close to him, though she
had liked his wife.
Maria was nice.
It was true that the old man had been a first
class designer but nobody is so good that
he can't be replaced - especially if they're
half crazy and more trouble than they're worth.
Besides, the company had already made a lot
of money from his designs.
There were plenty of excellent young designers
already applying for his job - they weren't
troubled by noise at all.
They were cheaper, too.
'No, there will be no problem replacing Arlo
Penton,' Eva thought to herself as she poured
out a second cup of coffee.
'No problem at all.'
Arlo had given up his job as soon as he .had
read the letter.
There was no way he was going to work in that
noisy factory!
He had enough money saved.
He could take care of himself all right.
He didn't need false friends who broke their
promises.
He could manage alone.
That's what he kept telling himself.
But it was a month since he had left his job
and die noises in Arlo's head were getting
worse.
He often forgot to take his pills now.
Sometimes he would wake up in the early hours
of the morning covered in sweat and screaming
at the ceiling.
Only now there was no Maria to help him get
over the nightmare.
His memories of the war had returned and he
was alone in the middle of them.
To Arlo, it seemed that the guns were firing
again.
The guns in his head and the sounds outside
were joining together.
The difference between memories and reality
was breaking down in his mind.
When he went out in the car for his groceries
he would hear the guns.
Every loud radio, every noisy machine seemed
like an exploding bomb to his ears.
He wondered why something wasn't done about
it but nothing ever was.
And all the time the noise was there.
Why didn't people notice what was going on?
Were they all deaf?
He could hear the enemy.
His enemy was noise.
He had to do something or he would go crazy.
Nobody else seemed to be doing a thing about
it.
It was all up to him.
He would have to stop the noise.
But how?
'That ought to be enough,' said Arlo.
It was one week later and he had decided what
he would do.
He had been making the tower he had next to
his house higher and stronger so that he could
increase the range of the radio signals to
his models.
He placed his electronic equipment on top
of the tower and the higher he built it the
better his electronic equipment worked.
He now had more control over his wonderful
models than ever before with a range that
allowed him to fly them high over the city.
Arlo had a wide variety of models to choose
from.
He had, over the years, collected over a hundred
models in his garage.
They were all in perfect working order.
Teckno- Toys had let him keep them.
He had tiny television cameras fitted to his
models.
This allowed him to see on his computer screen
indoors where his models were while they were
in use, even when it was cloudy or too hot
for him to go outside.
Arlo had learned a lot about how to make explosives
during the war.
He could attach a small but powerful explosive
onto a model and then, from the comfort of
his own home, direct it to a target.
The video cameras would show him exactly where
his target was; all he had to do was aim the
model (usually an aeroplane) towards the target
and BOOM!
- the target was destroyed.
Nobody suspected anything.
Arlo, after all, was just working on his models
like he always did.
No-one knew that he was making bombs as well.
Chico called by with more rats for Susie.
He saw Arlo working in his garage where Susie
lay sleeping in her glass-fronted box.
Chico liked Arlo, even if he didn't eat snakes.
He stopped to watch in admiration while Arlo
flew one of his wonderful models high into
the sky.
He had no idea that Arlo's campaign against
the enemy had begun.
Arlo's first bombing campaign was against
the old Tucson rock music radio station.
It was successful.
Just one small model aeroplane had delivered
enough home-made explosives to bring down
the radio station's tower.
It was easy.
They wouldn't be playing loud music from that
station for some while.
Tucson's local papers all published stories
about a strange explosion that had blown up
essential equipment at the local rock radio
station.
Nobody had been hurt in the explosion, they
said, but the station would be out of action
for a long time.
The police could see no motive for the crime
but did not reject the idea of some individual
playing around with explosives for fun.
This was worrying.
They were right to be worried.
Over the next week there were several more
explosions: large noisy machines on building
areas were destroyed and a fireworks factory
was seriously damaged.
But nobody had been hurt.
Not yet.
It was a few days after the explosion in the
fireworks factory and Sheriff Calhoun was
in the office of the Vice President of Teckno-Toys.
He badly wanted a cigarette.
He was trying to give up again and had not
brought any cigarettes with him.
Worse still, none of the other officers smoked
so he couldn't even get a cigarette from one
of them.
This was making him bad-tempered, but he had
a job to do.
He stuck another piece of chewing gum into
his mouth.
'Tell me again, Mr Dimaggio...'
The Sheriff paused as he softened the fresh
gum in his mouth.
'You told me when you rang me on the telephone
earlier that this guy - what was his name...?'
'Arlo Penton, Sheriff.'
'Yeah, Arlo Penton.
You said he had been one of the top designers
at Teckno-Toys?'
'The best we had.
That's him in that picture on the wall just
there.
He's the one holding the model Mustang fighter
plane.
That's our biggest selling model and he designed
it.'
Sheriff Calhoun looked at the picture in Bernie
Dimaggio's office.
Bernie liked to keep photographs of all of
Teckno-Toys' best toys with their designers.
Arlo featured in a lot of them.
In this one, Arlo was smiling and looked happy
and relaxed.
'And you got rid of the guy?' asked the Sheriff.
'No, Sheriff.
It was his choice.
He... er... left the company a few months
ago.'
The Sheriff recognised a note of guilt in
Bernie's voice.
Years of listening to countless interviews
had trained his ears to know when somebody
was trying to hide something.
That was what he was hearing now.
'With less than a year to go before he was
due to retire?
He sure must have had a reason.
Can you think of a reason, Mr Dimaggio?
After all, you say you've known him a long
time.
Not that I'm accusing anybody of anything,
you understand, but I have to ask these things.'
Bernie had felt bad about the way the promise
he and Diego had made to Arlo had been broken.
He felt bad about his own weakness before
Diego's daughter - his boss - who had not
respected that promise.
He knew that Arlo must have been disturbed
by the loss of The Havens but he hadn't been
brave enough to talk to Arlo about it after
he had given him the letter.
Could Arlo have used his expert skills to
make these explosions?
Bernie told the Sheriff everything about Arlo,
about Teckno-Toys and The Havens and how he
thought Arlo might be responsible for the
explosions.
Bernie felt glad to have finally told somebody
how he really felt about things.
'So, what will happen to Arlo now?'
Bernie asked.
'Now hold on, Mr Dimaggio.
You may have given us a motive for Mr Penton,
but we don't know that he did any of these
things.
There have been a number of explosions: at
the Tucson radio station, some heavy machines
blown up and the one a few nights ago at a
fireworks factory.
That caused serious damage.
But we can't be sure that any one person is
responsible for all of these crimes.
For all we know, there may be any number of
people out there making their own bombs.'
'But you don't really think so, do you Sheriff?'
Bernie asked.
Sheriff Calhoun took a few more thoughtful
chews of his gum and wished he had a cigarette.
He looked again at the photograph of Arlo.
Suddenly, he noticed a model aeroplane, like
a child's toy, fly past and before he could
reply, there was a loud BANG! from outside.
Bernie rushed to his window to look.
'Sheriff, it's the factory.
It's on fire!'
Arlo had been working hard.
He could not see the results of his work immediately
because the television cameras were destroyed
once his models hit their targets.
He had to listen to the radio for news of
his work - not the loud music stations, of
course.
His last action had been against the electrical
generator at the Teckno-Toys factory.
Without the generator they would not have
the power to work their loud machines, and
the hated factory noise would be silenced
at last.
Unfortunately, though the action had been
a success, three people had been badly burned.
He heard about them on the radio.
It upset him.
'But it's not my fault,' he told himself.
'This is war.
Every war hurts some innocent people.
It's the enemy's fault, not mine.
Once the enemy is defeated there will be peace.
I have to fight on for peace.
There's nobody else.
I have to.'
But Arlo had no peace.
His heart was saddened by the news of the
three injured people.
And the noises that disturbed him had not
been silenced.
The enemy was strong and there was much work
left to do.
He made his way to the garage again.
Arlo began working immediately.
He had to do the next one right.
He had no idea that the Sheriff and a large
number of police officers were, while he was
working, speeding towards his house in their
cars.
All he was concerned about was putting the
finishing touches to his model Mustang fighter
plane.
He had saved the Mustang for the new radio
tower they were building at the place where
The Havens used to be.
They would never finish it.
No way.
Not if he could help it.
It would not need much explosive, just enough
to bring the tower down.
That would be enough.
He got his little computer ready as he switched
on the video camera attached to the model
aeroplane.
It was time to fly.
Arlo placed the Mustang on the ground by his
garage then sat down by his controls.
He did not see the Sheriff's men, but they
saw him.
They had positioned themselves some distance
away from him.
They all had powerful guns.
They saw the Mustang as it started to take
off.
A shot was fired before the model had gone
far enough to leave the ground.
There was an explosion.
Arlo felt a force hit his ears and he was
knocked to the floor.
There was a pain in his arm.
He had closed his eyes.
Was he dead?
Had the enemy beaten him?
He opened his eyes and saw that his arm had
blood on it.
As he started to get himself up, Arlo did
not see the pieces of broken glass on the
floor behind him.
He did not notice the angry shaking sound
of the snake whose sleep had been disturbed.
He hardly felt Susie's bite before he sank
to the floor again.
His eyes felt heavy as the daylight turned
to darkness and death ran with the poison
in his blood.
But he was happy.
Arlo's world was, at last, a silent one.
- THE END -