CHAPTER ONE
The Stradivarius
Thirty years ago there were many places like
Minx Mills in the southern United States.
People said there was no way to find them
except by accident.
But it was no accident that brought Jesse
McCord to Minx Mills.
When Boone Elliot saw the car stop in front
of his house he did not move.
People always came to see him when their cars
needed to be fixed.
They knew that Boone Elliot could repair anything
with wheels on it.
A stranger got out of his car slowly.
"Are you Boone Elliot, the musician?"
Boone was very pleased to be called a musician
instead of a car mechanic.
He nodded his head, "Yes."
The stranger smiled and closed his car door.
He had blond hair, small blue eyes and a narrow
face with a long chin.
He wore a thin moustache across his upper
lip.
Boone thought he must be about fifty years
old.
Boone walked over to him.
The stranger shook Boone's hand.
"I'm Jesse McCord," he said.
"I have something I want to show you."
He opened his car door and pulled out a violin
case.
"Can we get out of the sun?" he asked.
Boone led the way to the porch.
Boone's wife Molly brought them ice tea in
tall glasses.
McCord drank his tea slowly.
Then he wiped his mouth with his fingers.
"Does the name Antonio Stradivarius mean anything
to you?" he asked.
"Are you saying that you have a fiddle made
by Stradivarius in that case?"
"I'm not saying what I have," McCord said.
Boone Elliot leaned forward in his chair.
"Mister, if you have a Stradivarius violin
I want to see it."
McCord opened the case and lifted up a violin
made of golden red wood.
The sunlight slid over the violin like a warm
wave.
"Here, take it," McCord said.
Boone tried to reach for the violin but his
hands would not move.
Boone had always thought he would find a Stradivarius
in a museum some day.
He never dreamed that he would see one in
his own home.
McCord turned the violin so that Boone could
read the writing on the back of it.
"See that?" he asked.
"Antonio Stradivarius.
Romona, Italia," he read.
As Boone leaned forward to read the words
himself McCord placed the violin in his hands.
"Go ahead," he said.
"Play something."
Boone put the violin under his chin and picked
up the bow.
He began to play "The Tennessee Waltz."
The violin sounded so good, he began to play
faster.
Nothing in his life had ever felt so wonderful.
Then Boone played "I am Thinking of My Blue
Eyes" for Molly.
He finished with the religious song "Amazing
Grace."
As he played the song, McCord and Molly sang
the words.
When Boone finished playing McCord shook his
head.
"Too bad I have to sell this fiddle," he said.
"But I have a sick child at home and I need
the money."
Boone put the violin back in its case.
"How much do you want for it?" he asked.
"Well," McCord said.
"I need 1500 dollars to pay the doctor and
the hospital."
Boone had expected the violin to cost much
more than that.
"Maybe, I will buy it myself," he said.
"Can you lower the price?"
McCord shook his head, "No.
No, I...
I need 1500 dollars for my child."
Boone thought for a minute.
"All right," he said.
"I will buy it.
But...
I can't give you the money until I go to the
bank tomorrow."
He handed the violin to McCord.
"No," McCord said.
"Keep it, friend.
It's yours."
They shook hands, and Molly invited McCord
to stay for dinner.
After dinner, McCord left and Molly began
washing the dishes.
She was very angry.
"How could you spend so much money without
talking to me about it?
Besides, you already have a violin."
Molly banged the pots she was washing as she
talked.
"I don't believe that story about a sick baby,"
she said.
"I don't either," Boone said.
"In fact, I don't even think McCord is married.
But I could not argue about that violin."
Boone put his arms around Molly and held her
close.
She turned and rested her head on his chest.
"I never should've married a musician," she
sighed.
"There's still some coffee left," she said.
"And I saved you a piece of pie."
The next morning McCord came to the house
early.
And the two men went into town to the bank.
Boone had no trouble borrowing the money to
buy the violin.
He promised Mr. Austin, the banker, that he
would work at Sam Boatwright's Garage to pay
off the bank loan.
After he got the money Boone gave it to McCord
who stuffed it in his pocket.
Boone walked across the street to Boatwright's
Garage.
It took Boone five years to pay the bank the
money he had borrowed to buy the Stradivarius.
Then, Boone had more time to play his violin.
He played at dances and at funerals; he played
in churches and schools.
Boone remembered those years as the best in
his life.
He called them his "golden time."
He could tell Molly felt good too.
She was very loving and he felt very close
to her.
Whenever Boone picked up his Stradivarius
he felt as if God's spirit had touched his
soul.
Then Molly became sick and the golden time
ended.
Boone took her to the hospital where the doctors
operated on her.
For a while Molly felt better.
But she had lost a lot of weight and was very
weak.
Boone went back to work at Boatwright's Garage
to pay Molly's doctors and the hospital.
But the money he got from working in the garage
was not enough.
So, he returned to Mr. Austin at the bank
and borrowed several thousand dollars.
Even that was not enough.
In the end, there was Just one thing left
for him to do.
The idea was so awful that he put off doing
it for as long as he could.
Finally, one day he took the Stradivarius
from its case for the last time.
He held it in his arms as if it were a baby,
but he was too sad to play it.
Then he put the violin in his truck and drove
to the city.
The first music store he went to was not interested
in the violin.
The second store offered him fifty dollars
for it.
The last store offered him seventy-five dollars.
Boone expected to get at least ten thousand
dollars for his violin.
After all, it was a Stradivarius!
It was clear they did not know how valuable
it was.
Finally, he went to the biggest music store
in the city.
"I have to sell my fiddle," he told the manager.
The manager opened the case and picked' up
the violin.
"Did you get this fiddle from a man named
McCord?" he asked.
"How did you know that?"
The manager put the violin back in its case.
"Every year we see five or six of these imitation
Stradivarius violins," he said.
"They all come from this man McCord.
This violin of yours, when new, was worth
about two hundred dollars.
I can only give you about... a hundred dollars
for It, though."
Boone could feel his face become hot.
"Thank you very much, sir, " he said.
He picked up the violin and left the store.
McCord had lied and cheated him.
He had taken Boone's 1500 dollars and given
him an Imitation Stradivarius.
Boone decided that he would look for McCord
and punish him.
Yes, he promised himself, he would find McCord
even if it took him the rest of his life...
Then Boone drove to the hospital to see Molly.
But she had died a few minutes before he got
there.
The doctor said she died peacefully.
But Boone did not believe him.
For him the whole world was full of liars
now.
And all the lies began with McCord.
Two days later Boone buried Molly.
Molly's hospital bill was almost 10 thousand
dollars.
Boone sold his home to pay it.
He rented a small room in town and went to
work fixing cars in Sam Boatwright's Garage.
When he saved 500 dollars Boone quit his job
at the garage.
He got into his truck and drove away to look
for McCord.
When he came to a town he would ask if anybody
there knew Jesse McCord.
Near the end of August during the second year
of his search he arrived in the town of Merryville,
Tennessee.
He found a woman there who said she knew Jesse
McCord.
She told Boone where McCord lived.
He got into his truck and followed a dirt
road out of town.
He drove for fifteen kilometers to an old
farmhouse.
The house was so old that it looked ready
to fall down.
An old man wearing a dark wool cap and a dirty
coat sat in front of the house.
He seemed to be sleeping.
Boone drove up to the house and got out of
his truck.
The old man opened his eyes.
Boone looked at him closely.
The man's skin was gray and dirty.
A thick moustache of hair covered his upper
up.
His face was thin and his chin was pointed.
"Are you Jesse McCord?"
Boone asked softly.
"I am what is left of him," the old man said.
"Who the hell are you?"
"I'm Boone Elliot."
The old man stared at him.
"Do I know you?"
"You sold me a fiddle."
McCord sighed, "I sold hundreds of fiddles.
Have you come to thank me?"
Boone shook his head, "I've come to kill you."
The old man laughed weakly, "You're too late.
I'm dead already.
If I live through the night, it will be a
miracle.
I haven't eaten in two days."
Tears filled his eyes and rolled down his
thin cheeks.
"I've done a lot of bad things in my life,"
the old man said.
"But I don't deserve to die like this.
Please, help me, mister."
McCord fainted.
Boone carried him into the house and tried
to find a place to put him down.
He walked into the bedroom.
There were no sheets on the bed and the mattress
was torn.
Boone put McCord on the bed.
"I'm going to get some food," he said.
"Don't die while I'm gone."
Boone climbed into his truck and drove back
to town as fast as he could.
He didn't want to help McCord, but once he
started he could not stop.
McCord was asleep when he got back to the
farm.
Boone looked down at him.
Suddenly, he became very angry.
"I should've known you wouldn't die!" he yelled.
Boone went into the kitchen and filled some
large pots with water.
He put the pots on the stove to heat up.
When the water was hot he brought one pot
into the bedroom.
He took off McCord's dirty clothing and washed
the old man's body.
He looked for clean clothes but there weren't
any.
So, Boone took some of his own clothing out
of his suitcase and put them on McCord.
When he finished he heated some soup and brought
it to McCord.
The old man was too weak to feed himself.
So Boone fed him the soup.
The next morning, McCord was strong enough
to sit up and feed himself.
After he ate, McCord sat on the porch with
Boone.
"How long have you been looking for me?"
McCord asked.
Boone shook his head, "I don't remember."
"Have you still got the fiddle?"
McCord asked.
Boone looked at the old man.
"Of course, I have it.
Who would I sell it to?"
McCord smiled, "Why don't you play me something
on that fiddle?"
"I can't," Boone said.
"Too much has happened - my wife died, I lost
my home and all my money.
And it all started because you sold me that
fiddle for ten times its real value."
"That may be true," McCord said.
"But it is still the same fiddle.
It isn't the fiddle that changed."
He began to cough.
Boone leaned toward him.
"Are you all right?" he asked.
"Hmm...
No," McCord said.
He coughed some more and his eyes filled 'with
tears.
McCord grabbed Boone's arm.
"Don't bury me in the cemetery in town," he
said.
"I want to be buried in the old cemetery behind
the church at the end of the road.
Some of my people are there."
Boone stood over him.
"Don't you have any family living around here?"
he asked.
"No," the old man said.
"You are the only person I have."
That night McCord coughed so much that Boone
could not sleep.
Later there was a storm with thunder and lightning.
Some time during the storm McCord stopped
coughing and quietly died.
The next morning, Boone wrapped McCord's body
in a sheet and buried him in the cemetery
behind the church.
A man should be buried where he wants, Boone,
thought.
After he filled the grave with the dirt Boone
went to his truck and took out the fiddle.
He carefully tuned the fiddle's strings and
began to play.
The first song was "Amazing Grace."
He and Molly used to sing the song in church
on Sundays.
Then he played "The Tennessee Waltz," because
he thought McCord would've liked it.
And finally, he played "I'm Thinking Tonight
of My Blue Eyes" for Molly, because he had
not played any music at her funeral.
- THE END -