CHAPTER ONE
The Real Aunt Molli
My Aunt Molly is the kindest, sweetest person
on earth.
She may not be the cleverest woman in the
world, but I love her a lot.
However, a strange thing happened to Aunt
Molly and now we don't know what to do.
It all started when her husband, Uncle Dalton,
died.
Well, I called him Uncle Dalton but she always
called him 'Dally'.
He was my mother's only brother.
Aunt Molly really loved him, we all knew that.
Life had been quite difficult for Aunt Molly
when she was a child.
She was poor and her parents had died early
on.
She was left to look after herself.
She had never learned to read properly and
left school at an early age.
But she was always cheerful and honest and
never complained about the hard work she did
to earn her living.
She worked as a cleaner wherever there was
work to do.
She liked cleaning because she didn't have
to make any difficult decisions.
Aunt Molly didn't like making decisions.
Perhaps she wasn't used to it.
I don't know.
But everybody liked her and she was never
out of work.
She met Uncle Dalton when she was working
as a cleaner at the bus station.
He was a bus driver and it was when he had
just finished for the day that he first saw
her cleaning the station office.
He fell in love with her as soon as he saw
her.
It was the same for Aunt Molly.
As soon as their eyes met it was love for
both of them.
He soon grew to love her gentleness and she
loved his kind heart and willingness to make
decisions.
They got married two weeks later.
A year after that she gave birth to twin boys.
They were my cousins and their names were
Winston and Clement.
I was born in the same year two months later.
I was called Rufus.
I still am.
Anyway, Uncle Dalton got a better job at die
bus station soon afterwards, and they bought
a house near us.
Aunt Molly and Uncle Dalton had a happy marriage.
Uncle Dalton earned the money and Aunt Molly
cooked, cleaned and made the house a wonderful
home for her dear Dally and the boys.
It would not be quite right to say that Aunt
Molly actually ran the house.
In fact, all the big decisions were left to
Uncle Dalton.
But she made sure that everything went smoothly.
Everybody was happy.
I was happy, too, because I liked to play
with my cousins.
I also looked forward to the delicious home-made
biscuits Aunt Molly always gave me.
My cousins and I were five years old when
Uncle Dalton was run over by a bus at the
station.
It was an accident.
Uncle Dalton didn't know what hit him and
he was killed immediately.
Well, I suppose he guessed it was a bus, but
I don't think he had much time to think it
over, if you see what I mean.
Anyway, he was dead.
In a way, once Uncle Dalton had died, I think
a part of Aunt Molly died too.
She was still a hard worker and remained a
good mother to Winston and Clement.
Indeed, the routine of running the house was
something she no longer needed any help with.
My parents and Uncle Dalton's parents - my
grandparents - all helped Aunt Molly with
the decision making.
But the cheerfulness that we had come to expect
from her had gone.
It was as if all her cheerfulness had died
with Uncle Dalton, her 'dear Dally'.
She got some money from the bus company because
Uncle Dalton had been killed at work.
At least she didn't have to leave the twins
in order to earn money.
Life continued.
The twins grew into fine boys.
But by the time they were fourteen they wanted
to see a bit more of the world outside their
comfortable home.
Both of them were bright and interested in
the world outside.
Especially Winston.
They were beginning to get bored with life
at home with all its safe routines.
That's where the trouble really began.
Aunt Molly had not really changed since their
father's death.
She had not even learned to read properly.
She never went out and had no outside interests.
She spent what free time she had listening
to the radio or watching the television, especially
game shows.
The boys, though they loved their mother,
wanted to decide more things for themselves.
And like me, they wanted to go out more.
Aunt Molly, however, just wanted to stay at
home all the time.
The boys never went out much with their mother
- whenever they did go out, it was with me
and my parents or with our grandparents.
Aunt Molly always stayed at home.
It was Winston who thought of taking their
mother to the theatre on her next birthday.
She would be thirty-nine.
The boys planned it all out carefully with
the help of the rest of the family.
We were all there, my parents and my grandparents.
'I don't think Mum would like to see a Shakespeare
play or anything like that,' said Clement.
'But I'm sure that going to see something
would do her good!'
'You're right,' said Gran.
'I think your mother should go to see something
she would enjoy.
It would make a nice change for her.
Something like those shows she likes on the
television.'
'Gran, you're brilliant!' said Winston.
'What about that show on the television with
that hypnotist guy... the Maxwell Marvel Show?
Mum loves that!'"
'What's that all about?' asked Grandpa.
'I don't think I've seen it.'
'You must be the only person in the country
who hasn't,' said Clement.
'Maxwell Marvel is an expert hypnotist - he
gives people suggestions and orders after
he has made them go to sleep.
When they wake up they do all kinds of funny
things.
Then, at an order from Maxwell Marvel, they
go to sleep again.
When they wake up again, they can't remember
a thing about it.'
Grandpa laughed.
'I've had a few evenings like that myself.'
Gran looked at him.
'Er... when I was much younger, of course,'
he added quickly.
'Mum would really like to see that show - I
just know it,' said Winston.
'Yes, but how do we get your Mum on a television
show?
Won't it be expensive?
How will we get the money?'
I asked.
'Relax,' said Winston.
'All we have to do is write to the television
company and they'll send us the tickets free
- that's where they get their live audiences
from!
All we have to do is make sure we let them
know in time for the show.'
We all agreed that this was a great idea.
So we did it.
Aunt Molly, of course, was at first unwilling
to go along with it.
However, we had all made the decision for
her and we wouldn't take no for an answer.
In her heart, though, she did not really care
what happened to her, not since her dear Dally
had gone.
But she went along to please her boys because
she cared deeply for them, and did not want
to disappoint them.
The television studio - the place where the
show took place - was not at all what Aunt
Molly imagined it would be like.
She thought it would be like the inside of
a theatre or a cinema.
It wasn't.
It was full of lighting and sound equipment.
There were all kinds of people around whose
job it was to make sure that everything worked
properly.
The audience itself was smaller than she expected.
She could see the star of the show, Maxwell
Marvel, nervously brushing his jacket in full
view of the audience.
'Don't worry, Mum,' said Winston with confidence.
'It's always like this in a television studio.
They're just getting ready for the show.'
Aunt Molly was sitting in the middle of the
second row between the twins.
I was there, too, along with Grandpa, who,
from time to time, took little drinks from
a small bottle of something he kept in his
pocket.
He was smiling.
Gran had stayed at home.
'Hey, the show's starting,' said Clement.
A man came out and told some jokes to make
everybody feel more relaxed.
He explained how the show was recorded for
television and what was expected of the audience.
Then the lights went down and the opening
music to the show started.
Maxwell Marvel came into the centre of the
studio, full of smiles.
The audience clapped for a long time.
Aunt Molly had seen this show many times on
television, so she knew what to expect.
Even so, we could tell that she was getting
excited.
We could see her smiling.
It had been a long time since we had seen
her smile like that.
Then the show began.
Maxwell Marvel asked for some people from
the audience to be hypnotised.
Quite a few of the audience were willing but
only about ten were chosen.
They came on to the small stage and were immediately
hypnotised by Maxwell.
They were told to do the strangest things
- such as behaving like farm animals, or dancing
at a disco, or acting like famous people.
And they did everything they were told to
do!
Even the quiet looking ones were persuaded
to do things that looked completely different
from their usual behaviour.
Then, at a word or sign from Maxwell, they
became themselves again and couldn't remember
anything about what they had done.
Some of them didn't even believe that they
had been hypnotised at all and would only
believe Maxwell after they were shown a video
of what they had been doing.
Everybody loved it.
Including Aunt Molly.
The final part of the show came when Maxwell
asked for a last person to come forward.
'Here!' shouted Winston.
He was pointing at his mother.
'Winston!
What are you doing?' she said.
'I can't do that - I'd die of embarrassment!'
'Oh, go on, Mum.
Do something different for once,' Clement
whispered loudly.
Grandpa and I were smiling.
Aunt Molly smiled too.
She felt that she couldn't say no after all
the trouble they had taken.
What if she did look silly?
That wouldn't matter.
Nothing mattered now but her boys.
'All right - I'll do it!'
she said.
Aunt Molly, for some reason, was an especially
easy person to hypnotise.
As she sat on a chair she 'went to sleep'
to the sound of Maxwell's voice like a baby.
We all wondered what hypnotic suggestions
Maxwell would give her.
Then Maxwell turned to Winston and said: 'What
suggestions would you like to make, young
man?
I'll tell this lovely lady to do anything
that won't get her into trouble with the police!'
The audience laughed.
The twins whispered to each other, then Winston
spoke.
'Well...
Mum's always needed a bit more confidence,
so what could you do to make her more...'
'Decisive said Clement.
'That's it,' said Winston.
'More able to make decisions and be more confident
- let her live life to the full!'
'Let's see what we can do,' said Maxwell.
He first asked for her name and Grandpa told
him.
Then Maxwell turned to Aunt Molly who was
still fast asleep.
'Now, Molly, you will answer only to my voice,
do you understand?'
'I understand,' said Aunt Molly quietly, though
she was still asleep.
'You will be a confident woman, full of strength.
Whatever you want to do, you will succeed
in doing.
Nothing is too difficult for you.
Is that clear to you, Molly?' said Maxwell.
Molly said that it was.
'When I tell you to open your eyes you will
be that intelligent, confident woman; you
will live life to the full.
You will not remember that you have been hypnotised
but you will be a new, confident woman who
will live life to the full.
You will continue until I - and only I - tell
you to return to your normal life.
Is that understood, Molly?' said Maxwell loudly
and with quite a4ot confidence of his own.
Molly said she understood.
'Now, Molly,' said Maxwell.
'Open your eyes...'
But as he said this he suddenly gave a loud
cry and fell at Aunt Molly's feet while holding
on to his tie.
His face had turned grey.
Maxwell Marvel had a heart attack just as
Aunt Molly was opening her eyes.
The first thing she saw was Maxwell Marvel
lying at her feet.
She turned to the nearest person in the audience
and said, 'Well, don't just sit there, man!
This man has obviously had a heart attack
- call for a doctor and an ambulance at once.
He needs immediate attention.'
The man did as he was told while Aunt Molly
undid Maxwell's tie and put him in a comfortable
position.
She acted as if she knew exactly what to do.
Help soon arrived and the unconscious Maxwell
was taken away in an ambulance.
A man from the television company spoke to
the audience and explained that, because of
Maxwell Marvel's sudden and unfortunate accident,
the show was at an end.
He said he was very sorry that things had
been cut short in this way.
Somebody behind us called out that it had
been the best part of the show.
Grandpa went up to the man who had spoken
to us.
He asked him what they could do to get Aunt
Molly back to normal now that Maxwell Marvel
wasn't here.
'You heard Maxwell,' the man told him.
'Only his voice can undo the orders.
I'm sorry - you'll have to wait until Maxwell
can speak to her himself.'
'But what if...' asked Grandpa, '... what
if he doesn't get better?'
'Let's all hope that he does,' the man said.
'It's a popular show.
Anyway, the order he gave her wasn't so bad
was it?
It's not as if he told her to start acting
like a monkey or something!
Don't worry - we'll get in touch.'
In the car on the way back home we talked
about what had happened that evening.
We had all been surprised, to say the least,
at the way Aunt Molly had behaved when Maxwell
Marvel had had his heart attack; she had been
more in control than anybody.
It was as if she had known exactly what to
do.
'Nonsense,' said Aunt Molly when we put this
to her.
'just a little common sense.
Besides, everything about his condition showed
that his attack was not a serious one.
He should get better soon if he rests for
a while and looks after himself
Was this Aunt Molly talking?
We could hardly believe what we were hearing.
She sounded like a doctor.
'How do you know that, Mum?' asked Winston.
'I heard a radio programme all about looking
after your heart - it described everything
about heart conditions very clearly,' she
answered.
'And when, exactly, did you hear this?' asked
Grandpa.
'Oh, ten years ago while I was cleaning the
carpet.
When Dally was alive.
Bless him,' said Molly with a smile.
The week that followed Aunt Molly's return
home was full of surprises for all of us.
She was not the Molly we all knew.
For a start, she soon discovered that she
could read, after all.
After years of hardly looking at even a newspaper,
she began to read anything she could get her
hands on.
At first it was cheap magazines and love stories.
Then she started on serious newspapers and
Russian novels.
During the following weeks she took up painting
and found that she was able to paint beautiful
pictures.
Soon she could paint as well as a professional.
Then her beloved cooking changed.
No longer did she cook simple but delicious
meals.
Now she tried Indian, Chinese and Italian
meals which were also, it must be said, delicious.
She started to go out to all kinds of places
- museums, art shows, scientific talks given
by experts, political meetings - and she took
the twins, too!
'You were complaining that we never went out
- we're going out!'
she said to them.
Nobody dared to advise her anymore.
'I'm a grown woman - I can do things for myself,
thank you very much!'
she would tell us.
Then she came home with Horace, the Professor
of Classics at the university.
He was an expert on ancient Greek and Roman
history.
'Horace has asked me to spend a week in Greece
with him.
We're going to explore the ancient buildings,'
she said.
'But Mum...' began the twins.
'No buts...'
Molly said.
'I'd rather explore an ancient building than
look like one.
Besides, Horace is a good-looking man - with
brains, too.
He likes me.
And I'm still an attractive woman; I could
marry again.
It's about time I started to live life to
the full.
I've stayed at home for too long.'
We were all amazed by this new Aunt Molly.
She could, it seemed, do anything she put
her mind to.
And although we loved the old Aunt Molly,
we soon liked this new person who had come
into our lives.
In fact, she was now a lively, funny and thoughtful
woman.
She scared us a little, too, with her burning
wish for improvement.
But we all found her very, very easy to like.It
was twelve weeks after Maxwell Marvel hkd
had his heart attack.
We had heard nothing from him but we saw on
the television that he had been let out of
hospital.
Two days after he left hospital he was found
dead in the bed of his latest twenty-year-old
girlfriend.
He had died of another heart attack.
He was forty-nine.
A week after Maxwell Marvel's death, Grandpa
received a letter from the man he had spoken
to at the television studio.
There was a taped message with the letter.
On the tape was a recording of Maxwell giving
the order for Aunt Molly to return to what
she had been before.
He had recorded the message just before he
left hospital, just before he hurried off
to meet his new lover.It has now been a week
since Grandpa got the letter.
We still haven't played the tape to Aunt Molly.
We can't decide what we should do.
We have discovered another person in Aunt
Molly and we love her, too.
She's a new Aunt Molly who has rediscovered
life.
Yet we also love and miss the sweet, kind
lady who The truth is, we don't know which
Aunt Molly is now the real one.
What would happen if we played her the tape?
Would a part of her die once again, as it
had seemed to do when Uncle Dalton died?
Would it be right for us to take this new
life away from her?
Then, again, perhaps nothing would happen
and she would remain as she is - full of the
love of life.
And which Aunt Molly has the most right to
be here -the old or the new?
Who is the real Aunt Molly?
She and Horace are going off to Greece next
week.
That will give us all time to think things
over.
Then we will decide.
The old or the new?
Well, what would you do?
- THE END -