CHAPTER ONE
Pig
Once upon a time, in the city of New York,
a beautiful baby boy was born, and his joyful
parents named him Lexington.
The mother had just returned from hospital
carrying Lexington in her arms when she said
to her husband, 'Darling, now you must take
me out to a most wonderful restaurant for
dinner.'
Her husband kissed her and told her that any
woman who could have such a beautiful baby
as Lexington deserved to go anywhere she wanted.
So that evening they both dressed themselves
in their best clothes and, leaving little
Lexington in the care of a trained nurse who
was costing them twenty dollars a day, they
went out to the finest and most expensive
restaurant in town.
After a wonderful evening, they arrived back
at their house at around two o'clock in the
morning.
The husband paid the taxi driver and then
began feeling in his pockets for the key to
the front door.
After a while, he announced that he must have
left it in the pocket of his other suit, and
he suggested they ring the bell and get the
nurse to come down and let them in.
A nurse who was costing them twenty dollars
a day must expect to have to get out of bed
occasionally in the night, the husband said.
So he rang the bell.
They waited.
Nothing happened.
He rang it again, long and loud.
They waited another minute.
Then they both stepped back on to the street
and shouted the nurse's name up at the nursery
window on the third floor, but there was still
no answer.
The house was dark and silent.
The wife began to become frightened.
If the nurse couldn't hear the front doorbell,
then how did she expect to hear the baby crying?
'You mustn't worry.
I'll let you in.'
He was feeling rather brave after all he had
drunk.
He bent down and took off a shoe.
Then, holding the shoe by the toe, he threw
it hard and straight through the dining-room
window on the ground floor.
'There you are,' he said, laughing.
He stepped forward and very carefully put
a hand through the hole in the glass and undid
the lock.
Then he raised the window.
'I'll lift you in first, little mother,' he
said, and he took his wife around the waist
and lifted her off the ground.
Then her husband turned her round and began
moving her gently through the open window
into the dining room.
At this moment, a police car came driving
silently along the street towards them.
It stopped about thirty meters away and three
policemen jumped out of the car and started
running in the direction of the husband and
wife.
The policemen were all holding guns.
'Hands up!' the policemen shouted.
'Hands up!'
But it was impossible for the husband to obey
this order without letting go of his wife.
If he had done this, she would either have
fallen to the ground or would have been left
half in and half out of the house, which is
a very uncomfortable position for a woman;
so he continued to push her upwards and inwards
through the window.
The policemen, all of whom had received rewards
before for killing robbers, shot at them immediately.
Although the policemen were still running,
they hit both bodies several times and killed
both of them.
So, when he was no more than twelve days old,
little Lexington became an orphan.
The news of this killing was brought to all
the relatives of the dead couple by newspaper
reporters, and the next morning the closest
of the relatives got into taxis and left for
the house with the broken window.
They gathered in the living room and sat around
in a circle, smoking cigarettes and talking
about what should be done with the baby upstairs,
the orphan Lexington.
It soon became clear that none of the relatives
wanted responsibility for the child, and they
talked and argued all through the day.
Everybody declared an enormous desire to look
after him, and would have done so with the
greatest of pleasure but their apartment was
too small, or they already had one baby and
couldn't possibly afford another, or they
wouldn't know what to do with the poor little
child when they went abroad in the summer,
or they were getting old, which would surely
be very unfair on the boy.
They all knew, of course, that the father
had been heavily in debt for a long time and
that there would be no money at all to go
with the child.
They were still arguing at six the next morning
when suddenly, in the middle of it all, an
old aunt (her name was Glosspan) arrived from
Virginia.
Without taking off her hat and coat, without
even sitting down, she announced firmly to
the gathered relatives that she herself intended
to look after the baby boy.
She would take full responsibility, she said,
for the boy's education - and all the costs
- and everyone else could go home.
She went upstairs to the nursery and took
Lexington and went out of the house with the
baby held tightly in her arms.
The relatives simply sat, stared, smiled and
looked content.
And so the baby, Lexington, left the city
of New York when he was thirteen days old
and travelled southwards to live with Great
Aunt Glosspan in the State of Virginia.
Aunt Glosspan was nearly seventy when she
took Lexington to Virginia, but you would
never have guessed it.
She was as youthful as a woman half her age.
She had a small, but still quite beautiful
face and two lovely brown eyes.
But she was a strange old woman.
For the past thirty years she had lived alone
in a small cottage high up on the slopes of
the Blue Ridge Mountains, several kilometers
from the nearest village.
She had three cows, some fields for them,
some land for growing vegetables, a flower
garden and a dozen chickens.
And now she had little Lexington, too.
She was a strict vegetarian and thought that
eating animal meat was not only unhealthy
and disgusting, but cruel, too.
She lived on foods like milk, butter, eggs,
cheese, vegetables, nuts and fruit, and she
was happy to think that no creature would
ever be slaughtered for her sake.
She did not know very much about babies but
that didn't worry her.
At the railway station in New York she bought
some things for feeding the baby and a book
called The Care Of Infants.
What more could anyone want?
When the train started moving, she fed the
baby some milk and laid it down on the seat
to sleep.
Then she read The Care Of Infants from beginning
to end.
Strangely there wasn't any problem.
Back home in the cottage everything went well.
Little Lexington drank his milk and cried
and slept exactly as a good baby should, and
Aunt Glosspan was filled with joy whenever
she looked at him and she kissed him all day
long.
By the time he was six years old, young Lexington
had become a most beautiful boy with long
golden hair and deep blue eyes.
He was bright and cheerful, and already he
was learning to help his old aunt in all sorts
of different ways around the farm, collecting
the eggs from the chicken house, making butter,
and digging up potatoes in the vegetable garden.
Soon, Aunt Glosspan told herself, she would
have to start thinking about his education.
But she could not bear the thought of sending
him away to school.
She loved him so much now that it would kill
her to be separated from him for long.
There was, of course, that village school
down in the valley, but it was a horrible-looking
place, and if she sent him there, she was
sure they would start forcing him to eat meat
as soon as he arrived.
'You know what, my darling?'
she said to him one day when he was sitting
in the kitchen watching her make cheese.
'I'll teach you myself.'
The boy looked at her with his large blue
eyes, and gave her a trusting smile.
'That would be nice,' he said.
'And the first thing I should do is to teach
you how to cook.'
'I think I would like that, Aunt Glosspan.'
'You're going to have to learn some time,'
she said.
'Vegetarians like us don't have nearly so
many foods to choose from as ordinary people,
and so they must learn to cook doubly well.'
'Aunt Glosspan,' the boy said, 'what do ordinary
people eat that we don't?'
'Animals,' she answered with disgust.
'Do you mean live animals?'
'No,' she said.
'Dead ones.'
'Do you mean that when they die they eat them
instead of burying them?'
'They don't wait for them to die, dear.
They kill them.'
'How do they kill them, Aunt Glosspan?'
'They usually cut their throats with a knife.'
'But what kind of animals?'
'Cows and pigs mostly, and sheep.'
'Cows!'
the boy cried.
'You mean like our cows?'
'Exactly, my dear.'
'But how do they eat them, Aunt Glosspan?'
'They cut them up into little bits and they
cook them.
They like the meat best when it's all red
and bloody and sticking to the bones.
They love to eat cow's flesh with the blood
running out of it.'
'Pigs, too?'
'They love pigs.'
'Lumps of pig's meat,' the boy said.
'Imagine that.
What else do they eat, Aunt Glosspan?'
'Chickens.'
'Chickens?
Feathers, too?'
'No, dear, not the feathers.
Now go outside and play, will you?'
Soon after that, the lessons began.
There were five subjects, including reading
and writing, but cooking was the most popular
with both teacher and pupil.
In fact, it soon became very clear that young
Lexington was a talented cook.
He was clever and quick.
In so young a boy, this surprised Aunt Glosspan
and she could not quite understand it at all.
But she was very proud of him and thought
that the child would have a wonderful future.
'How good it is,' she said, 'that I have such
a wonderful little fellow to look after me
when I'm old.'
A couple of years later, she left the kitchen
forever, and put Lexington in charge of all
household cooking.
The boy was now ten years old, and Aunt Glosspan
was nearly eighty.
Alone in the kitchen, Lexington immediately
began experimenting with dishes of his own
invention.
There were hundreds of new ideas in his head.
Hardly a day went by without some wonderful
new dish being placed on the table.
There were many delicious inventions.
Aunt Glosspan had never tasted food like this
in all her life.
In the mornings, before lunch, she would go
outside the house and sit there in her chair,
thinking about the coming meal.
She loved to sit there and smell what came
through the kitchen window.
Then he would come out, this ten-year-old
child, a little smile of pleasure on his face
and a big steaming pot of the most wonderful
food imaginable in his hands.
'Do you know what you ought to do?'
his aunt said to him, eating the food.
'You ought to sit down and write a cookbook.'
He looked at her across the table, eating
slowly.
'Why not?'
she cried.
'I've taught you how to write and I've taught
you how to cook, and now you've only got to
put the two things together.
You write a cookbook, my darling, and it'll
make you famous all over the world.'
'All right,' he said.
'I will.'
And that same day, Lexington began writing
the first page of that great book on which
he worked for the rest of his life.
He called it Eat Well And Healthily.
Seven years later, by the time he was seventeen,
he had recorded over nine thousand different
recipes, all of them original, all of them
wonderful.
But now, suddenly, his work was interrupted
by the death of Aunt Glosspan.
She was ill during the night and Lexington
found her lying on the bed screaming with
pain.
She was a terrible sight.
The boy wondered what he should do.
Finally, to cool her down, he fetched a bucket
of water from the river and poured it over
her head, but this only made her worse, and
the old lady died in an hour.
'This is really too bad,' the poor boy said,
pinching her several times to make sure that
she was dead.
'And how sudden!
Only a few hours ago she seemed in the very
best health.
She even ate three large portions of my newest
mushroom dish and told me how good it was.'
After crying bitterly for several minutes,
because he had loved his aunt very much, he
carried her outside and buried her in the
garden.
The next day, while he was tidying up her
things, he found an envelope that was addressed
to him in Aunt Glosspan's handwriting.
He opened it and took out two fifty-dollar
notes and a letter.
The letter said:
Darling boy, I know that you have never been
down the mountain since you were thirteen
days old, but as soon as I die you must put
on a pair of shoes and a clean shirt and walk
down into the village and find the doctor.
Ask the doctor to give you a death certificate.
Then take this to my lawyer, a man called
Mr Samuel Zuckermann, who lives in New York
City and who has a copy of my will.
Mr Zuckermann will arrange everything.
The money in this envelope is to pay the doctor
for the certificate and for the cost of your
journey to New York.
Mr Zuckermann will give you more money when
you get there, and it is my wish that you
use it to continue your work on that great
book of yours until you are satisfied that
it is complete in every way.
Your loving aunt, Glosspan
Lexington, who had always done everything
his aunt had told him, put the money in his
pocket, put on a pair of shoes and a clean
shirt, and went down the mountain to the village
where the doctor lived.
'Old Glosspan?'
the doctor said.
'Is she dead?'
'Certainly she's dead,' the boy answered.
'If you come home with me now I'll dig her
up and you can see for yourself.'
'How deep did you bury her?'
the doctor asked.
'Two or three meters down, I think.'
'And how long ago?'
'Oh, about eight hours.'
'Then she's dead,' the doctor announced.
'Here's the certificate.'
Lexington now left for the city of New York
to find Mr Samuel Zuckermann.
He travelled on foot, and he slept under bushes,
and he lived on berries and wild plants, and
it took him sixteen days to reach the city.
'What a place this is!' he cried, as he stood
staring around him.
'There are no chickens or cows anywhere and
none of the women looks like Aunt Glosspan
at all.'
Lexington had never seen anyone like Mr Zuckermann
before, either.
He was a small man with a large nose, and
when he smiled, bits of gold flashed at you
from lots of different places inside his mouth.
In his office, he shook Lexington warmly by
the hand and congratulated him on his aunt's
death.
'I suppose you know that your dearly loved
aunt was a woman of great wealth?' he said.
'Do you mean the cows and the chickens?'
'I mean five hundred thousand dollars,' Mr
Zuckermann said.
'How much?'
'Five hundred thousand dollars, my boy.
And she's left it all to you.'
Mr Zuckermann leaned back in his chair.
'Of course, I shall have to take 50 percent
for my services,' he said, 'but that still
leaves you with two hundred and fifty thousand
dollars.'
'I am rich!'
Lexington cried.
'This is wonderful!
How soon can I have my money?'
'Well,' said Mr Zuckermann, 'luckily for you,
I know the people at the city tax office and
I'm confident that I'll be able to persuade
them to forget about any taxes that your aunt
owed.'
'How kind you are,' said Lexington.
'I shall have to give some people a small
tip, of course.'
'Whatever you say, Mr Zuckermann.'
'I think a hundred thousand would be enough.'
'But how much does that leave for me?'
the youth asked.
'One hundred and fifty thousand.
But then you've got the funeral expenses to
pay out of that.'
'Funeral expenses?'
'You've got to pay the funeral company.
Surely you know that?'
'But I buried her myself, Mr Zuckermann, in
the field behind the house.
I never used a funeral company.'
'Listen,' Mr Zuckermann said patiently.
'You may not know it but there is a law in
this State which says that no one can receive
any money from a will until the funeral company
has been paid.'
'You mean that's a law?'
'Certainly it's a law, and a very good law,
too.
Funerals are one of our country's great traditions.
They must be protected at all costs.'
Mr Zuckermann himself, together with a group
of doctors, controlled a large funeral company
in the city.
The celebration of death was therefore a deeply
religious affair in Mr Zuckermann's opinion.
'You had no right to go out and bury your
aunt like that,' he said.
'None at all.'
'I'm very sorry, Mr Zuckermann.'
'It's completely un-American.'
'I'll do whatever you say, Mr Zuckermann.
All I want to know is how much I'm going to
get in the end, when everything's paid.'
There was a pause.
'Shall we say fifteen thousand?' he suggested,
flashing a big gold smile.
'That's a nice figure.'
'Can I take it with me this afternoon?'
'I don't see why not.'
So Mr Zuckermann called his chief clerk and
told him to give Lexington fifteen thousand
dollars.
The youth, who was delighted to be getting
anything at all, accepted the money gratefully
and put it in his bag.
Then he shook Mr Zuckermann warmly by the
hand, thanked him for all his help, and went
out of the office.
'The whole world is in front of me!'
Lexington cried as he went into the street.
'I now have fifteen thousand dollars to help
me until my book is ready.
After that, of course, I shall have a lot
more.'
He stood in the street, wondering which way
to go.
He turned left and began walking slowly down
the street, staring at the sights of the city.
'I must have something to eat.
I'm so hungry!' he said.
The boy had eaten nothing except berries and
wild plants for the past two weeks, and now
his stomach wanted solid food.
He crossed the street and entered a small
restaurant.
The place was hot inside, and dark and silent.
There was a strong smell of cooking-fat.
Lexington seated himself at a corner table
and hung his bag on the back of the chair.
This, he told himself, is going to be most
interesting.
In all my seventeen years I have tasted only
the cooking of two people, Aunt Glosspan and
myself.
But now I am going to try the food of a new
cook and perhaps, if I am lucky, I might get
a few ideas for my book.
A waiter came out of the shadows at the back
and stood beside the table.
'Do you want the roast pork and potatoes?'
he asked.
'That's all we've got left.'
'Roast what and potatoes?'
The waiter took a dirty handkerchief from
his trouser pocket and shook it open.
Then he blew his nose loudly.
'Do you want it or don't you?' he said, wiping
his nose.
'I don't know what it is,' Lexington answered,
'but I'd love to try it.
I'm writing a cookbook and...'
'One pork and potatoes!'
the waiter shouted, and somewhere in the back
of the restaurant, far away in the darkness,
a voice answered him.
The waiter disappeared and soon returned carrying
a plate on which there lay a thick grey-white
piece of something hot.
Lexington leaned forward anxiously to smell
it.
'But this is absolutely heavenly!' he cried.
'What a smell!
It's wonderful!'
The waiter stepped back a little, watching
the youth.
'I have never in all my life smelled anything
as wonderful as this!'
Lexington cried, seizing his knife and fork.
'What is it made of?'
But the waiter was moving backwards towards
the kitchen.
Lexington cut off a small piece of the meat
and put it into his mouth, beginning to eat
it slowly, his eyes half closed.
'This is wonderful!' he cried.
'It's a fine new flavour!
Oh, Glosspan, I wish you were here with me
now so that you could taste this dish!
Waiter!
Come here at once!
I want you!'
The waiter was now watching him from the other
end of the room.
'If you will come and talk to me, I will give
you a present,' Lexington said, waving a hundred-dollar
note.
'Please come over here and talk to me.'
The waiter came cautiously back to the table,
seized the money and put it quickly into his
pocket.
'What can I do for you, my friend?'
'Listen,' Lexington said.
'If you will tell me what this dish is made
of, and exactly how it is prepared, I will
give you another hundred.'
'I've already told you,' the man said.
'It's pork.'
'And what exactly is pork?'
'Have you never had roast pork before?'
the waiter asked, staring.
'Just tell me what it is.'
'It's pig,' the waiter said.
'You just put it in the oven.'
'Pig?'
'All pork is pig; didn't you know that?'
'You mean this is pig's meat?'
'Of course.'
'But... but... that's impossible,' the youth
said.
'Aunt Glosspan said that meat of any kind
was disgusting and horrible, but this is without
doubt the most wonderful thing I have ever
tasted.
How do you explain that?'
'Perhaps your aunt didn't know how to cook
it,' the waiter said.
'Is that possible?'
'It certainly is.
Especially with pork.
Pork has to be very well cooked or you can't
eat it.'
'That's it!'
Lexington cried.
'That's exactly what must have happened.
She cooked it wrong!'
He handed the man another hundred-dollar note.
'Lead me to the kitchen,' he said.
'Introduce me to the man who prepared this
meat.'
Lexington was at once taken to the kitchen,
and there he met the cook, who was an old
man with large, unpleasant red patches on
his skin.
'This will cost you another hundred,' the
waiter said.
Lexington was happy to pay, but this time
he gave the money to the cook.
'Now listen to me,' he said.
'I am really rather confused by what the waiter
has been telling me.
Are you quite sure that the dish I've been
eating was prepared from pig's flesh?'
The cook raised his right hand and began scratching
his neck.
'Well,' he said, winking at the waiter, 'all
I can tell you is that I think it was pig's
meat.'
'Do you mean you're not sure?'
'One can never be sure.'
'Then what else could it have been?'
'Well,' the cook said, speaking very slowly
and still staring at the waiter.
'There's just a chance that it could have
been a piece of human flesh.'
'Do you mean - a man?'
'Yes.'
'Good heavens!'
'Or a woman.
It could have been either.
They both taste the same.'
'Well - now you really surprise me,' the youth
said.
'One lives and learns.'
'In fact, we've been getting a lot of it recently
from the meat factory in place of pork,' the
cook declared.
'Have you really?'
'The trouble is, it's almost impossible to
tell which is which.
They're both very good.'
'The piece I had just now was wonderful.'
'I'm glad you liked it,' the cook said.
'But to be quite honest, I think that was
a bit of pig.
In fact, I'm almost sure it was.'
'You are?'
'Yes, I am.'
'In that case we shall have to believe you,'
Lexington said.
'So now will you please tell me - and here
is another hundred-dollar note for your trouble
- will you please tell me how you prepared
it?'
The cook, after taking the money, told Lexington
how to cook pork, while the youth, not wanting
to miss a single word, sat down at the kitchen
table and recorded every detail in his notebook.
'Is that all?' he asked when the cook had
finished.
'That's all, but you must have a good piece
of meat and it must be cut right.'
'Show me how,' said Lexington.
'Kill one now so I can learn.'
'We don't kill pigs in the kitchen,' the cook
said.
'The meat you've just eaten came from a slaughterhouse.'
'Then give me the address!'
The cook gave him the address, and Lexington,
after thanking them both many times for their
kindness, rushed outside and went by taxi
to the slaughterhouse.
It was a big brick building, and the air around
it smelled sweet and heavy.
At the main entrance gates, there was a large
notice which said: VISITORS ARE WELCOME AT
ANY TIME.
Lexington walked through the gates and entered
a yard which surrounded the building itself.
He then followed some signs (THIS WAY FOR
THE GUIDED TOURS) and came to a small hut
near the main building (VISITORS'WAITING ROOM).
After knocking politely on the door, he went
in.
There were six other people in the waiting
room.
There was a fat mother with her two little
boys aged about nine and eleven.
There was a bright-eyed young couple and there
was a pale woman with long white gloves, looking
straight ahead, with her hands folded in front
of her.
Nobody spoke.
Lexington wondered whether they were all writing
cookbooks, like himself, but when he put this
question to them aloud, he got no answer.
They just shook their heads and smiled.
Soon the door opened and a man with a pink
face came into the room and said, 'Next, please.'
The mother and the two boys got up and went
out.
About ten minutes later, the same man returned.
'Next, please,' he said again, and the couple
stood up and followed him outside.
Two new visitors came in and sat down - a
middle-aged husband and a middle-aged wife,
the wife carrying a basket.
'Next, please,' said the guide, and the woman
with the long gloves got up and left.
Several more people came in and took their
places on the wooden chairs.
Soon the guide returned for the third time,
and now it was Lexington's turn to go outside.
'Follow me, please,' the guide said, leading
the youth across the yard towards the main
building.
'How exciting this is!'
Lexington cried.
First they visited a big area at the back
of the building where several hundred pigs
were wandering around.
'Here's where they start,' the guide said.
'And over there is where they go in.'
'Where?'
'Right there.'
The guide pointed to a long wooden shed that
stood against the outside wall of the factory.
'This way, please.'
Three men, wearing long rubber boots, were
taking a dozen pigs into the shed just as
Lexington and the guide arrived, so they all
went in together.
'Now,' the guide said, 'watch how they catch
them.'
Inside, the shed was simply a bare wooden
room with no roof, but there was a metal wire
with hooks on it that kept moving slowly along
the length of one wall.
When it reached the end of the hut, it suddenly
changed direction and climbed upwards through
the open roof towards the top floor of the
main building.
The twelve pigs were brought together at the
far end of the hut.
They stood quietly and looked anxious.
One of the men in rubber boots pulled a length
of metal chain down from the wall and advanced
upon the nearest animal from the back.
Then he bent down and quickly put one end
of the chain around one of the animal's back
legs.
The other end he put on a hook on the moving
wire as it went by.
The wire kept moving and the chain tightened.
The pig's leg was pulled up and back, and
the pig itself began to be dragged backwards
until it reached the end of the hut, where
the wire changed direction and went upwards.
The creature was suddenly pulled off its feet
and was carried up.
The pig's cries filled the air.
'Truly interesting,' Lexington said.
The rubber-booted men were busy catching the
rest of the pigs, and one after another the
animals were hooked on to the moving wire
and carried up through the roof, crying loudly
as they went.
At this point, while Lexington was staring
upwards at the last pig, a man in rubber boots
came up quietly behind him and put one end
of a chain around the youth's own leg, hooking
the other end of the chain to the moving belt.
The next moment, before he had time to realize
what was happening, Lexington was pulled off
his feet and dragged backwards along the floor
of the hut.
'Stop!' he cried.
'Stop everything!
My leg is caught!'
But nobody seemed to hear him, and five seconds
later the unhappy young man was pulled off
the floor and lifted up through the open roof
of the hut upside down, panging like a fish.
'Help!' he shouted.
'Help!
There's been a mistake!
Stop the engine!
Let me down!'
The guide took a cigarette out of his mouth
and looked up at the youth hanging from the
chain, but he said nothing.
The men in rubber boots were already on their
way out to collect the next pigs.
'Oh, save me!'
Lexington cried.
'Let me down!
Please let me down!'
But he was now nearing the top floor of the
building, where the moving belt entered a
large hole in the wall, a kind of doorway
without a door; and there, waiting to greet
him, in dark-stained rubber clothes, the slaughterer
stood.
Lexington saw him only from upside down, and
very quickly, but he noticed the expression
of absolute peace on the man's face, the cheerfulness
in his eyes and the little smile.
All these things gave him hope.
'Hi, there!'
the man said, smiling.
'Quick!
Save me!'
Lexington cried.
'With pleasure,' the man said, and taking
Lexington gently by one ear with his left
hand, he raised his right hand and quickly
cut the boys throat with a knife.
The belt moved on.
Lexington went with it.
Everything was still upside down and the blood
was pouring out of his throat and getting
into his eyes, but he could still see a little.
He thought he was in a very long room, and
at the far end of the room there was a great
smoking pot of water, and there were dark
figures half hidden in the steam.
These figures were dancing round the edge
of the pot and they were holding long sticks.
The belt seemed to be travelling right over
the top of the pot and the pigs seemed to
be dropping down one by one into the boiling
water and one of the pigs seemed to be wearing
long white gloves on its front feet.
Suddenly Lexington started to feel very sleepy,
but it was not until his good strong heart
had pumped the last drop of blood from his
body that he passed out of this, the best
of all possible worlds, into the next.
- THE END -