CHAPTER ONE
A Mountain Accident
Aron pulled his arm, carefully at first, and
then more strongly, but it did not come free.
It was a beautiful spring day and 27-year-old
Aron Ralston was walking in the mountains
after a hard week at work. The air was
fresh, and the sun was high in the sky.
Aron stopped walking to listen
to the silence of the mountains.
"This is wonderful," he thought. "No work
or noise. Only beautiful country around me.
As he continued on his way, he heard a
low noise. He looked up quickly at the
mountainside above him-but he was too late.
Large pieces of rock were falling toward him
and he could not escape quickly
enough. The earth was moving,
and the noise was terrible. In seconds, Aron's arm
was caught under a rock that weighed 500 kilos.
The pain was terrible, but Aron stayed calm.
He knew a lot about the mountains. He knew how
to live in the wildest and most dangerous open
spaces. He pulled his arm, carefully at first,
and then more strongly, but it did not come free.
Next, he pushed the rock as hard as possible.
Again-nothing. It was getting dark. Aron ate a
small amount of food and drank some of his water.
He wanted to keep strong, get some
rest, and try again in the morning.
After a difficult night's sleep, Aron
thought carefully about his problem.
Today was Sunday, a popular day for walking.
He decided to wait for help to arrive.
He looked hopefully up and
down the narrow mountain path,
but the mountains were empty and silent. The
morning passed and the sun moved to the west.
By late afternoon it was too late for
walkers. Aron needed a different plan.
Using his climbing equipment, he tried to move the
rock. He tried a number of different ways, but it
was too heavy. Next, he took his pocket knife and
tried to break away small pieces of the rock near
his arm. "This will destroy my good knife," he
thought, "but my life is more important!" But
the knife failed to cut even the smallest piece
of rock. Aron knew that he was really caught.
He made himself as comfortable as
possible for another lonely night.
Aron had enough water and food with him
for a day's walk. But it was day three
now and the food was almost finished. He
only had enough for one more small meal.
In his mind, a difficult and dangerous plan
was growing, but he did not want to try yet.
It was Tuesday morning. After three difficult
nights in the mountains, Aron was tired and
hungry. He drank the last of his water and thought
carefully. Now he knew that he had to cut off
his arm. He took his knife from his pocket
and bravely put the metal against his skin.
He pressed down hard and began to cut. But after
his work on the rock, the knife was not sharp.
"I couldn't even cut the hair off my arm,"
he explained to newspaper reporters later.
Aron used the rock to make his knife sharp again.
Then he cut through his skin as far as the bone.
"Then I found that I couldn't cut the bone," he
calmly told the reporters. For two more days Aron
tried different ways to cut his arm off. Without
food or drink, his body was getting weaker.
But his mind was clear and strong. "I
did what I had to do," he explained.
Aron turned his arm the opposite way to his
body. The first arm bone broke easily. Then he
broke the second. He tied a piece of cloth tightly
around the top of his right arm to stop the blood.
Then, slowly, he cut through the rest of his arm.
At last Aron was free! He looked down at his
lifeless arm under the rock. It seemed like a
strange dream. His clothes were covered in blood
and the pain in his right shoulder was terrible.
Aron felt very small and unimportant under
the wide sky and tall, dark mountains.
Aron was still in great danger.
He was a long way from home and he was losing
blood fast. Darkness was only a few hours away.
He had to get to a road as quickly as possible.
He looked below him and thought carefully.
It was an eighteen-meter drop to the valley floor,
but it was the fastest way back. He had to try.
Aron started to lower himself
down the steep mountainside.
It was hard, slow work with only one arm, but
finally his feet touched the valley floor.
The nearest road was still
sixteen kilometers away.
There was no time to rest. Aron
felt weak. It was difficult to
think clearly. "I am going to do it," he
told himself. "Just one step at a time..."
Aron started walking. He had to reach help
quickly. One more night in the wild mountains was
too dangerous. Each painful step took him closer
to help. But the walk was very long and difficult.
At last, after six hours, Aron saw two
other walkers. He wanted to run and shout,
but his body was too weak.
When they finally saw him,
the worried walkers gave Aron chocolate cookies
and water. Then they moved him to open ground.
Here, the flying mountain police found the
group, and they took Aron immediately to the
nearest hospital. For the first time, Aron
knew that he was safe. He was truly alive!
Hours later, Aron lay quietly in his hospital bed
and looked up at the shiny white walls around him.
He was in a different world now - a
small, safe world of men and machines.
But part of him belongs forever to the
wilder world of rock and mountain and sky.
Aron says that he cannot wait to
get out into the wild again.
-
THE END -