CHAPTER ONE
Lady of the Lake
Merlin closed his eyes and pointed his finger
at another mountain of rocks.
They exploded into a thousand pieces!
When he opened his eyes, all he could see
was blue sky.
Everything round him was empty and silent
- the trees, the hills, the lakes.
Slowly, a voice reached Merlin's ears.
It was Uther, the King of England, speaking
in his castle miles away.
Merlin was a magician with special powers
to see, hear and know all things human.
Merlin took a magic crystal ball from the
long, blue robe he always wore.
He wanted to see Uther in the magic ball,
talking to his brother in the castle.
Uther was a strong man who had won many battles.
Yet England was still divided by many wars.
"I have won enough battles to rule a thousand
countries, yet England stands divided.
What else must I do?"
Using his magic power again, Merlin shut his
eyes and when he opened them again, he was
in Uther's castle, hiding behind a wall.
He came out when Uther's brother had gone.
Uther was not surprised to see Merlin as his
magic was respected and feared throughout
the land.
"Merlin, why do you appear now when I wish
to be alone?"
"Because I believe I can help you."
"How?
No one can stop our people fighting each other."
"Excalibur can."
Uther was puzzled.
"What is Excalibur?"
Merlin became very serious.
"Excalibur is the most powerful sword in the
world.
Whoever owns it cannot be killed or lose a
battle."
"Give it to me!
I must have it!"
"It is not only mine to give.
The Lady of the Lake must feel that you deserve
it."
Uther asked to be shown the Lady of the Lake
so he could prove himself to her.
Merlin agreed.
He took Uther to a dark valley far from the
kingdom, in which lay a crystal lake.
Uther and Merlin stood in front of the still
water of the deep lake.
They stared at their reflections in its mirror-like
surface.
"You must promise me something if I allow
you to take Excalibur from the lake."
"Say it and it is yours."
"I want your first-born child."
Uther looked at himself in the lake.
He saw himself killing men and ruling with
a power that had never been seen before.
Since he had no children, it did not seem
a great deal to ask.
He gave Merlin his word of honour.
The water before them began to stir.
A woman's figure appeared below the surface
of the water.
Her hands rose from the water, holding the
gold handle of the silver sword called Excalibur.
"Take it, Uther.
It is yours if you want it."
Uther stepped into the water, taking the magnificent
sword into his hands.
When he touched it, he was filled with a strange
energy.
He held it up to the sky, admiring the reflections
of light on its silver surface.
Merlin watched the Lady of the Lake disappear
below the dark mysterious water.
He knew he must watch over the use of Excalibur,
as the Lady of the Lake trusted him.
"You've made a promise Uther.
Do not forget what it is."
Yet Uther had already forgotten.
All he could think of, as he looked at his
face reflected in the sword, was how strong
and powerful he would become.
CHAPTER TWO
Uther's Promise
A few years passed, and in time, the Queen
gave birth to a son.
Uther had completely forgotten his promise
to Merlin until the day Merlin came to claim
what was his.
He entered the chamber where the Queen was
playing with her baby son.
Uther followed behind.
His face was deathly pale.
The Queen saw by her husband's expression
that something terrible had happened.
She rose to greet him.
"What is it Uther?
You do not look well."
He explained the promise he had made to Merlin.
Igraine, the Queen, was furious.
"You fool!
You would give up your own child for the price
of a sword?"
Uther turned to Merlin.
"Please Merlin, I beg you, don't take our
child!
I'll give you anything else you ask."
"You gave me your word of honour.
The child is mine."
And with that, he took the baby from Igraine's
arms.
She screamed for the King to take the child
back, but Uther was weak against Merlin's
powers.
Merlin cast a spell over the King and Queen,
which kept them from moving.
When Merlin was gone, the spell went with
him, so the King took Excalibur to the forest
to find Merlin and his son.
Heavy clouds came over the sky, and it began
to rain.
Uther called out for Merlin as he moved through
the forest.
The rain, and his wish to see his son, prevented
Uther from seeing the thieves hiding in the
trees.
A thief jumped on Uther's back.
"Give us the sword and we will let you live."
Uther couldn't reach Excalibur.
He tried to grasp it, but one of the thieves
stabbed him with a knife.
As he fell, he touched Excalibur.
It gave him the strength to rise and fight,
but he was badly injured.
He knew he was going to die, and crawled to
the nearest rock to rest.
The rain poured down on him as he called out
to Merlin.
"Merlin!
I have kept my promise.
I will leave Excalibur in this rock, but you
must make my son a king."
Uther rose up with all his strength and pushed
Excalibur into the rock right up to the handle.
The King fell down on the ground and died
next to that rock.
Merlin appeared beside Uther.
"No man shall pull this sword from this rock
unless he is the next king of England."
CHAPTER THREE
Arthur
For many years after Uther's death, knights
from all over the country tried to pull Excalibur
from the stone, but none succeeded.
They competed to see who was the strongest
knight.
When these competitions ended, the winner
would go to the rock, with a crowd of people
watching, to see if he would be the next king
of England.
On one such day a very large man, over six
feet tall, with broad shoulders and long dark
hair stepped up to Excalibur to try to lift
it from its resting place of eighteen years.
The country had suffered during these years
as there had never been one ruler to bring
peace to the entire land.
The crowd waited quietly as the tall, dark-haired
man grabbed the handle of Excalibur.
He pulled with all his strength, but the sword
would not move.
The man walked away, disappointed, as a new
round of games began to see who would try
the sword next.
"Arthur!
Where is my sword?
The games are about to begin."
Arthur, the slave of a knight called Kay,
was sent to bring Kay's sword for the next
round of games.
Arthur had misplaced Kay's sword, and, in
a panic, he ran trying to find another sword
for his master.
Arthur ran with fear to the rock where Excalibur
stood.
He had never noticed the men trying to pull
the sword from the rock, as he was always
busy serving Kay.
Arthur pulled it from the rock and ran to
his master, happy to have found a sword.
Everyone knew Excalibur from its gold handle
and its silver blade.
Arthur handed it to Kay, who stood admiring
its magnificence.
"Arthur!
Where did you get this?"
"From a rock, just behind the trees."
The crowd around them held their breath.
"The boy.
He's pulled the sword from the rock."
Arthur became uneasy, not knowing what he
had done.
Merlin, in his long blue robe, appeared beside
the boy and placed a hand on his shoulder.
"This boy is the son of Uther, the last king
of England.
He is the heir to the throne."
There was much whispering among the crowd.
No one believed that this servant boy could
be a king.
Only Merlin knew, as he had made Arthur a
servant to teach him what it was like to be
ruled by other men.
He believed that when the time came for Arthur
to be king, he would learn from his master's
mistakes and therefore be wiser than his father,
Uther.
Merlin also knew that he had to prove to the
people that Arthur was truly the King's son.
He told Arthur to put Excalibur back into
the rock.
Arthur did.
Merlin asked Kay, and any others who thought
they were worthy of the sword, to try to pull
it out.
No one could.
"If this boy, Arthur, pulls the sword from
the rock, he is the true king of England and
you must do as he says."
Arthur pulled Excalibur from the rock and
held it up for all the crowd to see.
The people knelt with respect.
As he held Excalibur, Arthur felt the same
power his father had once felt run through
his body.
"With this sword, I will unite England into
a land of peace and prosperity."
With these words, Arthur began to fulfill
his promise.
CHAPTER FOUR
Guinevere.
Arthur stood on the wall above his castle's
entrance at Camelot as he watched a woman
riding a horse, accompanied by men in armour,
near the castle.
She was dressed in white, with a green cape
covering her arms and shoulders, and a hood
hiding her face.
She threw back the hood to announce that she
was Guinevere, princess of Carmelide, daughter
to the baron Leodegran.
Arthur, charmed by the lady's beauty - her
red hair, fair skin and clear, green eyes
- didn't know why she had arrived at the castle.
He only nodded to the guards to let her in.
Arthur went to hear what this beautiful woman
had to say.
"Your grace, my father's castle is under attack.
He is loyal to your lordship, and he needs
your help."
"Guards!
Send our best knights to the castle in Carmelide.
I will soon follow.
Prepare the table and some food for the lady
and her men.
She will stay here until her father is safe."
"I thank you for your kindness, but I must
return to my father.
He is in need of my help."
"Your loyalty to your father equals your beauty.
I promise you, my men and I will protect your
father and keep him safe."
Guinevere thought Arthur had a strong, handsome
face.
She liked his quick, thoughtful decisions,
and she agreed to stay.
Arthur rode to Carmelide where he and his
men quickly defeated those who had tried to
overtake the baron's castle.
Baron Leodegran lowered the drawbridge of
the castle for the King.
When the two men met, Leodegran knelt before
Arthur, promising his loyalty to the King
and his support of a unified England.
Arthur thanked him, and asked him to return
to Camelot with him and his men to celebrate
their victory.
As they rode to Camelot, Arthur spoke to Leodegran
of his daughter, the princess.
"Guinevere does great honour to your family
name, sir.
I am overcome by her beauty and charm and
I would like to make her my wife."
"No man could wish for more than for his daughter
to marry a king, especially one as noble as
yourself, but I ask you only to speak to Guinevere.
If she is in agreement, then so am I."
They rode on in silence, with Arthur determined
to find a time when he could tell Guinevere
his thoughts.
At Camelot, they celebrated with a feast large
enough for two kingdoms.
The people danced, and musicians sang of the
battles won and the hope that peace would
soon visit the country.
Arthur had a moment alone with Guinevere,
away from the noise of the celebration.
He told her that he had never seen a beauty
like hers in all his travels through the countryside.
"What is more, your strength of character
goes beyond my idea of a bride.
Will you stand by my side, as my queen?"
He took her hand, and they stood for a moment.
"You have saved my father, therefore you have
saved me.
It would be unwise of me to refuse the hand
of a man who is truly a king,"
They kissed, giving those in the castle even
more cause to celebrate.
CHAPTER FIVE
Lancelot.
Guinevere rode towards Camelot with Arthur's
knights riding in front and behind her.
Her father was at her side.
It was the day of her marriage to Arthur,
and her white dress stood out among the shining
silver of the knights' armour and the green
grass on the hills beside them.
They were on a winding road when they turned
a corner and saw a tree on fire.
They stopped, left the road, and climbed a
hill to go around the fire.
Enemies of Guinevere's father, Leodegran,
had set the fire, and they were waiting on
the opposite side of the hill to attack those
guarding Guinevere.
They were led by a man called Maleagant who
once served Leodegran at his castle.
He was in love with Guinevere, but she disliked
him because she did not trust him.
He was also the one who led the attack against
Leodegran which caused Guinevere to ask for
Arthur's help.
As the enemies fought, Guinevere was left
unguarded.
Maleagant saw his opportunity and pulled Guinevere
from her horse onto his own.
She screamed but she could do nothing.
He rode away quickly before any of Arthur's
knights knew what had happened.
A horseman stood alone on the opposite hilltop
watching the battle.
He saw Maleagant ride away with Guinevere.
He did not know who Guinevere was when he
rode after them, but his noble character would
not allow him to watch injustice being done.
His name was Lancelot, son of the baron of
Benoic.
His father had been killed in one of the battles
dividing the country, and when he heard Arthur
had pulled Excalibur from the rock, he had
set off for Camelot to offer his help in ending
the wars in England.
Lancelot had to ride quickly to be able to
watch Maleagant and Guinevere, but he was
careful not to be seen.
He wanted to know where Maleagant would take
Guinevere.
Maleagant stopped in a clearing surrounded
by large rocks.
Lancelot hid behind the rocks, so he could
surprise Maleagant.
Maleagant tied Guinevere's hands and feet,
as he wished to rest after the long journey.
He stood before Guinevere, staring at her
with the dark, distrustful eyes she had first
seen and disliked in him.
"If you do not have what you desire in this
world Guinevere, you must take it, one way
or another."
As he said this, Lancelot appeared on the
rocks above him.
Only Guinevere could see him.
She looked at his kind, brave face and he
assured her with a nod of his head that he
was there for her.
"There is a man who is about to change the
world you think you know so well."
"If you mean that tool you wish to call your
husband, you are less intelligent than I thought."
"There are more men than the king who believe
in what is true and just."
At that, Lancelot jumped from the rocks above
Maleagant's head and knocked him to the ground.
Without a helmet, without knowing where Lancelot
was, Maleagant was dead before he could draw
his sword.
"I thank you for saving me, but perhaps there
is one who will be even more thankful.
We were to marry today.
He is the King, Arthur."
"I was on my way to Camelot when I saw what
happened.
I am honoured."
Lancelot knelt before Guinevere.
She was charmed.
"Stand sir.
I am not yet a queen and do not deserve such
honour."
"Yet your beauty alone should have told me
that one day I would serve you."
"Tell me your name, and we will ride to Camelot
together, where I'm sure the King will be
as pleased as I am with your feelings."
"My name is Lancelot, son of the baron of
Benoic.
I am at your service."
They rode back together to Camelot where they
were met outside the castle by Arthur and
his men.
When Arthur heard what Guinevere had to say,
he approached Lancelot.
"You have done me a great service, brave sir,
and I wish to do the same for you."
"My only wish is to help your highness unite
this land where men braver than myself have
been killed for no reason."
"Kneel, Lancelot.
From this day forward, you will be Sir Lancelot,
the most favoured knight of the King of England.
Together, we will unite this land."
Guinevere watched as Lancelot knelt and Arthur
touched each of Lancelot's shoulders with
Excalibur.
She knew that these two men would always be
close to her heart.
CHAPTER SIX
Sir Lancelot and Sir Gawain.
After peace came to England and people were
living in harmony, Arthur decided to establish
a symbol of the country's unity which would
help keep the unity and peace they enjoyed.
He invited all the barons of the castles in
England who had remained loyal to the king
during his fight for peace to come and sit
at a round table Arthur had specially designed.
At this table, all men's opinions were equal
and matters on how to keep peace and unity
in England were discussed.
Sir Lancelot sat to the right of Arthur and
Sir Gawain sat to the left.
They were the bravest and most noble of Arthur's
knights, and Arthur put complete trust in
them.
Sir Gawain was jealous of Sir Lancelot.
He knew Lancelot was Arthur's favourite knight
because he had been the first to be knighted
by the King.
Lancelot was said to have a pure heart.
He had no ambitions for himself, only for
the King and Queen.
Gawain did not believe this.
He thought Lancelot, like all men, wanted
to be King himself.
If Lancelot were King, Gawain thought, he
would have a Queen as beautiful and virtuous
as Guinevere.
Arthur was called from the castle to visit
Guinevere's father, Leodegran.
Arthur asked Lancelot to guard the Queen's
tower while he was gone, as Lancelot was surely
the best swordsman in England.
Sir Gawain gained the trust of one of the
Queen's maids.
He asked her to give a letter to the Queen
which he said was from Lancelot.
In it, Gawain wrote that Lancelot was in love
with the Queen, and that although Lancelot
did not want to betray the King, he would
like to talk to the Queen in private.
The Queen sent for Lancelot the moment she
read the letter.
Lancelot, unwilling to leave his post, was
grateful that Gawain was there to watch the
tower while he spoke to Guinevere.
The Queen was very direct with Lancelot.
She asked him to explain the letter.
"Although it is in my name, I'm afraid it
is not by my hand."
"And your heart?"
"My heart is at the service of the King and
Queen."
"Do you love me Sir Lancelot?"
"I love you as my Queen and as the King's
wife."
Guinevere was satisfied with Lancelot's answers,
but she was surprised to find that her own
heart was moved by his nobility and grace.
She asked him to sit with her to play a game
of chess.
Lancelot trusted Sir Gawain to keep his post,
at the door of the tower.
The king returned, surprised to see Sir Gawain
at the door of the queen's tower.
"My King.
I saw the door unguarded and so I have been
guarding it myself.
I am sure the Queen is safe, for I have heard
laughter from her chamber."
Sir Gawain couldn't have planned it better.
But, as the king arrived at the Queen's chamber,
the Queen and Lancelot had reached for the
same game piece at the same time.
Their hands touched.
Guinevere lightly held Lancelot's fingers.
Lancelot raised her hand with his.
"Will you kiss my hand before you return it?"
"As my Queen, I will..."
Arthur kicked the door open.
Lancelot stood up, reaching for his sword.
Arthur thought he saw them holding hands.
The expression of embarrassment on Guinevere's
face gave Arthur more need to worry.
"You left your post."
"I was called."
"Silence!
You left your post.
Now, do as I say and attend to your duties!"
The love Arthur felt for Lancelot and Guinevere
hurt him as he was now not sure the love was
being returned.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Morgan Le Fay.
Merlin would often go to the island of Avalon,
where a young and very beautiful woman practised
the art of magic Merlin had taught her.
Her name was Morgan Le Fay, and she could
change herself into any shape, and heal all
illnesses.
Yet this did not satisfy her.
She wanted to cause evil and disharmony in
the world.
She thought this would make her truly powerful.
"You are young and foolish, Morgan.
You possess the greatest power there is.
Yet, you want to destroy it."
Morgan begged Merlin to explain how evil is
caused.
He agreed because he wanted her to understand
human pain.
Merlin took out his crystal ball.
In it, he showed Morgan what had happened
between Lancelot, Guinevere and Arthur.
"Evil is created by forcing a man, or a woman,
to concentrate on a part of their character
which it is better to forget.
You see that man does himself enough harm
without our involvement."
Morgan was not satisfied.
Arthur's anger, and the possibility of Lancelot's
desire for Guinevere, lit an evil fire in
Morgan's heart.
When Merlin left her, Morgan turned herself
into a falcon and flew to Camelot.
She circled Camelot until she saw Lancelot
and Gawain riding their horses through the
forest.
With a strong wind, she blew the leaves on
the forest floor into the air around her,
as she changed forms again.
This time she took the form of Guinevere on
horseback.
Sir Gawain and Sir Lancelot were stopped by
the wind and leaves which temporarily blinded
them.
They sat on their horses, wiping the dust
from their eyes.
Then they saw the beautiful Guinevere riding
towards them through the forest.
Guinevere told Gawain to stay with the horses
and the servants while she led Lancelot by
the hand to a clearing some distance away,
but still where Sir Gawain could see them.
She told Lancelot his touch had moved her
so much that she couldn't take a step without
thinking of him.
If he would hold her, if her cheek could touch
his, if he would kiss her, she believed that
she would be tree of this desire and could
devote her life again to the King.
Lancelot was torn between his feelings of
loyalty towards the King and an unexpected
desire to take Guinevere in his arms.
He thought if he kissed her, just once, he
would satisfy his desire, as well as the Queen's,
and then he could remain loyal to the King
forever.
They held each other and kissed while Gawain
watched with excited and open eyes.
Morgan left Lancelot and the forest as Guinevere.
She flew through the air as an eagle and dived
into the sea as a dolphin.
When she returned to Avalon, she was satisfied.
True power, she felt, was now hers.
Gawain reported to the King what he had seen,
and the King called Lancelot before him.
Lancelot, unable to lie, admitted everything.
"Your seat at the round table shall remain
empty as a reminder of your disloyalty and
disgrace.
I banish you from Camelot.
You have betrayed me."
Lancelot accepted his punishment as his heart
told him that he had been wrong.
Sir Gawain was pleased with himself.
"Now I will be the King's favourite knight,"
he thought to himself.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Mordred.
Guinevere could not believe what she heard
when the King told her what Sir Gawain had
seen.
She insisted she had never ridden out to the
forest without her husband.
"Lancelot has admitted to everything.
He has been banished."
"He is lying!
My lips have only touched one man's, and here
he stands before me, willing to listen to
a traitor rather than his own wife."
"But Sir Gawain said..."
"Sir Gawain is a fool.
Look into his eyes and you will see that he
does not know the difference between truth
and fantasy.
Call Lancelot here and we will settle this
matter.
Until then, I will see no one."
With that, the Queen left for her chambers.
The King was alone, thinking, when Merlin
appeared.
Merlin knew that Morgan Le Fay had caused
this trouble, but he also knew Arthur had
made a great mistake.
Not asking Guinevere what had happened showed
a lack of faith.
Sending Lancelot away would cause disharmony
in the kingdom and throughout the land.
Merlin told Arthur to call the knights to
the Round Table so he could speak to them.
When the knights were seated around King Arthur,
Merlin stopped at Lancelot's empty seat.
"The circle has been broken.
Evil, whatever its cause, has touched one
man, therefore it touches you all.
I have seen the future.
England will once again be at war.
There is a truth, which must be discovered
before the country can be united.
It is your duty to find this truth."
Merlin rolled his crystal ball across the
table.
Gradually, it became a ball of blinding light
until it stopped in the centre of the table.
Inside the light, a golden cup with a long
thin stem appeared.
"Observe it, all of you.
It is the Holy Grail, and it holds the secrets
of truth and justice.
Find it, and peace will return to England."
Thunder shook the walls of the castle and
it began to rain.
Merlin and the Grail had disappeared.
It became dark.
Arthur ordered his men to search for the Grail
which would again unite England.
He felt the absence of Lancelot as he sat
next to his empty seat, and he too left the
Round Table.
Merlin believed he had made a mistake by showing
Morgan the weakness of humans.
He returned to Avalon to see if he was right.
Morgan was training a small boy to fight like
a warrior.
She had stolen him as a newborn child to raise
him as the new leader of England who would
carry out her wishes.
"Morgan, you've disobeyed me.
It must stop."
"Stop?
But do you not see this son of mine, Mordred?
He will one day rule with a power you have
never imagined!"
Merlin raised his hand to destroy what he
had helped create in Morgan, but she turned
herself into a mirror, and his spell was reflected
back on him, banishing him from the earth
forever.
Morgan turned back into the woman she was,
and looked at her stolen child.
"Mordred, now nothing will come between you
and the throne."
CHAPTER NINE
Message.
England now became more divided than it had
ever been, as the round table had broken up.
Violent battles in the countryside divided
the duty of the King's men between searching
for the Holy Grail and defending the King's
rule.
Arthur stayed at the castle more often as
he felt there was something missing in this
search for the truth the Grail was supposed
to offer.
Guinevere went to speak to the King because
she understood his trouble.
"It's Lancelot.
You have acted unfairly.
Until you find him, and peace within yourself,
the country will never be united."
Guinevere's mentioning Lancelot's name filled
Arthur's heart with feelings of guilt.
He was so overwhelmed by those feelings that
he was finally able to accept that this was
the truth for him.
"I have also wronged you, my Queen!
I shall ride from the castle and not return
without Lancelot, so that we may be united
again in our love for one another."
Arthur called the last of his men together
to ride in search of the most honoured knight
in Camelot, Sir Lancelot.
As the men passed a certain tree in a valley,
the tree changed into the form of Morgan Le
Fay.
"Your end is near, Arthur.
My time is just beginning."
Morgan rose in the air as an eagle, and she
flew to Avalon to meet her starving son.
Mordred was hungry because he had never met
another human, and his mother filled his head
with ideas that he was a great leader whose
men would follow him to the ends of the earth.
His voice was rough and undisciplined, as
he had never spoken with others.
He yelled to the sky as the eagle approached
him.
"I will die if I do not kill and become King!"
Morgan landed beside the evil person she had
created.
His eyes searched hers like an animal's and
he breathed heavily as she spoke in his ear.
"It is time, Mordred.
You shall be King!
Climb onto my back and follow me to your glory!"
At that moment, it was no longer Morgan, his
mother, who stood beside him but a large,
shining black horse with wings.
Mordred mounted the animal and let out a sound
like no one - human or beast - had ever made.
It shook the whole island and Mordred, on
his horse, flew over the waves to England
to claim what he believed was his.
Merlin saw all of this, but from a world,
most people would never know.
He had banished himself from the earth by
not respecting the art of magic he had been
taught to use wisely.
Yet he knew that Morgan could still hear his
voice.
He had a message for her, and he was about
to deliver it.
CHAPTER TEN
Arthur Fights Mordred.
Two separate forces inhabited the land of
England.
Arthur, in the east, fought and won battles
to reunite the country.
Mordred, in the west, destroyed whatever stood
in his way.
It was the two men's destiny to meet.
Their battle would determine the fate of England.
A river separated Arthur and Mordred's men
as they prepared to face each other.
They agreed to fight to the death at dawn,
with the winner taking complete control of
the country.
Mordred fell asleep that night as his mother
was talking to him of his future victory.
Arthur slept thinking of not being able to
find Lancelot.
Arthur dreamed that he saw Lancelot waiting
for him.
Sir Gawain was there watching them.
Each time Arthur approached Lancelot, Lancelot
moved away, warning the King that they were
being watched.
Arthur also saw a woman running.
He ran after her, but before he could touch
her dress, she flew up into the air, leaving
him staring at the empty sky.
He saw Merlin's face and he woke up terrified.
The woman was not Guinevere, he knew it, and
he began to realise that he had been cruelly
deceived.
Arthur went to where Sir Gawain lay asleep.
He woke him, touching him on the chest with
Excalibur.
"Sir Gawain, how deep was your jealousy of
Sir Lancelot?"
Sir Gawain could not move.
He was held paralysed by Excalibur's force.
"As deep as my love for you, my King!"
Arthur lifted the sword and walked to the
river bank.
A strip of golden daylight broke the horizon.
The sun had risen, and Arthur promised to
fight in the name of Sir Lancelot, a knight
whose faith and honour he had judged unfairly.
Morgan woke in a place where there was no
sun, only clouds of smoke.
She called for Mordred; she ran through the
smoke, only to find herself again in the same
spot, surrounded by the same rising smoke.
She tried to change herself into something
which would take her away from this awful
place, but she could not.
Her powers had left her.
Merlin's voice spoke to her.
"Those who do not respect the magic they practise
are condemned to wander worlds where their
powers are useless.
I see worlds no man or woman could imagine.
You will see a world no person would want
to."
As Merlin's voice faded, Morgan realised that
she was completely alone - forever.
She let out a horrible scream into the emptiness
- a scream which only she would hear.
Mordred was uneasy without his mother at his
side.
Yet his animal instincts and his desire for
blood led him into battle.
The fighting was the most violent England
had ever seen.
Knights who once had been united now fought
each other.
Knights on horseback, in the river below,
killed each other without feeling.
The river turned red with their blood.
Mordred fought his way to the other side of
the river.
Arthur had been waiting for him.
When he saw Mordred approach him, snarling
like a dog, Arthur drew Excalibur.
They fought, and though Mordred was trained
well, he was no match for King Arthur and
Excalibur.
His true strength had left him when his mother
disappeared.
Arthur stood over Mordred's wounded body,
about to put an end to Mordred's evil existence.
As he raised Excalibur above his head, a knight
from the battle approached.
It was Lancelot, who had returned to defend
the King.
Arthur stopped and stared.
His heart leapt with joy.
Mordred quickly picked up his sword and wounded
Arthur deeply in his right side.
Arthur took Excalibur and put an end to the
ugly life which was Mordred, before he himself
fell to the ground.
"My King, it is I who have injured you.
You turned your head for my benefit."
"Lancelot, I am dying, but there is no better
sight than you before I do.
I ask your forgiveness for not believing in
your loyalty."
"You have it and anything else I can offer
you."
"Take Excalibur to a dark valley far away
from the kingdom, far from sight and sound.
When you reach the crystal lake that lies
in it, throw the sword in its water.
I was not the King it was meant for."
"If that is your wish, it is my command."
Lancelot rode through the night.
As the sun rose behind the mountains, which
surrounded the lake he stood before, he threw
Excalibur into it with all the strength in
his body.
As he watched it fly through the air and into
the lake, his eyes widened as he saw a woman's
hand reach out of the water to grab its handle.
It held it straight above the water for a
moment, then pulled it fast below.
Lancelot understood then that no man in his
lifetime would unite all of England.
He left the lake hoping that one-day one man
would.
- THE END -