The End of a Dream
Paul McCartney once said, The Beatles were
always a great little band - nothing more,
nothing less.'
Millions of fans around the world disagree
with this.
To them, the Beatles were a 'great little
band' who changed modern music forever.
When the Beatles ended in 1970, people around
the world couldn't believe it.
John, Paul, George and Ringo all followed
their own interests successfully.
But all four faced the same question everywhere
they went: 'When will you play together again?'
The answer always seemed the same - never
- but fans could hope and dream.
Then, on 8 December 1980, the dream ended.
John Lennon and Yoko Ono were returning home
to their building in New York.
Mark Chapman was waiting in the shadows.
He shouted to John and then he shot the singer
in the back and chest.
John Lennon died in hospital that night.
The news was met with sadness all around the
world.
The Beatles could never play together again.
Early Days
The four boys from Liverpool were all born
during the Second World War.
Life in the northern city wasn't always easy
after the war.
Most people lived in small houses and many
were poor.
But like many ports, Liverpool was open to
new ideas.
Sometimes ships brought something that other
places in Britain couldn't get - rock and
roll records from the US!
For the young people of Liverpool in the 1950s,
the exciting sound of rock and roll was an
escape from their daily lives.
Richard Starkey (Ringo Starr) was born in
1940 and grew up in one of Liverpool's poorest
areas.
He was often ill, and he first played drums
in hospital.
He bought his first drum around 1956 - just
one big drum!
He played with a few local bands.
Then he joined Rory Storm and the Hurricanes.
Around this time, Richard took a new name
- 'Ringo' - because of all the rings on his
hands.
George Harrison, the youngest Beatle, was
born in 1943.
His father was a bus driver, but before that
he worked on ships.
George loved his father's records from the
US.
At school, he sat in class drawing pictures
of guitars.
When he did get his guitar, he practiced all
the time.
Paul McCartney was born in 1942, the son of
a nurse and a cotton salesman.
The family loved music.
When Paul was old enough, his father bought
him a trumpet.
But Paul couldn't play the trumpet and sing
at the same time.
So he changed the trumpet for a guitar.
He sometimes talked about music with a younger
boy at his school - George Harrison.
John Lennon was born in 1940.
After his father left, his mother sent the
four-year-old boy to his Aunt Mimi and her
husband's big house in a pleasant part of
Liverpool.
John loved rock and roll.
He remembered seeing an Elvis Presley film.
When the audience screamed, he thought, 'That's
a good job!'
John's mother loved music too - and she taught
her son well.
He started a band, the Quarry Men.
The name came from his school, Quarry Bank.
One afternoon in July 1957, a friend took
Paul to see the Quarry Men at a church garden
party.
John was singing, but he couldn't remember
all the words.
This didn't stop him - he sang new words.
After the concert, Paul played a song on his
guitar for John.
Years later, John remembered the meeting.
Paul was better than the people in the band,
but John was a little worried.
What was more important: his own strong position
in the group, or a stronger group?
He chose the group.
Lennon and McCartney were together.
From Liverpool to Hamburg
One day, Paul showed John one of his own songs.
After that, John began to write his own musical
ideas, and soon the two young men were writing
song after song.
Sometimes they worked together, sometimes
alone.
But each of them pushed himself harder because
of the other one.
This was true during all the Beatles years.
Not long after Paul joined, he told John about
his friend George.
John wasn't sure - George was only fifteen.
But George joined after John heard him play.
They were on the top of a bus at the time!
Soon John, Paul and George were playing concerts
in Liverpool, but there was a problem.
They didn't have a drummer or a bass guitarist.
One of John's art-school friends, Stu Sutcliffe,
looked like James Dean and he was an artist.
When he sold a painting, the boys in the band
asked him to buy a bass guitar.
Stu wanted to be in a band, but there was
one small problem: he couldn't play.
Stu often turned his back to the crowds in
concerts because of this!
What's in a name?
John and Stu probably thought of the name
'the Beatles', but there are other stories.
John wrote that, at twelve years old, he was
told the name by a little man.
There was a more serious story, too: they
heard it in a Marlon Brando film, The Wild
One.
But many years later, Paul McCartney named
a 1997 album Flaming Pie, for the place where
John saw his little man!
People were starting to like the band.
The Beatles got a job playing with a rock
and roll singer, Johnny Gentle.
They toured Scotland under the name the Silver
Beetles.
For a time, Paul played drums because they
couldn't find a drummer.
Then, back in Liverpool, they were offered
another job.
Bands were needed to play in clubs in the
German city of Hamburg.
The band said yes - but first they needed
a drummer.
They asked Pete Best, the drummer in another
local band (and the owner of some nice drums!).
Pete agreed and the band travelled to Germany
in the summer of 1960.
To five boys from Liverpool, Hamburg was another
world - a world of all-night bars and street
crime.
Concerts weren't always easy.
On some nights, John had to push people off
the stage.
To keep audiences happy, bands had to play
well for six or seven hours every night.
With all this practice, the band became better
and better.
Another of the Liverpool bands in Hamburg
was called Rory Storm and the Hurricanes.
The band was famous in Liverpool.
The band's drummer loved to come and watch
the Beatles.
Sometimes, when Pete Best was ill, he even
played with the band.
His name was Ringo Starr.
The first trip to Hamburg ended suddenly.
George was sent home by the police because
he was too young to play in the clubs - he
was only seventeen.
But the Beatles returned often to Hamburg.
Each time they played to bigger crowds in
better clubs.
In The Cavern
On their second trip to Hamburg, a record
producer asked the Beatles to play on a record
for the singer Tony Sheridan.
The song was 'My Bonnie Lies Over the Ocean'
and they played as the Beat Brothers.
The boys were becoming successful.
But one of the band decided that he didn't
want to be a Beatle.
Stu met a young photographer, Astrid Kirchherr,
in Hamburg.
Her photos of the band later became famous.
She also helped the band's look.
One day, she cut Stu's hair.
At first, the others in the band laughed - they
all pushed their hair back off their faces
like rock and roll singers.
But later John, Paul and George all had the
same haircut.
After the band's second trip to Hamburg, Stu
decided to stay there.
He was in love with Astrid and he wanted to
study art in Hamburg.
Paul never had a high opinion of Stu's playing,
and he started to play the bass.
Back in Liverpool, people were interested
in the new band 'from Hamburg'.
At first, someone told John, 'You speak good
English.'
But the band became more and more popular
in their home city.
They often played at a club called The Cavern.
Hundreds of fans crowded into the small, dark
club when the Beatles played there.
The band was famous now in Liverpool, but
was that enough?
Everything changed when they met Brian Epstein.
He was the manager of a big music shop in
the city.
When he heard about the Beatles, he went to
The Cavern.
In his suit and tie, Epstein probably looked
very different from The Cavern's young crowd.
In his opinion, the band were a little rough.
But, he has said.
'I immediately liked what I heard.'
Epstein met the band and offered to become
their manager.
When he promised to make an agreement with
a record company, the band said yes!
Brian Epstein immediately gave the band new
rules.
They couldn't eat, drink or smoke on stage.
The four young men started wearing suits.
Epstein worked hard for the band and on the
last day of 1962, they drove down to London.
They played for Decca, a big record company,
but it didn't go well.
Two months later, the company said no to Brian
Epstein and the Beatles.
In their opinion, guitar bands weren't popular
now.
Worse news came from Germany.
Stu was ill with terrible headaches.
He died in April 1962, a day before the Beatles'
third trip to Hamburg.
He was only twenty-one.
During the band's third trip to Hamburg, they
received a message from their manager.
Another record company, Parlophone - part
of the big company EMI - wanted to hear them
in the studio.
On Their Way!
In June 1962, the Beatles were in London again
- this time, at the Abbey Road studios.
George Martin was one of the producers who
was listening to them for the record company.
Martin didn't like their songs much, but he
liked the boys.
After the Beatles finished playing, he showed
them around the studio.
The band were quiet.
'Is there anything you don't like?' asked
Martin.
Finally, George spoke.
'Well, I don't like your tie.'
The fifth Beatle?
Before the Beatles, the producer George Martin
mainly produced records of funny songs.
But Martin knew a lot about music and about
recording.
Over the years, he helped the Beatles to grow
as musicians.
At first, he was really the boss.
But after a time, the band told him what they
wanted.
A few weeks later, Martin called Brian Epstein.
Yes, the band could make a record with him...
but not with Pete Best on drums.
In the producers opinion, Pete wasn't good
enough.
It was a hard decision for the band, but Pete
had to go.
The drummer was angry when Brian Epstein told
him the news.
The next decision was easier.
In Paul's words, they wanted 'the greatest
drummer in Liverpool' - their friend from
Hamburg, Ringo Starr.
Epstein called Ringo on a Wednesday and asked
him to join the band.
By Saturday, Ringo was the new drummer.
Some fans weren't happy about the change.
At The Cavern, a few people shouted angrily
and held up signs: 'Pete is Best!'
The married Beatle
Before they went back to London John married
his girlfriend, Cynthia.
Marriage to a Beatle wasn't easy.
John was often away from home.
When their son Julian was born in 1963, fans
even ran after John at the hospital.
Later, the Beatles didn't want their young
fans to know that one of the band was married.
After their first tour of the US, a reporter
asked John, 'Did your wife like the country?'
John joked, 'Who?
Who?'
The band recorded their first single, 'Love
Me Do', at Abbey Road in September 1962.
It was one of Paul's songs.
Fans wrote to radio stations, asking them
to play the record.
By December 1962, the song was quite successful
at number seventeen.
The Beatles were on their way!
Beatlemania
It was time to choose a song for the important
second record.
George Martin didn't like any of John and
Paul's songs at the time, so he chose a new
song.
The group said no.
They wanted to do one of their songs.
Today many bands write their own songs, but
at the time this was a brave decision for
a new band.
Finally, Martin agreed to record one of John's
songs, 'Please Please Me'.
At first it was a slow song, but the producer
asked them to play it faster.
After they recorded it, Martin told them,
'You have just recorded your first number
one.'
The Beatles worked hard to make this true.
They drove all over Britain to concerts.
Sometimes they stopped the van to listen to
their own song on the radio.
Once the van was freezing after the front
window broke.
The Beatles lay together in the back to keep
warm!
In March 1963, 'Please Please Me' reached
number one.
George Martin was right.
After that, number one followed number one.
Their singles in 1963 were 'From Me to You',
'She Loves You' and 'I Want to Hold Your Hand'.
Suddenly, everybody loved the Beatles.
When the band played in concert, police had
to hold back crowds of screaming fans - mainly
girls.
One newspaper thought of a new word to describe
the country's love of the boys from Liverpool
- 'Beatlemania'!
Every Beatles single reached number one until
1967.
The band also recorded their first album early
in 1963.
George Martin asked them to come to the studio
and play all the songs from their live show.
They did this... in one long day!
The album Please Please Me was recorded in
about twelve hours.
It went to number one, too.
'America was ours!'
The Beatles were selling millions of records
in Britain.
The Sunday Times newspaper compared Lennon
and McCartney with Beethoven.
But many of the group's fans had other things
on their minds.
A lot of young fans dreamt about their favorite
Beatle:
Paul was the sweet, romantic one.
George was the quiet one.
Ringo was the happy, funny one.
John was the intelligent one.
He often made jokes, but they weren't always
kind.
Follow the leader
In the very early days, John was the band's
leader.
When the band became successful, his position
wasn't so clear.
Both he and Paul wrote songs and sang for
the band.
In front of the cameras, Paul often spoke
for the band, but John usually had the last
word.
To George, John was always the strongest person
in the group.
Years after John's death, he said, 'I think
he is still the leader now, probably.'
At the beginning of 1964, the Beatles were
the most popular band in Britain.
They were famous in Europe, but they were
still a little nervous about the United States.
Many English stars looked for success across
the Atlantic before the Beatles, but failed.
The Beatles' first singles in the US didn't
do very well.
But interest grew, and finally 'I Want to
Hold Your Hand' reached number one.
The band flew there in February 1964.
They all knew how important this trip was.
In Ringo's words, America was all that they
dreamt about years earlier.
The trip was a big success.
When the band played on TV's The Ed Sullivan
Show, they were watched by an American TV
audience of almost seventy-three million people.
It was one of the most important shows in
the history of popular music.
The Beatles played in Washington and Miami,
and went home happy.
As Ringo said, 'America was ours now.'
The band were world stars.
The Beatles returned to the United States
later in 1964, as part of a big world tour.
This trip was as successful as the last one.
Ringo remembers that 'it was just so much
fun.
As usual, nobody could hear the music at the
concerts because of the screams of the fans.
At this time it wasn't a big problem for the
band, but it became more and more important
later.
George's memory of this tour was less happy
than Ringo's.
President Kennedy was killed only a year before,
and George didn't want anyone to shoot one
of the Beatles.
Up and Up
After the first American tour, the Beatles
turned to another world - films.
They made A Hard Day's Night in the spring
of 1964.
The title of the film and the song of the
same name was something that Ringo said.
The rest of the band often laughed at the
drummer's unusual way of saying things.
The film's writer, Alan Owen, spent a few
days with the band.
The Beatles were funny, and the film showed
this.
Owen also understood the band's daily life.
For much of the film, they were running away
from screaming fans.
The band liked making the film, but George
probably enjoyed it most.
He fell in love with one of the actresses,
Patti Boyd.
They were married in 1966.
The black-and-white film was first shown in
London and Liverpool.
It was a big success.
(The album was, too.
This time, all the songs were by Lennon and
McCartney.)
Many people really liked Ringo's acting in
the film.
Some even called him 'the new Charlie Chaplin'.
But Ringo remembers that he came straight
from a club for one very funny part.
He says that he wasn't acting much!
John and Paul's musical ideas were growing
all the time.
Each new song was different and exciting.
A different sound
John and Paul were both big fans of Bob Dylan's
music.
The subjects and language in the young American's
songs were always unusual and interesting.
The song 'I'm a Loser' on the album Beatles
for Sale, at the end of 1964, sounded a little
like a Dylan song.
The same was true of the following year's
'You've Got to Hide Your Love Away'.
John even found time to write a book in 1964.
John Lennon In His Own Write was full of funny
short stories and pictures.
It didn't have any serious meaning.
In the introduction Paul wrote, 'If it seems
funny, then that's enough.'
John wrote another book the next year.
In early 1965, the Beatles made their second
film.
After the success of A Hard Day's Night, there
was more money.
But the band just wanted to travel and have
a good time.
'We started saying, "We've never been to the
Bahamas.
Could you write that in?"'
Paul remembers.
As George said later, 'We had fun in those
days.'
But John remembered it differently.
This wasn't a happy time for him.
'You can't see it but I'm singing "Help!"'
he said.
'Here to stay'
Later in 1965, Paul wrote one of the most
popular songs of all time.
Yesterday was a beautiful, sad song about
lost love.
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
The music for Yesterday' came to Paul in a
dream.
He 'just woke up one morning' with the song
in his head.
At first, he thought it was an old song.
But none of his friends knew it.
The first words to the song were about eggs!
George Martin loved the song immediately.
But, in his opinion, it needed something different.
Paul recorded it without the rest of the band.
He played the guitar alone, while a small
group of musicians played strings.
The song is one of the band's most famous
- it has been recorded by many different singers
and groups and in many different ways.
Paul was sometimes angry when people called
it their favorite Beatles song.
The King and the Queen
In August, the Beatles were back in the United
States.
Fifty-six thousand fans saw them at a concert
in New York.
At the time, it was the biggest concert crowd
ever.
The concert was exciting, but Ringo's memories
of it weren't good.
At times John was joking too much on stage,
in Ringo's opinion.
Also, not many people at the concert really
heard the band.
Like most Beatles concerts, the sound of the
crowd was louder than the music.
The Beatles couldn't hear much of the music
either.
So, of course, it was difficult to play well.
'I always wanted to play with good players,'
remembers Ringo.
But now the band was playing badly on stage,
and nobody was listening.
On the same tour, the Beatles met one of their
favourite singers - Elvis Presley.
'It was one of the great meetings of my life,'
Paul has said.
The boys and the 'King' had a good time.
But years later the band discovered that Elvis
was worried about the Beatles' success in
his country.
He asked the American government to send them
home.
Back in Britain, the government gave all the
Beatles the MBE.
This award was often given to successful businesspeople
or to people who fought bravely for their
country.
Many Britons were angry.
How could the government give this award to
a pop group?
But the usual crowd of screaming fans were
outside Buckingham Palace when the Queen gave
them the award in October 1965.
The Beatles were nervous - George later remembered
that they rested and had a cigarette in the
toilets in Buckingham Palace!
Rubber Soul
The next album, Rubber Soul, came out in December
1965.
It was another big step for the band.
They were exploring different kinds of music
and different subjects.
'In My Life' was a beautiful song about places
and people in the past.
Even the album's love songs weren't the simple
love songs of the band's early days.
One of the most interesting songs on the album
was John's 'Norwegian Wood'.
Many people wanted to know what the song meant.
It was about a girl, but he didn't want his
wife Cynthia to know this.
George played the Indian musical instrument
the sitar on 'Norwegian Wood'.
He first noticed the instrument in an Indian
restaurant in the film Help!
This was the start of George's long interest
in Indian music and ideas.
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
Around the time of Rubber Soul, the single
'Day Tripper' 'We Can Work It Out' reached
number one.
Paul wrote most of 'We Can Work It Out' and
John wrote the middle part.
This song showed the differences between the
two men clearly.
The main part was more hopeful, as Paul sang,
'Try to see it my way...'
John's part of the song was less hopeful:
'Life is very short and there's no time...'
The band's success continued with Paul's 'Paperback
Writer' in 1966.
It was their first single that wasn't about
love.
The music was becoming less and less simple,
too.
But now the Beatles faced a new problem - how
could they play the songs in concert?
'Beatles go home!'
In June 1966, the Beatles were in Hamburg
again to begin a new tour.
Then they flew to Tokyo and the tour began
to go wrong.
There were many Beatles fans in Japan.
But some people there thought the group was
a bad example to young people.
The band had to stay in their hotel.
They only came out to play in concert.
Things became worse in the Philippines.
In George's words, it was 'bad news' from
the beginning.
The real problem came after the concert in
Manila.
Imelda Marcos, the wife of the country's leader,
invited the band to a party.
The band's answer was a polite no.
(Some of them can't even remember the invitation.)
The next day, something was clearly wrong.
Nobody at the hotel brought breakfast for
the band.
Then they turned on the television and suddenly
they understood: they saw Imelda Marcos in
tears!
The camera showed crying children and the
empty dinner table.
In George's words, 'We watched ourselves not
arriving.'
The people of the Philippines were very angry.
As the band drove to the airport, crowds shouted,
Beatles go home!
The band was pushed around at the airport
and their road manager was knocked over.
Before they could leave, Brian Epstein was
called off the airplane.
He had to give back all the money from the
band's concert there.
Years later, Paul knew more about Marcos's
government.
Then he was happy about missing the garden
party.
Ringo has said about the country, 'I've never
been back
The Sound of the Future
The 1966 tour wasn't a happy one, but in the
studio that year the band were going into
exciting new areas.
George Martin had to find newer and newer
sounds to record the band's ideas.
The album Revolver was his favorite.
The album was important for all the Beatles
in different ways:
George was growing as a song writer.
At first, it was difficult for the guitarist.
His very early songs weren't strong, and he
was in a band with two of the most famous
songwriters in the world.
In Revolvers 'Love You To', he showed his
continuing interest in Indian music.
His best song on the album was probably 'Taxman'.
The band liked Ringo to sing a song on every
album.
Paul decided to give the drummer a song that
wasn't very serious.
He thought of 'Yellow Submarine' one night
in bed.
Paul continued to write about new subjects
and to explore new kinds of music.
'Eleanor Rigby' was a sad song about the lives
of lonely people in a big city.
Again, strings were used, and McCartney recorded
the song without the other Beatles.
'We were just drinking tea,' said George.
John was exploring, too.
With the songs 'She Said She Said' and Tomorrow
Never Knows', he went into strange new musical
areas.
Tomorrow Never Knows' was like a promise of
the wild music at the end of the 1960s.
Listen to this song and compare it to any
song from the Beatles' first two or three
albums.
A lot changed in those few years!
Burning Records
In 1966, John spoke to a reporter in London.
They were talking about the modern church,
and he said, 'We're more popular than Jesus
now.'
When John's words were reported in the US
a few months later, many people were angry.
There were newspaper stories like 'Lennon
Says that the Beatles are Bigger than Jesus'.
This wasn't what John meant.
But some shops refused to sell their records.
Some radio stations refused to play them.
A few radio stations asked listeners to burn
their Beatles records.
Years later, Ringo joked, 'It was OK for us,
because then they bought them again!'
But at the time, the band and their manager
were worried.
So what did John mean?
He tried to explain his words to the American
people before the band toured the country
again.
'I was just saying it as a fact,' he explained.
'It is true - more for England than here.
I'm not saying that we're better or greater...
I'm sorry that I opened my mouth.'
It was a bad start to the Beatles last tour.
The End of Touring
The tour continued, but it wasn't a happy
time.
Some newspapers in the United States were
against the band now.
For the first time, there were a few empty
seats at some concerts.
But it was still impossible to hear the music
because of the screams.
As George said, touring wasn't 'fun' now.
Also, their lives were different.
Only one Beatle - Paul - wasn't married.
It was time to stop travelling.
At first, Paul wanted to tour more, but finally
he agreed with the others.
On 29 August 1966, they played at Candlestick
Park in San Francisco.
They played eleven songs, finishing with 'I'm
Down'.
It was the Beatles' last concert.
The band faced a new question: what now?
In his heart, John thought, 'This is the end,
really.'
For some time the Beatles all did different
things:
George spent a few weeks in India.
Paul worked with George Martin on the music
for a film, The Family Way.
The music won an award.
John went to Spain to act in a film, How I
Won the War.
It wasn't a good film, and John wasn't a good
actor.
But he did come back wearing the famous small,
round 'John Lennon glasses'!
Ringo spent a few weeks in Spain with John,
and he enjoyed time at home with his wife
and child.
Back in the studio, the band felt more free.
Now they didn't have to play any new songs
on stage.
They could do anything, and they did - with
George Martin's help.
The next songs were another big step into
new musical areas.
But they also looked back, as both John and
Paul turned to their Liverpool past for 'Strawberry
Fields Forever' and 'Penny Lane'.
STORY BEHIND THE SONGS
When he was a child, John lived near a children's
home.
The home was called Strawberry Field.
John's song 'Strawberry Fields Forever' wasn't
really about that place; it just took the
home's name.
The line 'Nothing is real' perfectly described
this strange, beautiful song.
Paul then wrote a song about Liverpool, too.
'Penny Lane' was a much happier song, describing
people and places from the old days in Liverpool.
The band was still using instruments that
were unusual in pop records.
A trumpet played on the song.
There were many differences between Paul and
John.
Paul was very interested in studio recording.
He worked carefully with George Martin.
John had little time for this.
He just told the producer what he wanted.
In fact, the band played Strawberry Fields
Forever' in two very different ways.
John couldn't choose his favorite.
Finally, the producer joined the two.
(Years later, John wasn't happy about this
recording of his song.)
Together, 'Strawberry Fields Forever' and
'Penny Lane' became the Beatles' next single.
It was a great record, but for the first time
in years the band didn't reach number one.
The Most Famous Album in the World
In the opinion of some newspapers in early
1967, the Beatles didn't have any more ideas.
And then came Sergeant Pepper's Lonely Hearts
Club Band.
The title song was Paul's.
He had the idea after a trip to the United
States.
Bands with very long names were becoming popular
there.
Paul wanted the Beatles to be a different
band for the album.
In his mind, the album was a concert by this
other band.
John and George didn't see the album in this
way.
'It doesn't go anywhere,' John once said about
the Sergeant Pepper idea.
But there were great songs on the album.
Songs like 'When I'm Sixty-Four' and 'With
a Little Help From My Friends' were happy
and light.
John took almost all the words for 'Being
for the Benefit of Mr Kite' from an old sign
that he found in a shop.
The words and the music of 'Lucy in the Sky
With Diamonds' were like a dream.
The title came from a picture by John's young
son, Julian.
'A Day in the Life' was one of the best examples
of Paul and John's strong points.
John wrote the main part of the song, beginning
'I read the news today, oh boy.'
The idea came from two newspaper stories.
Paul added the middle part.
It worked perfectly in John's song.
The album was a big step in the band's music.
They used the studio wonderfully, but this
took a long time.
The Beatles' first album was made in around
twelve hours, but Sergeant Pepper took over
700 hours!
Both Ringo and George said later that it was
sometimes boring.
'My heart was still in India,' George said.
Famous faces
Everything about the album was special - even
the cover.
It showed the band with a crowd of famous
people - writers, singers, actors, thinkers.
At first there was a photo of Mahatma Gandhi,
but the record company asked the band to take
it off.
They didn't want to make people in India angry.
Today, fans disagree about which is the best
Beatles album.
But most of them believe that Sergeant Pepper
was the most important.
The world was changing fast in 1967.
While the American war in Vietnam continued,
young people around the world were exploring
new ideas, new sounds.
The summer of 1967 became known as 'the summer
of love'.
Sergeant Pepper helped to make that summer.
Life and Death
Not long after Sergeant Pepper, the Beatles
were invited to play in a live television
programme called Our World.
Different countries had to make different
parts of the show, and the makers of the programme
wanted the Beatles to play for Britain's part.
John wrote the song and on 25 June 1967, about
350 million people all around the world watched
the programme.
The Beatles weren't alone in the television
studio.
A lot of other musicians played and it was
like a big party.
Eric Clapton and Mick Jagger were both there.
John's song was perfect for the programme:
'All You Need Is Love' was a mirror for the
dreams and hopes of young people around the
world in 1967.
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
At the end of 'All You Need Is Love', the
Beatles joked about two of their old songs.
John sang 'Yesterday' and Paul sang a line
from 'She Loves You'.
Around this time, George was continuing to
learn more about Eastern ideas.
He asked John and Paul to listen to a talk
by the Maharishi Mahesh Yogi in London.
The Maharishi was an Indian who taught Eastern
ways of thinking.
The Beatles wanted to know more.
In August, all four of them took a train to
Bangor in North Wales.
They wanted to spend a few days studying with
the Maharishi.
A sad sign
Cynthia Lennon wanted to go too, but the usual
Beatles crowds were at the train station and
Cynthia missed the train.
She watched as her husband left without her.
For her, this was a sign of the end of their
marriage.
While the Beatles were searching for the meaning
of life, sad news reached them from London.
Brian Epstein was dead.
'He was one of us,' John told a reporter.
On the Bus
Epstein's death brought another problem.
The Beatles knew nothing about business.
'We were in trouble then,' said John.
Ringo has described the band as 'chickens
without heads' at that time.
In the middle of this difficult time, Paul
had an idea.
He wanted to make a television film.
He was trying to help the band, but in John
and George's opinion, Paul was trying to lead
them.
The idea for the film was simple.
Forty-three people - with the Beatles - drove
around the country in a bus.
This time, they didn't have a story to act.
They just filmed what happened.
There was one problem - nothing really did
happen.
Magical Mystery Tour was shown on television
in Britain just after Christmas, 1967.
Almost fifteen million people watched.
They loved the songs, like Paul's The Fool
on the Hill' and Johns 'I Am the Walrus'.
But not many people liked the film.
The color film was shown in black and white
on television.
But this wasn't the reason why it wasn't popular.
For some people it was boring, for others
it was too strange.
For the first time, the Beatles really failed.
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
The idea for 'I Am The Walrus' came from Lewis
Carroll's book Alice in Wonderland.
John said, 'The words don't say a lot...'
In February 1968, the Beatles travelled to
India to study again with the Maharishi.
The trip had a different meaning for each
of them.
Ringo went with two suitcases - one of clothes
and one of English food in tins!
He didn't stay long.
Paul says that he enjoyed this time in India.
But John and George stayed longer.
George continued to defend the Maharishi,
but John soon became angry at their old teacher.
A song on the band's next album was an angry
attack on him.
Back in Britain, there were no simple answers
in business for the Beatles.
They opened the Apple shop in London.
Paul called it 'a beautiful place where you
can buy beautiful things.'
The shop lost money almost immediately.
But Apple was more than a shop.
It was a big company that produced music and
films.
The Beatles began to produce other musicians.
Paul was most interested in Apple's business.
He was there more because he lived in London.
But the others felt that Paul was trying to
lead the band again.
Yellow Submarine
In July 1968, there was another Beatles film
in cinemas.
The band recorded a few new songs for Yellow
Submarine, but they didn't even do the voices
in the film.
In the story, the band saved a strange place
called Pepperland with their music.
A New Album and a New Love
In 1968, Cynthia and John Lennon's marriage
ended.
John was with Yoko Ono now.
He first met the Japanese-American artist
at an art show in 1966 and they slowly fell
in love.
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
Paul felt sorry for Cynthia and Julian Lennon.
The boy was only five.
Paul wrote a song for him.
He later changed the words from 'Hey Jules'
to 'Hey Jude'.
Everything changed for John with Yoko.
He often spoke of her as his teacher.
Together they explored new ideas.
These were called crazy by many people, but
John and Yoko weren't worried.
They made their first record together in one
night.
It was an exploration of sounds.
But the biggest news was the cover.
It showed John and Yoko without any clothes.
'We just wanted to be together all the time,'
remembered John.
John and Yoko were together in the studio,
too, as the Beatles started their next album.
This soon became a problem for the other Beatles.
Ringo asked him, 'What's this all about?'
The other two and George Martin were angrier.
When Yoko was ill, John even brought a bed
into the studio for her!
In 1968 the Beatles' White Album had other
problems.
Ringo left the band for a time.
(The band recorded a few songs without him.)
In his opinion, the other Beatles didn't need
him.
When they all asked him back, the drummer
returned happily.
'I loved the White Album', he remembers now.
But not everyone had this opinion.
John spoke about the start of the band's 'slow
death' at this time.
The musical interests in the band were more
and more different.
The Beatles were less and less a real group.
Sometimes the album was recorded in three
different studios at the same time, as John,
Paul and George worked on their own songs.
The double album mixed many different kinds
of music.
'Ob-La-Di, Ob-La-Da' was a happy pop song,
while 'Revolution 9' was a strange piece of
sound art.'
In 'Back in the USSR' the band cleverly sounded
like the Beach Boys.
George's best song on the album was probably
'While My Guitar Gently Weeps'.
His friend Eric Clapton joined the band to
play on this song.
Secret messages
Two songs from the album later became famous
for the wrong reasons.
In the mind of Californian Charles Manson,
the songs 'Piggies' and 'Helter Skelter' were
secret messages telling him to kill.
George Martin thought that there were too
many different songs on the double album.
He wanted it to be an excellent single album.
But Paul has said, 'It's a fine little album.'
John also liked the simpler way of recording.
An Unhappy Film and Two Weddings
At the start of 1969, the band needed new
plans.
Paul was full of ideas for the band's future.
They decided to write an album and then play
it on stage - all in front of cameras.
This was the start of Let It Be.
It was a bad time.
The band weren't happy together, and all the
cameras made everything worse.
George even left the band for a short time
after angry words with Paul.
Things only got better when a guest musician,
American Billy Preston, joined them.
The cameras filmed everything.
The cameramen didn't know it at the time,
but in fact they were recording the end of
the group.
The film Let It Be is difficult to watch at
times.
The idea of a big concert soon died.
Looking for a way to end the film, the band
decided to play a few songs on the Apple building's
roof.
People in London looked up in surprise as
the Beatles played 'Get Back' above them.
For a short time, the old days were back!
In Ringo's words, when the music was good,
they forgot all the problems.
Finally, the police asked the band to stop.
They never played live together again.
Producer George Martin didn't want to touch
the long Let It Be recordings.
So American Phil Spector took the job.
Finally, the Let It Be album came out after
the end of the Beatles.
Paul didn't like Spector's work on it.
Both he and George Martin hated the strings
on The Long and Winding Road'.
In 1969, Paul married for the first time and
John married for the second time.
Even the two marriages showed the differences
between the two men.
Paul married American photographer Linda Eastman
on 12 March.
They wanted a quiet wedding, but nothing could
be quiet for a Beatle.
Hundreds of fans cried as Paul and his new
wife drove away.
Weeks later, John and Yoko were married in
Gibraltar.
The story is told in the song 'The Ballad
of John and Yoko.'
Later, they invited reporters to a 'bed-in'
at their hotel.
They stayed in bed for seven days.
They wanted people to think about the meaning
of love.
(At a later 'bed-in', they recorded the song
'Give Peace a Chance'.)
John and Yoko gave their opinions on a lot
of subjects, like the Vietnam War.
John sent his MBE back to the British government.
He had more and more interests in his life,
and the band wasn't one of them.
But the Beatles stayed together for one more
record.
The Last Album
After the troubles on Let It Be, George Martin
was surprised to receive a telephone call
from Paul.
The band wanted to make another album.
Paul and Martin agreed to do one the 'old'
way - in the studio.
The album was named after the Abbey Road studio
in London, and the Beatles worked on it there
during July and August 1969.
John and Paul disagreed about some of their
ideas for the album.
Paul wanted to join all the songs together.
John just liked to do different 'three-minute
records'.
To keep both men happy, only the songs on
the second half of the record are joined together.
Abbey Road was a happy record to work on for
most of the time.
But not always.
When Paul took three days to record 'Maxwell's
Silver Hammer', George told him, 'It's only
a song.'
STORY BEHIND THE SONG
Abbey Road's 'Something' was the band's first
single written by George Harrison.
Many people think that it is his best song.
Later, Frank Sinatra often sang it on stage.
He described it as his favorite Lennon and
McCartney song.
Telling this story, Paul once joked, 'Thanks,
Frank.'
Nobody knew it at the time, but Abbey Road
was the last album.
But the band ended it well.
The last song was called 'The End.'
John, Paul and George all played guitar on
it.
All four Beatles were playing together as
a real band again.
You can hear the fun in the music.
Paul sang the last lines of the last album.
They were about love.
Paul Is dead!
After Abbey Road arrived in the shops in October
1969, a radio station in the US started a
strange story about Paul.
He was dead!
The 'signs' were on the album's cover.
Paul wasn't wearing shoes.
In some countries, dead people are dressed
in clothes but not shoes.
The story grew.
The hand over Paul's head on the cover of
Sergeant Pepper was, fans decided, a sign
of death.
A line in 'A Day in the Life' was also about
Paul's death.
More and more signs were found.
But if Paul was dead, who was the new person
on the front of Abbey Road?
The story became sillier.
It was a man called William Campbell.
Or it was Billy Shears (a singer's name from
the title song on Sergeant Pepper).
This new person looked exactly like Paul,
of course.
Finally, Life magazine found Paul on his farm
in Scotland.
The magazine proved it.
Paul wasn't dead.
Paul described himself as 'the last to know'
about his death.
Differences of Opinion
Even before Abbey Road, the Beatles' company
Apple was losing a lot of money.
Something had to change.
They needed someone to manage the business.
John wanted Allan Klein, the manager of the
Rolling Stones, to be the group's manager.
George and Ringo agreed, but Paul didn't.
He wanted Lee Eastman - his wife's father
- to manage Apple's business.
Paul was still full of ideas for the band
and the company, but it was too late.
In one meeting, John spoke about the end of
the Beatles: 'It feels good.'
In fact, Paul ended the band in 1970.
A few weeks after his first album McCartney
was in the shops, he told the world.
He was leaving the Beatles 'because of personal,
business and musical differences'.
The band was finished, but the fights about
business and money continued in court for
years.
It was a sad end for the greatest band in
the world.
Life After the Beatles
All four of the Beatles found success alone.
Ringo acted in a few films and he continued
to make records.
His 1973 album Ringo was a big success.
All the other Beatles played on this album...
but not at the same time.
Ringo is still playing and touring with his
All Starr Band.
Many of Ringo's famous friends from the world
of music - and his son, Zak - have played
in this band.
Many British children know and love Ringo
for another reason.
He was the voice of a train in a famous children's
television programme!
George seemed happy to be away from the shadows
of Lennon and McCartney.
His 1970 album All Things Must Pass reached
number one around the world.
George's most famous song in the 1970s was
'My Sweet Lord', but he was taken to court
because of it.
In the court's opinion, part of it was copied
from an old song.
In the early 1980s, George also played in
the Travelling Wilburys with Bob Dylan and
Roy Orbison.
George became interested in films, but not
as an actor.
He produced films like Monty Python's Life
of Brian and Time Bandits.
In 1999, someone failed to kill George in
his home.
But sadly, two years later, he died after
a long illness.
Paul has had the most success after the Beatles.
After the albums McCartney and Ram, he wanted
to be in a real band again.
In 1971 he started a new band, Wings, with
his wife Linda and guitarist Denny Laine.
At first, Wings drove all over Britain playing
small concerts.
It was like the old days of the Beatles again.
Wings soon became big.
1973's Band on the Run was Paul's most successful
album.
In 1977, the band recorded 'Mull of Kintyre'.
This song sold more than any other single
in Britain before that time.
Wings ended in 1981, but Paul continued making
records.
In 1997, he was back at Buckingham Palace.
He became Sir Paul McCartney.
Paul has sold millions of records since 1970,
but one of his biggest successes was his happy
family life with Linda and their children.
Sadly, in 1998, Linda McCartney died.
Paul now has another woman, Heather Mills,
in his life.
John and Yoko moved to New York.
They still spoke openly on many subjects,
and at one time the American government wanted
to throw him out of the country.
Some of John's most interesting work was on
his first two albums, John Lennon Plastic
Ono Band and Imagine.
On the first album, John sang painfully honest
songs about his mothers death.
In another song, he sang the words, 'I don't
believe in Beatles I just believe in me.'
The title song of Imagine is probably his
most famous song.
Most people think that John's later work in
the 1970s wasn't as good.
For some time, John and Yoko weren't together.
John called this his 'lost weekend', but it
lasted eighteen months.
Back with Yoko, John didn't make music for
a few years.
He looked after their son, Sean.
He returned to the recording studio in the
summer of 1980 to make Double Fantasy with
Yoko.
Much of the album was about family life.
One of the songs from the album, '(Just Like)
Starting Over' was doing well when John was
killed.
Friends again
The Beatles ended badly, and some of the band
were angry for a long time.
On 1971's Imagine, John's song 'How Do You
Sleep?'
was an attack on Paul.
(George Harrison was angry too - he played
guitar on the song.)
But finally, Paul and John became friendlier
again.
Paul visited John a few times in New York
after Sean Lennon's birth.
In 1994, years after John's death, both men
were given an important music award.
On stage, Paul read out a letter to John.
In it, he remembered their past together.
He ended, 'This letter comes, with love, from
your friend Paul.'
At the Top Again
The Beatles ruled the music world in the 1960s.
They had twenty-two singles in Britain, and
eighteen reached number one.
Every album of new songs got to number one.
In the United States, there were nineteen
number one singles.
Many people still think that they were the
world's greatest band of all time.
In one list of best albums, the top five were
all by the Beatles!
But the band's success wasn't just for their
musical past.
In 1995, the three living Beatles came together
to record two 'new' Beatles songs - 'Free
as a Bird' and 'Real Love'.
Both songs were by John.
The singer recorded them, but they weren't
finished.
Paul, George and Ringo worked with these recordings,
adding to them.
In their minds, they were finishing the music
for John while he worked on something else.
Fans could buy new Beatles records again!
They also loved the video for 'Free as a Bird'.
It showed people and places from the band's
past - Stu Sutcliffe, Brian Epstein, The Cavern,
the street outside the Abbey Road studios.
There were hundreds of memories of Beatles
songs.
A few are:
a cake with the number sixty-four ('When I'm
Sixty-Four')
a man writing a book ('Paperback Writer')
a photo of Mao Tse Tung (a line from 'Revolution')
a stone with the name Eleanor Rigby ('Eleanor
Rigby')
At the same time, the living Beatles told
their story in the television programme The
Beatles Anthology.
More than twenty million copies of the Anthology
albums were sold.
In 2000, there was a very successful album
of the Beatles' number one songs.
They made more money from the album than any
other British artist that year.
The Beatles were back in the right place - at
the top!
- THE END -