CHAPTER ONE
Beginnings
If you know Starkfield, Massachusetts, you
know the post office there. If you know the
post office, you have probably seen Ethan
Frome driving up to it in his buggy, and you
have probably wondered who he was.
It was there that, several years ago, I saw
him for the first time. He was a noticeable
figure. His tall, strong body was badly twisted,
and much shorter on the right side than on
the left. He moved slowly and painfully, pulling
himself along. Just the few steps from his
buggy to the post office were clearly difficult
for him. His face had a sad, grim look. It
was the face and body of an old man, and I
was surprised to hear that he was only fifty-two.
I learnt this from Harmon Gow, a man who knew
all the families around Starkfield.
'He's been like that since his bad accident,
nearly twenty-four years ago,' said Harmon.
'But Fromes don't die young. Ethan'll live
to a hundred, probably.'
'He looks like a dead man already,' I said.
'I guess he's been in Starkfield too many
winters,' said Harmon. 'Most smart people
get out of here.'
'Why didn't he get out?' I asked.
'He had to stay and take care of his family
- first his father got hurt, then his mother
fell sick, then his wife.'
'And then the accident?'
Harmon gave a little smile. 'That's right.
He had to stay then.'
Ethan Frome used to drive in from his farm
every day at about midday, and because I picked
up my mail at about the same time, I often
saw him. He came to the post office only for
a newspaper, and sometimes for a packet from
a medicine company for 'Mrs Zeena Frome'.
Starkfield people understood that he did not
want to stop and talk, and on most days Frome
climbed slowly back into his buggy and drove
away without a word to anyone.
At that time, my company had sent me on an
engineering job near Starkfield, and I was
staying at the home of a lady called Mrs Ruth
Hale. Before she was married, her name had
been Ruth Varnum, but her husband Ned Hale
was now dead, and she had returned to live
with her mother in the Varnum home. It was
a grand house, large and white, with tall
dark trees outside. Although it was clear
that the Varnums no longer had much money,
theirs was still the finest house in the village.
Ruth Hale enjoyed talking about her neighbours,
and I hoped that she could tell me more about
Ethan Frome. But when I asked her, she just
looked unhappy and said in a low voice:
'Yes, I knew them both... it was awful...
I asked other people, and everybody in Starkfield
agreed that Ethan Frome had had more troubles
in his life than most people. But nobody explained
why he had that sad, grim took on his face,
in the end, I learnt the story, piece by piece,
from several people. As often happens, the
story was different each time, but I slowly
began to put it together. And my interest
in Ethan Frome grew stronger when - a little
later - I met the man himself.
It happened like this. Every day I had to
travel about three miles to the station, where
I got my train to work, I usually hired a
horse from Denis Eady, the rich village shopkeeper.
But in the middle of winter, his and most
of the other Starkfield horses caught an illness.
For a day or two, I could not find a horse
to hire anywhere, until Harmon Gow had an
idea.
'Why don't you ask Ethan Frome to drive you?'
he said. 'His horse ain't sick, and he needs
a dollar or two. That Frame farm and sawmill
don't make enough money to keep a cat alive.'
So Ethan Frome agreed to drive me, and every
day for a week I sat beside him in his sleigh
as his thin horse pulled us over the hard
snow to the station. Then, in the icy evenings,
he brought me back to Starkfield.
He was not unfriendly, but during the hour's
drive, he never turned to look at me, and
spoke very little. Once I said something about
Florida and he told me that he had been there.
Another time he showed interest in a science
book of mine, which I had left in his sleigh
by mistake in the morning. But most of the
time Frome drove without a word, and I began
to feel that he was like the land around him.
This sad, silent man and the snow-covered
fields had the same kind of cold loneliness.
Anything warm and alive inside him was locked
away, under the deep icy cold of too many
Starkfield winters.
After about a week, we were driving back one
night in terrible weather. Heavy snow was
falling, hiding everything in a soft white
cloud, and the air had an icy coldness. The
old horse was getting tired, and I got out
to walk beside him, but I found it hard to
keep moving.
After a time Frome looked into the darkness
and said: 'That's my place down there. We've
had enough of this.'
I understood that he was offering me a bed
for the night, and we turned down towards
the poor, lonely-looking farmhouse. After
I had helped him put away the sleigh and take
care of the horse, we fought our way through
the snow to the front of the house. I followed
him inside, and from behind a door on our
right, I heard a woman's voice, a thin, high,
whining voice.
Frome opened the door of the room. 'Come in,'
he said to me, and as he spoke, the whining
voice fell silent.
That was the night when I began to understand
Ethan Frome, and to put together his story...
CHAPTER TWO
Coming home from the dance
It was a cold, clear night, and the village
lay under deep snow. Bright, icy stars shone
from a dark sky down on the silent whiteness
below.
Young Ethan Frome walked quickly down the
empty, moonlit street. He passed Eady's fine
new shop and the Varnums' house with its two
tall black trees. Below that was the slope
of the Corbury road. On clear nights, this
was often full of young people coasting down,
laughing and shouting as they went. But there
was not a sound from the icy slope as Ethan
passed by. Tonight all Starkfield's life was
in a room in the church. Its windows sent
yellow light across the snow, and the sound
of dance music flowed out into the still midnight
air. Ethan hid in the shadows outside the
church, and looked in through the nearest
window.
The room was hot, bright, and filled with
young men and girls. The music had finished,
and people were getting ready to leave. Suddenly,
a lively young man with thick black hair jumped
into the middle of the floor. He went into
the crowd and pulled out a young girl. She
was dark-haired, and had a bright red scarf
around her head. The music started again,
and soon the floor was alive with dancing
figures.
Outside in the cold, Ethan's heart was beating
fast. His eyes followed the girl's red scarf
and cloud of brown hair as she danced in faster
and faster circles. The young, man was. Denis
Eady, the son of Starkfield's most successful
shopkeeper, Denis's own success with the young
women of the village was well known. Ethan
watched jealously as Mattie, the dark-haired
girl, held Eady's hands and smiled at him
with her dark, shining eyes.
'How can she look at him like that?' Ethan
wondered unhappily. 'Doesn't she realize what
he is like?'
Ethan used to walk into Starkfield to fetch
home his wife's cousin, Mattie Silver, on
the few evenings when some chance of amusement
brought her to the village. Mattie had been
with the Fromes for a year now. She lived
with them in their lonely farmhouse and helped
Ethan's wife, Zeena, with the housework. Ethan
had liked the warm, smiling girl from the
moment that she arrived. She brought hope
and life and brightness into his home, like
someone lighting a fire in a cold room. But
she had more than brightness; Ethan found
that she loved the beauty of the natural world
around them. Here at his side, living under
his roof and eating his bread, was someone
who felt the same wonder as he did. He could
tell her things and show her things - the
bright stars in the clear night sky, birds
flying over golden fields, the blue shadows
of trees on sunlit snow. And he knew that
these things gave Mattie and him the same
feelings of deep, silent happiness.
But now those feelings seemed so far away.
He watched Mattie's laughing face as she flew
round and round the room, and he felt lonely
and unhappy. Then he remembered a fear that
he had tried to forget. His wife was a cold,
silent woman who noticed everything but said
very little. Her only real interest was her
own ill health. But recently she had started
to complain more and more about Mattie's housework,
and to say things, which worried Ethan.
'I'll need someone to help me when Mattie
leaves,' she had said suddenly one morning.
'Oh, Mattie'll never leave us while you need
her,' he replied.
His wife lay in bed and watched, as he got
dressed. 'If a poor girl like her has a chance
to marry a smart boy like Denis Eady, I ain't
going to stop her,' she said in her flat,
whining voice. 'The doctor says I can't manage
on my own, so we'll need to hire a girl.'
Life without Mattie! Ethan could not think
of it. Her voice, her sweet smile, her gentle
arm in his arm during those night walks back
to the farm - these were the only things,
which mattered in his world. Had he been stupid
to think that Zeena would not notice his interest
in Mattie? He had not thought about it before,
but now, as he stood in the darkness outside
the church, he remembered other things that
Zeena had said, and his fear grew...
The dancers, now in their thick coats and
scarves, came out into the cold night air.
Ethan heard Mattie's voice in the crowd, and
he stepped back into the shadows, suddenly
afraid to speak to her. The crowd quickly
disappeared, and Mattie stood alone outside
the church, looking around her. Then a man's
figure appeared.
'Nobody to walk you home, Matt? What a pity!
But ain't I lucky that I got my dad's horse
and sleigh down here waiting for us? Come
on, let's take a ride!'
The girl said nothing, but stood still, watching,
while Denis Eady went to untie the horse.
In the shadows, Ethan too watched and waited,
with his heart beating fast. Mattie held his
life in her hands. Eady got into the sleigh
and called to Mattie to join him. Then she
turned and ran up the slope.
'Goodbye! Have a lovely ride!' she called
back.
Eady laughed and followed her up the slope
in his sleigh.
After a moment, he jumped down and tried to
put his arm through hers. She stepped quickly
out of the way, and Ethan's sudden fear turned
to happiness. A moment later, he heard the
sound of Eady's sleigh going away, and saw
Mattie walking alone across the snow.
He caught up with her by the Varnums' trees.
She turned round, surprised.
'Oh!' she said. 'I thought maybe you couldn't
come.'
'If you thought I couldn't come, why didn't
you ride back with Denis Eady?' he answered.
'Oh, how did you know?' she cried. 'Where
were you? I never saw you!'
They stood in the dark shadows of the trees,
and their laughing voices ran together like
water dancing down from the mountains in springtime.
He put his arm through hers, but neither of
them moved. Ethan wished he could stand there
with her all night in the blackness. Mattie
took a few steps forward and then stopped,
looking down the icy slope of the Corbury
road.
'There were lots of people coasting this evening,'
she said. 'Ned Hale and Ruth Varnum almost
crashed into the big tree- down there. It's
so dangerous, that tree.'
'You'd be safe with me, Matt,' replied Ethan.
'Would you like to come coasting some night?
We could come tomorrow if there's a moon.'
'Oh, yes. How lovely!'
They walked along in silence, but then all
Ethan's jealous fears returned.
'I guess it's natural that you're going to
leave us,' he said at last.
'Leave? You mean Zeena ain't happy with me?
I know I ain't so strong or so smart, but
I want to try, I really do.'
'So you don't want to leave us, Matt?'
'Where could I go?' she whispered, almost
crying.
Her answer made Ethan sad and happy at the
same time. They continued their walk, with
the dark, starry sky above them, and the quiet,
lonely fields all around. At the entrance
to Ethan's farmland they passed by the Frome
graves. Ethan had always felt that the gravestones
were looking at him and saying 'We never got
out of Starkfield. Why should you?' But now
he didn't want to escape. All he wanted was
to be with Mattie, and some day to lie under
that cold ground with Mattie beside him. Ethan
was happy now, in his world of dreams. For
the first time he put his arm around Mattie.
She let it stay there, and they walked up
to the farmhouse.
The house was dark and quiet. Zeena always
went to bed early. On the nights when they
came back late, she used to Jock up the house
and hide the key outside the kitchen door.
Ethan felt for the key under the usual stone.
'Matt, the key's not there!' he said. This
had never happened before. They began to look
for it in the darkness. Suddenly there was
a sound inside the house. They heard a step
on the stairs and saw light under the door.
Then the door opened, and Ethan saw his wife.
She stood in the dark doorway, a tall thin
woman with a blanket round her shoulders.
She held a lamp in one hand, and its light
threw strange shadows onto her thin lined
face. She said nothing, and they stepped into
the kitchen. It was deadly cold, like a grave.
Ethan shook the snow off his boots. 'I guess
you forgot us,' he said, looking at Zeena.
'No. I just felt too bad. I couldn't sleep.'
'I'm sorry,' said Mattie, 'Can I do anything
to help, Zeena?'
'No, there's nothing you can do.' Zeena turned
away from her. 'And why couldn't you shake
that snow off outside?' she said to her husband.
They left the kitchen, and the two women went
towards the stairs. 'If I go up now, Mattie'll
see me go into the bedroom with Zeena,' thought
Ethan. 'And I don't want that, not tonight.'
'I think I'll stay down here a bit longer.
I've got some paperwork to do,' he said.
'What, now?' said Zeena. 'You'll die of cold.'
Ethan did not answer, but turned back towards
the kitchen. Then he saw the look in Mattie's
eyes. Was it a look of warning?
'I guess you're right. It is awful cold down
here,' he agreed. With his head down, he slowly
followed his wife up to their bedroom.
CHAPTER THREE
A visit to the doctor
The next morning was cold and bright. Ethan
was down at his sawmill early because he had
to take some wood to the village builder that
day. The winter sunburned red in a clear sky,
and the sunlight danced over the bright, snowy
fields, leaving deep blue shadows under the
trees.
Ethan's thoughts were always clearest when
he was working in the quiet morning air. Last
night, after the bedroom door had closed behind
them, Zeena had taken her medicine and gone
to bed without a word. Ethan lay next to her,
watching the light from under Mattie's door,
and thinking. Why had he not kissed her on
the walk home? He remembered her soft lips
in the moonlight. Now, in the clear morning
sunshine, he could still see her face. He
could see it in the red sky and in the bright
shining snow.
Mattie was the daughter of Orin Silver, a
cousin of Zeena Frome's. Silver's medicine
company had seemed successful, and he had
lived like a rich man. But when he died, his
wife and daughter had a terrible surprise.
They discovered that he had borrowed thousands
of dollars, which he could not pay back. This
awful news killed Mrs Silver immediately.
He had also lost money, which belonged to
his brothers and sisters, so there was nobody
in the family who wanted to help poor Mattie.
The twenty-year-old girl was alone in the
world, without money and without friends.
She was not strong, and she had never studied
or learnt to do a job. So Mattie came to Starkfield
to work, without pay, in her cousin Zeena's
home. At first Zeena often complained about
the girl's work. Then, as the months went
by, Mattie grew stronger and found the work
easier. Zeena had more time to think about
her illnesses, and life under the Fromes'
roof became more peaceful.
But now, Zeena's strange silent looks, the
warning in Mattie's eyes last night... Ethan
was sure that something was wrong. By midday,
the wood was all loaded, ready to take to
Andrew Hale the builder. But Ethan decided
to go home. If there was going to be trouble,
he wanted to be there. So Ethan and Jotham
Powell, his hired man, walked through the
fields back to the house.
When they entered the kitchen, Mattie was
making coffee. Zeena was sitting at the table,
wearing her best brown dress and a tall hat.
A suitcase stood beside her.
'Where're you going, Zeena?' asked Ethan,
surprised.
'My pains are getting really bad. I'm going
over to my aunt's in Bettsbridge for the night,
and tomorrow I'll see that new doctor,' she
answered. 'If you're too busy, I suppose you
can let Jotham Powell drive me to the station.'
Ethan said nothing. He was lost in his own
thoughts. He realized that, for the first
time, he and Mattie would be alone for the
night. He looked at Mattie. Was she thinking
the same thing? Then he looked at his wife's
thin, lined, bloodless face. Zeena was thirty-five,
only seven years older than he was, but she
was already an old woman.
'Of course Jorham'll take you,' he said at
last. 'I can't do it myself, because I've
got to get the money for the wood from Andrew
Hale.'
This was a lie. Andrew Hale never paid immediately,
but Ethan really had no wish to make the long,
slow journey to the station with his miserable
wife at his side.
Zeena made no reply, and soon afterwards,
she left with Jotham. Ethan picked up his
coat and stood for a moment in the doorway.
'See you later, Matt,' he said.
It was warm and bright: in the kitchen. The
sun shone in on the flowering pot plants by
the window, and the cat sleeping in a chair.
Mattie looked up from her housework. 'See
you later, Ethan,' she said happily.
All the way down to the village, Ethan thought
of his return to Mattie that night. Without
Zeena, his house seemed more like a home.
And as he drove through the snowy fields,
this usually silent man began to sing.
Ethan Frome had not always been so quiet and
lonely. As a student he had liked being among
happy, friendly, young people. He had enjoyed
his science studies and wanted to become an
engineer. But after his father's accident
and death, Ethan had to leave his studies
and return home. Life was hard for him, working
alone on the poor farm and unsuccessful sawmill.
Then his mother fell ill, and became more
and more silent. Sometimes she used to say
a few crazy words, but for most of the time,
she refused to speak at all. So with each
long, cold Starkfield winter, the silence
and loneliness round Ethan grew deeper.
As his mother came towards her last illness,
Ethan's cousin Zeena arrived to take care
of her. It was wonderful to hear another person's
voice in the house again, and Zeena was an
excellent nurse and housekeeper. Old Mrs Frome
finally died one dark winter's day, and the
idea of being alone again filled Ethan with
fear. He was grateful to Zeena for all that
she had done, and he asked her to stay and
marry him. They had at first planned to sell
the farm and move to the town. But it was
hard to find a buyer, and Ethan soon realized
that his wife could not live in a place where
she was not someone 'important'. In less than
a year her 'sickliness' appeared; then she
too fell silent. Her strange, wordless looks
worried Ethan. Was she going a little crazy,
like his mother? What thoughts and plans were
hidden behind her cold eyes?
But that afternoon, as Ethan drove to the
village with his sleigh full of wood for the
builder, he felt less afraid. Zeena had gone
away to Bettsbridge, with all her thoughts
on her own health. And tonight he had an evening
alone with Mattie. But there was still one
worry - the lie about the money from Andrew
Hale. He knew that Zeena would want to know
where it was.
When Ethan arrived at the builder's, Hale
invited him into his office to sit down and
get warm. He was a large, red faced and likeable
man, an old friend of Ethan's family. Ethan
did not know how to begin, but at last, he
managed to ask Hale for the first fifty dollars
towards this winter's wood. The builder was
surprised. He always paid at the end of three
months, never before. He refused in his warm,
friendly way, and then asked:
'Look, you ain't got money problems, have,
you?'
'No, not at all,' replied Ethan, very embarrassed.
The afternoon had turned into a cold grey
evening by the time Ethan left the builder's.
He heard the sound of sleigh-bells, and Denis
Eady drove past, shouting 'Hello, Ethe!' Eady
was going towards the Frome farm. Did he know
that Zeena had gone? Was he going there to
spend some time alone with Mattie? Ethan felt
wildly jealous, then moments later was ashamed
of his feelings.
By the Varnum house, Ethan saw two figures
standing together under the trees. He heard
a kiss, and a surprised 'Oh!' as he passed
by. Two happy lovers, kissing where he had
stood with Mattie the night before. But unlike
him, Ruth Varnum and Ned Hale didn't need
to hide their feelings. How lucky they were!
As night fell, Ethan passed by the Frome gravestones
and drove up to the farmhouse. A light shone
in a room upstairs.
'She's getting herself ready for supper,'
he thought.
CHAPTER FOUR
An evening together
Ethan went up to the kitchen door, and found
that it was locked. He called 'Hello, Matt!'
but there was no answer. He stood in the darkness
and waited. After a moment, he heard a sound
on the stairs, and saw light round the door.
And just like the night before, the door opened
and there stood a woman with a lamp in her
hand. The lamplight shone on the milky whiteness
of Mattie's young skin, on her soft lips and
shining dark eyes. She smiled gently, and
stepped to the side to let Ethan come in.
The kitchen was warm and welcoming. On the
table were cakes and fruit in a bright red
glass dish, and the cat was lying lazily in
front of a warm fire.
'Well, Matt, any visitors?' asked Ethan.
'Just one,' replied Mattie, laughing. A black
cloud came down over Ethan's world.
'Who was that?'
She looked at him and laughed again. 'Jotham
Powell. He came in and asked for a drop of
coffee.'
The blackness lifted and Ethan's world grew
bright again.
'Well, I hope you gave him some,' he said,
then added, 'I suppose Zeena got to the station
in time?'
Zeena's name brought an immediate coolness
into the kitchen. After a few moments, Mattie
said: 'I guess it's about time for supper,'
and they sat down.
But they still felt uncomfortable - Zeena
seemed to be in the room with them, with her
cold eyes and strange looks. They ate in embarrassed
silence, then began to talk about the weather.
As they were speaking, the cat climbed quietly
onto the table and started to move towards
the milk-jug. When they saw it, they both
reached forwards at once, their hands meeting
on the jug. Ethan kept his hand on Mattie's
a few seconds longer than was necessary. At
that moment, the cat suddenly jumped backwards
and knocked into the red glass dish. The dish
fell to the floor with a crash.
'Oh, Ethan,' Mattie cried. 'It's all in pieces!
What will Zeena say? It was her very best
dish!'
'Don't worry. I'll get another one.'
'You'll never find one! It was a wedding present
from her aunt in Philadelphia. That's why
she never uses it. I had to climb up to get.it
from the top of her cupboard! Oh, Ethan, what
shall I do?'
She began to cry, and her tears seemed to
burn into Ethan's heart.'
'Oh, Matt, don't cry! Please don't cry!' he
said softly.
They looked at the bits of red glass lying
like the broken pieces of their evening. Ethan
picked them up and walked out of the kitchen
to the hall. Reaching up his long arm, he
put the broken pieces at the top of the cupboard
and arranged them carefully. From below, nobody
could see that the dish was broken.
'I'll get some glue to mend it tomorrow,'
thought Ethan. 'Zeena won't look at it for
months, and I'm sure I'll find another one
somewhere.'
He went back to the kitchen. 'It's all right,
Matt,' he said. 'Let's finish supper.'
After the meal, Mattie cleared the table and
Ethan went out to see the cows. The world
was dark and still outside. When he came back,
Mattie had pushed his chair near the fire
and had seated herself by the lamp with a
bit of sewing. He sat down, feeling warm and
dreamy and at peace with the world. The only
trouble was that he could not see Mattie from
where he sat. But he felt too lazy to move
and after a moment, he said: 'Come over here
and sit by the fire.'
Mattie got up and sat opposite him in Zeena's
rocking - chair. He looked at the chair and
for a moment, he saw his wife's grim face
there. Mattie seemed to feel uncomfortable
too. After a while she got up, saying, 'I
can't see to sew,' and went back to sit by
the lamp.
The cat jumped into the empty rocking - chair
and Ethan moved his own chair a little. Now
he could see Mattie as she sat and sewed in
the soft lamplight. A deep quiet came over
the kitchen. The 'tick-tick' of the clock
was the only sound in the room, and the smoke
from Ethan's pipe and the smell of Mattie's
flowering plants filled the air.
They began to talk easily of everyday things,
it all seemed so comfortable and so peaceful.
Ethan began to dream that they always spent
their evenings like this...
'This was the night when we were going coasting,
he said after a while.
She smiled back at him. 'I guess you forgot!'
'No, I didn't forget. It's too dark tonight,
but we can go tomorrow if there's a moon.'
'That would be lovely, Ethan!' Mattie laughed
happily, and her eyes shone in the lamplight.
Ethan loved the way that her face changed
as she talked, like a field of grass moving
under a gentle summer wind.
'It's too dangerous on a dark night like this,'
he went on. 'You've got to keep your eyes
open on that slope, you know, Matt. That's
a dangerous corner down by that big tree.
You could crash right into it if you're not
careful.' Then he added: 'I guess we're fine
here, aren't we?'
'Yes, we're fine here,' agreed Mattie in a
soft, sweet voice. Ethan put down his pipe
and pulled his chair up to the table. He touched
the end of her piece of sewing.
'Say, Matt, guess what I saw tonight? Your
friends kissing under the Varnum trees,' Mattie's
face turned bright red. 'That'll be Ruth and
Ned,' she answered, looking down at her sewing.
Ethan felt embarrassed too. Last night on
their walk home, he had put his arm around
Mattie, and had wanted to kiss her. But tonight,
in the warm lamp lit room, she seemed so much
further away.
'I guess they'll get married soon,' said Ethan.
'And then maybe you'll be next.'
'Why do you say that?' she replied in a low
voice. 'Is it because Zeena doesn't want me
to stay?'
'What do you mean?' asked Ethan, afraid again.
'I thought that last night she seemed... Oh,
I don't know. Nobody knows what Zeena thinks.
She hasn't said anything to you, has she?'
He shook his head. 'No, not a word.'
'I guess it was nothing then. Let's not think
about it,' said Mattie, and went on with her
sewing.
Ethan watched her in silence. Then he gently
took hold of the other end of her piece of
sewing. Mattie's warmth seemed to flow along
it towards him. Could she feel the answering
warmth from his own hand? They sat like this
for a few moments, then Ethan heard a sound
behind. The cat had jumped down from Zeena's
chair, and because of the sudden movement,
the empty chair had started a ghostly rocking.
'Zeena'll be in that chair herself this time
tomorrow,' thought Ethan. 'I've been in a
dream, and this is the only evening we'll
ever have together...' The return to the real
world filled him with pain, and he suddenly
felt very tired.
Mattie looked at him, and for a moment, he
saw fear cross her face. He held onto her
sewing and kissed the end of it softly. She
pulled it slowly from his lips and put it
away. It was eleven o'clock.
'Is the fire all right?' she asked in a low
voice.
They checked the fire, moved the plant pots
away from the cold window, and put out the
lamp.
'Goodnight, Matt,' he said, as she put her
foot on the first step of the stairs.
'Goodnight, Ethan,' she answered, and went
up.
When the door of her room had closed, he remembered
that he had not even touched her hand.
CHAPTER FIVE
Zeena's news
The next morning Jotham Powell came, round
early to help load some more wood. Ethan could
still feel inside him the sweetness of the
evening before, and he tried hard not to show
his happiness.
He did not know why he felt so happy. There
was no reason for it, because nothing had
changed in his life or in Mattie's.
But their evening together had given him a
dream a picture of life with Mattie at his
side.
He wanted to load the wood quickly and then
drive it down to Starkfield, where he could
buy the glue to mend the broken dish. He was
sending Jotham to fetch Zeena from the station
after dinner, so they needed to work fast.
But the morning went badly. A wet snow had
fallen in the night, and the roads were like
glass. One of his horses fell and cut its
leg. Icy rain started to fall, making the
loading slow and difficult. It was after midday
when they finished.
Immediately after dinner, Ethan put his coat
on again. Jotham was drying his wet feet by
the fire and Mattie was washing the dishes.
'I'll be back early,' Ethan said to Mattie
in a low voice. He was afraid to say more
in front of Jotham, but he thought that Mattie
understood him.
The journey down to the village was long and
slow, with his two old horses pulling their
heavy load over the snow and ice underfoot.
By the time he had unloaded the wood and managed
to buy the glue, it was already late afternoon.
On the way, back the rain began again, turning
to ice as it fell on the snow and making the
road even more glassy and dangerous. Once
or twice Ethan heard sleigh-bells and turned
round, afraid that Jotham and Zeena were coming
up behind him. But for most of the journey,
he just looked grimly into the falling rain,
as his tired horses made their way up the
hill.
At last, he arrived home and hurried into
the kitchen. Mattie was alone.
'Look, Matt,' he cried, 'I've got the glue
to mend the dish with! Quick, let me get it!'
'Oh, Ethan - Zeena's back!' she said in a
whisper, holding onto his arm.
Ethan looked round the kitchen, which looked
cold and unwelcoming in the wintry evening
light.
'How is she?' he asked, in the same low whisper.
'I don't know. She didn't say anything, she
just went straight upstairs.'
Ethan put the glue back in his pocket. 'Don't
worry. I'll come down and mend the dish in
the night,' he said.
Then, just as she had done the evening before,
Mattie said: 'I guess it's about time for
supper.'
Ethan called Zeena, but there was no answer.
He went up to the bedroom, and pushed open
the door. In the darkness, he saw Zeena's
figure sitting by the window, still wearing
her travelling dress.
'Well, Zeena, supper's ready. Ain't you coming?'
'I don't think I could eat a thing,' she replied,
then turned her head towards him. 'I'm much
sicker than you think.'
'I hope that's not so, Zeena.'
'The doctor says I mustn't do anything at
all in the house. So we'll have to get a hired
girl.'
'A hired girl?'
'Yes. My aunt's found me one already. She's
coming tomorrow afternoon.'
'Why didn't you tell me what you planned to
do?' he asked angrily. 'Where do you think
I'll get the money to pay her?'
'How did I know what the doctor would say?
I'm ashamed to have a husband like you, Ethan
Frome. I lost my health taking care of your
own mother! Marrying me was the least that
you could do after -'
'Zeena!'
The darkness between them was filled with
anger. It was their first moment of open fighting
in their sad seven years together. Ethan felt
ashamed, and tried to speak more calmly.
'You know I don't have the money, Zeena. She'll
have to go back.'
'What about that fifty dollars from Andrew
Hale?'
'He remembered the he lie had told the day
before. I guess that was a mistake.'
'You mean you ain't going to get it?'
'No. I'm sorry, Zeena. You're a poor man's
wife. But I'll do the best I can to help you.'
'Oh, I guess we'll manage,' she said more
gently. 'And without Mattie's food to pay
for -'
'Without Mattie's -?' he began.
Zeena laughed. It was a strange sound. He
couldn't remember hearing her laugh before.
'You didn't think Mattie was staying, did
you?'
'But you can't send her away - she's your
cousin.'
'Well, we can't keep two girls here.'
Ethan could not believe what he was hearing.
'Ethan - Zeena! Supper's ready!' Mattie called
brightly from downstairs.
Ethan felt angry and helpless. 'But where
will she go? A poor girl with no friends or
money...'
'She's been here long enough. We've kept her
for over a year now, and it's time for her
to go.'
Ethan looked at his wife with eyes full of
hate. It was an angry, bitter hate. It was
a hate, which had grown during years of hard
work, hopeless poverty, and broken dreams.
This woman had destroyed all his hopes. She
had taken everything from him, and now wanted
to take the one beautiful thing left in his
life. He made a sudden, violent movement towards
her, then stopped.
'I don't think I'll come down,' said Zeena
calmly. 'I guess I'll just lie on the bed
a while.'
Ethan went downstairs to the kitchen, and
Mattie gave him a plate of food. He took a
mouthful, then pushed the plate away.
'What's the matter, Ethan? Doesn't it taste
right?'
'It's fine, Matt. Only I -' He stood up quickly.
She looked at him with frightened eyes. 'I
knew there was something wrong. What is it,
Ethan? What is it?'
He took her in his arms and found her lips
at last. He kissed and kissed her. He was
lost in the sweetness of her lips. Then she
pulled away from him, her face white with
fear, and he cried out:
'You can't go, Matt! I'll never let you go!'
'Go... go?' she whispered. 'Must I go? Ethan,
what has happened? Is Zeena angry with me?'
He told her what the doctor had said. Mattie
looked so small and helpless. His heart ached
for her, and he wanted to hold her in his
arms again. They were silent for a long while,
then Mattie said in a low voice:
'Don't be too sorry, Ethan.'
'Oh, Matt - Matt - where'll you go?'
'Maybe I'll get something to do in town.'
But they both knew that she had little chance
of finding a job. There were too many people
looking for work in the towns, and there were
no jobs that Mattie could do. And Ethan knew
what happened to girls who had no job, no
money, and no friends... He sat down in despair,
and hid his face in his hands.
Then they heard Zeena's footsteps on the stairs.
She came down wearing her usual dress. Then
she sat down in her usual seat, and took a
large plateful of food. She ate well, and
talked in an everyday way about the illnesses
of her friends and family in Bettsbridge.
As she spoke, she looked at Mattie with a
small smile on her thin lips. When supper
was finished, she stood up and said:
'That meal's given me a stomachache. I think
I'll go and look for the stomach medicine
that I bought last year.'
She left the room. Ethan's and Mattie's eyes
met, full of silent despair. The kitchen looked
as warm and peaceful as the night before,
but now everything had changed. Then suddenly
Zeena was back, her face burning with anger.
In her hands, she held the broken pieces of
the red glass dish.
'I want to know who did this,' she said in
a shaking voice.
'I can tell you. It was the cat,' answered
Ethan after a few moments.
'The cat? How did the cat get into my hall
cupboard?'
'Oh, Zeena, it was my fault, not Ethan's!'
cried Mattie. 'I got it down from your cupboard.
I - I wanted the supper table to look pretty,'
'You wanted the supper table to look pretty!
So you rook my very best dish, the one that
I never, ever use. Not for visitors, not for
anyone. You're a bad girl, Mattie Silver,
just like your father. I always knew you were
bad - that's why I hid my things from you.
And now you've taken the thing that I cared
for the most -' Tears ran down her thin, yellowish
face. Then she left the room, carrying the
pieces of broken glass like a dead body.
CHAPTER SIX
No escape
When Zeena had gone, Ethan and Mattie stood
in silence for a moment. Then Mattie began
to tidy the kitchen and Ethan went outside
to check the animals, as he did every night.
The room was empty when he returned, but on
the table under his pipe was a piece of paper.
Three words were written on it: 'Ethan, don't
worry'.
There was a small room at the back of the
house where Ethan kept his books and papers.
His mother had let him use it as a study-room
when he first returned to the farm after his
father's accident. He still sat there in summer,
but the room had no fire and in winter, it
was too cold. This was where he went to look
again at his message from Mattie. It was the
first time she had ever written to him. He
read her words and felt nearer to her, but
at the same time, he remembered that very
soon he would never see her again. 'Soon there'll
be no warm smile, no gentle voice, only this
- cold paper and dead words,' he thought.
He lay down on a hard little bed that was
there, covered himself with an old coat, and
began to think about his life. He had lost
so many chances and forgotten so many of his
dreams, all to please Zeena. But she was now
far more discontented than when he had married
her. Must he live the rest of his days beside
this bitter, complaining woman? No. He was
too young and strong, too full of life to
throw away all hope of happiness. Then he
thought - why shouldn't he leave with Mattie
the next day? He would hide his suitcase under
the seat of the sleigh, leave Zeena a letter...
He jumped up, lit the lamp again, sat down
at the table and began to write.
Zeena, 'I've done everything I could for you.
But it hasn't worked. It's neither my fault
nor yours. Maybe it'll be better for both
of us if we live apart. I'm going to see what
I can find in the West. You can sell the farm
and sawmill and keep the money -'
At that word, he stopped writing and began
to think.
Without the farm, he would have no money.
He was sure that he could find work in the
West, but would he get enough money to take
care of Mattie too? And what about Zeena,
alone on the farm? She couldn't keep it going
on her own, and it would be hard to sell.
The land was poor and not many people would
want to buy it. But how could he let poor
Mattie leave alone?
As he picked up his pen, his eye fell on a
Bettsbridge newspaper. He saw the words 'Journeys
to the West', and pulled the lamp nearer to
see the prices of the tickets. Then the pen
fell from his hand, and he pushed the unfinished
letter away. He didn't even have the money
to take Mattie to the West. He had already
borrowed to mend the sawmill, and couldn't
borrow any more. The cold facts closed around
him like prison doors. There was no way out
- none. He was locked in that prison for life,
and now his one light was disappearing.
He lay down again with a heavy heart and tears
burning in his eyes. Through the window, he
saw the snow-covered slopes shining in the
moonlight, the silver-edged darkness of the
woods, and the shadowy purple of the hills
against the sky. He felt that the beauty of
the night was laughing at him, lying there
so miserably.
He fell asleep. In the morning, he woke cold
and hungry. He went to the window, and saw
a red sun coming up over the grey edges of
the fields. 'This is Matt's last day,' he
said to himself. He tried to think how the
place would be without her.
He heard a step behind him, turned round and
saw Mattie. She looked so small and thin,
standing there in her poor dress in the cold,
wintry light.
'I'll come and light the kitchen fire,' he
said.
Mattie started her usual morning housework.
The kitchen slowly became warmer, and the
first sunlight entered the room. Ethan began
to feel more hopeful. 'Maybe Zeena didn't
mean what she said,' he thought, 'Maybe, now
that daylight's here, she'll think again and
let Mattie stay.'
He went up to Mattie and touched her arm gently.
'I don't, want you to worry, Matt,' he said,
looking down into her eyes with a smile. 'I
guess things will be all right.'
'No, I ain't going to worry,' she said softly.
He went out to the farm, and soon afterwards,
Jotham Powell joined him. As they were doing
their morning's work with the COWS, Jotham
said:
'Mrs Frome told me the new girl's coming'
today, and Mattie's leaving'. I got to take
her down to the station.' Ethan felt the blood
beating in his head. After a moment, he found
his voice, and said:
'Oh, it ain't so sure that Mattie's going
-'
'Is that so?' said Jotham, not at all interested,
and he went on with his work.
When they returned to the kitchen, the two
women were already at breakfast. Zeena was
eating well, and seemed very lively and busy.
She looked at the hired man.
'Jotham, I want you here mid-afternoon to
pick up Mattie,' she said. The new girls getting
to the station at five o'clock. Mattie can
get the train at six.' Then she turned to
Mattie and went on, 'Now, what've you done
with one of my best cotton sheets? And there
are a few other things missing, too.' Mattie
followed Zeena out of the room, leaving the
two men alone.
'I guess I'll come round mid-afternoon, then,'
said Jotham to his employer.
When the morning's work was finished, Ethan
said to Jotham: 'I'm going down to Starkfield.
Tell them not to wait for me at dinnertime.'
It was a clear, still morning, with a whisper
of spring in the air. The snowy fields shone
silver in the bright morning sunlight. Ethan
walked down the road, angry and ashamed. So
Mattie really was leaving, and he could only
stand by, helpless. What must she think of
him? As he walked, he could feel laughing
voice in the song of the birds. He knew that
he had to do something. But what?
Then a thought came to him. Andrew Hale was
a kind-hearted man. 'Maybe,' thought Ethan,
'he'll let me have some money now, if I tell
him that Zeena's really sick and that we need
a hired girl to help her. Mrs Hale will listen
to me, I'm sure.'
He thought about this idea as he walked faster
and faster down the road. With each long step,
he felt more sure of his plan's success. And
with fifty dollars in his pocket, nothing
could keep him from Mattie...
As he came into Starkfield, he saw the Hales'
sleigh, and hurried forward to meet it. The
sleigh stopped, and Mrs Hale's round, motherly
face looked out. She smiled at Ethan, told
him that her husband was at home, then added:
'I'm sorry that Zeena's feeling bad again.
She's lucky to have you to take care of her.
And so was your poor mother. You've had an
awful hard life, Ethan Frome.'
When she had gone, Ethan felt less alone in
his unhappiness. It had been a long time since
anyone had spoken to him as kindly as Mrs
Hale. The Hales were caring people who felt
sorry for him, and now he felt sure that they
would help him.
He started down the road to their house, then
stopped after a few steps. He suddenly saw
himself, and his life, in the clear light
of day. He was a poor man, planning to leave
his sickly wife all alone and without money.
And how was he planning to do this heartless
thing? By telling lies to two kind people
who felt sorry for him.
He turned and walked slowly back to the farm.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The last ride
It was about midday when Ethan got home. Zeena
was by the fire with a scarf on her head and
a book about stomach pains in her hand. She
did not move or look up.
'Where's Mattie?' Ethan asked.
Zeena continued to read her book. 'I guess
she's packing her case,' she replied.
Ethan went straight upstairs. Mattie's door
was closed. 'Matt,' he said in a low voice.
There was no answer, so he gently pushed open
the door.
Mattie was sitting on her case in her best
dress, with her back to the door and her face
in her hands. She was crying. Ethan put his
hands on her shoulders.
'Matt - oh, don't - oh, Matt!'
'Ethan - I thought you weren't coming back!'
she cried, lifting her wet face to his.
He took her in his arms, and kissed her soft
hair. Then they heard Zeena calling, and moved
away from each other.
He carried her suitcase downstairs, and with
every 'tick' of the clock, the pain in his
heart grew.
At dinner, he could eat nothing. After the
meal, Zeena sat down by the fire and Mattie
began to wash the dishes, Jotham got up from
the table and asked Ethan:
'So what time will I come round for Mattie?'
'You needn't come round; I'm going to drive
her over myself,' he answered.
Zeena lifted her head. 'I want you here this
afternoon, Ethan. You'll have to get the room
ready for the new girl. Jotham can take Mattie.'
'I'm going to drive her over myself,' he repeated
in a hard voice. He turned to Mattie: 'You
be ready at three, Matt. I've got business
in Corbury.'
With those words, he left the house. He could
feel the hot blood beating in his head, as
the anger burned inside him. He hurried through
his work, then went to get the horse and sleigh.
He remembered the day when he had got the
sleigh ready in order to fetch his wife's
cousin from the station. It was little more
than a year ago, on a soft afternoon just
like this, with a whisper of spring in the
air. And all the days between then and now
came back to him, one by one.
He jumped into the sleigh and drove up to
the house. The kitchen was empty, and Mattie's
case and coat lay ready by the door. After
a moment, he heard someone moving about in
his study-room. He pushed open the door and
saw Mattie standing by the table.
'What are you doing in there, Matt?'
'Just looking round,' she replied.
'Where's Zeena?'
'Gone upstairs. She said she had her pains
again.'
'Didn't she say goodbye?'
'No. That was all she said.'
They went back into the kitchen. Ethan looked
slowly around the room, thinking, 'In a few
hours I shall return here alone. I'm looking
at Mattie here for the last time.' He could
not believe it; it all seemed so unreal.
'Come on,' he said, opening the door. He helped
her into the sleigh, and with a 'Go along!'
to the horse, they started off down the hill.
'We got lots of time for a good ride, Matt!'
he said, taking her hand in his.
As they left the farm, he did not take the
road towards Starkfield, but turned the horse
to the light, up the Bettsbridge road. Mattie
did not seem surprised.
'Are you going round by Shadow Pond?'
'You knew, didn't you?' he laughed.
The road took them down into a wood, where
the trees shone reddish in the afternoon sun,
leaving soft blue shadows on the untouched
snow. There was a warm stillness in the wood.
In the middle was a small icy pond, with sweet-smelling
trees all around. It was a quiet, secret place,
like the quiet sadness in Ethan's heart. They
saw a fallen tree by the icy water, half covered
in snow. It was where they had sat once last
August, together with a group of young people
from Starkfield church.
They sat down now in the same place, and remembered
those few happy moments from that hot summer
afternoon. Ethan looked at Mattie's hair,
and wished he could touch it again. He wanted
to tell her that it smelled of the woods in
springtime, but he had never learned to say
things like that.
When the sun began to go down behind the hill,
Mattie said: 'We mustn't stay here any longer.'
As they drove back towards Starkfield, the
sky was turning grey, with a cold red over
the western hills.
'Matt,' Ethan said at last. 'What'll you do?
Can't you ask your father's family for help?'
'I don't want to ask them,' she replied, then
after a moment added: 'I guess I'll find something.'
'You know I'd do anything for you -'
'Yes, I know.'
'But I can't -'
She was silent, but he felt her shoulder shaking.
'Oh, Matt,' he cried. 'I wish...'
She turned to him. 'Ethan, I found this.'
She held out a piece of paper. It was the
unfinished letter to his wife, which he had
forgotten to destroy. A painful happiness
ran through him. Were Mattie's dreams the
same as his? He had to know. 'Do you feel
like that too, Matt? Tell me, Matt, tell me!'
'Oh, Ethan, what does it matter now?' she
cried. With a sudden movement, she tore the
letter into pieces and threw them onto the
snow. For a moment, she was silent, then said
in a low voice:
'The first time I thought of you like that
was at Shadow Pond. Then I often used to think
about you on summer nights when the moon was
too bright and I couldn't sleep.'
Her words filled Ethan's heart with sweetness.
Darkness began to fall and they drove on in
silence for a while.
'I'm fastened hand and foot, Matt. There isn't
a thing I can do,' he began again.
'You must write to me sometimes, Ethan.'
'Oh, what can writing do? I want to put my
hand out and touch you. I want to take care
of you. I want to be there when you're sick
and when you're lonely.'
'Oh, Ethan, I wish I was dead!' she cried.
'Don't let's talk that way,' he whispered.
As they arrived in Starkfield, a sleigh with
bells passed them. They heard happy children's
voices and saw a group of village boys with
sleds. They drove on to the top of the Corbury
road. On one side was the tall white shape
of the church, on the other were the dark
shadows of the Varnum trees. The steep slope
lay empty and white below them. An idea came
to Ethan, to help himself and her through
their miserable last hour. He turned to Mattie.
'We never went coasting last night. Shall
we go down now? How would you like that?'
'There isn't time!'
'There's as much time as we want,' he said.
'The hired girl can wait. Lock, someone's
left a sled under the trees.'
He helped her out of the sleigh, and took
her by the hand towards the sled. They both
sat down on it, with Mattie in front and Ethan
behind.
'It's so dark, Ethan. Are you sure you can
see?'
'Oh, I can do this with my eyes closed!' he
laughed. She laughed with him, then after
a moment, he cried: 'Now!' They started off,
and soon the sled was flying down the slope,
round the corner by the big tree, and down
the second slope. They came to a stop, picked
up the sled, and began to climb up the hill
again.
'It was wonderful!' laughed Mattie.
'Weren't you afraid when we went round the
tree?'
'I'm never afraid with you,' she replied.
A deep silence seemed to fall from the starless
sky. At each step of their climb, Ethan said
to himself: 'If's the last time we'll ever
walk together.'
When they reached the Varnum trees, Ethan
put back the sled. 'I guess this must be Ned
Hale's sled,' he said.
'Is this where Ned and Ruth kissed each other?'
Mattie whispered throwing her arms round Ethan.
Her lips found his, and Ethan held her close
to him.
'Goodbye - goodbye,' she said in a shaking
voice, and kissed him again.
'Matt, I can't let you go! What'll we do?
What'll we do?' They stood holding hands like
children. Through the stillness, they heard
the church clock.
'Oh, Ethan, it's already five o'clock. It's
time!'
'Time for what? I'm not leaving you now. How
can we go anywhere without each other, after
this?'
Suddenly she threw her arms round his neck
again. 'Ethan! Ethan! I want you to take me
down again!'
'Down where?'
'Down there. Into the tree, to finish it all.
Then we'll never have to leave each other
again.'
'Matt! What are you saying? Are you crazy?'
'No, but I will be crazy if I leave you. Where'll
I go without you? You're the only person who's
ever been good to me. And there'll be a strange
girl sleeping in my bed where I used to lie
at night and think of you...'
Her words were like pieces torn from his heart.
Now at last he knew that Mattie's feelings
were as strong as his. How could he go back
to that hated house, to the woman who was
waiting for him there?
He held her close and kissed her, but when
her face touched his, it was cold and wet
with tears. He saw the road down to the station,
and through the still air, he heard a train.
The dark trees covered them in blackness and
silence, like a grave. 'Perhaps it'll be like
this,' he thought. 'After this I won't feel
anything.'
'Come,' she whispered, pulling at his hand.
He picked the sled up, and they took their
places on it. This time he made her sit behind
him. She put her arms round him, and he turned
his head and kissed her. She was right - this
was better than being apart.
Just as they started, he heard his horse whinny.
First came the steep drop, and they seemed
to be flying through the air, high up into
the cloudy night. Then Ethan saw the big tree
at the corner of the road, and he said between
his teeth: 'We can do it; I know we can do
it -'
As they flew towards the tree, Mattie held
him closer and he seemed to feel her heart
beating. The tree became bigger and nearer.
'It's waiting for us; it knows,' he thought.
But suddenly his wife's face, grim and twisted,
appeared before him, and he moved to push
the picture away. There was a last moment
when the air shot past him like millions of
burning stars. And then the tree...
The sky was still cloudy, but when he looked
straight up he saw a single star. What was
its name? He used to know, but he couldn't
remember. He felt so tired... Through the
deep stillness, he heard a little animal making
a small, frightened sound. He knew the animal
was in terrible pain - he could feel its pain
shooting through his own body. He reached
out his left arm to help the poor animal,
and felt something soft under his hand. He
tried to move but could not, because there
was a rock, or some heavy thing, lying on
him. Then he realized that his hand was on
Mattie's face, and the sound was coming from
her lips...
He put his face next to hers, and in the darkness,
he saw her eyes open and heard her say his
name.
'Oh, Matt, I thought we'd done it,' he whispered;
and far away, up the hill, he heard the horse
whinny, and thought: 'I ought to give him
his supper...'
CHAPTER EIGHT
Endings
The whining voice stopped as I stepped into
Frome's kitchen. There were two women sitting
there, and I could not tell which one had
been the speaker.
One of them stood up when we entered, and
without a word went to bring a dish of food
to the table. She was tall and thin, and wore
an untidy, shapeless dress. Her lined face
and thin lips were of the same yellowish colour,
and she had thin grey hair and grey, lifeless
eyes.
The other woman was smaller, and she also
had grey hair and a thin, bloodless face.
She turned her head towards me quickly, but
her body did not move at all. Her dark eyes
shone with the crazy brightness that is sometimes
seen in people with disease of the spine.
The kitchen was a poor place. The few pieces
of furniture were of the poorest kind, mostly
broken and dirty.
'My, it's cold in here,' said Frome, looking
around.
The tall woman said nothing, but the dark-eyed
woman answered complainingly, in a thin, whining
voice:
'It's Zeena's fault. She fell asleep and the
fire went out. I've been so cold, waiting
for her to wake up.'
I knew then that it was her voice that I had
heard.
The tall woman brought the food to the table.
Frome looked at me and said: 'This is my wife,
Mrs Frome.' After a moment, he added, turning
to the figure in the armchair: 'And this is
Miss Mattie Silver...
Ruth Hale was very pleased to see me return
safely in the morning, and most surprised
to hear how I had spent the night.
'You must be the first stranger there in twenty
years,' she said. 'It's awful to see them,
all locked up together in that house. And
they're not easy people, any of them. Mattie
used to be; before the accident, she was a
really sweet girl. But not now - she's had
too much pain. Now, when she and Zeena fight,
the look on Ethan's face is enough to break
your heart.'
'Yes, it must be awful for them,' I agreed.
'It was just terrible at the beginning,' she
went on. 'They brought Mattie here, and I
stayed with her all night. Then in the morning,
she opened her eyes and said... Oh, I don't
know why I'm telling you this...' She stopped,
crying.
After a few moments, she dried her tears and
continued: 'Then when the doctors said we
could move Mattie, Zeena sent for her and
took her back to the farm.'
'And she's been there ever since?' I asked.
There was no other place for her to go,' Ruth
Hale answered simply; and I thought how hard
life was for the poor.
'Zeena's cared for the pair of them for over
twenty years now,' Ruth Hale went on. 'And
there they all are, shut up in that one kitchen.'
Then she looked at me and said in a low voice:
There was one day, about a week after the
accident, when they thought Mattie couldn't
live. Well, I say it was a pity she did. People
think that's an awful thing to say, but they
weren't with her when she first woke up...
And I say this, too. All those years with
Mattie have destroyed Ethan. The way they
are now, there's not much difference between
the Fromes up at the farm and the Fromes down
in their graves - except that down there they're
all silent and the women have to keep quiet.'
- THE END -