Rapacini's Daughter
Many years ago a young man named Giovanni
Guasconti left his home in Naples to study
in Northern Italy.
He rented a small room on the top floor of
a dark and ancient palace.
Long ago the building had belonged to a noble
family.
Now an old woman, Seniora Lisabetta rented
its rooms to students at the University of
Padua.
Giovanni's room had a small window.
From it he could see a large garden that had
many plants and flowers.
"Does the garden belong to you?" he asked
Seniora Lisabetta one day.
"Oh, no," she said quickly.
"That garden belongs to the famous doctor
Giacomo Rapacini.
People say he uses those plants to make strange
kinds of medicine.
He lives in that small brown house in the
garden with his daughter Beatrice."
Giovanni often sat by his window to look at
the garden.
He had never seen so many different kinds
of plants.
They all had enormous green leaves and magnificent
flowers in every color of the rainbow.
Giovanni's favorite plant was in a white marble
vase near the house.
It was covered with big purple flowers.
One day when Giovanni was looking out his
window he saw an old man in a black cape walking
in the garden.
The old man was tall and thin.
His face was an unhealthy yellow color.
His black eyes were very cold.
The old man wore thick gloves on his hands
and a mask over his mouth and nose.
He walked carefully among the plants as if
he were walking among wild animals or poisonous
snakes.
Although he looked at the flowers very closely
he did not touch or smell any of them.
When the old man arrived at the plant with
the big purple flowers he stopped.
He took off his mask and called loudly, "Beatrice!
Come help me!"
"I'm coming, Father.
What do you want?"
answered a warm young voice from inside the
house.
A young woman came into the garden.
Her thick dark hair fell around her shoulders
in curls.
Her cheeks were pink, and her eyes were large
and black.
She seemed full of life, health and energy
as she walked along the plants.
Giovanni thought she was as beautiful as the
purple flowers in the marble vase.
The old man said something to her.
She nodded her head as she touched and smelled
the flowers that her father had been so careful
to avoid.
Several weeks later Giovanni went to visit
Pietro Baglioni, a friend of his father's.
Professor Baglioni taught medicine at the
University.
During the visit Giovanni asked about Dr.
Rapacini.
"He is a great scientist," Professor Baglioni
replied.
"But he is also a dangerous man."
"Why?"
asked Giovanni.
The older man shook his head slowly.
"Because Rapacini cares more about science
than he does about people.
He has created many terrible poisons from
the plants in his garden.
He thinks he can cure sickness with these
poisons.
It is true, and several times he has cured
a very sick person that everyone thought would
die.
But Rapacini's medicine has also killed many
people.
I think he would sacrifice any life, even
his own, for one of his experiments."
"But, what about his daughter?"
Giovanni said.
"I'm sure he loves her."
The old professor smiled at the young man.
"So," he said, "you have heard about Beatrice
Rapacini.
People say she is very beautiful.
But few men in Padua have ever seen her.
She never leaves her father's garden."
Giovanni left Professor Baglioni's house as
the sun was setting.
On his way home he stopped at a flower shop
where he bought some fresh flowers.
He returned to his room and sat by the window.
There the little sunlight was left.
The garden was quiet.
The purple flowers on Giovanni's favorite
plant seemed to glow in the evening's fading
light.
Then someone came out of the doorway of the
little brown house.
It was Beatrice.
She entered the garden and walked along the
plants.
She bent to touch the leaves of a plant or
to smell a flower.
Rapacini's daughter seemed to grow more beautiful
with each step.
When she reached the purple plant she burled
her face in its flowers.
Giovanni heard her say, "Give me your breath,
my sister.
The ordinary air makes me weak.
And give me one of your beautiful flowers."
Beatrice gently broke off one of the largest
flowers.
As she lifted it to put it in her dark hair
a few drops of liquid from the flower fell
to the ground.
One of the drops landed on the head of a tiny
lizard crawling near the feet of Beatrice.
For a moment the small animal twisted violently.
Then, it moved no more.
Beatrice did not seem surprised.
She sighed and placed the flower in her hair.
Giovanni leaned out of the window so he'd
see her better.
At this moment a beautiful butterfly flew
over the garden wall.
It seemed to be attracted by Beatrice and
flew once around her head.
Then the insect's bright wings stopped and
it fell to the ground dead.
Beatrice shook her head sadly.
Suddenly, she looked up to Giovanni's window.
She saw the young man looking at her.
Giovanni picked up the flowers he had bought
and threw them down to her.
"Young lady," he said.
"Wear these flowers as a gift from Giovanni
Guasconti."
"Thank you," Beatrice answered.
She picked up the flowers from the ground
and quickly ran to the house.
She stopped at the door for a moment to wave
shyly at Giovanni.
It seemed to him that his flowers were beginning
to turn brown in her hands.
For many days the young man stayed away from
the window that looked out in Rapacini's garden.
He wished he'd not talked to Beatrice.
Because now he felt under the power of her
beauty.
He was a little afraid of her too.
He could not forget how the little lizard
and the butterfly had died.
One day while he was returning home from his
classes he met Professor Baglioni on the street.
"Well, Giovanni," the old man said.
"Have you forgotten me?"
Then he looked closely at the young man.
"What is wrong, my friend?
Your appearance has changed since the last
time we met."
It was true, Giovanni had become very thin.
His face was white and his eyes seemed to
burn with fever.
As they stood talking a man dressed in a long
black cape came down the street.
He moved slowly like a person in poor health.
His face was yellow but his eyes were sharp
and black.
It was the man Giovanni had seen in the garden.
As he passed them the old man nodded coldly
to Professor Baglioni, but he looked at Giovanni
with a great deal of interest.
"It's Dr. Rapacini," Professor Baglioni whispered
after the old man had passed them.
"Has he ever seen your face before?"
Giovanni shook his head.
"No," he answered.
"I don't think so."
Professor Baglioni looked worried.
"I think he has seen you before.
I know that cold look of his.
He looks the same way when he examines an
animal he has killed in one of his experiments.
Giovanni, I will bet my life on it, you are
the subject of one of Rapacini's experiments."
Giovanni stepped away from the old man.
"You are Joking," he said.
"No, I'm serious."
The professor took Giovanni's arm.
"Be careful, my young friend.
You are in great danger."
Giovanni pulled his arm away.
"I must be going," he said.
"Good night."
As Giovanni hurried to his room he felt confused
and a little frightened.
Seniora Lisabetta was waiting for him outside
his door.
She knew he was interested in Beatrice.
"I have good news for you," she said.
"I know where there is a secret entrance into
Rapacini's garden."
Giovanni could not believe his ears.
"Where is it?" he asked.
"Show me the way!"
He went in.
The plants all seemed wild and unnatural.
Giovanni realized that Rapacini must have
created these strange and terrible flowers
through his experiments.
Suddenly, Rapacini's daughter came into the
garden.
She moved quickly among the flowers until
she reached him.
Giovanni apologized for coming into the garden
without an invitation.
But Beatrice smiled at him and made him feel
welcome.
"I see you love flowers," she said.
"And so you have come to take a closer look
at my father's rare collection."
While she spoke Giovanni noticed a perfume
in the air around her.
He wasn't sure if this wonderful smell came
from the flowers or from her breath.
She asked him about his home and his family.
She told him she had spent her life in this
garden.
Giovanni felt as if he were talking to a very
small child.
Her spirits sparkled like clear water.
They walked slowly through the garden as they
talked.
At last, they reached a beautiful plant that
was covered with large purple flowers.
He realized that the perfume from those flowers
was like the perfume of Beatrice's breath,
but much stronger.
The young man reached out to break off one
of the purple flowers, but Beatrice gave a
scream that went through his heart like a
knife.
She caught his hand and pulled it away from
the plant with all her strength.
"Don't ever touch those flowers!"
she cried.
"They will take your life."
Hiding her face she ran into the house.
Then Giovanni saw Dr. Rapacini standing in
the garden.
That night Giovanni could not stop thinking
about how sweet and beautiful Beatrice was.
Finally, he fell asleep.
But, when the morning came he woke up in great
pain.
He felt as if one of his hands was on fire.
It was the hand that Beatrice had grabbed
in hers when he had reached for one of the
purple flowers.
Giovanni looked down at his hand.
There was a purple mark on it that looked
like four small fingers and a little thumb.
But, because his heart was full of Beatrice
Giovanni forgot about the pain in his hand.
He began to meet her in the garden every day.
At last she told him that she loved him.
But she would never let him kiss her or even
hold her hand.
One morning several weeks later Professor
Baglioni visited Giovanni.
"I was worried about you," the older man said.
"You have not come to your classes at the
University for more than a month.
Is something wrong?"
Giovanni was not pleased to see his old friend.
"No, nothing is wrong.
I am fine, thank you."
He wanted Professor Baglioni to leave, but
the old man took off his hat and sat down.
"My dear Giovanni," he said, "you must stay
away from Rapacini and his daughter.
Her father has given her poison from the time
she was a baby.
The 'poison is in her blood and on her breath.
If Rapacini did this to his own daughter what
is he planning to do to you?"
Giovanni covered his face with his hands.
"Oh, my god!" he cried.
"Don't worry," the old man continued.
"It is not too late to save you.
And we may succeed in helping Beatrice, too.
Do you see this little silver bottle?
It holds a medicine that will destroy even
the most powerful poison.
Give it to your Beatrice to drink."
Professor Baglioni put the little bottle on
the table and left Giovanni's room.
The young man wanted to believe that Beatrice
was a sweet and Innocent girl, and yet, Professor
Bagllonl's words had put doubts in his heart.
It was nearly time for his daily meeting with
Beatrice.
As Giovanni combed his hair he looked at himself
in the mirror near his bed.
He could not help noticing how handsome he
was.
His eyes looked particularly bright, and his
face had a healthy warm glow.
He said to himself, "At least her poison has
not gotten into my body yet."
As he spoke he happened to look at some flowers
he had Just bought that morning.
A shock of horror went through his body.
The flowers were turning brown.
Giovanni's face became very white as he stared
at himself in the mirror.
Then he noticed a spider crawling near his
window.
He bent over the insect and blew a breath
of air at it.
The spider trembled and fell dead.
"I am cursed," Giovanni whispered to himself.
"My own breath is poisoned."
At that moment, a rich, sweet voice came floating
up from the garden, "Giovanni, you are late.
Come down!"
"You are a monster!"
Giovanni shouted as soon as he reached her.
"And with your poison you have made me into
a monster too.
I am a prisoner of this garden."
"Giovanni!"
Beatrice cried looking at him with her large
bright eyes.
"Why are you saying these terrible things?
It is true that I can never leave this garden.
But you are free to go wherever you wish."
Giovanni looked at her with hate in his eyes.
"Don't pretend that you don't know what you've
done to me!"
A group of insects had flown into the garden.
They came toward Giovanni and flew around
his head.
He blew his breath at them.
The insects fell to the ground dead.
Beatrice screamed:
"I see it!
I see it!
My father's science has done this to us.
Believe me, Giovanni.
I did not ask him to do this to you.
I only wanted to love you."
Giovanni's anger changed to sadness.
Then he remembered the medicine that Professor
Baglioni had given him.
Perhaps, the medicine would destroy the poison
in their bodies and help them to become normal
again.
"Dear Beatrice," he said.
"Our fate is not so terrible."
He showed her the little silver bottle and
told her what the medicine inside it might
do.
"I will drink first," she said.
"You must wait to see what happens to me before
you drink it."
She put Baglioni's medicine to her lips and
took a small sip.
At the same moment Rapacini came out of his
house and walked slowly toward the two young
people.
He spread his hands out to them as if he were
giving them a blessing.
"My daughter," he said.
"You are no longer alone in the world.
Give Giovanni one of the purple flowers from
your favorite plant.
It will not hurt him now.
My science and your love have made him different
from ordinary men."
"My father," Beatrice said weakly, "why did
you do this terrible thing to your own child?"
Rapacini looked surprised.
"What do you mean, my daughter?" he asked.
"You have power no other woman has.
You can defeat your strongest enemy with only
your breath.
Would you rather be a weak woman?"
"I want to be loved, not feared," Beatrice
replied.
"But now it does not matter.
I am leaving you, Father.
I'm going where the poison you have given
me will do no harm.
Good-bye to you, Giovanni."
Beatrice dropped to the ground.
She died at the feet of her father and Giovanni.
The poison had been too much a part of the
young woman.
The medicine that destroyed the poison destroyed
her as well.
- THE END -