CHAPTER ONE
An African Story
In East Africa there was a young man who was
a hunter, who loved the plains and the valleys
and the cool nights on the slopes of Mount
Kilimanjaro.
In September 1939 war had begun in Europe
and he had travelled over the country to Nairobi
and was training to be a pilot with the RAF.
He was doing quite well, but after five weeks
he got into trouble because he took his plane
up and flew off in the direction of Nakuru
to look at the wild animals when he should
have been practicing spins and turns.
While he was flying there, he thought he saw
some rare animals, became excited and flew
down low to get a better view of them.
He flew too low and damaged the wing, but
he managed to get back to the airfield in
Nairobi.
After six weeks, he was allowed to make his
first cross-country flight on his own, and
he flew off from Nairobi to a little town
called Eldoret two thousand meters up in the
Highlands.
But again he was unlucky; this time he had
engine failure on the way, due to water in
the fuel tanks.
He kept calm and made a beautiful forced landing
without damaging his aircraft, not far from
a little hut which stood alone on the highland
plain with no other building in sight.
That is lonely country up there.
He walked over to the hut, and there he found
an old man, living alone, with only a small
garden of sweet potatoes, some brown chickens
and a black cow.
The old man was kind to him.
He gave him food and milk and a place to sleep,
and the pilot stayed with him for two days
and two nights, until a rescue plane from
Nairobi found his aircraft, landed beside
it, found out what was wrong, went away and
came back with clean petrol which enabled
him to take off and return.
But during his stay, the old man, who was
lonely and had seen no one for many months,
was glad of his company and of the opportunity
to talk.
He talked a lot and the pilot listened.
He talked of his lonely life, of the lions
that came in the night and of the elephant
that lived over the hill in the west, of the
heat of the days and of the silence that came
with the cold at midnight.
On the second night he talked about himself.
He told a long, strange story, and as he told
it, it seemed to the pilot that the old man
was lifting a great weight off his shoulders
by telling it.
When he had finished, he said that he had
never told that to anyone before, and that
he would never tell it to anyone again, but
the story was so strange that the pilot wrote
it down as soon as he got back to Nairobi.
He wrote it in his own words, although he
had never written a story before.
Of course he made mistakes because he didn't
know any of the tricks that writers use, but
when he had finished writing he left a rare
and powerful story.
We found the story in his suitcase two weeks
later when we were packing his things after
he had been killed in training.
The pilot seemed to have had no relatives
and because he was my friend, I took the story
and looked after it for him.
This is what he wrote.
The old man came out of the door into the
bright sunshine, and for a moment he leaned
on his stick and looked around him.
He stood with his head on one side, looking
up, listening for the noise which he thought
he had heard.
He was small and over seventy years old, although
he looked nearer eighty-five because of illness.
His face was covered with grey hair, and when
he moved his mouth, he moved it only on one
side of his face.
On his head, indoors or outdoors, he wore
a dirty white hat.
He stood quite still in the bright sunshine,
his eyes almost closed, listening for the
noise.
Yes, there it was again.
He looked towards the small wooden hut which
stood a hundred meters away in the field.
This time there was no doubt about it; the
cry of a dog, the high, sharp cry of pain
which a dog gives when he is in great danger.
Twice more it came and this time the noise
was more like a scream.
The note was higher and sharper, as if it
were torn from some small place inside the
body.
The old man turned and walked across the grass
towards the wooden hut where Judson lived,
pushed open the door and went in.
The small white dog was lying on the floor
and Judson was standing over it, his legs
apart, his black hair falling all over his
long red face, sweating through his dirty
white shirt.
His mouth hung open in a strange lifeless
way, as if his jaw were too heavy for him,
and there was spit down the middle of his
chin.
He stood there looking at the small white
dog which was lying on the floor, and with
one hand he was slowly twisting his left ear;
in the other hand he held a heavy wooden stick.
The old man ignored Judson and went down on
his knees beside his dog and gently moved
his thin hands over its body.
The dog lay still, looking up at him with
sad eyes.
Judson did not move.
He was watching the dog and the man.
Slowly, the old man got up, rising with difficulty,
holding the top of his stick with both hands
and pulling himself to his feet.
He looked around the room.
There were dirty bedclothes lying on the floor
in the far corner; there was a wooden table
made of old boxes, and on it a blue pot.
There were chicken feathers and mud on the
floor.
The old man saw what he wanted.
It was a heavy iron bar standing against the
wall near the bedding and he went over to
it, thumping the hollow wooden floorboards
with his stick as he went.
The eyes of the dog followed his movements
as he walked with difficulty across the room.
The old man changed his stick to his left
hand, took the iron bar in his right, came
back to the dog and, without pausing, lifted
the bar and brought it down hard upon the
animal's head.
He threw the bar to the ground and looked
up at Judson, who was standing there with
his legs apart.
He went right up to him and began to speak.
He spoke very quietly and slowly, with a terrible
anger, and as he spoke he moved only one side
of his mouth.
'You killed him,' he said.
'You broke his back.'
Then, as the tide of anger rose and gave him
strength, he found more words.
He looked up and spat them into the face of
the tall Judson, who moved back towards the
wall.
'You dirty, cruel coward.
That was my dog.
What right have you got to beat my dog, tell
me that.
Answer me, you madman.
Answer me.'
Judson was slowly rubbing his left hand up
and down the front of his shirt and now the
whole of his face began to tremble.
Without looking up he said, 'He wouldn't stop
licking that place on his leg.
I couldn't stand the noise it made.
You know I can't stand noises like that, licking,
licking, licking.
I told him to stop but he went on licking.
I couldn't stand it any longer, so I beat
him.'
The old man did not say anything.
For a moment it looked as if he were going
to hit this creature.
He half raised his arm, dropped it again,
spat on the floor, turned round and went out
of the door into the sunshine.
He went across the grass to where a black
cow was standing in the shade of a small tree.
The cow was eating, moving its jaws regularly,
mechanically, as it watched him walk across
the grass from the hut.
The old man came and stood beside it, stroking
its neck.
Then he leaned against its shoulder and scratched
its back with the end of his stick.
He stood there for a long time, leaning against
the cow, scratching it with his stick, and
now and then he spoke to it, whispering quiet
little words, like one person telling a secret
to another.
There was shade under the little tree, and
the country around him looked rich and pleasant
after the long rains, because the grass grows
green up in the Highlands of Kenya, and at
this time of the year, after the rains, it
is as green and rich as any grass in the world.
In the distance stood Mount Kenya with snow
on its head, with a thin stream of what looked
like white smoke coming from the top where
the cold winds made a storm and blew the white
powder from the top of the mountain.
Down below, on the slopes of that mountain,
there were lions and elephants, and sometimes
during the night one could hear the roar of
the lions as they looked at the moon.
The days passed and Judson went on with his
work on the farm in a silent, mechanical way,
taking in the corn, digging the potatoes and
milking the black cow while the old man stayed
indoors away from the fierce African sun.
He only went out in the late afternoon when
the air began to get cool and sharp, and then
he always went over to his black cow and spent
an hour with it under the tree.
One day, when he came out, he found Judson
standing beside the cow, looking at it strangely,
standing with one foot in front of the other,
gently twisting his ear with his right hand.
'What is it now?' said the old man.
'The cow's making that noise again.'
'She's just chewing the grass,' said the old
man.
'Leave her alone.'
Judson said, 'It's the noise.
Can't you hear it?
It sounds as if she's chewing stones, but
she isn't.
Listen to her.
The noise goes right into my head.'
'Get out,' said the old man.
'Get out of my sight.'
At dawn the old man sat, as he always did,
looking out of his window, watching Judson
come across from his hut to milk the cow.
He saw him coming sleepily across the field,
talking to himself as he walked, dragging
his feet, leaving long dark green marks across
the wet grass, and carrying the petrol can
which he used for the milk.
The sun was coming up and making long shadows
behind the man, the cow and the small tree.
The old man saw Judson put the can down and
he saw him fetch a box from beside the tree
and settle himself on it, ready for the milking.
He saw him suddenly kneeling down, feeling
under the cow with his hands, and at the same
time the old man noticed that the animal had
no milk.
He saw Judson get up and come walking fast
towards the hut.
He came and stood under the window where the
old man was sitting, and looked up.
'The cow's got no milk,' he said.
The old man leaned through the open window,
placing both his hands on the sill.
'You dirty thief!
You've stolen it.'
'I didn't take it,' said Judson.
'I've been asleep.'
'You stole it.'
The old man was leaning further out of the
window, speaking quietly with one side of
his mouth.
'I'll beat you for this,' he said.
Judson said, 'Someone stole it in the night.
Perhaps it was a native.
Or maybe the cow's sick.'
It seemed to the old man that he was telling
the truth.
'We'll see,' he said, 'if there's any milk
this evening; now, get out of my sight!'
By evening, the cow was full and the old man
watched Judson take good thick milk from her.
The next morning she was empty.
In the evening she was full.
On the third morning she was empty again.
On the third night, the old man went to watch.
As soon as it began to get dark, he positioned
himself at the open window with an old gun
lying on his lap, waiting for the thief who
came and milked his cow in the night.
At first it was dark and he could not even
see the cow, but soon a three-quarter moon
came over the hills and it became light, almost
as if it were daytime.
But it was bitterly cold because the Highlands
are two thousand meters up, and the old man
pulled his brown blanket closer around his
shoulders.
He could see the cow well now, just as well
as in daylight, and the little tree threw
a shadow across the grass, since the moon
was behind it.
All through the night, the old man sat there
watching the cow, and except when he got up
and went back into the room to fetch another
blanket, his eyes never left her.
The cow stood calmly under the small tree,
chewing and staring at the moon.
An hour before dawn she was full.
The old man could see it; he had been watching
it the whole time, and although he had not
seen the movement of the swelling, all the
time he had been conscious of the filling
as the milk came down.
The moon was now low, but the light had not
gone.
He could see the cow and the little tree and
the greenness of the grass around the cow.
Suddenly he moved his head quickly.
He heard something.
Surely that was a noise he heard?
Yes, there it was again, right under the window
where he was sitting.
Quickly he pulled himself up and looked over
the sill to the ground.
Then he saw it.
A large black snake, a Mamba, nearly three
meters long and as thick as a man's arm, was
sliding towards the cow.
Its small head was raised slightly off the
ground and the movement of its body against
the wetness made a sound like gas escaping
from a jet.
He raised his gun to shoot.
Almost at once he lowered it again - he didn't
know why - and he sat there not moving, watching
the Mamba as it approached the cow, listening
to the noise it made as it went, watching
it come up close to the cow and waiting for
it to strike.
But it did not strike.
It lifted its head and for a moment let it
move gently from side to side; then it raised
the front part of its black body into the
air under the cow and began to drink from
her.
The cow did not move.
There was no noise anywhere, and the body
of the Mamba curved gracefully up from the
ground and hung under the cow.
The black snake and the black cow were clearly
visible out there in the moonlight.
For half an hour the old man watched the Mamba
taking the milk of the cow.
He saw the gentle movement of the snake's
body as it sucked at the liquid until at last
there was no milk left.
Then the Mamba lowered itself to the ground
and slid back through the grass in the direction
from which it had come.
Again it made a soft noise as it went, and
again it passed underneath the window where
the old man was sitting, leaving a thin dark
mark in the wet grass where it had gone.
Then it disappeared behind the hut.
Slowly the moon went down behind the mountain
in the distance.
Almost at the same time the sun rose in the
east and Judson came out of his hut with the
petrol can in his hand, walking sleepily towards
the cow, dragging his feet in the wet grass
as he went.
The old man watched him coming and waited.
Judson bent down and felt the underneath of
the cow, and as he did so, the old man shouted
at him.
Judson jumped at the sound of the old man's
voice.
'It's gone again,' said the old man.
Judson said, 'Yes, the cow's empty.'
'I think,' said the old man slowly, 'that
it was a native boy.
I was sleeping a bit and only woke up as he
was leaving.
I couldn't shoot because the cow was in the
way.
I'll wait for him tonight.
I'll get him tonight,' he added.
Judson did not answer.
He picked up his can and walked back to his
hut.
That night the old man sat up again by the
window, watching the cow.
For him there was this time a certain pleasure
in waiting for what he was going to see.
He knew that he would see the Mamba again,
but he wanted to be quite sure.
And so, when the great black snake slid across
the grass towards the cow an hour before sunrise,
the old man leaned over the window sill and
watched the movements of the Mamba as it approached
the cow.
He saw it wait for a moment under the animal's
stomach, letting its head move slowly backwards
and forwards half a dozen times before it
finally raised its body from the ground and
started to drink the milk.
He saw it drink for half an hour, until there
was none left, and he saw it lower its body
and slide smoothly back behind the hut from
where it had come.
And while he watched these things, the old
man began laughing quietly with one side of
his mouth.
Then the sun rose up behind the hills, and
Judson came out of his hut with the petrol
can in his hand, but this time he went straight
to the window of the hut where the old man
was sitting, wrapped up in his blankets.
'What happened?' said Judson.
The old man looked down at him from the window.
'Nothing,' he said.
'Nothing happened.
I fell asleep again and the native came and
took the milk.
Listen, Judson,' he added, 'we have to catch
this boy, otherwise you won't have enough
milk.
We've got to catch him.
I can't shoot because he's too clever; the
cow's always in the way.
You'll have to get him.'
'Me get him?
How?'
The old man spoke very slowly.
'I think,' he said, 'I think you must hide
beside the cow.
That is the only way you can catch him.'
Judson was scratching his head with his left
hand.
'Today you will dig a shallow hole beside
the cow.
If you lie in it and if I cover you over with
cut grass, the thief won't notice until he's
beside you.'
'He may have a knife,' Judson said.
'No, he won't have a knife.
You take your stick.
That's all you'll need.'
Judson said, 'Yes, I'll take my stick.
When he comes, I'll jump up and beat him with
my stick.'
Then suddenly he seemed to remember something.
'What about the noise the cow makes when she's
chewing?' he said.
'I couldn't stand that noise all night.'
He began twisting at his left ear with his
hand.
'You'll do as I tell you,' said the old man.
That day Judson dug his hole beside the cow.
The cow was tied to the tree so that she could
not wander around the field.
Then, as evening came and he was preparing
to lie down in the hole for the night, the
old man came to the door of the house and
said, 'Don't do anything until early morning.
He won't come until the cow's full.
Come in here and wait; it's warmer than your
dirty little hut.'
Judson had never been invited into the old
man's house before.
He followed him in, happy that he would not
have to lie all night in the hole.
There was a candle burning in the room.
It was stuck in the neck of a beer bottle
and the bottle was on the table.
'Make some tea,' said the old man.
Judson did as he was told.
The two of them sat down on a couple of wooden
boxes and began to drink.
The old man drank his tea hot and made loud
sucking noises as he drank.
Judson kept blowing on his tea, drinking cautiously
and watching the old man over the top of his
cup.
The old man kept sucking at his tea until
suddenly Judson said, 'Stop.'
He said it quietly, and as he said it, the
corners of his eyes and mouth began to tremble.
'What?' said the old man.
Judson said, 'That noise, that sucking noise
you're making.'
The old man put down his cup and looked at
the other quietly for a few moments.
Then he said, 'How many dogs have you killed,
Judson?'
There was no answer.
'I said how many?
How many dogs?
Judson!'
the old man shouted.
Then quietly and very slowly, like someone
to a child, he said, 'In all your life, how
many dogs have you killed?'
Judson said, 'Why should I tell you?'
He did not look up.
'I want to know, Judson.'
The old man was speaking very gently.
'I'm getting interested in this, too.
Let's talk about it and make some plans for
more fun.'
Judson looked up.
A ball of spit rolled down his chin, hung
for a moment in the air and fell to the floor.
'I only kill them because of their noise.'
'How often have you done it?
I'd love to know how often.'
'Lots of times long ago.'
'How?
Tell me how you used to do it.
What way did you like best?'
No answer.
'Tell me, Judson.
I'd love to know.'
'I don't see why I should tell you.
It's a secret.'
'I won't tell.
I swear I won't tell.'
'Well, if you promise.'
Judson shifted his seat closer and spoke in
a whisper.
'Once I waited till one was sleeping, then
I got a big stone and dropped it on his head.'
The old man got up and poured himself a cup
of tea.
'You didn't kill mine like that.'
'I didn't have time.
The noise of its tongue was so bad, the licking.
I just had to do it quickly.'
'You didn't even kill him.'
'I stopped the licking.'
The old man went over to the door and looked
out.
It was dark.
The moon had not yet risen, but the night
was clear and cold, with many stars.
In the east there was a little paleness in
the sky, and as he watched, the paleness grew
and it changed into brightness.
Slowly, the moon rose over the hills.
The old man turned and said, 'You'd better
get ready.
You never know.
He might come early tonight.'
Judson got up and the two of them went outside.
Judson lay down in the shallow hole beside
the cow and the old man covered him with grass,
so that only his hand showed above the ground.
'I'll be watching, too,' he said, 'from the
window.
If I give a shout, jump up and catch him.'
He went back to the hut, went upstairs, wrapped
himself in blankets and took up his position
by the window.
It was early still.
The moon was nearly full and it was rising.
It shone on the snow on top of Mount Kenya.
After an hour, the old man shouted out of
the window, 'Are you still awake, Judson?'
'Yes,' he answered, 'I'm awake.'
'Don't go to sleep,' said the old man.
'Whatever you do, don't go to sleep.'
'The cow's making that noise all the time,'
said Judson.
'Good, and I'll shoot you if you get up now,'
said the old man.
'You'll shoot me?'
'I said I'll shoot you if you get up now.'
A gentle noise came from where Judson lay,
a strange sound as if a child were trying
not to cry, and in the middle of it, Judson's
voice.
'I've got to move; please let me move.
This chewing!'
'If you get up,' said the old man, 'I'll shoot
you in the stomach.'
For another hour or so the crying continued,
then quite suddenly it stopped.
Just before four o'clock, it began to get
very cold and the old man shouted, 'Are you
cold out there, Judson?
Are you cold?'
'Yes,' came the answer.
'So cold.
But I don't mind because the cow's not chewing
any more.
She's asleep.'
The old man said, 'What are you going to do
with the thief when you catch him?'
'I don't know.'
'Will you kill him?'
A pause.
'I don't know.
I'll just grab him.'
'I'll watch,' said the old man.
'It should be fun.'
He was leaning out of the window with his
arms resting on the sill.
Then he heard the soft noise under the window,
looked out and saw the black Mamba, sliding
through the grass towards the cow, going fast
and holding its head just a little above the
ground as it went.
When the Mamba was five meters away, the old
man shouted, 'Here he comes, Judson; here
he comes.
Go and get him.'
Judson lifted his head quickly and looked
up.
As he did so he saw the Mamba and the Mamba
saw him.
There was a second, or perhaps two, when the
snake stopped, pulled its head back and raised
the front part of its body in the air.
Then the stroke.
Just a flash of black and a slight thump as
it hit him in the chest.
Judson screamed, a long high scream which
did not rise or fall, but remained constant
until gradually it faded into nothingness
and there was silence.
Now he was standing up, tearing open his shirt,
feeling for the place in his chest, crying
quietly and breathing hard with his mouth
wide open.
And the old man sat quietly at the open window,
leaning forward and never taking his eyes
away from the scene below.
Everything happens very quickly when one is
bitten by a snake, by a black Mamba, and almost
at once the poison began to work.
He fell to the ground, where he lay on his
back, rolling around on the grass.
He no longer made any noise.
It was all very quiet, as if a man of great
strength were fighting with someone whom one
could not see, and it was as if this invisible
person were twisting him and not letting him
get up, stretching his arms through the fork
of his legs and pushing his knees up under
his chin.
Then he began pulling up the grass with his
hands and soon after that he lay on his back
kicking gently with his legs.
But he didn't last very long.
He gave a quick shake, twisted his back, then
lay on the ground quite still, lying on his
stomach with his right knee underneath his
chest and his hands stretched out above his
head.
Still the old man sat by the window, and even
after it was all over, he stayed where he
was and did not move.
There was a movement in the shadow under the
little tree and the Mamba came forward slowly
towards the cow.
It came forward a little, stopped, raised
its head, waited, and slid forward again right
under the stomach of the cow.
It raised itself into the air and began to
drink.
The old man sat watching the Mamba taking
the milk of the cow, and once again he saw
the gentle movement of its body as it sucked
out the liquid.
While the snake was still drinking, the old
man got up and moved away from the window.
'You can have his share,' he said quietly.
'We don't mind you having his share,' and
as he spoke, he glanced back and saw again
the black body of the Mamba curving upwards
from the ground, joining the underneath of
the cow.
'Yes,' he said again, 'we don't mind you having
his share.'
- THE END -