CHAPTER ONE
In the beginning
Think of a big, beautiful, empty land with
mountains, forests, lakes, animals, and fish,
but no people.
This was America 16,000 years ago.
Around that time, the first people probably
arrived in Alaska from Asia.
They travelled south and became the Native
Americans of North America and the Maya, Aztecs,
Inca and other peoples of Central and South
America.
The Inuit (Eskimos) came to Canada and the
Arctic the same way.
But there are only a few of these peoples
in America today.
In the sixteenth century Europeans started
to come to America, and soon after that, they
brought slaves from Africa to work for them.
Large numbers of immigrants continued to arrive
from all over the world until the middle of
the twentieth century.
The empty land was now full of people, speaking
different languages and with different ideas.
There are just three countries now in North
America - Canada, Mexico and the USA - but
there were nearly several more.
And the 300 million people who live in the
fifty states of the United States are not
all the same.
About 67 per cent are white, 13 per cent Hispanic
(Spanish-speaking), 13 per cent black, 4 per
cent Asian and just 1 per cent Native American.
Most of them speak English, but it is not
the same English as people speak in Britain,
and many Americans speak Spanish as their
first language.
So how was the USA born?
How did it grow?
What kind of country is it now?
This book will try to answer those questions,
and many more.
CHAPTER TWO
The Pilgrim Fathers
The name 'America' comes from an Italian businessman
called Amerigo Vespucci, who sailed to South
America between 1499 and 1502.
But he was not the first European to make
the dangerous journey across the Atlantic.
The Vikings came to 'Vinland' (probably Canada
or New England) from Scandinavia around AD
1000, but they did not stay.
Then, in 1492, a brave Italian sailor called
Christopher Columbus reached the Caribbean
while he was looking for a sea route from
Europe to India.
Columbus called the Native Americans 'Indians'
because he thought that he had reached India.
When Columbus returned to Europe he told people
about his adventures and other sailors like
Cabot and Cartier followed him across the
Atlantic.
Europeans came to fish the rich seas of America
too.
But it was only in the seventeenth century
that the French, the Dutch and the British
all came to live in North America: the French
in Quebec, the Dutch in New York and the British
in Virginia and New England.
Two very different groups of English people
crossed the Atlantic.
The first group began the colony of Jamestown
in Virginia in 1607.
They hoped to find gold there, but life was
very hard for them.
There was very little food, and many of them
died during the first winter.
Then Pocahontas, the daughter of a Native
American chief, became a friend of Captain
John Smith and helped him and the other English
people.
She later married a man called John Rolfe
and went to England with him.
Luckily, tobacco saved the young colony.
It was easy to grow tobacco in Virginia, and
smoking was becoming very fashionable.
People in the colony stopped looking for gold
and began to grow tobacco, which they sold
in Europe.
Soon they started to bring people from Africa
to work as their slaves and help them to grow
more and more.
John Smith travelled north in 1614 to the
part of America that he called New England.
When he returned to London, he told people
that it was a good place to live.
In 1620, another group of 101 English men,
women and children arrived in Plymouth, Massachusetts.
These people are called the 'Pilgrims' or
'Pilgrim Fathers', and they had very strong
ideas about religion.
They did not want to live in England because
they did not agree with the English church,
so they sailed to America in a ship called
the Mayflower.
They farmed the land and they bought and sold
animal skins.
They thought that all people were equal and
so they did not have slaves.
The Pilgrims too were often ill and hungry,
and nearly half of them died in the first
year.
But they had help from some of the Native
Americans, particularly a man called Squanto.
He went to Europe as a prisoner in 1605, and
spent some years in England, so he spoke some
English.
He showed the Pilgrims how to hunt and grow
corn.
In the autumn of 1621, the Pilgrims had a
big dinner to give thanks for the first food
that they had grown themselves.
This day was called Thanksgiving, and Americans
still celebrate it every year, on the fourth
Thursday of November.
It is one of the most important holidays in
the year, and people often travel many hundreds
of kilometres to be with their families.
They eat a big dinner with two of the foods
that the Pilgrim Fathers found in America,
turkey and pie filled with pumpkin.
CHAPTER THREE
The War of Independence
More and more British people came to live
on the east coast of North America in the
seventeenth century, starting colonies in
Maryland, Rhode Island, Connecticut, New Hampshire,
North and South Carolina, New Jersey, and
Pennsylvania.
Georgia followed in the eighteenth century,
when the British also took New York and Delaware
from the Dutch.
By 1770, there were thirteen colonies along
the east coast of North America, and they
were all governed by Britain.
But Britain was a long way away, and the people
of the colonies became angry at the high taxes
that the government made them pay.
In December 1773 a group of men threw 342
boxes of tea into the sea at Boston because
they did not want to pay the British tax on
it.
This was the 'Boston Tea Party'.
The British government was now angry too,
and in April 1775 some Americans fought a
group of British soldiers at the towns of
Lexington and Concord, near Boston in Massachusetts.
More and more Americans arrived until the
British soldiers had to move back to Boston.
A few months later, after the Battle of Bunker
Hill, near Boston, it was clear that Britain
was at war with its American colonies.
A rich farmer from Virginia, George Washington,
became the chief of the American army.
People tell a story about Washington, to show
that he was an honest man.
They say that when he was a boy he cut down
a tree and this made his father angry.
But when his father asked him about it, he
told him, 'I cannot tell a lie, I cut down
the tree.'
The colonies did not say that they wanted
to be fully independent until the summer of
1776.
A man called Thomas Jefferson wrote the famous
'Declaration of Independence' where he said
that the king, George the Third, was not a
good king because he had not let his people
have their rights: the right to life, to freedom
and to happiness.
The day of the Declaration of Independence,
4 July, is another important American holiday.
The Americans finally won the war in October
1781, and two years after that, they were
free to govern themselves.
In 1789 they made George Washington their
first president.
Although he wanted to go back to his farm
at Mount Vernon and enjoy a quiet life he
stayed president until 1797.
He died in 1799, just two years after he returned
home.
The names 'United States of America' and 'American'
were first used at the time of the War of
Independence.
The thirteen colonies became the first thirteen
states of the United States.
In 1803, after Jefferson became the third
president, he bought a large area of land
in the Midwest from France.
It was five times as big as France, and it
only cost 15 million dollars.
Jefferson then sent two brave men, Meriwether
Lewis and William Clark, to travel across
America all the way to the Pacific.
With a young Native American woman called
Sacagawea to help them, the two men travelled
13,000 kilometres between 1804 and 1806.
They found many animals, plants, and fish
that were new to Europeans, and they made
maps of the rivers, mountains, and land that
they crossed.
In 1819, the USA bought Florida from Spain.
The United States was now twice as big as
it had been in 1781.
And by 1848, after it won Texas and the Southwest
from Mexico, it had grown again.
It now reached all the way from the Atlantic
to the Pacific, over 5,000 kilometres.
Finally, the American government bought the
land north-west of Canada from Russia in 1867
for 7.2 million dollars and it became the
state of Alaska in 1959.
The American flag, known as the 'Stars and
Stripes', first appeared at the time of the
War of Independence.
It has a stripe for each of the first thirteen
states, and a star was added every time a
new state joined, so there are now fifty stars.
The last star was added when the beautiful
islands of Hawaii, in the Pacific 4,000 kilometres
west of California, became the fiftieth state
of the USA in 1959.
CHAPTER FOUR
The Civil War
The young country grew quickly, and by the
middle of the nineteenth century it had 31
million people.
But there were serious differences between
the North and the South.
And in 1861 a terrible war started.
At least 600,000 people died in the battles
or from disease.
The war began because the southern states
kept slaves to work in the cotton fields but
slaves were not allowed in the North.
People from the South wanted to have slaves
in the new lands of the west, but people from
the North argued against this.
In 1860, Abraham Lincoln was elected sixteenth
president of the USA.
He belonged to the Republican Party, which
did not want people to have slaves.
On 24 December, South Carolina said that it
wanted to be independent and the other southern
states soon followed.
The fighting began on 12 April 1861, at Fort
Sumter.
The South had some of the best soldiers - one
was the famous Robert E. Lee - and they had
plenty of money from selling their cotton
to Britain.
But the North had more men and more factories.
They also had Lincoln, one of the best presidents
that the USA has ever had.
He was born on a farm in Kentucky but he worked
hard in order to learn as much as he could.
Lincoln made the Republican Party strong and
spoke about rights and freedom.
A very important battle was won by the soldiers
of the North at Gettysburg in Pennsylvania
in 1863.
Lincoln spoke there afterwards about the brave
soldiers who had died.
This became known as the Gettysburg Address
and contains the famous words: '...government
of the people, by the people, for the people.'
Two famous soldiers helped the North to win
the war.
General Sherman is remembered in a famous
song that tells the story of how he took 60,000
of his soldiers on a journey of 400 kilometres
from Atlanta in Georgia to the Atlantic coast.
In this way he cut a wide path through the
southern states, and after that it was hard
for the armies of the South to join together
and fight the North.
After the war, Sherman became head of the
American army.
General Ulysses S. Grant represented the North
at Appomattox in 1865 when the South, under
Lee, accepted that they had lost the war.
Grant was very fair to Lee's soldiers, who
did not have to go to prison.
Some years later, in 1868, he became president.
Sadly, on 14 April 1865, five days after the
end of the war, President Lincoln was shot
at the theatre by a man called John Wilkes
Booth, who hated Lincoln and was angry about
the war.
After Lincoln's death, the new president was
not strong enough to bring the North and the
South together, and people continued to argue
about the rights of black people.
During the Civil War Louisa May Alcott wrote
her famous book Little Women about a family
of four girls living at home in the North
with their mother while their father was away
at the war.
Another very famous book (and later film)
about the war is Gone with the Wind written
in 1936.
It tells the story of Scarlett O'Hara, a rich
young girl who is living comfortably in the
southern state of Georgia when her life is
destroyed by the war.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Wild West
During the nineteenth century, more and more
people went to live in the West of the USA.
The 'Wild West' that you can see on television
and in films is full of cowboys, Indians,
and fighting.
In fact there were very few cowboys - no more
than 40,000 - and real cowboys did not shoot
each other or fight Indians very often.
They worked hard at their job, taking care
of the cows, and at least a quarter of them
were black or Mexican.
They took cows from Texas up to the railway
towns in Kansas and Missouri.
From there the cows were sent to Chicago and
killed, and the meat was sent to the East
and sold.
The cowboys almost disappeared after about
thirty years because the government gave the
land to farmers and their families.
From 1862 to 1900 more than half a million
farmers came to live in the West, where they
made new farms and grew food.
One family that moved west was the Ingalls
family, whose daughter Laura Ingalls Wilder
told the story of their journey in books like
Little House on the Prairie.
Life for these farmers was very hard, particularly
in winter.
The farms were very lonely, but soon the railways
helped to bring people together.
In 1869, the railway line from the east met
the line from the west in Utah, so then Americans
could travel right across the USA by train.
Before the railway, from 1860 to 1861 the
post was carried across the country by the
famous Pony Express.
Horses and riders waited at different places;
one man rode with a bag of letters for about
120 kilometres and then gave it to the next
man.
In this way, letters only took about ten days
to cross the country.
One very well-known rider was Buffalo Bill
Cody.
He later became a soldier and a hunter - they
say that he shot 4,280 buffalo in one year!
In the 1880s, Buffalo Bill started his Wild
West Show, a kind of travelling theatre, with
the famous cowgirl Annie Oakley.
CHAPTER SIX
Native Americans
There were about two million Native Americans
in North America in the fifteenth century
when the Europeans arrived.
They belonged to 300 different groups and
spoke more than 2,000 different languages.
Sadly, the Europeans fought and killed many
Native Americans and also brought diseases
which killed them.
The film The Last of the Mohicans, from the
book by James Fenimore Cooper, shows the sad
end of a group of Native Americans in the
eighteenth century.
The Native Americans that we know as 'Indians'
in cowboy films lived in the West.
They were the Cheyenne, the Blackfoot, and
the Sioux (also known as Lakota), for example.
There were about 60 million buffalo in North
America, and the Native Americans hunted them
and used them for food, clothes, houses, knives,
and other things.
But when the Europeans arrived, they wanted
to take the land for farms or railways.
They shot millions of buffalo, and by 1900
there were fewer than a thousand of these
animals in all of the USA - and fewer than
250,000 Native Americans!
The great Sioux chief Sitting Bull fought
against the white men who wanted to move his
people from their own land to 'Indian' land
further west.
He won an important battle at Little Big Horn
in 1876 but could not win the war.
The 'Indian wars' ended in 1890 with the Battle
of Wounded Knee, when American soldiers killed
many Sioux men, women and children.
After this, Native Americans had to live in
special places called 'reservations'.
Even today, about a third of the 4.4 million
Native Americans live on reservations.
They are often very poor and a lot of them
do not have jobs, so they sometimes drink
too much alcohol in order to forget their
problems.
Some Native Americans build casinos where
people can go to win money from cards and
other games, and this brings in money for
the reservations.
Other groups refuse to do this and also do
not allow alcohol on their reservations.
Many of the big reservations are in the Southwest,
the home of a different type of Native American.
Among the people of the Southwest are the
Hopi and the Zuni.
They keep sheep, make pots, and also make
beautiful jewellery from silver and blue-green
stones.
Their religion is very important to them;
their dancing often has a religious meaning,
and they make beautiful religious pictures.
The biggest reservation, where 200,000 Navajo
people live, is nearly 65,000 square kilometres.
The Navajo make wonderful coloured blankets.
The Navajo language is very unusual; during
the Second World War, the American army used
Navajo soldiers to send secret radio messages
that the enemy could not understand.
CHAPTER SEVEN
New Americans
At the beginning of the nineteenth century
most American families had come from Britain,
Germany and Scandinavia, and they were farmers
or businesspeople.
But soon that began to change.
Factories were built and cities grew; poor
people arrived from other countries, hoping
to find work.
Between 1840 and 1900, about five million
people came from one country - Ireland.
Another five million immigrants came from
Italy, and millions more from Russia, Poland,
and other countries of Eastern Europe, hoping
to find jobs and freedom.
America kept an 'open door' until 1924 and
about 27 million people arrived between 1880
and 1930.
They were often poor, had different religions,
and had not been to school for very long;
there was a lot of prejudice against them.
Immigrants from Europe arrived at Ellis Island
in New York, where they were all checked for
disease and for other problems.
Close to Ellis Island is the Statue of Liberty
(liberty means 'freedom').
On it are these famous words: 'Give me your
tired, your poor ...' The statue welcomed
the poor, tired immigrants who hoped for a
happier life in the USA.
The Chinese immigrants who arrived in the
West of the USA also found prejudice.
Many people came to live in California after
gold was found there in 1848, and among them
were 300,000 Chinese.
Many of the Chinese stayed to work building
the new railways.
Like black people and Native Americans, the
Chinese had no civil rights and after 1882,
they were no longer allowed to enter the USA.
But in the twentieth century Chinese people
started to arrive again and now the cities
of the west coast have large numbers of Chinese
families.
The writer Amy Tan tells stories about life
as a Chinese American in The Joy Luck Club
and other books.
Today, most immigrants to the USA come from
Spanish-speaking countries like Mexico and
Puerto Rico.
More than six million have arrived since 1980
and Spanish has become the second language
of the United States.
The Irish, Italians and Eastern Europeans
usually stayed in the big cities of the East
or the Midwest, like New York, Boston or Chicago,
and worked in the factories.
Although most of them learned English and
became Americans, they also wanted to keep
their own way of life.
So in many cities you can find places called
Little Italy or Chinatown, for example, where
the restaurants have Italian or Chinese food.
In New York, Boston, and Chicago, St Patrick's
Day is a big celebration for the Irish on
17 March and Chinese New Year is a big celebration
in San Francisco.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Black Americans
Today about 39 million of the 300 million
people in the USA are black.
They used to live mostly in the South, working
in the cotton and tobacco fields.
A story about the hard life of slaves, Uncle
Tom's Cabin by Harriet Beecher Stowe, was
very popular in the mid-nineteenth century.
It made a lot of people see that keeping slaves
was wrong, and it told the exciting story
of how a slave family escaped, using the 'Underground
Railway'.
This was not a real railway but a number of
places where slaves could find help.
People in each house could show them the way
to the next safe house.
Harriet Tubman and Frederick Douglass were
famous slaves who helped many other slaves
to escape from the South to the North using
the Underground Railway.
Frederick Douglass escaped in 1838 and started
to work for the freedom of other black people.
He had understood that in order to be free
he needed to learn to read and write and he
wrote a book about his life.
After this he travelled to Europe to speak
about slavery and later returned to New York
and started several newspapers.
During the Civil War he told black men to
join the army to fight for the North and after
the war he worked for the government.
Harriet Tubman travelled 140 kilometres to
freedom in 1849 with the help of white people
and free blacks.
Although it was dangerous, she returned in
order to help her family, and she bravely
said, 'I can only die once.'
In the 1850s she helped more than 300 slaves
escape.
After the Civil War, white southerners were
angry that they had lost the war and angry
that slaves were now free.
They showed a lot of prejudice against black
people.
Some white people joined the Ku Klux Klan,
groups of men who dressed in white, covered
their faces, and went out to beat and murder
black people.
Black men could not vote until 1870, and even
after they got the right to vote, they often
did not use it because they were frightened.
The book To Kill a Mocking Bird by Harper
Lee tells the frightening story of a black
man, Tom Robinson, in 1930s Alabama.
Although Tom has done nothing wrong, people
easily believe that he is a criminal - just
because he is black.
In the twentieth century, black people began
to travel to the cities of the North to look
for work, so there are now more black people
in the North than in the South.
But even in the North, they lived separately.
In the South they had to sit separately on
buses and eat in separate parts of restaurants.
Until 1954, they also had to go to different
schools.
Then in the 1950s, a churchman called Martin
Luther King began to fight for the civil rights
of black people.
Groups of black people started to break the
law, but not in a violent way.
In 1955 in Montgomery, Alabama, a woman called
Rosa Parks became famous when she refused
to give her seat on a bus to a white man.
Then more black people refused to use the
buses, and the bus companies lost a lot of
money.
Black people also started to go into 'whites
only' restaurants.
In August 1963 200,000 people met in Washington
and heard Martin Luther King speak about the
need for black people to be equal with white
people.
He began with these words, which have become
famous: 'I have a dream...'
Finally, in 1964, a law was passed which gave
black people their rights and Martin Luther
King was given the Nobel Peace Prize.
But in 1968, he was murdered in Memphis and
fighting started in more than a hundred cities.
During the 1970s and 1980s, prejudice against
black people slowly began to appear less often,
and many black people now have good jobs in
business and government.
A black woman like Condoleezza Rice can represent
the American government in other countries
and perhaps even think about becoming president.
But there are still problems.
When Hurricane Katrina destroyed the city
of New Orleans in 2005, most of the people
who lost their houses were black.
Many of them waited a long time for help from
the government.
Was it because they were black?
A lot of people think so.
CHAPTER NINE
The government of the USA
The government of the USA has three separate
but equal parts: Congress, the President,
and the Supreme Court.
Women got the vote in 1920 and all Americans
can now vote when they are eighteen.
There are some rights that all Americans have
by law: for example, the right to speak freely.
Congress makes the laws.
There are in fact two 'houses' of Congress:
the Senate and the House of Representatives.
There are a hundred people in the Senate (two
from each state) and they are elected for
six years.
There are 435 people in the House of Representatives,
and they are elected for two years only.
The states with more people, like California,
have more representatives.
States which do not have many people, like
Wyoming or Delaware, only have one representative.
The President is elected by votes from each
state.
A state has the same number of votes as the
number of its representatives and senators,
so the states with most people become very
important.
Florida has 25 votes and so when just 51 per
cent of people in Florida voted for George
Bush in 2000 he got all 25 votes from that
state.
The President is the most important of all
the people in the government.
He (until now the president has always been
a man) is the chief of the country, like a
king or queen, and he is also the head of
the army.
He is elected for four years and no one can
be president for more than eight years.
He can say 'no' to laws passed by Congress
(but Congress can also say 'no' to him), and
he chooses the judges for the Supreme Court.
He lives and works in the White House in Washington
DC.
The Supreme Court is the most important court
in the country and has nine judges; their
job is to decide what the laws mean.
They can also say that Congress has made a
law which is wrong, or that the President
has done something wrong.
As well as the government in Washington, each
state has its own government.
Laws can be very different from one state
to the next.
They say very different things about, for
example, how old you must be to get married,
or to drive a car.
Different states punish criminals differently
too; in some states, you must die if you murder
someone, but in others you only go to prison.
The island of Puerto Rico in the Caribbean
is not a state, but it is not independent
either.
People from Puerto Rico do not pay American
taxes and cannot vote in American elections.
There are two important political parties:
the Republicans and the Democrats.
The Republicans want people to work to help
themselves, and so they think that taxes should
be low.
The Democrats think that the government should
help the poor and so it needs taxes.
But the difference between the two is not
always clear.
After the 2000 election a map showed that
the Democrat states were on the north-east
and west coasts and around the Great Lakes
in the North, but the Republican states were
across the centre and in the South of the
USA.
Americans are happy that they do not have
a king or queen and they say that anyone can
become president.
But you need a lot of money to tell people
about yourself and your ideas, so it is easier
to become president if you come from a rich
family.
The second and sixth presidents, John Adams
and John Quincy Adams, were father and son,
and in modern times the Bush family has had
two presidents.
From 1989 to 1993 George Bush was president,
and in 2001 his son George W. Bush became
president too.
At the same time Jeb Bush, the brother of
George W. Bush, was head of the government
of Florida.
Some other families have also nearly had two
presidents.
President Kennedy's brother Robert hoped to
become president but he was killed in 1968,
and many people think that Hillary Clinton
will follow her husband Bill.
If she does, she will be the first woman president.
A president must also be able to speak well
to crowds of people.
Ronald Reagan, the fortieth president, could
do this because he used to be an actor.
He became head of the government of California
in 1967, and was president from 1981 to 1989.
Another actor, Arnold Schwarzenegger, also
became head of the government of California
in 2003 and some people believe that film
stars will become successful politicians more
often in future.
CHAPTER TEN
Living in the USA
Many people who have never been to the USA
recognize it from films and TV programmes.
Then there is the work of the artist Edward
Hopper, whose pictures of ordinary American
people, streets, and houses, in the city and
in the country, make us think of old films.
But what is life in America really like?
Most Americans who have jobs live more comfortably
than people in almost any other country in
the world.
They usually work a forty-hour week and they
have two weeks' holiday a year as well as
holidays like Thanksgiving and Christmas.
In 60 per cent of families, the husband and
the wife both work.
Although more than 40 per cent of the land
is farmed, not many people work as farmers,
and fewer Americans work in factories than
in the past.
Most jobs are now in places like hospitals,
banks, hotels, and shops.
If you do not have a job (and around 6 per
cent of Americans do not), life is hard.
The government gives you a little money but
it is not enough to buy everything that you
need.
How many Americans are poor?.
Around 13 per cent of all Americans are poor,
but 25 per cent of black people and 22 per
cent of Hispanic people are poor.
The money in the USA is the dollar, which
contains a hundred cents.
Some coins have special names: 5 cents is
a nickel, 10 cents is a dime, and 25 cents
is a quarter.
In taxis, restaurants, and other places people
give a 'tip' - extra money on top of the price.
Without this extra money, many workers do
not have enough money to live.
Americans do not use kilograms and kilometres
but pounds and miles.
Dates are also written differently from dates
in Britain: 4 July is 7/4, not 4/7.
Sadly, the world learned about how Americans
say dates on 11 September 2001, the date that
we remember as 'nine eleven'.
Because the USA is such a big country, the
time changes as you travel from one side to
the other.
When it is 12 midday in New York (Eastern
Time), it is 11 a.m. in Kansas (Central Time),
10 a.m. in Arizona (Mountain Time), and 9
a.m. in Seattle (Pacific Time).
And the time in Alaska is 8 a.m. and in Hawaii
7 a.m.
The pictures by the artist Norman Rockwell
tell stories of the life of ordinary families
from the 1920s to the 1970s.
Although they are often too happy to be true,
they give us an idea of life in small towns
that has not all disappeared yet.
Two-thirds of Americans own their homes, often
with a garden.
At least 85 per cent of families have a car
and more than 75 per cent of Americans drive
to work.
They also use their car to go to 'drive-in'
restaurants, coffee shops, or even banks.
Henry Ford, who made the famous Ford cars,
was born in Michigan, near Detroit.
His 'Model T' (1908) was the first car that
was cheap enough for ordinary people.
'Anyone can drive a Ford,' they said, and
by 1918 half the cars in the USA were Model
Ts.
Now more and more Americans drive very big
cars called SUVs.
The USA does not have a state religion, and
no religion is allowed in schools.
Instead every morning American students make
a promise to the American flag.
But over 80 per cent of Americans belong to
a Christian church and Christianity is very
important, particularly in the South of the
USA.
In some states books are not allowed in schools
if they say something different from the Christian
story of the beginning of the world.
Some churches are just for black people and
black churchmen like Martin Luther King and
Jesse Jackson have worked very hard for the
rights of black people.
One large religious group is the Latter Day
Saints, or Mormons, who live mainly in Utah.
They have very strong ideas about how to dress
and are against alcohol and tobacco.
If they do not want to go out, Americans can
stay at home and watch television.
Nearly all families have a TV and an ordinary
family watches more than seven hours a day.
There are over 10,000 TV stations, and most
of them belong to businesses, not to the government.
American TV programmes are sold all over the
world.
There are more than 1,500 daily newspapers
but most of them are just for one city.
The most popular newspaper is USA Today, which
sells five million copies a day.
You can buy papers like the New York Times
and the Washington Post everywhere, as well
as the magazines Time and Newsweek.
And, of course, Americans love to shop; the
supermarket first appeared in America, and
now many shops are open twenty-four hours
a day.
Some of the biggest shopping centres in the
world are in the USA - Mall of America in
Minneapolis has over 500 shops and covers
1.25 million square metres.
You could put thirty-two Boeing 747 planes
into it!
Americans have to pay if they visit a doctor
or go to hospital, but they do not usually
pay to go to school.
Schools, like the laws, are different from
state to state, but in most places, everyone
goes to school for about twelve years.
The years are called 'grades': grades 1 to
5 are 'elementary school', 6 to 8 are 'middle
school', and 9 to 12 'high school'.
About 85 per cent of students finish high
school and celebrate with a party known as
a 'prom'.
They also make a 'year book'; this has photos
of all the students in their class and some
information about each person.
Films like American Graffiti and The Breakfast
Club have shown what life is like at an American
high school.
About half the students who finish high school
go on to study for another two or four years.
Harvard and Yale in the east and Berkeley
in California are among America's famous universities.
Most Americans enjoy sports, and baseball,
basketball, and football are popular.
American football is a very different game
from European football; players carry the
ball more than they use their feet.
But the favourite sport in the USA is baseball.
The film Field of Dreams tells the story of
a farmer from Iowa in the mid-west, played
by Kevin Costner, who dreams of the Chicago
White Sox team and makes a baseball field
for them in a field on his farm.
Baseball is played by two teams of nine people.
Each player from the first team tries to hit
the ball and run round a big square from corner
to corner.
The players from the second team try to catch
the ball.
Players try to get all the way round the square
before the other team can get the ball to
a corner.
After three players go 'out', it is the turn
of the second team to hit the ball.
Some famous teams are the Los Angeles Dodgers,
the New York Yankees, and the Boston Red Sox.
Perhaps the greatest baseball player in history
was Babe Ruth.
He was born in 1895 and played with the Boston
Red Sox and then the New York Yankees.
He died in 1948 but he is still remembered
today.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Eating and drinking the American way
What do Americans eat?
American 'fast food' is sold in restaurants
in almost every country of the world.
The most famous examples are probably hamburgers,
hot dogs, and chips, which are called 'french
fries'.
A lot of Americans are fat, perhaps because
they eat too much fast food.
These days many families in America do not
sit down to eat dinner together but eat alone
every few hours all through the day.
Sweet foods, like pies and ice-cream, are
very popular too.
The famous Ben and Jerry's ice-cream started
in Vermont in New England.
But more and more people are interested in
healthy eating, so they choose foods that
are better for them or they decide to stop
eating meat.
If you visit the USA you will be able to enjoy
an American breakfast.
Eggs are cooked in a lot of different ways;
'sunny side up' means with the yellow on top,
'over easy' means with the yellow underneath
but still soft.
With your breakfast you can drink as much
coffee as you want, all for the same price.
In fact, you can drink coffee all day in the
USA.
It is of course the home of Starbucks, which
since the 1990s has changed the way everybody
drinks coffee.
Now all over the world you can go to a coffee
shop and choose from a very long menu of coffees.
What else can you drink that is really American?
Coca-Cola was first made in 1886 by an American
called John Pemberton.
Today it is sold in 195 countries and Coke
is one of the best-known words in the world.
You can also find excellent American wine
from the west coast, particularly California.
But Americans are not allowed to buy alcohol
until they are 21.
In many states you cannot smoke in places
like bars, restaurants, and places of work.
From 1920 to 1933, during Prohibition, it
was against the law to drink alcohol at all
in the USA, but many people still wanted to
drink it.
So criminals like Al Capone brought alcohol
into the country and made a lot of money.
In American restaurants you can eat all kinds
of tasty food from different countries: Chinese,
Mexican, and Italian, for example.
The immigrants who came to the USA brought
their own favourite foods with them.
These then changed into new styles of cooking
that are special to the USA.
For example Tex Mex (Texan Mexican) food is
like Mexican but uses more meat.
Cajun food is spicy food from Louisiana with
unusual names like 'gumbo' and 'jambalaya'.
'Soul food' is the food that black families
like to cook in the South.
It is usually meat or fish with green vegetables,
sweet potatoes, and corn bread, perhaps with
pie afterwards.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Music from America
All over the world people listen to American
music.
It began with the songs of black American
slaves.
Black slaves in the South sang work songs
and religious songs with a shape of 'call
and response'.
This is like a conversation in music - one
person sings, and then another answers.
When the slaves got their freedom after the
Civil War they began to tell their own stories
in music called the 'blues', particularly
in the area around the Mississippi River.
It had the same shape, where the singer sings
and the guitar answers.
The word 'blue' can mean sad, and the songs
tell a sad story of hard work and danger.
At the beginning of the twentieth century
black people moved from the South to the North
to find work.
They took their music with them to cities
like Chicago and Detroit.
Musicians like Muddy Waters, Willie Dixon,
John Lee Hooker, and Howlin' Wolf were the
first to use electric guitars.
Records of the blues became very popular in
the 1920s and 1930s when singers like Bessie
Smith became famous.
In the 1950s Elvis Presley, who came from
Mississippi, was the first white singer to
sing music that came from the blues.
In the 1960s 'soul' was born from the old
style blues, with singers like Marvin Gaye
and Otis Redding.
The city of Detroit has a lot of motor (car)
factories, and it gave the name 'Motown' (motor
town) to soul music.
People all over the world listened to Motown
singers like Diana Ross, Stevie Wonder, and
the Jackson Five in the 1960s and 70s.
Jazz was born in the city of New Orleans,
on the Mississippi River in the far south
of the USA.
It too probably began with the songs and dancing
of black slaves in the 1830s.
The musician Jelly Roll Morton said he was
the first to play 'jazz' in 1897, but nobody
really knows when it began.
Black musicians like Louis Armstrong became
famous in the 1920s in Chicago, and jazz music
became popular across the world after it travelled
to New York and Paris in the 1930s.
George Gershwin, who made music for films
and theatre, thought jazz was an important
part of American life and he used it in music
like his Rhapsody in Blue.
During the Second World War, American soldiers
brought the 'swing' music of the big dance
bands like Glenn Miller to Europe.
This was not jazz but part of the same family
of music.
Now names of great jazz musicians like Miles
Davis, Stan Getz, and John Coltrane are known
all over the world, and people write, sing,
and play jazz in many countries.
But New Orleans, where it all began, is not
the exciting place that it once was.
The city was famous for Mardi Gras, which
was like a wonderful party in the streets,
with colorful clothes, music, and dancing.
But the city is on land which is lower than
the sea, and in 2005 Hurricane Katrina covered
its streets and houses with water.
Several thousand people died, and the city
was badly damaged.
Will New Orleans live again one day as the
home of music?
The musicians hope so, and many still come
every year to play in the New Orleans Jazz
Festival.
Another popular kind of American music is
'country' (or 'country and western') which
has its home in Nashville, Tennessee.
It started from the music of the Scottish,
Irish, and English people who came to live
in the Appalachian Mountains.
Country music began to be really popular in
the 1920s, when Jimmie Rodgers and the Carter
family made the first country records and
the Grand Ole Opry radio show started in Nashville.
Music is still recorded in Nashville and if
you go there you can visit the Country Music
'Hall of Fame'.
One of the most famous women country singers
is Dolly Parton, who has also appeared in
films like 9 to 5 and Steel Magnolias.
Johnny Cash, 'The Man in Black', sold millions
of records in the 1960s and 1970s, and was
still popular when he died in 2003.
The 2005 film Walk the Line, which told the
story of Johnny's early life, was very successful.
In the 1990s a new kind of music called 'rap'
became popular in New York.
It came from black and Puerto Rican people
and told of a dangerous life on the streets,
where there was fighting and killing.
Rappers don't sing but they talk very fast
over music.
Some famous rappers are Eminem, Snoop Dogg,
and Missy Elliott.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
Some great American cities
Some of America's greatest cities are on the
Atlantic coast.
Boston in the Northeast, where the fight for
independence began in the eighteenth century,
is one of the oldest cities in the USA.
Here you can walk the 'Freedom Trail' and
visit the place where the tea was thrown into
the sea.
A few kilometres away in the city of Cambridge
is Harvard, the oldest university in the USA,
which was opened in 1636.
The famous Massachusetts Institute of Technology
(MIT) is in Cambridge too.
Perhaps the most famous family in twentieth-century
Boston was the Kennedy family.
Like many other Boston families, they came
from Ireland.
They became very rich, and John F. Kennedy,
a Democrat, became President of the United
States in 1961.
At that time he said '... ask not what your
country can do for you, but what you can do
for your country.'
He and his beautiful wife Jacqueline were
young and popular, but sadly, in 1963, Kennedy
was shot and killed in Dallas, Texas.
New York is the biggest city in the USA.
It is a great place for theatre, shopping
and restaurants.
It is also the home of the United Nations,
whose offices are in a beautiful glass skyscraper.
But people remember two even taller skyscrapers,
those of the World Trade Center, because on
11 September 2001 two planes flew into them
and killed nearly 3,000 people.
The Empire State Building is now the most
famous skyscraper in the city once again.
It is 443 metres high, has 102 floors, and
has appeared in King Kong and many other films.
The Statue of Liberty is another favourite
place for tourists.
It is 93 metres tall and the best way to see
it is by boat.
It was a present from the people of France
for the hundredth birthday of the USA in 1876.
Many visitors to New York go there just to
shop.
The biggest shops, selling all kinds of things,
are Macy's and Bloomingdales.
Tiffany's on Fifth Avenue sells beautiful
jewellery but it is very expensive.
Times Square and Broadway are the centre of
the theatre area, and Greenwich Village has
been the home of artists and musicians since
the 1940s.
There are many museums in New York and the
biggest is the wonderful Metropolitan Museum
of Art.
Or if you get tired of the city, you can go
into Central Park, a big area of green in
the middle of the busy streets of Manhattan.
Washington DC is the capital of the USA.
It was built in a special area, the District
of Columbia (DC), on land that came from the
states of Maryland and Virginia.
It is different from most American cities
because it has no skyscrapers; its highest
building is the Capitol, home of the Senate
and House of Representatives.
You can visit the White House, where the President
lives, as well as museums of history, art
and air travel.
Some of the city's most beautiful houses are
in the old area of Georgetown.
Much further south are the old cities of Savannah,
Georgia, and Charleston, South Carolina, where
there are also many beautiful old houses.
They look the same as they did 150 years ago
or more.
But not all southern cities are old.
Atlanta in Georgia is big and modern, with
one of the busiest airports in the world.
There are plenty of jobs, and people think
that it is a comfortable city to live in.
Away from the coast in the state of Illinois,
Chicago is sometimes called the 'Windy City'
because of the cold winds that blow in from
Lake Michigan.
The first really tall buildings were built
in Chicago after the great fire of 1871.
Today, the Sears Tower in Chicago (more than
500 metres high) is the tallest building in
the USA.
Frank Lloyd Wright (1867-1959), who made beautiful
houses and other buildings, worked in Chicago
and you can see examples of his houses there.
Like any big city, Chicago has factories,
shops, museums and restaurants, but only Chicago
has Wrigley Field, the famous baseball field.
On the west coast, Seattle has become one
of the most popular cities in America since
the 1980s.
In 1985 Starbucks started the fashion for
Italian coffee shops here.
In the 1990s it was the home of new music
from bands like Pearl Jam and Nirvana.
Bill Gates of Microsoft, one of the richest
men in the world, was born in Seattle.
Films and TV programmes are made about people
who live in Seattle.
A city that was once quiet has become crowded
and more expensive.
Las Vegas in the hot, dry state of Nevada
is full of casinos.
People win and lose thousands of dollars there,
playing cards or other games.
People also go there to get married quickly
and easily.
If you want, a man dressed like Elvis Presley
can be at your wedding!
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
California
More people live in California than in any
other state - over 30 million of them.
It is the biggest state after Texas and Alaska
and it is a state of differences.
The highest mountain in the USA outside Alaska
is Mount Whitney in the east of the state;
it is 4,420 metres high.
And California has the lowest, driest place
in the USA: Death Valley, which is 86 metres
lower than the sea.
It is very hot there (56.7 degree C on the
hottest day, in 1913) and in some years it
does not rain at all.
But the north of the state is quite cold and
wet.
This is where the great redwood trees grow
- the tallest trees in the world.
The biggest is 115.5 metres high.
Also in the north is the Napa Valley area,
where excellent wines are made.
California grows more fruit and vegetables
than any other state in the USA but it is
also famous for its computer factories.
Hewlett and Packard started their business
in California, and Apple have their head offices
there.
San Francisco is, many people think, one of
the most beautiful cities in the world.
In 1849, people came here to look for gold
and they became known as 'Forty-Niners'.
Jeans were first made in San Francisco by
Levi Strauss in those days.
The city grew fast but was nearly destroyed
in 1906 by an earthquake and the fire which
followed it.
There was another big earthquake in 1989 when
62 people died, and everyone knows that one
day there will be another.
But 800,000 Americans continue living in San
Francisco because life there is fun.
San Francisco was the meeting place for two
groups of people who wanted a life that was
different from the life of ordinary people.
In the 1950s there were the 'beatniks' (like
writers Allen Ginsberg and Jack Kerouac),
who wore black and were not interested in
money and jobs.
Then in the 1960s 'hippies' came to San Francisco.
They wore bright clothes, had long hair, and
wanted a world full of peace and love.
1967 was the 'summer of love', with songs
that talked about peace and love and told
young people, 'If you go to San Francisco,
wear a flower in your hair'.
San Francisco is also famous for the Golden
Gate Bridge, which was built in 1937 and joins
the city to Marin County.
More than 40 million journeys are made across
it every year.
It is 2.7 kilometres long and 67 metres above
the water.
From the bridge you can see the island of
Alcatraz, which was a prison until 1963.
Los Angeles is the second biggest city in
the USA, with 3.8 million people.
It can take hours to drive from one side to
the other - and people almost always drive!
The number of cars means that the city has
a problem with dirty air; in some parts of
the city crime is a problem too.
But visitors still come to see places like
Hollywood and Beverly Hills.
The first film was made in Hollywood in 1911
in a place where orange trees used to grow.
The first films, with actors like Rudolf Valentino,
Charlie Chaplin, and Buster Keaton were silent,
but then in 1927 films got sound.
In the 1930s and 1940s famous stars like Clark
Gable, Humphrey Bogart, and Katharine Hepburn
appeared in films like It Happened One Night,
Casablanca, and The Philadelphia Story.
Some of the greatest films of the time came
from the crime stories of the famous Californian
writers Dashiell Hammett and Raymond Chandler.
Chandler wrote about the detective Philip
Marlowe, who was played by Bogart in The Big
Sleep.
Today, films are big business - it costs millions
of dollars to make them, but they can make
millions of dollars more.
On Hollywood Boulevard you can visit Mann's
Chinese Theatre, where film stars have left
the shapes of their hands and feet in the
ground.
You can visit Paramount Studios in Hollywood,
where the Godfather films were made, or Universal
Studios outside the city, where you can feel
an earthquake or see King Kong and Jurassic
Park.
In Beverly Hills you can drive past the homes
of famous stars.
Mickey Mouse first appeared in 1928 in films
by Walt Disney.
Disney died in 1966, but his company continues
to make very popular films like Pirates of
the Caribbean.
Disneyland is the top place for tourists in
California.
It is in Orange County in the south of the
state.
If you visit Disneyland, you will meet Mickey
Mouse and his friends walking around the park.
You can visit the castle of Sleeping Beauty,
ride on a river boat, or have an Indiana Jones
or Tarzan adventure.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Beautiful places to visit
The USA has some of the biggest cities in
the world, and more than three-quarters of
its people live in cities or towns.
This means that there are also some very empty
places, which have not changed much since
the first Europeans arrived.
The government has kept some of them as national
parks, beautiful natural places where people
are not allowed to build houses or factories.
Many artists have photographed the beautiful
parks of America.
One of the most famous is Ansel Adams, who
was born in San Francisco a few years before
the earthquake of 1906.
Two of his favourite places were Yosemite
in northern California, which has been a park
since 1890, and the coast of California.
Travelling north from California, you come
to Oregon and then Washington.
These states are cool and wet, but very beautiful,
with big forests and high mountains.
Here you will find a number of national parks
like Mount Rainier and Crater Lake.
The wonderful Rocky Mountains are in the states
of Wyoming, Montana, Colorado, Idaho and Utah,
and are great for holidays.
Walking, climbing, fishing, hunting, and horse-riding
are some of the things visitors enjoy here.
You can also enjoy winter sports in places
like Aspen, where there is a lot of snow.
The only big city in the Rockies is Denver.
Also in the Rocky Mountains is Yellowstone
Park in the states of Idaho, Wyoming, and
Montana.
It is famous for the geyser called Old Faithful
that shoots hot water up into the air, up
to 55 metres high.
Salt Lake City, the capital city of Utah,
is next to a lake that is much saltier than
the sea.
If you try to swim in this lake, you will
find that you cannot stay under the water!
South of the Rockies is the hot, dry state
of Arizona, where the land has fantastic colours:
not just brown and green, but red, pink, orange,
and blue.
The most famous place in Arizona is the Grand
Canyon.
This deep river valley was made by the Colorado
River cutting through the rock many thousands
of years ago.
Today it is 1,600 metres deep, 446 kilometres
long, and between 0.4 and 24 kilometres wide
with rocks in extraordinary shapes.
You can walk down to the river, but it will
take you two days to get there and back, and
you must take plenty of water to drink.
Next to Arizona, New Mexico is another hot,
dry state, where farming is difficult and
the ordinary people are poor.
But many artists have also come from other
parts of America to live in and around Santa
Fe and Taos.
One of the first was Georgia O'Keeffe and
there is a museum of her work in Santa Fe.
In the Badlands National Park of South Dakota
visitors remember the Sioux who fought and
died at Wounded Knee, but the Black Hills
of Dakota are famous for Mount
Rushmore, where the faces of four American
presidents, Washington, Jefferson, Lincoln,
and Theodore Roosevelt were cut in the rock.
It took fourteen years, from 1927 to 1941.
You can see them in the Hitchcock film North
by Northwest, where Cary Grant nearly falls
from the mountain while he is trying to escape.
Canada and the USA meet at the five Great
Lakes, which are an important route for ships
travelling from the Atlantic to the Midwest
along the St Lawrence Seaway.
The famous Niagara Falls are between Lakes
Ontario and Erie.
These waterfalls are 51 metres high.
You can look at them from the top from Canada
or the USA, or you can take a boat trip and
see them from below.
Together, Lakes Erie, Ontario, Huron, Michigan,
and Superior cover 244,108 square kilometres
- more than any other group of lakes in the
world.
If you go there in the summer, it is almost
like going to the sea; you can lie on the
beach or sail a boat.
But in winter it is very cold.
Thousands of kilometres south of the Great
Lakes is the state of Louisiana, which used
to be French.
The Mississippi River is 3,778 kilometres
long and in the nineteenth century it was
an important route between the North and the
South.
Mark Twain wrote wonderful stories about life
on and around the river: The Adventures of
Tom Sawyer and Huckleberry Finn (1884).
Next to Louisiana, the state of Mississippi
was also the home of several great writers
like Tennessee Williams and William Faulkner.
Together the states of Maine, New Hampshire,
Vermont, Massachusetts, Connecticut and Rhode
Island are known as New England.
Autumn, or 'fall' as the Americans call it,
is a good time to visit New England, because
the leaves on the trees turn yellow and orange
and red and gold.
October is a good month to see the colours
at their best.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
Hot and cold, big and small
Florida in the far Southeast is called the
'Sunshine State' because it is so warm and
sunny.
Oranges grow there, and visitors come to enjoy
beach holidays.
They can also visit Walt Disney World and
the Kennedy Space Center.
Florida has the Everglades, an area which
is not like any other place in the USA.
The land is very wet and has many trees, plants,
animals and birds that are not found in other
parts of America.
But Florida is very popular with older people
who want to live somewhere warm.
This means new houses and roads, and building
them has destroyed a lot of the land.
There are also more and more factories, and
some people are angry that this beautiful
state is losing many of its wild birds and
animals because of its dirty air and water.
Cold, lonely Alaska is the largest state in
the USA, and Canada stands between it and
the other states.
Fishing and hunting used to bring money to
Alaska, and gold was found there too.
But today it is important for its oil.
North America's highest mountain, Mount McKinley
(6,194 metres), is in Alaska.
A great way to travel there is by boat from
Seattle.
Most visitors go in summer; in winter it is
very cold, and it is dark for most of the
day because it is so far north.
However, if you are lucky you will see the
Northern Lights (aurora borealis), which fill
the sky with fantastic colours.
Texas is the second biggest state after Alaska.
There are still cowboys who work there, but
the modern state of Texas, like Alaska, is
rich because of its oil.
The smallest state of the USA is little Rhode
Island to the east of Connecticut.
Newport in Rhode Island has three big music
festivals each year.
In Texas the capital city, Austin, is also
famous for its music.
Janis Joplin sang there, as well as Bruce
Springsteen, Van Morrison, and country singer
Kinky Friedman, who also writes very funny
crime books.
The holiday islands of Hawaii are a long way
from the other states of the USA.
Many Americans go there to enjoy the beaches,
like the famous Waikiki Beach, and the warm
sunshine.
Although there are a lot of tourists, you
can escape to quieter places where you can
see trees, waterfalls and many unusual plants
and birds.
There are sadly only 9,000 true Hawaiians,
but around a third of the people who live
in the islands are part-Hawaiian.
But there are more interesting and exciting
places to visit in the USA than will fit into
one book.
Choose what you prefer, busy city or quiet
national park, cold mountains or warm sea,
shopping or sports, and plan your own American
journey!
- THE END -