Time: the present Place: Sheffield, England
Everybody knew about the comet.
It was in all the newspapers.
When it finally passed close to the Earth,
it lit up the sky for three nights.
It was beautiful.
People who were not usually interested in
looking beyond their television screens took
at least one look outside.
Even people like Darren.
Darren was looking in the bathroom mirror
at the spots on his face.
They were near his nose.
His mum always said he got spots because he
ate too many sweets.
But he hated sweets.
And he never ate chocolate.
His mum loved chocolate and she never got
spots.
It wasn't fair.
Darren was just going to examine his biggest
spot when his mum called out.
'Darren!
Darren, look at this!'
'Aw, Mum.
I'm busy!'
But Darren's mum refused to take no for an
answer.
She knew her thirteen-year-old son liked science
fiction.
A bit of science fact would do him no harm.
This sort of thing didn't happen every day,
after all.
They said that this comet was only going to
pass the Earth once.
She didn't want Darren to miss it.
'Darren Miller, come down right now!'
When Darren got downstairs, the door to the
garden was open.
He could see both his parents outside.
They were looking up, their faces lit by a
gentle light.
He went out and stood next to them.
Then he, too, looked up.
It was, indeed, a lovely thing to see.
Darren was pleased his mum had called him.
The sky was full of beautiful, coloured light.
It made Darren think of Christmas lights and
all the bright colours he loved when he was
younger.
It was so beautiful that he almost forgot
about his spots.
The next day all of the newspapers were full
of pictures and stories about the comet.
Some of the newspapers were quite excited
about it, because the comet had passed very
close to the Earth.
'Comet nearly hits Earth!' said one headline
in a newspaper.
'Earth escapes comet!' said another.
Most of the newspaper reports also mentioned
the beauty of the comet.
They all said how lucky we were to see such
a wonderful thing.
Of course, there were the usual pessimists
who said that the comet would put something
nasty into the air we breathe.
Others said the comet was a sign that the
end of the Earth was coming.
However, most people took no notice of these
warnings.
Life went on as usual.
Life for Darren meant getting ready for school
again after the holidays.
Comets were nice but now he had more important
things to think about.
He had to make himself look good for the beautiful
Vanessa.
Darrens school was just an ordinary school
in the city of Sheffield in England.
It was no better than any other school in
Sheffield.
But it did have Vanessa.
Vanessa was a brown-haired, brown-eyed girl
in the same year as Darren.
She had smiled at Darren once.
He remembered it well.
It had happened in the last week before the
holidays.
He had let her go in front of him in the queue
for lunch.
She hadn't said 'thank you,' but she had given
him a little smile.
It had showed her perfect white teeth.
He had been too nervous to speak to her.
He just couldn't do it.
It would be easier, he felt, to grow wings
and fly up to the ceiling.
This time he would be ready.
He would put on lots of deodorant to make
himself smell nice.
He wanted to have another look at his spots
and, just maybe, have a shave.
The night before he had felt something above
his mouth that might be the first hairs of
a moustache.
He made sure he got to the bathroom before
everyone else that morning.
He wanted to have a close look at those spots...
and his new moustache.
'Darren, will you be in there for a long time?'
It was Darren's mum.
'Your father wants to use the bathroom.'
Darren knew his dad always spent ages in the
bathroom.
Well, his dad could wait today, for a change.
'I'll be out soon, Mum,' said Darren.
But he was lying.
He wanted to look good and smell good.
It could take a long time.
His new deodorant smelled very good this morning.
He suddenly noticed all the different smells
that went into it.
There were flowers, spices - lots of things
he had never smelled before.
His nose felt a bit wet too.
Was he getting a cold?
Probably not, if he could smell things so
well.
Darren walked over to the mirror and looked
at his face.
His face looked worse than ever!
His nose was wet and shiny.
It was moving a lot, like an animal's nose.
It looked like a rabbit smelling its breakfast.
But this wasn't the most shocking thing.
His top lip had long, thick hairs on it.
They were like the hairs on an animal's nose.
They were like the whiskers of a rabbit!
Darren screamed.
Time: the present Place: Singapore
Julie Ong had been fourteen for three weeks.
A lot of her friends were fourteen too.
They all agreed that a young woman should
watch her weight.
It was especially important not to eat sweets
and cakes.
Julie hadn't eaten a cake or a piece of chocolate
since her birthday.
But there were still no signs that her parents
saw Julie as a young woman.
To them, she was still a child.
Then there was the strange thing with the
comet.
Everybody was talking about it.
Julies English teacher gave her class homework
about it.
They had to describe the comet in a poem.
It was so unfair!
The comet had been quite beautiful, but writing
about it was no fun at all.
Julie decided to take a break from her Sunday
morning homework.
Instead of writing she would comb her long
black hair in the mirror.
It was more interesting than writing a poem,
at least.
Her parents wouldn't notice that she was wasting
time.
She could hear them at the other end of the
house talking about the comet.
They weren't talking loudly, but she could
still hear them.
Her hearing wasn't normally that good.
It was very odd.
Julie picked up her hairbrush - her favourite
pink one - and walked towards her bedroom
mirror.
But when she looked at herself, she immediately
noticed something strange.
There were two things rising up and out from
her hair.
They were on both sides of her head.
Julie pushed back her hair and saw that the
two things were her ears.
They were now pointed at the top, like an
animal's ears, and they were bigger too.
Much bigger.
Julie fainted.
Darrens new whiskers grew even longer over
the next week.
His nose became much, much better at smelling
things too.
He could smell almost anything from a long
distance away now.
His dad had his own smell, so had his mum.
Everybody had their own smell.
Having a good nose was useful and Darren liked
it.
He liked his whiskers too, and he couldn't
really shave them off.
It would hurt, he was sure, if he tried.
Anyway, he was getting used to them.
In Singapore, Julie Ong discovered that her
hearing had become extremely good.
She could hear almost everything.
Darren didn't know it yet, but the beautiful
Vanessa had now grown long teeth like a cat's.
She had whiskers too.
And suddenly she seemed to enjoy eating a
lot of fish.
Darren, Julie and Vanessa were not alone.
Sudden changes were happening all over the
world.
Many young people between the ages of twelve
and eighteen had developed the special strength
of some kind of animal.
Sometimes it wasn't immediately obvious - like
having the fantastic eyesight of a hunting
bird.
But often the changes were obvious.
Some had grown long tails and they could hold
on to things with them.
Some had webbed skin on their hands and feet
so that they could swim fast.
Some had the strength of a bull; others could
run as fast as a horse.
They all looked human still, but in some way
they had changed.
Of course, adults everywhere were extremely
worried.
Why had their children changed?
What had produced the changes?
What could they do to help their children?
Darren discovered that his amazing nose had
many advantages too.
He found that he could tell what mood people
were in just by their smell - even if they
were trying to hide it.
That was useful.
This new sense of smell was useful in other
ways too.
If he lost something, he could always find
it by using his nose.
He helped his mum buy the freshest and tastiest
food in the supermarket.
He now used deodorant which didn't have a
strong smell.
His new nose didn't like strong smells any
more.
'You'd better not get too used to it,' said
his dad.
'Some day soon we'll be able to get you back
the way you were.'
'Maybe, Dad,' Darren said.
'But what if I don't want to go back to the
way I was?'
Darrens father didn't say anything.
Like many other parents, he didn't understand
how his son could like the changes.
He wanted the old Darren back - the Darren
without the whiskers and the amazing sense
of smell.
And why had some young people changed while
others hadn't?
That was the question every adult in the world
was asking.
Some adults blamed the children themselves
for the changes.
They said they watched too much TV or ate
the wrong things or didn't behave in the right
way.
Most people blamed the comet.
'Comet causes horrible teenage changes!'
was the kind of headline found on the front
page of many newspapers.
They all had similar stories.
Everybody was saying that it must have been
the comet - what else could it have been?
The comet had, in some strange way, affected
the bodies of some teenagers.
'I don't think the changes are horrible!'
said Julie to her friends.
'I think my new hearing is very useful.
I think my ears are rather beautiful too!'
Some of Julie's friends agreed with her.
'I like my new wings,' said one.
'I can change colour like a chameleon - isn't
that cool?' said another.
Teenagers everywhere were comparing their
changes.
Some were stronger, others were faster, others
could jump higher.
But no matter what changes happened, they
were still teenagers.
But then something strange happened.
Some teenagers began to return to normal.
Some eventually lost all sign of their changes
and went back to what they had been before.
But why?
The answer came almost by accident.
A teen called Danny was given a job in an
advertisement.
Danny had wings and he could fly.
In the advertisement, Danny had to fly over
a childrens party and give out chocolate biscuits.
Danny hated chocolate biscuits, but he had
to eat some during the advertisement.
It was after he ate his second biscuit that
something started happening.
His wings started to get smaller.
Soon they disappeared completely.
He couldn't fly any more.
Danny was a 'normal' teenager again.
Why had it happened?
It was the chocolate.
It had to be.
Scientists tested the effect of chocolate
on other teenagers.
They discovered that if the teenagers ate
a few things with chocolate in them, they
went back to normal.
The world now knew why some children hadn't
been affected by the comet.
The mystery was solved.
The comet had only changed teenagers who didn't
eat chocolate!
'I don't like chocolate, you know that,' Darren
told his parents.
'I've never liked it.'
'But all you have to do is eat a bit and you'll
go back to normal!' said Dad.
'You want to be normal again, don't you, Darren?'
Darren thought about Vanessa.
He liked her new cat looks.
Vanessa had found Darrens changes attractive
too.
She had spoken to him quite a lot lately.
'If you mean do I want to be like most of
my friends, then yes.
But some of my friends have changed and we
like the changes.
Why should I want to go back?
Anyway, I hate chocolate.'
His parents couldn't make him change his mind.
Maybe if his friends agreed to change back,
Darren would too.
But that wasn't as easy as it seemed.
A lot of teenagers felt the same way as Darren.
Some adults accepted their new teenagers because
the changes were useful in daily life.
If you were faster and stronger, for example,
you could work better.
But most adults expected that their teenagers
would want to return to how they had been
before.
Many of them did.
But a lot of teenagers simply didn't care
what the adults wanted.
They refused to eat the chocolate.
In Singapore, Julie Ong finally ate some chocolate.
Soon, her beautiful big ears were gone.
She often remembered them and was sad.
In Sheffield, Darren Miller was using his
nose to enjoy the sweet smell of the carrots
growing in Vanessa's garden.
Vanessa watched him happily as she ate a fish
on top of the garden wall.
- THE END -