Miracles
Who am I? And how, I wonder, will this story
end?
The sun has come up and I am sitting by a
window that is foggy with the breath of a
life gone by. I’m a sight this morning:
two shirts, heavy pants, a scarf wrapped twice
around my neck and tucked into a thick sweater
knitted by my daughter thirty birthdays ago.
The thermostat in my room is set as high as
it will go, and a smaller space heater sits
directly behind me. It clicks and groans and
spews hot air like a fairy-tale dragon, and
still my body shivers with a cold that will
never go away, a cold that has been eighty
years in the making. Eighty years, I think
sometimes, and despite my own acceptance of
my age, it still amazes me that I haven’t
been warm since George Bush was president.
I wonder if this is how it is for everyone
my age.
My life? It isn’t easy to explain. It has
not been the rip-roaring spectacular I fancied
it would be, but neither have I burrowed around
with the gophers. I suppose it has most resembled
a blue-chip stock: fairly stable, more ups
than downs, and gradually trending upward
over time. A good buy, a lucky buy, and I’ve
learned that not everyone can say this about
his life. But do not be misled. I am nothing
special; of this I am sure. I am a common
man with common thoughts, and I’ve led a
common life. There are no monuments dedicated
to me and my name will soon be forgotten,
but I’ve loved another with all my heart
and soul, and to me, this has always been
enough.
The romantics would call this a love story,
the cynics would call it a tragedy. In my
mind it’s a little bit of both, and no matter
how you choose to view it in the end, it does
not change the fact that it involves a great
deal of my life and the path I’ve chosen
to follow. I have no complaints about my path
and the places it has taken me; enough complaints
to fill a circus tent about other things,
maybe, but the path I’ve chosen has always
been the right one, and I wouldn’t have
had it any other way.
Time, unfortunately, doesn’t make it easy
to stay on course. The path is straight as
ever, but now it is strewn with the rocks
and gravel that accumulate over a lifetime.
Until three years ago it would have been easy
to ignore, but it’s impossible now. There
is a sickness rolling through my body; I’m
neither strong nor healthy, and my days are
spent like an old party balloon: listless,
spongy, and growing softer over time.
I cough, and through squinted eyes I check
my watch. I realize it is time to go. I stand
from my seat by the window and shuffle across
the room, stopping at the desk to pick up
the notebook I have read a hundred times.
I do not glance through it. Instead I slip
it beneath my arm and continue on my way to
the place I must go.
I walk on tiled floors, white in color and
speckled with gray. Like my hair and the hair
of most people here, though I’m the only
one in the hallway this morning. They are
in their rooms, alone except for television,
but they, like me, are used to it. A person
can get used to anything, if given enough
time.
I hear the muffled sounds of crying in the
distance and know exactly who is making those
sounds. Then the nurses see me and we smile
at each other and exchange greetings. They
are my friends and we talk often, but I am
sure they wonder about me and the things that
I go through every day. I listen as they begin
to whisper among themselves as I pass. “There
he goes again,” I hear, “I hope it turns
out well.” But they say nothing directly
to me about it. I’m sure they think it would
hurt me to talk about it so early in the morning,
and knowing myself as I do, I think they’re
probably right.
A minute later, I reach the room. The door
has been propped open for me, as it usually
is. There are two others in the room, and
they too smile at me as I enter. “Good morning,”
they say with cheery voices, and I take a
moment to ask about the kids and the schools
and upcoming vacations. We talk above the
crying for a minute or so. They do not seem
to notice; they have become numb to it, but
then again, so have I.
Afterward I sit in the chair that has come
to be shaped like me. They are finishing up
now; her clothes are on, but still she is
crying. It will become quieter after they
leave, I know. The excitement of the morning
always upsets her, and today is no exception.
Finally the shade is opened and the nurses
walk out. Both of them touch me and smile
as they walk by. I wonder what this means.
I sit for just a second and stare at her,
but she doesn’t return the look. I understand,
for she doesn’t know who I am. I’m a stranger
to her. Then, turning away, I bow my head
and pray silently for the strength I know
I will need. I have always been a firm believer
in God and the power of prayer, though to
be honest, my faith has made for a list of
questions I definitely want answered after
I’m gone.
Ready now. On go the glasses, out of my pocket
comes a magnifier. I put it on the table for
a moment while I open the notebook. It takes
two licks on my gnarled finger to get the
well-worn cover open to the first page. Then
I put the magnifier in place.
There is always a moment right before I begin
to read the story when my mind churns, and
I wonder, Will it happen today? I don’t
know, for I never know beforehand, and deep
down it really doesn’t matter. It’s the
possibility that keeps me going, not the guarantee,
a sort of wager on my part. And though you
may call me a dreamer or fool or any other
thing, I believe that anything is possible.
I realize the odds, and science, are against
me. But science is not the total answer; this
I know, this I have learned in my lifetime.
And that leaves me with the belief that miracles,
no matter how inexplicable or unbelievable,
are real and can occur without regard to the
natural order of things. So once again, just
as I do every day, I begin to read the notebook
aloud, so that she can hear it, in the hope
that the miracle that has come to dominate
my life will once again prevail.
And maybe, just maybe, it will.
Ghosts
It was early October 1946, and Noah Calhoun
watched the fading sun sink lower from the
wraparound porch of his plantation-style home.
He liked to sit here in the evenings, especially
after working hard all day, and let his thoughts
wander without conscious direction. It was
how he relaxed, a routine he’d learned from
his father.
He especially liked to look at the trees and
their reflections in the river. North Carolina
trees are beautiful in deep autumn: greens,
yellows, reds, oranges, every shade in between.
Their dazzling colors glow with the sun, and
for the hundredth time, Noah Calhoun wondered
if the original owners of the house had spent
their evenings thinking the same things.
The house was built in 1772, making it one
of the oldest, as well as largest, homes in
New Bern. Originally it was the main house
on a working plantation, and he had bought
it right after the war ended and had spent
the last eleven months and a small fortune
repairing it. The reporter from the Raleigh
paper had done an article on it a few weeks
ago and said it was one of the finest restorations
he’d ever seen. At least the house was.
The remaining property was another story,
and that was where he’d spent most of the
day.
The home sat on twelve acres adjacent to Brices
Creek, and he’d worked on the wooden fence
that lined the other three sides of the property,
checking for dry rot or termites, replacing
posts when he had to. He still had more work
to do on it, especially on the west side,
and as he’d put the tools away earlier he’d
made a mental note to call and have some more
lumber delivered. He’d gone into the house,
drunk a glass of sweet tea, then showered.
He always showered at the end of the day,
the water washing away both dirt and fatigue.
Afterward he’d combed his hair back, put
on some faded jeans and a long-sleeved blue
shirt, poured himself another glass of sweet
tea, and gone to the porch, where he now sat,
where he sat every day at this time.
He stretched his arms above his head, then
out to the sides, rolling his shoulders as
he completed the routine. He felt good and
clean now, fresh. His muscles were tired and
he knew he’d be a little sore tomorrow,
but he was pleased that he had accomplished
most of what he had wanted to do.
Noah reached for his guitar, remembering his
father as he did so, thinking how much he
missed him. He strummed once, adjusted the
tension on two strings, then strummed again.
This time it sounded about right, and he began
to play. Soft music, quiet music. He hummed
for a little while at first, then began to
sing as night came down around him. He played
and sang until the sun was gone and the sky
was black.
It was a little after seven when he quit,
and he settled back into his chair and began
to rock. By habit, he looked upward and saw
Orion and the Big Dipper, Gemini and the Pole
Star, twinkling in the autumn sky.
He started to run the numbers in his head,
then stopped. He knew he’d spent almost
his entire savings on the house and would
have to find a job again soon, but he pushed
the thought away and decided to enjoy the
remaining months of restoration without worrying
about it. It would work out for him, he knew;
it always did. Besides, thinking about money
usually bored him. Early on, he’d learned
to enjoy simple things, things that couldn’t
be bought, and he had a hard time understanding
people who felt otherwise. It was another
trait he got from his father.
Clem, his hound dog, came up to him then and
nuzzled his hand before lying down at his
feet. “Hey, girl, how’re you doing?”
he asked as he patted her head, and she whined
softly, her soft round eyes peering upward.
A car accident had taken her leg, but she
still moved well enough and kept him company
on quiet nights like these.
He was thirty-one now, not too old, but old
enough to be lonely. He hadn’t dated since
he’d been back here, hadn’t met anyone
who remotely interested him. It was his own
fault, he knew. There was something that kept
a distance between him and any woman who started
to get close, something he wasn’t sure he
could change even if he tried. And sometimes
in the moments right before sleep came, he
wondered if he was destined to be alone forever.
The evening passed, staying warm, nice. Noah
listened to the crickets and the rustling
leaves, thinking that the sound of nature
was more real and aroused more emotion than
things like cars and planes. Natural things
gave back more than they took, and their sounds
always brought him back to the way man was
supposed to be. There were times during the
war, especially after a major engagement,
when he had often thought about these simple
sounds. “It’ll keep you from going crazy,”
his father had told him the day he’d shipped
out. “It’s God’s music and it’ll take
you home.”
He finished his tea, went inside, found a
book, then turned on the porch light on his
way back out. After sitting down again, he
looked at the book. It was old, the cover
was torn, and the pages were stained with
mud and water. It was Leaves of Grass by Walt
Whitman, and he had carried it with him throughout
the war. It had even taken a bullet for him
once.
He rubbed the cover, dusting it off just a
little. Then he let the book open randomly
and read the words in front of him:
This is thy hour O Soul, thy free flight into
the wordless,
Away from books, away from art, the day erased,
the lesson done,
Thee fully forth emerging, silent, gazing,
pondering the themes thou lovest best,
Night, sleep, death and the stars.
He smiled to himself. For some reason Whitman
always reminded him of New Bern, and he was
glad he’d come back. Though he’d been
away for fourteen years, this was home and
he knew a lot of people here, most of them
from his youth. It wasn’t surprising. Like
so many southern towns, the people who lived
here never changed, they just grew a bit older.
His best friend these days was Gus, a seventy-year-old
black man who lived down the road. They had
met a couple of weeks after Noah bought the
house, when Gus had shown up with some homemade
liquor and Brunswick stew, and the two had
spent their first evening together getting
drunk and telling stories.
Now Gus would show up a couple of nights a
week, usually around eight. With four kids
and eleven grandchildren in the house, he
needed to get out of the house now and then,
and Noah couldn’t blame him. Usually Gus
would bring his harmonica, and after talking
for a little while, they’d play a few songs
together. Sometimes they played for hours.
He’d come to regard Gus as family. There
really wasn’t anyone else, at least not
since his father died last year. He was an
only child; his mother had died of influenza
when he was two, and though he had wanted
to at one time, he had never married.
But he had been in love once, that he knew.
Once and only once, and a long time ago. And
it had changed him forever. Perfect love did
that to a person, and this had been perfect.
Coastal clouds slowly began to roll across
the evening sky, turning silver with the reflection
of the moon. As they thickened, he leaned
his head back and rested it against the rocking
chair. His legs moved automatically, keeping
a steady rhythm, and as he did most evenings,
he felt his mind drifting back to a warm evening
like this fourteen years ago.
It was just after graduation 1932, the opening
night of the Neuse River Festival. The town
was out in full, enjoying barbecue and games
of chance. It was humid that night—for some
reason he remembered that clearly. He arrived
alone, and as he strolled through the crowd,
looking for friends, he saw Fin and Sarah,
two people he’d grown up with, talking to
a girl he’d never seen before. She was pretty,
he remembered thinking, and when he finally
joined them, she looked his way with a pair
of hazy eyes that kept on coming. “Hi,”
she’d said simply as she offered her hand,
“Finley’s told me a lot about you.”
An ordinary beginning, something that would
have been forgotten had it been anyone but
her. But as he shook her hand and met those
striking emerald eyes, he knew before he’d
taken his next breath that she was the one
he could spend the rest of his life looking
for but never find again. She seemed that
good, that perfect, while a summer wind blew
through the trees.
From there, it went like a tornado wind. Fin
told him she was spending the summer in New
Bern with her family because her father worked
for R. J. Reynolds, and though he only nodded,
the way she was looking at him made his silence
seem okay. Fin laughed then, because he knew
what was happening, and Sarah suggested they
get some cherry Cokes, and the four of them
stayed at the festival until the crowds were
thin and everything closed up for the night.
They met the following day, and the day after
that, and they soon became inseparable. Every
morning but Sunday when he had to go to church,
he would finish his chores as quickly as possible,
then make a straight line to Fort Totten Park,
where she’d be waiting for him. Because
she was a newcomer and hadn’t spent time
in a small town before, they spent their days
doing things that were completely new to her.
He taught her how to bait a line and fish
the shallows for largemouth bass and took
her exploring through the backwoods of the
Croatan Forest. They rode in canoes and watched
summer thunderstorms, and to him it seemed
as though they’d always known each other.
But he learned things as well. At the town
dance in the tobacco barn, it was she who
taught him how to waltz and do the Charleston,
and though they stumbled through the first
few songs, her patience with him eventually
paid off, and they danced together until the
music ended. He walked her home afterward,
and when they paused on the porch after saying
good night, he kissed her for the first time
and wondered why he had waited as long as
he had. Later in the summer he brought her
to this house, looked past the decay, and
told her that one day he was going to own
it and fix it up. They spent hours together
talking about their dreams—his of seeing
the world, hers of being an artist—and on
a humid night in August, they both lost their
virginity. When she left three weeks later,
she took a piece of him and the rest of summer
with her. He watched her leave town on an
early rainy morning, watched through eyes
that hadn’t slept the night before, then
went home and packed a bag. He spent the next
week alone on Harkers Island.
Noah ran his hands through his hair and checked
his watch. Eight-twelve. He got up and walked
to the front of the house and looked up the
road. Gus wasn’t in sight, and Noah figured
he wouldn’t be coming. He went back to his
rocker and sat again.
He remembered talking to Gus about her. The
first time he mentioned her, Gus started to
shake his head and laugh. “So that’s the
ghost you been running from.” When asked
what he meant, Gus said, “You know, the
ghost, the memory. I been watchin’ you,
workin’ day and night, slavin’ so hard
you barely have time to catch your breath.
People do that for three reasons. Either they
crazy, or stupid, or tryin’ to forget. And
with you, I knew you was tryin’ to forget.
I just didn’t know what.”
He thought about what Gus had said. Gus was
right, of course. New Bern was haunted now.
Haunted by the ghost of her memory. He saw
her in Fort Totten Park, their place, every
time he walked by. Either sitting on the bench
or standing by the gate, always smiling, blond
hair softly touching her shoulders, her eyes
the color of emeralds. When he sat on the
porch at night with his guitar, he saw her
beside him, listening quietly as he played
the music of his childhood.
He felt the same when he went to Gaston’s
Drug Store, or to the Masonic theater, or
even when he strolled downtown. Everywhere
he looked, he saw her image, saw things that
brought her back to life.
It was odd, he knew that. He had grown up
in New Bern. Spent his first seventeen years
here. But when he thought about New Bern,
he seemed to remember only the last summer,
the summer they were together. Other memories
were simply fragments, pieces here and there
of growing up, and few, if any, evoked any
feeling.
He had told Gus about it one night, and not
only had Gus understood, but he had been the
first to explain why. He said simply, “My
daddy used to tell me that the first time
you fall in love, it changes your life forever,
and no matter how hard you try, the feelin’
never goes away. This girl you been tellin’
me about was your first love. And no matter
what you do, she’ll stay with you forever.”
Noah shook his head, and when her image began
to fade, he returned to Whitman. He read for
an hour, looking up every now and then to
see raccoons and possums scurrying near the
creek. At nine-thirty he closed the book,
went upstairs to the bedroom, and wrote in
his journal, including both personal observations
and the work he’d accomplished on the house.
Forty minutes later, he was sleeping. Clem
wandered up the stairs, sniffed him as he
slept, and then paced in circles before finally
curling up at the foot of his bed.
Earlier that evening and a hundred miles away,
she sat alone on the porch swing of her parents’
home, one leg crossed beneath her. The seat
had been slightly damp when she sat down;
rain had fallen earlier, hard and stinging,
but the clouds were fading now and she looked
past them, toward the stars, wondering if
she’d made the right decision. She’d struggled
with it for days—and had struggled some
more this evening—but in the end, she knew
she would never forgive herself if she let
the opportunity slip away.
Lon didn’t know the real reason she left
the following morning. The week before, she’d
hinted to him that she might want to visit
some antique shops near the coast. “It’s
just a couple of days,” she said, “and
besides, I need a break from planning the
wedding.” She felt bad about the lie but
knew there was no way she could tell him the
truth. Her leaving had nothing to do with
him, and it wouldn’t be fair of her to ask
him to understand.
It was an easy drive from Raleigh, slightly
more than two hours, and she arrived a little
before eleven. She checked into a small inn
downtown, went to her room, and unpacked her
suitcase, hanging her dresses in the closet
and putting everything else in the drawers.
She had a quick lunch, asked the waitress
for directions to the nearest antique stores,
then spent the next few hours shopping. By
four-thirty she was back in her room.
She sat on the edge of the bed, picked up
the phone, and called Lon. He couldn’t speak
long, he was due in court, but before they
hung up she gave him the phone number where
she was staying and promised to call the following
day. Good, she thought while hanging up the
phone. Routine conversation, nothing out of
the ordinary. Nothing to make him suspicious.
She’d known him almost four years now; it
was 1942 when they met, the world at war and
America one year in. Everyone was doing their
part, and she was volunteering at the hospital
downtown. She was both needed and appreciated
there, but it was more difficult than she’d
expected. The first waves of wounded young
soldiers were coming home, and she spent her
days with broken men and shattered bodies.
When Lon, with all his easy charm, introduced
himself at a Christmas party, she saw in him
exactly what she needed: someone with confidence
about the future and a sense of humor that
drove all her fears away.
He was handsome, intelligent, and driven,
a successful lawyer eight years older than
she, and he pursued his job with passion,
not only winning cases, but also making a
name for himself. She understood his vigorous
pursuit of success, for her father and most
of the men she met in her social circle were
the same way. Like them, he’d been raised
that way, and in the caste system of the South,
family name and accomplishments were often
the most important consideration in marriage.
In some cases, they were the only consideration.
Though she had quietly rebelled against this
idea since childhood and had dated a few men
best described as reckless, she found herself
drawn to Lon’s easy ways and had gradually
come to love him. Despite the long hours he
worked, he was good to her. He was a gentleman,
both mature and responsible, and during those
terrible periods of the war when she needed
someone to hold her, he never once turned
her away. She felt secure with him and knew
he loved her as well, and that was why she
had accepted his proposal.
Thinking these things made her feel guilty
about being here, and she knew she should
pack her things and leave before she changed
her mind. She had done it once before, long
ago, and if she left now, she was sure she
would never have the strength to return here
again. She picked up her pocketbook, hesitated,
and almost made it to the door. But coincidence
had pushed her here, and she put the pocketbook
down, again realizing that if she quit now,
she would always wonder what would have happened.
And she didn’t think she could live with
that.
She went to the bathroom and started a bath.
After checking the temperature, she walked
to the dresser, taking off her gold earrings
as she crossed the room. She found her makeup
bag, opened it, and pulled out a razor and
a bar of soap, then undressed in front of
the bureau.
She had been called beautiful since she was
a young girl, and once she was naked, she
looked at herself in the mirror. Her body
was firm and well proportioned, breasts softly
rounded, stomach flat, legs slim. She’d
inherited her mother’s high cheekbones,
smooth skin, and blond hair, but her best
feature was her own. She had “eyes like
ocean waves,” as Lon liked to say.
Taking the razor and soap, she went to the
bathroom again, turned off the faucet, set
a towel where she could reach it, and stepped
in gingerly.
She liked the way a bath relaxed her, and
she slipped lower in the water. The day had
been long and her back was tense, but she
was pleased she had finished shopping so quickly.
She had to go back to Raleigh with something
tangible, and the things she had picked out
would work fine. She made a mental note to
find the names of some other stores in the
Beaufort area, then suddenly doubted she would
need to. Lon wasn’t the type to check up
on her.
She reached for the soap, lathered up, and
began to shave her legs. As she did, she thought
about her parents and what they would think
of her behavior. No doubt they would disapprove,
especially her mother. Her mother had never
really accepted what had happened the summer
they’d spent here and wouldn’t accept
it now, no matter what reason she gave.
She soaked a while longer in the tub before
finally getting out and toweling off. She
went to the closet and looked for a dress,
finally choosing a long yellow one that dipped
slightly in the front, the kind of dress that
was common in the South. She slipped it on
and looked in the mirror, turning from side
to side. It fit her well and made her look
feminine, but she eventually decided against
it and put it back on the hanger.
Instead she found a more casual, less revealing
dress and put that on. Light blue with a touch
of lace, it buttoned up the front, and though
it didn’t look quite as nice as the first
one, it conveyed an image she thought would
be more appropriate.
She wore little makeup, just a touch of eye
shadow and mascara to accent her eyes. Perfume
next, not too much. She found a pair of small-hooped
earrings, put those on, then slipped on the
tan, low-heeled sandals she had been wearing
earlier. She brushed her blond hair, pinned
it up, and looked in the mirror. No, it was
too much, she thought, and she let it back
down. Better.
When she was finished she stepped back and
evaluated herself. She looked good: not too
dressy, not too casual. She didn’t want
to overdo it. After all, she didn’t know
what to expect. It had been a long time—probably
too long—and many different things could
have happened, even things she didn’t want
to consider.
She looked down and saw her hands were shaking,
and she laughed to herself. It was strange;
she wasn’t normally this nervous. Like Lon,
she had always been confident, even as a child.
She remembered that it had been a problem
at times, especially when she dated, because
it had intimidated most of the boys her age.
She found her pocketbook and car keys, then
picked up the room key. She turned it over
in her hand a couple of times, thinking, You’ve
come this far, don’t give up now, and almost
left then, but instead sat on the bed again.
She checked her watch. Almost six o’clock.
She knew she had to leave in a few minutes—she
didn’t want to arrive after dark, but she
needed a little more time.
“Damn,” she whispered, “what am I doing
here? I shouldn’t be here. There’s no
reason for it,” but once she said it she
knew it wasn’t true. There was something
here. If nothing else, she would have her
answer.
She opened her pocketbook and thumbed through
it until she came to a folded-up piece of
newspaper. After taking it out slowly, almost
reverently, being careful not to rip it, she
unfolded it and stared at it for a while.
“This is why,” she finally said to herself,
“this is what it’s all about.”
Noah got up at five and kayaked for an hour
up Brices Creek, as he usually did. When he
finished, he changed into his work clothes,
warmed some biscuits from the day before,
grabbed a couple of apples, and washed his
breakfast down with two cups of coffee.
He worked on the fencing again, repairing
most of the posts that needed it. It was Indian
summer, the temperature over eighty degrees,
and by lunchtime he was hot and tired and
glad for the break.
He ate at the creek because the mullets were
jumping. He liked to watch them jump three
or four times and glide through the air before
vanishing into the brackish water. For some
reason he had always been pleased by the fact
that their instinct hadn’t changed for thousands,
maybe tens of thousands, of years.
Sometimes he wondered if man’s instincts
had changed in that time and always concluded
that they hadn’t. At least in the basic,
most primal ways. As far as he could tell,
man had always been aggressive, always striving
to dominate, trying to control the world and
everything in it. The war in Europe and Japan
proved that.
He quit working a little after three and walked
to a small shed that sat near his dock. He
went in, found his fishing pole, a couple
of lures, and some live crickets he kept on
hand, then walked out to the dock, baited
his hook, and cast his line.
Fishing always made him reflect on his life,
and he did it now. After his mother died,
he could remember spending his days in a dozen
different homes, and for one reason or another,
he stuttered badly as a child and was teased
for it. He began to speak less and less, and
by the age of five, he wouldn’t speak at
all. When he started classes, his teachers
thought he was retarded and recommended that
he be pulled out of school.
Instead, his father took matters into his
own hands. He kept him in school and afterward
made him come to the lumberyard, where he
worked, to haul and stack wood. “It’s
good that we spend some time together,”
he would say as they worked side by side,
“just like my daddy and I did.”
During their time together, his father would
talk about birds and animals or tell stories
and legends common to North Carolina. Within
a few months Noah was speaking again, though
not well, and his father decided to teach
him to read with books of poetry. “Learn
to read this aloud and you’ll be able to
say anything you want to.” His father had
been right again, and by the following year,
Noah had lost his stutter. But he continued
to go to the lumberyard every day simply because
his father was there, and in the evenings
he would read the works of Whitman and Tennyson
aloud as his father rocked beside him. He
had been reading poetry ever since.
When he got a little older, he spent most
of his weekends and vacations alone. He explored
the Croatan Forest in his first canoe, following
Brices Creek for twenty miles until he could
go no farther, then hiked the remaining miles
to the coast. Camping and exploring became
his passion, and he spent hours in the forest,
sitting beneath blackjack oak trees, whistling
quietly, and playing his guitar for beavers
and geese and wild blue herons. Poets knew
that isolation in nature, far from people
and things man-made, was good for the soul,
and he’d always identified with poets.
Although he was quiet, years of heavy lifting
at the lumberyard helped him excel in sports,
and his athletic success led to popularity.
He enjoyed the football games and track meets,
and though most of his team-mates spent their
free time together as well, he rarely joined
them. An occasional person found him arrogant;
most simply figured he had grown up a bit
faster than everyone else. He had a few girlfriends
in school, but none had ever made an impression
on him. Except for one. And she came after
graduation.
Allie. His Allie.
He remembered talking to Fin about Allie after
they’d left the festival that first night,
and Fin had laughed. Then he’d made two
predictions: first, that they would fall in
love, and second, that it wouldn’t work
out.
There was a slight tug at his line and Noah
hoped for a largemouth bass, but the tugging
eventually stopped, and after reeling his
line in and checking the bait, he cast again.
Fin ended up being right on both counts. Most
of the summer, she had to make excuses to
her parents whenever they wanted to see each
other. It wasn’t that they didn’t like
him—it was that he was from a different
class, too poor, and they would never approve
if their daughter became serious with someone
like him. “I don’t care what my parents
think, I love you and always will,” she
would say. “We’ll find a way to be together.”
But in the end they couldn’t. By early September
the tobacco had been harvested and she had
no choice but to return with her family to
Winston-Salem. “Only the summer is over,
Allie, not us,” he’d said the morning
she left. “We’ll never be over.” But
they were. For a reason he didn’t fully
understand, the letters he wrote went unanswered.
Eventually he decided to leave New Bern to
help get her off his mind, but also because
the Depression made earning a living in New
Bern almost impossible. He went first to Norfolk
and worked at a shipyard for six months before
he was laid off, then moved to New Jersey
because he’d heard the economy wasn’t
so bad there.
He eventually found a job in a scrap yard,
separating scrap metal from everything else.
The owner, a Jewish man named Morris Goldman,
was intent on collecting as much scrap metal
as he could, convinced that a war was going
to start in Europe and that America would
be dragged in again. Noah, though, didn’t
care about the reason. He was just happy to
have a job.
His years in the lumberyard had toughened
him to this type of labor, and he worked hard.
Not only did it help him keep his mind off
Allie during the day, but it was something
he felt he had to do. His daddy had always
said: “Give a day’s work for a day’s
pay. Anything less is stealing.” That attitude
pleased his boss. “It’s a shame you aren’t
Jewish,” Goldman would say, “you’re
such a fine boy in so many other ways.”
It was the best compliment Goldman could give.
He continued to think about Allie, especially
at night. He wrote her once a month but never
received a reply. Eventually he wrote a final
letter and forced himself to accept the fact
that the summer they’d spent with one another
was the only thing they’d ever share.
Still, though, she stayed with him. Three
years after the last letter, he went to Winston-Salem
in the hope of finding her. He went to her
house, discovered that she had moved, and
after talking to some neighbors, finally called
RJR. The girl who answered the phone was new
and didn’t recognize the name, but she poked
around the personnel files for him. She found
out that Allie’s father had left the company
and that no forwarding address was listed.
That trip was the first and last time he ever
looked for her.
For the next eight years, he worked for Goldman.
At first he was one of twelve employees, but
as the years dragged on, the company grew,
and he was promoted. By 1940 he had mastered
the business and was running the entire operation,
brokering the deals and managing a staff of
thirty. The yard had become the largest scrap
metal dealer on the East Coast.
During that time, he dated a few different
women. He became serious with one, a waitress
from the local diner with deep blue eyes and
silky black hair. Although they dated for
two years and had many good times together,
he never came to feel the same way about her
as he did about Allie.
But neither did he forget her. She was a few
years older than he was, and it was she who
taught him the ways to please a woman, the
places to touch and kiss, where to linger,
the things to whisper. They would sometimes
spend an entire day in bed, holding each other
and making the kind of love that fully satisfied
both of them.
She had known they wouldn’t be together
forever. Toward the end of their relationship
she’d told him once, “I wish I could give
you what you’re looking for, but I don’t
know what it is. There’s a part of you that
you keep closed off from everyone, including
me. It’s as if I’m not the one you’re
really with. Your mind is on someone else.”
He tried to deny it, but she didn’t believe
him. “I’m a woman—I know these things.
When you look at me sometimes, I know you’re
seeing someone else. It’s like you keep
waiting for her to pop out of thin air to
take you away from all this. . . .” A month
later she visited him at work and told him
she’d met someone else. He understood. They
parted as friends, and the following year
he received a postcard from her saying she
was married. He hadn’t heard from her since.
While he was in New Jersey, he would visit
his father once a year around Christmas. They’d
spend some time fishing and talking, and once
in a while they’d take a trip to the coast
to go camping on the Outer Banks near Ocracoke.
In December 1941, when he was twenty-six,
the war began, just as Goldman had predicted.
Noah walked into his office the following
month and informed Goldman of his intent to
enlist, then returned to New Bern to say good-bye
to his father. Five weeks later he found himself
in boot camp. While there, he received a letter
from Goldman thanking him for his work, together
with a copy of a certificate entitling him
to a small percentage of the scrap yard if
it ever sold. “I couldn’t have done it
without you,” the letter said. “You’re
the finest young man who ever worked for me,
even if you aren’t Jewish.”
He spent his next three years with Patton’s
Third Army, tramping through deserts in North
Africa and forests in Europe with thirty pounds
on his back, his infantry unit never far from
action. He watched his friends die around
him; watched as some of them were buried thousands
of miles from home. Once, while hiding in
a foxhole near the Rhine, he imagined he saw
Allie watching over him.
He remembered the war ending in Europe, then
a few months later in Japan. Just before he
was discharged, he received a letter from
a lawyer in New Jersey representing Morris
Goldman. Upon meeting the lawyer, he found
out that Goldman had died a year earlier and
his estate liquidated. The business had been
sold, and Noah was given a check for almost
seventy thousand dollars. For some reason
he was oddly unexcited about it.
The following week he returned to New Bern
and bought the house. He remembered bringing
his father around later, showing him what
he was going to do, pointing out the changes
he intended to make. His father seemed weak
as he walked around, coughing and wheezing.
Noah was concerned, but his father told him
not to worry, assuring him that he had the
flu.
Less than one month later his father died
of pneumonia and was buried next to his wife
in the local cemetery. Noah tried to stop
by regularly to leave some flowers; occasionally
he left a note. And every night without fail
he took a moment to remember him, then said
a prayer for the man who’d taught him everything
that mattered.
After reeling in the line, he put the gear
away and went back to the house. His neighbor,
Martha Shaw, was there to thank him, bringing
three loaves of homemade bread and some biscuits
in appreciation for what he’d done. Her
husband had been killed in the war, leaving
her with three children and a tired shack
of a house to raise them in. Winter was coming,
and he’d spent a few days at her place last
week repairing her roof, replacing broken
windows and sealing the others, and fixing
her woodstove. Hopefully, it would be enough
to get them through.
Once she’d left, he got in his battered
Dodge truck and went to see Gus. He always
stopped there when he was going to the store
because Gus’s family didn’t have a car.
One of the daughters hopped up and rode with
him, and they did their shopping at Capers
General Store. When he got home he didn’t
unpack the groceries right away. Instead he
showered, found a Budweiser and a book by
Dylan Thomas, and went to sit on the porch.
She still had trouble believing it, even as
she held the proof in her hands.
It had been in the newspaper at her parents’
house three Sundays ago. She had gone to the
kitchen to get a cup of coffee, and when she’d
returned to the table, her father had smiled
and pointed at a small picture. “Remember
this?”
He handed her the paper, and after an uninterested
first glance, something in the picture caught
her eye and she took a closer look. “It
can’t be,” she whispered, and when her
father looked at her curiously, she ignored
him, sat down, and read the article without
speaking. She vaguely remembered her mother
coming to the table and sitting opposite her,
and when she finally put aside the paper,
her mother was staring at her with the same
expression her father had just moments before.
“Are you okay?” her mother asked over
her coffee cup. “You look a little pale.”
She didn’t answer right away, she couldn’t,
and it was then that she’d noticed her hands
were shaking. That had been when it started.
“And here it will end, one way or the other,”
she whispered again. She refolded the scrap
of paper and put it back, remembering that
she had left her parents’ home later that
day with the paper so she could cut out the
article. She read it again before she went
to bed that night, trying to fathom the coincidence,
and read it again the next morning as if to
make sure the whole thing wasn’t a dream.
And now, after three weeks of long walks alone,
after three weeks of distraction, it was the
reason she’d come.
When asked, she said her erratic behavior
was due to stress. It was the perfect excuse;
everyone understood, including Lon, and that’s
why he hadn’t argued when she’d wanted
to get away for a couple of days. The wedding
plans were stressful to everyone involved.
Almost five hundred people were invited, including
the governor, one senator, and the ambassador
to Peru. It was too much, in her opinion,
but their engagement was news and had dominated
the social pages since they had announced
their plans six months ago. Occasionally she
felt like running away with Lon to get married
without the fuss. But she knew he wouldn’t
agree; like the aspiring politician he was,
he loved being the center of attention.
She took a deep breath and stood again. “It’s
now or never,” she whispered, then picked
up her things and went to the door. She paused
only slightly before opening it and going
downstairs. The manager smiled as she walked
by, and she could feel his eyes on her as
she left and went to her car. She slipped
behind the wheel, looked at herself one last
time, then started the engine and turned right
onto Front Street.
She wasn’t surprised that she still knew
her way around town so well. Even though she
hadn’t been here in years, it wasn’t large
and she navigated the streets easily. After
crossing the Trent River on an old-fashioned
drawbridge, she turned onto a gravel road
and began the final leg of her journey.
It was beautiful here in the low country,
as it always had been. Unlike the Piedmont
area where she grew up, the land was flat,
but it had the same silty, fertile soil that
was ideal for cotton and tobacco. Those two
crops and timber kept the towns alive in this
part of the state, and as she drove along
the road outside town, she saw the beauty
that had first attracted people to this region.
To her, it hadn’t changed at all. Broken
sunlight passed through water oaks and hickory
trees a hundred feet tall, illuminating the
colors of fall. On her left, a river the color
of iron veered toward the road and then turned
away before giving up its life to a different,
larger river another mile ahead. The gravel
road itself wound its way between antebellum
farms, and she knew that for some of the farmers,
life hadn’t changed since before their grandparents
were born. The constancy of the place brought
back a flood of memories, and she felt her
insides tighten as one by one she recognized
landmarks she’d long since forgotten.
The sun hung just above the trees on her left,
and as she rounded a curve, she passed an
old church, abandoned for years but still
standing. She had explored it that summer,
looking for souvenirs from the War between
the States, and as her car passed by, the
memories of that day became stronger, as if
they’d just happened yesterday.
A majestic oak tree on the banks of the river
came into view next, and the memories became
more intense. It looked the same as it had
back then, branches low and thick, stretching
horizontally along the ground with Spanish
moss draped over the limbs like a veil. She
remembered sitting beneath the tree on a hot
July day with someone who looked at her with
a longing that took everything else away.
And it had been at that moment that she’d
first fallen in love.
He was two years older than she was, and as
she drove along this roadway-in-time, he slowly
came into focus once again. He always looked
older than he really was, she remembered thinking.
His appearance was that of someone slightly
weathered, almost like a farmer coming home
after hours in the field. He had the callused
hands and broad shoulders that came to those
who worked hard for a living, and the first
faint lines were beginning to form around
the dark eyes that seemed to read her every
thought.
He was tall and strong, with light brown hair,
and handsome in his own way, but it was his
voice that she remembered most of all. He
had read to her that day; read to her as they
lay in the grass beneath the tree with an
accent that was soft and fluent, almost musical
in quality. It was the kind of voice that
belonged on radio, and it seemed to hang in
the air when he read to her. She remembered
closing her eyes, listening closely, and letting
the words he was reading touch her soul:
It coaxes me to the vapor and the dusk.
I depart as air, I shake my white locks at
the runaway sun . . .
He thumbed through old books with dog-eared
pages, books he’d read a hundred times.
He’d read for a while, then stop, and the
two of them would talk. She would tell him
what she wanted in her life— her hopes and
dreams for the future—and he would listen
intently and then promise to make it all come
true. And the way he said it made her believe
him, and she knew then how much he meant to
her. Occasionally, when she asked, he would
talk about himself or explain why he had chosen
a particular poem and what he thought of it,
and at other times he just studied her in
that intense way of his.
They watched the sun go down and ate together
under the stars. It was getting late by then,
and she knew her parents would be furious
if they knew where she was. At that moment,
though, it really didn’t matter to her.
All she could think about was how special
the day had been, how special he was, and
as they started toward her house a few minutes
later, he took her hand in his and she felt
the way it warmed her the whole way back.
Another turn in the road and she finally saw
it in the distance. The house had changed
dramatically from what she remembered. She
slowed the car as she approached, turning
into the long, tree-lined dirt drive that
led to the beacon that had summoned her from
Raleigh.
She drove slowly, looking toward the house,
and took a deep breath when she saw him on
the porch, watching her car. He was dressed
casually. From a distance, he looked the same
as he had back then. For a moment, when the
light from the sun was behind him, he almost
seemed to vanish into the scenery.
Her car continued forward, rolling slowly,
then finally stopped beneath an oak tree that
shaded the front of the house. She turned
the key, never taking her eyes from him, and
the engine sputtered to a halt.
He stepped off the porch and began to approach
her, walking easily, then suddenly stopped
cold as she emerged from the car. For a long
time all they could do was stare at each other
without moving.
Allison Nelson, twenty-nine years old and
engaged, a socialite, searching for answers
she needed to know, and Noah Calhoun, the
dreamer, thirty-one, visited by the ghost
that had come to dominate his life.
Reunion
Neither one of them moved as they faced each
other.
He hadn’t said anything, his muscles seemed
frozen, and for a second she thought he didn’t
recognize her. Suddenly she felt guilty about
showing up this way, without warning, and
this made it harder. She had thought it would
be easier somehow, that she would know what
to say. But she didn’t. Everything that
came into her head seemed inappropriate, somehow
lacking.
Thoughts of the summer they’d shared came
back to her, and as she stared at him, she
noticed how little he’d changed since she’d
last seen him. He looked good, she thought.
With his shirt tucked loosely into old faded
jeans, she could see the same broad shoulders
she remembered, tapering down to narrow hips
and a flat stomach. He was tan, too, as if
he’d worked outside all summer, and though
his hair was a little thinner and lighter
than she remembered, he looked the same as
he had when she’d known him last.
When she was finally ready, she took a deep
breath and smiled.
“Hello, Noah. It’s good to see you again.”
Her comment startled him, and he looked at
her with amazement in his eyes. Then, after
shaking his head slightly, he slowly began
to smile.
“You too . . . ,” he stammered. He brought
his hand to his chin, and she noticed he hadn’t
shaved. “It’s really you, isn’t it?
I can’t believe it. . . .”
She heard the shock in his voice as he spoke,
and surprising her, it all came together—being
here, seeing him. She felt something twitch
inside, something deep and old, something
that made her dizzy for just a second.
She caught herself fighting for control. She
hadn’t expected this to happen, didn’t
want it to happen. She was engaged now. She
hadn’t come here for this ...yet ...
Yet...
Yet the feeling went on despite herself, and
for a brief moment she felt fifteen again.
Felt as she hadn’t in years, as if all her
dreams could still come true.
Felt as though she’d finally come home.
Without another word they came together, as
if it were the most natural thing in the world,
and he put his arms around her, drawing her
close. They held each other tightly, making
it real, both of them letting the fourteen
years of separation dissolve in the deepening
twilight.
They stayed like that for a long time before
she finally pulled back to look at him. Up
close, she could see the changes she hadn’t
noticed at first. He was a man now, and his
face had lost the softness of youth. The faint
lines around his eyes had deepened, and there
was a scar on his chin that hadn’t been
there before. There was a new edge to him;
he seemed less innocent, more cautious, and
yet the way he was holding her made her realize
how much she’d missed him since she’d
seen him last.
Her eyes brimmed with tears as they finally
released each other. She laughed nervously
under her breath while wiping the tears from
the corners of her eyes.
“Are you okay?” he asked, a thousand other
questions on his face.
“I’m sorry, I didn’t mean to cry....”
“It’s okay,” he said, smiling, “I
still can’t believe it’s you. How did
you find me?”
She stepped back, trying to compose herself,
wiping away the last of her tears.
“I saw the story on the house in the Raleigh
paper a couple of weeks ago, and I had to
come see you again.”
Noah smiled broadly. “I’m glad you did.”
He stepped back just a bit. “God, you look
fantastic. You’re even prettier now than
you were then.”
She felt the blood in her face. Just like
fourteen years ago.
“Thank you. You look great, too.” And
he did, no doubt about it. The years had treated
him well.
“So what have you been up to? Why are you
here?”
His questions brought her back to the present,
making her realize what could happen if she
wasn’t careful. Don’t let this get out
of hand, she told herself; the longer it goes
on, the harder it’s going to be. And she
didn’t want it to get any harder.
But God, those eyes. Those soft, dark eyes.
She turned away and took a deep breath, wondering
how to say it, and when she finally started,
her voice was quiet. “Noah, before you get
the wrong idea, I did want to see you again,
but there’s more to it than just that.”
She paused for a second. “I came here for
a reason. There’s something I have to tell
you.”
“What is it?”
She looked away and didn’t answer for a
moment, surprised that she couldn’t tell
him just yet. In the silence, Noah felt a
sinking feeling in his stomach. Whatever it
was, was bad.
“I don’t know how to say it. I thought
I did at first, but now I’m not so sure.
. . .”
The air was suddenly rattled by the sharp
cry of a raccoon, and Clem came out from under
the porch, barking gruffly. Both of them turned
at the commotion, and Allie was glad for the
distraction.
“Is he yours?” she asked.
Noah nodded, feeling the tightness in his
stomach. “Actually it’s a she. Clementine’s
her name. But yeah, she’s all mine.” They
both watched as Clem shook her head, stretched,
then wandered toward the sounds. Allie’s
eyes widened just a bit when she saw her limp
away.
“What happened to her leg?” she asked,
stalling for time.
“Hit by a car a few months back. Doc Harrison,
the vet, called me to see if I wanted her
because her owner didn’t anymore. After
I saw what had happened, I guess I just couldn’t
let her be put down.”
“You were always nice like that,” she
said, trying to relax. She paused, then looked
past him toward the house. “You did a wonderful
job restoring it. It looks perfect, just like
I knew it would someday.”
He turned his head in the same direction as
hers while he wondered about the small talk
and what she was holding back.
“Thanks, that’s nice of you. It was quite
a project, though. I don’t know if I would
do it again.”
“Of course you would,” she said. She knew
exactly how he felt about this place. But
then, she knew how he felt about everything—or
at least she had a long time ago.
And with that thought, she realized how much
had changed since then. They were strangers
now; she could tell by looking at him. Could
tell that fourteen years apart was a long
time. Too long.
“What is it, Allie?” He turned to her,
compelling her to look, but she continued
to stare at the house.
“I’m being rather silly, aren’t I?”
she asked, trying to smile.
“What do you mean?”
“This whole thing. Showing up out of the
blue, not knowing what I want to say. You
must think I’m crazy.”
“You’re not crazy,” he said gently.
He reached for her hand, and she let him hold
it as they stood next to one another. He went
on:
“Even though I don’t know why, I can see
this is hard for you. Why don’t we go for
a walk?”
“Like we used to?”
“Why not? I think we both could use one.”
She hesitated and looked to his front door.
“Do you need to tell anyone?”
He shook his head.
“No, there’s no one to tell. It’s just
me and Clem.” Even though she’d asked,
she had suspected there wouldn’t be anyone
else, and inside she didn’t know how to
feel about that. But it did make what she
wanted to say a little harder. It would have
been easier if there was someone else.
They started toward the river and turned on
a path near the bank. She let go of his hand,
surprising him, and walked on with just enough
distance between them so that they couldn’t
accidentally touch.
He looked at her. She was pretty still, with
thick hair and soft eyes, and she moved so
gracefully that it almost seemed as though
she were gliding. He’d seen beautiful women
before, though, women who caught his eye,
but to his mind they usually lacked the traits
he found most desirable. Traits like intelligence,
confidence, strength of spirit, passion, traits
that inspired others to greatness, traits
he aspired to himself.
Allie had those traits, he knew, and as they
walked now, he sensed them once again lingering
beneath the surface. “A living poem” had
always been the words that came to mind when
he tried to describe her to others.
“How long have you been back here?” she
asked as the path gave way to a small grass
hill.
“Since last December. I worked up north
for a while, then spent the last three years
in Europe.”
She looked to him with questions in her eyes.
“The war?”
He nodded and she went on.
“I thought you might be there. I’m glad
you made it out okay.”
“Me too,” he said.
“Are you glad to be back home?”
“Yeah. My roots are here. This is where
I’m supposed to be.” He paused. “But
what about you?” He asked the question softly,
suspecting the worst.
It was a long moment before she answered.
“I’m engaged.”
He looked down when she said it, suddenly
feeling just a bit weaker. So that was it.
That’s what she needed to tell him.
“Congratulations,” he finally said, wondering
how convincing he sounded. “When’s the
big day?”
“Three weeks from Saturday. Lon wanted a
November wedding.”
“Lon?”
“Lon Hammond Jr. My fiancé.”
He nodded, not surprised. The Hammonds were
one of the most powerful and influential families
in the state. Cotton money. Unlike that of
his own father, the death of Lon Hammond Sr.
had made the front page of the newspaper.
“I’ve heard of them. His father built
quite a business. Did Lon take over for him?”
She shook her head. “No, he’s a lawyer.
He has his own practice downtown.”
“With his name, he must be busy.”
“He is. He works a lot.”
He thought he heard something in her tone,
and the next question came automatically.
“Does he treat you well?”
She didn’t answer right away, as if she
were considering the question for the first
time. Then:
“Yes. He’s a good man, Noah. You would
like him.”
Her voice was distant when she answered, or
at least he thought it was. Noah wondered
if it was just his mind playing tricks on
him.
“How’s your daddy doing?” she asked.
Noah took a couple of steps before answering.
“He passed on earlier this year, right after
I got back.”
“I’m sorry,” she said softly, knowing
how much he had meant to Noah.
He nodded, and the two walked in silence for
a moment.
They reached the top of the hill and stopped.
The oak tree was in the distance, with the
sun glowing orange behind it. Allie could
feel his eyes on her as she stared in that
direction.
“A lot of memories there, Allie.”
She smiled. “I know. I saw it when I came
in. Do you remember the day we spent there?”
“Yes,” he answered, volunteering no more.
“Do you ever think about it?”
“Sometimes,” he said. “Usually when
I’m working out this way. It sits on my
property now.”
“You bought it?”
“I just couldn’t bear to see it turned
into kitchen cabinets.”
She laughed under her breath, feeling strangely
pleased about that. “Do you still read poetry?”
He nodded. “Yeah. I never stopped. I guess
it’s in my blood.”
“Do you know, you’re the only poet I’ve
ever met.”
“I’m no poet. I read, but I can’t write
a verse. I’ve tried.”
“You’re still a poet, Noah Taylor Calhoun.”
Her voice softened. “I still think about
it a lot. It was the first time anyone ever
read poetry to me before. In fact, it’s
the only time.”
Her comment made both of them drift back and
remember as they slowly circled back to the
house, following a new path that passed near
the dock. As the sun dropped a little lower
and the sky turned orange, he asked:
“So, how long are you staying?”
“I don’t know. Not long. Maybe until tomorrow
or the next day.”
“Is your fiancé here on business?”
She shook her head. “No, he’s still in
Raleigh.” Noah raised his eyebrows. “Does
he know you’re here?”
She shook her head again and answered slowly.
“No. I told him I was looking for antiques.
He wouldn’t understand my coming here.”
Noah was a little surprised by her answer.
It was one thing to come and visit, but it
was an entirely different matter to hide the
truth from her fiancé.
“You didn’t have to come here to tell
me you were engaged. You could have written
me instead, or even called.”
“I know. But for some reason, I had to do
it in person.”
“Why?”
She hesitated. “I don’t know . . . ,” she
said, trailing off, and the way she said it
made him believe her. The gravel crunched
beneath their feet as they walked in silence
for a few steps. Then he asked:
“Allie, do you love him?”
She answered automatically. “Yes, I love
him.” The words hurt. But again, he thought
he heard something in her tone, as if she
were saying it to convince herself. He stopped
and gently took her shoulders in his hands,
making her face him. The fading sunlight reflected
in her eyes as he spoke.
“If you’re happy, Allie, and you love
him, I won’t try to stop you from going
back to him. But if there’s a part of you
that isn’t sure, then don’t do it. This
isn’t the kind of thing you go into halfway.”
Her answer came almost too quickly.
“I’m making the right decision, Noah.”
He stared for a second, wondering if he believed
her. Then he nodded and the two began to walk
again. After a moment he said: “I’m not
making this easy for you, am I?”
She smiled a little. “It’s okay. I really
can’t blame you.”
“I’m sorry anyway.”
“Don’t be. There’s no reason to be sorry.
I’m the one who should be apologizing. Maybe
I should have written.”
He shook his head. “To be honest, I’m
still glad you came. Despite everything. It’s
good to see you again.”
“Thank you, Noah.”
“Do you think it would be possible to start
over?”
She looked at him curiously.
“You were the best friend I ever had, Allie.
I’d still like to be friends, even if you
are engaged, and even if it is just for a
couple of days. How about we just kind of
get to know each other again?”
She thought about it, thought about staying
or leaving, and decided that since he knew
about her engagement, it would probably be
all right. Or at least not wrong. She smiled
slightly and nodded.
“I’d like that.”
“Good. How about dinner? I know a place
that serves the best crab in town.”
“Sounds great. Where?”
“My house. I’ve had the traps out all
week, and I saw that I had some good ones
caged a couple days ago. Do you mind?”
“No, that sounds fine.”
He smiled and pointed over his shoulder with
his thumb. “Great. They’re at the dock.
I’ll just be a couple of minutes.”
Allie watched him walk away and noticed the
tension she’d felt when telling him about
her engagement was beginning to fade. Closing
her eyes, she ran her hands through her hair
and let the light breeze fan her cheek. She
took a deep breath and held it for a moment,
feeling the muscles in her shoulders further
relax as she exhaled. Finally, opening her
eyes, she stared at the beauty that surrounded
her.
She always loved evenings like this, evenings
where the faint aroma of autumn leaves rode
on the backs of soft southern winds. She loved
the trees and the sounds they made. Listening
to them helped her relax even more. After
a moment, she turned toward Noah and looked
at him almost as a stranger might.
God, he looked good. Even after all this time.
She watched him as he reached for a rope that
hung in the water. He began to pull it, and
despite the darkening sky, she saw the muscles
in his arm flex as he lifted the cage from
the water. He let it hang over the river for
a moment and shook it, letting most of the
water escape. After setting the trap on the
dock, he opened it and began to remove the
crabs one by one, placing them into a bucket.
She started walking toward him then, listening
to the crickets chirp, and remembered a lesson
from childhood. She counted the number of
chirps in a minute and added twenty-nine.
Sixty-seven degrees, she thought as she smiled
to herself. She didn’t know if it was accurate,
but it felt about right.
As she walked, she looked around and realized
she had forgotten how fresh and beautiful
everything seemed here. Over her shoulder,
she saw the house in the distance. He had
left a couple of lights on, and it seemed
to be the only house around. At least the
only one with electricity. Out here, outside
the town limits, nothing was certain. Thousands
of country homes still lacked the luxury of
indoor lighting.
She stepped on the dock and it creaked under
her foot. The sound reminded her of a rusty
squeeze-box, and Noah glanced up and winked,
then went back to checking the crabs, making
sure they were the right size. She walked
to the rocker that sat on the dock and touched
it, running her hand along the back. She could
picture him sitting in it, fishing, thinking,
reading. It was old and weather-beaten, rough
feeling. She wondered how much time he spent
here alone, and she wondered about his thoughts
at times like those.
“It was my daddy’s chair,” he said,
not looking up, and she nodded. She saw bats
in the sky, and frogs had joined the crickets
in their evening harmony.
She walked to the other side of the dock,
feeling a sense of closure. A compulsion had
driven her here, and for the first time in
three weeks the feeling was gone. She’d
somehow needed Noah to know about her engagement,
to understand, to accept it—she was sure
of that now—and while thinking of him, she
was reminded of something they’d shared
from the summer they were together. With head
down, she paced around slowly, looking for
it until she found it—the carving. Noah
loves Allie, in a heart. Carved into the dock
a few days before she’d left.
A breeze broke the stillness and chilled her,
making her cross her arms. She stood that
way, alternately looking down at the carving
and then toward the river, until she heard
him reach her side. She could feel his closeness,
his warmth, as she spoke.
“It’s so peaceful here,” she said, her
voice dreamlike.
“I know. I come down here a lot now just
to be close to the water. It makes me feel
good.”
“I would, too, if I were you.”
“Come on, let’s go. The mosquitoes are
getting vicious, and I’m starved.”
The sky had turned black, and Noah started
toward the house, Allie right beside him.
In the silence her mind wandered, and she
felt a little light-headed as she walked along
the path. She wondered what he was thinking
about her being here and wasn’t exactly
sure if she knew herself. When they reached
the house a couple of minutes later, Clem
greeted them with a wet nose in the wrong
place. Noah motioned her away, and she left
with her tail between her legs.
He pointed to her car. “Did you leave anything
in there that you need to get out?”
“No, I got in earlier and unpacked already.”
Her voice sounded different to her, as if
the years had suddenly been undone.
“Good enough,” he said as he reached the
back porch and started up the steps. He set
the bucket by the door, then led the way inside,
heading toward the kitchen. It was on the
immediate right, large and smelling of new
wood. The cabinets had been done in oak, as
was the floor, and the windows were large
and faced east, allowing the light from morning
sun. It was a tasteful restoration, not overdone
as was common when homes like this were rebuilt.
“Do you mind if I look around?”
“No, go ahead. I did some shopping earlier,
and I still have to put the groceries away.”
Their eyes met for a second, and Allie knew
as she turned that he continued to watch her
as she left the room. Inside she felt that
little twitch again.
She toured the house for the next few minutes,
walking through the rooms, noticing how wonderful
it looked. By the time she’d finished, it
was hard to remember how run-down it had been.
She came down the stairs, turned toward the
kitchen, and saw his profile. For a second
he looked like a young man of seventeen again,
and it made her pause a split second before
going on. Damn, she thought, get a hold of
yourself. Remember that you’re engaged now.
He was standing by the counter, a couple of
cabinet doors open wide, empty grocery bags
on the floor, whistling quietly. He smiled
at her before putting a few more cans into
one of the cabinets. She stopped a few feet
from him and leaned against the counter, one
leg over the other. She shook her head, amazed
at how much he had done.
“It’s unbelievable, Noah. How long did
the restoration take?”
He looked up from the last bag he was unpacking.
“Almost a year.”
“Did you do it yourself?”
He laughed under his breath. “No. I always
thought I would when I was young, and I started
that way. But it was just too much. It would
have taken years, and so I ended up hiring
some people . . . actually a lot of people.
But even with them, it was still a lot of
work, and most of the time I didn’t stop
until past midnight.”
“Why’d you work so hard?”
Ghosts, he wanted to say, but didn’t.
“I don’t know. Just wanted to finish,
I guess. Do you want anything to drink before
I start dinner?”
“What do you have?”
“Not much, really. Beer, tea, coffee.”
“Tea sounds good.”
He gathered the grocery bags and put them
away, then walked to a small room off the
kitchen before returning with a box of tea.
He pulled out a couple of teabags and set
them by the stove, then filled the teapot.
After putting it on the burner, he lit a match,
and she heard the sound of flames as they
came to life.
“It’ll be just a minute,” he said. “This
stove heats up pretty quick.”
“That’s fine.”
When the teapot whistled, he poured two cups
and handed one to her.
She smiled and took a sip, then motioned toward
the window. “I’ll bet the kitchen is beautiful
when the morning light shines in.”
He nodded. “It is. I had larger windows
put in on this side of the house for just
that reason. Even in the bedrooms upstairs.”
“I’m sure your guests enjoy that. Unless
of course they want to sleep late.”
“Actually, I haven’t had any guests stay
over yet. Since my daddy passed on, I don’t
really know who to invite.”
By his tone, she knew he was just making conversation.
Yet for some reason it made her feel . . . lonely.
He seemed to realize how she was feeling,
but before she could dwell on it, he changed
the subject.
“I’m going to get the crabs in to marinate
for a few minutes before I steam ’em,”
he said, putting his cup on the counter. He
went to the cupboard and removed a large pot
with a steamer and lid. He brought the pot
to the sink, added water, then carried it
to the stove.
“Can I give you a hand with something?”
He answered over his shoulder. “Sure. How
about cutting up some vegetables for the fryer.
There’s plenty in the icebox, and you can
find a bowl over there.”
He motioned to the cabinet near the sink,
and she took another sip of tea before setting
her cup on the counter and retrieving the
bowl. She carried it to the icebox and found
some okra, zucchini, onions, and carrots on
the bottom shelf. Noah joined her in front
of the open door, and she moved to make room
for him. She could smell him as he stood next
to her— clean, familiar, distinctive—and
felt his arm brush against her as he leaned
over and reached inside. He removed a beer
and a bottle of hot sauce, then returned to
the stove.
Noah opened the beer and poured it in the
water, then added the hot sauce and some other
seasoning as well. After stirring the water
to make sure the powders were dissolved, he
went to the back door to get the crabs.
He paused for a moment before going back inside
and stared at Allie, watching her cut the
carrots. As he did that, he wondered again
why she had come, especially now that she
was engaged. None of this seemed to make much
sense to him.
But then, Allie had always been surprising.
He smiled to himself, remembering back to
the way she had been. Fiery, spontaneous,
passionate—as he imagined most artists to
be. And she was definitely that. Artistic
talent like hers was a gift. He remembered
seeing some paintings in the museums in New
York and thinking that her work was just as
good as what he had seen there.
She had given him a painting before she’d
left that summer. It hung above the fireplace
in the living room. She’d called it a picture
of her dreams, and to him it had seemed extremely
sensual. When he looked at it, and he often
did late in the evening, he could see desire
in the colors and the lines, and if he focused
carefully, he could imagine what she had been
thinking with every stroke.
A dog barked in the distance, and Noah realized
he had been standing with the door open a
long time. He quickly closed it, turning back
to the kitchen. And as he walked, he wondered
if she had noticed how long he’d been gone.
“How’s it going?” he asked, seeing she
was almost finished.
“Good. I’m almost done here. Anything
else for dinner?”
“I have some homemade bread that I was planning
on.”
“Homemade?”
“From a neighbor,” he said as he put the
pail in the sink. He started the faucet and
began to rinse the crabs, holding them under
the water, then letting them scurry around
the sink while he rinsed the next one. Allie
picked up her cup and came over to watch him.
“Aren’t you afraid they’ll pinch you
when you grab them?”
“No. Just grab ’em like this,” he said,
demonstrating, and she smiled.
“I forget you’ve done this your whole
life.” “New Bern’s small, but it does
teach you how to do the things that matter.”
She leaned against the counter, standing close
to him, and emptied her cup. When the crabs
were ready he put them in the pot on the stove.
He washed his hands, turning to speak to her
as he did so.
“You want to sit on the porch for a few
minutes? I’d like to let ’em soak for
a half hour.”
“Sure,” she said.
He wiped his hands, and together they went
to the back porch. Noah flipped on the light
as they went outside, and he sat in the older
rocker, offering the newer one to her. When
he saw her cup was empty, he went inside for
a moment and emerged with another cup of tea
and a beer for himself. He held out the cup
and she took it, sipping again before she
set it on the table beside the chairs.
“You were sitting out here when I came,
weren’t you?”
He answered as he made himself comfortable.
“Yeah. I sit out here every night. It’s
a habit now.”
“I can see why,” she said as she looked
around. “So, what is it you do these days?”
“Actually, I don’t do anything but work
on the house right now. It satisfies my creative
urges.”
“How can you ...I mean . . .”
“Morris Goldman.”
“Excuse me?”
He smiled. “My old boss from up north. His
name was Morris Goldman. He offered me a part
of the business just as I enlisted and died
before I got home. When I got back to the
States, his lawyers gave me a check big enough
to buy this place and fix it up.”
She laughed under her breath. “You always
told me you’d find a way to do it.”
They both sat quietly for a moment, thinking
back again. Allie took another sip of tea.
“Do you remember sneaking over here the
night you first told me about this place?”
He nodded, and she went on:
“I got home a little late that evening,
and my parents were furious when I finally
came in. I can still picture my daddy standing
in the living room smoking a cigarette, my
mother on the sofa staring straight ahead.
I swear, they looked as if a family member
had died. That was the first time my parents
knew I was serious about you, and my mother
had a long talk with me later that night.
She said to me, ‘I’m sure you think that
I don’t understand what you’re going through,
but I do. It’s just that sometimes, our
future is dictated by what we are, as opposed
to what we want.’ I remember being really
hurt when she said that.”
“You told me about it the next day. It hurt
my feelings, too. I liked your parents, and
I had no idea they didn’t like me.”
“It wasn’t that they didn’t like you.
They didn’t think you deserved me.”
“There’s not much difference.”
There was a sadness in his voice when he responded,
and she knew he was right to feel that way.
She looked toward the stars while she ran
her hand through her hair, pulling back the
strands that had fallen onto her face.
“I know that. I always did. Maybe that’s
why my mother and I always seem to have a
distance between us when we talk.”
“How do you feel about it now?”
“The same as I did back then. That it’s
wrong, that it isn’t fair. It was a terrible
thing for a girl to learn. That status is
more important than feelings.”
Noah smiled softly at her answer but said
nothing.
“I’ve thought about you ever since that
summer,” she said.
“You have?”
“Why wouldn’t you think so?” She seemed
genuinely surprised.
“You never answered my letters.”
“You wrote?”
“Dozens of letters. I wrote you for two
years without receiving a single reply.”
She slowly shook her head before lowering
her eyes.
“I didn’t know . . . ,” she finally
said, quietly, and he knew it must have been
her mother, checking the mail, removing the
letters without her knowledge. It was what
he had always suspected, and he watched as
Allie came to the same realization.
“It was wrong of her to do that, Noah, and
I’m sorry she did. But try to understand.
Once I left, she probably thought it would
be easier for me to just let it go. She never
understood how much you meant to me, and to
be honest, I don’t even know if she ever
loved my father the way I loved you. In her
mind, she was just trying to protect my feelings,
and she probably thought the best way to do
that was to hide the letters you sent.”
“That wasn’t her decision to make,”
he said quietly.
“I know.”
“Would it have made a difference even if
you’d got them?”
“Of course. I always wondered what you were
up to.”
“No, I mean with us. Do you think we would
have made it?”
It took a moment for her to answer.
“I don’t know, Noah. I really don’t,
and you don’t either. We’re not the same
people we were then. We’ve changed, we’ve
grown. Both of us.”
She paused. He didn’t respond, and in the
silence she looked toward the creek. She went
on:
“But yes, Noah, I think we would have. At
least, I’d like to think we would have.”
He nodded, looked down, then turned away.
“What’s Lon like?”
She hesitated, not expecting the question.
Bringing up Lon’s name brought slight feelings
of guilt to the surface, and for a moment
she didn’t know how to answer. She reached
for her cup, took another sip of tea, and
listened as a woodpecker tapped in the distance.
She spoke quietly.
“Lon’s handsome, charming, and successful,
and most of my friends are insanely jealous.
They think he’s perfect, and in a lot of
ways he is. He’s kind to me, he makes me
laugh, and I know he loves me in his own way.”
She paused for a moment, collecting her thoughts.
“But there’s always going to be something
missing in our relationship.”
She surprised herself with her answer but
knew it was true nonetheless. And she also
knew by looking at him that Noah had suspected
the answer in advance.
“Why?”
She smiled weakly and shrugged as she answered.
Her voice was barely above a whisper.
“I guess I still look for the kind of love
we had that summer.”
Noah thought about what she had said for a
long while, thinking about the relationships
he’d had since he’d last seen her.
“How about you?” she asked. “Did you
ever think about us?”
“All the time. I still do.”
“Are you seeing anyone?”
“No,” he answered, shaking his head.
Both of them seemed to think about that, trying
but finding it impossible to displace from
their minds. Noah finished his beer, surprised
that he had emptied it so quickly.
“I’m going to go start the water. Can
I get you anything?”
She shook her head, and Noah went to the kitchen
and put the crabs in the steamer and the bread
in the oven. He found some flour and cornmeal
for the vegetables, coated them, and put some
grease into the frying pan. After turning
the heat on low, he set a timer and pulled
another beer from the icebox before heading
back to the porch. And while he was doing
those things, he thought about Allie and the
love that was missing from both their lives.
Allie, too, was thinking. About Noah, about
herself, about a lot of things. For a moment
she wished she weren’t engaged but then
quickly cursed herself. It wasn’t Noah she
loved; she loved what they once had been.
Besides, it was normal to feel this way. Her
first real love, the only man she’d ever
been with— how could she expect to forget
him?
Yet was it normal for her insides to twitch
whenever he came near? Was it normal to confess
things she could never tell anyone else? Was
it normal to come here three weeks from her
wedding day?
“No, it’s not,” she finally whispered
to herself as she looked to the evening sky.
“There’s nothing normal about any of this.”
Noah came out at that moment and she smiled
at him, glad he’d come back so she didn’t
have to think about it anymore. “It’s
going to take a few minutes,” he said as
he sat back down.
“That’s fine. I’m not that hungry yet.”
He looked at her then, and she saw the softness
in his eyes. “I’m glad you came, Allie,”
he said.
“Me too. I almost didn’t, though.”
“Why did you come?”
I was compelled, she wanted to say, but didn’t.
“Just to see you, to find out what you’ve
been up to. To see how you are.”
He wondered if that was all but didn’t question
further. Instead he changed the subject.
“By the way, I’ve been meaning to ask,
do you still paint?”
She shook her head. “Not anymore.”
He was stunned. “Why not? You have so much
talent.”
“I don’t know....”
“Sure you do. You stopped for a reason.”
He was right. She’d had a reason.
“It’s a long story.”
“I’ve got all night,” he answered.
“Did you really think I was talented?”
she asked quietly.
“C’mon,” he said, reaching for her hand,
“I want to show you something.”
She got up and followed him through the door
to the living room. He stopped in front of
the fireplace and pointed to the painting
that hung above the mantel. She gasped, surprised
she hadn’t noticed it earlier, more surprised
it was here at all.
“You kept it?”
“Of course I kept it. It’s wonderful.”
She gave him a skeptical look, and he explained.
“It makes me feel alive when I look at it.
Sometimes I have to get up and touch it. It’s
just so real— the shapes, the shadows, the
colors. I even dream about it sometimes. It’s
incredible, Allie—I can stare at it for
hours.”
“You’re serious,” she said, shocked.
“As serious as I’ve ever been.”
She didn’t say anything.
“You mean to tell me no one has ever told
you that before?”
“My professor did,” she finally said,
“but I guess I didn’t believe him.”
He knew there was more. Allie looked away
before continuing.
“I’ve been drawing and painting since
I was a child. I guess that once I got a little
older, I began to think I was good at it.
I enjoyed it, too. I remember working on this
painting that summer, adding to it every day,
changing it as our relationship changed. I
don’t even remember how it started or what
I wanted it to be, but somehow it evolved
into this.
“I remember being unable to stop painting
after I went home that summer. I think it
was my way of avoiding the pain I was going
through. Anyway, I ended up majoring in art
in college because it was something I had
to do; I remember spending hours in the studio
all by myself and enjoying every minute. I
loved the freedom I felt when I created, the
way it made me feel inside to make something
beautiful. Just before I graduated, my professor,
who happened to also be the critic for the
paper, told me I had a lot of talent. He told
me I should try my luck as an artist. But
I didn’t listen to him.”
She stopped there, gathering her thoughts.
“My parents didn’t think it was proper
for someone like me to paint for a living.
I just stopped after a while. I haven’t
touched a brush in years.”
She stared at the painting.
“Do you think you’ll ever paint again?”
“I’m not sure if I can anymore. It’s
been a long time.”
“You can still do it, Allie. I know you
can. You have a talent that comes from inside
you, from your heart, not from your fingers.
What you have can’t ever go away. It’s
what other people only dream about. You’re
an artist, Allie.”
The words were spoken with such sincerity
that she knew he wasn’t saying it just to
be nice. He truly believed in her ability,
and for some reason that meant more to her
than she expected. But something else happened
then, something even more powerful.
Why it happened, she never knew, but this
was when the chasm began to close for Allie,
the chasm she had erected in her life to separate
the pain from the pleasure. And she suspected
then, maybe not consciously, that there was
more to this than even she cared to admit.
But at that moment she still wasn’t completely
aware of it, and she turned to face him. She
reached over and touched his hand, hesitantly,
gently, amazed that after all these years
he’d somehow known exactly what she’d
needed to hear. When their eyes locked, she
once again realized how special he was.
And for just a fleeting moment, a tiny wisp
of time that hung in the air like fireflies
in summer skies, she wondered if she was in
love with him again.
The timer went off in the kitchen, a small
ding, and Noah turned away, breaking the moment,
strangely affected by what had just happened
between them. Her eyes had spoken to him and
whispered something he longed to hear, yet
he couldn’t stop the voice inside his head,
her voice, that had told him of her love for
another man. He silently cursed the timer
as he walked to the kitchen and removed the
bread from the oven. He almost burned his
fingers, dropped the loaf on the counter,
and saw that the frying pan was ready. He
added the vegetables and heard them begin
to crackle. Then, muttering to himself, he
got some butter out of the icebox, spread
some on the bread, and melted a bit more for
the crabs.
Allie had followed him into the kitchen and
cleared her throat.
“Can I get the table ready?”
Noah used the bread knife as a pointer. “Sure,
plates are over there. Utensils and napkins
there. Make sure you get plenty—crabs can
be messy, so we’ll need ’em.” He couldn’t
look at her as he spoke. He didn’t want
to realize he’d been mistaken about what
had just happened between them. He didn’t
want it to be a mistake.
Allie, too, was wondering about the moment
and feeling warm as she thought of it. The
words he’d spoken replayed in her head as
she found everything she needed for the table:
plates, place settings, salt and pepper. Noah
handed her the bread as she was finishing
the table, and their fingers touched briefly.
He turned his attention back to the frying
pan and turned the vegetables. He lifted the
lid of the steamer, saw the crabs still had
a minute, and let them cook some more. He
was more composed now and returned to small
talk, easy conversation.
“Have you ever had crab before?”
“A couple of times. But only in salads.”
He laughed. “Then you’re in for an adventure.
Hold on a second.” He disappeared upstairs
for a moment, then returned with a navy blue
button-down shirt. He held it open for her.
“Here, put this on. I don’t want you to
stain your dress.”
Allie put it on and smelled the fragrance
that lingered in the shirt—his smell, distinctive,
natural.
“Don’t worry,” he said, seeing her expression,
“it’s clean.”
She laughed. “I know. It just reminds me
of our first real date. You gave me your jacket
that night, remember?”
He nodded. “Yeah, I remember. Fin and Sarah
were with us. Fin kept elbowing me the whole
way back to your parents’ house, trying
to get me to hold your hand.”
“You didn’t, though.”
“No,” he answered, shaking his head.
“Why not?”
“Shy, maybe, or afraid. I don’t know.
It just didn’t seem like the right thing
to do at the time.”
“Come to think of it, you were kind of shy,
weren’t you.”
“I prefer the words ‘quiet confidence,’”
he answered with a wink, and she smiled.
The vegetables and crabs were ready about
the same time. “Be careful, they’re hot,”
he said as he handed them to her, and they
sat across from each other at the small wooden
table. Then, realizing the tea was still on
the counter, Allie stood and brought it over.
After putting some vegetables and bread on
their plates, Noah added a crab, and Allie
sat for a moment, staring at it.
“It looks like a bug.”
“A good bug, though,” he said. “Here,
let me show you how it’s done.”
He demonstrated quickly, making it look easy,
removing the meat and putting it on her plate.
Allie crushed the legs too hard the first
time and the time after that, and had to use
her fingers to get the shells away from the
meat. She felt clumsy at first, worrying that
he saw every mistake, but then she realized
her own insecurity. He didn’t care about
things like that. He never had.
“So, whatever happened to Fin?” she asked.
It took a second for him to answer.
“Fin died in the war. His destroyer was
torpedoed in forty-three.”
“I’m sorry,” she said. “I know he
was a good friend of yours.”
His voice changed, a little deeper now.
“He was. I think of him a lot these days.
I especially remember the last time I saw
him. I’d come home to say good-bye before
I enlisted, and we ran into each other again.
He was a banker here, like his daddy was,
and he and I spent a lot of time together
over the next week. Sometimes I think I talked
him into joining. I don’t think he would
have, except that I was going to.”
“That’s not fair,” she said, sorry she’d
brought up the subject.
“You’re right. I just miss him, is all.”
“I liked him, too. He made me laugh.”
“He was always good at that.”
She looked at him slyly. “He had a crush
on me, you know.”
“I know. He told me about it.”
“He did? What did he say?”
Noah shrugged. “The usual for him. That
he had to fight you off with a stick. That
you chased him constantly, that sort of thing.”
She laughed quietly. “Did you believe him?”
“Of course,” he answered, “why wouldn’t
I?” “You men always stick together,”
she said as she reached across the table,
poking his arm with her finger. She went on.
“So, tell me everything you’ve been up
to since I saw you last.”
They started to talk then, making up for lost
time. Noah talked about leaving New Bern,
about working in the shipyard and at the scrap
yard in New Jersey. He spoke fondly of Morris
Goldman and touched on the war a little, avoiding
most of the details, and told her about his
father and how much he missed him. Allie talked
about going to college, painting, and her
hours spent volunteering at the hospital.
She talked about her family and friends and
the charities she was involved with. Neither
of them brought up anybody they had dated
since they’d last seen each other. Even
Lon was ignored, and though both of them noticed
the omission, neither mentioned it.
Afterward Allie tried to remember the last
time she and Lon had talked this way. Although
he listened well and they seldom argued, he
was not the type of man to talk like this.
Like her father, he wasn’t comfortable sharing
his thoughts and feelings. She’d tried to
explain that she needed to be closer to him,
but it had never seemed to make a difference.
But sitting here now, she realized what she’d
been missing.
The sky grew darker and the moon rose higher
as the evening wore on. And without either
of them being conscious of it, they began
to regain the intimacy, the bond of familiarity,
they had once shared.
They finished dinner, both pleased with the
meal, neither talking much now. Noah looked
at his watch and saw that it was getting late.
The stars were out in full, the crickets a
little quieter. He had enjoyed talking to
Allie and wondered if he’d talked too much,
wondered what she’d thought about his life,
hoping it would somehow make a difference,
if it could.
Noah got up and refilled the teapot. They
both brought the dishes to the sink and cleaned
up the table, and he poured two more cups
of hot water, adding teabags to both.
“How about the porch again?” he asked,
handing her the cup, and she agreed, leading
the way. He grabbed a quilt for her in case
she got cold, and soon they had taken their
places again, the quilt over her legs, rockers
moving. Noah watched her from the corner of
his eye. God, she’s beautiful, he thought.
And inside, he ached.
For something had happened during dinner.
Quite simply, he had fallen in love again.
He knew that now as they sat next to one another.
Fallen in love with a new Allie, not just
her memory.
But then, he had never really stopped, and
this, he realized, was his destiny.
“It’s been quite a night,” he said,
his voice softer now.
“Yes, it has,” she said, “a wonderful
night.” Noah turned to the stars, their
twinkling lights reminding him that she would
be leaving soon, and he felt almost empty
inside. This was a night he wanted never to
end. How should he tell her? What could he
say that would make her stay?
He didn’t know. And thus the decision was
made to say nothing. And he realized then
that he had failed.
The rockers moved in quiet rhythm. Bats again,
over the river. Moths kissing the porch light.
Somewhere, he knew, there were people making
love.
“Talk to me,” she finally said, her voice
sensual. Or was his mind playing tricks?
“What should I say?”
“Talk like you did to me under the oak tree.”
And he did, reciting distant passages, toasting
the night. Whitman and Thomas, because he
loved the images. Tennyson and Browning, because
their themes felt so familiar.
She rested her head against the back of the
rocker, closing her eyes, growing just a bit
warmer by the time he’d finished. It wasn’t
just the poems or his voice that did it. It
was all of it, the whole greater than the
sum of the parts. She didn’t try to break
it down, didn’t want to, because it wasn’t
meant to be listened to that way. Poetry,
she thought, wasn’t written to be analyzed;
it was meant to inspire without reason, to
touch without understanding.
Because of him, she’d gone to a few poetry
readings offered by the English department
while in college. She’d sat and listened
to different people, different poems, but
had stopped soon after, discouraged that no
one inspired her or seemed as inspired as
true lovers of poetry should be.
They rocked for a while, drinking tea, sitting
quietly, drifting in their thoughts. The compulsion
that had driven her here was gone now—she
was glad for this—but she worried about
the feelings that had taken its place, the
stirrings that had begun to sift and swirl
in her pores like gold dust in river pans.
She’d tried to deny them, hide from them,
but now she realized that she didn’t want
them to stop. It had been years since she’d
felt this way.
Lon could not evoke these feelings in her.
He never had and probably never would. Maybe
that was why she had never been to bed with
him. He had tried before, many times, using
everything from flowers to guilt, and she
had always used the excuse that she wanted
to wait until marriage. He took it well, usually,
and she sometimes wondered how hurt he would
be if he ever found out about Noah.
But there was something else that made her
want to wait, and it had to do with Lon himself.
He was driven in his work, and it always commanded
most of his attention. Work came first, and
for him there was no time for poems and wasted
evenings and rocking on porches. She knew
this was why he was successful, and part of
her respected him for that. But she also sensed
it wasn’t enough. She wanted something else,
something different, something more. Passion
and romance, perhaps, or maybe quiet conversations
in candlelit rooms, or perhaps something as
simple as not being second.
Noah, too, was sifting through his thoughts.
To him, the evening would be remembered as
one of the most special times he had ever
had. As he rocked, he remembered it all in
detail, then remembered it again. Everything
she had done seemed somehow electric to him,
charged.
Now, sitting beside her, he wondered if she’d
ever dreamed the same things he had in the
years they’d been apart. Had she ever dreamed
of them holding each other again and kissing
in soft moonlight? Or did she go further and
dream of their naked bodies, which had been
kept separate for far too long. . . .
He looked to the stars and remembered the
thousands of empty nights he had spent since
they’d last seen each other. Seeing her
again brought all those feelings to the surface,
and he found it impossible to press them back
down. He knew then he wanted to make love
to her again and to have her love in return.
It was what he needed most in the world.
But he also realized it could never be. Now
that she was engaged.
Allie knew by his silence that he was thinking
about her and found that she reveled in it.
She didn’t know what his thoughts were exactly,
didn’t care really, just knew they were
about her and that was enough.
She thought about their conversation at dinner
and wondered about loneliness. For some reason
she couldn’t picture him reading poetry
to someone else or even sharing his dreams
with another woman. He didn’t seem the type.
Either that, or she didn’t want to believe
it.
She put down the tea, then ran her hands through
her hair, closing her eyes as she did so.
“Are you tired?” he asked, finally breaking
free from his thoughts.
“A little. I should really be going in a
couple of minutes.”
“I know,” he said, nodding, his tone neutral.
She didn’t get up right away. Instead she
picked up the cup and drank the last swallow
of tea, feeling it warm her throat. She took
the evening in. Moon higher now, wind in the
trees, temperature dropping.
She looked at Noah next. The scar on his face
was visible from the side. She wondered if
it had happened during the war, then wondered
if he’d ever been wounded at all. He hadn’t
mentioned it and she hadn’t asked, mostly
because she didn’t want to imagine him being
hurt.
“I should go,” she finally said, handing
the quilt back to him.
Noah nodded, then stood without a word. He
carried the quilt, and the two of them walked
to her car while fallen leaves crunched beneath
their feet. She started to take off the shirt
he’d loaned her as he opened the door, but
he stopped her.
“Keep it,” he said. “I want you to have
it.”
She didn’t ask why, because she wanted to
keep it, too. She readjusted it and crossed
her arms afterward to ward off the chill.
For some reason, as she stood there she was
reminded of standing on her front porch after
a high school dance, waiting for a kiss.
“I had a great time tonight,” he said.
“Thank you for finding me.”
“I did, too,” she answered.
He summoned his courage. “Will I see you
tomorrow?”
A simple question. She knew what the answer
should be, especially if she wanted to keep
her life simple. “I don’t think we should,”
was all she had to say, and it would end right
here and now. But for a second she didn’t
say anything.
The demon of choice confronted her then, teased
her, challenged her. Why couldn’t she say
it? She didn’t know. But as she looked in
his eyes to find the answer she needed, she
saw the man she’d once fallen in love with,
and suddenly it all came clear.
“I’d like that.”
Noah was surprised. He hadn’t expected her
to answer this way. He wanted to touch her
then, to take her in his arms, but he didn’t.
“Can you be here about noon?”
“Sure. What do you want to do?”
“You’ll see,” he answered. “I know
just the place to go.”
“Have I ever been there before?”
“No, but it’s a special place.”
“Where is it?”
“It’s a surprise.”
“Will I like it?”
“You’ll love it,” he said.
She turned away before he could attempt a
kiss. She didn’t know if he would try but
knew for some reason that if he did, she would
have a hard time stopping him. She couldn’t
handle that right now, with everything going
through her head. She slid behind the wheel,
breathing a sigh of relief. He shut the door
for her, and she started the engine. As the
car idled, she rolled down the window just
a bit.
“See you tomorrow,” she said, her eyes
reflecting the moonlight.
Noah waved as she backed the car out. She
turned it around, then drove up the lane,
heading toward town. He watched the car until
the lights vanished behind far-off oak trees
and the engine noise was gone. Clem wandered
up to him and he squatted down to pet her,
paying special attention to her neck, scratching
the spot she couldn’t reach anymore. After
he looked up the road one last time, they
returned to the back porch side by side.
He sat in the rocker again, this time alone,
trying once again to fathom the evening that
had just passed. Thinking about it. Replaying
it. Seeing it again. Hearing it again. Running
it by in slow motion. He didn’t feel like
playing his guitar now, didn’t feel like
reading. Didn’t know what he felt.
“She’s engaged,” he finally whispered,
and then was silent for hours, his rocker
making the only noise. The night was quiet
now, with little activity except for Clem,
who visited him occasionally, checking on
him as if to ask “Are you all right?”
And sometime after midnight on that clear
October evening, it all rushed inward and
Noah was overcome with longing. And if anyone
had seen him, they would have seen what looked
like an old man, someone who’d aged a lifetime
in just a couple of hours. Someone bent over
in his rocker with his face in his hands and
tears in his eyes.
He didn’t know how to stop them.
Phone Calls
Lon hung up the phone.
He had called at seven, then at eight-thirty,
and now he checked his watch again. Nine forty-five.
Where was she?
He knew she was where she had said she would
be because he had spoken to the manager earlier.
Yes, she had checked in and he had last seen
her around six. Going to dinner, he thought.
No, he hadn’t seen her since.
Lon shook his head and leaned back in his
chair. He was the last one in the office,
as usual, and everything was quiet. But that
was normal with an ongoing trial, even if
the trial was going well. Law was his passion,
and the late hours alone gave him the opportunity
to catch up on his work without interruption.
He knew he would win the case because he mastered
the law and charmed the jury. He always did,
and losses were infrequent now. Part of it
came from being able to select the cases he
had the expertise to win. He had reached that
level in his practice. Only a select few in
the city had that kind of stature, and his
earnings reflected that.
But the more important part of his success
came from hard work. He had always paid attention
to details, especially when he’d begun his
practice. Little things, obscure things, and
it had become a habit now. Whether it was
a matter of law or presentation, he was diligent
in his study, and it had won him a few cases
early in his career when he should have lost.
And now, a little detail bothered him.
Not about the case. No, that was fine. It
was something else.
Something about Allie.
But damn, he couldn’t put his finger on
it. He was fine when she’d left this morning.
At least he thought he was. But sometime after
her call, maybe an hour or so, something clicked
in his mind. The little detail.
Detail.
Something insignificant? Something important?
Think . . . think . . . Damn, what was it?
His mind clicked.
Something . . . something . . . something
said? Something had been said? Yes, that was
it. He knew it. But what was it? Had Allie
said anything on the phone? That had been
when it started, and he ran through the conversation
again. No, nothing out of the ordinary.
But that was it, he was sure now.
What had she said?
Her trip was good, she had checked in, had
done some shopping. Left her number. That’s
about all.
He thought about her then. He loved her, he
was sure of that. Not only was she beautiful
and charming, but she’d become his source
of stability and best friend as well. After
a hard day at work, she was the first person
he would call. She would listen to him, laugh
at the right moments, and had a sixth sense
about what he needed to hear.
But more than that, he admired the way she’d
always spoken her mind. He remembered that
after they’d gone out a few times, he’d
said to her what he said to all women he dated—that
he wasn’t ready for a steady relationship.
Unlike the others, though, Allie had simply
nodded and said, “Fine.” But on her way
out the door, she’d turned and said: “But
your problem isn’t me, or your job, or your
freedom, or whatever else you think it is.
Your problem is that you’re alone. Your
father made the Hammond name famous, and you’ve
probably been compared to him all your life.
You’ve never been your own person. A life
like that makes you empty inside, and you’re
looking for someone who will magically fill
that void. But no one can do that but you.”
The words had stayed with him that night and
rung true the following morning. He’d called
again, asked for a second chance, and after
some persistence, she’d reluctantly agreed.
In the four years they’d dated, she’d
become everything he ever wanted, and he knew
he should spend more time with her. But practicing
law made limiting his hours impossible. She’d
always understood, but still, he cursed himself
for not making the time. Once he was married,
he’d shorten his hours, he promised himself.
He’d have his secretary check his schedule
to make sure he wasn’t overextending himself.
. . .
Check? ...
And his mind clicked another notch.
Check . . . checking . . . checking in?
He looked to the ceiling. Checking in?
Yes, that was it. He closed his eyes and thought
for a second. No. Nothing. What, then?
C’mon, don’t fail now. Think, damn it,
think. New Bern.
The thought popped into his head just then.
Yes, New Bern. That was it. The little detail,
or part of it. What else, though?
New Bern, he thought again, and knew the name.
Knew the town a little, mainly from a few
trials he had been in. Stopped there a few
times on the way to the coast. Nothing special.
He and Allie had never been there together.
But Allie had been there before. . . .
And the rack tightened its grip, another part
coming together.
Another part. . . but there was more. . . .
Allie, New Bern . . . and . . . and . . . something
at a party. A comment in passing. From Allie’s
mother. He’d hardly noticed it. But what
had she said?
And Lon paled then, remembering. Remembering
what had been said so long ago. Remembering
what Allie’s mother had said.
It was something about Allie being in love
one time with a young man from New Bern. Called
it puppy love. So what, he had thought when
he’d heard it, and had turned to smile at
Allie.
But she hadn’t smiled. She was angry. And
then Lon guessed that she had loved that person
far more deeply than her mother had suggested.
Maybe even more deeply than she loved him.
And now she was there. Interesting.
Lon brought his palms together, as though
he were praying, resting them against his
lips. Coincidence? Could be nothing. Could
be exactly what she said. Could be stress
and antique shopping. Possible. Even probable.
Yet . . . yet . . . what if?
Lon considered the other possibility, and
for the first time in a long time, he became
frightened.
What if? What if she’s with him?
He cursed the trial, wishing it were over.
Wishing he had gone with her. Wondering if
she’d told him the truth, hoping that she
had.
And he made up his mind then not to lose her.
He would do anything it took to keep her.
She was everything he’d always needed, and
he’d never find another quite like her.
So, with trembling hands, he dialed the phone
for the fourth and last time that evening.
And again there was no answer.
Kayaks and Forgotten Dreams
Allie woke early the next morning, forced
by the incessant chirping of starlings, and
rubbed her eyes, feeling the stiffness in
her body. She hadn’t slept well, waking
after every dream, and she remembered seeing
the hands of the clock in different positions
during the night, as if verifying the passage
of time.
She’d slept in the soft shirt he’d given
her, and she smelled him once again while
thinking about the evening they’d spent
together. The easy laughter and conversation
came back to her, and she especially remembered
the way he’d talked about her painting.
It was so unexpected, yet uplifting, and as
the words began to replay in her mind, she
realized how sorry she would have been had
she decided not to see him again.
She looked out the window and watched the
chattering birds search for food in early
light. Noah, she knew, had always been a morning
person who greeted dawn in his own way. She
knew he liked to kayak or canoe, and she remembered
the one morning she’d spent with him in
his canoe, watching the sun come up. She’d
had to sneak out her window to do it because
her parents wouldn’t allow it, but she hadn’t
been caught and she remembered how Noah had
slipped his arm around her and pulled her
close as dawn began to unfold. “Look there,”
he’d whispered, and she’d watched her
first sunrise with her head on his shoulder,
wondering if anything could be better than
what was happening at that moment.
And as she got out of bed to take her bath,
feeling the cold floor beneath her feet, she
wondered if he’d been on the water this
morning watching another day begin, thinking
somehow he probably had.
She was right.
Noah was up before the sun and dressed quickly,
same jeans as last night, undershirt, clean
flannel shirt, blue jacket, and boots. He
brushed his teeth before going downstairs,
drank a quick glass of milk, and grabbed two
biscuits on the way out the door. After Clem
greeted him with a couple of sloppy licks,
he walked to the dock where his kayak was
stored. He liked to let the river work its
magic, loosening up his muscles, warming his
body, clearing his mind.
The old kayak, well used and river stained,
hung on two rusty hooks attached to his dock
just above the waterline to keep off the barnacles.
He lifted it free from the hooks and set it
at his feet, inspected it quickly, then took
it to the bank. In a couple of seasoned moves
long since mastered by habit, he had it in
the water working its way upstream with himself
as the pilot and engine.
The air was cool on his skin, almost crisp,
and the sky was a haze of different colors:
black directly above him like a mountain peak,
then blues of infinite range, becoming lighter
until it met the horizon, where gray took
its place. He took a few deep breaths, smelling
pine trees and brackish water, and began to
reflect. This had been part of what he’d
missed most when he had lived up north. Because
of the long hours at work, there had been
little time to spend on the water. Camping,
hiking, paddling on rivers, dating, working
. . . something had had to go. For the most
part he’d been able to explore New Jersey’s
countryside on foot whenever he’d had extra
time, but in fourteen years he hadn’t canoed
or kayaked once. It had been one of the first
things he’d done when he returned.
There’s something special, almost mystical,
about spending dawn on the water, he thought
to himself, and he did it almost every day
now. Sunny and clear or cold and bitter, it
never mattered as he paddled in rhythm to
music in his head, working above water the
color of iron. He saw a family of turtles
resting on a partially submerged log and watched
as a heron broke for flight, skimming just
above the water before vanishing into the
silver twilight that preceded sunrise.
He paddled out to the middle of the creek,
where he watched the orange glow begin to
stretch across the water. He stopped paddling
hard, giving just enough effort to keep him
in place, staring until light began to break
through the trees. He always liked to pause
at daybreak—there was a moment when the
view was spectacular, as if the world were
being born again. Afterward he began to paddle
hard, working off the tension, preparing for
the day.
While he did that, questions danced in his
mind like water drops in a frying pan. He
wondered about Lon and what type of man he
was, wondered about their relationship. Most
of all, though, he wondered about Allie and
why she had come.
By the time he reached home, he felt renewed.
Checking his watch, he was surprised to find
that it had taken two hours. Time always played
tricks out there, though, and he’d stopped
questioning it months ago.
He hung the kayak to dry, stretched for a
couple of minutes, and went to the shed where
he stored his canoe. He carried it to the
bank, leaving it a few feet from the water,
and as he turned toward the house, he noted
that his legs were still a little stiff.
The morning haze hadn’t burned off yet,
and he knew the stiffness in his legs usually
predicted rain. He looked to the western sky
and saw storm clouds, thick and heavy, far
off but definitely present. The winds weren’t
blowing hard, but they were bringing the clouds
closer. From the looks of them, he didn’t
want to be outside when they got here. Damn.
How much time did he have? A few hours, maybe
more. Maybe less.
He showered, put on new jeans, a red shirt,
and black cowboy boots, brushed his hair,
and went downstairs to the kitchen. He did
the dishes from the night before, picked up
a little around the house, made himself some
coffee, and went to the porch. The sky was
darker now, and he checked the barometer.
Steady, but it would start dropping soon.
The western sky promised that.
He’d learned long ago to never underestimate
the weather, and he wondered if it was a good
idea to go out. The rain he could deal with;
lightning was a different story. Especially
if he was on the water. A canoe was no place
to be when electricity sparked in humid air.
He finished his coffee, putting off the decision
until later. He went to the toolshed and found
his ax. After checking the blade by pressing
his thumb to it, he sharpened it with a whetstone
until it was ready. “A dull ax is more dangerous
than a sharp one,” his daddy used to say.
He spent the next twenty minutes splitting
and stacking logs. He did it easily, his strokes
efficient, and didn’t break a sweat. He
set a few logs off to the side for later and
brought them inside when he was finished,
putting them by the fireplace.
He looked at Allie’s painting again and
reached out to touch it, bringing back the
feelings of disbelief at seeing her again.
God, what was it about her that made him feel
this way? Even after all these years? What
sort of power did she have over him?
He finally turned away, shaking his head,
and went back to the porch. He checked the
barometer again. It hadn’t changed. Then
he looked at his watch.
Allie should be here soon.
Allie had finished her bath and was already
dressed. Earlier she’d opened the window
to check the temperature. It wasn’t cold
outside, and she’d decided on a cream-colored
spring dress with long sleeves and a high
neck. It was soft and comfortable, maybe a
little snug, but it looked good, and she had
selected some white sandals that matched.
She spent the morning walking around downtown.
The Depression had taken its toll here, but
she could see the signs of prosperity beginning
to work their way back. The Masonic theater,
the oldest active theater in the country,
looked a little more run-down but was still
operating with a couple of recent movies.
Fort Totten Park looked exactly the same as
it had fourteen years ago, and she assumed
the kids who played on the swings after school
looked the same as well. She smiled at the
memory then, thinking back to when things
were simpler. Or at least had seemed to be.
Now, it seemed, nothing was simple. It seemed
so improbable, everything falling into place
as it had, and she wondered what she would
have been doing now, had she never seen the
article in the paper. It wasn’t very difficult
to imagine, because her routines seldom changed.
It was Wednesday, which meant bridge at the
country club, then on to the Junior Women’s
League, where they would probably be arranging
another fund-raiser for the private school
or hospital. After that, a visit with her
mother, then home to get ready for dinner
with Lon, because he made it a point to leave
work by seven. It was the one night a week
she saw him regularly.
She suppressed a feeling of sadness about
that, hoping that one day he would change.
He had often promised to and usually followed
through for a few weeks before drifting back
to the same schedule. “I can’t tonight,
honey,” he would always explain. “I’m
sorry, but I can’t. Let me make it up to
you later.”
She didn’t like to argue with him about
it, mostly because she knew he was telling
the truth. Trial work was demanding, both
beforehand and during, yet she couldn’t
help wondering sometimes why he had spent
so much time courting her if he didn’t want
to spend the time with her now.
She passed an art gallery, almost walked by
it in her preoccupation, then turned and went
back. She paused at the door for a second,
surprised at how long it had been since she’d
been in one. At least three years, maybe longer.
Why had she avoided it?
She went inside—it had opened with the rest
of the shops on Front Street—and browsed
among the paintings. Many of the artists were
local, and there was a strong sea flavor to
their works. Lots of ocean scenes, sandy beaches,
pelicans, old sailing ships, tug-boats, piers,
and seagulls. But most of all, waves. Waves
of every shape, size, and color imaginable,
and after a while they all looked alike. The
artists were either uninspired or lazy, she
thought.
On one wall though, there were a few paintings
that more suited her tastes. All were by an
artist she’d never heard of, Elayn, and
most appeared to have been inspired by the
architecture of the Greek islands. In the
painting she liked the best, she noted the
artist had purposely exaggerated the scene
with smaller-than-life figures, wide lines,
and heavy sweeps of color, as if not completely
focused. Yet the colors were vivid and swirling,
drawing the eye in, almost directing what
it should see next. It was dynamic, dramatic.
The more she thought about it, the more she
liked it, and she considered buying it before
she realized that she liked it because it
reminded her of her own work. She examined
it more closely and thought to herself that
maybe Noah was right. Maybe she should start
painting again.
At nine-thirty Allie left the gallery and
went to Hoffman-Lane, a department store downtown.
It took a few minutes to find what she was
looking for, but it was there, in the school
supply section. Paper, drawing chalk, and
pencils, not high quality but good enough.
It wasn’t painting, but it was a start,
and she was excited by the time she got back
to her room. She sat at the desk and started
working: nothing specific, just getting the
feel of it again, letting shapes and colors
flow from the memory of her youth. After a
few minutes of abstraction, she did a rough
sketch of the street scene as seen from her
room, amazed at how easily it came. It was
almost as if she’d never stopped.
She examined it when she was finished, pleased
with the effort. She wondered what to try
next and finally decided. Since she didn’t
have a model, she visualized it in her head
before starting. And though it was harder
than the street scene, it came naturally and
began to take form.
Minutes passed quickly. She worked steadily
but checked the time frequently so she wouldn’t
be late, and she finished it a little before
noon. It had taken almost two hours, but the
end result surprised her. It looked as though
it had taken a great deal longer. After rolling
it up, she put it in a bag and collected the
rest of her things. On her way out the door,
she looked at herself in the mirror, feeling
oddly relaxed, not exactly sure why.
Down the stairs again and out the door. As
she left she heard a voice behind her.
“Miss?”
She turned, knowing it was directed at her.
The manager. Same man as yesterday, a curious
look on his face.
“Yes?”
“You had some calls last night.”
She was shocked. “I did?”
“Yes. All from a Mr. Hammond.”
Oh, God.
“Lon called?”
“Yes, ma’am, four times. I talked to him
when he called the second time. He was rather
concerned about you. He said he was your fiancé.”
She smiled weakly, trying to hide what she
was thinking. Four times? Four? What could
that mean? What if something had happened
back home?
“Did he say anything? Is it an emergency?”
He shook his head quickly. “He really didn’t
say, miss, but he didn’t mention anything.
Actually, he sounded more concerned about
you, though.”
Good, she thought. That’s good. And then,
just as suddenly, a pang in her chest. Why
the urgency? Why so many calls? Had she said
anything yesterday? Why would he be so persistent?
It was completely unlike him.
Is there any way he could have found out?
No . . . that was impossible. Unless someone
saw her here yesterday and called. . . . But
they would have had to follow her out to Noah’s.
No one would have done that.
She had to call him now; no way to get around
it. But she didn’t want to, strangely. This
was her time, and she wanted to spend it doing
what she wanted. She hadn’t planned on speaking
to him until later, and for some reason she
felt almost as if talking to him now would
spoil the day. Besides, what was she going
to say? How could she explain being out so
late? A late dinner and then a walk? Maybe.
Or a movie? Or . . .
“Miss?”
Almost noon, she thought. Where would he be?
His office, probably.... No. In court, she
suddenly realized, and immediately felt as
if she’d been released from shackles. There
was no way she could talk to him, even if
she wanted to. She was surprised by her feelings.
She shouldn’t feel this way, she knew, and
yet it didn’t bother her. She looked at
her watch, acting now.
“Is it really almost twelve?”
The manager nodded after looking at the clock.
“Yes, a quarter till, actually.”
“Unfortunately,” she started, “he’s
in court right now and I can’t reach him.
If he does call again, could you tell him
I’m shopping and that I’ll try to call
him later?”
“Of course,” he answered. She could see
the question in his eyes, though: But where
were you last night? He had known exactly
when she’d come in. Too late for a single
woman in this small town, she was sure.
“Thank you,” she said, smiling. “I’d
appreciate it.”
Two minutes later she was in her car, driving
to Noah’s, anticipating the day, largely
unconcerned about the phone calls. Yesterday
she would have been, and she wondered what
that meant.
As she was driving over the drawbridge less
than four minutes after she’d left the inn,
Lon called from the courthouse.
Moving Water
Noah was sitting in his rocker, drinking sweet
tea, listening for the car, when he finally
heard it turn up the drive. He went around
front and watched the car pull up and park
beneath the oak tree again. Same spot as yesterday.
Clem barked a greeting at her car door, tail
wagging, and he saw Allie wave from inside
the car.
She stepped out, patted Clem on the head while
she cooed at her, then turned, smiling at
Noah as he walked toward her. She looked more
relaxed than yesterday, more confident, and
again he felt a slight shock at seeing her.
It was different from yesterday, though. Newer
feelings now, not simply memories anymore.
If anything, his attraction for her had grown
stronger overnight, more intense, and it made
him feel a little nervous in her presence.
Allie met him halfway, carrying a small bag
in one hand. She surprised him by kissing
him gently on the cheek, her free hand lingering
at his waist after she pulled back.
“Hi,” she said, radiance in her eyes,
“where’s the surprise?”
He relaxed a little, thanking God for that.
“Not even a ‘Good afternoon’ or ‘How
was your night?’”
She smiled. Patience had never been one of
her strongest attributes.
“Fine. Good afternoon. How was your night?
And where’s the surprise?”
He chuckled lightly, then paused. “Allie,
I’ve got some bad news.”
“What?”
“I was going to take you someplace, but
with those clouds coming in, I’m not sure
we should go.”
“Why?”
“The storm. We’ll be outside and might
get wet. Besides, there might be lightning.”
“It’s not raining yet. How far is it?”
“Up the creek about a mile.”
“And I’ve never been there before?”
“Not when it was like this.”
She thought for a second while she looked
around. When she spoke, her voice was determined.
“Then we’ll go. I don’t care if it rains.”
“Are you sure?”
“Absolutely.”
He looked at the clouds again, noting their
approach. “Then we’d better go now,”
he said. “Can I bring that in for you?”
She nodded, handing her bag to him, and he
jogged to the house and brought it inside,
where he placed it on a chair in the living
room. Then he grabbed some bread and put it
in a bag, bringing it with him as he left
the house.
They walked to the canoe, Allie beside him.
A little closer than yesterday.
“What exactly is this place?”
“You’ll see.”
“You’re not even going to give me a hint?”
“Well,” he said, “do you remember when
we took the canoe out and watched the sun
come up?”
“I thought about it this morning. I remember
it made me cry.”
“What you’re going to see today makes
what you saw then seem ordinary.”
“I guess I should feel special.”
He took a few steps before responding.
“You are special,” he finally said, and
the way he said it made her wonder if he wanted
to add something else. But he didn’t, and
Allie smiled a little before glancing away.
As she did, she felt the wind in her face
and noticed it had picked up since the morning.
They reached the dock a moment later. After
tossing the bag in the canoe, Noah quickly
checked to make sure he hadn’t missed anything,
then slid the canoe to the water.
“Can I do anything?”
“No, just get in.”
After she climbed in, he pushed the canoe
farther into the water, close to the dock.
Then he gracefully stepped off the dock into
the canoe, placing his feet carefully to prevent
the canoe from capsizing. Allie was impressed
by his agility, knowing that what he had done
so quickly and easily was harder than it looked.
Allie sat at the front of the canoe, facing
backward. He had said something about missing
the view when he started to paddle, but she’d
shaken her head, saying she was fine the way
she was.
And it was true.
She could see everything she really wanted
to see if she turned her head, but most of
all she wanted to watch Noah. It was him she’d
come to see, not the creek. His shirt was
unbuttoned at the top, and she could see his
chest muscles flex with every stroke. His
sleeves were rolled up, too, and she could
see the muscles in his arms bulging slightly.
His muscles were well developed there from
paddling every morning.
Artistic, she thought. There’s something
almost artistic about him when he does this.
Something natural, as if being on the water
were beyond his control, part of a gene passed
on to him from some obscure hereditary pool.
When she watched him, she was reminded of
how the early explorers must have looked when
they’d first discovered this area.
She couldn’t think of anyone else who remotely
resembled him. He was complicated, almost
contradictory in so many ways, yet simple,
a strangely erotic combination. On the surface
he was a country boy, home from war, and he
probably saw himself in those terms. Yet there
was so much more to him. Perhaps it was the
poetry that made him different, or perhaps
it was the values his father had instilled
in him, growing up. Either way, he seemed
to savor life more fully than others appeared
to, and that was what had first attracted
her to him.
“What are you thinking?”
She felt her insides jump just a bit as Noah’s
voice brought her back to the present. She
realized she hadn’t said much since they’d
started, and she appreciated the silence he
had allowed her. He’d always been considerate
like that.
“Good things,” she answered quietly, and
she saw in his eyes that he knew she was thinking
about him. She liked the fact that he knew
it, and she hoped he had been thinking about
her as well.
She understood then that something was stirring
within her, as it had so many years ago. Watching
him, watching his body move, made her feel
it. And as their eyes lingered for a second,
she felt the heat in her neck and breasts,
and she flushed, turning away before he noticed.
“How much farther?” she asked.
“Another half mile or so. Not any more than
that.”
A pause. Then, she said: “It’s pretty
out here. So clean. So quiet. It’s almost
like going back in time.”
“In a way it is, I think. The creek flows
from the forest. There’s not a single farm
between here and where it starts, and the
water is pure as rain. It’s probably as
pure as it’s ever been.”
She leaned toward him. “Tell me, Noah, what
do you remember most from the summer we spent
together?”
“All of it.”
“Anything in particular?”
“No,” he said.
“You don’t remember?”
He answered after a moment, quietly, seriously.
“No, it’s not that. It’s not what you’re
thinking. I was serious when I said ‘all
of it.’ I can remember every moment we were
together, and in each of them there was something
wonderful. I can’t really pick any one time
that meant more than any other. The entire
summer was perfect, the kind of summer everyone
should have. How could I pick one moment over
another?
“Poets often describe love as an emotion
that we can’t control, one that overwhelms
logic and common sense. That’s what it was
like for me. I didn’t plan on falling in
love with you, and I doubt if you planned
on falling in love with me. But once we met,
it was clear that neither of us could control
what was happening to us. We fell in love,
despite our differences, and once we did,
something rare and beautiful was created.
For me, love like that has happened only once,
and that’s why every minute we spent together
has been seared in my memory. I’ll never
forget a single moment of it.”
Allie stared at him. No one had ever said
anything like that to her before. Ever. She
didn’t know what to say and stayed silent,
her face hot.
“I’m sorry if I made you feel uncomfortable,
Allie. I didn’t mean to. But that summer
has stayed with me and probably always will.
I know it can’t be the same between us,
but that doesn’t change the way I felt about
you then.”
She spoke quietly, feeling warm.
“It didn’t make me uncomfortable, Noah.
...It’s just that I don’t ever hear things
like that. What you said was beautiful. It
takes a poet to talk the way you do, and like
I said, you’re the only poet I’ve ever
met.”
Peaceful silence descended on them. An osprey
cried somewhere in the distance. A mullet
splashed near the bank. The paddle moved rhythmically,
causing baffles that rocked the boat ever
so slightly. The breeze had stopped, and the
clouds grew blacker as the canoe moved toward
some unknown destination.
Allie noticed it all, every sound, every thought.
Her senses had come alive, invigorating her,
and she felt her mind drifting through the
last few weeks. She thought about the anxiety
coming here had caused her. The shock at seeing
the article, the sleepless nights, her short
temper during daylight. Even yesterday she
had been afraid and wanted to run away. The
tension was gone now, every bit of it, replaced
by something else, and she was glad about
that as she rode in silence in the old red
canoe.
She felt strangely satisfied that she’d
come, pleased that Noah had turned into the
type of man she’d thought he would, pleased
that she would live forever with that knowledge.
She had seen too many men in the past few
years destroyed by war, or time, or even money.
It took strength to hold on to inner passion,
and Noah had done that.
This was a worker’s world, not a poet’s,
and people would have a hard time understanding
Noah. America was in full swing now, all the
papers said so, and people were rushing forward,
leaving behind the horrors of war. She understood
the reasons, but they were rushing, like Lon,
toward long hours and profits, neglecting
the things that brought beauty to the world.
Who did she know in Raleigh who took time
off to fix a house? Or read Whitman or Eliot,
finding images in the mind, thoughts of the
spirit? Or hunted dawn from the bow of a canoe?
These weren’t the things that drove society,
but she felt they shouldn’t be treated as
unimportant. They made living worthwhile.
To her it was the same with art, though she
had realized it only upon coming here. Or
rather, remembered it. She had known it once
before, and again she cursed herself for forgetting
something as important as creating beauty.
Painting was what she was meant to do, she
was sure of that now. Her feelings this morning
had confirmed it, and she knew that whatever
happened, she was going to give it another
shot. A fair shot, no matter what anyone said.
Would Lon encourage her painting? She remembered
showing him one of her paintings a couple
of months after they had first started going
out. It was an abstract painting and was meant
to inspire thought. In a way, it resembled
the painting above Noah’s fireplace, the
one Noah understood completely, though it
may have been a touch less passionate. Lon
had stared at it, studied it almost, and then
had asked her what it was supposed to be.
She hadn’t bothered to answer.
She shook her head then, knowing she wasn’t
being completely fair. She loved Lon, and
always had, for other reasons. Though he wasn’t
Noah, Lon was a good man, the kind of man
she’d always known she would marry. With
Lon there would be no surprises, and there
was comfort in knowing what the future would
bring. He would be a kind husband to her,
and she would be a good wife. She would have
a home near friends and family, children,
a respectable place in society. It was the
kind of life she’d always expected to live,
the kind of life she wanted to live. And though
she wouldn’t describe theirs as a passionate
relationship, she had convinced herself long
ago that this wasn’t necessary to be fulfilled
in a relationship, even with a person she
intended to marry. Passion would fade in time,
and things like companionship and compatibility
would take its place. She and Lon had this,
and she had assumed this was all she needed.
But now, as she watched Noah rowing, she questioned
this basic assumption. He exuded sexuality
in everything he did, everything he was, and
she caught herself thinking about him in a
way that an engaged woman shouldn’t. She
tried not to stare and glanced away often,
but the easy way he moved his body made it
hard to keep her eyes from him for long.
“Here we are,” Noah said as he guided
the canoe toward some trees near the bank.
Allie looked around, not seeing anything.
“Where is it?”
“Here,” he said again, pointing the canoe
at an old tree that had fallen over, obscuring
an opening almost completely hidden from view.
He guided the canoe around the tree, and both
of them had to lower their heads to keep from
bumping them.
“Close your eyes,” he whispered, and Allie
did, bringing her hands to her face. She heard
the baffles of the water and felt the movement
of the canoe as he propelled it forward, away
from the pull of the creek.
“Okay,” he finally said after he’d stopped
paddling. “You can open them now.”
Swans and Storms
They sat in the middle of a small lake fed
by the waters of Brices Creek. It wasn’t
large, maybe a hundred yards across, and she
was surprised at how invisible it had been
just moments before.
It was spectacular. Tundra swan and Canada
geese literally surrounded them. Thousands
of them. Birds floating so close together
in some places that she couldn’t see the
water. From a distance, the groups of swans
looked almost like icebergs.
“Oh, Noah,” she finally said softly, “it’s
beautiful.”
They sat in silence for a long while, watching
the birds. Noah pointed out a group of chicks,
recently hatched, following a pack of geese
near the shore, struggling to keep up.
The air was filled with honking and chirping
as Noah moved the canoe through the water.
The birds ignored them for the most part.
The only ones who seemed bothered were those
forced to move when the canoe approached them.
Allie reached out to touch the closest ones
and felt their feathers ruffling under her
fingers.
Noah brought out the bag of bread he’d brought
earlier and handed it to Allie. She scattered
the bread, favoring the little ones, laughing
and smiling as they swam in circles, looking
for food.
They stayed until thunder boomed in the distance—faint
but powerful—and both of them knew it was
time to leave.
Noah led them back to the current of the creek,
paddling stronger than he had earlier. She
was still amazed by what she had seen.
“Noah, what are they doing here?”
“I don’t know. I know the swans from up
north migrate to Lake Matamuskeet every winter,
but I guess they came here this time. I don’t
know why. Maybe the early blizzard had something
to do with it. Maybe they got off track or
something. They’ll find their way back,
though.”
“They won’t stay?”
“I doubt it. They’re driven by instinct,
and this isn’t their place. Some of the
geese may winter here, but the swans will
go back to Matamuskeet.”
Noah paddled hard as dark clouds rolled directly
overhead. Soon rain began to fall, a light
sprinkle at first, then gradually harder.
Lightning ...a pause . . . then thunder again.
A little louder now. Maybe six or seven miles
away. More rain as Noah began to paddle even
harder, his muscles tightening with every
stroke.
Thicker drops now.
Falling . . .
Falling with the wind . . .
Falling hard and thick . . . Noah rowing . . . racing
the sky . . . still getting wet . . . cursing
to himself . . . losing to Mother Nature...
The downpour was steady now, and Allie watched
the rain fall diagonally from the sky, trying
to defy gravity as it rode on westerly winds
that whistled over the trees. The sky darkened
a little more, and big heavy drops fell from
the clouds. Hurricane drops.
Allie enjoyed the rain and leaned her head
back for a moment to let it hit her face.
She knew the front of her dress would soak
through in a couple of minutes, but she didn’t
care. She did wonder, though, if he noticed,
then thought he probably did.
She ran her hands through her hair, feeling
its wetness. It felt wonderful, she felt wonderful,
everything felt wonderful. Even through the
rain, she could hear him breathing hard and
the sound aroused her sexually in a way she
hadn’t felt in years.
A cloud burst directly above them, and the
rain began to come down even harder. Harder
than she’d ever seen it. Allie looked upward
and laughed, giving up any attempt at keeping
dry, making Noah feel better. He hadn’t
known how she was feeling about it. Even though
she’d made the decision to come, he doubted
that she’d expected to be caught in a storm
like this.
They reached the dock a couple of minutes
later, and Noah moved in close enough for
Allie to step out. He helped her up, then
got out himself and dragged the canoe up the
bank far enough not to drift away. Just in
case, he tied it to the dock, knowing another
minute in the rain wouldn’t make any difference.
As he was tying the canoe, he looked up at
Allie and stopped breathing for just a second.
She was incredibly beautiful as she waited,
watching him, completely comfortable in the
rain. She didn’t try to keep dry or hide
herself, and he could see the outline of her
breasts as they pressed through the fabric
of the dress that clung tightly to her body.
It wasn’t a cold rain, but he could see
her nipples erect and protruding, hard like
little rocks. He felt his loins begin to stir
and quickly turned away, embarrassed, muttering
to himself, glad the rain muffled any sound
of it. When he finished and stood, Allie took
his hand in hers, surprising him. Despite
the downpour, they didn’t rush toward the
house, and Noah imagined what it would be
like to spend the night with her.
Allie, too, was wondering about him. She felt
the warmth in his hands and wondered what
it would be like to have them touch her body,
feeling all of her, lingering slowly across
her skin. Just thinking about it made her
take a deep breath, and she felt her nipples
begin to tingle and a new warmth between her
legs.
She realized then that something had changed
since she’d come here. And although she
couldn’t pinpoint the exact time—yesterday
after dinner, or this afternoon in the canoe,
or when they saw the swans, or maybe even
now as they walked holding hands—she knew
that she had fallen in love with Noah Taylor
Calhoun again, and that maybe, just maybe,
she had never stopped.
There was no uneasiness between them as they
reached the door and both of them went inside,
pausing in the foyer, clothes dripping.
“Did you bring a change of clothes?”
She shook her head, still feeling the roll
of emotions within her, wondering if it showed
on her face.
“I think I can find something here for you
so you can get out of those clothes. It might
be a little big, but it’s warm.”
“Anything,” she said.
“I’ll be back in a second.”
Noah slipped off his boots, then ran up the
stairs, descending a minute later. He had
a pair of cotton pants and a long-sleeved
shirt under one arm and some jeans with a
blue shirt in the other.
“Here,” he said, handing her the cotton
pants and shirt. “You can change in the
bedroom upstairs. There’s a bathroom and
towel up there too if you want to shower.”
She thanked him with a smile and went up the
stairs, feeling his eyes on her as she walked.
She entered the bedroom and closed the door,
then set the pants and shirt on his bed and
peeled everything off. Naked, she went to
his closet and found a hanger, put her dress,
bra, and panties on it, and then went to hang
it in the bathroom so it wouldn’t drip on
the hardwood floor. She felt a secret thrill
at being naked in the same room he slept in.
She didn’t want to shower after being in
the rain. She liked the soft feeling on her
skin, and it reminded her of how people used
to live long ago. Naturally. Like Noah. She
slipped on his clothes before looking at herself
in the mirror. The pants were big, but tucking
in the shirt helped, and she rolled up the
bottoms just a little so they wouldn’t drag.
The neck was torn a little and it nearly hung
off one shoulder, but she liked the way it
looked on her anyway. She pulled the sleeves
up almost to the elbows, went to the bureau,
and slipped on some socks, then went to the
bathroom to find a hairbrush.
She brushed her wet hair just enough to get
out the snarls, letting it rest on her shoulders.
Looking in the mirror, she wished she had
brought a clasp or a couple of hairpins.
And a little more mascara. But what could
she do? Her eyes still had a little of what
she’d put on earlier, and she touched up
with a washcloth, doing the best she could.
When she was finished, she checked herself
in the mirror, feeling pretty despite everything,
and went back down the stairs.
Noah was in the living room squatting before
a fire, doing his best to coax it to life.
He didn’t see her come in, and she watched
him as he worked. He had changed his clothes
as well and looked good: his shoulders broad,
wet hair hanging just over his collar, jeans
tight.
He poked the fire, moving the logs, and added
some more kindling. Allie leaned against the
door-jamb, one leg crossed over the other,
and continued to watch him. In a few minutes
the fire had turned to flames, even and steady.
He turned to the side to straighten the remaining
unused logs and caught a glimpse of her out
of the corner of his eye. He turned back to
her quickly.
Even in his clothes she looked beautiful.
After a moment he turned away shyly, going
back to stacking the logs.
“I didn’t hear you come in,” he said,
trying to sound casual.
“I know. You weren’t supposed to.” She
knew what he had been thinking and felt a
tinge of amusement at how young he seemed.
“How long have you been standing there?”
“A couple of minutes.”
Noah brushed his hands on his pants, then
pointed to the kitchen. “Can I get you some
tea? I started the water while you were upstairs.”
Small talk, anything to keep his mind clear.
But damn, the way she looked . . .
She thought for a second, saw the way he was
looking at her, and felt the old instincts
take over.
“Do you have anything stronger, or is it
too early to drink?”
He smiled. “I have some bourbon in the pantry.
Is that okay?”
“That sounds great.”
He started toward the kitchen, and Allie watched
him run his hand through his wet hair as he
disappeared.
Thunder boomed loudly, and another downpour
started. Allie could hear the roaring of the
rain on the roof, could hear the snapping
of logs as the flickering flames lit the room.
She turned to the window and saw the gray
sky flash lighter for just a second. Moments
later, another boom of thunder. Close this
time.
She took a quilt from the sofa and sat on
the rug in front of the fire. Crossing her
legs, she adjusted the quilt until she was
comfortable and watched the dancing flames.
Noah came back, saw what she had done, and
went to sit beside her. He put down two glasses
and poured some bourbon into each of them.
Outside, the sky grew darker.
Thunder again. Loud. The storm in full fury,
winds whipping the rain in circles.
“It’s quite a storm,” Noah said as he
watched the drops flow in vertical streams
on the windows. He and Allie were close now,
though not touching, and Noah watched her
chest rise slightly with every breath, imagining
the feel of her body once again before fighting
it back.
“I like it,” she said, taking a sip. “I’ve
always liked thunderstorms. Even as a young
girl.”
“Why?” Saying anything, keeping his balance.
“I don’t know. They just always seemed
romantic to me.”
She was quiet for a moment, and Noah watched
the fire flicker in her emerald eyes. Then
she said, “Do you remember sitting together
and watching the storm a few nights before
I left?”
“Of course.”
“I used to think about it all the time after
I went home. I always thought about how you
looked that night. It was the way I always
remembered you.”
“Have I changed much?”
She took another sip of bourbon, feeling it
warm her. She touched his hand as she answered.
“Not really. Not in the things that I remember.
You’re older, of course, with more life
behind you, but you’ve still got the same
gleam in your eye. You still read poetry and
float on rivers. And you’ve still got a
gentleness that not even the war could take
away.”
He thought about what she’d said and felt
her hand lingering on his, her thumb tracing
slow circles.
“Allie, you asked me earlier what I remembered
most about the summer. What do you remember?”
It was a while before she answered. Her voice
seemed to come from somewhere else.
“I remember making love. That’s what I
remember most. You were my first, and it was
more wonderful than I ever thought it would
be.”
Noah took a drink of bourbon, remembering,
bringing back the old feelings again, then
suddenly shook his head. This was already
hard enough. She went on.
“I remember being so afraid beforehand that
I was trembling, but at the same time being
so excited. I’m glad you were the first.
I’m glad we were able to share that.”
“Me too.”
“Were you as afraid as I was?”
Noah nodded without speaking, and she smiled
at his honesty.
“I thought so. You were always shy like
that. Especially in the beginning. I remember
you had asked if I had a boyfriend, and when
I said I did, you barely talked to me anymore.”
“I didn’t want to get between the two
of you.” “You did, though, in the end,
despite your professed innocence,” she said,
smiling. “And I’m glad you did.”
“When did you finally tell him about us?”
“After I got home.”
“Was it hard?”
“Not at all. I was in love with you.”
She squeezed his hand, let go, and moved closer.
She put her hand through his arm, cradling
it, and rested her head on his shoulder. He
could smell her, soft like the rain, warm.
She spoke quietly:
“Do you remember walking home after the
festival? I asked you if you wanted to see
me again. You just nodded your head and didn’t
say a word. It wasn’t too convincing.”
“I’d never met anyone like you before.
I couldn’t help it. I didn’t know what
to say.”
“I know. You could never hide anything.
Your eyes always gave you away. You had the
most wonderful eyes I’d ever seen.”
She paused then, lifted her head from his
shoulder, and looked directly at him. When
she spoke, her voice was barely above a whisper.
“I think I loved you more that summer than
I ever loved anyone.”
Lightning flashed again. In the quiet moments
before the thunder, their eyes met as they
tried to undo the fourteen years, both of
them sensing a change since yesterday. When
the thunder finally sounded, Noah sighed and
turned from her, toward the windows.
“I wish you could have read the letters
I wrote you,” he said.
She didn’t speak for a long while.
“It wasn’t just up to you, Noah. I didn’t
tell you, but I wrote you a dozen letters
after I got home. I just never sent them.”
“Why?” Noah was surprised. “I guess
I was too afraid.” “Of what?”
“That maybe it wasn’t as real as I thought
it was. That maybe you forgot me.”
“I would never do that. I couldn’t even
think it.” “I know that now. I can see
it when I look at you. But back then, it was
different. There was so much I didn’t understand,
things that a young girl’s mind couldn’t
sort out.”
“What do you mean?”
She paused, collecting her thoughts.
“When your letters never came, I didn’t
know what to think. I remember talking to
my best friend about what happened that summer,
and she said that you got what you wanted,
and that she wasn’t surprised that you wouldn’t
write. I didn’t believe that you were that
way, I never did, but hearing it and thinking
about all our differences made me wonder if
maybe the summer meant more to me than it
had meant to you. . . . And then, while all
this was going through my head, I heard from
Sarah. She said that you had left New Bern.”
“Fin and Sarah always knew where I was—”
She held up her hand to stop him. “I know,
but I never asked. I assumed that you had
left New Bern to start a new life, one without
me. Why else wouldn’t you write? Or call?
Or come see me?”
Noah looked away without answering, and she
continued:
“I didn’t know, and in time, the hurt
began to fade and it was easier to just let
it go. At least I thought it was. But in every
boy I met in the next few years, I found myself
looking for you, and when the feelings got
too strong, I’d write you another letter.
But I never sent them for fear of what I might
find. By then, you’d gone on with your life
and I didn’t want to think about you loving
someone else. I wanted to remember us like
we were that summer. I didn’t want to ever
lose that.”
She said it so sweetly, so innocently, that
Noah wanted to kiss her when she finished.
But he didn’t. Instead he fought the urge
and pushed it back, knowing it wasn’t what
she needed. Yet she felt so wonderful to him,
touching him. . . .
“The last letter I wrote was a couple of
years ago. After I met Lon, I wrote to your
daddy to find out where you were. But it had
been so long since I’d seen you, I wasn’t
even sure he’d still be there. And with
the war . . .”
She trailed off, and they were quiet for a
moment, both of them lost in thought. Lightning
lit the sky again before Noah finally broke
the silence.
“I wish you would have mailed it anyway.”
“Why?”
“Just to hear from you. To hear what you’ve
been up to.”
“You might have been disappointed. My life
isn’t too exciting. Besides, I’m not exactly
what you remembered.”
“You’re better than I remembered, Allie.”
“You’re sweet, Noah.”
He almost stopped there, knowing that if he
kept the words inside him, he could somehow
keep control, the same control he had kept
the past fourteen years. But something else
had overtaken him now, and he gave in to it,
hoping somehow, in some way, it would take
them back to what they’d had so long ago.
“I’m not saying it because I’m sweet.
I’m saying it because I love you now and
I always have. More than you can imagine.”
A log snapped, sending sparks up the chimney,
and both of them noticed the smoldering remains,
almost burned through. The fire needed another
log, but neither of them moved.
Allie took another sip of bourbon and began
to feel its effects. But it wasn’t just
the alcohol that made her hold Noah a little
tighter and feel his warmth against her. Glancing
out the window, she saw the clouds were almost
black.
“Let me get the fire going again,” Noah
said, needing to think, and she released him.
He went to the fireplace, opened the screen,
and added a couple of logs. He used the poker
to adjust the burning wood, making sure the
new wood could catch easily.
The flame began to spread again, and Noah
returned to her side. She snuggled up against
him again, resting her head on his shoulder
as she had before, not speaking, rubbing her
hand lightly against his chest. Noah leaned
closer and whispered in her ear.
“This reminds me of how we once were. When
we were young.”
She smiled, thinking the same thing, and they
watched the fire and smoke, holding each other.
“Noah, you’ve never asked, but I want
you to know something.”
“What is it?”
Her voice was tender.
“There’s never been another, Noah. You
weren’t just the first. You’re the only
man I’ve ever been with. I don’t expect
you to say the same thing, but I wanted you
to know.”
Noah was silent as he turned away. She felt
warmer as she watched the fire. Her hand ran
over the muscles beneath his shirt, hard and
firm as they leaned against each other.
She remembered when they’d held each other
like this for what they’d thought would
be the last time. They were sitting on a sea
wall designed to hold back the waters of the
Neuse River. She was crying because they might
never see each other again, and she wondered
how she could ever be happy again. Instead
of answering, he pressed a note into her hand,
which she read on the way home. She had saved
it, occasionally reading all of it or sometimes
just a part. One part she’d read at least
a hundred times, and for some reason it ran
through her head now. It said:
The reason it hurts so much to separate is
because our souls are connected. Maybe they
always have been and will be. Maybe we’ve
lived a thousand lives before this one and
in
each of them we’ve found each other. And
maybe each time, we’ve been forced apart
for the same reasons. That means that this
goodbye is both a good-bye for the past ten
thousand years and a prelude to what will
come.
When I look at you, I see your beauty and
grace and know they have grown stronger with
every life you have lived. And I know I have
spent every life before this one searching
for you. Not someone like you, but you, for
your soul and mine must always come together.
And then, for a reason neither of us understands,
we’ve been forced to say good-bye.
I would love to tell you that everything will
work out for us, and I promise to do all I
can to make sure it does. But if we never
meet again and this is truly good-bye, I know
we will see each other again in another life.
We will find each other again, and maybe the
stars will have changed, and we will not only
love each other in that time, but for all
the times we’ve had before.
Could it be? she wondered. Could he be right?
She had never completely discounted it, wanting
to hold on to its promise in case it was true.
The idea had helped her through many hard
times. But sitting here now seemed to test
the theory that they were destined to always
be apart. Unless the stars had changed since
they were last together.
And maybe they had, but she didn’t want
to look.
Instead she leaned into him and felt the heat
between them, felt his body, felt his arm
tight around her. And her body began to tremble
with the same anticipation she had felt the
first time they were together.
It felt so right to be here. Everything felt
right. The fire, the drinks, the storm—it
couldn’t have been more perfect. Like magic,
it seemed, their years apart didn’t matter
anymore.
Lightning cut the sky outside. Fire danced
on white-hot wood, spreading the heat. October
rain sheeted itself against the windows, drowning
out all other sounds.
They gave in then to everything they had fought
the last fourteen years. Allie lifted her
head off his shoulder, looked at him with
hazy eyes, and Noah kissed her softly on the
lips. She brought her hand to his face and
touched his cheek, brushing it softly with
her fingers. He leaned in slowly and kissed
her again, still soft and tender, and she
kissed back, feeling the years of separation
dissolve into passion.
She closed her eyes and parted her lips as
he ran his fingers up and down her arms, slowly,
lightly. He kissed her neck, her cheek, her
eyelids, and she felt the moisture of his
mouth linger wherever his lips had touched.
She took his hand and led it to her breasts,
and a whimper rose in her throat as he gently
touched them through the thin fabric of the
shirt.
The world seemed dreamlike as she pulled back
from him, the firelight setting her face aglow.
Without speaking, she started to undo the
buttons on his shirt. He watched her as she
did it and listened to her soft breaths as
she made her way downward. With each button
he could feel her fingers brushing against
his skin, and she smiled softly at him when
she finally finished. He felt her slide her
hands inside, touching him as lightly as possible,
letting her hands explore his body. He was
hot and she ran her hand over his slightly
wet chest, feeling his hair between her fingers.
Leaning in, she kissed his neck gently as
she pulled the shirt over his shoulders, locking
his arms behind his back. She lifted her head
and allowed him to kiss her as he rolled his
shoulders, freeing himself from the sleeves.
With that, he slowly reached for her. He lifted
her shirt and ran his finger slowly across
her belly before raising her arms and slipping
it off. She felt short of breath as he lowered
his head and kissed between her breasts and
slowly ran his tongue up to her neck. His
hands gently caressed her back, her arms,
her shoulders, and she felt their heated bodies
press together, skin to skin. He kissed her
neck and nibbled gently as she lifted her
hips and allowed him to pull off her bottoms.
She reached for the snap on his jeans, undid
it, and watched as he slipped them off as
well. It was almost slow motion as their naked
bodies finally came together, both of them
trembling with the memory of what they had
once shared together.
He ran his tongue along her neck while his
hands moved over the smooth hot skin of her
breasts, down her belly, past her navel, and
up again. He was struck by her beauty. Her
shimmering hair trapped the light and made
it sparkle. Her skin was soft and beautiful,
almost glowing in the firelight. He felt her
hands on his back, beckoning him.
They lay back, close to the fire, and the
heat made the air seem thick. Her back was
slightly arched as he rolled atop her in one
fluid motion. He was on all fours above her,
his knees astride her hips. She lifted her
head and kissed his chin and neck, breathing
hard, licking his shoulders, and tasting the
sweat that lingered on his body. She ran her
hands through his hair as he held himself
above her, his arm muscles hard from the exertion.
With a little tempting frown, she pulled him
closer, but he resisted. Instead he lowered
himself and lightly rubbed his chest against
her, and she felt her body respond with anticipation.
He did this slowly, over and over, kissing
every part of her body, listening as she made
soft, whimpering sounds while he moved above
her.
He did this until she couldn’t take it anymore,
and when they finally joined as one, she cried
aloud and pressed her fingers hard into his
back. She buried her face in his neck and
felt him deep inside her, felt his strength
and gentleness, felt his muscle and his soul.
She moved rhythmically against him, allowing
him to take her wherever he wanted, to the
place she was meant to be.
She opened her eyes and watched him in the
firelight, marveling at his beauty as he moved
above her. She saw his body glisten with crystal
sweat and watched as beads rolled down his
chest and fell onto her like the rain outside.
And with every drop, with every breath, she
felt herself, every responsibility, every
facet of her life, slipping away.
Their bodies reflected everything given, everything
taken, and she was rewarded with a sensation
she never knew existed. It went on and on,
tingling throughout her body and warming her
before finally subsiding, and she struggled
to catch her breath while she trembled beneath
him. But the moment it was over, another one
started to build again, and she started to
feel them in long sequences, one right after
the next. By the time the rain had stopped
and the sun had set, her body was exhausted
but unwilling to stop the pleasure between
them.
They spent the day in each other’s arms,
alternately making love by the fire and then
holding each other as they watched the flames
curl around the wood. Sometimes he recited
one of his favorite poems as she lay beside
him, and she would listen with her eyes closed
and almost feel the words. Then, when they
were ready, they would join again and he murmured
words of love between kisses as they wrapped
their arms around one another.
They went on throughout the evening, making
up for their years apart, and slept in each
other’s arms that night. Occasionally he
would wake up and look at her, her body spent
and radiant, and feel as if everything were
suddenly right in this world.
Once, when he was looking at her in the moments
before daybreak, her eyes fluttered open and
she smiled and reached up to touch his face.
He put his fingers to her lips, gently, to
keep her from speaking, and for a long time
they just looked at one another.
When the lump in his throat subsided, he whispered
to her, “You are the answer to every prayer
I’ve offered. You are a song, a dream, a
whisper, and I don’t know how I could have
lived without you for as long as I have. I
love you, Allie, more than you can ever imagine.
I always have, and I always will.”
“Oh, Noah,” she said, pulling him to her.
She wanted him, needed him now more than ever,
like nothing she’d ever known.
Courtrooms
Later that morning, three men—two lawyers
and the judge—sat in chambers while Lon
finished speaking. It was a moment before
the judge answered.
“It’s an unusual request,” he said,
pondering the situation. “It seems to me
the trial could very well end today. Are you
saying this urgent matter can’t wait until
later this evening or tomorrow?”
“No, Your Honor, it can’t,” Lon answered
almost too quickly. Stay relaxed, he told
himself. Take a deep breath.
“And it has nothing to do with this case?”
“No, Your Honor. It’s of a personal nature.
I know it’s out of the ordinary, but I really
need to take care of it.” Good, better.
The judge leaned back in his chair, evaluating
him for a moment. “Mr. Bates, how do you
feel about this?”
He cleared his throat. “Mr. Hammond called
me this morning and I’ve already spoken
to my clients. They’re willing to postpone
until Monday.”
“I see,” the judge said. “And do you
believe it is in your clients’ best interests
to do this?”
“I believe so,” he said. “Mr. Hammond
has agreed to reopen discussion on a certain
matter not covered by this proceeding.”
The judge looked hard at both of them and
thought about it.
“I don’t like it,” he finally said,
“not at all. But Mr. Hammond has never made
a similar request before, and I assume the
matter is very important to him.”
He paused for effect, then looked to some
papers on his desk. “I’ll agree to adjourn
until Monday. Nine o’clock sharp.”
“Thank you, Your Honor,” Lon said.
Two minutes later he was leaving the courthouse.
He walked to the car he had parked directly
across the street, got in, and began the drive
to New Bern, his hands shaking.
An Unexpected Visitor
Noah made breakfast for Allie while she slept
in the living room. Bacon, biscuits, and coffee,
nothing spectacular. He set the tray beside
her as she woke up, and as soon as they had
finished eating, they made love again. It
was relentless, a powerful confirmation of
what they had shared the day before. Allie
arched her back and cried out fiercely in
the final tidal wave of sensations, then wrapped
her arms around him as they breathed in unison,
exhausted.
They showered together, and afterward Allie
put on her dress, which had dried overnight.
She spent the morning with Noah. Together
they fed Clem and checked the windows to make
sure no damage had been done in the storm.
Two pine trees had blown over, though neither
had caused much damage, and a few shingles
had blown off the shed, but other than that,
the property had escaped pretty much unscathed.
He held her hand most of the morning and the
two talked easily, but sometimes he would
stop speaking and just stare at her. When
he did, she felt as though she should say
something, but nothing meaningful ever came
into her head. Lost in thought, she usually
just kissed him.
A little before noon, Noah and Allie went
in to prepare lunch. Both of them were starving
again because they hadn’t eaten much the
day before. Using what he had on hand, they
fried some chicken and baked another batch
of biscuits, and the two of them ate on the
porch, serenaded by a mockingbird.
While they were inside doing the dishes, they
heard a knock at the door. Noah left Allie
in the kitchen.
Knock again.
“I’m coming,” Noah said.
Knock, knock. Louder.
He approached the door.
Knock, knock.
“I’m coming,” he said again as he opened
the door. “Oh, my God.”
He stared for a moment at a beautiful woman
in her early fifties, a woman he would have
recognized anywhere.
Noah couldn’t speak.
“Hello, Noah,” she finally said. Noah
said nothing.
“May I come in?” she asked, her voice
steady, revealing nothing.
He stammered out a reply as she walked past
him, stopping just before the stairs.
“Who is it?” Allie shouted from the kitchen,
and the woman turned at the sound of her voice.
“It’s your mother,” Noah finally answered,
and immediately after he said it, he heard
the sound of breaking glass.
“I knew you would be here,” Anne Nelson
said to her daughter as the three of them
sat around the coffee table in the living
room.
“How could you be so sure?”
“You’re my daughter. One day when you
have kids of your own, you’ll know the answer.”
She smiled, but her manner was stiff, and
Noah imagined how difficult this must be for
her. “I saw the article, too, and I saw
your reaction. I also saw how tense you’ve
been during the last couple of weeks, and
when you said you were going shopping near
the coast, I knew exactly what you meant.”
“What about Daddy?”
Anne Nelson shook her head. “No, I didn’t
tell your father or anyone else about it.
Nor did I tell anyone where I was going today.”
The table was silent for a moment as they
wondered what was coming next, but Anne remained
quiet.
“Why did you come?” Allie finally asked.
Her mother raised an eyebrow. “I thought
I would be the one to ask that question.”
Allie paled.
“I came because I had to,” her mother
said, “which I’m sure is the same reason
you came. Am I right?”
Allie nodded.
Anne turned to Noah. “These last couple
of days must have been full of surprises.”
“Yes,” he answered simply, and she smiled
at him. “I know you don’t think so, but
I always liked you, Noah. I just didn’t
think you were right for my daughter. Can
you understand that?”
He shook his head as he answered, his tone
serious. “No, not really. It wasn’t fair
to me, and it wasn’t fair to Allie. Otherwise
she wouldn’t be here.”
She watched him as he answered, but she said
nothing. Allie, sensing an argument, cut in:
“What do you mean when you say you had to
come? Don’t you trust me?”
Anne turned back to her daughter. “This
has nothing to do with trust. This has to
do with Lon. He called the house last night
to talk to me about Noah, and he’s on his
way here right now. He seemed very upset.
I thought you’d want to know.”
Allie inhaled sharply. “He’s on his way?”
“As we speak. He arranged to have the trial
postponed until next week. If he’s not in
New Bern yet, he’s close.”
“What did you say to him?”
“Not much. But he knew. He had it all figured
out. He remembered my telling him about Noah
a long time ago.”
Allie swallowed hard. “Did you tell him
I was here?”
“No. And I won’t. That’s between you
and him. But knowing him, I’m sure he’ll
find you here if you stay. All it takes is
a couple of phone calls to the right people.
After all, I was able to find you.”
Allie, though obviously worried, smiled at
her mother. “Thank you,” she said, and
her mother reached for her hand.
“I know we’ve had our differences, Allie,
and that we haven’t seen eye to eye on everything.
I’m not perfect, but I did the best I could
with raising you. I’m your mother and I
always will be. That means I’ll always love
you.”
Allie was silent for a moment, then: “What
should I do?”
“I don’t know, Allie. That’s up to you.
But I would think about it. Think about what
you really want.”
Allie turned away, her eyes reddening. A moment
later a tear drifted down her cheek.
“I don’t know. . . ” She trailed off,
and her mother squeezed her hand. Anne looked
at Noah, who had been sitting with his head
down, listening carefully. As if on cue, he
returned her gaze, nodded, and left the room.
When he was gone, Anne whispered, “Do you
love him?”
“Yes, I do,” Allie answered softly, “very
much.” “Do you love Lon?”
“Yes, I do. I love him, too. Dearly, but
in a different way. He doesn’t make me feel
the way Noah does.”
“No one will ever do that,” her mother
said, and she released Allie’s hand.
“I can’t make this decision for you, Allie,
this one’s all yours. I want you to know,
though, that I love you. And I always will.
I know that doesn’t help but it’s all
I can do.”
She reached in her pocketbook and removed
a bundle of letters held together with string,
the envelopes old and slightly yellowed.
“These are the letters that Noah wrote you.
I never threw them away, and they haven’t
been opened. I know I shouldn’t have kept
them from you, and I’m sorry for that. But
I was just trying to protect you. I didn’t
realize . . .”
Allie took them and ran her hand over them,
shocked.
“I should go, Allie. You’ve got some decisions
to make, and you don’t have much time. Do
you want me to stay in town?”
Allie shook her head. “No, this is up to
me.” Anne nodded and watched her daughter
for a moment, wondering. Finally she stood,
went around the table, leaned over, and kissed
her daughter on the cheek. She could see the
question in her daughter’s eyes as Allie
stood from the table and embraced her.
“What are you going to do?” her mother
asked, pulling back. There was a long pause.
“I don’t know,” Allie finally answered.
They stood together for another minute, just
holding each other.
“Thanks for coming,” Allie said. “I
love you.”
“I love you, too.”
On her way out the door, Allie thought that
she heard her mother whisper, “Follow your
heart,” but she couldn’t be sure.
Crossroads
Noah opened the door for Anne Nelson as she
went out.
“Good-bye, Noah,” she said quietly. He
nodded without speaking. There wasn’t anything
else to say; they both knew that. She turned
from him and left, closing the door behind
her. Noah watched her walk to her car, get
in, and drive away without looking back. She
was a strong woman, he thought to himself,
and he knew where Allie got it from.
Noah peeked in the living room, saw Allie
sitting with her head down, then went to the
back porch, knowing that she needed to be
alone. He sat quietly in his rocker and watched
the water drifting by as the minutes passed.
After what seemed like an eternity he heard
the back door open. He didn’t turn to look
at her just then—for some reason he couldn’t—and
he listened as she sat in the chair beside
him.
“I’m sorry,” Allie said. “I had no
idea this would happen.”
Noah shook his head. “Don’t be sorry.
We both knew it was coming in some form or
another.”
“It’s still hard.”
“I know.” He finally turned to her, reaching
for her hand. “Is there anything I can do
to make it easier?”
She shook her head. “No. Not really. I have
to do this alone. Besides, I’m not sure
what I’m going to say to him yet.” She
looked down and her voice became softer and
a little more distant, as if she were talking
to herself. “I guess it depends on him and
how much he knows. If my mother was right,
he may have suspicions, but he doesn’t know
anything for sure.”
Noah felt a tightness in his stomach. When
he finally spoke his voice was steady, but
she could hear the pain in it.
“You’re not going to tell him about us,
are you?” “I don’t know. I really don’t.
While I was in the living room, I kept asking
myself what I really wanted in my life.”
She squeezed his hand. “And do you know
what the answer was? The answer was that I
wanted two things. First, I want you. I want
us. I love you and I always have.”
She took a deep breath before going on.
“But I also want a happy ending without
hurting anyone. And I know that if I stayed,
people would be hurt. Especially Lon. I wasn’t
lying when I told you that I love him. He
doesn’t make me feel the same way you do,
but I care for him, and this wouldn’t be
fair to him. But staying here would also hurt
my family and friends. I would be betraying
everyone I know.
...I don’t know if I can do that.”
“You can’t live your life for other people.
You’ve got to do what’s right for you,
even if it hurts some people you love.”
“I know,” she said, “but no matter what
I choose I have to live with it. Forever.
I have to be able to go forward and not look
back anymore. Can you understand that?”
He shook his head and tried to keep his voice
steady. “Not really. Not if it means losing
you. I can’t do that again.”
She didn’t say anything but lowered her
head. Noah went on:
“Could you really leave me without looking
back?”
She bit her lip as she answered. Her voice
was beginning to crack. “I don’t know.
Probably not.”
“Would that be fair to Lon?”
She didn’t answer right away. Instead she
stood, wiped her face, and walked to the edge
of the porch where she leaned against the
post. She crossed her arms and watched the
water before answering quietly.
“No.”
“It doesn’t have to be like this, Allie,”
he said. “We’re adults now, we have the
choice we didn’t have before. We’re meant
to be together. We always have been.”
He walked to her side and put his hand on
her shoulder. “I don’t want to live the
rest of my life thinking about you and dreaming
of what might have been. Stay with me, Allie.”
Tears began to fill her eyes. “I don’t
know if I can,” she finally whispered.
“You can. Allie . . . I can’t live my
life happily knowing you’re with someone
else. That would kill a part of me. What we
have is rare. It’s too beautiful to just
throw it away.”
She didn’t respond. After a moment he gently
turned her toward him, took her hands, and
stared at her, willing her to look at him.
Allie finally faced him with moist eyes. After
a long silence, Noah brushed the tears from
her cheeks with his fingers, a look of tenderness
on his face. His voice caught as he saw what
her eyes were telling him.
“You’re not going to stay, are you?”
He smiled weakly. “You want to, but you
can’t.”
“Oh, Noah,” she said as the tears began
again, “please try to understand. ...”
He shook his head to stop her.
“I know what you’re trying to say—I
can see it in your eyes. But I don’t want
to understand it, Allie. I don’t want it
to end this way. I don’t want it to end
at all. But if you leave, we both know we’ll
never see each other again.”
She leaned into him and began to cry harder
as Noah fought back his own tears.
He wrapped his arms around her.
“Allie, I can’t force you to stay with
me. But no matter what happens in my life,
I’ll never forget these last couple of days
with you. I’ve been dreaming about this
for years.”
He kissed her gently, and they embraced as
they had when she first got out of her car
two days ago. Finally Allie let him go and
wiped her tears.
“I have to get my things, Noah.”
He didn’t go inside with her. Instead he
sat down in the rocker, spent. He watched
her go into the house and listened as the
sound of her movements faded into nothing.
She emerged from the house minutes later with
everything she’d brought and walked toward
him with her head down. She handed him the
drawing she had done yesterday morning. As
he took it, he noticed that she hadn’t stopped
crying.
“Here, Noah. I made this for you.”
Noah took the drawing and unrolled it slowly,
careful not to tear it.
There were dual images, one overlapping the
other. The image in the foreground, which
occupied most of the page, was a picture of
how he looked now, not fourteen years ago.
Noah noticed that she had penciled in every
detail of his face, including the scar. It
was almost as if she’d copied it from a
recent photograph.
The second image was that of the front of
the house. The detail there was also incredible,
as if she had sketched it while sitting beneath
the oak tree.
“It’s beautiful, Allie. Thank you.”
He attempted a smile. “I told you that you
were an artist.” She nodded, her face cast
downward, her lips pressed together. It was
time for her to go.
They walked to her car slowly, without speaking.
When they reached it, Noah embraced her again
until he could feel the tears welling up in
his own eyes. He kissed her lips and both
cheeks, then with his finger softly brushed
the places he’d kissed.
“I love you, Allie.”
“I love you, too.”
Noah opened her car door, and they kissed
one more time. Then she slid behind the wheel,
never taking her eyes from him. She put the
packet of letters and the pocketbook next
to her on the seat and fumbled for the keys,
then turned the ignition. It started easily,
and the engine began to turn over impatiently.
It was almost time.
Noah pushed her door closed with both hands,
and Allie rolled down the window. She could
see the muscles in his arms, the easy smile,
the tanned face. She reached out her hand
and Noah took it for just a moment, moving
his fingers softly against her skin.
“Stay with me,” Noah mouthed without sound,
and this for some reason hurt more than Allie
would have expected. The tears began to fall
hard now, but she couldn’t speak. Finally,
reluctantly, she looked away and pulled her
hand from his. She put the car in gear and
eased the pedal down just a bit. If she didn’t
leave now, she never would. Noah backed up
just a bit as the car started to roll away.
He fell into an almost trancelike state as
he felt the reality of the situation. He watched
the car roll slowly forward; he heard the
gravel crunching under the wheels. Slowly
the car began to turn from him, toward the
road that would take her back to town. Leaving—she
was leaving!—and Noah felt dizzy at the
sight.
Edging forward . . . past him now . . .
She waved one last time without smiling before
she began to accelerate, and he waved back
weakly. “Don’t go!” he wanted to shout
as the car moved farther away. But he didn’t
say anything, and a minute later the car was
gone and the only remaining signs of her were
the tracks that her car had left behind.
He stood there without moving for a long time.
As quickly as she had come, she was gone.
Forever this time. Forever.
He closed his eyes then and watched her leave
once more, her car moving steadily away from
him, taking his heart with her.
But, like her mother, he realized sadly, she
never looked back.
A Letter fromYesterday
Driving with tears in her eyes was difficult,
but she went on anyway, hoping that instinct
would take her back to the inn. She kept the
window rolled down, thinking the fresh air
might help clear her mind, but it didn’t
seem to help. Nothing would help.
She was tired, and she wondered if she would
have the energy she needed to talk to Lon.
And what was she going to say? She still had
no idea but hoped that something would come
to her when the time came.
It would have to.
By the time she reached the drawbridge that
led to Front Street, she had herself a little
more under control. Not completely, but well
enough, she thought, to talk to Lon. At least
she hoped so.
Traffic was light, and she had time to watch
strangers going about their business as she
drove through New Bern. At a gas station,
a mechanic was looking under the hood of a
new automobile while a man, presumably its
owner, stood beside him. Two women were pushing
baby carriages just outside Hoffman-Lane,
chatting between themselves while they window-shopped.
In front of Hearns Jewelers, a well-dressed
man walked briskly, carrying a briefcase.
She made another turn and saw a young man
unloading groceries from a truck that blocked
part of the street. Something about the way
he held himself, or the way he moved, reminded
her of Noah harvesting crabs at the end of
the dock.
She saw the inn just up the street while she
was stopped at a red light. She took a deep
breath when the light turned green and drove
slowly until she reached the parking lot that
the inn shared with a couple of other businesses.
She turned in and saw Lon’s car sitting
in the first spot. Although the one next to
it was open, she passed it and picked a spot
a little farther from the entrance.
She turned the key, and the engine stopped
promptly. Next she reached into the glove
compartment for a mirror and brush, finding
both sitting on top of a map of North Carolina.
Looking at herself, she saw her eyes were
still red and puffy. Like yesterday after
the rain, as she examined her reflection she
was sorry she didn’t have any makeup, though
she doubted it would help much now. She tried
pulling her hair back on one side, tried both
sides, then finally gave up.
She reached for her pocketbook, opened it,
and once again looked at the article that
had brought her here. So much had happened
since then; it was hard to believe it had
been only three weeks. It felt impossible
to her that she had arrived only the day before
yesterday. It seemed like a lifetime since
her dinner with Noah.
Starlings chirped in the trees around her.
The clouds had begun to break up now, and
Allie could see blue in between patches of
white. The sun was still shaded, but she knew
it would only be a matter of time. It was
going to be a beautiful day.
It was the kind of day she would have liked
to spend with Noah, and as she was thinking
about him, she remembered the letters her
mother had given her and reached for them.
She untied the packet and found the first
letter he had written her. She began to open
it, then stopped because she could imagine
what was in it. Something simple, no doubt—things
he’d done, memories of the summer, perhaps
some questions. After all, he probably expected
an answer from her. Instead she reached for
the last letter he’d written, the one on
the bottom of the stack. The good-bye letter.
This one interested her far more than the
others. How had he said it? How would she
have said it?
The envelope was thin. One, maybe two pages.
Whatever he had written wasn’t too long.
First, she turned it over and checked the
back. No name, just a street address in New
Jersey. She held her breath as she used her
fingernail to pry it open.
Unfolding it, she saw it was dated March 1935.
Two and a half years without a reply.
She imagined him sitting at an old desk, crafting
the letter, somehow knowing this was the end,
and she saw what she thought were tearstains
on the paper. Probably just her imagination.
She straightened the page and began to read
in the soft white sunlight that shone through
the window.
My dearest Allie,
I don’t know what to say anymore except
that I couldn’t sleep last night because
I knew that it is over between us. It is a
different feeling for me, one that I never
expected, but looking back, I suppose it couldn’t
have ended another way.
You and I were different. We came from different
worlds, and yet you were the one who taught
me the value of love. You showed me what it
was like to care for another, and I am a better
man because of it. I don’t want you to ever
forget that.
I am not bitter because of what has happened.
On the contrary. I am secure in knowing that
what we had was real, and I am happy we were
able to come together for even a short period
of time. And if, in some distant place in
the future, we see each other in our new lives,
I will
smile at you with joy, and remember how we
spent a summer beneath the trees, learning
from each other and growing in love. And maybe,
for a brief moment, you’ll feel it too,
and you’ll smile back, and savor the memories
we will always share together.
I love you, Allie.
Noah
She read the letter again, more slowly this
time, then read it a third time before she
put it back into the envelope. Once more,
she imagined him writing it, and for a moment
she debated reading another, but she knew
she couldn’t delay any longer. Lon was waiting
for her.
Her legs felt weak as she stepped out of the
car. She paused and took a deep breath, and
as she started across the parking lot, she
realized she still wasn’t sure what she
was going to say to him.
And the answer didn’t finally come until
she reached the door and opened it and saw
Lon standing in the lobby.
Winter for Two
The story ends there, so I close the notebook,
remove my glasses, and wipe my eyes. They
are tired and bloodshot, but they have not
failed me so far. They will soon, I am sure.
Neither they nor I can go on forever. I look
to her now that I have finished, but she does
not look back. Instead she is staring out
the window at the courtyard, where friends
and family meet.
My eyes follow hers, and we watch it together.
In all these years the daily pattern has not
changed. Every morning, an hour after breakfast,
they begin to arrive. Young adults, alone
or with family, come to visit those who live
here. They bring photographs and gifts and
either sit on the benches or stroll along
the tree-lined paths designed to give a sense
of nature. Some will stay for the day, but
most leave after a few hours, and when they
do, I always feel sadness for those they’ve
left behind. I wonder sometimes what my friends
think as they see their loved ones driving
off, but I know it’s not my business. And
I do not ever ask them because I’ve learned
that we’re all entitled to have our secrets.
But soon, I will tell you some of mine.
I place the notebook and magnifier on the
table beside me, feeling the ache in my bones
as I do so, and I realize once again how cold
my body is. Even reading in the morning sun
does nothing to help it. This does not surprise
me anymore, though, for my body makes its
own rules these days.
I’m not completely unfortunate, however.
The people who work here know me and my faults
and do their best to make me more comfortable.
They have left me hot tea on the end table,
and I reach for it with both hands. It is
an effort to pour a cup, but I do so because
the tea is needed to warm me and I think the
exertion will keep me from completely rusting
away. But I am rusted now, no doubt about
it. Rusted as a junked car twenty years in
the Everglades.
I have read to her this morning, as I do every
morning, because it is something I must do.
Not for duty—although I suppose a case could
be made for this—but for another, more romantic,
reason. I wish I could explain it more fully
right now, but it’s still early, and talking
about romance isn’t really possible before
lunch anymore, at least not for me. Besides,
I have no idea how it’s going to turn out,
and to be honest, I’d rather not get my
hopes up.
We spend each and every day together now,
but our nights are spent alone. The doctors
tell me that I’m not allowed to see her
after dark. I understand the reasons completely,
and though I agree with them, I sometimes
break the rules. Late at night when my mood
is right, I will sneak from my room and go
to hers and watch her while she sleeps. Of
this she knows nothing. I’ll come in and
see her breathe and know that had it not been
for her, I would never have married. And when
I look at her face, a face I know better than
my own, I know that I have meant as much or
more to her. And that means more to me than
I could ever hope to explain.
Sometimes, when I am standing there, I think
about how lucky I am to have been married
to her for almost forty-nine years. Next month
it will be that long. She heard me snore for
the first forty-five, but since then we have
slept in separate rooms. I do not sleep well
without her. I toss and turn and yearn for
her warmth and lie there most of the night,
eyes open wide, watching the shadows dance
across the ceilings like tumbleweeds rolling
across the desert. I sleep two hours if I
am lucky, and still I wake before dawn. This
makes no sense to me.
Soon, this will all be over. I know this.
She does not. The entries in my diary have
become shorter and take little time to write.
I keep them simple now, since most of my days
are the same. But tonight I think I will copy
a poem that one of the nurses found for me
and thought I would enjoy. It goes like this:
I ne’er was struck before that hour
With love so sudden and so sweet, Her face
it bloomed like a sweet flower
And stole my heart away complete.
Because our evenings are our own, I have been
asked to visit the others. Usually I do, for
I am the reader and I am needed, or so I am
told. I walk the halls and choose where to
go because I am too old to devote myself to
a schedule, but deep down I always know who
needs me. They are my friends, and when I
push open their doors, I see rooms that look
like mine, always semidarkened, illuminated
only by the lights of Wheel of Fortune and
Vanna’s teeth. The furniture is the same
for everyone, and the TVs blare because no
one can hear well anymore.
Men or women, they smile at me when I enter
and speak in whispers as they turn off their
sets. “I’m so glad you’ve come,” they
say, and then they ask about my wife. Sometimes
I tell them. I might tell them of her sweetness
and her charm and describe how she taught
me to see the world for the beautiful place
it is. Or I tell them of our early years together
and explain how we had all we needed when
we held each other under starry southern skies.
On special occasions I whisper of our adventures
together, of art shows in New York and Paris
or the rave reviews from critics writing in
languages I do not understand. Mostly, though,
I smile and I tell them that she is the same,
and they turn from me, for I know they do
not want me to see their faces. It reminds
them of their own mortality. So I sit with
them and read to lessen their fears.
Be composed—be at ease with me . . .
Not till the sun excludes you do I exclude
you, Not till the waters refuse to glisten
for you and the leaves to rustle for you,
do my words refuse to glisten and rustle for
you.
And I read, to let them know who I am.
I wander all night in my vision, . . .
Bending with open eyes over the shut eyes
of sleepers,
Wandering and confused, lost to myself, ill-assorted,
contradictory,
Pausing, gazing, bending, and stopping.
If she could, my wife would accompany me on
my evening excursions, for one of her many
loves was poetry. Thomas, Whitman, Eliot,
Shakespeare, and King David of the Psalms.
Lovers of words, makers of language. Looking
back, I am surprised by my passion for it,
and sometimes I even regret it now. Poetry
brings great beauty to life, but also great
sadness, and I’m not sure it’s a fair
exchange for someone my age. A man should
enjoy other things if he can; he should spend
his final days in the sun. Mine will be spent
by a reading lamp.
I shuffle toward her and sit in the chair
beside her bed. My back aches when I sit.
I must get a new cushion for this chair, I
remind myself for the hundredth time. I reach
for her hand and take it, bony and fragile.
It feels nice. She responds with a twitch,
and gradually her thumb begins to softly rub
my finger. I do not speak until she does;
this I have learned. Most days I sit in silence
until the sun goes down, and on days like
those I know nothing about her.
Minutes pass before she finally turns to me.
She is crying. I smile and release her hand,
then reach in my pocket. I take out a handkerchief
and wipe at her tears. She looks at me as
I do so, and I wonder what she is thinking.
“That was a beautiful story.”
A light rain begins to fall. Little drops
tap gently on the window. I take her hand
again. It is going to be a good day, a very
good day. A magical day. I smile, I can’t
help it.
“Yes, it is,” I tell her.
“Did you write it?” she asks. Her voice
is like a whisper, a light wind flowing through
the leaves.
“Yes,” I answer.
She turns toward the nightstand. Her medicine
is in a little cup. Mine too. Little pills,
colors like a rainbow so we won’t forget
to take them. They bring mine here now, to
her room, even though they’re not supposed
to.
“I’ve heard it before, haven’t I?”
“Yes,” I say again, just as I do every
time on days like these. I have learned to
be patient.
She studies my face. Her eyes are as green
as ocean waves.
“It makes me feel less afraid,” she says.
“I know.” I nod, rocking my head softly.
She turns away, and I wait some more. She
releases my hand and reaches for her water
glass. It is on her nightstand, next to the
medicine. She takes a sip.
“Is it a true story?” She sits up a little
in her bed and takes another drink. Her body
is still strong. “I mean, did you know these
people?”
“Yes,” I say again. I could say more,
but usually I don’t. She is still beautiful.
She asks the obvious:
“Well, which one did she finally marry?”
I answer: “The one who was right for her.”
“Which one was that?”
I smile. “You’ll know,” I say quietly,
“by the end of the day. You’ll know.”
She does not know what to think about this
but does not question me further. Instead
she begins to fidget. She is thinking of a
way to ask me another question, though she
isn’t sure how to do it. Instead she chooses
to put it off for a moment and reaches for
one of the little paper cups.
“Is this mine?”
“No, this one is,” and I reach over and
push her medicine toward her. I cannot grab
it with my fingers. She takes it and looks
at the pills. I can tell by the way she is
looking at them that she has no idea what
they are for. I use both hands to pick up
my cup and dump the pills into my mouth. She
does the same. There is no fight today. That
makes it easy. I raise my cup in a mock toast
and wash the gritty flavor from my mouth with
my tea. It is getting colder. She swallows
on faith and washes them down with more water.
A bird starts to sing outside the window,
and we both turn our heads. We sit quietly
for a while, enjoying something beautiful
together. Then it is lost, and she sighs.
“I have to ask you something else,” she
says. “Whatever it is, I’ll try to answer.”
“It’s hard, though.”
She does not look at me, and I cannot see
her eyes. This is how she hides her thoughts.
Some things never change.
“Take your time,” I say. I know what she
will ask. Finally she turns to me and looks
into my eyes. She offers a gentle smile, the
kind you share with a child, not a lover.
“I don’t want to hurt your feelings because
you’ve been so nice to me, but . . .”
I wait. Her words will hurt me. They will
tear a piece from my heart and leave a scar.
“Who are you?”
We have lived at Creekside Extended Care Facility
for three years now. It was her decision to
come here, partly because it was near our
home, but also because she thought it would
be easier for me. We boarded up our home because
neither of us could bear to sell it, signed
some papers, and just like that we received
a place to live and die in exchange for some
of the freedom for which we had worked a lifetime.
She was right to do this, of course. There
is no way I could have made it alone, for
sickness has come to us, both of us. We are
in the final minutes in the day of our lives,
and the clock is ticking. Loudly. I wonder
if I am the only one who can hear it.
A throbbing pain courses through my fingers,
and it reminds me that we have not held hands
with fingers interlocked since we moved here.
I am sad about this, but it is my fault, not
hers. It is arthritis in the worst form, rheumatoid
and advanced. My hands are misshapen and grotesque
now, and they throb during most of my waking
hours. I look at them and want them gone,
amputated, but then I would not be able to
do the little things I must do. So I use my
claws, as I call them sometimes, and every
day I take her hands despite the pain, and
I do my best to hold them because that is
what she wants me to do.
Although the Bible says man can live to be
120, I don’t want to, and I don’t think
my body would make it even if I did. It is
falling apart, dying one piece at a time,
steady erosion on the inside and at the joints.
My hands are useless, my kidneys are beginning
to fail, and my heart rate is decreasing every
month. Worse, I have cancer again, this time
of the prostate. This is my third bout with
the unseen enemy, and it will take me eventually,
though not till I say it is time. The doctors
are worried about me, but I am not. I have
no time for worry in this twilight of my life.
Of our five children, four are still living,
and though it is hard for them to visit, they
come often, and for this I am thankful. But
even when they aren’t here, they come alive
in my mind every day, each of them, and they
bring to mind the smiles and tears that come
with raising a family. A dozen pictures line
the walls of my room. They are my heritage,
my contribution to the world. I am very proud.
Sometimes I wonder what my wife thinks of
them as she dreams, or if she thinks of them
at all, or if she even dreams. There is so
much about her I don’t understand anymore.
I wonder what my daddy would think of my life
and what he would do if he were me. I have
not seen him for fifty years and he is now
but a shadow in my thoughts. I cannot picture
him clearly anymore; his face is darkened
as if a light shines from behind him. I am
not sure if this is due to a failing memory
or simply the passage of time. I have only
one picture of him, and this too has faded.
In another ten years it will be gone and so
will I, and his memory will be erased like
a message in the sand. If not for my diaries,
I would swear I had lived only half as long
as I have. Long periods of my life seem to
have vanished. And even now I read the passages
and wonder who I was when I wrote them, for
I cannot remember the events of my life. There
are times I sit and wonder where it all has
gone.
“My name,” I say, “is Duke.” I have
always been a John Wayne fan.
“Duke,” she whispers to herself, “Duke.”
She thinks for a moment, her forehead wrinkled,
her eyes serious.
“Yes,” I say, “I’m here for you.”
And always will be, I think to myself.
She flushes with my answer. Her eyes become
wet and red, and tears begin to fall. My heart
aches for her, and I wish for the thousandth
time that there was something I could do.
She says:
“I’m sorry. I don’t understand anything
that’s happening to me right now. Even you.
When I listen to you talk I feel like I should
know you, but I don’t. I don’t even know
my name.”
She wipes at her tears and says, “Help me,
Duke, help me remember who I am. Or at least,
who I was. I feel so lost.”
I answer from my heart, but I lie to her about
her name. As I have about my own. There is
a reason for this.
“You are Hannah, a lover of life, a strength
to those who shared in your friendships. You
are a dream, a creator of happiness, an artist
who has touched a thousand souls. You’ve
led a full life and wanted for nothing because
your needs are spiritual and you have only
to look inside you. You are kind and loyal,
and you are able to see beauty where others
do not. You are a teacher of wonderful lessons,
a dreamer of better things.”
I stop for a moment and catch my breath. Then,
“Hannah, there is no reason to feel lost,
for:
Nothing is ever really lost, or can be lost,
No birth, identity, form—no object of the
world,
Nor life, nor force, nor any visible thing;
. . . The body, sluggish, aged, cold—the
embers left from earlier fires,
. . . shall duly flame again;”
She thinks about what I have said for a moment.
In the silence, I look toward the window and
notice that the rain has stopped now. Sunlight
is beginning to filter into her room. She
asks:
“Did you write that?”
“No, that was Walt Whitman.” “Who?”
“A lover of words, a shaper of thoughts.”
She does not respond directly. Instead she
stares at me for a long while, until our breathing
coincides. In. Out. In. Out. In. Out. Deep
breaths. I wonder if she knows I think she’s
beautiful.
“Would you stay with me a while?” she
finally asks.
I smile and nod. She smiles back. She reaches
for my hand, takes it gently, and pulls it
to her waist. She stares at the hardened knots
that deform my fingers and caresses them gently.
Her hands are still those of an angel.
“Come,” I say as I stand with great effort,
“let’s go for a walk. The air is crisp
and the goslings are waiting. It’s beautiful
today.” I am staring at her as I say these
last few words.
She blushes. It makes me feel young again.
She was famous, of course. One of the best
southern painters of the twentieth century,
some said, and I was, and am, proud of her.
Unlike me, who struggled to write even the
simplest of verses, my wife could create beauty
as easily as the Lord created the earth. Her
paintings are in museums around the world,
but I have kept only two for myself. The first
one she ever gave me and the last one. They
hang in my room, and late at night I sit and
stare and sometimes cry when I look at them.
I don’t know why.
And so the years passed. We led our lives,
working, painting, raising children, loving
each other. I see photos of Christmases, family
trips, of graduations and of weddings. I see
grandchildren and happy faces. I see photos
of us, our hair growing whiter, the lines
in our faces deeper. A lifetime that seems
so typical, yet uncommon.
We could not foresee the future, but then
who can? I do not live now as I expected to.
And what did I expect? Retirement. Visits
with the grandchildren, perhaps more travel.
She always loved to travel. I thought that
perhaps I would start a hobby, what I did
not know, but possibly shipbuilding. In bottles.
Small, detailed, impossible to consider now
with my hands. But I am not bitter.
Our lives can’t be measured by our final
years, of this I am sure, and I guess I should
have known what lay ahead in our lives. Looking
back, I suppose it seems obvious, but at first
I thought her confusion understandable and
not unique. She would forget where she placed
her keys, but who has not done that? She would
forget a neighbor’s name, but not someone
we knew well or with whom we socialized. Sometimes
she would write the wrong year when she made
out her checks, but again I dismissed it as
simple mistakes that one makes when thinking
of other things.
It was not until the more obvious events occurred
that I began to suspect the worst. An iron
in the freezer, clothes in the dishwasher,
books in the oven. Other things, too. But
the day I found her in the car three blocks
away, crying over the steering wheel because
she couldn’t find her way home was the first
day I was really frightened. And she was frightened,
too, for when I tapped on her window, she
turned to me and said, “Oh God, what’s
happening to me? Please help me.” A knot
twisted in my stomach, but I dared not think
the worst.
Six days later the doctor met with her and
began a series of tests. I did not understand
them then and I do not understand them now,
but I suppose it is because I am afraid to
know. She spent almost an hour with Dr. Barnwell,
and she went back the next day. That day was
the longest day I ever spent. I looked through
magazines I could not read and played games
I did not think about. Finally he called us
both into his office and sat us down. She
held my arm confidently, but I remember clearly
that my own hands were shaking.
“I’m so sorry to have to tell you this,”
Dr. Barn-well began, “but you seem to be
in the early stages of Alzheimer’s. . . .”
My mind went blank, and all I could think
about was the light that glowed above our
heads. The words echoed in my head: the early
stages of Alzheimer’s . . .
My world spun in circles, and I felt her grip
tighten on my arm. She whispered, almost to
herself: “Oh, Noah . . . Noah . . .”
And as the tears started to fall, the word
came back to me again: . . . Alzheimer’s
...
It is a barren disease, as empty and lifeless
as a desert. It is a thief of hearts and souls
and memories. I did not know what to say to
her as she sobbed on my bosom, so I simply
held her and rocked her back and forth.
The doctor was grim. He was a good man, and
this was hard for him. He was younger than
my youngest, and I felt my age in his presence.
My mind was confused, my love was shaking,
and the only thing I could think was:
No drowning man can know which drop of water
his last breath did stop; . . .
A wise poet’s words, yet they brought me
no comfort. I don’t know what they meant
or why I thought of them.
We rocked to and fro, and Allie, my dream,
my timeless beauty, told me she was sorry.
I knew there was nothing to forgive, and I
whispered in her ear. “Everything will be
fine,” I whispered, but inside I was afraid.
I was a hollow man with nothing to offer,
empty as a junked stovepipe.
I remember only bits and pieces of Dr. Barnwell’s
continuing explanation.
“It’s a degenerative brain disorder affecting
memory and personality . . . there is no cure
or therapy. . . .
There’s no way to tell how fast it will
progress . . . it differs from person to person.
...I wish I knew more. . . .
Some days will be better than others. ...It
will grow worse with the passage of time.
. . . I’m sorry to be the one who has to
tell you. . . .”
I’m sorry . . .
Everyone was sorry. My children were broken-hearted,
my friends were scared for themselves. I don’t
remember leaving the doctor’s office, and
I don’t remember driving home. My memories
of that day are gone, and in this my wife
and I are the same.
It has been four years now. Since then we
have made the best of it, if that is possible.
Allie organized, as was her disposition. She
made arrangements to leave the house and move
here. She rewrote her will and sealed it.
She left specific burial instructions, and
they sit in my desk, in the bottom drawer.
I have not seen them. And when she was finished,
she began to write. Letters to friends and
children. Letters to brothers and sisters
and cousins. Letters to nieces, nephews, and
neighbors. And a letter to me.
I read it sometimes when I am in the mood,
and when I do, I am reminded of Allie on cold
winter evenings, seated by a roaring fire
with a glass of wine at her side, reading
the letters I had written to her over the
years. She kept them, these letters, and now
I keep them, for she made me promise to do
so. She said I would know what to do with
them. She was right; I find I enjoy reading
bits and pieces of them just as she used to.
They intrigue me, these letters, for when
I sift through them I realize that romance
and passion are possible at any age. I see
Allie now and know I’ve never loved her
more, but as I read the letters, I come to
understand that I have always felt the same
way.
I read them last three evenings ago, long
after I should have been asleep. It was almost
two o’clock when I went to the desk and
found the stack of letters, thick and tall
and weathered. I untied the ribbon, itself
almost half a century old, and found the letters
her mother had hidden so long ago and those
from afterward. A lifetime of letters, letters
professing my love, letters from my heart.
I glanced through them with a smile on my
face, picking and choosing, and finally opened
a letter from our first anniversary.
I read an excerpt:
When I see you now—moving slowly with new
life growing inside you—I hope you know
how much you mean to me, and how special this
year has been. No man is more blessed than
me, and I love you with all my heart.
I put it aside, sifted through the stack,
and found another, this from a cold evening
thirty-nine years ago.
Sitting next to you, while our youngest daughter
sang off-key in the school Christmas show,
I looked at you and saw a pride that comes
only to those who feel deeply in their hearts,
and I knew that no man could be more lucky
than me.
And after our son died, the one who resembled
his mother . . . It was the hardest time we
ever went through, and the words still ring
true today:
In times of grief and sorrow I will hold you
and rock you, and take your grief and make
it my own. When you cry, I cry, and when you
hurt, I hurt. And together we will try to
hold back the floods of tears and despair
and make it through the potholed streets of
life.
I pause for just a moment, remembering him.
He was four years old at the time, just a
baby. I have lived twenty times as long as
he, but if asked, I would have traded my life
for his. It is a terrible thing to outlive
your child, a tragedy I wish upon no one.
I do my best to keep the tears away, sift
through some more to clear my mind, and find
the next from our twentieth anniversary, something
much easier to think about:
When I see you, my darling, in the morning
before showers or in your studio covered with
paint with hair matted and tired eyes, I know
that you are the most beautiful woman in the
world.
They went on, this correspondence of life
and love, and I read dozens more, some painful,
most heartwarming. By three o’clock I was
tired, but I had reached the bottom of the
stack. There was one letter remaining, the
last one I wrote her, and by then I knew I
had to keep going.
I lifted the seal and removed both pages.
I put the second page aside and moved the
first page into better light and began to
read:
My dearest Allie,
The porch is silent except for the sounds
that float from the shadows, and for once
I am at a loss for words. It is a strange
experience for me, for when I think of you
and the life we have shared, there is much
to remember. A lifetime of memories. But to
put it into words? I do not know if I am able.
I am not a poet, and yet a poem is needed
to fully express the way I feel about you.
So my mind drifts, and I remember thinking
about our life together as I made coffee this
morning. Kate was there, and so was Jane,
and they both became quiet when I walked in
the kitchen. I saw they’d been crying, and
without a word, I sat myself beside them at
the table and held their hands. And do you
know what I saw when I looked at them? I saw
you from so long ago, the day we said good-bye.
They resemble you and how you were then, beautiful
and sensitive and wounded with the hurt that
comes when something special is taken away.
And for a reason I’m not sure I understand,
I was inspired to tell them a story.
I called Jeff and David into the kitchen,
for they were here as well, and when the children
were ready, I told them about us and how you
came back to me so long ago. I told them about
our walk, and the crab dinner in the kitchen,
and they listened with smiles when they heard
about the canoe ride, and sitting in front
of the fire with the storm raging outside.
I told them about your mother warning us about
Lon the next day—they seemed as surprised
as we were—and yes, I even told them what
happened later that day, after you went back
to town.
That part of the story has never left me,
even after all this time. Even though I wasn’t
there, you described it to me only once, and
I remember marveling at the strength you showed
that day. I still cannot imagine what was
going through your mind when you walked into
the lobby and saw Lon, or how it must have
felt to talk to him. You told me that the
two of you left the inn and sat on a bench
by the old Methodist church, and that he held
your hand, even as you explained that you
must stay.
I know you cared for him. And his reaction
proves to me he cared for you as well. No,
he could not understand losing you, but how
could he? Even as you explained that you had
always loved me, and that it wouldn’t be
fair to him, he
did not release your hand. I know he was hurt
and angry, and tried for almost an hour to
change your mind, but when you stood firm
and said, “I can’t go back with you, I’m
so sorry,” he knew that your decision had
been made. You said he simply nodded and the
two of you sat together for a long time without
speaking. I have always wondered what he was
thinking as he sat with you, but I’m sure
it was the same way I felt only a few hours
before. And when he finally walked you to
your car, you said he told you that I was
a lucky man. He behaved as a gentleman would,
and I understood then why your choice was
so hard.
I remember that when I finished the story,
the room was quiet until Kate finally stood
to embrace me. “Oh, Daddy,” she said with
tears in her eyes, and though I expected to
answer their questions, they did not ask any.
Instead, they gave me something much more
special.
For the next four hours, each of them told
me how much we, the two of us, had meant to
them growing up. One by one, they told stories
about things I had long since forgotten. And
by the end, I was crying because I realized
how well we had done with raising them. I
was so proud of them, and proud of you, and
happy about the life we have led. And nothing
will ever take that away. Nothing. I only
wish you would have been here to enjoy it
with me.
After they left, I rocked in silence, thinking
back on our life together. You are always
here with me when I do so, at least in my
heart, and it is impossible for me to remember
a time when you were not a part of me. I do
not know who I would have become had you never
come back to me that day, but I have no doubt
that I would have lived and died with regrets
that thankfully I’ll never know.
I love you, Allie. I am who I am because of
you. You are every reason, every hope, and
every dream I’ve ever had, and no matter
what happens to us in the future, every day
we are together is the greatest day of my
life. I will always be yours.
And, my darling, you will always be mine.
Noah
I put the pages aside and remember sitting
with Allie on our porch when she read this
letter for the first time. It was late afternoon,
with red streaks cutting the summer sky, and
the last remnants of the day were fading.
The sky was slowly changing color, and as
I was watching the sun go down, I remember
thinking about that brief, flickering moment
when day suddenly turns into night.
Dusk, I realized then, is just an illusion,
because the sun is either above the horizon
or below it. And that means that day and night
are linked in a way that few things are; there
cannot be one without the other, yet they
cannot exist at the same time. How would it
feel, I remember wondering, to be always together,
yet forever apart?
Looking back, I find it ironic that she chose
to read the letter at the exact moment that
question popped into my head. It is ironic,
of course, because I know the answer now.
I know what it’s like to be day and night
now; always together, forever apart.
There is beauty where we sit this afternoon,
Allie and I. This is the pinnacle of my life.
They are here at the creek: the birds, the
geese, my friends. Their bodies float on the
cool water, which reflects bits and pieces
of their colors and make them seem larger
than they really are. Allie too is taken in
by their wonder, and little by little we get
to know each other again.
“It’s good to talk to you. I find that
I miss it, even when it hasn’t been that
long.”
I am sincere and she knows this, but she is
still wary. I am a stranger.
“Is this something we do often?” she asks.
“Do we sit here and watch the birds a lot?
I mean, do we know each other well?”
“Yes and no. I think everyone has secrets,
but we have been acquainted for years.”
She looks to her hands, then mine. She thinks
about this for a moment, her face at such
an angle that she looks young again. We do
not wear our rings. Again, there is a reason
for this. She asks:
“Were you ever married?”
I nod.
“Yes.”
“What was she like?”
I tell the truth.
“She was my dream. She made me who I am,
and holding her in my arms was more natural
to me than my own heartbeat. I think about
her all the time. Even now, when I’m sitting
here, I think about her. There could never
have been another.”
She takes this in. I don’t know how she
feels about this. Finally she speaks softly,
her voice angelic, sensual. I wonder if she
knows I think these things.
“Is she dead?”
What is death? I wonder, but I do not say
this. Instead I answer, “My wife is alive
in my heart. And she always will be.”
“You still love her, don’t you?”
“Of course. But I love many things. I love
to sit here with you. I love to share the
beauty of this place with someone I care about.
I love to watch the osprey swoop toward the
creek and find its dinner.”
She is quiet for a moment. She looks away
so I can’t see her face. It has been her
habit for years.
“Why are you doing this?” No fear, just
curiosity. This is good. I know what she means,
but I ask anyway.
“What?”
“Why are you spending the day with me?”
I smile.
“I’m here because this is where I’m
supposed to be. It’s not complicated. Both
you and I are enjoying ourselves. Don’t
dismiss my time with you—it’s not wasted.
It’s what I want. I sit here and we talk
and I think to myself, What could be better
than what I am doing now?”
She looks me in the eyes, and for a moment,
just a moment, her eyes twinkle. A slight
smile forms on her lips.
“I like being with you, but if getting me
intrigued is what you’re after, you’ve
succeeded. I admit I enjoy your company, but
I know nothing about you. I don’t expect
you to tell me your life story, but why are
you so mysterious?”
“I read once that women love mysterious
strangers.”
“See, you haven’t really answered the
question. You haven’t answered most of my
questions. You didn’t even tell me how the
story ended this morning.”
I shrug. We sit quietly for a while. Finally
I ask: “Is it true?”
“Is what true?”
“That women love mysterious strangers?”
She thinks about this and laughs. Then she
answers as I would:
“I think some women do.”
“Do you?”
“Now don’t go putting me on the spot.
I don’t know you well enough for that.”
She is teasing me, and I enjoy it.
We sit silently and watch the world around
us. This has taken us a lifetime to learn.
It seems only the old are able to sit next
to one another and not say anything and still
feel content. The young, brash and impatient,
must always break the silence. It is a waste,
for silence is pure. Silence is holy. It draws
people together because only those who are
comfortable with each other can sit without
speaking. This is the great paradox.
Time passes, and gradually our breathing begins
to coincide just as it did this morning. Deep
breaths, relaxed breaths, and there is a moment
when she dozes off, like those comfortable
with one another often do. I wonder if the
young are capable of enjoying this. Finally,
when she wakes, a miracle.
“Do you see that bird?” She points to
it, and I strain my eyes. It is a wonder I
can see it, but I can because the sun is bright.
I point, too.
“Caspian stern,” I say softly, and we
devote our attention to it and stare as it
glides over Brices Creek. And, like an old
habit rediscovered, when I lower my arm, I
put my hand on her knee and she doesn’t
make me move it.
She is right about my evasiveness. On days
like these, when only her memory is gone,
I am vague in my answers because I’ve hurt
my wife unintentionally with careless slips
of my tongue many times these past few years,
and I am determined not to let it happen again.
So I limit myself and answer only what is
asked, sometimes not too well, and I volunteer
nothing.
This is a split decision, both good and bad,
but necessary, for with knowledge comes pain.
To limit the pain I limit my answers. There
are days she never learns of her children
or that we are married. I am sorry for this,
but I will not change.
Does this make me dishonest? Perhaps, but
I have seen her crushed by the waterfall of
information that is her life. Could I look
myself in the mirror without red eyes and
quivering jaw and know I have forgotten all
that was important to me? I could not and
neither can she, for when this odyssey began,
this is how I began. Her life, her marriage,
her children. Her friends and her work. Questions
and answers in the game show format of This
Is Your Life.
The days were hard on both of us. I was an
encyclopedia, an object without feeling, of
the whos, whats and wheres in her life, when
in reality it is the whys, the things I did
not know and could not answer, that make it
all worthwhile. She would stare at pictures
of forgotten offspring, hold paintbrushes
that inspired nothing, and read love letters
that brought back no joy. She would weaken
over the hours, growing paler, becoming bitter,
and ending the day worse than when it began.
Our days were lost, and so was she. And selfishly,
so was I.
So I changed. I became Magellan or Columbus,
an explorer in the mysteries of the mind,
and I learned, bumbling and slow, but learning
nonetheless what had to be done. And I learned
what is obvious to a child. That life is simply
a collection of little lives, each lived one
day at a time. That each day should be spent
finding beauty in flowers and poetry and talking
to animals. That a day spent with dreaming
and sunsets and refreshing breezes cannot
be bettered. But most of all, I learned that
life is about sitting on benches next to ancient
creeks with my hand on her knee and sometimes,
on good days, for falling in love.
“What are you thinking?” she asks.
It is now dusk. We have left our bench and
are shuffling along lighted paths that wind
their way around this complex. She is holding
my arm, and I am her escort. It is her idea
to do this. Perhaps she is charmed by me.
Perhaps she wants to keep me from falling.
Either way, I am smiling to myself.
“I’m thinking about you.”
She makes no response to this except to squeeze
my arm, and I can tell she likes what I said.
Our life together has enabled me to see the
clues, even if she does not know them herself.
I go on:
“I know you can’t remember who you are,
but I can, and I find that when I look at
you, it makes me feel good.”
She taps my arm and smiles. “You’re a
kind man with a loving heart. I hope I enjoyed
you as much before as I do now.”
We walk some more. Finally she says, “I
have to tell you something.”
“Go ahead.”
“I think I have an admirer.”
“An admirer?”
“Yes.”
“I see.”
“You don’t believe me?”
“I believe you.”
“You should.”
“Why?”
“Because I think it is you.”
I think about this as we walk in silence,
holding each other, past the rooms, past the
courtyard. We come to the garden, mainly wildflowers,
and I stop her. I pick a bundle—red, pink,
yellow, violet. I give them to her, and she
brings them to her nose. She smells them with
eyes closed and she whispers, “They’re
beautiful.” We resume our walk, me in one
hand, the flowers in another. People watch
us, for we are a walking miracle, or so I
am told. It is true in a way, though most
times I do not feel lucky.
“You think it’s me?” I finally ask.
“Yes.”
“Why?”
“Because I have found what you have hidden.”
“What?”
“This,” she says, handing a small slip
of paper to me. “I found it under my pillow.”
I read it, and it says:
The body slows with mortal ache, yet my promise
remains true at the closing of our days,
A tender touch that ends with a kiss will
awaken love in joyous ways.
“Are there more?” I ask.
“I found this in the pocket of my coat.”
Our souls were one, if you must know and never
shall they be apart;
With splendid dawn, your face aglow
I reach for you and find my heart.
“I see,” and that is all I say.
We walk as the sun sinks lower in the sky.
In time, silver twilight is the only remainder
of the day, and still we talk of the poetry.
She is enthralled by the romance.
By the time we reach the doorway, I am tired.
She knows this, so she stops me with her hand
and makes me face her. I do and I realize
how hunched over I have become. She and I
are now level. Sometimes I am glad she doesn’t
know how much I have changed. She turns to
me and stares for a long time.
“What are you doing?” I ask.
“I don’t want to forget you or this day,
and I’m trying to keep your memory alive.”
Will it work this time? I wonder, then know
it will not. It can’t. I do not tell her
my thoughts, though. I smile instead because
her words are sweet.
“Thank you,” I say.
“I mean it. I don’t want to forget you
again. You’re very special to me. I don’t
know what I would have done without you today.”
My throat closes a little. There is emotion
behind her words, the emotions I feel whenever
I think of her. I know this is why I live,
and I love her dearly at this moment. How
I wish I were strong enough to carry her in
my arms to paradise.
“Don’t try to say anything,” she tells
me. “Let’s just feel the moment.”
And I do, and I feel heaven.
Her disease is worse now than it was in the
beginning, though Allie is different from
most. There are three others with the disease
here, and these three are the sum of my practical
experience with it. They, unlike Allie, are
in the most advanced stages of Alzheimer’s
and are almost completely lost. They wake
up hallucinating and confused. They repeat
themselves over and over. Two of the three
can’t feed themselves and will die soon.
The third has a tendency to wander and get
lost. She was found once in a stranger’s
car a quarter mile away. Since then she has
been strapped to the bed. All can be very
bitter at times, and at other times they can
be like lost children, sad and alone. Seldom
do they recognize the staff or people who
love them. It is a trying disease, and this
is why it is hard for their children and mine
to visit.
Allie, of course, has her own problems, too,
problems that will probably grow worse over
time. She is terribly afraid in the mornings
and cries inconsolably. She sees tiny people,
like gnomes, I think, watching her, and she
screams at them to get away. She bathes willingly
but will not eat regularly. She is thin now,
much too thin, in my opinion, and on good
days I do my best to fatten her up.
But this is where the similarity ends. This
is why Allie is considered a miracle, because
sometimes, just sometimes, after I read to
her, her condition isn’t so bad. There is
no explanation for this. “It’s impossible,”
the doctors say. “She must not have Alzheimer’s.”
But she does. On most days and every morning
there can be no doubt. On this there is agreement.
But why, then, is her condition different?
Why does she sometimes change after I read?
I tell the doctors the reason—I know it
in my heart, but I am not believed. Instead
they look to science. Four times specialists
have traveled from Chapel Hill to find the
answer. Four times they have left without
understanding. I tell them, “You can’t
possibly understand it if you use only your
training and your books,” but they shake
their heads and answer: “Alzheimer’s does
not work like this. With her condition, it’s
just not possible to have a conversation or
improve as the day goes on. Ever.”
But she does. Not every day, not most of the
time, and definitely less than she used to.
But sometimes. And all that is gone on these
days is her memory, as if she has amnesia.
But her emotions are normal, her thoughts
are normal. And these are the days that I
know I am doing right.
Dinner is waiting in her room when we return.
It has been arranged for us to eat here, as
it always is on days like these, and once
again I could ask for no more. The people
here take care of everything. They are good
to me, and I am thankful.
The lights are dimmed, the room is lit by
two candles on the table where we will sit,
and music is playing softly in the background.
The cups and plates are plastic, and the carafe
is filled with apple juice, but rules are
rules and she doesn’t seem to care. She
inhales slightly at the sight. Her eyes are
wide.
“Did you do this?”
I nod and she walks in the room.
“It looks beautiful.”
I offer my arm in escort and lead her to the
window. She doesn’t release it when we get
there. Her touch is nice, and we stand close
together on this crystal springtime evening.
The window is open slightly, and I feel a
breeze as it fans my cheek. The moon has risen,
and we watch for a long time as the evening
sky unfolds.
“I’ve never seen anything so beautiful,
I’m sure of it,” she says, and I agree
with her.
“I haven’t, either,” I say, but I am
looking at her. She knows what I mean, and
I see her smile. A moment later she whispers:
“I think I know who Allie went with at the
end of the story,” she says.
“You do?”
“Yes.”
“Who?”
“She went with Noah.”
“You’re sure?”
“Absolutely.”
I smile and nod. “Yes, she did,” I say
softly, and she smiles back. Her face is radiant.
I pull out her chair with some effort. She
sits and I sit opposite her. She offers her
hand across the table, and I take it in mine,
and I feel her thumb begin to move as it did
so many years ago. Without speaking, I stare
at her for a long time, living and reliving
the moments of my life, remembering it all
and making it real. I feel my throat begin
to tighten, and once again I realize how much
I love her. My voice is shaky when I finally
speak.
“You’re so beautiful,” I say. I can
see in her eyes that she knows how I feel
about her and what I really mean by my words.
She does not respond. Instead she lowers her
eyes and I wonder what she’s thinking. She
gives me no clues, and I gently squeeze her
hand. I wait. With all my dreams, I know her
heart, and I know I’m almost there.
And then, a miracle that proves me right.
As Glenn Miller plays softly in a candlelit
room, I watch as she gradually gives in to
the feelings inside her. I see a warm smile
begin to form on her lips, the kind that makes
it all worthwhile, and I watch as she raises
her hazy eyes to mine. She pulls my hand toward
her.
“You’re wonderful. . . .” she says softly,
trailing off, and at that moment she falls
in love with me, too; this I know, for I have
seen the signs a thousand times.
She says nothing else right away, she doesn’t
have to, and she gives me a look from another
lifetime that makes me whole again. I smile
back, with as much passion as I can muster,
and we stare at each other with the feelings
inside us rolling like ocean waves. I look
around the room, then up to the ceiling, then
back at Allie, and the way she’s looking
at me makes me warm. And suddenly I feel young
again. I’m no longer cold or aching, or
hunched over or deformed, or almost blind
with cataractal eyes.
I’m strong and proud, and the luckiest man
alive, and I keep on feeling that way for
a long time across the table.
By the time the candles have burned down a
third, I am ready to break the silence. I
say, “I love you deeply, and I hope you
know that.”
“Of course I do,” she says breathlessly.
“I’ve always loved you, Noah.”
Noah, I hear again. Noah. The word echoes
in my head. Noah . . . Noah. She knows, I
think to myself, she knows who I am. . . .
She knows. . . .
Such a tiny thing, this knowledge, but for
me it is a gift from God, and I feel our lifetime
together, holding her, loving her, and being
with her through the best years of my life.
She murmurs, “Noah . . . my sweet Noah . . .” And
I, who could not accept the doctor’s words,
have triumphed again, at least for a moment.
I give up the pretense of mystery, and I kiss
her hand and bring it to my cheek and whisper
in her ear. I say:
“You are the greatest thing that has ever
happened to me.”
“Oh . . . Noah,” she says with tears in
her eyes, “I love you, too.”
If only it would end like this, I would be
a happy man.
But it won’t. Of this I’m sure, for as
time slips by, I begin to see the signs of
concern in her face.
“What’s wrong?” I ask, and her answer
comes softly.
“I’m so afraid. I’m afraid of forgetting
you again. It isn’t fair ...I just can’t
bear to give this up.”
Her voice breaks as she finishes, but I don’t
know what to say. I know the evening is coming
to an end, and there is nothing I can do to
stop the inevitable. In this I am a failure.
I finally tell her:
“I’ll never leave you. What we have is
forever.” She knows this is all I can do,
for neither of us wants empty promises. But
I can tell by the way she is looking at me
that once again she wishes there were more.
The crickets serenade us, and we begin to
pick at our dinner. Neither one of us is hungry,
but I lead by example and she follows me.
She takes small bites and chews a long time,
but I am glad to see her eat. She has lost
too much weight in the past three months.
After dinner, I become afraid despite myself.
I know I should be joyous, for this reunion
is the proof that love can still be ours,
but I know the bell has tolled this evening.
The sun has long since set and the thief is
about to come, and there is nothing I can
do to stop it. So I stare at her and wait
and live a lifetime in these last remaining
moments.
Nothing.
The clock ticks.
I take her in my arms and we hold each other.
Nothing.
I feel her tremble and I whisper in her ear.
I tell her for the last time this evening
that I love her.
And the thief comes.
It always amazes me how quickly it happens.
Even now, after all this time. For as she
holds me, she begins to blink rapidly and
shake her head. Then, turning toward the corner
of the room, she stares for a long time, concern
etched on her face.
No! my mind screams. Not yet! Not now ...not
when we’re so close! Not tonight! Any night
but tonight. . . . Please! The words are inside
me. I can’t take it again! It isn’t fair
. . . it isn’t fair....
But once again, it is to no avail.
“Those people,” she finally says, pointing,
“are staring at me. Please make them stop.”
The gnomes.
A pit rises in my stomach, hard and full.
My breathing stops for a moment, then starts
again, this time shallower. My mouth goes
dry, and I feel my heart pounding. It is over,
I know, and I am right. The sundowning has
come. This, the evening confusion associated
with Alzheimer’s disease that affects my
wife, is the hardest part of all. For when
it comes, she is gone, and sometimes I wonder
whether she and I will ever love again.
“There’s no one there, Allie,” I say,
trying to fend off the inevitable. She doesn’t
believe me.
“They’re staring at me.”
“No,” I whisper while shaking my head.
“You can’t see them?”
“No,” I say, and she thinks for a moment.
“Well, they’re right there,” she says,
pushing me away, “and they’re staring
at me.”
With that, she begins to talk to herself,
and moments later, when I try to comfort her,
she flinches with wide eyes.
“Who are you?” she cries with panic in
her voice, her face becoming whiter. “What
are you doing here?” There is fear growing
inside her, and I hurt, for there is nothing
I can do. She moves farther from me, backing
away, her hands in a defensive position, and
then she says the most heartbreaking words
of all.
“Go away! Stay away from me!” she screams.
She is pushing the gnomes away from her, terrified,
now oblivious of my presence.
I stand and cross the room to her bed. I am
weak now, my legs ache, and there is a strange
pain in my side. I don’t know where it comes
from. It is a struggle to press the button
to call the nurses, for my fingers are throbbing
and seem frozen together, but I finally succeed.
They will be here soon now, I know, and I
wait for them. While I wait, I stare at my
wife.
Ten...
Twenty . . .
Thirty seconds pass, and I continue to stare,
my eyes missing nothing, remembering the moments
we just shared together. But in all that time
she does not look back, and I am haunted by
the visions of her struggling with unseen
enemies.
I sit by the bedside with an aching back and
start to cry as I pick up the notebook. Allie
does not notice. I understand, for her mind
is gone.
A couple of pages fall to the floor, and I
bend over to pick them up. I am tired now,
so I sit, alone and apart from my wife. And
when the nurses come in they see two people
they must comfort. A woman shaking in fear
from demons in her mind, and the old man who
loves her more deeply than life itself, crying
softly in the corner, his face in his hands.
I spend the rest of the evening alone in my
room. My door is partially open and I see
people walk by, some strangers, some friends,
and if I concentrate, I can hear them talking
about families, jobs, and visits to parks.
Ordinary conversations, nothing more, but
I find that I envy them and the ease of their
communication. Another deadly sin, I know,
but sometimes I can’t help it.
Dr. Barnwell is here, too, speaking with one
of the nurses, and I wonder who is ill enough
to warrant such a visit at this hour. He works
too much, I tell him. Spend the time with
your family, I say, they won’t be around
forever. But he doesn’t listen to me. He
cares for his patients, he says, and must
come here when called. He says he has no choice,
but this makes him a man torn by contradiction.
He wants to be a doctor completely devoted
to his patients and a man completely devoted
to his family. He cannot be both, for there
aren’t enough hours, but he has yet to learn
this. I wonder, as his voice fades into the
background, which he will choose or whether,
sadly, the choice will be made for him.
I sit by the window in an easy chair and I
think about today. It was happy and sad, wonderful
and heart-wrenching. My conflicting emotions
keep me silent for many hours. I did not read
to anyone this evening; I could not, for poetic
introspection would bring me to tears. In
time, the hallways become quiet except for
the footfalls of evening soldiers. At eleven
o’clock I hear the familiar sounds that
for some reason I expected. The footsteps
I know so well.
Dr. Barnwell peeks in.
“I noticed your light was on. Do you mind
if I come in?”
“No,” I say, shaking my head.
He comes in and looks around the room before
taking a seat a few feet from me.
“I hear,” he says, “you had a good day
with Allie.” He smiles. He is intrigued
by us and the relationship we have. I do not
know if his interest is entirely professional.
“I suppose so.”
He cocks his head at my answer and looks at
me. “You okay, Noah? You look a little down.”
“I’m fine. Just a little tired.”
“How was Allie today?”
“She was okay. We talked for almost four
hours.” “Four hours? Noah, that’s . . . incredible.”
I can only nod. He goes on, shaking his head.
“I’ve never seen anything like it, or
even heard about it. I guess that’s what
love is all about. You two were meant for
each other. She must love you very much. You
know that, don’t you?”
“I know,” I say, but I can’t say anything
more. “What’s really bothering you, Noah?
Did Allie say or do something that hurt your
feelings?”
“No. She was wonderful, actually. It’s
just that right now I feel . . . alone.”
“Alone?”
“Yes.”
“Nobody’s alone.”
“I’m alone,” I say as I look at my watch
and think of his family sleeping in a quiet
house, the place he should be, “and so are
you.”
The next few days passed without significance.
Allie was unable to recognize me at any time,
and I admit my attention waned now and then,
for most of my thoughts were of the day we
had just spent. Though the end always comes
too soon, there was nothing lost that day,
only gained, and I was happy to have received
this blessing once again.
By the following week, my life had pretty
much returned to normal. Or at least as normal
as my life can be. Reading to Allie, reading
to others, wandering the halls. Lying awake
at night and sitting by my heater in the morning.
I find a strange comfort in the predictability
of my life.
On a cool, foggy morning eight days after
she and I had spent our day together, I woke
early, as is my custom, and puttered around
my desk, alternately looking at photographs
and reading letters written many years before.
At least I tried to. I couldn’t concentrate
too well because I had a headache, so I put
them aside and went to sit in my chair by
the window to watch the sun come up. Allie
would be awake in a couple of hours, I knew,
and I wanted to be refreshed, for reading
all day would only make my head hurt more.
I closed my eyes for a few minutes while my
head alternately pounded and subsided. Then,
opening them, I watched my old friend, the
creek, roll by my window. Unlike Allie, I
had been given a room where I could see it,
and it has never failed to inspire me. It
is a contradiction—this creek—a hundred
thousand years old but renewed with each rainfall.
I talked to it that morning, whispered so
it could hear, “You are blessed, my friend,
and I am blessed, and together we meet the
coming days.” The ripples and waves circled
and twisted in agreement, the pale glow of
morning light reflecting the world we share.
The creek and I. Flowing, ebbing, receding.
It is life, I think, to watch the water. A
man can learn so many things.
It happened as I sat in the chair, just as
the sun first peeked over the horizon. My
hand, I noticed, started to tingle, something
it had never done before. I started to lift
it, but I was forced to stop when my head
pounded again, this time hard, almost as if
I had been hit in the head with a hammer.
I closed my eyes, then squeezed my lids tight.
My hand stopped tingling and began to go numb,
quickly, as if my nerves were suddenly severed
somewhere on my lower arm. My wrist locked
as a shooting pain rocked my head and seemed
to flow down my neck and into every cell of
my body, like a tidal wave, crushing and wasting
everything in its path.
I lost my sight, and I heard what sounded
like a train roaring inches from my head,
and I knew that I was having a stroke. The
pain coursed through my body like a lightning
bolt, and in my last remaining moments of
consciousness, I pictured Allie, lying in
her bed, waiting for the story I would never
read, lost and confused, completely and totally
unable to help herself. Just like me.
And as my eyes closed for the final time,
I thought to myself, Oh God, what have I done?
I was unconscious on and off for days, and
in those moments when I was awake, I found
myself hooked to machines, tubes up my nose
and down my throat and two bags of fluid hanging
near the bed. I could hear the faint hum of
machines, droning on and off, sometimes making
sounds I could not recognize. One machine,
beeping with my heart rate, was strangely
soothing, and I found myself lulled to never-land
time and time again.
The doctors were worried. I could see the
concern in their faces through squinted eyes
as they scanned the charts and adjusted the
machines. They whispered their thoughts, thinking
I couldn’t hear. “Strokes could be serious,”
they’d say, “especially for someone his
age, and the consequences could be severe.”
Grim faces would prelude their predictions—“loss
of speech, loss of movement, paralysis.”
Another chart notation, another beep of a
strange machine, and they’d leave, never
knowing I heard every word. I tried not to
think of these things afterward but instead
concentrated on Allie, bringing a picture
of her to my mind whenever I could. I did
my best to bring her life into mine, to make
us one again. I tried to feel her touch, hear
her voice, see her face, and when I did tears
would fill my eyes because I didn’t know
if I would be able to hold her again, to whisper
to her, to spend the day with her talking
and reading and walking. This was not how
I’d imagined, or hoped, it would end. I’d
always assumed I would go last. This wasn’t
how it was supposed to be.
I drifted in and out of consciousness for
days until another foggy morning when my promise
to Allie spurred my body once again. I opened
my eyes and saw a room full of flowers, and
their scent motivated me further. I looked
for the buzzer, struggled to press it, and
a nurse arrived thirty seconds later, followed
closely by Dr. Barnwell, who smiled almost
immediately.
“I’m thirsty,” I said with a raspy voice,
and Dr. Barnwell smiled broadly.
“Welcome back,” he said, “I knew you’d
make it.”
Two weeks later I am able to leave the hospital,
though I am only half a man now. If I were
a Cadillac, I would drive in circles, one
wheel turning, for the right side of my body
is weaker than the left. This, they tell me,
is good news, for the paralysis could have
been total. Sometimes, it seems, I am surrounded
by optimists.
The bad news is that my hands prevent me from
using either cane or wheelchair, so I must
now march to my own unique cadence to keep
upright. Not left-right-left as was common
in my youth, or even the shuffle-shuffle of
late, but rather slow-shuffle, slide-the-right,
slow-shuffle. I am an epic adventure now when
I travel the halls. It is slow going even
for me, this coming from a man who could barely
outpace a turtle two weeks ago.
It is late when I return, and when I reach
my room, I know I will not sleep. I breathe
deeply and smell the springtime fragrances
that filter through my room. The window has
been left open, and there is a slight chill
in the air. I find that I am invigorated by
the change in temperature. Evelyn, one of
the many nurses here who is one-third my age,
helps me to the chair that sits by the window
and begins to close it. I stop her, and though
her eyebrows rise, she accepts my decision.
I hear a drawer open, and a moment later a
sweater is draped over my shoulders. She adjusts
it as if I were a child, and when she is finished,
she puts her hand on my shoulder and pats
it gently. She says nothing as she does this,
and by her silence I know that she is staring
out the window. She does not move for a long
time, and I wonder what she is thinking, but
I do not ask. Eventually I hear her sigh.
She turns to leave, and as she does, she stops,
leans forward, and then kisses me on the cheek,
tenderly, the way my granddaughter does. I
am surprised by this, and she says quietly,
“It’s good to have you back. Allie’s
missed you and so have the rest of us. We
were all praying for you because it’s just
not the same around here when you’re gone.”
She smiles at me and touches my face before
she leaves. I say nothing. Later I hear her
walk by again, pushing a cart, talking to
another nurse, their voices hushed.
The stars are out tonight, and the world is
glowing an eerie blue. The crickets are singing,
and their sound drowns out everything else.
As I sit, I wonder if anyone outside can see
me, this prisoner of flesh. I search the trees,
the courtyard, the benches near the geese,
looking for signs of life, but there is nothing.
Even the creek is still. In the darkness it
looks like empty space, and I find that I’m
drawn to its mystery. I watch for hours, and
as I do, I see the reflection of clouds as
they begin to bounce off the water. A storm
is coming, and in time the sky will turn silver,
like dusk again.
Lightning cuts the wild sky, and I feel my
mind drift back. Who are we, Allie and I?
Are we ancient ivy on a cypress tree, tendrils
and branches intertwined so closely that we
would both die if we were forced apart? I
don’t know. Another bolt and the table beside
me is lit enough to see a picture of Allie,
the best one I have. I had it framed years
ago in the hope that the glass would make
it last forever. I reach for it and hold it
inches from my face. I stare at it for a long
time, I can’t help it. She was forty-one
when it was taken, and she had never been
more beautiful. There are so many things I
want to ask her, but I know the picture won’t
answer, so I put it aside.
Tonight, with Allie down the hall, I am alone.
I will always be alone. This I thought as
I lay in the hospital. This I’m sure of
as I look out the window and watch the storm
clouds appear. Despite myself I am saddened
by our plight, for I realize that the last
day we were together I never kissed her lips.
Perhaps I never will again. It is impossible
to tell with this disease. Why do I think
such things?
I finally stand and walk to my desk and turn
on the lamp. This takes more effort than I
think it will, and I am strained, so I do
not return to the window seat. I sit down
and spend a few minutes looking at the pictures
that sit on my desk. Family pictures, pictures
of children and vacations. Pictures of Allie
and me. I think back to the times we shared
together, alone or with family, and once again
I realize how ancient I am.
I open a drawer and find the flowers I’d
once given her long ago, old and faded and
tied together with ribbon. They, like me,
are dry and brittle and difficult to handle
without breaking. But she saved them. “I
don’t understand what you want with them,”
I would say, but she would just ignore me.
And sometimes in the evenings I would see
her holding them, almost reverently, as if
they offered the secret of life itself. Women.
Since this seems to be a night of memories,
I look for and find my wedding ring. It is
in the top drawer, wrapped in tissue. I cannot
wear it anymore because my knuckles are swollen
and my fingers lack for blood. I unwrap the
tissue and find it unchanged. It is powerful,
a symbol, a circle, and I know, I know, there
could never have been another. I knew it then,
and I know it now. And in that moment I whisper
aloud, “I am still yours, Allie, my queen,
my timeless beauty. You are, and always have
been, the best thing in my life.”
I wonder if she hears me when I say this,
and I wait for a sign. But there is nothing.
It is eleven-thirty and I look for the letter
she wrote me, the one I read when the mood
strikes me. I find it where I last left it.
I turn it over a couple of times before I
open it, and when I do my hands begin to tremble.
Finally I read:
Dear Noah,
I write this letter by candlelight as you
lie sleeping in the bedroom we have shared
since the day we were married. And though
I can’t hear the soft sounds of your slumber,
I know you are there, and soon I will be lying
next to you again as I always have. And I
will feel your warmth and your comfort, and
your breaths will slowly guide me to the place
where I dream of you and the wonderful man
you are.
I see the flame beside me and it reminds me
of another fire from decades ago, with me
in your soft clothes and you in your jeans.
I knew then we would always be together, even
though I wavered the following day. My heart
had been captured, roped by a southern poet,
and I knew inside that it had always been
yours. Who was I to question a love that rode
on shooting stars and roared like crashing
waves? For that is what it was between us
then and that is what it is today.
I remember coming back to you the next day,
the day my mother visited. I was so scared,
more scared than I had ever been because I
was sure you would never forgive me for leaving
you. I was shaking as I got out of the car,
but you took it all away with your smile and
the way you held your hand out to me. “How
’bout some coffee,” was all you said.
And you never brought it up again. In all
our years together.
Nor did you question me when I would leave
and walk alone the next few days. And when
I came in with tears in my eyes, you always
knew whether I needed you to hold me or to
just let me be. I don’t know how you knew,
but you did, and you made it easier for me.
Later when we went to the small chapel and
traded our rings and made our vows, I looked
in your eyes and knew I had made the right
decision. But more than that, I knew I was
foolish for ever
considering someone else. I have never wavered
since.
We had a wonderful life together, and I think
about it a lot now. I close my eyes sometimes
and see you with speckles of gray in your
hair, sitting on the porch and playing your
guitar while little ones play and clap to
the music you create. Your clothes are stained
from hours of work and you are tired, and
though I offer you time to relax, you smile
and say, “That’s what I am doing now.”
I find your love for our children very sensual
and exciting. “You’re a better father
than you know,” I tell you later, after
the children are sleeping. Soon after, we
peel off our clothes and kiss each other and
almost lose ourselves before we are able to
slip between the flannel sheets.
I love you for many things, especially your
passions, for they have always been those
things which are most beautiful in life. Love
and poetry and fatherhood and friendship and
beauty and nature. And I am glad you have
taught the children these things, for I know
their lives are better for it. They tell me
how special you are to them, and every time
they do, it makes me feel like the luckiest
woman alive.
You have taught me as well, and inspired me,
and supported me in my painting, and you will
never know how much it has meant to me. My
works hang in museums and private collections
now, and though there have been times when
I was frazzled and distracted because of shows
and critics, you were always there with kind
words, encouraging me. You understood my need
for my own studio, my own space, and saw beyond
the paint on my clothes and in my hair and
sometimes on the furniture. I know it was
not easy. It takes a man to do that, Noah,
to live with something like that. And you
have. For forty-five years now. Wonderful
years.
You are my best friend as well as my lover,
and I do not know which side of you I enjoy
the most. I treasure each side, just as I
have treasured our life together. You have
something inside you, Noah, something beautiful
and strong. Kindness, that’s what I see
when I look at you now, that’s what everyone
sees. Kindness. You are the most forgiving
and peaceful man I know. God is with you,
He must be, for you are the closest thing
to an angel that I’ve ever met.
I know you thought me crazy for making us
write our story before we finally leave our
home, but I have my reasons and I thank you
for your patience. And though you asked, I
never told you why, but now I think it is
time you knew.
We have lived a lifetime most couples never
know, and yet, when I look at you, I am frightened
by the knowledge that all this will be ending
soon. For we both know my prognosis and
what it will mean to us. I see your tears
and I worry more about you than I do about
me, because I fear the pain I know you will
go through. There are no words to express
my sorrow for this, and I am at a loss for
words.
So I love you so deeply, so incredibly much,
that I will find a way to come back to you
despite my disease, I promise you that. And
this is where the story comes in. When I am
lost and lonely, read this story—just as
you told it to the children—and know that
in some way, I will realize it’s about us.
And perhaps, just perhaps, we will find a
way to be together again.
Please don’t be angry with me on days I
do not remember you, and we both know they
will come. Know that I love you, that I always
will, and that no matter what happens, know
I have led the greatest life possible. My
life with you.
And if you save this letter to read again,
then believe what I am writing for you now.
Noah, wherever you are and whenever this is,
I love you. I love you now as I write this,
and I love you now as you read this. And I
am so sorry if I am not able to tell you.
I love you deeply, my husband. You are, and
always have been, my dream.
Allie
When I am finished with the letter, I put
it aside. I rise from my desk and find my
slippers. They are near my bed, and I must
sit to put them on. Then, standing, I cross
the room and open my door. I peek down the
hall and see Janice seated at the main desk.
At least I think it is Janice. I must pass
this desk to get to Allie’s room, but at
this hour I am not supposed to leave my room,
and Janice has never been one to bend the
rules. Her husband is a lawyer.
I wait to see if she will leave, but she does
not seem to be moving, and I grow impatient.
I finally exit my room anyway, slow-shuffle,
slide-the-right, slow-shuffle. It takes aeons
to close the distance, but for some reason
she does not see me approaching. I am a silent
panther creeping through the jungle, I am
as invisible as baby pigeons.
In the end I am discovered, but I am not surprised.
I stand before her.
“Noah,” she says, “what are you doing?”
“I’m taking a walk,” I say. “I can’t
sleep.”
“You know you’re not supposed to do this.”
“I know.”
I don’t move, though. I am determined.
“You’re not really going for a walk, are
you? You’re going to see Allie.”
“Yes,” I answer.
“Noah, you know what happened the last time
you saw her at night.”
“I remember.”
“Then you know you shouldn’t be doing
this.”
I don’t answer directly. Instead I say,
“I miss her.” “I know you do, but I
can’t let you see her.”
“It’s our anniversary,” I say. This
is true. It is one year before gold. Forty-nine
years today.
“I see.”
“Then I can go?”
She looks away for a moment, and her voice
changes. Her voice is softer now, and I am
surprised. She has never struck me as the
sentimental type.
“Noah, I’ve worked here for five years
and I worked at another home before that.
I’ve seen hundreds of couples struggle with
grief and sadness, but I’ve never seen anyone
handle it like you do. No one around here,
not the doctors, not the nurses, has ever
seen anything like it.”
She pauses for just a moment, and strangely,
her eyes begin to fill with tears. She wipes
them with her finger and goes on:
“I try to think what it’s like for you,
how you keep going day after day, but I can’t
even imagine it. I don’t know how you do
it. You even beat her disease sometimes. Even
though the doctors don’t understand it,
we nurses do. It’s love, it’s as simple
as that. It’s the most incredible thing
I’ve ever seen.”
A lump has risen in my throat, and I am speechless.
“But Noah, you’re not supposed to do this,
and I can’t let you. So go back to your
room.” Then, smiling softly and sniffling
and shuffling some papers on the desk, she
says: “Me, I’m going downstairs for some
coffee. I won’t be back to check on you
for a while, so don’t do anything foolish.”
She rises quickly, touches my arm, and walks
toward the stairs. She doesn’t look back,
and suddenly I am alone. I don’t know what
to think. I look at where she had been sitting
and see her coffee, a full cup, still steaming,
and once again I learn that there are good
people in the world.
I am warm for the first time in years as I
begin my trek to Allie’s room. I take steps
the size of Pixie straws, and even at that
pace it is dangerous, for my legs have grown
tired already. I find I must touch the wall
to keep from falling down. Lights buzz overhead,
their fluorescent glow making my eyes ache,
and I squint a little. I walk by a dozen darkened
rooms, rooms where I have read before, and
I realize I miss the people inside. They are
my friends, whose faces I know so well, and
I will see them all tomorrow. But not tonight,
for there is no time to stop on this journey.
I press on, and the movement forces blood
through banished arteries. I feel myself becoming
stronger with every step. I hear a door open
behind me, but I don’t hear footsteps, and
I keep going. I am a stranger now. I cannot
be stopped. A phone rings in the nurses’
station, and I push forward so I will not
be caught. I am a midnight bandit, masked
and fleeing on horseback from sleepy desert
towns, charging into yellow moons with gold
dust in my saddlebags. I am young and strong
with passion in my heart, and I will break
down the door and lift her in my arms and
carry her to paradise.
Who am I kidding?
I lead a simple life now. I am foolish, an
old man in love, a dreamer who dreams of nothing
but reading to Allie and holding her whenever
I can. I am a sinner with many faults and
a man who believes in magic, but I am too
old to change and too old to care.
When I finally reach her room my body is weak.
My legs wobble, my eyes are blurred, and my
heart is beating funny inside my chest. I
struggle with the knob, and in the end it
takes two hands and three truckloads of effort.
The door opens and light from the hallway
spills in, illuminating the bed where she
sleeps. I think, as I see her, I am nothing
but a passerby on a busy city street, forgotten
forever.
Her room is quiet, and she is lying with the
covers halfway up. After a moment I see her
roll to one side, and her noises bring back
memories of happier times. She looks small
in her bed, and as I watch her I know it is
over between us. The air is stale and I shiver.
This place has become our tomb.
I do not move, on this our anniversary, for
almost a minute, and I long to tell her how
I feel, but I stay quiet so I won’t wake
her. Besides, it is written on the slip of
paper that I will slide under her pillow.
It says:
Love, in these last and tender hours is sensitive
and very pure
Come morning light with soft-lit powers to
awaken love that’s ever sure.
I think I hear someone coming, so I enter
her room and close the door behind me. Blackness
descends and I cross her floor from memory
and reach the window. I open the curtains,
and the moon stares back, large and full,
the guardian of the evening. I turn to Allie
and dream a thousand dreams, and though I
know I should not, I sit on her bed while
I slip the note beneath her pillow. Then I
reach across and gently touch her face, soft
like powder. I stroke her hair, and my breath
is taken away. I feel wonder, I feel awe,
like a composer first discovering the works
of Mozart. She stirs and opens her eyes, squinting
softly, and I suddenly regret my foolishness,
for I know she will begin to cry and scream,
for this is what she always does. I am impulsive
and weak, this I know, but I feel an urge
to attempt the impossible and I lean toward
her, our faces drawing closer.
And when her lips meet mine, I feel a strange
tingling I have never felt before, in all
our years together, but I do not pull back.
And suddenly, a miracle, for I feel her mouth
open and I discover a forgotten paradise,
unchanged all this time, ageless like the
stars. I feel the warmth of her body, and
as our tongues meet, I allow myself to slip
away, as I had so many years ago. I close
my eyes and become a mighty ship in churning
waters, strong and fearless, and she is my
sails. I gently trace the outline of her cheek,
then take her hand in mine. I kiss her lips,
her cheeks, and listen as she takes a breath.
She murmurs softly, “Oh, Noah . . . I’ve
missed you.” Another miracle—the greatest
of all!—and there’s no way I can stop
the tears as we begin to slip toward heaven
itself. For at that moment, the world is full
of wonder as I feel her fingers reach for
the buttons on my shirt and slowly, ever so
slowly, she begins to undo them one by one.