CHAPTER ONE
MIRACLES
WHO AM I?
And how, I wonder, will this story end?
The sun has come up and I am sitting by a
window that is foggy with the breath of a
life gone by.
I'm a sight this morning: two shirts, heavy
pants, a scarf around my neck and a thick
sweater knitted by my daughter thirty birthdays
ago.
Still my body shivers with a cold that will
never go away, because I am eighty years old.
Eighty years.
I wonder if this is how it is for everyone
my age.
I am nothing special, of this, I am sure.
I am a common man with common thoughts, and
I've led a common life.
There are no monuments dedicated to me and
my name will soon be forgotten, but I've loved
another with all my heart and soul, and to
me this has always been enough.
The romantics would call this a love story;
the cynics would call it a tragedy.
In my mind it's a little bit of both, and
no matter how you choose to view it in the
end, it does not change the fact that it involves
a great deal of my life.
I have no complaints about the path I have
chosen to follow and the places it has taken
me - the path has always been the right one.
I cough, and
through squinted eyes, I check my watch.
I realize it is time to go.
I stand and shuffle across the room stopping
at the desk to pick up the notebook I have
read a hundred times.
I put it beneath my arm and continue on my
way to the place I must go.
I walk on tiled floors.
I'm the only one in the hallway this morning.
They are in their rooms, alone except for
television, but they, like me, are used to
it.
A person can get used to anything, if there
is enough time.
I hear the sounds of crying in the distance
and know who is making them.
The nurses see me, and we smile and exchange
greetings.
I am sure they wonder about me and the things
that I go through every day.
I listen as they begin to whisper among themselves
when I pass.
"There he goes again."
I hear.
"I hope it turns out well."
But they say nothing directly to me about
it.
A minute later, I reach the room.
The door is open for me, as usual.
There are two nurses in the room, and as I
enter they say "Good morning" with cheery
voices, and I take a moment to ask about the
kids and the schools and upcoming vacations.
We talk above the crying for a minute or so.
It seems they do not notice it: they have
become numb to it, and so have I.
Afterwards I sit in the chair.
They are finishing up now; her clothes are
on, but she is crying.
It will become quieter after they leave.
I know.
The excitement of the morning always upsets
her, and today is no exception.
Finally, the nurses walk out.
Both of them touch me and smile as they walk
by.
I sit for just a second and stare at her,
but she doesn't return the look.
I understand, for she doesn't know who I am.
I'm a stranger to her.
Then, turning away, I bow my head and pray
silently for the strength I know
I will need.
Ready now.
On go the glasses, out of my pocket comes
a magnifier.
There is always a moment right before I begin
to read the story when I wonder if it will
happen today.
I don't know, for I never know beforehand
and deep down it really doesn't matter.
It's the possibility that keeps me going.
And though you may call me a dreamer or a
fool, I believe that anything is possible.
I realize that science is against me.
But science is not the total answer.
This I know, this I have learned in my lifetime.
And that leaves me with the belief that miracles,
no matter how inexplicable or unbelievable,
are real and can occur without regard to the
natural order of things.
So once again, just as I do every day, I begin
to read the notebook aloud, so that she can
hear it, in the hope that the miracle that
has come to dominate my life will once again
prevail.
And maybe, just maybe, it will.
CHAPTER TWO
GHOSTS
IT
WAS EARLY October 1946, and Noah Calhoun watched
the fading sun sink lower from the porch of
his plantation style home.
He liked to sit here in the evenings, especially
after working hard all day, and let his thoughts
wander.
It was how he relaxed, a routine he'd learned
from his father.
The house
was built in 1772.
It was one of the oldest, as well as largest,
homes in New Bern.
Originally, it was the main house on a working
plantation, and he had bought it right after
the war ended and had spent the last eleven
months and a small fortune repairing it.
The reporter from the Raleigh paper had done
an article on it a few weeks ago and said
it was one of the finest restorations he'd
ever seen.
At least the house was.
The rest of the property was another story,
and that was where Noah had spent most
of the day.
He'd gone into the house, drunk a glass of
sweet tea, then showered; the water was washing
away dirt and fatigue.
Afterwards he'd combed his hair back, put
on some faded jeans and a long-sleeved blue
shirt, poured himself another glass of tea
and gone to the porch, where he sat every
day at this time.
He reached for his guitar, remembering his
father as he did so, thinking how much he
missed him.
He hummed at first, then began to sing as
night came down around him.
It was a little after seven when he stopped
and settled back into his rocking chair.
By habit, he looked upwards and saw Orion,
the Big Dipper and the Pole Star, twinkling
in the autumn sky.
Clem, his dog, came up to him and lay down
at his feet.
He was thirty-one now, not too old, but old
enough to be lonely.
He hadn't dated since he'd been back here,
hadn't met anyone who remotely interested
him.
It was his own fault, he knew.
There was something that kept a distance between
him and any woman who started to get close,
something he wasn't sure he could change even
if he tried.
And sometimes, in the moments before sleep,
he wondered if he was destined to be alone
forever.
He smiled to himself.
He was glad he'd come back.
Though he'd been away for fourteen years,
this was home and he knew a lot of people
here, most of them from his youth.
It wasn't surprising.
Like so many southern towns, the people who
lived here never changed, they just grew a
bit older.
His best friend these days was Gus, a seventy-year-old
black man who lived down the road.
They had met a couple of weeks after Noah
bought the house, when Gus had shown up with
some homemade liquor and stew, and the two
had spent their first evening together getting
drunk and telling stories.
Now Gus showed up a couple of nights a week,
usually around eight.
With four kids and eleven grandchildren in
the house, he needed to get out now and then,
and Noah couldn't blame him.
Usually Gus brought his harmonica and, after
talking for a little while, they played a
few songs together.
He'd come to regard Gus as family.
There really wasn't anyone else, at least
not since his father died last year.
He was an only child and his mother had died
of influenza when he was two.
And though he had wanted to at one time, he
had never married.
But he had been
in love once, that he knew.
Once and only once, and a long time ago.
And it had changed him forever.
Perfect love did that to a person, and this
had been perfect.
It was just after graduation 1932, the opening
night of the Neuse River Festival.
The town was enjoying barbecues and games
of chance.
He arrived alone, and as he strolled through
the crowd, looking for friends, he saw Fin
and Sarah, two people he'd grown up with,
talking to a girl he'd never seen before.
She was pretty.
When he finally joined them, she looked his
way with a pair of hazy eyes.
"Hi," she said simply as she offered her hand.
"Finley's told me a lot about you."
An ordinary beginning.
But as he shook her hand and met those striking
emerald eyes, he knew before he'd taken his
next breath that she was the only one he could
spend the rest of his life with.
She seemed that good, that perfect.
From there, it went like a tornado wind.
Fin told him she was spending the summer in
New Bern with her family, because her father
worked for a tobacco firm.
Sarah suggested getting some cherry cokes,
and the four of them stayed at the festival
until the crowds were thin and everything
closed up for the night.
They met the following day, and the day after
that, and they soon became inseparable.
Every morning but Sunday, when he had to go
to church, he finished his chores as quickly
as possible, then went to the park, where
she was waiting for him.
Because she was a newcomer and hadn't lived
in a small town before, they spent their days
doing things that were completely new to her.
He taught her how to fish.
They rode in canoes and watched summer thunderstorms,
and it seemed as though they'd always known
each other.
But he learned things as well.
At the town dance, it was she who taught him
how to waltz and do the Charleston.
Later in the summer, he brought her to this
house, and told her that one day he was going
to own it and fix it up.
They spent hours together talking about their
dreams - his of seeing the world, hers of
being an artist.
On a humid night in August, they both lost
their virginity.
When she left three weeks later, she took
a piece of him and the rest of summer with
her.
He watched her leave town on an early rainy
morning then went home and packed a bag.
He spent the next week alone on a small island.
Noah checked his watch.
Eight twelve.
He got up, walked to the front of the house
and looked up the road.
Gus wasn't in sight, and Noah thought he wouldn't
come.
He went back and sat again.
He remembered how he had talked to Gus about
her.
The first time he mentioned her Gus started
to shake his head and laugh.
"So that's the ghost you've been running from."
When asked what he meant, Gus said, "You know,
the ghost, the memory.
I've been watching you working day and night,
so hard you barely have time to catch your
breath.
People do that for three reasons.
Either they are crazy, or stupid, or trying
to forget.
And with you, I knew you were trying to forget.
I just didn't know what."
Gus was right, of course.
New Bern was haunted now.
Haunted by the ghost of her memory.
He saw her in the park, their place, every
time he walked by.
When he sat on the porch at night with his
guitar, he saw her beside him, listening as
he played the music of his childhood.
Everywhere he looked, he saw things that brought
her back to life.
EARLIER THAT evening and a hundred miles away,
she sat alone on the porch swing of her parents'
home, wondering if she'd made the right decision.
She'd struggled with it for days, but in the
end she knew she would never forgive herself
if she let the opportunity slip away.
Lon didn't know the real reason she left the
following morning.
The week before, she'd hinted to him that
she might want to visit some antique shops
near the coast.
"It's just a couple of days," she said, "and
besides, I need a break from planning the
wedding."
She felt bad about the lie, but knew there
was no way she could tell him the truth.
Her leaving had nothing to do with him, and
it wouldn't be fair of her to ask him to understand.
It was an easy drive from Raleigh, slightly
more than two hours, and she arrived a little
before eleven.
She checked into a small inn downtown, went
to her room and unpacked her suitcase, hanging
her dresses in the closet and putting everything
else in the drawers.
She had a quick lunch, asked the waitress
for directions to the nearest antique stores,
then spent the next few hours shopping.
By four thirty, she was back in her room.
She sat on the edge of the bed, picked up
the phone and called Lon.
He couldn't speak long, but before they hung
up she gave him the phone number where she
was staying and promised to call the following
day.
Good, she thought while hanging up the phone.
Routine conversation, nothing out of the ordinary.
Nothing to make him suspicious.
She'd known him almost four years now, it
was 1942 when they met, the world at war and
America one year in.
She was volunteering at the hospital downtown.
The first waves of wounded young soldiers
were coming home, and she spent her days with
broken men.
When Lon, with his easy charm, introduced
himself at a party, she saw in him exactly
what she needed: someone with confidence about
the future and a sense of humour that drove
all her fears away.
He was handsome and intelligent, a successful
lawyer eight years older than she, and he
pursued his job with passion, not only winning
cases but also making a name for himself.
She understood his vigorous pursuit of success,
for her father and most of the men she met
in her social circle were the same way.
In the caste system of the South, family name
and accomplishments were often the most important
consideration in marriage.
In some cases, they were the only consideration.
Lon was a gentleman, mature and responsible,
and during those terrible periods of the war
when she needed someone to hold her, he never
once turned her away.
She felt secure with him and knew he loved
her as well and that was why she had accepted
his proposal.
Thinking these things made her feel guilty
about being here, and she knew she should
pack her things and leave before she changed
her mind.
She picked up her handbag, hesitated and almost
walked to the door.
But coincidence had pushed her here, and she
put the bag down, again realizing that if
she quit now she would always wonder what
would have happened.
She couldn't live with that.
She went to the bathroom and started a bath.
After checking the temperature, she undressed
and looked at herself in the mirror.
Her body was firm and well proportioned.
She'd inherited her mother's high cheekbones,
smooth skin and blonde hair, but her best
feature was her own.
She had "eyes like ocean waves", as Lon liked
to say.
She liked the way a bath relaxed her, and
she slipped lower in the water.
The day had been long and her back was tense,
but she was pleased she had finished shopping
so quickly.
She had to go back to Raleigh with something
tangible, and the things she had picked out
would be fine.
She made a mental note to find the names of
some other stores in the area, then suddenly
doubted she would need to.
Lon wasn't the type to check up on her.
She soaked a while longer in the bath before
finally getting out.
She went to the closet and looked for a dress,
finally choosing a light blue one, buttoned
up at the front.
She wore little make-up, just a touch of eye
shadow and mascara to accent her eyes.
Perfume next, not too much.
She found a pair of small-hooped earrings,
put those on, then slipped on the low-heeled
sandals she had been wearing earlier.
She brushed her blonde hair and let it back
down.
When she was finished, she stepped back and
evaluated herself.
She looked good: not too dressy, not too casual.
She didn't want to overdo it.
After all, she didn't know what to expect.
It had been a long time - probably too long.
She found her handbag and car keys, then picked
up the room key.
She turned it over in her hand a couple of
times, thinking - "You've come this far, don't
give up now."
She nearly left then, but instead sat on the
bed again.
She checked her watch.
Almost six o'clock.
She knew she had to leave in a few minutes
- she didn't want to arrive after dark - but
she needed a little more time.
"Damn," she whispered.
"What am I doing here?
I shouldn't be here.
There's no reason for it."
But once she said it she knew it wasn't true.
She opened her handbag and found a folded-up
piece of newspaper.
After taking it out slowly, almost respectfully,
she unfolded it and stared at it for a while.
"This is why," she finally said to herself,
"this is what it's all about."
NOAH GOT UP at five and kayaked for an hour
up the river, as he usually did.
When he finished, he changed into his work
clothes, warmed some bread rolls from the
day before, grabbed a couple of apples and
washed his breakfast down with two cups of
coffee.
He continued repairing the posts.
It was an Indian summer, the temperature over
eighty degrees, and by lunchtime he was hot
and tired and glad of the break.
He ate at the river because the fish were
jumping.
He liked to watch them jump three or four
times and glide through the air before they
vanished into the brackish water.
He stopped working a little after three and
walked to a small shed that sat near his dock.
He went in, found his fishing pole, some live
crickets, then walked out to the dock, baited
his hook and cast his line.
Fishing always made him reflect on his life,
and he did so now.
After his mother died, he could remember spending
his days in a dozen different homes.
For one reason or another, he stuttered badly
as a child and was teased for it.
He began to speak less and less, and by the
age of five, he didn't want to speak at all.
When he started classes, his teachers thought
he was retarded and recommended that his father
take him out of school.
Instead, his father took matters into his
own hands.
He kept him in school and afterwards made
him come to the timber yard where he worked,
to stack wood.
"It's good that we spend some time together,"
he said as they worked side- by-side, "just
like my daddy and I did."
His father talked about animals or told stories
and legends common to North Carolina.
Within a few months, Noah was speaking again,
though not well, and his father decided to
teach him to read with books of poetry.
"Learn to read this aloud and you'll be able
to say anything you want to."
His father had been right again, and by the
following year, Noah had lost his stutter.
But he continued going to the timber yard
every day simply because his father was there,
and in the evenings he read the works of Whitman
and Tennyson aloud as his father rocked beside
him.
He had been reading poetry ever since.
When he got a little older, he spent most
of his weekends and vacations alone.
Camping and exploring became his passion,
and he spent hours in the forest, whistling
quietly and playing his guitar for wild animals.
Poets knew that isolation in nature, far from
people and things man-made, was good for the
soul, and he'd always identified with poets.
Although he was quiet, years of heavy lifting
at the timber yard helped him become good
at sports, and his athletic success led to
popularity.
He enjoyed the football and track meets, and,
though most of his teammates spent their free
time together as well, he rarely joined them.
He had a few girlfriends in school but none
had ever made an impression on him.
Except for one.
And she came after graduation.
Allie.
His Allie.
Most of the summer Allie had to make excuses
to her parents whenever they wanted to see
each other.
It wasn't that they didn't like him - it was
that he was from a different class, too poor,
and they would never approve if their daughter
became serious with someone like him.
"I don't care what my parents think, I love
you and always will," she said.
"We'll find a way to be together."
But in the end they couldn't.
By early September, the tobacco had been harvested
and she had no choice but to return with her
family to Winston-Salem.
"Only the summer is over, Allie, not us,"
he'd said the morning she left.
"We'll never be over."
But they were.
For a reason he didn't understand, the letters
he wrote went unanswered.
He decided to leave New Bern to help get her
off his mind.
He went to New Jersey.
He found a job in a scrap yard, separating
scrap metal from everything else.
The owner, Morris Goldman, was convinced that
a war was going to start in Europe and that
America would be dragged in again.
Noah didn't care.
He was just happy to have a job.
He worked hard.
It helped him keep his mind off Allie during
the day, and it was something he felt he had
to do.
His daddy had always said, "Give a day's work
for a day's pay.
Anything less is stealing."
That attitude pleased his boss.
He thought about Allie at night.
He wrote to her once a month but never received
a reply.
Eventually he wrote one final letter and forced
himself to accept the fact that the summer
they'd spent with one another was the only
thing they'd ever share.
For the next eight years, he worked for Goldman.
As the years dragged on, the company grew
and he was promoted.
By 1940, he had mastered the business and
was running the entire operation, managing
a staff of thirty.
The yard had become the largest scrap-metal
dealer on the east coast.
During that time, he dated a few different
women.
He became serious with one, a waitress from
the local cafe with deep blue eyes and silky
black hair.
Although they dated for two years and had
many good times together, he never came to
feel the same way about her as he did about
Allie.
Towards the end of their relationship she'd
told him once, "I wish I could give you what
you're looking for, but I don't know what
it is.
There's a part of you that you keep closed
off from everyone, including me.
It's like your mind is on someone else and
you keep waiting for her to take you away
from all this..."
A month later, she visited him at work and
told him she'd met someone else.
He understood.
They parted as friends, and the following
year he received a postcard from her saying
she was married.
He hadn't heard from her since.
In December 1941, when he was twenty-six,
the war began, just as Goldman had predicted.
Noah walked into his office the following
month and informed Goldman of his intention
to join the army, then returned to New Bern
to say goodbye to his father.
Five weeks later, he was in training camp.
While there, he received a letter from Goldman
thanking him for his work, together with a
copy of a certificate giving him the right
to get a small percentage of the scrap yard
if it was ever sold.
He spent his next three years with Patton's
Third Army, tramping through deserts in North
Africa and forests in Europe.
He watched his friends die around him; watched
as some of them were buried thousands of miles
from home.
He remembered the war ending in Europe, then
a few months later in Japan.
Just before he was discharged, he received
a letter from a lawyer in New Jersey representing
Morris Goldman.
When he met the lawyer, he found out that
Goldman had died a year earlier and his estate
had been liquidated.
The business had been sold, and Noah was given
a cheque for almost seventy thousand dollars.
The following week he returned to New Bern
and bought the house.
He remembered bringing his father around later,
pointing out the changes, he intended to make.
His father seemed weak as he walked, coughing.
Noah was concerned, but his father told him
not to worry, assuring him that he had the
flu.
Less than one month later, his father died
of pneumonia and was buried next to his wife
in the local cemetery.
Noah tried to stop by regularly to leave some
flowers.
And every night he took a moment to say a
prayer for the man who'd taught him everything
that mattered.
SOON HE went back to the house.
He got into his old Dodge truck and went to
see Gus.
He always stopped there when he was going
to the store, because Gus's family didn't
have a car.
One of the daughters hopped up and rode with
him, and they did their shopping.
When he got home, he didn't unpack the groceries
right away.
Instead, he showered, found a Budweiser and
a book of poetry, and went to sit on the porch.
SHE STILL did not believe it, even as she
held the proof in her hands.
It had been in the newspaper at her parents'
house three Sundays ago.
She had gone to the kitchen to get a cup of
coffee, and when she'd returned to the table
her father had smiled and pointed at a small
picture.
"Remember this?"
He handed her the paper and, after an uninterested
first glance, something in the picture caught
her eye and she took a closer look.
"It can't be," she whispered, and when her
father looked at her curiously, she ignored
him, sat down and read the article without
speaking.
She vaguely remembered her mother coming to
the table and sitting opposite her, and when
she finally put aside the paper, her mother
was staring at her.
"Are you okay?"
she asked over her coffee cup.
"You look a little pale."
Allie didn't answer right away, she couldn't,
and then she noticed that her hands were shaking.
So it started.
"And here it will end, one way or the other,"
she whispered again.
She refolded the piece of paper and put it
back.
And now, after three weeks of long walks alone,
after three weeks of distraction, it was the
reason she'd come.
When asked, she said her strange behaviour
was due to stress.
It was the perfect excuse; everyone understood,
including Lon, and that's why he hadn't argued
when she'd wanted to get away for a couple
of days.
The wedding plans were stressful to everyone
involved.
Almost five hundred people were invited, including
the governor, one senator and the ambassador
to Peru.
It was too much, in her opinion, but their
engagement was news and had dominated the
social pages since they had announced their
plans six months ago.
She took a deep breath and stood again.
"It's now or never," she whispered, then picked
up her things and went to the door.
She went downstairs and went out to her car.
She slipped behind the wheel, started the
engine and turned right onto Front Street.
She still knew her way around the small town,
even though she hadn't been here in years.
A magnificent oak tree on the riverbank came
into view, and the memories became more intense.
She remembered sitting beneath the tree on
a hot July day with someone who looked at
her with a longing that took everything else
away.
And at that moment she'd first fallen in love.
He was two years older than she was.
He had the calloused hands and broad shoulders
that came to those who worked hard for a living
and the first faint lines were beginning to
form around dark eyes that seemed to read
her every thought.
He was tall and strong, with light brown hair,
and handsome in his own way, but most of all
she remembered his voice.
He had read to her that day as they lay beneath
the tree with an accent that was soft and
fluent, almost musical in quality.
She remembered closing her eyes, listening
closely and letting the words he was reading
touch her soul.
Another turn in the road and she finally saw
the house in the distance.
It had changed dramatically from what she
remembered.
She slowed the car, turning into the long,
tree- lined drive.
She took a deep breath when she saw him on
the porch, watching her car.
He was dressed casually.
From a distance, he looked the same as he
had back then.
Her car continued forward slowly, and then
finally stopped beneath an oak tree that shaded
the front of the house.
She turned the key, never taking her eyes
from him.
He stepped off the porch and started approaching
her, walking easily, then suddenly stopped
as she emerged from the car.
For a long time all they could do was stare
at each other without moving.
Allison Nelson, twenty-nine years old and
engaged, a socialite, searching for answers,
and Noah Calhoun, the dreamer, thirty-one,
visited by the ghost that had come to dominate
his life.
CHAPTER THREE
REUNION
NEITHER ONE of them moved as they faced each
other.
As she stared at him, she noticed how little
he had changed since she had last seen him.
He looked good, she thought.
He looked the same as he had when she had
known him last.
She took a deep breath and smiled.
"Hello, Noah.
It's good to see you again."
He looked at her with amazement in his eyes.
Then, after shaking his head slightly, he
slowly smiled.
"You too," he said.
"It's really you, isn't it?
I can't believe it..."
She felt something tremble inside, something
deep and old, something that made her dizzy
for just a second.
She caught herself fighting for control.
She hadn't expected this to happen, didn't
want it to happen.
She was engaged now.
She hadn't come here for this.
Yet.
Yet the feeling went on despite herself, and
for a brief moment, she felt fifteen again.
Felt as she hadn't in years, as if all her
dreams could still come true.
Felt as though she'd finally come home.
Without another word, they came together,
and he put his arms around her.
They held each other tightly; both of them
letting the fourteen years of separation dissolve
in the deepening twilight.
They stayed like that for a long time before
she finally pulled back to look at him.
Up close, she could see the changes she hadn't
noticed at first.
His face had lost the softness of youth.
The faint lines around his eyes had deepened.
There was a new edge to him; he seemed less
innocent, more cautious, and yet the way he
was holding her made her realize how much
she'd missed him.
"I still can't believe it's you.
How did you find me?" asked he.
She stepped back, trying to compose herself.
"I saw the story on the house in the Raleigh
paper a couple of weeks ago, and I had to
come and see you again."
Noah smiled broadly.
"I'm glad you did."
He stepped back.
"You look fantastic.
You're even prettier now than you were then."
She felt the blood in her face.
Just like fourteen years ago.
"Thank you.
You look great, too."
And he did, no doubt about it.
"So why are you here?"
She turned away and took a deep breath, wondering
how to say it, and when she finally started,
her voice was quiet.
"Noah, before you get the wrong idea, I really
wanted to see you again, but there's more
to it than just that."
She paused for a second.
"I came here for a reason.
There's something I have to tell you."
"What is it?"
She looked away and didn't answer for a moment,
surprised that she couldn't tell him just
yet.
In the silence, Noah felt a sinking feeling
in his stomach.
Whatever it was, it was bad.
"I don't know how to say it.
I thought I did at first, but now I'm not
so sure..."
"What is it, Allie?"
"I'm rather silly, aren't I?" she asked, trying
to smile.
"What do you mean?"
"This whole thing.
Showing up suddenly, not knowing what I want
to say.
You must think I'm crazy."
"You're not crazy," he said gently.
He reached for her hand, and she let him hold
it as they stood next to one another.
He went on, "Even though I don't know why,
I can see this is hard for you.
Why don't we go for a walk?"
"Like we used to?"
"Why not?"
She hesitated and looked to his front door.
"Do you need to tell anyone?"
He shook his head.
"There's no one to tell.
It's just me and Clem, my dog."
Even though she had asked, she had suspected
there wouldn't be anyone else, and inside
she didn't know how to feel about that.
But it made what she wanted to say a little
harder.
They started towards the river and turned
onto a path near the bank.
She let go of his hand and walked on with
just enough distance between them so that
they couldn't accidentally touch.
He looked at her.
She was still pretty, with thick hair and
soft eyes, and she moved so gracefully.
He'd seen beautiful women before, women who
caught his eye, but to his mind, they usually
lacked the traits he found most desirable.
Traits like intelligence, confidence, strength
of spirit, passion, traits that inspired others
to greatness.
Allie had those traits, he knew, and as they
walked now he sensed them once again.
"How long have you been back here?"
she asked as the path gave way to a small
grass hill.
"Since last December.
I worked up north for a while, and then spent
the last three years in Europe."
She looked at him with questions in her eyes.
"The war?"
He nodded and she went on.
"I thought you might be there.
I'm glad it's finished."
"Me too," he said.
"Are you glad to be back home?"
"Yeah.
My roots are here.
This is where I'm supposed to be."
He paused.
"But what about you?"
He asked the question softly, suspecting the
worst.
It was a long moment before she answered.
"I'm engaged."
He looked down when she said it, suddenly
feeling just a bit weaker.
So that was it.
That's what she needed to tell him.
"Congratulations," he finally said, wondering
how convincing he sounded.
"When's the big day?"
"Three weeks.
Lon wanted a November wedding."
"Lon?"
"Lon Hammond Junior.
My fiance."
He nodded.
The Hammonds were one of the most powerful
and influential families in the state.
Cotton money.
Unlike that of his own father, the death of
Lon Hammond Senior had made the front page
of the newspaper.
"I've heard of them.
His father built quite a business.
Did Lon take over for him?"
She shook her head.
"No, he's a lawyer.
He has his own practice."
"With his name, he must be busy."
"He is.
He works a lot."
He thought he heard something in her tone,
and the next question came automatically.
"Does he treat you well?"
She didn't answer right away, as if she were
considering the question for the first time.
Then she said, "Yes.
He's a good man, Noah.
You'd like him."
Her voice was distant when she answered, or
at least he thought it was.
Noah wondered if it was just his mind playing
tricks on him.
"How's your daddy doing?" she asked.
Noah took a couple of steps before answering.
"He passed on earlier this year, right after
I got back."
"I'm sorry," she said softly.
He nodded, and they walked on in silence.
They reached the top of the hill and stopped.
The oak tree was in the distance, with the
sun glowing orange behind it.
Allie could feel his eyes on her as she stared
in that direction.
"A lot of memories there, Allie."
She smiled.
"I know.
I saw it when I came in.
Do you remember the day we spent there?"
"Yes," he answered.
"Do you ever think about it?"
"Sometimes," he said.
"Usually when I'm working out this way.
It sits on my property now."
"You bought it?"
"I just couldn't bear to see it turned into
kitchen cabinets."
She laughed under her breath, feeling strangely
pleased about that.
As the sun dropped a little lower and the
sky turned orange, he asked, "So, how long
are you staying?"
"I don't know.
Not long.
Maybe until tomorrow or the next day."
"Is your fiance here on business?"
"No, he's still in Raleigh."
Noah raised his eyebrows.
"Does he know you're here?"
She shook her head and answered slowly.
"No.
I told him I was looking for antiques.
He wouldn't understand my coming here."
Noah was a little surprised.
It was one thing to come and visit, but it
was an entirely different matter to hide the
truth from her fiance.
He asked, "Allie, do you love him?"
She answered automatically, "Yes, I love him."
The words hurt.
But again, he thought he heard something in
her tone, and decided she was saying it to
convince herself.
He stopped and gently took her shoulders in
his hands, making her face him.
The sunlight reflected in her eyes as he spoke.
"If you're happy, Allie, and you love him,
I won't try to stop you from going back to
him.
But if there's a part of you that isn't sure,
then don't do it.
This isn't the kind of thing you go into halfway."
Her answer came almost too quickly.
"I'm making the right decision, Noah."
He stared for a second, wondering if he believed
her.
Then he nodded and they began to walk again.
He said, "I'm not making this easy for you,
am I?"
She smiled a little.
"It's okay.
I really can't blame you."
"I'm sorry anyway."
"Don't be.
There's no reason to be sorry."
"I'm glad you came.
It's good to see you again.
You were the best friend I ever had, Allie.
I'd still like to be friends, even if you
are engaged, and even if it is just for a
couple of days.
How about getting to know each other again?"
She thought about it, and decided that since
he knew about her engagement, it would probably
be all right.
Or at least not wrong.
She smiled slightly and nodded.
"I'd like that."
"Good.
How about dinner?
I know a place that serves the best crab in
town."
"Sounds great.
Where?"
"My house.
I've had the traps out all week, and I saw
that I had some good ones caged a couple of
days ago.
Do you mind?"
"No, that sounds fine."
He smiled and pointed over his shoulder with
his thumb.
"Great.
They're at the dock.
I'll just be a couple of minutes."
A breeze broke the stillness and chilled her,
making her cross her arms.
She stood that way, until she heard him reach
her side.
She could feel his closeness, his warmth.
"It's so peaceful here," she said, and her
voice was dreamlike.
"I know.
I come down here a lot now just to be close
to the water.
It makes me feel good.
Come on, let's go.
The mosquitoes are getting vicious, and I'm
starved."
THE SKY had turned black and they started
towards the house.
Noah set the bucket by the door, and then
led the way inside to the kitchen.
It was on the right, large and smelling of
new wood.
The cabinets were made of oak, like the floor,
and the windows were large and faced east,
allowing the light from the morning sun.
"Do you mind if I look around?"
"No, go ahead.
I did some shopping earlier and I still have
to put the groceries away."
She toured the house for the next few minutes,
walking through the rooms, noticing how wonderful
it looked.
She came down the stairs, turned towards the
kitchen, and saw his profile.
For a second he looked like a young man of
seventeen again, and it made her pause a second
before going on.
"Damn," she thought, "get a hold of yourself.
Remember that you're engaged now."
"It's unbelievable, Noah.
How long did the restoration take?"
He looked up from the last bag he was unpacking.
"Almost a year."
"Did you do it all yourself?"
He laughed.
"No.
I always thought I would when I was young,
and I started that way.
But it was just too much, so I had to hire
some people... actually a lot of people.
But even with them it was still a lot of work,
and most of the time I didn't stop until past
midnight."
"Why did you work so hard?"
Ghosts, he wanted to say, but didn't.
"I don't know.
Just wanted to finish, I guess.
Do you want anything to drink before I start
dinner?"
"What do you have?"
"Not much, really.
Beer, tea, coffee."
"Tea sounds good."
He gathered the grocery bags and put them
away, then walked to a small room off the
kitchen before returning with a box of tea.
He pulled out a couple of tea bags and put
them by the stove, then filled the kettle.
After putting it on the burner, he lit a match
and she heard the sound of flames as they
came to life.
"It'll be just a minute," he said, "this stove
heats up pretty quick."
"That's fine."
When the kettle whistled, he poured two cups
and handed one to her.
She smiled and took a sip.
"I'm going to get the crabs in to marinate
for a few minutes before I steam them," he
said, putting his cup on the counter.
He went to the cupboard and removed a large
pot with a steamer and lid.
He brought the pot to the sink, added water,
and then carried it to the stove.
"Can I help you?"
He answered over his shoulder, "Sure.
How about cutting up some vegetables to fry.
There's plenty in the icebox, and you can
find a bowl over there."
He stared at Allie, watching her cut the carrots.
As he did that, he wondered again, why she
had come, especially now that she was engaged.
None of this made much sense to him.
But then Allie had always been surprising.
He smiled, remembering the way she had been.
Fiery, spontaneous, passionate - as he imagined
most artists to be.
And she was definitely that.
Artistic talent like hers was a gift.
He remembered seeing some paintings in the
museums in New York and thinking that her
work was just as good.
She had given him a painting before she'd
left that summer.
It hung above the fireplace in the living
room.
She'd called it a picture of her dreams, and
to him it had seemed extremely sensual.
When he looked at it, he could see desire
in the colours and the lines, and if he focused
carefully, he could imagine what she had been
thinking with every stroke.
A dog barked in the distance, and Noah realized
he had been standing with the door open a
long time.
He closed it quickly and went into the kitchen.
"How's it going?" he asked, seeing she was
nearly finished.
"Good.
I'm almost done here.
Anything else for dinner?"
"I have some homemade bread.
From a neighbour," he added.
He began to wash the crabs, holding them under
the tap.
Allie picked up her cup and came over to watch
him.
"You want to sit on the porch for a few minutes?
I'd like to let them marinate for a half-hour."
"Sure," she said.
He wiped his hands, and together they went
to the back porch.
Noah turned on the light as they went outside,
and he sat in the older rocker, offering the
newer one to her.
"You were sitting out here when I came, weren't
you?"
she asked.
"Yeah.
I sit out here every night.
It's a habit now."
"I can see why," she said as she looked around.
"So, what is it you do these days?"
"Actually, I don't do anything but work on
the house right now.
It satisfies my creative urges."
"How can you...
I mean..."
"Morris Goldman.
My old boss from up north.
He offered me a part of the business just
as I joined the army, and died before I got
home.
When I got back to the States, his lawyers
gave me a cheque big enough to buy this place
and fix it up."
She laughed under her breath.
"You always told me you'd find a way to do
it."
They both sat quietly for a moment, thinking
back again.
Allie took another sip of tea.
"Do you remember sneaking over here the night
you first told me about this place?"
He nodded, and she went on: "I got home a
little late that evening, and my parents were
furious when I finally came in.
I can still picture my daddy standing in the
living room smoking a cigarette, my mother
on the sofa staring straight ahead.
I swear, they looked as if a family member
had died.
That was the first time my parents knew I
was serious about you, and my mother had a
long talk with me later that night.
She said to me, 'I'm sure you think that I
don't understand what you're going through,
but I do.
It's just that sometimes our future is dictated
by what we are, as opposed to what we want.'
I remember I was really hurt when she said
that."
"You told me about it the next day.
It hurt my feelings, too.
I liked your parents and I had no idea they
didn't like me."
"It wasn't that they didn't like you.
They didn't think you deserved me."
"There's not much difference."
"I feel that it's wrong, that it isn't fair.
It was a terrible thing for a girl to learn,
that status is more important than feelings."
Noah said nothing.
"I've thought about you ever since that summer,"
she said.
"You have?"
"Why wouldn't you think so?"
She seemed genuinely surprised.
"You never answered my letters."
"You wrote?"
"Dozens of letters.
I wrote to you for two years without receiving
a single reply."
She slowly shook her head before lowering
her eyes.
"I didn't know," she said finally, quietly,
and then he thought that her mother had been
checking the mail, removing the letters without
her knowledge.
It was what he had always suspected, and he
watched as Allie came to the same realization.
"It was wrong of her to do that, Noah, and
I'm sorry she did.
But try to understand.
Once I left, she probably thought it would
be easier for me to just let it go.
She never understood how much you meant to
me, and, to be honest, I don't even know if
she ever loved my father the way I loved you.
In her mind, she was just trying to protect
my feelings, and she probably thought the
best way to do that was to hide the letters
you sent."
"That wasn't her decision to make," he said
quietly.
"I know."
"Would it have made a difference even if you'd
got them?"
It took a moment for her to answer.
"I don't know, Noah.
I really don't, and you don't either.
We're not the same people we were then.
We've changed.
Both of us."
She paused and went on.
"But yes, Noah, I think...
at least, I'd like to think that it would
have made a difference."
He nodded, looked down, and then turned away.
"What's Lon like?"
She hesitated, not expecting the question.
"Lon's handsome, charming and successful.
He's kind to me, he makes me laugh, and I
know he loves me in his own way."
She collected her thoughts.
"But there's always going to be something
missing in our relationship."
She surprised herself with her answer but
knew it was true nonetheless.
And she also knew by looking at him that Noah
had suspected the answer in advance when he
asked, "Why?"
She shrugged and her voice was barely above
a whisper.
"I guess I still look for the kind of love
we had that summer."
Noah thought about what she had said, thought
about the relationships he'd had since he'd
last seen her.
"How about you'?" she asked.
"Did you ever think about us?"
"All the time.
I still do."
"Are you seeing anyone?"
"No," he answered, shaking his head.
"I'm going to go and start the water.
Can I get you anything'?"
She shook her head, and Noah went to the kitchen.
He was thinking about Allie and the love that
was missing from both their lives.
Allie, too, was thinking.
About Noah, about herself, about many things.
For a moment, she wished that she weren't
engaged, but then quickly cursed herself.
It wasn't Noah she loved; she loved what they
once had been.
Besides, it was normal to feel this way.
Her first real love, the only man she'd ever
been with - how could she expect to forget
him?
Yet was it normal for her insides to tremble
whenever he came near?
Was it normal to confess things she could
never tell anyone else?
Was it normal to come here three weeks before
her wedding day?
"No, it's not," she finally whispered to herself
as she looked at the evening sky, "there's
nothing normal about any of this."
Noah came out at that moment and she smiled
at him, glad he'd come back so she didn't
have to think about it anymore.
"It's going to take a few minutes," he said
as he sat down.
"That's fine.
I'm not that hungry yet."
He looked at her then, and she saw the softness
in his eyes.
"I'm glad you came, Allie," he said.
"Me too.
I almost didn't, though."
"Why did you come?"
"I was compelled," she wanted to say, but
didn't.
"Just to see you, to find out what you are
doing.
To see how you are."
He wondered if that was all, but didn't question
further.
Instead, he changed the subject.
"By the way, do you still paint?"
She shook her head.
"Not anymore."
He was stunned.
"Why not?
You have so much talent."
"It's a long story."
"I've got all night," he answered.
"Did you really think I was talented?"
she asked quietly.
"Come on," he said, reaching out for her hand.
"I want to show you something."
She got up and followed him through the door
to the living room.
He stopped in front of the fireplace and pointed
to the painting that hung above the mantelpiece.
She gasped, surprised she hadn't noticed it
earlier, more surprised it was here at all.
"You kept it'?"
"Of course I kept it.
It's wonderful."
She gave him a skeptical look, and he explained.
"It makes me feel alive when I look at it.
Sometimes I have to get up and touch it.
It's incredible, Allie.
You mean to tell me no one has ever told you
that before?"
"My professor did," she said, "but I guess
I didn't believe him."
He knew there was more.
Allie looked away before continuing.
"I've been drawing and painting since I was
a child.
I guess that once I got a little older I began
to think I was good at it.
I enjoyed it too.
I remember working on this painting that summer,
adding to it every day, changing it as our
relationship changed.
I don't even remember how it started or what
I wanted it to be, but somehow it developed
into this.
"I remember that I was unable to stop painting
after I went home that summer.
I think it was my way of avoiding the pain
I was going through.
Anyway, I ended up majoring in art in college
because it was something I had to do; I remember
how I spent hours in the studio all by myself
and enjoyed every minute.
I loved the freedom I felt when I created,
the way it made me feel to make something
beautiful.
Just before I graduated, my professor, who
was also the critic for the paper, told me
I had a lot of talent.
He told me I should try my luck as an artist.
But I didn't listen to him."
She stopped for a moment, gathering her thoughts.
"My parents didn't think it was good for someone
like me to paint for a living.
I just stopped after a while.
I haven't touched a brush in years."
She stared at the painting.
"I'm not sure if I can paint anymore.
It's been a long time."
"You can still do it, Allie.
I know you can.
You have a talent that comes from inside you,
from your heart, not from your fingers.
What you have can't ever go away.
It's what other people only dream about.
You're an artist, Allie."
The words were spoken with such sincerity
that she knew he wasn't saying it just to
be nice.
He truly believed in her ability, and for
some reason that meant more to her than she
expected.
She turned to face him.
She reached over and touched his hand, hesitantly,
gently, amazed that after all these years
he had somehow known exactly what she'd needed
to hear.
When their eyes locked, she once again realized
how special he was.
And for just a fleeting moment, she wondered
if she was in love with him again.
THE TIMER WENT off in the kitchen and Noah
turned away, strangely affected by what had
just happened between them.
Her eyes had spoken to him and whispered something
he longed to hear; yet he couldn't stop the
voice inside his head, her voice that had
told him of her love for another man.
He silently cursed the timer as he walked
to the kitchen and removed the bread from
the oven.
He saw that the frying pan was ready.
He added the vegetables and heard them crackling.
Then he spread some butter on the bread and
melted a bit more for the crabs.
Allie had followed him into the kitchen and
cleared her throat.
"Can I get the table ready?"
Noah used the bread knife as a pointer.
"Sure, plates are over there.
Utensils and napkins there."
He couldn't look at her as he spoke.
He didn't want to be mistaken about what had
just happened between them.
Allie, too, was wondering about the moment
and feeling warm as she thought of it.
The words he'd spoken replayed in her head
as she found everything she needed for the
table settings.
Noah handed her the bread and their fingers
touched briefly.
He turned his attention back to the frying
pan and stirred the vegetables.
He lifted the lid of the steamer, and let
the crabs cook some more.
He was more composed now and returned to small
talk, easy conversation.
"Have you ever had crab before?"
"A couple of times.
But only in salads."
He laughed.
"Then you're in for an adventure.
Hold on a second."
He disappeared upstairs for a moment, then
returned with a navy-blue button-down shirt.
He held it out for her.
"Here, put this on.
I don't want you to stain your dress."
Allie put it on and smelt the fragrance that
lingered in the shirt - his smell, distinctive,
natural.
"Don't worry." he said, seeing her expression,
"it's clean."
She laughed.
"I know.
It just reminds me of our first real date.
You gave me your jacket that night, remember?"
He nodded.
The vegetables and crabs were ready at about
the same time.
"Be careful, they're hot," he said as he handed
them to her, and they sat across from each
other at the small wooden table.
After putting some vegetables and bread on
their plates, Noah added a crab, and Allie
sat for a moment, staring at it.
"Here, let me show you how it's done," he
said.
He made it look easy, removing the meat and
putting it on her plate.
They started talking then, making up for lost
time.
Noah talked about leaving New Bern, about
working at the scrap yard in New Jersey.
He spoke fondly of Morris Goldman and touched
on the war a little, and told her how much
he missed his father.
Allie talked about going to college, painting,
and her hours spent volunteering at the hospital.
She talked about her family.
Neither of them mentioned anybody they had
dated since they'd last seen each other.
Even Lon was ignored, and though both of them
noticed the omission, neither spoke of it.
Afterwards Allie tried to remember the last
time she and Lon had talked this way.
Although he listened well and they seldom
argued, he was not the type of man to talk
like this.
Like her father, he wasn't comfortable sharing
feelings.
She'd tried to explain that she needed to
be closer to him, but it had never changed
anything.
Sitting here now, she realized what she'd
been missing.
The sky grew darker and the moon rose higher
as the evening wore on.
And though they were not conscious of it,
they began to regain the intimacy, the bond
of familiarity, they had once shared.
THEY FINISHED dinner, both pleased with the
meal, neither talking much now.
Noah looked at his watch and saw that it was
getting late.
The stars were shining brightly, the crickets
were a little quieter now.
"How about the porch again?" he asked, handing
her the cup, and she agreed, leading the way.
He grabbed a quilt for her in case she got
cold, and soon they had taken their places
again.
The quilt was over her legs; their rockers
were moving.
Noah watched her from the comer of his eye.
"God, she's beautiful," he thought.
And inside he ached.
For something had happened during dinner.
Quite simply, he had fallen in love again.
He knew that now as they sat next to one another.
Fallen in love with a new Allie, not just
her memory.
But then he had never really stopped, and
this, he realized, was his destiny.
Noah glanced up at the stars, their twinkling
lights reminded him that she would be leaving
soon, and he felt almost empty inside.
This was a night he wanted never to end.
How should he tell her?
What could he say that would make her stay?
"Talk to me," she finally said.
"What should I say?"
"Talk like you did to me under the oak tree."
And he did, reciting distant passages, toasting
the night.
She rested her head against the back of the
rocker, closing her eyes.
It wasn't just the poems or his voice that
did it.
It was all of it, the whole greater than the
sum of the parts.
Lon could not evoke these feelings in her.
He never had and probably never would.
Maybe that was why she had never been to bed
with him.
She had always used the excuse that she wanted
to wait until marriage.
He took it well, usually, and she sometimes
wondered how hurt he would be if he ever found
out about Noah.
But there was something else that made her
want to wait, and it had to do with Lon himself.
His work always came first.
For him there was no time for poems and wasted
evenings on porches.
She knew this was why he was successful, and
part of her respected him for that.
But she also sensed it wasn't enough.
She wanted something more.
Passion and romance, perhaps, or quiet conversations.
Noah, too, was thinking.
As he rocked, he remembered the thousands
of empty nights he had spent since they'd
last seen each other.
Seeing her again brought all those feelings
to the surface, and he found it impossible
to press them back down.
He knew then he wanted to make love to her
again and to have her love in return.
It was what he needed most in the world.
But he also realized it could never be.
Now that she was engaged.
Allie put down the tea, then ran her hands
through her hair, closing her eyes as she
did so.
"Are you tired?" he asked, finally breaking
free from his thoughts.
"A little.
I should really be going in a couple of minutes."
"I know," he said, nodding, and his tone was
neutral.
She didn't get up right away.
Instead, she picked up the cup and drank the
last swallow of tea, feeling it warm her throat.
She took the evening in.
Moon was higher now; temperature was dropping.
"I should go," she finally said, handing the
quilt back to him.
Noah nodded, and then stood without a word.
He carried the quilt, and the two of them
walked to her car while fallen leaves crunched
beneath their feet.
She started to take off the shirt he'd lent
her as he opened the door, but he stopped
her.
"Keep it," he said.
"I want you to have it."
She didn't ask why, because she wanted to
keep it, too.
"I had a great time tonight," he said, "thank
you for finding me."
"I did, too," she answered.
He summoned his courage.
"Will I see you tomorrow?"
A simple question.
She knew what the answer should be.
"I don't think we should," was all she had
to say, and it would end right here and now.
But for a second the demon of choice confronted
her, teased her, challenged her.
Why couldn't she say it?
As she looked in his eyes to find the answer
she needed, she saw the man she'd once fallen
in love with, and suddenly it all came clear.
"I'd like that."
Noah was surprised.
He hadn't expected her to answer this way.
He wanted to touch her then, to take her in
his arms, but he didn't.
"Can you be here about noon?"
"Sure.
What do you want to do?"
"You'll see," he answered.
"I know just the place to go."
"Have I ever been there before?"
"No, but it's a special place.
You'll love it."
She moved away before he could attempt a kiss.
She slid behind the wheel, breathing a sigh
of relief.
He shut the door for her, and she started
the engine.
"See you tomorrow," she said.
Noah waved as she turned the car around and
then drove up the lane, heading back towards
town.
He watched until the lights vanished behind
far-off oak trees and the engine noise was
gone.
Clem wandered up to him and they returned
to the back porch side by side.
He sat in the rocker again, trying once more
to fathom the evening that had just passed.
Replaying it.
Running it in slow motion.
"She's engaged," he finally whispered, and
then was silent for hours.
The night was quiet, with little activity
except for Clem, who checked on him occasionally
as if to ask, "Are you all right?"
And some time after midnight on that clear
October evening, Noah was overcome with longing.
He looked like an old man now, like someone
who'd aged a lifetime in just a couple of
hours.
He bent over in his rocker with tears in his
eyes.
He didn't know how to stop them.
CHAPTER FOUR
PHONE CALLS
LON HUNG up the phone.
He had called at seven, then at eight thirty,
and now he checked his watch again.
Nine forty-five.
Where was she?
He knew she was where she had said she would
be because he had spoken to the manager.
Yes, she had checked in and he had last seen
her around six.
Going to dinner, he thought.
No, he hadn't seen her since.
Lon shook his head and leaned back in his
chair.
He was the last one in the office as usual.
That was normal with an ongoing trial, even
if the trial was going well.
Law was his passion.
He knew he would win the case because he mastered
the law and charmed the jury.
He always did, and losses were infrequent
now.
But most of his success came from hard work.
He had always paid attention to details, especially
when he'd begun his practice.
Little things, obscure things, and it had
become a habit now.
And now, a little detail bothered him.
Not about the case.
That was fine.
It was something else.
Something about Allie.
The little detail.
Detail...
Something insignificant?
Something important?
Think...
Damn, what was it?
His mind clicked.
Something...
something... something said?
Something had been said?
Yes, that was it.
But what was it?
Had Allie said anything on the phone?
That had been when it started, and he ran
through the conversation again.
What had she said?
Her trip was good; she had checked in, had
done some shopping.
Checked in?
Yes, that was it.
He closed his eyes and thought for a second.
New Bern.
The thought popped into his head.
Yes.
New Bern.
That was it.
The little detail or part of it.
What else, though?
New Bern, he thought again, and knew the name.
He knew the town a little, mainly from a few
trials he had been in.
Stopped there a few times on the way to the
coast.
Nothing special.
He and Allie had never been there together.
But Allie had been there before.
Allie, New Bern... and... something at a party.
A comment from Allie's mother.
What had she said?
Lon paled then, remembering.
Remembering what Allie's mother had said so
long ago.
It was something about Allie being in love
one time with a young man from New Bern.
Called it puppy love.
So what, he had thought when he'd heard it,
and had turned to smile at Allie.
But she hadn't smiled.
She was angry.
And then Lon guessed that she had loved that
person far more deeply than her mother had
suggested.
Maybe more deeply than she loved Lon.
And now she was there.
Interesting.
Coincidence?
Could be nothing.
Could be exactly what she said.
Could be stress and antique shopping.
Possible.
Even probable.
Yet... what if?
Lon considered the other possibility, and
for the first time in a long while, he became
frightened.
What if she's with him?
He made up his mind then that he would do
anything it took to keep her.
She was everything he'd always needed, and
he'd never find another quite like her.
So, with trembling hands, he dialled the phone
for the fourth and last time that evening.
And again there was no answer.
CHAPTER FIVE
KAYAK AND FORGOTTEN DREAMS
ALLIE WOKE early the next morning.
She'd slept in the shirt he'd given her, and
she smelt him once again while thinking about
the evening they'd spent together.
She looked out of the window and watched the
singing birds.
Noah, she knew, had always been a morning
person.
She knew he liked to kayak or canoe, and she
remembered one morning she'd spent with him
in his canoe, watching the sun come up.
She'd had to sneak out of her window to do
it because her parents wouldn't allow it,
but she hadn't been caught and she remembered
how Noah had slipped his arm around her and
pulled her close as dawn began to unfold.
"Look there," he'd whispered, and she'd watched
her first sunrise with her head on his shoulder,
wondering if anything could be better than
that moment.
As she got out of bed to take her bath, feeling
the cold floor beneath her feet, she wondered
if he'd been on the water this morning watching
another day begin, and thought that he probably
had.
SHE WAS RIGHT.
Noah was up before the sun and dressed quickly,
walked to the dock where his kayak was stored.
He liked to let the river work its magic,
loosening up his muscles, warming his body,
clearing his mind.
Questions danced in his mind.
He wondered about Lon and what type of man
he was, wondered about their relationship.
Most of all, though, he wondered about Allie
and why she had come.
By the time he reached home, he felt renewed.
Checking his watch, he was surprised to find
that it had taken two hours.
Time always played tricks out there.
In the western sky he saw storm clouds, thick
and heavy, far off but definitely present.
The winds weren't blowing hard but they were
bringing the clouds closer.
From the look of them, he didn't want to be
outside when they got here.
Damn.
How much time did he have?
A few hours, maybe more.
He showered, put on new jeans, a red shirt
and black cowboy boots, brushed his hair and
went downstairs to the kitchen.
He did the dishes from the night before, made
himself some coffee and went to the porch.
The sky was darker now and he checked the
barometer.
Steady, but it would start dropping soon.
ALLIE SPENT the morning downtown.
The park looked exactly the same as it had
fourteen years ago, and the kids who played
on the swings after school probably looked
the same as well.
She smiled at the memory then, thinking back
to when things were simpler.
Or at least had seemed to be.
Now, nothing was simple.
She wondered what she would be doing now,
had she never seen the article in the paper.
It wasn't very difficult to imagine, because
her routines seldom changed.
It was Wednesday, which meant bridge at the
country club, then on to the Junior Women's
League, where they would probably arrange
another fund-raiser for the private school
or hospital.
After that, a visit to her mother, then home
to get ready for dinner with Lon, because
he left work by seven.
It was the one night a week she saw him regularly.
She suppressed a feeling of sadness about
that, hoping that one day he would change.
She came to an art gallery.
She paused at the door for a second, surprised
at how long it had been since she'd been in
one.
At least three years, maybe longer.
She went inside and walked among the paintings.
Many of the artists didn't seem to be very
talented.
On one wall, though, there were a few paintings
more suited to her tastes, by an artist she'd
never heard of.
In the painting, she liked the best, she noted
the artist had purposely exaggerated the scene
with smaller-than-life figures, wide lines
and heavy sweeps of vivid colour.
It was dynamic, dramatic.
Suddenly she realized that she liked it because
it reminded her of her own work.
She examined it more closely and thought to
herself that maybe Noah was right.
Maybe she should start painting again.
At nine thirty, Allie left the gallery and
went to a department store.
It took a few minutes to find what she was
looking for.
Paper, drawing chalk and pencils, not high
quality but good enough.
It was a start, and she was excited by the
time she got back to her room.
She sat at the desk and started working: nothing
specific, just getting the feel of it again,
letting shapes and colours flow from the memory
of her youth.
After a few minutes, she did a rough sketch
of the street scene as seen from her room,
amazed at how easily it came.
It was almost as if she'd never stopped.
She examined it when she was finished, pleased
with the effort.
She wondered what to try next and finally
decided.
Since she didn't have a model, she visualized
it in her head before starting.
And though it was harder than the street scene,
it began to take form.
Minutes passed quickly.
She worked steadily, checking the time frequently
so she wouldn't be late, and finished it a
little before noon.
It had taken almost two hours, but the result
surprised her.
It looked as though it had taken a great deal
longer.
After rolling it up, she put it in a bag and
collected the rest of her things.
On her way out of the door, she looked at
herself in the mirror, feeling oddly relaxed,
not exactly sure why.
Down the stairs and out of the door.
As she left, she heard a voice behind her.
"Miss?"
She turned.
The manager.
The same man as yesterday, with a curious
look on his face.
"Yes?"
"You had some calls last night."
She was shocked.
"I did?"
"Yes.
All from Mr. Hammond."
Oh, God.
"Lon called?"
"Yes, ma'am, four times.
He was concerned about you.
He said he was your fiance."
She smiled weakly, trying to hide what she
was thinking.
Four times?
Four?
What could that mean?
What if something had happened back home?
"Did he say anything?
Is it an emergency?"
He shook his head quickly.
"He really didn't say, miss.
Actually, he sounded more concerned about
you."
Good, she thought.
That's good.
And then, suddenly, she felt a pang in her
chest.
Why so many calls?
Had she said anything yesterday?
Why would he be so persistent?
It was completely unlike him.
She had to call him now: there was no way
to get around it.
But she didn't want to.
This was her time, and she wanted to spend
it doing what she wanted.
She hadn't planned on speaking to him until
later, and she felt that talking to him now
could spoil the day.
Besides, what was she going to say?
"Miss?"
Almost noon, she thought.
Where would he be?
His office, probably...
no.
In court, she suddenly realized, and immediately
felt fine.
There was no way she could talk to him, even
if she wanted to.
She was surprised by her feelings.
She shouldn't feel this way, she knew, and
yet it didn't bother her.
She looked at her watch, acting now.
"Is it really almost twelve?"
The manager looked at the clock.
"Yes, a quarter to."
"Unfortunately," she started, "he's in court
right now and I can't reach him.
If he calls again, could you tell him I'm
shopping and that I'll try to call him later?"
"Of course," he answered.
"Thank you," she said, smiling.
"I'd appreciate it."
Two minutes later, she was in her car, driving
to Noah's, anticipating the day, largely unconcerned
about the phone calls.
As she was driving over the bridge, less than
four minutes after she'd left the inn, Lon
called from the courthouse.
CHAPTER SIX
SWANS AND STORM
NOAH WAS sitting in his rocker, drinking sweet
tea, when he finally heard the car turn up
the drive.
He went around to the front and watched the
car pull up and park beneath the oak tree
again.
Noah saw Allie wave from inside the car.
Allie met him halfway, carrying a small bag.
She surprised him by kissing him gently on
the cheek; her free hand was lingering at
his waist after she pulled back.
"Hi," she said, with radiance in her eyes,
"where's the surprise?"
"Not even a 'Good afternoon' or 'How was your
night?'"
She smiled.
Patience had never been one of her strongest
attributes.
"Fine.
Good afternoon.
How was your night?
And where's the surprise?"
He laughed lightly, then paused.
"Allie, I've got some bad news.
I was going to take you someplace, but with
those clouds coming in I'm not sure we should
go."
"It's not raining yet.
How far is it?"
"Up the river about a mile."
"And I've never been there before?"
"Not when it was like this."
She thought for a second while she looked
around.
When she spoke, her voice was determined.
"Then we'll go.
I don't care if it rains."
"Are you sure?"
"Absolutely."
"Then we'd better go now.
Can I bring that in for you?"
She nodded, handing her bag to him, and he
jogged to the house and took it inside, placing
it on a chair in the living room.
Then he grabbed some bread and put it in a
bag, bringing it with him as he left the house.
They walked to the canoe.
Allie was beside him, a little closer than
yesterday.
After tossing the bag in the canoe, Noah slid
the canoe to the water.
"Can I do anything?"
Allie asked.
"No, just get in."
After she climbed in, he pushed the canoe
further into the water.
Then he gracefully stepped off the jetty into
the canoe.
She sat at the front of the canoe, facing
backwards.
She couldn't think of anyone else who remotely
resembled Noah.
He was complicated, almost contradictory in
so many ways, yet simple.
On the surface, he was a country boy, home
from war, and he probably saw himself in those
terms.
Yet there was so much more to him.
Perhaps it was the poetry that made him different,
or perhaps it was the values his father had
instilled in him.
Either way, he enjoyed life more fully than
others, and that was what had first attracted
her to him.
She understood then that something was stirring
within her, as it had so many years ago.
Watching his body move made her feel it.
And as their eyes met for a second, she felt
the heat in her neck and breasts, and she
flushed, turning away before he noticed.
"How much further?"
she asked.
"Another half-mile or so.
Not any more than that."
A pause.
Then she said, "Tell me, Noah, what do you
remember most from the summer we spent together?"
"All of it."
"Anything in particular?"
"No," he said.
"You don't remember?"
He answered quietly.
"No, it's not that.
It's not what you're thinking.
I was serious when I said 'all of it.'
I can remember every moment we were together,
and in each of them, there was something wonderful.
I can't pick any one time that meant more
than any other.
The entire summer was perfect.
How could I pick one moment over another?
"Poets often describe love as an emotion that
we can't control, one that overwhelms logic
and common sense.
That's what it was like for me.
I didn't plan on falling in love with you,
and I doubt if you planned on falling in love
with me.
But once we met, it was clear that neither
of us could control what was happening to
us.
We fell in love, despite our differences,
and once we did, something rare and beautiful
was created.
For me, love like that has happened only once,
and that's why every minute we spent together
is in my memory.
I'll never forget a single moment of it."
Allie stared at him.
No one had ever said anything like that to
her before.
Ever.
She didn't know what to say and stayed silent.
"I'm sorry if I made you feel uncomfortable,
Allie.
I didn't mean to.
But that summer has stayed with me and probably
always will.
I know it can't be the same between us, but
that doesn't change the way I felt about you
then."
"It didn't make me uncomfortable, Noah...
It's just that I don't ever hear things like
that.
What you said was beautiful."
Peaceful silence descended on them.
The paddle moved rhythmically.
The breeze had stopped, and the clouds grew
blacker as the canoe moved onwards.
Allie noticed it all, every sound, every thought.
Her senses had come alive, and she felt strangely
satisfied that she'd come, pleased that Noah
had turned into the type of man she'd thought
he would, pleased that she would live forever
with that knowledge.
She had seen too many men in the past few
years destroyed by war, or time, or even money.
It took strength to hold on to inner passion,
and Noah had done that.
This was a worker's world, not a poet's, and
people would have a hard time understanding
Noah.
Who did she know in Raleigh who took time
off to fix a house?
Or read poetry?
These weren't the things that drove society,
but she felt they made living worthwhile.
To her it was the same with art, though she
had realized it only upon coming here.
Or rather, remembered it.
She had known it once before, and again she
cursed herself for forgetting something as
important as creating beauty.
Painting was what she was meant to do, she
was sure of that now.
She was going to try it again, no matter what
anyone said.
Would Lon encourage her painting?
She remembered showing him one of her paintings
a couple of months after they had first started
going out.
It was abstract, meant to inspire thought.
Lon had stared at it, and then had asked her
what it was supposed to be.
She knew she wasn't completely fair.
She loved Lon for other reasons.
Lon was a good man.
With him, there would be no surprises, and
there was comfort in knowing what the future
would bring.
He would be a kind husband and she would be
a good wife.
She would have a home, friends and family,
children, a respectable place in society.
It was the kind of life she'd always expected
to live.
And though she wouldn't describe theirs as
a passionate relationship, she had convinced
herself long ago that this wasn't necessary
for fulfilment.
Passion would fade in time and things like
companionship and compatibility would take
its place.
She and Lon had this, and she had assumed
this was all she needed.
But now, as she watched Noah rowing, she questioned
this assumption.
He radiated sexuality in everything he did,
everything he was, and she caught herself
thinking about him in a way that an engaged
woman shouldn't.
"Here we are," Noah said as he guided the
canoe towards some trees near the bank.
Allie looked around, not seeing anything.
"Where is it?"
"Here," he said again, pointing the canoe
at a fallen tree that was almost completely
obscuring an opening.
He guided the canoe around the tree, and both
of them had to lower their heads to keep from
bumping them.
"Close your eyes," he whispered, and Allie
did, bringing her hands to her face.
She felt the movement of the canoe.
"Okay," he finally said after he'd stopped
paddling, "you can open them now."
THEY SAT in the middle of a small lake fed
by the waters of the river.
It wasn't large, maybe a hundred yards across,
and she was surprised at how invisible it
had been just moments before.
It was spectacular.
Swans and geese literally surrounded them.
Thousands of them.
Birds were floating so close together in some
places that she couldn't see the water.
From a distance, the groups of swans looked
almost like icebergs.
"Oh Noah," she finally said softly, "it's
beautiful."
They sat in silence for a long while, watching
the birds.
The birds ignored them for the most part.
The only ones that seemed bothered were those
forced to move when the canoe approached them.
Allie reached out to touch the closest ones
and felt their feathers under her fingers.
Noah took out the bread he'd brought in his
bag and handed it to Allie.
She scattered it, laughing and smiling as
the birds swam in circles looking for food.
They stayed until thunder boomed in the distance
- faint but powerful - and both of them knew
it was time to leave.
Noah paddled the canoe back.
She was still amazed by what she had seen.
"Noah, what are they doing here?"
"I don't know.
I know the swans from up north migrate to
Lake Matamuskeet every winter, but I guess
they came here this time.
I don't know why.
Maybe they got off track or something.
They'll find their way back, though.
They're driven by instinct, and this isn't
their place.
Some of the geese may winter here, but the
swans will go back to Matamuskeet."
Noah paddled hard as dark clouds rolled directly
overhead.
Soon rain began to fall.
Lightning... a pause... then thunder again.
A little louder now.
Maybe six or seven miles away.
More rain as Noah began to paddle even harder;
his muscles were tightening with every stroke.
Allie watched the rainfall.
The sky darkened a little more.
She leaned her head back for a moment to let
it hit her face.
She ran her hands through her hair, feeling
its wetness.
It felt wonderful, she felt wonderful.
Even through the rain, she could hear him
breathing hard, and the sound excited her
in a way she hadn't felt in years.
A cloud burst directly above them and the
rain began to come down harder than she'd
ever seen it.
Allie looked upwards and laughed, giving up
any attempt at keeping dry, making Noah feel
better.
Even though she'd made the decision to come,
he doubted that she'd expected to be caught
in a storm like this.
They reached the dock a couple of minutes
later, and Noah moved in close enough for
Allie to step out.
He helped her up, then got out himself and
dragged the canoe up the bank, tying it to
the jetty.
When he finished and stood, Allie took his
hands in hers, surprising him.
Despite the downpour, they didn't rush towards
the house, and Noah imagined what it would
be like to spend the night with her.
Allie felt the warmth in his hands and wondered
what it would be like to have them touch her
body.
Just thinking about it made her take a deep
breath.
She realized then that something had changed.
And she knew that she had fallen in love with
Noah Taylor Calhoun again, and that maybe,
just maybe, she had never stopped.
THERE WAS no uneasiness between them as they
reached the door and went inside.
"I think I can find something here for you
so you can get out of those clothes.
It might be a little big, but it's warm."
"Anything," she said.
"I'll be back in a second."
Noah slipped off his boots, then ran up the
stairs, descending a minute later.
He had a pair of cotton trousers and a long-sleeved
shirt under one arm and some jeans with a
blue shirt in the other.
"Here," he said, handing her the cotton trousers
and shirt.
"You can change in the bedroom upstairs.
There's a bathroom and towel up there too
if you want to shower."
She thanked him with a smile and went upstairs,
feeling his eyes on her as she walked.
She entered the bedroom and closed the door,
then set the trousers and shirt on his bed
and took everything off.
She didn't want to shower after the rain.
She liked the soft feeling on her skin.
She put on his clothes before looking at herself
in the mirror.
The trousers were big, but she rolled up the
bottoms so they wouldn't drag.
The neck was torn a little, but she liked
the way it looked on her anyway.
She pulled the sleeves up almost to the elbows,
went to the chest of drawers and slipped on
some socks, then went to the bathroom to find
a hairbrush.
When she was finished, she went back downstairs.
Noah was in the living room squatting before
a fire.
He poked the fire, moving the logs.
He didn't see her come in, and she watched
him as he worked.
He had changed his clothes as well and looked
good.
Allie stood in the doorway and continued to
watch him.
He caught a glimpse of her out of the comer
of his eye and looked up quickly.
Even in his clothes, she looked beautiful.
"I didn't hear you come in," he said, trying
to sound casual.
"How long have you been standing there?"
"A couple of minutes."
Noah pointed to the kitchen.
"Can I get you some tea?
I started the water while you were upstairs."
Small talk, anything to keep his mind clear.
But damn, the way she looked...
She thought for a second, and then asked,
"Do you have anything stronger, or is it too
early to drink?"
He smiled and said, "I have some bourbon in
the pantry.
Is that okay?"
"That sounds great."
He started towards the kitchen, and Allie
watched him run his hand through his wet hair
as he disappeared.
Thunder boomed loudly and another downpour
started.
Allie could hear the roaring of the rain on
the roof.
She took a quilt from the sofa and sat on
the rug in front of the fire.
Crossing her legs, she adjusted the quilt
until she was comfortable and watched the
dancing flames.
Noah came back, and sat beside her.
He put down two glasses and poured some bourbon
into each of them.
Outside, the sky grew darker.
Thunder again.
Loud.
The storm was in full fury.
"It's quite a storm," Noah said as he watched
the drops flow in vertical streams on the
windows.
He and Allie were close now, though not touching,
and Noah watched her chest rise slightly with
every breath.
"I like it," she said, taking a sip.
"I've always liked thunderstorms.
Even as a young girl."
"Why?"
"I don't know.
They just always seemed romantic to me."
She was quiet for a moment, and Noah watched
the fire flicker in her emerald eyes.
Then she said, "Do you remember sitting together
and watching the storm a few nights before
I left?"
"Of course."
"I used to think about it all the time after
I went home.
I always thought about how you looked that
night.
It was the way I remembered you."
"Have I changed much?"
She took another sip of bourbon, feeling it
warm her.
She touched his hand as she answered.
"Not really.
You're older, of course, with more life behind
you, but you've still got the same gleam in
your eye.
You still read poetry and float on rivers.
And you've still got a gentleness that not
even the war could take away."
He thought about what she'd said and felt
her hand lingering on his.
"Allie, you asked me earlier what I remembered
most about the summer.
What do you remember?"
It was a while before she answered.
"I remember making love.
That's what I remember most.
You were my first, and it was more wonderful
than I ever thought it would be."
Noah took a drink of bourbon, remembering,
bringing back the old feelings.
She squeezed his hand, let go, and moved closer.
She put her hand through his arm, and rested
her head on his shoulder.
He could smell her, soft like the rain, warm.
She spoke quietly.
"Do you remember walking home after the festival?
I asked you if you wanted to see me again.
You just nodded your head and didn't say a
word.
It wasn't too convincing."
"I'd never met anyone like you.
I didn't know what to say."
"I know.
You could never hide anything.
Your eyes always gave you away.
You had the most wonderful eyes I'd ever seen."
She lifted her head from his shoulder and
looked directly at him.
When she spoke, her voice was barely above
a whisper.
"I think I loved you more that summer than
I ever loved anyone."
Lightning flashed again.
In the quiet moments before the thunder, their
eyes met as they tried to undo fourteen years.
When the thunder finally sounded, Noah sighed
and turned from her towards the windows.
"It's a pity you didn't read the letters I
wrote you," he said.
She didn't speak for a while.
"Noah, I didn't tell you, but I wrote you
a dozen letters after I got home.
I just never sent them."
"Why?"
Noah was surprised.
"I guess I was too afraid."
"Of what?"
"That maybe it wasn't as real as I thought
it was.
That maybe you forgot me."
"I would never do that.
I couldn't even think it."
"I know that now.
I can see it when I look at you.
But back then it was different.
There was so much I didn't understand, things
that a young girl's mind couldn't sort out."
"What do you mean?"
"When your letters never came, I didn't know
what to think.
I remember talking to my best friend about
that summer, and she said that you had got
what you wanted, and that she wasn't surprised
that you didn't write.
I didn't believe that you were that way, I
never did, but I thought maybe the summer
meant more to me than to you..."
Noah looked away and she continued.
"In time, the hurt began to fade and it was
easier to just let it go.
At least I thought it was.
But in every boy I met in the next few years
I was looking for you, and when the feelings
got too strong I wrote you another letter.
But I never sent them for fear of what I might
find.
By then you'd gone on with your life and I
didn't want to think that you loved someone
else.
I wanted to remember us like we were that
summer."
"You're better than I remembered, Allie."
"You're sweet, Noah."
He almost stopped there, knowing that if he
kept the words inside him he could keep control,
the same control he had kept the past fourteen
years.
But then something overtook him and he gave
in to it, hoping it would take them back to
what they'd had so long ago.
"I'm not saying it because I'm sweet.
I'm saying it because I love you now and I
always have.
More than you can imagine."
Allie took a sip of bourbon and began to feel
its effects.
But it wasn't just the alcohol that made her
hold Noah a little tighter and feel his warmth
against her.
Glancing out of the window, she saw the clouds
were almost black.
"Noah, you've never asked, but I want you
to know something."
"What is it?"
Her voice was tender.
"There's never been another, Noah.
You weren't just the first.
You're the only man - I've ever been with,
I don't expect you to say the same thing,
but I wanted you to know."
Noah was silent as he turned away.
She felt warmer as she watched the fire.
She leaned into him and felt the heat between
them, felt his body, felt his arm tight around
her.
It felt so right to be here.
Everything felt right.
The fire, the drinks, the storm.
It seemed their years apart didn't matter
anymore.
They gave in then to everything they had fought
against for the last fourteen years.
Allie lifted her head off his shoulder, looked
at him with hazy eyes, and Noah kissed her
softly on the lips.
She brought her hand to his face and touched
his cheek, brushing it softly with her fingers.
He leaned in and kissed her tenderly, and
she kissed back, feeling the years of separation
dissolve into passion.
Without speaking, she started to undo the
buttons on his shirt.
He watched her as she did it and listened
to her soft breaths as she made her way downwards.
With each button, he could feel her fingers
brushing against his skin, and she smiled
softly at him when she finally finished.
She felt short of breath as his hands gently
caressed her, and she felt their heated bodies
press together, skin to skin.
They spent the day in each other's arms, alternately
making love by the fire and then holding each
other as they watched the flames.
He recited his favourite poems as she lay
beside him, and she listened with her eyes
closed and almost felt the words.
Then they joined again and he murmured words
of love between kisses as they wrapped their
arms around one another.
They went on throughout the evening, making
up for their years apart, and slept in each
other's arms that night.
Occasionally he woke up and looked at her,
and felt that everything was suddenly right
in this world.
Once, when he was looking at her in the moments
before daybreak, her eyes opened and she smiled
and reached up to touch his face.
He put his fingers to her lips, gently, to
keep her from speaking, and for a long time
they just looked at one another.
When the lump in his throat subsided, he whispered
to her, "You are the answer to every prayer
I've offered.
You are a song, a dream, a whisper.
I love you, Allie, more than you can ever
imagine, I always have and I always will."
"Oh, Noah," she said, pulling him to her.
She wanted him, needed him now more than ever,
like nothing she'd ever known.
CHAPTER SEVEN
AN UNEXPECTED VISITOR
LATER THAT same morning, three men - two lawyers
and the judge - sat in a room of the courthouse
while Lon finished speaking.
"It's an unusual request," the judge answered,
thinking about the situation.
"It seems to me the trial could very well
end today.
Are you saying this matter can't wait until
later this evening or tomorrow?"
"No, your honour, it can't," Lon answered
almost too quickly.
He told himself to stay relaxed.
He took a deep breath.
"And it has nothing to do with this case?"
"No, your honour.
It's of a personal nature.
I know it's out of the ordinary, but I really
need to take care of it."
The judge leaned back in his chair, looking
at him for a moment, and then said, "Mr. Bates,
how do you feel about this?"
The lawyer cleared his throat.
"Mr. Hammond called me this morning and I've
already spoken to my clients.
They agree to postpone until Monday."
The judge looked hard at both of them.
"I don't like it," he said, "not at all.
But Mr. Hammond has never made such a request
before, and I assume the matter is very important
to him."
He paused, then looked at some papers on his
desk.
"I'll agree to postpone until Monday; nine
o'clock sharp."
"Thank you, your honour," Lon said.
Two minutes later, he was leaving the courthouse.
He walked to the car he had parked directly
across the street, got in and began the drive
to New Bern.
His hands were shaking.
NOAH MADE breakfast for Allie while she slept
in the living room.
Bacon, rolls and coffee, nothing special.
He set the tray beside her as she woke up,
and as soon as they had finished eating, they
made love again.
They showered and afterwards Allie put on
her dress, which had dried overnight.
She spent the morning with Noah.
Together they fed Clem and checked the windows
to make sure no damage bad been done in the
storm.
Noah held Allie's hand most of the morning
and they talked easily, but sometimes he stopped
speaking and just stared at her.
When he did, she felt as though she should
say something, but nothing meaningful ever
came into her head.
She usually just kissed him.
A little before noon, Noah and Allie went
in to prepare lunch.
Using what he had, they fried some chicken
and baked many bread rolls, and the two of
them ate on the porch, listening to the birds
singing.
While they were inside doing the dishes, they
heard a knock at the door.
Noah left Allie in the kitchen.
Knock, knock.
Louder.
Noah approached the door.
Knock, knock.
"I'm coming," he said as he opened the door.
"Oh, my God."
He stared for a moment at a beautiful woman
in her early fifties, a woman he recognized
at once.
"Hello, Noah," she said.
Noah said nothing.
"May I come in?"
she asked; her voice was steady, showing nothing.
He mumbled a reply as she walked past him,
stopping just before the stairs.
"Who is it?"
Allie shouted from the kitchen, and the woman
turned at the sound of her voice.
"It's your mother," Noah finally answered,
and immediately after he said it he heard
the sound of breaking glass.
"I knew you would be here," Anne Nelson said
to her daughter as the three of them sat around
the coffee table in the living room.
"How could you be so sure?"
"You're my daughter.
One day when you have kids of your own, you'll
know the answer."
She smiled, but her manner was tense, and
Noah imagined how difficult this was for her.
"I saw the article, too, and I saw your reaction.
I also saw how nervous you've been during
the last couple of weeks, and when you said
you were going shopping near the coast, I
knew exactly what you meant."
"What about daddy?"
Anne Nelson shook her head, "No, I didn't
tell your father or anyone else about it.
Nor did I tell anyone where I was going today."
"Why did you come?"
Allie asked.
"I came because I had to," her mother said,
"Which I'm sure is the same reason you came.
Am I right?"
Allie nodded.
Anne turned to Noah.
"I know you don't think so, but I always liked
you.
I just didn't think you were right for my
daughter.
Can you understand that?"
He shook his head as he answered, "No, not
really.
It wasn't fair to me, and it wasn't fair to
Allie.
Otherwise she wouldn't be here."
She watched him as he spoke, but she said
nothing.
Allie, sensing an argument, cut in.
"What do you mean when you say you had to
come?
Don't you trust me?"
Anne turned back to her daughter.
"This has nothing to do with trust.
This has to do with Lon.
He called the house last night to talk to
me about Noah, and he's on his way here right
now.
He seemed very upset.
I thought you'd want to know."
Allie inhaled sharply.
"He's on his way?"
"As we speak.
He arranged to have the trial postponed until
next week.
If he's not in New Bern yet, he's close."
"What did you say to him?"
"Not much.
But he guessed.
He remembered my telling him about Noah a
long time ago."
Allie swallowed hard, and then asked, "Did
you tell him I was here?"
"No.
And I won't.
That's between you and him.
But knowing him, I'm sure he'll find you.
All it takes is a couple of phone calls to
the right people.
After all, I was able to find you."
Allie, though obviously tired, smiled at her
mother.
"Thank you," she said, and her mother reached
for her hand.
"I know we've had our differences, Allie,
and that we haven't seen eye to eye on everything.
But I'm your mother and that means I'll always
love you."
Allie was silent for a moment, and then asked,
"What should I do?"
"I don't know, Allie.
That's up to you.
But I would think about it.
Think about what you really want."
Allie turned away, her eyes were reddening.
A moment later, a tear drifted down her cheek.
"I don't know..."
Her mother squeezed her hand.
Anne looked at Noah, who had been sitting
with his head down, listening carefully.
As if reading her mind, he returned her gaze,
nodded and left the room.
When he was gone, Anne whispered, "Do you
love him?"
"Yes, I do," Allie answered softly, "very
much."
"Do you love Lon?"
"Yes, I do.
I love him, too.
Dearly, but in a different way.
He doesn't make me feel the way Noah does."
"No one will ever do that," her mother said,
and she released Allie's hand.
"I can't make this decision for you, Allie,
this one's all yours.
I want you to know, though, that I love you.
And I always will.
I know that doesn't help, but it's all I can
do."
She reached in her handbag and removed a packet
of letters held together with string; the
envelopes were old and slightly yellowed.
"These are the letters that Noah wrote to
you.
I never threw them away, and I didn't open
them.
I know, it was wrong of me to keep them from
you, and I'm sorry for that.
But I was just trying to protect you.
I didn't realize..."
Allie took them and ran her hand over them,
shocked.
"I should go, Allie.
You've got some decisions to make, and you
don't have much time.
Do you want me to stay in town?"
Allie shook her head, "No, this is up to me."
Anne nodded and watched her daughter for a
moment.
Finally, she stood, went around the table,
leaned over and kissed Allie on the cheek.
She could see the confusion in her daughter's
eyes as Allie embraced her.
They stood together for another minute, just
holding each other.
"Thanks for coming," Allie said, "I love you."
"I love you too."
As her mother left the living room, Allie
thought that she heard her whisper, "Follow
your heart," but she couldn't be sure.
NOAH OPENED the door for Anne Nelson as she
went out.
"Goodbye Noah," she said quietly.
He nodded without speaking.
There wasn't anything else to say; they both
knew that.
She turned from him and left, closing the
door behind her.
Noah watched her leave without looking back.
She was a strong woman, he thought to himself,
and he knew then where Allie got it.
Noah peeped into the living room, saw Allie
sitting with her head down, then went to the
back porch, knowing that she needed to be
alone.
He sat quietly in his rocker and watched the
water.
After a while, he heard the back door open.
He didn't turn to look at her - for some reason
he couldn't - and he listened as she sat in
the chair beside him.
"I'm sorry," Allie said, "I had no idea this
would happen."
Noah shook his head.
"Don't be sorry.
We both knew it was coming to some form or
another."
"It's still hard."
"I know."
He finally turned to her, reaching for her
hand.
"Is here anything I can do to make it easier?"
She shook her head.
"No.
Not really.
I have to do this alone.
Besides, I'm not sure what I'm going to say
to him yet."
She looked down and her voice became softer.
"I guess it depends on him and how much he
knows.
If my mother was right, he may have suspicions,
but he doesn't know anything for sure."
Noah felt tightness in his stomach.
When he finally spoke his voice was steady,
but she could hear the pain in it.
"You're not going to tell him about us, are
you?"
"I don't know.
I really don't.
While I was in the living room, I was asking
myself what I really wanted in my life."
She squeezed his hand.
"And do you know what the answer was?
The answer was that I want you.
I want us.
I love you and I always have."
She took a deep breath before going on.
"But I also want a happy ending without hurting
anyone.
And I know that if I stayed, people would
be hurt.
Especially Lon.
I wasn't lying when I told you that I love
him.
He doesn't make me feel the same way you do,
but I care for him, and this wouldn't be fair
to him.
Staying here would also hurt my family and
friends.
I would betray everyone I know... I don't
know if I can do that."
"You can't live your life for other people.
You've got to do what's right for you, even
if it hurts some people you love."
"I know," she said, "but no matter what I
choose I have to live with it.
Forever.
I have to be able to go forward and not look
back any more.
Can you understand that?"
He shook his head and tried to keep his voice
steady.
"Not really.
Not if it means losing you.
I can't do that again."
She didn't say anything but lowered her head.
Noah went on, "Could you really leave me without
looking back?"
She bit her lip as she answered.
"I don't know.
Probably not."
"Would that be fair to Lon?"
She didn't answer.
Instead, she stood up, wiped her face and
walked to the edge of the porch where she
leaned against the post and watched the water
before answering quietly: "No."
"It doesn't have to be like this, Allie,"
he said.
"We're adults now, we have the choice we didn't
have before.
We're meant to be together.
We always have been."
He walked to her side and put his hand on
her shoulder.
"I don't want to live the rest of my life
thinking about you and dreaming of something
that never happened.
Stay with me, Allie."
Tears filled her eyes.
"I don't know if I can," she whispered.
"You can, Allie...
I can't live my life happily knowing you're
with someone else.
That would kill a part of me.
What we have is rare.
It's too beautiful to just throw it away."
After a moment, he gently turned her towards
him, took her hands and stared at her.
Allie finally faced him with wet eyes.
After a long silence, Noah brushed the tears
from her cheeks with his fingers.
He saw what her eyes were telling him.
"You're not going to stay, are you?"
He smiled weakly.
"You want to, but you can't."
"Oh, Noah," she said as the tears began again,
"try to understand-"
He shook his head to stop her.
"I know what you're trying to say - I can
see it in your eyes.
But I don't want to understand it, Allie.
I don't want it to end this way.
I don't want it to end at all.
But if you leave, we both know we'll never
see each other again."
She leaned into him and began to cry harder
as Noah fought back his own tears.
He wrapped his arms around her.
"Allie, I can't force you to stay with me.
But no matter what happens in my life, I'll
never forget these last couple of days with
you.
I've been dreaming about this for years."
He kissed her gently, and they embraced as
they had when she first got out of her car
two days ago.
Finally, Allie let him go and wiped her tears.
"I have to get my things, Noah."
He didn't go inside with her.
Instead, he sat down in the rocker, exhausted.
He watched her go into the house and listened
as the sound of her movements faded away.
She emerged minutes later with everything
she'd brought and walked towards him with
her head down.
She handed him the drawing she had done yesterday
morning.
"Here, Noah.
I made this for you."
Noah took the drawing and unrolled it slowly.
The image in the foreground was a picture
of how he looked now.
Noah noticed that she had depicted every detail
of his face.
It was almost as if she'd copied it from a
recent photograph.
The second image was the front of the house.
The detail there was also incredible, as if
she had sketched it while sitting beneath
the oak tree.
"It's beautiful, Allie.
Thank you."
He attempted a smile.
"I told you that you were an artist."
She nodded with her lips pressed together.
It was time for her to go.
They walked to her car slowly, without speaking.
When they reached it, Noah embraced her again
until he could feel the tears in his own eyes.
He kissed her lips and both cheeks, then with
his finger softly brushed the places he'd
kissed.
"I love you, Allie."
"I love you, too."
Noah opened her car door and they kissed one
more time.
Then she slid behind the wheel, never taking
her eyes from him.
She put the packet of letters and her handbag
next to her on the seat and took the keys,
then started the engine.
It was almost time.
Noah pushed her door closed with both hands
and Allie rolled down the window.
She reached out her hand and Noah took it
for just a moment, moving his fingers softly
against her skin.
"Stay with me," Noah mouthed without sound,
and this for some reason hurt more than Allie
could expect.
The tears began to fall hard now, but she
couldn't speak.
Reluctantly, she looked away and pulled her
hand from his.
He fell into an almost trancelike state as
he watched the car roll slowly forwards.
Slowly it turned towards the road that would
take her back to town.
Noah felt dizzy at the sight.
"Don't go!" he wanted to shout.
But he didn't say anything, and a minute later
the only remaining signs of her were the tracks
that her car had left behind.
She was gone.
Forever this time.
Forever.
He closed his eyes.
DRIVING WITH TEARS in her eyes was difficult,
but Allie went on anyway.
She kept the window rolled down, thinking
the fresh air might help clear her mind.
By the time she reached Front Street, she
had herself a little more under control.
Traffic was light and she had time to watch
strangers going about their business as she
drove through New Bern.
She saw the inn just up the street drove slowly
until she reached the parking lot.
She turned in and saw Lon's car sitting in
the first spot.
Although the one next to it was open, she
passed it and picked a spot a little further
from the entrance.
She turned off the engine, then reached into
the glove compartment for a mirror and brush.
Looking at herself, she saw her eyes were
still red and swollen.
She took her purse, opened it, and once again
looked at the article that had brought her
here.
It felt impossible to her that she had arrived
only the day before yesterday.
It seemed like a lifetime since her dinner
with Noah.
She remembered the letters her mother had
given her and reached for them.
She untied the package and found the first
letter he had written her.
She began to open it, then stopped because
she could imagine what was in it.
Something simple, no doubt - things he'd done,
memories of the summer, perhaps some questions.
Instead, she reached for the last letter,
the one on the bottom of the stack.
The goodbye letter.
This one interested her far more.
How had he said it?
The envelope was thin.
One, maybe two pages.
The letter wasn't too long.
She turned it over and checked the back.
No name, just a street address in New Jersey.
She held her breath.
Unfolding it, she saw it was dated March 1935.
Two and a half years without a reply.
She began to read.
My dearest Allie,
I don't know what to say any more except that
I couldn't sleep last night because I knew
that it is over between us.
It is a different feeling for me, one that
I never expected.
Looking back, I suppose it is a natural ending
of our story.
You and I were different.
We came from different worlds, and yet you
were the one who taught me the value of love.
You showed me what it was like to care for
another, and I am a better man because of
it.
I don't want you ever to forget that.
I am not bitter because of what has happened.
I am happy we were able to come together for
even a short time.
And if, in some distant place in the future,
we see each other in our new lives, I will
smile at you with joy, and remember how we
spent a summer learning from each other and
growing in love.
And maybe, for a brief moment, you'll feel
it too, and you'll smile back and enjoy the
memories we will always share.
I love you, Allie.
Noah
She read the letter again, then put it back
into the envelope.
She knew she couldn't delay any longer.
Lon was waiting for her.
Her legs felt weak as she stepped out of the
car.
She paused and took a deep breath, and as
she started across the parking lot, she realized
that she still wasn't sure what she was going
to say to him.
And the answer didn't finally come until she
reached the door and opened it and saw Lon
standing in the lobby.
CHAPTER EIGHT
WINTER FOR TWO
THE STORY ends there, so I close the notebook,
remove my glasses and wipe my eyes.
I look at her now that I have finished, but
she does not look back.
Instead, she is staring out of the window
at the courtyard, where friends and family
meet.
I read to her this morning, as I do every
morning, because it is something I must do.
Not for duty but for another, more romantic
reason.
I wish I could explain it more fully right
now, but it's still early, and talking about
romance isn't really possible before lunch
any more, at least not for me.
Besides, I have no idea how it's going to
turn out.
We spend every day together now, but our nights
are spent alone.
The doctors tell me that I'm not allowed to
see her after dark.
I understand the reasons, and though I agree
with them completely I sometimes break the
rules.
Late at night when my mood is right, I leave
my room and go to hers and watch her while
she sleeps.
Of this, she knows nothing.
I come in and see her breathe and know that,
had it not been for her, I would never have
married.
And when I look at her face, I know that I
have meant as much to her.
And that means more to me than I could ever
hope to explain.
Sometimes, when I am standing there, I think
about how lucky I am to have been married
to her for almost forty-nine years.
She heard me snore for the first forty-five
years, but since then we have slept in separate
rooms.
I do not sleep well without her.
I turn and yearn for her warmth and lie there
most of the night, with my eyes open wide,
watching the shadows on the ceiling.
I sleep two hours if I am lucky, and still
I wake before dawn.
I shuffle towards her and sit in the chair
beside her bed.
My back aches when I sit.
I reach for her hand and take it; it's bony
and fragile.
It feels nice.
She responds - gradually her thumb begins
to rub my finger softly.
I do not speak until she does; this I have
learned.
Most days I sit in silence until the sun goes
down.
Minutes pass before she finally turns to me.
She is crying.
I smile and release her hand, then reach in
my pocket.
I take out a handkerchief and wipe at her
tears.
She looks at me as I do so, and I wonder what
she is thinking.
"That was a beautiful story."
A light rain begins to fall.
Little drops tap gently on the window.
I take her hand again.
It is going to be a good day, a very good
day.
A magical day.
I smile.
"Yes, it is," I tell her.
"Did you write it?"
she asks; her voice is like a whisper.
"Yes," I answer.
She turns towards the nightstand.
Her medicine is in a little cup.
Mine too.
Little pills, their colours are like a rainbow
so we won't forget to take them.
The nurses bring my pills here to her room
now.
"I've heard it before, haven't I?"
"Yes," I say again, just as I do every time.
I have learned to be patient.
She studies my face.
Her eyes are as green as ocean waves.
"It makes me feel less afraid," she says.
"I know," I nod.
She turns away, and I wait some more.
She releases my hand and reaches for her water
glass.
She takes a sip.
"Is it a true story?"
She sits up a little in her bed and takes
another drink.
Her body is still strong.
"I mean, did you know these people?"
"Yes," I say again.
I could say more, but usually I don't.
She is still beautiful.
She asks the obvious.
"Well, which one did she finally marry?"
I answer, "The one who was right for her."
"Which one was that?"
I smile.
"You'll know," I say quietly, "by the end
of the day.
You'll know."
She does not question me further.
Instead, she begins to fidget.
She is thinking of a way to ask me another
question, though she isn't sure how to do
it.
"I have to ask you something else," she says
finally.
"Whatever it is, I'll try to answer."
"It's hard, though."
She does not look at me and I cannot see her
eyes.
This is how she hides her thoughts.
Some things never change.
"Take your time," I say.
I know what she will ask.
She turns to me and looks into my eyes.
She offers a gentle smile, the kind you share
with a child, not a lover.
"I don't want to hurt your feelings because
you've been so nice to me, but..."
I wait.
Her words will hurt me.
They will tear a piece from my heart and leave
a scar.
"Who are you?"
WE HAVE LIVED at the nursing home for three
years now.
It was her decision to come here, because
she thought it would be easier for me.
We signed some papers, and received a place
to live and die in exchange for some of the
freedom for which we had worked a lifetime.
She was right to do this, of course.
There is no way I could make it alone, for
sickness has come to us, both of us.
We are in the final minutes of our lives,
and the clock is ticking.
Loudly.
I wonder if I am the only one who can hear
it.
A burning pain courses through my fingers,
and it reminds me that we have not held hands
with fingers interlocked since we moved here.
I am sad about this, but it is my fault, not
hers.
It is arthritis in the worst form.
But every day I take her hands despite the
pain, and I do my best to hold them because
that is what she wants me to do.
Although the Bible says man can live to be
a hundred and twenty years old, I don't want
to.
My body is falling apart.
My kidneys are beginning to fail and my heart
rate is decreasing every month.
What is worse, I have cancer again, this time
of the prostate.
This is my third battle with the unseen enemy,
and it will take me eventually, though not
till I say it is time.
The doctors are worried about me, but I am
not.
I have no time for worry now.
Of our five children, four are still living,
and though it is hard for them to visit, they
come often, and for this, I am thankful.
But even when they aren't here, they come
alive in my mind every day, each of them,
and they bring to mind the smiles and tears
that come with raising a family.
There are many pictures on the walls of my
room.
My children are my contribution to the world.
I am very proud.
Sometimes I wonder what my wife thinks of
them as she dreams, or if she thinks of them
at all, or if she even dreams.
There is so much about her I don't understand
anymore.
"My name," I say, "is Duke."
I have always been a John Wayne fan.
"Duke," she whispers to herself, "Duke."
She thinks for a moment.
"Yes," I say, "I'm here for you."
And always will be, I think to myself.
She flushes with my answer.
Her eyes become wet and red, and tears begin
to fall.
My heart aches for her, but there is nothing
I could do.
She says, "I'm sorry.
I don't understand anything that's happening
to me right now.
Even you.
When I listen to you talk I feel like I should
know you, but I don't.
I don't even know my name."
She wipes at her tears and says, "Help me,
Duke, help me remember who I am.
Or at least, who I was.
I feel so lost."
I answer from my heart, but I lie to her about
her name.
As I have about my own.
There is a reason for this.
"You are Hannah, a lover of life, a loyal
friend.
You are a dream, a creator of happiness, an
artist who has touched a thousand souls.
You've led a full life and wanted for nothing,
because your needs are spiritual and you have
only to look inside you.
You are kind, and you are able to see beauty
where others do not.
You are a teacher of wonderful lessons, a
dreamer of better things."
She does not respond.
Instead, she stares at me for a long while,
until our breathing coincides.
In.
Out.
Deep breaths.
I wonder if she knows I think she's beautiful.
"Would you stay with me a while?"
she finally asks.
I smile and nod.
She smiles back.
She reaches for my hand, takes it gently and
pulls it to her waist.
She stares at the knots that deform my fingers
and touches them gently.
Her hands are still those of an angel.
"Come," I say as I stand with great effort,
"let's go for a walk.
The air is fresh and the birds are waiting.
It's beautiful today."
I am staring at her as I say these last few
words.
She blushes.
It makes me feel young again.
SHE WAS FAMOUS, of course.
One of the best southern painters of the twentieth
century, some said, and I was, and am, proud
of her.
Her paintings are in museums around the world,
but I have kept only two for myself.
The first one she ever gave me and the last
one.
They hang in my room, and late at night I
sit and stare and sometimes cry when I look
at them.
I don't know why.
And so the years passed.
We led our lives, working, painting, raising
children, loving each other.
I see photos of Christmases, family trips,
of graduations and of weddings.
I see grandchildren and happy faces.
I see photos of us, our hair growing whiter,
the lines in our faces deeper.
A lifetime that seems so typical, yet uncommon.
We could not foresee the future, but who can?
I do not live now as I expected to.
But I am not bitter.
Our lives can't be measured by our final years,
of this I am sure.
Looking back, I suppose it seems obvious,
but at first, I thought her confusion understandable
and not unique.
She would forget where she placed her keys,
but who has not done that?
She would forget a neighbour's name, but not
someone we knew well or with whom we socialized.
Sometimes she would write the wrong year when
she made out her cheques, but again I took
it for simple mistakes that one makes when
thinking of other things.
But when the more obvious events occurred
I began to suspect the worst.
An iron in the freezer, clothes in the dishwasher,
books in the oven.
Other things, too.
But the day I found her in the car three blocks
away, crying because she couldn't find her
way home, was the first day I was really frightened.
And she was frightened, too, for when I tapped
on her window, she turned to me and said,
"Oh God, what's happening to me?
Please help me."
A knot twisted in my stomach, but I dared
not think the worst.
Six days later the doctor saw her and began
a series of tests.
I did not understand them then and I do not
understand them now, but I suppose it is because
I am afraid to know.
She spent almost an hour with Dr. Barnwell.
Finally, he called us both into his office
and sat us down.
She held my arm confidently, but I remember
clearly that my own hands were shaking.
"I'm so sorry to have to tell you this," Dr.
Barnwell began, "but you seem to be in the
early stages of Alzheimer's..."
The words echoed in my head: the early stages
of Alzheimer's...
My world spun in circles, and I felt her grip
tighten on my arm.
She whispered, almost to herself, "Oh, Noah...
Noah..."
And tears started to fall.
It is a dreadful disease, as empty and lifeless
as a desert.
It is a thief of souls and memories.
I did not know what to say to her as she cried,
so I simply held her and rocked her back and
forth.
I remember only bits and pieces of Dr. Barnwell's
continuing explanation.
"It's a degenerative brain disorder affecting
memory and personality...
there is no cure or therapy...
there's no way to tell how fast it will progress...
it differs from person to person...
I wish I knew more...
Some days will be better than others...
It will grow worse with the passage of time...
I'm sorry..."
It has been four years now.
Since then we have made the best of it, if
that is possible.
Allie made arrangements to leave the house
and move here.
She rewrote her will and sealed it.
She left specific burial instructions, and
they are in my desk.
I have not seen them.
And when she was finished, she began to write.
Letters to friends and children.
Letters to brothers and sisters and cousins.
Letters to nieces, nephews and neighbours.
And a letter to me.
I read it sometimes when I am in the mood
and, when I do, I remember Allie on cold winter
evenings, sitting by a fireplace with a glass
of wine at her side, reading the letters I
had written to her over the years.
She kept them, these letters, and now I keep
them, for she made me promise to do so.
She said I would know what to do with them.
She was right; I find I enjoy reading them
from time to time.
I see Allie now and know I've never loved
her more, but as I read the letters, I come
to understand that I have always felt the
same way.
I read them last three evenings ago.
It was almost two o'clock when I went to the
desk and took out the stack of letters.
I untied the string and found the letters
her mother had hidden so long ago and those
from afterwards.
A lifetime of letters, letters expressing
my love, letters from my heart.
I glanced through them with a smile on my
face, picking and choosing, and finally opened
a letter from a cold evening thirty-nine years
ago.
I read an extract:
Sitting next to you, while our youngest daughter
sang in the school Christmas show, I looked
at you and saw a pride that comes only to
those who feel deeply in their hearts, and
I knew that no man could be luckier than me.
And after our son died, the one who resembled
his mother...
It was the hardest time we ever went through,
and the words still ring true today:
In times of grief and sorrow, I will hold
you and rock you, and take your grief and
make it my own.
When you cry, I cry, and when you hurt, I
hurt.
And together we will try to hold back the
floods of tears and despair and make it through.
I pause for just a moment, remembering him.
He was four years old at the time, just a
baby.
It is a terrible thing to outlive your child,
a tragedy I wish upon no one.
They went on, this correspondence of life
and love, and I read dozens more, some painful,
most heart-warming.
By three o'clock, I was tired, but I had reached
the bottom of the stack.
There was one letter remaining, the last one
I wrote to her.
I moved the first page into better light and
began to read:
My dearest Allie,
The porch is silent, and for once, I am at
a loss for words.
It is a strange experience for me, for when
I think of you and the life we have shared,
there is much to remember.
A lifetime of memories.
But to put it into words?
I am not a poet, and yet a poem is needed
to fully express the way I feel about you.
So my mind drifts and I remember thinking
about our life together as I made coffee this
morning.
Kate was there, and so was Jane, and they
both became quiet when I walked into the kitchen.
I saw they'd been crying, and without a word
I sat myself beside them at the table and
held, their hands.
And when I looked at them, I saw you from
so long-ago, the day we said goodbye.
They resemble you and how you were then, beautiful
and sensitive and wounded with the hurt that
comes when something special is taken away.
And for a reason I'm not sure I understand,
I was inspired to tell them a story.
I called Jeff and David into the kitchen,
for they were here as well, and when the children
were ready I told them about us and how you
came back to me so long ago.
I told them about our walk, and the crab dinner
in the kitchen, and they listened with smiles
when they heard about the canoe ride, and
sitting in front of the fire with the storm
raging outside.
I told them about your mother warning us about
Lon the next day - they seemed as surprised
as we were - and yes, I even told them what
happened later that day, after you went back
to town.
That part of the story has never left me,
even after all this time.
Even though you described it to me only once,
I remember how impressed I was at the strength
you showed that day.
I still cannot imagine what was going through
your mind when you walked into the lobby and
saw Lon.
You told me that the two of you left the inn
and sat on a bench by the old Methodist church,
and that he held your hand, even as you explained
that you must stay.
I know you cared for him.
And his reaction proves to me he cared for
yur as well.
Even as you explained that you had always
loved me, and that it wouldn't be fair to
him, he did not release your hand.
I know he was hurt and angry, and tried for
almost an hour to change your mind, but when
you stood firm and said, "I can't go back
with you, I'm so sorry," he knew that you
had made your decision.
You said he simply nodded and the two of you
sat together for a long time without speaking.
I have always wondered what he was thinking
as he sat with you, but I'm sure it was the
same way I felt only a few hours before.
And when he finally walked you to your car,
you said he told you that I was a lucky man.
He behaved as a gentleman would, and I understood
then why your choice was so hard.
I remember that when I finished the story,
the room was quiet until Kate finally stood
to embrace me.
"Oh, Daddy," she said with tears in her eyes,
and though I expected to answer their questions,
they did not ask any.
Instead, they gave me something much more
special.
For the next four hours, each of them told
me how much the two of us had meant to them
while they were growing up.
One by one, they told stories about things
I had long since forgotten.
And by the end I was crying, because I realized
how well we had done with raising them.
I was so proud of them, and proud of you,
and happy about the life we have led.
And nothing will ever take that away.
Nothing.
I only regret that you were not here to enjoy
it with me.
After they left, I rocked in silence, thinking
back on our life together.
You are always here with me when I do so,
at least in my heart, and it is impossible
for me to remember a time when you were not
a part of me.
I love you, Allie.
I am who I am because of you.
You are every reason, every hope and every
dream I've ever had, and no matter what happens
to us in the future, every day we are together
is the greatest day of my life.
I will always be yours.
And, my darling, you will always be mine.
Noah
I put the pages aside and remember sitting
with Allie on our porch when she read this
letter for the first time.
It was late afternoon.
The sky was slowly changing colour, and as
I watched the sun go down, I thought about
that brief moment when day suddenly turns
into night.
Dusk, I realized, is just an illusion, because
the sun is either above the horizon or below
it.
And that means that day and night are linked
in a way that few things are; there cannot
be one without the other, yet they cannot
exist at the same time.
How would it feel, I wondered, to be always
together, yet forever apart?
I know the answer now.
I know what it's like to be day and night
now; always together, forever apart.
THERE IS BEAUTY where we sit this afternoon,
Allie and I.
The birds, the geese, float on the cool water,
which makes them seem larger than they really
are.
Allie too is watching them, and little by
little, we get to know each other again.
"It's good to talk to you.
I find that I miss it, even when it hasn't
been that long."
I am sincere and she knows this, but she is
still cautious.
I am a stranger.
"Is this something we do often?"
she asks.
"Do we sit here and watch the birds a lot?
I mean, do we know each other well?"
"Yes and no.
I think everyone has secrets, but we have
been acquainted for years."
She looks to her hands, then mine.
She thinks about this for a moment.
We do not wear our rings.
Again, there is a reason for this.
She asks, "Were you ever married?"
I nod.
"Yes."
"What was she like?"
I tell the truth.
"She was my dream.
She made me who I am, and holding her in my
arms was more natural to me than my own heartbeat.
I think about her all the time.
Even now, when I'm sitting here, I think about
her."
She takes this in.
I don't know how she feels about this.
Finally, she speaks softly, her voice is angelic,
sensual.
I wonder if she knows I think these things.
"Is she dead?"
"My wife is alive in my heart.
And she always will be," I answer.
"You still love her, don't you?"
"Of course.
But I love many things.
I love to sit here with you.
I love to share the beauty of this place with
someone I care about."
She is quiet for a moment.
She looks away so I can't see her face.
It has been her habit for years.
"Why are you doing this?"
No fear, just curiosity.
This is good.
I know what she means, but I ask anyway.
"What?"
"Why are you spending the day with me?"
I smile.
"I'm here because this is where I'm supposed
to be.
It's not complicated.
Both you and I are enjoying ourselves.
My time with you is not wasted.
It's what I want.
I sit here and we talk and I think to myself,
'What could be better than what I am doing
now?"'
She looks in my eyes, and for a moment, just
a moment, her eyes twinkle.
A slight smile forms on her lips.
"I admit I enjoy your company, but I know
nothing about you.
I don't expect you to tell me your life story,
but why are you so mysterious?"
"I read once that women love mysterious strangers."
"See, you haven't really answered the question.
You haven't answered most of my questions.
You didn't even tell me how the story ended
this morning."
I shrug.
We sit quietly for a while.
Finally, I ask, "Is it true that women love
mysterious strangers?"
She thinks about this and laughs.
Then she answers as I would, "I think some
women do."
"Do you?"
"Now don't go putting me on the spot.
I don't know you well enough for that."
She is teasing me and I enjoy it.
We sit and watch the world around us.
This has taken us a lifetime to learn.
It seems only the old are able to sit next
to one another and not say anything and still
feel happy.
The young, impatient, must always break the
silence.
It is a waste, for silence is pure.
Silence is holy.
It draws people together because only those
who are comfortable with each other can sit
without speaking.
This is the great paradox.
Time passes, and gradually our breathing begins
to coincide.
Deep breaths, relaxed breaths, and there is
a moment when she dozes off, like those comfortable
with one another often do.
When she wakes, a miracle: "Do you see that
bird?"
She points to it, and I can see it because
the sun is bright.
"Caspian stem," I say softly, and we devote
our attention to it as it flies over the river.
And, like an old habit rediscovered, when
I lower my arm, I put my hand on her knee
and she doesn't make me move it.
SHE IS RIGHT about my evasiveness.
On days like these, when only her memory is
gone, I am vague in my answers because I've
hurt my wife unintentionally with careless
slips of my tongue many times these past few
years, and I am determined not to let it happen
again.
So I limit myself and answer only what is
asked, to limit the pain.
There are days she never learns of her children
or that we are married.
I am sorry for this, but I will not change.
Does this make me dishonest?
Perhaps, but I have seen her crushed by the
waterfall of information that is her life.
Could I look myself in the mirror without
red eyes and trembling jaw and know I have
forgotten all that was important to me?
I could not and neither can she, for when
this odyssey began, that is how I began.
Her life, her marriage, her children.
Her friends and her work.
The days were hard on both of us.
I was an encyclopedia, an object without feeling,
of the who's, what's and where's in her life,
when in reality it is the whys, the things
I did not know and could not answer, that
make it all worthwhile.
She stared at pictures of forgotten children,
held paintbrushes that inspired nothing, and
read love letters that brought back no joy.
She became weaker over the hours, grew paler,
and ended the day worse than when it began.
Our days were lost and so was she.
So I changed.
I learned what is obvious to a child.
That life is simply a collection of little
lives, each lived one day at a time.
That each day should be spent finding beauty
in flowers and poetry and talking to animals.
That a day spent with dreaming and sunsets
and refreshing breezes cannot be better.
But most of all, I learned that life is for
sitting on benches next to rivers with my
hand on her knee and sometimes, on good days,
for falling in love.
"WHAT ARE you thinking?"
she asks.
It is now dusk.
We have left our bench and are walking slowly.
She is holding my arm and I am her escort.
It is her idea to do this.
Perhaps she is charmed by me.
Perhaps she wants to keep me from falling.
Either way, I am smiling to myself.
"I'm thinking about you."
She makes no response to this except to squeeze
my arm, and I can tell she likes what I said.
I go on, "I know you can't remember who you
are, but I can, and I find that when I look
at you it makes me feel good."
She taps my arm and smiles.
"You're a kind man with a loving heart.
I hope I enjoyed you as much before as I do
now."
I think about this as we walk in silence,
holding each other, past the rooms, past the
courtyard.
We come to the garden, mainly with wild flowers,
and I stop her.
I pick some flowers - red, pink, yellow, violet.
I give them to her, and she brings them to
her nose.
She smells them with eyes closed and she whispers,
"They're beautiful."
We continue our walk, me in one hand, the
flowers in another.
People watch us, for we are a walking miracle,
or so I am told.
It is true in a way.
By the time we reach the doorway, I am tired.
She knows this, so she stops me with her hand
and makes me face her.
She turns to me and stares for a long time.
"What are you doing?"
I ask.
"I don't want to forget you or this day, and
I'm trying to keep your memory alive."
I wonder for a moment if it will work this
time, then I know it will not.
It can't.
I do not tell her my thoughts, though.
I smile instead because her words are sweet.
"Thank you," I say.
"I mean it.
I don't want to forget you again.
You're very special to me."
My throat closes a little.
There is emotion behind her words, the emotions
I feel whenever I think of her.
I know this is why I live, and I love her
dearly at this moment.
How I wish I were strong enough to carry her
in my arms to paradise.
"Don't try to say anything," she tells me.
"Let's just feel the moment."
And I do, and I feel heaven.
HER DISEASE is worse now than it was in the
beginning, though Allie is different from
most.
There are three others with the disease here,
and they are the sum of my practical experience
of it.
They, unlike Allie, are in the most advanced
stages of Alzheimer's and are almost completely
lost.
They wake up hallucinating and confused.
They seldom recognize the people who love
them.
It is a trying disease, and this is why it
is hard for their children and mine to visit.
Allie, of course, has her own problems.
She is terribly afraid in the mornings and
cries inconsolably.
She sees tiny people, like gnomes, I think,
watching her, and she screams at them to get
away.
She bathes willingly but doesn't want to eat
regularly.
She is thin now, much too thin in my opinion,
and on good days, I do my best to fatten her
up.
But this is where the similarity ends.
This is why Allie is considered a miracle,
because sometimes, just sometimes, after I
read to her, her condition isn't so bad.
There is no explanation for this.
"It's impossible," the doctors say, "she cannot
have Alzheimer's."
But she does.
On most days and every morning, there can
be no doubt.
But why, then, is her condition different?
Why does she sometimes change after I read?
I tell the doctors the reason - I know it
in my heart, but they don't believe me.
Four times specialists have travelled from
Chapel Hill to find the answer.
Four times, they have left without understanding.
I tell them, "You can't possibly understand
it if you use only your science training and
your books," but they shake their heads and
answer, "Alzheimer's does not work like this.
With her condition, it's just not possible
to have a conversation or improve as the day
goes on.
Ever."
But she does.
Not every day, not most of the time, and definitely
less than she used to.
But sometimes.
And all that is gone on these days is her
memory, as if she has amnesia.
Her emotions are normal, her thoughts are
normal.
And these are the days that I know I am doing
right.
DINNER IS WAITING in her room when we return.
It has been arranged for us to eat here, as
it always is on days like these, and once
again, I could ask for no more.
The people here are good to me and I am thankful.
The room is lit by two candles on the table
where we will sit, and music is playing softly
in the background.
The cups and plates are plastic and the jug
is filled with apple juice, but rules are
rules and she doesn't care.
She inhales slightly at the sight.
Her eyes are wide.
"Did you do this?"
I nod and she walks into the room.
"It looks beautiful."
I offer my arm in escort and lead her to the
window.
She doesn't release it when we get there.
Her touch is nice, and we stand close together
on this crystal springtime evening.
The window is open slightly and I feel a breeze.
The moon has risen and we watch for a long
time as the evening sky unfolds.
"I've never seen anything so beautiful, I'm
sure of it," she says.
"I haven't, either," I say, but I am looking
at her.
She knows what I mean and I see her smile.
A moment later she whispers, "I think I know
who Allie went with at the end of the story."
"Who?"
"She went with Noah."
"You're sure?"
"Absolutely."
I smile and nod.
"Yes, she did," I say softly, and she smiles
back; her face is radiant.
She sits and I sit opposite her.
She offers her hand across the table and I
take it in mine, and I feel her thumb begin
to move as it did so many years ago.
I stare at her for a long time, living and
reliving the moments of my life, remembering
it all and making it real.
I feel my throat begin to tighten and once
again, I realize how much I love her.
My voice is shaky when I finally speak.
"You're so beautiful," I say.
I can see in her eyes that she knows how I
feel about her and what I really mean by my
words.
She does not respond.
Instead, she lowers her eyes and I wonder
what she's thinking.
I gently squeeze her hand.
I wait.
I know her heart and I know I'm almost there.
And then a miracle that proves me right.
As Glenn Miller plays softly in the room,
I watch as she gradually gives in to the feelings
inside her.
I see a warm smile begin to form on her lips,
the kind that makes it all worthwhile, and
I watch as she raises her hazy eyes to mine.
She pulls my hand towards her.
"You're wonderful..."
she says softly, and at that moment she falls
in love with me, too; this I know, for I have
seen the signs a thousand times.
She says nothing else, she doesn't have to,
and she gives me a look from another lifetime
that makes me whole again.
I smile back, and we stare at each other with
the feelings inside us rolling like ocean
waves.
I look about the room, then back at Allie,
and the way she's looking at me makes me warm.
And suddenly I feel young again.
I'm no longer cold or aching, or almost blind
with cataracts.
I'm strong and proud and the luckiest man
alive.
By the time the candles have burned down a
third, I am ready to break the silence.
I say, "I love you deeply and I hope you know
that."
"Of course I do," she says.
"I've always loved you, Noah."
Noah, I hear again.
The word echoes in my head.
Noah...
Noah.
She knows, I think to myself, she knows who
I am...
She knows...
Such a tiny thing, this knowledge, but for
me it is a gift from God, and I feel our lifetime
together, holding her, loving her, and being
with her through the best years of my life.
She murmurs, "Noah... my sweet Noah..."
And I, who could not accept the doctors' words,
have won again, at least for a moment.
I give up the pretence of mystery, and I kiss
her hand and bring it to my cheek and whisper
in her ear, "You are the greatest thing that
has ever happened to me."
"Oh...
Noah," she says with tears in her eyes, "I
love you, too."
IF ONLY IT would end like this, I would be
a happy man.
But it won't.
Of this, I'm sure, for soon I begin to see
the signs of worry in her face.
"What's wrong?"
I ask, and her answer comes softly.
"I'm so afraid.
I'm afraid of forgetting you again.
It isn't fair...
I just can't bear to give this up."
Her voice breaks as she finishes, but I don't
know what to say.
I know the evening is coming to an end and
there is nothing I can do to stop the inevitable.
In this, I am a failure.
I finally tell her, "I'll never leave you.
What we have is forever."
She knows this is all I can do, for neither
of us wants empty promises.
After dinner, I become afraid for I know the
bell has tolled this evening.
The sun has long since set and the thief is
about to come, and there is nothing I can
do to stop it.
So I stare at her and wait and live a lifetime
in these last remaining moments.
The clock ticks.
Nothing.
I take her in my arms and we hold each other.
I feel her tremble and I whisper in her ear.
Nothing.
I tell her for the last time this evening
that I love her.
And the thief comes.
It always amazes me how quickly it happens.
Even now, after all this time.
For as she holds me, she begins to blink rapidly
and shake her head.
Then, turning towards the comer of the room,
she stares for a long time, worried.
No!
My mind screams.
Not yet!
Not now... not when we're so close!
Not tonight!
Please!
I can't take it again!
It isn't fair...
But once again, it is useless.
"Those people," she finally says, pointing,
"are staring at me.
Please make them stop."
The gnomes.
My mouth goes dry.
It is over, I know.
This, the evening confusion that affects my
wife, is the hardest part of all.
For when it comes, she is gone, and sometimes
I wonder whether she and I will ever love
again.
"There's no one there, Allie," I say, trying
to stop the inevitable.
She doesn't believe me.
"They're staring at me.
You can't see them?"
"No," I say, and she thinks for a moment.
"Well, they're right there," she says, "and
they're staring at me."
With that, she begins to talk to herself,
and moments later, when I try to comfort her,
she steps back with wide eyes.
"Who are you?"
she cries in panic, her face is becoming whiter.
"What are you doing here?"
She backs away from me, her hands are in a
defensive position, and then she says the
most heartbreaking words of all.
"Go away!
Stay away from me!"
She is pushing the gnomes away from her, terrified,
not noticing my presence.
I stand and cross the room to her bed.
I am weak now, my legs ache, and there is
a strange pain in my side.
I press the button to call the nurses.
They will be here soon now, I know, and I
wait for them.
I sit by the bed with an aching back and start
to cry.
I am tired now, so I sit, alone and apart
from my wife.
And when the nurses come in they see two people
they must comfort.
A woman shaking in fear and the old man who
loves her more deeply than life itself, crying
softly in the comer, with his face in his
hands.
ON A COOL, foggy morning eight days after
she and I had spent our day together, I woke
early, as is my custom, and read letters written
many years before.
At least I tried to.
I couldn't concentrate too well because I
had a headache, so I put them aside and went
to sit in my chair by the window to watch
the sun come up.
It happened as I sat in the chair, just as
the sun peeped over the horizon.
My hand, I noticed, started to tingle, something
it had never done before.
I started to lift it, but I was forced to
stop when I felt a terrible headache.
I closed my eyes tightly.
My hand stopped tingling and began to go numb.
A shooting pain flew down my neck and into
every cell of my body, like a wave, crushing
and wasting everything in its path.
I lost my sight and I heard what sounded like
a train roaring, and I knew that I was having
a stroke.
The pain coursed through my body, and in my
last remaining moments of consciousness I
pictured Allie, lying in her bed, waiting
for the story I would never read, lost and
confused, completely and totally unable to
help herself.
I WAS UNCONSCIOUS on and off for days, and
in those moments when I was awake I found
myself fixed to machines; two bags of fluid
were hanging near the bed.
I drifted in and out of consciousness for
days until another foggy morning when my promise
to Allie stimulated my body once again.
I opened my eyes and saw a room full of flowers,
and their scent motivated me further.
I looked for the button, struggled to press
it, and a nurse arrived thirty seconds later,
followed closely by Dr. Barnwell.
"I'm thirsty," I said, and Dr. Barnwell smiled
broadly.
"Welcome back," he said, "I knew you'd make
it."
TWO WEEKS LATER I am able to leave the hospital,
though I am only half a man now.
The right side of my body is weaker than the
left.
I can't use either my cane or wheelchair,
so I must march now to my own unique rhythm
to keep upright.
Not left-right-left as in my youth, or even
the shuffle-shuffle of late, but rather slow-shuffle,
slide-the- right, slow-shuffle.
I am on a heroic adventure now when I travel
the halls.
When I return to my room, I know I will not
sleep.
I breathe deeply and smell the spring through
the open window.
Evelyn, one of the many nurses here, helps
me to the chair by the window.
She puts her hand on my shoulder and pats
it gently.
She says nothing, and by her silence, I know
that she is staring out of the window.
Then she leans forward and tenderly kisses
me on the cheek.
"It's good to have you back.
Allie's missed you and so have the rest of
us.
We were all praying for you because it's just
not the same around here when you're gone."
She smiles at me and touches my face before
she leaves.
I say nothing.
The stars are out tonight and the crickets
are singing.
As I sit, I wonder if anyone outside can see
me, this prisoner of flesh.
I watch for hours.
A storm is coming and in time, the sky will
turn silver.
Lightning cuts the wild sky and I feel my
mind drift back.
Who are we, Allie and I?
Are we ancient ivy on a tree, intertwined
so closely that we would both die if we were
forced apart?
On the desk, I see a picture of Allie, the
best one I have.
I reach for it and hold it inches from my
face.
She was forty-one when it was taken, and she
had never been more beautiful.
There are so many things I want to ask her,
but I know the picture won't answer, so I
put it aside.
I finally stand and turn on the lamp.
This is a night of memories, so I look for
and find my wedding ring.
It is in the top drawer.
I cannot wear it anymore because my knuckles
are swollen.
The ring is powerful - a symbol, a circle.
I whisper aloud, "I am still yours, Allie,
my queen, my timeless beauty.
You are, and always have been, the best thing
in my life."
It is eleven thirty and I look for the letter
she wrote to me, the one I read when the mood
strikes me.
I find it where I last left it.
I open it and my hands begin to tremble:
Dear Noah,
I write this letter by candlelight, as you
lie sleeping in the bedroom we have shared
since the day we were married.
I see the flame beside me and
it reminds me of another fire from decades
ago, with me in your soft clothes, and I knew
then we would always be together.
I remember how I came back to you the day
after my mother had left.
I was so scared because I was sure you would
never forgive me for leaving you.
I was shaking as I got out of the car, but
you took it all away with your smile.
"How about some coffee?"
was all you said.
And you never spoke about it again in all
our years together.
You didn't ask questions when I left and walked
alone from time to time, during the next few
days.
When I came in with tears in my eyes, you
always knew whether I needed you to hold me
or to just let me be.
I don't know how but you did, and you made
it easier for me.
Later, when we went to the small chapel and
exchanged our rings, I looked into your eyes
and knew I had made the right decision.
More than that, I knew I was foolish forever
considering someone else.
We had a wonderful life together, and I think
about it a lot now.
I close my eyes sometimes and see you, sitting
on the porch and playing your guitar while
little ones clap to the music you create.
"You're a better father than you know," I
tell you later, after the children are sleeping.
I love you for many things, especially your
passions: love, and poetry, and fatherhood,
and friendship, and beauty, and nature.
And I am glad you have taught the children
these things, for I know their lives are better
for it.
They tell me how special you are to them,
and it makes me feel like the luckiest woman
alive.
You have taught me as well, and inspired me
and supported me in my painting, and you will
never know how much it has meant to me that
you were always ready to comfort and encourage
me.
You understood my need for my own studio,
my own space, and saw beyond the paint on
my clothes and in my hair.
I know it was not easy to live with something
like that.
And you have.
For forty-five years now.
Wonderful years.
You are my best friend as well as my lover,
and I do not know which side of you I enjoy
the most.
I treasure each side, just as I have treasured
our life together.
You have something inside you, Noah, something
beautiful and strong.
Kindness, that's what I see when I look at
you now, that's what everyone sees.
Kindness.
I know you think me crazy for making us write
our story before we finally leave our home,
but I have my reasons and I thank you for
your patience.
I never told you why, but now I think it is
time for you to know.
We have lived a lifetime most couples never
know, and when I look at you I am frightened
by the knowledge that all this will be ending
soon.
For we both know my prognosis.
I worry more about you than I do about me,
because I fear the pain I know you will go
through.
There are no words to express my sorrow for
this.
I love you so deeply, so much, that I will
find a way to come back to you despite my
disease, I promise you that.
And this is where the story comes in.
When I am lost and lonely, read this story
- just as you told it to the children - and
know that in some way I will realize it's
about us.
And perhaps, just perhaps, we will find a
way to be together again.
Please don't be angry with me on days I do
not remember you - we both know they will
come.
Know that I will always love you, and no matter
what happens, know that I have led the greatest
life possible.
My life with you.
Noah, wherever you are and whenever you read
this, I love you.
I love you deeply, my husband.
You are, and always have been, my dream.
Allie
I put the letter aside, rise from my desk
and find my slippers.
I must sit to put them on.
Then, standing, I cross the room and open
my door.
I look down the hall and see Janice seated
at the main desk, which I must pass to get
to Allie's room.
At this hour, I am not supposed to leave my
room, and Janice does not break the rules.
I wait to see if she will leave, but she does
not and I grow impatient.
I finally exit my room anyway, slow-shuffle,
slide-the-right, slow-shuffle.
In the end, I am discovered, but I am not
surprised.
I stand before her.
"Noah," she says, "what are you doing?"
"I'm taking a walk," I say.
"I can't sleep."
"You're not really going for a walk, are you?
You're going to see Allie."
"Yes," I answer.
"Noah, you know what happened the last time
you saw her at night.
You shouldn't do this."
"I miss her."
"I know you do, but I can't let you see her."
"It's our anniversary," I say.
This is true.
It is one year before gold.
Forty-nine years today.
"I see."
She looks away for a moment, and her voice
becomes softer.
I am surprised.
She has never struck me as the sentimental
type.
"Noah, I've seen hundreds of couples struggle
with grief, but I've never seen anyone handle
it like you do.
No one around here has ever seen anything
like it."
She pauses for just a moment and her eyes
begin to fill with tears.
"I try to think what it's like for you, how
you keep going day after day, but I can't
imagine it.
I don't know how you do it.
You even beat her disease sometimes.
Even though the doctors don't understand it,
we nurses do.
It's love - it's as simple as that.
It's the most incredible thing I've ever seen."
A lump has risen in my throat, and I am speechless.
"But, Noah, you're not supposed to do this,
and I can't let you.
So go back to your room."
Then, smiling, she says, "I'm going downstairs
for some coffee.
I won't be back to check on you for a while,
so don't do anything foolish."
She rises quickly, touches my arm and walks
towards the stairs.
She doesn't look back and suddenly I am alone.
I look at her desk and see her coffee, a full
cup, and once again, I learn that there are
good people in the world.
As I begin my way to Allie's room, I take
tiny steps, and even at that pace, my legs
grow tired.
I find I must touch the wall to keep from
falling down.
When I finally reach her room, my body is
weak.
My legs are trembling, and my eyes are blurred.
The door opens and light from the hallway
illuminates the bed where she sleeps.
She is lying with the covers halfway up.
After a moment, I see her roll to one side.
She looks small in her bed.
I think I hear someone coming, so I enter
her room and close the door behind me.
Blackness descends and
I cross her floor from memory and reach the
window.
I open the curtains, and the moon stares back,
large and full.
Though I know I should not, I sit on her bed.
Then I reach across and gently touch her face.
I stroke her hair, and I feel wonder.
She moves and opens her eyes and I suddenly
regret my foolishness, for I know she will
begin to cry and scream, for this is what
she always does.
But I feel an urge to attempt the impossible
and lean towards her.
Her lips meet mine.
And suddenly a miracle, for I feel her mouth
open and I discover a forgotten paradise,
unchanged all this time, ageless like the
stars.
I feel the warmth of her body, I close my
eyes and become young again - a mighty ship,
strong and fearless, and she is my sails.
I gently stroke her cheek, then take her hand
in mine.
I kiss her lips, her cheeks, and listen as
she takes a breath.
She murmurs softly, "Oh, Noah...
I've missed you."
Another miracle - the greatest of all! - and
there's no way I can stop the tears as we
begin to slip towards heaven itself.
For
at
that moment, the world is full of wonder as
I feel her fingers reach for
the buttons on my shirt and slowly, very slowly,
she begins to undo them
one
by one.
- THE
END -