Darkest Hour
by Anthony McCarten
CHAPTER ONE
Searching for a new leader
It was May 1940, and the situation in Europe was extremely
serious.
The Nazi dictator, Adolf Hitler, and his armies had already invaded Czechoslovakia, Poland, Denmark and Norway Now
Hitler was preparing to attack the rest of Europe.
Britain and its ally France had declared war on Hitler eight months before, after Germany invaded Poland in September
1939.
But things were going badly for the Allies.
The British Parliament and many of the British people were no longer confident about their leader, the Conservative
prime minister, Neville Chamberlain.
They did not believe that he had the ability to defeat
Hitler and lead Britain to victory.
On the afternoon of 7th May, a meeting of the Members of Parliament (MPs) was taking place in the Houses of
Parliament in London.
The meeting had already continued for several hours and was
very noisy.
Many MPs were so angry with Chamberlain that they could not
hide their feelings.
They stood up and shouted at him, excitedly, "Out! Out!
Resign! Resign!"
Chamberlain looked sad, tired and worried.
Earlier in the afternoon, he had made a speech to
Parliament, but it had not gone well.
The MPs knew that Britain was in terrible danger from a
possible attack by Hitler.
They had realized that they needed a great leader, a strong person who could prevent the Nazis from controlling Britain
and Europe.
But they did not believe that Chamberlain was the right man
for the job.
Chamberlain had not thought that Hitler was a dangerous threat to Europe, and two years before, in 1938, he had
tried to make a peace agreement with Hitler.
Five days ago, Parliament learned there had been a terrible
disaster for Britain in April.
The Nazis had invaded Norway and attacked British troops there. 1800 British soldiers had died, and several warships
were destroyed.
Many people felt Chamberlain and his government were responsible because they had not believed that Hitler would
attack Norway.
Many MPs stood up to speak against Chamberlain that day.
One was Clement Attlee, the leader of the Labour Opposition.
"The Prime Minister and his friends made a serious mistake
about Norway," he said.
"Many soldiers and ships have been lost because of them. But Norway wasn't their only mistake. They've been wrong about
other things, too. They didn't believe that Hitler would
attack Czechoslovakia. A few years ago, they even thought we
should try to make a peace agreement with him."
The meeting continued long into the summer night, but
Chamberlain
still refused to resign.
The next afternoon, Parliament met again.
Meanwhile, some important members of the Conservative government talked to some Labour MPs; they thought the
Labour Party should join the government.
They thought it would be good for Britain if Conservative
and Labour MPs could work together.
But the Labour MPs refused.
"We won't be part of a government led by Chamberlain," they
said.
"If you want us to work with you, Chamberlain and his
friends must go." The MPs continued to attack Chamberlain.
"Resign! Resign!" they shouted at him.
Then an important man stood up: the Liberal MP David Lloyd George, who had been British prime minister from 1916 to
1922.
Everyone was silent as they listened to Lloyd George,
because he had guided Britain to victory in the First World
War.
"You've put Britain in a terrible position," Lloyd George
told Chamberlain.
"It's time for you to go." When he sat down again, the MPs
shouted and cheered.
Later that night, a vote was held in Parliament to find out whether the MPs still had confidence in Chamberlain's
government and the way it was running the war.
In the vote, forty-one members of the Conservative Party
voted against their own government.
So, finally, Chamberlain had to accept that he could not
continue as prime minister.
A new leader must be found quickly, but the big question was
- who could that leader be?
A few seats away from Chamberlain, one man was sitting
quietly, watching and listening to everything that was
happening.
His name was Winston Spencer Churchill.
He had an important position in the government as First Lord
of the Admiralty, the man in charge of the British navy, but he was not popular with everyone.
Jokes were made about him, and there were funny pictures of
him in the newspapers.
Many people did not trust him because earlier in his
political career, he had changed his party twice.
In 1904, he had left the Conservative Party and joined the Liberal Party, and then in 1924, he had joined the
Conservative Party again.
As the top man in the Admiralty, some people also felt he
was responsible for the recent terrible disaster in Norway.
So when the Conservative MPs were considering a new prime
minister, they did not immediately think of Winston
Churchill.
Instead, many people wanted the Foreign Secretary, Lord
Halifax, to be prime minister.
Chamberlain, too, thought Halifax would be a good prime
minister.
Other people also wanted Halifax: the King of Britain, George VI, wanted Halifax, and even the Labour Party wanted
Halifax.
However, there was a problem with Lord Halifax.
He was a member of the House of Lords, and in British politics, a member of the House of Lords could not also be
an ordinary Member of Parliament who was chosen in an election by
the British people.
On Thursday 9th May, Chamberlain invited Lord Halifax to his
home at Number 10, Downing Street, and asked him to be prime minister.
But to Chamberlain's great surprise, Halifax said that he
did not want the job.
He said that he would have no real power, because, as a Lord, he was not allowed to take part in meetings of the MPs
in Parliament.
Chamberlain was very disappointed because he had been sure
that Halifax wanted to be prime minister.
But perhaps there was another reason why Halifax did not
want the job.
Halifax knew that Winston Churchill might cause problems for
him.
Winston was clever and ambitious, and he had wanted to be
prime minister since he was a child.
He had the ability to be a good leader, and he was very good
at making speeches.
But in his political career, Winston had made some bad
mistakes.
One of his most serious mistakes had been during the First World War, when hundreds of thousands of men had lost their
lives at Gallipoli in Turkey.
However, Winston knew a lot more about battles and war than
Halifax.
As a young man, he had trained as an army officer and had direct experience of two important wars, the Boer War and
the First World War.
He had fought bravely in the First World War and a war in the Sudan, and he had also worked on the front line of
battle as a war journalist.
Halifax did not understand war and military matters as well
as Winston.
Also, much of the British public did not trust Halifax because he had agreed with Chamberlain's idea of making a
peace agreement with Hitler.
After the meeting with Halifax in the morning, Chamberlain
made an important decision.
He asked Halifax and Winston to come to the prime minister's
house at Number 10, Downing Street, that afternoon.
He told them he had decided to resign, but he would be happy
to be in a government led by either of them.
Halifax repeated that he did not want to be prime minister
and said that Winston would be the right man for the job.
So Winston Churchill agreed to be the new prime minister of
Britain.
He knew he had a very difficult job ahead of him - to save Britain and its people from the terrible threat of a Nazi
attack.
But Winston felt strong and confident.
Later, he said, "I felt as if all my past life had prepared me for this moment... I was sure I would not fail." Winston
had become responsible for the future of his country.
CHAPTER TWO
Winston's early life
So who was Winston Churchill, the man with the difficult job
of leading Britain to victory?
Winston had done many different things in his life.
He had been a soldier, a painter, a journalist and had a
political career.
He knew how to use words well and make excellent speeches.
He had acted bravely in two important wars and had been a
prisoner of war, too.
But he had also made some serious mistakes.
He took risks, and sometimes he made decisions without
thinking about them carefully enough.
Winston's father, Lord Randolph Churchill, had been in
politics, too.
Lord Randolph came from a very old and famous English
family.
Winston's mother, Jennie Jerome, was the daughter of a rich American businessman who was known as "The King of Wall
Street".
Winston was their first child, and he was born at Blenheim Palace, Oxfordshire, on 30th November 1874, when Victoria
was Queen of Britain.
In Victorian times, most rich parents did not have a close
relationship with their children.
They did not look after their children themselves but
employed a lady to take care of them.
Winston's mother, Jennie, was a beautiful young woman who loved parties and travel, so she did not spend much time
with Winston and his younger brother, Jack.
Later, Winston wrote:
"My mother... shone for me like the Evening Star. I loved her (very much) - but (from far away) Winston also loved his
father, Lord Randolph Churchill. But
Randolph was even further from his sons than Jennie because he was very busy with his political career. He was a
Conservative MP with an important position in Parliament. However,
Randolph's health was not good, and he died from illness at the age of forty-five. Winston was very sad about his
father's death because he had wanted to be closer to him and
understand him better. He had hoped to become an MP like
Randolph and enter Parliament at his father's side.
When he was a child, the most important person for Winston
was the
lady who looked after him, Mrs Elizabeth Everest. She had no children of her own, and she loved Winston and Jack very
much. When she became ill in 1895, the same year as his
father's death, Winston hurried to her house and was with her when she died. In his book My Early Life, he wrote, "She
had been my (closest) friend during the whole twenty years
that I had lived."
When Winston was young, most rich parents sent their sons
away to school.
So when he was seven, Winston was sent away to school, too,
and he hated it.
He wrote, "I had been so happy (at home) with all my toys...
Now it was to be all lessons." Life away from home at school was very hard for a small boy.
In those days, teachers often punished pupils by hitting
them, and Winston was hit, too.
In 1888, when he was fourteen, he was sent to Harrow, a very
famous school for boys in North London.
Winston was not very good at studying, and he was often put
in the bottom class.
But he enjoyed English and history, and one of his teachers,
Mr Somervell, helped him very much.
He taught Winston to use words well, and to speak and write
excellent English.
Winston wrote poetry and reports for the school newspaper, and his love of words, both spoken and written, stayed with
him all his life.
After leaving school, Winston decided to join the army.
In August 1893, he entered Sandhurst, where officers in the
British army are trained.
He did very well there, and in 1894, he left in eighth
position out of 150 young men.
Then Winston joined a regiment called the 4th Queen's Own
Hussars and trained with them for six months.
This was very hard work, but again, Winston did well.
At the same time, he was able to enjoy himself, as he was
invited to parties and dinners.
But Winston was beginning to feel frustrated.
As a young army officer, he wanted to get direct experience
of battle.
In early 1895, the Cuban War of Independence had started
between Spain and Cuba.
Winston travelled to Cuba and sent reports about the war to
a British newspaper in London.
In his new job as a war journalist, he was able to use the
writing skills he had learned at school.
After a month in Cuba, he went back to London to live with
his mother.
However, on 11th September, Winston and 1,200 other men from
the 4th Hussars regiment were sent to India.
In Victorian times, India was the most important colony in
the British Empire, the countries ruled by Britain.
Winston's regiment arrived in Bombay at the start of October
1896, then moved to the southern city of Bangalore.
Winston enjoyed his new life in India very much and found it
very interesting.
Winston was always interested in learning new things and
educating himself more.
He loved reading, but he had realized that there were many
subjects he did not know enough about.
So he asked his mother to send him books from England about
history and politics and other subjects.
Every month, new books arrived, and from November 1896 to
May 1897, Winston read for four or five hours every day.
He learned many things that would help him greatly in his
future political career.
In the spring of 1897, Winston started to feel that it was
time to go back to England.
He was still with the army in India, but now he wanted to enter politics and become a Member of Parliament like his
father.
So he returned to London, and on 26th June, he made his
first political speech.
It went well, but immediately afterwards he had to return to India because fighting had started between the British and
the Afghans.
Winston sent reports about the fighting to two newspapers.
Winston never forgot that his father had died an early death
at the age of forty-five.
People had sometimes described Lord Randolph as "a man in a
hurry", and Winston was the same kind of person.
Like his father, he wanted to do many things as fast as
possible.
In 1898, there was a war in the Sudan.
Winston travelled there to join the regiment of Lord
Kitchener, the officer in charge of the British army.
Winston not only fought in battles but also continued his work as a war journalist and sent reports about the war to
British newspapers.
He returned to England in March 1899 because he had a chance
of starting a political career.
The MP for Oldham, a town in the north-west of England, had
died, so there was an election for a new MP there.
Winston stood as the Conservative candidate, but although he worked very hard, he did not succeed in winning the
election.
In October 1899, another war, the Boer War, started in South
Africa.
Winston became a war journalist again and travelled to South Africa to report on the war, but after only a few weeks, he
was taken prisoner.
However, he managed to escape, and after walking for many
miles in the hot sun, he came to a railway line.
He jumped on a train, which took him to a safe part of the
country.
By this time, Winston was becoming quite famous.
Many people in South Africa and Britain read about his
adventures, and they thought he was very brave.
After he returned to England in July 1900, he immediately
began to think about politics.
He stood as Conservative candidate for Oldham again, and
this time he won the election.
On 1st October 1900, he finally became a Member of
Parliament at the age of twenty-five.
But although Winston was now an MP, he did not stop doing
other things.
He continued writing, and he went on a speaking tour of the UK, the USA and Canada, making speeches about his adventures
in the Boer War.
On 22nd January 1901, news reached him that Queen Victoria
had died and there was a new king, Edward VII.
Winston immediately returned to England and took his place in Parliament, making his first speech there on 18th
February.
The first four years of Winston's life as an MP were quiet.
He watched and listened to everything carefully, and he
learned many things about politics.
But he was also ambitious and did not want to sit quietly
all his life at the back of Parliament.
He wanted to be at the front, making important decisions
about Britain.
However, he would have to wait another forty years before
that happened.
Winston did not always agree with the policies of his party,
the Conservative Party.
So on 31st May 1904, he left the Conservative Party and
joined the Liberal Party.
Many people were shocked that Winston had changed his
political party, but he did not care.
In the Liberal Party, he worked closely with David Lloyd George, his friend and ally, who would later become prime
minister.
In December 1905, the Conservative prime minister resigned,
and a Liberal MP became prime minister.
Winston was given the job of being responsible for the
colonies.
He did well, and in 1908, he was offered a position in the Cabinet, the group of important ministers who controlled
government policy.
At about this time, something very important happened in
Winston's private life.
He was invited to dinner by a friend in London.
A woman was sitting next to him at the dinner table.
Her name was Clementine (Clemmie) Hozier.
She was twenty- three years old and had just left the
Sorbonne University in Paris.
Winston and Clemmie fell in love and were married six months
later.
Clemmie was the perfect wife for Winston.
She always thought about what was best for Winston and
Britain before herself.
However, sometimes Winston could be quite rude to people,
and Clemmie always told him when he was behaving badly.
Winston and Clemmie had special names for each other:
Winston called Clemmie "Kat", and she called him "Pug" or
"Pig".
On 11th July 1909, Winston and Clemmie's first daughter,
Diana, was born.
But after the baby's birth, Clemmie was not well, so she
went to stay with her sister in the countryside.
When she returned to London, she found Winston very busy
with his political career.
CHAPTER THREE
A dangerous threat
Winston had to stand for Parliament again, and this time he
lost to the Conservative Party candidate.
But two weeks later, he stood again for election as the Liberal candidate in Dundee, Scotland, and won an easy
victory, which gave him a safe place in Parliament.
In 1911, the Liberal Prime Minister, H.H.
Asquith, gave Winston a top job as First Lord of the Admiralty Winston was now in charge of the British navy and
was lent a wonderful house, Admiralty House, in London.
On 28th May 1911, Winston and Clemmie's second child,
Randolph, was born there.
Winston's new job was not an easy one.
He was also becoming very worried about Germany.
For a long time, he had seen that Germany was slowly
building up its army and navy, making them larger and
stronger.
Winston thought this situation was very dangerous, because
Germany could be planning to attack Britain.
So he spent a lot of money on building British warships and
making them faster and better.
The money spent on the navy was increased from 39 pounds
million to 50 pounds million.
Most of Winston's colleagues in the Cabinet were not as
worried as he was about Germany.
Also, many British people thought Germany was a peaceful
European country and not a possible threat to Britain.
However, Winston continued making speeches in Parliament,
warning people that Germany was becoming dangerous.
When the First World War started in 1914, Winston was ready.
But in the first few months of the war, over 5,500 men in
the navy died.
Many of his colleagues did not think that Winston was doing a good job as top man in the navy, and the newspapers
attacked his policies.
Then Winston travelled to the city of Antwerp in Belgium.
The British army was in a very difficult situation because Antwerp was surrounded by German troops, so when Winston
arrived, he immediately wanted to help the army.
He decided the best way of doing this would be to lead the
British troops himself.
So he sent a message to Prime Minister Asquith, saying that he wanted to resign from his job as First Lord of the
Admiralty.
But Asquith refused and told Winston to come back to London
at once.
However, Winston stayed in Belgium for three more days, finally arriving back in England on 7th October, the same
day as his third child, his daughter Sarah, was born.
Then a terrible disaster happened for Winston, possibly the
worst of his political career.
Britain and Russia were allies, so they were fighting on the
same side in the war.
But the Ottoman Empire (Turkey) was an ally of Germany and
an enemy of Britain and Russia.
The government of Britain had made an ambitious plan for
British warships to take British troops to Gallipoli in
Turkey.
The British government was sure that, if Britain invaded Turkey, Turkey would quickly decide to leave the war and
make a peace agreement with Britain and its ally Russia.
Then Britain would be able to sail its warships past
Istanbul and up through the Black Sea to Russia.
However, the British plan was very badly organized.
This was because there was not just one plan but three plans, each with a different person in charge - Winston; one
of Winston's colleagues in the Admiralty; and Lord Kitchener.
Each man had different ideas about how the plan should work.
Winston was sure that his ideas were the best, and he did
not want to follow the other plans.
His plan was to use only warships, without the help of the
army.
This was accepted, but after three British warships were destroyed by the Turkish army, the British government
decided Winston's plan was no good.
So in April 1915, troops arrived at Gallipoli, but the
British had not expected that the Turkish army would fight
back.
Over the next eight months, about 400,000 men lost their lives: 73,000 British and Irish; 36,000 Australian and New
Zealand; 27,000 French; 4,800 Indian; and 251,000 Turkish.
Finally, in January 1916, the British government decided to
evacuate the troops from Gallipoli.
The disaster at Gallipoli was not Winston's mistake alone, but many people still felt he was responsible for what had
happened.
He had pushed his plan forward and had not listened to his
colleagues' ideas.
After what happened at Gallipoli, many people in Britain were not happy with the Liberal government, so Prime
Minister Asquith invited some Conservative MPs to join the
government, too.
However, the Conservative MPs refused to work with Winston,
so he had to go.
Winston was very sad and angry.
"I am finished!" he said.
Winston was no longer First Lord of the Admiralty, so he, Clemmie and their children had to move out of Admiralty
House, where they had been very happy.
Later, Clemmie said this had been one of the saddest times
in Winston's life.
He still wanted to help Britain, so he decided to join the
British army, which was fighting the Germans in France.
At the end of January 1917, his regiment travelled to Belgium, where he fought with the troops in the front line
of battle.
On 7th May 1917, Winston returned to London and his political career, but it would be almost three years before
he became a Cabinet minister again.
On 11th November 1918, Britain and its allies made peace with Germany, and four days later, Winston and Clemmie's
fourth child, a daughter, was born.
They called her Marigold.
Winston's old friend and ally, David Lloyd George, had become prime minister, and he appointed Winston as Minister
for War.
Winston was very happy about this, but in 1921, he made some bad decisions about the war in Russia so he was moved to a
different job, Minister for the Colonies.
The year 1921 was terrible for Winston and Clemmie.
First, Clemmie's brother, Bill, killed himself in a hotel room in Paris, and then a few months later Winston's mother
died.
Then another very sad thing happened.
Their little daughter, Marigold, became very ill, and
Winston and Clemmie hurried to be with her.
On the evening of 22nd August, Marigold asked Clemmie to sing her favourite song, but, as Clemmie was singing,
Marigold put her hand on her mother's arm and said, "Not tonight...
finish it tomorrow." However, the next morning the little
girl died.
All their lives, Winston and Clemmie felt terrible pain
about the death of Marigold.
They went on holiday to France, and just over a year later,
their fifth and last child, Mary, was born.
The same year, they bought a house in the country,
thirty-five miles south of London in Kent.
They called the house Chartwell.
Clemmie did not really like Chartwell, but she knew it was important for Winston to have a quiet place of his own where
he could relax, write and paint.
In 1924, Winston changed political parties again and went
back to the Conservative Party.
Soon afterwards, the new prime minister, Stanley Baldwin,
appointed him Chancellor of the Exchequer.
So Winston and his family moved into the Chancellor's house in London at 11 Downing Street, next door to the prime
minister.
Over the next few years, there were many problems in both Britain and other countries for Winston and the British
government.
One difficult problem was India.
India was a British colony, but now she wanted independence
from Britain and its own government.
Winston was very much against this idea because India was
the most important country in the British Empire.
He thought that, if India left the British Empire, the
Empire would be destroyed.
But many people did not agree with Winston, and they thought
he did not understand India very well.
One of these people was Lord Halifax, who was responsible
for India then.
Another big problem was Germany.
For a long time, Winston had strongly believed that there was a serious threat to Britain from Hitler and the National
Socialist German Workers' Party (the Nazi Party).
The Party had started in 1920, two years after the end of
the First World War.
It had grown larger over the years and was now very strong.
Winston had travelled a lot through Germany and had been worried about the large groups of young men he had seen
marching through the cities.
They wanted to fight for their country and make Germany
great again after it was defeated in the First World War.
In April 1933, Winston made a long speech in Parliament
about a possible threat from Germany.
He said that Hitler was a dangerous dictator and that he was
probably planning to attack Britain.
Over the next few years, Winston continued to make speeches,
warning people about Hitler and the Nazi Party.
He wrote letters to newspapers and also to his colleagues.
But many people in Britain did not believe that Hitler was dangerous, and they were more worried about a possible
threat from Russia.
Winston warned people that Germany was building up its army and navy, and he advised that Britain should build up its
army, too.
He was sure that Hitler was planning to attack Austria,
Poland, Czechoslovakia and Romania.
Some of Winston's colleagues were starting to listen to him,
but others said he was a "warmonger" - someone who wants war with other countries.
In May 1937, Neville Chamberlain became prime minister.
His Foreign Secretary was Anthony Eden, who shared the same
opinion as Winston about Hitler.
Eden thought that Chamberlain was making a big mistake about Hitler and that he was too soft and friendly towards both
Hitler and the Italian dictator, Benito Mussolini.
In November 1937, Lord Halifax, now back in Britain from India, went on holiday to Germany, and Chamberlain
encouraged him to visit Hitler while he was there.
Eden was not happy about a meeting between Halifax and
Hitler, and he warned Halifax to be hard on Hitler.
But when Halifax returned, he said that Hitler had been
extremely friendly and did not want to start a war in
Europe.
Eden thought that Hitler was lying, so he resigned from the government in February 1938, and Halifax became Foreign
Secretary.
Winston was shocked that Eden had resigned and could not
sleep all night when he heard the news.
He was sure Eden was the only man strong enough to save
Britain.
In September 1938, Chamberlain travelled to Germany to meet
Hitler in Munich.
When he came back, he was very happy because he was sure he
had saved Britain from war.
He told the British people that he had discussed many things with Hitler, and Hitler had said he did not want war and
promised not to invade other European countries.
But many people in Britain did not believe Hitler.
They felt that Chamberlain had been too soft with him and
agreed too easily to everything Hitler wanted.
At the next meeting in Parliament, Winston made a very
strong speech, warning his colleagues again about Hitler.
Then on 15th March 1939, German troops marched into
Czechoslovakia.
Finally, everyone understood that Winston had been right for many years, and that Hitler had lied to Chamberlain in
Munich.
So when Hitler invaded Poland in September 1939, Britain and
France declared war on Germany.
CHAPTER FOUR
The new prime minister
As the evening of 9th May 1940 ended, Winston was preparing
himself for the huge job of leading Britain.
Randolph, his son, had called him at the Admiralty earlier that day, and Winston had said, "I think I shall be prime
minister tomorrow." Every morning, Winston's breakfast was
brought to his bedroom.
But on the morning of 10th May, Winston had a shock.
He was woken a little after 5.30 a.m. not by someone bringing his breakfast, but by some terrible news: Germany
had invaded Holland.
Boxes of telegrams were arriving from the Admiralty, the War
Office and the Foreign Office.
At 6 a.m., Winston called the French ambassador to discuss
sending troops into Belgium, the country south of Holland.
But then news came that Hitler had invaded Belgium, too.
At the start of the war, both Holland and Belgium had said
that they did not want to take part in the war.
So it was very easy for Germany to invade these countries,
because their armies were not ready for an attack.
After Winston finished his phone call with the French ambassador, he went to a meeting with the Ministers for Air
and War, Sir Samuel Hoare and Oliver Stanley, to discuss what
Britain was going to do about the German attack.
Later, Hoare remembered that Winston was very strong and
full of confident advice.
The three men then moved to the upstairs War Room at the Admiralty for a meeting with Britain's top military leaders
at 7 a.m.
More news was beginning to arrive about the terrible
situation in Europe.
It was reported that the Germans had begun their attack at 3
a.m.
The German air force, the Luftwaffe, were bombing important places in Holland, Belgium and now Luxembourg, and thousands
of German soldiers had arrived in these countries, which
were known as the Low Countries.
Winston and the military leaders decided to order the French
and British armies to begin marching into Belgium.
Meanwhile, British people listening to the seven o'clock news on the radio had a great shock when it was announced
that Germany had invaded Holland.
Randolph was with Winston's old regiment, the 4th Queen's
Own Hussars.
He called his father at 7.30 a.m. to try to find out what
was happening.
Winston informed him that the Germans had invaded the Low Countries but that the British and French armies were
marching forward to fight them.
Then Randolph asked, "What about... you becoming prime
minister?"
"Oh, I don't know about that," replied Winston.
"Nothing (is important) now except beating the enemy."
But this was still the big question - who would be prime
minister?
Chamberlain had still not resigned.
He had said he would be happy to stay as prime minister if the Labour Members of Parliament agreed to join his
government.
So everything depended on Labour's decision.
However, Clement Attlee and his colleague, Arthur Greenwood, had gone to an important Labour Party meeting in
Bournemouth, so they would not be able to contact Chamberlain until
later.
Just before 8 a.m., Winston, Hoare and Stanley walked from the Admiralty to the prime minister's house at Number 10,
Downing Street, where the War Cabinet was meeting.
Twenty ministers, military leaders and other important
people sat around the table to discuss the German attack.
Although Chamberlain, not Winston, was prime minister, it soon became clear to everyone that Winston was in charge of
the meeting.
In less than three hours, he was running the war.
Although Chamberlain had nothing important to say during the meeting, afterwards he told Hoare that he did not think he
should resign "until the French battle was finished".
This was very surprising because most people were expecting
Chamberlain to go immediately.
That morning, the British newspapers had all said Chamberlain was going to resign and Winston was going to
become prime minister.
Chamberlain had been wrong about too many things.
For the past six years, Winston had warned the government, Parliament and the British people about the threat from
Hitler, but Chamberlain had not listened.
When Hitler and Chamberlain met in Munich in September 1938,
Hitler had promised that he would not attack other countries in Europe, and Chamberlain had believed him; he thought
he had made a peace agreement with Hitler.
But Winston knew that Hitler was lying, and he refused to be
silent.
Many rich and important people did not want to listen to Winston and called him a warmonger, but Winston knew that it
was impossible to make a peace agreement with a dictator.
However, when Chamberlain refused to resign, he was not only
thinking about his own position.
He really believed that Winston was not the right man to
lead Britain, and many other people agreed with him.
They thought that Britain needed a leader who was calm and
quiet, and thought carefully before making decisions.
Winston was neither calm nor quiet, and in the past, he had
taken a lot of risks and made some bad mistakes.
So a lot of people were very nervous about Winston becoming
prime minister.
Also, some important people like Lord Halifax still believed
it would be possible to have peace talks with Hitler.
The War Cabinet met again that day, at 11.30 a.m.
By this time, the German tanks were moving quickly across
the Low Countries and had almost reached France.
The War Cabinet learned that the Germans had also bombed the city of Nancy in France, but there was not much information
about this and some of it was not correct.
General Ironside, the head of the British army, informed the Cabinet that the Germans were probably planning to cross
through Luxembourg and the Ardennes Forest to the Belgian
line at the River Meuse.
At the same time, the Germans were probably going to march
through Belgium towards the troops of the Allies.
But actually, the German army had moved more quickly than the Allies thought and had managed to get much further,
because the Belgian troops had not been ready for a German attack.
A third meeting was held at the Admiralty at 1 p.m. and a fourth meeting at Number 10, Downing Street, at 4.30 p.m. to
discuss what to do about the attack on Belgium.
At 1 p.m., General Sir Hastings Ismay, a strong ally of Winston, reminded his colleagues of a plan, Plan D, made
earlier by the British.
Since the start of the war, over 394,000 British soldiers
had been in France.
These troops were called the British Expeditionary Force
(BEF).
According to Plan D, if the Germans attacked Belgium, the
British government would send the BEF to defend it.
At 4.30p.m, the War Cabinet discussed the possible bombing
of Germany.
The Germans had already bombed important places in Holland, Belgium, France and Switzerland, as well as five places on
the coast of Kent, in southeast England.
Winston listened carefully to the opinions of his
colleagues.
All the men sitting around the Cabinet table were very
experienced, and he trusted them greatly.
Hoare and another top man in the air force, Sir Cyril Newall, wanted to start bombing Germany immediately, but
Ironside was against this idea because it would not help the battle
on the ground.
He said it would be better to wait for twenty-four hours before starting the attack, and both Winston and Chamberlain
supported his opinion.
At the end of the meeting, Chamberlain announced that he had
received a message from the Labour Party.
They said that they were ready to be part of "a new
Government, under a new Prime Minister".
Chamberlain realized that he could not continue as prime
minister if the Labour Party were not going to support him.
He said he would go and see King George VI that evening and
tell him he was going to resign.
Shortly afterwards, he left for Buckingham Palace and met
with the king.
He formally resigned from his position and advised the king
that the new prime minister should be Winston.
But Winston's name was not the one the king had been hoping
to hear.
Later, the king wrote in his diary that he thought
Parliament had behaved very badly towards Chamberlain.
He thought Halifax was the best man to be the new prime minister, and when Chamberlain told him Halifax did not want
the job, he was very disappointed.
He wrote in his diary: "Then I knew that there was only one person whom I could send for to form a Government... and
that was Winston. I asked Chamberlain his advice, and he told
me Winston was the man to send for."
Winston knew not everybody was happy about him becoming prime minister, and sometimes he felt he could never escape
from his past mistakes.
During this time, Clemmie, his wife, had been away, and
Winston missed her love, help and advice very much.
So he called her, asking her to return to London as soon as
possible.
Clemmie arrived just before he left for Buckingham Palace and told Winston she believed he was the only man who could
be prime minister.
Shortly before 6 p.m. on 10th May 1940, on his way to the palace, Winston began to feel very excited about his new
position.
It was the job he had dreamed of all his life.
The meeting with the king went surprisingly well, and
Winston felt very happy.
Later, Winston wrote that the king had even joked with him and said, "'I suppose you don't know why I have sent for
you.' I replied, 'Sir, I (really) couldn't imagine why.' He
laughed and said, 'I want to ask you to form a Government.'"
After Winston was driven back home and stepped out of the
car for the first time as prime minister of Great Britain,
he turned to a policeman beside him and said, "God alone knows how great it is. All I hope is that it is not too
late. I am very much afraid it is. We can only do our best." Tears
came into his eyes as he turned away and said something
quietly to himself.
Then he began climbing the stairs to start planning his new
War Cabinet.
After Winston became prime minister, the first thing he did
was to write a letter to Chamberlain.
He thanked Chamberlain for promising to support him and help
Britain during this difficult time.
He said that he knew that the road ahead would be long and dangerous, and he needed and depended on Chamberlain and was
proud to have him as his friend.
Then he wrote a similar letter to Halifax.
It was very clever of Winston to write these letters to Chamberlain and Halifax, because they were a way of keeping
them on his side.
He hoped that they would support him and not cause him any
problems.
Winston also appointed himself as Minister of Defence because this would give him the chance to run the war as
well as the country.
Then he appointed his close ally, Anthony Eden, as Minister for War, a Labour MP as First Lord of the Admiralty, and the
leader of the Liberal Party as Minister for Air.
Then Winston read all the letters and telegrams that had
arrived, wishing him well in his new job.
At 9 p.m. he turned on the radio to hear Chamberlain
speaking to the British people for the last time.
Chamberlain spoke for five minutes, and his speech was very
good.
He told the people about the terrible things that had happened that day and that Hitler had added to his "horrible
crimes" by attacking Holland, Belgium and Luxembourg.
Then Chamberlain explained that, during his three years as prime minister, he had always tried to solve problems
through peace, but now he realized that it was impossible to avoid
war.
He said the British people must support their new leader and
fight Hitler to the end.
After listening to Chamberlain's speech, Winston continued
working for another six hours until 3 a.m.
The day had brought enormous changes to his life, but he
felt happy and excited, and he slept very well that night.
CHAPTER FIVE
Two different kinds of men
Many people in Parliament and Britain had hoped that Lord Halifax would become prime minister, and when Halifax said
he did not want the
job, they were very surprised.
An American friend wrote in his diary, "I don't understand
why, since a more ambitious man never lived..."
Halifax and Winston were two different kinds of men, both in
how they
looked and in their ideas.
Halifax was very tall with pale skin, and he had no left
hand.
He was also very good at horse riding.
He was born on 16th April 1881 in Devon, into a rich family
who were deeply religious.
Halifax was his parents' fourth son, but sadly, his three
older brothers had all died by the time he was ten.
Like the sons of many rich parents, he was sent away to school at Eton College and later went to the University of
Oxford.
After Halifax left university, he decided to enter politics
in 1909 as a Conservative MP.
He owned land and houses in Yorkshire and London, and later the same year he married Lady Dorothy Onslow, a very kind
woman.
In 1910, Halifax became the MP for Ripon in North Yorkshire.
When the First World War started, he joined the regiment of the Queen's Own Yorkshire Dragoons and went to fight in
Flanders.
The fighting there was terrible, and many of his friends
died.
For the rest of his life, Halifax never forgot the awful things he saw in battle, and this was a strong reason why he
was always against war.
Winston's political relationship with Halifax did not begin
well.
In 1921, Winston was Minister for the Colonies, and it was
suggested that Halifax could work with him.
But Winston was not happy about working with Halifax, and
for two weeks he refused to meet him.
Halifax was angry about the way Winston was behaving and
went to his office to argue with him.
After this bad start, the two men worked together for some years, but they had different opinions about many important
subjects.
One of these was India.
At that time, India was ruled by Britain, but many Indians wanted independence from Britain, and there had been some
violent fighting.
In 1926, Halifax was made responsible for the government of
India and went there for five years.
Halifax strongly supported the idea of Indian independence and had a good relationship with the Indian leader Mahatma
Gandhi.
Other important members of the Conservative Party, including Winston, were against Indian independence and thought that
Halifax was too weak about India.
On 31st March 1931, Halifax made an agreement with Gandhi,
and Winston was very angry about this.
Later that year, Halifax returned to England and made his
first speech in the House of Lords.
In 1935, Stanley Baldwin appointed him Minister of War, and five months later, he was given two more important
government positions.
By this time, Hitler had been Chancellor in Germany for two years and was slowly building up the German army, navy and
air force.
Anthony Eden, the new British Foreign Secretary, felt very worried about this, but other people in Britain, including
Halifax, did not think there was anything to worry about.
The Allies had defeated Germany in the First World War, and they thought it would take a long time before it became a
strong country again.
However, Germany was beginning to show that it was not as
weak as some people thought.
After the First World War, Germany and the Allies had signed two important peace treaties: the Treaty of Versailles and
the Treaty of Locarno.
In the Treaty of Locarno, Germany promised never to go to
war again with other countries.
It also promised that German troops would never enter the Rhineland, the area of Germany around the River Rhine, close
to the border with France, Belgium, Holland and Luxembourg.
But in 1936, Hitler broke these promises and sent German
tanks into the Rhineland.
Many people in Britain were not very worried about the
Rhineland.
They thought invading the Rhineland was not the same as invading a foreign country, so the British government did
nothing to stop Hitler.
When he realized that the Allies were not going to punish him for breaking the peace treaties, Hitler started planning
to take back some of the lands Germany had lost after the
First World War.
After Neville Chamberlain became prime minister of Britain in 1937, he wanted to avoid a second world war, so he tried
to make a peace agreement between Hitler and the British
government.
In November 1937, Halifax went on holiday to Germany, and afterwards Hitler invited him to his house in the Bavarian
Alps.
Anthony Eden, the Foreign Secretary, did not want Halifax to
meet Hitler.
He knew that Halifax supported the idea of a peace
agreement, and he did not want him to discuss this with
Hitler.
However, Halifax had a very good relationship with
Chamberlain, and Chamberlain encouraged him to go and meet
Hitler.
When Halifax returned to Britain, Eden was shocked and angry because Halifax had discussed some things with Hitler that
Eden had warned him not to talk about.
Halifax spoke warmly about Hitler and said that people in Britain were worried only because they did not know about
the wonderful changes he had made in Germany.
Halifax reported to the Cabinet that the Germans were not interested in war, because they were "too busy building up
their country".
Two months later, in January 1938, Chamberlain formally
announced his policy of making a peace agreement with
Hitler.
The British government started to consider ways that some of the lands that Germany had lost after the First World War
could be returned to Hitler.
Many people, including Anthony Eden, were not happy about
this.
But in February 1938, after Eden resigned, Chamberlain
offered the job of Foreign Secretary to Halifax.
Just over two weeks later, German troops marched into Vienna
because Hitler had decided to attach Austria to Germany.
Although Halifax had known this was going to happen, he had
done nothing to stop it until it was too late.
Next, Hitler started thinking about the Sudetenland, the
area of Czechoslovakia where German-speaking people lived.
Everybody wondered what Halifax would do if Hitler decided
to attach the Sudetenland to Germany as well.
By the summer of 1938, thousands of German troops had
arrived on the border with Czechoslovakia.
Chamberlain became worried and asked Hitler for a meeting to
discuss the situation.
At the meeting, which happened in Munich in September 1938,
Chamberlain believed all Hitler's promises.
As he stepped off the plane back in Britain, he waved a
"peace agreement" that Hitler had signed.
Part of the agreement was that Hitler would be given the Sudetenland, and on 1st October 1938 German troops entered
the Sudetenland peacefully.
Halifax seemed to keep changing his opinion about Hitler.
On 12th October 1938, he invited Joseph Kennedy, the
American ambassador to Britain, to tea at his house.
Later, Kennedy reported to Washington, "I spent an hour and a half with Halifax this afternoon drinking tea... Halifax
does not believe that Hitler wants to have a war with Great
Britain." Halifax told Kennedy that he thought Britain should build up its air force, and France should do the
same, and then Hitler could be allowed to "do what he likes in
Central Europe".
However, on 9th and 10th November 1938, some terrible things happened in Germany during Kristallnacht, also known as the
Night of Broken Glass.
Jewish shops, businesses and other buildings were destroyed all over the country, and many Jewish people were killed or
hurt.
People in Britain and other countries were extremely shocked, and Halifax realized that Hitler and the Nazis were
doing terrible things.
He said that there could never be peace until the Nazis were
destroyed.
Meanwhile, Chamberlain was becoming old and tired, and he
was beginning to make some serious mistakes.
Without telling Halifax, he announced to the newspapers that the situation with Germany was much better than it had been
for some time.
But less than a week later, German tanks entered Prague, and
Hitler invaded the rest of Czechoslovakia.
Poland was now in danger, and Halifax promised Poland that,
if Germany attacked, Britain would protect them.
So, when Hitler invaded Poland on 1st September 1939,
Britain declared war on Germany.
Winston and Halifax were two different kinds of men, and there were many subjects, like India, that they could not
agree about.
Both of them loved Britain deeply and wanted to protect it,
but their ideas about how to do this were very different.
Winston believed that the best policy was to meet threats
and dangers face-to-face.
Halifax believed that the best policy was to leave other
countries alone.
Both of them believed that their way was the only right way
for Britain.
On 10th May 1940, the day that he became prime minister,
Winston did not go to bed until 3 a.m.
As soon as he woke the next morning, he sent another letter to Neville Chamberlain, asking him and Halifax to meet with
him in the War Room in the Admiralty at 12.30 p.m. so they
could look at maps of Europe together and discuss what to
do.
Chamberlain agreed, adding that, until Winston had appointed his War Cabinet, he, Halifax and Winston would have to be
responsible for running the war.
However, Winston had a problem.
He needed the Labour MPs Clement Attlee and Arthur Greenwood
to be in his War Cabinet.
Attlee and Greenwood not only had refused to be part of a government led by Chamberlain, but now they were saying they
did not want Chamberlain to be in the War Cabinet.
So that morning, after he had written to Chamberlain and Halifax, Winston met with Attlee and Greenwood and succeeded
in persuading them to work with Chamberlain.
Winston went to his first "Meeting of Ministers" at 12.30 p.m. that day, when he met with Chamberlain, Halifax and six
of the top men in the army, navy and air force.
They discussed a number of important subjects about the war
and made decisions about what Britain was going to do.
After the meeting finished, they agreed to meet again, at 10
p.m.
Winston had only just become prime minister, but already he
was having problems with some of his own party.
Everybody had different opinions about who should be in the
new War Cabinet.
General Ironside believed it was very important to include the two Labour MPs, but Halifax and Chamberlain were against
this idea.
Also, not everybody was confident about Winston's way of
running things.
That afternoon, Halifax and his wife were walking through the gardens of Buckingham Palace on their way to the
Admiralty when they met the king and queen.
The king told Halifax he had hoped Halifax would be prime
minister and seemed very worried about Winston.
The new War Cabinet was announced on the nine o'clock news
that evening.
The second "Meeting of Ministers" was pushed back from 10
p.m. to 10.30 p.m. and did not finish until after midnight.
Halifax was very unhappy about the late meeting, and wrote in his diary: "This night-life is no good to me." But this
was Winston's way of doing things.
For him, the best time to have meetings was late at night,
and that was not going to change.
This was how he was going to run the war.
Things were not easy for Winston.
He was working very hard, with very little sleep.
But he did not get much thanks from his colleagues for his
hard work and, instead, some of them complained about him.
CHAPTER SIX
"Blood, toil, tears and sweat"
Winston had his own ways of doing things.
Although he worked late at night, he usually woke up quite
early.
However, he would often work while he was still in bed; he was not a formal kind of person and liked to lie in bed,
smoking, while he discussed what was happening in the war with
his colleagues.
He always had a short sleep of two hours in the afternoons,
because he knew he was going to stay up late.
After sleeping, he had a hot bath, his second bath of the
day, at 7p.m.
Winston loved baths and enjoyed turning over in his bath
like a huge fish.
Sometimes this caused a lot of water to come out of the bath and pass through the floor on to visitors' coats hanging in
a small room below.
While Winston was in his bath, his secretary had to wait outside the bathroom door, listening to what he said and
writing it down.
"Chips" Gemmell, one of his secretaries, remembered that Winston used to shout, "Don't come in!" As she stood outside
the bathroom door, she heard "wonderful bathroom noises" and
the sound of Winston washing himself.
Sometimes, she said, "he'd call out, 'Don't go away!' (and I said), 'No, no, I'm still here' and the sounds of bathing
(went) on and sometimes... he'd forgotten what he'd wanted
to say".
After Winston got out of his bath, he walked from the
bathroom to his bedroom wearing only a bath towel.
However, at Winston's house in Chartwell, if he got out of his bath and wanted to go to another room, he did not wear
clothes at all.
Winston wore expensive silk underwear because his skin was
very soft.
Even Hitler and his colleagues had heard stories about Winston, and the Nazi leader Joseph Goebbels wrote in his
diary, "A book on Churchill reports that he drinks too much and
wears silk underwear. He (gives his messages to his secretaries) in the bath..." According to Goebbels, Hitler
thought this was very funny.
It was true that, for many years, Winston had drunk a lot, and because of this, some of his colleagues did not think he
would be able to guide Britain to victory.
Not everybody in Parliament had a good opinion of Winston,
and he knew this could be dangerous.
He needed to find a way of winning those people over to his
side.
Although he was extremely popular with the British public,
he needed his colleagues to support him, too.
This was why he wrote the letters to Chamberlain and Halifax immediately after he became prime minister - to win them to
his side.
Winston and Clemmie were very kind to Neville Chamberlain
and his wife.
They decided not to move into the prime minister's house at Number 10, Downing Street, immediately, but to stay at the
Admiralty for another month so that the Chamberlains did not
have to move out of their home quickly.
In his first few days as prime minister, Winston did all he could to make his relationships with his political
colleagues more smooth.
At the same time, he wanted to do his best for the ordinary
British people.
General Ismay remembered how, "two or three days after (Winston) became prime minister, I walked with him from
Downing Street to the Admiralty. A number of people waiting outside
the private entrance (shouted), 'Good luck, Winnie'... as soon as we were inside the building, he (started to cry).
'Poor people,' he said, 'poor people. They trust me, and I can
give them nothing but disaster for quite a long time.'"
Winston had formed his new government, and now he started thinking about what he could offer not only to his
colleagues in
Parliament, but also to his country in its darkest hour.
On Monday 13th May 1940, three days after Winston had become prime minister, he made his first speech to Parliament in
his new position.
Winston understood that words were powerful, and he was very
clever at using them.
He knew this had to be a great speech to win his political
colleagues to his side, so he prepared it well.
Winston always took a long time to write his speeches and
thought carefully about what he was going to say.
It was said that every minute of a speech took Winston one
hour's work to prepare.
When he was a young army officer in India in 1896, he had taught himself about many different subjects, including the
art of making speeches.
He studied the speeches of famous Greeks, like Socrates, Plato and Aristotle, and different political leaders in
history.
He believed that, although a good speaker was born with a great skill, they still needed a lot of practice to become
better.
Winston's first speech to Parliament as prime minister was aimed at not only his political colleagues but also the
British public and the world.
He needed people to understand that the situation was very dangerous, but he also wanted them to trust him as their
leader.
Parliament had not met since 9th May, when they had discussed what to do about the Nazi attack on British troops
in Norway.
At that time, a large number of Conservative MPs had been
very angry with Chamberlain and shouted at him to resign.
But now some of these MPs felt that they had acted too
quickly, and they were sorry Chamberlain had gone.
They were worried about what was going to happen next, and
they were not confident about Winston as prime minister.
So when he entered Parliament, they did not welcome him very warmly; however, when Chamberlain came in, everyone shouted
and cheered.
During the weekend, reports from the war had said that the
situation in Europe was getting worse.
That day, German troops had invaded France through the Ardennes Forest, and the queen of Holland, Queen Wilhelmina,
had left her country and come to Britain.
Winston knew that, in his speech, he had to make people feel
better about the situation.
Words were all he had to encourage them and give them hope.
At 2.54 p.m., he stood up and began to speak.
He started by asking Parliament to welcome the new government, which the king had asked him to form and which
included members of all parties.
He had appointed the new War Cabinet very quickly because
there was no time to lose.
The most important Cabinet positions were already filled,
and the others would be filled the next day.
The next words in Winston's speech have become very famous: "... I said to those who have joined this Government: 'I
have nothing to offer but blood, toil, tears and sweat.'"
Winston said there were very difficult times ahead, which would continue for many months, and, of course, people
wanted to know what the government was going to do.
He said, "You ask, what is our policy? I can say: it is to (fight), by sea, land and air... What is our aim? I can
answer in one word: it is victory..." Without victory, he said,
it would be the end of Britain and the British Empire.
However, said Winston, he was sure that it would not be the
end of Britain and that Britain would not fail.
He finished by asking everyone to join together and help:
"... I say, 'Come then, let us go forward together...'"
Winston's speech was just seven minutes long.
Today, that speech is thought to be one of the greatest
speeches ever made in politics.
When Hitler made a speech, he said "I" and "me" a lot, but
Winston always said "we" and "us" in his speeches.
In this way, he made the British people feel he was with
them and on their side.
He could not promise victory, but he gave his listeners
hope.
But on that day, some people in Parliament did not think his
speech was strong enough.
Winston was disappointed because he had worked very hard to
prepare it.
However, Winston's old friend and ally, Lloyd George, the Liberal prime minister who had guided Britain to victory in
the First World War, then made a speech thanking Winston and
supporting him strongly.
Winston did not have to worry about what the British public
thought.
The ordinary British people loved his speech and were happy
with their new prime minister.
Many newspapers also supported him.
One newspaper showed a picture of a crowd of men following Winston, with the words "All behind you, Winston" under the
picture.
Meanwhile, Winston and the War Cabinet met again to discuss
the latest reports from the war.
The War Cabinet met in special War Rooms under Whitehall in central London, where they received telephone reports about
the war and discussed their plans.
Winston informed the meeting that he thought the Germans
were going to attack Britain by air.
Everything was now happening very quickly in Europe.
Three million German troops were marching across Europe, with another two million German soldiers ready and waiting
back home.
On Tuesday 14th May, the War Cabinet received the news that the French had retreated to the city of Antwerp in Belgium
and, together with Belgian troops, were trying to hold the
line against the Germans.
Further, south, the German army had crossed the River Meuse
into France.
This was a terrible shock for the Allies.
For many centuries, the River Meuse had protected France, Belgium and Holland from enemies attacking from the east,
but the German army had managed to cross it easily.
There was other bad news, too.
Halifax told the meeting that the French ambassador to London had received a message from Queen Wilhelmina of
Holland, now living in Buckingham Palace, saying that Holland was
considering peace talks with Hitler.
Then Halifax informed the meeting about a telegram he had
received from the British ambassador in Rome.
It said that the Italian leader, the dictator Benito
Mussolini, was making threats to enter the war on Germany's
side.
Everybody was extremely worried about this, but Winston said
they would have to wait and see what happened.
Later that day, Winston informed the War Cabinet about a
telephone message from the French prime minister, Paul
Reynaud.
The message said that German troops and tanks had crossed the French army lines at Sedan, a town further south on the
River Meuse.
Reynaud said the French could not stop the German army unless they received help from the British, and asked
Winston to send a large number of fighter planes as soon as possible.
Winston called Reynaud early the next morning.
Reynaud was worried and nervous, and he had terrible news.
Although the French army had tried to stop the Germans, they
had failed, and the Germans were now marching towards Paris.
The road to Paris was open, said Reynaud, and the battle was
lost.
He asked if Britain could send more troops to help the French, but Winston replied that this was impossible,
although he also said that Britain would continue fighting to the end.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Friends and enemies
Meanwhile, Halifax had two more pieces of bad news.
The first was that Holland was planning to surrender two
cities, Rotterdam and Utrecht, to the Nazis.
The second was about a report that Joseph Kennedy, the American ambassador to London, had received from a colleague
in Rome, which said that Mussolini had decided to join the war.
If this happened, France would be in a terrible position, because it would have two enemies on its borders - Germany
and Italy.
Halifax asked Winston to send a message to Mussolini to try to persuade him not to enter the war, and Winston agreed to
do this.
Winston then informed the War Cabinet about another message
he was planning to send to President Franklin D.
Roosevelt of the USA, asking for his help against the Nazis.
When Winston was First Lord of the Admiralty, he had formed a very good relationship with President Roosevelt, so now he
was able to write to him very openly.
He told Roosevelt that the situation in Europe was getting
worse.
Hitler had invaded France and was destroying the smaller countries one by one, and Mussolini was probably going to
enter the war on Hitler's side.
Britain was expecting an air attack from the Germans, but the British people were preparing for it and, "If necessary,
we shall continue the war alone, and we are not afraid of
that".
He asked if Roosevelt could send forty or fifty warships and
several hundred planes and other equipment to help Britain.
Winston told Roosevelt the British would pay for everything they were asking for, but if at some time in the future
Britain had no money, he hoped that Roosevelt would simply give
these things to Britain.
He also asked if Roosevelt could send American ships to Ireland, to prevent Hitler invading Britain through that
country.
Since 1933, when Hitler rose to power as Chancellor of Germany, Roosevelt had said that America would not take part
in any future war in Europe.
However, although they had no active part in the war, many
people in the US were against Hitler.
Roosevelt supported the Allies by selling them planes, ships
and other war equipment.
Two weeks before Winston wrote to Roosevelt, Britain had bought 324 fighter planes from the US for the army and
eighty-one for the navy.
After he had written to Roosevelt, Winston also wrote to the Italian dictator, Mussolini, but it was a very different
kind of letter from his letter to Roosevelt.
That letter had been warm and friendly, but Winston's letter
to Mussolini was very short.
He reminded Mussolini about meetings they had had in Rome and asked if it was too late to stop "a river of blood"
between the British and Italian peoples.
Although they could hurt each other badly, he did not want
this to happen.
Nobody knew what the result of the battles in Europe would be, he told Mussolini, but "England will go on to the end,
even quite alone, as we have done before".
However, Winston continued, he was confident that the United
States would help Britain.
He finished by saying it would be terrible for Britain and Italy to fight each other and asked Mussolini to think again
about entering the war.
Two days later, Winston received Mussolini's reply, but it
was not very positive or friendly.
He reminded Winston that, in 1935, when Italy had attacked Abyssinia in Africa, Britain had encouraged other countries
to join together against Italy.
He also informed Winston that Italy had recently signed a treaty with Germany, so Italy's actions would be according
to the policy in this treaty.
At 11.30 a.m. on 16th May, there was another meeting of the War Cabinet, and again the reports about the situation with
the war were terrible.
The German army had marched into France at a place near the Ardennes Forest that the French had thought would be very
difficult for the Germans to cross.
Now everything depended on what the French would do and if
the French army would surrender to the Germans.
Winston knew that the French prime minister, Paul Reynaud, was very worried and nervous, and he was afraid that Reynaud
was planning to make a peace agreement with Hitler.
So he decided to go to Paris and meet with Reynaud and
encourage him to be strong and fight back.
That afternoon, Winston flew to Paris with General Ismay.
During the meeting, Reynaud and the French Minister of Defence asked if Britain could send more fighter planes to
France.
Although the French had begun the battle with 650 fighter
planes, they now had only 150.
Britain had lost thirty-six planes when defending the River Meuse, but Winston still called the War Cabinet and asked
them to agree to send more planes to France.
The War Cabinet met at 11 p.m. and agreed with Winston that
they should send more planes.
This made the French leaders feel more confident.
Early the next day, Winston returned to London and reported what had happened at the meeting in Paris to the War
Cabinet.
He said that, although Reynaud was very happy that Britain
was sending more planes, the meeting had not been easy.
Meanwhile, Winston had received a message from Roosevelt,
but it was not the answer he was hoping for.
Roosevelt said that he was considering carefully everything Winston had said in his letter, but he could not help the
Allies immediately, and everything would "take time".
Winston was very disappointed, as Roosevelt had been his
last hope.
So the War Cabinet decided Winston should tell the British people that they were in a situation of the greatest
emergency, and Chamberlain asked Winston to make a speech on
national radio.
Meanwhile, the German army was moving quickly towards the
north coast of France.
There were about 400,000 British troops in France with the British Expeditionary Force (BEF), in a position near the
Belgian border with France.
On Sunday 19th May, the War Cabinet met again to discuss whether it would be better for the BEF to retreat from their
position and start moving to the north coast of France, from
where it might be possible to evacuate them.
However, Winston and some other members of the War Cabinet thought this would be a bad idea because it would be very
easy for the German planes to bomb the troops.
After the meeting, at 6 p.m., Winston started planning what
he was going to say to the people of Britain.
He worked hard for three hours, thinking about the best
words to make people feel strong and brave.
At 9 p.m., he went on national radio to make his speech.
Winston spoke to the British people honestly and openly because he wanted them to understand that the situation was
very serious.
First, he told them about what was happening in the war.
He said that a huge battle was taking place and the German troops and tanks were moving quickly across France, but that
the British Royal Air Force was helping the French army to
stand against them.
The German army was large, strong and well trained, with
excellent equipment.
However, Winston said he felt very confident about the
French army and its leaders.
Winston said that the German army had only invaded a small
area of France and had lost many men in the attack.
Britain's fighter planes were doing a great job and had attacked and destroyed many of the German planes, as well as
bombing places in Germany where war equipment and weapons were
produced.
He then warned the British people to expect attacks from
Germany over the next few days.
Britain was ready for these attacks, and now people at home had to do everything possible to support the British
soldiers fighting on the front line of battle.
If Britain was going to win the war, the army needed more
planes and weapons with which to fight the enemy.
He continued by saying that "our (job) is not only to win the battle - but to win the war" and that after the battle
in France was over, "there will come the battle for our island
- for all that Britain is, and all that Britain means" and
that this would be a very difficult time.
However, he had received promises from the French prime minister that "(the French) will fight to the end", and
Britain would do the same.
In the government he had formed, people came from different parties and in the past had different opinions, but now
everybody had only one aim - to fight "until victory is won,
and never to surrender..."
The British and French people would fight side by side to
save Europe from the terrible danger in front of it.
Winston's colleagues in Parliament thanked him warmly for
this wonderful speech.
Anthony Eden wrote to him that evening and said, "You have never done anything as good or as great. Thank you, and
thank God for you." Stanley Baldwin, who had once been prime
minister, wrote to him to say, "I listened to your well-known voice last night and I (want to shake) your hand
for a (short) moment and to tell you that from the bottom of my
heart I wish you all that is good - health and (a strong)
mind and body..."
Meanwhile, the first German tanks had reached the French
coast near the town of Abbeville, just fifty
miles across the sea from England.
Ten days before, when the Nazis invaded Holland, Belgium and Luxembourg, most people had not believed that a strong
country like France could also fall to Germany.
But now it looked as if this could actually happen.
Winston was becoming very frustrated that he could not get
correct information about the war quickly enough.
So he sent General Ironside to France to find out what was happening with the battle and the situation of the French,
Belgian and British armies.
Meanwhile, the War Cabinet met again on 20th May at 11.30
a.m. to discuss how Britain could best support its allies.
Winston and the War Cabinet agreed that they could not send
any more fighter planes to help the French.
They believed that the Nazis were probably going to try to attack Britain very soon, and if Britain was going to
continue fighting, it needed all its planes to protect itself.
However, if Britain did not help France, there was the
danger that the French army would surrender to the Germans.
The evening before, Winston had sent a telegram to President Roosevelt asking if he could send more planes to Britain,
and he was still waiting for Roosevelt's reply.
He had told Roosevelt that Britain would never surrender to
Hitler.
General Ironside returned to London on the morning of 21st
May, and came straight to the War Cabinet.
Things had not gone very well for him in France.
While he was staying at a hotel in Calais, the Germans had started to bomb it, and he had just managed to escape with
his life.
There was only bad news to report.
He had become very frustrated with the French military
leaders because they could not decide what to do.
The Allied troops could not move quickly along the roads because of hundreds of thousands of people trying to escape
from Belgium and the towns in the north of France.
The German army was pushing forward to Boulogne on the coast, with the aim of preventing the British and Belgian
armies in the north from joining up with the French army to the
south.
Winston decided that he had to return to France as soon as
possible to persuade the French leaders not to surrender.
So, early the next morning, 22nd May, he flew back to Paris
to meet Prime Minister Reynaud.
The BEF was in a terrible situation without enough food or
equipment.
If they reached the north coast of France, there was still
the problem of how to evacuate 300,000 soldiers.
The German air force, the Luftwaffe, controlled the skies and would bomb the troops while they were waiting on the
beaches.
However, when Winston arrived in Paris, there was some good
news.
The French had appointed a new military leader, General
Weygand.
Although the general was seventy-three, he was very ready to
make decisions and told Winston about his "plan of war".
Britain had already sent as many troops to France as
possible.
More British soldiers had arrived at Boulogne that day and were on the way to protect the towns of Calais and Dunkirk
on the north coast of France.
Weygand informed Winston that there was already a large number of French troops in these towns, and it would be a
disaster for the British, Belgian and French troops in the north
to try to join up with the rest of the French army in the
south.
Winston agreed with Weygand and flew back to London for a
meeting with the War Cabinet at 7.30 p.m.
Later, General Ironside wrote in his diary that he had been
very surprised because Winston seemed so full of hope.
Winston told the War Cabinet that an attack by British and
French troops was going to happen the next day.
But when they met again on 23rd May, there were no reports
of an attack.
Instead, the Luftwaffe were bombing Boulogne, and the German
army had almost surrounded the town.
The British had sent ships with more food and equipment for the BEF to Calais, but the Luftwaffe were preventing it from
being taken off the ships.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Saving the British army
Neville Chamberlain had not spoken very much during the War Cabinet meetings of the past few days, but at the meeting on
23rd May, he gave
his opinion.
He said that, instead of attacking, it would be better for
the BEF to retreat.
There was still a chance to evacuate the troops back to Britain, but if this did not happen and the BEF was
destroyed, there would be no army to defend Britain.
As usual, Lord Halifax supported Chamberlain, and then he read out a telegram he had received from the British
ambassador in Rome.
According to the ambassador, Mussolini was only waiting for the German army to control the towns on the north coast of
France before declaring war.
It was clear that Halifax thought Italy had a key part in
what was going to happen next in Europe.
The situation had become extremely serious, with the British army retreating, the fall of France and a possible new
enemy, Italy, entering the war.
Winston needed to tell Parliament what was happening.
He spoke to them at 3 p.m., but in this speech, he did not
mention anything about "victory".
The next morning, Winston was shocked to learn that the German army was already in Boulogne, that the soldiers in
the BEF had only half their normal amount of food and that
Weygand's plan to attack the Germans in the north had not
yet begun.
So Winston called Weygand at 6 p.m. to ask what was going
on.
Weygand informed Winston that the French army had succeeded
in taking back three French towns from the Germans.
Although Winston believed him, actually this information was
false.
When the War Cabinet met at 7 p.m. that evening, Winston told them he was considering Chamberlain's idea of
evacuating the British army from France.
The situation in Boulogne was a disaster, he said, and perhaps it was time for the BEF to retreat to the coast,
although General Weygand still thought that the British and French
armies should continue attacking the Germans.
Winston was not confident that the general's plan would succeed, but he was not sure about evacuating the troops,
either.
It would be very dangerous, and many soldiers would probably
die.
Winston then went to Buckingham Palace to inform King George
VI about the situation.
The king was very worried and later wrote in his diary, "The Prime Minister came at 10.30 p.m. He told me that if the
French plan made... by Weygand did not (succeed), he would
have to order the BEF back to England. This... would mean (they would lose) all guns, tanks... in France. The question
was whether we could get the troops back from Calais and
Dunkirk." After Winston returned to the Admiralty, he was
told that Weygand's plan was going wrong.
During that night, 1,000 British troops were evacuated from Boulogne while the Germans were bombing them heavily, but
200 soldiers were not able to escape.
Meanwhile, just over twenty miles up the coast, Brigadier
Nicholson and his troops were defending Calais.
The town was surrounded by the German army, and there was no
way out.
But Nicholson and his soldiers had to continue fighting because there was no other large town between Calais and
Dunkirk, where most of the BEF was arriving.
If Nicholson surrendered, there would be nothing to prevent the German army from reaching Dunkirk before the BEF could
be evacuated.
As the situation in France became worse and the direct danger to Britain increased, Winston became more and more
worried.
He became ill, and his doctor ordered him to stay in bed.
But Winston was not a good patient, and he continued to run
the war from his bed.
He heard that General Ismay had sent a message to Brigadier
Nicholson in Calais to advise him to evacuate his men.
Winston was very angry about this and sent another message
to Nicholson.
He told him his job was to stay in Calais and fight the German troops, to give the army time to evacuate the BEF
from Dunkirk.
Eater that day on 24th May, General Ironside reported that the German tanks had passed the west side of Calais and were
now between the town and the sea.
Brigadier Nicholson was hoping for another order to evacuate his men from Calais, and he did not know that the War
Cabinet had decided not to do this.
At 7.05 p.m., Nicholson sent a message asking for more
troops.
At 11.23 p.m., Nicholson received an answer from the War Cabinet, telling him not to evacuate and ordering him to
"(choose the) best position and fight on".
The next day, Winston himself sent a strong message to Nicholson, telling him how important for Britain and France
it was to defend Calais.
"The eyes of the Empire are upon... Calais." Meanwhile, Winston had received a telegram from Paul Reynaud informing
him that the BEF was no longer following General Weygand's plan
and was moving towards the towns on the north coast of
France.
The road to Dunkirk was now wide open to both British and
German troops.
When Halifax realized that there was no longer a plan for the BEF to attack the Germans, but instead it was retreating
to the coast, he started thinking again about approaching
Mussolini with the idea of making peace.
He knew that many rich people in the Conservative Party would support this idea because it was very important for
them to keep their lands and families safe.
They would be very happy about making a peace agreement with
Mussolini if Britain could not continue fighting because its army was destroyed.
Prime Minister Reynaud was on his way from France to London
to discuss the war situation.
Winston warned the War Cabinet that Reynaud was probably
going to tell them that France could not continue fighting.
Halifax could no longer be silent.
He informed the War Cabinet about a meeting he had at the
Italian Embassy in London.
At this meeting, it was said that there were many important people in Italy who did not want war, and that if the
British government approached the Italian government to discuss a
possible agreement, this would be welcomed by the Italians.
The Italian ambassador had told Halifax that Mussolini
wanted "peace in Europe".
Halifax had replied that this was what Britain wanted, too.
Halifax told the War Cabinet that the most important thing now for Britain was not to win the war but to keep
independence for itself and its Empire.
Britain was losing the war, and if there was a chance to prevent the deaths of more young people, Britain should take
it.
Now Winston was in a very difficult position.
Only one week before, Mussolini had replied to a letter from
Winston in a way that was not very friendly.
But now the situation had changed for Britain.
Britain's ally, France, was probably going to surrender to
Germany, and the BEF was in terrible danger.
Winston did not like the idea of approaching Mussolini, and
he did not think it would succeed.
He was worried that, if Britain approached Mussolini, this
could lead to peace talks with Hitler.
He did not want Britain to be in a weak position "in which we went to... Mussolini and invited him to go to... Hitler
and ask him to (act) nicely".
But he had to think about what was best for the British
people, so he agreed that perhaps they should consider it.
If most British people had known that their leaders were considering making a peace agreement with a dictator, they
would have been shocked.
But the newspapers often reported false information, so people believed that Britain and the Allies were winning the
war.
Everything depended on what France was going to do.
If France surrendered, Britain would be in a much weaker
position, and Winston had to consider that.
If France was not going to continue fighting, it was still important for Britain that France stayed in the war as long
as possible.
The BEF needed the French army to support them and help them
escape safely.
But nobody knew if Britain would succeed in evacuating its
troops.
If the BEF was destroyed, Britain would have no army to
defend it, and it would be in the same weak position as
France.
So, on 26th May, after a four-hour meeting, Winston agreed that Halifax could write a paper suggesting how to approach
Mussolini, which the War Cabinet would discuss the next day.
Halifax went happily away to write his paper.
But meanwhile, Winston was thinking hard about how the
British army could be saved.
The big question was - how could the troops be safely
evacuated back to Britain?
More than 300,000 British troops were about to arrive at Dunkirk, but the British navy ships could not get close
enough to the beach to protect them because of air attacks by the
Luftwaffe.
General Ironside had said that he thought only ten per cent
of the men could be saved.
President Roosevelt once said about Winston, "He has a hundred ideas a day. Four are good, the other ninety-six...
dangerous." Six days before, at the meeting of the War Cabinet
on 20th May, Winston had had an excellent idea.
He had suggested that the Admiralty could collect a large number of small boats to sail across the English Channel to
Dunkirk and bring back the British troops of the BEE They
could do this by asking ordinary people who owned boats for
help.
Winston had contacted an old friend who had worked for the Admiralty and asked him to put out a public call for boats
on national radio.
There were now 800 little ships waiting to sail across the
English Channel to Dunkirk.
Winston knew that the plan was taking a huge risk with the lives of ordinary people, but if the British army could be
saved, then Britain could continue fighting.
So, on 26th May, Winston hurried to the Admiralty, and at
6.57 p.m. he gave the order for the boats to start sailing.
At the same time, he sent another telegram to Brigadier Nicholson at Calais, informing him again of the decision not
to evacuate and saying his men must continue to "fight to the
end".
Nicholson and his brave men followed their orders.
They refused to surrender and continued fighting until the last moment, when the German flag was raised above the tower
in the Hotel de Ville, the most important building in
Calais.
Then they were led out of the building with their hands
above their heads and a line of German guns pointing at
them.
They were sent to prisoner- of-war camps for the rest of the
war.
Sadly, Nicholson died three years later when he fell out of
a window at his camp.
Anthony Eden described the decision not to evacuate
Nicholson and his men as "one of the most painful of the
war".
Winston, too, felt terribly sad.
He had ordered 2,000 men to fight to the end in the hope of
saving several hundred thousand others.
At dinner at Admiralty House that evening with Eden, Ismay
and Ironside, he was unusually silent.
CHAPTER NINE
Dark days
Winston had many things to think about - Nicholson and his brave men at Calais, Halifax and Mussolini, and the hundreds
of little boats sailing through the
night across the Channel to Dunkirk.
The next morning, 27th May, at 7.15 a.m., he received some
worrying news from the British navy in Dover.
According to this message, "a bad situation is developing between Calais and Dunkirk. The enemy have (brought) forty
guns as far as Gravelines (the small town between Calais and
Dunkirk)... and are (destroying ships) approaching Dunkirk..." If the small boats could not reach the harbour
to collect the British soldiers, the BEF would soon be surrounded by
the German army, with no way to escape.
Halifax was busy preparing the paper about a possible peace
agreement for his colleagues.
But when he arrived at the 11.30 a.m. meeting of the War
Cabinet, he also had some bad news.
He had learned from the Belgian Embassy in London that the king of Belgium, King Leopold III, was considering
surrendering to Germany and making a separate peace agreement with
Hitler.
Winston immediately sent a message to the Belgian king,
asking him not to do that.
The Belgian army was in the north of France, fighting beside
the BEF, although they did not know that there was a plan to evacuate the British soldiers.
If the Belgian army surrendered and stopped fighting at that moment, it would be very easy for the Germans to attack the
BEF from the north.
The British ambassador in Washington had sent a telegram to Halifax, suggesting that perhaps Britain could give some of
its colonies in the New World to America to pay for war
equipment.
Halifax was ready to consider this idea, but Winston
refused.
He said that the US had given Britain very little help, and
Britain might need those colonies itself.
He then asked his military leaders to examine the idea "of our continuing the war alone against Germany and probably
Italy" before the next meeting of the War Cabinet.
This meeting, which was a very important one, happened later
that afternoon, at 4.30 p.m.
There were usually twenty people at War Cabinet meetings, but at this meeting there were only eight - Winston,
Halifax, Chamberlain, Clement Attlee and Arthur Greenwood (the
Labour MPs), Sir Alexander Cadogan (Halifax's close colleague in the Foreign Office), Sir Archibald Sinclair
(the Liberal Party leader and an old friend of Winston's) and Sir
Edward Bridges, who recorded what happened at War Cabinet
meetings.
There was only one subject to discuss - whether to approach Mussolini about a possible peace agreement, as Halifax had
suggested.
The day before, the French prime minister, Paul Reynaud, had sent a message suggesting that the governments of Britain
and France should approach Mussolini together.
Halifax had written down his ideas in a paper that he had
already sent to the people at the meeting.
He suggested telling Mussolini that, if he made a peace agreement with Britain and France, both countries would do
their best to help Italy.
Halifax also said that President Roosevelt had already
written to Mussolini about this but had not received an
answer.
Everybody at the meeting gave their opinions, one by one.
Sir Archibald Sinclair and the two Labour MPs were very much
against the idea of approaching Mussolini.
Like Winston, they were afraid that an agreement with Mussolini could be seen as a first step to peace talks
between Britain and Germany.
Then Winston said there was no purpose in approaching
Mussolini.
He did not believe that France was ready to surrender, but
even if this happened, Britain would not go down with
France.
The best help Britain could give to Reynaud, said Winston, was to show him that "we were going to fight it out to the
end".
At the moment, many people in Europe believed that Britain was in a very weak position, and the only way to change
their minds was "by showing the world that Germany had not
beaten us".
If Britain approached Mussolini to talk about peace, said Winston, this would have no purpose and could even be a
disaster for Britain.
If the worst happened, and Britain was beaten in the war, "it would not be a bad thing for this country to go down
fighting for other countries" that the Nazis had attacked and
invaded.
Winston and Halifax had not agreed with each other many
times in the past, and now it was happening again.
It was clear that Winston had very different ideas from
Halifax.
Halifax felt very surprised and frustrated because, the day before, Winston had thought it might be possible to approach
Mussolini.
However, it now seemed that he had changed his mind and was
strongly against it.
Halifax could not understand what Winston was trying to do.
Like Winston, he loved his country very much, and he really believed that a peace agreement was the best hope for
Britain.
He did not want more young people to lose their lives in war, and he did not believe that peace talks would be a
danger or a disaster.
But almost everyone else in the room was on Winston's side,
and Halifax found himself alone.
The only person to support him was his friend and colleague
Chamberlain.
Winston knew that he had to be careful about Halifax.
Halifax was the Foreign Secretary, and many Conservative MPs
supported him.
He needed to keep Halifax on his side, because some people
were still not confident that Winston was a good leader.
If Halifax decided to resign, they could turn against
Winston.
Then the Conservative MPs would form two groups - those who
supported peace and those who were against it.
This would be very bad for Britain at a time when it was important for all the members of the government to work
together.
So now, Winston said that, although he would not join France in asking for a peace agreement, if he was told what the
results of that agreement were, he would be ready to consider
them.
Once again, it seemed that Winston had changed his mind.
The War Cabinet sent a message to Reynaud, agreeing that the
French could approach Mussolini.
After the meeting, Halifax asked Winston if he could speak
to him privately in the garden of Number 10, Downing Street.
As Halifax was leaving the room, he said to his colleague Alexander Cadogan, "I can't work with Winston anymore." In
the garden, Halifax said he was thinking of resigning, but
Winston said he was sorry and persuaded him to stay in his
job.
Later that day, at 7 p.m., there was another meeting to
discuss the latest news from France.
The BEF was in an even worse situation and was retreating to
the coast.
Winston told the War Cabinet that Britain had done
everything possible to support its allies.
However, the French military leaders had made some serious
mistakes, and the Belgian government had also been very
weak.
They had not wanted Belgium to enter the war and had not
allowed British and French soldiers to enter Belgium.
When the German army invaded Belgium, there were no troops
to stop them, so now the BEF was in a dangerous position.
Later, Winston received news that King Leopold III of
Belgium had approached the Germans to discuss surrendering.
When Winston told the War Cabinet this, they felt sorry for
King Leopold III.
The Belgian government, not the king, were responsible for
what had happened.
The government had left Belgium, but the king had stayed in
his country with his troops to support him.
The Minister of Information, Duff Cooper, advised Winston to
tell the British people about the BEF's true situation.
He said that the public did not know what was really going on in the war, because the newspapers mostly reported only
positive things about what was happening in France.
If people knew the truth they would be shocked, but it would
also prepare them for more bad news if and when it came.
Winston agreed to give a speech to Parliament in a week's time and returned to Admiralty House with his private
secretary, Jock Colville.
He worked till midnight, then went up to bed.
He had a lot of things to think about.
Was Halifax right?
Was he himself wrong?
Had he done the right thing for Britain in not allowing
Halifax to move forward with his peace plan?
What was the best thing to do now?
Halifax described Tuesday 28th May as "a very black day".
News came that the Belgian army had surrendered at 4 a.m.
that morning.
At the 11.30 a.m. meeting of the War Cabinet, Winston read out the important parts of the peace agreement between
Belgium and Germany:
1.
The Belgian troops were not allowed to move.
They had to stand by the side of the road in a line, waiting
for orders and holding white signs and flags.
2.
No war equipment could be destroyed.
3.
The way to the coast had to be open for German troops.
4.
The way to Ostend had to be open, and nothing was to be
destroyed.
5.
If the Belgians refused to follow orders, they would be
punished.
Meanwhile, large numbers of British troops had begun to
arrive at Dunkirk.
A report was received from Dover that 11,400 British soldiers had arrived there the night before and that another
2,500 men were already on their way across the Channel.
There were 2,000 soldiers waiting on the beaches of Dunkirk to be evacuated and 7,000 in the hills of sand behind the
beaches.
The British Royal Air Force were protecting the soldiers,
but the Luftwaffe had destroyed many of the British planes.
Winston made a short speech on the national radio news at
1p.m. and spoke to Parliament later that afternoon.
He said that the British and French armies were in a
dangerous situation, and that the Belgian army had
surrendered.
But the troops were fighting well and were "in good heart".
Winston's political colleagues were very happy about his
speech, and many people thanked him afterwards.
At 4 p.m. that afternoon, the War Cabinet met again with the
same eight people as the day before.
Halifax spoke first and said that President Roosevelt had received an answer from Mussolini, but it had not been
helpful.
Meanwhile, the French had sent a stronger message, asking
for Britain and France to approach Mussolini together.
Winston was very much against this idea, and he and Halifax
argued about it for a long time.
Halifax, supported by Chamberlain, could not understand what was wrong with the idea of asking Mussolini to act in
possible peace talks between Britain and Germany.
Chamberlain said that, if Britain could keep its independence and if the important parts of the peace
agreement looked good, it should be ready to consider it.
Winston refused to accept this, and the meeting finished at
6.15 p.m., still with no decision made about peace talks.
Earlier that day, Winston had asked for a meeting with the twenty-five other ministers who were not part of the War
Cabinet.
He had not had a chance to speak to them about Britain's situation since he became prime minister, and he knew that
some of them were still not happy about him as leader.
Winston knew that if Halifax, his Foreign Secretary, was no longer going to support him, he needed his full Cabinet of
ministers on his side.
As Winston walked over to Parliament, he thought carefully
about what he was going to say.
The ministers were all waiting for him in his office.
As he entered, they became silent, afraid of what he was
going to tell them.
What was going to happen?
Was the British army destroyed?
Was Hitler going to invade?
Were they going to lose their homes, families and way of
life?
Winston told the ministers that he had decided to prepare
the British people for bad news.
Some people would say that the situation in Northern France "would be the greatest British military defeat for many
centuries" and "we must now be prepared for the sudden turning
of the war against this island".
The British people must not be told that France could soon surrender, but if this happened, said Winston, it would be
"easier to defend this island alone than to defend this
island plus France".
He added that, if Britain was going to fight on alone, it was possible that the United States could enter the war on
Britain's side.
Winston spoke in a very positive way about Britain's
military forces.
He said that although the Germans would probably try to
invade Britain, this would be very difficult for them.
The British navy was extremely strong, the air force was very well organized, and Britain had enough food and oil and
very good troops, with help from troops in countries in the
British Empire.
British factories were also busy producing more planes.
Winston also said that he had considered making a peace
agreement with Hitler, but there was no good reason for
this.
The Germans would then be able to take Britain's navy and many other things, so it was better for Britain to continue
fighting.
If the time had come for Britain's "long island story" to finish, that would only happen "when each one of us lies...
in his own blood upon the ground".
Winston spoke from his heart and proved again that he was an
excellent speaker.
He had made it clear that he was not going to support Halifax's ideas of peace, even though he was risking the
chance of Halifax resigning.
He had decided to return to his own first idea - that it was
better to fight on.
This great speech by Winston brought all his ministers on to
his side.
Several jumped up and ran around the table to thank him.
When the War Cabinet met again, at 7 p.m. that evening, Winston told them what had happened and that all the
ministers were supporting him.
Halifax and Chamberlain realized that Winston had beaten them, and they never mentioned the idea of a peace agreement
between Britain and Germany again.
Winston was very happy because he knew that his political
colleagues supported him and felt confident about him.
Before he went to bed, he called Paul Reynaud, the French prime minister, to say that, if necessary, Britain would
continue fighting alone, although he hoped the French would not
surrender.
CHAPTER TEN
"Fight on the beaches"
The next morning, 29th May, Winston received some good news.
Prime Minister Reynaud was feeling much better because
Winston's message the evening before had greatly encouraged
him.
Winston realized that the strongest weapon he had to save
Britain was hope.
He immediately sent a message to his ministers, telling them always to use positive and encouraging words when speaking
to their friends and colleagues about the war.
At 11.30 a.m., the War Cabinet met again, but this time Halifax did not try to change the minds of Winston or other
ministers.
He said he had received a telegram from the British ambassador in Rome, who said that Italy was definitely going
to enter the war soon, but it was not certain when.
The ambassador had told the Italian government that although
Britain did not want war with Italy, "if Italy made war, war would be met with war", and Mussolini alone would be
responsible for this.
The War Cabinet was also told about the latest news from Dunkirk, which was not good. 40,000 British troops had
arrived in England from France, but the military leaders did not
think that it was possible to save many more.
The Luftwaffe had bombed Dunkirk and destroyed the harbour and several ships so that now other ships could not enter
the harbour.
Lord Gort, the man in charge of the BEF, had sent a telegram asking what the British government wanted him to do if all
hope was lost and he could no longer contact them.
Winston said he had ordered Lord Gort to continue attacking the German army for as long as possible to allow the British
troops more time to escape from Dunkirk.
But Halifax was not happy with this and said that, if Lord Gort wanted to retreat to save the lives of his own men,
they should allow him to do this.
Clement Attlee, the Labour leader, said that Lord Gort was an experienced soldier who could judge the situation for
himself.
So if the War Cabinet could no longer contact him, they
should allow him to make his own decisions.
Winston and the other members of the War Cabinet agreed, and
after the meeting, Winston sent a telegram to Lord Gort.
As soon as Winston came out of the meeting, he contacted his closest colleagues to say that it was very important to
evacuate French troops as well as British from Dunkirk.
That evening, after dinner with General Ironside and Clemmie at Admiralty House, he sent a telegram to Reynaud repeating
that he wanted to evacuate as many French troops as
possible.
He said that, after the troops had arrived back in Britain, and the people of Britain had prepared themselves for a
possible attack, they could start building up a new BEF.
As Winston was going to bed, one of the officers working for the War Cabinet asked for four days' holiday so he could go
to Dunkirk and help evacuate the troops.
Winston immediately agreed and said, "I wish I were going
with you myself."
The next day, there was fog at Dunkirk, so the Luftwaffe
could not continue bombing the harbour, but
now it was only possible for small boats to enter it.
Two men arrived in London to inform Winston about the latest
situation.
He was very surprised to see that one of them was a young relative of his, John Spencer- Churchill, who was very wet
and wearing his full battle uniform.
He told Winston that the greatest need was for "small boats to get the troops off the beaches and out to the bigger
ships".
The other man added that Lord Gort also believed that small
boats could save the troops.
At the next meeting of the War Cabinet, at 5.30 p.m., Winston announced that 100,000 British soldiers had arrived
back on the English coast, but the fog was causing problems and
making it very difficult to evacuate more troops.
Meanwhile, General Weygand, who was fighting with the French army near the River Somme, had asked if Britain could send
more soldiers to help him.
Winston replied that Britain would send help as soon as it
could, but at the moment this was not possible.
Winston always wanted to see things for himself so he could
learn what was happening.
So he suggested that, the next day, he could go to Paris with the aim of explaining Britain's situation to Reynaud
and the French leaders.
He very much wanted French troops to be evacuated from Dunkirk with the BEE At 8.30 a.m. on the morning of 31st
May, Winston left London, together with General Ismay and the
Labour leader Clement Attlee.
As their plane flew over France, they saw crowds of ordinary people trying to move away from the line of fighting as
quickly as possible.
At the meeting, Winston informed the French leaders that
165,000 men had now arrived in England.
But Reynaud said that, although 150,000 of the 220,000 British troops in Holland, Belgium and France had been
evacuated, only 15,000 of the 200,000 French troops had been
evacuated.
He said that if more French troops were not able to escape,
French public opinion could turn against the British.
Winston replied that the British government had ordered the BEF to evacuate, and he had come to France to make sure the
French troops had received the same orders.
Reynaud thanked the British military forces for the
wonderful job they had done in evacuating the troops in
Dunkirk.
However, he was certain that Germany would soon attack the French troops in the south and asked if the British could
send fighter planes to protect them, together with soldiers.
Winston said this would not be possible until he knew how
many British troops had arrived safely back in Britain.
He tried to make Reynaud feel stronger and more positive
about the situation.
He said that the British people were not afraid of an attack by the Germans, and were ready to fight them in every small
village, but to do this, they needed soldiers to help them.
Winston said it was very important for Britain and France to work closely together if they were going to succeed in
beating the enemy, and even if one country was beaten, the
other had to continue fighting.
Clement Attlee supported Winston and said he agreed with
everything he had said.
Attlee added that the British people now realized the danger and that, if the Germans won the war, "everything they had
built up would be destroyed" because "the Germans killed
not only men, but ideas".
After the meeting, the British ambassador to France sent a message to Halifax saying that Winston's visit to France had
been extremely valuable.
Other people in London heard about the meeting, too, and
were happy it had gone well.
At the meeting of the War Cabinet the next day, 1st June, Winston announced that almost 225,000 troops had now arrived
in Britain from Dunkirk.
Halifax met with the American ambassador, Joseph Kennedy, who said that the American government thought that the
British military forces had done a great job in evacuating the
troops, and it was a good chance for Winston to ask
President Roosevelt again for warships to help Britain.
However, bad news came - the fog had disappeared at Dunkirk, so the Luftwaffe were able to start bombing the harbour
again.
Seventeen ships were destroyed, including four valuable
warships, and ten more ships were badly hit.
But Winston said that the ships must continue to evacuate
the troops for as long as possible.
Some British people and MPs were beginning to lose hope because the newspapers were reporting on Hitler's plans to
invade Britain.
Also, Britain had lost a lot of its equipment, the French had lost 80 percent of their army, and many French people
felt that Britain had not supported France enough.
So Duff Cooper, Minister of Information, spoke on national radio to give the British people the good news that 276,030
troops had arrived safely in England.
By noon on 3rd June, the news was even better, as 292,380
troops had come back.
It was time for Winston to speak to Parliament and the
British people again, but he had not finished writing his
speech.
He knew that it was very important to speak from his heart and encourage the British people to stay positive about the
war, even when there was bad news.
When writing, Winston would try several words and groups of
words before choosing which were the best.
He would read the speech again and again, and make changes with a red pencil, then practise it while walking around the
room, speaking sometimes softly and sometimes loudly At
3.40 p.m. on 4th June 1940, Winston made one of the best and
most famous speeches of his life.
He started by describing the situation in France over the past weeks and was able to give the good news that now
330,000 troops had arrived safely home.
Winston spoke about the terrible crimes of the Nazis and the brave actions of those who had lost their lives defending
Dunkirk.
He said that Hitler was probably planning to invade Britain, but he also reminded people that Napoleon and other
dictators over the centuries had never succeeded in this.
He said that he was very confident that the British people would again prove themselves "able to defend our island
home" and would never surrender to a dictator.
This was what everyone in Parliament and the British
government had decided, together with the British people.
Britain and France would help each other to defend their countries to the end, and although much of Europe had fallen
to the Nazis, Britain would never lose heart.
"We shall go on to the end. We shall fight in France, we shall fight on the seas and oceans, we shall fight... in the
air, we shall defend our island... we shall fight on the
beaches... we shall fight in the fields and in the streets,
we shall fight in the hills; we shall never surrender..."
In this speech, Winston touched the hearts and minds of
Parliament and the British public.
By using the word "we" so many times, he gave the British people the strong message they needed - that they would not
be alone, but that he would be with them, at their side,
every step of the way, ready to fight to the death if
necessary.
Afterwards, Winston said that the people of Britain had the heart of a lion, and all he had done was to give them a
voice.
When he made this speech, Winston had been prime minister for only twenty-five days, and during that time, he had met
some difficult problems, not only because of the war but also
from some of his own political colleagues.
But now everyone was ready to support him.
Although the future was not certain, at that moment, in
their darkest hour, he brought hope to the people of Britain.