The Tell-Tale Heart
True!
Nervous, very, very dreadfully nervous I had
been and am; but why will you say that I am
mad?
The disease had sharpened my senses, not destroyed,
not dulled them.
Above all was the sense of hearing acute.
I heard all things in the heaven and in the
earth.
I heard many things in hell.
How then am I mad?
Hearken!
And observe how healthily, how calmly, I can
tell you the whole story.
It is impossible to say how first the idea
entered my brain, but, once conceived, it
haunted me day and night.
Object there was none.
Passion there was none.
I loved the old man.
He had never wronged me.
He had never given me insult.
For his gold I had no desire.
I think it was his eye!
Yes, it was this!
One of his eyes resembled that of a vulture
- a pale blue eye with a film over it.
Whenever it fell upon me my blood ran cold,
and so by degrees, very gradually, I made
up my mind to take the life of the old man,
and thus rid myself of the eye for ever.
Now this is the point.
You fancy me mad.
Madmen know nothing.
But you should have seen me.
You should have seen how wisely I proceeded
- with what caution - with what foresight,
with what dissimulation, I went to work!
I was never kinder to the old man than during
the whole week before I killed him.
And every night about midnight I turned the
latch of his door and opened it oh, so gently!
And then, when I had made an opening sufficient
for my head, I put in a dark lantern all closed,
closed so that no light shone out, and then
I thrust in my head.
Oh, you would have laughed to see how cunningly
I thrust it in!
I moved it slowly, very, very slowly, so that
I might not disturb the old man's sleep.
It took me an hour to place my whole head
within the opening so far that I could see
him as he lay upon his bed.
Ha!
Would a madman have been so wise as this?
And then when my head was well in the room
I undid the lantern cautiously - oh, so cautiously
- cautiously (for the hinges creaked), I undid
it just so much that a single thin ray fell
upon the vulture eye.
And this I did for seven long nights, every
night just at midnight, but I found the eye
always closed, and so it was impossible to
do the work, for it was not the old man who
vexed me but his Evil Eye.
And every morning, when the day broke, I went
boldly into the chamber and spoke courageously
to him, calling him by name in a hearty tone,
and inquiring how he had passed the night.
So you see he would have been a very profound
old man, indeed , to suspect that every night,
just at twelve, I looked in upon him while
he slept.
Upon the eighth night I was more than usually
cautious in opening the door.
A watch's minute hand moves more quickly than
did mine.
Never before that night had I felt the extent
of my own powers, of my sagacity.
I could scarcely contain my feelings of triumph.
To think that there I was opening the door
little by little, and he not even to dream
of my secret deeds or thoughts.
I fairly chuckled at the idea, and perhaps
he heard me, for he moved on the bed suddenly
as if startled.
Now you may think that I drew back - but no.
His room was as black as pitch with the thick
darkness (for the shutters were close fastened
through fear of robbers), and so I knew that
he could not see the opening of the door,
and I kept pushing it on steadily, steadily.
I had my head in, and was about to open the
lantern, when my thumb slipped upon the tin
fastening , and the old man sprang up in the
bed, crying out, "Who's there?"
I kept quite still and said nothing.
For a whole hour I did not move a muscle,
and in the meantime I did not hear him lie
down.
He was still sitting up in the bed, listening;
just as I have done night after night hearkening
to the death watches in the wall.
Presently, I heard a slight groan, and I knew
it was the groan of mortal terror.
It was not a groan of pain or of grief - oh,
no!
It was the low stifled sound that arises from
the bottom of the soul when overcharged with
awe.
I knew the sound well.
Many a night, just at midnight, when all the
world slept, it has welled up from my own
bosom, deepening, with its dreadful echo,
the terrors that distracted me.
I say I knew it well.
I knew what the old man felt, and pitied him
although I chuckled at heart.
I knew that he had been lying awake ever since
the first slight noise when he had turned
in the bed.
His fears had been ever since growing upon
him.
He had been trying to fancy them causeless,
but could not.
He had been saying to himself, "It is nothing
but the wind in the chimney, it is only a
mouse crossing the floor," or, "It is merely
a cricket which has made a single chirp."
Yes he has been trying to comfort himself
with these suppositions ; but he had found
all in vain.
ALL IN VAIN, because Death in approaching
him had stalked with his black shadow before
him and enveloped the victim.
And it was the mournful influence of the unperceived
shadow that caused him to feel, although he
neither saw nor heard, to feel the presence
of my head within the room.
When I had waited a long time very patiently
without hearing him lie down, I resolved to
open a little - a very, very little crevice
in the lantern.
So I opened it - you cannot imagine how stealthily,
stealthily - until at length a single dim
ray like the thread of the spider shot out
from the crevice and fell upon the vulture
eye.
It was open, wide, wide open, and I grew furious
as I gazed upon it.
I saw it with perfect distinctness - all a
dull blue with a hideous veil over it that
chilled the very marrow in my bones, but I
could see nothing else of the old man's face
or person, for I had directed the ray as if
by instinct precisely upon the damned spot.
And now have I not told you that what you
mistake for madness is but over-acuteness
of the senses?
Now, I say, there came to my ears a low, dull,
quick sound, such as a watch makes when enveloped
in cotton.
I knew that sound well too.
It was the beating of the old man's heart.
It increased my fury as the beating of a drum
stimulates the soldier into courage.
But even yet I refrained and kept still.
I scarcely breathed.
I held the lantern motionless.
I tried how steadily I could maintain the
ray upon the eye.
Meantime the hellish tattoo of the heart increased.
It grew quicker and quicker, and louder and
louder, every instant.
The old man's terror must have been extreme!
It grew louder, I say, louder every moment!
- do you mark me well?
I have told you that I am nervous: so I am.
And now at the dead hour of the night, amid
the dreadful silence of that old house, so
strange a noise as this excited me to uncontrollable
terror.
Yet, for some minutes longer I refrained and
stood still.
But the beating grew louder, louder!
I thought the heart must burst.
And now a new anxiety seized me - the sound
would be heard by a neighbour!
The old man's hour had come!
With a loud yell, I threw open the lantern
and leaped into the room.
He shrieked once - once only.
In an instant I dragged him to the floor,
and pulled the heavy bed over him.
I then smiled gaily, to find the deed so far
done.
But for many minutes the heart beat on with
a muffled sound.
This, however, did not vex me; it would not
be heard through the wall.
At length it ceased.
The old man was dead.
I removed the bed and examined the corpse.
Yes, he was stone, stone dead.
I placed my hand upon the heart and held it
there many minutes.
There was no pulsation.
He was stone dead.
His eye would trouble me no more.
If still you think me mad, you will think
so no longer when I describe the wise precautions
I took for the concealment of the body.
The night waned, and I worked hastily, but
in silence.
I took up three planks from the flooring of
the chamber, and deposited all between the
scantlings.
I then replaced the boards so cleverly so
cunningly, that no human eye - not even his
- could have detected anything wrong.
There was nothing to wash out - no stain of
any kind - no blood-spot whatever.
I had been too wary for that.
When I had made an end of these labours, it
was four o'clock - still dark as midnight.
As the bell sounded the hour, there came a
knocking at the street door.
I went down to open it with a light heart,
- for what had I now to fear?
There entered three men, who introduced themselves,
with perfect suavity, as officers of the police.
A shriek had been heard by a neighbour during
the night; suspicion of foul play had been
aroused; information had been lodged at the
police office, and they (the officers) had
been deputed to search the premises.
I smiled, - for what had I to fear?
I bade the gentlemen welcome.
The shriek, I said, was my own in a dream.
The old man, I mentioned, was absent in the
country.
I took my visitors all over the house.
I bade them search - search well.
I led them, at length, to his chamber.
I showed them his treasures, secure, undisturbed.
In the enthusiasm of my confidence, I brought
chairs into the room, and desired them here
to rest from their fatigues, while I myself,
in the wild audacity of my perfect triumph,
placed my own seat upon the very spot beneath
which reposed the corpse of the victim.
The officers were satisfied.
My MANNER had convinced them.
I was singularly at ease.
They sat and while I answered cheerily, they
chatted of familiar things.
But, ere long, I felt myself getting pale
and wished them gone.
My head ached, and I fancied a ringing in
my ears; but still they sat, and still chatted.
The ringing became more distinct: I talked
more freely to get rid of the feeling: but
it continued and gained definitiveness - until,
at length, I found that the noise was NOT
within my ears.
No doubt I now grew VERY pale; but I talked
more fluently, and with a heightened voice.
Yet the sound increased - and what could I
do?
It was A LOW, DULL, QUICK SOUND - MUCH SUCH
A SOUND AS A WATCH MAKES WHEN ENVELOPED IN
COTTON.
I gasped for breath, and yet the officers
heard it not.
I talked more quickly, more vehemently but
the noise steadily increased.
I arose and argued about trifles, in a high
key and with violent gesticulations; but the
noise steadily increased.
Why WOULD they not be gone?
I paced the floor to and fro with heavy strides,
as if excited to fury by the observations
of the men, but the noise steadily increased.
O God!
What COULD I do?
I foamed - I raved - I swore!
I swung the chair upon which I had been sitting,
and grated it upon the boards, but the noise
arose over all and continually increased.
It grew louder - louder - louder!
And still the men chatted pleasantly, and
smiled.
Was it possible they heard not?
Almighty God!
- No, no?
They heard!
- They suspected!
- They KNEW!
- They were making a mockery of my horror!
- This I thought, and this I think.
But anything was better than this agony!
Anything was more tolerable than this derision!
I could bear those hypocritical smiles no
longer!
I felt that I must scream or die!
- And now - again - hark!
Louder!
LOUDER!
-
"Villains!"
I shrieked, "Dissemble no more!
I admit the deed!
- tear up the planks!
- Here, here!
- it is the beating of his hideous heart!"
- THE END -