FEVER DREAM
They put him between fresh, clean, laundered
sheets and there was always a newly squeezed
glass of thick orange juice on the table under
the dim pink lamp.
All Charles had to do was call and Mom or
Dad would stick their heads into his room
to see how sick he was.
The acoustics of the room were fine; you could
hear the toilet gargling its porcelain throat
of mornings, you could hear rain tap the roof
or sly mice run in the secret walls or the
canary singing in its cage downstairs.
If you were very alert, sickness wasn't too
bad.
He was thirteen, Charles was.
It was mid-September, with the land beginning
to burn with autumn.
He lay in the bed for three days before the
terror overcame him.
His hand began to change.
His right hand.
He looked at it and it was hot and sweating
there on the counterpane alone.
It fluttered, it moved a bit.
Then it lay there, changing color.
That afternoon the doctor came again and tapped
his thin chest like a little drum.
"How are you?" asked the doctor, smiling.
"I know, don't tell me: 'My cold is fine,
Doctor, but I feel awful!'
Ha!"
He laughed at his own oft-repeated joke.
Charles lay there and for him that terrible
and ancient jest was becoming a reality.
The joke fixed itself in his mind.
His mind touched and drew away from it in
a pale terror.
The doctor did not know how cruel he was with
his jokes!
"Doctor," whispered Charles, lying flat and
colorless.
"My hand, it doesn't belong to me any more.
This morning it changed into something else.
I want you to change it back, Doctor, Doctor!"
The doctor showed his teeth and patted his
hand.
"It looks fine to me, son.
You just had a little fever dream."
"But it changed, Doctor, oh, Doctor," cried
Charles, pitifully holding up his pale wild
hand.
"It did!"
The doctor winked.
"I'll give you a pink pill for that."
He popped a tablet onto Charles' tongue.
"Swallow!"
"Will it make my hand change back and become
me, again?"
"Yes, yes."
The house was silent when the doctor drove
off down the road in his car under the quiet,
blue September sky.
A clock ticked far below in the kitchen world.
Charles lay looking at his hand.
It did not change back.
It was still something else.
The wind blew outside.
Leaves fell against the cool window.
At four o'clock his other hand changed.
It seemed almost to become a fever.
It pulsed and shifted, cell by cell.
It beat like a warm heart.
The fingernails turned blue and then red.
It took about an hour for it to change and
when it was finished, it looked just like
any ordinary hand.
But it was not ordinary.
It no longer was him any more.
He lay in a fascinated horror and then fell
into an exhausted sleep.
Mother brought the soup up at six.
He wouldn't touch it "I haven't any hands,"
he said, eyes shut.
"Your hands are perfectly good," said Mother.
"No," he wailed.
"My hands are gone.
I feel like I have stumps.
Oh, Mama, Mama, hold me, hold me, I'm scared!"
She had to feed him herself.
"Mama," he said, "get the doctor, please,
again.
I'm so sick."
"The doctor'll be here tonight at eight,"
she said, and went out.
At seven, with night dark and close around
the house, Charles was sitting up in bed when
he felt the thing happening to first one leg
and then the other.
"Mama!
Come quick!" he screamed.
But when Mama came the thing was no longer
happening.
When she went downstairs, he simply lay without
fighting as his legs beat and beat, grew warm,
red-hot, and the room filled with the warmth
of his feverish change.
The glow crept up from his toes to his ankles
and then to his knees.
"May I come in?"
The doctor smiled in the doorway.
"Doctor!"
cried Charles.
"Hurry, take off my blankets!"
The doctor lifted the blankets tolerantly.
"There you are.
Whole and healthy.
Sweating, though.
A little fever.
I told you not to move around, bad boy."
He pinched the moist pink cheek.
"Did the pills help?
Did your hand change back?"
"No, no, now it's my other hand and my legs!"
"Well, well, I'll have to give you three more
pills, one for each limb, eh, my little peach?"
laughed the doctor.
"Will they help me?
Please, please.
What've I got?
"
"A mild case of scarlet fever, complicated
by a slight cold."
"Is it a germ that lives and has more little
germs in me?"
"Yes."
"Are you sure it's scarlet fever?
You haven't taken any tests!"
"I guess I know a certain fever when I see
one," said the doctor, checking the boy's
pulse with cool authority.
Charles lay there, not speaking until the
doctor was crisply packing his black kit.
Then in the silent room, the boy's voice made
a small, weak pattern, his eyes alight with
remembrance.
"I read a book once.
About petrified trees, wood turning to stone.
About how trees fell and rotted and minerals
got in and built up and they look just like
trees, but they're not, they're stone."
He stopped.
In the quiet warm room his breathing sounded.
"Well?" asked the doctor.
"I've been thinking," said Charles after a
time.
"Do germs ever get big?
I mean, in biology class they told us about
one-celled animals, amoebas and things, and
how millions of years ago they got together
until there was a bunch and they made the
first body.
And more and more cells got together and got
bigger and then finally maybe there was a
fish and finally here we are, and all we are
is a bunch of cells that decided to get together,
to help each other out.
Isn't that right?"
Charles wet his feverish lips.
"What's all this about?"
The doctor bent over him.
"I've got to tell you this.
Doctor, oh, I've got to!" he cried.
"What would happen, oh just pretend, please
pretend, that just like in the old days, a
lot of microbes got together and wanted to
make a bunch, and reproduced and made more-"
His white hands were on his chest now, crawling
toward his throat.
"And they decided to take over a person!"
cried Charles.
"Take over a person?"
"Yes, become a person.
Me, my hands, my feet!
What if a disease somehow knew how to kill
a person and yet live after him?"
He screamed.
The hands were on his neck.
The doctor moved forward, shouting.
At nine o'clock the doctor was escorted out
to his car by the mother and father, who handed
him his bag.
They conversed in the cool night wind for
a few minutes.
"Just be sure his hands are kept strapped
to his legs," said the doctor.
"I don't want him hurting himself."
"Will he be all right, Doctor?"
The mother held to his arm a moment.
He patted her shoulder.
"Haven't I been your family physician for
thirty years?
It's the fever.
He imagines things."
"But those bruises on his throat, he almost
choked himself."
"Just you keep him strapped; he'll be all
right in the morning."
The car moved off down the dark September
road.
At three in the morning, Charles was still
awake in his small black room.
The bed was damp under his head and his back.
He was very warm.
Now he no longer had any arms or legs, and
his body was beginning to change.
He did not move on the bed, but looked at
the vast blank ceiling space with insane concentration.
For a while he had screamed and thrashed,
but now he was weak and hoarse from it, and
his mother had gotten up a number of times
to soothe his brow with a wet towel.
Now he was silent, his hands strapped to his
legs.
He felt the walls of his body change, the
organs shift, the lungs catch fire like burning
bellows of pink alcohol.
The room was lighted up as with the flickerings
of a hearth.
Now he had no body.
It was all gone.
It was under him, but it was filled with a
vast pulse of some burning, lethargic drug.
It was as if a guillotine had neatly lopped
off his head, and his head lay shining on
a midnight pillow while the body, below, still
alive, belonged to somebody else.
The disease had eaten his body and from the
eating had reproduced itself in feverish duplicate.
There were the little hand hairs and the fingernails
and the scars and the toenails and the tiny
mole on his right hip, all done again in perfect
fashion.
I am dead, he thought.
I've been killed, and yet I live.
My body is dead, it is all disease and nobody
will know.
I will walk around and it will not be me,
it will be something else.
It will be something all bad, all evil, so
big and so evil it's hard to understand or
think about.
Something that will buy shoes and drink water
and get married some day maybe and do more
evil in the world than has ever been done.
Now the warmth was stealing up his neck, into
his cheeks, like a hot wine.
His lips burned, his eyelids, like leaves,
caught fire.
His nostrils breathed out blue flame, faintly,
faintly.
This will be all, he thought.
It'll take my head and my brain and fix each
eye and every tooth and all the marks in my
brain, and every hair and every wrinkle in
my ears, and there'll be nothing left of me.
He felt his brain fill with a boiling mercury.
He felt his left eye clench in upon itself
and, like a snail, withdraw, shift.
He was blind in his left eye.
It no longer belonged to him.
It was enemy territory.
His tongue was gone, cut out.
His left cheek was numbed, lost.
His left ear stopped hearing.
It belonged to someone else now.
This thing that was being born, this mineral
thing replacing the wooden log, this disease
replacing healthy animal cell.
He tried to scream and he was able to scream
loud and high and sharply in the room, just
as his brain flooded down, his right eye and
right ear were cut out, he was blind and deaf,
all fire, all terror, all panic, all death.
His scream stopped before his mother ran through
the door to his side.
It was a good, clear morning, with a brisk
wind that helped carry the doctor up the path
before the house.
In the window above, the boy stood, fully
dressed.
He did not wave when the doctor waved and
called, "What's this?
Up?
My God!"
The doctor almost ran upstairs.
He came gasping into the bedroom.
"What are you doing out of bed?" he demanded
of the boy.
He tapped his thin chest, took his pulse and
temperature.
"Absolutely amazing!
Normal.
Normal, by God!"
"I shall never be sick again in my life,"
declared the boy, quietly, standing there,
looking out the wide window.
"Never."
"I hope not.
Why, you're looking fine, Charles."
"Doctor?"
"Yes, Charles?"
"Can I go to school now?" asked Charles.
"Tomorrow will be time enough.
You sound positively eager."
"I am.
I like school.
All the kids.
I want to play with them and wrestle with
them, and spit on them and play with the girls'
pigtails and shake the teacher's hand, and
rub my hands on all the cloaks in the cloakroom,
and I want to grow up and travel and shake
hands with people all over the world, and
be married and have lots of children, and
go to libraries and handle books and - all
of that I want to!" said the boy, looking
off into the September morning.
"What's the name you called me?"
"What?"
The doctor puzzled.
"I called you nothing but Charles."
"It's better than no name at all, I guess."
The boy shrugged.
"I'm glad you want to go back to school,"
said the doctor.
"I really anticipate it," smiled the boy.
"Thank you for your help, Doctor.
Shake hands."
"Glad to."
They shook hands gravely, and the clear wind
blew through the open window.
They shook hands for almost a minute, the
boy smiling up at the old man and thanking
him.
Then, laughing, the boy raced the doctor downstairs
and out to his car.
His mother and father followed for the happy
farewell.
"Fit as a fiddle!" said the doctor.
"Incredible!"
"And strong," said the father.
"He got out of his straps himself during the
night.
Didn't you, Charles?"
"Did I?" said the boy.
"You did!
How?"
"Oh," the boy said, "that was a long time
ago."
"A long time ago!"
They all laughed, and while they were laughing,
the quiet boy moved his bare foot on the sidewalk
and merely touched, brushed against a number
of red ants that was scurrying about on the
sidewalk.
Secretly, his eyes shining, while his parents
chatted with the old man, he saw the ants
hesitate, quiver, and lie still on the cement.
He sensed they were cold now.
"Good-by!"
The doctor drove away, waving.
The boy walked ahead of his parents.
As he walked he looked away toward the town
and began to hum "School Days" under his breath.
"It's good to have him well again," said the
father.
"Listen to him.
He's so looking forward to school!"
The boy turned quietly.
He gave each of his parents a crushing hug.
He kissed them both several times.
Then without a word he bounded up the steps
into the house.
In the parlor, before the others entered,
he quickly opened the bird cage, thrust his
hand in, and petted the yellow canary, once.
Then he shut the cage door, stood back, and
waited.
- THE END -