Marcia met Howard Collins at church. Marcia
was thirty-five years old, Howard was forty-one.
Howard lived with his mother in a small house
on the south side of the town. Marcia lived
with her sister and father in an apartment,
three streets away.
Marcia did not work. Her father, George Grant,
was ill and never left the apartment. He stayed
in bed most of the time and always needed
somebody with him. So Marcia stayed at home
with her father, and only went out when her
sister Karin was in the house.
The two sisters were very different. Marcia
was short with a small round face and short
black hair. Karin was ten years younger. She
was tall, had long brown hair, and good legs,
and a suntan all through the summer. People
often said to Marcia, 'Your sister is very
beautiful.' There were always lots of men
ready to take Karin out to dinner or to the
cinema. But Marcia stayed at home.
Karin worked in a shop in the town. When she
was at home, she liked to sit up on the roof
garden of their apartment building.
It was one Sunday in May when Marcia came
home with Howard the first time. She took
him to see her father. George Grant was in
bed. He had grey hair and a grey face. Sometimes
he read a book, but mostly he just sat in
bed and watched television.
'This is Howard, father,' Marcia said. 'He
works at the hospital, and we met at church.
I told you about him last week. Do you remember?'
'No,' her father said. And he turned his face
away, back to his television. He was not interested
in new people or his daughters' friends.
Just then, Karin came into the room. She wore
a white bikini and white shoes. She smiled
at Howard.
'So you're Howard,' she said. 'My big sister
has got a boyfriend at last!'
Howard's face went red and he looked down
at his feet.
Karin laughed. 'Come on up to the roof garden
and have some wine. The sun is wonderful this
morning.'
'Oh, I...' Howard began.
Marcia looked angrily at her sister. But then
she said, 'Yes, I must get father a drink.
See you in a minute, Howard. Go up to the
roof and talk to Karin.'
The sun was hot on the roof and Howard took
off his coat. He looked around. There were
three chairs, a sun umbrella, a sunbed, and
a table with three glasses and a bottle of
wine on it. There were tiles on the floor,
and next to the little wall around the edge
of the roof, there were some flowers in boxes.
This was the 'garden'.
'Very nice,' said Howard.
Karin smiled at him.
'We don't see many good-looking men up here,'
she said. 'Sit down and have a drink.'
Howard's face went red again. He gave a shy
little laugh. 'Oh, er... thank you,' he said.
He tried not to look at Karin's long suntanned
legs, but it was not easy.
'I come up here all the time when it's sunny,'
Karin said. She began to put suntan oil on
her arms and legs.
Howard watched.
Then Marcia arrived, and the three of them
sat in the sun and drank wine. Marcia looked
at Howard with love in her eyes. She did not
look at Karin.
Karin watched them. Her eyes went from her
sister, to Howard, and back again to her sister.
She smiled.
It was not a nice smile.
Every Sunday morning after that, Marcia brought
Howard home for a glass of wine after church.
Howard stopped his car in the street outside
the apartment building, and Marcia said, 'Sound
the horn, Howard. Tell Karin we're here, then
she can get the wine ready.'
So Howard gave three little toots on his car
horn. On sunny days, Karin always came to
the wall at the edge of the roof, and looked
over to wave at them. Then she went to get
the wine.
She always wore her bikini or a very short
skirt. Marcia never wore short skirts or a
bikini.
'My legs are too fat for bikinis,' she told
Howard. 'Your legs are... very nice,' he said
shyly.
One day in June Karin asked Howard, 'What
time do you finish work, Howard?'
'About six o'clock,' he said.
'Could you bring me home after work?' Karin
said. 'My shop's very near the hospital - you
drive right past it. And you only live three
streets away from us.'
'There's a very good bus,' said Marcia quickly.
'It stops outside our building.'
'But the bus is so slow!' Karin said. 'Please,
Howard!'
Howard looked from one sister to the other.
'Oh, well... er, yes, all right then,' he
said.
'Thank you!' Karin said, and gave him a quick
kiss.
So every evening Howard drove Karin home.
On the first Friday, they were an hour late.
When they arrived, Marcia was at the door
of the apartment building.
'What happened?' she asked. 'Why are you so
late?'
'There was an accident,' Karin said. 'Three
cars, all across the road - on that hill by
the cinema, you know. We couldn't get past,
we couldn't go back. There were so many cars!
Nobody could move!'
Howard said nothing.
It was a long, hot summer that year. Marcia
went to church every Sunday morning, and Karin
stayed at home with their father. When it
was sunny - and it often was - Karin went
up to her sunbed on the roof.
When Marcia went up to the roof garden, she
always sat under the umbrella. But Karin put
on lots of suntan oil and sat in the sun in
her bikini.
'The hot sun's not good for your body,' Marcia
said. Karin laughed. 'Howard likes my body.'
'No, he doesn't!' Marcia said angrily.
'Oh, he does!' Karin said. 'He's very shy
with women, but he always looks at my body
very carefully. He does it all the time. Perhaps
he wants me to take off-'
'Stop it, Karin!' Marcia said. 'Don't say
those things!' Karin laughed. 'What's the
matter, big sister? Are you afraid I'm going
to take him from you?'
Marcia did not answer.
The next Sunday, Howard phoned Marcia early
in the morning.
'I - I don't feel very well,' he said. 'I'm
not going to church today.'
'My love, I'm sorry,' Marcia said. 'Can I
phone you when I get home?'
'Yes, of course,' he said.
'I can't phone before one o'clock,' Marcia
said. 'I'm going to be late back because there's
a meeting after church. Something about Africa,
I think.'
'Oh yes, I remember,' Howard said.
But Marcia was wrong. There was no meeting
after church that morning. It was the next
Sunday. So she left church at the usual time
and arrived home at a quarter to twelve.
First, she went in to see her father, but
he was asleep. Then she phoned Howard, but
there was no answer.
'Perhaps he's sleeping,' she thought. 'And
his mother doesn't want to answer the phone.'
She went to her room and put on a long summer
skirt. Then she went up to the roof garden.
She put her hand on the door to the roof...
and stopped. The door was half open and she
could hear voices. There was someone with
Karin.
A man. Howard. Howard? Marcia listened.
'I feel bad about this,' Howard said. 'We
must tell Marcia soon, Karin.'
'No!' Karin said quickly. She gave a little
laugh. 'It's our secret, Howard. Only for
a little longer. All right?'
'I - I don't like...' he began.
'But you do love me, Howard,' Karin said.
'Not Marcia? Say you love me. Please!'
Marcia suddenly felt cold.
'You... you know I do,' Howard answered. 'But-'
Karin kissed him. 'It's our little secret.
Oh, is your car outside, my love? We don't
want Marcia to see it.'
'I didn't bring my car,' Howard said. 'I walked
here.'
'Good,' Karin said. 'But it's getting late.
You must go, before she comes home.'
They kissed again.
'See you tomorrow, usual time, usual place,'
said Karin. 'Now, go!'
Marcia moved quickly and quietly away from
the roof door, and ran to her bedroom. She
did not want Howard or Karin to see her.
She heard their voices. Then the front door
of the apartment opened and closed. Howard
was gone.
Marcia sat on her bed for an hour. 'Why, why,
why?' she thought. 'Why does she do it? I
stay at home with an old man all the time.
I can't go out to work, I can't make new friends,
I can't meet new people. I go shopping once
a week and I go to church once a week. That's
all. And then I met Howard. When he said "I
love you", I was so happy. And now...?'
Karin had everything. Good looks, a job, friends.
She was young, she was beautiful, she could
have any man. So why Howard? Why, why, why?
'It's not because she wants him,' Marcia thought.
'It's because I love him. It's because she
doesn't want me to be happy.'
But you do love me, Howard. Not Marcia?
You know I do.
Was it true? Did Howard love Karin and not
her? No! He saw only the beautiful, suntanned
body. He didn't know her.
'She's not going to have him...' Marcia thought.
Every evening that week, Howard drove Karin
home after work. And every evening they got
later and later.
The next Sunday, Marcia didn't go to church.
'I've got a bad head,' she told Karin. 'I
just phoned Howard and told him, and he's
coming here after church as usual. I'm going
back to sleep for an hour or two.' And she
went into her bedroom and shut the door.
Later in the morning, when Karin was with
their father, Marcia went up to the roof garden.
Karin's bottle of suntan oil was on the table,
and Marcia smiled.
When Karin came up to the roof, Marcia was
in her chair under the umbrella with a book
in her hand.
'Oh, is your head better?' Karin asked.
'Yes, thanks,' Marcia said.
Karin wore her bikini, a new yellow one. She
opened her bottle of suntan oil.
'Oh, there's not much here,' she said. 'I
must get some more.' She began to put some
oil on her legs.
Twenty minutes later, Howard stopped his car
in the street below. Up on the roof, Karin
and Marcia heard the usual three little toots
on his car horn.
'He's here,' Karin said excitedly. 'Your man's
here, big sister!' And she laughed.
Yes, Marcia thought. My man, not yours, Karin.
Karin jumped up from her sunbed. She ran to
the wall at the edge of the roof to look down
and wave to Howard. She had no shoes on, and
at the wall, her feet suddenly slipped away
from under her.
'Aaagh!' she cried.
She fell forward, and put out her hands to
grab the wall. But the top of the wall was
slippery too. Her hands could not hold it,
and slipped away, off the wall, over the edge.
And her body went on too, over the edge of
the wall, and down...
Down... down... down...
Before she hit the ground, she knew.
Slippery... suntan oil... Marcia...
- THE END -