CHAPTER ONE
Jean Valjean
One evening in October 1815,
an hour before sunset, a man with a long beard and
dusty, torn clothes walked into the town of Digne.
He was in his late forties, of medium
height, broad-shouldered and strong.
A leather cap half-hid his face, which
was sunburnt and shining with sweat.
His rough yellow shirt was
unbuttoned, revealing a hairy chest.
On his back was a heavy soldier's bag,
and in his hand was a large wooden stick.
The townspeople, who had never seen him before,
watched with interest as he
stopped for water at a fountain.
Children followed him to the marketplace, where
he stopped for more water at another fountain.
He then crossed the square towards an
inn, and entered by the kitchen door.
The innkeeper, who was also the cook,
was busy with his pots and pans,
preparing a meal for a group of travellers
who were laughing and joking in the next room.
'What can I do for you, Monsieur?'
he asked without looking up.
'A meal and a bed,' said the stranger.
'Of course.'
The innkeeper turned to look at him.
Then, seeing the visitors rough appearance,
he added, 'If you can pay for it.'
'I have money.'
The stranger produced an old
leather purse from his jacket.
'Then you're welcome,' the innkeeper said.
The stranger smiled with relief
and sat down by the fire.
He did not see a young boy run out with a
note that the innkeeper had quickly written.
He did not see the boy return a short time
later and whisper something to the innkeeper.
'When will the meal be ready?' the stranger asked.
'I'm sorry, Monsieur,' the innkeeper said.
'You can't stay here.
I've got no free rooms.'
'Then put me in a stable.
All I need is a quiet corner somewhere.
After dinner
'You can't eat here either,'
the innkeeper interrupted.
'I haven't enough food.'
'What about all that food in the pots?'
The innkeeper approached and, bending towards
the man, said in a fierce whisper, 'Get out.
I know who you are.
Your name is Jean Valjean.
You've just been released from prison.
I can't serve people like you here.'
The man rose without another word,
picked up his bag and stick, and left.
Outside, it was growing dark and a cold wind
was blowing from the mountains in the east.
The man looked around, desperate
for somewhere to spend the night.
He tried another inn, but the same thing happened.
He knocked on the doors of people's houses,
but news of his arrival had quickly spread and
nobody would offer him shelter from the cold.
He even tried sleeping in a garden,
but was chased away by a dog.
Finally, he found himself in the cathedral square.
He shook his fist at the church and then,
cold and hungry, he lay down on
a stone bench by the doorway.
A few minutes later, an old woman came out
of the cathedral and saw him lying there.
'What are you doing?' she asked.
He answered angrily, 'Can't
you see? I'm trying to sleep.'
'On this bench, in this cold wind?'
'I've slept for nineteen years on a piece of wood.
Now it's stone.
What's the difference?'
'Why don't you go to an inn?'
'Because I haven't any money,' he lied.
The old woman opened her purse
and gave him a few coins.
Then she said, 'Have you tried everywhere?'
'I've knocked at every door.'
'What about that one over there?'
she said, pointing across the square to
a small house beside the bishop's palace.
***
The Bishop of Digne was a kind
old man who, many years earlier,
had given his palace to the town hospital.
He lived a simple life with his
sister, Mademoiselle Baptistine,
and his old servant, Madame Magloire, and
he was much loved by the people in the town.
He trusted everyone.
His doors were never locked, so that anybody
who needed his help could find him easily.
That evening, Mme Magloire was chatting with
Mile Baptistine before serving the meal.
'People say there's a stranger in town,' she said.
'The police say that he looks dangerous,
and it would be better for everyone
to lock their windows and doors.'
'Brother.'
Mile Baptistine turned to the
bishop, who was sitting by the fire.
'Did you hear what Mme Magloire was saying?'
'Something about a dangerous stranger walking
the streets?' he asked with an amused smile.
'This is no joke,' Mme Magloire said.
'The man is in rags and has
an evil look on his face.
Everybody in the town agrees that
something terrible will happen tonight.
And your sister agrees with
me that this house isn't safe.
If you like, I can make arrangements
now to get a lock put on the door
Before the bishop could reply,
there was a heavy knock on the door.
'Come in,' said the bishop.
The door opened and Jean
Valjean, the stranger, walked in.
Mme Magloire trembled, open-mouthed
with fear, while Mile Baptistine
rose from her seat with alarm.
The bishop, however, looked
calmly at his unexpected visitor.
'My name is Jean Valjean,' the stranger
said before anybody could speak.
'I've been in prison for nineteen years.
They let me out four days ago.
I've been walking all day, and nobody in this
town will give me food or a bed for the night.
A woman saw me lying on a stone bench across
the square and suggested that I come here.
So here I am.
What is this place? Is it an inn? I've got money.
Will you let me stay?'
'Mme Magloire,' said the bishop,
'will you please prepare another place
at the table for this gentleman?'
Valjean took a step forward.
'No, you don't understand,' he said.
'I've spent five years in
prison for violent robbery,
another fourteen years for
trying to escape four times.
I'm a dangerous man.'
'Mme Magloire,' the bishop went on, 'you must
put clean sheets on the bed in the spare room.'
Mme Magloire, an obedient servant,
left the room without protest.
The bishop turned to the man.
'Sit down and warm yourself, Monsieur.
Supper will soon be ready.'
Jean Valjean's face, which had been
hard and fierce, suddenly softened.
'You really mean it?' he asked, his
voice trembling with childish excitement.
'You'll let me stay?
I'm a dangerous criminal,
but you called me "Monsieur".
I don't believe it.
May I ask your name, sir? Are you an innkeeper?'
'I'm a priest,' said the bishop.
'And this is where I live.'
'A priest?' Valjean said, sitting by the fire.
'So I don't have to pay?'
'You can keep your money,' the bishop replied.
During dinner, Mile Baptistine
looked at Valjean kindly while
the bishop talked about the
local cheese-making industry.
Valjean was so hungry that, at first,
he paid no attention to anyone.
Soon, however, he began to relax,
and looked around the room.
'This is not the house of a rich man,' he thought.
'And the travellers in the
inn eat better than this.'
But then he looked at the table, and saw the
beautiful silver candlesticks, knives and forks.
After dinner, the bishop said goodnight to his
sister, picked up one of the two candlesticks and,
handing the other to his guest, said,
'I'll show you to your room, Monsieur.'
Valjean followed the bishop
upstairs into a bedroom.
This was the bishop's bedroom.
As he was following the bishop
across the room, however,
he noticed Mme Magloire putting the silver
knives and forks in a cupboard by the bed.
The bishop showed his guest into the spare room.
'Sleep well,' he said.
'Before you leave tomorrow, you must
have a bowl of warm milk from our cows.'
Valjean was so tired that he fell asleep,
fully-dressed, on top of the sheets,
but he didn't sleep for long.
When he woke up, the cathedral clock was striking
two, but he had not woken because of this.
He had woken because the bed was too comfortable;
he had not slept in a proper bed for twenty years.
Unable to return to sleep, he gazed into the
darkness, thinking about the past twenty years.
Life had been unjust to him, and he was angry.
In 1795, he had lost his job as a tree-cutter.
At that time he was looking after his sister,
whose husband had died, and her seven children.
Out of work, and with no food in the house, he had
been arrested for trying to steal a loaf of bread.
Now, at last, he was free, but he felt
bitter and angry about his lost years.
The world had been unfair to
him, and he wanted revenge.
Then, remembering the silver on
the bishop's table, he had an idea.
He sat up, swung his feet to
the floor and slowly stood up.
The house was silent.
He moved carefully towards
the window and looked out.
The night was not very
dark; there was a full moon,
hidden from time to time by large
clouds moving quickly across the sky.
After studying the garden, he
decided that escape would be easy.
He turned back to the room, picked up his bag and
took out a short iron bar, sharpened at one end.
He then put his shoes into the bag and,
grasping the iron bar in his right hand,
he moved quietly towards the
door of the bishop's bedroom.
It was half-open.
The bishop had not closed it.
Valjean stood listening.
There was no sound.
He gave the door a gentle push
and crept into the bedroom.
Just as he reached the side of the bishop's bed,
the moon came out from behind a
cloud and filled the room with light.
Valjean gazed down at the bishop's gentle,
sleeping face, and felt a kind of terror.
He had never before seen such
peace, such kindness, such trust.
He suddenly turned away and
moved quickly to the cupboard.
The first thing he saw when he opened
the door was the basket of silver.
He grabbed it, hurried back to the spare
bedroom, picked up his stick and bag,
climbed out of the window, emptied the silver
into his bag and threw the basket into the garden.
A minute later he climbed the garden
wall and disappeared into the trees.
Early the next morning, while the bishop
was studying the flowers in his garden,
Mme Magloire ran out of the house
with a look of alarm on her face.
'Monseigneur, do you know
where the silver-basket is?'
'Yes,' said the bishop.
'I found it in one of the flowerbeds.'
'But it's empty!' she cried.
'Where's the silver?'
'Oh, you're worried about the
silver? I don't know where that is.'
'Heaven save us, it's been stolen!' she cried.
'The man who came last night!
He's run off with our silver!'
The bishop, who had been bending sadly
over a plant damaged by the basket,
looked up and said gently, 'I think I
was wrong to keep the silver for so long.
It really belongs to the poor.
I should have given it away a long time ago.'
Later that morning, as the bishop
and his sister were having breakfast,
there was a knock on the door.
Four men walked into the room.
Three of them were policemen;
the fourth was Jean Valjean.
'Monseigneur...
' the sergeant in charge of the group began.
Valjean raised his head with surprise.
'Monseigneur?' he repeated.
'I thought he was a priest.'
'Silence,' said one of the policemen,
'This is the Bishop of Digne.'
The bishop, meanwhile, had moved towards the
group of men and was smiling at Jean Valjean.
'I'm delighted to see you
again, dear friend,' he said.
'But what about the candlesticks? I gave
you those as well, don't you remember?
They're silver like the rest, and
worth at least two hundred francs.
Did you forget to take them?'
Jean Valjean's eyes widened with disbelief.
'Monseigneur,' said the sergeant, 'do I
understand that this man was telling the truth?
We found this silver in his bag, and
'And he told you,' the bishop
finished the sentence for him,
'that an old priest had given it to
him? Yes, he was telling the truth.'
'So this man isn't a thief? 'The
sergeant looked as surprised as Valjean.
'Not at all.
So you can let him go at once.'
The policemen let go of Valjean's arms.
He moved his feet nervously,
uncertain of what to say at first.
Then he murmured, 'Am I really free to go?'
'Of course,' said the bishop.
'But this time, you mustn't
forget your candlesticks.'
He fetched them from a shelf
and gave them to Valjean.
'Now, go in peace,' he said softly.
The policemen left, but Valjean did not move.
He did not know what to think.
The bishop walked up to him
and said in a low voice,
'Don't forget that you've promised to use
the money to make yourself an honest man.'
Valjean, who did not remember having
made such a promise, was silent.
'Jean Valjean,' the bishop continued,
'I've bought your soul from the
Devil, and have given it to God.'
***
Jean Valjean left the town
and ran into the countryside,
blindly following lanes and paths, not
realizing that he was running in circles.
He was filled with a strange kind
of anger, but he did not know why.
Finally, as evening fell, he
sat on the ground, exhausted,
and gazed across the fields at the distant
mountains, wishing that he was back in prison.
When he had been angry at the world,
he had felt calm and sure of himself.
But now, for the first time in twenty
years, a man had shown him great kindness,
and he did not know what to feel.
Suddenly, he heard the sound of singing.
A boy of about ten years old was
coming along a footpath with a
small box on his back and dirty knees
showing through holes in his trousers.
As he sang, he threw a coin into the
air and caught it before it fell.
Not noticing Jean Valjean sitting by the side of
the path, he threw the coin higher into the air.
This time, however, he did not catch it and
it rolled along the ground towards Valjean,
who immediately put his foot on it.
The boy, unafraid, walked up to Valjean.
'Please, Monsieur, may I have my coin?'
'What's your name?' asked Valjean.
'Petit-Gervais,' said the boy, smiling trustfully.
'I'm a chimney sweep, and
that money is all I have.'
'Go away,' said Valjean.
'Please, Monsieur, that's my money.'
Valjean lowered his head and did not reply.
'My money!' the boy cried.
'My piece of silver! My coin!'
Valjean seemed not to hear him.
The boy seized his collar and shook him.
'I want my money!' he cried.
Valjean slowly raised his head and stared
with a sort of amazement at the child.
Then, reaching for his
stick, he said, 'Go to Hell!'
The boy, suddenly afraid of the mad, fierce
look in Valjean's eyes, turned and ran.
Valjean stood for some time gazing emptily around
him at the sunset and the
shadows moving in on him.
Suddenly he shivered, as if he had become
aware for the first time of the icy wind.
He bent down to pick up his bag but, as he did so,
he caught sight of the silver coin,
half-buried by his foot in the earth.
It affected him like an electric shock.
'What's that?' he murmured.
He stared at the coin with a look of puzzlement,
as if he were trying to remember something.
Then, with a sudden movement,
he bent down and picked it up.
He looked around but could see
nothing in the darkness - just
a purple mist rising slowly from the fields.
He called the boy's name, but there was no reply.
Within minutes he was running
along the path, shouting.
'Petit-Gervais! Petit-Gervais!'
There was still no reply.
A short time later, he met a priest on horseback.
'Have you seen a boy go by?' he asked.
The priest shook his head.
'No.
Why do you ask?'
Valjean produced two five-franc
pieces and gave them to the priest.
'This is for your poor, Monsieur.
He was a boy of about ten, a chimney sweep.
Monsieur, you must report me to the police.
I'm a thief.
I stole money from him.
Here, let me give you more money
But before Valjean could produce more
coins, the priest rode away in terror.
Valjean looked for the boy for another hour,
running along the path, calling
out his name, but with no success.
Finally he stopped and sat, exhausted, on a rock.
Then, his heart full of grief for what he
had done, he buried his face in his hands
and, for the first time in
nineteen years, he cried.
CHAPTER TWO
Fantine
On a spring evening in 1818, in the
village of Montfermeil, not far from Paris,
two little girls were playing
on a swing outside a small inn.
Their mother - a big, red-haired
woman with a plain face - sat on
the doorstep of the inn, watching them.
'You have two very pretty children,
Madame,' a voice said from close beside her.
The woman looked round and saw a young woman
with a child sleeping peacefully in her arms.
The mother was young and pretty,
but she looked poor and unhappy.
She did not smile, and lines of sadness
ran down the side of her pale cheeks.
Her clothes were old and dirty, and she wore a
tight, plain cap over her beautiful blonde hair.
'Thank you,' said the woman.
'Why don't you sit down for
a minute? You look tired.
'When the young woman had sat down next to
her, the red-haired woman introduced herself.
'My name's Thenardier.
My husband and I manage this inn.'
'My names Fantine,' the young woman said.
'I used to work in Paris, but my
husband died and I lost my job.'
She could not tell Mme Thenardier the truth,
which was that she had been made pregnant
by a young man who had then abandoned her.
'I left Paris this morning to look
for work in Montreuil,' she continued.
'My little girl walked some of
the way, but she's very small.
I had to carry her and she's fallen asleep.'
As she spoke these words, she gave her
daughter a loving kiss, which woke her up.
The child's eyes were as wide
and blue as her mother's.
With a little laugh,
she jumped off her mother's lap and ran
to play with the two girls on the swing.
'What's your little girl's
name?' Mme Thenardier asked.
'Euphrasie - but I call her Cosette.
She's nearly three.'
The two women watched the
children playing together.
'Children make friends very easily,
don't they?' Mme Thenardier smiled.
'Look at them.
They could easily be sisters.'
At these words, Fantine did a very strange thing.
She took Mme Thenardiers hand and said,
'Will you look after my daughter for me?'
Mme Thenardier looked at Fantine
thoughtfully, but said nothing.
'I can't take her with me,' Fantine continued.
'I have to find work, and that's not
easy with a child but no husband.
As soon as I find a job, I'll come and fetch her.
Will you do that for me? I
could pay six francs a month.'
Mme Thenardier still said nothing, but a
man's voice from inside the house called,
'We'll take seven francs a month,
and six months in advance.'
Fantine agreed.
'And another fifteen francs
for extras,' called the man.
'You will have them,' said Fantine, assuming
that she was talking to Mme Thenardiers husband.
'I have eighty francs.'
'Does the child have enough
clothes?' the man asked.
'She has some beautiful clothes,' Fantine replied.
'Plenty of everything and
silk dresses like a lady.
They're all in my bag.'
The man's face finally appeared in the doorway.
'Then we agree to look
after her for you,' he said.
The next morning, Fantine kissed her
daughter goodbye and left for Montreuil,
crying as if her heart would break.
'This money will be
useful,'Thenardier said to his wife.
'Now I can pay off all my
debts and stay out of prison.
I'm proud of you.
You set a very clever trap.'
'Without even intending to,' his wife replied.
One month later, Thenardier
was short of money again,
so he took Cosette's beautiful silk clothes
to Paris and sold them for sixty francs.
The couple dressed Cosette in rags
and gave her very little food,
which they made her eat from
a wooden bowl under the table.
The dog and the cat, who ate with
her, were her only companions.
Fantine, meanwhile, found work in Montreuil
and asked for news of her daughter every month.
The Thenardiers always replied that
she was in good health and very happy.
At the end of the year, however, Thenardier was
not happy with just seven francs a month; he
demanded twelve and Fantine paid without protest,
happy that her daughter was being well cared for.
The Thenardiers, who were loving and gentle
to their own daughters, Eponine and Azelma,
treated Cosette like a slave.
They made her get up before dawn every day
and do all the dirty jobs around the house,
while Eponine and Azelma wore pretty
clothes and played with dolls.
By the age of five, Cosette had become
a thin, pale-faced, silent child.
Misery had made her ugly and only
her beautiful blue eyes remained.
The Thenardiers did not feel guilty
about treating Cosette badly because
Fantine had stopped sending them regular payments.
'The child is lucky to have a
home at all,' they told everybody.
'Without us, she'd be living on the streets.'
***
When Fantine first arrived in Montreuil,
she had immediately found work in a factory.
She rented a small room, sent money
regularly to the Thenardiers and,
for a short time, was almost happy.
She forgot many of her problems, and dreamt
only of Cosette and her plans for the future.
But her happiness did not last long.
Although she was careful to say
nothing about her daughter to anyone,
other women at the factory
soon discovered her secret.
An unmarried woman with a child was a terrible
thing in those days, and Fantine lost her job.
She tried to find work as a servant,
but no one would employ her.
She finally managed to earn
a little money sewing shirts,
but she was unable to send money
regularly to the Thenardiers.
That winter, Fantine saved money by not having
a fire, and developed a small, dry cough.
By the following winter, her debts had increased.
The Thenardiers wrote her a frightening letter in
which they told her that Cosette had no clothes,
and that they needed ten francs
immediately to buy her a new dress.
Fantine, who did not have ten francs,
but who was afraid that her daughter would
freeze to death, went to the barber's shop.
She took out her comb and let her
blonde hair fall down to her waist.
'Such beautiful hair!' the barber said.
'How much will you give me for it?' Fantine asked.
'Ten francs.'
'Then cut it off.'
After selling her hair to the barber,
Fantine was able to buy a woollen dress,
which she sent to the Thenardiers.
The Thenardiers, however, were very angry
- they had wanted money, not clothes.
They gave the dress to their daughter,
Eponine, and Cosette went on shivering.
A few weeks later, Fantine received
another letter from the Thenardiers.
This time they wanted forty francs because
Cosette was very ill and urgently needed medicine.
Fantine felt desperate; she did not know
how to obtain such a large sum of money.
As she was wandering around the town,
desperately trying to decide what to do,
she noticed a crowd of
people in the market square.
She approached them without thinking,
and discovered that they had
gathered around a travelling dentist.
Forgetting her troubles for a moment,
she smiled at the dentist's humorous efforts
to sell the people of Montreuil false teeth.
Suddenly the dentist saw her.
'You've got lovely teeth,' he said.
'If you sold me your two front
teeth, I'd pay you forty francs.'
Fantine ran home, upset and disgusted.
'My hair will grow again,' she thought,
'but teeth would be gone forever.'
But then she thought about her daughter, and
her own appearance suddenly seemed unimportant.
That evening, she visited the dentist
at the inn where he was staying,
and allowed him to remove her teeth.
Fantine could not sleep that night.
She sat on her bed, cold and shivering, and
looked at the two coins shining on the table.
Then she gave a blood-stained smile.
'I'm happy,' she told herself.
'My baby isn't going to die.'
Fantine earned less and
less money from her sewing,
and the Thenardiers demanded more
and more money to look after Cosette.
Fantine spent whole nights crying.
What could she do? She had sold her hair
and her teeth; what else could she sell?
And then she decided that she had no other
choice: she would have to sell herself.
She became a prostitute.
CHAPTER THREE
Monsieur Madeleine
One winter's evening, a toothless woman
with a grey face and flowers in her hair
was arrested for attacking a man in the street.
She was taken to the police
station, where Inspector Javert,
the chief of police, sent
her to prison for six months.
'Please, M.
Javert.'
The woman fell to her knees.
'I owe a hundred francs.
If I don't pay, my little girl will lose her
home and be thrown out on to the streets.
Please don't send me to prison.'
Javert listened to her coldly, then
ordered a policeman to take her away.
While the policeman was trying
to drag her to her feet, however,
a voice from the shadows
said, 'One moment please.'
Javert looked up and saw Monsieur Madeleine,
one of the most important people in the town.
M.
Madeleine had arrived mysteriously in
Montreuil one December evening in 1815.
He had no money but he had a revolutionary idea:
he knew a cheap and efficient
method of manufacturing glass.
Within a few months of his arrival, thanks to his
new idea, the glass-making factory in
Montreuil was making enormous profits.
With the money he made, M.
Madeleine built two new factories, which
provided the town with hundreds of new jobs.
He became a very wealthy
man but lived a simple life,
using most of his money to
build new hospitals and schools.
He was so popular that, in 1820, the
townspeople elected him mayor of Montreuil.
There was one man, however, who did not like M.
Madeleine.
This was the chief of police, Inspector Javert.
He had always been suspicious of M.
Madeleine, and was sure that he had seen
him somewhere before, many years earlier.
But he kept his suspicions to himself, not
daring to say what he really believed: that M.
Madeleine was, in fact, a dangerous
criminal with a terrible past.
Now, years later, M.
Madeleine was in the police station,
trying to save Fantine from prison.
Fantine, however, was not grateful.
In fact, when she saw who it was, she spat at him.
'You own the factory where I used
to work!' she shouted at him.
'I lost my job because of you.
Now I've become a bad woman,
but what choice did I have? I'll never get
my daughter back if I don't make money.'
The mayor turned to Inspector Javert and said, in
a soft, firm voice, 'This woman must be released.'
'That's impossible,' Javert replied.
'She attacked a man in the
street, a respectable citizen.
And now I've just seen her spit
at you, the mayor of our town.
A woman like this deserves to be punished.'
'But I saw what happened
in the street just now,' M.
Madeleine said.
'It was the man's fault, not this woman's.
You should arrest him, not her.'
Javert argued with M.
Madeleine for some time, but finally gave in.
He walked angrily out of the room, leaving
the mayor and the prostitute alone together.
Fantine trembled, as confused as Javert had been.
The man who had just saved her from prison was
also the man who had caused all her troubles.
The devil had suddenly decided to be
kind, and she did not know what to think.
'I heard what you said,' M.
Madeleine said to her.
'I honestly didn't know that you had lost
your job, but I'll try to help you now.
I'll pay your debts and arrange
for your child to return to you.
I'll give you all the money you need.
I'll make you happy again.
And I promise that, in the eyes of
God, you have never been a bad woman.'
Fantine gazed at M.
Madeleine with tears in her eyes.
After all her pain and suffering she
had, for the first time in her life,
found kindness in another human being.
At last she would be cared for, and she could
look forward to a life of happiness with Cosette.
Without a word, she fell to her
knees and kissed the back of M.
Madeleine's hand.
M.
Madeleine sent the Thenardiers 300 francs and told
them to send Cosette to Montreuil immediately.
Thenardier, thinking that Fantine had suddenly
become rich, wrote back and demanded 500 francs.
M.
Madeleine sent the money, but
the Thenardiers found even more
dishonest excuses for not sending Cosette back.
***
The weeks passed and, although she was happier
than she had been for a long
time, Fantine caught a fever.
Months of poverty and misery had made her ill,
and she soon became so weak that
she was unable to leave her bed.
'When shall I see Cosette?' she kept asking M.
Madeleine when he visited her.
'Very soon,' he would reply, and her
pale face would light up with joy.
One morning, as M.
Madeleine was making preparations
to leave for Montfermeil and to
fetch Cosette himself, he had a visitor.
Inspector Javert walked into his office,
and stood in silence waiting for
him to look up from his work.
'Well, Javert, what is it?' M.
Madeleine finally said.
'I've come to apologize, M.
Madeleine,' the inspector replied.
'What are you talking about?'
'I've treated you unjustly.
I was angry with you six weeks ago
when you told me to release that woman.
I wrote to the police headquarters
in Paris and told them about you.'
'Told them what about me?'
'Forgive me, M.
Madeleine, but I believed you
were a man called Jean Valjean.
He was a prisoner I saw twenty years
ago, when I worked at a prison in Toulon.
After being released from prison,
this Valjean stole some silver from
the Bishop of Digne and robbed a
small boy on a public footpath.
We tried to catch him, but he disappeared.
When you arrived in Montreuil, I
felt sure that you were this man,
but now I know I was wrong, and I'm sorry.
You will, of course, dismiss me from my job,
as I've shown that I don't deserve your trust.'
M.
Madeleine, looking hard at Javert
without expression, said quietly,
'I'm afraid I don't understand.'
'The police headquarters in Paris told
me that Jean Valjean was arrested last
autumn for stealing apples,' Javert explained.
He'd changed his name to Champmathieu and had
lived for several years in the
village of Ailly-le-Haut-Cloche.
Two ex-prisoners from Toulon
recognized him as Jean Valjean.
I visited the man in Arras prison, and I saw
for myself that he is indeed Jean Valjean.
Of course, he denies everything,
but that's not surprising.
If he's found guilty of stealing from the
bishop - who, as you know, died a couple
of years ago - and of robbing the small boy,
he'll spend the rest of his life in prison.'
M.
Madeleine looked down at his papers.
'This matter is of no interest
to me, Javert,' he said casually.
'I'm sure you have other work to do.'
'I was going to the man's trial
in Arras tomorrow, 'Javert said.
'But after this conversation,
you must dismiss me.'
M.
Madeleine rose to his feet.
'Javert,' he said, 'you're an honourable man.
You made one small mistake, that's all.
I want you to continue your excellent
work as inspector of police.'
He offered Javert his hand, but
the inspector refused to take it.
Instead, he said, 'I've behaved
unjustly towards an innocent man.
I cannot shake his hand.'
With those words he bowed and
left the office, leaving M.
Madeleine to stare at the papers on his desk
with an empty, puzzled look in his eyes.
That afternoon, M.
Madeleine visited Fantine.
She had a high fever, and was coughing badly,
but she still had only one thing on her mind.
'Cosette?' she asked him.
'Very soon,' he assured her.
He sat by her bed for an hour and then,
having told the nurses to look
after her, he returned to his home.
He stayed awake all night, thinking
of Javert's story about Champmathieu.
The reader has probably already realized that M.
Madeleine was really Jean Valjean, and M.
Madeleine - as we shall continue to call
him for this part of the story - knew
that he could not let Champmathieu go to
prison for crimes he had not committed.
He knew - although he was not
happy to admit this - that he
would have to go to Arras and tell the truth.
He would lose everything that he
had worked so hard to achieve.
He would also have to break his promise to
Fantine about bringing Cosette from Montfermeil.
But what choice did he have? The truth
was more important than anything else.
***
The next morning, M.
Madeleine set off on the long journey to Arras.
It took him more than twelve hours,
and when he arrived, he discovered that
Champmathieu's trial had already started.
The courtroom was full but, because
he was such an important man, M.
Madeleine was allowed to sit
behind the judge's chair.
He watched as several witnesses swore on the Bible
that the man standing before
the judge was Jean Valjean.
Champmathieu, a large, simple-minded man,
denied everything when his chance came to speak,
but the crowd thought he was trying to be funny.
The courtroom filled with laughter and
Champmathieu began to laugh himself,
which did him no good at all.
Finally, having heard all the
evidence, the judge called for silence.
He was preparing to announce his decision when M.
Madeleine, pale and trembling, stood up and said:
'That man is not Jean Valjean.'
An excited whisper went around the
courtroom as everybody recognized M.
Madeleine.
M.
Madeleine waited for the whispers to stop
before announcing in a loud, clear
voice that he was Jean Valjean.
At first, no one believed him, but he managed to
persuade the court by skilfully questioning each
of the witnesses, revealing personal information
that only the real Jean Valjean could have known.
When he had persuaded the court
of the truth of his confession,
he was faced with a shocked
but respectful silence.
'I must leave now,' M.
Madeleine finally said.
'I have important business to attend to.
You know where to find me, and
I shall not try to escape.'
Everybody stood to one side to let him
pass as he made his way towards the door.
When he had gone, the judge immediately allowed
Champmathieu to leave the court a free man.
Champmathieu went home in
a state of total confusion,
thinking all men mad and understanding
nothing of what had happened.
***
At dawn the next day, M.
Madeleine entered Fantine's room.
'How is she?' he asked the nurse,
who was watching her as she slept.
'She seems better.
She's looking forward to seeing her child.'
'I haven't brought the child with me,' M.
Madeleine said.
'Then what can we say to her when she wakes
up?' The nurse looked suddenly worried.
'It will destroy her if she doesn't see her
child now, after you promised to bring her.'
'God will guide me,' M.
Madeleine sighed.
For some time M.
Madeleine sat by the bedside and
watched Fantine while she slept.
She was breathing with great difficulty,
but her face looked peaceful and calm.
Suddenly, she opened her eyes and saw M.
Madeleine.
'Cosette?' she asked, with a soft smile.
'Later,' M.
Madeleine said gently, taking her hand.
'You're too weak to see her at the moment.
First you must get well.'
Fantine smiled, and began to talk dreamily
about her future life with her daughter,
and how happy they would be together.
But suddenly her face froze, and
she stared with horror at the door.
M.
Madeleine, who was holding her hand,
turned and saw Inspector Javert.
Fantine, thinking that the inspector
had come for her, gripped M.
Madeleine's hand tightly and
begged him to protect her.
'Don't be afraid.'
M.
Madeleine tried to calm her.
'He hasn't come for you.'
Then, gently rising from his
chair, he moved towards Javert.
'I know what you've come for,' he said
quietly so that Fantine wouldn't hear.
'But give me three days, please.
That's all I ask.
Three days to fetch this
unfortunate woman's child.
I'll pay anything you like.'
'Do you think I'm stupid?'
Javert gave an unpleasant laugh.
'Three days to escape, you mean.'
Fantine, who had heard what M.
Madeleine said, despite his efforts
to speak quietly, began to tremble.
'To fetch my child?' she cried.
'Isn't she here? Nurse, answer me...
where's my little Cosette? I want to see her.
M.
Madeleine
'Be quiet, you dirty prostitute,'
Javert interrupted her angrily.
'There is no Monsieur Madeleine.
This man's name is Jean Valjean, and
he's a criminal no better than you are.
And you can forget all that
nonsense about your child.
Fantine suddenly sat up.
She stared wildly at the two
men, then turned to the nurse.
She looked as if she was going to
speak, but no words came from her lips.
Instead, with a small sigh, she fell back
against her pillow and lay completely still.
Jean Valjean (as we must now call him) shook
Javert's hand from his collar and ran to the bed.
He gazed into Fantine's eyes and
knew immediately that she was dead.
'You've killed her!' he cried angrily, turning
to Javert with a fierce look in his eyes.
'I didn't come here to argue,' Javert said,
stepping back nervously, afraid that
Valjean was going to attack him.
'If you don't come with me
now, I'll have to call my men.'
Valjean looked around the room, thinking
for a second of making his escape.
But the idea did not last for long.
He turned again to Fantine and looked for one last
time at her sad, pale face and empty, blue eyes.
Bending down, he closed her eyes and
pressed his lips against her forehead.
Then he rose and turned back to Javert.
'I'm ready now,' he said.
News of M.
Madeleine's arrest spread quickly around the town.
Most people pretended not to be surprised.
'We always knew there was something
strange about him,' they said.
Two days after his arrest, Jean
Valjean escaped from prison.
The bars of his window had
been broken during the night.
Again, most people pretended not to be surprised.
'It takes more than a small town prison to
hold a man as strong as that,' they all agreed.
CHAPTER FOUR
The Man in the Long Yellow Coat
Christmas 1823 was especially lively and
colourful in the village of Montfermeil.
Entertainers and traders from
Paris set up their stalls in
the streets, and business at the
Thenardiers' inn was very good.
While guests and visitors ate and drank noisily,
Cosette - now eight years old - sat in
her usual place under the kitchen table.
Dressed in rags, she knitted woollen
stockings for Eponine and Azelma.
One evening, Madame Thenardier ordered
Cosette out into the cold to fetch water.
The nearest water supply was half-way down
the wooded hill on which Montfermeil stood,
and Cosette hated fetching
water, especially in the dark.
Miserably, she picked up a large, empty
bucket that was almost as big as she was,
and was walking with it to the door
when Madame Thenardier stopped her.
'Buy some bread on the way,' she
said, giving the girl some money.
Cosette took the coin, put it
carefully in her pocket and left.
She was cold and hungry as she dragged the
bucket behind her along the crowded street,
but she could not resist stopping
in front of one of the stalls.
It was like a palace to her, with its bright
lights, shining glass and pretty objects.
But the object that most attracted
Cosette's attention was a large,
golden-haired doll in a beautiful long pink dress.
All the children in Montfermeil
had gazed with wonder at this doll,
but nobody in the village
had enough money to buy it.
Cosette gazed at the doll for several minutes
but, remembering her job, she
sighed and continued on her way.
She had soon left the colourful lights and
the happy laughter of the village behind her,
and was running down the hill into
the frightening darkness of the wood.
Finding the stream, she bent forward
and began to till her bucket.
She did not notice the coin that
Mme Thenardier had given her for
the bread fall out of her pocket into the water.
When the bucket was full, she
gripped the handle with her tiny,
frozen hands and tried to
pull it back up the hill.
But the bucket was so heavy that, after a
dozen steps, she had to stop for a rest.
She managed a few more steps, and stopped again.
Her progress became slower and slower.
She was almost at the end of her strength,
and she was still not out of the wood.
Leaning against a tree, she cried aloud:
'Oh God help me! Please, dear God!'
Suddenly, an enormous hand reached down from
the sky and took the bucket of water from her.
Looking up, Cosette saw a huge,
white-haired man standing next to her.
He looked very strange with his
tall black hat and long yellow coat.
'This is a very heavy bucket for
such a small child,' he said gently,
looking down at her from his great height.
For some reason, Cosette was not afraid.
There was something about his eyes, tilled with
a strange sadness, that she liked and trusted.
She let him carry the bucket up the hill
and, as they walked back towards the village,
she told him everything about
her life with the Thenardiers.
The old man listened with great
interest, and asked her many questions.
As they were approaching the inn,
Cosette turned to him and said,
'May I have the bucket now? If Mme Thenardier sees
that someone has been helping me, she'll beat me.'
The old man gave her the bucket,
and they entered the inn together.
'What took you so long?' Mme Thenardier
said angrily when she saw the little girl.
'This gentleman wants a room for the night,'
Cosette said, trembling with
fear, expecting to be beaten.
Mme Thenardier glanced at
the old man without interest.
She could tell from his clothes
that he probably had no money.
'I'm sorry, the rooms are full,' she said.
'I can pay the price of a room,' the old man said.
'Forty sous,' Mme Thenardier replied
(although the usual price was twenty).
'Forty sous,' the man agreed.
He sat down and Cosette, after serving him some
wine, returned to her place under the table.
But before she could start her knitting, she
heard Mme Thenardier's angry voice demanding,
'Where's the bread I told you to get?'
Cosette, who had forgotten about the
bread, came out from under the table.
'The baker's was shut,' she lied.
'Well, give me back the money.'
Cosette felt in her pocket and suddenly went pale.
The coin was not there.
'I'm waiting,' Mme Thenardier said threateningly.
Cosette said nothing, speechless with fear
as the woman raised her arm to hit her.
But before she could deliver the blow the old
man, who had seen everything, interrupted her.
'Madame, I've just noticed this on the floor.
It must have fallen from the child's pocket.'
Mme Thenardier took the coin the old
man held towards her and walked away.
At that moment the door opened
and Eponine and Azelma appeared.
They were two healthy girls, the old man noticed,
dressed in warm clothes and
with pink, healthy cheeks.
After hugging and kissing their mother, they sat
on the floor by the fire and played with a doll.
Cosette, who had returned to
her place under the table,
looked up from her knitting
and watched them sadly.
A short time later, the girls
grew bored with their game.
They left the doll on the floor and
went off to play with a baby cat.
Cosette, checking that no one was watching,
reached out and picked up the doll.
She turned her back on the
room and began to play with it,
hoping that no one could see what she was doing.
Her happiness did not last long, however.
The two girls, when they saw Cosette with
their doll, ran crying to their mother.
Mme Thenardier rushed across
the room towards Cosette who,
afraid that she would be punished, put the
doll gently on the floor and began to cry.
'What's the matter?' the old
man said, rising to his feet.
'Can't you see?' Mme Thenardier
said, red with anger.
'That nasty little girl, who isn't
even my own daughter, who I feed and
look after out of the kindness of my heart,
has been playing with my daughters' doll.'
'I don't understand,' the old man said.
'She's touched it with her dirty hands!'
Then, hearing Cosette crying, she turned to
the little girl and shouted, 'Stop that noise!'
The old man left the inn and, minutes
later, returned with something in his hands:
the beautiful doll from the stall across the road.
'Here,' he said softly, placing it
gently on the floor in front of Cosette.
'It's for you.'
There was a sudden silence in the room.
Mme Thenardier, Eponine and
Azelma stood absolutely still.
The drinkers at the other tables paused, glasses
half-way to their lips, and stared with disbelief.
'What kind of man is this?' they thought.
'He dresses so poorly but can afford to buy
the most expensive doll in Montfermeil!'
The Thenardiers gave the old man
their best room for the night.
The next morning they gave him the bill,
charging him three times the usual price
for a meal and a bed for the night.
They waited nervously while the
man studied the bill carefully,
expecting him to complain or cause trouble.
Finally, he looked up from the
bill without expression and said,
'Tell me, is business good here in Montfermeil?'
'Times are very hard,' Mme
Thenardier replied immediately.
'This is a poor country.
I don't know how we would manage without the
occasional rich and generous
traveller like yourself.
We have so many expenses.
That child, for instance - you've
no idea how much she costs.
We have our own daughters to look after.
I can't afford to look after
other people's children, too.'
'What would you say,' the old man
said after a moment's thought,
'if I offered to take the child from you?'
'Oh!' Madame Thenardiers face brightened.
'That would be wonderful.'
'Just a minute,' her husband said.
'We love that child very much.
It's true we're poor, and we have bad debts,
but love is more important than money.'
'How much do you need?' the old man asked, taking
an old leather wallet from the pocket of his coat.
'1500 francs,' Thenardier, who had
already done his arithmetic, replied.
The old man put three 500-franc notes on the table
and said, without smiling, 'Now fetch Cosette.'
When Cosette came downstairs, the
old man gave her new clothes to wear:
a black woollen dress, black
stockings, scarf and shoes.
Half an hour later, the people of Montfermeil
saw an old man in a tall hat and long yellow
coat walking along the road to Paris, hand-in-hand
with a little girl dressed completely in black.
No one knew the man.
And, because she was carrying
an expensive doll and was no
longer wearing rags, not many recognized Cosette.
Cosette was leaving at last.
She did not know where to, or with whom.
But, as she held the old man's hand,
she gazed wide-eyed at the sky.
She had the strange but comforting feeling
that she was somehow travelling closer to God.
CHAPTER FOUR
Valjean and Cosette
Somewhere on the outskirts of Paris,
Jean Valjean stopped outside a large,
ancient building with damp walls.
He took a key from the pocket of his long
yellow coat and opened the old wooden door.
He then carried Cosette, who was sleeping in
his arms, along a dark corridor and up some
stairs to the room he had rented
since his escape from Montreuil.
There was not much furniture
in the room - just an old bed,
a mattress on the floor, a table,
some chairs and a lighted stove.
A streetlamp shone through the only window,
lighting the dark interior of the room.
Valjean laid Cosette on
the bed without waking her.
He lit a candle and sat by the
bed, watching her while she slept.
He felt sad that Fantine had not
lived to see her child again,
but happy that he had been able to rescue
her child from the terrible Thenardiers.
He bent and kissed the sleeping child's forehead
just as, nine months earlier,
he had kissed her mother's.
The next morning, Cosette opened her eyes
and immediately started to get out of bed.
'I'm coming, Madame,' she yawned, blinded
by the bright winter's sunlight
that was shining into the room.
Then, as her eyes adjusted to the light,
she saw the kind old face of Jean Valjean
looking down at her, and she relaxed.
'Of course!' she cried with joy.
'It's all true.
I was afraid that it was just a dream.'
She hugged her doll and asked
Valjean hundreds of questions.
Finally, she asked him, 'Do you
want me to sweep the floor?'
'No,' he said.
'I just want you to enjoy yourself.'
The December days passed in great happiness
for Cosette and for Jean Valjean, too.
For twenty-five years he
had been alone in the world.
Nothing had ever touched his heart
until he had rescued Cosette.
Now, he discovered the greatest joy
he had ever known by just standing
beside her bed and looking at her
innocent, trusting little face.
He had discovered love.
***
After escaping from Montreuil,
Jean Valjean had taken all his
money from the bank and buried
it in a forest near Montfermeil.
Although he was rich, he had chosen a room in a
poor part of Paris, where nobody would find him.
His only neighbour was an old woman, who did
his housework and kept his stove burning.
Paying her six months in advance, he told
her that he was a ruined Spanish gentleman,
and that the little girl was his granddaughter.
Weeks passed, and the two lived happily.
Valjean gave Cosette lessons
in reading and writing,
and spent hours watching her as
she dressed and undressed her doll.
To avoid being seen, he never
went out during the day.
He walked for a couple of hours every evening,
sometimes alone, sometimes with Cosette.
He often gave money to beggars, which was unwise,
because he soon became known in the area
as 'the beggar who gives money to beggars'.
One evening, towards the end of winter,
Valjean gave some money to a beggar sitting
under a streetlamp outside a church.
The beggar raised his face and stared
hard at Valjean for just a second,
then quickly bowed his head.
This gave Valjean a shock.
Although he had only seen the beggar's face
for a second, it had seemed strangely familiar.
'I'm going mad,' he thought, as he walked home.
The next evening he returned to
the steetlamp outside the church.
The beggar was still there, in the same
position, wearing the same clothes.
This time, Valjean spoke to
him as he gave him some money.
The beggar laughed and joked with him, and
Valjean returned that evening a happier man.
'I must have been dreaming
yesterday,' he laughed to himself.
'But for a second, there was something about
the beggars eyes that reminded me of Javert.
How could I have thought such a thing?
After speaking to him this evening,
I can see that he doesn't look
like the inspector at all.'
A few evenings later, while he was
giving Cosette a reading lesson in
his room, Valjean heard the front
door of the house open and close.
This was unusual.
The old woman, the only other person who lived in
the building, always went to bed before nightfall.
Valjean signalled to Cosette to keep quiet.
Someone was coming up the stairs.
He blew out the candle and, just as he was kissing
Cosette on the forehead, the footsteps stopped.
Valjean did not move.
He sat in his chair with his back
to the door and held his breath.
A few minutes later, having heard
only silence, he turned round.
A light was shining through a crack in his door.
Someone with a candle was
standing outside his room.
Several minutes passed, and
then the light disappeared.
Valjean quietly lay down on the mattress on his
floor, but he could not close his eyes all night.
At daybreak, as he was falling asleep at last,
he heard footsteps in the
corridor outside his room again.
Running to the door, he put
his eye to the large keyhole
and saw the back view of a man who
was walking towards the stairs.
A tall man in a long coat
with a stick under his arm.
Valjean's heart almost stopped
beating and he began to sweat.
'Javert,' he breathed to himself.
***
Valjean spent all day making
preparations to leave.
It was too dangerous for him and
Cosette to stay there another night.
That evening, he went downstairs
and looked up and down the street.
It seemed empty, although he could not
see into the shadows behind the trees.
He went back upstairs for Cosette, who was
waiting for him patiently, holding her doll.
'Come along,' he said.
'It's time to leave.'
Cosette took his hand, and
went with him down the stairs.
There was a full moon, and this pleased Valjean
as he moved quickly along the narrow streets.
By keeping close to the walls in the shadows, he
could clearly see what was happening in the light.
After a while, he felt confident that
he and Cosette were not being followed.
But, as the church bells of the city struck
eleven o'clock, something made him look back.
In the light of a lamp above a doorway, he saw
four men moving along the street in his direction.
He gripped Cosette's hand and
began to walk more quickly.
Every few minutes, he stopped in the shadows of a
doorway or at the corner of a street to look back.
The four men were still following him.
He could see their faces clearly in the moonlight,
and one of them belonged to Inspector Javert.
By now, Cosette was exhausted.
Valjean picked her up and ran with her through a
confusing system of alleys
until he came to a bridge.
On the other side of the river, he stopped at the
entrance of a high-walled alley and looked back.
He could see four figures in the
distance on the far side of the bridge.
Walking more slowly now, thinking
he was safe from his pursuers,
Valjean followed the alley until he came to a
lane that seemed to lead away from the city.
He walked along this lane for a
long time until, to his horror,
he discovered his way blocked by a high wall.
There was no way forward,
but as he was turning back,
he saw movements in the distance
and the flash of moonlight on metal.
Seven or eight soldiers were moving
slowly along the lane in his direction.
Valjean looked desperately for an escape
from the alley, but could see none.
On one side of him was a tall building, all
its doors and windows covered with metal bars.
On the other side there was
a wall, higher than a tree.
He would be able to climb the wall on
his own, but how could he carry Cosette?
Suddenly, he had an idea.
He ran to a nearby streetlight and pulled
some wire from a metal box at its base.
He tied one end of the wire
around Cosette's waist,
climbed the wall and, with great
difficulty, pulled the girl up behind him.
He was only just in time.
There was a tree on the other side of the wall,
and Valjean carried Cosette down into its
branches just as the soldiers arrived.
'He must be here!' He heard Javert's voice
clearly on the other side of the wall.
'He can't have escaped.
There's no way out!'
At last, the soldiers gave up their search
and went back in the direction they had come.
Valjean hugged Cosette tightly with relief,
knowing that at last they were both safe.
CHAPTER SIX
Marius
On the night after the Battle of Waterloo,
in June 1815, a robber moved quietly
around the battlefield, stealing money and
jewellery from the bodies of dead soldiers.
He saw a hand sticking out from
a pile of dead men and horses,
a gold ring on its middle
finger, shining in the moonlight.
The robber took the ring but, as he turned
to leave, the hand grabbed his jacket.
The robber pulled the body from the pile of bodies
and saw that he had rescued a French officer.
The man had a terrible wound in
his head, but he was still alive.
'Thank you,' the officer whispered.
'You've saved my life.
What's your name?'
'Thenardier,' the robber replied.
'I shall not forget that
name,' the officer replied.
'And you must remember mine.
My name's Pontmercy.'
Without another word, the robber took
the wounded man's watch and purse,
and disappeared into the night.
Georges Pontmercy was married with a young son.
He survived the Battle of Waterloo but
unfortunately, in the same year, his wife died.
His father-in-law, M.
Gillenormand, was a very wealthy man,
but the two men hated each other.
M.
Gillenormand hated everybody who liked Napoleon.
He thought that Pontmercy
was no better than a beggar,
a penniless adventurer who only wanted his money.
Pontmercy thought that M.
Gillenormand was an old fool.
When his daughter died, M.
Gillenormand made Pontmercy an
offer which he could not refuse.
'You have no money, and I am rich,' he said.
'If you want to keep your son,
Marius, I'll give you no money.
But if you give the boy to me, and promise
never to see him again, I'll look after him.'
Pontmercy, wanting his son to have a
good life, had sadly given him to M.
Gillenormand and never saw his
son or father-in-law again.
Marius grew up with his grandfather,
and never knew his father.
M.
Gillenormand always told him that
his father had been no good - that
he was a poor soldier and a drunk who had
abandoned him after his mother's death.
For many years, Marius believed this, but when
he was seventeen years old, he learnt the truth.
His father, a brave officer who had
fought for Napoleon and nearly died
at the Battle of Waterloo, had really
loved him and his mother very much.
Without telling his grandfather,
Marius tried to contact his father and
finally discovered where he was living.
He went at once to visit him, but he was too late.
His father had just died.
A poor man, Georges Pontmercy had left
his son nothing apart from a letter:
For my son.
My life was saved at Waterloo by a sergeant.
His name was Thenardier.
I believe that he recently managed a small inn in
the village of Montfermeil, not far from Paris.
If you ever find this man, I want
you to help him in any way you can.
Marius returned to Paris, but continued
to visit his father's grave regularly,
without telling his grandfather.
One day, however, his grandfather
discovered what he was doing.
They had a big quarrel, and M.
Gillenormand ordered Marius to leave his house.
***
For the next three years, Marius lived in a
small room in an old, damp-walled building on the
outskirts of Paris - the same room that Valjean
and Cosette had lived in eight years earlier.
He gave up studying law and
earned his living by working
in a bookshop and helping to write dictionaries.
He did not earn very much money, but it
was enough for the rent and simple meals.
He rarely bought new clothes, but he was proud
of the fact that he had never been in debt.
His grandfather often tried to send him
money, but Marius always returned it.
He hated his grandfather for the unjust,
cruel way he had treated his poor father.
Life was hard for him, but he never forgot
the promise he had made his father: that he
would find Thenardier, the man who had saved his
father's life, and help him in any way he could.
Marius was a handsome young man,
but he was also extremely shy.
When girls looked at him and smiled, he
thought they were laughing at his old clothes.
In fact, they were attracted by his good looks,
but he was not confident enough to realize this.
As a result, he had no girlfriend,
but he was happy with his books.
'You shouldn't stay alone all the time,'
his good friend, Enjolras, said to him.
'You should get out more.
Give the girls a chance.
They'd be good for you, Marius.
Otherwise you'll turn into a priest!'
Marius paid little attention to his friend,
and continued his quiet life
of work, study and daily walks.
While walking around his part of the city,
Marius had noticed in elderly man and
a young girl in the Luxembourg Gardens.
They always sat next to each
other on the same bench.
The man, who was perhaps sixty, had white
hair and a serious but friendly-looking face.
The girl, who was aged thirteen or fourteen,
always wore the same badly-cut black dress.
She was very thin, almost ugly, but Marius
noticed that she had lovely blue eyes.
They seemed to be father and daughter.
Marius saw this couple frequently
on his regular walks in the Gardens.
But, although he was very interested in
them, they seemed not to notice him at all.
The girl was always talking happily,
while the man said very little.
He just looked at the girl from time to
time with an affectionate, fatherly smile.
Enjolras had often seen the couple, too.
'Do you know who they are?'
Marius asked him one day.
'I call the man M.
Leblanc, because of his white hair,
and the girl Mile Lanoire, because of
her black dress,' his friend replied.
***
For almost a year, Marius saw the old man and
the young girl daily in the
same place at the same time.
Then, for some reason, Marius stopped
going to the Luxembourg Gardens.
When he returned, one summer
morning six months later,
he saw the same couple sitting on the same
bench, but something amazing had happened.
The man was the same, but the thin,
plain girl of six months earlier
had become a beautiful young woman.
Her rough black dress had been
replaced by one of fine black silk.
She had soft brown hair, pale, smooth skin,
deep blue eyes and a lovely smile
that lit up her face like sunshine.
She looked up when Marius passed for the
second time, and gave him a casual glance.
Marius, however, walked on,
thinking of other things.
For the next few days he passed the bench
in the Gardens without looking at her.
Then one day, as he was passing,
thinking about nothing in particular,
the girl looked up at him and their eyes met.
A second later she looked away and
Marius walked on but, in a strange way,
he knew his life had changed.
What he had experienced in that moment was
not the honest, innocent gaze of a child.
It was something more than that.
Whatever it was, Marius sensed that, after
that moment, his life would never be the same.
The next day, Marius returned to the
Luxembourg Gardens wearing his best clothes.
He walked around slowly, stopping
to look at the ducks on the lake,
then casually approached the bench where
Mile Lanoire and her father were sitting.
As he walked past, he kept his eyes fixed on
the girl, but she did not seem to notice him.
She was talking quietly to her father, and Marius
could hear the soft, exciting murmur of her voice.
Without intending to, he stopped, turned
round and walked past the bench again.
He felt his face go red and his
heart beat loudly in his chest.
He was sure, this time, that she
had watched him as he passed.
He did not go back a third time, but sat down
on a bench at the opposite end of the Gardens.
He looked at the girl out
of the corner of his eye.
She seemed to fill the far end of
the Gardens with a kind of blue mist.
Taking a deep breath, he rose and was going to
pass the bench for a third time when he stopped.
He suddenly realized that, in his feverish
state, he had forgotten about the old man.
What would he be thinking when he saw a
strange young man walking backwards and
forwards in front of his bench? Without another
thought, Marius left the Gardens and went home.
He returned the next morning and sat on a
bench all day, pretending to read a book,
not daring to go near the bench where
the girl and her father were sitting.
He did the same every day for two weeks.
Towards the end of the second week,
while Marius was sitting in his usual
place, he looked up from his book.
And his face went pale.
Something had happened at
the far end of the Gardens.
M.
Leblanc and his daughter had risen from their
bench and were slowly walking in his direction.
Marius shut his book, opened it
again and made an effort to read.
When he felt that they were near him,
he looked up and saw that the girl was
looking steadily at him with a soft, thoughtful
gaze that made him tremble from head to foot.
He gazed after her until she
had disappeared from sight,
then rose to his feet and walked
around, laughing and talking to himself.
Finally he left the Gardens in the
mad hope of seeing her in the street,
but instead he met Enjolras,
who invited him to a meal.
Every day for the next month, Marius went to
the Luxembourg Gardens, excited by knowing
that the girl was secretly looking at him, but
too shy and embarrassed to know what to do.
He avoided walking directly in front
of the bench, partly from shyness,
partly because he did not want to
attract her father's attention.
Sometimes he stood for half an hour in a
place where her father could not see him,
looking at her and enjoying the
small, secret smiles she sent him.
But it seemed that M.
Leblanc had begun to suspect
what was happening because often,
when Marius appeared, he got to his feet and
walked away, taking his daughter with him.
Sometimes M.
Leblanc took his daughter to a different
bench, to see if Marius would follow them.
Marius failed to understand the trick,
and made the mistake of doing so.
Then M.
Leblanc became irregular in his visits and
did not always bring his daughter with him.
When this happened, Marius did not stay
in the Gardens, which was another mistake.
Marius was too much in love to think clearly.
His desire for the girl was growing
daily, and he dreamt of her every night.
One evening, he found a handkerchief
lying on the bench which M.
Leblanc and his daughter had just left.
It was a plain, white handkerchief
with the initials U.F.
in one corner.
'Ursula.'
Marius said the first name
that came into his head.
'A delicious name!'
He kissed the handkerchief,
breathed in its perfume,
wore it next to his heart by day and
kept it under his pillow at night.
'I can feel her whole soul in it!' he told himself
In fact, the handkerchief belonged to M.
Leblanc and had simply fallen out of his
pocket, but Marius was unaware of this.
He never appeared in the
Luxembourg Gardens without
the handkerchief pressed to his lips or his heart.
The girl could not understand his behaviour at
all, and looked at him with a puzzled expression.
'Such modesty!' Marius sighed.
Eventually, Marius was not satisfied
with just knowing the girl's name;
he wanted to know where she lived.
He found that she lived in a small house
at the quiet end of the rue de l'Ouest.
As well as the joy of seeing her in the Gardens,
he now had the pleasure of following her home.
One evening, having followed them
to the house and watched them enter,
he went in after them and spoke to the concierge.
The concierge, however, became suspicious,
thinking that Marius was connected with
the police, and refused to say anything.
The following day, M.
Leblanc and his daughter did
not come to the Gardens at all.
They did not come for a whole week,
and Marius began to feel depressed.
Every night he stood outside their house
and gazed up at their lighted windows.
Sometimes he saw a shadow pass in front
of a lamp, and his heart beat faster.
On the eighth night there
was no light in the windows.
Marius waited, his heart aching
with pain, until finally going home.
The next day they did not go to the Gardens,
so again Marius went to the
house as night was falling.
Once again, there were no lights in the windows.
He knocked on the door and spoke to the concierge.
'Where's the old gentleman?' he asked.
'He's left.'
Marius felt the blood leave his face.
Almost fainting, he asked in a
weak voice, 'When did he leave?'
'Yesterday.'
'Where has he gone?'
'I've no idea.'
'Did he leave an address?'
The concierge then recognized
Marius from the previous week.
He stared fiercely at him and said,
'So, it's you again! I was right.
You are some kind of policeman.'
With those words he slammed
the door in Marius's face.
CHAPTER SEVEN
The Jondrettes
Summer and autumn passed, and winter
came, but Marius saw no sign of M.
Leblanc or 'Ursula'.
He searched everywhere for
them, but without success.
He became like a homeless dog, wandering
the streets in a mood of dark despair.
Without 'Ursula', his life had become
meaningless, work disgusted him,
walking tired him, solitude bored him.
'If only I hadn't followed
them home,' he told himself.
'It gave me so much happiness
just to look at her, and now,
through my stupidity, I've lost even that.'
Enjolras and his other friends tried to
cheer him up by taking him to exciting
places, but these expeditions
always ended in the same way:
Marius would leave the group and walk around
the streets of Paris unhappily on his own.
One cold but sunny afternoon in February,
Marius was walking along the street when two
young girls dressed in rags ran into him.
One was tall and thin, the other smaller.
From what they were shouting at each other, he
understood that they were running from the police.
He stood for a moment staring after
them as they disappeared round a corner.
Then he noticed a small parcel
of papers lying on the ground.
Realizing that one of the
girls must have dropped it,
he picked it up and called
after them, but it was too late.
The girls had already disappeared from sight.
With a sigh, he put the package in
his pocket and went on to dinner.
That night at home, Marius opened the package
and found that it contained four letters,
all addressed to different people, and
smelling strongly of cheap tobacco.
Marius read the four letters and discovered
that they were all asking for money.
However, there was something strange about
them: although they all seemed to be written
by different people, they were written on
the same rough paper in the same handwriting.
He also noticed that each of them
had similar spelling mistakes.
Thinking no more about it, he
wrapped the letters up again,
threw them into a corner and went to bed.
The next morning, while he was working,
there was a gentle knock on his door.
'Come in,' Marius said, expecting
it to be the concierge, Mme Bougon.
But the voice that answered, saying, 'I beg your
pardon, Monsieur,' was not that of Mme Bougon.
It was more like the voice of a sick old man.
Marius looked up quickly and saw that his visitor
was a thin girl wearing just a skirt and shirt.
She looked cold and ill, and when she spoke,
Marius saw that she had lost several of her teeth.
There was, however, still a trace of
beauty in the sixteen-year-old lace,
like pale sunlight beneath the
thick clouds of a winter's dawn.
Marius rose to his feet, sure that he
had seen the girl somewhere before.
'What can I do for you, Mademoiselle?' he asked.
'I've got a letter for you, M.
Marius.'
Marius opened the letter and read:
My warm-hearted neighbour, I have heard of how
you kindly paid my rent for me six months ago.
I thank you for it.
But my eldest daughter will tell you that my wife
is sick and none of us have
had any food for four days.
Please, Monsieur, show us the
kindness of your generous heart again.
My daughter is at your service.
Yours truly, Jondrette.
Marius realized at once that the handwriting,
the yellow paper and the smell of cheap tobacco
was the same as in the four letters
he had read the previous evening.
He now had five letters,
all the work of one author:
the man who lived with his
family in the next room.
The Jondrette family had been Marius's neighbours
for many months, but he had never
before paid much attention to them.
This was why he had failed to recognize the
two daughters when they had
run into him on the street.
But now he understood that Jondrette's
business was writing dishonest letters,
asking for money from people he
imagined were wealthier than himself.
Marius looked up from the letter and watched
the girl moving fearlessly around his room,
studying the furniture and the mirror on the wall.
Her eyes lit up when she noticed
the books on his writing desk.
'Books!' she said, and then added with
pride, 'I know how to read and write.
Look, I'll show you.'
Picking up a pen that lay on the
table, she wrote on a piece of paper,
Be careful! The police are coming! She showed
Marius her work and then, changing the subject
quickly, for no reason at all, she gazed into
his eyes and said shyly, 'Do you know, M.
Marius, that you're a very handsome boy?'
Approaching him, she rested a cold red hand on
his shoulder and said, 'You never notice me, M.
Marius, but I know you.
I see you on the stairs, and I see you walking
around the streets, looking so sad and alone.'
Marius's cheeks went red.
He moved away from the girl's touch and said,
'I think, Mademoiselle, that I
have something belonging to you.'
He handed her the parcel of letters.
She clapped her hands and cried, 'We've
been looking for that everywhere!
How did you know they were mine?
Of course, the handwriting.
You were the man we ran into last night.'
While she talked excitedly, she
took out one of the letters.
'Ah, this is for the old man
who goes to church every day.
If I hurry, I might be able to catch him.
Perhaps he'll give me enough for a dinner.
We haven't eaten for three days...
'
Marius took a five-franc piece from
his pocket and handed it to the girl.
'The sun's come out at last!' she
cried, eagerly accepting the coin.
'That's enough food for two days.
You're a real gentleman, Monsieur.'
With those words, she gave
a little laugh and wave,
grabbed some dry bread from the table
and disappeared out of the door.
***
Marius had lived for five years without much
money, but he had never been really poor.
Now, after his conversation with the girl from the
next room, he understood what real poverty was.
Only a thin wall separated him from the
family of lost souls in the room next door.
He had heard them and seen them, but had paid
them no attention, and he suddenly felt guilty.
'If they had had another neighbour,' he
thought, 'one who had noticed their suffering,
perhaps they could have been rescued by now.'
As Marius was thinking about the sad
life of the family in the next room,
he stared dreamily at the
wall that separated them.
Then, in the top corner near the ceiling,
Marius saw that there was a triangular hole.
'Let's see what these people are
really like,' Marius thought.
'Then I'll be in a better position to help them.'
He stood on a cupboard, put his eye to the hole,
and looked through it into his neighbours' room.
The Jondrettes' room was dirty and evil-smelling,
unlike Marius's bare but clean room.
Its only furniture was a chair, an old table,
some cracked dishes and two dirty
beds, one on each side of a fireplace.
A man with a long, grey beard was sitting at
the table, writing a letter and smoking a pipe.
A large woman with greying hair,
once red, was sitting by the fire,
while a thin, pale-faced
child sat on one of the beds.
Marius, depressed at what he saw, was
going to get down from the cupboard
when the door of the Jondrettes' room
opened and the elder girl came in.
Slamming the door shut behind her she
cried victoriously, 'He's coming!'
'Who's coming?' Her father looked up.
'The old man who goes to church.
He's following me.
I saw him with his daughter in the
church, and gave him the letter.
He said he would follow me here.
I ran ahead to tell you he'll
be here in two minutes.'
'You're a good girl,' the man
said, rising quickly to his feet.
Then, turning to his wife, he said, 'Quickly!
Put out the fire!' While she poured water on
the flames, the man broke the chair with his foot
and told his younger daughter to break a window.
She put her fist through the glass and ran to her
bed, crying because her arm was covered in blood.
'Excellent,' her father smiled, tearing a
piece off his shirt and using it as a bandage.
'Now we're ready for the kind gentleman.
When he sees how miserable we are, he'll
give us a lot of money, you'll see.'
Moments later, there was a
gentle knock on the door.
Jondrette rushed to open it, bowing
almost to the ground as he did so.
'Please come in, my dear sir! Please
enter, with your charming young lady.'
An elderly man and a young girl
appeared in the doorway and Marius,
still looking through the hole in
the wall, could not believe his eyes.
It was She.
She! Everyone who has ever loved will
feel the force of that small word.
In the bright mist that clouded his vision,
Marius could hardly see the features of the sweet
face that had lit his life for six months and had
then disappeared, filling his life with darkness.
And now the vision had reappeared!
When Marius had recovered some of his senses, he
saw that she seemed a little paler than before.
Her companion as usual was M.
Leblanc.
As she entered the room, she
put a large parcel on the table.
'Monsieur, you will find some woollen
stockings and blankets in the parcel,' M.
Leblanc told Jondrette.
'You are extremely generous, Monsieur,'
Jondrette said, again bowing to the ground.
'But as you can see, we are
unfortunate in many ways.
We are without food,
Monsieur, and without heating.
No warmth for my unhappy children.
Our only chair is broken.
A broken window - in this weather! My wife
ill in bed and our younger daughter injured.'
'Oh, the poor child,' 'Ursula' said,
seeing the girl's bleeding wrist.
'She had an accident in the machine-shop where she
works for six sous an hour, 'Jondrette explained.
'They may have to cut off her arm.'
The daughter, taking her father's words
seriously, began to scream with fear.
While M.
Leblanc and 'Ursula' tried to comfort her,
Jondrette approached his wife and said in
a whisper, 'Take a good look at that man.'
He then returned to M.
Leblanc and told him about his debts.
'I owe sixty francs in rent,' he said.
M.
Leblanc took a coin out of his
pocket and put it on the table.
'Five francs is all I have with me,' he said.
'But I'll take my daughter home and come
back this evening with more money for you.'
Jondrette accompanied M.
Leblanc and 'Ursula' out of the door
and, after a few minutes' indecision,
Marius jumped down from the cupboard
and ran out into the street.
But he was too late; their
carriage had already gone.
Miserably, he turned back to the house.
He went into his room, pushing the door
behind him, but the door would not shut.
Turning, Marius saw that a
hand was holding it open.
'What is it?' he demanded.
It was the Jondrette girl.
'So it's you again,' he said almost fiercely.
'What do you want now?'
She did not reply but stood
thoughtfully looking at him,
seeming to have lost all her earlier confidence.
She had not entered the room, but was still
standing in the half-light of the corridor.
'What do you want?' Marius repeated angrily.
'M.
Marius,' she said at last, a faint
light in her sad eyes, 'you seem upset.
What's the matter?'
'Nothing.
Now please leave me alone.'
Marius tried again to shut the
door, but she still held it open.
'You're making a mistake,' she said.
'You aren't rich, but you
were generous this morning.
You've been kind to us - now
I want to be kind to you.
Is there anything that I can do?'
Marius considered her offer, then had an idea.
Moving closer to her, he said,
'Do you know the address of those
people who've just left your room?'
'No.'
'Can you find out for me?'
'Is that what you want?' she said,
a disappointed look on her face.
'Yes.'
The girl looked hard at him for a minute.
'What will you give me?' she said at last.
'Anything you want.'
'Anything?'
'Yes.'
'Then I'll get it.'
She left immediately, closing the door behind her.
Marius sat down and buried his face in his
hands, too overcome by emotion to think clearly.
But then he heard a loud voice from the next room.
'I tell you I'm sure.'
Jondrette was speaking to his wife.
'I recognized him.'
Without another thought, Marius jumped on to
the cupboard and looked again
through the hole in the wall.
'Really?' His wife looked puzzled.
'Are you sure?'
'Of course I'm sure.
It's been eight years, but
I recognized him at once.'
He told the two girls to leave the room and then,
when alone with his wife, he said,
'And I recognized the girl too.
I'm surprised you didn't.'
'Why should I? I've never seen her'
But Jondrette bent down and
whispered something in her ear.
Straightening up, he said,
'Now do you recognize her?'
'Her?' said the woman, her
voice filled with sudden hatred.
'Are you sure? That's impossible!' she cried.
'Our daughters barefoot and
without a dress between them,
while she wears leather boots and
a fur coat? You must be wrong.
You've forgotten, that child was
ugly, and this one's not bad-looking.'
'I tell you, it's the same girl.
You'll see.
And I'll tell you another thing.
She's going to make us a fortune.
I'm tired of being poor.
We deserve a better life, and this is our chance.'
'What do you mean?'
'He said he'll be here at six
o'clock, with sixty francs.
I'll bring some friends round, and we'll
make sure he gives us a lot more money.'
'What will you do if he
doesn't give you more money?'
Jondrette stroked his beard and laughed.
'We'll know what to do about it.'
And then, as he was going to leave the
room, he turned to his wife and said,
'You know, it's lucky he didn't recognize me.
If he had, he wouldn't be coming back here again.
It's the beard that saved me -
my lovely, long, romantic beard!'
With an ugly laugh, he pulled his cap
down over his eyes and left the room.
***
Although Marius was a dreamer and not a man of
action, he knew immediately that he had to save M.
Leblanc and 'Ursula' from the trap
that Jondrette was setting for them.
But what could he do? He could not warn M.
Leblanc because he did not
know the old man's address.
There was only one thing to
do: he had to tell the police.
Half an hour later, Marius was
at the nearest police station.
The desk clerk showed him into the police
chief's office, where a tall man with a
wide face and a thin, tight mouth was
trying to keep warm next to a tire.
'Are you the chief of police?' Marius asked.
'He's away,' the tall man said.
'I'm Inspector Javert.
Now, what do you want?'
Marius told Javert about the morning's events.
When he told Javert his address, he noticed the
inspector's eyes light up with great interest.
Then, when everything had been
explained, Javert thought for a moment.
Finally, he asked Marius for his
door key and told him to go home
and hide quietly in his room so that
his neighbours would think he was out.
'Take these with you,' the inspector
went on, producing two small guns.
'When the old man and the girl
arrive, let them start their business.
When you think it's getting
dangerous, shoot one of these guns.
After that, I'll take charge.'
Back in his room, Marius sat
down nervously on his bed.
It was nearly six o'clock.
Outside it had stopped snowing, and a full moon
was growing steadily brighter above the mist.
Suddenly, he heard voices.
Taking off his boots, he quietly climbed on to the
cupboard and looked through the hole in the wall.
A fire burned in the corner of the
room, filling it with blood-red light.
Jondrette, who had just come in,
was shaking snow from his shoes.
'Everything's arranged,' he said.
'Has the concierge gone out?'
'Yes,' his wife said.
'And you're sure he's not in next door?'
'Positive.'
'Good.'
Then he turned to his daughters.
'Now, you two must go and
keep guard in the street,
one by the gate, one at the street corner.'
'A fine job!' the elder girl called back.
'Keeping guard barefoot in the snow.'
'Tomorrow you'll have fur boots!'
her father called out after her.
A few minutes later, there was nobody in the
building except for Marius and the Jondrettes.
Marius watched as Jondrette put a metal bar in
the fire and inspected a rope ladder on the table.
Next, he opened a drawer, took out a long
knife and tested its blade with his finger.
Suddenly, at exactly six o'clock, the
door into the Jondrettes' room opened.
'Welcome, Monsieur, 'Jondrette
said, rising to his feet.
M.
Leblanc appeared and put four coins on the table.
'That is for your rent and
food, Monsieur,' he said.
'Now we must discuss what else is needed.'
Jondrette quietly told his
wife to dismiss the carriage,
and when she had left the room,
turned back to his visitor.
'How is the wounded child?' M.
Leblanc asked him.
'Not well.'
Jondrette smiled sadly.
'She's in great pain.
Her sister has taken her to
hospital, but they'll be back soon.'
The conversation continued politely
in this way for several minutes.
M.
Leblanc asked Jondrette about his circumstances,
and Jondrette smiled sadly
as he invented lie after lie.
Finally, Jondrette picked up a large picture that
was leaning against the wall, and showed it to M.
Leblanc.
'What's that?' M.
Leblanc said, looking at the badly-drawn
picture of a soldier in uniform.
'It's a work of art,' Jondrette informed him.
'I love this picture as much
as I love my two daughters.
But, unfortunately, I have to sell it.
What do you think it's worth?'
'It's just an old inn-sign.
It's worth about three francs.'
'I'll accept a thousand,'
Jondrette softly replied.
M.
Leblanc rose and, standing with his back
to the wall, looked quickly round the room.
Jondrette was on his left, his wife was
standing on his right near the door.
Jondrette put the picture down and
stepped quietly towards the old man.
'You don't recognize me, do you?'
he said in a loud, clear voice.
At this signal, which he had
pre-arranged with his friends,
three men armed with metal
poles rushed into the room.
M.
Leblanc grew pale, and gripped the back
of the broken chair with his huge hands.
Marius, meanwhile, raised his right hand
with the gun, ready to fire the warning shot.
'The carriage is ready?'
Jondrette asked the three men.
'Yes, with two good horses,' one of them replied.
'Excellent.'
He turned to M.
Leblanc and repeated his earlier question.
'You still don't recognize me, do you?'
'No.'
'My name isn't Jondrette.
It's Thenardier.
Now do you recognize me?'
M.
Leblanc trembled slightly,
but still shook his head.
Marius, however, who had been going to fire
the gun as a signal for the police to arrive,
shook so much that he almost
fell off the cupboard.
'Thenardier,' he thought.
'That's the name of the man who saved my
father's life at the Battle of Waterloo.
The man I've promised to help!'
If he fired the warning shot, M.
Leblanc would be saved and
Thenardier would be destroyed.
But he would also have broken
his promise to his father.
He felt his knees grow weak.
What should he do?
Thenardier walked up and down in front of M.
Leblanc.
'Do you remember the little inn
in Montfermeil eight years ago?
You took away our Cosette, do you
remember? Wearing that old yellow coat,
pretending you were a tramp! Well, now
you're going to learn that you can't make
things right by just bringing a few hospital
blankets! You're the cause of all my troubles.
For 1500 francs you took away a girl
who was bringing me lots of money.'
'I don't know what you're talking about,' M.
Leblanc said.
'I don't know who you are,
but I know what you are.
You're a dirty criminal.'
'A criminal?' Thenardier said, suddenly angry.
'That's what you rich people call people like me,
isn't it? Just because I've failed in business.
I was a war hero, you know - I saved
an officer's life at Waterloo! And you
call me a criminal! Well, I'm
going to teach you a lesson.'
He began to move towards M.
Leblanc, but the old man was too quick for him.
With surprising speed, he pushed the table
and chair to one side and ran to the window.
He managed to open it but, before he could jump,
the three men jumped on him
and held him to the floor.
This was too much for Marius.
'Forgive me, father,' he murmured,
preparing to fire the gun.
But suddenly Thenardier cried, 'Don't hurt him!'
After a long fight, M.
Leblanc was tied up and taken to the bed.
'No wallet?' Thenardier cried,
having searched his pockets.
'Never mind.'
He sat on the bed next to the helpless but brave
old man, and said, 'Let's discuss things quietly.
All I'm asking for is 200,000 francs.
I realize that you don't have the money with
you now, but I want you to write a letter.
I'll tell you what to say.'
He untied M.
Leblanc's right hand and,
producing a pen and paper, began:
My dearest daughter, You must come at once.
I need you urgently.
The person who gives you this
note will bring you to me.
I shall be waiting.
M.
Leblanc signed his name Urbain Fabre,
which seemed to satisfy Thenardier,
and wrote an address on the envelope.
Thenardier then took the
letter and gave it to his wife.
'There's a carriage outside.
Don't be long.'
Nearly half an hour passed.
Thenardier seemed lost in his own dark thoughts.
The prisoner did not move.
Finally, there was the sound of
horses in the street outside and,
moments later, the door to
the room was thrown open.
'It's a false address,' Mme Thenardier cried.
'There's no Urbain Fabre.
The old man's been lying to us!'
Thenardier sat on the corner of the
table in silence for some moments,
swinging his leg and gazing with
a fierce satisfaction at the fire.
Then he turned to the prisoner and
said in a slow, threatening voice,
'What did you hope to gain by
giving me a false name and address?'
'Time!' cried the prisoner in a
loud voice, jumping from the bed,
having secretly cut the ropes that tied him.
Before the others in the room could react, M.
Leblanc was standing by the fire,
holding a metal bar above his head.
'I'm not afraid of you,' he said.
'But neither should you fear me.'
With those words he threw the metal bar
out of the window into the street below.
'Get him!' Thenardier shouted.
'He's defenceless.'
Two men grabbed him by the shoulders.
'Now cut his throat!' Thenardier called.
Marius stared, frozen with fear as Thenardier,
knife in hand, stood hesitating a
few steps away from the prisoner.
The brave man was in terrible danger,
but Marius still could not fire the gun.
Then, in the moonlight, he saw
the solution to his problem.
On top of the cupboard, by his feet,
he noticed the piece of paper that
the elder daughter had written on:
Be careful! The police are coming!
He immediately saw what he had to do.
He took a piece of brick from the
wall, wrapped the piece of paper
around it and threw it through the hole
into the middle of Thenardier's room.
He was just in time.
Thenardier was advancing towards his prisoner,
knife in hand, when his wife
cried, 'Something fell!'
She picked up the piece of paper and handed
it to her husband, who read it quickly.
'It's Eponine's handwriting!'
he cried a moment later.
'Quick! Get the ladder.
The police are coming and we've got to go!'
They threw the rope ladder from the open
window but, before they could escape,
the door opened and Inspector Javert walked in.
'Relax,' he smiled.
'You can't escape through the window.
There are five of you, and fifteen of us.
You have no chance.
Why not come quietly?'
The men put down their weapons
and surrendered without a fight.
When everybody had been arrested and taken
from the room, Javert noticed the prisoner,
who was standing, head bowed, by the window.
He turned to speak to another policeman but, when
he looked back, he saw that the prisoner had gone.
Javert rushed to the open window and looked down.
The rope ladder was swinging
gently above the empty street.
'He must have been the cleverest of them
all, 'Javert murmured angrily to himself.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Marius and Cosette
Not wishing to give evidence against Thenardier
in court, Marius made immediate
arrangements to leave his room.
Early the following morning,
he paid the concierge his final rent and
went to live with his friend, Enjolras.
Inspector Javert looked for Marius
everywhere, but without success.
Two months later, Marius was deeply unhappy.
He sent money every Monday to Thenardier,
who was in prison, which meant that
he had even less money for himself.
But the main reason for his unhappiness was that
he was forced to live his life
with no hope of seeing 'Ursula'.
One afternoon he was sitting in a
field, looking down at a small river,
when his dreams of 'Ursula' were suddenly
broken by the sound of a familiar voice.
He looked up and recognized
Eponine, Thenardiers elder daughter.
Still wearing the same rags, with
the same bold look in her eyes and
the same rough voice, she had
somehow become more beautiful.
She stared at Marius with a look
of pleasure on her pale face,
and for some moments seemed unable to speak.
'So at last I've found you,' she finally said.
'I've been looking for you everywhere.
You aren't living in the same room any more?'
'No,' said Marius.
'Well, I can understand that.
It's not nice, that sort of thing.
But why are you wearing that dirty old hat?
'When Marius gave no answer, she went
on, 'And you've got a hole in your shirt.
I'll mend it for you.
A young man like you ought to be nicely dressed.'
Marius still said nothing, and
after a moments pause she said,
'You don't seem very glad to see me, but I
could make you look happy if I wanted to!'
'How?' said Marius.
'What do you mean?'
'You weren't so unfriendly last time.'
'I'm sorry, but what do you mean?'
She bit her lip and hesitated, as if
trying to make up her mind about something.
Finally, she said, 'I've got the address.'
Marius's heart seemed to miss a beat.
'You mean
'The address you wanted me to find out.
The young lady, you know...'
Her voice sank into a sigh.
Marius jumped up and took her by the hand.
'Let's go at once!' he
cried, wild with excitement.
Then he suddenly frowned and
seized Eponine by the arm.
'But you must promise me,' he said, 'that
you'll never tell your father the address.'
'I promise,' the girl replied,
staring at Marius with amusement.
They had only gone a few steps
when Eponine stopped and said,
'You remember you promised me something?'
Marius felt in his pocket.
All he had in the world was the five-franc
piece he intended to give her father in prison.
He pushed it into her hand, but she opened her
fingers and let the coin fall to the ground.
She looked at him with a mixture of
disappointment and sadness in her eyes.
'I don't want your money,' she said.
***
That evening, Cosette was alone in the house which
Jean Valjean had bought about a year earlier.
It was a small house in a back
street, with a large, wild garden.
Valjean had gone away on
business for a couple of days,
and Cosette was in the downstairs
sitting room, playing the piano.
Suddenly, she thought she heard the
sound of footsteps in the garden.
She listened at the window for a
minute, then ran up to her bedroom,
opened the window and looked out.
The moonlit garden and the street
beyond it were completely empty.
Cosette, not a nervous girl by nature, smiled
to herself and thought no more about it.
The next evening, as she
was walking in the garden,
she was sure that she heard
someone moving in the trees.
Again, when she looked round, she saw nothing.
When Jean Valjean returned from
his business the following day,
Cosette told him about the noises in the garden.
He told her not to worry, but she
noticed an anxious look in his eyes.
He spent the next two nights walking around the
garden, checking the gate, listening for noises,
but nothing unusual happened.
Then one morning, a few days later, Cosette
noticed a large stone lying on the garden bench.
Nervously, she picked it up and
discovered an envelope underneath it.
Inside, there was a small
notebook filled with love poems.
Cosette sat down and began to read,
enjoying the music of the language
and the beauty of the handwriting.
She had never read anything like this
before, and it affected her deeply.
Her heart on fire, she took the notebook upstairs
to her bedroom and read every word again.
She remembered the handsome young man she
had seen so often in the Luxembourg Gardens.
As she read the notebook, she
knew in her heart that he was
the author of these beautiful, romantic words.
Finally, she kissed the book, held it
to her heart and waited for the evening,
when she knew that something
special was going to occur.
That evening, Jean Valjean went out.
Cosette spent a long time in front of the mirror,
making her hair look beautiful
and deciding which dress to wear.
Finally, she went out into the garden.
She sat on the bench where
she had found the notebook
and, moments later, had the strange
feeling that she was being watched.
She looked round and jumped to her feet.
It was He!
He looked paler and thinner than she remembered.
His dark clothes were almost
invisible in the shadows,
and his face shone softly in the fading light.
Cosette felt suddenly faint, but
she did not move or make a sound.
'Forgive me for being here.'
Marius spoke at last.
'But I've been so unhappy.
Do you recognize me? You mustn't be afraid.
It's a long time ago, but do you remember the day
when you first looked at me - in the Luxembourg
Gardens? And the day you walked past me?
Those things happened nearly a year ago.
Forgive me for talking like this, I don't know
what I'm saying - perhaps I'm annoying you?
But the truth is, I can't live without you.'
'Mother!' Cosette murmured, and began to fall.
Marius caught her and held her tightly in his arms
without realizing what he was
doing, lost in a mist of love.
Cosette, feeling her body close to his, took
his hand and pressed it against her heart.
Aware of the shape of the notebook under her
dress, he said, 'So, you've read my notebook.
Do you love me, too?'
'Of course,' she answered in a low voice.
'You know I do.'
Then, as if by magic, her lips were
next to his and they were kissing.
Afterwards, they sat together on the garden bench
in a state of shock, neither of them speaking.
Beneath the stars, they were happy just to look
into each others eyes and hold each other's hands.
Then, at last, they began to speak.
They talked all evening about
their dreams, their mistakes,
their moments of happiness,
their moments of despair.
When everything had been said, she laid her head
on his shoulder and asked, 'What's your name?'
'My name's Marius.
And yours?'
'Cosette.'
During that month of May in the
year 1832, Cosette and Marius met
every day in the wild garden
of that small, secret house.
They would sit and hold hands and talk, or
just gaze into each other's eyes and smile.
'How lovely you are,' Marius would sigh.
'There are moments when I think this is a dream.
There are other moments when
I think I'm a little mad.
I love you so much.'
To which Cosette would reply, 'I love
you more with every minute that passes.'
In this way, bathed in happiness,
they lived untroubled by the world.
***
One beautiful, starry evening, Marius found
Cosette sitting unhappily in her garden.
'What's the matter?' he asked,
sitting next to her on the bench.
'My father said that we may
have to leave,' she replied.
Marius trembled.
For six weeks, he had known nothing
but uncomplicated happiness.
Now, for the first time, there was a
cloud in the clear blue sky of his life.
He could not speak, and Cosette
felt his hand grow cold.
She asked, as he had done, 'What's the matter?'
He replied, in a voice so low
that she could hardly hear it,
'I don't understand what you mean.'
'Father told me this morning
that I have to pack everything
and be ready to leave for England within a week.'
Marius rose to his feet and said
coldly, 'Cosette, are you going?'
She looked up at him, her
pale face lined with misery.
'What else can I do?' she cried.
'So you're leaving me.'
'Oh, Marius, why are you being so cruel to me?'
Marius turned his back to her and
said, 'Then I shall have to go away.'
'No, Marius, wait.
I've got an idea.'
Marius turned and was
surprised to see her smiling.
'What is it?'
'If we go, you must come too.
I'll tell you where, and you must
meet me there, wherever it is.'
'How can I possibly do that?' he cried.
'Are you crazy? You need money to go
to England, and I haven't got any.
I haven't told you, Cosette, but I'm a poor man.
I wear a cheap hat, my jacket has lost half
its buttons and there are holes in my boots.'
He turned away from her and
stood with his face pressed
to the trunk of a tree, almost ready to faint.
He stayed in that position for some time.
Finally, he heard a small sound behind him and,
turning round, he saw that Cosette was in tears.
He fell on his knees in front of her
and pressed her hand to his lips.
'Don't cry,' he said.
'I cannot let you leave me.
I promise you that if you leave me, I shall die.
But listen to me - I have a plan.
Don't expect me here tomorrow.'
'Why not?' Cosette said, drying her tears.
'A whole day without seeing
you! That's unbearable!'
'It's worth losing a day together if we
want to be happy for the rest of our lives.'
'But what are you going to do?'
'Wait until the day after tomorrow.
I'll tell you then.
But until then, I must give you my address.
I'm living with a friend of mine, Enjolras.'
Marius then took a knife out
of his pocket and scratched
his address on the wall - 16, rue de la Verrerie.'
'Please, Marius,' Cosette said as she watched him.
'Where are you going tomorrow evening? I
won't be able to sleep if you don't tell me.'
'I'm going to try something.'
'Well, I'll pray for you to succeed
and I'll never stop thinking about you.
I'll ask no more questions, but you must
promise to be here early the day after tomorrow.
Not later than nine o'clock.'
'I promise,' Marius said.
CHAPTER NINE
Monsieur Gillenormand
M.
Gillenormand, Marius's grandfather,
was now ninety years old.
He was unhappy about many things - about losing
his teeth, about the political situation but, most
of all, about the fact that he had not seen his
grandson for four years, since their big quarrel.
Although he was too proud to admit he
was wrong, and although he was angry, M.
Gillenormand hoped that Marius, whom
he still loved, would return one day.
One evening in June, M.
Gillenormand was sitting in front of a large fire,
staring into the flames and
thinking bitterly of Marius.
He was feeling depressed, because he realized that
he would probably never see his grandson again.
While he was gazing into the
fire, thinking these sad thoughts,
his old servant entered the room
and asked, 'Will Monsieur receive M.
Marius?'
For a moment all the blood seemed to leave M.
Gillenormand's face, and the servant
began to worry that his master was ill.
But the old man finally raised his head
and said, in a low voice, 'Show him in.'
Marius stood uncertainly in the doorway.
The poor condition of his clothes could not
be seen in the half-darkness of the room.
Nothing of him was clearly
visible except his face,
which was calm and serious, but strangely sad.
M.
Gillenormand stared at his
grandson with disbelief.
At last! After four years! Was it really
him? He wanted to open his arms and hug him,
but all he said was, 'What have you come for?'
Marius murmured something in embarrassment.
'I can't hear you,' the old
man said, looking annoyed.
'Have you come to apologize? Do
you now see that you were wrong?'
'No, Monsieur.'
Marius lowered his eyes.
'Well then,' the old man
shouted, 'what do you want?'
'Monsieur, I ask you to have pity on me.
I know I'm not welcome here, but I
have come to ask for only one thing.
Then I'll go away at once.'
'You're a young fool,' the old man said.
'Who said you had to go away?
You left me - your grandfather! - to join in those
street protests against the government, I suppose.
You're probably in trouble with the police, or
you're in debt, and you've run back to me for help
'Monsieur, it's none of those things.'
'Well, what is it exactly that you want?'
'I have come to ask your
permission to get married.'
The old man paused for a moment before saying,
'So, you want to get married
at the age of twenty-one.
I suppose you've got some sort of career,
now? Perhaps you've made a fortune.
What do you earn as a lawyer?'
'Nothing.'
'Well then, I imagine the
lucky girl must have money.'
'She's no richer than I am.'
'What does her father do?'
'I don't know.'
M.
Gillenormand turned away with disgust.
'So that's it.
Twenty-one years old, no job, no money.
Your wife will have to count the sous
when she goes to the market, won't she?'
'I beg you, Monsieur,' Marius cried.
'I love her so much.
Please allow me to marry her!'
The old man gave a high, unpleasant laugh.
'So you said to yourself, "I'll have
to go and see him, that old fool.
He'll be so happy to see me
that he won't care who I marry.
I haven't a pair of shoes, and she
hasn't a shirt, but never mind.
I'm going to throw away my youth, my career,
my whole life, and dive into poverty
with a woman around my neck...
" That's what you think, isn't it?
Well, my boy, you can do whatever you want.
But I will never give you my permission! Never!'
'Grandfather
'Never!'
The tone of his grandfather's
voice robbed Marius of all hope.
He rose and crossed the room
slowly, with his head bowed.
He had just reached the door, however, when M.
Gillenormand moved quickly towards him,
pulled him back into the room
and pushed him into an armchair.
'Tell me about it,' he said to Marius, who
stared back with silent amazement, unaware
that the word 'grandfather' was responsible
for the change in the old man's behaviour.
'Come on, tell me about your love affairs.
Don't be afraid to talk.
Don't forget, I'm your grandfather.
Here...
' he said, taking a purse from a
drawer and putting it on the table.
'Here's some money for you.
Buy yourself some new clothes.'
Marius told his grandfather all about
Cosette and how much he loved her.
M.
Gillenormand listened carefully and,
when Marius had finished, he laughed.
'You must enjoy yourself
when you're young,' he said.
'But you must also be sensible.
Don't get married yet, that's my advice.
Have fun with the girl, but don't marry her.
Make her your lover but not your wife.'
Marius, too shocked to reply, shook
his head and rose to his feet.
He then turned slowly to the old man, bowed deeply
and said, 'Four years ago you insulted my father.
Today you have insulted my future wife.
I shall ask no more favours of you, Monsieur.
Goodbye.'
M.
Gillenormand called for Marius to
come back, but it was too late.
The proud young man had closed the door and gone.
'Oh my God,' the old man cried,
burying his face in his hands.
'What have I done? This
time he'll never come back.'
***
Marius left his grandfathers
house in a state of despair,
and returning to his room, fell
asleep fully-dressed on the bed.
When he woke up, Enjolras was in
the room with a few other friends.
They all looked very nervous
and excited about something.
'What's the matter?' Marius asked sleepily
'Are you coming to the
funeral of General Lamarque?'
'Who's he?'
Enjolras and his friends shook their heads with
amazement at their friend's lack of
awareness, and soon left the room.
Marius opened a drawer and took out the two guns
which Inspector Javert had lent him in February.
Putting them in his jacket pocket, he went out and
continued to wander aimlessly around the streets,
noticing only occasionally the strange atmosphere
of excitement that was growing in the town.
People were running around, and there was a
lot of noise, but Marius paid little attention.
He could think of only one thing: his
meeting later that evening with Cosette.
This would be his last brief happiness;
after that, there would be only darkness.
At nine o'clock that evening, Marius
crept into the garden of Cosette's house,
but she was not there waiting
for him as she had promised.
Looking up, he saw that there were no lights on
in the house and that all the windows were closed.
Unable to control himself, he beat his
fists against the walls of the house.
'Cosette!' he cried, not caring who heard him.
'Where are you?'
He called her name again and again until,
exhausted, he sat down on the stone steps.
Now she was gone, he told
himself, he had no future.
There was nothing for him to do except die.
Suddenly he heard a voice calling
through the trees from the street.
'M.
Marius!'
He looked up.
'Who's that?'
'Is that you, M.
Marius?'
'Yes.'
'Your friends are waiting for you at
the barricade in the rue de Chanvrerie.'
Marius ran to the gate and was just
in time to see the figure of Eponine,
Thenardier's daughter, disappearing into
the shadows at the end of the street.
CHAPTER TEN
The Barricade
In the spring of 1832, the people
of Paris were ready for revolution.
Charles X, who had become king in 1824, believed
that he had total power over the French people.
He was a strong supporter of the
Catholic church and the aristocracy,
and he took away the freedoms that
Napoleon had given the ordinary citizens.
Although this made him very unpopular,
he thought that his opponents would be
too weak to prevent him from doing what he wanted.
He was wrong.
In 1830, there was a peaceful
revolution, and he was forced to leave.
The new king, Louis-Philippe, was a brave
and clever man who loved his country.
The ordinary people liked him at
first, but he soon showed that he
was more interested in power for his
family than democracy for his people.
He understood business, but he could not
understand the problems of poor people.
Neither could he understand the
concept of freedom of speech,
and he often sent soldiers into the streets to
attack people who were making public protests.
As the summer approached, the mood of the
workers and the poor became angrier and angrier.
Their anger exploded into violence in
June 1832, when General Lamarque died.
The General had been very popular with the people
of France because of his love for Napoleon.
The day of his funeral was arranged for
5 June, and thousands of people saw this
as a chance to make a public protest
against the king and his government.
At first, the funeral went quietly.
Soldiers accompanied the coffin as
it was carried slowly across Paris.
A large crowd followed behind, waving
flags and carrying swords and heavy sticks.
The crowd grew more and more excited,
until finally they tried to take the coffin away
from the soldiers and carry it across a bridge.
Their exit was blocked by
more soldiers on horseback.
For a moment, nothing happened.
Then there were two gunshots.
The first shot killed the commander of the
soldiers guarding the exit to the bridge.
The second killed a deaf old woman
who was trying to shut her window.
Then the fighting started.
Soldiers attacked the crowd with swords; the crowd
threw stones and ran screaming across the bridge.
Minutes later, the sounds of war
echoed across the whole city of Paris.
***
As soon as the fighting started, Enjolras
and several of his friends started to
build a barricade outside the Corinth
wine shop in the rue de la Chanvrerie,
a small street surrounded by dark
alleys in the market district of Paris.
Enjolras had been joined by many strangers as he
and his friends had run shouting along the street.
There was a tall, grey-haired man
whom nobody knew, but whose strong,
brave face had impressed everybody.
There were several street children, excited
by the sound of battle, who also joined them.
One of these children was Eponine,
who had dressed like a boy so that
no one would tell her to go home.
Having run to tell Marius that
his friends were waiting for him,
she was helping Enjolras and his
companions to build the barricade.
New people arrived all the time,
bringing with them gunpowder and
weapons to fight the soldiers
who would be arriving very soon.
Enjolras, who was the leader of the rebels,
organized the building of a second barricade and
the manufacture of bullets from melted silver.
The tall, grey-haired man was doing
useful work on the larger barricade,
and Eponine (whom everyone thought
was a boy) worked hard too.
The barricades were finished in less than an hour
and, with the sound of drums in the city growing
louder, Enjolras brought a table out into the
street and sat down with his friends for a drink.
Night fell, but nothing happened.
While the fifty men behind the barricade
waited impatiently for the arrival of sixty
thousand soldiers, Enjolras
approached the tall, grey-haired man.
'Who are you?' he asked.
When the man said nothing,
Enjolras became suspicious.
'You're a policeman, aren't you?' he said.
The man smiled and eventually
admitted that he was.
'My name's Javert,' he said.
Before he could move, Enjolras
ordered four men to search him.
When they found a letter in his pocket which
proved that he had been sent to spy on them,
they tied him to a post inside the inn,
'You'll be shot two minutes before the
barricade falls,' Enjolras informed him.
***
Marius left the garden and, mad
with grief at losing Cosette,
walked towards the sound of drums and
gunfire in the centre of the city.
He had only one thought in
his mind: he wanted to die.
Marius pushed his way through
the crowds of frightened,
murmuring people that filled the streets
until he reached the market area.
Here, he found the unlit streets
suddenly filled with soldiers.
Unafraid, Marius ran through the
shadows, ignoring shouts for him to stop.
Someone fired a gun and a bullet hit a
wall just behind him, but he didn't care.
He was just approaching the rue de Chanvrerie when
he heard a loud voice calling from the shadows:
'Who's there?'
'The French Revolution!' he heard a distant
voice reply - the voice of his friend, Enjolras.
Marius stood behind an alley
wall, hidden in the shadows.
Around the corner, he could see
a row of soldiers aiming their
guns down the rue de Chanvrerie,
waiting for the order to fire.
'Fire!' the order finally came.
The street was lit with a sudden flash of
light and filled with the thunder of gunfire.
Then the soldiers attacked.
Marius stood up and ran along
a series of alleys that led
into the rue de la Chanvrerie,
behind the Corinth wine shop.
When he reached the stronghold,
soldiers were already climbing the
barricade, shooting at the rebels.
Marius saw a soldier attacking Enjolras, who
had fallen backwards and was calling for help.
Marius took Javert's guns from his
pockets and shot the soldier dead.
Soldiers now occupied the top of the barricade,
but were unable to advance any further
because the defenders fought so fiercely.
Marius, who had thrown away his
guns and was now without a weapon,
began to move towards a barrel of gunpowder
he had seen near the door of the wine shop.
He did not notice a soldier aiming his gun at him.
Neither did he see, at the moment the
soldier fired, a young boy dressed in
rags jump in front of the gun and fall wounded as
the bullet meant for Marius hit him in the hand.
'Put down your weapons and surrender!' a
soldier called from the top of the barricade.
'Fire!' Enjolras shouted.
The soldiers and the rebels fired
at each other at the same time,
filling the air with thick clouds of dark smoke.
When the smoke cleared, there were
many dead bodies on both sides.
The survivors were reloading their guns in
silence, when suddenly a loud voice called,
'Get out now, or I'll blow up the barricade!'
All heads turned to stare in
the direction of the voice.
Marius was standing at the foot of the barricade,
holding a flaming torch
above a barrel of gunpowder.
'If you blow up the barricade,' a sergeant
called, 'you'll blow up yourself as well!'
Marius smiled and lowered the
torch towards the gunpowder.
Within seconds, the soldiers had left
the barricade, leaving their dead and
wounded behind, and were running into the
darkness at the far end of the street.
Enjolras threw his arms around Marius's neck.
'So you've come!' he cried.
Marius hugged Enjolras and many
other friends he recognized.
While the soldiers waited at the far
end of the street for further orders,
and the rebels removed dead bodies from
the barricade and took care of the wounded,
Marius walked around the
stronghold in a kind of dream.
After two months of happiness with
Cosette, he was now in the middle of a war.
He could not believe this was happening to him.
He was so confused that he
did not recognize Javert,
tied to a post inside the
inn throughout the battle.
As he was walking by the smaller barricade,
his thoughts were interrupted by a weak
voice calling his name from the shadows.
'M.
Marius!'
He looked about him but, seeing
no one, he started to walk away,
thinking that he was imagining things.
'M.
Marius!' He heard the voice again.
Marius gazed into the shadows,
but could still see nothing.
'I'm at your feet,' the voice said.
Looking down, Marius saw a dark shape
crawling along the ground towards him.
By the light of a lamp on the pavement,
he could see a torn jacket, trousers
with holes in them, and two bare feet.
A white face was turned towards him and the
voice asked, 'Do you recognize me? It's Eponine.'
Marius bent down quickly, and saw
that it was indeed that unhappy girl,
dressed in a man's clothes.
'What are you doing here?' he said.
Then, noticing the pool of blood
on the ground behind her, cried,
'You're wounded! I'll carry you to the inn.
They'll take care of you there.
Is it very bad?'
She showed him the bullet hole in her hand.
'A soldier was going to shoot you,' she
said, her voice no more than a whisper.
'But I put my hand in front of his gun.'
'You poor child,' Marius said.
'We'll put a bandage on that wound immediately.
You'll be all right.'
'The bullet passed through my hand,' Eponine
murmured, 'but it came out through my back.
It's no use trying to move me, but I'll tell you
how you can treat my wound better than any doctor.
Sit down on that stone, close beside me.'
Marius sat next to her.
She rested her head on his knee and said
without looking at him, 'Oh, what happiness.
Now I don't feel any pain,'
For a moment she was silent.
She pressed her hand to her chest, from
which blood was pouring like dark wine.
Then, with a great effort, she
raised herself on one arm and,
struggling for breath, looked into Marius's eyes.
'I can't cheat you,' she said at last.
'I have a letter for you in my pocket.
I've had it since yesterday.
I was asked to post it, but I didn't.
I didn't want you to get it.
But now we're both going to die, it doesn't
matter, does it? I can't be jealous any more.
Take your letter.'
She took hold of Marius's hand
with her wounded hand and,
without seeming to feel the pain, guided it
to her pocket, from which he took the letter.
'Now you must promise me something
for my trouble,' she said.
'You must kiss me on the
forehead after I'm dead...
I shall know.'
She let her head fall back on his knees.
Her eyelids trembled, and then she was still.
Just as Marius thought that her sad soul had
finally left her body, she slowly opened her eyes,
and said in a voice so sweet that it seemed
already to come from another world, 'You know, M.
Marius, I think I was a
little bit in love with you.'
With those words, she closed her
eyes for the last time and died.
Marius kissed her pale forehead
and laid her gently on the ground.
Then he returned to the wine shop, and
opened the letter that she had given him.
By candlelight he read,
My dearest, We are leaving this house at once.
We go tonight to Number 7, rue de l'Homme-Arme,
and in a week we shall be in England.
Cosette, 4 June.
Marius covered Cosette's letter with kisses.
So she still loved him! He thought
for a moment that now he must not die,
but then he thought, 'She's going away.'
She was going with her father to England,
and his grandfather had refused to
give his permission for him to marry.
Nothing had changed, and he decided
that he had one last duty to perform:
he must send Cosette a final
message and tell her of his death.
He tore a page out of the pocket
notebook he always carried and wrote:
Our marriage was impossible.
I went to my grandfather, and he
refused to give his permission.
I have no money, and neither have you.
I hurried to see you, but you had gone.
You remember the promise I made you.
I shall keep it.
I shall die.
I love you.
When you read this, my soul will
be very near and smiling at you.
He folded the letter, wrote Cosette's new
address on the back and called over a young boy.
'What's your name?' he asked the boy.
'Gavroche.'
'Well, Gavroche, will you do something for me?
I want you to deliver this letter to
the address written on the outside.'
The boy scratched his head, thought for a moment,
and then, with a sudden movement, took
the letter and ran off into the night.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
The Letter
Jean Valjean, at that moment,
was in a state of terrible shock.
For the first time in their life
together, he and Cosette had quarrelled.
She had not wanted to leave the house,
but she had eventually obeyed him.
They had left quickly, at nightfall,
bringing their servant, Toussaint,
with them, but very little luggage.
Cosette had brought her letter
case and blotter with her,
Valjean his box of child's clothing and
the old National Guard uniform which all
respectable men possessed, and which
he had worn under a previous identity.
In their new house, they went to bed in silence.
Cosette, however, did not leave her bedroom the
next day, and Jean Valjean had dinner alone.
As he was eating, Toussaint told
him about the fighting in the city,
but he did not pay much attention.
He was too worried about Cosette.
There was no reason, he thought, why they should
not continue to live happily together in England.
As long as he had Cosette, he would be happy,
and it did not matter where they lived.
He began to feel happier as he thought
about the journey they would soon be making.
He stood up and was going to leave
the room when something made him stop.
He glanced again at the mirror.
Cosette's blotter was lying on a cupboard just
below it and, as Valjean stared at its reflection,
he read the following lines:
My dearest, We are leaving this house at once.
We go tonight to Number 7, rue de 1'Homme-Arme,
and in a week we shall be in England.
Cosette, 4June.
In her unhappy state of mind, Cosette had
forgotten to remove the page that she had
used to blot the letter she had written to Marius.
She had left it on the cupboard and the mirror,
reflecting the backwards handwriting,
made the message clearly visible.
Valjean moved closer to the mirror and read
the lines again, not wanting to believe them.
But there was no doubt that
this was Cosette's handwriting.
He began to shake and he fell back into
an armchair, feeling angry and betrayed.
He had suffered terribly over the years and,
until now, he had survived every disaster.
But this was the worst thing that
had ever happened to him - someone
was threatening to rob him
of the only person he loved!
He murmured to himself, 'She's going to leave me,'
and the pain of those words cut
into his heart like a knife.
After a short time, he rose to his
feet and looked again at the blotter.
His anger and misery of minutes before
had been replaced by a terrible calmness.
He stared at the blotter, coldness in his eyes,
the darkness of the deepest night in his heart.
He remembered clearly the young man in the
Luxembourg Gardens who had shown such great
interest in Cosette, and he was certain
that this was the man she had written to.
He went out into the night
and sat on the doorstep,
his heart filled with a terrible hatred for the
man who was trying to steal Cosette from him.
He sat for a long time listening to the
sound of distant gunfire in the city,
wondering how to get his revenge,
when suddenly he heard footsteps.
Looking up, he saw a pale-faced boy,
dressed in rags, studying the
numbers of the houses in the street.
Seeing Valjean on his doorstep, the boy stopped
and asked, 'Do you live in this street?'
'Yes.
Why?'
'I'm looking for Number Seven.
I have a letter for a girl who lives here.'
'Well, I'm the girl's father.
You can give the letter to me.
Oh, and one more thing before you go,'Valjean
said when the boy had handed him the letter.
'Where should I take the reply?'
'That letter comes from the barricade in
the rue de la Chanvrerie,' the boy replied.
'Which is where I'm going now.
Goodnight citizen.'
Jean Valjean went back into
the house and tried to make
sense of the words that danced
before his eyes: I shall die...
When you read this, my soul will be very near...
This was enough to fill his
hate-filled heart with sudden joy.
So, the problem was solved! The
man who threatened his happiness
was going to die - was perhaps already dead.
Then Valjean frowned and,
after a quick calculation,
decided that Marius was probably still alive.
But it made no difference.
He was still certain to die, and
Valjean's happiness would be safe.
If he kept the letter in his pocket,
Cosette would never know what had
happened to the other man, and life with
her would continue the same as before.
What happiness!
But his happiness had no sooner returned than
it disappeared again in a cloud of despair.
In his heart he knew he had no choice.
For the sake of Cosette's happiness,
he would have to try and save the
life of the man she loved - the man he
hated more than any other in the world.
Half an hour later he left the house, dressed
in his National Guard uniform, with a loaded
gun and a pocket full of gunpowder, and made
his way towards the market district of Paris.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Fight to the Death
During the night, the thirty-seven
remaining rebels strengthened the
main barricade and made more bullets.
The ground floor of the wine shop
became a hospital for the wounded,
and the bodies of the dead were taken to an
alley near the smaller of the two barricades.
Four of the dead people were National
Guards, and their uniforms were removed.
After a long discussion with his friends,
Enjolras decided that the married men
(there were five of them) had to leave.
'It's your duty not to die,' he told them.
'You must return to your families.'
'How can we leave?' they protested.
'We're surrounded.
The soldiers will shoot us
as soon as they see us.'
'You can wear these.'
Enjolras pointed to the National Guard uniforms
that had been taken off the dead soldiers.
'But there are only four,' Marius observed.
'Then one of us must stay and fight,'
one of the married men replied.
A long argument followed, during which each of the
married men tried to persuade the others to go.
Finally, someone shouted to Marius,
'You decide which one must stay.'
Marius went pale at the thought of
having to choose which man had to die.
He stared down at the four
uniforms but, as he did so,
a fifth uniform fell as if by magic at his feet.
Looking round, Marius recognized Cosette's father.
Jean Valjean, who had arrived
unnoticed at the barricade,
had been listening to the argument and
had quickly understood the situation.
'Now you can all leave,' he said.
The sky grew lighter, but not a door
or window was open in the street.
The barricade was stronger than
it had been for the first assault,
and the rebels were at their positions,
guns loaded and ready for action.
They did not have long to wait.
Sounds of chains and of heavy wheels moving
along the stone streets could be heard,
and then soldiers came into view at the
end of the street, pulling a large cannon.
The rebels fired their guns but, when the
smoke had cleared, they saw the soldiers,
unharmed, steadily aiming
the cannon at the barricade.
Moments later, an officer shouted a
command and the cannon roared into action.
The cannonball crashed into
the bottom of the barricade
with a loud explosion, but did little damage.
The rebels clapped and cheered.
More soldiers moved into position at the
end of the street, behind the cannon,
and started to build a low wall
with pieces of broken stone.
At the same time, the leader of the gun
crew adjusted the aim of the cannon.
'Heads down!' Enjolras shouted.
The next cannonball exploded against
the wall at one end of the barricade,
killing two men and wounding three.
'We mustn't let that happen again,' Enjolras said.
He aimed his gun over the barricade at
the leader of the gun crew, and fired.
The gunner - a fair-haired, handsome young man
- spun round twice with his head thrown back,
and fell sideways across the cannon.
Blood poured from the middle of his back.
A tear rolled down Enjolras's cheek.
'It's sad,' he murmured to Marius,
who was standing next to him.
'He looked a brave young man.'
***
The battle continued for some time; the cannon
destroyed the upper windows of the wine shop,
and did some damage to the barricade,
but the rebels did not withdraw.
They fired back at the soldiers, killing many men.
In the pauses between shooting,
the rebels could hear the sound of
fighting in other parts of Paris.
They were filled with hope that help would
come soon, but the hope did not last long.
Within half an hour the sound of
gunfire in other places had stopped,
and the rebels knew that they were alone.
When a second cannon was moved into position next
to the first, they knew that the end was near.
Both cannons fired together,
accompanied by gunfire from soldiers at
the end of the street and on the rooftops.
As other guns began firing at the smaller
barricade, the rebels fought back bravely,
but they were running out of bullets.
There were only twenty-six men left,
and the main attack on the barricade
was going to take place very soon.
Some men, including Marius,
stayed on the main barricade,
while the others built a low stone
wall around the door of the wine shop.
Enjolras, inside the wine shop, turned to
Javert, who was still tied to the post.
'I haven't forgotten you,' he said,
putting a loaded gun on the table.
'The last man to leave this
place will blow your brains out.'
At this point, Jean Valjean spoke to Enjolras.
'You're the leader, aren't you?
Can I ask you for a favour?'
'You saved a man's life by
giving him your uniform.
You deserve some reward.
What do you want?'
'Let me kill this man.'
'That's fair,' Enjolras
decided, when nobody objected.
'You can have your spy.'
At the same moment there was the sound
of a drum, followed by a loud roar.
'They're coming!' cried Marius
from the top of the barricade.
The rebels rushed to their positions, leaving
Valjean alone with Javert inside the wine shop.
Valjean untied the rope around Javert's feet and,
taking him by the belt of
his coat, led him outside.
Only Marius, looking over his shoulder,
saw them cross the stronghold
towards the smaller barricade.
Valjean, his gun in one hand, pulled
Javert behind him over the barricade
and into a narrow alley, where the
corner of a house hid them from view.
A terrible heap of dead bodies lay not far away,
among them the blood-stained body of a
young girl in man's clothes - Eponine.
Javert glanced at the dead body and
murmured, 'I think I know that girl.
'Then, returning his attention to Valjean,
he said calmly, 'I think you know me, too.
Take your revenge.'
Valjean, however, took a knife from his pocket
and cut the ropes that tied Javert's wrists.
'You're free to go,' he said.
When Javert stared at him, speechless
with surprise, Valjean went on,
I don't suppose I'll leave here alive.
But if I do, I'm staying at
Number 7, rue de l'Homme-Arme.
Now go.'
Javert buttoned his coat,
straightened his shoulders and,
with a puzzled look on his face, began to
walk off in the direction of the market.
He had only gone a few steps, however,
when he turned and looked at Valjean.
'I find this embarrassing,' he said.
'I'd rather you killed me.'
'Go away,' Valjean replied.
Javert walked away slowly and Valjean,
waiting for him to turn a corner,
fired his gun into the air and
returned to the stronghold.
'It's done,' he said.
***
There was a roar of gunfire and the soldiers
attacked, rushing towards the barricade.
Many fell, but many more reached the barricade.
The first assault was beaten back by the brave
rebels, but the soldiers attacked again and again.
Soon, the ground below the barricade
was piled with dead and wounded men
as the rebels and soldiers fought hand to hand.
The rebels fought long and
hard to defend the stronghold,
but finally they had to withdraw to
the low wall outside the wine shop.
They stood with their backs to the door, shooting
up at the soldiers who were climbing
down towards them from the barricade.
One by one the remaining rebels
escaped into the wine shop,
until only Enjolras and Marius were left outside.
As the two friends moved back towards
the door, fighting off the soldiers,
a bullet hit Marius in the shoulder.
His eyes closed and, in great pain,
he felt a hand grab him as he fell.
'They've taken me prisoner,' he thought,
moments before losing consciousness.
'Now I shall be shot.'
The soldiers, meanwhile, attacked the wine shop.
Before long, they broke down
the door and rushed inside.
Enjolras and the few surviving rebels fought
bravely, but the soldiers were too strong.
Soon, all the rebels were dead, including
Enjolras, who was the last to die.
Sword in hand, surrounded by
soldiers, he refused to surrender.
He died in a rain of bullets with a
strangely victorious smile on his lips.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The Sewers of Paris
Marius had indeed been taken
prisoner, but not by the soldiers.
It was Jean Valjean's hand
that had caught him as he fell.
Valjean had taken no part in the battle.
He had been looking after wounded men
while bullets flew all around him.
When Marius had been hit, Valjean ran to
him at once, grabbed him before he fell
and carried his unconscious body into
a small alley behind the wine shop.
Valjean lowered Marius to the ground, stood
with his back to the wall and looked around him.
The situation was terrible.
There seemed to be no escape.
On one side of him was the field of battle.
On the other side was the low barricade,
behind which hundreds of soldiers
waited for rebels trying to escape.
Both ways meant certain death.
It was a situation that only a
bird could have escaped from.
Valjean looked desperately around him, at the
house opposite, the barricade, the ground.
And then he had a sudden idea!
At the foot of the smaller barricade,
half-hidden by broken stones and pieces
of wood, there was a hole in the
road covered with an iron grille.
Valjean leapt forward and, using all his
strength, he moved the stones and wood,
opened the grille, lifted Marius on to his
shoulders and climbed down into the darkness.
A few minutes later, he found himself
in a long underground passage,
a place of absolute peace and silence.
He was inside the Paris sewers.
He could just see, by the grey light
from the grille above his head,
that he was surrounded by walls.
Ahead of him lay total
darkness, but he had to go on.
The soldiers might discover
the grille by the barricade
at any moment, and come down in search of him.
With Marius lying across his shoulders,
Valjean walked forward into the darkness,
feeling his way along the wet,
slippery walls with his hands.
He moved from one passage into another,
slipping several times on the wet floor.
He could not see where he was going,
but he knew he had to follow the downward
slope of the passages towards the river.
He walked blindly downwards in this way for
a long time, his clothes wet with the blood
from Marius's wound, the faint whisper
of the young man's breath in his ear.
He walked in total darkness, the silence
broken occasionally by the thunder of gun
carriages and horses racing along the
streets of Paris far above his head.
Suddenly, he saw his own shadow on the
floor of the passage in front of him.
Looking back, he saw the distant light of a torch.
He was being followed! He pressed himself
against the wall, held his breath and waited.
In the distance, a group of men
formed a circle around the torchlight.
They seemed to be listening for
something, waiting for someone to move.
Finally, the group of men moved
off along another passage,
and Valjean was left in total darkness once again.
He continued his journey through the sewers.
Sometimes the roof of the passages was so
low that he had to bend down as he walked.
His feet slipped all the time
in the water on the ground,
and he felt sick and faint with
the terrible, airless smell.
At last, exhausted, he stopped beneath
a large grille that brought him
much-needed light and fresh air.
He laid Marius down gently at the edge of
the sewer, and looked down at his face.
It was covered with blood and as pale as death.
Valjean tore pieces oft his own shirt and bandaged
Marius's wounded shoulder as well as he could.
Then, bending over the unconscious body, Valjean
stared at Marius with hatred in his eyes.
He found two objects in Marius's
clothing: a piece of bread and a wallet.
Valjean ate the bread and, opening the
wallet, found a note which Marius had written:
My name is Marius Pontmercy.
My body must be taken to the
house of my grandfather, M.
Gillenormand, 6 rue des Filles-du-
Calvaire, in the Marais.
Valjean repeated the address until he could
remember it, returned the wallet to Marius's
pocket, picked Marius up again and continued
his journey downwards towards the river.
He did not know what part of the city he
was passing under or how far he had come.
The only thing he was sure of was
that the light through the grilles
far above his head was growing weaker,
which meant that the sun was setting.
At one point he had to walk
waist-deep through water,
and almost sank as the ground
turned to sand beneath his feet.
Finally, when even his great
strength was beginning to fade,
he saw ahead of him a light
- the clear light of day.
He was suddenly filled with
new energy at the sight,
at last, of his way of escape from the sewers.
Forgetting the weight of Marius
on his shoulders and his own
hunger and tiredness, he ran towards the light.
He had to bend as the roof
of the tunnel became lower,
but when he reached the light, Valjean
stopped and gave a cry of despair.
The opening was closed with a strong iron
gate, held firm by a huge, rusty lock.
Through the bars, Valjean could see daylight,
the river, a narrow riverbank
- but how could he get out?
Valjean laid Marius down by the
wall, where the floor was dry.
Then, moving to the gate, he
shook it fiercely with both hands,
trying to bend the bars with
the last of his strength.
But the gate was solid and the bars were firm.
Valjean turned his back to the gate and sank to
the ground, his head bowed between his knees.
There was no way out and, as all hope of
escape left him, he began to think of Cosette.
***
While in this state of despair,
Valjean felt a hand on his shoulder.
He thought he was dreaming.
He looked up and saw a man dressed
in old clothes standing beside him.
Despite the unexpectedness of this meeting,
Valjean recognized the man at once.
It was Thenardier.
Valjean did not show that he recognized the man,
and saw with relief that
Thenardier had not recognized him.
'I'll make a bargain with you,' the man said.
'What do you mean?'
Thenardier nodded in Marius's direction.
'You've killed a man.
Give me half of what you found in this man's
pockets, and I'll unlock the gate for you.'
He produced a large key from
his pocket, and a piece of rope.
'I'll give you this as well,' he said.
'Then you can tie stones to the
body and throw it in the river.'
Valjean took the rope without speaking.
'What about my share of the
money?'Thenardier asked.
Valjean took thirty francs from his
pockets and showed it to Thenardier,
who stared with disbelief.
'You killed a man for just
thirty francs? You're a fool.'
He searched Marius's pockets
himself, and then Valjean's.
'It's true,' he said at last.
'That's all there is.
Oh well.
Never say that I'm not a kind man.'
He took the thirty francs and, helping
Valjean to lift Marius on to his shoulders,
he put the key in the lock and opened the gate
just wide enough for Valjean to pass through.
When Valjean was outside, Thenardier
closed the gate behind him and disappeared,
like a rat, into the darkness of the sewers.
***
Valjean laid Marius gently
on the grass and stood up,
surrounded by silence, enjoying the
feeling of fresh air on his face.
Then, just as he was bending to splash
water from the river on Marius's face,
he was aware of someone else standing behind him.
He looked round quickly and saw a tall man
in a long coat, a large stick in his hand.
Although the man's face was hidden in shadow,
Valjean recognized him as Inspector Javert.
Javert, however, did not
recognize Valjean at first.
He had been more interested
in catching Thenardier,
who had escaped from prison and
was known to be in the area.
'Who are you?' he asked.
Valjean told him his name
and stood, without moving,
as Javert approached and stared into his eyes.
'Inspector Javert,' Valjean said quietly.
'I beg you to do me one favour.
I promise not to try and escape.
I gave you my address this
morning, if you remember,
so you would know where to find me anyway.'
Javert did not seem to hear.
He stared into Valjean's eyes for a long
time, then, stepping back with a look
of confusion in his eyes, asked dreamily,
'What are you doing here? Who is this man?'
'Will you help me to take him home?' Valjean said.
'He's badly injured.'
Javert looked unhappy, but he did not refuse.
Bending down, he took a
handkerchief from his pocket,
wet it in the river and bathed
Marius's blood-stained forehead.
Then he felt Marius's wrist.
'He's dead,' he said.
'No, not yet,' Valjean replied, feeling
in Marius's jacket for the wallet.
'Look,' he said, showing Javert the note
with Marius's grandfather's address.
'That's where we need to take him.'
Javert shouted to the driver who was waiting for
him to bring his carriage close to the river.
With Marius in the back seat, Valjean
and Javert side by side in the front,
the carriage drove off quickly through the
dark and strangely empty streets of Paris.
When they arrived at M.
Gillenormand's house, a servant answered the door.
'Does M.
Gillenormand live here?' Javert asked.
'Yes.
What do you want?'
'We're bringing back his grandson.
He's dead.
Go and wake his grandfather.
We're bringing him in.'
Javert, Valjean and the driver carried Marius
into the house and laid him gently on a sofa in M.
Gillenormand's sitting-room.
While one servant ran to find a doctor
and another looked for clean sheets,
Valjean felt Javert's hand on his arm.
He understood, and went downstairs
with Javert close behind him.
When they had got back into the
carriage, however, Valjean said,
'Inspector, will you do one last
thing for me before you arrest me?'
'What is it? 'Javert replied impatiently.
'Let me go home for a minute.
After that, you can do whatever you want with me.'
Javert was silent for some moments, his
chin sunk in the collar of his overcoat.
Then he pulled down the window in front of him.
'Number 7, rue de l'Homme-Arme,'
he told the driver.
Neither man spoke during the journey.
At the end of the rue de l'Homme-Arme, which
was too narrow for the carriage to enter,
Javert paid the driver and accompanied
Valjean to his front door on foot.
'Go in,' said Javert, with a
strange, distant look in his eyes.
'I'll wait for you here.'
Valjean went into his house and
called, 'It's me!' Climbing the stairs,
he paused for a moment to look out of
the window to see what Javert was doing.
But the street was empty; there was no one there.
The next morning, Inspector Javert's body
was discovered floating in the river.
The poor man, unable to understand
the kindness and gentle nature of the
man he had spent his whole life hating, had
taken his own life by jumping from a bridge.
It was the only way he knew to escape the
confusion that was poisoning his heart.
***
When M.
Gillenormand saw his pale, lifeless-looking
grandson lying on the sofa,
he shook from head to foot.
Leaning against the door for
support, he murmured, 'Marius!'
'He has just been brought here,' said a servant.
'He was on the barricade and
'He's dead!' cried the old
man in a terrible voice.
'The fool! He did this to
hurt me, the ungrateful boy.
I try to be good to him, and
this is how he rewards me!'
The old man walked to the window and,
while he complained to the night about
the pain and grief his grandson
had caused him, the doctor arrived.
After listening to Marius's heart, he
organized his removal to a bed in another room,
and returned to M.
Gillenormand, who was still
standing by the window.
'Will he live?' M.
Gillenormand asked, his eyes wild with fear.
'I don't know,' the doctor replied.
'The wound to his body is not serious,
but there are deep cuts on his head.
It's difficult to say M.
Gillenormand went to Marius's bedside.
'You heartless boy,' he said angrily.
'A fool who prefers fighting
to dancing and having fun.
What kind of man are you? Are you
mad? But it makes no difference.
I too shall die.
That makes you a murderer, a cold-hearted killer.
I cannot feel grief for you.
At that moment, Marius's eyes slowly
opened and his gaze rested upon M.
Gillenormand.
'Marius!' the old man cried.
'Marius, my child, grandson!
You're alive after all!'
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
The Wedding
Marius lay for a long time between
life and death in a state of fever,
endlessly repeating the name of Cosette.
'He mustn't get excited,' the doctor warned.
Every day, according to one of
the servants, a white-haired,
well-dressed gentleman came to
ask for news of the sick man.
Finally, after three months, the doctor
announced that Marius was out of danger.
But he had to spend the next two months
resting because of the damage to his shoulder.
M.
Gillenormand grew happier as his
grandson's condition improved.
He did strange, unexpected things, like
running up and down stairs without knowing why.
He gave his neighbour, a pretty woman, a bunch
of flowers, which greatly annoyed her husband.
Marius, meanwhile, tried to make
sense of what had happened to him.
He thought about Enjolras and Eponine,
and wondered why Cosette's
father had been at the barricade.
He could not understand why nobody
could tell him how he had been saved.
All he knew was that he had been brought
to his grandfather's house in a carriage.
He noticed his grandfather's tenderness
towards him, but he could not forget
the old man's unfairness and cruelty to his
father, who had died penniless and unloved.
Most of all, however, he thought about
Cosette, and how he could find her again.
'There's something I have to say to you,'
Marius told his grandfather one day.
'What is it?'
'I want to get married.'
'But of course,' the old man laughed.
'What do you mean - of course?'
'That's understood.
You will have your little girl.'
'I don't understand,' Marius said,
almost speechless with amazement.
'You will have her,' the old man repeated.
'She comes here every day in the shape
of an old man who asks for news of you.
While you've been ill, she's spent her
time crying and making bandages for you.
I know all about her.
She lives at Number 7, rue de l'Homme-Arme.
You see, I'm not as unkind as you think.
I've found out that she's a charming
girl and that she loves you.
I knew you were angry with me, and I
thought, "What can I do to make him love me?"
Then I thought, "I can give him Cosette."
I wanted to invite her to see you, but the doctor
warned me that you would probably get too excited.
So I advise you, dear boy, to eat
more meat and get better soon.
Then you can marry your Cosette and be happy.'
Having said this, the old man burst into tears.
He held Marius's head to his
chest and they cried together.
'Grandfather,' Marius said at last,
'I'm feeling much better already.
When can I see her?'
'You can see her tomorrow.'
'Why not today?'
'All right, I'll fetch her today.
You've called me "grandfather"; you've
shown me that you love me after all.
You've earned your reward!'
***
Later that day, Cosette arrived at M.
Gillenormand's house.
Standing beside her on the doorstep was a
white-haired man with a strangely nervous smile.
M.
Gillenormand showed them up to
the room where Marius was waiting.
Cosette stood in the doorway,
overcome with happiness.
She wanted to throw herself into Marius's arms,
but was unable to move, afraid to
show the world that she loved him.
'Monsieur.'
M.
Gillenormand addressed Jean Valjean.
'I have the honour, on behalf of
my grandson, Marius Pontmercy,
to ask for your daughter's hand in marriage.'
Jean Valjean bowed.
'Good, then that is agreed,' M.
Gillenormand said and, turning
to Marius and Cosette, he added,
'My children, you are free to love one another.'
When they were alone together,
Cosette and Marius kissed.
'Is it really you?' Cosette murmured at last.
'I can't believe it.
I'm so happy to see you.
I was so excited today that I
haven't even dressed up for you.
I must look terrible.
But why don't you say something? Why
are you letting me do all the talking?
Do you still love me? Oh,
I'm so wild with happiness
'My love...'
Marius whispered.
***
The wedding was arranged for
February the following year.
Jean Valjean arranged everything.
Having been a mayor, he knew how to solve an
awkward problem: the question of Cosette's
real family He told everybody that he
was not her father, but her guardian.
He also invented a dead family for Cosette,
so that everybody believed she was an orphan.
Valjean, as her guardian,
gave Cosette a large amount
of money - half a million francs - but
did not tell her that the money was his.
He told her that the money came from
a man who preferred to remain unknown.
It was arranged that the couple,
who could not believe their sudden,
new-found happiness, would live with M.
Gillenormand after the wedding.
Cosette, accompanied by Jean
Valjean, visited Marius every day.
Marius did not speak much to Valjean.
Despite enjoying an occasional conversation with
him, he found something strange about the old man.
He could not believe that this
was the same man he had seen at
the barricade all those months ago
- it seemed like a bad dream to him.
But there were more important
things for Marius to think about.
Apart from preparing for his wedding, there
were two people that he wanted to find.
First, there was Thenardier.
He was, without doubt, a bad man, but Marius had
promised his father to find him and help him.
He employed agents to find
Thenardier, but without success.
The only thing they discovered
was that Mme Thenardier had died,
and that her husband had escaped from prison and
disappeared with his surviving daughter, Azelma.
Second, there was the mysterious
stranger who had saved his life.
Marius's attempts to find
him also ended in failure,
and the true story of his escape from the
barricade remained a complete mystery to him.
One evening, when Marius was talking to Cosette
and Jean Valjean about the mystery and
his unsuccessful attempts to solve it,
he became angry with Cosette's
guardian's lack of interest in his story.
'The man was a hero,' Marius said.
'Do you realize, Monsieur, how brave this man was?
He rescued me from the field of battle and
carried me through the sewers of Paris.
He risked his life to save a dying
man, and why? He was a total stranger.
He did it without any thought of a reward.
Oh, I wish Cosette's money were mine.'
'It is yours,' Valjean reminded him.
'I would give it all,' said
Marius,'to find that man!'
Jean Valjean was silent.
***
Cosette and Marius made a handsome
couple on their wedding day.
All previous unhappiness was forgotten as they
kissed in the church, watched proudly by M.
Gillenormand and Jean Valjean.
There were flowers everywhere
when they returned to M.
Gillenormand's house for the wedding feast.
It was the happiest night of Cosette's life,
spoilt only by one thing: the fact that her
guardian - whom she still thought of as her
father - went home before the feast
had started, saying that he felt ill.
But Cosette was not unhappy for long.
She had Marius, and she would be happy
with him for the rest of her life!
Jean Valjean, meanwhile, went home, lit
his candle and went upstairs to bed.
That night, however, he was unable to sleep.
He remembered the little girl he had rescued
from the Thenardiers ten years earlier,
and felt sad that he was no longer
the most important man in her life.
Another man was the centre of her universe.
He was proud of having helped to bring
her happiness with Marius, but another
thing troubled his soul: the fact that nobody,
not even Cosette, knew the truth about him.
That he was Jean Valjean, a criminal who
had spent nineteen years in prison and who
had stolen silver candlesticks from
a trusting and kind-hearted bishop.
He knew that if he told
Cosette and Marius the truth,
he would spoil everybody's happiness and
he would lose their love and respect.
On the other hand, if he continued to lie
about his past, he would lose his own soul.
What could he do?
***
The next day Valjean visited M.
Gillenormand's house, and asked
to speak to Marius in private.
Marius hugged Valjean warmly, addressed
him as 'father' and invited him to lunch,
but Valjean shook his head and said,
'Monsieur, I have something to tell you.'
Marius listened quietly as Valjean
told him everything about his life.
Finally, in a state of shock and
confusion, the young man said,
'Why have you told me all
this? No one forced you to.'
'If I had continued to keep my secret to myself,
I would have destroyed my
own heart,' Valjean replied.
'Besides, I belong to no family.
Cosette was the only family I ever had.
Everything ended for me when
she married you yesterday.
She is happy with the man she loves.
I tried to persuade myself that it would be
better not to admit the truth about my past,
but it was no use.
I could not silence the voice that
speaks to me when I am alone.'
Neither of them spoke for several minutes.
Then Marius murmured, 'Poor Cosette.
When she hears
'But you must promise not to
tell her!' Valjean interrupted.
'She'll be heart-broken if
she hears the truth about me.
I don't think I could bear it...
'
He sank into an armchair and
buried his face in his hands.
'Don't worry,' Marius said at last.
'I'll keep your secret.
But I think it would be better
if you stopped seeing her.'
'I understand,' Valjean said, rising to leave.
But at the door he half-turned
and said, 'Monsieur,
if you will permit me, I would
like to come and see her.
I wouldn't come often or stay very long.
We could meet in that little
room on the ground floor.
Please Monsieur, if I can't see Cosette
again, I'll have nothing left to live for.
Besides, if I suddenly stopped visiting, people
would become suspicious and begin to talk
'You can come every evening,' said Marius.
'Monsieur, you are very kind,' said Jean Valjean,
shaking Marius's hand and leaving the room.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
The Truth at Last
Marius kept his promise about not telling Cosette,
and Valjean visited her every evening
in a small room on the ground floor.
It was cold and damp, but a fire had been lit
and two armchairs had been placed in front of it.
At first, Cosette could not understand
why Valjean refused to meet her upstairs.
When he refused to kiss her
cheek, she began to feel unhappy,
afraid that she had done something to offend him.
She pressed his hands in hers
and held them to her lips.
'Please, please be kind!' she begged.
'I want you to come and live with us.
You'll always be my father and
I'm not going to let you go.'
He released his hands.
'You mustn't call me "father"
any more,' he told her.
'You must call me "Monsieur Jean".'
'I don't understand,' she said, becoming angry.
'This is ridiculous.
You're upsetting me very much, and I
don't know why you're being so cruel.'
'You don't need a father any more.
You have a husband.'
'What a thing to say!' Cosette replied.
'Are you angry with me because I'm happy?'
'Cosette,' he said, 'your happiness
is the only thing that matters to me.
You're happy now, and so my work is complete.'
With these words, he picked up his hat and left.
Jean Valjean continued his evening visits,
but the relationship between himself and
Cosette became cooler and more distant.
She stopped calling him 'father'
or asking him questions.
As 'Monsieur Jean', he gradually
became a different person to her,
and she began not to depend
on him for her happiness.
Valjean would sit looking at Cosette in silence,
or would talk about incidents from their past.
One evening in April, he called at the usual
time but was told that Cosette
had gone out with her husband.
He waited in the small, damp room for
an hour before sadly returning home.
Over the next few days, his visits began to be
interrupted by servants calling Cosette to dinner.
When he arrived, he discovered
that the fire had not been lit,
and the armchairs had been left near the door.
One evening he discovered there were
no chairs in the room at all - he and
Cosette had to stand in the
cold for their whole meeting.
Valjean realized what was happening;
Marius was telling the servants
not to make him welcome any more.
That night he went home in despair, and
the next evening he did not come at all.
When Valjean did not appear
for the second evening,
Cosette sent a servant to his
house to ask if he was well.
Valjean replied that he was very well,
but that he had business to attend to.
He did not return to the house again,
and Cosette was too busy with married
life to think too much about him.
She did not realize that, every
evening, Valjean would walk slowly
from his house until he reached the
corner of the street where she lived.
He would then stare at the
house for several minutes,
tears rolling down his cheeks, before
turning round and slowly returning home.
***
Marius thought it was right to
exclude Valjean from Cosette's life.
He achieved this without
cruelty, but without weakness.
Apart from the details about his life
that Valjean had confessed to him,
he knew that Valjean had killed
Inspector Javert at the barricade.
His private investigations into the old man's past
had also revealed an even more disgusting fact.
He had discovered that Valjean's money really
belonged to somebody called Monsieur Madeleine,
a wealthy manufacturer from Montreuil
who had mysteriously disappeared.
He persuaded Cosette, therefore, not to use
any of the money her guardian had given her,
and to live on the money that he
had started to earn as a lawyer.
Cosette had not been happy about this.
She could not understand why her father,
as she still thought of Valjean,
had stopped visiting her.
She still loved him in her heart.
But she loved her husband even more,
and she gradually became used to not
depending on the old man for her happiness.
One evening a servant brought Marius a letter,
saying, 'The writer is waiting in the hall.'
The smell of tobacco and the handwriting on the
envelope was so familiar that Marius
immediately thought of the Jondrettes.
He read the letter quickly.
It was signed 'Thenard', and was asking for money.
Marius could not believe his luck.
He had tried without success to find the man
who had saved his father's lite at Waterloo,
and now the man had come to him! He immediately
asked the servant to show the man in.
However, Marius had a shock when he
saw the man - he did not recognize
him at all! He was an old man with a
big nose, glasses and neat grey hair.
He was wearing smart black clothes, and a
gold watch chain hung from his jacket pocket.
'What do you want?' Marius asked
coldly, as the stranger bowed to him.
The stranger explained in great detail how he used
to work for the government in foreign countries
and that, now he was retired, he wanted to move
to South America with his wife and daughter.
Unfortunately, it was a long
journey, and he needed money.
'What has that to do with me?'
'Has M.
Pontmercy not read my letter?'
Marius had only read the letter quickly, and could
not remember the details, so he said, 'Go on.'
'I have a secret to tell you, M.
Pontmercy,' the stranger said.
'I'll tell you the first part for nothing.
I think you'll be interested;
'Well?'
'The man you think is your wife's
guardian is a murderer and a thief.
His name is Jean Valjean.'
'I know that.'
'Did you know that he spent
nineteen years in prison?'
'I know that too.'
The stranger narrowed his eyes, trying to hide
his disappointment and anger at Marius's calmness.
Then he gave a strange smile.
'I have more information to tell you.
It concerns money that belongs to your wife.
It's a remarkable secret and I'll sell
the information to you for 20,000 francs.'
'I know this secret already,' Marius
said, 'just as I knew the others.'
'10,000 francs?'
'I repeat, you have nothing to tell me.'
'But I need to eat, Monsieur!' the
visitor said, losing confidence.
'I'll tell you for twenty francs.'
'I know it already,' Marius said.
'I know everything.
I even know your real name.
It's Thenardier.'
The visitor laughed, but Marius
went on, 'You're also Jondrette.
And you once had an inn in Montfermeil.'
'I deny it!'
'You're a completely rotten
man, but I'll give you this.'
Marius took a banknote out of his pocket
and threw it in the stranger's face.
'Thank you, M.
Pontmercy!' the man said, examining the note.
'500 francs! That's real money.
Oh well, I suppose we can relax.'
With those words, he removed his
false nose, glasses and neat grey wig.
'M.
Pontmercy is absolutely right,'
he said, changing his voice.
'I am Thenardier.'
He waited for a few seconds
to see Marius's reaction.
Marius, meanwhile, was grateful
for finally having the chance to
help Thenardier, and therefore to keep
the promise he had made to his father.
Thenardier's presence, however,
offered him another opportunity;
it gave him the chance to solve
the mystery of Cosette's fortune.
'Thenardier,' he said.
'Shall I tell you the secret that
you were planning to sell me?
I, too, have sources of information, and
probably know more about the subject than you do.
Jean Valjean, as you say,
is a murderer and a thief.
He's a thief because he robbed a wealthy
manufacturer and mayor of Montreuil, M.
Madeleine.
Jean Valjean, who knew the mayor's background,
reported him to the police and took advantage
of his arrest to take over half a
million francs from his Paris bank.
The manager of the bank told me this himself.
And he murdered the policeman, Javert.
I know this because I was there at the time.'
Thenardier looked puzzled for a moment, then
said, 'Monsieur, I think you are mistaken.'
'What! Are you denying what
I said? Those are facts!'
'They are incorrect, and I do not
like to hear a man unjustly accused.
Jean Valjean did not rob M.
Madeleine, nor did he kill Javert.'
'How do you know?'
'First, he did not kill M.
Madeleine because he was M.
Madeleine! And second, he did not kill
Javert because Javert killed himself.
He killed himself by jumping into the river.'
'What proof do you have?' Marius
said, wide-eyed with disbelief.
'I have all the proof here,' Thenardier said,
producing an envelope in which there were
several documents and newspaper articles.
'I've spent a long time discovering
the truth about Jean Valjean.'
Marius studied the documents carefully,
then looked up with a smile of joy.
'But he's a splendid man!
The fortune was really his,
and he's not a murderer or thief
at all! He's a hero and a saint!'
'He's a thief and a
murderer,'Thenardier said quietly.
'What do you mean?'
'I told you that I do not like
to see a man accused unjustly,
but I do like to see a man punished
for crimes he has committed.'
'And what crimes are those?'
Thenardier sat down and told
Marius about the time he had
helped Valjean to escape from the Paris sewer.
'He was carrying the body of a man he
had robbed and killed,' Thenardier said.
'Look, I have a piece of cloth
from the dead man's coat as proof.'
He produced a muddy piece of
cloth and showed it to Marius,
who immediately went pale and
rose unsteadily to his feet.
As Thenardier continued to talk, Marius
opened a cupboard door and took out a coat.
'That man was me!' Marius cried.
'And here is the coat I was wearing!'
Thenardier stared at the coat and the
cloth in his hands, speechless with fear.
He was even more surprised when,
instead of chasing him out of the room,
Marius ran towards him and pressed several
thousand-franc notes into his hand.
'You're a terrible man,' Marius said.
'A thief and a liar.
You came here to destroy a man,
but you have done the opposite.
If you hadn't saved my father's life at
Waterloo, I'd report you to the police.
I know that your wife is dead,
but take the money and start a new
life in America with your daughter.
When you arrive there, I'll
send you another 20,000 francs.
Now get out.
I never want to see you again!'
When Thenardier had left, unable
to believe his good fortune,
Marius ran to find Cosette and
told her everything immediately.
'We must go to him at once,' Marius said.
'He was the man who saved my life.
We must waste no time!'
Minutes later, he and Cosette were travelling
in a carriage to Number 7, rue de l'Homme-Arme.
***
Jean Valjean looked up when he heard the knock on
his door and called in a weak voice, 'Come in.'
The door opened and Marius and Cosette appeared.
Cosette rushed to the chair
where Jean Valjean was sitting.
'Father!' she cried, falling into his arms.
'So you've forgiven me?' Valjean whispered,
hugging Cosette to him and turning to Marius.
'Cosette, did you hear what he said?'
Marius cried, tears of shame and
guilt rolling down his cheeks.
'He asked me to forgive him.
And do you know what he did? He saved
my life and he brought me back to you.
He came to the barricade to save
me, just as he saved Javert.
He carried me on his back through the
sewers of Paris, to bring me to you.
Oh Cosette, I feel so ashamed
of the way I've treated him!'
'You have no need to say
all this,' Valjean murmured.
'Why didn't you say it yourself?' Marius demanded.
'Why didn't you tell me that you were M.
Madeleine and that you saved Javert's life at the
barricade? Why didn't you tell
me that I owed you my life?'
'Because I thought it would
be better to break away.
If you had known the truth, you would have felt
obliged to be good to me, a worthless criminal.
That would have upset everything.'
'What or whom would it have upset?' Marius said.
'Well, we're not going to allow
you to stay here on your own.
You're going to come home with us.
You're Cosette's father and mine.
I won't allow you to spend another day here.'
'And you can't refuse this time,' Cosette agreed,
sitting on Jean Valjean's
lap and kissing his forehead.
'There's a carriage waiting for you.
I'm kidnapping you - by force, if necessary!'
Jean Valjean listened as she described
the view from the room that would be his,
the beauty of the garden,
the singing of the birds,
but he was listening more to the music of
her voice than to the meaning of her words.
Finally, he said, 'Yes, it
would be delightful, but
Cosette, frightened, took his two hands in hers.
'Your hands are so cold,' she said.
'Are you ill? Are you in pain?'
'No,' said Valjean.
'I'm not in pain.
But
'But what?'
'I'm going to die soon.'
'Father, no!' Cosette cried.
'You're going to live! You
must live, do you understand?'
Marius and Cosette both did their best
to raise Valjean's spirits, to show him
how much they loved and needed him, to fill him
with the strength and the desire to live again.
But it was too late.
Valjean smiled, his eyes shining with love and
happiness, but he was beginning to lose strength.
'To die is nothing,' he murmured.
'But it is terrible not to live.'
Then, taking Cosette's sleeve and pressing it to
his lips, he said, 'Come close to me, both of you.
I love you dearly.
How sweet it is to die like this.
And you love me too, dear Cosette.
You'll feel some grief for me, but not too much.
I want you to have no great sorrows.
You must enjoy life, my children.
I'm leaving the two candlesticks
by the bed to Cosette.
They're made of silver, but
to me they are pure gold.
I don't know whether the person who gave them to
me is pleased as he looks down on me from above.
I've done my best.
You mustn't forget, my children, that,
despite my money, I am one of the poor.'
As he spoke, Valjean's breathing became more
painful and he had difficulty moving his arms.
But as the weakness of his body
increased, his spirit grew in strength.
The light of an unknown world
was shining brightly in his eyes.
'Now, Cosette,' he breathed softly, 'the time
has come for me to tell you your mother's name.
It was Fantine.
You must not forget it.
Your mother loved you greatly
and she suffered greatly.
She was as rich in sorrow as you are in happiness.
That is how God balances things out.
He watches us all from above and knows
what he is doing among his splendid stars.
And now I must leave you, my children.
Love one another always.
There is nothing else that matters
in this world except love.'
Cosette and Marius fell to their knees on
either side of him, holding back their tears.
Jean Valjean's hands rested on their
bowed heads, and did not move again.
He lay back with his head turned to the sky,
the light from the two silver candlesticks
falling on his smiling, peaceful face.