CHAPTER ONE
An Island without a King
''If you prefer to destroy my property, then stay.
But I will ask Zeus for a day of judgement,
and on that day I will destroy you.'
Odysseus's unlucky fate is causing me great
sadness,' said the goddess Athene to her father,
the great god Zeus. 'It is now twenty years since
he has seen his home and loving family. Zeus,
Father, King of Kings, why are you
doing nothing to help this man?'
'I have not forgotten the great hero
Odysseus, my child,' replied Zeus.
'You are right - his troubles have continued
long enough. We should bring him home.'
'Thank you, Father,' said bright-eyed
Athene. 'First I will go to Odysseus's palace
and talk to his son, young Telemachus. I
must make him ready for his father's return.'
Athene put on her shoes of gold, which carried
her as fast as the wind down from Mount Olympus,
over land and sea, to the island of Ithaca.
As she arrived at Odysseus's palace,
she disguised herself as a man called
Mentes, a family friend of Odysseus.
Outside the house she found a group of men playing
a noisy game while servants were busy around them.
Some of the servants were
mixing wine and water in bowls;
others were piling meat onto plates
and preparing the tables for dinner.
Odysseus's son, Telemachus, was sitting unhappily
among the men, dreaming of his father's return.
Telemachus saw Athene in her disguise, and felt
ashamed that no one was greeting the visitor.
He hurried towards her. 'Welcome, friend!'
he said. 'Come and have some food.
Then you can tell us why you are here.'
He led Athene to a table away from the other men,
worried that his visitor would be upset by their
noise and rudeness. A servant poured water into a
fine silver bowl so they could wash their hands.
Then plates of bread and meat were brought,
and their gold cups were filled with wine.
The other men also ate well, then
called for a song from the bard Phemius.
As Phemius began, Telemachus said to his guest,
'Those men over there worry about nothing
except music. They have an easy life, living free
while another man pays! If Odysseus returned now,
they would wish for a faster pair
of legs, not gold or fine clothes.
But unfortunately that will never happen.
My father was once the king of this island,
but now his bones are probably being washed by the
rain in a faraway land, or by the salt sea waves.
No one can give us any news of him.
But tell me, what is your name, and
what is the reason for your visit?'
'My name is Mentes,' answered bright-eyed
Athene. 'My family and yours have been friends
for many years. I am here because I heard
that your father had already arrived home.
The gods must be making his journey difficult,
but I am sure that he is still alive.
He is a resourceful man; he
will think of a way to get home.
But are you really Odysseus's son? You have grown
so tall! You certainly have your father's eyes -
although I have not seen him for twenty years,
since he left to fight in the Trojan War.'
'Sometimes I wish I had a different father,
who was growing old in his own home,'
Telemachus replied. 'Odysseus is the most
unfortunate man that has ever lived.'
'He is lucky, at least, in his choice of
wife, the loving Penelope. But tell me,
what are you celebrating with this special
meal? And who are these men, who bring no food
but behave like the owners of the house?
I have never seen such impolite guests.'
'My friend,' Telemachus replied, 'these men
have a meal like this every day of the year.
My father's disappearance has
brought disaster to this house.
Many great heroes died in the Trojan War, but
their sons are lucky. Their fathers left them
a famous name. Odysseus was still alive at the
end of the war, but he has left me only tears.
These men have come from Ithaca and neighbouring
lands, hoping to marry my mother. She does not
want to accept any of her suitors. But with no
news of my father, she cannot refuse them all.
They wait for her answer, eating and
drinking until we are nearly ruined.'
'How terrible!' the goddess replied. 'They
will die if your father ever finds them here.
But while he is away, you must try
to change the situation yourself.
Here is my advice. Choose your best ship,
hire a crew of twenty strong oarsmen,
and go in search of news of your father.
Someone may be able to tell you about him.
Go to Pylos first and question its king,
wise Nestor. Then continue to King Menelaus
in Sparta, since he was the last of the Greeks to
reach home. If you hear that your father is alive,
prepare yourself for another year with the
suitors. But if you hear that he is dead, give
your mother in marriage to another man and end the
suitors' stay in your house. You are not a child
now. Act like a man, and your grandchildren's
grandchildren will celebrate your name. But it
is getting late. I must return to my ship or my
crew will start to worry. Think about my advice.'
'Thank you, good Mentes,' Telemachus said warmly.
'You have shown me the kindness of a father to
his son. But will you not stay a little longer?
Have a bath and relax. Then you can go back to
your ship with a gift from my house - something
beautiful and valuable, as you
have proved to be a good friend.'
'No,' replied Athene. 'I am in a hurry to
get back to my ship and reach my destination,
the port of Temesa. But I will be
glad to accept a gift on my way home.'
When she had finished speaking, the goddess
disappeared suddenly, like a bird through a
hole in the roof. Telemachus was left feeling
braver and more resourceful than before.
Noticing this change, he realised
that a god had been with him.
His mind was filled with thoughts of
his father as he rejoined the suitors.
He found them listening in silence to Phemius,
who was singing about the Greeks' problems
on their return from the Trojan War.
In her rooms upstairs, Penelope
could hear the bard too.
She came down the stairs with tears in her eyes.
'Phemius,' she said, 'you know so many wonderful
songs about great heroes and powerful gods.
Choose one of those songs for tonight, and
let the men here drink their wine in peace.
But give us no more of your present
song. It always makes me cry.
In the events of your story, no one lost
a dearer or a better husband than I,
whose husband is famous in
every corner of Greece.'
But wise young Telemachus interrupted
Penelope. 'Mother,' he said, 'do not
stop our great bard from entertaining us as he
chooses. The gods are responsible for our fates,
not the songs of a bard. It is not surprising
that Phemius has chosen this story, as the newest
songs are always the most popular. Go back to your
rooms, Mother, and busy yourself with your work.
I am the master of this house, so leave
decisions about the entertainment here to me.'
Penelope was surprised by her son's words, but
she knew that he spoke wisely. She returned to
her rooms, and there she lay crying for Odysseus
until the goddess Athene closed her eyes in sleep.
Back in the hall, the suitors were shouting and
joking about their hopes to marry the beautiful
lady of the house. Telemachus stood up and
spoke to them. 'Gentlemen,' he said, 'this
is not the way for suitors to behave. Stop this
rudeness! Let us enjoy the food and the song -
Phemius has the voice of a god. But tomorrow
morning there is going to be a meeting.
I am going to make a formal
request that you leave my house.
After tonight, eat your meals somewhere else.
If you prefer to destroy my property, then stay.
But I will ask Zeus for a day of judgement,
and on that day I will destroy you.'
The suitors were shocked by Telemachus's
new confidence. For a moment they did
not know what to say. Then Antinous spoke.
'Are the gods teaching you this arrogance,
Telemachus? If you are already so arrogant
now, I hope you never become king of Ithaca.'
'I will gladly become king if the gods
wish it,' replied Telemachus. 'But many
other princes in Greece want that title and
they are welcome to it, since my father is dead.
I just want to be the master of my own house,
and of the servants won by my father in war.'
Eurymachus now spoke. 'You are right, Telemachus.
The gods must decide who Ithaca's next king will
be. And you should keep your own property and rule
your own house. But tell us, who was your guest
and where was he from? Did he bring news of your
father, or was he here on business of his own?
He left so quickly that we had
no opportunity to meet him.'
'There is never any news of my father. We
must accept that he is not coming back.
My guest was Mentes, an old friend of my father.'
Telemachus did not tell them what he knew in
his heart - that Mentes was a god in disguise.
The rest of the evening was spent
dancing and listening to music.
When it grew dark, the suitors
slowly returned to their own homes.
In his bedroom, Telemachus lay awake all
night, thinking about Athene's advice.
The next morning, he called the
people of Ithaca to a meeting.
When everyone was ready, Telemachus walked to the
meeting-place with only two dogs as companions.
He looked so proud and confident that
everyone's eyes turned to him in admiration.
The older men moved away so that
he could take his father's seat.
Telemachus stood to address the people. 'I called
this meeting, gentlemen, to ask for your help.
Great trouble has fallen on my house.
First, I have lost my father, Odysseus.
But worse than this, a second problem will soon
ruin me. A group of suitors spend their days in
our house, eating our animals and drinking our
wine. Soon all our property will be wasted.
Some of the suitors are from the families of
Ithaca - some are even here, among us now.
Tell them to leave my mother alone. Or did you
dislike my father Odysseus's treatment of you,
and think that our house deserves these
troubles? I would gladly fight all the suitors
if I had the strength. But I am one and they
are many. I cannot defend our house alone.'
As he spoke, his anger grew, and at the end
of his speech his eyes were wet with tears.
Many people felt sorry for Telemachus. No
one spoke - until Antinous broke the silence.
'What a speech, Telemachus!' he said. 'And
what anger! You blame me and the other suitors
for your troubles, but you are wrong. The
fault is not ours, but your own mother's.
For nearly four years she has made us wait for
her answer. She gives each of us a reason to hope
for her hand in marriage. She
makes promises in private messages,
but she never keeps those promises. And then there
was that shroud. "I need to finished it before I
marry again," she told us. "It is to cover the
body of Odysseus's father, Laertes, when he dies.
It would be bad for my reputation if such
a great lord had no shroud on his death."
We decided to be patient and agree to her
wishes. She worked on the shroud every day,
but at night she undid all her work. For
three years she tricked us in this way.
In the end, one of her servants told us of
her dishonesty, and we forced her to complete
the shroud. But still she has not chosen a
husband. This is the suitors' answer, Telemachus.
Tell your mother to stop her tricks.
We will not leave your house in peace
until she has made her choice
and married one of us.'
'I cannot force her to marry while she
still hopes for my father's return,'
replied Telemachus. 'If I did that, the anger
of the gods would bring me even more disasters.
Go and eat your meals somewhere else.
If you stay, the gods will surely
punish you for your unlawful behavior.'
The great god Zeus was listening to his words and
sent two eagles to fly above the meeting-place.
In the sky, the birds attacked each other,
biting each other's faces and necks
before flying away over the town.
The people stared at the birds, asking
themselves what this sign from the gods meant.
Halitherses, a wise old man
skilled in prophecy, spoke first.
'People of Ithaca, and suitors too, hear my
words. Odysseus will not be absent much longer,
and his return will bring a violent end
to the lives of these arrogant suitors.
This will be a disaster for many of us on Ithaca.
We must stop the suitors before it is too late.
Or even better, the suitors should
stop their bad behavior themselves.'
The suitor Eurymachus stood to reply. 'Go home,
old man,' he laughed. 'Tell your stories to your
children and leave us to understand the signs
of the gods. But now I will make a prophecy.
If you say anything more about Odysseus's
return or disaster for the suitors,
you yourself will meet a violent end.
And this is my advice to Telemachus:
he should order his mother to choose a husband.
Until she does this, the suitors will never leave.
We are afraid of no one - and certainly
not of Telemachus and his brave words.'
Mentor, an old friend of Odysseus,
spoke now. 'People of Ithaca,
do you care nothing for Odysseus, who ruled you
with the love of a father? Why should a king aim
to be fair and kind to his people, if this is your
repayment? The suitors are few and you are many.
But you sit here in silence and say nothing
to criticize their shocking behavior.'
The suitors shouted over Mentor's
words, but Telemachus silenced them.
'Eurymachus and you other suitors,' he said,
'I will say no more. The gods and the people of
Ithaca have heard my request. But now, I need
a fast ship and a crew of twenty strong men.
I am going to Pylos and Sparta to ask for news of
my father. If I hear that he is alive, I will wait
one more year. But if I hear that he is dead, I
will give my mother in marriage to a new husband.'
The suitors laughed at his plan, saying
that he would never even find a crew.
And so the meeting ended.
Telemachus went to the seashore to think. Athene
came to him there, this time disguised as his
father's Ithacan friend Mentor. 'Do not worry
about the suitors,' she said. 'They are fools.
The resourceful son of a resourceful
father has nothing to fear from them.
I myself will be your companion on your journey.
Go back to your house and get food and wine,
while I find you a ship and a crew.' Telemachus
returned to his house, where he found the suitors
preparing for another great dinner. With
a laugh, Antinous ran up to him. 'Come and
eat with us,' he called. 'And later I will
help you find a ship for your journey.'
'I will make my own arrangements for a ship
- and for a nasty end for you suitors too,'
replied Telemachus.
Hearing this, all the suitors started shouting.
'He is planning to bring back an army from
Pylos to cut our throats!' laughed one.
'Perhaps he will buy some poison to
put in our wine-bowl!' cried another.
'Or he may get lost at sea like his
father. Oh, how sad that would be!
We would have so much trouble sharing his
property between us all!' added a third.
Telemachus let them talk. He went downstairs and
unlocked a room full of his father's treasure.
There were piles of gold and silver, clothes,
and jars of oil and wine. Everything was being
kept safe for Odysseus's return by his loyal
servant Eurycleia. Odysseus's father, Laertes,
had bought Eurycleia when she was still a girl,
for the price of twenty cows. She had looked
after both Odysseus and Telemachus when they were
babies, and no one loved them more than she did.
Calling the old woman now to
the room, Telemachus said,
'Please could you get twelve jars of fine wine for
me, and plenty of food? But do not tell anyone!
I will come and collect it this evening, when
my mother has gone upstairs for the night.
I am going to Pylos and Sparta
to ask for news of my father.'
There were tears in Eurycleia's eyes as she
replied, 'Dear child, no! The suitors will
find a way to murder you on your journey and
share all this wealth between them. Stay here,
at home with your mother, where you belong. Do
not go looking for trouble on the stormy seas.'
'Please do not worry,
Eurycleia,' answered Telemachus.
'I have the gods on my side. But promise me that
you will not tell my mother that I have gone.
We do not want to upset her for no reason.'
Eurycleia promised to keep his secret and
started organising the food and drink.
Telemachus went back upstairs to
the hall and rejoined the suitors.
At the same time, Athene was going round the
town disguised as Telemachus, choosing twenty
strong men for the ship's crew. She had already
borrowed a ship from an Ithacan man called Noemon.
When the ship and crew were ready, she returned
to Odysseus's palace and made the suitors sleepy.
They soon found that they
could not keep their eyes open,
so one after the other they went to bed.
Athene took on the appearance of Mentor again,
and went to find Telemachus. 'Come,' she said to
him. 'Twenty companions are sitting at their oars,
waiting to start their journey. Let us not delay.'
Telemachus followed Athene to the ship.
The food and wine was carried on board,
and soon they were at sea. Athene called
for a good wind to take them to Pylos,
and Telemachus ordered his men to put up the sail.
As night turned to day, the ship was making
good progress on its way to Pylos.
CHAPTER TWO
Telemachus's Travels
'If Odysseus ever proved that he was your friend
in the hard years of the war, tell me
everything that you know about his death.'
As Telemachus and his companions came near to
Pylos, they saw a great crowd of people on the
beach, including King Nestor and his family.
Telemachus's crew brought the ship to land.
Then they all followed Athene, who was
still disguised as Mentor, onto the shore.
Telemachus was the last to leave the ship. As
they walked towards the crowd, Athene said to him,
'Remember, this is not a time to be
shy. We are here to find out how your
father's life ended. Go, then, and ask
Nestor confidently if he has any news.'
'But I will be embarrassed, talking in public to
Nestor,' Telemachus replied. 'He is so much older
than me and so famous. I have no experience
of public life. How should I speak to him?'
'Do not worry,' Athene advised. 'When your
own words fail you, the gods will help.
They are looking kindly on this journey of yours.'
When they reached the crowd, they
were greeted warmly by Nestor
and his family, who had just made a
sacrifice to the sea-god Poseidon.
The king's son, Peisistratus, offered
them some meat from the sacrificed cows,
and servants poured them some wine. After they
had finished the wonderful food, Nestor spoke.
'Who are you, friends, and where have you come
from? What is your business here in Pylos?'
Athene gave Telemachus the confidence to reply.
'Nestor, son of Neleus, great hero of the
Greeks, we are from the island of Ithaca.
I have come here looking for news of
my father, long-suffering Odysseus.
It is said that he fought by your
side until the end of the Trojan War.
But he has never come home, and no one
can tell us when or where he died.'
'Ah, my friend,' cried King Nestor, 'what memories
I have of that long war! It would take years just
to tell you of all the disasters that struck us
at Troy. We lost our best men there - Achilles,
Patroclus, and my own son Antilochus
too, a handsome boy, fast and strong.
'For nine years we tried to beat the Trojans,
but Zeus threw many difficulties in our path.
In all those years, no one showed better
judgment than Odysseus - your father, if you
really are his son. It is not hard to believe,
since you look and speak exactly like him.
In all those long years, your wise father and I
never once spoke on opposite sides of an argument.
At every stage of the war, we
agreed on the best plan of action.
'After we destroyed the city of Troy, we
left in our ships. But then Zeus sent us
all in different directions, because some
people among us had displeased the gods.
We had arguments about the route home,
and some ships were caught by storms.
I myself was lucky - my voyage was very smooth.
So I heard no news of the other commanders.'
'But what is the news from Ithaca? Are the stories
true, that a crowd of your mother's suitors are
living as uninvited guests in your house? I only
wish that the goddess Athene showed you some
of the kindness that helped your father so much
during the war. If she cared for you like that,
the suitors would soon have their
thoughts of marriage knocked out of them.'
'Good Nestor,' replied Telemachus, 'I
cannot hope for an end to my troubles
with the suitors, even if it
is the gods' dearest wish.'
'Telemachus,' interrupted bright-eyed Athene,
'what are you saying? Nothing is
impossible if the gods are helping you.'
'The gods have already sent my
father to his death, Mentor,'
said Telemachus to the goddess. 'Is
that their way of helping my family?'
'Well, my advice to you, Telemachus,' continued
Nestor, 'is to go home quickly and guard your
property from the greedy suitors. But there is
one more person that you should visit. Menelaus
has only just returned home, after years lost at
sea. Perhaps he will have news of your father.
Go now, with your ship and crew;
or my sons can go with you by land,
and show you the way to red-haired
Menelaus's palace in Sparta.'
Darkness was falling, so Nestor invited
them to stay the night at the palace.
'You are very kind, my lord,' said Athene.
'Telemachus will gladly accept your invitation,
but I must return to the ship. In the morning
the crew and I must continue our voyage.
Telemachus can travel to Sparta in one of your
chariots, if your son can be his companion.'
When she finished, the goddess
turned into a bird and flew away.
Nestor and Telemachus stared at the sky in
shock. 'Telemachus, my boy!' cried Nestor,
'I think your friend Mentor was
really Athene, whose help was so
valuable to your father. With a goddess at your
side, you have a great future ahead of you!'
Telemachus spent the night in Nestor's palace,
and in the morning Nestor's son Peisistratus
called for a chariot to take them to Sparta.
They arrived two days later and found
Menelaus celebrating a family wedding.
A bard and dancers were entertaining the
guests in the hall as they ate their dinner.
Telemachus and Peisistratus stopped their chariot
outside the palace. Menelaus's friend Eteoneus
came out of the hall and saw them there. He
hurried to his king, saying, 'There are two
strangers at the gates. Should we welcome them
inside or ask them to continue on their journey?'
Red-haired Menelaus answered him angrily.
'Eteoneus, you are not usually a fool,
but you are certainly talking like one now.
You and I enjoyed the welcome of strangers in
many far lands before we reached home. Go and help
our guests at once, and invite them to join us.'
Telemachus and Peisistratus were soon
following Eteoneus into the palace,
where they were washed by the servant-girls
and dressed in fine new clothes.
Then they took their seats
next to Menelaus in the hall.
The servants brought them food and
drink and Menelaus greeted them warmly.
Telemachus whispered to Peisistratus, 'Look
at this room! Have you ever seen so much gold?
Surely even Zeus's palace on Mount
Olympus does not shine as brightly!'
Menelaus heard his words and said, 'No one's home
can compare with the palace of the gods, dear boy.
But few ordinary men have collected
more treasure than I have.
For seven long years I travelled the world
and made my fortune - in Cyprus, Egypt,
Ethiopia and Libya. But there were many hard
times during those years, and while I was away,
my brother was cruelly murdered by his wife
and her lover. I would happily exchange all
the gold and silver in this house for the return
of my brother and the friends who I lost at Troy.
But although I miss every
one of my lost companions,
there is one whose death upsets
me even more than the rest.
Odysseus always tried harder, fought harder,
thought harder than anyone else in the war.
But his resourcefulness did not help him in the
end. He has never returned home. I often think
of his family - his father, old Laertes, his
loyal wife, Penelope, and his son Telemachus,
who was only a baby when Odysseus left for the
war. It must be hard to wait for him year after
year. They have probably given up waiting now.
It is twenty years since he was last in Ithaca.'
These words brought tears to Telemachus s
eyes, and Menelaus realized at once who his
young visitor must be. As he was deciding what to
say to him, his wife Helen arrived in the hall.
Everyone's eyes followed her across the room in
admiration. Long ago, her beauty had been the
cause of the Trojan War. A Trojan prince, Paris,
had stolen her from her husband's home in Sparta
and taken her to live with him in Troy. The
Greeks had attacked the Trojans to win her back.
Now, returned to her loving husband, her
goddess-like beauty still shone bright.
One of her ladies helped her into a chair; another
brought her a fine blanket of the softest wool;
a third passed her her silver work-basket,
a gift from a friend in Egypt.
As Helen started her work, she asked
her husband about the visitors.
'Do we know their names, Menelaus? I must
say, that young man looks exactly like
Odysseus. Could he be Odysseus's son, who was only
a baby when the Greek army followed me to Troy?'
'I think you are right,' her husband replied.
'A few minutes ago he was crying when
I spoke of my memories of Odysseus.'
Peisistratus now spoke. 'Menelaus, great
king, you have guessed rightly. My friend
here is Odysseus's son, Telemachus, and I am
Peisistratus, son of Nestor. Because Telemachus
is shy in the company of great men like yourself,
my father asked me to be his companion here.'
'Well, he is a very welcome visitor,'
cried Menelaus. 'I had hoped to build his
father a home near mine, so that we could
meet regularly and continue to be friends. But a
jealous god has robbed me of this happy future.'
Everyone's eyes filled with tears. For some
time they were silent, lost in their own
unhappy thoughts, until Peisistratus said,
'The dead deserve our tears, but this is
meant to be a wedding celebration.
Let us talk of happier subjects.'
'Wise words, Peisistratus,' replied Menelaus.
'You have your father's good sense.'
He called for more food and wine,
and their good humor slowly returned.
After a comfortable night in the palace,
Telemachus was woken by Menelaus. 'What is the
purpose of your visit here, Telemachus?' he asked.
'Is it public business or a private matter?'
'Great king, I came here to ask you for news of
my father. My mother is surrounded by arrogant
suitors, who spend their days as uninvited guests
in my house. They will not leave until my mother
chooses one of them, but she delays her choice
as she is still hoping for my father's return.
So the suitors wait in my hall, eating my meat and
drinking my wine until I am nearly ruined. I have
come here to ask if you have any information about
my father. Please, if Odysseus ever proved that
he was your friend in the hard years of the war,
tell me everything that you know about his death.'
'I cannot believe that those cowardly suitors
are planning to take brave Odysseus's place in
Ithaca! Ha! They will get a shock if Odysseus ever
returns - and a quick death too. But to answer
your question, I will tell you everything I heard
from the god Proteus, whose lips can never lie.
I was in Egypt. For twenty days my companions and
I had been on an island in the mouth of the Nile
with no wind to take our ships home. We had no
more food and were starting to fear for our lives.
But luckily the goddess Eidothee, Proteus's
daughter, saw us there and felt sorry for us.
"My father, sea-loving Proteus, lives on
this island," she said. "He can tell you
how to get home. He can also tell you what has
happened in Greece while you have been away."
"But how will I make your
father tell me all this?"
I asked her. "Proteus does not
give information willingly."'
'"When the sun is high in the sky, Proteus comes
out of the sea and sleeps on the beach with the
seals. If you and a few companions dress in seal
skins, you can hide on the beach and surprise him.
Hold him down with all your strength. He will
turn into all kinds of shapes as he tries to
escape you. But if this fails, he will
finally change back to his normal shape.
Then you can let him go, and he
will answer all your questions."'
'The next day we did as Eidothee suggested.
At sunrise, she dug holes in the sand. We climbed
inside and she put seal skins over our bodies.
There we waited, with the horrible
smell of dead seals in our noses.
Soon a great crowd of seals came out of the
sea and lay down around us on the beach, and
at midday Proteus joined them for a sleep. With
a shout, we jumped on him and held him tightly.
Immediately he started turning into different
kinds of animal, then into water and into a tree,
but he could not escape us. Finally he changed
back into his normal shape, and I said to him,
"Are you going to change shape all day,
or will you tell us what we need to know?
We have been unable to leave this island for
twenty days. What can we do to get home?"'
'"You did not sacrifice to the gods before
you started your voyage," Proteus said,
"so now they are angry with you. If you want to
see your home again, you will have to sail the
waters of the Nile once more and make the right
sacrifices. Then your voyage home can continue."'
'My heart was filled with sadness at the
thought of returning to the Egyptian mainland.
But I hid my feelings and
said, "I will do as you say.
But tell me, what news is there of the rest of the
Greek army? Has everyone reached home safely?"'
'"Why, Menelaus, are you asking me this? I warn
you, you will cry an ocean of tears when you hear
my answer. Most of the Greek commanders are now
safe in their homes, but two have died. A third,
though alive, is held prisoner on an unknown
island, far from his friends and loving family."'
'"Ajax was the first to die, in a terrible storm
at Gyrae. But your brother Agamemnon, who had been
with Ajax just before the storm, was lucky and
sailed from Gyrae with all his ships unharmed.
It seemed that he had escaped his rate. When
he landed safely in his homeland, Mycenae,
he kissed the earth in happiness. His arrival,
though, was watched by one of Aegisthus's spies."'
'"While you and your brother were
at Troy, your cousin Aegisthus had
turned his attention to wife-stealing. Your
brother's wife, Clytemnestra, was his prize.
At first she had listened to his words of love
with deaf ears, but before long she had become his
willing lover. Now Aegisthus was
waiting for Agamemnon's return."'
He had already won the wife.
Next he was planning to murder the husband and
rule the great lands of Mycenae in his place.
'"When Aegisthus heard the spy's news, he
sent soldiers to hide in Agamemnon's palace.
Then he went in his chariot to meet the king.
Your brother, never guessing Aegisthus's terrible
plans, came up with him from the coast and they
celebrated his return together. Then Aegisthus
killed him in his own palace, as a
man might sacrifice a cow to the gods.
Agamemnon's companions were murdered too.
There was not a single man left alive."'
'This was Proteus's story, and it broke my
heart. I sat down on the sands and cried.
After some time, Proteus interrupted
me, saying, "You have cried long enough!
Waste no more time in tears. Is it not better
to do everything in your power to reach home,
so that you can punish Aegisthus for his crime?"'
'These words made me feel a little better. "You
have described the fates of two Greek commanders.
Who is the third, who is a
prisoner on an unknown island?
Please tell me his name, even if
it brings me more unhappiness."
'"The third is Odysseus," he replied. "I saw
him on the island of the goddess Calypso,
with tears running down his face. His
only desire is to return to Ithaca,
but Calypso is in love with him
and does not want him to leave.
Without her help, he is a prisoner on the island
- he has no ship or crew to carry him home."
'The old man had nothing more to say. Soon
he sank back into the deep salt waters,
and I returned with my companions to the ships.
The next day, we sailed back to the Egyptian
mainland, and there we made the right sacrifices
to the gods. We also built a great mound of earth,
so that the name of Agamemnon would
live in that far land forever.
In front of Odysseus's palace, the
suitors were sitting and joking as usual.
Noemon came to Antinous and handsome
Eurymachus. 'Do you know when Telemachus
is expected home from Pylos? He went in my ship,
and I need it for a voyage to my farm on Elis.'
'Pylos!' cried Antinous. 'I thought he was up in
the hills of Ithaca with his pigs and his sheep.'
'Yes, we all thought that,' agreed Eurymachus.
'Noemon, tell us exactly what you know.
'He left several days ago, and his
crew were the best young men on Ithaca,
after ourselves. Mentor went as his captain
- well, it looked like Mentor on the ship,
but in fact I saw Mentor here on
Ithaca yesterday. Very strange!'
As Noemon walked away, Antinous and
Eurymachus called all the suitors together.
'Telemachus is in trouble
now,' thundered Antinous.
'We said that his voyage to Pylos would
never happen. And he has already gone,
taking the best men on Ithaca with him! There
is only one way to answer this arrogance.
Give me a fast ship and a strong crew, and
I will wait for him in the water between
Ithaca and the Samian rocks. His voyage to
find his father is going to end in blood.'
The other suitors agreed to this plan, and
asked Antinous to make all the arrangements.
The servant Medon heard their conversation and ran
to tell his queen. When Penelope heard the news,
her knees shook and her eyes filled with tears.
'But why has my son gone?' she asked Medon.
'Does he want his bones to join his
father's, washed by the salt sea waves?'
'I understand that he was looking
for news of his father, my lady,'
replied Medon, leaving the room quietly.
Penelope fell to the floor. Her women-servants
surrounded her as she cried, 'Is there any woman
whose fate is crueler than mine? Zeus gave
me a good husband, then took him from me.
And now my son has been stolen away without
a word. And you servants are cruel too.
You all knew of Telemachus's voyage,
I am sure. Why did no one wake me from
my bed as he went to his ship, so that
I could stop this foolish adventure?'
'Dear lady,' replied old Eurycleia, 'I
knew all about his voyage, and I even
gave him the food that he needed for it. But
he made me promise that I would not tell you.
He did not want to upset you unnecessarily.
Now, go and wash, and put on some fresh clothes.
Then pray to Athene. Although the danger is
great, the goddess may be able to save him.'
While Penelope prayed to Athene, Antinous
and his crew prepared their ship.
As the sky grew dark, they left the shore and
sailed to Asteris, a little island between Ithaca
and the rocky coast of Samos. There they waited
for Telemachus's ship to come into view.
CHAPTER THREE
Leaving Calypso
''Even well-built ships do
not cross this endless sea.
It would be mad to travel such a
long distance in a home-made raft.'
While Athene was helping young Telemachus,
Zeus sent his messenger Hermes to talk to the
goddess Calypso. For many years, Odysseus had
been an unwilling guest on Calypso's island.
Outside Calypso's cave, Hermes
stopped to admire the beautiful scene.
A little stream ran between trees filled with
birdsong, and flowers and fruit grew everywhere.
A fire burned brightly at the cave's entrance,
and inside he could hear Calypso singing.
When she noticed the god entering her
home, she said, 'Hermes, you are welcome.
Come and have something to eat,
and tell me what brings you here.'
'I have been sent here by Zeus,' he replied. 'I
had no wish to make this long journey - across
endless, empty sea, with no cities or people on
the way. But no one can refuse the orders of Zeus.
This is Zeus's message: it is not Odysseus's
fate to end his days on your island,
so send him on his way without delay.
He must continue his voyage to Ithaca.'
Calypso's body shook with sadness. 'Zeus is so
unfair. He himself is allowed any number of human
girlfriends. But if a goddess finds love with
a human, he ends her happiness immediately.
I saved Odysseus from death after his ship was
destroyed in a storm; I welcomed him here on my
island and looked after all his needs;
I even offered to turn him into a god.
But now Zeus orders me to let him go. Well,
I must do it - I have no choice. But I have
no boat to give him, and the voyage is long.
I can only tell him the direction to take.'
'Then send him on his way at once and you
will not have to worry about Zeus's anger.'
With these words, Hermes started his
journey back to the palace of the gods.
Calypso went at once to look for Odysseus.
She found him sitting on the shore,
crying for his lost home as usual. 'Dry your
tears,' she said to him, 'and waste no more
of your life on this island that brings you
no pleasure. I am ready to help you leave.
Cut down some trees and make a raft. I will
give you food and drink for your voyage.
I will even give you a wind that will blow you
to Ithaca, if more powerful gods do not stop me.'
'Even well-built ships do
not cross this endless sea,'
he replied. 'It would be mad to travel such
a long distance in a home-made raft. I will
not do it. Or can you give me your word that
this is not a trick to cause me more trouble?'
Calypso smiled and touched his face with her
hand. 'How can you think that I would trick you
like that? By the earth and the sky and by death
itself, I promise you: I am just trying to help.'
After they had eaten together in the cave, she
said, 'So have you definitely decided to leave?
Please think again. I know you miss your wife
Penelope, but you will have so much pain and
suffering before you reach your homeland. Is it
not better to stay here with me? A goddess is
more beautiful than any human wife, and with me
you can escape death forever by becoming a god.'
'Do not be angry with me, goddess,' he replied.
'Of course you are more beautiful than Penelope,
but I want nothing more than
to return home to my family.
And I stopped worrying about the
dangers of my journey long ago.
I have suffered so much already. One
more disaster means nothing to me now.'
When morning came, Calypso gave Odysseus
some tools and he started work on his raft.
After four days of hard work, the raft was ready.
It had a cloth sail, and plenty of food
and drink on board. A warm and gentle
wind blew up at Calypso's command, and with
a happy heart Odysseus sailed out to sea.
Keeping his eyes on the stars, he travelled
east for seventeen days without sleeping,
and on the eighteenth day the land
of the Phaeacians came into view.
But Poseidon, god of the sea, saw Odysseus
on his raft and the sight made him angry.
'It seems that the other gods have
changed their minds about Odysseus,'
he said to himself. 'He has nearly
reached the land of the Phaeacians,
where his suffering is going to end. But I have
not forgiven him for the harm he did to my son.
It is not too late to send a little
more trouble in his direction.'
With those words, he covered both land and
sea with thick fog. Then he called all the
winds together to make a violent storm, and
enormous waves crashed down on Odysseus's raft.
'Oh gods!' cried Odysseus, 'have you not
finished with me yet? Calypso's prophecy
is coming true - that I will have more pain
and suffering before I reach my homeland.
How lucky were my companions who were killed at
Troy! They died with their friends around them,
and their names live forever; I am going to
die in a sea storm, alone and forgotten.'
As he spoke, a wave the size of a mountain
thundered down on him and threw him off the raft.
The waters closed over his head. His clothes -
a gift from Calypso - were heavy in the water,
and made swimming difficult. But at last he
reached the air and coughed out the salt water
from his mouth. With the last of his energy, he
swam back to the raft and threw himself on board.
He held on tightly, but the violent winds
drove him in every direction except to safety.
Then Poseidon sent another enormous wave towards
him. For a second or two, it hung above his head,
then it crashed violently down on the
raft, throwing the wood in all directions.
Odysseus held onto a piece of wood, kicked
off his clothes and bravely started swimming.
Poseidon laughed when he saw this. 'It
is a long way to the coast, Odysseus,
but swim there if you can.
I have had my fun with you.'
Athene now sent the south, east and west
winds back to bed. She calmed the north wind
so it could blow Odysseus gently
towards the land of the Phaeacians.
For two days and two nights he swam.
Time after time he thought he would die,
but on the third day, a wave lifted him
a little and he saw that land was near.
He felt like a child who learns that his father,
after suffering from a long and painful illness,
has been cured. Odysseus felt a similar happiness
when he saw the welcome sight of hills and trees.
He swam more quickly in his excitement, until he
heard the thunder of the waves on the rocks ahead.
Too late, he realized that there were no
beaches to land on, there were only sharp
walls of broken rock. An enormous wave lifted him
towards them, and it looked like certain death.
But luckily he managed to save himself
by catching onto a rock with both hands.
The powerful waves soon pulled his hands away,
and he was back under water. He kicked hard to
reach the air. Finally, he decided to swim further
along the shore, although he was already so tired.
At last Odysseus came to a more welcoming
coastline. He found the mouth of a stream,
and there he landed safely. He fell to the ground,
too weak to move. He lay there for some time,
until he realized that it was getting late. With
no clothes, he might freeze at night if he stayed
where he was. But was he safer in the woods, where
wild animals might be looking for an easy supper?
After some thought, he chose
the warmer ground of the woods,
and looked for a suitable place to sleep. He
found two trees growing together so tightly
that their branches kept out the wind and sun
and rain. Between these trees he lay down and
covered himself with a blanket of dry leaves. For
the first time in three weeks, he fell asleep.
As Odysseus slept, Athene went to the
palace of Alcinous, the Phaeacian king.
Alcinous had a young daughter called
Nausicaa, as tall and beautiful as a goddess.
Athene, disguised as one of Nauiscaa's friends,
went into her bedroom and whispered in
her ear as she slept in her soft bed.
'Nausicaa, why are you being so lazy? You will
need lots of fine clothes when you are married,
but all your clothes are lying around the palace
unwashed. Let us go and wash them together in
the morning. We must hurry. The young men from
every good family in the land want to marry you,
and your father will certainly
choose a husband for you soon.'
Athene then returned to her home on Mount
Olympus, and a little later Nausicaa woke up.
Remembering the strange dream
that she had had in the night,
she immediately went to find her father.
'Father, could I have one of the horses today,
and a vehicle to carry our dirty clothes to
the stream? Your own clothes need washing,
and my brothers often ask for clean
clothes to wear at their dances.'
She did not talk about her own marriage - she was
too shy to discuss this matter with her father.
But he understood completely and replied, 'The
servants will bring you what you need, my child.'
While the servants brought a vehicle and a horse,
Nausicaa rushed around the palace collecting her
family's finest and most colourful clothes. Her
mother packed her some food and wine for the trip,
and soon Nausicaa and a group of her friends
were on their way to the stream, talking happily.
There were some deep pools in the
stream, perfect for washing the clothes.
The girls threw them into the water by the armful
and started their work. When everything was clean,
they stretched out the clothes on the beach.
Then they bathed in the stream and sat down for
some food while the sunshine dried the clothes.
When they had finished their meal,
they started playing a ball game,
and Nausicaa sang the instructions.
She looked like a young goddess, more beautiful
than all the beautiful girls around her.
The girls' voices woke Odysseus and he got
out of his bed between the trees to see what
was happening. Luckily, he remembered that he was
wearing no clothes, and used some leaves to hide
his body. But he looked dirty and wild after his
terrible days at sea, like a dangerous animal mad
with hunger. When the girls saw him, they screamed
and ran away. Only Nausicaa stayed to face him.
Odysseus's first thought was to throw his arms
around the beautiful girl's knees and ask her for
help. But he did not want to upset her by touching
her. Instead, he kept his distance and said,
'Are you a human or a goddess? I cannot
guess the answer, since I have never
seen such beauty. If you have a human family,
how lucky they are! What pleasure they must feel
when you dance in their company. And luckiest of
all is the man who takes you home as his wife.
'Princess, I must ask you for help.
Yesterday I arrived on this shore, carried here
by the winds after three weeks on the stormy seas.
My raft and my clothes are lost, and I know no
one in this land. Pity me in my troubles. Tell me,
please, how do I reach your city? And do you
have anything that I can use for clothes?'
'Sir,' she replied, 'you will be given everything
that you need. The king of this land is Alcinous,
and I am his daughter. I will gladly
show you the way to his palace.'
'I thank you with all my
heart,' answered Odysseus.
Nausicaa now called to her friends. 'Come
back, girls. There is nothing to fear.
This man is an unlucky voyager and we will help
him, since all strangers are protected by Zeus.'
Odysseus washed his salty skin in the stream,
while the girls looked for some clothes to give
him. As he dressed, clean at last, Athene used
her powers to make him taller and stronger,
with thicker hair. Nausicaa whispered to
her friends, 'When I first saw this man,
I thought he was terribly unattractive; now,
though, he looks more like the gods on Olympus.
How I would like a man like this as my husband!
Hurry, now, girls. Take him
something to eat and drink.'
Odysseus was very grateful for the food.
While he ate hungrily, the girls packed up the
washed clothes. Then Nausicaa called to Odysseus,
We are going back to the city now. I am sure you
will understand when I ask you to follow with my
friends only as far as the city gates. Inside the
city, I must be more careful of my reputation.
You can imagine what people will say if they
see me with a handsome stranger. They will
guess that I have refused all the men from local
families and chosen a foreign husband instead,
or that a god has taken me as his wife. That kind
of talk will not help me to find a good husband
when the time comes. So, we will leave you
at the entrance to the city. Give us time to
return to the palace, then join us there later.
In the city, look at no one and ask no questions.
My people are great sailors, thanks to Poseidon,
with the fastest ships in the world - but they are
not always good hosts. When you enter the palace,
look for my mother, Queen Arete. She usually sits
next to my father in the great hall and, as the
daughter of the last king, she is as powerful and
popular as King Alcinous himself. Throw your
arms around her knees and ask for her help.
If she feels pity for your situation,
you will soon see your homeland again.'
Odysseus willingly agreed to the plan.
At the entrance to the city, he waited while the
princess and her friends returned to the palace.
Athene threw a magic fog over him so that no one
could see him as he walked through the city. When
he reached the gates of the palace, he was almost
blinded by the shining sight that met his eyes.
Hanging on silver posts were two great doors of
gold, and inside were hundreds of beautiful works
of art, also made of gold. Around the palace was a
brightly coloured garden full of tall fruit trees.
Still protected by Athene's magic fog, he
entered the palace. He found the great hall
and walked, unseen, past a long
table of Phaeacians eating dinner.
When he got to Queen Arete's seat, he threw his
arms round her knees and, at the same moment,
Athene lifted the fog from his shoulders.
Everyone in the room looked at him in shock.
CHAPTER FOUR
With the Phaeacians
'I can think of no better
companion for my daughter.
I would give you a house and great treasures if
you were willing to stay here as her husband.'
'Arete, great queen,' said Odysseus, 'I am here
to ask you and your royal husband for help.
I pray that the gods give your family good fortune
and great happiness. For myself, my dearest
wish is to return to my home across the seas,
after all the disasters that I have suffered.'
No one spoke, and Odysseus sat
down on the floor by the fire.
At last, the silence was broken by an older
Phaeacian man named Echeneus. 'My king,
it is not right to let this man sit on the floor.
Offer him one of our silver chairs to sit on,
and ask the servants to bring him some wine. We
should pray to Zeus, protector of strangers.'
Alcinous did as Echeneus suggested,
giving Odysseus the seat where his
favourite son usually sat. When Odysseus
had had food and drink, Alcinous said,
'Phaeacians, we have eaten well. Now it is time
for you to return to your homes for the night.
In the morning, we will decide how to arrange
this stranger's safe return to his homeland.'
The Phaeacian guests left the room.
While the servants cleared the tables,
Arete looked more closely at Odysseus and
recognised the clothes that he was wearing.
She herself had made them with her ladies'
help. 'Sir,' she said, 'who are you?
And who gave you those clothes? Did you say
that you have come here from across the sea?'
'Great queen, it would be boring for you to
listen to all my troubles, as the gods have
sent me so many. But I will tell you this.
I have come from an island far out to sea,
the home of the goddess Calypso. Before
that, I was travelling with my companions,
but they all died when Zeus destroyed
our ship. Only I managed to stay alive,
by holding onto a piece of the broken ship
until the winds blew me to Calypso's shore.
For seven years she tried to win my love, and for
all that time I was an unhappy prisoner on her
island. But, finally, she allowed me to leave.
I made a raft and sailed safely until I caught
sight of the mountains here in Phaeacian lands.
But then Poseidon sent a storm to destroy my raft,
and I nearly lost my life many
times as I swam to your shore.
'I slept near the coast, and in the morning
I was woken by your daughter and her friends.
I asked her for help and
she gave me these clothes.
You should be proud of her. She has the
beauty of a goddess, and the good sense too.'
'She made one mistake,' said Alcinous. 'Why
did she not bring you home with her friends?'
'Do not blame your daughter, great king,' replied
Odysseus. 'She wanted me to follow her. It was my
decision to stay behind, fearing that you would
not like a stranger as your daughter's companion.'
'My friend, I can think of no better companion for
my daughter. I would give you a house and great
treasures if you were willing to stay here as her
husband. But we will not keep you here by force.
Tomorrow you can make your voyage home. It
will only take a day - it does not matter
how far you are going. You will soon learn why the
Phaeacians have such a good reputation as seamen.'
Odysseus's heart filled with happiness as he heard
Alcinous's words. Arete showed him to the bed that
the servants had prepared for him, and he spent
the night dreaming of a happy return to Ithaca.
In the morning, fifty-two young men were chosen
as the crew for the voyage to Odysseus's homeland.
They prepared their boat down at the
port, then came to the palace for a meal.
When they had eaten, Alcinous
called for his bard, Demodocus.
'Demodocus, the gods have given you a special
gift. Your songs never fail to please our ears,
whatever subject you choose for your story. Sing!'
Demodocus sang of the Trojan War, and the
argument between Odysseus and Achilles that
had started a great wave of disasters for the
Greeks. As Odysseus listened to the bard's song,
he put his hands over his face and cried. He
tried to hide his tears from the Phaeacians,
but Alcinous noticed his sadness. Not wishing
to upset his guest, he stopped Demodocus
after a pause in the song. 'Good people,
we have enjoyed the food and the song.
Now let us go outside and show our guest
that the Phaeacians are also good sportsmen.'
Everyone followed Alcinous
to the city's meeting-place.
The finest young men in the land
rushed forward to show their skill.
First there was a running race. A great cloud
of dust followed the runners around the course.
Euryalus was soon far ahead of the
rest, and won the race easily. Next
came throwing, jumping and fighting competitions,
each had a different winner. Alcinous's son
Laodamas, who had won the fighting, then went
to Odysseus and said, 'Come, sir, and join our
games. Forget your troubles for a few minutes,
since you will soon be back in your homeland.
If you are good at sport, there is no better
way to make a famous name for yourself.'
Odysseus replied, 'My heart is too
full of sadness to play in your games.
I have suffered disaster after disaster, and now
I can think of nothing except my voyage home.'
Euryalus, the winner of the running race,
joined them. 'We understand, sir,' he said.
'We were wrong to think that you might have
strength or speed. You are more like a sea
captain, worrying about his business and
his ship. Clearly you are not a sportsman.'
Odysseus gave him an angry look. 'You should be
ashamed of yourself for that insult,' he said
angrily. 'Some men do not have the fortune of good
looks, but they win popularity with the people for
their fine intelligence and wise words. Others -
and you are one - are good-looking but arrogant,
with no good sense at all. Your words have
angered me. I am not unskilled at sport,
as you suggest, but after years at war and on
the stormy seas I am not as strong as I once was.
I will join your competition, though, if you wish
it. I will not listen to more of your insults.'
Odysseus jumped from his seat and picked
up a stone disk, much bigger than the ones
that the Phaeacians usually used. Putting all
his weight into the throw, he sent the disk
flying through the air. It landed far beyond
the throw that had won the competition earlier.
Odysseus turned to the Phaeacians with
a smile. 'Now beat that if you can,'
he said. 'But I will probably make
an even longer throw in a minute.
You said that you wanted a competition.
Well, I am happy to beat you in a fight,
or with a bow and arrow. I am confident that I
can win at anything except running. I am weak
after my days at sea, and a younger man
would probably be faster on his legs.'
'My friend,' said King Alcinous,
'I do not blame you for your anger.
Euryalus was wrong to speak to you as he did.
But let us forget the games. When you are at
home with your wife and children, I want you
to tell them of our special Phaeacian skills.
We are not the world's greatest fighters
or throwers, but we can run fast and we are
excellent seamen. We are also very proud
of the fine food, music and dance at our
dinners, and of our wonderful hot baths and
comfortable beds. So come, forget the games,
and let our dancers perform for you. And later our
bard Demodocus can entertain us with his songs.'
For the rest of the afternoon, Odysseus watched
the traditional dances of the Phaeacians
and listened to Demodocus's stories of the
gods. The entertainment ended with a dance
by two of Alcinous's sons, Laodamas and Halius,
in which they threw a purple ball to each other
as they moved in time to the music. 'You
are right to be proud of your dancers,'
Odysseus said to his host. 'I have never
seen such a wonderful performance.'
His words pleased Alcinous.
'Phaeacians,' said the king,
'we must give our guest
suitable gifts to take home.
I and the other twelve princes of the land should
each give him some fine clothes and a bar of gold.
And Euryalus should add his own gift too,
to apologise for his rudeness at the games.'
Everyone agreed with Alcinous's suggestion
and the gifts were organized at once.
Euryalus gave Odysseus a well-made sword,
saying, 'Sir, your visit has been a great
pleasure to the Phaeacian people. If my words
upset you, let the winds blow them away. I pray
to the gods that you have a safe voyage on our
ship and a warm welcome when you reach your home.'
'Friend,' replied Odysseus, 'I thank you,
and pray that the gods give you a happy life.
Your words at the games are now forgotten.'
Queen Arete packed the new clothes and the gold
in a chest, and added a gold cup from her husband.
Then the servants poured Odysseus a hot bath -
and what a pleasure it was to lie in that bath,
after his hard weeks at sea.
When he was dressed, he
went back to the great hall.
Nausicaa was standing at the entrance
to the hall, looking like a goddess.
She was filled with admiration when she saw
Odysseus. 'Good luck, my friend,' she said.
'Think of me sometimes when you are safely
back home. You would not be alive without me.'
'Princess Nausicaa,' replied Odysseus, 'I pray
that Zeus will soon let me see my home again.
If he does, I will always remember you.'
With these words, he entered the hall and
took his seat next to King Alcinous at dinner.
When he saw Demodocus arrive, he asked a servant
to take the bard a plate of meat. Demodocus
accepted it with pleasure, and Odysseus said,
'I have never heard music as beautiful as yours,
Demodocus, and it is wonderful that you know the
story of the Greeks' actions at Troy so well.
Can you tell us now about another part of the
war, when the Greeks built their wooden horse?
If you sing of this as it really happened, I
will tell the world of your God-given skill.'
The bard was happy to take
this story as his subject.
The wooden horse was, he sang, Odysseus's idea for
getting Greek soldiers inside the walls of Troy.
An enormous, hollow horse was made and
Odysseus and some others hid inside.
Then the rest of the Greeks burnt their
defenses and sailed away from the coast,
pretending that they had given up the war. When
the Trojans saw the horse, they pulled it through
the gates of the city, but they argued about what
to do next. Some wanted to throw it off a hillside
and break it on the rocks below, but others
wanted to keep it as a great gift to the gods.
In the end the horse was left untouched. That
night, Odysseus and his friends climbed out
of the horse and opened the city gates to their
army outside. Greek soldiers poured through the
gates to destroy the city. They ran through
the steep streets leaving death behind them,
while Odysseus and Menelaus had the fight of
their lives against the son of the Trojan king.
While the bard was singing, tears ran down
Odysseus's face. When Alcinous noticed his
guest's condition, he said, 'Phaeacians,
though Demodocus tells his story beautifully,
it does not please everyone in the room.
Since we began our meal, our guest has
been crying bitterly. Let us stop the story now,
so that he can enjoy his last evening with us.
We do not want to upset him. And sir,
you should tell us now who you are.
Where is your home? Our seamen will need
to know where to take you. And tell us
about your life and your travels. What places
have you visited? What sights have you seen?
And explain why our bard's stories of the Trojan
War cause you so much unhappiness. Did you know
someone who died at Troy? Did you lose a good
friend, or someone from your family?'
CHAPTER FIVE
A Monster with One Eye
'He jumped up, caught two of my
companions in his great hands,
and knocked their heads against
the stone floor of the cave.'
'King Alcinous,' said Odysseus, 'I do
not know where to begin and end my story.
The gods have put so many troubles in my
path! But I shall start by giving you my name.
Though my home is far from here, I want
you all to think of me as your friend.
I am Odysseus, son of Laertes,
and my home is on Ithaca.
'It is a rocky island, but there is no
sweeter sight for a man than his own country.
The whole world talks about my
clever plans during the Trojan War.
But let me tell you about the
disastrous voyage that followed.'
'From Troy, I sailed with my companions to
the city of the Cicones, who had fought for
the Trojans in the war. We destroyed the city
and killed most of the men who lived there.
We shared the women and the treasures from
the city between us, and then I told my
men to leave. The fools refused. There was
still a lot of wine and meat in the city,
so they stayed there, filling their
stomachs. This gave the Cicones time
to get help from other cities in the area,
whose armies were larger and better trained.
In the morning, they attacked us - as
many of them as the leaves and flowers in
spring. We held them back at first, but after
a whole day of fighting they broke our line.
My men and I had to run to our ships in confusion,
with the enemy at our back. Six men from
each of our twelve ships were killed. The
rest of us were lucky to escape alive.'
'We sailed away as fast as we could,
crying for our lost companions.
Soon there was more trouble. When we were nearly
home, the winds carried us in the wrong direction,
past Cythera. For nine days we were chased
across the waves by those disastrous winds,
and on the tenth day we reached the land of
the Lotus-eaters. We got out of the ships,
collected fresh water for the next part of our
voyage, and had a quick meal on the beach. Then
I sent three of my companions to find out
what sort of people lived in this land.
'The men soon met the Lotus-eaters.
Luckily, they were peaceful people who liked
to share their lotus fruit with strangers.
There was just one problem - if you ate this
sweet fruit, you forgot all thoughts of home.
Immediately, my companions had
no wish to return to the ships
and bring us news. They only wanted to stay with
the Lotus-eaters and eat lotus fruit all day.
In the end, I had to use force to bring
them back. Tears ran down their faces
as I tied them onto the ship and ordered
the other men to continue the voyage home.
'Next we came to the land of the Cyclopes.
They are rough, lawless people, one-eyed and
much taller than normal men. They have no form
of government, but live with their families
and their sheep in caves in the mountains,
paying no attention to their neighbours.
They live on good farm land,
but they do not grow food on it.
They have no ships, either, so
know nothing of the outside world.
'We landed on an island not far from the
Cyclopes's coast and had a look around. No
one lived on the island, but there were
plenty of animals and fruit for food,
and a fresh-water stream. It was a
perfect place to rest from our voyage.
Some of the men went hunting, and soon
there was meat cooking on the fires.'
'All day we ate, washing down the food with
red wine that we had taken from the Cicones.
We looked across the sea to
the land of the Cyclopes.
We could see the smoke from their fires, and
could even hear them calling to their sheep.'
'The next morning, I called the
men together. "My friends," I said,
"I am going to take my ship to find out what
kind of people live in that land over there.
The rest of you, stay here
and wait for our return."'
'My crew sat at their oars and it was not
long before we had crossed to the mainland.
As we were making the ship safe on the
beach, we noticed a cave close to the sea.
It had a very tall entrance, and an area outside
surrounded by a great wall of stones and branches.
I chose my twelve best men to come with me, and
told the rest of my loyal companions to guard
the ship. I filled a large wineskin
with the finest wine from the ship.
It had been a present from one of the Cicones,
a servant of the god Apollo, whose family I
had protected during our attack on his city.
It was a wonderful drink. The servant
had kept it secret for many years,
and when he drank it he mixed one cupful of wine
with twenty cupful's of water. The smell of the
wine was heavenly, and no one could refuse a drink
of it. I brought this wine with me, and some food,
because I had a strange feeling that the people
in this land were not going to be welcoming hosts.
'It did not take us long to reach
the cave. Its owner was not at home,
so we went inside and looked around.
There were enormous baskets of cheese,
wooden buckets full of milk, and sheep
organized into different age groups - new-born
babies in one area, spring-born in
another, and summer-born in a third.
My men suggested taking some cheese and
sheep to the ship and sailing away quickly.
Although this was good advice, I decided instead
to wait for the owner of the cave to return.
I was hoping for some gifts from our host.
'We lit a fire, ate some cheese, and sat down to
wait. At last, the cave's owner arrived. He was a
great monster, more like a mountain than a man,
and had one big eye in the middle of his face.
He was carrying an enormous pile of dry wood for
the fire, which he threw down on the ground inside
the cave with a great crash. We were so frightened
by the noise that we ran to the back of the cave.
He had been out on the hills with the adult
sheep. Now he drove some of the sheep into
the cave for milking, and left the
others in the walled area outside.
Then he closed the entrance with an enormous
stone, too big for twenty horses to pull.
He milked his sheep, then put
each mother with her young.
He used some of the milk for cheese, and left
the rest in a bucket to drink with supper. When
he had finished his work, he lit the fire
again. That was the moment when he saw us.
'"Strangers!" he cried. "Who are you? Where are
you from? And why have you come to these shores?"
'The man's monstrous body and deep,
loud voice filled us with terror,
but I managed to find the words to reply. "We
are Greeks," I said, "on our way back from Troy.
The winds drove us in the wrong direction - as
the gods intended, I suppose. We are proud to
say that we fought with great Agamemnon in the
Trojan War. But now we are asking for your help.
We are hoping that you can welcome us as your
guests, and perhaps even give us some gifts.
Remember your duty to Zeus, who is the protector
of travellers in need of a friendly welcome."
"'Stranger, you must be a fool, or from
very far from here, if you think that I
care about Zeus and the other gods. We
Cyclopes are much stronger than the gods.
I will only be kind to you and your men if it
suits me, not out of fear of Zeus's punishments.
But tell me, where did you leave your ship?
Was it near here, or further along the coast?"
'His question was intended to trick me,
but I am not a fool. I quickly thought
of a story to tell him. "Our ship was
destroyed in a storm off your coast.
It is in pieces on the rocks north of here.
Luckily, I and my friends here escaped alive."
The cruel monster did not reply. Instead, he
jumped up, caught two of my companions in his
great hands, and knocked their heads
against the stone floor of the cave.
He ate their legs first, then their arms,
then the rest of them, even the bones,
until there was nothing left. We watched in shock,
praying to Zeus for pity. When the Cyclops had
finished his meal and washed it down with milk,
he stretched out next to his sheep for a sleep.
I felt for my sword, planning to kill him
as he slept. But then I saw the heavy stone
in the entrance and realized that without his
strength we could never get out of the cave.
So we waited fearfully for morning.
When he woke, the Cyclops lit the fire again and
milked his sheep. Then he took two more of my
men and ate them greedily. Finally, he pushed the
stone away from the entrance without difficulty,
drove the adult sheep out of the
cave, and replaced the stone.
As he went with the sheep to find grass, I
was left in the cave with murder in my heart.
This was my plan. In the cave there was an
enormous stick. The Cyclops sometimes carried it
when he was out walking, but it was big
enough to support the sail of a good-sized
ship. I cut off part of this stick
and gave it a sharp point at the end.
Then my men and I held it over the fire
to make it hard. When it was ready,
we hid it at the back of the cave. Then I chose
four men to help me when the Cyclops returned.
'Evening finally came, and the
Cyclops returned with his sheep.
This time he left none of the
sheep outside in the walled area.
When they were all safely inside the cave with
him, he closed the entrance with the stone,
did the milking, took another two of my men
and started eating. Trying to hide my fear,
I went to him with a wooden bowl full of the
wine that I had brought with me. "Here, Cyclops,
have some wine to wash down your meal.
There was some very fine wine on our ship.
We brought it to you as a gift, hoping that
you would help us on our journey home. We
wanted to be your friends, but your treatment of
us has been more terrible than we ever imagined.
Are you not ashamed of your behavior?"
The Cyclops laughed and took the wine.
"It tasted so good that he drank
it quickly and asked for more."
"And while you pour it, tell me your name,"
he said. "I would like to give you a present
too - something that you will really like.
We Cyclopes have wine, too, but it is
nothing compared to this drink of yours."
'I gave him another bowlful of wine, and
he drank it even more quickly than before.
Three times I filled the bowl for him, and three
times the fool drank to the bottom of the bowl.
Finally, when the wine had confused his
mind, I said, "Cyclops, you asked me my name.
I will tell you, and then you can give me the
gift that you have promised. My name is Nobody."
The cruel monster answered, "And here is my
gift. Of all these men, I will eat Nobody last."
'Soon after he said this, he fell to the ground.
He did not get up, but lay on his back, laughing,
until he went to sleep. In this alcoholic
sleep, he was sick. Wine mixed with bits of
my eaten men poured from his mouth. It was hard
not to be sick ourselves at this terrible sight.
But this was our moment to act. I put the end
of our stick into the dying fire to make it hot.
Just before the stick started to burn, I pulled
it out of the fire. Then my companions and I drove
the sharp point of the stick into the Cyclops's
eye. With all our force, we held it there,
as his eye smoked and burned. He gave a
terrible scream, and we moved away in terror.
'He pulled the stick from his eye,
which was pouring blood onto the ground.
Throwing the stick away, he called to the
other Cyclopes who lived in caves in the area.
Hearing his screams, they came to find out what
was wrong. From outside the cave, they shouted,
"What is the matter, Polyphemus? Why have
you woken us all up with those screams and
shouts of yours? Is someone stealing
your sheep or trying to kill you?"
Out of the cave came Polyphemus's reply.
"My friends, Nobody is trying to kill me."
"Well, if no one is attacking
you and your sheep are safe,
you must be crazy," said his neighbours.
"Illnesses of the mind are sent by Zeus,
so we can do nothing to help you. You should
pray to your father, the god Poseidon."
'And his neighbours went home, while I laughed
that my false name had tricked them so easily.
The Cyclops was still crying out in pain. He
felt around the mouth of the cave with his hands,
hoping to catch us as we tried to escape.
Did he really think that I was so stupid?
But if we wanted to leave the land of
the Cyclopes alive, we needed a good
plan. I spent a long time thinking. In
the end, this is what I decided to do.
'The male sheep in the cave were fine animals,
big and strong with coats of thick black wool.
I quietly tied these sheep together in groups
of three, putting one of my men under the
middle sheep in each group so that there
was a sheep on either side to protect him.
For myself I chose the biggest sheep of all.
I held on to his wool and hung upside-down between
his legs. We waited like this until morning.
When it grew light, the sheep made
their way to the mouth of the cave.
Their master, although still in great pain,
passed his hands over the backs of all the animals
as they stopped in front of him. The fool never
thought of looking under the sheep's chests,
where my men were tied. My own sheep
was the last one to reach the doorway;
he walked more slowly than the others because
of my heavy weight. As Polyphemus felt his back,
he said, "Dear sheep, why are
you the last to leave today?
Usually you lead your companions proudly to the
best grass and the clearest water in the stream,
and return first in the evening to the
cave. But today you are last of all.
You must be sad about your master's eye.
How cruel was the man who did this to me!
Nobody was his name, and I will find a
way to punish him. He is not safe yet.
Ah, if you had a voice, you could tell me where
to look for him. I would break open his head
on the floor of the cave to pay him back
for the pain that he has caused me!"
With these words, he let the sheep
pass through the mouth of the cave.
When we were a safe distance from the
Cyclops, I came out from under my sheep
and untied my companions. Then we quickly
drove the sheep down towards our ship.
The men at the ship were very happy to see us,
but their smiles soon disappeared when they heard
of the terrible fate of our lost companions.
Their loud crying was putting us all in danger,
so I made them get the sheep onto the
ship as quickly and quietly as possible.
Then the crew sat at their oars
and took the ship out to sea.
Before we were too far from Polyphemus, I
shouted, "Cyclops! Your strength could not
protect you from the resourceful Greeks. This
is your punishment for eating your guests."
My words made the Cyclops so angry that he pulled
a great rock from the mountainside and threw it at
us. It fell just in front of our ship, causing
a wave that sent us back towards the shore.
With a long stick, I pushed us back out to sea,
and the crew pulled hard on their
oars to save us from disaster.
When I started to shout at the Cyclops
again, my men tried to stop me. "Why do
you want to anger this monster?" they asked.
"He nearly killed us with that last rock.
The next one will certainly be the end of us."
'But I was too full of emotion to listen to
their advice. "Cyclops!" I shouted again,
"you should know the name of the man who
blinded you. If anyone asks you, tell them
that it was Odysseus, destroyer of cities, son
of Laertes, who lives on the island of Ithaca."
'The Cyclops cried sadly,
"So the prophecy was true!
Long ago I was warned that a man called
Odysseus would rob me of my sight. But
I had always expected a powerful man, someone
bigger and stronger than me. And here you are,
a weak little man who confused my mind with wine
and destroyed my eye. But come here, Odysseus,
so that I can give you some gifts and ask Poseidon
to protect you on your voyage home. Poseidon is my
father, so he will listen to my request. He will
give me back my sight, too, if that is my fate."
I shouted in reply, "You are a fool,
Cyclops. Poseidon will never mend your eye."
The Cyclops held up his hands to the
sky and prayed to his father. "Poseidon,
hear your son's request. Stop Odysseus, son
of Laertes, from reaching his home in Ithaca.
That is my dearest wish. But if you cannot do
this, at least give him a terrible journey.
Kill his companions, destroy his ships,
and cause trouble in his palace at home."
The sea-god Poseidon was listening.
Again, the Cyclops picked up a great rock -
an even bigger one than before - and threw
it with all his strength at our ship. This
time, though, we were further from the shore;
the rock fell behind us and its
wave swept us forward to safety.
At last, we reached the island where the
rest of the men were waiting for our return.
We shared the sheep equally
between the twelve ships,
but the men gave me the sheep that had
carried me out of Polyphemus's cave.
I sacrificed this fine animal to the great
god Zeus. But Zeus was not interested in
the sacrifice. He was already busy planning
the death of all my loyal companions.'
CHAPTER SIX
Circe
'They had taken the shape of pigs. Their minds
were still human, but they could not speak;
only pig noises came from their mouths.'
We sailed towards home, thinking sadly of
the dead friends that we were leaving behind.
Next we came to the island of Aeolia, the
home of Aeolus and his twelve children - six
daughters and six fine sons. Each son
is married to one of the daughters,
and they spend all their days with their parents,
eating wonderful food from dishes of gold.
'For a whole month Aeolus entertained us.
He wanted to know all about the war in Troy,
the Greek army, and our return home.
I told him everything that I could.
I soon learnt that Zeus had given Aeolus control
of the winds. He offered to help us on our journey
by giving me a leather bag in which all the strong
and stormy winds were kept prisoner. He put this
bag carefully in my ship and tied it up tightly
so that the winds had no chance of escape. Then
he sent us on our way with a gentle wind from the
west, which blew our ships safely towards home.
For nine days we sailed east. I guided the ship
home myself, without a minute's rest. Then,
finally, our homeland came into view. We could
even see people working outside their houses.
At last I felt that I could
relax, and fell into a deep sleep.
While I slept, my crew started talking about the
bag from Aeolus. "There must be a fortune in gold
and silver in that bag," they said. "Odysseus
is so greedy. He is going home rich, but we,
who have travelled the same distances and lived
through the same dangers, are returning with
nothing. It is just not fair! Let us see
how much treasure he has got in that bag."
Without stopping to think, they untied the
bag. Immediately the winds rushed out and
a violent storm blew up. Our twelve
ships were carried back out to sea,
far away from our homes on Ithaca. The
men were all crying when I woke up.
When I realized what had happened, I nearly
threw myself into the sea to end my life.
But I stayed on the ship, and we were
all driven back to the island of Aeolus.
After a quick rest on the beach, I went with
two companions to Aeolus's palace. When he
saw us outside his hall, he cried, "Odysseus?
What unlucky fate has brought you here again?"
'Sadly, I answered, "The stupidity
of my crew and my own need for sleep
have brought me back. Please, help me again. I am
sure that this time my voyage will be successful."
'He was silent. Finally, he shouted,
"Get off this island at once!
It is not right for me to help a
man who is so hated by the gods.
Your arrival here proves that you have
no friends on Mount Olympus. Leave now!"
His words upset me deeply, but I left the palace
as he ordered and returned to the ships. We
sailed for home again, but with none of the good
humor that went with us on our earlier voyage.
After six days at sea, we reached
the land of the Laestrygonians.
There we found a great curve of beach circled by
high walls of rock, with only a narrow entrance.
The captains of the other ships sailed straight
in and landed on the shore. I did not follow them.
Instead, I tied my own ship to a rock just
outside the entrance. We all climbed up the
steep rocks to find out what kind of land we
had come to. We saw no farms and no people,
but there was some smoke in the distance. I sent
three of my men in the direction of the smoke.
They followed a path for some
time, until they saw a big,
strong girl carrying buckets of water into a town.
When they asked her about her country's king, she
pointed to the high roof of her father's home.
She was the daughter of King Antiphates. The
men entered the king's palace and met his wife,
a woman as tall as a mountain. They stood
still in terror as she called her husband
from the city's meeting-place. When the enormous
Antiphates arrived, he immediately caught one of
my companions in his hands and ate him. The other
two ran away, and managed to reach the ships.
But Antiphates was soon at the coast
with an army of monstrous Laestrygonians.
Standing high above the beach, they threw
rocks down at the ships and men on the shore.
When the ships were all broken, they picked up
the men one by one and ate them. The cries of the
dying men were terrible, but I could do nothing to
help them. My ship was beyond the entrance to the
beach, safe from the monsters. My crew, fearing
for their lives, pulled hard on their oars,
and we were soon in the safety of the open sea.
But that was the end of all the other ships.
My crew and I travelled across the sea to
the island of Aeaea. There we lay on the
beach for two days, not eating or drinking,
but thinking sadly about our lost companions.
On the morning of the third day, I
climbed a hill to look at the island.
There was just one house, in the middle of
a forest. I decided not to go there at once.
Instead, I went hunting and returned
to my men with some fresh meat.
"My friends," I said to them, "disaster
has followed disaster recently,
but we are still alive. Get up and eat.
There is no point in dying from hunger."
They did as I advised, and when night came, they
were feeling a little stronger and more hopeful.
The next morning, I called a meeting. "I
will not lie to you, friends," I began.
"We are completely lost. With all these clouds in
the sky, we do not even know which way is east.
We must make a sensible plan, but I do not
know what to suggest. We are on an island,
and there is a house in the middle of a forest.
There is nothing else that I can tell you."
At this news, the men lost all hope.
They thought of the Laestrygonians
and refused to visit any more strangers.
But we had to find help from somewhere.
In the end, I put the men into two groups. We
said goodbye to each other with tears in our eyes,
fearing that we would never meet
again. My group stayed by the ships
and Eurylochus led the
other group into the forest.
Between the trees, they soon found a house built
of stone. Dangerous animals surrounded the house,
but instead of attacking the men, they greeted
them as a friendly dog greets its master.
The men stopped, confused
by this unusual behavior.
'They could hear a woman singing inside the house.
After a whispered discussion, the men decided to
call out to her. She came quickly. She said that
her name was Circe, and she invited them in. In
their innocence, they followed her into the house.
Only Eurylochus sensed the
danger and stayed outside.
Circe gave the rest of the men a wonderful meal.
But she had added a magic drug to their drink.
When the men finished, they saw that they
had taken the shape of pigs. Their minds
were still human, but they could not speak,
only pig noises came from their mouths.
Circe took a stick and drove them outside.
There they sat in the mud, eating
the pig food that she threw to them.
After waiting near the house for several hours,
Eurylochus ran back to the ship. In tears,
he told us that none of his companions had
reappeared after they had entered Circe's house.
I picked up my sword and asked him to lead
the way back there. He went down on his knees,
crying, "No, Odysseus, please! Do not make
me go with you. You cannot help the others,
and you will not return yourself. It is better
to sail away quickly with the men that are left."
"Dry your tears, Eurylochus," I
replied. "You can stay by the ship.
But I must go - I have no choice."
I walked into the forest alone. I was
near Circe's house when I met Hermes,
the messenger of the gods. He took my hand
and said, "Where are you going now, Odysseus?
Are you planning to free your friends from Circe's
magic? Be careful! She has turned them into pigs.
You are likely to suffer the same fate and never
see your homeland again. But I can help you.
This flower is a drug that will
protect you from Circe's magic.
Eat it now, and when she hits you with
her stick, attack her with your sword.
She will be very frightened and will immediately
ask to be your friend. You should agree.
But first make her promise not
to trick you or drug you again."
I ate the white flower that he gave me. Then I
continued along the path to Circe's house. I stood
outside and called. Circe heard me and invited
me in. She gave me some of her magic drink,
but because of Hermes's drug, it had no effect
on me. She hit me with her stick and shouted,
"Go and join your pig friends in the mud!"
At that moment, I attacked her with my sword.
She went down on her knees, screaming and crying,
and said, "Who are you and where are you from?
You are the only man who has ever had that
magic drink and not suffered any ill effects.
You must be Odysseus. Hermes has often warned
me to expect you on your way back from Troy.
But we should not be enemies. Let us be friends."
"Circe," I replied, "how can we be friends
when you have turned my companions into pigs?
I will only agree if you promise
not to trick me or drug me again."
She promised, and so we went back inside.
She gave me a bath, dressed me in
new clothes and offered me more food.
When she saw that I was not eating,
she asked me what the matter was.
"How can I eat," I replied, "when
I do not know if my men are safe?
There will be no pleasure for me in food and
drink until I see my loyal companions again."
Circe went outside at once, and
came back with some smelly pigs
covered in mud. She put a special
cream on the head of each one,
and they magically turned into men again, but
younger, taller and more handsome than before.
We all cried tears of happiness. It was
wonderful to see everyone safe and well.
Circe now told me to fetch the rest of my
men from the seashore. When they saw me,
they greeted me with great excitement. They
had been sure that I would never return.
We pulled the ship onto dry land and hid
our treasure and equipment in a cave.
The men were in a hurry to see
their friends at Circe s house,
but Eurylochus stopped them. "Where are
you going now, you fools?" he said to them.
"Have you learned nothing from the past few weeks?
Odysseus leads us from one disaster to another.
It is because of his thoughtless love of adventure
that our companions died in the Cyclops's cave."
When I heard Eurylochus's words, I nearly
cut his head from his body with my sword.
But my men held me back. "Let
Eurylochus stay here with the ship,"
they said. "The rest of us want
to go with you to meet Circe."
In the end, Eurylochus came too. He
did not want to stay alone by the ship.
So together we walked back to Circes house
and found our companions having baths.
Everyone greeted each other with tears in their
eyes. Then Circe ordered her servants to prepare
a meal, and we celebrated our first evening
at Circe's house in very good humor.'
CHAPTER SEVEN
Teiresias's Prophecy
If you leave his cows unharmed,
you will arrive safely in Ithaca.
But if you hurt those cows, your
ship and your men will be destroyed.'
Circe was a very welcoming hostess, and
we stayed with her for a whole year.
But as the months passed and the
long days of summer returned,
my companions became anxious that I had
forgotten my home in Ithaca. "Why are we
still here on Circe's island?" they asked me
one day. "It is time to continue our voyage."
That night I spoke to Circe. I told
her about my companions' complaints,
and she agreed to help us with our voyage.
"But first," she said, "you must visit the
Underworld and talk to blind old Teiresias.
Although he is dead, his prophecies are
as true as they were during his lifetime."
This news broke my heart. I nearly chose
to end my life there in Circe's house
to escape the awful journey
to the world of the dead.
But finally I asked her, "How can I find the
way? No one has ever sailed a ship into Hell."
"Do not worry. The north wind
will blow you to the right place.
At the edge of the world, you will see a place
where tall trees grow. Land your ship there
and the ghosts of the
Underworld will come to you."
She told me what to do and say when I reached that
terrible place. She promised that Teiresias
would tell me the route of my journey home.
Waking everyone up in the morning,
I shouted, "Hurry, my friends,
and say goodbye to your comfortable beds.
It is time to go. Circe has given us
instructions for the next part of our journey."
My brave companions were happy to make their
way back to the ship. But even this time I
did not lead everyone away safely. Elpenor was
the youngest in our group, and not very clever.
The night before, after too much wine, he had
decided to sleep on the roof because the air
was fresher there. Woken in the morning by the
noise of our departure, he jumped up suddenly
and fell off the roof. The fall broke his neck.
When we went to help him, we found him dead.
By the ship, I told the men that our voyage
would not take us straight home. When they
heard that our destination was the world of
the dead, they were filled with terror. But
they could say nothing to change the
fate that the gods had chosen for us.
Circe gave us a good wind to fill our
sails and, a day after leaving Aeaea,
we reached a dark land at the edge of the world.
There we found the place that Circe had described,
where tall trees grow. I landed the ship and
started to follow Circe's instructions for calling
the dead. I dug a hole in the ground, the size of
a man's arm. Into this hole I poured milk, water
and sweet wine. I prayed to the dead and
sacrificed two fine sheep from my ship.
As their blood poured into the hole, ghosts
started to come up from the earth - young girls,
old men, and soldiers killed in war.
They were making a strange noise, and cold
fear ran through me. I guarded the hole with
my sword held tightly. I did not want any
ghosts to get to the blood before Teiresias.
Suddenly, I recognised the ghost of Elpenor.
In our hurry to leave Circe's island, we had not
burnt his body or built a mound of earth for him.
I called out, "Elpenor! You have reached here more
quickly on foot than we did in our fast ship."
"Yes, master, but you rushed away from Aeaea too
fast. Please, when you return, remember my body.
Burn it on the beach with my sword, and
build a mound of earth in my memory.
At the top, plant the oar that I used
on the ship with my dear companions."
"I will do all that you ask,
dear Elpenor," I replied.
Teiresias was not far behind him.
"Odysseus, son of Laertes, why have
you left the sunlight to visit the dead
in this sad, dark place? If you want
a prophecy, step away from the blood.
I will tell you your future after I have drunk."
I let him drink the blood, and he soon
said, "My lord Odysseus, you want an
easy route home. But Poseidon is angry
about your cruel treatment of his son,
the Cyclops, and he is going to make your journey
hard. You and your men will finally reach home,
though, if you can control your hunger
when you come to the island of Thrinacie.
There you will find the fat cows of the Sun
god, who can see everything on his daily
journey across the sky. If you leave his cows
unharmed, you will arrive safely in Ithaca.
But if you hurt those cows, your ship and
your men will be destroyed. You yourself
will return home on a foreign ship and find
your family in terrible trouble. You will find
arrogant suitors in your palace, eating your
food and demanding marriage with your wife.
You will kill the suitors for their crimes.
But then you must start another journey.
Take an oar and travel until you find a
place where the people know nothing about
the sea and ships and the use of salt in their
food. You will meet a man who calls your oar
a farm tool. That will be your sign. Plant
your oar in the earth and sacrifice a sheep,
a cow and a pig to the great god Poseidon. After
this, you can go home. You will have a long life,
and you will die peacefully of old
age, far from the terrors of the sea."
"So this is the fate that the gods have chosen
for me," I said. "Thank you, Teiresias."
As Teiresias went back to the Underworld, the
ghost of my mother, Anticleia, came towards
me. I was deeply upset to see her there. She had
been alive when I left Ithaca for the war in Troy.
"Mother, tell me what happened to you," I cried.
"What death brought you to this terrible place?"
"It was sadness that killed me, Odysseus, my
child. I missed your wise and gentle ways,
and life gave me no pleasure. In
death, I have escaped that pain."
I tried to put my arms around her,
but there was nothing to hold. My
arms went straight through her.
"You cannot touch me, Odysseus. When life
leaves the body, we become no more than a dream.
But go now, return to the world of
the sun, and find your way back home."
"But what can you tell me about home,"
I asked her. "How is the rest of
the family? Are they safe and well?"
"Penelope and Telemachus are still living in your
palace, trying to keep your lands safe from the
greedy suitors. But your father Laertes lives
a sad and lonely life, alone on his fruit farm.
He never goes down to the city now. In winter
he sleeps on the floor by his fire, without a
bed or a blanket to keep him warm. In summer, he
sleeps under the fruit trees in a bed of leaves.
As old age presses down on him, he
thinks of nothing except your return."
Soon Persephone, Queen of the Underworld, drove
away my mother and the other women ghosts who
were with her. In shock, I saw another ghost that
I recognised - Agamemnon. He drank the dark blood
and stretched out his hand towards me. But all
the strength had left the body that had been
so powerful, and he could not reach me. He and
I looked at each other with tears in our eyes.
Finally, I said, "Great king, what
terrible fate has brought you here?
Were you killed in a storm on your way home
from Troy, or in a fight on enemy lands?"
"No, my friend," Agamemnon replied. "I was
murdered when I reached my homeland by my cousin
Aegisthus. Aegisthus welcomed me to my palace,
then killed me like a sheep for a sacrifice.
My companions were cut down too, and
the floor of the hall swam with blood.
You saw the deaths of many fine men at Troy,
Odysseus, but none were as pitiful as ours.
"And, worst of all, my wife
Clytaemnestra was there watching.
When I was dying, with a sword in my chest,
she turned away coldly and joined her lover,
Aegisthus. She did not even close
my eyes or mouth for me in death."
"Poor man!" I cried. "Zeus has
been a cruel enemy to your family,
using the tricks of women
to destroy your happiness.
Your brother s wife Helen caused the Trojan
War, and now your own wife has sent you here."
"Yes," replied Agamemnon. "Never tell a woman
all your secrets, Odysseus, not even your wife,
because one day she may turn against you. When
you reach home, do not sail openly into port.
Hide your return until you are sure that you are
safe. But you are luckier than I was, my friend.
Your own wife, Penelope, has a
loyal heart and a wise head."
I said a sad goodbye to Agamemnon.
I had learned what I needed to in this
terrible place. It was time to leave.
I called to my men to get the ship ready, and soon
we were on our way. With a good wind in our sails,
we quickly reached Aeaea, the
island of beautiful Circe.
We found Elpenors body and took it to the
highest place on the coast. There we built a fire
and placed his body on it. We watched
sadly as the flames surrounded him.
When the fire was dead, we covered
the place with a mound of earth
and planted Elpenor's oar on top. I prayed that
his death would be the last on our journey home.
Circe had noticed our return, and came now with
her servants, carrying bread, meat and wine.
We had a good meal on the beach, in
preparation for our voyage the next day.
When it grew dark, my men went to sleep by
the ship, but Circe held me back. She wanted
to warn me about the dangers of the voyage ahead.
"Listen to my advice, Odysseus, and hopefully you
will remember it when you need it most. You will
soon meet the Sirens. They sit on their island,
singing to the sailors who pass. They ask people
to come closer, and their voices are so beautiful
that the sailors cannot refuse. But be careful.
Piles of dead bodies lie all around that island.
Its rocks destroy any ship that goes near.
But it is possible to sail past safely.
Put wax in the ears of your crew, so that
they cannot hear the Sirens' magical song.
If you wish to hear it yourself, your
men must tie you tightly to the ship.
They must not free you until the danger
has passed. When the Sirens are behind you,
you will have to choose between two routes.
One takes you to the Moving Rocks, which crash
together whenever a ship sails between them. Even
the birds cannot fly through this place safely,
but lose a wing or a tail when the rocks squeeze
tight. For sailors, there is no hope of escape.
In the other direction lie two rocks. One
is so tall and steep that no one could climb
to the top of it. Half way up there is a
cave, and this is the home of the monster
Scylla. She is a terrible sight, with twelve
feet and six long necks, each ending in a head
full of teeth as sharp as knives. She lies
in her cave, stretching her long necks down
to the sea in search of seals and fish to eat.
No crew has ever passed her without losing men.
She always catches a sailor in each of her
six mouths. The other rock is not as high,
and is only a short distance across
the water from Scylla's cave.
A fruit tree grows from the rock, and below it
the awful Charybdis pulls down the dark water to
the sea floor. Three times a day she pulls it
down, and three times she throws it up again.
I pray that the gods keep you away from her,
because not even the sea-god Poseidon could
save your ship from her violent seas.
No, you must stay close to Scylla's rock
and sail past as quickly as you can. It is better
to lose six of your men than your whole crew."
"Yes," I replied. "But is there really no way
to protect all my men from these two monsters?"
"Are you still looking for trouble,
Odysseus, after all that you have suffered?
Scylla is a monster of great power.
She cannot die. You will waste time
if you try to fight her. Then she will be
able to take even more of your men. No,
you must accept your fate. Sacrifice six
of your men and the rest will be safe."
As she finished speaking, the sun came up. I said
goodbye to Circe and went back to my companions.
We untied the ship and were soon on
our way. We made good progress as the
men pulled on their oars. It was time
to prepare them for the danger ahead.
"My friends, Circe has given me advice for the
rest of our journey. I must share it with you.
First, we will come to the island of the Sirens.
I will protect your ears from the magic of the
Sirens' song. But one of us should listen. Tie me
very tightly to the ship so that I cannot escape.
If I complain, tie me more tightly.
Do not take the ship near the island,
even if I command it a hundred times. The
rocks destroy all ships that go near."
I took some wax and made it warm in my hands.
Then I pushed a little into everyone's
ears, so that they could hear nothing.
When this was done, the men tied my hands and
feet to the ship, and we were ready to continue.
The Sirens' island soon came into view.
We saw three strange women on the island,
with beautiful human faces but the bodies
of birds. They started their magical song,
and it was the most beautiful music in the
world. I was filled with desire to hear more.
When they asked me to come to them, I wanted to
with all my heart. I ordered my men to untie me,
but of course they could not hear. I tried
to break free, but they tied me more tightly.
Sadly, I watched the men take me further
and further from the Sirens' island.
Finally, they untied me and took out the wax
from their ears. With Circe's help, we were safe.
But there was no time to
discuss what had happened.
We saw rough water ahead, and heard
the thunder of waves against rocks.
The crew were so frightened that the oars fell
from their hands. I walked around the ship,
saying, "We have met trouble before, my friends.
With my help, you escaped the Cyclops's cave.
Today you must follow my orders again. We are
going to go as close as possible to the higher
rock, keeping the ship away from the rough water.
Stay at your oars and pull as hard as you can."
The crew obeyed. I did not tell them about Scylla,
because fear of the monster would stop them from
pulling on their oars. I stood at the front of
the ship, hoping to get the first view of those
six long necks. I looked until my eyes
grew tired, but I could see nothing.
Then, suddenly, Charybdis threw up
the water from the deep sea floor.
Salt water fell down on us like rain, and
the top of the sea was like boiling water.
Then she pulled the water down again, and we
could see the sand at the bottom of the sea.
My men were pale with fear. Then, while
everyone was looking at Charybdis,
Scylla stretched her necks down from her cave
and caught six of my strongest men in her mouths.
Their arms and legs waved pitifully in the air
as they called for help. But we could do nothing
to save them. In seconds, the monster had carried
them up to her cave and started her terrible meal.
We continued sadly on our way, and soon we saw
the lovely island of Thrinacie. As we came near
the beach, we could heard the sound of cows.
I remembered the words of Teiresias and said,
"Listen carefully, my friends. In the Underworld,
Teiresias warned me about this island. There is
a greater danger here than any that we have met
before. Sail past the island. We should not land."
My men were very upset. Eurylochus
shouted, "Do you never get tired, Odysseus?
How can you tell us not to land here,
after everything that has happened today?
You must be made of iron! It is nearly sunset,
and we are tired and hungry. If we continue past
this island, we will be at sea all night
- there is no other land near here.
And storms are always worse at night. Do you
really want the winds to destroy our ship? You are
crazy. We should land here and cook our supper.
In the morning, we can go back to the open sea."
The rest of the crew agreed with him,
and I realized that the gods had already
decided our fate. "I am one against many,
Eurylochus. I cannot refuse your demands.
But I ask every one of you to promise that
you will not harm the animals on the island.
Sit peacefully and eat the
food that Circe has given us.
If you eat anything else, I cannot
save you from a disastrous end."
When everyone on the ship had given me their
promise, we landed on the Sun-god's island. We ate
a good supper, but the conversation kept returning
to the men that Scylla had taken from us.
During the night, a storm blew up, and
in the morning it was not safe to sail.
I called my companions to a meeting and said,
"We still have plenty of food on the ship.
Keep your hands off the cows on this island, or
disaster will follow. They belong to the Sun-god,
who can see everything on his
daily journey across the sky."
The men agreed willingly. But the storm
did not stop. For a whole month it blew,
and we were unable to leave the island. While our
bread and wine lasted, the men obeyed my orders.
When there was nothing more to eat, they went
fishing and caught birds from the trees, but they
were still hungry. I hoped that one of the gods
would take pity on us and show me a way to escape.
I found a quiet place, out of the wind, to pray.
But when I had finished, the
gods sent me into a deep sleep.
While I slept, Eurylochus was causing trouble down
by the ship. "No death is pleasant," he argued,
"but a death from hunger is the
worst. I say we should eat those cows.
We can sacrifice them to the gods, and promise
to give all our treasure to the Sun god
when we return to Ithaca. If he is still
angry with us, let him destroy our ship.
A quick death at sea is easier than a
slow and painful one on this island."
The rest of the crew agreed to his plan. Quickly,
they brought the cows together and sacrificed them
to the gods. They had no wine to pour over the
meat as it cooked, so they used seawater instead.
As I woke from my sleep, I smelled
the meat cooking on the fire. "So
the gods have decided to ruin me," I
cried. "There is no hope for us now!"
High in the sky, the Sun god
had seen my companions' crime.
He went to Zeus in anger, saying, "Odysseus
and his followers have killed my fine cows.
You must punish them, as they deserve.
If you leave their actions unpunished,
I will disappear from the sky and
shine on the dead in the Underworld."
"Shine on us here on Olympus and
on the world of men," Zeus replied.
"You can be sure that I
will punish the criminals."
This was their conversation on Olympus.
Calypso heard about it from Hermes
and later reported it to me.
Down on the Sun god's island, the men were
frightened. They could already see the
signs of the gods' anger. The skins of the dead
animals were moving magically around the beach,
and the pieces of meat on the fire were
calling out to each other like cows.
But we could do nothing to change the situation.
The cows were dead. The damage had been done.
For six days, the men ate the meat of
the Sun-god's cows. On the seventh,
the wind dropped and it was safe to sail. With
fear in our hearts, we took our ship out to sea.
Almost immediately, a cloud formed above the
ship, making a dark shadow on the sea around us.
Then came the wind. With the force of a wild
animal, it attacked us. It pulled the sail from
the ship in seconds. Wood came crashing down onto
the sailors below and one man was knocked into
the sea. Worse followed, as Zeus struck the ship
with lightning. The whole ship shook violently.
The men held on tightly, but one by
one they were thrown from the ship.
They were pulled this way and that in the water
until they went down under the waves forever.
I alone was left on board. But soon the strength
of the enormous waves broke the ship into pieces.
Luckily, I managed to climb onto a broken piece
of wood, and I held on tightly. All night I was
blown around by the wind. At sunrise I saw that
I had been driven back to the rocks of Scylla
and Charybdis. Charybdis was beginning to pull the
waters down and I was swept towards a great hole
in the sea. Just in time, I managed to catch
a branch of the tree that grew from the rock.
I could not get my feet onto the tree,
but I hung by my arms, hour after hour.
Finally, my wait was over. Charybdis threw
up the wood that had saved me from the storm.
I let myself fall back into the sea, swam
to the wood and climbed back on. Luckily,
Scylla did not see me, because there was
nothing to protect me from her greedy mouths.
'I was at sea for another nine days, until the
waves carried me to the shores of Calypso's
island. She was kind to me and gave me a
home. But I have already told you about
my life with Calypso, good Phaeacians. I
have reached the end of my story.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
Coming Home
'Look around you, Odysseus. Do
you not recognise this beach,
those rocks, and that tree on the hills above?'
When Odysseus had finished, the hall was
silent until Alcinous said, 'Odysseus,
you have suffered greatly. But I am sure that
you will reach home safely now, with our help.'
Then he spoke to his Phaeacian guests. 'Friends,'
he said, 'we have already given our guests fine
gifts, but does this man not deserve more after
all his troubles? Go now and bring him some more
treasure from your home. Later we will ask
the common people to pay for these gifts;
we do not want any man's generosity to ruin him.'
The next day the Phaeacians came to the
port with their gifts of gold and silver,
and Alcinous himself helped to
put the gifts safely on the ship.
Then they all returned to the
palace for more food and music,
as the voyage was not going to start until
sunset. All day Odysseus kept looking at the sun.
He was like a farmer who has worked hard in the
fields all day; sunset is a welcome sight to a
man with tired legs and an empty stomach - it
is the time to stop work and go home for supper.
In the same way, Odysseus welcomed sunset that
day. As soon as the sun had sunk below the sea,
he said, 'Alcinous, great king, let me say
goodbye. You have given me the two things
that I most wanted - valuable gifts and a crew
to take me home. I pray that the gods bring
you and your family all the happiness that you
deserve, and keep your people safe from harm.'
Odysseus and the Phaeacians walked down to the
port, and the servants carried bread and wine for
the voyage. On the ship, a blanket was spread out
for Odysseus to sleep on. Then, after praying to
the gods, Odysseus climbed on board. He lay down
on the blanket and the crew sat at their oars.
As the ship left the port, Odysseus immediately
fell into a deep and peaceful sleep.
And now, like a team of four
horses in a chariot race,
the ship raced through the water towards Ithaca.
After a journey of magical speed, it arrived
on the coast of Ithaca just before sunrise. The
crew found a beach with a large cave beside it.
There the Phaeacian oarsmen landed the ship and
lifted Odysseus, still asleep, onto the sand. They
took all his gifts from the ship and piled them
next to him. Then they started their voyage home.
Athene threw a fog over the island of Ithaca, so
that no one noticed Odysseus before she could warn
him of the dangers in his palace. As a result,
when Odysseus woke up he did not recognise his
homeland. He jumped to his feet and cried, 'Oh
no! Whose country have I come to this time?
Will they be kind hosts, or dangerous monsters?
Where can I keep my treasure safe? And what were
those dishonest Phaeacians thinking? They promised
that they would take me home to Ithaca, but
instead they have left me in this strange place.
Let Zeus punish them for breaking their promise.
I should look at my treasure too, to
check that they have not stolen anything.'
He checked his gifts carefully,
but none were missing. Just then,
Athene came to him, disguised as a good-looking
young farmworker. Odysseus was very
happy to see that the people of the
island were not monsters, and said,
'Good morning, friend. You are the first
person that I have met in this land.
Please help me. I need to find a safe place for
my treasure. And I need to know where I am.'
'I am surprised that you do not know this land.
It is famous in countries far west and far east of
here. It is rocky - not a good place for horses
- but it has good farmland and produces fine
sheep and cows. Yes, even far away in
Troy they know the name of Ithaca.'
Odysseus's heart filled with happiness
when he heard that lovely name, but just
in time he remembered to be careful.
'Of course,' he replied, 'even in Crete we have
heard of Ithaca. Crete has been my home until now.
But the king's son tried to take from
me all the treasure that I won at Troy.
It was very unfair. I had
only one choice - to kill him.
But when he was dead, I could not live safely in
Crete. So I took the first ship that I could find.
We were aiming for Pylos, but the wind was too
strong and we were driven here instead. Last
night we slept on this beach. When I woke in
the morning, the ship and its crew had gone.'
Athene smiled at Odysseus's story,
then changed into her true form.
Odysseus stared in wonder at the
beautiful goddess in front of him.
'So even in your homeland you have not given up
your tricks, Odysseus! You and I are so similar.
You are the cleverest and most resourceful person
in the world of men, and I am the cleverest
and most resourceful of the
gods. But, though you are clever,
you did not realize that the goddess Athene
was beside you through all your adventures. I
made the Phaeacians look after you
kindly. And now I will help you again.'
'It is hard to recognise you in all your
disguises, great goddess,' Odysseus replied.
'I remember your kindness at Troy, but have
I really had much help from you since then?
Where were you when the Greek ships were
separated because of arguments and storms?
Where were you when my
companions were lost at sea?'
'You must understand that I
could not act against Poseidon,
who was very angry about your
treatment of his son, the Cyclops.'
'But tell me, goddess, and I
pray that you answer me honestly:
is this really Ithaca, or were your words
intended to make me suffer even more?'
'Look around you, Odysseus. Do
you not recognise this beach,
those rocks, and that tree on the hills above?'
As she spoke, she lifted the fog
that was hiding the land from view.
Odysseus recognised it at last. He threw
himself down on the ground and kissed the sand.
'Come,' said the goddess. 'We must hide
your treasure in that cave over there.'
When everything was safely in the cave, Athene
warned him about the situation in the palace.
'Penelope is surrounded by suitors. They are
arrogant and greedy men, who will do anything.
They are even trying to murder your son
Telemachus. When it is time to fight them, I will
be at your side,' she said. 'But at the moment
they must not know about your return. I will
disguise you as a man so old and poorly dressed
that even your wife will not recognise you.
Go and stay with Eumaeus, the pig farmer.
He is still loyal to you and Penelope,
and he loves Telemachus like a son. He can
give you the news from the town. And I will
bring Telemachus home from Sparta, where he
has been asking Menelaus for news of you.'
Athene used her magic to change Odysseus into a
weak old man. His skin hung loose on his body,
his hair was white, and his
clothes were dirty pieces of cloth.
Then she disappeared suddenly,
hurrying to Telemachus in Sparta.
Odysseus followed a path up to
the hills and the home of Eumaeus,
the pig farmer, the most loyal
of all Odysseus's farmworkers.
He found Eumaeus near his hut, busy with his
pigs. There were eight hundred on his farm,
although their number was reduced every
day by the enormous meals at the palace.
The guard dogs saw Odysseus first and ran
towards him. Luckily, Eumaeus called them
back before they attacked the stranger. 'Those
dogs almost pulled you to pieces, old man,'
he said. 'Then I would have even more
worries. The situation is bad enough now.
I spend my days making my master's pigs fat
so that other men can eat them. But my good,
kind master is probably dying of hunger, lost
in a foreign land, or perhaps already dead.
But come inside. When you have had some food
and wine, you can tell me about yourself.'
Inside the hut, Eumaeus offered his guest a
seat on a pile of sticks with a sheepskin thrown
over it. 'Thank you for this warm welcome,' said
Odysseus. 'I hope that the gods are kind to you.'
Eumaeus prepared some simple food
and gave it to Odysseus, saying,
'It is not much, I am afraid. But we have
little left after we have sent all our best
pigs to those arrogant men in the palace.
They want to marry my absent master's wife,
but they do not behave like future husbands.
Instead, they sit around the palace all day.
They kill several pigs every night and drink my
master's wine like water. They must know that my
master will never return, because they fear
no punishment for their unlawful behavior.'
Odysseus ate the food gratefully, thinking
about what he would do to those suitors.
When he had finished, he asked,
'So who is your absent master?
You seem to have a very good opinion of
him. Perhaps I have met him on my travels.'
'His name is Odysseus. It was Odysseus, I should
say, because he is now lying dead somewhere.
He was the kindest of masters and the best of men.
He owned land here on Ithaca and on the mainland.
He was rich in pigs and cows and sheep, and in
treasure too. But the suitors are destroying
his property day by day, and soon there will be
nothing left. My heart aches when I think of it.
But tell me, stranger, who you are.
What has brought you to this island?'
Odysseus told him that he
had been a prince of Crete.
He had had an argument with his brother and had to
leave his homeland. After many years of travel and
a lot of bad luck, he now owned nothing in the
world except the clothes that he was wearing.
'I met Odysseus once,' he added. 'He stayed
at our palace in Crete on the way to Troy.
And a few days ago I heard talk of him
again. There was a ship in Thesprotia
waiting to carry him home. The crew were
expecting to start their voyage this week.'
'I am sorry for all your troubles, old man,'
the pig farmer replied. 'But I cannot believe
your story about Odysseus. Why are you telling
such lies? Another man told me a similar story
last year, and travellers regularly
upset Penelope with false information.
Odysseus never arrives, and only
a fool now believes that he will.'
'If my story proves false, you can throw me from
the highest rock on this island,' said Odysseus.
'Zeus would soon punish a man who
invited a stranger into his home
and then killed him for lying,' replied Eumaeus.
They spent the evening in friendly
conversation in front of the fire.
When it was time for sleep, Eumaeus lent
Odysseus a thick coat to use as a blanket.
Then, always careful of his master's
property, he went out to sleep with
the pigs, to protect them from thieves
and wild animals during the night.
CHAPTER NINE
Telemachus Returns
'I am not a god,' replied Odysseus.
'But I am your father, who has been
the cause of so many problems for you.'
Athene now went to Sparta and found Telemachus
and Peisistratus in the palace of King Menelaus.
Peisistratus was asleep, but
Telemachus was lying awake,
worrying about his absent father
and the problem of the suitors.
Athene stood near him and said, 'Go back to your
palace and keep it safe from the greedy suitors.
Your mother's father has told her to marry
Eurymachus, since he is the richest of her
suitors. If you do not go home soon, you will
return to an empty house. But be careful.
The suitors have sent a ship to attack you
on your voyage home. They are waiting for
you between Ithaca and the coast of Samos, with
swords in their hands and murder in their hearts.
Make sure that you go home a different way,
and sail at night so that they cannot see
your ship. Get off the ship at a quiet part of
the coast and go straight to Eumaeus's pig farm,
while your crew sail to the port
and spread the news of your return.'
When she had delivered her message, she went back
to Mount Olympus. Telemachus woke Peisistratus
with a gentle kick and said, 'Come, my friend,
we must get the chariot ready and be on our way.'
'We should leave soon, I agree, Telemachus.
But it is the middle of the night.
We cannot drive in complete darkness, and what
would Menelaus think if we rushed away like
thieves in the night? Can our journey not
wait until morning?' Telemachus agreed to
stay in Sparta for a few more hours. When
daylight came, he went to speak to his host.
'Menelaus,' he said, 'I must go home. But
I will never forget your kindness to me.'
'I will not keep you here against your
wishes,' replied the king. 'But give me
time to bring you some gifts. And enjoy
one last meal with us before you leave.'
Menelaus gave him the bowl of fine silver
that he had promised him the day before.
Queen Helen added a present of her own. 'I
made this dress myself,' she told Telemachus.
'It is for your future wife
to wear on your wedding day.'
They then had some food, and after the meal
Telemachus and Peisistratus
climbed into their chariot.
'Goodbye, young friends,' said Menelaus.
'Give my good wishes to Nestor.'
'We will,' replied Telemachus. 'I
only hope that one day I can give
your good wishes to my father too,
and tell him of your kindness to me.'
As he spoke, an eagle flew across the sky,
carrying a chicken from a local farm in its feet.
Some farmworkers were chasing
the eagle, but it gave a cry
and flew out to sea, far beyond their reach.
'This was a sign from the gods,' said Helen.
'And its message seems clear. Just as the eagle
attacked the chicken, Odysseus will attack
the suitors when he finds his way home.
Or perhaps he is already in
Ithaca, planning their death.'
'I pray that you are right,' said Telemachus.
And with a shout to the
horses, he started the chariot.
After a smooth journey, they
reached Pylos the next day.
Telemachus said goodbye to Peisistratus at the
port. 'I am sorry that I cannot say goodbye
to your father too. But I have no time to go
to the palace. I need to get home urgently.'
As the crew carried the gifts from Menelaus
onto the ship, a stranger came to Telemachus.
'Can you take me with you?' he
asked. 'In Argos, my homeland,
I have enemies who are trying to kill
me. I think they have followed me here.'
'You are welcome to come with us,' replied
Telemachus. 'We are going to Ithaca,
and there you can stay as my guest.'
'I am grateful for your kindness, good
friend,' said the stranger. 'My name
is Theoclymenus. In Argos I am a famous prophet.'
They all climbed on board, and the crew pulled
on their oars until Pylos was far behind them.
In open sea, they put up the sail and the
wind carried them quickly towards Ithaca. As
Telemachus stared out at the waves, he wondered
what would happen at the end of the voyage.
Would he get home alive, or would the
suitors succeed in their plan to murder him?
At the same time, Odysseus was having
supper with Eumaeus in the hut.
Wanting to test his host's loyalty, he said, 'I
cannot take advantage of your kindness any longer.
Tomorrow I will go to town and
ask for work at the palace.
And I can tell Queen Penelope that
her husband will soon be home.'
'No, no!' replied Eumaeus. 'Penelope has listened
to too many stories about Odysseus already.
You would do no good. You would just upset her.
And the suitors in the palace will
not want you as their servant.
They are surrounded only by good-looking young
men with oil in their hair and handsome clothes.
You might die a violent death if you
went to the palace in search of work.
No, it is better to stay here with me. When my
master's son, Telemachus, returns from Pylos,
he will give you some new clothes
and send you wherever you want.'
'Your kindness continues, Eumaeus,'
said his guest. 'I will wait for Telemachus
s return as you suggest. But tell me,
while I am here, about your masters family.
Does he have a father or mother still living?'
'His father, Laertes, is still alive,
but life brings him no happiness. He
lost his son when Odysseus went to Troy, and
then his dear wife died of a broken heart
because of Odysseus's absence.
She was a lovely woman.
She was like a mother to me when I first
came to Ithaca - I grew up in her house.'
'So you were still quite young when
you came to Ithaca,' said Odysseus.
'What happened to you? How were you
separated from your home and family?'
'Well, I was born in the far land of
Syrie. My father, Ctesius, was its king.
One day a ship arrived from Phoenicia with
lots of jewels and pretty things for sale.
One of my father's servants was Phoenician.
As a young girl, she had been stolen from
her homeland by criminals. Now she was a
tall, beautiful woman, good at her work,
but not very sensible. Well, this servant fell
in love with one of the Phoenician sailors.
He offered to take her home with him to
Phoenicia and she was very excited at the idea.
But to pay for her voyage the sailors asked
her to steal some gold from my father's palace.
She agreed willingly, saying, "There is
something else that I can give you too.
At the palace I look after my master's young son.
He is a clever boy and he follows me everywhere.
If I brought him too, you could sell him
for a high price at any foreign port."
'The plan was made. She left the palace
secretly with a bag full of gold cups,
and I, innocent child, went with
her. But a few days into our voyage,
the servant died suddenly on the ship. Her
body was thrown to the fishes and I was left
friendless. Later we came to Ithaca and
Laertes bought me from the Phoenicians.'
'What a strange story of bad luck,' said
Odysseus. 'I am sorry for your troubles.
But you had good luck too, since
you were bought by a kind master.'
Their conversation continued far into the night,
until it was time to sleep. At the same
time, Telemachus had had a lucky night.
His ship was near the coast of Ithaca, and
the crew had not seen the murderous suitors.
'Land on that beach,' he said to the men. 'I
am going to get off there and visit my farms.
Take the ship to the city without me.' He turned
to one of the oarsmen, his loyal friend Peiraeus,
and said, 'Could you give Theoclymenus a bed for
the night? I will meet you in the city tomorrow.'
The crew took the ship onto the beach
and Telemachus jumped out. He watched
his companions as they sailed towards the city,
then started along the path to Eumaeus's hut.
Eumaeus and Odysseus were preparing breakfast when
Telemachus appeared in the doorway. Eumaeus jumped
up in surprise, and the bowls in his hands fell
noisily to the floor. He threw his arms around his
young master like a loving father welcoming
back his dear son after many years abroad.
'You are back, then, Telemachus!
And I thought that I would never see you
again after you sailed to Pylos. Come in,
come in, dear child, and let me look at you. I
do not see you often enough here on the farm.'
'It is good to see you too, Eumaeus. I have
come here to ask for news from the palace.
Is my mother still there, or has she married
again and gone to her new husband's home?'
'She is still at the palace,' said the pig farmer.
'And she still spends most of her days in tears.'
Telemachus came into the hut, and Odysseus stood
up to give him his seat. But Telemachus stopped
him. 'Please, stranger, do not get up. I am sure
that there is something else for me to sit on.'
Eumaeus made another seat of sticks
and sheepskin, and Telemachus sat
down next to his father, Odysseus. 'So
who is your guest, Eumaeus?' he asked.
'He is from Crete,' replied the
servant, 'but he cannot go back there.
I am hoping that you can look
after him at the palace.'
'The palace?' cried Telemachus. 'But how can I? My
mother is usually too upset to receive visitors,
and the suitors are a dangerous crowd. I can
do little to protect him against so many. I
am happy to give him food and new clothes.
And I will send him wherever he wants to go.
But while he is in Ithaca he should stay
here with you. It will be safer for him here.
But now, Eumaeus, old friend, can I ask you to
take a message to my mother? Tell her that I am
back from Pylos. Tell no one except her. There
are many people who are trying to harm me.'
Eumaeus wasted no time. He left the hut
immediately in the direction of the palace.
Athene saw him go. She appeared suddenly at the
door of the hut, although only Odysseus could
see her. Odysseus followed her outside, where she
said, 'It is time to tell your son who you are.
Together you must start planning the fate
of those men in your palace.' As she spoke,
she took away his disguise of old age.
His strength and good looks returned;
his beard grew dark on his chin;
and he was wearing fine new clothes.
Then the goddess disappeared, and
Odysseus went back into the hut.
Telemachus looked at him now in wonder. 'Stranger,
you look completely different. Only the gods can
change their appearance in this way. Which
god are you, and what can I do for you?'
'I am not a god,' replied Odysseus.
'But I am your father, who has been
the cause of so many problems for you.'
He kissed his son, and tears ran down his face.
But Telemachus stepped back from him.
'You are not my father,' he said. 'A
god is playing a cruel trick on me. No man can
change his appearance as you have just done.'
'I promise you that this is no trick.
My disguise was the work of Athene, who has
been a great help to me in my troubles.'
Telemachus was satisfied by this answer.
He threw his arms around his father's neck.
Together they cried tears of great sadness and
great happiness. This was the moment that
they had both dreamt about for so many years.
'But how did you get to Ithaca?'
Telemachus asked finally.
'In a Phaeacian ship. I have a great pile
of treasure, which is hidden in a cave by
the beach. But we should waste no time.
We must plan the death of those suitors.
Tell me how many of them there are.
Then I can decide how to fight them.'
'There are more than a hundred suitors. I know
that you have a great reputation as a soldier,
Father. But we cannot possibly fight them alone.
We must think of some people
who will fight with us.'
'Athene and Zeus will fight with us,' his father
replied. 'Their help will be enough, I think.'
'If you are right, then the suitors
have no chance,' Telemachus agreed.
'Tomorrow,' continued Odysseus, you will go back
to the palace. I will join you later in the day,
disguised again as an old man. If the suitors
are rough with me, do not worry. Their day of
judgment is coming. But tell no one about my
return - not my father Laertes, or Eumaeus,
or even your mother. It must be a complete secret
until we have destroyed the suitors' power.'
'We must do that very soon, or Mother will
marry one of them. Then it will be too late.'
As father and son discussed their plans,
Telemachus's crew arrived at the port in the city.
A messenger was sent to tell Penelope that her
son was safe. This messenger arrived at the palace
at the same time as Eumaeus, and soon gave the
queen his message in front of all her servants.
In private, Eumaeus told her everything
that he knew. Then he went back to his
farm - to Telemachus and Odysseus, who
Athene had changed back into an old man.
The news of Telemachus's return soon
spread to the suitors, who were very angry.
When Antinous's ship came into port, they
rushed to find out what had happened.
'The lucky young fool!' shouted Antinous. 'My
people were looking for him all along the coast,
but he managed to get past us. We must find
another way to kill him, and do it fast.
If we do not, he will call another meeting
and turn the people of Ithaca against us.
They will not be happy that we have tried to
murder their prince. If we are not careful,
we will soon be thrown off this island.
We have no choice. We must kill
him now, before it is too late.'
Silence followed this speech. Finally, Amphinomus
stood up to speak. He was a more thoughtful man
than the rest, one of the few suitors who Penelope
liked to talk to. 'My friends,' he said now,
'I cannot agree to this murder. It is wrong to
kill a prince, unless the gods have given clear
signs that they want him dead. We should wait for
those signs. Until then, we should do nothing.'
The other suitors agreed with him. For
the moment, Telemachus was safe.
CHAPTER TEN
Odysseus at the Palace
She quickly looked up at the stranger above
her, and she knew - her master had returned.
The next morning, Telemachus prepared
to visit his mother at the palace.
As he left Eumaeus's hut,
he said to the pig farmer,
After I have gone, take our visitor to the
city. He can ask the people there for food.'
Telemachus met the prophet Theoclymenus in
town, then walked with him to the palace.
Loyal old Eurycleia was the first to see her
young master, and she ran up to him with a cry
of happiness. The other servants followed, and
finally Penelope came out of her room. Tears ran
down her face as she threw her arms around him.
'You are back, my child! And I thought I would
never see you again after your secret departure.
But come, tell me what you learnt on your voyage.'
'Well, we went first to Pylos. King Nestor
received us kindly, but knew nothing about
Odysseus's fate. He lent me a chariot, though,
and with his son Peisistratus I went by land
to Sparta and the palace of King Menelaus.
During Menelaus's journey home from the war,
he met the god Proteus. Proteus told
him that my father was still alive,
a prisoner on the goddess Calypso's island,
without a ship or a crew to take him home.'
Telemachus's words warmed his mother's
heart. Then his guest Theoclymenus added,
'Great Penelope, Menelaus's information is old.
Listen to my prophecy. Your husband Odysseus is
already in Ithaca, studying his enemies, the
suitors, and planning their day of judgment.'
'I pray that you are right,' replied Penelope.
Eumaeus and Odysseus were preparing to walk to
the city. 'Are you sure you want to do this?'
asked Eumaeus. 'The walk is not easy for a man of
your age. Why not stay here in the hut instead?'
'Thank you, Eumaeus,' replied his guest.
'But your young master Telemachus is right.
It is time for me to go. Could I ask you,
though, for a stick to help me walk?'
Eumaeus got him a stick and
they started their journey.
The path was steep, but Odysseus went slowly and
carefully and before long they came to a stream at
the edge of the city. There they met Melanthius,
who also looked after a farm on Odysseus's land.
When this man saw Eumaeus, he immediately
started shouting at him. 'Where are you
going with that old ruin of a man? I hope you
are not planning to take him to the palace.
I doubt that he will manage a day in the
suitors' company without broken bones.
And the suitors are right too. He is a
lazy fool who deserves nothing better.'
Melanthius then gave Odysseus a hard kick
that almost knocked him over. As Odysseus was
preparing to fight back, Eumaeus cried, 'Great
Zeus, I pray that my master is returned to us.
He would soon cure Melanthius of the arrogant
ways that he has learnt from the suitors.'
Melanthius laughed as he walked away. 'Odysseus's
chance of returning is as low as Telemachus s
chance of escaping the suitors' violence. Things
have changed, Eumaeus. You have new masters now.'
The pig farmer and the old man
continued towards the palace.
There was a dog called Argus lying
near the gates. When he was younger,
he had been an excellent hunting dog, trained
by Odysseus himself and famous for his speed.
But now he was old and lay all day
in the dust, alone and forgotten.
When this dog heard the sound of Odysseus's
voice, he lifted his head and moved his
tail in excitement. He did not have the
strength to get up and greet his master.
Odysseus saw his old hunting companion and gently
touched the dog's head. At that same moment,
Argus died - happy at last after waiting
twenty years for his master's return.
Eumaeus went into the palace and joined Telemachus
at the dinner in the hall. Odysseus followed a few
minutes later and sat quietly in a dark corner.
Seeing him there, Telemachus sent him a plate
of food and an empty bag. Odysseus went from table
to table, asking the suitors for food for his bag.
'I am a poor man,' he said to each man in
the hall. 'Please, take pity on my hunger.'
When the suitors saw the thin old man,
most gave him food from their plate.
But Antinous had other ideas.
'Who let this smelly old fool
into the city? There are enough poor people on
Ithaca already. How rude he is, asking for food
when he offers nothing in return. You should
throw him out of the palace, Telemachus.'
'Thank you for your advice,' replied Telemachus.
'You are very anxious not to let my food go
to waste, I see! How can you be so greedy,
Antinous? You have plenty on your
plate. Give some of it to our guest.'
'I will do as I wish,' Antinous shouted back. He
picked up a chair and threw it at Odysseus. It hit
him hard on the shoulder. Telemachus managed
to control his anger when he saw the attack.
Odysseus, too, stayed calm. He looked around the
hall at the suitors, saying, 'You are fortunate
men, who know nothing about hunger. Does an
empty stomach deserve this violent treatment?
I hope that the gods are watching, and that
Antinous will be dead before his wedding day.'
Then he went back to sit on his
chair in the corner of the hall.
The other suitors were shocked
by Antinous's behavior.
Amphinomus spoke for them all when he said, 'This
old man might be a god in disguise, Antinous.
Be careful, or you will soon
meet the fate that you deserve.'
Amphinomus then walked over to Odysseus and said,
'Your health, my friend! Fortune has not been kind
to you recently, but I wish you a happy future.'
'Amphinomus,' Odysseus replied,
you seem to be a sensible man.
Why do you spend your days
with these arrogant suitors?
I have seen their violence and their greedy
ways. And I know that Odysseus will soon be home.
Listen to my advice, Amphinomus. Leave now and
save yourself from Odysseus's bloody punishment.'
Amphinomus walked back to the table shakily, his
mind full of doubt. Then he took some more meat
and joined in the other suitors' conversation.
News of Antinous's attack on the stranger
soon reached Penelope in her room.
'I hope that the gods strike Antinous as he struck
that old man!' she cried to her servants. 'I hate
all the suitors, but Antinous is even worse
than the rest. He has a cold and cruel heart.'
She called Eumaeus to her so that she could
ask about the stranger. When she learnt
that he had travelled widely and had news of
Odysseus, she wanted to question him herself.
But she decided to wait until the
suitors had gone home to their beds.
First, though, she wanted to talk
to her son. 'It is not good for him
to spend so much time in the company of
those suitors,' she said to Eurycleia.
'You are right,' replied the servant.
'But you can be grateful, at least,
that Telemachus has returned home safely
and seems so grown up. It was always your greatest
wish to see your son with a beard on his face.'
Penelope thought about her servant's
words as she walked down to the hall.
There, turning to her son, she said, 'Telemachus,
you were always a sensible child, but now your
good judgment has left you. Someone attacked
an old man in this hall, and you did nothing
to stop him! We are lucky that
the stranger was not badly hurt.'
'Mother,' replied Telemachus,
'you are right to be upset.
But I cannot always control the behavior
of your suitors. I am one against so many.'
Penelope now addressed the suitors. 'When my
husband sailed to Troy, he warned me of the
dangers that he would face. "I cannot promise that
I will ever return," he said. "Wait patiently for
me. But when you see a beard on our son's chin,
it will be time for you to choose a new husband."
'Well, gentlemen, that time has come. I would
prefer to die, but I must accept my fate.
How, though, can I choose a husband,
when none of my suitors behave correctly?
Suitors usually bring their own animals to eat
at dinners, and they also bring their lady gifts.
They do not enjoy free meals
given by their lady's own family.'
Antinous quickly replied, 'We will be
happy to bring you presents, good lady.
But we will not leave here - not
until you have married one of us.'
The other suitors agreed. They sent servants
to fetch the finest dresses and jewellery
that they owned. Penelope accepted the
gifts politely and took them to her room.
The suitors spent the rest of
the day dancing and singing.
But before darkness fell, Eurymachus started a
conversation with Odysseus. 'Stranger,' he said,
'I could give you a job on my lands if you wanted.
You could build walls and plant trees, and
receive food and clothes in payment. But I
doubt that you want an honest job. You prefer
to get your food for nothing, you lazy dog!'
'What an insult!' replied Odysseus. 'We
should have a competition, you and I.
We could see who works harder - at
building walls or digging fields,
or any other work that you choose.
Or would you prefer a swordfight?
I could beat you in anything, you arrogant fool.
You think you are a big man, a hero, but you
have never had to face a real hero. If Odysseus
returned now, you would soon run away in fear.'
Eurymachus was very angry. He took a chair
and threw it at Odysseus. Odysseus stepped
out of the way just in time, but it hit one
of the servants. This man fell to the ground,
dropping the wine cup that he was holding. There
was a loud crash, and everyone started shouting.
Telemachus called out, 'What is
wrong with you all this evening?
Perhaps you have had too much wine. But it is
late now. I suggest you all go home to your beds.'
The suitors were surprised by
Telemachus's new confidence,
but they followed his advice. Soon only
Telemachus and his father were left in the hall.
Odysseus took advantage of their time alone.
'Quick, Telemachus,' he said. 'We must
collect all the swords in the hall
and hide them in an upstairs room. Leave only
two swords here - one for you and one for me.'
'But what will I say if the suitors
notice their absence?' asked Telemachus.
'Say that you are worried about their fights
when they have drunk too much wine. You have
taken the swords away for their own safety.'
When the swords were safely
hidden, Telemachus went to bed.
Penelope chose this quiet time of the evening to
come down from her room and meet the stranger.
Her servants came too, to clear
the plates from the tables.
'Come and sit with me by the
fire, stranger,' said Penelope.
'Tell me who you are and where you come from.'
'Please do not ask me about my home and
family,' replied Odysseus. 'I have had a
sad and difficult life. But no one likes
to hear about other people's troubles.
Let us talk about something else.'
'I, too, have had a sad and difficult
life, stranger,' said Penelope. 'Since
my husband's departure for the war in Troy,
the passing years have brought me only tears.
And now my father wants me to marry one of
the men who behave so rudely in my home.
But tell me about yourself. I
would like to know your story.'
The old man repeated the story that
he had told Eumaeus in his hut.
When Penelope heard that he had once met Odysseus
in Crete, she decided to test his honesty.
'Tell me, stranger, what Odysseus
was like in those days. Can you
remember any details of his clothes,
or any companions that were with him?'
'It was twenty years ago, so I do not
remember much. But I have not forgotten this:
his clothes were a deep purple colour, and he also
wore a gold pin with a picture of a dog on it.
Everyone admired that pin. He had many companions,
but he seemed closest to a man called Eurybates.'
Penelope was pleased with his answer.
'Friend, those were the clothes and
the pin that I gave him when he left. But I
will never again see the man who wore them.'
'Dear lady, do not upset yourself. I heard
in Thesprotia that your husband was planning
to sail here this week. For many years he was a
prisoner far across the seas on Calypso's island,
but now he is almost home. I promise
you, he will be here very soon.'
'I hope that you are right, but I cannot believe
it. In my heart I know that he will never return.
But enough of this. The servants must get you
a blanket. And Eurycleia, the oldest and best
of them, will wash your feet.' She called
to Eurycleia. 'Come and help, old friend.
Wash the dust from this man's aching feet. He once
knew Odysseus, and has travelled far and wide.
If Odysseus is still alive somewhere,
his feet will be aching and dusty too.'
'Oh, Odysseus,' cried the servant
as she fetched a bowl of water,
'the gods are so cruel! I looked after you
as a baby, and still love you like a son.
I want to be able to wash your
feet, not the feet of a stranger.'
She sat at the stranger's feet to wash them, while
Penelope gave instructions to the other servants.
'Old man,' said Eurycleia, 'we have had many
travellers at the palace before, but none of
them looked like Odysseus. You, though, have
a very similar voice, and similar feet too...'
She started to wash his feet. As she passed
her hands over his legs, she felt a scar.
She remembered that Odysseus had had
a scar in exactly the same place,
from a hunting accident when he was a boy.
She quickly looked up at the stranger above
her, and she knew - her master had returned.
She dropped his foot in shock, and it
knocked over the bowl with a crash.
But as the servant started to shout to
Penelope, Odysseus put his hand over her mouth.
'Say nothing, dear Eurycleia,' he
whispered. 'No one in the palace can know.'
'I will be as silent as a stone, my
child,' she answered with a smile.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
The Day of Judgement
'The walls of this hall will be covered with your
blood, and screams of pain will fill the air.'
Odysseus could not sleep that night. He lay awake
under the blanket that the servants had brought
him, thinking angrily about the suitors.
They deserved to die. But how could
he and Telemachus alone kill so many?
Athene came down from Mount Olympus to talk to
him. 'Are you sleepless again, Odysseus? Stop
worrying! You are in your own home, under the same
roof as your wife and son. And you have a goddess
to help you. You and I could kill ten times this
number of suitors. Their fate is already decided.'
Then she closed Odysseus's eyes in
sleep and returned to Mount Olympus.
At the same moment, Penelope woke. In her
dream, she had seen Odysseus next to her in bed.
He was young and good-looking, as he had
been on the day of his departure for Troy.
The thought of him brought tears to her
eyes. 'Oh gods,' she cried, 'let me die!
A painful death would be better than
marriage to any man who is not Odysseus.'
In the morning, the palace was busy with
preparations for a meal even bigger than
usual. The day was a public holiday, and
the suitors planned to celebrate it well.
Eumaeus arrived with some pigs for the
meal, and the cow farmer Philoetius
also brought some animals. When he saw Odysseus
sitting quietly in a corner, he stopped suddenly
and stared. 'Greetings, stranger,' he said. 'You
confused me just then, because you reminded me
so much of my master Odysseus. Oh, it would
be a wonderful surprise if he ever came home.
I often think of leaving Ithaca so that I do
not have to obey the arrogant suitors' orders.
But I cannot do it, because I cannot
give up all hope of my master's return.'
Odysseus replied, 'You are clearly a loyal and
honest servant, so I will give you some news.
Odysseus is on his way home. Before the end of the
day, you will see him again with your own eyes.'
'Stranger, I hope that you are
right. It is my dearest wish.'
The farmer Melanthius, who had also come for the
meal, heard their conversation. 'This smelly old
man is mad, Philoetius,' he laughed. 'And you are
mad too, if you listen to his crazy prophecies.'
When the food was ready, everyone
took their seats in the hall.
Telemachus carefully made sure that Odysseus
was given a seat near the doorway. 'Sit and
eat with the suitors,' he said loudly. 'Suitors,
there will be no fights or insults here today.'
But they did not listen. Soon they were
shouting and laughing at Odysseus. One
of them threw a cow's foot at his head, but it
missed. Telemachus turned to the man and said,
'You were lucky that that did not hit him. I will
put my sword through any man who strikes my guest.
I am not a child now. I cannot stop you eating
my food and drinking my wine - there are too
many of you. But I will stop your bad behavior.
If you want to murder me for that, then do it.
I would prefer to die than
to let you hurt my guest.'
The suitors laughed at his
words, until they saw strange
drops of blood on their food.
Was this a sign from the gods?
At that moment, the voice of the
prophet Theoclymenus was heard.
'Unhappy men,' he cried,
'this is my prophecy. The walls of this
hall will be covered with your blood,
and screams of pain will fill the air. Your ghosts
will soon be on their way to the Underworld.'
Eurymachus laughed at him. 'He is out of his
mind, poor man. Can someone show him the door?'
'I need no help to find the door, Eurymachus,'
replied Theoclymenus. 'I am going through it now.
I can see disaster coming your way, and I want to
be as far from you as possible when it arrives.'
He left the hall. The suitors looked at each other
nervously, but then started to laugh again. 'You
have chosen some strange people to invite here
as your guests, Telemachus,' said one. 'First
a smelly old man, and now a mad prophet.'
At this point Penelope entered the hall.
She had spent the morning thinking sadly about
her situation. Now she had reached a decision.
'Suitors,' she said, you have taken
advantage of my son for long enough.
Although I have no wish to marry
again, I must now choose a new husband.
That is the only way to save my son's
property from your greedy hands.
Today will be the last day that you eat
free food in this palace. Tomorrow I will
go to the home of my chosen husband, and
the rest of you will leave this place.
'As you can see, I am carrying a bow. This
belonged to my husband, the famous hero
Odysseus. I will marry the man among you
who is most skilled at using this bow.
You must string it, which is not easy if you do
not have Odysseus's great strength. And then you
must shoot an arrow through twelve axe handles.
Telemachus, please arrange the axes in a line.'
Telemachus took the axes that his
mothers' servants were carrying.
He dug the axe heads into the ground, so that the
metal rings on the handles were exactly in line.
Then he said, 'Gentlemen, you have your
instructions for the competition. But before
you start, I would like to try the bow myself.
Tomorrow I will have to say goodbye to my mother.
But if I succeed with the bow, at least I
will know that I am as strong as my father.'
Telemachus stood in the doorway with the bow.
Three times he tried to bend it, but three times
his strength failed. The bow shook but it did
not bend. He tried a fourth time and felt that he
would succeed. But Odysseus shook his head gently
and Telemachus put the bow back on the ground.
'Well, clearly I will always be known
as a weak man compared to my father,'
he said. 'This bow is too much
for me. Who else will try it?'
Leodes was the first suitor to come
forward. He tried and tried to bend the bow,
but it was impossible. 'Friends, I cannot
do it,' he said. 'Let someone else try. But
I fear that this bow will break the heart
of many men here today.' Antinous cried,
'Do you think that you are the strongest man
in the room, Leodes? You cannot string the bow,
but others will do it. Wait and see.'
Other men tried, but they failed too.
Eurymachus and Antinous watched and
waited, learning from the others' mistakes.
At this point Eumaeus and Philoetius the
cow farmer left the hall. The competition
was bringing to an end their hopes for Odysseus's
happy return. They could not watch it any longer.
But Odysseus came running after them. 'My
friends,' he said, 'do not leave yet. I have an
important question for you. If Odysseus returned,
would you fight with him, or with the suitors?'
'You would soon see the strength of my right arm
if I could fight the suitors at Odysseus's side!'
Philoetius replied. Eumaeus
agreed enthusiastically.
Odysseus continued, 'Well, here I am!
Yes, it is true - I am your master,
returned at last. Look, here is the scar
that I got in a hunting accident as a boy.'
As he spoke, he showed them his
leg. When they saw the scar,
the farmers threw their arms around their
master and tears ran down their faces.
'Stop crying,' said Odysseus,
'or someone will see us.
Now, I need your help. Come back inside and
wait until I have the bow in my hands. Then,
Philoetius, go and lock the palace gate. Eumaeus,
you must lock the door to the women's rooms.
Tell the servants not to listen to any
noises that they hear in the hall.'
They went back inside and continued
to watch the suitors with the bow.
It was now Eurymachus's turn. He was a
proud man, used to success in all things.
He tried again and again to string the bow, but it
refused to bend. Finally, he cried out in anger,
'Stupid bow! This is bad news for all of us.
I do not care about the marriage - there are
plenty of other rich women. But all over Greece,
people will say that we are weak
compared to the great Odysseus.'
'Everything will be fine, Eurymachus,'
said Antinous. 'Today is a public holiday
- a day for fun, not for tests of strength.
Let us leave the competition for now.
Tomorrow we will pray to the god Apollo,
whose skill with the bow is famous among gods
and men. Then we will try our strength again.'
The other suitors liked this idea. But
Odysseus stood up and said, 'Before you
stop, could I try? I would like to see if there
is any strength left in these old arms of mine.'
The suitors were very angry.
They were frightened that the strange old
man would succeed where they had failed.
'If you touch that bow, stranger,
we will take you prisoner and sell you
abroad,' said Antinous. 'We will...'
Penelope interrupted him. 'Antinous, stop.
This poor stranger is our guest, and you must
talk to him politely. He has no intention of
becoming my husband. I am sure he knows that
that is impossible. So let him try his strength
against the rest of you. What harm could it do?'
It was Eurymachus who replied. 'The people
will think badly of us if he succeeds. He is
old and homeless, and we are the finest young
men in Greece. Our reputations will be ruined!'
Penelope gave a little laugh. 'For
years you have been eating and drinking,
uninvited, at another man's table. Your
reputations were ruined long ago, Eurymachus.'
'Mother,' said Telemachus, 'the bow was my
father's, so now it is mine. I should choose
who can hold it. But go now to your room and
busy yourself with your work. Or sleep if you
can - you look tired today. The competition to
choose your husband will start again tomorrow.'
Penelope realized that Telemachus was right.
She left the hall and returned to her bedroom.
There, tired after her sleepless
night, she fell asleep.
Telemachus now ordered Eumaeus
to take the bow to Odysseus.
The suitors shouted insults at the pig farmer,
but Eumaeus did as Telemachus said. When he had
given Odysseus the bow, he went up to the women's
rooms and locked the doors. At the same time,
Philoetius went out quietly and locked the palace
gate. Now there was no escape for the suitors.
Odysseus was looking carefully at the bow,
to see if the passing years had damaged it.
When he was satisfied that
it was as strong as before,
he started to bend it. As easily as a bard strings
his instrument before a musical performance,
Odysseus bent the bow and put on the string.
As the suitors looked at him angrily,
they heard thunder outside. Odysseus smiled at
this sign of support from the great god Zeus.
He picked up an arrow, aimed and
shot. He did not miss a single
ring. The arrow sped straight through
from the first axe handle to the last.
Odysseus looked at Telemachus to check that he
had his sword ready. Then he said, 'Suitors,
I have won your competition. But now I am
going to shoot something that no one has
ever hit before.' From the doorway,
he aimed an arrow at Antinous.
Antinous had just reached for his wine cup.
He never imagined for one moment that anyone
would try to kill him in the company of so many
friends. The arrow hit him in the neck. The cup
dropped from his hand and he
fell to the floor with a crash.
The suitors stared at Antinous's dead body in
shock. 'Stranger,' they shouted, you will pay
for this accident with your blood.' Many of them
were not carrying their swords, so they looked for
the swords on the walls. Too late, they realized
that the swords had disappeared. They still had
no idea who the stranger was, and believed that
Antinous's death had been a horrible mistake.
Odysseus cried, 'You dogs! You never thought
that I would come back from Troy. So you stole my
food. Then you tried to steal my wife and murder
my son. For those crimes, you will all die.'
The suitors' faces turned white with fear,
and they looked around for somewhere to hide.
Only Eurymachus was brave enough to speak.
'If you really are Odysseus,
then you are right to be angry.
But the person responsible for those crimes lies
dead already. Antinous was power-hungry and cruel.
He wanted to make himself King of Ithaca after
killing your son - but he has paid the price.
The rest of us are guilty of nothing
except eating your food without permission.
For this we will each give you twenty
cows and a generous repayment in gold.
Think carefully, Odysseus,
before you murder innocent men.'
'Eurymachus,' replied Odysseus, 'no amount of
gold could pay for your crimes. You have only
two choices - to fight or to run. But
whatever you choose, you will soon be dead.'
Eurymachus called to the other suitors,
'Odysseus will not be stopped with words.
Get your swords ready, men. We must fight!'
Eurymachus ran at Odysseus with his sword,
but Odysseus shot an arrow at his chest. He
fell across the table, knocking food and wine cups
everywhere before lying, dead, in a pool of blood.
Amphinomus came straight after him. Telemachus
killed him from behind as he ran at Odysseus.
'Father,' shouted Telemachus, 'I will go and
get some swords for Eumaeus and Philoetius.'
'Yes,' replied Odysseus. 'But do it quickly.
When I have no more arrows, I will need help.'
Telemachus got swords for the two loyal servants.
Odysseus shot arrow after arrow, and each one
brought death to a suitor. When there were no more
arrows, he took his sword and fought
with his son and servants at his side.
The suitors, with few swords between them,
could do little to defend themselves.
But Melanthius the farmer had an idea.
'Telemachus must have the swords from
the hall somewhere in the palace. I know the
building well. I will go and look for them.'
He came back a few minutes later with an armful
of swords. Then he went back to get more. With
new confidence, the suitors threw themselves
at Odysseus and his companions in the doorway.
Suddenly, Odysseus felt less sure
that they could win against so many.
'Where are they getting the swords from?' he asked
his son. 'Who in the palace is helping them?'
'Look!' cried Eumaeus. 'Melanthius has a
great pile of swords. He has found the room
where they are hidden. He has given them
to the suitors, and is going to get more.'
'Telemachus and I will keep
the suitors in the hall,'
Odysseus said to Eumaeus. 'Go now
with Philoetius and stop Melanthius.'
Odysseus's loyal servants went in
the same direction as Melanthius.
They found him getting more swords
from Telemachus's secret room.
They jumped on him before he saw them and
he was dead when they ran back to the hall.
The suitors were now fighting hard, but Odysseus
and Telemachus had managed to keep them from the
doorway. At this point, Athene came to them
disguised as Odysseus's old friend Mentor.
'Mentor!' cried Odysseus, guessing that
he was really speaking to the goddess,
you have come at just the right
moment. Will you fight with us?'
'You were braver when you were
fighting the Trojans' finest soldiers,'
she replied. 'Now you are in your own home,
against a group of lazy fools. You do
not need me to fight with you, Odysseus.'
She changed into a bird and flew high
above the men's heads to watch the fight.
The suitors started to attack in groups of
six. But Athene made sure that their swords
could not hurt Odysseus and his companions.
As their attacks failed again and again,
the suitors' confidence left them.
Finally, they ran to hide where they could.
Odysseus and his men ran after
them and cut them down without
pity. The suitors screamed horribly as they
died, and the floor was a lake of blood.
Phemius the bard looked around in terror. He felt
sure that he was going to die with the suitors.
But his only crime had been to
entertain them with his songs.
He ran to Odysseus and threw his arms around the
hero's knees. 'Sir,' he cried, 'take pity on me.
You will be sorry later if you kill a bard. My
songs bring pleasure to both gods and men. Your
son, Telemachus, can tell you - I did not choose
to come here. I was forced here by the suitors.'
'It is true, Father,' said
Telemachus. 'The man is innocent.'
'Then go outside to safety,' Odysseus said
to Phemius. 'I have more work to do in here.'
When the bard had gone, Odysseus looked round
the hall for more suitors to kill. But they were
all piled on the floor on top of each
other. No one was left alive.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Odysseus and Penelope
As she walked towards the hall, Penelope
could not decide how to greet him.
Should she be polite but cold, or should
she run into his arms and kiss him?
Odysseus now said to Telemachus,
'Go and fetch Eurycleia and the other
servants. We must clean up the mess.'
The servants came out of their rooms and learnt
what had happened. They threw their arms around
Odysseus to welcome him home. He greeted each one
by name, trying to keep the tears from his eyes.
When they had taken the suitors' bodies
outside and washed away the blood in the hall,
Odysseus said, 'Tomorrow I will visit my father.
But now, Eurycleia, it is time to fetch Penelope.'
'Dear child,' replied the servant, you
should first change your clothes. It is
not right for the King of Ithaca to
be dressed in dirty bits of cloth.'
'No,' said Odysseus, 'I have waited twenty years
for this moment. I will not wait a minute longer.'
So Eurycleia hurried upstairs to wake Penelope.
She almost fell over her own feet in her
excitement to tell the news. 'Penelope,
my dear, wake up!' she cried. 'Come and see the
sight that you have prayed for all these years.
Odysseus is home at last, and he has
killed every one of the suitors.'
'Have the gods driven you mad,
Eurycleia?' replied Penelope.
'Please, do not make fun of my unhappiness. Go
back downstairs and let me sleep some more.'
'But I am not making fun of you,
dear child,' the servant continued.
'Odysseus really has come home. He is the
stranger who the suitors insulted in the hall.'
Penelope's heart jumped inside her chest.
She rushed out of bed and held Eurycleia in
her arms, with tears running down her face.
'Eurycleia, can it really be true?
And how did he manage to kill all the
suitors without an army to help him?'
'I did not see anything, and I was not told
anything, but from my room I heard the cries
of dying men. Then Telemachus called me
and the other servants into the hall,
and we saw Odysseus standing
among the dead bodies.
We have cleaned up the mess, and now Odysseus
wants to see you. Come now and welcome him home.'
'You believe too easily, dear Eurycleia. There is
something strange about this story. I feel sure
that the gods are trying to trick us. Perhaps
the man in the hall is a god in disguise.'
'But I saw his scar - you know, the
one that he got in a hunting accident.'
'Eurycleia, you are a wise woman, but even you
cannot see into the hearts and minds of the gods.
But come, I am glad that the suitors are
dead. I will talk to the man who killed them.'
As she walked towards the hall, Penelope
could not decide how to greet him.
Should she be polite but cold, or should
she run into his arms and kiss him?
When she saw the man by the fire, she
just stared at his face in confusion.
At times she saw her husband's face there, but
at other times he looked to her like a stranger.
'Mother,' said Telemachus crossly, 'why
are you not welcoming my father home?'
'I am sorry, my son,' she replied. 'The
shock has turned my tongue to stone.
I cannot say a word to him.'
Odysseus now said, 'Telemachus, I need to wash,
and then your mother and I need some time alone.
Go and organize a dance for the servants.
And do not worry. Everything will be fine.'
While Telemachus asked Phemius for some music,
Odysseus had a bath and put
on some fine new clothes.
Then Athene worked her magic on his appearance,
giving him a younger face and a stronger body.
When he went back to Penelope in
the hall, he looked like a god.
'Well, Penelope, you are a strange woman.
Few wives would stay out of their husbands' arms
for as long as this. But I can wait. Eurycleia,
please prepare a bed for me somewhere in the
palace. I will be sleeping alone tonight.'
'You seem a strange man to me too. All these
years I have carried a picture of you in my head.
But you do not look like that picture. Come,
Eurycleia, we must move the great bed that
Odysseus himself built. Take it outside the
bedroom and make it comfortable for him.'
This was Penelope's test for the man in
front of her. He replied angrily, 'Lady,
your words are like a knife in my heart. What
have you done to our bed? I built it myself,
using a tree that was growing in
the palace as one of the bed's legs.
No one can move it - unless you have cut
through the wood of the tree and destroyed it.'
At these words, Penelope's knees began
to shake. No one knew the secret of
the tree-bed except her husband and a
servant who had died many years before.
'Do not be angry with me, Odysseus,' she
cried. 'The bed is exactly as you left it.
But I was so frightened that someone
would come here pretending to be you.
This was my test - and now I
know. Husband, it is really you!'
She threw her arms around
him. She was like a sailor
whose ship has been destroyed in a storm.
After swimming for many hours, he sees dry land
and knows that he is saved. Penelope felt
the same way about seeing her husband again.
For a long time Odysseus and Penelope
held each other, crying silently.
When everyone else in the palace had gone
to bed, Odysseus finally broke the silence.
'Dear wife, we have not yet come to the
end of our troubles. On my journey home,
I spoke with the prophet Teiresias.
He told me that I had to make another long
journey before I could enjoy a peaceful old age.'
Penelope questioned her husband about the details
of this prophecy. 'If the gods have promised you
a more peaceful old age,' she said finally, 'then
there is hope that one day our troubles will end.'
Odysseus smiled at her words.
Then he took his dear wife  to their bed.
- THE END -