CHAPTER ONE
Life at Night
When the sun goes down, it gets dark and the air
gets a lot colder. For many people, it's time to
go to sleep, but a lot of animals only come out
at night. They are called nocturnal animals.
The opossum is a nocturnal animal.
At night, it looks for plants and small animals
to eat. In the day, it hides and goes to sleep.
The armadillo is a nocturnal animal, and it
sleeps for more than 17 hours in the day!
Nocturnal animals aren't the only
animals that come out at night.
Some animals, like the tiger, come out in the
day and at night. Other animals, like the rabbit,
only come out in the morning when it's getting
light, and in the evening when it's getting dark.
Some animals come out at night because there are
not so many predators - animals that want to hunt
and eat them. Some animals find more food because
they eat other animals that come out at night.
In very hot places, it's sometimes
too hot to come out in the day.
CHAPTER TWO
Special Senses
Many animals that come out at night have
special senses. This means that they can see,
hear, touch, smell, or taste very well.
These special senses help them to find
food and to stay safe in the dark.
Wild dogs, like foxes, usually hunt in the dark.
They have a big nose, and an amazing sense of
smell that helps them to find food. A fox can
smell mice through up to 12 centimeters of snow!
Foxes also have very big ears that they can
move, so they can hear very well all around them.
Raccoons are nocturnal animals that have
long fingers and a very good sense of touch.
When they are hunting for food in water, they
use their fingers to find fish and frogs.
Many nocturnal animals can see much
better than people in the dark.
They have very big eyes that let in lots of light.
A tarsier's eye is bigger than its brain!
It can see very well in the dark.
CHAPTER THREE
Flying at Night
In the day, owls stay in trees or
buildings, but at night they hunt for food.
Owls can see very well in the dark, and they also
have an amazing sense of hearing. They listen for
little noises from their prey - rabbits, mice,
and other small animals that they like to eat.
Then they fly down and catch
them in their sharp claws.
Many owls have soft feathers on their
wings, so they can fly very quietly.
Their prey don't know that they are coming!
Most types of bat are nocturnal.
At night they look for fruit and flowers,
or they hunt for insects, fish, and mice.
Bats can see and smell very well, and many bats
have a special sense called echolocation. This
helps them to find food in the dark. Bats make
special noises when they fly. The noises bounce
off things and come back as echoes. These echoes
tell bats where things are and how big they are.
In the day, bats hang upside down and
stay in caves, trees, and buildings.
Bats are the only mammals that can fly!
CHAPTER FOUR
Ocean Animals
Some fish live near the top of the ocean in the
day and then they swim down to the deep ocean
at night. Other fish swim up to the top
of the ocean at night, and they look for
plankton - very small animals that swim up to
the top of the ocean every evening to find food.
Plankton are food for fish like the lantern
fish. The lantern fish stays down in the deep
ocean in the day, but when the sun goes
down it swims to the top of the ocean.
It feeds near the top of the ocean at night,
and then swims back down before morning.
The Lantern fish has lights
on it's body when it swims.
The white tip reef shark also comes out at night.
It stays in caves down in the deep ocean in the
day, and doesn't move very much. Then at night,
it comes out to hunt for fish and octopuses.
CHAPTER FIVE
Minibeasts
Many minibeasts, like moths and spiders, come
out at night. Minibeasts come out at night
because there are not so many
predators that hunt and eat them.
Slugs and snails look for food at night
because the sun can dry them out in the day.
Moths are insects. They have a body
that's good for living at night.
They have special antennae on their head. These
help them to look for food and to find their way
in the dark. Moths also have patterns on their
wings that help them to hide in trees in the day.
Tarantulas are spiders. They
hunt for their prey at night.
Special hairs on their body help them to
feel when another animal is near. They hide,
and then they jump on their
prey, and put poison in its body.
Nocturnal fireflies make lights in their
body that turn on and off at night.
They use these lights to communicate.
CHAPTER SIX
Desert Animals
In many deserts, it's very hot in the day,
so many animals only come out at night.
The fennec fox lives in the Sahara Desert
in Africa. It stays in a burrow in the sand
in the day, and at night it hunts for mice,
lizards, and insects. It's the smallest fox
in the world, but it has very big ears, so
it can easily hear its prey in the dark.
Kangaroo rats need to drink! They get
water from the seeds that they eat.
Kangaroo rats live in deserts in North America.
At night, they jump around and find seeds.
They keep seeds in their mouth, and
then they put them in their burrow.
Desert scorpions stay out of the sun in the day.
At night, they come out to feed on minibeasts.
Scorpions can't see well, but they have special
hairs on their legs so that they can feel
when prey is near. They kill their
prey with a sting from their tail.
CHAPTER SEVEN
African Animals
There are many nocturnal animals in Africa. Many
big cats, like leopards, hunt for food at night.
It's usually easier to catch prey when
it's dark, and when it's cooler, too.
Big cats see very well, and they have
a very good sense of hearing and smell,
so they are good night hunters. Their eyes
have a special part called the tapetum.
The tapetum reflects light so that the cats can
see in the dark. It can make their eyes glow.
Aardvarks can't see very well, but they have
a big nose and big ears that they use to find
ant nests at night. They dig up the nests
and catch the ants on their sticky tongue.
An aardvark can eat 50,000 insects in one night!
Hippos come out at night to eat grass.
In the day, they stay in water because
their skin needs to be wet and cool.
Bushbabies hunt for food at night.
They use their big eyes to look in trees
for insects, flowers, seeds, and eggs.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Animals Asleep
At night, when many animals are looking
for food, others are asleep, just like you!
In the evening, baboons climb up cliffs or into
the tops of trees, and they sleep for about
ten hours every night. In these high places,
they know that they are safe from predators
Flamingoes sleep at night, standing on one leg!
They have special ankles that keep their
legs straight so that they don't fall down.
Walruses live in the Arctic. It's
light all night in the summer there.
Walruses sleep on land, on ice, or
in water. They can sleep for up to 19
hours. Walruses have special pouches on
their body. When they sleep in water,
they put lots of air in the pouches,
to keep their head above the water.
Walruses sometimes put their
tusks over big pieces of ice
so that they don't move away
when they are asleep.
CHAPTER NINE
Noises at Night
It's hard to see at night, so animals
often use noises to communicate.
Owls call to each other, and lions roar
if predators come near their babies.
When deer are in danger, they try to
communicate with other deer. They make noises
in their nose, and they hit
the ground with their feet.
Most birds do not sing at night, but
the male nightingale sings a beautiful
song when it's looking for a female. Some
insects make a lot of noise at night, too.
The grasshopper makes noises
with its wings and legs.
The Tasmanian devil is a small animal that
comes out to hunt for food in the dark. When
it's scared or it thinks that another animal is
going to take its food, it makes terrible noises.
When howler monkeys call to each other at night,
you can hear them from about 5 kilometers away!
CHAPTER TEN
Traveling at Night
Every year, many types of bird migrate -
they move from one place to another to live.
These birds usually only come out in the day,
but when they migrate, they travel at night.
This is because they are safer from predators, and
they can fly for longer because it's cooler. Also,
they feed in the day, and then they have lots of
energy to fly at night when they are full of food.
Green turtles are not usually nocturnal, but they
travel at night when they are ready to lay their
eggs. They swim to a beach and come out of the
ocean. They wait until night when it's cooler.
Then they move up the beach
and lay their eggs in the sand.
When the baby turtles come out of the eggs, they
dig their way out of the sand and they go to the
ocean. The baby turtles do this at night when it's
cooler, and when there are not so many predators.
There's a lot happening at night! All around the
world, millions of animals are moving around,
hunting for food, and traveling
from one place to another.
- THE END -