Marcel is a French mouse. He's a detective
and he lives in Paris. But Marcel doesn't
live in Pans all year. Every November he visits
London. His old friend - Henry - has a small
flat there.
Marcel loves London. The beautiful buildings...
the big, black taxis... the museums and shops.
He loves Paris, but he loves London too.
This story is about one of Marcel's November
holidays. It starts at three o'clock on a
Tuesday afternoon. Marcel is walking from
Knightsbridge station to Henry's flat. He
has two heavy bags with him.
Henry's address is 42 Old Wilton Street. Marcel
looks at the numbers - 36 - 38 - 40. Yes,
here it is. Number 42.
He sees a sign. It says: 'Professor J. T.
Barton'. Marcel looks at it and thinks, 'That's
new.' Then he goes down to Henry's flat.
Henry opens the door and smiles.
'Marcel!' he says. 'Come in, come in!'
'Hello, Henry,' Marcel says.
'How are you?' (His English is very good.)
'I'm very well. And you?'
'Yes, thanks.'
'Good, good.' Henry takes Marcel's coat. 'Now,'
he says, 'let's have some tea.'
The two friends sit in big chairs. They drink
tea and talk.
At five o'clock Marcel says, 'There's a new
person in number 42. What's his name? Burton?
Barnam?'
'Barton,' Henry says. 'Professor Barton. He's
very, very clever. And that's not all. After
tomorrow he's going to be famous, too!'
'Famous?!' Marcel looks at his English friend.
'Why?'
'It's a very interesting story,' Henry says.
'He has some letters. They were under the
floor of an old woman's house in Oxford.'
'And...?' Marcel says.
'And they're from Shakespeare to his son,'
Henry says.
'Shakespeare!'
'Yes.' Henry smiles. 'Shakespeare. The old
lady telephoned Professor Barton, and the
Professor visited her. They talked about the
letters and she said, "I want to give them
to the British Museum in London. Can you do
that for me?"'
'And Professor Barton said yes?'
'That's right.'
'Where are the letters now?' Marcel asks.
'In the professor's flat. He's going to give
them to the British Museum tomorrow morning
at ten o'clock. A lot of journalists and TV
people are going to be there.'
Suddenly there's a big BANG! and then a long
WHIZZZ!
'What's that noise?' Marcel asks. He goes
to the window. Then he remembers. 'Oh - fireworks.
Of course, it's the 5th of November - your
"Guy Fawkes Day".'
Then a man walks down the steps from 42 Old
Wilton Street.
Marcel looks at him. 'Is that Professor Barton?'
he asks.
'Yes,' Henry answers.
'He always goes to the cinema on Tuesday evenings.'
'Aha!' Marcel says.
'Why do you say "Aha!"?' Henry looks at his
French friend.
Then suddenly he understands. 'Oh, you want
to look at the Shakespeare letters.' He smiles.
'OK. Why not?'
After tea, the two mice visit Professor Barton's
flat. There's a small hole near the front
door. Henry stops in front of it.
'Here we are,' he says. 'Do you want to go
in first?'
'No, no. After you,' Marcel says.
At 5.55 they're in the professor's flat. It's
very big, with a lot of old chairs and books.
There are some beautiful pictures, too.
'Come with me,' Henry says.
He walks across the floor. Then he starts
to climb a very tall bookcase. Marcel is behind
him. They go up and up and up for a long time.
Then Marcel sits on Charles Dickens's book,
Little Dorrit. He can hear a lot of fireworks
in the street.
'BANG! BANG! BANG!' they go. 'WHEEE! POW!
WHOOSH!'
There's a small, white button in the bookcase.
Henry smiles at Marcel, and presses it. Suddenly,
some of the books start to move.
'Why are they moving?' Marcel says. Then he
understands.
'Ah, I understand. There's a safe.'
'Yes,' Henry says. 'Now, you stay here. I'm
going to open it.'
He takes some blue paper from his jeans. Then
he climbs down to the safe. There are some
numbers on the paper. He starts to read them.
'55 - 14 - 62 - 29 - 8. Yes, that's right.'
After that, he puts his hands on the safe
and moves the dial to the left. '55,' he says.
Then he moves the dial to the right. '14.'
Suddenly there's a very, very big BANG!!!
'Wow!' Marcel says. 'That was a big firework.'
Henry doesn't stop. '62,' he says. '29. And...!'
He moves the dial again. '... 8. There - that's
it.' He smiles at Marcel and opens the safe.
But then suddenly his mouth falls open.
'Oh no!' he says.
'What's wrong?' Marcel asks. 'They're not
here,' Henry says. 'The Shakespeare letters.
They're not here!'
Marcel climbs down the bookcase and looks.
His friend is right. The letters aren't in
the safe, 'But that's not all.'
There's a big hole at the back of the safe,
and a lot of smoke, too.
Marcel looks at Henry. Henry looks at Marcel.
Then they climb into the safe.
'Look,' Marcel says. He can see a room in
number 40 Old Wilton Street. He can see a
person, too - a tall woman in a red dress.
She's sitting at a table and talking on the
telephone.
'Do you think...?' Henry starts.
'Ssshh,' Marcel says. The two mice sit and
listen.
'That's right,' the woman says. 'I'm going
to New York. Yes, this evening.' She writes
on a notepad. 'Thank you.' She puts down the
telephone.
There's a bag on the bed in front of her.
In it Marcel can see some letters.
The woman closes the bag. After that, she
walks to the door. She opens it, and then
closes it behind her.
Henry looks at Marcel in the hot, dark safe.
'What are we going to do?' he asks. 'That
woman's got the letters. Let's telephone the
police.'
'No, there isn't time,' Marcel says. 'Do you
know her?'
'The woman? No, I don't.'
'Who usually lives in that flat?'
'Two old women, but they're on holiday in
Spain. Oh Marcel, what are we going to do?'
Marcel looks into the dark flat. 'Come with
me,' he says. He climbs into the old women's
flat. Henry is behind him. The two mice run
across the floor. Then they climb up a table.
On the table, there's a yellow light and a
small, white notepad. Marcel looks at it under
the light.
'What are you doing?' Henry asks.
Marcel doesn't answer. Then he says, 'Aha!
I was right. Can you see?'
Henry smiles. 'Yes, I can. Not very well,
but... it says, "Concorde - 7.20".'
Marcel puts down the notepad and looks at
his watch. It's six o'clock. Then he starts
to run down the leg of the table.
Henry runs down the leg of the table, too.
'Where are we going now?' he asks.
'Heathrow Airport, of course,' Marcel says.
At 6.05 the two mice are in Old Wilton Street.
It's dark and cold. They walk quickly to Knightsbridge
station. There are a lot of fireworks. 'BANG!
WHEEE! POP! WHOOSH!' Marcel watches them.
Then he remembers the very big BANG!!! in
the professor's flat.
'That was clever,' he thinks. 'Very, very
clever.'
There are hundreds of people at Knightsbridge
station. Marcel and Henry run under their
legs and bags. Marcel can hear a noise.
'Quick, Henry,' he says. 'A train's coming.'
He's right. A train is coming into the station.
A sign on the front of it says, 'Heathrow'.
The doors open and the mice get on.
Henry looks at Marcel in the hot, dark safe.
'What are we going to do?' he asks. 'That
woman's got the letters. Let's telephone the
police.'
'No, there isn't time,' Marcel says. 'Do you
know her?' 'The woman? No, I don't.'
'Who usually lives in that flat?'
'Two old women, but they're on holiday in
Spain. Oh Marcel, what are we going to do?'
Marcel looks into the dark flat. 'Come with
me,' he says. He climbs into the old women's
flat. Henry is behind him. The two mice run
across the floor. Then they climb up a table.
On the table there's a yellow light and a
small, white notepad. Marcel looks at it under
the light.
'What are you doing?' Henry asks.
Marcel doesn't answer. Then he says, 'Aha!
I was right. Can you see?'
Henry smiles. 'Yes,
I can. Not very well, but... it says,
"Concorde - 7.20".'
Marcel puts down the notepad and looks at
his watch. It's six o'clock. Then he starts
to run down the leg of the table.
Henry runs down the leg of the table, too.
'Where are we going now?' he asks.
'Heathrow Airport, of course,' Marcel says.
At 6,05 the two mice are in Old Wilton Street.
It's dark and cold. They walk quickly to Knightsbridge
station. There are a lot of fireworks. 'BANG!
WHEEE! POP! WHOOSH!' Marcel watches them.
Then he remembers the very big BANG!!! In
the professor's flat.
'That was clever,' he thinks. 'Very, very
clever.'
There are hundreds of people at Knightsbridge
station. Marcel and Henry run under their
legs and bags. Marcel can hear a noise.
'Quick, Henry,' he says. 'A train's coming.'
He's right. A train is coming into the station.
A sign on the front of it says, 'Heathrow'.
The doors open and the mice get on.
There are fifteen stations before Heathrow.
Every time, the train stops. Henry says, 'Quick,
quick - what are we waiting for?' Then the
doors close and the train starts again.
At Heathrow, the mice get off. Marcel looks
left and right. 'Where do we go now?' he asks.
'I don't know,' Henry says. He looks left
and right, too.
There are a lot of signs. Then suddenly Henry
smiles.
'Marcel, look! That blue sign says "Concorde".'
'Good,' Marcel says. He looks at his watch.
It's 7.10. 'Let's go,' he says.
The mice start to run again. 'Marcel,' Henry
says, 'what are we going to do? OK, we find
the woman... but then what do we do? How do
we get the letters back?'
Marcel smiles. 'Wait and see,' he says.
They come to a door. It says, 'CONCORDE',
but it's closed. Henry and Marcel stop in
front of it.
'Oh no,' says Henry.
But then two men with big bags open the door
and go in. The mice go in, too.
'Good,' Marcel says. He looks at the people
in the room. 'Now... can you see her?'
'No, I can't,' Henry says.
Marcel smiles. 'I can,' he says.
'Where?'
'There. In front of us.'
Henry looks. Marcel is right. The American
woman is sitting on a chair and listening
to her Walkman. She's reading a newspaper,
too. Her bag is on the floor,
'OK - let's go,' Marcel says. He takes a small
knife from his coat. 'Walk behind me, Henry
- but be very, very quiet.'
He starts to walk across the room. Henry walks
behind his friend. 'Marcel's a detective,'
he thinks. 'It's going to be OK. He knows
his job. He does this every day. Yes... it's
- going - to be - O - K.'
Marcel stops in front of the American woman's
bag. He looks at Henry. 'Ssshh,' he says.
'Wait here.' Then he climbs up the bag.
After a short time, he starts to make a hole
in it with his knife. Henry watches. His mouth
is open. He looks at the American woman. She's
listening to music and reading. She doesn't
look down.
Marcel climbs into the bag. It's dark. He
closes his eyes and opens them again. Now
he can see some jeans a radio - some books.
Then suddenly he sees the Shakespeare letters.
'Good,' he thinks.
He puts the letters on his back and starts
to climb down again. Henry sees him and smiles.
But then the mice hear a noise.
'Bing bong!'
The American woman looks at her watch. Then
she takes off her Walkman and starts to put
it in her bag.
'Hey!' she says. 'What...? Two mice! What's
this?'
'Quick, Henry - catch!' Marcel says. He gives
the letters to Henry. Then he climbs down
the bag. The mice run very quickly with the
Shakespeare letters. They can hear the American
woman behind them. She's running very quickly,
too.
The door is open. A man is coming in. He's
fat and he has two bags. The mice run under
his legs. Then Marcel hears a big noise! He
looks behind him. The American woman is on
the floor, and the man is talking to her.
'Sorry,' he says. 'Are you OK?'
The woman stands up. 'No!' she says. Then
she looks for the mice, but she can't see
them.
At nine o'clock Marcel and Henry are back
at Professor Barton's flat in Old Wilton Street.
They're very happy. Marcel is sitting on the
table. The Shakespeare letters are in front
of him. He's reading them. Henry is standing
at the window. He's watching the fireworks.
Suddenly he sees a man in a brown coat. It's
Professor Barton. He's coming home.
The professor is smiling. Then he walks into
his flat and suddenly he stops smiling. Marcel
and Henry are standing behind a chair. They
watch him.
He goes to the safe. It's open. He looks in
it and says, 'Oh no!'
Then he sees the Shakespeare letters on the
table. 'But...' He puts one hand on his head.
'I don't understand.' He looks at the safe.
Then he looks at the letters - and then he
looks at the safe again. 'Why are the letters
here?' he says.
'When...? How...? I don't understand.'
In the morning, Henry and Marcel go to the
British Museum. It's a cold day, and it's
raining.
In the museum, there are a lot of journalists
and TV people. They're waiting for Professor
Barton.
He arrives at ten o'clock.
'Good morning,' he says to them.
He starts to talk about the Shakespeare letters.
Then he gives the letters to a man from the
museum.
'Thank you very much, Professor,' the man
says.
Henry and Marcel are standing at the back
of the room. Henry smiles at his French friend.
'And thank you, Marcel,' he says.
- THE END -