CHAPTER ONE
The Club
I dressed a bit more speedily than normal
on that snowy, windy, bitter night-I admit
it. It was 23 December, 1970, and I suspect
that there were other members of the club
who did the same. Taxis are notoriously hard
to come by in New York on stormy nights, so
I called for a radio-cab. I did this at five-thirty
for an eight o'clock pick-up-my wife raised
an eyebrow but said nothing. I was under the
awning of the apartment building on East 58th
Street, where Ellen and I had lived since
1946, by quarter to eight, and when the taxi
was five minutes late, I found myself pacing
up and down impatiently.
The taxi arrived at 8.10 and I got in, too
glad to be out of the wind to be as angry
with the driver as he probably deserved. That
wind, part of a cold front that had swept
down from Canada the day before, meant business.
It whistled and whined around the cab's window,
occasionally drowning out the salsa on the
driver's radio and rocking the big Checker
on its springs. Many of the stores were open
but the sidewalks were nearly bare of last-minute
shoppers. Those that were abroad looked uncomfortable
or actually pained.
It had been flurrying off and on all day,
and now the snow began again, coming first
in thin membranes, then twisting into cyclone
shapes ahead of us in the street. Coming home
that night, I would think of the combination
of snow, a taxi, and New York City with considerably
greater unease but I did not of course know
that then.
At the corner of 3rd and Fortieth, a large
tinsel Christmas bell went floating through
the intersection like a spirit. 'Bad night,'
the cabbie said. "They'll have an extra two
dozen in the morgue tomorrow. Wino Popsicles.
Plus a few bag-lady Popsicles.'
'I suppose.'
The cabbie ruminated. 'Well, good riddance,'
he said finally. 'Less welfare, right?'
'Your Christmas spirit,' I said, 'is stunning
in its width and depth.'
The cabbie ruminated. 'You one of those bleeding-heart
liberals?' he asked finally.
'I refuse to answer on the grounds that my
answer might tend to incriminate me,' I said.
The cabbie gave a why-do-I-always-get-the-wisenheimers
snort but he shut up.
He let me out at 2nd and Thirty-Fifth, and
I walked halfway down the block to the club,
bent over against the whistling wind, holding
my hat on my head with one gloved hand.
In almost no time at all the life-force seemed
to have been driven deep into my body, a flickering
blue flame about the size of the pilot-light
in a gas oven. At seventy-three, a man feels
the cold quicker and deeper. That man should
be home in front of a fireplace or at least
in front of an electric heater. At seventy-three,
hot blood isn't even really a memory; it's
more of an academic concept.
The latest flurry was letting up, but snow
as dry as sand still beat into my face. I
was glad to see that the steps leading up
to the door of 249 had been sanded-that was
Stevens's work, of course-Stevens knew the
base alchemy of old age well enough: not lead
into gold but bones into glass. When I think
about such things, I believe that God probably
thinks a great deal like Groucho Marx.
Then Stevens was there, holding the door open,
and a moment later I was inside. Down the
mahogany-panelled hallway, through double
doors standing three-quarters of the way open
on their recessed tracks, into the library
cum reading-room cum bar. It was a dark room
in which occasional pools of light gleamed-reading-lamps.
A richer, more textured light glowed across
the oak parquet floor, and I could hear the
steady snap of birch logs in the huge fireplace.
The heat radiated all the way across the room
-surely there is no welcome for a man or a
woman that can equal a fire on the hearth.
A paper rustled-dry, slightly impatient. That
would be Johanssen, with his Wall Street Journal.
After ten years, it was possible to recognize
his presence simply by the way he read his
stocks. Amusing and in a quiet way, amazing.
Stevens helped me off with my overcoat, murmuring
that it was a dirty night; WCBS was now forecasting
heavy snow before morning.
I agreed that it was indeed a dirty night
and looked back into that big, high-ceilinged
room again. A dirty night, a roaring fire
and a ghost story. Did I say that at seventy-three
hot blood is a thing of the past? Perhaps
so. But I felt something warm in my chest
at the thought something that hadn't been
caused by the fire of Stevens's reliable,
dignified welcome.
I think it was because it was McCarron's turn
to tell the tale.
I had been coming to the brownstone which
stands at 249 East 35th Street for ten years
-coming at intervals that were almost-but
not quite-regular. In my own mind I think
of it is a 'gentleman's club', that amusing
pre-Gloria Steinem antiquity. But even now
I am not sure that's what it really is, or
how it came to be in the first place. On the
night Emlyn McCarron told his story-the story
of the Breathing Method-there were perhaps
thirteen clubmembers in all, although only
six of us had come out on that howling, bitter
night. I can remember years when there might
have been as few as eight full-time members,
and others when there were at least twenty,
and perhaps more. I suppose Stevens might
know how it all came to be-one thing I am
sure of is that Stevens has been there from
the first, no matter how long that may be
and I believe Stevens to be older than he
looks. Much, much older. He has a faint Brooklyn
accent, but in spite of that he is as brutally
correct and as cuttingly punctilious as a
third-generation English butler. His reserve
is part of his often maddening charm, and
Stevens's small smile is a locked and latched
door. I have never seen any club records-if
he keeps them. I have never gotten a receipt
of dues-there are no dues. I have never been
called by the club secretary-there is no secretary,
and at 249 East 35 th, there are no phones.
There is no box of white marbles and black
balls. And the club-if it is a club-has never
had a name.
I first came to the club (as I must continue
to call it) as the guest of George Waterhouse.
Waterhouse headed the law firm for which I
had worked since 1951. My progress upward
in the firm-one of New York's three biggest-had
been steady but extremely slow; I was a slogger,
a mule for work, something of a centre puncher
but I had no real flair or genius. I had seen
men who had begun at the same time I had,
promoted in giant steps while I only continued
to pace -and I saw it with no real surprise.
Waterhouse and I had exchanged pleasantries,
attended the obligatory dinner put on by the
firm each October, and had little more congress
until the fall of 1960, when he dropped by
my office one day in early November.
This in itself was unusual enough, and it
had me thinking black thoughts (dismissal)
that were counterbalanced by giddy ones (an
unexpected promotion). It was a puzzling visit.
Waterhouse leaned in the doorway, his Phi
Beta Kappa key gleaming mellowly on his vest,
and talked in amiable generalities-none of
what he said seemed to have any real substance
or importance. I kept expecting him to finish
the pleasantries and get down to cases: 'Now
about this Casey brief,' or 'We've been asked
to research the Mayor's appointment of Salkowitz
to -' But it seemed there were no cases. He
glanced at his watch, said he had enjoyed
our talk and that he had to be going. I was
still blinking, bewildered, when he turned
back and said casually: There's a place where
I go most Thursday nights-a sort of club.
Old duffers, mostly, but some of them are
good company. They keep a really excellent
cellar, if you've a palate. Every now and
then someone tells a good story, as well.
Why not come down some night, David? As my
guest.'
I stammered some reply-even now I'm not sure
what it was. I was bewildered by the offer.
It had a spur-of-the-moment sound, but there
was nothing spur-of-the-moment about his eyes,
blue Anglo-Saxon ice under the bushy white
whorls of his eyebrows. And if I don't remember
exactly how I replied, it was because I felt
suddenly sure that this offer -vague and puzzling
as it was-had been exactly the specific I
had kept expecting him to get down to.
Ellen's reaction that evening was one of amused
exasperation. I had been with Waterhouse,
Garden, Lawton, Frasier, and Effingham for
something like twenty years, and it was clear
enough that I could not expect to rise much
above the mid-level position I now held; it
was her idea that this was the firm's cost-efficient
substitute for a gold watch.
'Old men telling war stories and playing poker,'
she said. 'A night of that and you're supposed
to be happy in the Research Library until
they pension you off, I suppose oh, I put
two Becks' on ice for you.' And she kissed
me warmly. I suppose she had seen something
on my face-God knows she's good at reading
me after all the years we've spent together.
Nothing happened over a course of weeks. When
my mind turned to Waterhouse's odd offer-certainly
odd coming from a man with whom I met less
than a dozen times a year, and who I only
saw socially at perhaps three parties a year,
including the company party in October- I
supposed that I had been mistaken about the
expression in his eyes, that he really had
made the offer casually, and had forgotten
it. Or regretted it-ouch! And then he approached
me one late afternoon, a man of nearly seventy
who was still broad-shouldered and athletic
looking. I was shrugging on my topcoat with
my briefcase between my feet. He said: 'If
you'd still like to have a drink at the club,
why not come tonight?' 'Well, I...'
'Good.' He slapped a slip of paper into my
hand. 'Here's the address.' He was waiting
for me at the foot of the steps that evening,
and Stevens held the door for us. The wine
was as excellent as Waterhouse had promised.
He made no attempt whatsoever to 'introduce
me around'- I took that for snobbery but later
recanted the idea -but two or three of them
introduced themselves to me. One of those
who did so was Emlyn McCarron, even then in
his early seventies. He held out his hand
and I clasped it briefly. His skin was dry,
leathery, tough; almost turtle-like. He asked
me if I played bridge. I said I did not.
'God damned good thing,' he said 'That god
damned game has done more in this century
to kill intelligent after-dinner conversation
than anything else I can think of.' And with
that pronouncement he walked away into the
murk of the library, where shelves of books
went up apparently to infinity.
I looked around for Waterhouse, but he had
disappeared. Feeling a little uncomfortable
and a lot out of place, I wandered over to
the fireplace. It was, as I believe I have
already mentioned, a huge thing-it seemed
particularly huge in New York, where apartment-dwellers
such as myself have trouble imagining such
a benevolence big enough to do anything more
than pop corn or toast bread. The fireplace
at 249 East 35th was big enough to broil an
ox whole. There was no mantle; instead a brawny
stone arch curved over it This arch was broken
in the centre by a keystone which jutted out
slightly. It was just on the level of my eyes,
and although the light was dim, I could read
the legend engraved on that stone with no
trouble: IT IS THE TALE, NOT HE WHO TELLS
IT. 'Here you go, David,' Waterhouse said
from my elbow, and I jumped. He hadn't deserted
me after all; had only trudged off into some
uncharted locale to bring back drinks. 'Bombay
martini's yours, isn't it?'
'Yes. Thank you. Mr Waterhouse -'
'George,' he said. 'Here it's just George.'
'George, then,' I said, although it seemed
slightly mad to be using his first name. 'What
is all of-'
'Cheers,' he said.
We drank. The martini was perfect. I said
so instead of finishing my question. 'Stevens
tends the bar. He makes fine drinks. He likes
to say it's a small but vital skill. ' The
martini took the edge off my feelings of disorientation
and awkwardness (the edge, but the feelings
themselves remained- I had spent nearly half
an hour gazing into my closet and wondering
what to wear; I had finally settled on dark
brown slacks and a rough tweed jacket that
almost matched them, hoping I would not be
wandering into a group of men either turned
out in tuxedos or wearing bluejeans and L.
L. Bean's lumberjack shirts it seemed that
I hadn't gone too far wrong on the matter
of dress, anyway). A new place and a new situation
makes one crucially aware of every social
act, no matter how small, and at that moment,
drink in hand and the obligatory small toast
made, I wanted very much to be sure that I
hadn't overlooked any of the amenities. 'Is
there a guest book I ought to sign?' I asked.
'Something like that?' He looked mildly surprised.
'We don't have anything like that,' he said.
'At least, I don't think we do.' He glanced
around the dim, quiet room. Johanssen rattled
his Wall Street Journal, I saw Stevens pass
in a doorway at the far end of the room, ghostly
in his white mess jacket. George put his drink
on an endtable and tossed a fresh log onto
the fire. Sparks corkscrewed up the black
throat of the chimney.
'What does that mean?' I asked, pointing to
the inscription on the keystone. 'Any idea?'
Waterhouse read it carefully, as if for the
first time. IT IS THE TALE, NOT HE WHO TELLS
IT.
'I suppose I have an idea,' he said. 'You
may, too, if you should come back. Yes, I
should say you may have an idea or two. In
time. Enjoy yourself, David.' He walked away.
And, although it may seem odd, having been
left to sink or swim in such an unfamiliar
situation, I did enjoy myself. For one thing,
I have always loved books, and there was a
trove of interesting ones to examine here.
I walked slowly along the shelves, examining
the spines as best I could in the faint light,
pulling one out now and then, and pausing
once to look out a narrow window at the 2nd
Avenue intersection up the street. I stood
there and watched through the frost-rimmed
glass as the traffic light at the intersection
cycled from red to green to amber and back
to red again, and quite suddenly I felt the
queerest-and yet very welcome -sense of peace
come to me. It did not flood in; instead it
seemed to almost steal in. Oh yes, I can hear
you saying, that makes great sense; watching
a stop-and-go light gives everyone a sense
of peace. All right; it made no sense. I grant
you that. But the feeling was there, just
the same. It made me think for the first time
in years of the winter nights in the Wisconsin
farmhouse where I grew up: lying in bed in
a draughty upstairs room and marking the contrast
between the whistle of the January wind outside,
drifting snow as dry as sand along miles of
snow-fence, and the warmth my body created
under the two quilts. There were some law
books, but they were pretty damn strange:
Twenty Cases of Dismemberment and Their Outcomes
under British Law is one title I remember.
Pet Cases was another. I opened that one and
sure enough, it was a scholarly legal tome
dealing with the law's treatment (American
law, this time) of cases which bore in some
important respect upon pets-everything from
housecats that had inherited great sums of
money to an ocelot that had broken its chain
and seriously injured a postman. There was
a set of Dickens, a set of Defoe, a nearly
endless set of Trollope; and there was also
a set of novels-eleven of them-by a man named
Edward Gray Seville. They were bound in handsome
green leather, and the name of the firm gold-stamped
on the spine was Stedham & Son. I had never
heard of Seville nor of his publishers. The
copyright date of the first Seville-These
Were Our Brothers-was 1911. The date of the
last, Breakers, was 1935.
Two shelves down from the set of Seville novels
was a large folio volume which contained careful
step by step plans for Erector Set enthusiasts.
Next to it was another folio volume which
featured famous scenes from famous movies.
Each of these pictures filled one whole page,
and opposite each, filling the facing pages,
were free-verse poems either about the scenes
with which they were paired or inspired by
them. Not a very remarkable concept, but the
poets who were represented were remarkable-Robert
Frost, Marianne Moore, William Carlos Williams,
Wallace Stevens, Louis Zukofsky, and Erica
Jong, to mention just a few. Halfway through
the book I found a poem by Archibald MacLeish
set next to that famous photograph of Marilyn
Monroe standing on the subway grating and
trying to hold her skirt down. The poem was
titled The Toll' and it began: The shape of
the skirt is -we would say-the shape of a
bell The legs are the clapper-And some such
more. Not a terrible poem, but certainly not
MacLeish's best or anywhere near the top drawer.
I felt I could hold such an opinion because
I had read a good deal of Archibald MacLeish
over the years. I could not, however, recall
this poem about Marilyn Monroe (which it is;
the poem announces it even when divorced from
the picture-at the end MacLeish writes: My
legs clap my name: (Marilyn, ma belle). I
have looked for it since then and haven't
been able to find it; which means nothing,
of course. Poems are not like novels or legal
opinions; they are more like blown leaves
and any omnibus volume titled The Complete
So-and-So must certainly be a lie. Poems have
a way of getting lost under sofas-it is one
of their charms, and one of the reasons they
endure. But...
At some point Stevens came by with a second
martini (by then I had settled into a chair
of my own with a volume of Ezra Pound). It
was as perfect as the first. As I sipped it
I saw two of those present, George Gregson
and Harry Stein (Harry was six years dead
on the night Emlyn McCarron told us the story
of the Breathing Method), leave the room by
a peculiar door less than three feet high.
It was an Alice Down the Rabbit-Hole door
if ever there was one. They left it open,
and shortly after their odd exit from the
library I heard the muted click of billiard
balls.
Stevens passed by and asked if I would like
another martini. I declined with real regret.
He nodded. 'Very good sir.' His face never
changed, and yet I had an obscure feeling
that I had somehow pleased him.
Laughter startled me from my book sometime
later. Someone had thrown a packet of chemical
powder into the fire and turned the flames
momentarily particoloured. I thought of my
boyhood again but not in any wistful, sloppily
romantic-nostalgic way. I feel a great need
to emphasize that, God knows why. I thought
of times when I had done just such a thing
as a kid, but the memory was a strong one,
pleasant, untinged with regret.
I saw that most of the others had drawn chairs
up around the hearth in a semicircle. Stevens
had produced a heaping, smoking platter of
marvellous hot sausages. Harry Stein returned
through the down-the-rabbit-hole door, introducing
himself hurriedly but pleasantly to me. Gregson
remained in the billiard room, practising
shots, by the sound. After a moment's hesitation
I joined the others. A story was told-not
a pleasant one. It was Norman Stett who told
it, and while it is not my purpose to recount
it here, perhaps you'll understand what I
mean about its quality if I tell you that
it was about a man who drowned in a telephone
booth.
When Stett-who is also dead now-finished,
someone said, 'You should have saved it for
Christmas, Norman.' There was laughter, which
I of course did not understand. At least,
not then.
Waterhouse himself spoke up then, and such
a Waterhouse I never would have dreamed of
in a thousand years of dreaming. A graduate
of Yale, a Phi Beta Kappa, silver-haired,
three-piece-suited head of a law firm so large
it was more enterprise than company - this
Waterhouse told a story that had to do with
a teacher who had gotten stuck in a privy.
The privy stood behind the one-room schoolhouse
in which she had taught, and the day she got
her caboose jammed into one of the privy's
two holes also happened to be the day the
privy was scheduled to be taken away as Anniston
County's contribution to the Life As It Was
in New England exhibition being held at the
Prudential Center in Boston. The teacher hadn't
made a sound during all the time it took to
load the privy onto the back of a flatbed
truck and to spike it down; she was struck
dumb with embarrassment and horror, Waterhouse
said. And then the privy door blew off into
the passing lane of Route 128 in Somerville
during rush hour-But draw a curtain over that,
and over any other stories which might have
followed it; they are not my stories tonight.
At some point Stevens produced a bottle of
brandy that was more than just good; it was
damned near exquisite. It was passed around
and Johanssen raised a toast-the toast, one
might almost say: The tale, not he who tells
it. We drank to that.
Not long after, men began slipping away. It
wasn't late; not yet midnight, anyway; but
I've noticed that when your fifties give way
to your sixties, late begins coming earlier
and earlier. I saw Waterhouse slipping his
arms into the overcoat Stevens was holding
open for him, and decided that must be my
cue. I thought it strange that Waterhouse
would slip away without so much as a word
to me (which certainly seemed to be what he
was doing; if I had come back from shelving
the Pound book forty seconds later, he would
have been gone), but no stranger than most
of the other things that had gone on that
evening.
I stepped out just behind him, and Waterhouse
glanced around, as if surprised to see me
and almost as if he had been startled out
of a light doze. 'Share a taxi?' he asked,
as though we had just met by chance on this
deserted, windy street 'Thank you,' I said.
I meant thanks for a great deal more than
his offer to share a cab, and I believe that
was unmistakable in my tone, but he nodded
as if that was all I had meant.
A taxi with its for-hire light lit was cruising
slowly down the street-fellows like George
Waterhouse seem to luck onto cabs even on
those miserably cold or snowy New York nights
when you would swear there isn't a cab to
be had on the entire island of Manhattan-and
he flagged it.
Inside, safely warm, the taxi-meter charting
our journey in measured clicks, I told him
how much I had enjoyed his story. I couldn't
remember laughing so hard or so spontaneously
since I was eighteen, I told him, which was
not flattery but only the simple truth.
'Oh? How kind of you to say.' His voice was
chillingly polite. I subsided, feeling a dull
flush in my cheeks. One does not always need
to hear a slam to know that the door has been
closed.
When the taxi drew up to the curb in front
of my building, I thanked him again, and this
time he showed a trifle more warmth. 'It was
good of you to come on such short notice,'
he said. 'Come again, if you like. Don't wait
for an invitation: we don't stand much on
ceremony at two-four-nine. Thursdays are best
for stories, but the club is there every night.'
Am I then to assume membership?
The question was on my lips. I meant to ask
it; it seemed necessary to ask it. I was only
mulling it over, listening to it in my head
(in my tiresome lawyer's way) to hear if I
had got the phrasing right-perhaps that was
a little too blunt-when Waterhouse told the
cabbie to drive on. The next moment the taxi
was rolling on towards Madison. I stood there
on the sidewalk for a moment, the hem of my
topcoat whipping around my shins, thinking:
He knew I was going to ask that question-he
knew it, and he purposely had the driver go
on before I could. Then I told myself that
was utterly absurd -paranoid, even.
And it was. But it was also true. I could
scoff all I liked; none of the scoffing changed
that essential certainty.
I walked slowly to the door of my building
and went inside.
Ellen was sixty per cent asleep when I sat
down on the bed to take off my shoes. She
rolled over and made a fuzzy interrogative
sound deep in her throat. I told her to go
back to sleep.
She made the fuzzy sound again. This time
approximated English: 'Howwuzzit?'
For a moment I hesitated, my shirt half-unbuttoned.
And I thought with one moment's utter clarity:
If I tell her, I will never see the other
side of that door again.
'It was all right,' I said. 'Old men telling
war stories.'
'I told you so.'
'But it wasn't bad. I might go back again.
It might do me some good with the firm.'
'"The firm",' she mocked lightly. 'What an
old buzzard you are, my love.'
'It takes one to know one,' I said, but she
had already fallen asleep again. I undressed,
showered, towelled, put on my pyjamas and
then, instead of going to bed as I should
have done (it was edging past one by that
time), I put on my robe and had another bottle
of Beck's. I sat at the kitchen table, drinking
it slowly, looking out the window and up the
cold canyon of Madison Avenue, thinking. My
head was a trifle buzzy from my evening's
intake of alcohol-for me an unexpectedly large
intake. But the feeling was not at all unpleasant,
and I had no sense of an impending hangover.
The thought which had come to me when Ellen
asked me about my evening was as ridiculous
as the one I'd entertained about George Waterhouse
as the cab drew away from me -what in God's
name could be wrong with telling my wife about
a perfectly harmless evening at my boss's
stuffy men's club and even if something were
wrong with telling her, who would know that
I had? No, it was every bit as ridiculous
and paranoid as those earlier musings and,
my heart told me, every bit as true.
I met George Waterhouse the next day in the
hallway between Accounts and the Reading Library.
Met him Passed him would be more accurate.
He nodded my way and went on without speaking
as he had done for years.
My stomach muscles ached all day long. That
was the only thing that completely convinced
me the evening had been real.
Three weeks passed. Four five. No second invitation
came from Waterhouse.
Somehow I just hadn't been right; hadn't fitted.
Or so I told myself. It was a depressing,
disappointing thought. I supposed it would
begin to fade and lose its sting, as all disappointments
eventually do. But I thought of that evening
at the oddest moments-the isolated pools of
library lamplight, so still and tranquil and
somehow civilized; Waterhouse's absurd and
hilarious tale of the schoolteacher stuck
in the privy; the rich smell of leather in
the narrow stacks. Most of all I thought of
standing by that narrow window and watching
the frost crystals change from green to amber
to red. I thought of that sense of peace I
had felt.
During that same five-week period I went to
the library and checked out four volumes of
Archibald MacLeish's poetry (I had three others
myself, and had already checked through them);
one of these volumes purported to be The Complete
Poems of. I reacquainted myself with some
old favourites, including my favourite MacLeish
poem, 'Epistle to Be Left in Earth.' But I
found no poem called 'The Toll' in any of
the volumes.
On that same trip to the New York Public Library,
I checked the card catalogue for works of
fiction by a man named Edward Gray Seville.
A mystery novel by a woman named Ruth Seville
was the closest I came.
Come again, if you like; don't wait for an
invitation
I was waiting for an invitation anyway, of
course; my mother taught me donkey's years
ago not to automatically believe people who
tell you glibly to 'drop by anytime' or that
'the door is always open'. I didn't feel I
needed an engraved card delivered to my apartment
door by a footman in livery bearing a gilt
plate, I don't mean that, but I did want something,
even if it was only a casual remark: 'Coming
by some night, David? Hope we didn't bore
you.' That kind of thing.
But when even that didn't come, I began to
think more seriously about going back anyway-after
all, sometimes people really did want you
to drop in anytime; I supposed that, at some
places, the door always was open; and that
mothers weren't always right.
Don't wait for an invitation
Anyway, that's how it happened that, on 10
December of that year, I found myself putting
on my rough tweed coat and dark brown pants
again and looking for my darkish red tie.
I was rather more aware of my heartbeat than
usual that night, I remember.
'George Waterhouse finally broke down and
asked you back?' Ellen asked. 'Back into the
sty with the rest of the male chauvinist oinkers?'
'That's right,' I said, thinking it must be
the first time in at least a dozen years that
I had told her a lie and then I remembered
that, after the first meeting, I had answered
her questions about what it had been like
with a lie. Old men telling war stories, I
had said.
'Well, maybe there really will be a promotion
in it,' she said though without much hope.
To her credit, she said it without much bitterness,
either.
'Stranger things have happened,' I said, and
kissed her goodbye.
'Oink-oink,' she said as I went out the door.
The taxi ride that night seemed very long.
It was cold, still, and starry. The cab was
a Checker and I felt somehow very small in
it, like a child seeing the city for the first
time.
It was excitement I was feeling as the cab
pulled up in front of the brownstone-something
as simple and yet complete as that. But such
simple excitement seems to be one of life's
qualities that slips away almost unnoticed,
and its rediscovery as one grows older is
always something of a surprise, like finding
a black hair or two in one's comb years after
one had last found such a thing.
I paid the driver, got out, and walked towards
the four steps leading to the door. As I mounted
them, my excitement curdled into plain apprehension
(a feeling the old are much more familiar
with). What exactly was I doing here?
The door was of thick panelled oak, and to
my eye it looked as stout as the door of a
castle keep. There was no doorbell that I
could see, no knocker, no closed circuit TV
camera mounted unobtrusively hi the shadow
of a deep eave, and, of course, no Waterhouse
waiting to take me in. I stopped at the foot
of the steps and looked around.
Thirty-Fifth Street suddenly seemed darker,
colder, more threatening. The brownstones
all looked somehow secret, as if hiding mysteries
best not investigated. Their windows looked
like eyes.
Somewhere, behind one of those windows, there
may be a man or woman contemplating murder,
I thought. A shudder worked up my spine. Contemplating
it or doing it.
Then, suddenly, the door was open and Stevens
was there.
I felt an intense surge of relief. I am not
an overly imaginative man, I think-at least
not under ordinary circumstances-but this
last thought had had all the eerie clarity
of prophecy. I might have babbled aloud if
I hadn't glanced at Stevens's eyes first.
His eyes did not know me. His eyes did not
know me at all.
Then there was another instance of that eerie,
prophetic clarity; I saw the rest of my evening
in perfect detail. Three hours in a quiet
bar. Three martinis (perhaps four) to dull
the embarrassment of having been fool enough
to go where I wasn't wanted. The humiliation
my mother's advice had been intended to avoid-that
which comes with knowing one has overstepped.
I saw myself going home a little tipsy, but
not in a good way. I saw myself merely sitting
through the cab ride rather than experiencing
it through that childlike lens of excitement
and anticipation. I heard myself saying to
Ellen, It wears thin after a while Waterhouse
told the same story about winning a consignment
of T-bone steaks for the 3rd Battalion in
a poker game and they play Hearts for a dollar
a point, can you believe it? go back? I suppose
I might, but I doubt it. And that would be
the end of it. Except, I suppose, for my own
humiliation.
I saw all of this in the nothing of Stevens's
eyes. Then the eyes warmed. He smiled slightly
and said: 'Mr Adley! Come in. I'll take your
coat.'
I mounted the steps and Stevens closed the
door firmly behind me. How different a door
can feel when you are on the warm side of
it! He took my coat and was gone with it.
I stood in the hall for a moment, looking
at my own reflection in the pier glass, a
man of sixty-three whose face was rapidly
becoming too gaunt to look middle-aged. And
yet the reflection pleased me. I slipped into
the library.
Johanssen was there, reading his Wall Street
Journal. In another island of light, Emlyn
McCarron sat over a chessboard opposite Peter
Andrews. McCarron was and is a cadaverous
man, possessed of a narrow, bladelike nose;
Andrews was huge, slope-shouldered, and choleric.
A vast ginger-coloured beard sprayed over
his vest.
Face to face over the inlaid board with its
carved pieces of ivory and ebony, they looked
like Indian totems: eagle and bear.
Waterhouse was there, frowning over that day's
Times. He glanced up, nodded at me without
surprise, and disappeared into the paper again.
Stevens brought me a Bombay martini, unasked.
I took it into the stacks and found that puzzling,
enticing set of green volumes again. I began
reading the works of Edward Gray Seville that
night. I started at the beginning, with These
Were Our Brothers. Since then I have read
them all, and believe them to be eleven of
the finest novels of our century.
Near the end of the evening there was a story
-just one -and Stevens brought brandy around.
When the tale was told, people began to rise,
preparing to leave. Stevens spoke from the
double doorway which communicated with the
hallway. His voice was low and pleasant, but
carrying: 'Who will bring us a tale for Christmas,
then?'
People stopped what they were doing and glanced
around. There was some low, goodnatured talk
and a burst of laughter.
Stevens, smiling but serious, clapped his
hands together twice, like a grammar school
teacher calling an unruly class to order.
'Come, gentlemen-who'll bring the tale?' Peter
Andrews, he of the sloped shoulders and gingery
beard, cleared his throat. 'I have something
I've been thinking about I don't know if it's
quite right; that is, if it's
'That will be fine,' Stevens interrupted,
and there was more laughter. Andrews had his
back slapped good naturedly. Cold draughts
swirled up the hallway as men slipped out.
Then Stevens was there, as if by benign magic,
holding my coat for me. 'Good evening, Mr
Adley. Always a pleasure.'
'Do you really meet on Christmas night?' I
asked, buttoning my coat I was a little disappointed
that I was going to miss Andrews's story,
but we had made firm plans to drive to Schenectady
and keep the holiday with Ellen's sister.
Stevens managed to look both shocked and amused
at the same time. 'In no case,' he said. 'Christmas
is a night a man should spend with his family.
That night, if no other. Don't you agree,
sir?'
'I certainly do.'
'We always meet on the Thursday before Christmas.
In fact, that is the one night of the year
when we're assured a large turnout.'
He hadn't used the word members, I noticed-just
happenstance or neat avoidance? 'Many tales
have been spun out in the main room, Mr Adley,
tales of every sort, from the comic to the
tragic to the ironic to the sentimental. But
on the Thursday before Christmas, it's always
a tale of the uncanny. It's always been that
way, at least as far back as I can remember.'
That at least explained the comment I had
heard on my first visit, the one to the effect
that Norman Stett should have saved his story
for Christmas. Other questions hovered on
my lips, but I saw a reflected caution in
Stevens's eyes. Do you catch my drift? It
was not a warning that he would not answer
my questions; it was, rather, a warning that
I should not even ask them.
'Was there something else, Mr Adley?'
We were alone in the hall now. All the others
had left And suddenly the hallway seemed darker,
Stevens's long face paler, his lips redder.
A knot exploded in the fireplace and a red
glow washed momentarily across the polished
parquet floor. I thought I heard, from somewhere
in those as-yet-unexplored rooms beyond, a
kind of slithery bump. I did not like the
sound. Not at all.
'No,' I said in a voice that was not quite
steady. 'I think not.'
'Goodnight, then,' Stevens said, and I crossed
the threshold. I heard the heavy door close
behind me. I heard the lock turn. And then
I was walking towards the lights of 2nd Avenue,
not looking back over my shoulder, somehow
afraid to look back, as if I might see some
frightful fiend matching me stride for stride,
or glimpse some secret better kept than known.
I reached the corner, saw an empty cab, and
flagged it.
'More war stories?' Ellen asked me that night
She was in bed with Philip Marlowe, the only
lover she has ever taken. [Note: Phillip Marlowe
is a fictitious detective in novels]
"There was a war story or two,' I said, hanging
up my overcoat. 'Mostly I sat and read a book.'
'When you weren't oinking.'
'Yes, that's right. When I wasn't oinking.'
'Listen to this: "The first time I ever laid
eyes on Terry Lennox he was drunk in a Rolls-Royce
Stiver Wraith outside the terrace of the Dancers,"'
Ellen read.' "He had a young-looking face
but his hair was bone white. You could tell
by his eyes that he was plastered to the hairline,
but otherwise he looked like any other nice
young guy in a dinner jacket who had been
spending too much money in a place that exists
for that purpose and for no other." Nice,
huh? It's -'
'The Long Goodbye' I said, taking off my shoes.
'You read me that same passage once every
three years. It's part of your life-cycle.'
She wrinkled her nose at me. 'Oink-oink.'
'Thank you,' I said.
She went back to her book. I went out into
the kitchen to get a bottle of Beck's. When
I came back, she had laid The Long Goodbye
open on the counterpane and was looking at
me closely. 'David, are you going to join
this club?'
'I suppose I might if I'm asked.' I felt uncomfortable.
I had perhaps told her another lie. If there
was such a thing as membership at 249 East
35 th, I already was a member. 'I'm glad,'
she said. 'You've needed something for a long
time now. I don't think you even know it,
but you have. I've got the Relief Committee
and the Commission on Women's Rights and the
Theatre Society. But you've needed something.
Some people to grow old with, I think.'
I went to the bed and sat beside her and picked
up The Long Goodbye. It was a bright, new-minted
paperback. I could remember buying the original
hardback edition as a birthday present for
Ellen. In 1953. 'Are we old?' I asked her.
'I suspect we are,' she said, and smiled brilliantly
at me.
I put the book down and touched her breast.
'Too old for this?'
She turned the covers back with ladylike decorum
and then, giggling, kicked them onto the floor
with her feet. 'Beat me, daddy,' Ellen said,
'eight to the bar.'
'Oink, oink,' I said, and then we were both
laughing.
The Thursday before Christmas came. That evening
was much the same as the others, with two
notable exceptions. There were more people
there, perhaps as many as eighteen.
And there was a sharp, indefinable sense of
excitement in the air. Johansson took only
a cursory glance at his Journal and then joined
McCarron, Hugh Beagleman, and myself.
We sat near the windows, talking of this and
that, and finally fell into a passionate-and
often hilarious-discussion of pre-war automobiles.
There was, now that I think of it, a third
difference as well-Stevens had concocted a
delicious eggnog punch. It was smooth, but
it was also hot with rum and spices. It was
served from an incredible Waterford bowl that
looked like an ice-sculpture, and the animated
hum of the conversation grew ever higher as
the level of the punch grew lower.
I looked over in the corner by the tiny door
leading to the billiard room and was astounded
to see Waterhouse and Norman Stett flipping
baseball cards into what looked like a genuine
beaver tophat. They were laughing uproariously.
Groups formed and re-formed. The hour grew
late and then, at the time when people usually
began slipping out through the front door,
I saw Peter Andrews seated in front of the
fire with an unmarked packet, about the size
of a seed envelope, in one hand. He tossed
it into the flames without opening it, and
a moment later the fire began to dance with
every colour of the spectrum-and some, I would
have sworn, from outside it-before turning
yellow again. Chairs were dragged around.
Over Andrews's shoulder I could see the keystone
with its etched homily: IT IS THE TALE, NOT
HE WHO TELLS IT.
Stevens passed unobtrusively among us, taking
punch glasses and replacing them with snifters
of brandy. There were murmurs of 'Merry Christmas'
and 'Top of the season, Stevens,' and for
the first time I saw money change hands-a
ten dollar bill was unobtrusively tendered
here, a bill that looked like a fifty there,
one which I clearly saw was a hundred from
another chair.
'Thank you, Mr McCarron Mr Johansson Mr Beagleman'
A quiet, well-bred murmur.
I have lived in New York long enough to know
that the Christmas season is a carnival of
tips; something for the butcher, the baker,
the candlestick-maker-not to mention the doorman,
the super, and the cleaning lady who comes
in Tuesdays and Fridays. I've never met anyone
of my own class who regarded this as anything
but a necessary nuisance but I felt none of
that grudging spirit on that night. The money
was given willingly, even eagerly and suddenly,
for no reason (it was the way thoughts often
seemed to come when one was at 249), I thought
of the boy calling up to Scrooge on the still,
cold air of a London Christmas morning: 'Wot?
The goose that's as big as me?' And Scrooge,
nearly crazed with joy, giggling 'A good boy!
An excellent boy!'
I found my own wallet. In the back of this,
behind the pictures of Ellen I keep, there
has always been a fifty dollar bill which
I keep for emergencies. When Stevens gave
me my brandy, I slipped it into his hand with
never a qualm although I was not a rich man.
'Happy Christmas, Stevens,' I said.
'Thank you, sir. And the same to you.'
He finished passing out the brandies and collecting
his honorariums and retired. I glanced around
once, at the midpoint of Peter Andrews's story,
and saw him standing by the double doors,
a dim manlike shadow, still and silent.
'I'm a lawyer now, as most of you know,' Andrews
said after sipping at his glass, clearing
his throat, and then sipping again. 'I've
had offices on Park Avenue for the last twenty-two
years. But before that, I was a legal assistant
in a firm of lawyers which did business in
Washington, DC. One night in July I was required
to stay late in order to finish indexing case
citations in a brief which hasn't anything
at all to do with this story. But then a man
came in- a man who was at that time one of
the most widely known Senators on the Hill,
a man who later almost became President. His
shirt was matted with blood and his eyes were
bulging from their sockets.
'"I've got to talk to Joe," he said. Joe,
you understand, was Joseph Woods, the head
of my firm, one of the most influential private-sector
lawyers in Washington, and this Senator's
close personal friend.
'"He went home hours ago," I said. I was terribly
frightened, I can tell you-he looked like
a man who had just walked away from a dreadful
car accident, or perhaps from a knife-fight
And somehow seeing his face which I had seen
in newspaper photos and on Meet the Press-seeing
it streaked with gore, one cheek twitching
spasmodically below one wild eye all of that
made my fright worse. "I can call him if you
-" I was already fumbling with the phone,
mad with eagerness to turn this unexpected
responsibility over to someone else. Looking
behind him, I could see the caked and bloody
footprints he had left on the carpet ' "I've
got to talk to Joe right now," he reiterated
as if he hadn't heard me.' "There's something
in the trunk of my car something I found out
at the Virginia place. I've shot it and stabbed
it and I can't kill it. It's not human, and
I can't kill it" 'He began to giggle and then
to laugh and finally to scream. And he was
still screaming when I finally got Mr Woods
on the phone and told him to come, for God's
sake, to come as fast as he could '
It is not my purpose to tell Peter Andrews's
story, either. As a matter of fact, I am not
sure I would dare to tell it. Suffice it to
say that it was a tale so gruesome that I
dreamed of it for weeks afterwards, and Ellen
once looked at me over the breakfast table
and asked me why I had suddenly cried out
'His head! His head is still speaking in the
earth!' in the middle of the night 'I suppose
it was a dream,' I said. 'One of those you
can't remember afterwards.' But my eyes dropped
immediately to my coffee cup, and I think
that Ellen knew the lie that time.
One day in August of the following year, I
was buzzed as I worked in the Readers Library.
It was George Waterhouse. He asked me if I
could step up to his office. When I got there
I saw that Robert Garden was also there, and
Henry Effingham. For one moment I was positive
I was about to be accused of some really dreadful
act of stupidity or malfeasance.
Then Garden stepped around to me and said:
'George believes the time has come to make
you a junior partner, David. The rest of us
agree.'
'It's going to be a little bit like being
the world's oldest JayCee,' Effingham said
with a grin, 'but it's the channel you have
to go through, David. With any luck, we can
make you a full partner by Christmas.'
There were no bad dreams that night. Ellen
and I went out to dinner, drank too much,
went on to a jazz place where we hadn't been
in nearly six years, and listened to that
amazing blue-eyed black man, Dexter Gordon,
blow his horn until almost two in the morning.
We woke up the next morning with fluttery
stomachs and achey heads, both of us still
unable to completely believe what had happened.
One of them was that my salary had just climbed
by eight thousand dollars a year long after
our expectations of such a staggering income
jump had fallen by the wayside.
The firm sent me to Copenhagen for six weeks
that fall, and I returned to discover that
John Hanrahan, one of the regular attendees
at 249, had died of cancer. A collection was
taken up for his wife, who had been left in
unpleasant circumstances. I was pressed into
service to total the amount-which was given
entirely in cash-and convert it to a cashier's
check. It came to almost ten thousand dollars.
I turned the check over to Stevens and I suppose
he mailed it.
It just so happened that Arlene Hanrahan was
a member of Ellen's Theatre Society, and Ellen
told me some time later that Arlene had received
an anonymous check for ten thousand four hundred
dollars. Written on the check stub was the
brief and unilluminating message 'Friends
of your late husband John'.
'Isn't that the most amazing thing you ever
heard in your life?' Ellen asked me.
'No,' I said, 'but it's right up there in
the top ten. Are there any more strawberries,
Ellen?'
The years went by. I discovered a warren of
rooms upstairs at 249-a writing room, a bedroom
where guests sometimes stayed overnight (although
after that slithery bump I had heard-or imagined
I had heard- I believe I personally would
rather have registered at a good hotel), a
small but well-equipped gymnasium, and a sauna
bath. There was also a long, narrow room which
ran the length of the building and contained
two bowling alleys.
In those same years I re-read the novels of
Edward Gray Seville, and discovered an absolutely
stunning poet-the equal of Ezra Pound and
Wallace Stevens, perhaps-named Norbert Rosen.
According to the back flap on one of the three
volumes of his work in the stacks, he had
been born in 1924 and killed at Anzio. All
three volumes of his work had been published
by Stedham & Son, New York and Boston.
I remember going back to the New York Public
Library on a bright spring afternoon during
one of those years (of which year I am no
longer sure) and requesting twenty years'
worth of Literary Market Place. The LMP is
an annual publication the size of a large
city's Yellow Pages, and the reference room
librarian was quite put out with me, I'm afraid.
But I persisted, and went through each volume
carefully. And although LMP is supposed to
list every publisher, great and small, in
the United States (in addition to agents,
editors, and book club staffs), I found no
listing for Stedham & Son. A year later-or
perhaps it was two years later- I fell into
conversation with an antiquarian book dealer
and asked him about the imprint. He said he
had never heard of it.
I thought of asking Stevens-saw that warning
light in his eyes-and dropped the question
unasked.
And, over those years, there were stories.
Tales, to use Stevens's word. Funny tales,
tales of love found and love lost, tales of
unease. Yes, and even a few war stories, although
none of the sort Ellen had likely been thinking
of when she made the suggestion.
I remember Gerard Tozeman's story the most
clearly-the tale of an American base of operations
which took a direct hit from German artillery
four months before the end of World War I,
killing everyone present except for Tozeman
himself.
Lathrop Carruthers, the American general who
everyone had by then decided must be utterly
insane (he had been responsible for better
than eighteen thousand casualties by then-lives
and limbs spent as casually as you or I might
spend a quarter in a jukebox), was standing
at a map of the front lines when the shell
struck. He had been explaining yet another
mad flanking operation at that moment-an operation
which would have succeeded only on the level
of all the others Carruthers had hatched:
it would be wonderfully successful at making
new widows.
And when the dust cleared, Gerard Tozeman,
dazed and deaf, bleeding from his nose, his
ears, and the corners of both eyes, his testicles
already swelling from the force of the concussion,
had come upon Carruthers's body while looking
for a way out of the abbatoir that had been
the staff HQ only minutes before. He looked
at the general's body and then began to scream
and laugh. The sounds went unheard by his
own shellshocked ears, but they served to
notify the medicos that someone was still
alive in that strew of matchwood.
Carruthers had not been mutilated by the blast
at least, Tozeman said, it hadn't been what
the soldiers of that long-ago war had come
to think of as mutilation-men whose arms had
been blown off, men with no feet, no eyes;
men whose lungs had been shrivelled by gas.
No, he said, it was nothing like that The
man's mother would have known him at once.
But the map the map before which Carruthers
had been standing with his butcher's pointer
when the shell struck
It had somehow been driven into his face.
Tozeman had found himself staring into a hideous,
tattooed deathmask. Here was the stony shore
of Brittany on the bony ridge of Lathrop Carruthers's
brow. Here was the Rhine flowing like a blue
scar down his left cheek. Here were some or
the finest wine-growing provinces in the world
bumped and ridged over his chin. Here was
the Saar drawn around his throat like a hangman's
noose and printed across one bulging eyeball
was the word VERSAILLES.
That was our Christmas story in the year 197-.
I remember many others, but they do not belong
here. Properly speaking, Tozeman's doesn't,
either but it was the first 'Christmas tale'
I heard at 249, and I could not resist telling
it. And then, on the Thursday after Thanksgiving
of this year, when Stevens clapped his hands
together for attention and asked who would
favour us with a Christmas tale, Emlyn McCarron
growled: 'I suppose I've got something that
bears telling. Tell it now or tell it never;
God'll shut me up for good soon enough.'
In the years I had been coming to 249, I had
never heard McCarron tell a story. And perhaps
that's why I called the taxi so early, and
why, when Stevens passed out eggnog to the
six of us who had ventured out on that bellowing,
frigid night, I felt so keenly excited. Nor
was I the only one; I saw that same excitement
on a good many other faces. McCarron, old
and dry and leathery, sat in the huge chair
by the fire with the packet of powder in his
gnarled hands. He tossed it in, and we watched
the flames shift colours madly before returning
to yellow again, Stevens passed among us with
brandy, and we passed him his Christmas honorariums.
Once, during that yearly ceremony, I heard
the clink of change passing from the hand
of the giver to the hand of the receiver;
on another occasion, I had seen a one thousand
dollar bill for a moment in the firelight.
On both occasions the murmur of Stevens's
voice had been exactly the same: low, considerate,
and entirely correct. Ten years, more or less,
had passed since I had first come to 249 with
George Waterhouse, and while much had changed
in the world outside, nothing had changed
in here, and Stevens seemed not to have aged
a month, or even a single day. He moved back
into the shadows, and for a moment there was
a silence so perfect that we could hear the
faint whistle of boiling sap escaping from
the burning logs on the hearth. Emlyn McCarron
was looking into the fire and we all followed
his gaze. The flames seemed particularly wild
that night. I felt almost hypnotized by the
sight of the fire-as, I suppose, the cavemen
who binned us were once hypnotized by it as
the wind walked and talked outside their cold
northern caves.
At last, still looking into the fire, bent
slightly forward so that his forearms rested
on his thighs and his clasped hands hung in
a knot between his knees, McCarron began to
speak.
CHAPTER TWO
The Breathing Method
I am nearly eighty now, which means that I
was born with the century. All my life I have
been associated with a building which stands
almost directly across from Madison Square
Garden; this building, which looks like a
great grey prison -something out of A Tale
of Two Cities-is actually a hospital, as most
of you know. It is Harriet White Memorial
Hospital. The Harriet White after whom it
was named was my father's first wife, and
she got her practical experience in nursing
when there were still actual sheep grazing
on the Sheep's Meadow in Central Park. A statue
of the lady herself (who would have been my
stepmother, had she still been alive when
I was born) stands on a pedestal in a pavillion
before the building, and if any of you have
seen it, you may have wondered how a woman
with such a stern and uncompromising face
could have found such a gentle occupation.
The motto chiselled into the statue's base,
once you get rid of the Latin folderol, is
even less comforting: There is no comfort
without pain; thus we define salvation through
suffering. Cato, if you please or if you don't
please! I was born inside that grey stone
building on 20 March, 1900. I returned there
as an intern in the year 1926. Twenty-six
is old to be just starting out in the world
of medicine, but I had done a more practical
internship in France, at the end of World
War I, trying to pack ruptured guts back into
stomachs that had been blown wide open and
dealing on the black market for morphine which
was often tinctured and sometimes dangerous.
As with the generation of physicians following
World War II, we were a bedrock-practical
lot of sawbones, and the records of the major
medical schools show a remarkably small number
of washouts in the years 1919 to 1928. We
were older, more experienced, steadier. Were
we also wiser? I don't know but we were certainly
more cynical. There was none of this nonsense
you read about in the popular medical novels,
stuff about fainting or vomiting at one's
first autopsy. Not after Belleau Wood, where
mamma rats sometimes raised whole litters
of ratlings in the gas-exploded intestines
of the soldiers left to rot in no-man's land.
We had gotten all our puking and passing out
behind us.
The Harriet White Memorial Hospital also figured
largely in something that happened to me nine
years after I had interned there-and this
is the story I want to tell you gentlemen
tonight. It is not a tale to be told at Christmas,
you would say (although its final scene was
played out on Christmas Eve), and yet, while
it is certainly horrible, it also seems to
express to me all the amazing power of our
cursed, doomed species. In it I see the wonder
of our will and also its horrible, tenebrous
power.
Birth itself, gentlemen, is a horrid thing
to many; it is the fashion now that fathers
should be present at the birth of their children,
and while this fashion has served to indict
many men with a guilt which I feel they may
not deserve (it is a guilt which some women
use knowingly and with an almost prescient
cruelty), it seems by and large to be a healthful,
salubrious thing. Yet I have seen men leave
the delivery room white and tottering and
I have seen them swoon like girls, overcome
by the cries and the blood. I remember one
father who held up just fine only to begin
screaming hysterically as his perfectly healthy
son pushed its way into the world. The infant's
eyes were open, it gave the impression of
looking around and then its eyes settled on
the father. Birth is wonderful, gentlemen,
but I have never found it beautiful-not by
any stretch of the imagination. I believe
it is too brutal to be beautiful. A woman's
womb is like an engine. With conception, that
engine is turned on. At first it barely idles
but as the creative cycle nears the climax
of birth, that engine revs up and up and up.
Its idling whisper becomes a steady running
hum, and then a rumble, and finally a bellowing,
frightening roar. Once that silent engine
has been turned on, every mother-to-be understands
that her life is in check. Either she will
bring the baby forth and the engine will shut
down again, or that engine will pound louder
and harder and faster until it explodes, killing
her in blood and pain.
This is a story of birth, gentlemen, on the
eve of that birth we have celebrated for almost
two thousand years.
I began practising medicine in 1929-a bad
year to begin anything. My grandfather was
able to loan me a small sum of money, so I
was luckier than many of my colleagues, but
I still had to survive over the next four
years mostly on my wits.
By 1935, things had improved a bit. I had
developed a bedrock of steady patients and
was getting quite a few outpatient referrals
from White Memorial. In April of that year
I saw a new patient, a young woman whom I
will call Sandra Stansfield-that name is close
enough to what her name really was. This was
a young woman, white, who stated her age to
be twenty-eight. After examining her, I guessed
her true age to be between three and five
years younger than that. She was blonde, slender,
and tall for that time-about five feet eight
inches. She was quite beautiful, but in an
austere way that was almost forbidding. Her
features were clear and regular, her eyes
intelligent and her mouth every bit as determined
as the stone mouth of Harriet White on the
statue in the pavilion across from Madison
Square Garden. The name she put on her form
was not Sandra Stansfield but Jane Smith.
My examination subsequently showed her to
be about two months gone in pregnancy. She
wore no wedding ring. After the preliminary
exam-but before the results of the pregnancy
test were in, my nurse, Ella Davidson, said:
"That girl yesterday? Jane Smith? If that
isn't an assumed name, I never heard one.'
I agreed. Still, I rather admired her. She
had not engaged in the usual shillyshallying,
toe-scuffing, blushing, tearful behaviour.
She had been straightforward and businesslike.
Even her alias had seemed more a matter of
business than of shame. There had been no
attempt to provide verisimilitude by creating
a 'Betty Rucklehouse' or whomping up a 'Ternina
DeVille'. You require a name for your form,
she seemed to be saying, because that is the
law. So here is a name; but rather than trusting
to the professional ethics of a man I don't
know, I'll trust in myself. If you don't mind,
Ella sniffed and passed a few remarks-'modern
girls' and 'bold as brass'-but she was a good
woman, and I don't think she said those things
except for the sake of form. She knew as well
as I did that, whatever my new patient might
be, she was no little trollop with hard eyes
and round heels. No; 'Jane Smith' was merely
an extremely serious, extremely determined
young woman-if either of those things can
be described by such a milquetoast adverb
as 'merely'. It was an unpleasant situation
(it used to be called 'getting in a scrape',
as you gentlemen may remember; nowadays it
seems that many young women use a scrape to
get out of the scrape), and she meant to go
through it with whatever grace and dignity
she could manage.
A week after her initial appointment, she
came in again. That was a peach of a day-one
of the first real days of spring. The air
was mild, the sky a soft, milky shade of blue,
and there was a smell on the breeze- a warm,
indefinable smell that seems to be nature's
signal that she is entering her own birth
cycle again. The sort of day when you wish
you were miles from any responsibility, sitting
opposite a lovely woman of your own-at Coney
Island, maybe, or on the Palisades across
the Hudson with a picnic hamper on a checkered
cloth and the lady in question wearing a great
white cartwheel hat and a sleeveless gown
as pretty as the day.
'Jane Smith's' dress had sleeves, but it was
still almost as pretty as the day; a smart
white linen with brown edging. She wore brown
pumps, white gloves, and a cloche hat that
was slightly out of fashion-it was the first
sign I saw that she was a far from rich woman.
'You're pregnant,' I said. 'I don't believe
you doubted it much, did you?'
If there are to be tears, I thought, they
will come now.
'No,' she said with perfect composure. There
was no more a sign of tears in her eyes than
there were rainclouds on the horizon that
day. 'I'm very regular as a rule.'
There was a pause between us.
'When may I expect to deliver?' she asked
then, with an almost soundless sigh. It was
the sound a man or woman might make before
bending over to pick up a heavy load.
'It will be a Christmas baby,' I said. '10
December is the date I'll give you, but it
could be two weeks on either side of that'
'All right.' She hesitated briefly, and then
plunged ahead. 'Will you attend me? Even though
I'm not married?'
'Yes,' I said. 'On one condition.'
She frowned, and in that moment her face was
more like the face of Harriet White, my father's
first wife, than ever. One would not think
that the frown of a woman perhaps only twenty-three
could be particularly formidable, but this
one was. She was ready to leave, and the fact
that she would have to go through this entire
embarrassing process again with another doctor
was not going to deter her.
'And what might that be?' she asked with perfect,
colourless courtesy.
Now it was I who felt an urge to drop my eyes
from her steady hazel ones, but I held her
gaze. 'I insist upon knowing your real name.
We can continue to do business on a cash basis
if that is how you prefer it, and I can continue
to have Mrs Davidson issue you receipts in
the name of Jane Smith. But if we are going
to travel through the next seven months or
so together, I would like to be able to address
you by the name to which you answer in all
the rest of your life.'
I finished this absurdly stiff little speech
and watched her think it through. I was somehow
quite sure she was going to stand up, thank
me for my time, and leave forever. I was going
to feel disappointed if that happened. I liked
her. Even more, I liked the straightforward
way she was handling a problem which would
have reduced ninety women out of a hundred
to inept and undignified liars, terrified
by the living clock within and so deeply ashamed
of their situation that to make any reasonable
plan for coping with it became impossible.
I suppose many young people today would find
such a state of mind ludicrous, ugly, even
hard to believe. People have become so eager
to demonstrate their broad-mindedness that
a pregnant woman who has no wedding ring is
apt to be treated with twice the solicitude
of one who does. You gentlemen will well remember
when rectitude and hypocrisy were combined
to make a situation that was viciously difficult
for a woman who had gotten herself 'in a scrape'.
In those days, a married pregnant woman was
a radiant woman, sure of her position and
proud of fulfilling what she considered to
be the function God put her on earth for.
An unmarried pregnant woman was a trollop
in the eyes of the world and apt to be a trollop
in her own eyes as well. They were, to use
Ella Davidson's word, 'easy', and in that
world and that time, easiness was not quickly
forgiven. Such women crept away to have their
babies in other towns or cities. Some took
pills or jumped from buildings. Others went
to butcher abortionists with dirty hands or
tried to do the job themselves; in my time
as a physician I have seen four women die
of blood-loss before my eyes as the result
of punctured wombs-in one case the puncturing
was done by the jagged neck of a Dr Pepper
bottle that had been tied to the handle of
a whisk-broom. It is hard to believe now that
such things happened, but they did, gentlemen.
They did. It was, quite simply, the worst
situation a healthy young woman could find
herself in.
'All right' she said at last. 'That's fair
enough. My name is Sandra Stansfield.' And
she held her hand out. Rather amazed, I took
it and shook it. I'm rather glad Ella
Davidson didn't see me do that. She would
have made no comment, but the coffee would
have been bitter for the next week.
She smiled-at my own expression of bemusement,
I imagine-and looked at me frankly.
'I hope we can be friends, Dr McCarron. I
need a friend just now. I'm quite frightened.'
'I can understand that, and I'll try to be
your friend if I can, Miss Stansfield. Is
there anything I can do for you now?'
She opened her handbag and took out a dime-store
pad and a pen. She opened the pad, poised
the pen, and looked up at me. For one horrified
instant I believed she was going to ask me
for the name and address of an abortionist.
Then she said: 'I'd like to know the best
things to eat. For the baby, I mean.'
I laughed out loud. She looked at me with
some amazement.
'Forgive me-it's just that you seem so businesslike.'
'I suppose,' she said. 'This baby is part
of my business now, isn't it, Dr McCarron?'
'Yes. Of course it is. And I have a folder
which I give to all my pregnant patients.
It deals with diet and weight and drinking
and smoking and lots of other things. Please
don't laugh when you look at it. You'll hurt
my feelings if you do, because I wrote it
myself.'
And so I had-although it was really more of
a pamphlet than a folder, and in time became
my book, A Practical Guide to Pregnancy and
Delivery. I was quite interested in obstetrics
and gynaecology in those days-still am -although
it was not a thing to specialize in back then
unless you had plenty of uptown connections.
Even if you did, it might take ten or fifteen
years to establish a strong practice. Having
hung out my shingle at a rather too-ripe age
as a result of the war, I didn't feel I had
the time to spare. I contented myself with
the knowledge that I would see a great many
happy expectant mothers and deliver a great
many babies in the course of my general practice.
And so I did; at last count I had delivered
well over two thousand babies -enough to fill
two hundred classrooms.
I kept up with the literature on having babies
more smartly than I did on that applying to
any other area of general practice. And because
my opinions were strong, enthusiastic ones,
I wrote my own pamphlet rather than just passing
along the stale chestnuts so often foisted
on young mothers then. I won't run through
the whole catalogue of these chestnuts-we'd
be here all night-but I'll mention a couple.
Expectant mothers were urged to stay off their
feet as much as possible, and on no account
were they to walk any sustained distance lest
a miscarriage or 'birth damage' result. Now
giving birth is an extremely strenuous piece
of work, and such advice is like telling a
football player to prepare for the big game
by sitting around as much as possible so he
won't tire himself out! Another sterling piece
of advice, given by a good many doctors, was
that moderately overweight mothers-to-be take
up smoking smoking! The rationale was perfectly
expressed by an advertising slogan of the
day: 'Have a Lucky instead of a sweet.' People
who have the idea that when we entered the
twentieth century we also entered an age of
medical light and reason have no idea of how
utterly crazy medicine could sometimes be.
Perhaps it's just as well; their hair would
turn white.
I gave Miss Stansfield my folder and she looked
through it with complete attention for perhaps
five minutes. I asked her permission to smoke
my pipe and she gave it absently, without
looking up. When she did look up at last,
there was a small smile on her lips. 'Are
you a radical, Dr McCarron?' she asked.
'Why do you say that? Because I advise that
the expectant mother should walk her round
of errands instead of riding in a smoky, jolting
subway car?'
'"Pre-natal vitamins," whatever they are swimming
recommended and breathing exercises! What
breathing exercises?'
'That comes later on, and no-I'm not a radical.
Far from it What I am is five minutes overdue
on my next patient.'
'Oh! I'm sorry.' She got to her feet quickly,
tucking the thick folder into her purse.
'No need.'
She shrugged into her light coat, looking
at me with those direct hazel eyes as she
did so.
'No,' she said. 'Not a radical at all. I suspect
you're actually quite comfortable? Is that
the word I want?'
'I hope it will serve,' I said. 'It's a word
I like. If you speak to Mrs Davidson, shell
give you an appointment schedule. I'll want
to see you again early next month.'
'Your Mrs Davidson doesn't approve of me.'
'Oh, I'm sure that's not true at all.' But
I've never been a particularly good liar,
and the warmth between us suddenly slipped
away. I did not accompany her to the door
of my consulting room. 'Miss Stansfield?'
She turned towards me, coolly enquiring. 'Do
you intend to keep the baby?'
She considered me briefly and then smiled-
a secret smile which I am convinced only pregnant
women know. 'Oh yes,' she said, and let herself
out. By the end of that day I had treated
identical twins for identical cases of poison
ivy, lanced a boil, removed a hook of metal
from a sheet-welder's eye, and had referred
one of my oldest patients to White Memorial
for what was surely cancer. I had forgotten
all about Sandra Stansfield by then. Ella
Davidson recalled her to my mind by saying:
'Perhaps she's not a chippie after all.'
I looked up from my last patient's folder.
I had been looking at it, feeling that useless
disgust most doctors feel when they know they
have been rendered completely helpless, and
thinking I ought to have a rubber stamp made
up for such files-only instead of saying ACCOUNT
RECEIVABLE or PAID IN FULL or PATIENT MOVED,
it would simply say DEATH-WARRANT. Perhaps
with a skull and crossbones above, like those
on bottles of poison. 'Pardon me?'
'Your Miss Jane Smith. She did a most peculiar
thing after her appointment this morning.'
The set of Mrs Davidson's head and mouth made
it clear that this was the sort of peculiar
thing of which she approved. 'And what was
that?'
'When I gave her her appointment card, she
asked me to tot up her expenses. All of her
expenses. Delivery and hospital stay included.'
That was a peculiar thing, all right. This
was 1935, remember, and Miss Stansfield gave
every impression of being a woman on her own.
Was she well off, even comfortably off? I
didn't think so. Her dress, shoes, and gloves
had all been smart, but she had worn no jewellery
-not even costume jewellery. And then there
was her hat, that decidedly out-of-date cloche.
'Did you do it?' I asked.
Mrs Davidson looked at me as though I might
have lost my senses. 'Did I? Of course I did!
And she paid the entire amount. In cash.'
The last, which apparently had surprised Mrs
Davidson the most (in an extremely pleasant
way, of course), surprised me not at all.
One thing which the Jane Smiths of the world
can't do is write cheques.
Took a bank-book out of her purse, opened
it, and counted the money right out onto my
desk,' Mrs Davidson was continuing. Then she
put her receipt in where the
cash had been, put the bank-book into her
purse again, and said good day. Not half bad,
when you think of the way we've had to chase
some of these so-called "respectable" people
to make them pay their bills!'
I felt chagrined for some reason. I was not
happy with the Stansfield woman for having
done such a thing, with Mrs Davidson for being
so pleased and complacent with the arrangement,
and with myself, for some reason I couldn't
define then and can't now. Something about
it made me feel small. 'But she couldn't very
well pay for a hospital stay now, could she?'
I asked-it was a ridiculously small thing
to seize on, but it was all I could find at
that moment on which to express my pique and
half-amused frustration. 'After all, none
of us know how long shell have to remain there.
Or are you reading the crystal now, Ella?'
'I told her that very thing, and she asked
what the average stay was following an uncomplicated
birth. I told her three days. Wasn't that
right, Dr McCarron?'
I had to admit it was.
'She said that she would pay for three days,
then, and if it was longer, she would pay
the difference, and if-'
'- if it was shorter, we could issue her a
refund,' I finished wearily. I thought: Damn
the woman, anyway!-and then I laughed. She
had guts. One couldn't deny that. All kinds
of guts.
Mrs Davidson allowed herself a smile and if
I am ever tempted, now that I am in my dotage,
to believe I know all there is to know about
one of my fellow creatures, I try to remember
that smile. Before that day I would have staked
my life that I would never see Mrs Davidson,
one of the most 'proper' women I have ever
known, smile fondly as she thought about a
girl who was pregnant out of wedlock.
'Guts? I don't know, Doctor. But she knows
her own mind, that one. She certainly does.'
A month passed, and Miss Stansfield showed
up promptly for her appointment, simply appearing
out of that wide, amazing flow of humanity
that was New York then and is New York now.
She wore a fresh-looking blue dress to which
she managed to communicate a feeling of originality,
of one-of-a-kind-ness, despite the fact that
it had been quite obviously picked from a
rack of dozens just like it. Her pumps did
not match it; they were the same brown ones
in which I had seen her last time.
I checked her over carefully and found her
normal in every way. I told her so and she
was pleased. 'I found the pre-natal vitamins,
Dr McCarron.'
'Did you? That's good.'
Her eyes sparkled impishly. "The druggist
advised me against them.'
'God save me from pestle-pounders,' I said,
and she giggled against the heel of her palm-it
was a childlike gesture, winning in its unselfconsciousness.
'I never met a druggist that wasn't a frustrated
doctor. And a Republican. Pre-natal vitamins
are new, so they're regarded with suspicion.
Did you take his advice?'
'No, I took yours. You're my doctor.'
Thank you.'
'Not at all.' She looked at me straightforwardly,
not giggling now. 'Dr McCarron, when will
I begin to show?'
'Not until August, I should guess. September,
if you choose garments which are uh, voluminous.'
Thank you.' She picked up her purse but did
not rise immediately to go. I thought that
she wanted to talk and didn't know where or
how to begin.
'You're a working woman, I take it?'
She nodded. 'Yes. I work.'
'Might I ask where? If you'd rather I didn't
-'
She laughed- a brittle, humourless laugh,
as different from that giggle as day is from
dark. 'In a department store. Where else does
an unmarried woman work in the city? I sell
perfume to fat ladies who rinse their hair
and then have it done up in tiny finger-waves.'
'How long will you continue?'
'Until my delicate condition is noticed. I
suppose then I'll be asked to leave, lest
I upset any of the fat ladies. The shock of
being waited on by a pregnant woman with no
wedding-band might cause their hair to straighten.'
Quite suddenly her eyes were bright with tears.
Her lips began to tremble, and I groped for
a handkerchief. But the tears didn't fall-not
so much as a single one. Her eyes brimmed
for a moment and then she blinked them back.
Her lips tightened and then smoothed out.
She simply decided she was not going to lose
control of her emotions and she did not. It
was a remarkable thing to watch.
'I'm sorry,' she said. 'You've been very kind
to me. I won't repay your kindness with what
would be a very common story.'
She rose to go, and I rose with her.
'I'm not a bad listener,' I said, 'and I have
some time. My next patient cancelled.'
'No,' she said. 'Thank you, but no.'
'All right,' I said. 'But there's something
else.'
'Yes?'
'It's not my policy to make my patients-any
of my patients-pay for services in advance
of those services being rendered. I hope if
you that is, if you feel you'd like to or
have to' I fumbled my way into silence.
I've been in New York four years, Dr McCarron,
and I'm thrifty by nature. After August-or
September-I'll have to live on what's in my
savings account until I can go back to work
again. It's not a great amount and sometimes,
during the nights, mostly, I become frightened.'
She looked at me steadily with those wonderful
hazel eyes.
'It seemed better to me-safer-to pay for the
baby first. Ahead of everything. Because that
is where the baby is in my thoughts, and because,
later on, the temptation to spend that money
might become very great'
'All right,' I said. 'But please remember
that I see it as having been paid before accounts.
If you need it, say so.'
'And bring out the dragon in Mrs Davidson
again?' The impish light was back in her eyes.
'I don't think so. And now, Doctor-'
'You intend to work as long as possible? Absolutely
as long as possible?'
'Yes. I have to. Why?'
'I think I'm going to frighten you a little
before you go,' I said.
Her eyes widened slightly. 'Don't do that,'
she said. 'I'm frightened enough already.'
'Which is exactly why I'm going to do it Sit
down again, Miss Stansfield.' And when she
only stood there, I added: 'Please.'
She sat. Reluctantly.
'You're in a unique and unenviable position,'
I told her, leaning back against the examination
table. 'You are dealing with the situation
with remarkable grace.'
She began to speak, and I held up my hand
to silence her.
'That's good. I salute you for it But I would
hate to see you hurt your baby in any way
out of concern for your own financial security.
I had a patient who, in spite of my strenuous
advice to the contrary, continued packing
herself into a girdle month after month, strapping
it tighter and tighter as her pregnancy progressed.
She was a vain, stupid, tiresome woman, and
I don't believe she really wanted the baby
anyway. I don't subscribe to many of these
theories of the subconscious which everyone
seems to discuss over the Man-Jong boards
these days, but if I did, I would say that
she-or some part of her-was trying to kill
the baby.'
'And did she?' Her face was very still.
'No, not at all. But the baby was born retarded.
It's very possible that the baby would have
been born retarded anyway, and I'm not saying
otherwise-we know next to nothing about what
causes such things. But she may have caused
it.'
'I take your point,' she said in a low voice.
'You don't want me to to pack myself in so
I can work another month or six weeks. I'll
admit the thought had crossed my mind. So
thank you for the fright.'
This time I walked her to the door. I would
have liked to ask her just how much-or how
little-she had left in that savings book,
and just how close to the edge she was. It
was a question she would not answer; I knew
that well enough. So I merely bade her goodbye
and made a joke about her vitamins. She left
I found myself thinking about her at odd moments
over the next month, and-Johanssen interrupted
McCarron's story at this point. They were
old friends, and I suppose that gave him the
right to ask the question that had surely
crossed all our minds.
'Did you love her, Emlyn? Is that what all
this is about, this stuff about her eyes and
smile and how you "thought of her at odd moments"?'
I thought that McCarron might be annoyed at
this interruption, but he was not. 'You have
a right to ask the question,' he said, and
paused, looking into the fire. It seemed that
he might almost have fallen into a doze. Then
a dry knot of wood exploded, sending sparks
up the chimney in a swirl, and McCarron looked
around, first at Johanssen and then at the
rest of us.
'No. I didn't love her. The things I've said
about her sound like the things a man who
is falling in love would notice-her eyes,
her dresses, her laugh.' He lit his pipe with
a special boltlike pipe-lighter that he carried,
drawing the flame until there was a bed of
coals there. Then he snapped the bolt shut,
dropped it into the pocket of his jacket,
and blew out a plume of smoke that shifted
slowly around his head in an aromatic membrane.
'I admired her. That was the long and short
of it. And my admiration grew with each of
her visits. I suppose some of you sense this
as a story of love crossed by circumstance.
Nothing could be further from the truth. Her
story came out a bit at a time over the next
half-year or so, and when you gentlemen hear
it, I think you'll agree that it was every
bit as common as she herself said it was.
She had been drawn to the city like a thousand
other girls; she had come from a small town
in Iowa or Nebraska. Or possibly it was Minnesota-I
don't really remember anymore.
She had done a lot of high school dramatics
and community theatre in her small town-good
reviews in the local weekly written by a drama
critic with an English degree from Cow and
Sileage Junior College-and she came to New
York to try a career in acting.
She was practical even about that-as practical
as an impractical ambition will allow one
to be, anyway. She came to New York, she told
me, because she didn't believe the unstated
thesis of the movie magazines-that any girl
who came to Hollywood could become a star,
that she might be sipping a soda in Schwab's
Drug Store one day and playing opposite Gable
or MacMurray the next. She came to New York,
she said, because she thought it might be
easier to get her foot in the door there and,
I think, because the legitimate theatre interested
her more than the talkies.
She got a job selling perfume in one of the
big department stores and enrolled in acting
classes. She was smart and terribly determined,
this girl-her will was pure steel, through
and through-but she was as human as anyone
else. She was lonely, too. Lonely in a way
that perhaps only single girls fresh from
small midwestern towns know. Homesickness
is not always a vague, nostalgic, almost beautiful
emotion, although that is somehow the way
we always seem to picture it in our mind.
It can be a terribly keen blade, not just
a sickness in metaphor but in fact as well.
It can change the way one looks at the world;
the faces one sees in the street look not
just indifferent but ugly perhaps even malignant.
Homesickness is a real sickness-the ache of
the uprooted plant. Miss Stansfield, admirable
as she may have been, determined as she may
have been, was not immune to it And the rest
follows so naturally it needs no telling.
There was a young man in her acting classes.
The two of them went out several times. She
did not love him, but she needed a friend.
By the time she discovered he was not that
and never would be, there had been two incidents.
Sexual incidents. She discovered she was pregnant.
She told the young man, who told her he would
stand by her and 'do the decent thing'. A
week later he was gone from his lodgings,
leaving no forwarding address. That was when
she came to me.
During her fourth month, I introduced Miss
Stansfield to the Breathing Method-what is
today called the Lamaze Method. In those days,
you understand, Monsieur Lamaze was yet to
be heard from.
'In those days'-the phrase has cropped up
again and again, I notice. I apologize for
it but am unable to help it-so much of what
I have told you and will tell you happened
as it did because it happened 'in those days'.
So 'in those days', over forty-five years
ago, a visit to the delivery rooms in any
large American hospital would have sounded
to you like a visit to a madhouse. Women weeping
wildly, women screaming that they wished they
were dead, women screaming that they could
not bear such agony, women screaming for Christ
to forgive them their sins, women screaming
out strings of curses and gutter-words their
husbands and fathers never would have believed
they knew. All of this was quite the accepted
thing, in spite of the fact that most of the
world's women give birth in almost complete
silence, aside from the grunting sounds of
strain that we would associate with any piece
of hard physical labour.
Doctors were responsible for some of this
hysteria, I'm sorry to say. The stories the
pregnant woman heard from friends and relatives
who had already been through the birthing
process also contributed to it. Believe me:
if you are told that some experience is going
to hurt, it will hurt. Most pain is in the
mind, and when a woman absorbs the idea that
the act of giving birth is excruciatingly
painful-when she gets this information from
her mother, her sisters, her married friends,
and her physician-that woman has been mentally
prepared to feel great agony.
Even after only six years' practice, I had
become used to seeing women who were trying
to cope with a twofold problem: not just the
fact that they were pregnant and must plan
for the new arrival, but also the fact-what
most of them saw as a fact, anyway-that they
had entered the valley of the shadow of death.
Many were actually trying to put their affairs
in coherent order so that if they should die,
their husbands would be able to carry on without
them.
This is neither the time nor place for a lesson
on obstetrics, but you should know that for
a long time before 'those days', the act of
giving birth was extremely dangerous in the
Western countries. A revolution in medical
procedure, beginning around 1900, had made
the process much safer, but an absurdly small
number of doctors bothered to tell their expectant
mothers that. God knows why. But in light
of this, is it any wonder that most delivery
rooms sounded like Ward Nine in Bellevue?
Here are these poor women, their time come
round at last, experiencing a process which
has, because of the almost Victorian decorum
of the times, been described to them only
in the vaguest of terms; here are these women
experiencing that engine of birth finally
running at full power. They were seized with
an awe and wonder which they immediately interpreted
as insupportable pain, and most of them felt
that they would very shortly die a dog's death.
In the course of my reading on the subject
of pregnancy, I discovered the principle of
the silent birth and the idea of the Breathing
Method. Screaming wastes energy which would
be better used to expel the baby, it causes
the women to hyperventilate, and hyperventilation
puts the body on an emergency basis-adrenals
running full blast, respiration and pulse-rate
up-that is really unnecessary. The Breathing
Method was supposed to help the mother focus
her attention on the job at hand and to cope
with pain by utilizing the body's own resources.
It was used widely at that time in India and
Africa; in America, the Shoshone, Kiowa, and
Micmac Indians all used it; the Eskimos have
always used it; but, as you may guess, most
Western doctors had little interest in it.
One of my colleagues-an intelligent man -returned
the typescript of my pregnancy pamphlet to
me in the fall of 1931 with a red line drawn
through the entire section on the Breathing
Method. In the margin he had scribbled that
if he wanted to know about 'nigger superstitions',
he would stop by a newsstand and buy an issue
of Weird Tales!
Well, I didn't cut the section from the pamphlet
as he had suggested, but I had mixed results
with the method-that was the best one could
say. There were women who used it with great
success. There were others who seemed to grasp
the idea perfectly in principle but who lost
their discipline completely as soon as their
contractions became deep and heavy. In most
of those cases I found that the entire idea
had been subverted and undermined by well-meaning
friends and relatives who had never heard
of such a thing and thus could not believe
it would actually work.
The method was based on the idea that, while
no two labours are ever the same in their
specifics, all are pretty much alike in general.
There are four stages: contractive labour,
mid-labour, birth, and the expulsion of the
afterbirth. Contractions are a complete hardening
of the abdominal and pelvic-area muscles,
and the expectant mother often finds them
beginning in the sixth month. Many women pregnant
for the first time expect something rather
nasty, like bowel cramps, but I'm told it's
much cleaner- a strongly physical sensation,
which may deepen into a pain like a charley
horse. A woman employing the Breathing Method
began to breathe in a series of short, measured
inhales and exhales when she felt a contraction
coming on. Each breath was expelled in a puff,
as if one were blowing a trumpet Dizzy Gillespie
fashion.
During mid-labour, when more painful contractions
begin coming every fifteen minutes or so,
the woman switched to long inhales followed
by long exhales-it's the way a marathon runner
breathes when he's starting his final kick.
The harder the contraction, the longer the
inhale-exhale. In my pamphlet, I called this
stage 'riding the waves'. The final stage
we need concern ourselves with here I called
'locomotive', and Lamaze instructors today
frequently call it the 'choo-choo' stage of
breathing. Final labour is accompanied by
pains which are most frequently described
as deep and glassy. They are accompanied by
an irresistible urge on the mother's part
to push to expel the baby. This is the point,
gentlemen, at which that wonderful, frightening
engine reaches its absolute crescendo. The
cervix is fully dilated. The baby has begun
its short journey down the birth canal, and
if you were to look directly between the mother's
legs, you would be apt to see the baby's fontanell
pulsing only inches from the open air. The
mother using the Breathing Method now begins
to take and let out short, sharp breaths between
her lips, not filling her lungs, not hyperventilating,
but almost panting in a perfectly controlled
fashion. It really is the sound children make
when they are imitating a steam-driven locomotive.
All of this has a salutary effect on the body-the
mother's oxygen is kept high without putting
her systems on an emergency basis, and she
herself remains aware and alert, able to ask
and answer questions, able to take instructions.
But of course the mental results of the Breathing
Method were even more important. The mother
felt she was actively participating in the
birth of her child-that she was in some part
guiding the process. She felt on top of the
experience and on top of the pain.
You can understand that the whole process
was utterly dependent on the patient's state
of mind. The Breathing Method was uniquely
vulnerable, uniquely delicate, and if I had
a good many failures, I'd explain them this
way-what a patient can be convinced of by
her doctor she may be unconvinced of by relatives
who raise their hands in horror when told
of such a heathenish practice.
From this aspect, at least, Miss Stansfield
was the ideal patient She had neither friends
nor relatives to talk her out of her belief
in the Breathing Method (although, in all
fairness, I must add that I doubt anyone ever
talked her out of anything once she had made
up her mind on the subject) once she came
to believe in it. And she did come to believe
in it 'It's a little like self-hypnosis, isn't
it?' she asked me the first time we really
discussed it I agreed, delighted. 'Exactly!
But you mustn't let that make you think it's
a trick, or that it will let you down when
the going gets tough.'
'I don't think that at all. I'm very grateful
to you. I'll practise assiduously, Dr McCarron.'
She was the sort of woman the Breathing Method
was invented for, and when she told me she
would practise, she spoke nothing but the
truth. I have never seen anyone embrace an
idea with such enthusiasm but, of course,
the Breathing Method was uniquely suited to
her temperament There are docile men and women
in this world by the millions, and some of
them are damn fine people. But there are others
whose hands ache to hold the throttles of
their own lives, and Miss Stansfield was one
of those.
When I say she embraced the Breathing Method
totally, I mean it and I think the story of
her final day at the department store where
she sold perfumes and cosmetics proves the
point. The end of her gainful employment finally
came late in August. Miss Stansfield was a
slim young woman in fine physical condition,
and this was, of course, her first child.
Any doctor will tell you that such a woman
is apt not to 'show' for five, perhaps even
six months and then, one day and all at once,
everything will show.
She came in for her monthly checkup on the
first of September, laughed ruefully, and
told me she had discovered the Breathing Method
had another use.
'What's that?' I asked her.
'It's even better than counting to ten when
you're mad as hell at someone,' she said.
Those hazel eyes were dancing. 'Although people
look at you as if you might be a lunatic when
you start puffing and blowing.'
She told me the tale readily enough. She had
gone to work as usual on the previous Monday,
and all I can think is that the curiously
abrupt transition from a slim young woman
to an obviously pregnant young woman-and the
transition really can be almost as sudden
as day to dark in the tropics -had happened
to her over the weekend. Or maybe her supervisor
finally decided that her suspicions were no
longer just suspicions.
'I'll want to see you in the office on your
break,' this woman, a Mrs Kelly, said coldly.
She had previously been quite friendly to
Miss Stansfield. She had shown her pictures
of her two children, both in high school,
and they had exchanged recipes at one point.
Mrs Kelly was always asking her if she had
met 'a nice boy' yet. That kindliness and
friendliness was gone now. And when she stepped
into Mrs Kelly's office on her break, Miss
Stansfield told me, she knew what to expect.
'You're in trouble,' this previously kind
woman said curtly.
'Yes,' Miss Stansfield said. 'It's called
that by some people.'
Mrs Kelly's cheeks had gone the colour of
old brick. 'Don't you be smart with me, young
woman,' she said. 'From the looks of your
belly, you've been too smart by half already.'
I could see the two of them in my mind's eye
as she told me the story-Miss Stansfield,
her direct hazel eyes fixed on Mrs Kelly,
perfectly composed, refusing to drop her eyes,
or weep, or exhibit shame in any other way.
I believe she had a much more practical conception
of the trouble she was in than her supervisor
did, with her two almost grown children and
her respectable husband, who owned his own
barbershop and voted Republican.
'I must say you show remarkably little shame
at the way you've deceived me!' Mrs Kelly
burst out bitterly.
'I have never deceived you. No mention of
my pregnancy has been made until today.' She
looked at Mrs Kelly almost curiously. 'How
can you say I have deceived you?'
'I took you home!' Mrs Kelly cried. 'I had
you to dinner with my sons.' She looked at
Miss Stansfield with utter loathing.
This is when Miss Stansfield began to grow
angry. Angrier, she told me, than she had
ever been in her life. She had not been unaware
of the sort of reaction she could expect when
the secret came out, but as any one of you
gentlemen will attest, the difference between
academic theory and practical application
can sometimes be shockingly huge.
Clutching her hands firmly together in her
lap, Miss Stansfield said: 'If you are suggesting
I made or ever would make any attempt to seduce
your sons, that's the dirtiest, filthiest
thing I've ever heard in my life.'
Mrs Kelly's head rocked back as if she had
been slapped. That bricky colour drained from
her cheeks, leaving only two small spots of
hectic colour. The two women looked grimly
at each other across a desk littered with
perfume samples in a room that smelled vaguely
of flowers. It was a moment, Miss Stansfield
said, that seemed much longer than it actually
could have been.
Then Mrs Kelly yanked open one of her drawers
and brought out a buff-coloured cheque.
A bright pink severance slip was attached
to it. Showing her teeth, actually seeming
to bite off each word, she said, 'With hundreds
of decent girls looking for work in this city,
I hardly think we need a strumpet such as
yourself in our employ, dear.'
She told me it was that final, contemptuous
'dear' that brought all her anger to a sudden
head. A moment later Mrs Kelly's jaw dropped
and her eyes widened as Miss Stansfield, her
hands locked together as tightly as links
in a steel chain, so tightly she left bruises
on herself (they were fading but still perfectly
visible when I saw her on 1 September), began
to 'locomotive' between her clenched teeth.
It wasn't a funny story, perhaps, but I burst
out laughing at the image and Miss Stansfield
joined me. Mrs Davidson looked in-to make
sure we hadn't gotten into the nitrous oxide,
perhaps-and then left again.
'It was all I could think to do,' Miss Stansfield
said, still laughing and wiping her streaming
eyes with her handkerchief. 'Because at that
moment, I saw myself reaching out and simply
sweeping those sample bottles of perfume-every
one of them-off her desk and onto the floor,
which was uncarpeted concrete. I didn't just
think it, I saw it! I saw them crashing to
the floor and filling the room with such a
God-awful mixed stench that the fumigators
would have to come.
'I was going to do it; nothing was going to
stop me doing it. Then I began to Breathe,
and everything was all right. I was able to
take the cheque, and the pink slip, and get
up, and get out. I wasn't able to thank her,
of course- I was still being a locomotive"
We laughed again, and then she sobered.
'It's all passed off now, and I am even able
to feel a little sorry for her-or does that
sound like a terribly stiff-necked thing to
say?'
'Not at all. I think it's an admirable way
to be able to feel.'
'May I show you something I bought with my
severance pay, Dr McCarron?'
'Yes, if you like.'
She opened her purse and took out a small
flat box. 'I bought it at a pawnshop,' she
said.
'For two dollars. And it's the only time during
this whole nightmare that I've felt ashamed
and dirty. Isn't that strange?'
She opened the box and laid it on my desk
so I could look inside. I wasn't surprised
at what I saw. It was a plain gold wedding
ring.
'I'll do what's necessary,' she said. 'I am
staying in what Mrs Kelly would undoubtedly
call "a respectable boarding house". My landlady
has been kind and friendly but Mrs Kelly was
kind and friendly, too. I think she may ask
me to leave at any time now, and I suspect
that if I say anything about the rent-balance
due me, or the damage deposit I paid when
I moved in, she'll laugh in my face.'
'My dear young woman, that would be quite
illegal. There are courts and lawyers to help
you answer such -'
The courts are men's clubs,' she said steadily,
'and not apt to go out of their way to befriend
a woman in my position. Perhaps I could get
my money back, perhaps not.
Either way, the expense and the trouble and
the the unpleasantness hardly seem worth the
forty-seven dollars or so. I had no business
mentioning it to you in the first place. It
hasn't happened yet, and maybe it won't. But
in any case, I intend to be practical from
now on.'
She raised her head, and her eyes flashed
at mine.
'I've got my eye on a place down in the Village-just
in case. It's on the third floor, but it's
clean, and it's five dollars a month cheaper
than where I'm staying now.' She picked the
ring out of the box. 'I wore this when the
landlady showed me the room.'
She put it on the third finger of her left
hand with a small moue of disgust of which
I believe she was unaware. There. Now I'm
Mrs Stansfield. My husband was a truck-driver
who was killed on the Pittsburgh-New York
run. Very sad. But I am no longer a little
roundheels strumpet, and my child is no longer
a bastard.'
She looked up at me, and the tears were in
her eyes again. As I watched, one of them
overspilled and rolled down her cheek.
'Please,' I said, distressed, and reached
across the desk to take her hand. It was very,
very cold. 'Don't, my dear.'
She turned her hand-it was the left-over in
my hand and looked at the ring. She smiled,
and that smile was as bitter as gall and vinegar,
gentlemen. Another tear fell-just that one.
'When I hear cynics say that the days of magic
and miracles are all behind us, Dr McCarron,
I'll know they're deluded, won't I? When you
can buy a ring in a pawnshop for a dollar
and a half and that ring will instantly erase
both bastardy and licentiousness, what else
would you call that but magic? Cheap magic.'
'Miss Stansfield Sandra, if I may if you need
help, if there's anything I can do -'
She drew her hand away from me-if I had taken
her right hand instead of her left, perhaps
she would not have done. I did not love her,
I've told you, but in that moment I could
have loved her; I was on the verge of falling
in love with her. Perhaps, if I'd taken her
right hand instead of the one with that lying
ring on it, and if she had allowed me to hold
her hand only a little longer, until my own
warmed it, perhaps then I should have.
'You're a good, kind man, and you've done
a great deal for me and my baby and your Breathing
Method is a much better kind of magic than
this awful ring. After all, it kept me from
being jailed on charges of wilful destruction,
didn't it?'
She left soon after that, and I went to the
window to watch her move off down the street
towards Madison Avenue. God, I admired her
just then: She looked so slight, so young,
and so obviously pregnant-but there was still
nothing timid or tentative about her. She
did not scutter up the street; she walked
as if she had every right to her place on
the sidewalk.
She left my view and I turned back to my desk.
As I did so, the framed photograph which hung
on the wall next to my diploma caught my eye,
and a terrible shudder worked through me.
My skin-all of it, even the skin on my forehead
and the backs of my hands-crawled up into
cold knots of gooseflesh. The most suffocating
fear of my entire life fell on me like a horrible
shroud, and I found myself gasping for breath.
It was a precognitive interlude, gentlemen.
I do not take part in arguments about whether
or not such things can occur; I know they
can, because it has happened to me. Just that
once, on that hot early September afternoon.
I pray to God I never have another.
The photograph had been taken by my mother
on the day I finished medical school. It showed
me standing in front of White Memorial, hands
behind my back, grinning like a kid who's
just gotten a full-day pass to the rides at
Palisades Park. To my left the statue of Harriet
White can be seen, and although the photograph
cuts her off at about mid-shin, the pedestal
and that queerly heartless inscription-There
is no comfort without pain; thus we define
salvation through suffering-could be clearly
seen. It was at the foot of the statue of
my grandfather's first wife, directly below
that inscription, that Sandra Stansfield died
not quite four months later in a senseless
accident that occurred just as she arrived
at the hospital to deliver her child.
She exhibited some anxiety that fall that
I would not be there to attend her during
her labour-that I would be away for the Christmas
holidays or not on call. She was partly afraid
that she would be delivered by some doctor
who would ignore her wish to use the Breathing
Method and who would instead give her gas
or a spinal block. I assured her as best I
could. I had no reason to leave the city,
no family to visit over the holidays. My mother
had died two years before, and there was no
one else except a maiden aunt in California
and the train didn't agree with me, I told
Miss Stansfield. 'Are you ever lonely?' she
asked.
'Sometimes. Usually I keep too busy. Now,
take this.' I jotted my home telephone number
on a card and gave it to her. 'If you get
the answering service when your labour begins,
call me here.'
'Oh, no, I couldn't-'
'Do you want to use the Breathing Method,
or do you want to get some sawbones who'll
think you're mad and give you a capful of
ether as soon as you start to "locomotive"?'
She smiled a little. 'All right. I'm convinced.'
But as the autumn progressed and the butchers
on 3rd Avenue began advertising the per-pound
price of their 'young and succulent Toms',
it became clear that her mind was still not
at rest She had indeed been asked to leave
the place where she had been living when I
first met her, and had moved to the Village.
But that, at least, had turned out quite well
for her. She had even found work of a sort.
A blind woman with a fairly comfortable income
had hired her to come in twice a week, do
some light housework, and then to read to
her from the works of Jean Stratton-Porter
and Pearl Buck. She had taken on that blooming,
rosy look that most healthy women come to
have during the final trimester of their pregnancies.
But there was a shadow on her face. I would
speak to her and she would be slow to answer
and once, when she didn't answer at all, I
looked up from the notes I was making and
saw her looking at the framed photograph next
to my diploma with a strange, dreamy expression
in her eyes. I felt a recurrence of that chill
and her response, which had nothing to do
with my question, hardly made me feel easier.
'I have a feeling, Dr McCarron, sometimes
quite a strong feeling, that I am doomed.'
Silly, melodramatic word! And yet, gentlemen,
the response that rose to my own lips was
this: Yes; I feel that, too. I bit it off,
of course; a doctor who would say such a thing
should immediately put his instruments and
medical books up for sale and investigate
his future in the plumbing or carpentry business.
I told her that she was not the first pregnant
woman to have such feelings, and would not
be the last. I told her that the feeling was
indeed so common that doctors knew it by the
tongue-in-cheek name of The Valley of the
Shadow Syndrome. I've already mentioned it
tonight, I believe.
Miss Stansfield nodded with perfect seriousness,
and I remember how young she looked that day,
and how large her belly seemed. 'I know about
that,' she said. 'I've felt it. But it's quite
separate from this other feeling. This other
feeling is like like something looming up.
I can't describe it any better than that.
It's silly, but I can't shake it.'
'You must try,' I said. 'It isn't good for
the -'
But she had drifted away from me. She was
looking at the photograph again. 'Who is that?'
'Emlyn McCarron,' I said, trying to make a
joke. It sounded extraordinarily feeble. 'Back
before the Civil War, when he was quite young.'
'No, I recognized you, of course,' she said.
"The woman. Who is the woman?'
'Her name is Harriet White,' I said, and thought:
And hers will be the first face you see when
you arrive to deliver your child. The chill
came back-that dreadful drifting formless
chill. Her stone face.
'And what does it say there at the base of
the statue?' she asked, her eyes still dreamy,
almost trancelike.
'I don't know,' I lied. 'My conversational
Latin is not that good.'
That night I had the worst dream of my entire
life -I woke up from it in utter terror, and
if I had been married, I suppose I would have
frightened my poor wife to death.
In the dream I opened the door to my consulting
room and found Sandra Stansfield in there.
She was wearing the brown pumps, the smart
white linen dress with the brown edging, and
the slightly out-of-date cloche hat. But the
hat was between her breasts, because she was
carrying her head in her arms. The white linen
was stained and streaked with gore. Blood
jetted from her neck and splattered the ceiling.
And then her eyes fluttered open-those wonderful
hazel eyes-and they fixed on mine.
'Doomed,' the speaking head told me. 'Doomed.
I'm doomed. There's no salvation without suffering.
It's cheap magic, but it's all we have.'
That's when I woke up screaming: Her due date
of 10 December came and went. I examined her
on 17 December and suggested that, while the
baby would almost certainly be born in 1935,
I no longer expected the child to put in his
or her appearance until after Christmas. Miss
Stansfield accepted this with good grace.
She seemed to have thrown off the shadow that
had hung over her that fall. Mrs Gibbs, the
blind woman who had hired her to read aloud
and do light housework, was impressed with
her-impressed enough to tell her friends about
the brave young widow who, in spite of her
recent bereavement and delicate condition,
was facing her own future with such determined
good cheer. Several of the blind woman's friends
had expressed an interest in employing her
following the birth of her child.
'I'll take them up on it, too,' she told me.
'For the baby. But only until I'm on my feet
again, and able to find something steady.
Sometimes I think the worst part of this -of
everything that's happened-is that it's changed
the way I look at people. Sometimes I think
to myself, "How can you sleep at night, knowing
that you've deceived that dear old thing?"
and then I think, "If she knew, she'd show
you the door, just like all the others."
Either way, it's a lie, and I feel the weight
of it on my heart sometimes.'
Before she left that day, she took a small,
gaily wrapped package from her purse and slid
it shyly across the desk to me. 'Merry Christmas,
Dr McCarron.'
'You shouldn't have,' I said, sliding open
a drawer and taking out a package of my own.
'But since I did, too -'
She looked at me for a moment, surprised and
then we laughed together. She had gotten me
a silver tie-clasp with the medical symbol
on it. I had gotten her an album in which
to keep photographs of her baby. I still have
the tie-clasp. What happened to the album,
I cannot say.
I saw her to the door, and as we reached it,
she turned to me, put her hands on my shoulders,
stood on tiptoe, and kissed me on the mouth.
Her lips were cool and firm. It was not a
passionate kiss, gentlemen, but neither was
it the sort of kiss you might expect from
a sister or an aunt.
'Thank you again, Dr McCarron,' she said a
little breathlessly. The colour was high in
her cheeks and her hazel eyes glowed lustrously.
'Thank you for so much.'
I laughed-a little uneasily. 'You speak as
if we'll never meet again, Sandra.' It was,
I believe, the second and last time I ever
used her Christian name.
'Oh, we'll meet again,' she said. 'I don't
doubt it a bit.'
And she was right-although neither of us could
have foreseen the dreadful cricumstances of
that last meeting.
Sandra Stansfield's labour began on Christmas
Eve, at just past six p. m. By that time,
the snow which had fallen all that day had
changed to sleet. And by the time Miss Stansfield
entered mid-labour, not quite two hours later,
the city streets were a dangerous glaze of
ice.
Mrs Gibbs, the blind woman, had a large and
spacious first-floor apartment, and at 6:30
p. m. Miss Stansfield worked her way carefully
downstairs, knocked at her door, was admitted,
and asked if she might use the telephone to
call a cab.
'Is it the baby, dear?' Mrs Gibbs asked, fluttering
already.
'Yes. The labour's only begun, but I can't
chance the weather. It will take a cab a long
time.'
She made that call and then called me. At
that time, 6:40, the pains were coming at
intervals of about twenty-five minutes. She
repeated to me that she had begun everything
early because of the foul weather. 'I'd rather
not have my child in the back of a Yellow,'
she said. She sounded extraordinarily calm.
The cab was late and Miss Stansfield's labour
was progressing more rapidly than I would
have predicted-but as I have said, no two
labours are alike in their specifics. The
driver, seeing that his fare was about to
have a baby, helped her down the slick steps,
constantly adjuring her to 'be careful, lady'.
Miss Stansfield only nodded, preoccupied with
her deep inhale-exhales as a fresh contraction
seized her. Sleet ticked off streetlights
and the roofs of cars; it melted in large,
magnifying drops on the taxi's yellow dome-light.
Miss Gibbs told me later that the young cab
driver was more nervous than her 'poor, dear
Sandra', and that was probably a contributing
cause to the accident.
Another was almost certainly the Breathing
Method itself.
The driver threaded his hack through the slippery
streets, working his way slowly past the fender-benders
and inching through the clogged intersections,
slowly closing on the hospital. He was not
seriously injured in the accident, and I talked
to him in the hospital.
He said the sound of the steady deep breathing
coming from the back seat made him nervous;
he kept looking in the rear view mirror to
see if she was 'dine or sumpin'. He said he
would have felt less nervous if she had let
out a few healthy bellows, the way a woman
in labour was supposed to do. He asked her
once or twice if she was feeling all right
and she only nodded, continuing to 'ride the
waves' in deep inhales and exhales.
Two or three blocks from the hospital, she
must have felt the onset of labour's final
stage.
An hour had passed since she had entered the
cab-the traffic was that snarled-but this
was still an extraordinarily fast labour for
a woman having her first baby. The driver
noticed the change in the way she was breathing.
'She started pantin' like a dog on a hot day,
Doc,' he told me. She had begun to 'locomotive'.
At almost the same time the cabbie saw a hole
open up in the crawling cross-traffic and
shot through it The way to White Memorial
was now open. It was less than three blocks
ahead. 'I could see the statue of that broad,'
he said. Eager to be rid of his panting, pregnant
passenger, he stepped down on the gas again
and the cab leaped forward, wheels spinning
over the ice with little or no traction.
I had walked to the hospital, and my arrival
coincided with the cab's arrival only because
I had underestimated just how bad driving
conditions had become. I believed I would
find her upstairs, a legally admitted patient
with all her papers signed, her prep completed,
working her way steadily through her mid-labour.
I was mounting the steps when I saw the sudden
sharp convergence of two sets of headlights
reflected from the patch of ice where the
janitors hadn't yet spread cinders. I turned
just in time to see it happen.
An ambulance was nosing its way out of the
Emergency Wing rampway as Miss Stansfield's
cab came across the Square and towards the
hospital. The cab was simply going too fast
to stop. The cabbie panicked and stamped down
on the brake-pedal rather than pumping it.
The cab slid, then began to turn broadside.
The pulsing dome-light of the ambulance threw
moving stripes and blotches of blood-coloured
light over the scene, and, freakishly, one
of these illuminated the face of Sandra Stansfield.
For that one moment it was the face in my
dream, the same bloody, open-eyed face that
I had seen on her severed head.
I cried out her name, took two steps down,
slipped, and fell sprawling. I cracked my
elbow a paralyzing blow but somehow managed
to hold on to my black bag. I saw the rest
of what happened from where I lay, head ringing,
elbow smarting. The ambulance braked, and
it also began to fishtail. Its rear end struck
the base of the statue. The loading doors
flew open. A stretcher, mercifully empty,
shot out like a tongue and then crashed upside
down in the street with its wheels spinning.
A young woman on the sidewalk screamed as
the two vehicles approached each other and
tried to run. Her feet went out from under
her after two strides and she fell on her
stomach. Her purse flew out of her hand and
shot down the icy sidewalk like a weight in
a pinball bowling game. The cab swung all
the way around, now travelling backwards,
and I could see the cabbie clearly. He was
spinning his wheel madly, like a kid in a
Dodgem Car. The ambulance rebounded from Mrs
White's statue at an angle and smashed broadside
into the cab. The taxi spun around once in
a tight circle and was slammed against the
base of the statue with fearful force. Its
yellow light, the letters ON RADIO CALL still
flashing, exploded like a bomb. The left side
of the cab crumpled like tissue-paper. A moment
later I saw that it was not just the left
side; the cab had struck an angle of the pedestal
hard enough to tear it in two. Glass sprayed
onto the slick ice like diamonds. And my patient
was thrown through the rear right-side window
of the dismembered cab like a rag-doll. I
was on my feet again without even knowing
it. I raced down the icy steps, slipped again,
caught at the railing, and kept on. I was
only aware of Miss Stansfield lying in the
uncertain shadow cast by that hideous statue
of Harriet White, some twenty feet from where
the ambulance had come to rest on its side,
flasher still strobing the night with red.
There was something terribly wrong with that
figure, but I honestly don't believe I knew
what it was until my foot struck something
with a heavy enough thud to almost send me
sprawling again. The thing I'd kicked skittered
away-like the young woman's purse, it slid
rather than rolled. It skittered away and
it was only the fall of hair-bloodstreaked
but still recognizably blonde, speckled with
bits of glass-that made me realize what it
was. She had been decapitated in the accident.
What I had kicked into the frozen gutter was
her head.
Moving in total numb shock, now I reached
her body and turned it over. I think I tried
to scream as soon as I had done it, as soon
as I saw. If I did, no sound came out; I could
not make a sound. The woman was still breathing,
you see, gentlemen. Her chest was heaving
up and down in quick, light, shallow breaths.
Ice pattered down on her open coat and her
blood-drenched dress. And I could hear a high,
thin whistling noise. It waxed and waned like
a teakettle which can't quite reach the boil.
It was air being pulled into her severed windpipe
and then exhaled again; the little screams
of air through the crude reed of the vocal
chords which no longer had a mouth to shape
their sounds. I wanted to run but I had no
strength; I fell on my knees beside her on
the ice, one hand cupped to my mouth. A moment
later I was aware of fresh blood seeping through
the lower part of her dress-and of movement
there. I became suddenly, frenziedly convinced
that there was still a chance to save the
baby.
'Cheap magic!' I roared into the sleet, and
I believe that as I yanked her dress up to
her waist I began laughing. I believe I was
mad. Her body was warm. I remember that. I
remember the way it heaved with her breathing.
One of the ambulance attendants came up, weaving
like a drunk, one hand clapped to the side
of his head. Blood trickled through his fingers.
'Cheap magic!' I screamed again, still laughing,
still groping. My hands had found her fully
dilated.
The attendant stared down at Sandra Stansfield's
headless body with wide eyes. I don't know
if he realized the corpse was still somehow
breathing or not Perhaps he thought it was
merely a thing of the nerves- a kind of final
reflex action. If he did think such a thing,
he could not have been driving an ambulance
long. Chickens may walk around for a while
with their heads cut off, but people only
twitch once or twice if that 'Stop staring
at her and get me a blanket,' I snapped at
him.
He wandered away, but not back towards the
ambulance. He was pointed more or less towards
Times Square. He simply walked off into the
sleety night. I have no idea what became of
him. I turned back to the dead woman who was
somehow not dead, hesitated a moment, and
then stripped off my overcoat. Then I lifted
her hips so I could get it under her. Still
I heard that whistle of breath as her headless
body did 'locomotive' breathing. I sometimes
hear it still, gentlemen. In my dreams.
Please understand that all of this had happened
in an extremely short time-it seemed longer
to me, but only because my perceptions had
been heightened to a feverish pitch. People
were only beginning to run out of the hospital
to see what had happened, and behind me a
woman shrieked as she saw the severed head
lying by the edge of the street. I yanked
open my black bag, thanking God I hadn't lost
it in my fall, and pulled out a short scalpel.
I opened it, cut through her underwear, and
pulled it off. Now the ambulance driver approached-he
came to within fifteen feet of us and then
stopped dead. I glanced over at him, still
wanting that blanket. I wasn't going to get
it from him, I saw; he was staring down at
the breathing body, his eyes widening until
it seemed they must slip from their orbits
and simply dangle from their optic nerves
like grotesque seeing yo-yos. Then he dropped
to his knees and raised his clasped hands.
He meant to pray, I am quite sure of that.
The attendant might not have known he was
seeing an impossibility, but this fellow did.
The next moment he had fainted dead away.
I had packed forceps in my bag that night;
I don't know why. I hadn't used such things
in three years, not since I had seen a doctor
I will not name punch through a newborn's
temple and into the child's brain with one
of those infernal gadgets. The child died
instantly. The corpse was 'lost' and what
went on the death certificate was stillborn.
But, for whatever reason, I had them.
Miss Stansfield's body tightened down, her
belly clenching, turning from flesh to stone.
And the baby crowned. I saw the crown for
just a moment, bloody and membranous and pulsing.
Pulsing. It was alive, at least then. Definitely
alive.
Stone became flesh again. The crown slipped
back out of sight. And a voice behind me said:
'What can I do, Doctor?'
It was a middle-aged nurse, the sort of woman
who is so often the backbone of our profession.
Her face was as pale as milk, and while there
was terror and a kind of superstitious awe
on her face as she looked down at that weirdly
breathing body, there was none of that dazed
shock which would have made her difficult
and dangerous to work with.
'You can get me a blanket, stat,' I said curtly.
'We've still got a chance, I think.' Behind
her I saw perhaps two dozen people from the
hospital standing on the steps, not wanting
to come any closer. How much or how little
did they see? I have no way of knowing for
sure. All I know is that I was avoided for
days afterwards (and forever by some of them),
and no one, including this nurse, ever spoke
to me of it. She now turned and started back
towards the hospital.
'Nurse!' I called. 'No time for that. Get
one from the ambulance. This baby is coming
now.'
She changed course, slipping and sliding through
the slush in her white crepe-soled shoes.
I turned back to Miss Stansfield.
Rather than slowing down, the locomotive breathing
had actually begun to speed up and then her
body turned hard again, locked and straining.
The baby crowned again. I waited for it to
slip back but it did not; it simply kept coming.
There was no need for the forceps after all.
The baby all but flew into my hands. I saw
the sleet ticking off its naked, bloody body-for
it was a boy, his sex unmistakable. I saw
steam rising from it as the black, icy night
snatched away the last of its mother's heat.
Its blood-grimed fists waved feebly; it uttered
a thin, wailing cry.
'Nurse!' I bawled, 'move your ass, you bitch!'
It was perhaps inexcusable language, but for
a moment I felt I was back in France, that
in a few moments the shells would begin to
whistle overhead with a sound like that remorselessly
ticking sleet; the machine-guns would begin
their hellish stutter; the Germans would begin
to materialize out of the murk, running and
slipping and cursing and dying in the mud
and smoke. Cheap magic, I thought, seeing
the bodies twist and turn and fall. But you're
right, Sandra, it's all we have. It was the
closest I have ever come to losing my mind,
gentlemen.
'NURSE, FOR GOD'S SAKE!'
The baby wailed again-such a tiny, lost sound!-and
then it wailed no more. The steam rising from
its skin had thinned to ribbons. I put my
mouth against its face, smelling blood and
the bland, damp aroma of placenta. I breathed
into its mouth and heard the jerky sussurrus
of its breathing resume. Then the nurse was
there, the blanket in her arms.
I held out my hand for it.
She started to give it to me, and then held
it back. 'Doctor, what what if it's a monster?
Some kind of monster?'
'Give me that blanket,' I said. 'Give it to
me now, Sarge, before I kick your fucking
asshole right up your fucking shoulderblades.'
'Yes, doctor,' she said with perfect calmness
(we must bless the women, gentlemen, who so
often understand simply by not trying to),
and gave me the blanket I wrapped the child
and gave it to her.
'If you drop him, Sarge, you'll be eating
those stripes.'
'Yes, doctor.'
'It's cheap fucking magic, Sarge, but it's
all God left us with.'
'Yes, doctor.'
I watched her half-walk, half-run back to
the hospital with the child and watched the
crowd on the steps part for her. Then I rose
to my feet and backed away from the body.
Its breathing, like the baby's, hitched and
caught stopped hitched again stopped
I began to back away from it. My foot struck
something. I turned. It was her head. And
obeying some directive from outside of me,
I dropped to one knee and turned the head
over. The eyes were open-those direct hazel
eyes that had always been full of such life
and such determination. They were full of
determination still. Gentlemen, she was seeing
me.
Her teeth were clenched, her lips slightly
parted. I heard the breath slipping rapidly
back and forth between those lips and through
those teeth as she "locomotived". Her eyes
moved; they rolled slightly to the left in
their sockets so as to see me better. Her
lips parted. They mouthed four words: Thank
you, Doctor McCarron. And I heard them, gentlemen,
but not from her mouth. They came from twenty
feet away. From her vocal cords. And because
her tongue and lips and teeth, all of which
we use to shape our words, were here, they
came out only in unformed modulations of sound.
But there were seven of them, seven distinct
sounds, just as there are seven syllables
in that phrase, Thank you, Doctor McCarron.
'You're welcome, Miss Stansfield,' I said.
'It's a boy.' Her lips moved again, and from
behind me, thin, ghostly, came the sound hoyyyyyy-Her
eyes lost their focus and their determination.
They seemed now to look at something beyond
me, perhaps in that black, sleety sky. Then
they closed. She began to locomotive again
and then she simply stopped. Whatever had
happened was now over. The nurse had seen
some of it, the ambulance driver had perhaps
seen some of it before he fainted.
But it was over now, over for sure. There
was only the remains of an ugly accident out
here and a new baby in there.
I looked up at the statue of Harriet White
and there she still stood, looking stonily
away towards the Garden across the way, as
if nothing of any particular note had happened,
as if such determination in a world as hard
and as senseless as this one meant nothing
or worse still, that it was perhaps the only
thing which meant anything, the only thing
that made any difference at all.
As I recall, I knelt there in the slush before
her severed head and began to weep. As I recall,
I was still weeping when an intern and two
nurses helped me to my feet and inside.
McCarron's pipe had gone out.
He relit it with his bolt-lighter while we
sat in perfect, breathless silence. Outside,
the wind howled and moaned. He snapped his
lighter closed and looked up. He seemed mildly
surprised to find us still there.
'That's all,' he said.' That's the end! What
are you waiting for? Chariots of fire?' He
snorted, then seemed to debate for a moment
'I paid her burial expenses out of my own
pocket She had no one else, you see.' He smiled
a little. 'Well there was Ella Davidson, my
nurse. She insisted on chipping in twenty-five
dollars, which she could ill afford. But when
Davidson insisted on a thing-' He shrugged,
and then laughed a little. 'You're quite sure
it wasn't a reflex?' I heard myself demanding
suddenly. 'Are you quite sure -'
'Quite sure,' McCarron said imperturbably.
'The first contraction, perhaps. But the completion
of her labour was not a matter of seconds
but of minutes. And I sometimes think she
might have held on even longer, if it had
been necessary. Thank God it was not.'
'What about the baby?' Johanssen asked.
McCarron puffed at his pipe. 'Adopted,' he
said. 'And you'll understand that, even in
those days, adoption records were kept as
secret as possible.'
'Yes, but what about the baby?' Johanssen
asked again, and McCarron laughed in a cross
way.
'You never let go of a thing, do you?' he
asked Johanssen.
Johanssen shook his head. 'Some people have
learned it to their sorrow. What about the
baby?'
'Well, if you've come with me this far perhaps
you'll also understand that I had a certain
vested interest in knowing how it all came
out for that child. Or I felt that I did.
There was a young man and his wife-their name
was not Harrison, but that is close enough.
They lived in Maine. They could have no children
of their own. They adopted the child and named
him well, John's good enough, isn't it? John
will do you fellows, won't it?' He puffed
at his pipe but it had gone out again. I was
faintly aware of Stevens hovering behind me,
and knew that somewhere our coats would be
at the ready. Soon we would slip back into
them and back into our lives. As McCarron
had said, the tales were done for another
year.
The child I delivered that night is now head
of the English Department at one of the two
or three most respected private colleges in
the country,' McCarron said. 'He's not forty-five
yet. A young man. It's early for him, but
the day may well come when he will be President
of that school. I shouldn't doubt it a bit.
He is handsome, intelligent, and charming.
'Once, on a pretext, I was able to dine with
him in the private faculty club. We were four
that evening. I said little and so was able
to watch him. He has his mother's determination,
gentlemen ' and his mother's hazel eyes.'
3: The Club
Stevens saw us out as he always did, holding
coats, wishing men the happiest of happy Christmases,
thanking them for their generosity. I contrived
to be the last, and Stevens looked at me with
no surprise when I said: 'I have a question
I'd like to ask, if you don't mind.'
He smiled a little. 'I suppose you should,'
he said, 'Christmas is a fine time for questions.'
Somewhere down the hallway to our left- a
hall I had never been down- a grandfather
clock ticked sonorously, the sound of the
age passing away. I could smell old leather
and oiled wood and, much more faintly than
either of these, the smell of Stevens's aftershave.
'But I should warn you,' Stevens added as
the wind rose in a gust outside, 'it's better
not to ask too much. Not if you want to keep
coming here.'
'People have been closed out for asking too
much?' Closed out was not really the phrase
I wanted, but it was as close as I could come.
'No,' Stevens said, his voice as low and polite
as ever. 'They simply choose to stay away.'
I returned his gaze, feeling a chill prickle
its way up my back-it was as if a large, cold,
invisible hand had been laid on my spine.
I found myself remembering that strangely
liquid thump I had heard upstairs one night
and wondered (as I had more than once before)
exactly how many rooms there really were here.
'If you still have a question, Mr Adley, perhaps
you'd better ask it. The evening's almost
over -'
'And you have a long train-ride ahead of you?'
I asked, but Stevens only looked at me impassively.
'All right,' I said. There are books in this
library that I can't find anywhere else-not
in the New York Public Library, not in the
catalogues of any of the antiquarian book-dealers
I've checked with, and certainly not in Books
in Print. The billiard table in the Small
Room is a Nord. I'd never heard of such a
brand, and so I called the International Trademark
Commission. They have two Nords-one makes
crosscountry skis and the other makes wooden
kitchen accessories. There's a Seafront jukebox
in the Long Room. The ITC has a Seeburg listed,
but no Seafront.'
'What is your question, Mr Adley?'
His voice was as mild as ever, but there was
something terrible in his eyes suddenly no;
if I am to be truthful, it was not just in
his eyes; the terror I felt had infused the
atmosphere all around me. The steady tock-tock
from down the lefthand hall was no longer
the pendulum of a grandfather clock; it was
the tapping foot of the executioner as he
watches the condemned led to the scaffold.
The smells of oil and leather turned bitter
and menacing, and when the wind rose in another
wild whoop, I felt momentarily sure that the
front door would blow open, revealing not
35th Street but an insane Clark Ashton Smith
landscape where the bitter shapes of twisted
trees stood silhouetted on a sterile horizon
below, which double suns were setting in a
gruesome red glare.
Oh, he knew what I had meant to ask; I saw
it in his grey eyes.
Where do all these things come from? I had
meant to ask. Oh, I know well enough where
you come from, Stevens; that accent isn't
Dimension X, it's pure Brooklyn. But where
do you go? What has put that timeless look
in your eyes and stamped it on your face?
And, Stevens-- where are we RIGHT THIS SECOND?
But he was waiting for my question.
I opened my mouth. And the question that came
out was: 'Are there many more rooms upstairs?'
'Oh, yes, sir,' he said, his eyes never leaving
mine. 'A great many. A man could become lost
In fact, men have become lost. Sometimes it
seems to me that they go on for miles. Rooms
and corridors.'
'And entrances and exits?'
His eyebrows went up slightly. 'Oh yes. Entrances
and exits.' He waited, but I had asked enough,
I thought -I had come to the very edge of
something that would, perhaps, drive me mad.
"Thank you, Stevens.'
'Of course, sir.' He held out my coat and
I slipped into it.
'There will be more tales?'
'Here, sir, there are always more tales.'
That evening was some time ago, and my memory
has not improved between then and now (when
a man reaches my age, the opposite is much
more likely to be true), but I remember with
perfect clarity the stab of fear that went
through me when Stevens swung the oaken door
wide-the cold certainty that I would see that
alien landscape, cracked and hellish in the
bloody light of those double suns, which might
set and bring on an unspeakable darkness of
an hour's duration, or ten hours, or ten thousand
years. I cannot explain it, but I tell you
that world exists-I am as sure of that as
Emlyn McCarron was sure that the severed head
of Sandra Stansfield went on breathing. I
thought for that one timeless second that
the door would open and Stevens would thrust
me out into that world and I would then hear
that door slam shut behind me forever.
Instead, I saw 35th Street and a radio-cab
standing at the curb, exhaling plumes of exhaust.
I felt an utter, almost debilitating relief.
'Yes, always more tales,' Stevens repeated.
'Goodnight, sir.' Always more tales.
Indeed there have been. And, one day soon,
perhaps I'll tell you another.
- THE END -