CHAPTER ONE
Life Cycles
There are millions of different species of
animal in the world.
Some animals, like the blue whale, are very
big.
Others are so small that we almost can't see
them.
These animals all have very different life
cycles.
Animal Groups
Scientists put animals into groups.
The animals in each group are the same in
many ways, and they often have very similar
life cycles.
The two biggest animal groups are invertebrates
and vertebrates.
Invertebrates are animals that have no backbone.
More than 95% of the animal species in the
world are invertebrates, and most of them
are very small.
There are many different groups of invertebrates.
The biggest group is called arthropods.
Insects, spiders, and animals like crabs that
have a hard shell, are all arthropods.
Animals that have a backbone are called vertebrates.
Only a few percent of the animals in the world
are vertebrates, and most of them are much
bigger than invertebrates.
Because of this, we see vertebrates more often
than invertebrates.
Scientists put vertebrates into five big groups
- they are called fish, amphibians, reptiles,
birds, and mammals.
Staying Alive
All animals need to find food to stay alive.
Some animals are carnivores.
This means that they eat other animals.
Herbivores eat plants, and omnivores eat plants
and animals.
There are many dangers for animals.
They have to keep safe from predators - animals
that hunt and eat other animals.
People hunt birds and other animals.
People also cut down trees and build houses
and roads on land.
When they do this, animals lose their homes
and their food.
Many animals also become sick or die because
of pollution of the land, oceans, rivers,
and air.
Life is very dangerous for animals.
Many animals die before they are old enough
to produce young.
Different animals live for different amounts
of time.
A Galapagos tortoise can live for 150 years,
but an adult mayfly usually lives for just
a few hours.
Breeding
Most species of animal have males and females.
Males produce sperm, and females produce eggs.
Baby animals are made when sperm from the
male joins together with an egg from the female.
This is called fertilization.
Some animals give birth to baby animals.
Other animals, like reptiles and birds, lay
eggs.
Their babies hatch - they break the egg open
and come out.
Most reptiles and birds care for their babies.
Most insects and fish do not care for their
eggs or their babies.
All mammals care for their babies and feed
them milk.
Some big mammals stay with their babies for
many years.
CHAPTER TWO
Insects
Insects are small animals like butterflies,
beetles, flies, bees, and ants.
There are more than a million species of insect
in the world.
Many insects change in amazing ways during
their life.
Larvae and Nymphs
Almost all insects start their life in an
egg.
The young insect grows inside the egg and
then it hatches.
Some baby insects, like bees, look very different
from their parents.
These baby insects are called larvae.
Other baby insects, like locusts, look more
like their parents.
These baby insects are called nymphs.
Larvae and nymphs are very small when they
hatch.
Growing Up
A young insect eats a lot of food and grows
very quickly.
It has a hard cover, called an exoskeleton.
When the exoskeleton is too small for the
young insect, it breaks open and comes off.
A new exoskeleton grows under the old one.
This is called molting.
Some insects grow wings that get bigger every
time they molt.
After the insect molts for the last time,
it becomes an adult that can fly and produce
young.
This is called incomplete metamorphosis.
Most insects change by complete metamorphosis.
When the larva is ready to change into an
adult, its exoskeleton comes off.
Under the exoskeleton there's a pupa - it's
like a closed case.
Inside the pupa, an amazing change happens.
The larva changes into an adult that looks
completely different!
Finding a Mate
When insects become adults, they are ready
to breed and produce young.
First they need to find a mate.
Male crickets, cicadas, and grasshoppers sing
to find females that they can mate with.
Female butterflies and moths produce special
chemicals called pheromones that have a strong
smell.
Male butterflies and moths can smell the pheromones
from up to 2 kilometers away.
They then fly toward the smell.
Male fireflies make special lights in their
body.
They turn these lights on and off so that
female fireflies know that they are looking
for a mate.
Laying Eggs
Some insects only lay a few eggs during their
life, but others lay thousands.
Many insects are careful to keep their eggs
safe.
The cardinal beetle makes a hole in dead wood
and lays her eggs inside.
When the eggs hatch, you can't see the larvae
very well.
Cockroaches lay their eggs in a special case,
and beetle eggs are usually yellow, green,
or black so that they are camouflaged.
When these insect eggs hatch, the life cycle
starts again!
Termite queens lay up to 30,000 eggs every
day!
CHAPTER THREE
Other Invertebrates
There are many other groups of invertebrate,
and they all have very different life cycles.
Did you know that earthworms, octopuses, spiders,
and lobsters are all invertebrates?
Earthworms
All earthworms lay eggs, because they are
hermaphrodites.
This means that they all have male parts that
produce sperm and female parts that produce
eggs, but they cannot fertilize their own
eggs.
After earthworms mate, their bodies make special
rings with eggs inside.
The ring moves forward over the worm's body
and then it comes off.
Then the ends of the ring join together.
The eggs hatch after about three months, and
young earthworms can mate when they are 12
months old.
Octopuses
Baby octopuses live in the open ocean at first,
but when they grow, they move down to the
bottom of the ocean.
Here they live on their own in dens.
Octopuses are ready to mate when they are
one or two years old.
Some female octopuses lay about 200,000 eggs,
and many put them in strings from the top
of their dens.
The females keep the eggs safe from predators
and they carefully push water over them so
that they get enough oxygen.
The octopuses do not eat for up to ten months
when they are caring for their eggs.
After the eggs hatch, the female octopuses
die.
Spiders
Spiders produce silk, and they use it to make
webs, where they catch flies and other insects.
Most species of spider also put lots of silk
around their eggs to make a special cover,
called a cocoon.
Most spider eggs hatch after a few days or
weeks.
The baby spiders, or spider lings, grow fast
and they molt a few times.
They can soon make their own webs and catch
their own food.
Many spiders die after they lay their eggs.
Some spider lings eat their mother's body
after she dies!
Lobsters
A female lobster can lay up to 10,000 eggs,
but only about ten of them will live.
The female lobster carries her eggs hidden
under her tail for almost a year.
When they are ready to hatch, she lifts her
tail and they float away.
When the eggs hatch, the larvae move to the
top of the ocean.
Life here is very dangerous because of predators
and difficult currents.
Lobster larvae look very different from adult
lobsters.
When they are about one month old, the larvae
move to the bottom of the ocean.
They molt about 25 times before they become
adults.
Lobsters often eat their old shell after molting.
This helps their new shell to become hard.
CHAPTER FOUR
Fish
Fish are vertebrates that are cold-blooded.
This means that their body is as hot or cold
as the water around them.
All fish live and breathe in water, and most
baby fish hatch from eggs.
Eggs
Female fish can lay hundreds of eggs.
Inside every egg there's a bag of food called
the yolk.
The unborn baby fish eats the yolk, so that
it can grow bigger and stronger.
Fish often try to hide their eggs because
many other animals like to eat fish eggs.
Female seahorses lay their eggs into a special
pouch on the male's front, where they stay
safe until they are ready to hatch.
Some species of shark lay their eggs in a
hard egg case to keep the eggs safe until
they hatch.
Young Fish
When young fish hatch, the yolk bag is still
stuck to their body.
The young fish use this as food at first.
Life is very dangerous for young fish.
Most of them don't have fins, so they can't
swim well.
They often float into colder water or places
where there's no food.
Also, many predators, like seals, birds, frogs,
and other fish, hunt them.
This is why fish lay so many eggs.
A large female tuna fish can lay up to six
million eggs at one time, but only about two
of these will grow into adult tuna!
Growing Up
Most fish never see their parents because
they swim away after they have laid their
eggs.
The young fish have to find food for themselves
so that they can grow bigger.
They eat small plants and insect eggs or larvae.
Most small fish grow into adults just a few
months after hatching, but whale sharks do
not grow into adults until they are 25 years
old!
The whale shark is the biggest fish in the
world.
An adult whale shark can be about 12 meters
long and it can weigh more than 21 metric
tons.
Breeding
Fish need to find mates so that they can breed.
When the male three-spined stickleback is
ready to breed, he builds a nest.
Part of his body changes to a red color.
Females see his bright colors and they lay
their eggs in his nest.
Many fish go back to the same place to breed
every year.
Salmon live in the ocean, but to breed, they
swim back to the rivers where they hatched.
Some salmon travel hundreds of kilometers
up rivers, and sometimes they have to jump
up waterfalls.
They change color from silver to red when
they are swimming back to their breeding places.
CHAPTER FIVE
Amphibians
Like fish, amphibians are cold-blooded vertebrates.
Most amphibians live for some of their life
in water and for some of their life on land.
Salamanders, toads, and frogs are all amphibians.
Metamorphosis
All amphibians have two different parts of
life.
At first they are larvae that breathe in water
through special gills.
Then they change into adults with lungs.
This change is called metamorphosis.
Usually, amphibians live in water for the
first part of their life and on land for the
second part.
Some salamanders live in water all the time.
Eggs and Larvae
Amphibians often lay thousands of eggs.
The eggs have a sticky cover, and they float
in water.
Most amphibians do not care for their eggs,
but the male midwife toad carries them on
his back until they are ready to hatch.
The young that hatch from eggs are called
larvae, but young frogs and toads are also
called tadpoles.
At first, tadpoles don't have legs or feet
and they breathe through gills.
It's easy for predators to catch and eat eggs
and tadpoles.
Frogs can lay about 2,000 eggs, but probably
only 5% live to become adults.
The male Darwin's frog keeps his tadpoles
safe and wet in his throat, until they are
big enough to swim away.
Becoming Adults
When amphibians begin to change into adults,
they grow lungs inside their body and their
gills close.
At the same time, most amphibians grow legs
and feet.
An adult frog looks completely different from
a tadpole!
Most adult amphibians can breathe through
their skin and their lungs!
They can only breathe through their skin if
it's wet, so most amphibians live near water.
Amphibians are cold-blooded, so when it gets
very cold they have no energy.
Some amphibians in colder countries hibernate
for the winter.
They hide in a safe, wet place and go into
a special, long sleep.
Breeding
Most amphibians go to wet places like ponds,
lakes, or rivers to breed, because their eggs
and larvae live in water.
Many go back to the same place every year,
and some go back to the pond or stream where
they were born.
Male frogs croak and shout to tell the females
that they are ready to breed.
They push their throats out so that their
calls are louder.
When the female has chosen a mate, she lays
her eggs in the water, and the male covers
them with sperm.
CHAPTER SIX
Reptiles
Reptiles are cold-blooded, and their skin
is dry and covered with special scales.
Lizards, snakes, crocodiles, alligators, and
turtles are all reptiles.
Some live on land and some live in water.
Eggs
Most reptiles hatch from eggs, but a few are
born as living animals.
Females lay their eggs in a warm, wet place.
They usually lay a lot of eggs, but many eggs
are eaten by predators.
Most reptiles lay their eggs and then they
leave them, but pythons put their body around
their eggs to keep them warm.
Alligators make a big nest from mud and leaves.
They lay their eggs and stay near the nest.
They don't eat for weeks when they are keeping
their eggs safe.
Growing Up
Crocodiles and alligators are very good parents
after their eggs hatch.
The female Nile crocodile is very careful
- she puts her babies inside her mouth to
carry them to water.
She stays near them to keep them safe for
up to two months.
When snakes and lizards grow, they get too
big for their skin.
The old skin comes off and there's a new one
underneath.
This is called sloughing.
Most snakes lose their old skin three or four
times every year.
Breeding
When reptiles are ready to breed, they have
to find a mate.
Male crocodiles lift their head up and make
a loud sound.
They also blow bubbles in the water so that
females will see and hear them.
Snakes find their mate by smell.
The females leave a special smell that the
male follows.
Other male reptiles, like monitor lizards,
fight each other for a mate.
The females choose the winner of the fight
because he's the strongest.
Some whiptail lizards can produce young without
mating!
The eggs are not fertilized, but they still
hatch.
Keeping Safe
Reptiles are in danger from many predators,
and they have lots of ways of keeping safe.
If a predator catches a lizard by its tail,
the lizard can break its tail off and escape.
It then grows a new tail.
The stinkpot turtle makes a horrible smell
from its legs to make predators go away.
Many reptiles also use camouflage to keep
safe.
Some chameleons can change color so that predators
do not see them, and the leaf-tailed gecko
can hide easily because its body looks like
a leaf.
CHAPTER SEVEN
Birds
There are about 9,000 different species of
bird, and they all lay eggs.
Baby birds called chicks come from eggs.
Birds are the only animals that have feathers.
All birds have wings and most birds can fly.
Courtship
Courtship is when male birds try to find female
birds that they can mate with.
Male birds do many different things to find
a mate.
Some males show females their colors.
The male frigate bird pushes his red throat
out like a balloon.
The blue-footed booby shows his big blue feet.
Songbirds sing for their females, and the
bower bird builds a special place with twigs
and puts bright colored things in it so that
it looks pretty.
Nests
Birds work very hard to build nests - special
homes where they can keep their eggs and chicks
safe and warm.
They find grass, mud, and twigs, and they
push them together.
Many birds build nests in high places like
trees and cliffs.
Others build them on the ground.
These birds are usually brown and speckled,
so they are well camouflaged.
Eggs
The female bird lays her eggs in the nest.
Then the female or the male sits on the eggs
to keep them warm.
When the chick is ready to hatch, it breaks
the shell with a special 'tooth' on its beak.
Cuckoos lay their eggs in other birds' nests.
When the baby cuckoo hatches, it pushes the
other eggs or chicks out of the nest so that
it can have more food.
It often grows much, much bigger than the
adult bird that is feeding it!
Ostrich eggs are the biggest bird eggs, and
they can weight about 2 kilograms.
If you stand on one, it will not break!
Chicks
Many chicks have no feathers, and they can't
see or move when they hatch, but some can
run, swim, and find food.
Birds feed their chicks and keep them safe
until they can care for themselves.
Birds often have to fly to and from the nest
hundreds of times a day to bring enough food
for their chicks.
Growing Up
Some small birds can fly just two weeks after
they hatch, but bigger birds take longer.
Chicks watch their parents and learn to fly,
feed, sing, and keep safe.
Some baby birds do not become adults for months
or even years.
Many birds that migrate every year have to
make long, dangerous journeys when they are
still very young.
These birds fly to warmer places for winter
and come back to their breeding places for
summer.
CHAPTER EIGHT
Mammals
All mammals have fur or hair and they produce
milk to feed their babies.
Giraffes, bears, kangaroos, elephants, and
people are all mammals.
Breeding
It's usually the female mammals who choose
a mate, so the males want the females to look
at them.
Leopards make marks on trees with their claws
so that the females will know they are there.
Other animals make special smells.
Males often fight with each other to win a
mate.
Male giraffes fight with their head and neck
to show which animal is the strongest.
Having Babies
Most mammals do not lay eggs.
The babies grow inside the mother's body,
and they get food and oxygen from a special
part of the body called the placenta.
This is called gestation.
The gestation time for shrews is only two
weeks, but for African elephants it's 22 months!
When mammals are ready to have their babies,
many look for safe, quiet places.
Polar bears dig special dens in the snow so
that their babies will be warm and safe.
Baby Mammals
Some baby mammals grow a lot inside their
mother's body, and they can stand up as soon
as they are born.
Other baby mammals can't see or move when
they are born.
Mammals produce milk for their babies, and
this is the only food or drink that they need
at first.
Marsupials
Marsupials are animals like kangaroos and
koalas.
Baby marsupials only grow for a short time
inside their mother's body.
After they are born, they continue to grow
on the outside of their mother's body, usually
in a pouch.
Baby kangaroos are only 5 centimeters long
when they are born.
They climb into their mother's pouch, where
they stay for up to a year.
Growing Up
Mammals are different from many other types
of animal because they feed and care for their
babies.
Anteaters carry their babies on their back
for the first year, and elephants stay near
their mother until they are ten years old.
Baby mammals learn from their parents, and
they learn by playing, too.
Life Cycles
Life is very dangerous for a lot of animals.
Many are killed by predators.
Also, people hunt them and damage their habitats
- the places where they live.
Many animals die before they become adults,
but if they grow up, then they can produce
young.
This is all part of their life cycle.
Because of this, there will always be millions
of species of animal on Earth, if we care
for them and their habitats.
- THE END -