CHAPTER ONE
The Man in the Moon
HOW DID WE GET TO KNOW THE MOON?
Long ago, people in every part of the world
looked up at the sky, the same way we do now.
The two most important things they saw were
the Sun and the Moon.
The Sun gave a lot of light, but the Moon
gave only a little.
So many people thought the Sun was a man god,
and the Moon a woman god - a goddess.
And people saw a face on the Moon.
They called it "the Man in the Moon."
Parents still tell their children about him
today.
Then people studied astronomy, and they thought
about how the Moon changed.
In the end, the astronomers understood.
The Moon was a big ball!
They understood that the Moon and the Earth
go around the Sun.
The Sun shines light on half of the Earth
all the time - this gives us day and night.
The Sun shines on half of the Moon all the
time, too.
But from Earth, we can't always see all of
the light on the Moon.
When the half of the Moon with light is away
from us, the sky is dark.
This is called a new moon.
When we can see all of the light on the Moon,
it's a full moon.
Between the new moon and the full moon, there
are half-moons and crescent moons.
CHAPTER TWO
A Helping Hand
HOW DOES THE MOON HELP THE EARTH?
In 1969, three American astronauts flew in
a rocket to the Moon.
Neil Armstrong was the first man to walk on
the Moon.
When he was there, he talked to people on
Earth on the radio.
But they heard him 1.25 seconds later.
That's because it's more than 350,000 kilometers
from the Moon to the Earth.
The Moon pulls the Earth.
Because of this, the Earth is turning more
and more slowly.
Our day is getting 0.000015 seconds longer
every year.
But, of course, we don't feel the difference.
The Moon goes around the Earth, but really,
the Earth and the Moon go around each other.
At the same time, the Earth and the Moon,
together, go around the Sun.
The Earth has a tilt of 23.5 degrees.
Because of the pull of the Moon, this tilt
doesn't change.
And that's a good thing, because it's the
Earth's tilt that gives us our seasons.
Thanks to the Moon, we enjoy spring, summer,
fall, and winter.
And the Earth doesn't get too hot or too cold
for life.
The Moon's pull gives us tides, too.
The Moon pulls the sea, and the water goes
up and down.
The Sun also pulls the sea and gives us tides,
but the Moon's tides are much bigger because
it is closer to the Earth.
Tides can help us.
We can use them to make electricity for our
factories and homes.
And that electricity is clean to make.
It isn't bad for plants and animals.
The Moon also helps sailors on boats at sea.
At night, they can see where the Moon is - if
there are no clouds.
Then they know where to go.
The Moon helps animals, too.
Many animals go out at night.
A little moonlight helps them to see.
Of course, for some small animals, that's
not always a good thing.
Big animals can see them in the moonlight
and eat them!
The Moon can also tell animals where to go.
Baby olive ridley turtles start their life
in a hole in the sand on a beach.
They use the Moon to find the sea.
CHAPTER THREE
Lunatics
CAN THE MOON MAKE PEOPLE CRAZY?
The word lunar is the adjective we use for
the Moon.
It comes from Latin, the language of the Ancient
Romans.
They called the Moon "Luna."
And lunatic is an old English word for a crazy
person.
A long time ago, people thought the Moon changed
people.
Lunatics went crazy when the Moon was full.
The Ancient Greek thinker and teacher Aristotle
said this was because there was too much light
from the full moon.
Some people couldn't sleep.
That made them crazy.
Was he right?
We now have streetlights to see at night.
People don't go crazy because of streetlights.
But we know that people in countries with
no night in the summer or no sunlight in the
winter can have problems.
We need both day and night.
Today, it's often bad to use the word "lunatic."
England stopped using the word in its laws
in 1930.
But people still use it when they talk.
For example, if someone is a crazy driver,
we say, "He drives like a lunatic!"
CHAPTER FOUR
Moon Stories
WHY IS THE MOON SO INTERESTING
There are old stories about the Moon in every
country.
The Maoris were the first people in New Zealand.
They lived there before Europeans came.
One old Maori story is about Rona.
Rona was the daughter of the sea god, Tangaroa.
She made the sea go up and down at high and
low tide.
One night, Rona had water in a bucket to take
to her children at home.
She could see where to go in the moonlight.
But then a cloud in the sky covered the Moon.
Rona couldn't see.
She said some bad things about the Moon.
But the Moon heard her and was very angry.
It pulled Rona up into the sky!
Today, many Maoris see a woman and a bucket
in the Moon.
They say that rain is water from Rona's bucket.
In another Maori story, a man - also called
Rona - went to the Moon to find a wife.
Every four weeks, the man eats his wife and
then she eats him.
That's why the dark and light parts of the
Moon get bigger and smaller each month.
There are many stories about the Moon in science
fiction books and movies.
Science fiction is about what things are going
to be like in a hundred, a thousand, or a
million years.
Or about worlds that are different from ours.
In 1901, H.G. Wells wrote a book called The
First Men in the Moon.
In the book, two men fly a rocket to the Moon.
They find different kinds of aliens there.
Some aliens want to stop them leaving.
In the end, one man goes home, but the other
stays.
Today, we know there's no life on the Moon.
But in 1901, people didn't know that.
Anything was possible.
In 1867, the USA wanted to buy Alaska from
Russia.
So they sent a scientist called George Davidson
to study it.
He wrote down what he saw, and the USA paid
the Russians $7.2 million for Alaska.
Davidson, an astronomer, wanted to see an
eclipse.
So in 1869, he went back to Alaska, to a place
called Chilkat Valley.
Davidson told the people there, "The Sun's
going to go dark tomorrow!"
The Chilkats laughed.
That was impossible, they thought.
But the next day, the Moon went in front of
the Sun.
Everything was dark!
Some Chilkats thought Davidson did it!
The Moon can change how we feel, but can it
change us into animals?
In many countries, there are stories about
people who change into birds, cats, or fish.
Or werewolves!
In the stories, people change into werewolves
when the Moon is full.
Some people change because a werewolf bites
them.
They get big teeth and hair on all their body.
Then they eat animals - or sometimes people!
Some stories say you can only kill werewolves
with silver, possibly because the color of
the Moon is silver.
The stories aren't true, but they make great
movies!
In an Ancient Greek story, a man called Lycaon
doesn't think Zeus is really a god.
To find out, Lycaon kills Zeus's son and cooks
him for Zeus!
But Zeus knows the food isn't animal meat.
He's angry and changes Lycaon into a wolf.
This is one of the oldest werewolf stories.
One of the newest is in the Harry Potter books.
Harry's teacher, Remus Lupin, is a werewolf.
Werewolves in stories are usually bad, but
Lupin is a good man.
So he isn't happy about being a werewolf.
- THE END -