CHAPTER ONE
Dawn in Bangkok
Hu decided to get up. She couldn't sleep.
The first bird of the Bangkok dawn, the cuckoo,
started its noisy, morning cry, 'Gow-wow!
Gow-wow! Get up! Get up!' Hu could hear the
growing noise of the early morning traffic.
It was not yet six o'clock.
It was impossible to sleep. She walked over
to her window and opened it. The noise and
the smell of the big city washed over her.
It was still dark. It was a cool January morning,
the first day of the spring term.
Hu looked out of the window. The newspaperman
arrived on his motorbike and gave his parcel
of newspapers to the man at the entrance of
the apartment block. The two men laughed,
and then the newspaperman waved and drove
noisily away to the next apartment block in
the Soi, the next street. There was light
in the sky now, a soft orange light in the
grey dawn.
It was always difficult to sleep the night
before the new term, but this time it was
even harder. Hu was excited. She would see
Marwa and Thomas and Yoshiko again, and that
was exciting. She would do less housework
and more school work, and that was exciting
too.
Hu was seventeen and a good student. She studied
at the Bangkok International Academy, an international
school for the children of foreign people
working in Thailand. It was expensive, but
the Chinese oil company, where her father
worked, helped her family to pay for her education.
She had to study very hard, and all the classes
- except her Thai language class - were in
English. Hu loved English. Her father wanted
her to become a doctor. Her mother said she
didn't mind what Hu wanted as long as Hu was
happy. But Hu wasn't sure if she wanted to
be a doctor, or that she would get good enough
results to go to medical school.
Hu liked to work hard, but she was worried
about her studies, about her English exam.
Today Mr Stanyer, her English teacher, would
give out the results of last term's English
test. Hu knew she had problems with her English,
but she didn't know what the problems were.
She loved English - or she had loved English
until she started with Mr Stanyer last term
- and she thought she was good at English.
Her classmates thought she was good at English
too. She helped Marwa with her English homework
sometimes, but then Marwa got better results
than Hu. Better results with her work!
Hu didn't understand. Mr Stanyer seemed to
like her, he always smiled at her. But at
the end of last term, after the test, he had
asked her to stay after class.
'Come here and sit down,' Mr Stanyer said.
Hu sat at his desk in the empty classroom,
facing her teacher.
'How was the test, Hu Jian Ming?' asked Mr
Stanyer.
'OK, Mr Stanyer. I think I did quite well,'
said Hu.
'I hope so. Your father has great hopes for
you. He works for an oil company, doesn't
he?' Mr Stanyer smiled and looked Hu in the
eye.
'He's an engineer with a Chinese oil company.'
Hu felt uncomfortable.
'He wants you to take the International Baccalaureate,
the IB, doesn't he?' Mr Stanyer continued
with questions.
'Well, you must get better results next term.
This is just a test, but next term we have
the real exam. Then we decide if you can start
the IB programme,' said Mr Stanyer.
'Yes, Mr Stanyer.' She noticed Mr Stanyer
was sweating, although the classroom was cool.
Mr Stanyer smiled and put his hands on his
bald head. 'Perhaps you should do some extra
work on your English. Think about it over
the holiday.'
'Oh!' said Hu. Her cat, Lao Mao, had jumped
suddenly into her room through the open window,
surprising her. 'Stupid cat!' said Hu as she
picked up Lao Mao. Hu loved animals, she loved
nature. Her home city, Wu Xi, was in beautiful
countryside, with lakes and low hills in the
distance. When Hu's family had to leave China
and come to Thailand so that Hu's father could
work for his oil company in Bangkok, her mother
and father allowed her to bring one thing
to remind her of home. Hu chose to bring Lao
Mao. Hu liked to talk to him when she was
sad, or worried, or feeling a long way from
home. Very quietly, she explained her problems
with her results for her English studies to
the cat.
'If I fail my English test, what can I do?'
whispered Hu. Lao Mao said nothing. The noisy
cuckoo sang back across the waking city: ' Gow-wow!
Gow-wow!'
Hu looked over the apartment blocks to the
raised motorway carrying traffic over the
city, and the private gardens of the few remaining
houses. Bangkok. She missed her own country
very much. The sun was rising over the block
opposite hers like a big, wet, orange ball.
A man in yellow clothes, a Buddhist monk,
was walking up the road asking for food. A
big Mercedes car came round to the front gate.
'Probably a businessman going to the airport,'
thought Hu.
Hu yawned. What would she do?
Something caught her eye in the Soi below.
A very large orange and black animal, a squirrel,
was running along an electricity line over
the Soi. Electricity lines ran across the
Soi in a hundred different directions, meeting
at the posts at the sides of the street in
big balls. Hu thought these balls of electricity
lines looked like spaghetti. The squirrels
used the electricity lines like motorways,
running to and from whatever important business
squirrels have to do. Hu looked towards the
raised motorway in the distance. All the cars
were stopped even now, at half past six in
the morning. Another Bangkok traffic jam.
Hu's eyes followed the racing squirrel along
the line and down into another garden.
There was a knock at the door.
'Jian Ming! Come on, my love. It's a school
day today.'
That was her father. He was usually out of
bed first. He worked very hard.
'I'm out of bed, father. I'm coming. Don't
worry.'
'Don't worry,' thought Hu. 'My father mustn't
worry,' she told Lao Mao, her cat. 'He works
too hard.'
Lao Mao said nothing. He didn't care.
CHAPTER TWO
New term, old friends
Hu walked up the narrow Soi to school. She
felt happy and excited. The early morning
sun was bright. It almost hurt her eyes. It
was cool and the skies were blue and clear.
There were street restaurants, which had small
tables and tiny plastic chairs on the pavements.
Hu stepped into the road as she walked past
them. City workers sat and ate bowls of Khao
Chom, a thick rice soup. They wore their office
clothes, and they ate quickly, talking and
laughing at the same time. The shop opposite
the school was full of students from the international
school in their blue uniforms. They were buying
drinks and snacks. Some of them had spent
two hours or more fighting their way through
the Bangkok traffic jams to get to school.
There was a loud noise as a boat raced down
the long, the canal at the end of the Soi.
Water flew into the air. The smell of the
dirty water made Hu feel sick for a moment.
'Everybody is trying to get to work or to
school. Everyone is busy, hurrying,' thought
Hu. It filled her with excitement.
She walked past the building workers' dark,
small homes. They were building another expensive
apartment building for rich people to live
in, but the building workers lived in their
own tiny, dark city. They had built their
small world on some waste ground between two
tall new buildings, the Royal Luxury Tower
and Executive Mansion Apartments. Their homes
were made out of old sheets of metal, pieces
of wood and useful bits of rubbish. Babies
were crying, women were washing clothes, themselves,
and children. Hu could see a television, men
playing cards, chickens looking for food in
the dirt and a small dog asleep in the middle
of all the noise. Women and men were walking
in silence from their crowded homes to their
work. Hu tried to look into their sad, dark
eyes. They would breathe and eat the dirt
all the long working day, and often late into
the night. Hu tried to smile at them but they
didn't smile back.
It was wonderful for Hu to see her friends
again. They crowded together at the entrance
to the school. They were all trying to tell
the others what they had been doing during
the holidays at once. Thomas Kuhlauf had been
home to Germany for Christmas. He had a special
German cake, called a stolen. He gave Hu and
Marwa and Yoshiko a piece each while they
waited for the bell for the beginning of school.
They were still eating Thomas' wonderful cake
as they went into the school hall.
Hu found herself sitting next to a new student.
He was tall and had blond hair. He had a friendly
face, with quick eyes and a ready smile.
'Hi! I'm John Truman from the USA. This is
my first day here. What's your name?' said
the stranger, smiling. He very politely offered
Hu his hand. Hu was surprised, but she smiled
and shook his hand.
'I'm Hu. From China... Hu Jian Ming. Your
first day?'
'Shhhh!' said Marwa, who was sitting on her
other side. 'Mr Grisman! Mustn't talk!'
The school principal, Mr Grisman, walked on
to the stage and raised his hands to tell
the whole school to be quiet and listen. He
was tall and had grey hair. He was wearing
dark clothes and a very serious expression.
Hu thought he looked silly. He stared at them
importantly until there was silence, and then
he smiled and said:
'Welcome! Welcome! Happy New Year! And welcome
to a new year at the Bangkok International
Academy...'
'It's not my New Year yet, it's not the Chinese
New Year until next month. It's not the Thai
New Year until April. It's not Marwa's or
Yoshiko's either,' thought Hu. She stopped
listening.
She looked at the teachers sitting behind
Mr Grisman on the stage. Mr Stanyer, her English
teacher, was yawning. He was very sun-tanned.
Mr Riding, the school counsellor, looked like
a sleeping animal, until his eyes suddenly
opened and slowly stared around the hall.
Mrs Patel, the music teacher, was looking
very pleased with life. She was wearing a
lovely new sari, her traditional Indian dress.
Where was Dr Nyondo, the head of Upper School?
There was a new woman. She was tall and about
forty years old. She sat very straight. She
had blond hair and a kind, intelligent face.
'... And as Dr Nyondo has left us to take
up the position of principal of a high school
in Australia, it is my pleasure...' Mr Grisman
looked round at the woman who stood up. '... My
great pleasure to introduce Mrs Verity Truman
as the new head of Upper School.'
'That's my mother!' said John.
'Shhh!' said Marwa. 'Mustn't talk!'
But they did, as quietly as they could. Hu
and John made friends while his mother made
a short speech.
John was from Chicago, Illinois. He had one
sister, Mary, who was in the fifth year. His
father was a lawyer with a multinational company.
John's father was now working in the Bangkok
headquarters of his company, and working very
long hours.
'My father's like that!' said Hu. 'I don't
see much of him. I go to bed before he comes
home in the evening. We don't have much time
to talk even in the mornings.'
'What does he do?' asked John.
Hu told him that her father worked as an engineer
for a Chinese oil company, managing the company's
Bangkok office and projects in Eastern Thailand.
And that her mother looked after small children
at a kindergarten in the mornings and sometimes
did baby-sitting at night. She told him that
she had a pet cat called Lao Mao and that
she liked music... and all kinds of things.
Mr Grisman was still talking. He invited Mrs
Patel to talk to the school about the new
school show. It was a musical called 'The
Wizard of Oz'. Mrs Patel was going to hold
auditions on Friday after school.
'What does "auditions" mean?' whispered Hu
to John.
'You have to try out acting and singing in
front of the people organising the show. If
you're good, they give you a part. Do you
sing, Hu?' asked John.
Hu was excited. 'I love singing. I can act
too. I...'
'Shhh!' said Marwa. Mrs Patel looked angrily
at Hu and John. Hu's face went red with embarrassment.
The first day passed happily and quickly.
Hu was happy to be back among her friends
and studying again after the holidays.
As Hu went into her last class, a Thai language
class, her Thai teacher, Khun Naraporn, handed
her a note. It was from Mr Stanyer, her English
teacher. It read:
Please see me after class today. I want to
discuss your English results with you.
D. S.
Marwa watched her read the note.
'Are you OK?' Marwa asked.
Hu passed her the note.
'Miss Hu! Please pay attention! Today we are
going to study the traditions of the Thai
New Year,' said Khun Naraporn.
'Oh dear!' thought Hu. She was very worried.
She was sure the note was bad news. What was
Mr Stanyer going to say? She tried to concentrate
on her Thai lesson.
CHAPTER THREE
Sharing troubles
'But, Mr Stanyer? Forty-six per cent?'
'It's not good, Hu. It's not good.' Mr Stanyer
was shaking his head.
'But, really, I...' Hu was close to tears.
'Listen!' said Mr Stanyer, leaning forward
across the desk. His big red face was close
to Hu's. He picked up Hu's writing test. 'Here's
your work!'
He threw it across the desk at Hu. Hu thought
this was very rude. As she collected the papers
together, she knew her feelings would show
in her face. She had worked hard on the essay
and now it was covered in red ink.
'OK, Hu,' said Mr Stanyer. He smiled. Hu didn't
like his smile. He tried to laugh and leant
back in his chair and put his hands on his
baldhead. The classroom was air- conditioned,
almost too cool, but there were dark marks
under his arms. 'You're a good kid, a bright
kid. Your father wants you to be a doctor,
right?'
'Yes, but...' Hu said.
'Yes, but!' Mr Stanyer moved forward suddenly
hitting his hands on the desk between them.
'YES BUT!' he repeated in a loud voice to
scare her. Then he remembered to smile. 'But
your results have got to improve. It's only
six weeks until the exams for the IB, the
International Baccalaureate programme. Forty-six
per cent is a fail. You can't be a doctor
unless you get the IB.'
He could see Hu was going to cry. He pushed
his chair back and stood up. He took a handkerchief
from his pocket and wiped his forehead. He
tried a new voice, a voice like a child asking
their mother for a sweet.
'Hu, we can work on this. Together.' Mr Stanyer
walked round the desk and slowly sat down
in the chair next to Hu. He smelled of sweat.
He put his arm on the back of Hu's chair.
Hu sat as far forward as she could and looked
at the desk. She was trying not to cry, trying
not to smell Mr Stanyer's fat smell.
'It's a question of work. You're intelligent.'
Hu looked at the desk. 'You work hard, Chinese
people work hard,' said Mr Stanyer, laughing.
'Maybe I can help you, Hu?'
Hu tried to look at him. He was smiling his
biggest, his most sugary smile.
'You need some extra lessons. Private lessons.
One-to-one. After class. We can work on this
exam preparation together.'
'You would give me lessons?' asked Hu. Mr
Stanyer stood up and walked back to his own
seat opposite her.
'Sure. Well, not exactly give you lessons.
I mean, you'd have to pay.'
'I don't have any money, Mr Stanyer. How can
I pay?' asked Hu.
'Hey! Your father's an oil engineer. You should
talk to him!'
'But I can't tell...' Hu started to say, but
she stopped. Now she stood up. She was very
angry. She looked down at Mr Stanyer.
'I shall have to discuss this with my father.'
She walked to the door without looking back.
'Sure!' Mr Stanyer called after her. 'Talk
to your father. But Hu, those results have
got to improve!'
Hu didn't start crying until she was outside
the classroom.
There is a small wooden house in a banyan
tree in the south corner of the school playing
field, near the klong. The klong smell is
very bad there, but after school it is a place
you can sit alone.
Hu climbed in and threw herself into a broken
car seat. She put her head in her hands and
cried. She couldn't go home like this.
Her father wanted her to be a doctor. And
now she was getting bad results. Hu's shoulders
shook as she cried.
But she still didn't understand. All her other
results were good or very good. In music and
in drama she was, her teachers said, a 'star'.
She dried her eyes.
Hu looked up. A face appeared in the entrance
to the tree house.
'Can I come in?' said the face. It was her
new friend, John Truman. As he said this,
another face appeared. It was a small blond
girl.
'This is my sister, Mary,' John said.
'Hi!' said Mary as the two pulled themselves
into the tree house.
'This is Hu Jian Ming, Mary. And she doesn't
look very happy,' John said.
'Hi Mary! Hi John!' Hu tried to look happy.
'What are you doing here?'
'Waiting for mother,' said Mary. 'She's at
a teachers' meeting.'
'What's that?' asked John, pointing at Hu's
hand.
Hu had not realised. Her English essay was
now a small ball in her hand. She was so angry.
She threw the essay to John.
John opened it out.
'That,' said Hu, 'is my English essay. My
rubbish essay. My forty-six per cent essay.
My failed essay. My...' She stopped because
she thought she was going to cry again.
John tried to read the essay.
'Hey, this is good,' said John. 'But Eve never
seen so much red ink.'
John read from the essay: '"Wu Xi, My Home
Town. The beautiful sailing boats, their red
sails full, moved slowly over the mirror-like
surface of the lakes." Wow! You can write!
Is this where you live?'
'My father was working in Beijing before we
came here. But I was born in Wu Xi. It is
my home. My grandmother still lives there,
and my mother's family. At our new year, we
used to go there...'
'"The friendly hills gather round the metal-smooth
lakes as the skies turn pink,"' John read.
'This is good! When can I go there?'
'My teacher doesn't like it,' said Hu, sadly.
'"Did..." I can't read his writing... "you
copy this from a guide book?" Huh. I don't
think this guy likes you, Hu.'
'I don't know. He's always looking at me in
class.' Hu was confused.
John laughed and then looked serious.
'Forty-six per cent isn't very good. I hope
this wasn't a test or something.'
John still had half a bottle of water he had
bought at the Chinese shop opposite the school
gates, and Hu had some of her morning snack
left. The three of them had a little picnic.
Hu made John and Mary promise not to tell
anybody else, and then she explained her problems
to them.
CHAPTER FOUR
To be a star
The noise in the school restaurant was very
loud. Three hundred students were all shouting
at once. Three hundred metal trays banged
upon the tables, and all the metal forks and
spoons and knives banged together at the same
time.
'A normal day at the BIA,' shouted Hu as she
sat down with Marwa, Yoshiko, Thomas and John.
'What's this?' shouted Thomas, pointing with
his fork at a small pool of wet brown stuff.
'Food, Mr Kuhlauf, but not as we know it!'
said John.
They all laughed except Marwa. She had her
own food from home. Her mother had prepared
a rice dish for her. It smelled delicious,
and Marwa ate quickly and in silence.
'Are you going to the meeting after school?'
asked Thomas. 'It's for the school show, "The
Wizard of Oz".'
'Yes, I'm going,' said Hu.
'That awful Melanie Gibson wants to be the
star,' said Thomas. 'You know her, she's got
long red hair and she sings like a duck! Quack,
quack!' he shouted.
'You are unkind, Thomas!' Hu said. 'It's true
about her singing though.' She tried to look
cross.
'And Sean Payne wants to be the Wizard,' Thomas
continued.
'Sean Payne? The one who wasn't allowed to
come to school for a while?' asked Yoshiko.
Sean Payne was always in trouble. Once he
let out the air of the tyres on the principal's
car. Mr Grisman sent him home and would not
let him come back to the school for two weeks.
'That's him. The ugly one with hair like a
brush. The one whose father runs a bar. He
married one of his dancers, did you know?'
said Thomas.
'Thomas Kuhlauf, you talk too much!' said
Hu crossly. This time she was really angry.
Thomas carried on talking about people who
wanted to be in the school show. Hu decided
not to listen any more.
John asked as quietly as he could. 'Did you
talk to your father about extra English lessons?'
'I can't talk here. It's too noisy. Come to
the library.'
Hu often went to the library at lunchtime
and after school. It was cool. Hu loved to
read, and the librarian, Miss Paula, helped
her find new and interesting books.
John and Hu found a desk in a corner and talked
quietly. Miss Paula let them talk, pretending
not to notice. Hu was her favourite student.
Hu read more than any other student in the
school and often stayed after school to help
her. Miss Paula was pleased to see Hu talking
to such a good-looking boy. She noticed Hu
was looking worried.
'No, I didn't talk to my father. I didn't
see him last night or this morning. An important
businessman is coming to Bangkok tonight,
and my father must prepare for the visit.
But...'
'Yes?' said John.
'But I don't want to talk to him about it.
He worries too much. If he knows about my
bad results, he'll be angry. He'll worry about
it. And Mr Stanyer wants me to pay for the
lessons. My father is not a rich man. I don't
know what to do,' Hu explained.
'I've been thinking. Maybe I can help. You
show me some more of your work and we can
look at it together.'
'But John, that's too kind.'
'Not at all,' said John, smiling. 'Let's do
a deal. I have to start Thai lessons, and
you already speak Thai...'
'I'm not very good,' said Hu.
'Better than me!' said John. 'I'm a complete
beginner. I have to wait after school with
Mary until my mother has finished. We can
study together in here some days.'
Hu thought for a moment. Most afternoons her
mother was out doing small jobs to earn some
extra money. Hu didn't like to return to the
empty flat. And she needed help. John was
very kind.
'OK, that's a good idea. Not today, though,
there's the meeting about the show. And tomorrow
Mr Stanyer wants me to have my first private
lesson. But we can start next week.'
'That's agreed then,' said John. 'Oh, and
give me your phone number. Then if I have
a problem with my homework, I can ring and
ask you for help. Or you can ring and ask
me. Mine's 250 1972. What's yours?'
'255 1970,' replied Hu without thinking. She
felt her face going red. 'But don't phone
too late, my parents... I mean, I go to bed
very early.'
Mrs Patel and John's mother, Mrs Truman, stood
on the stage in the main hall with three other
teachers.
'Sean? If you would be so good as to stop
talking...' Mrs Patel began.
'Hi!' shouted Sean, with a silly look on his
face.
'For the new students, my name is Mrs Patel,
and I am pleased to welcome you all. So many
people want to join the show! If we cannot
give you a singing part, there are many other
jobs... Mrs Truman' - Mrs Patel gestured to
Mrs Truman, who smiled - 'will explain that
in a moment. My job is to be musical director.
I will train you to sing and, I hope, to act
the parts. Mrs Truman will be the producer.
Mrs Truman will explain what she is going
to be doing, and then I will tell you about
how we will choose the actors.'
There were more than thirty students there.
Thomas Kuhlauf was very excited, he couldn't
keep still. Sean was already talking again.
Melanie Gibson was brushing her beautiful
red hair. She had changed out of her school
uniform and was now wearing a pretty pink
dress. 'Quack, quack,' thought Hu. Then she
felt guilty.
Mrs Truman explained the job of the producer
and all the jobs there were for people who
were not singing and acting in the show. 'Making
clothes, lighting, painting things, moving
things, organising, publicity, tickets...'
John knew he couldn't sing or act, but he
loved painting and organising. He would, he
decided, do one of these jobs.
Later they divided into groups. They had two
exercises, one singing and one acting exercise.
Hu sat and read the song through. It was easy.
She loved to sing. When she was not busy,
Hu's mother would teach her to sing. Hu's
mother had studied opera before she married.
When she was happy, Hu's mother would sing
as she did the housework. That was not very
often.
The singing went well. Hu sang simply while
Mrs Patel played the piano. Some of the other
students clapped their hands at the end. John
and Thomas clapped hard. Hu was surprised
when she saw Sean Payne clapping too, and
smiling at her stupidly.
She was even more surprised when she had to
act with Sean. Sean loved to make people laugh,
and he didn't care if he looked stupid. Often
he didn't know when to stop trying to make
people laugh, but this time everything went
well. He had learned his words and he didn't
change anything. He made the other students
laugh, and even Mrs Patel and Mrs Truman smiled.
Hu felt wonderful. Maybe Sean Payne was not
so stupid all the time.
'We think we can decide who will get the major
parts straight away,' said Mrs Patel. 'So,
I will read a list of people I want to stay
behind at five o'clock. The rest of you can
come back, please, next Thursday.'
Mrs Patel read out Hu's name. Hu was delighted.
She was in the show! And so was Thomas, and
Melanie Gibson and ('I don't believe it!'
said Hu to John.), Sean Payne.
It was hard to wait to talk to Mrs Patel,
Hu was so excited.
'You can have the part of Dorothy,' said Mrs
Patel when it was Hu's turn.
'But? But, Dorothy's an American farm girl.
I don't look right. I don't look like an American
girl. I don't speak like an American. Melanie
looks more like Dorothy... I...'
'Please, Hu!' said Mrs Patel, laughing. 'You
sing beautifully. And American girls look
just like you and me.'
Mrs Patel put her head back and laughed. 'I
mean like me when I was your age. American
girls are all different colours and shapes
and sizes and... and you can sing and you
can act.'
'My mother helped me learn to sing, she studied
opera,' Hu said.
'That explains it. And you act very simply
and very well. Melanie...' Mrs Patel paused.
She was searching for words.
'Melanie sings like a duck,' thought Hu, but
she didn't say anything.
'I think Melanie can be your understudy,'
said Mrs Patel, at last.
'Understudy?' Hu didn't understand.
'Yes, someone who can take your place if you
are ill. We call this person an "understudy".
She will learn your part. If, for some reason,
you cannot be in the show, she can be Dorothy.'
Mrs Patel looked at Hu, waiting for her reply.
Hu felt unhappy. 'And if I am in the show?
If I play Dorothy?'
'There are plenty of other parts for Melanie.
Will you take the part?'
Hu waited a few minutes after her talk with
Mrs Patel. She waited to know which part Thomas
had got. Sean waited with her.
As Melanie left the main hall, she turned
suddenly and looked Hu in the eyes. Melanie
had clearly been crying. Her face was white
with anger.
'You! Dorothy!' Melanie laughed. She laughed
too loud. 'Hu Jian Ming, I know what you're
doing! Just you wait! You'll see! I'll get
you!' she was shouting, almost screaming.
'Cool!' said Sean, smiling stupidly.
CHAPTER FIVE
Money worries
Hu was sitting on the balcony of her apartment.
It was evening. She had Lao Mao, the cat,
sitting on her knee, but otherwise she was
alone. The balcony was full of plants in pots.
Her mother loved plants, and filled the apartment
and the balcony with growing things. The balcony
was so full of plants it was difficult to
move. In the family, they called the balcony
'Mother's little jungle'. Hu's father liked
to water the plants in the early morning before
he went to work. He said it helped him relax.
'Stupid!' said Hu to the cat. Lao Mao said
nothing. Hu thought the cat smiled.
Hu was worrying about money.
'Lao Mao, you are lazy, and you don't listen
to me. Sit on your own chair!' Hu put the
cat on another plastic chair and stood up.
She went to the edge of the balcony and looked
across at Bangkok. Bangkok was coming home
from work. Bangkok was trying to come home.
Hu could see the traffic standing still on
the highway. There was the smell of the traffic,
a smell of cooking, a smell of dirt, and a
smell of plants from the balcony and from
the gardens in the Soi below.
'Stupid!' said Hu again, returning to her
chair. How could she pay for her extra English
lessons? She didn't get a lot of pocket money.
Her father was generous but he had said:
'Hu, we have been saving for when you to go
to medical school for a long time...'
'When?' Hu had thought. 'If not when I go.'
But she had said nothing.
'There will be other expenses,' her father
had continued. 'You must save too.'
Mr Stanyer had said he would want the money
after each lesson, twice a week. Without good
results in English, she could not enter the
IB programme. Without the IB, medical school
was a dream.
It was very quiet in the apartment. Hu's mother
was baby-sitting. Hu's mother did small jobs
for people, for neighbours in the apartment
block and for friends.
Hu's father was a good man, but he didn't
understand. He didn't want his wife to work,
but he didn't understand how expensive life
was in central Bangkok. The oil company gave
them a big apartment because he often had
to entertain important people from work. But
he wasn't a rich man.
Once Hu had offered to do work for money.
The answer was no. Her mother was shocked.
'Your education is more important,' she had
said. 'One day you will be a doctor. Then
you will have money. Concentrate on your studies
and your father will be proud of you. Your
father cannot let you work...'
The doorbell rang, waking Hu from her thoughts.
Hu answered it. Marwa stood at the door with
a pile of English books in one hand, a plastic
box in the other, and a big smile.
'Can I come in?' said Marwa.
'Of course,' said Hu. 'My father's still at
work and my mother's baby-sitting.'
It was getting dark in the big empty apartment,
so Hu switched the lights on and cleared the
dining table. Marwa put the books and the
box on the table.
'We've got sweets and we've got English homework!'
she said. 'Which do you want first?'
'Sweets!' said Hu. Mrs Marlati, Marwa's mother,
was famous for her homemade Iranian sweets.
The two friends sat eating sweets and began
the homework. Hu thought the homework was
easy, but explaining the answers to Marwa
made it more interesting.
'Your father always works late,' said Marwa
through a mouth full of sweets, 'like my father.'
Hu sighed. 'Yes, he works late. Tonight he
must meet an important businessman from the
airport. He won't be home before midnight.'
She took another sweet and turned the page
of the textbook. 'He works too hard, smokes
too much and worries too much.'
'My father's the same,' said Marwa.
'I only see him in the morning before school.
Even at the weekends, he must play golf with
important customers. In the morning, he wakes
me up coughing. He's always tired.'
But he's an oil engineer. Very important.
Very rich!' said Marwa.
Hu thought of her mother's little jobs. 'He's
an engineer and he manages the Bangkok office.
It's a good job but... But I wish he didn't
work so hard... Mr Stanyer wants us to do
up to exercise 3, modal verbs.'
Hu tried to explain modal verbs to Marwa.
They talked about their families and ate too
many sweets.
Just before half past nine, the doorbell and
the telephone rang at the same time. Marwa's
driver was at the door. He had come to take
her home. Hu waved goodbye to Marwa and went
to the telephone.
'Hu, sorry. Is it too late? John Truman here.'
'Oh,' said Hu.
'Yeah, good news. They will tell you at school
tomorrow. We're going on a field trip to Khao
Yai National Park.'
'Khao Yai? We? You mean all of year eleven?'
asked Hu.
'Sure. Well, if you want to. It's a geography
and biology field trip. Listen: "The oldest
and largest of Thailand's national parks...,"
sorry I'm reading, "... two hundred and fifty
wild elephants, twenty-five to thirty tigers,
eight hundred species of orchids..."'
'That sounds wonderful. But when? How many
days? Will it be expensive?' Hu was excited,
but she was thinking of money and all the
little jobs her mother had to do. She loved
animals, flowers and trees. And it would be
good to get away from Bangkok. Away from the
dirt and the traffic noise, the smells and
the hurrying crowds. They never went away
at the weekend, her father was always too
busy or resting.
'Let's see. Five days, Monday to Friday, first
week in March, before the heat gets too bad.
Listen...?'
'Sorry, John. Sounds great, but I must go!'
said Hu and she quickly put the phone down.
Her mother was home. 'Who was that?' she asked
quickly.
'John, John Truman,' Hu replied. 'A student
from school. An American boy.' Hu's face was
going red.
'And what was it about?' her mother asked.
'Oh, nothing. Homework. He wanted to know
about, er, geography homework.' Hu didn't
like to lie.
'At half past nine in the evening? Do you
have time to talk to "American boys" all night?
You must study in the evenings if you want
to be a doctor. Have you done the washing
up?'
Hu quietly went to the kitchen. She did not
want to tell her mother about the field trip
to Khao Yai National Park. She was thinking
about how much money the field trip would
cost.
CHAPTER SIX
Lessons in disappointment
All the year eleven students met in the video
room at lunchtime the next day. It was hard
to get a seat and some of the taller students
had to stand at the back. Mr Rodriguez gave
out some information explaining the field
trip and the kinds of activities the students
would have to do.
Hu looked through the information until she
found the part on cost: including everything,
it was six thousand Baht. Hu laughed sadly,
shaking her head. In a low voice she said,
'Stupid!'
Mr Rodriguez suddenly stopped speaking. With
all the students in the video room, it was
getting very hot.
'I'm sorry, Miss Hu, did you have something
to tell us?' he asked, drying his big black
moustache with a handkerchief.
'No... I... sorry, Mr Rodriguez.' Hu felt
embarrassed. Sean Payne laughed at the back.
'May I continue then?' Hu nodded, her face
red with embarrassment. 'Thank you, Miss Hu.
Where was I? Yes...'
Hu was adding up the cost in her head. It
was almost Chinese New Year, an expensive
time for Chinese families. All the presents,
all the food. Hu knew her family couldn't
afford to go home to China for the holiday
this year even if Hu's father was not too
busy. She had heard her parents arguing about
it late one night the week before. There was
no way her father could pay for her to go
on the field trip.
Then Mr Rodriguez put the lights out and switched
on the video. Hu thought it was wonderful.
The jungle and the mountains, the cool waterfalls,
the many colours of the birds. Hu forgot she
was at school.
'Hrrrmmph!' Sean Payne was being an elephant.
Mr Rodriguez stopped the video and switched
all the lights on. Sean was standing using
his arm as the elephant's trunk, while the
boys next to him were laughing.
'Get out, Sean!' shouted Mr Rodriguez. 'You
can come and see me at half past three.' Mr
Rodriguez touched his moustache with his handkerchief
and said something quietly in Spanish. Some
of the students at the back of the classroom
clapped their hands as Sean left the room.
Hu found Mr Stanyer's classroom empty when
she went there at half past three that afternoon.
She waited outside for nearly fifteen minutes
until Mr Stanyer came and opened the door.
His body touched hers as he pushed past her.
He smelled of sweat and tobacco smoke.
'Sorry Hu, I'm a bit late. Had to go to the
teachers' room...' He sat down heavily and
opened his desk, taking out a can of cola
and some textbooks. He pushed his desk back
and put his feet on the desk. He yawned and
turned the pages of the textbook.
'So you spoke to your father, Hu?'
'Mr Stanyer, I don't want my father to know
about these lessons. He worries about my results.
I don't want him to worry. If my results improve,
there won't be a problem.'
Mr Stanyer smiled slowly, his hands on his
bald head. He laughed quietly and smiled.
'That's fine, Hu. This can be our little secret.
Our little secret.' Then he laughed again.
'OK,' he said. 'Let's do something on tenses.
Things you usually do in the past. Page 14,
exercise 3a.' Mr Stanyer handed Hu an old
copy of the students' workbook that went with
their textbook.
Then he settled down with a magazine. Hu couldn't
see the magazine, but Mr Stanyer gave it all
his attention, smiling and laughing as he
turned the pages. He seemed not to know Hu
was in the classroom.
Hu worked through the exercises. At first
they seemed easy. But then she wanted to ask
a question.
'Mr Stanyer?'
'Mmm.' His eyes didn't leave the magazine.
'Is "used to" a tense?'
'Is "used to" a tense?' Mr Stanyer mocked
Hu's voice. 'The answers are at the back of
the book, Hu.'
'Yes, and I've got the answers right. All
right. But it doesn't seem like a tense. It
doesn't change and...'
'So you want to be the expert now?' Mr Stanyer
looked in the drawer in his desk. He pulled
out a grammar book and threw it on the desk
in front of Hu.
'Yeah, it's a kind of tense, er, in the past.
Look it up.' He pushed his chair back and
slowly stood up. 'Listen, I've got to make
a phone call... I'm going to the teachers'
room. I'll be back in five minutes, maybe
ten.' He carefully put the magazine back in
the drawer, locked the desk and left the room.
He didn't go to the teachers' room. Hu saw
him walking through the school gate and across
the road to the Chinese shop.
Hu looked up 'used to' in the grammar book.
The explanation didn't help her. She started
the next exercise.
It was nearly half past four when Mr Stanyer
came back. His face was red and he smelled
more strongly of cigarettes, and, she guessed,
rice whisky.
'Any problems?'
'No, I got all the answers right. But I still
don't understand if "used to" is a tense or...'
'Let's just call it an expression. Listen,
honey, sometimes we just say things a certain
way in English.' Mr Stanyer yawned. Hu said
nothing.
'OK, we've done enough for today,' said Mr
Stanyer.
'We?' thought Hu.
'So... er, that's five hundred Baht. That's
what we agreed?'
Hu didn't argue. That's what Mr Stanyer had
agreed, with himself. With all the pocket
money she had saved and her lunch money for
the last two days, Hu had exactly five hundred
Baht.
'See you on Wednesday,' said Mr Stanyer, counting
the hundred Baht notes and smiling to himself.
But how would she find the money for Wednesday?
How would she stand six more weeks with Mr
Declan Stanyer?
CHAPTER SEVEN
Of rings and lies
The two policemen entered the classroom during
her English lesson. One was fat, his stomach
tight in his brown uniform, the other was
small and thin. They had guns.
'We have come for Hu Jian Ming. She must come
now. She stole a gold ring.'
Before Hu could say anything, the small policeman
roughly took her by the arm and pulled her
towards the classroom door. Marwa started
crying.
'Huuuu...'
Hu started to try and speak. 'You must tell
my father...' But the words wouldn't come
out. She couldn't breathe. What was happening?
Mr Stanyer started laughing. The other children
started laughing. The thin policeman was pulling
her through the classroom door. Marwa was
screaming. Hu couldn't breathe. 'You must
tell my father...'
She was awake, breathing heavily, her heart
beating fast. It was quite dark. Bangkok was
very strange at four o'clock in the morning
because it was so quiet. From time to time,
there was the noise of a motorbike, but even
the building work had stopped until first
light. Where was she?
'I am in my own bed. I am at home. There are
no policemen. I did not steal the ring.' Hu
tried to calm herself. Slowly her breathing
and her heart returned to normal. It was a
dream.
Of course! The ring! Aunty Wang's ring. Aunty
Wang was Hu's mother's cousin. The ring had
belonged to Aunty Wang's mother before she
died. When Aunty Wang went to live in America
with her new husband, she had given the ring
to Hu.
'My husband is a rich man. I will have all
the rings and all the gold I want,' she had
told Hu.
The ring was very old and very valuable. Hu
kept it in a jewellery box her mother had
given her on her sixteenth birthday.
'I can sell it,' Hu told herself. 'Later I
can work and buy another one just like it.
It will just be like borrowing the money.'
Hu decided she would carefully write down
the dates and the amounts she paid to Mr Stanyer
after each 'lesson'. She would only spend
what she needed to. She felt very bad about
the idea, but she couldn't see any other way
out of her situation. It was a long time before
she slept again.
It was Saturday. Hu had told her mother she
was going to the Dusit zoo with Marwa and
Yoshiko. Hu's father was playing golf with
his important visitor that day. Her mother
was finishing a dress for the English woman
in the apartment above theirs. Hu was alone
in the apartment. She made herself a snack
to eat and then started across Bangkok.
It is always easy to find a jewellery shop
in Bangkok, but Hu didn't want to be recognised,
so she travelled to the other side of the
city. The bus journey was long and hot and
uncomfortable - even on a Saturday, the traffic
was very bad. But she had a seat, and she
sat holding tight to the gold ring in its
box, with a mixture of fear and guilt.
She tried three jewellery shops before she
could get a good price. In the third shop,
there was an old Chinese man with two gold
teeth. Hu could argue better in her own language.
The man didn't seem to believe that the ring
belonged to Hu, but she managed to raise the
price. Finally, the man said that she was
robbing a poor old man and disappeared into
the back of the dark shop. He came back with
lots of five hundred Baht notes. He counted
out the sum they had agreed and gave the notes
to Hu. Now she felt like a thief.
Hu buried the notes right at the bottom of
her shoulder bag and walked out into the sunshine.
Hu couldn't go home so soon. She sat at a
tiny table on the pavement and ordered a bowl
of noodles. They were hot and delicious. But
she couldn't eat them. She thought of the
money in the bag at her feet and felt sick
with fear. Bangkok is a safe enough city if
you are careful, but Hu had never had so much
money before. And it didn't feel like her
own money.
After a while, it was time to go home. She
would tell her mother she didn't feel well
and had to come back from the zoo early.
Another lie, but now she had the money for
her lessons.
CHAPTER EIGHT
A proud father
The next few weeks were a little easier. Hu
couldn't stop feeling guilty about selling
her gold ring, and worried about the money
hidden in her jewellery box. She still slept
badly. She spent as little of the money as
she could and wrote down each amount she 'borrowed'.
Hu tried to keep the lessons secret, but her
friends soon learnt about her situation. They
were very good to her.
Lessons! They were not real lessons. Hu learnt
to do the simple exercises Mr Stanyer gave
her from the workbook at the beginning of
the lesson, and then when he went to 'make
a telephone call', she would do her other
homework. She didn't ask questions. 'That's
just how we say things in English,' Mr Stanyer
would say. How she hated that!
And how she hated him, his smell of sweat
and cigarettes, his laziness. She hated the
way he laughed at his magazines, how he sat
with his feet on the desk. But he was too
stupid to worry about. And now that she was
paying for lessons, he was giving her higher
marks.
One day he looked up from his magazine and
found Hu yawning and stretching. She was bored,
and she had not slept well.
'You uncomfortable?' he said. 'These classroom
chairs are uncomfortable. And it's kind of
hot in here.' As usual, there were dark marks
under the arms of his shirt. Mr Stanyer pushed
his hands across his baldhead. He took a deep
breath, smiled, and then said:
'Hu, we don't have to be uncomfortable. We
don't have to have these lessons here. You
could come back to my place in Soi 35. You
could relax there... be more comfortable.'
'No!' said Hu, looking Mr Stanyer directly
in the eye. She said no with such strength,
with so much anger, Mr Stanyer looked as if
she had hit him.
Then he went to make a telephone call. He
never mentioned the idea again.
Hu learnt much more English in the library
with John than with Mr Stanyer. John told
her about his home in America, about his friends
and his family. Hu told him about China, about
the many changes in her life and the lives
of her friends and family. They talked about
Thailand, and of their hopes for their future
lives. John wanted to be an engineer; Hu was
not sure if she wanted to be a doctor or a
singer.
The school show was the best, the most exciting
part of her life at school. She knew her father
would not be happy about her taking part in
the show. 'Your studies must come first. You
won't become a doctor by singing in shows,'
he would say. But when she told her mother,
her mother was delighted and helped her learn
the songs. When she was not doing one of her
little jobs, baby-sitting or making clothes,
Hu's mother came to watch them practising.
She found the music and the style of singing
very different from her own training, but
it made her happy and excited. Afterwards,
Hu would hear her mother singing as she prepared
their supper. Sometimes Hu's mother would
sing her favourite love songs from Anhui opera,
and sometimes she would try the songs from
'The Wizard of Oz' in her strange Chinese
English. It made Hu laugh.
As she had expected, Hu's father was not very
happy about the school show, but he was glad
to see Hu's mother enjoying herself. He pointed
out that Hu needed all her spare time for
studying, but left the decision to her. After
a while, he said nothing. Perhaps he was too
busy and too tired to argue.
All the talk among her friends was about the
field trip to Khao Yai. They talked about
which groups they would join and which activities
they would do together. Hu didn't like to
feel jealous. She had told Mr Rodriguez she
couldn't go because she had to prepare for
the Chinese New Year holiday. Mr Rodriguez
was disappointed. Hu was his star pupil in
biology. Hu said nothing when her friends
were making their plans. She told herself
it was more important to prepare for the selection
tests for the IB. The tests were a week after
the field trip.
One morning, a week before the field trip,
Hu was woken up by the sound of her father
coughing. He was on the balcony outside her
room, watering mother's 'little jungle'. A
few seconds later, he knocked on her bedroom
door.
'Jian Ming, I want to talk to you.'
It sounded important. Hu put on her dressing
gown over her pyjamas and joined her father
at the breakfast table. Her mother was in
the kitchen.
'Father, you're smoking! It's not even seven
o'clock!' said Hu.
'Oh. Sorry.' He put out his cigarette. 'Important
meeting today. Sorry.' He held up some papers.
'What's this?'
Hu could see that it was the information about
the Khao Yai field trip.
'Your mother was looking in your school bag
for your dirty sports shirt,' he added.
'I'm sorry, father.'
'And she found this. Why didn't you tell us
about this?' Hu's father looked disappointed.
'I'm sorry. I... I forgot. It's not important.
I don't want to go.' Hu couldn't look at her
father.
He lit another cigarette without thinking.
Hu said nothing. Her father smoked the cigarette
and then asked her:
'Which is it? You forgot? You thought it wasn't
important? Or you don't want to go?'
'But father, it's so expensive...'
'But Jian Ming, it's so important. It's biology.
If you want to be a doctor, you must be good
at biology. There is always money for your
education. And I know how much you love plants
and birds and animals. You need a break from
Bangkok.' He sighed. 'I know I'm always too
busy to give us a holiday, I'm sorry. My work
is so important.'
'It's too late now. I've told them I cannot
go.'
'You told them you had to prepare for the
Chinese New Year holiday. You know that's
not true.' Her father looked hurt.
'You've spoken to Mr Rodriguez?' asked Hu.
'I have. And it's not too late. Another student
had to drop out. He has to go into hospital
for a small operation.'
Hu's father stood up, checking his jacket
pockets for cigarettes.
'It's all arranged. All paid for. You silly
girl.' He laughed and started coughing. As
he got to the door of the apartment, he shouted
goodbye to Hu and her mother, and then left.
Hu didn't know if she should cry or shout
for joy. Khao Yai National Park! Next week!
CHAPTER NINE
Losing the right path
Hu sat with her feet in the water. It was
hot, but she didn't feel too hot with her
feet in the water. The others were on the
other side of the pool formed by the waterfall.
They were feeding the last of the bread to
some grey fish. What were these fish? Hu wondered.
They could ask Mr Rodriguez when they returned
to the Field Centre.
It was a moment to herself. It was the first
moment to herself for three days, since she
left Bangkok.
Hu sat on the warm rock and put her head back.
She looked up through the trees, up and up
until maybe a hundred metres above her, she
could see bright blue sky among the leaves
and branches. Around her, she could hear water
crashing into the pool and her friends laughing
as the fish fought and jumped for pieces of
bread. From the trees came the sound of birdsong,
and always, never stopping, the continuous
noise of unseen insects. Up here, about one
thousand metres above sea level in the Dongrak
mountains, the air was clean and smelled of
plants and flowers; Hu could taste its freshness.
Her new happiness had been growing since she
left Bangkok. As they had passed Don Muang
International Airport and the last of the
traffic jams, Hu had turned in her seat at
the back of the tour bus and looked back.
She could see the milky orange cloud of dirt
hanging above the tall buildings of the great
city. She could still see the cloud fifty,
even eighty kilometres away.
The Thai students had started singing just
beyond the airport. They sang one of Hu's
favourite pop songs, 'Mae Ben Rae', which
means 'never mind'. It was perfect for her
mood. Mae Ben Rae, never mind money, never
mind Mr Stanyer, the IB tests.
As the Thai students sang, the other students
had joined in. Soon the students in the school
show were singing some of the songs from 'The
Wizard of Oz'. Hu was asked to sing some of
the show's big hit songs and Hu gave her very
best performance. They had sung all the way
to the national park's Field Centre where
they were staying.
Over the next two days, Hu had had very little
time to herself. Mr Rodriguez kept them busy
all day collecting, drawing maps, looking
at different plants and animals and trying
to name them. After supper, the teachers gave
them lectures on the park. The days were long
and tiring, and Hu slept better than she had
for weeks.
Now Hu could hear that Sean Payne had joined
their group by the waterfall. It seemed that
every time Hu looked round he was next to
her. He was too friendly. He wanted to give
her things, a cola, chewing gum, even a cigarette.
(He was always smoking when the teachers were
not looking.) Marwa and Yoshiko were very
good. They knew she didn't want to be alone
with Sean and stayed close to her when Sean
tried to talk to her. She didn't want to be
unkind, but she wanted some time to herself.
Or she wanted time to talk to Marwa or John
by herself. But Sean was always there.
Hu closed her eyes and listened to the music
of the waterfall, and smelled the perfume
of the air. But where was Sean now?
Suddenly there was a scream. It was Sean's
voice. Hu opened her eyes and for a moment
was blind in the brilliant sunshine. 'Stupid!'
she said to herself. Another scream, Sean's,
came from the trees behind her.
'Help! Please help me! I've broken my leg!'
Sean was screaming in English and Thai.
'Sean's in trouble,' said John. 'We've got
to do something!'
'He probably just wants us to go and look
for him,' said Hu.
Another scream.
'Over there,' said Thomas, pointing to the
trees behind Hu. 'We must go and look. We
must stay together.'
'He's probably just being silly,' said Hu,
putting on her walking boots.
Another scream. Thomas ran towards the noise.
The others followed him. When they left the
path, walking was difficult. Sean was somewhere
up ahead. Then the noise stopped. It was cool
by the waterfall, but as soon as they started
into the trees, it was hot. The plants scratched
them and Yoshiko was frightened of snakes.
They came to an open space among the trees,
and stopped to wait for Marwa.
'He's stopped screaming. We must find him!'
said Thomas.
'He was here. I can smell cigarettes,' Hu
said.
'He's just playing games with us,' said Yoshiko.
There was a louder scream. 'Help me! I'm dying!'
The screaming seemed very close.
'This way!' shouted Thomas, and he started
back into the trees. The others followed.
They crossed a stream.
Marwa found it difficult, but John helped
her. They heard Sean calling close by.
They came to another space. Sean was not there.
His calls had stopped for a moment.
'This is stupid,' said Hu. 'It's just a game
for him.'
'I guess...' John began.
'Snake!' screamed Sean.
Thomas was running. The others followed.
The search continued for almost an hour. They
crossed streams, climbed higher and higher.
'Stop!' said Hu. 'This is stupid. Look!' She
bent down and picked up an empty cigarette
packet. 'This is just a stupid game.'
They waited a few moments. John passed round
his water bottle. Nobody spoke.
'Roaaaarrrgh!' A horrible noise came from
behind them. 'Don't you know they have tigers
here?' said Sean, standing up from behind
a bush. He had a can of cola in one hand and
a cigarette in the other.
Sean had not broken his leg. He was smiling.
A moment passed. Thomas spoke first.
'You're an idiot!'
Sean said nothing. Then John spoke.
'I think we're lost!'
CHAPTER TEN
Towards the truth
They looked at each other in silence. Quietly
Marwa began to cry. Sean looked as if he was
going to say something, but Thomas gave him
such an angry look he changed his mind. Sean
began to look in his bag for something.
'What are we going to do?' asked Yoshiko.
She had her arm round Marwa to comfort her.
'We must think,' said Thomas.
'I can phone,' said Sean holding up his mobile
phone.
'Yes, but first we have to have some idea
where we are,' said John. 'We need something
we can tell them to look for.'
'We can only be about an hour's walk from
the waterfall,' said Thomas.
'But which direction?' asked Hu. 'We changed
direction so many times.'
'Sorry,' said Sean. Nobody said anything.
'We could climb to the top of the mountain
and look around?' offered Yoshiko after a
minute.
'No. You would just see trees. The answer
must be down, not up. We have been going up
all day, following the waterfalls. The last
one is at nine hundred and seventy metres,
and we're higher than that,' said John. 'We'll
find the road again if we travel downwards.'
'Yeah, you're right,' said Thomas. 'And the
main road through the park is west of the
waterfalls. The Pak Chong to Prachinburi road
more or less cuts the park in half from north
to south. Were in the eastern half. So we
must walk west and downwards.'
'Don't worry, Marwa,' said Hu. 'We'll find
the path.'
'No!' said Thomas. Sean had a can of cola
in his hand, ready to open it. 'No! Sean,
we must save water.'
'This is cola, Thomas...' said Sean with a
silly smile.
'Don't drink it now, stupid!' shouted Thomas.
'OK,' said Sean. He put the can back in his
bag.
'West is this way, I think,' said Hu. She
was pointing at a thick wall of trees. 'We
might have to go round those trees.'
'Follow me!' said Thomas. 'John, you must
stay at the back with Marwa. And Sean, you
mustn't play any more stupid games.' They
set out behind Thomas. Sean pretended to walk
like a soldier, quietly saying, 'must, mustn't,
must, mustn't' with each step.
It is impossible to walk in a straight line
in thickly forested hill country. Progress
was slow and painful. They often had to stop
and sometimes the boys would argue about which
way was west. Sean and Thomas argued more
and more through the afternoon, and Marwa
looked very tired and frightened.
They stopped by a stream. The boys were washing
the dirt and blood from their arms while the
girls tried to decide which way to try next.
Hu looked at Sean. 'Do you want to make that
phone call now, Sean?'
None of them knew the phone number of the
Field Centre.
'I'll phone my mother at work,' suggested
Sean. Thomas raised his eyebrows and was about
to say something, but Hu was standing next
to him and stepped hard on his foot. Thomas
said nothing.
They waited in total silence as Sean rang.
They all felt happy when someone answered
it. Sean turned his back to them while he
talked very quickly in Thai. Then he started
shaking the phone. He tried to phone again.
They were all looking at him.
'I think the phone is dead. I was talking
to my mother last night for maybe half an
hour.'
'Did you tell your mother what's happened?'
asked John.
'Yeah,' said Sean sadly. 'But I don't think
she believed me. I think she thought I was
making up stories...'
Thomas said something in German. To his surprise,
Sean said something back at him in German.
For a moment, Thomas didn't know what to say.
'You guys!' shouted John. 'That's enough!
We've got to think about stopping. We won't
get any further today.'
'Yes!' said Thomas. 'First we must find a
place. Then we must share some food and water.
We must make a fire.'
'Must, must, always must! Who makes you the
boss? Just because your father's a policeman,'
shouted Sean.
Thomas was much shorter than Sean, but that
didn't stop him. He threw himself at Sean.
Sean easily held him off. Thomas was kicking
and shouting in German.
'My father is Chief Police Officer at the
German Embassy,' shouted Thomas breathing
heavily. 'At least he's not a barman. And
he didn't marry a "dancer" from a bar!'
Sean's face went white. He held Thomas very
tightly by the arms, and lifted him off the
ground.
'Listen, Kuhlauf,' said Sean in a low, angry
voice. 'My father owns a chain of restaurants
in Bangkok, Hua Hin and Rayong.' Sean was
breathing very heavily. Thomas was suddenly
very frightened. 'My mother owned and managed
one of the restaurants when my father bought
it. Now she's company accountant.'
Sean put his face very close to Thomas' face
and said slowly and angrily, 'Don't you ever
repeat that rubbish again!'
There was a moment of total silence. Suddenly
he dropped Thomas. John quickly held Thomas
from behind. Sean and Thomas were both breathing
heavily, staring at each other angrily.
Hu, Marwa and Yoshiko took charge. They decided
to stay where they were, close to water to
wash in and with a few metres space before
the trees closed in. They went to look for
wood, Thomas and John in one direction, Hu
and Sean in the other direction. Yoshiko stayed
with Marwa who was very tired and frightened.
The two of them tried to clear some space
to sit and sleep in.
Men always like making a fire. The three boys
worked hard collecting wood and leaves. They
carefully built the fire and Sean encouraged
a small flame from his cigarette lighter to
catch the dry leaves. As darkness closed in,
they started sharing out what little food
they had. It was clear that Sean and Thomas
had cooled their anger. John tried to persuade
Thomas to apologise to Sean, but Thomas was
too angry or embarrassed. But they did sit
and share a few biscuits and sweets peacefully.
Hu found Sean sitting next to her. John was
sitting next to Thomas, as far away from Sean
as possible, and Marwa was asleep with her
head on Hu's knee. Sean started chatting to
Yoshiko in Japanese.
'How many languages do you speak, Sean?' asked
Hu. 'English from my father, Thai from my
mother,' then in Chinese he said, 'I learnt
Chinese from my mother's mother. I also know
some Japanese and German from the tourists
when I help in one of my father's restaurants
in the school holidays. I like languages.'
Yoshiko and Hu were surprised. Hu said so
in Chinese and Yoshiko in Japanese. Sean smiled
a kind smile.
'Maybe I'm not as stupid as I look.' He was
looking at Hu. She could see his eyes shining
in the light of the fire. 'Maybe you shouldn't
listen to what people say about me. I don't
believe what they are saying about you, Hu.'
Hu sat up quickly. 'And what are they saying
about me?' she said angrily.
'That you're one of Mr Stanyer's little friends.'
Hu was silent a moment. Sean Payne! He always
said the most stupid things. She almost shouted,
'Who says? Who says that?'
'Sorry, Hu, it's true. People are saying it.
Don't be angry. It's rubbish,' said Yoshiko.
Hu was frightened, angry. 'They say??'
'Mostly your understudy, Melanie Gibson, the
singing duck. You should be careful of her,
Hu. She has a nasty way of talking about people.'
'Just you wait! You'll see! I'll get you!'
Hu could hear Melanie's words ringing in her
head. Hu tried to sleep, but she was thinking,
thinking all the time. Marwa's head was heavy
on her knees. Hu couldn't feel her legs.
How long before her parents might hear something
about Mr Stanyer and the English lessons?
Hu looked into the dark. How long?
CHAPTER ELEVEN
A way out?
'Hu?'
Hu could feel him looking at her. It was still
dark. Her leg hurt and she wanted to move
Marwa, who was still sleeping. It was cold
too. Hu was hungry. The fire was finished.
'Shhhhh said Hu, quietly. 'Don't wake Marwa,
Sean.'
'OK.' Sean's voice was quiet. He spoke softly
in Chinese.
'I just wanted to explain. I don't believe
this stuff about Declan Stanyer. I know his
game.' Sean sat closer to her.
'Noroko Ito. Ilse Sphenson. Fatima Rashid.
Darunee Phalavadhana. It's a long list. He's
been doing this since he came to the school.'
'Doing what?' asked Hu.
'His game. Girls. His "private lesson" game.
Rich girls. Pretty girls.'
'I'm not rich, Sean,' said Hu. She could sense
him smiling.
'Maybe not. But he thinks you are. First you
get the bad results, then he says you need
extra private lessons. You don't tell your
parents, do you?'
'No. But Sean, how do you know?'
'He tried it with my sister. She told me,
and I, er, spoke to him. He didn't like that
one little bit.' Sean paused. 'Did he invite
you back to his apartment to be "more comfortable"?
No?'
'Yes, he did. I said no,' said Hu. 'He does
this to other students?'
Sean nodded.
Hu thought for a moment.
'Sean, what can I do?'
There was a moment's silence.
'I don't know, Hu. Do you want me to speak
to him? That man is bad news.' Sean sounded
sad.
'And now Melanie Gibson is saying things about
me?' Hu listened to the music of the stream
close by.
Perhaps Sean nodded. It was too dark to see.
'Sean. Listen...'
They listened. They listened to the music
of the stream. 'Which way does water go?'
asked Hu.
'Hmm. Down. That's called "gravity",' said
Sean.
'Down means out, don't you see? We're sitting
in the Dongrak mountains. Out is the Korat
plateau.'
'I get you,' said Sean. He sounded excited.
'So we follow the stream, the water... we
follow it out of the park. No more turning
in circles, no more arguments about which
way is west.'
Sean sighed. 'So down means out. Cool, Hu!
We just follow the water.' Sean smiled in
the dark.
Now there was some hope.
Dawn in a tropical forest is not a peaceful
matter. Everything that walks, or flies, or
moves, wakes up screaming 'hungry!' It is
like a crazy symphony orchestra tuning up
before a concert. It is a market place, a
building site, an animal city, busy, busy,
busy. The rush hour.
'Wake up, Hu. Breakfast!' shouted Marwa. Marwa
was still very hungry, but she was no longer
the tired and frightened child of yesterday.
Hu had been asleep for perhaps an hour. Marwa
and Yoshiko pulled her to her feet. Marwa
gave Hu some sweets and her last biscuit.
'Hi!' shouted Sean, climbing back from the
stream. 'Your turn!' He and John and Thomas
had washed first. Now it was the girls' turn.
Ten minutes later, they all met at the spot
where the fire had been the night before.
Sean tried to use his mobile phone again,
but it still didn't work.
'Sean told me about your idea, Hu. It's the
only idea we have. We'll follow the direction
of the water - the stream - down and, I hope,
out of here,' said Thomas.
'I'll go first with John. Sean will stay with
Marwa at the back,' said Thomas.
'I'm OK now!' shouted Marwa.
'Don't worry, little lady. We'll be out of
here soon,' said Sean. 'And I'll be right
behind you.'
They began to move slowly down the stream.
It wasn't easy. True, they were going downwards.
But, as they did so, the stream became wider
and steeper. They climbed from rock to rock.
Marwa seemed much stronger today, and Thomas
seemed ready to hurry, to take chances. They
had water from the stream, which they didn't
want to drink, and nothing left to eat. They
all knew that if they didn't find the path
today there would be nothing for them tonight.
Thomas raced ahead, and Sean was very kind
to Marwa, pulling her, sometimes half carrying
her from rock to rock, as they climbed down
the stream.
Towards the middle of the morning, they heard
a helicopter. Sean stopped in the middle of
the stream and spread his arms.
'Mama... I love you!' he called.
'We must make a sign. Make smoke! A fire!'
screamed Thomas from below.
Sean climbed out of the water and collected
some dry wood. Hu helped him. Sean tried to
start a fire, but his cigarette lighter was
wet. When the leaves and wood finally caught
fire, the helicopter had gone.
Thomas said something in German. Then he ran
back to the stream.
'Come on!' he shouted, running through the
moving water of the stream. He was soon out
of sight.
Thomas screamed. There was a crash and the
sound of water.
John and Sean ran to the stream first. There
were two large rocks and then a drop of about
five metres, a small waterfall. In the pool
below, they could see Thomas lying in the
water. He wasn't moving. The water next to
his head on the right side was red.
Sean didn't wait, not for a moment. He threw
his bag onto the bank of the stream and dived
into the pool beside Thomas's body. The others
climbed down the bank to join him.
They found Sean holding Thomas in his arms
by the side of the pool.
'He's OK,' said Sean. 'He's breathing. But
he's unconscious. He hit his head.'
'How did you know the water was deep enough,
Sean?' asked Yoshiko.
'I didn't,' said Sean.
There was a deep cut on Thomas's head. He
seemed to be asleep.
'John, you take my bag. I'll take Thomas.'
Sean lifted Thomas onto his shoulders. Thomas
seemed to weigh nothing.
Sean carried Thomas for another two hours
before they found a road. It was made of earth,
but wide enough for a car. They stopped. Sean
gently put Thomas down in the grass beside
the track. The others sat or lay by the road.
They were exhausted. Soon they heard the sound
of an engine. A lorry stopped about a hundred
metres in front of them. Hu stood up and started
to wave.
A tiny man in a grey uniform jumped down from
the lorry. He pulled out a gun and pointed
it in the air, shooting the gun and screaming
and laughing.
'What's he saying?' asked Marwa.
'He says we are the BIA students that got
lost,' said Sean. 'He says it's OK! There
are helicopters. Television. Television? This
guy is crazy,' Sean was laughing. The little
man climbed back into his lorry and drove
close to them. 'He says to climb in,' said
Sean.
Hu sat in the back of the oil company car.
She was half-asleep. Her father sat next to
her.
'Hu, I'm so glad you're safe. When your friend
Sean made that telephone call, it was on the
Channel 7 television news. We've been so worried.'
The car moved quickly along the highway back
to Bangkok.
'Please don't worry, father,' said Hu, sleepily.
'You're safe now. We'll soon be home. Oh,
and Hu?' Hu's father said softly.
'Hmm...?' said Hu. She was falling asleep.
'One piece of good news. Your Aunty Wang the
one who gave you the ring? She's coming to
stay with us.'
But Hu was already asleep.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Nothing but the truth
Hu and John met in the library after lunch.
Hu couldn't help crying.
'But Hu, I knew Stanyer was asking a lot for
his private lessons. But you sold your Aunty's
ring!'
'It was my ring!' cried Hu. 'But I didn't
know what to do.'
Miss Paula looked over her glasses and coughed
quietly. She was very worried about Hu. Since
she had come back from the field trip, she
had seemed unhappy.
'When does your aunt come, Hu?' asked John.
'Sunday. And Stanyer wants two more lessons
before the English test for the IB on Friday.'
Hu tried to stop crying.
'And from what Sean says, it's what he always
does. Did you speak to the other girls he
talked about?'
'I feel too stupid. I don't know what to say?'
'But Hu, what about Darunee Phalavadhana?
Her father's Wiwat Phalavadhana. He's an important
official in the Ministry of the Interior.
If he finds out... My mother knows him. Perhaps
I could speak to her?' John offered.
'But what can you say? "Are you one of Stanyer's
little friends?" Like Melanie is saying about
me?'
'I don't know, Hu. I think you've got to tell
someone about it. The story is coming out
already. You need to tell your side of the
story.'
Hu covered her face with her hands and cried.
'But I can't! Who can I tell?'
'My mother?' suggested John. 'She knows you
from the school show... and she likes you.
She knows there's nothing wrong with your
English.'
'No!' Hu had raised her voice. Miss Paula
looked across at them. 'I'm sorry, John, I
need to be on my own.' She got up quickly.
'I need to go and wash my face.'
John stayed in the library for a few minutes
after Hu had left. He tried to think. Eventually,
he made a decision. He decided to tell his
mother, even if Hu wouldn't like it. He felt
sad because he didn't want to do anything
behind Hu's back, but he couldn't see any
other way to help her.
Mr Riding, the school counsellor, spoke to
Hu as she hurried across the schoolyard from
the library. He fixed Hu with his hard blue
eyes and smiled.
'What's the hurry, Hu?' His stare seemed to
look right into her mind. 'You've been crying.'
Hu nodded silently. Mr Riding frightened her.
People said he could have power over you with
his eyes. His job was to counsel students
with 'problems', but he seemed to find problems
when people didn't even know they had them.
'I've been watching you recently. You seem
worried and unhappy a lot of the time, and
I've seen you crying several times. I think
we need to talk. Come to my office.'
'But Mr Riding, I have classes...'
Mr Riding stared at her hard. Then he turned
and walked to his office. Hu followed, her
head down to hide the tears.
From the library window, John saw Mr Riding
and Hu entering Mr Riding's counselling office.
He picked up his books and half ran to his
mother's office.
'Sit down, Hu, and try and relax,' said Mr
Riding.
'Relax?' thought Hu. 'Does he think I'm stupid?'
She sat very straight on the edge of a low
armchair. Mr Riding went to the window, turned
and looked down at Hu. He was a tall man in
his fifties with red hair which was turning
white.
'Do you mind if I smoke?' he asked.
Hu did mind if he smoked, and it was against
school rules. Mr Riding got out his pipe and
started to light it.
'No, go ahead,' said Hu.
'Like I said, I've been very worried about
you for some time. Some of the other teachers
have said that you're unhappy. How are things
at home?'
'Fine,' said Hu quietly.
'You get on with your parents? I mean, you
talk about things with them?'
'Yes.' Mr Riding waited, staring at her. Hu
felt uncomfortable. 'I... I do housework with
my mother and she helps me with my singing...'
'But can you talk about serious things with
her?'
Hu said nothing.
'What about your father?'
'He's always very busy. We talk sometimes
in the mornings.'
'Do you talk about important things, Hu?'
Mr Riding left the window and sat down heavily
in front of her. 'I mean, you're growing up,
Hu?' he said very quietly, never letting his
hard blue eyes leave hers.
Hu held her hands very tightly together and
looked away.
'I understand you've been seeing a lot of
Mr Stanyer recently.'
'He's been giving me extra classes,' said
Hu.
'Look at me, Hu.' Hu tried. 'Do you like Mr
Stanyer?'
'No!' shouted Hu, looking straight at Mr Riding.
'Relax!' said Mr Riding, with a false laugh.
He paused. 'It's not so unusual for a young
woman of your age to be... to be attracted
to an older man, a man in an... an important
position.' Mr Riding smiled to himself.
Hu couldn't breathe, she was so angry. She
decided not to speak.
'Uh huh,' said Mr Riding, standing up again
and walking towards the window. 'Does your
father know about these, er, "extra lessons",
Hu?'
'No. I...'
'Hu,' said Mr Riding, 'are you scared of your
father? Does he shout at you? Has he ever
hit you?'
That was when Hu could no longer keep her
anger inside. Suddenly she started crying,
and could not stop. Somehow, she told Mr Riding
the whole story.
At the end of the interview, Mr Riding put
his arm round her and led her to the door.
'What you've said is very serious. These are
very serious things to say about a teacher.'
Hu tried to move away from him.
'But...'
'And I'm not sure you completely understand
your own feelings about this man, Hu.' He
smiled. 'But don't worry. I think I can sort
this out. But we'll need to talk about this
again. In the meantime, I shall have to discuss
this with my colleagues.'
Hu felt her stomach turn to ice.
'Now, off you go back to class, Hu. And try
not to worry.'
Hu didn't go back to class. She went to the
main office and told the school nurse she
was feeling ill and then walked towards the
school gate. She met Mrs Patel carrying a
pile of music.
Are you going home, Hu?' asked Mrs Patel.
'What about the show? We have a rehearsal
after school. Are you OK?'
'I'm sorry, Mrs Patel, I...' Hu started crying
again.
'It is all right now, my dear, Melanie can
take your place. She took your place when
you were in Khao Yai. She is getting much
better. But you must not miss any more, or
I'll have to let her take the part of Dorothy
in the show.'
Hu ran. She ran home, blinded by tears. She
let herself into the empty apartment, locked
herself in her room and threw herself upon
her bed, crying.
Mrs Truman, John's mother, was late home.
She had been looking at Mr Stanyer's test
records in the main school office and making
telephone calls. She said nothing to John
and Mary when she entered her apartment, but
went straight into her study and closed the
door. She picked up the telephone.
'Can I speak to Wiwat Phalavadhana... Wiwat?
Is that you?'
The telephones were busy in Bangkok that night.
It was the telephone ringing which woke Hu
a little later. She had cried herself to sleep.
'Hello?' she said, her voice dry with crying.
'May I speak with Mr Hu An Yuan? It's Mr David
Riding here from the Bangkok International
Academy.'
Hu's heart stopped. 'It's Hu here. Father
is still at work. Do you have his number?'
And your mother's not there? OK. I'll phone
him at work.' He paused. 'Hu, are you still
there?'
Hu was thinking, 'What can I do?'
'Hu, I should tell you there will be a meeting
tomorrow at twelve o'clock. The things you
told me about Mr Stanyer are very serious.
You can't just say those things about a teacher.'
'But, Mr Riding, you were counselling me.
I trusted you!' cried Hu.
'My main responsibility is to the school,'
said Mr Riding. 'Just make sure you and your
father come to the meeting. Twelve o'clock.'
Hu made herself a cup of tea. She was too
tired to cry any more. What could she do?
The phone rang again. It was John.
'Sorry, Hu, I wanted to phone you earlier,
but my mother's been using the phone for hours.
Are you OK? You weren't in class this afternoon,
and I saw you with Mr Riding. What does he
want?'
Hu quickly explained about the meeting tomorrow.
What could she do?
John's answer was simple. 'Tell your parents
the truth. Tell them everything. Tell them
the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but
the truth. That's all you can do.'
That was all she could do. Nothing but the
truth. Hu decided she would tell the truth.
The truth, the whole truth, and nothing but
the truth.
She could hear her father and mother's voices
on the landing outside the apartment and a
key in the lock of the entrance door.
The truth, the whole truth, and nothing but
the truth.
Later that night, much later, Verity Truman
drove back to the school. She went to the
main office and took the master keys to the
classrooms. Quietly she let herself into Mr
Stanyer's classroom and tried the drawer of
his desk. Locked, as she expected.
'God forgive me!' she said under her breath.
She took a knife from her pocket and opened
the locked drawer.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The moment of truth
In an office in the Upper School building,
Verity Truman was sitting, staring at her
telephone.
'Come on, Wiwat. Come on!' She looked at her
watch again. Nearly twelve o'clock.
Meanwhile, in another part of the school,
Hu and her mother and father were waiting
outside the principal's office. They could
hear voices from inside. Hu and her mother
and father said nothing.
Hu thought about her parents. They had been
surprisingly calm when she had told them her
story. Her mother had been unhappy about Aunty
Wang's ring. 'It's been in the family for
a long time!' she had said. 'Your Aunty Wang
had it, her mother, and now you!'
But her father didn't think it was so very
important. 'Aunty Wang had so many jewels,
she won't notice,' he had said. Then, very
sadly, he added, 'Hu, it was your ring, and
your decision. You are almost an adult, a
young adult. Now this is your problem, your
responsibility. It was yours to sell. But
you should not have sold it secretly.'
Hu's father had seemed sad, not angry, Very
carefully, he had questioned Hu for every
detail of her problems with Mr Stanyer. Like
a good lawyer, he had got the whole story
from her - he had even made her show him the
book where she had written down the dates
of the classes and the money she had paid
Mr Stanyer.
'But why didn't you tell me?' he had asked.
'Because you want me to be a doctor so much,
and with bad results in English, they won't
let me do the IB. I didn't want to disappoint
you, father.'
It was late when Hu's father was satisfied
that he had the whole story. He told Hu to
go to bed, but before she left, she asked
him.
'Father, do you believe me?'
Hu's father didn't answer immediately.
'I want to believe you,' he said at last.
'You wanted to improve your results, so you
did extra lessons. That is not a bad thing,
although you should have told us. But these
are terrible things you say about Mr Stanyer.
I want to believe you, but there have been
too many lies, and too many secrets. And I
haven't met Mr Stanyer yet. I want to believe
you, but I must decide tomorrow in the meeting.
Now, good night, little one.'
Mr Grisman stood very tall and serious in
his black suit and Cambridge University tie.
He stood at the door of his office and asked
Hu and her parents to come in.
'Do sit down. Let me introduce you,' Mr Grisman
said.
Sitting at the long table in Mr Grisman's
very grand office were three other men in
suits. By the door Mr Stanyer sat, staring
at nothing.
Hu and her mother and father sat down at the
table. Mr Grisman took his seat opposite Mr
Stanyer and the Hu family. On his left Mr
Riding sat, leaning back and playing with
his empty pipe. On his right was Khun Preecha,
chair of the Board of Governors. He was a
tall Thai man with grey hair and he looked
at Hu steadily with sad, intelligent eyes.
He didn't smile.
Mr Grisman continued in his important voice.
'This is a very serious matter, very serious
indeed. Your daughter has said some very serious
things about our Mr Stanyer. Your daughter's
behaviour is quite unacceptable. She has deliberately
tried to harm him,' Mr Grisman raised his
voice, and the good name of the Academy itself.'
He paused. Khun Preecha looked embarrassed.
Hu looked at her mother and father. Her mother
looked pale and frightened. Her father's face
showed no emotion at all. He simply sat and
stared at Mr Grisman without expression.
Mr Grisman continued. 'I have invited Khun
Preecha to be here because we must decide
if, because of the things she's said about
Mr Stanyer, Hu can continue to study at the
Academy.'
Hu's father said nothing, and the expression
on his face didn't change. Hu's mother was
looking down, afraid to meet Mr Grisman's
eyes. Mr Stanyer was trying not to smile.
Hu closed her eyes.
In her office, Verity Truman was walking up
and down. She picked up the telephone to see
if it was working and quickly put it down
again. 'Wiwat, where are you? They must have
started by now!' she said to herself.
'Now,' said Mr Grisman, 'we must consider
just exactly what Hu Jian Ming has said about
Mr Stanyer.'
Mr Stanyer nodded, but he looked uncomfortable.
'Firstly, that he has been giving her private
lessons for money in the school itself, outside
of school hours. This is clearly untrue. That
would be a very serious matter indeed. Mr
Stanyer has told me that he simply wished
to give Hu some extra work after class, a
very kind and generous offer on his part.
Of course, no money was involved.'
Hu's mouth fell open. Hu's father's face didn't
change. Mr Grisman hurried on.
'Secondly, she says that Mr Stanyer gave Hu
bad results in order to persuade her to take
these "private lessons". A very serious matter.'
Mr Grisman looked at Hu angrily. 'You are
a student, Miss Hu; Mr Stanyer is a teacher,
a professional.'
Still Hu's father's face didn't change.
'Thirdly,' Mr Grisman continued, 'that on
one occasion Mr Stanyer invited her back to
his apartment for further lessons and "to
be more comfortable".' Mr Grisman looked at
Hu's parents angrily. 'I hope you realise
just how serious this is?'
There was a long silence. Hu's father stared
back at the school principal. He said nothing.
'And lastly, she says that other female students
have been in the same situation. We needn't
discuss that. There have been no other complaints.'
There was another long silence.
'Now, Hu Jian Ming,' said Khun Preecha, softly.
'What have you got to say for yourself?' He
looked at her in a kind and interested way.
Quietly and with dignity, Hu's father spoke.
He looked first at Khun Preecha and then at
Mr Grisman.
'Principal, my daughter has told me about
the things that happened with Mr Stanyer.
I will try to explain her point of view.'
The men on the other side of the table looked
at each other. Mr Grisman, Declan Stanyer
and David Riding seemed to be smiling. Khun
Preecha was not. He turned to look at Hu Jian
Ming. His eyes didn't leave hers.
Verity Truman looked at her watch again. She
reached for the phone. 'May I speak to Wiwat
Phalavadhana?' she asked. 'Left his office?...
When?... Coming here?... No, no. Thank you,
thank you.' She replaced the phone. She placed
her hands together and made a prayer. 'Please,
please don't let the traffic be too bad!'
Hu's father spoke very well, but the three
men facing him didn't seem to believe him.
He showed them the book Hu had used to write
down the times and money for her private lessons.
Suddenly Mr Riding sat forward.
'Principal, may I have that?' Mr Grisman gave
it to him. 'Hmph!' He laughed briefly. 'This
is pure teenage story telling.' He laughed
some more. Mr Riding's laugh was not a happy
or a funny laugh.
'It's not unusual for teenage girls to have
strong feelings for older men, particularly
men in an important position. A teacher perhaps.
Hu makes up a story about Mr Stanyer giving
her bad results because she doesn't like the
truth.
The truth is that her results in English just
aren't good enough. And she can't tell her
father because she's afraid of him.'
Hu's father showed emotion at last. He went
very red in the face.
'And then...' Mr Riding spoke slowly, smiling.
'And then we have the invitation back to Mr
Stanyer's apartment.' He turned and looked
at Hu. 'Would you like Mr Stanyer to invite
you back to his apartment?'
Hu looked at Mr Stanyer. He was smiling back
at Mr Riding. She looked at her father. She
had never seen him so angry. Khun Preecha
was not smiling. He was looking down; she
couldn't meet his eyes.
'At last!' said Verity Truman looking up.
Wiwat Phalavadhana was standing in the door
of her office, holding up his bag. He was
a small, bright-eyed man of about forty, well-dressed
and with a proud and happy smile.
'I have it, Verity!' he said.
'Let's go!' They hurried out of her office.
'I think we must make a decision,' said Mr
Grisman. 'And this is it. Mr Riding has shown
that Hu Jian Ming has some very serious problems.
I think it is these problems which have led
her to say these things about our friend and
colleague, Mr Stanyer.' Mr Riding nodded.
Then the door of the principal's office opened.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
A path to the future
'Mrs Truman!' said Mr Grisman angrily. 'I
am in an important meeting. I...' He stopped.
He was embarrassed. He didn't want the chair
of the school's Board of Governors, Khun Preecha,
to see him shouting at his head of Upper School.
Then he noticed the person standing behind
Verity Truman.
It was Khun Wiwat Phalavadhana. Mr Grisman
knew how important he was. Wiwat gave Mr Grisman
a very warm smile.
'I...' Mr Grisman began again. 'I'm sorry.
This is a very important meeting about one
of our teachers.'
'That's what we want to talk to you about,'
said Verity Truman. 'I think... we're sure
that what Hu Jian Ming has been saying about
Mr Stanyer is true.'
Khun Preecha stared at Mrs Truman. He was
listening carefully.
'Surely there must be some misunderstanding,'
said Mr Grisman. 'But come in, come in.'
Verity and Wiwat entered the office.
We don't think so. We don't think Hu has misunderstood
at all,' said Verity, opening her bag and
bringing out some papers. 'And other people
don't think so either. There are other students
involved, female students. I've spoken to
their parents and some of the students too.
Mr Stanyer's little game has been going on
for some time...'
'Stories, Verity,' said Mr Riding. 'Teenage
stories made up by teenage girls. They don't
understand their own feelings, they talk together...
Then they make up some story. If one girl
tells a story, if six girls tell a story,
it's still a story.' He looked at the principal.
Mr Grisman looked nervous.
'They're all telling the same story, Mr Riding,'
Verity Truman threw the papers down on the
table in front of the principal. 'And I've
been checking the results of the students
Mr Stanyer has been giving "private lessons"
to. They all had good results until they came
to his class, and the older ones have had
good results since they left his class. I
think he's been changing the results... downwards.'
'But Mrs Truman, you're not an English teacher.
You are attacking a colleague...' Mr Grisman
was very angry.
'And the girls all tell the story about being
invited back to his apartment to be "more
comfortable".'
'A story,' said Mr Riding, but he seemed less
certain now.
'Perhaps I can speak now?' said Wiwat Phalavadhana,
taking some papers from his case. He gave
them to Khun Preecha who nodded his head in
thanks. The papers were in Thai. 'Mr Stanyer
does not have permission to work in Thailand.'
A small administrative problem, Khun Wiwat.
I was not responsible for giving Mr Stanyer
the job,' Mr Grisman said.
'Mr Stanyer asked for permission to work in
Thailand about three months before he joined
the Academy,' Wiwat said. 'He wanted to work
for a small private school - Audio English
- on Siam Square. There was a problem. I telephoned
the director of Audio English. He told me
they had checked Mr Stanyer's qualifications
back in the USA...'
Mr Grisman looked at his hands.
'... and found that there was no student called
Mr Declan Stanyer at Ohio State University.
No record. They didn't believe he was qualified.
Since then Mr Stanyer has been coming in and
out of Thailand on tourist visas every few
months.'
Mr Grisman was shaking his head. 'I was not
responsible for giving Mr Stanyer a job. My
head of Upper School, Dr Nyondo, gave him
the job. But surely it's an administrative
problem?' said Mr Grisman, looking at Wiwat.
'It's the law, Mr Grisman,' said Khun Preecha,
quietly.
'And I think you'd better see these,' said
Verity. She handed Mr Grisman a large brown
envelope. 'I found them in Mr Stanyer's desk
drawer.'
'You've been looking in the drawer of his
desk, Mrs Truman?' Mr Grisman was shocked.
He took the envelope and pulled out a pile
of magazines.
Mr Grisman was silent for a moment. His face
went white. Everyone was looking at him as
he looked at the magazines. He opened one
of the magazines and shut it again quickly.
He shut his eyes. Then he stood up. He screamed:
'Mr Stanyer!'
But Mr Stanyer wasn't there. His chair was
empty. The door of the principal's office
was open.
Mr Stanyer had left them.
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
The right career
Hu found her parents standing outside the
school hall with Verity Truman and the principal,
Mr Grisman. It was a warm night. The summer
was coming. Hu was still wearing her make
up and her costume, her special clothes as
Dorothy. Hu felt wonderful, the show was a
success!
As she came closer to the group of adults,
she could see that Mr Grisman was talking
very quickly and waving his arms.
'Just disappeared! Three weeks now, and no-one's
seen him. Of course the police are still interested.
But I had no idea! I was away when he was
given the job. The head of Upper School then,
Mr Nyondo, had made the arrangements. And
of course, the school will pay back the money
Hu spent on the, er...' Mr Grisman laughed
nervously. 'The "private lessons". But your
daughter was wonderful, wonderful. A Chinese
Dorothy!' Mr Grisman seemed to find this very
funny.
'Wonderful!' said Verity Truman, taking Hu's
arm and smiling warmly.
Sean and Thomas joined the group. Sean was
also still in costume and make up.
'Sean, you were wonderful!' shouted Verity.
Everyone was talking at once. John Truman
and his sister, Mary, joined them. Marwa and
Yoshiko joined the group. They all told Hu
and Sean how wonderful the show had been.
'Hu, I'd like you to meet someone,' said Verity.
A tall Thai woman in a lovely silk dress came
over and joined the group. Hu's mother admired
the woman's dress. Hu's father simply stared.
Hu was embarrassed.
'This is Dr Irene, Director of the Bangkok
Operatic Society,' said Verity.
'Is this the star? Hu Jian Ming?' said Dr
Irene. 'I thought your performance was wonderful,
Hu. You sing beautifully. Have you had any
training?' Hu introduced Dr Irene to her mother.
They soon began talking about opera together.
Hu took the opportunity to speak to Thomas.
She hadn't seen him since the Khao Yai field
trip because he had been in hospital.
'Thomas, I'm sorry you couldn't be in the
show,' said Hu. 'Are you OK now?'
'Yes, thanks to him,' said Thomas. He pretended
to hit Sean. Sean pretended to fall over.
'I don't like hospital. Too many doctors.'
Hu's mother came towards them.
'Dr Irene wants you to sing with the Operatic
Society, Hu,' Hu's mother said in an excited
voice. 'And she's a professional singer!'
'I'm a semi-professional singer,' said Dr
Irene. 'I'm a professional doctor.'
'She's the senior doctor at the Pattana Clinic,
Hu,' said Hu's father. He was full of pride
for his daughter. 'She wants you to sing in
their new show.'
'Do you like Mozart, Hu?' asked Doctor Irene.
'Our next show at the Operatic Society is
a Mozart opera.'
Hu looked at Dr Irene.
'Well?' said Dr Irene.
Then Hu looked at her father.
'A singer and a doctor?' she said to her father,
smiling. 'Or a doctor and a singer?'
Her father just smiled, and smiled.
- THE END -