CHAPTER ONE
Confucius - the great Chinese philosopher
551 BCE-479 BCE
He who learns but does not think is lost.
He who thinks but does not learn is in great
danger.
Real knowledge is understanding that we actually
know very little.
***
I was born a very long time ago - the story
of my life was not written down until a long
time after my death, so many of the facts
are uncertain.
But here I will tell you what was believed
about my life and the events that shaped my
thinking.
I was born in China in the summer of 551 BCE
- nobody can agree on the exact date and naturally
I was too young to remember it myself.
I was born in the village of Zou, in the state
of Lu, near present-day Qufu in Shandong Province.
My father was from an aristocratic family
of warriors - brave, experienced fighters
- and he died when I was three years old.
This is not surprising when you know that
he was about forty years older than my mother.
Despite his family background, my father left
us little money - the family had lost their
fortune some time before - and we were often
hungry.
In Shandong Province, the winters were extremely
cold, and just staying alive was difficult
at times.
I managed to bring in some money by working
as a shepherd - looking after sheep - and
I also took care of a local farmer's cows,
so we did not starve.
My mother did her best to educate me and she
taught me many fine lessons about life.
The hours I spent with the animals gave me
the chance to think about life and what made
it good.
I asked myself about how we should live, what
was fair and unfair and how people should
live together.
As I grew older and became a teenager, these
questions became all the more important to
me.
When I was 19 years old, I met a girl called
Qi Guan.
Within a short time we had got married and
by the time I was 20, we had started our family.
After the birth of our son, King Li, we went
on to have two more children but our marriage
was not a happy one.
When I was 23, my mother died which affected
me deeply for the next three years.
After my mother's death, I started studying
philosophy.
Already, one of my 'life' questions had been
answered - as a family we learnt to understand
each other's emotional needs.
However, as I had a wife and children and
all the extra costs that came with a family,
I had to make sure that our practical needs
were met as well as our emotional ones.
I needed to make some more money.
Because I could read and write, and many people
at that time could not, I found a job as a
clerk - keeping records and doing the accounts
- for the Duke of Lu, the ruler of the state.
Lu was a powerful man who spent every day
making decisions about other people's lives.
Some people thought he was fair while others
felt that he was against them.
According to the way each person had been
treated, I saw happiness, sadness and anger
in their faces.
Understanding how much we are affected by
the things that people say and do, I developed
my Golden Rule - you should not do to others
what you would not like them to do to you.
Each day at work, watching how people made
decisions, I formed my views.
The solutions to the questions that I asked
myself were tried and tested each day and
people came to respect me.
I enjoyed working hard and I tried to be reliable,
both of which were noted, and I was promoted.
***
I lived during what became known as the Spring
and Autumn Period in Chinese history.
The country consisted of many small states
that were constantly fighting for power.
Chinese society was going through many changes
as traditional values were challenged.
There was tension and stress all around me
and I wanted to find a way in which we could
live in harmony - a state of peaceful cooperation.
I had very clear views on how people should
behave towards each other.
Everyone had a specific place in society and
according to where they fitted in, they had
different roles to play and had different
duties that they were responsible for.
Taking this a step further, I believed that
there were five different types of relationships
in the world.
The first was between ruler and subject - the
person living under the authority of the ruler.
The second was that between father and son.
The third was between elder brother and younger
brother.
The fourth was between husband and wife, and
the last was between friend and friend.
Apart from the last type, all the others involved
one person having authority over another.
The person who was not in the superior position
of authority had to obey and respect the person
who was, and the one with all the power had
a duty to be responsible for and kind to the
other.
In my language, I called this duty to be a
loving person ren.
***
In 518 BCE, I left my job and spent my time
reading and teaching.
My aim was to encourage and motivate my students,
not just to tell them what was right and wrong.
It didn't matter to me who my students were
or what social class they belonged to, I just
loved teaching.
This was unusual because at that time, education
was something only the rich had access to.
My approach seemed to be popular because it
wasn't long before I had a large number of
followers - people who supported me and believed
in what I was saying.
I decided to travel to the imperial capital
of China, Lo-yang, so that I could learn about
the customs and traditions of the empire.
Then, in 517 BCE, when I had come back, the
state of Lu was involved in war and I left
again, along with the Duke of Lu, and went
to a neighbouring state called Qi.
Here I learnt about music.
The next period of my life was spent with
my followers and I was also a teacher.
At the age of 51 in 500 BCE, I became the
Justice Minister of the state.
This was a job that required balance between
the law and politics and I saw myself not
as an inventor of the law but a messenger
of it.
In each case I listened to, all the facts
had to be collected, and then interpreted
and applied.
I believed that having a moral viewpoint,
rather than just following the law, was vital.
People would ask me if we needed laws.
My answer was that if people always behaved
well to each other, then that would be enough,
and no, it was not necessary to have laws.
But people can be greedy and unfair, wanting
more than their fair share, in which case,
society cannot function without laws.
Another one of my beliefs was that we should
appreciate our ancestors because without them
we would not be here.
I thought that it was vital to show respect
for our living elders and family members,
because without them, we would be alone.
For me, the basis of a strong community was
helping others, in the hope that they would
help you in return.
Life is a series of choices, choices which
can benefit some people and disadvantage others.
But it can be difficult to put the needs of
others before the things we ourselves want.
I believed that one of the keys to happiness
was to understand other people and their needs.
Another key was to be virtuous and by that,
I mean behaving in an honest and moral way.
However, it is much easier to be virtuous
in thought than it is in practice.
For example, nobody wants to find themselves
in the position where they may lose other
people's respect.
This may happen if you make a stupid mistake.
To avoid looking stupid, we sometimes try
to hide the mistake we made and in the process
we make more mistakes.
I always thought that it was better to be
honest and admit making the first mistake.
In this way, not only do we avoid making the
original situation worse, but also we can
learn and improve, and make fewer mistakes
in the future.
But to do this, you have to get to know yourself.
Knowing yourself is the first step in understanding
other people.
Without this first step, you will not be able
to live with other people in a calm and pleasant
way.
As well as asking me about the necessity of
laws, people around me were curious about
religion.
Did we need to have religion in our lives,
they asked me.
My answer was that I did not find religion
logical.
All religions have ideas of what is good and
bad, and often the religious rules as to what
is allowed and what is not allowed are not
flexible enough.
Society changes but these rules stay the same.
Another aspect of religion that I had difficulty
with was the existence of a god.
Was it possible that there was one god only,
and that this god had all the answers?
I doubted it very much.
What I didn't doubt was the need for some
kind of belief system, but I didn't know what
form it should take.
In contrast, I truly believed in democracy.
At any one time, there can only be one ruler
but it should be the people who decide who
is going to govern.
Cruel and unfair rulers can then be removed
from power.
I saw leadership as being a gift, not an absolute
right, and I believed that the person given
the honour of ruling should be a virtuous
person at all times.
If they do not behave in a correct, ethical
way, then people will rebel and choose a new
leader.
I knew that this system would work well in
a small place where everyone knew each other,
but I was not sure if it could be applied
to somewhere much larger.
How could a ruler communicate his beliefs
and rules in an area where great distances
had to be covered?
If his word was not widely known, how could
it be supported?
If a leader was not supported, he could not
be respected, and without respect, his future
was at risk.
Virtue, for me, was the all-important characteristic
for a leader.
If people were ruled by laws and were punished
when they broke them, they would try to avoid
the punishment but would not change their
behaviour.
However, if a ruler was a virtuous person
and ruled by example, that is, by always behaving
in a moral and ethical way, then people would
change their 'bad' behaviour and would start
to be virtuous, too, without needing to be
punished.
I stayed in my position as Minister of Justice
in the state of Qi for four years and in that
time, I was promoted to Prime Minister, but
due to serious political disagreements, in
495 BCE I decided to leave both my job and
the state of Qi.
I travelled, going from one region to another,
always in the company of my followers.
I talked to people wherever I went, hoping
that some of my principles would be adopted
by them.
I was especially hopeful that rulers would
lead their people based on a system of virtue,
but I did not see many examples of this.
In 483 BCE, I returned to the state of Lu
and continued my teaching.
In 479 BCE, when I was 72, I died.
My followers treated me as if I had been their
father, and as was the custom at the time,
mourned me for three years.
After my death, my followers started to write
down some of my theories and they produced
a publication now known as the Analects.
My beliefs could now be taught by others to
later generations of students.
In this way, the philosophical school of thought,
Confucianism, was born.
The Life of Confucius
551 BCE Confucius was born in the village
of Zou in the Chinese state of Lu, near present-day
Qufu, Shandong Province.
548 BCE When Confucius was three, his father
died.
He was raised by his mother, in poverty.
532 BCE Aged 19, he married Qi Guan and they
had a son and two daughters.
He worked as a shepherd, cowherd, clerk and
book keeper.
Due to his ability to read and write, he secured
a job with the Duke of Lu, as a clerk.
528 BCE His mother died and he spent the next
three years in mourning.
During that time, he studied philosophy.
He wanted to create harmony among people in
his home country of China which was in conflict
and fighting many wars.
519 BCE Confucius began teaching ancient customs.
His teachings were based upon moral and ethical
principles for day-to-day living.
He believed that there were five different
relationships in the world.
518 BCE He travelled to the imperial capital,
Lo-yang, and studied the traditions of the
empire.
517 BCE When there was war in the state of
Lu, the Duke of Lu and Confucius escaped to
the neighbouring state of Qi.
Confucius learned the art of music.
500 BCE At the age of 51, he was appointed
as the Minister of Justice of the state of
Lu.
He was promoted to Prime Minister.
495 BCE Confucius left the state of Lu and
his position in the government.
He spent the following years travelling from
one region to another hoping to put his principles
into practice.
483 BCE He returned to the state of Lu and
refused any offer of a Government position.
479 BCE Confucius died aged 72, in the state
of Lu.
CHAPTER TWO
Socrates - the great Greek philosopher
c.470 BCE-399 BCE
My greatest belief and one that guided me
my whole life, was a simple one.
If you have a problem and want to find the
solution that is right for you, you have to
make sure you ask the right questions.
***
I was born in the city of Athens, Greece in
470 BCE.
My father, Sophroniscus, was a stonemason
- someone who cuts stone for building work
- and sculptor and my mother, Phaenarete,
was a midwife.
As you can imagine, we were not wealthy and
we lived a simple life.
I had the most basic education and then when
I had finished school, my father taught me
his trade.
I also learned a great deal by watching him
as he worked.
Being a practical man, my father let his hands,
rather than his mouth, do the talking.
I trained myself to pay attention to detail
and I tried to be a good apprentice, working
hard.
Even though I tried, I was not very interested
in becoming a stonemason.
My real passion was listening to the stories
the elders in our village told.
Each day, I would hear these wise old men
sharing their views with whoever would listen.
They talked about what they knew, and their
opinions differed depending on how they saw
life.
They would discuss problems of the present,
such as how our way of life could be improved.
They would look at examples from the past
to help them reach conclusions.
Ideas for the future were also considered,
for example, whether new laws should be introduced
to improve society and if so, which ones.
Apart from practical issues, they also discussed
more abstract topics, such as whether truth
and certainty actually existed.
Each would try to convince the others that
their view was the correct one.
Those who were respected for their attitude
and contributions - for they were not all
judged equally - usually had the most success.
To me, these debates were at the centre of
reality.
Unlike the lifeless stone and wood that I
worked with every day, people were warm and
alive and were capable of thought.
I believed that it was our duty to share and
compare what was in our minds in order to
improve and develop as human beings.
This and only this would lead to happiness
and a contented, rich life.
I had seen that wealthy people were not necessarily
happier than the rest of us.
I had noticed that there are times in our
lives when difficult decisions have to be
made and we don't know which direction to
take to get the best result.
Let me explain what I mean.
From an early age I had seen people - my mother
is a good example - worry about areas of their
lives that they thought were problematic.
As with all families, we had plenty of disagreements.
My mother found it difficult to keep the peace
and be fair at the same time.
At times I am sure that I was responsible
for making her upset and angry but often she
didn't ask me why I was behaving badly.
Instead, she would decide for herself what
was troubling me and would act accordingly.
She wasn't always right and I discovered how
important it was to share thoughts and ideas.
***
In 431 BCE, the Peloponnesian War between
Athens and Sparta began.
I was a soldier at the time, doing my military
service.
In the heat of battle there was little time
for debate and sharing one's thoughts - differences
were settled by fighting - but having a set
of principles did help to guide me.
I tried to be brave and fearless.
People later told me that I was.
I was lucky enough to be able to save the
life of an Athenian general called Alcibiades,
who was respected and well-liked in Athens.
Greek society in the 4th century BCE was divided
up into cities, each functioning as a state
with its own government and rules.
It was normal for them all to be in conflict
with each other, but there was an alternative
way of dealing with such conflicts - a great
competition that we called the Olympic Games.
The original Olympics were held in honour
of Zeus, who, according to Greek mythology,
was one of the twelve gods who lived in the
temple of the gods at Mount Olympus.
Zeus was the father and king of the gods.
In the town of Olympia a huge, impressive
statue of him was built and Greeks from all
over the country came to see it.
It was here that the Games were first held.
All the Greek city states sent representatives
to compete in the games.
Everyone taking part had to swear an oath
to the king of the gods, and had to be able
to speak Greek.
It was important not only for the athletes
to compete in sporting competitions, but also
to participate in the many theatre, poetry,
sculpture, dance and singing events that were
held.
The Games were the perfect occasion for everyone
to celebrate their culture, their religion
and their artistic talents.
In the beginning, the sporting competitions
were open to both men and women, with the
women taking part in a series of races called
the Heraean Games, dedicated to the goddess
Hera.
Later on, however, women were excluded from
competing and then were not even allowed to
enter the stadium.
Eventually this rule was relaxed and women
were permitted to compete in equestrian events,
that is, those involving horses.
A Spartan princess called Cynisca, driving
a four-horse chariot, was the first woman
to become an Olympic winner.
In contrast, the first male Olympic champion
was a man called Coroebus, a cook who won
the first running event which covered the
distance of 192 metres.
For the men, there was a variety of events,
all designed to test mental and physical strength
as well as endurance.
It was a rule that athletes had to train for
at least ten months before the Games.
Winners did not get medals.
Instead, they were given a crown made from
leaves, called a laurel wreath.
They were also given a branch from an olive
tree.
As well as becoming a valued sporting event,
the ancient Olympic Games became a great social
occasion, too.
People from the city states who were not athletes
would meet to share ideas and do business
and in this way the Games helped develop Greek
culture and way of life.
But, of course, real life was not just about
taking part in sporting and cultural events,
nor was it about being polite to each other.
Politics, too, had its place and where there
was politics, there was also conflict, caused
by various types of bad behaviour.
People tried to dominate each other; they
tried to cheat each other; and they were jealous,
wanting what their neighbours had and they
did not.
I had become interested in philosophy, and
I was wondering about how social conditions
could be improved, for example, how could
we avoid injustice?
I developed a method of investigation which
people later called the Socratic Method.
It consisted of my asking people, both rich
and poor, questions based on political and
ethical issues.
The topics covered, among other things, courage,
love and respect, and the way people saw themselves.
I questioned anyone I found out and about
in the city streets and I didn't care whether
they were willing or not to talk to me.
I must have developed a particular style because
young people would copy the way I talked.
From people's answers I intended to create
what I saw as being 'truths'.
I would have the evidence I needed to state
that I had more than just a theory.
I would then use my evidence to try and make
a better world and better living conditions.
But finding real evidence could be difficult
because people didn't always want to answer
my questions.
When they did answer, they were often not
truthful.
I believed that those who were reluctant to
give answers were those who had something
to hide.
I soon discovered that it was the honest people
who had no problem with telling the truth.
I also believed that for the better world
I was looking for to exist, politics had to
be conducted in a honest way.
That came back to people again.
The government worked best when it was ruled
by individuals who had the greatest ability
and knowledge, and possessed a complete understanding
of themselves.
The only way to achieve this understanding
was to ask the right questions and answer
them truthfully.
When I was 50, after I had spent many years
on my work, I met a woman many years younger
than me, called Xanthippe and in 419 BCE we
became husband and wife.
We had three children, all boys, and although
I would like to say our family life was happy,
it was not.
Xanthippe always felt that I did not pay enough
attention to her and the boys.
I am afraid that she may have been right.
***
In 404 BCE, after 25 years of conflict and
fighting, Athens had been finally defeated
in the last battle of the Peloponnesian War.
The city was now going through a period of
instability and its people were feeling insecure.
They did not wish to let go of their memories
of successful battles, their ideas of wealth
and their obsession with physical beauty.
Good looks were seen as being incredibly important
for anyone wanting to be successful in the
world of politics.
For a long time, beauty and the idea of goodness
had been linked.
If you were not handsome, people thought you
could not be a good person either.
My own appearance did not help me as I could
not have been described as being good-looking
by anyone, probably not even my own mother.
Nor was I interested in money and what it
could buy.
This was probably a good thing as I was always
rather poor.
I did not try to look like a successful man
by wearing good clothes or by trying to look
clean and tidy.
I tried to convince society that it was the
mind that was of the greatest importance.
Unfortunately many people felt threatened
by what was, in their view, an attack on their
way of life.
I tried to use humour while I was challenging
their conventional wisdom but I was not always
very successful and I managed to upset both
politicians and the military.
A military government called the Thirty Tyrants
took control of the city and they ruled for
about a year.
During that time, I became even more unpopular
with the authorities.
On one occasion a man had been sentenced to
death and I thought the way he had been judged
was unfair.
I objected, as I was not the kind of man who
kept quiet about social injustice.
Once again, speaking my mind led to some dangerous
situations.
However, my message must have had some influence
because in 406 BCE I was invited to be a member
of the Boule.
The Boule was a council made up of city residents.
It dealt with matters such as property disagreements
and access to the facilities in the city.
For the council to be successful, it had to
be fair and make decisions that people could
accept, but there were often problems.
Other members of society who were not part
of the council wanted things to happen their
way.
They knew that money was a powerful tool and
they used it to get what they wanted.
Justice was replaced by corruption, something
that I found unacceptable.
I protested, with the result that I made more
enemies.
I had not stopped using my method of asking
questions to find solutions, but the questions
that I asked those in power gave offence.
The truth was often inconvenient, for if they
answered truthfully, they would expose themselves
as being dishonest or corrupt.
Still, I did not give up and with every question
I raised, the political temperature also rose.
I have to admit that I quite enjoyed seeing
these people arguing.
At least they were talking about what was
right and wrong.
As it turned out, though, they were also talking
about me and what was to be done with me.
During 399 BCE, a message arrived saying that
I was going to be arrested.
Friends advised me to escape but to me that
was to admit defeat.
I had always thought that running away from
a problem was no answer.
The right thing to do was to face my accusers,
so that's what I did.
There were many of them.
A jury of 500 Athenian men were gathered to
judge me.
At that time, religion was a serious thing
in Athens.
There were many religious festivals that people,
by law, had to take part in.
The many temples and shrines - the places
where people went to pray and worship - were
cared for with public money.
Showing religious disrespect was a serious
crime.
My accusers claimed that I did not believe
in the Athenian gods, but worshipped gods
of my own.
They believed that my attitude was dangerous
and that my views were corrupting young people,
who were also behaving in a disrespectful
way.
Others accused me of interfering with progress.
Few people openly said what really scared
them but I knew what it was.
I was the voice of the poor people, the majority
of citizens who could not vote and could not
be heard.
What would happen if I was allowed to become
their political champion?
Would there be a revolution?
Would we win?
That was the real fear!
Realizing the danger of allowing me to be
free, the majority of the powerful 500 had
their way, and I was found guilty of being
a revolutionary.
I was imprisoned, but I was not a murderer
or a thief I was really guilty of two things,
neither of which I considered to be a crime.
One was searching for truth and the other
was trying to abolish inequality from society.
I was sentenced to death by poison, which
1 drank myself.
The end of my life, however, was not the end
of the search for justice and truth, and it
certainly did not stop my ideas from taking
on a life of their own.
I like to think that my principles of ethics
and morality had considerable influence on
the development of scientific thought.
The Life of Socrates
470 BCE Socrates was born in Athens.
He was the son of Sophroniscus, an Athenian
stone-mason, and Phaenarete, a midwife.
Socrates learnt his father's trade at a young
age.
His interests were in ideas and later he focused
on education and philosophy.
459 BCE Socrates gained a basic education
and through his curiosity, he began to learn
about the customs and culture of Athens.
449 BCE He was probably working in his father's
business at this time.
439 BCE Socrates was developing his philosophy,
based on asking questions about social life.
These covered issues such as what is justice
and what is goodness.
435 BCE About that time, Socrates developed
the view that the best way to a happy life
is to focus on self-development, rather than
chase after wealth.
Building relationships came before making
money.
431 BCE The Peloponnesian War began (Athens
v. Sparta).
Socrates participated in three military campaigns
during the war, at Potidaea, Deliurn and Amphipolis,
as a soldier.
He saved the life of Alcibiades, a popular
Athenian general.
Socrates was known for his courage and fearlessness
in battle.
425 BCE Socrates continued to raise questions
about social life and may have earned his
living as a teacher.
418 BCE Socrates fought in the Battle of Mantinea.
419 BCE At the age of 50, Socrates married
Xanthippe, who was much younger.
They had three sons: Lamprocles, Sophroniscus
and Menexenus.
412 BCE Socrates had the opportunity to try
out his theories and ideas, as a parent.
He continued to make speeches and attract
the interest of the poor people and the youth,
as well as annoying some politicians and military
people.
404 BCE The Peloponnesian War ended.
Athenians entered into a period of instability
and doubt about their identity.
Socrates was critical of leaders who had failed
in the war.
406 BCE Socrates was a member of the governing
organization called the Boule.
407 BCE He met Plato and shared his ideas.
Plato wrote up his memory of the meetings,
which served as a record, as there was no
direct evidence of Socrates writing a book
of his philosophy or psychology.
400 BCE Socrates called himself a philosopher
and social critic.
Many people listened to his criticism of the
politicians and military leaders.
He was seen by some as a revolutionary, who
encouraged the ambitions of the poor.
399 BCE Socrates was sentenced to death for
being a revolutionary.
It was said that he worshipped new gods of
his own and not the Greek gods and that he
was encouraging young people to do the same.
CHAPTER THREE
Aristotle - the first man to organize scientific
knowledge
384-322 BCE
If you ask people to mention the names of
three great philosophers, my name will come
up along with those of Socrates and Plato.
People also remember me because Alexander
the Great was my most famous student.
***
I was born in 384 BCE in Macedonia in the
north of Greece in a town called Stagira,
which was a busy port.
Nowadays, many tourists want to see the place
that is famous because it was my birthplace.
There isn't much left of the old town, just
ruins, but people enjoy seeing part of the
wall that surrounded the town, some of the
old houses in it and the market place - the
Agora.
This was the most important part of the town
because it was here that people went to do
business, talk politics and of course socialize.
I was lucky enough to have parents who taught
me many things, but you could also say that
I was rather unlucky, too, because they both
died when I was just a boy.
My father, whose name was Nicomachus, was
a doctor but he wasn't an ordinary doctor.
He was the personal physician to King Amyntas
of Macedonia.
It was my father who made me interested in
learning about medicine.
Naturally we didn't really know very much
about how the human body worked, nor did we
know exactly what caused people to become
ill.
When they were sick, we tried to cure their
illnesses with herbs and prayers.
What we did understand, however, was that
keeping fit by taking regular exercise was
extremely important.
We saw that those who were fit got ill less
often than those who never exercised at all.
Medicine wasn't the only subject I was interested
in.
By nature, I was a curious child and, from
an early age, I listened with great interest
to the family discussions that often took
place at home.
These debates - because they were more than
just discussions - were about the political
situation in our town.
They focused on the activities of all the
influential people who lived there.
I don't know whether or not it was my father's
wish for me to become a politician.
Unfortunately, he died long before I knew
myself what I wanted to do with my life.
When my father died, leaving me an orphan,
my older sister Arimneste and her husband
Proxenus took me in and looked after me.
My father had been a wealthy man and there
was plenty of money available for my education.
In addition to my existing interest in politics
and medicine, what I was really fascinated
by was philosophy and science.
Not only did I want to continue my studies
in these subjects but I also wanted to study
in the city that was the most important academic
place on the planet.
So in 366 BCE, at the age of eighteen, I packed
up and moved to Athens.
***
Athens was a completely new world for me.
My first impression was of all these city
people rushing noisily through the streets
trying to make their fortune.
They were so busy in their attempts to make
money that very few of them actually had the
time to discover new things and explore the
world around them.
This, however, was exactly what I intended
to do with my time.
Having come from an aristocratic family, I
had enough money to follow my dream and to
live comfortably.
In Athens, I joined Plato's Academy.
Plato was a great thinker and teacher and
I learnt a great deal from him.
For the next twenty years, until his death,
I worked at the Academy.
It was the perfect chance to research and
teach and I focused on the 'science of living'
which included politics, physics, logic, biology
and psychology.
In one sense, original thought was easier
in my time because there was so much that
we didn't know.
We could research a subject, and with the
results, we could expand and develop what
we already knew about it.
When Plato died in 347 BCE, many people believed
that I would become the new director of the
Academy, but I was not offered the position.
Before his death, Plato had requested that
it would be his nephew, not I, who would inherit
the position.
During our time together Plato and I had had
many academic differences and it was inevitable
that we would disagree sometimes.
Perhaps his decision was based on these differences,
perhaps not, but anyway, I decided instead
to travel.
Travelling was hard work and took a long time
on dangerous rough roads.
I walked, or rode on horses or camels, whatever
the weather.
In the summer, it was hot and dusty; in the
winter, I froze in the snow, ice and fierce
winds.
In autumn and spring, I got very wet when
it rained.
Of course, every season had its spectacular
moments but there was no doubt that however
rich you were, travelling was uncomfortable.
When I finally reached Assos in Asia Minor,
I visited an ex-student of mine, Hermias,
who had once been a slave.
As well as gaining his freedom, he had managed,
surprisingly, to become King of Atarneus.
I stayed with Hermias's family for three years
and met his niece, Pythias.
We fell in love and got married.
I was already a happy man, but one of the
best days of my life was when little Pythias,
our daughter, was born.
***
In 343 BCE King Philip II, whose son would
become Alexander the Great, invited me back
to Macedonia to educate the thirteen-year-old
boy, and there I became the head of the Royal
Academy.
I taught Alexander and a few of his friends
philosophy, poetry, drama, science and politics.
Alexander dreamed of being a hero on the battlefields
and, when he was 16, he took part in his first
battle.
Two years after that, he helped his father
to defeat armies from both Athens and Thebes.
King Philip II was head of the Corinthian
League and he managed to get all the Greek
city states, with the exception of Sparta,
to agree to belong to it.
When Philip died in 336 BCE, Alexander became
King of Macedonia, but being King did not
give him the right to be the leader of the
League.
Athens was being ruled by Dimosthenis, whose
aim was to control the League himself.
Alexander sent his army south and persuaded
the members of the League to accept him as
their leader.
***
In 334 BCE, while Alexander was fighting for
control of Asia, I decided to return to the
city with my family.
I still wanted to teach and I was given permission
to open my own school, at the edge of the
city, which we called the Lyceum.
I gathered together a group of research students
who became known as the 'peripatetics'.
Their name was based on the Greek for 'walking'
because of their habit of wandering around
the school while they were thinking and discussing
different topics.
I wanted education to be available for everyone
and so many of our lectures were open to the
public and were free of charge.
It was in this school of mine that my type
of thinking was given a name: 'Aristotelian
logic', the key aspect of which was clarity
of thought, and here I wrote, among many others,
two of my better known books: De Anima and
Parva Naturalia.
Academic life wasn't easy.
We worked by the light of candles which was
hard on the eyes, and it was often cold.
It wasn't only at the Lyceum where conditions
were difficult.
Poverty and disease surrounded us and tragically,
because we did not have enough knowledge of
medicine to save her, my poor wife died in
335 BCE at a very young age.
I was sure that we wouldn't have lost her
if our level of education had been higher
and we'd been able to carry out proper scientific
research.
***
Education, in my view, consisted of three
parts and to be thorough and correct, had
to include all three: the practical, the poetical
and the theoretical.
The practical covered politics and ethics
in government and business, the poetical was
concerned with the arts and humanities, while
the theoretical was all about mathematics
and metaphysics.
The scientific method that I was in favour
of provided a link between the three areas,
but I was convinced that evidence, rather
than just opinion, had to be the basis for
assessment.
The problem with evidence, however, was that
it was proving hard to find for many of my
theories.
Before I returned to Athens and set up the
Lyceum, I had gone to the island of Lesbos
for a while in the hope of finding such evidence.
I wanted to study natural life in its natural
form.
In the sea, marine life provided new understanding
and I was completely fascinated by botany
- the study of plants.
I knew that plants had secrets that could
bring help to those who were ill.
I had learnt that much from my father, but
I was sure that there was still so much more
to be discovered.
In the field of agriculture, too, we had to
find better ways of growing crops so that
we could become more efficient at feeding
ourselves.
In contrast, I believed that because the study
of ethics is a personal subject, the best
way to learn about it was through life experience.
By 'life experience' I mean learning by thinking
about the decisions we make and the things
that we do.
This means studying our thoughts as they are
acted out.
Politics, however, is a public matter.
People in general use politics to survive.
It is all about using your skills to negotiate
who gets what, when and how.
Depending on how good you are at politics,
the results will either be positive with peace
and prosperity all around you, or negative,
leading to a state of conflict and revolution.
Philosophy became a key area of my thought
and teaching as I tried to find a way to integrate
logic, feelings and evidence.
Later, much of my approach was adopted and
turned into what was called Scholasticism
and some of my ideas were kept alive.
In a world where time destroys almost everything,
my life's work has survived.
Not only has it survived, it is now better
known than it was when I was alive, although
it did disappear for a while.
In about 1500 CE, after hundreds of years
in a world where science was forgotten, my
work suddenly came to life again as universities
began to teach Greek.
My work became visible and important once
more.
However, much of what I suggested then was
guesswork.
My claim that the earth was the centre of
the universe took more than 2,000 years to
be proved.
Theory is fine, but scientific evidence is
hard to establish because it requires clear
thinking and the strength not to give up.
Theories are ideas that mark the way for change
and development.
To get evidence, experiments need to be made
and we need to learn from our actions.
We need more people to face the challenge
of the unknown, people who will advance understanding,
despite the ignorance of others.
Innovation takes time to succeed, and it seems
to be a fact that having evidence by itself
is not enough.
It is also necessary to have a quick mind
and make good judgments.
You need to be able to publicize your ideas
and have the confidence to tell the whole
world about them and make people believe in
you.
Only in this way can people move forward.
In 323 BCE, Alexander the Great died and the
Macedonian government lost power.
In Athens there were considerable anti-Macedonian
feelings and I felt that my life was in danger.
I made the decision to leave the city and
to go to the island of Euboea.
A year later I died there of natural causes.
The Life of Aristotle
384 BCE Aristotle was born in Stagira, Chalcidice,
near Thessaloniki, Greece.
The name Aristotle means 'the best purpose'.
366 BCE He was sent to Plato's Academy in
Athens to study.
347 BCE Plato died and Aristotle left Athens
for Assos, Asia Minor.
There he met a former student, Hermias, and
later married Hermias' niece, Pythias.
They had one daughter, who they also named
Pythias.
344 BCE Aristotle lived on the island of Lesbos
for some time where he carried out botanical
research.
343 BCE Philip II of Macedonia invited Aristotle
to tutor his son, Alexander (the Great) and
he was appointed as head of the Royal Academy
there.
334 BCE He returned to Athens and established
his own school, called the Lyceum.
335-323 BCE His wife Pythias died and he then
became involved with Herpyllis, with whom
he had a son that he named after his father,
Nicomachus.
During these years, he wrote many of his works
including De Anima and Parva Naturalia.
323 BCE Alexander the Great died and anti-Macedonian
feelings increased in Athens.
Fearing a death sentence, Aristotle escaped
to the island of Euboea.
322 BCE Aristotle died of natural causes,
aged 61 or 62, on Euboea.
CHAPTER FOUR
William Wilberforce - the man who ended the
British slave trade
1759-1833
Freedom, slavery and Christianity - these
were the words that had the biggest impact
on my life.
They began to influence my thinking and action
as soon as I became mature enough to understand
their true meaning.
***
I was born in 1759 in the town of Hull, in
the north of England.
My father was a rich merchant and we lived
a comfortable life.
My parents were religious people, Christians,
who often mentioned the word slavery.
Of course, as a child it didn't really mean
much to me, nor did the concept of freedom.
I only knew that my own freedom to play and
join in games with other boys was limited
by my poor eyesight and bad health.
When I was nine years old, my father died.
My mother's grief was deep and resulted in
her not being able to look after me, so I
was sent south to London to live with my aunt
and uncle.
Religion to them was more than going to church
and praying, and they worked to end poverty
and slavery.
After a while, when my mother had recovered
from my father's death, I returned home.
However, I had been influenced by my time
with my relatives in London and their views
on life stayed with me.
I was lucky having had a privileged upbringing
but I realized that most people did not share
my luck.
When I was seventeen, I went to St John's
College, Cambridge University.
I had inherited money from different relatives,
so with money of my own I was financially
independent.
This meant that I could do what I wanted and
enjoy student life to the full.
I experienced a world of luxury that most
people at the time could only dream about
while all around me there was poverty and
misery.
I lived in an academic world where there was
a lot of talking and very little action.
Talking about the real world and the difficulties
most people were facing was not enough for
me.
I knew that with my wealth, education and
contacts, I could make a difference.
My friend, William Pitt, who later became
Prime Minister, suggested that I enter Parliament.
He knew a lot of influential people and introduced
me to political life.
I managed to get elected - using eight thousand
pounds of my own money undoubtedly helped
- and in 1780 I became a Member of Parliament
for Kingston-upon-Hull while I was still a
student.
I decided not to join a political party but
to be an Independent.
In that way, I could lead rather than follow
- I didn't want the restrictions that belonging
to a party would involve.
I had money, and with money it was possible
to have influence.
It was also possible to have a very enjoyable
social life.
In the evenings, I went to various gentlemen's
clubs.
These were clubs where upper-class men would
meet their friends, enjoy expensive dinners,
and gamble.
Some said that I was clever with words, a
talent that certainly helped me when speaking
in Parliament.
So my life as a wealthy politician began.
It was a pleasant type of existence and while
on a tour of Europe in 1785, I continued enjoying
the privileged kind of life that money could
buy.
But something had started to worry me.
I began to question why, when Britain was
a relatively rich country, there were very
poor people in every town and city.
There were people who were living in the most
desperate poverty.
The upper classes, however, were not only
living well, but were increasing their wealth,
for example by renting out land and property
to the poor.
My interest in spiritual matters grew and
I started asking myself what sort of a life
I should be leading.
To find answers, I read the Bible and I realized
that there was a better way.
I wanted to share my beliefs and make other
people think in the same way.
Naturally, this affected my politics but I
was doubtful if this was a good thing.
Would people take seriously a politician who
was as deeply religious as I was?
I asked William Pitt, who by this time was
Prime Minister, for advice, and he encouraged
me to continue and to act on what I believed
in.
One of these beliefs was that slavery was
wrong.
The British slave trade began in the 16th
century when Britain began to acquire territories
to add to its Empire.
Colonists started farming the land and they
needed workers.
In the beginning, they hired people but as
the farms grew larger, they needed more people
than were available.
In the British territories in North America,
American Indians weren't suitable because
they easily caught diseases the Europeans
had brought with them like pneumonia and tuberculosis
and they usually died as a result.
The Portuguese and Spanish were already using
slaves from Africa in their own colonies and
so the British decided to do the same.
Most of the British slave trade was centred
in the West Indies - a group of islands in
the Caribbean - which was part of the British
Empire.
The main crop on the plantations was sugar,
which was sent to Britain and other places
in the Empire.
The money that came from the plantations was
invested by the owners in other types of industry
such as banking and insurance, and Britain's
economy became partly dependent on the slave
trade.
Slaves were not only a valuable source of
income for the slave traders, they were also
the main reason the plantations were so profitable.
The owners did not have to pay wages and by
encouraging female slaves to have children,
there were future generations of workers born
into slavery.
It was clear that British business people
were leaders in the slave trade, although
Portugal, Spain, France and North America
were also involved.
Our supply of sugar, coffee, tobacco, cotton,
silver and gold was completely dependent on
using slaves in the great plantations.
By the 1730s some of the plantation owners,
many of whom lived in Britain, had become
extremely wealthy.
They had also become members of Parliament.
This meant that they were able to influence
the laws dealing with the colonies of the
Empire.
For two hundred years, laws were not passed
that would affect the source of their wealth
- in this case, the slave trade.
The North Americans had declared independence
in 1776.
The colonists, many of them slave owners,
had defeated the British army, and the United
States of America had elected their own politicians
and were making their own laws.
However, it was British businessmen in British
ships who were still running the slave trade.
They had developed a three-way system, which
was known as the triangular trade.
Guns, alcohol and other goods produced in
Britain were shipped from there to Africa.
Then local rulers exchanged the goods for
people - human beings who had been captured
and had become slaves.
The ships took the slaves across the Atlantic
Ocean where they were sold to plantation owners.
The ships, once they had delivered their human
cargo, would load up with products like sugar
or tobacco and would then sail back to Britain.
One evening at dinner, in 1783, I met a man
called James Ramsay, who had been a ship's
doctor in the West Indies and later a Church
of England priest.
He told me what he had seen on the ships arriving
from Africa and I was horrified.
Slave traders would travel to Africa to find
or hunt and capture healthy-looking men and
women, who were taken to large ships.
They were chained together and put below decks
with hardly enough space for them to breathe,
let alone move.
Conditions on the ships were terrible and
thousands died during the voyage.
When the ships arrived at their destinations,
the slaves had to face the humiliating experience
of being sold to their new owners.
Those who had survived the trip were usually
in the most terrible physical condition - at
best, they were exhausted, starving and thin.
On arrival they were washed, the men were
shaved and oil was put on their skins to make
them look healthier.
When the slaves had been made to look as good
as possible, potential buyers would come and
examine them as if they were animals, to choose
which ones they wanted.
The slaves were then sold in one of two ways.
Sometimes an auction was held.
At an auction, buyers would offer an amount
of money for a slave and the person offering
the greatest amount would be the one to buy
him or her.
On other occasions, the slaves would be put
together into one room.
The doors would open and the buyers would
all rush in and grab the slave or slaves they
wanted.
Either way, it was brutal.
The slaves did not know what was going to
happen to them or where they were going to
be taken, and they did not understand English.
In total, more than fifteen million Africans
became slaves and it was estimated that over
two million died during the dreadful eight-
to ten- week voyage from Africa.
In 1787, a man called Thomas Clarkson came
to see me.
He had researched and written an essay on
the slave trade, and the facts were shocking.
The British Parliament found itself able to
accept slavery, but for me, the question was
what could be done about it.
Looking around me, at the sugar, cotton, tobacco,
silver and gold that we took for granted in
our everyday lives, I felt that everything
I touched was tainted by slavery.
The people who had power in government had
to be persuaded that slavery was wrong.
Clarkson, with two other men, had started
the Society for the Abolition of the Slave
Trade.
The Quakers, a religious group that did not
believe in slavery or war, also protested
but they were not taken seriously.
Because they disagreed with the principles
of the Church of England, the Quakers were
unpopular and so their protests had little
effect.
James Ramsay had published An Inquiry into
the Effects of Putting a Stop to the African
Slave Trade and Treatment and Conversion of
African Slaves in the British Sugar Colonies.
Because he was a Church of England priest
he had more influence in the government than
the Quakers.
Ordinary people had to be told the truth about
slavery.
Most of them had no idea where their sugar
or tobacco came from and the few who did know
had no idea how terrible life was for the
slaves on the plantations.
A campaign was started to educate the British
people about the truth of slavery and slowly
people began to listen.
From then onwards, I focused all my energy
on trying to achieve my goal of making the
slave trade illegal.
Day after day and night after night, I tried
to convince people.
But it was a hard fight.
All around me there were people - rich influential
people - who benefited from slavery.
In 1790, I was allowed to set up a committee
to look at the slave trade and examine how
it was operated.
The following year I introduced the first
bill to abolish slavery but the politicians
voted against it.
They said there were more important issues
to be considered because of the threat presented
by the French Revolution and the rise of Napoleon.
They were also afraid of the new United States
of America and questioned if it was right
that we should interfere with their slave
system.
The politicians even went as far as to suggest
that it was the Americans' job, not ours,
to stop the practice of slavery.
This did not stop me, however, and I continued
to raise the question of slavery at every
opportunity.
***
I was so busy working and fighting for my
beliefs that my personal life had suffered
and I was alone.
Romance was the last thing on my mind until
I met the woman I would marry.
In 1797 a friend introduced me to a young
woman called Barbara Ann Spooner, whose smile
filled me with joy.
The day after I met her, I sent a note suggesting
that we meet again.
She agreed and we talked about my work.
Within a few days, I had made up my mind and
at a private dinner, I asked her if she would
be my wife.
To my delight she agreed and we starting making
plans for our wedding.
Our family and friends were not so enthusiastic
as we had only known each other for eight
days.
Barbara may have been eighteen years younger
than I was - which was not unusual at the
time - but I knew I had found true love.
In the next ten years we had six children
and my life at home filled me with the strength
to continue my battles at work.
My political campaign against slavery continued
at full speed, gradually gaining support and
on 22nd February 1807, the Slave Trade Act
was passed, making the buying and selling
of slaves illegal.
The British Parliament had decided with 283
votes for, and only 16 against, the Act.
The next year, the USA also made the slave
trade illegal, but it did not succeed in actually
stopping the trade of slaves, nor slavery
itself.
There was clearly a lot more to be done before
the practice of slavery would end and the
slaves would be given their freedom.
In 1816, the names and personal details of
all the slaves were written down in an official
list, and I started looking at other important
issues.
I wanted Parliament to pass laws to improve
working conditions, especially for children
and factory workers.
What I did not agree with was giving workers
the right to organize unions because I was
worried that this would lead to revolution,
as it had in France.
I was also concerned about people's morals
and I fully supported Bible studies for children
at Sunday School as well as helping to establish
the Church Missionary Society.
But my focus remained on abolishing slavery.
In 1833, the Slave Abolition Act was passed,
banning slavery in most colonies of the British
Empire and giving the slaves their freedom.
Full credit should go to Thomas Clarkson and
others for their efforts.
By that time, I was nearly blind and very
much poorer than when I had started my campaign.
My death came within days of the passing of
the Act but my sacrifices were minor compared
to those of the slaves.
While their 'Christian' owners had been seen
praying in church, more than two million slaves
had been killed, millions more had been beaten
and countless were badly-treated and worked
to death.
With the 1833 Act, my life's work to ban slavery
by the British had been achieved.
But elsewhere the battle continued.
The Life of William Wilberforce
1759 William Wilberforce was born in Hull,
Yorkshire, England.
1767 He began his schooling at Hull Grammar
School.
1768 At the age of nine, William's father
died.
He was sent to live with his aunt and uncle
at their homes in London and Wimbledon.
William was sent to a boarding school in Putney
and spent his holidays with relatives.
1771 William's mother and grandfather were
concerned about his religious instruction,
and therefore brought him back to Hull.
1776 He attended St John's College, in Cambridge.
His grandfather died, followed by his uncle.
Their deaths left William with his own money
to spend as he pleased.
1780 While still a student, on September 11th,
William was elected as a Member of Parliament
for Kingston-upon-Hull.
1783 His friend, William Pitt, was elected
Prime Minister.
1784 William was elected as a Member of Parliament
for the county of Yorkshire in the general
election.
In October, he toured Europe with his mother,
sister and Isaac Milner, the brother of his
former headmaster.
1785 He returned to England to support Pitt's
Parliamentary changes before continuing his
travels to Italy and Switzerland.
William read The Rise and Progress of Religion
in the Soul which had a serious effect on
him.
He began to pray and read the Bible.
1786 William rented a house near Parliament,
in Westminster.
He used his position to promote changes in
the law.
1787 Thomas Clarkson began calling on William
and asked him to bring forward the case to
the House of Commons for the Abolition of
Slavery.
The first meeting of the Society for Effecting
the Abolition of the Slave Trade took place.
1789 On May 12th, William delivered his first
speech in the House of Commons against the
slave trade.
He also introduced his first bill to abolish
the slave trade.
1790 He gained approval for a Parliamentary
Select Committee to consider the slave trade
and examine the evidence.
1791 In April, the first Parliamentary Bill
was introduced.
It was defeated by 163 votes to 88.
From then on, William introduced a motion
of favour of abolition during every session
of Parliament.
1793-1798 The war in France meant that although
the subject of the slave trade continued to
be debated in Parliament, serious consideration
was never given to it.
1797 William met and married Barbara Spooner.
They had six children over the next ten years.
1799 The Slave Trade Regulation Act was passed
to reduce overcrowding on slave ships.
1804 William helped to start the British and
Foreign Bible Society and the Church Missionary
Society.
1806 The new Foreign Slave Trade Act was passed.
It banned all British people from helping
in any way or taking part in the slave trade
to the French colonies.
In effect, the Act stopped two-thirds of the
British slave trade.
1807 On February 23rd, the British Parliament
finally abolished the slave trade.
Then on March 25th the Abolition of the Slave
Trade Act was passed.
It stopped the trading of slaves, but did
not actually abolish slavery.
1822 William helped form the Anti-Slavery
Society.
1823 He launched the campaign for slaves to
be given their freedom.
1825 He retired from Parliament after 45 years
of service.
1833 William died aged 73, in London, England.
Just three days before his death, on July
26th, the Slavery Abolition Act was passed.
Slavery was abolished in the whole of the
British Empire and all the slaves within it
were given their freedom.
CHAPTER FIVE
Karl Marx - the man who wrote The Communist
Manifesto and Das Kapital
1818-1883
I was not born into poverty but I hated the
inequality between the very rich and the very
poor.
I spent my life, through my writing, fighting
for equality.
I believed that everybody, whatever their
class and financial state, should have the
same rights.
***
I was born in 1818 in the city of Trier in
Germany.
My father was a lawyer and my mother had more
than a full-time job looking after my father,
myself and my eight brothers and sisters.
We had a comfortable life and I didn't go
to school until I was twelve because until
that point I had been educated at home by
private tutors.
After attending the high school in Trier for
five years, I went to the University of Bonn
and studied law.
Like many students suddenly thrown into an
adult world, I found myself in a bit of trouble.
I got into debt, had fights and once was even
sent to prison.
My father was not very pleased with my behaviour
and insisted that I take my studies more seriously.
At his suggestion - and as he was paying the
bills, I didn't really have much choice - I
moved to the University of Berlin, where I
studied law and philosophy.
In Berlin I joined a group of students called
the Young Hegelians, who were occupied with
criticizing the political and religious authorities.
The group was based on the teachings of the
philosopher Hegel.
I was not, in the beginning, that interested
in his theories but I became an active member
as my interest in politics grew.
It was during this time that I met my future
wife, Jenny von Westphalen.
Jenny came from quite an upper-class family
and there were many people who were interested
in her apart from me.
She was also four years older than I was.
We got engaged, secretly, and did not get
married until seven years later.
In 1841, I got my Doctorate in Philosophy
but due to my political beliefs, which others
saw as being extreme and unwelcome, I was
not able to get a teaching position at the
university.
In fact, I was forced to leave altogether.
The people in power were feeling increasingly
threatened by the articles I was publishing
which demanded a better life for the poor.
I went to live in Cologne, where I started
a left-wing political newspaper, then I moved
to Paris for a short time, where Jenny and
I got married.
However, it didn't seem to matter where I
went to live, because wherever I was, my views
on life were unpopular.
After Cologne, the city of Brussels, in Belgium,
seemed to be a good place to live and we stayed
there for two years.
I met my dear and life-long friend Friedrich
Engels and also I became involved with people
from the Communist League.
The communists believed that the government
should own a country's wealth - its industry,
property and natural resources - and that
it should be shared equally with everyone.
They thought it was unfair that the upper
classes and the aristocracy, who were a tiny
minority of the population, should have so
much while the working classes had almost
nothing.
The Communist League asked me to write down
the principles of communism in a document
that could be read and used by everyone, which
I did.
I explained in my writing that the working
class is exploited by the upper-class capitalists
whom I called the bourgeoisie.
Capitalists get rich from the work done by
the poor.
The true value of something - goods or services
- is the amount of work actually done.
Any extra money that is made - profit - should
belong to the people who did the work and
not the capitalists.
The only way that this situation can be changed
is if the workers have the power to make rules.
This can only be done if working classes take
power away from the capitalists by using force
and violence.
No wealth should belong to individuals and
all governments should be abolished.
I ended with the following: 'Working men of
all countries, unite!'
My involvement in the League drew attention
to my political views and I made yet more
enemies by speaking out for change and equality.
I was accused of trying to cause a revolution,
but I answered that if a revolution happened,
it would be the poverty of the people, not
me, that was responsible.
The poor were in the majority, but they had
no votes and therefore no power to change
the situation.
By 1849, many European countries were in the
middle of bitter revolutions and it was then
that Engels and I, now back in Cologne, published
The Communist Manifesto, which was based on
the written work I had done for the Communist
League.
This was seen as a huge challenge to the civilized
life enjoyed by the upper classes, and the
continuous threats that were being made to
my life made it necessary for me to leave
Cologne, too.
I had not shot or injured anyone, but I was
seen as an enemy, so I decided we should move
to London.
There I could write and spread my message
through my publications.
Perhaps the British would be more open to
hearing what I had to say.
***
Living conditions in Berlin, Paris and Brussels
had been bad but the poverty and misery in
London were far worse than anything I had
ever seen.
The streets were full of people who had no
choice other than to steal food or even pick
out rotting food from the rubbish to survive.
Many had no homes and were forced to live
on the streets, which were filthy and full
of rats.
Then there was the workhouse.
In 1834 the first workhouses were opened.
They were supposed to be places where people
who had absolutely nothing could go and live.
The government was afraid that 'lazy' people
would take advantage and so conditions inside
were made incredibly brutal and humiliating.
They did provide food and shelter for those
who would have died otherwise, but they were
widely hated, so much so that many preferred
to take their chances out in the streets than
face the shame and stigma of the workhouse.
There had been much whispering of the word
revolution and a group called the Chartists
had long been planning a series of political
attacks.
The Chartists were an organization that wanted
the government to be elected in a fairer way.
They wanted every man over the age of twenty-one
to have the right to vote.
At the time, only men who had property that
could be rented for at least ten pounds a
year could vote.
This meant that six out of every seven men
did not have the right to vote.
The Chartists were also campaigning for a
more acceptable system of representation in
the government.
Large cities, where mainly poor people with
no property lived, often did not have even
one member of parliament representing them.
Unfortunately, the Chartists were neither
well-organized nor successful.
I agreed with their principles and set to
work in the British Library - where it was
only possible to get access if you could prove
you were a serious researcher - to write the
plan that would get rid of capitalism.
This would be a plan that would remove the
great class divides between the rich and the
poor.
My ideas were ahead of their time as the people
in London had not yet heard about communism.
In the north of England, however, factory
and mine workers started to join together
to form unions to try and negotiate with the
government over working conditions.
New innovations like electricity and gas were
comforts for those who already had comfortable
lives.
The living conditions of the poor, who would
not have either electricity or gas for a long
time, were not getting better.
In fact, life became worse as more and more
people were attracted to the large cities.
The major cities, already too full, were becoming
unbearably overcrowded as people like myself
arrived from Europe.
In 1845-1846 a terrible famine happened in
Ireland when that year's potato crop failed.
The potato was one of the basic foods in Ireland
and without it, people starved.
The Irish who could, travelled to other countries.
Many moved to the USA but many others came
to England.
By 1849, 20 per cent of the population of
London were now Irish and like my family,
they were all immigrants - people who had
come from another country in search of a better
life.
We lived at 28 Dean Street, and paid twenty-two
pounds a year in rent for two basic rooms
in very bad condition.
It was very cramped as we were a large family.
My wife gave birth to seven babies but only
three of them lived to adulthood.
This horrible situation was far from unusual
and I was sure the terrible conditions - the
filth and poverty - played a major role in
the high death rate among children.
My family's accommodation and living standards
were far better than some, even though I was
not able to earn a living.
Nobody would employ me and if it had not been
for the generous help of my friend, Engels,
I do not think any members of my family would
have survived at all.
The Dukes of Bedford, Norfolk and Westminster
in their country estates were earning huge
rents from the poor, who had to live in filthy,
disgusting conditions.
We all lived in the same country but it was
as if we were in two different worlds: ours,
the working class, and the other that belonged
to the upper class.
I could not accept that a person who was unlucky
enough to have been born into a poor family
was forced to live a life of misery.
Across the English Channel, many countries
were in a state of anxious confusion, with
people demonstrating in the streets to get
better conditions.
I was sure that this would happen in Britain,
too.
After all, it was the place where the Industrial
Revolution had begun, I spent my days researching
and writing.
'A spectre is haunting Europe,' I wrote.
'The spectre of Communism.'
Looking around the miserable streets of London,
I waited.
Surely the working class would rise up and
take action.
But despite my best efforts to develop protest
through my writing, there was no revolution.
Some capitalists had produced useful innovations
- in addition to the gas and electricity we
already had, the invention of the telephone
improved communications.
But despite this, the working people continued
to be exploited in industry and agriculture,
in the factories and fields.
My proposal was to have a revolution by democratic
means - let all men have the right to vote
and elect the government of their choice and
then if that was not successful, we would
need to fight.
'From each according to his abilities, to
each according to their needs.'
That was the message I was trying to communicate
in Das Kapital - the most famous of all my
books.
I wanted to look in more depth at what I had
outlined in The Communist Manifesto.
I tried to explain how capitalism had developed
and what its future might be.
I focused on economic theory and described
more fully the relationship between workers
and capitalists, showing how workers are exploited
and giving specific examples from the past.
My aim was to demonstrate that capitalism
is unstable and why it should be abolished.
I believed there was a need for a 'science
of society'.
I saw that the class struggle was inevitable
- the struggle between capitalism and communism
or more simply, between the 'haves' and the
'have nots'.
It would be an economic civil war that would
change politics forever.
In 1871, after the Paris Commune rebellion,
where the people of Paris fought against the
government, I wrote a pamphlet - a short book
- called The Civil War in France, which became
famous.
I hoped that the struggle for equality would
occur peacefully, but feared that it would
not, especially not in my lifetime.
In 1883, I died at the age of sixty-four,
two years after the death of my wife, Jenny,
and I was buried in Highgate Cemetery in north
London.
The Life of Karl Marx
1818 Karl Heinrich Marx was born in Trier,
in the Prussian Rhineland.
1819 The family moved to a ten-room property
near the Porta Nigra, in Trier.
1830 Karl attended Trier High School after
his private education ended.
1835 He studied law at the University of Bonn.
The following year, Karl studied at the University
of Berlin, where he continued to study law.
1837 Karl joined the Young Hegelians.
He wrote a novel, Scorpion and Felix and a
drama, Oulanem, but they were not published.
1841 Karl earned his Doctorate in Philosophy
with his thesis The Difference Between the
Democritean and Epicurean Philosophy of Nature.
1842 Karl lived as a refugee in Cologne, where
he was a journalist for a left-wing newspaper
called Rhenish.
He later became the Editor-in-Chief
1843 Karl married Jenny von Westphalen.
They moved to Paris, where Karl studied political
economy, the French socialists and the history
of France.
1844 He met German socialist Friedrich Engels.
On the Jewish Question and The Economic and
Philosophical Manuscripts were published.
The following year, he wrote Theses on Feuerbach,
which was not published until after his death.
1845 Karl, Jenny and Friedrich moved to Brussels,
Belgium.
Karl and Friedrich published a criticism of
the philosophical ideas of Bruno Bauer called
The Holy Family.
They visited London and met the leaders of
the Chartists.
With Friedrich, Karl wrote The German Ideology,
which was published after his death.
1847 He wrote The Poverty of Philosophy.
1848 Karl and Jenny moved back to Cologne.
He started the publication of the left-wing
political paper, New Rhenish Newspaper.
Karl and Friedrich published The Communist
Manifesto.
Europe was in the middle of violent revolutions.
1849 Unable to return to Germany or Belgium,
Karl and Jenny moved to London, where he became
involved in the German Workers' Educational
Society.
1851 Karl wrote about the French Revolution
of 1848, The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis
Napoleon.
1852 He wrote for the New York Daily Tribune.
1859 Karl published Contribution to the Critique
of Political Economy.
1864 He became involved in the International
Workingmen's Association and was elected to
the General Council.
1867 The first volume of Capital: Critique
of Political Economy (Das Kapital) was published.
1871 When the citizens of Paris rebelled against
the government during the Paris Commune, Karl
wrote one of his most famous pamphlets, The
Civil War in France.
1881 His wife, Jenny, died.
1883 Karl died aged 64, in London, England.
CHAPTER SIX
Mahatma Gandhi - the man who helped free India
from British rule
1869-1948
All my life, all I ever wanted was for India
to be an independent, united country.
I wanted a peaceful end to 350 years of British
rule.
The British did leave but to my deepest regret,
they left behind an India that was divided
in two.
***
I was born in Porbandar, a city on the west
coast of India, where most people lived in
poverty and hardship.
We were lucky - my father was the chief minister
of the city - so we had a decent standard
of living.
My mother was a true follower of Jainism - an
Indian religion that believed, among other
things, in complete self-control.
This meant that although we were not poor,
our lifestyle was a simple one.
India was under the rule of the British Raj
and many white men from the British Isles
were sent to our country.
They forced their law on us, but could not
change our customs and beliefs.
People who believed in Jainism thought that
differences between people should be solved
with respect, mutual tolerance and understanding
- not violence.
I followed these principles faithfully my
entire life.
I was married at the age of thirteen to a
girl a year older than me who was called Kasturba.
As was the custom, it was an arranged marriage
with neither of us having any say in the matter.
Over the years we had four sons, although
our first child, born two years into our marriage,
died just a few days after birth.
Medical facilities were limited and basic
and many babies and children died as a result.
I was fortunate enough to have a good education
and I decided that I wanted to study law.
I had heard a great deal about all the fine
cities in Britain and the place I wanted to
go was London, which, I had heard, was the
greatest of them all.
So, having gained a place at University College
London, I left India.
It was a complete culture shock to arrive
in such a big city after living my whole life
in Porbandar.
I was used to the heat of India, and the cold
and never-ending damp of England was not a
pleasant experience for me.
I no longer kicked up dust on the roads of
my hometown - in London you were more likely
to be covered in mud than dust.
Before, I had been just one of many.
Now I was one of the few - an Indian man amongst
the British.
I was a long way from home and each day was
a challenge.
I spent many lonely days studying my law books.
Law to me was not just about what was legally
right or wrong.
I also wanted it to help people behave in
a way that was socially acceptable and this
meant looking at the principles behind the
law.
My early life in Porbandar influenced me greatly,
as the Jainist principles I had brought with
me guided me both in my studies and my social
life.
One of the battles everyone has to face is
how to beat their own inner enemies, such
as anger, intolerance and immorality.
I believed that self-control was important
and that taking responsibility for your own
actions was essential.
It was no use blaming someone else for your
own bad behaviour or lack of will-power.
Where I came from, these beliefs guided poor
and rich alike but in London I found many
different views.
It was not Jainism that was being debated
but capitalism and communism, or democracy
and theocracy and I found it fascinating to
be exposed to so many new ideas.
However, no matter what I heard, I held strongly
to my beliefs and managed to resist all the
temptations facing a young man in the city.
In 1891, I graduated from university and was
called to the Bar.
I thought it was a strange expression, as
if one was going to be served drinks but in
reality, it meant that I had become a qualified
barrister and could now represent people in
the law courts.
***
Two days after my graduation, on 12th June
1891, I set sail for India.
On arriving, instead of the joy I had been
expecting at coming home, I was told my mother
had died.
Days of sadness were followed by hard times
financially as I tried to care for my family.
I set up a law practice in Mumbai but the
lack of clients meant that I soon had to close
it down.
I decided to apply for a job as a school teacher
but I was unlucky there, too, and my application
was rejected.
In 1893,1 accepted a one-year contract in
the British colony of Natal in South Africa.
It was a relief to have some paid work but
frustration took its place as I experienced
countless acts of discrimination.
This is one example.
One day I was travelling, quite legally, in
the first-class carriage of a train, when
I was told by a guard to go and sit in third
class.
When I refused to move, I was actually thrown
off the train.
My Jainist beliefs of tolerance for all people
told me that action against prejudice was
required.
Realizing that the law was not enough to protect
one's rights, I knew I had to do something
myself.
***
I decided to stay and campaign for civil rights
for minority groups.
The Natal Indian Congress was formed in 1894,
providing the Indian community with a voice.
I persuaded my family to join me in South
Africa, but life there was not easy for us.
I had seen poverty, injustice and suffering
and my life-long aim was to bring about peace
and prosperity all over the world.
However, in South Africa it seemed a very
long way away - for example, Indian marriages
had been declared illegal.
In 1908, I was arrested for leading resistance
and spent two months in prison, which strengthened
my determination to stand up for my beliefs.
On the streets, prejudice against Indians
remained.
In 1913, I led 2,500 Indians in a protest
and once again, I was arrested and put in
prison.
In Europe the First World War had begun, with
more violence and destruction than had ever
been seen before.
I was worried that such a conflict could happen
in India.
I wanted to help our nation develop in a peaceful
way, which I called Ahimsa, but I didn't know
what role I could play.
South Africa was burning with racial conflict.
We had children born in a country where Indians,
an Asian minority, were always seen as immigrants.
However, the Indian population was caught
in the middle of a larger battle - the tribal
groups fighting against the British and Dutch
settlers.
I wondered if I should be using my talents
in my own country.
After twenty-one years in South Africa, it
was time to return to India.
Aged 45, I took my family home.
***
In India, we had the same issues of prejudice.
Indians were subservient to the British and
we were a divided nation under the Raj.
We were also divided between Hindus, Muslims
and other religions.
My family and followers needed support and
so I set up a farm, a place for them to go,
called Sabarmati Ashram.
I believed that Indians, not the British,
should rule India, and my political campaign
for independence began when I spoke at the
Indian National Congress.
The turning point in my campaign happened
when I visited a place called Champaran.
Here my goal was to help poor farm workers
working for British landlords.
The British ordered me to leave, but I refused
and told the workers to hold non-violent protests.
I was arrested.
Hundreds of thousands of people marched in
mass protests and eventually, the law was
changed, giving the farm workers more control.
The 'satyagraha' non-violent approach had
worked.
News of the success spread through cities,
towns and villages but the prejudice and violence
did not stop.
In 1919 in Amritsar, the Jallianwala Bagh
massacre happened.
379 people were murdered and over 1,000 wounded,
and I realized that self-government for India
was essential.
By 1920, I was the president of the All India
Home Rule League and our cry was 'Independence
from the British Empire'.
In 1921, the 'swadeshi policy' was introduced
where we decided not to buy foreign goods,
particularly cloth from Britain.
Other protests were organized to raise political
awareness but it was a long, slow and difficult
process.
Those in power were reluctant to admit defeat.
Month after month, I travelled across India,
encouraging people to protest.
I was arrested and put in prison for two years
for trying to make people disobey the government.
No prison is pleasant but the conditions there
were truly terrible.
Despite this, they could not break my spirit
and on my release, I became president of the
Indian National Congress (the INC).
Support for our cause was growing and on 30th
January 1930, I published the Declaration
of Independence of India.
I had not forgotten the bitter war that took
place when the Americans made their own declaration
of independence from Britain all those years
before.
I decided on non-violent action.
On 12th March, I led a 385 kilometre march
to the Gujarat coast in the west of the country.
Here I committed an 'act of defiance' against
the British, who had a monopoly of the salt
production.
I made salt from sea water.
I was arrested for this 'crime' and immediately
non-violent protest broke out across India,
and thousands of Indians were imprisoned.
News of this had spread across the world and
the leader of the British in India, Lord Irwin,
wanted satyagraha to end.
I was released from prison and I promised
to give up the satyagraha salt campaign on
three conditions.
The first was the release of those who had
been imprisoned, the second was to allow Indians
to make their own salt.
The third was for the INC to be invited to
the 1931 Round Table talks in London, where
the future of India was to be discussed.
Irwin agreed and on 5th March 1931 we signed
the Gandhi-Irwin agreement.
I felt that the people of Britain needed to
know more about our cause.
While I was in England in 1931 attending the
Round Table talks, I was invited by the Davies
family, who owned several mills, to meet the
mill workers in the north of England.
The mills were the factories that made cloth
and many mill workers had lost their jobs
when India stopped buying British cloth.
The Davies family wanted me to see the hardship
that the now unemployed workers were experiencing.
I understood their difficulties and I tried
to be sympathetic, but I wanted to make them
understand how much worse living conditions
were for the Indians.
I hope I made an impression on them.
In 1932 I started another major protest against
British rule.
This time it was on behalf of India's disadvantaged
lowest caste, the Dalits, better known as
the 'untouchables'.
I preferred to call them Harijans - 'God's
Children'.
The British rulers were planning a new political
system that would increase discrimination
against the Dalits, and would damage Hindu
society.
To gain attention, I refused to eat.
To no one's surprise, I was again thrown into
prison.
Although I was furious, I kept to my principle
of non-violence and I still refused to eat.
After six days of fasting, it was agreed that
the new system would not be introduced, and
it seemed that our non-violent protest was
again having an effect.
***
There was, however, still much to protest
about and I spoke at many meetings.
The British officials objected and they arrested
me again.
Had they learnt nothing from the loss of their
American colonies?
How could such well-educated men act in such
stupid ways?
More long days were wasted in prison.
As a lawyer, I knew the law but what good
did it do me?
On my release, I was 63 years old and it was
time to travel.
Over the next four years, I toured rural communities.
The poverty was depressing, but the spirits
of the people uplifted me and gave me new
energy.
However, far away, there was more conflict
as the Second World War had begun.
As India was a British colony it became involved
in the war, with many fine men going into
battle.
My principles of non-violence were tested
to the full.
Could one be a pacifist when mass murder was
being committed?
If it had been Jains instead of Jews being
gassed, could I have stood by?
The reality of Nazism and the death camps
made me think about pacifism.
The major aim of the Indian National Congress
was for India to be free of British rule but
we also wanted the country to remain united.
For a long time there had been violent racial
conflict between Hindus and Muslims.
The Muslims had their own organization, the
Muslim League, which wanted India to be divided
so that there could be an independent Muslim
state.
This was something that the British also supported.
In 1942 I led a movement called 'Quit India',
calling for immediate independence and I was
arrested.
In the meantime, the Muslim League promised
the British that the Indian army, whose soldiers
were mainly Muslim, would continue to fight
with them.
This promise was on the understanding that
two things would happen.
Firstly, negotiations would begin for the
British to leave India, and secondly, before
they left, they would divide India to create
an independent Muslim state.
In the summer of 1947, Indian independence
from the British was declared.
This was on the day after the British created
the Muslim state of Pakistan, dividing India.
My wife did not live to see the independence
of India as she died in 1944.
I am sure she hadn't realized what marriage
to me meant - at the age of thirteen I did
not know myself what I was going to do with
my life.
In truth, I was more married to the causes
I was following than to her, but whether she
knew it or not, her support kept me going.
Four years later, my spirit was also set free
when I was assassinated at a prayer meeting.
Ironically, it was not the British or the
Pakistanis that fired the gun, both of whom
had their reasons for killing me, but a Hindu
nationalist.
The Life of Mahatma Gandhi
1869 Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi was born in
Porbandar, Gujarat, British India.
Later in life, he was referred to as Mahatma,
meaning 'great soul'.
1876 The family moved to Kajkot.
1883 At the age of 13, Gandhi married Kasturba
Makhanji, in an arranged marriage.
1885 The couple's first child was born, but
died a few days later.
1888 Gandhi went to England to study law at
University College London.
He joined the Vegetarian Society and developed
an interest in religious thought.
1891 He passed the bar examination for lawyers
in London.
He then returned to India to discover his
mother had died.
He opened a law practice, which was unsuccessful.
1893 Gandhi accepted a one-year contract from
an Indian firm to travel to South Africa and
work as a lawyer.
1894 He helped set up the Natal Indian Congress
and started to campaign for Indian rights.
1896 Gandhi returned to India and took his
family back to South Africa.
1901-1902 Gandhi returned to India to attend
the Indian National Congress, where he met
nationalist leaders.
He also opened a law firm in Mumbai.
1903 He opened a law office in Johannesburg.
1906 He led a protest against anti-Indian
laws.
1907 The Transvaal Government bought in a
new Act forcing registration of the Indian
population.
1908 Gandhi led a mass non-violent protest
using his method of satyagraha (devotion to
the truth).
Gandhi spent two months in prison.
1909 He wrote a book, Hind Swaraj, or Home
Rule, as it was called in English.
This was the blueprint for the Indian Independence
Movement.
1913 Gandhi led 2,500 Indian miners in a protest.
He was arrested and put in prison.
1914 Aged 45, he left South Africa and planned
to return to India, after making a short stopover
in England.
While he was travelling home, the First World
War broke out.
1915 Gandhi left England and returned to India.
He was welcomed as a hero.
He joined the Indian National Congress.
As a form of protest, he began the first of
many fasts.
1918-1919 Gandhi used his satyagraha method
during the Champaran and Kheda protests.
The local farmers were being forced to grow
crops that they could not use themselves,
but that were to be sold, and were being highly
taxed.
Gandhi also became a high-profile spokesperson
for Muslims in the Khilafat movement.
1919 The Jallianwala Bagh massacre took place.
Gandhi led the first nationwide campaign against
Britain's unfair rule.
1921 Gandhi took on leadership of the India
National Congress.
1922 He led a non-cooperation movement and,
as a result, he was arrested and imprisoned
for two years.
1925-1929 He wrote a series of articles, later
called The Story of My Experiments with Truth.
1930 The Indian National Congress declared
the independence of India.
Gandhi led the 385 km Dandi Salt March to
protest about the tax on salt, and was imprisoned.
He published the Declaration of Independence
of India.
The first Round Table Conference was held
in London, where not one representative from
the Indian National Congress was invited.
1931 The Gandhi-Irwin agreement was signed
and Gandhi attended the second Round Table
Conference in London.
He also visited the cloth mills in the north
of England.
1932 The Indian National Congress refused
to attend the third Round Table Conference.
Gandhi began a long fast to protest against
the British Government's treatment of the
Indian people.
1934 Gandhi launched the All India Village
Industries Association.
1942 Gandhi led the 'Quit India' movement,
during the Second World War.
He called for immediate independence and was
arrested by the British and held in Aga Khan
Palace, Pune.
1944 His wife, Kasturba, died.
1947 The Indo-Pakistan war took place.
The British divided the land to create Pakistan,
and India and Pakistan were each given independence
from British rule.
1948 Mahatma Gandhi died aged 78, as a result
of an assassination by a Hindu nationalist,
in New Delhi, India.
- THE END -