Samurai
In the old days in Japan, the samurai were
warriors, fighting men.
They served a daimyo, one of the great Japanese
lords.
They lived in his castle, fought for him,
and died for him.
They fought with long swords and short swords,
spears, and bows and arrows.
They were brave, fierce men, famous for their
loyalty to their lord.
CHAPTER ONE
The Death of Asano
'Good morning, Lord Asano.'
The speaker was Lord Kira Yoshinaka, a tall
man, in black.
He stood in the middle of a room in the Shogun's
palace.
He watched Lord Asano, and waited.
Lord Asano Naganori was a younger man, thirty-four
years to Lord Kira's sixty years.
He walked slowly across the room from the
door, and stopped in front of Kira.
'Lord Kira,' he said coldly.
'Good morning.'
And then he bowed, just a small bow of the
head.
Lord Kira bowed too, an even smaller bow.
He smiled, but his eyes were cold.
'Are you ready for your next lesson, Lord
Asano?' he said.
'You have much to learn about palace ceremony,
and you are a very slow student.
Shall we begin?'
Lord Asano bowed again, but did not speak.
His mouth was a thin, hard line.
Every day Kira called him 'slow', or 'stupid',
or 'difficult', and he did not like it.
In the Shogun's palace at Edo in the year
1701, ceremony was very important.
The right words, at the right time of day.
The right bow, small or deep, for different
people.
The right clothes, at different hours of the
day.
The right presents, for the right people...
This was the way of life in the Shogun's palace,
and Lord Kira was the teacher of ceremony
- for this Shogun, and for many Shoguns before
him.
After forty years as a teacher, Kira knew
everything about the ceremony of the palace.
But Lord Asano knew nothing.
He was a daimyo from the country, from Ako
Castle, a place seventeen days' journey by
horse to the south-west of Edo.
The daimyo were powerful men in Japan at this
time, and were rulers in their own part of
the country.
But daimyo must also serve the Shogun, and
every year the Shogun called two of them to
his palace at Edo.
'Every day is the same,' said Asano angrily,
at his house in Edo that evening.
'Every day I must do this ceremony, or that
ceremony, I must stand here, or there, bow
to this person, or that person.
And I must do six months of this!
Every day Kira calls me bad names!
I make mistakes because he is a bad teacher!'
Hayami, one of Asano's samurai, helped him
with his ceremonial clothes.
Hayami was very good with the bow and arrow,
but not so good with words.
'Lord, I heard something about Kira,' he said.
'What?' said Asano.
'He likes presents, and money.
The other daimyo gives him presents or money,
and then Kira is happy, and the lessons go
well.
Why don't you give him a present?'
'No!'
shouted Asano.
'I am Lord Asano of Ako, and I do not give
presents to the Shogun's servants!
His job is to teach me ceremony, not to ask
for presents!'
Hayami said nothing more, but he was afraid
for his master.
Every day Asano came back from the palace
with an angry face, and angry words.
'How is this going to end?'
Hayami said to Kataoka, another of Asano's
samurai.
'Four more months of this.
What can I do?
We need Oishi here.
Lord Asano doesn't listen to me, but he listens
to Oishi sometimes.'
But Oishi Yoshio was at Ako Castle, a long
way away.
He was the captain of Lord Asano's three hundred
samurai.
When Lord Asano came to Edo, most of his samurai
came with him, but Oishi stayed behind at
Ako to take care of everything there.
***
It ended suddenly on a spring day in 1701.
The day began well, with a blue sky and the
song of birds in the palace gardens.
Lord Asano arrived at the palace, put on his
ceremonial clothes, and went for his lesson
with Lord Kira.
Perhaps Kira was tired that day.
Perhaps he was angry because there were no
presents from Lord Asano.
Perhaps he just did not like the young lord
from Ako.
'You must wait,' he told Asano.
'I have another, more important meeting first.'
He turned his back on Lord Asano.
'What a stupid man!'
Kira said.
Usually, he said things like this in a quiet
voice, but today he did not speak quietly,
and everybody in the great palace room could
hear him.
'I hear Asano's wife is stupid too, and his
children,' Lord Kira said to the room.
Something broke inside Lord Asano.
'Lord Kira, stop a moment,' he cried.
'Well, what is it?' said Kira, turning back
to Asano.
People remembered this moment for many years.
Asano drew his sword, and attacked Lord Kira.
With a cry, Kira put his hand to his head,
but he did not fall.
Asano lifted his sword again, but now there
were palace guards around him.
They: pulled him to the floor, and held his
sword arm.
Lord Kira ran away.
There was a deep cut on his face.
The Shogun's palace was a place of ceremony,
not a place for fighting.
It was a terrible thing to do - to draw a
sword and attack someone inside the palace.
The attack happened at about midday.
At one o'clock the guards took Asano to the
house of another daimyo.
At four o'clock an order came from the Shogun.
'Lord Asano must die, but because he is a
daimyo, he can die the samurai way, with honour.
He can commit seppuku.'
And so it happened.
At six o'clock that same day Lord Asano of
Ako committed seppuku.
He took out his long knife, and cut into his
stomach from left to right.
Outside the palace Lord Asano's samurai, Kataoka,
knew nothing of this.
He waited for his master to leave the palace
at the end of the day, but Asano never came.
At last another daimyo told Kataoka the terrible
news.
Kataoka ran back to Asano's house in Edo,
and called for Hayami and the other samurai.
'Our lord is dead,' he cried.
'Get the horses ready!
We must ride to Ako at once!'
CHAPTER TWO
The Plan
At that time, it was usually a journey of
seventeen days from Edo to Ako, but Kataoka
and Hayami did the journey in ten days.
When they arrived at Ako Castle, they were
tired, dirty, hungry, and thirsty.
Oishi Yoshio, the captain of the Ako samurai,
was not pleased with them.
'Look at you!' he said.
'What kind of samurai are you?
Dirty clothes, dirty horses...'
But Oishi forgot about that when he heard
the terrible news of Lord Asano's death.
'And that's not all,' said Hayami.
He pushed the hair out of his eyes.
'The Shogun's government is going to take
Lord Asano's castle, his land, his money - everything!
Can they do that, Oishi?'
'Yes,' said Oishi.
'They can.
To draw a sword in the Shogun's palace is
a crime.
But why did Lord Asano attack Kira?
What happened?
Did they fight?'
'We don't know,' said Kataoka, 'we weren't
there!
But Lord Asano was angry every day because
of Lord Kira.'
'But Asano didn't kill Kira?' said Oishi.
'No,' said Hayami.
'Kira is alive and well.
People say that he just has a cut on his head.'
'And where is Lord Asano's body now?' asked
Oishi.
'They're taking it to the temple of Sengaku-ji,'
said Kataoka, 'just outside Edo.
Some of our samurai went with the body.
Then they are coming back to Ako.'
***
During the next days, Lord Asano's samurai
made the journey down to Ako.
Some of them brought news.
'Lord Asano's younger brother, Daigaku, is
under house arrest in Edo,' Yoshida told Oishi.
Yoshida was one of the older samurai.
He and Oishi were old friends.
'Did you see Daigaku?'
asked Oishi.
'Yes, just for two minutes.
They're going to send him away, to Hiroshima,
to the Asano family there.'
Soon there were nearly three hundred of Asano's
samurai at Ako, and Oishi Yoshio called a
meeting.
It was a noisy, angry meeting.
Horibe was a famous swordsman.
He was a fierce fighter, and a brave man,
but he did not often stop to think before
he spoke.
He was the first to speak.
'Lord Asano is dead because of Kira,' he shouted
to the meeting.
'Kira is a killer.
A man cannot live under the same sky as the
killer of his lord.
This is the code of the samurai!
When do we attack Kira?'
The samurai began to talk, but Oishi held
up his hand.
'Nobody questions your honour as a samurai,
Horibe.
But we are not samurai now, we are ronin.
We have no master, no lord.
The Shogun's government killed Lord Asano
because of a crime - the crime of drawing
a sword in the palace.
And why did this crime happen?
Because of Lord Kira.
We want revenge for our lord's death, and
that means Kira must die.
But he knows that, and he has many friends
in the government.
So we must be careful, we must be clever.'
'Careful?
Clever?'
shouted Horibe.
'What kind of samurai are you?
We must attack Lord Kira at once!
In Edo, people in the streets are saying that.
They know we must take revenge for Asano's
death.
People want us to do that!
It is the samurai way!'
'So you want to die a dog's death outside
the palace?'
called Yoshida.
'How many guards are there at the palace?
Eh?
Tell me that!
Hundreds!
We can't get near Kira - he knows we want
him, so he has hundreds of guards around him,
day and night.'
'The government is going to take Ako Castle
away from the Asano family,' called another
samurai.
'When the government soldiers come here, can
we fight them?
Can we hold Ako Castle for Daigaku?
He's the head of the Asano family now.'
Kataoka answered this question.
'For a week, perhaps.
But not longer.
No, the Asano family at Ako is finished.
We must leave Ako Castle and begin new lives
as ronin.'
'So what can we do?'
called Okuda, one of Horibe's friends.
'Tell us, Oishi!
What can we do?'
'What do you want?' said Oishi.
'Do you want revenge?
Revenge has a price, and the price is death.
We cannot hope to live after we take our revenge
on Kira.
We must commit seppuku - everyone of us.'
'We are samurai!'
cried a man called Hara.
'Death with honour is always better than a
life without honour.
That is the samurai code!'
Oishi smiled.
'There are brave hearts in this room.
Now go away, and think.
Think about the samurai way.
Where is the road to honour?
Can you live under the same sky as the killer
of your daimyo?
Think long and carefully.
Talk to your families, and come back here
in three days.
Or leave Ako and begin a new life.'
In the next two days many ronin left the castle.
They took their families and went away, perhaps
to serve a new daimyo, perhaps to work in
the cities, perhaps to go hungry.
The life of a ronin was not easy.
After three days Oishi called the next meeting.
He and Yoshida stood at the door and watched.
Horibe, Okuda, and their friends arrived first,
of course.
Then more came, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty...
sixty-two.
Yoshida closed the doors, and Oishi began
to speak.
'You are here because you want revenge for
the death of our daimyo.
You are true samurai, loyal to your lord in
life - and in death.
We must make a league together - a league
for revenge.
But for now, we must be silent, we must be
secret, we must wait for months, maybe years,
before we can move.
We cannot attack Kira now, because he and
his guards are waiting for us.
But when he forgets about us, then we can
move.
Because we, the ronin - we do not forget.
We can wait a long, long time for revenge.'
CHAPTER THREE
The Long Wait
And so it was.
The soldiers of the Shogun's government came
to Ako, took the castle and the land.
And then the sixty-two ronin left Ako to go
their different ways.
Oishi talked to every ronin in the league
before they left Ako, and every man had a
plan.
Some of the ronin went to Edo.
There, they found jobs as workmen, guards,
or gardeners.
Other ronin went to live in Osaka or other
cities.
'Live very quietly,' Oishi told them.
'Don't talk about revenge, don't talk about
anything to anybody.
Meet secretly, and be careful of spies.
Kira's men are going to be everywhere, watching
and listening, all the time.'
Oishi took his family, his wife and three
children, to live near Kyoto.
Three of the ronin went with him - Kataoka,
Mimura, and Hara.
Kataoka and Mimura lived in Oishi's house,
and Hara found a job.
'What kind of job?' said Oishi.
Hara laughed.
'I'm teaching boys how to shoot with bow and
arrows,' he said.
'That's not a job for a samurai!' said Kataoka.
'But we're not samurai now, we're ronin, remember?'
said Hara.
'And a ronin needs rice to eat.'
***
Weeks went past, and weeks turned into months.
Oishi began to live a very different life
now from his old life as captain of the Asano
samurai.
Every day he went into the town, to the old
houses down by the river.
He made new friends, and spent his time with
bad people.
Often, he was out all night.
Kataoka and Mimura watched this, and they
were not happy about it.
'Why does he go to these places?' said Mimura.
'Why don't you ask him?'
Kataoka said.
'Not me!'
Mimura said.
'He gets angry when you ask questions.
He gets angry at bad news too.
You remember when the news came about the
seven ronin?'
Seven of the ronin from Ako did not want to
be in the league against Kira any longer.
The numbers were now down to fifty-five.
One day more news arrived - from one of the
ronin in Edo.
This man, Isogai, worked in the Shogun's palace
gardens.
He could watch government workers when they
came and went, and sometimes he heard things.
He sent this message to Oishi.
Lord Kira does not work in the palace now.
His job is finished.
People say that the Shogun is not pleased
with him.
Kira is living in his daimyo house, a big
mansion near the Sumida river.
Horibe says, can we attack him now?
Oishi suddenly came alive again.
'No, no, no!
Not yet!' he said.
'I must go to Edo and talk to them.
Kataoka, come with me.
Mimura - stay here with my family.'
In Edo, Oishi met secretly with some of the
ronin in the league.
'Listen,' he said.
'Kira's wife is from the Uesugi family, and
they are very rich and powerful.
There are many Uesugi guards around Kira's
mansion, because he is still afraid of us.
We can never get past all those guards with
just fifty-five men.
We must wait.'
'But how long?' said Horibe.
'Kira is an old man, and he could die any
day!
Where is our revenge then?'
'Begin planning,' said Oishi.
'Everybody has swords, but we need armour,
spears, and bows and arrows.
You can begin to find them, but secretly.
And hide them well!'
Oishi and Kataoka went back to Kyoto, and
again, Oishi spent his nights in the town
with all kinds of bad men.
People began saying that Oishi was a samurai
without honour.
Hara came to visit one day, and was angry.
'This is not good!' he said fiercely to Oishi.
'Where is your honour as a samurai?'
'Get out!'
shouted Oishi.
'Get out of my house!'
Kataoka walked with Hara down the street.
'What's happening to him?' said Hara.
'Why is he doing this?'
'It's all right,' said Kataoka.
'Just go home, and wait.'
It was not a happy house.
When he was there, Oishi shouted at everyone
- his wife, his children, Kataoka, Mimura,
the house servants.
Mimura often went out walking in the town,
to get away from the house and all the shouting.
One dark night he saw the cook from Oishi's
house at a street corner, talking to two men.
When they saw him, they stopped talking, and
the cook walked quickly away.
Mimura crossed the street to look at the two
men, but they turned away and went into a
house.
And in the light from the house doorway, Mimura
saw something very interesting...
He ran home at once with his news.
'Oishi, I think your cook is a spy for Kira!
Those men had on their coats the sign of the
Uesugi family.
It was very small, but I saw it clearly in
the light!'
'Ha!'
cried Kataoka.
'What shall we do with this spying cook, Oishi?
Kill him?'
Oishi smiled.
'Nothing,' he said.
'Nothing?' said Kataoka.
'We can't do "nothing"!'
'Oh yes, we can,' said Oishi.
'This is very good.
We want this spy to send news back to Kira
- the right kind of news.
We know the cook is a spy, but the cook doesn't
know that we know.
So this is good for us.
He can tell Kira that I am now a samurai without
honour.
And who is afraid of a samurai without honour?'
'Aaah!' said Mimura.
'I think I begin to understand.'
'Good,' said Oishi.
'At last.'
Kataoka laughed.
'So,' Oishi said, 'when you talk in the house,
be careful.
Remember who is listening.'
Suddenly, he began to shout at them.
'Get out!
I'm going out into town, and nobody is going
to stop me!'
Kataoka and Mimura left the room, smiling.
***
Time passed.
Spring 1702 came, and then summer.
The death of Lord Asano of Ako was now more
than a year ago.
In the streets of Edo, there was no talk of
revenge by the Asano samurai.
They were just ronin, living here and there
in different cities in Japan.
Their captain, Oishi Yoshio, was without honour,
and spent his time with bad men.
Kira began to feel safer, and the Uesugi guards
around his home went back to the Uesugi mansion
across the river.
At the end of the summer Oishi came home late
one night after an evening down by the river
in Kyoto.
When he came into the house, he shouted noisily.
'Riku!
Riku!
Where are you?
Come here!'
Riku, his wife of twenty years, came quietly
into the room, and Oishi began to shout at
her.
'I'm tired of you - I don't want to see your
face again.
Go away!
Leave my house!
Go back to your father's house - our marriage
is ended.
I can find more beautiful girls in the town.
Go!'
Riku put her face in her hands and began to
cry, very quietly.
From the other side of the room, Oishi shouted
some more.
Riku did not move.
Then she said, very quietly, 'Must I go?'
Oishi came and stood in front of her.
He put his mouth close to her ear, and spoke
in a whisper.
'The time is coming.
I don't want you here in this house when it
happens.
You know why.
So I must send you away, back to your father.
The government cannot do anything to you when
you live in your father's house.
That is best for you, and the children.'
Riku looked into his face.
'Yes, I understand.
Do you want me to take all the children with
me?'
They still spoke in whispers, because in that
house the walls had ears.
'The younger children, yes,' said Oishi.
'But Chikara is fifteen, nearly sixteen now,
and a man.
He is ready to be a samurai.
He can go with you, or he can stay with me.
Ask him.
Tell him to come and see me in the morning.'
Riku looked into his face one more time, then
turned to go.
Oishi put out his hand, and touched her face,
just for a second.
Then he, too, turned away.
That night he did not sleep.
He sat for a long time in the dark, looking
out at the stars in the night sky.
In the early morning his son Chikara found
him there.
'Father, I want to stay here with you.
I want to be a samurai, and I am ready.
I am a good swordsman now.'
Oishi put his hand on his son's shoulder.
'Good man,' he said.
'The league needs strong swordsmen like you.'
He was silent for a minute.
'Did you say goodbye to your mother?' he asked.
'Yes,' Chikara said.
'She left an hour ago.
She...'
He did not finish.
'Yes.
I know,' said Oishi.
'But this is the life of a samurai.
Come - we have work to do.'
CHAPTER FOUR
The Attack
Autumn came.
The leaves turned yellow and gold, and fell
from the trees.
Oishi sent messages to the ronin, and one
by one they began to arrive in Edo.
They travelled at different times, and went
to different 'safe houses' in the city.
Oishi made the journey in November 1702.
When he arrived in Edo, he called a meeting
in a room above a noisy restaurant.
'Now you must decide, for the last time,'
he told his men.
'Do you want revenge for Lord Asano, or not?
Some of you, I know, have young children,
or very old parents.
Do those men want to leave the league?
You can go with honour.'
Eight men left.
There were now forty-seven ronin in the league.
There were young men and old men - the youngest
was Chikara, now aged sixteen, and the oldest
was seventy-six.
There were brothers, and some fathers and
sons, like Oishi and Chikara.
In the weeks before the attack, many of the
ronin wrote letters home to their wives and
families - to say their last goodbyes.
They began to get ready.
One ronin had a ground plan of Kira's mansion,
and Oishi studied this very carefully.
There were high walls around the house - 132
metres on the long side and 61 metres on the
short side.
There were two gates, one in the east wall
and one in the west wall.
Inside the walls, there was a long building,
with courtyards and gardens all around it.
'We need to go in at both gates at the same
time,' said Oishi.
'We must have two groups of men, one to attack
the front gate and one to attack the back
gate.'
'Yes,' Yoshida said.
'And we must stop any servant from leaving
the mansion.
We don't want them to run across the river
to the Uesugi and call for help.'
There were high walls around the mansion.
'How many people are living in Kira's mansion?'
asked Hayami.
'And how many of them are samurai?'
'There are more than a hundred and twenty
people inside those walls,' said Okuda.
'Perhaps about fifty of them are guards...
We don't know how many samurai.'
'What about our weapons?' asked Oishi, looking
at Horibe.
'The weapons are ready,' Horibe said.
'Everybody has their swords.
We have spears for everybody too, and many
bows and arrows.
And we have armour.'
'Good,' said Oishi.
'So now we wait for the right time, when Kira
is at home.'
***
The right time came on December 14, 1702,
a dark night with snow falling from the sky.
The people of Edo slept quietly, warm in their
houses, but the ronin put on their armour,
took their weapons, and waited for midnight.
Before they left, Oishi spoke to his men.
'At last we can finish our work for Lord Asano,
and take revenge for his death, now nearly
two years ago.
We are here to kill Lord Kira Yoshinaka.
We must fight his guards and his samurai,
yes, and kill them, but do not kill women
and children.
We are not here to do that.
And remember, you all have a whistle.
When you find Lord Kira, blow your whistle.'
Then the forty-seven ronin went silently through
the snow to Lord Kira's mansion.
Oishi and Hara took their group to the front
gate, and Yoshida with Oishi's son Chikara
took their group of men to the back gate.
Outside the mansion they put signs in the
streets:
WE, THE RONIN FROM AKO CASTLE, ARE TAKING
OUR REVENGE ON KIRA YOSHINAKA TONIGHT, FOR
THE DEATH OF OUR DAIMYO, LORD ASANO NAGANORI.
WE ARE NOT NIGHT THIEVES AND DO NOT PLAN TO
ATTACK OTHER PEOPLE.
YOU ARE SAFE IN YOUR HOUSES.
Later, when the neighbours came out into the
streets, they saw the signs, and went back
into their houses.
They did not like Lord Kira, and so did nothing
to help him.
At the front gate, four men climbed over the
wall, and went silently into the guardroom.
They fought the guards and tied them up.
Then they broke down the gate from the inside,
and Oishi and his men came into the courtyard.
At the same time, at the back gate, Yoshida
and Chikara and their men climbed over the
wall into the back courtyard.
They tied up the guards there; then waited
quietly in the snow.
Before the attack began, Oishi sent four men
up onto the walls with bows and arrows.
The great mansion was still dark and silent,
and Oishi whispered his orders.
'Lord Kira's servants are going to try and
run away to get help,' he said.
'Watch carefully, and shoot them down at once.
Nobody must leave!'
Now everything was ready, and Oishi beat his
drum loudly.
The sound of the drum told the men at both
gates to start the attack at the same moment.
The ronin ran through the courtyards and gardens,
and broke into the house at the front and
the back.
By now, everybody in the mansion was awake,
and Lord Kira's men, still in their nightclothes,
came running with swords and spears and knives.
Suddenly, the night was full of noise - men
shouting, the sound of sword against sword,
the cries of women and children...
In the great front room of the mansion, the
fighting was very fierce.
Three of Kira's samurai, all famous swordsmen,
fought for a long time, and Oishi's men could
not get past them into the rooms behind.
But the ronin fought hard too, and in the
end Hara and two other ronin killed the three
samurai.
Then Oishi's men moved on into the next rooms.
At the other end of the long mansion, the
fighting was also fierce.
One of Kira's samurai attacked Yoshida, and
jumped in under Yoshida's sword arm with his
knife.
Yoshida fell back, but Horibe was right behind
the samurai, and cut him down with his long
sword.
Then the two ronin moved on into the next
room.
Soon there was fighting in every room.
Lord Kira's men fought bravely, but the ronin
were fierce and deadly.
Many men died, and some were hurt, but not
one of the ronin died that night.
In every room Oishi and his men looked for
Lord Kira, but he was never there.
At last the two groups of ronin met in the
middle of the mansion, and the fighting came
to a stop.
Seventeen of Kira's guards and samurai were
dead, and the others ran away.
Women and children sat in the corners of rooms,
crying.
Oishi called out to Yoshida, 'Kira?
Where is he?'
'I don't know,' called Yoshida.
'He wasn't in the rooms at the back of the
house when we came through.'
'What about the family living rooms?'
called Horibe.
'Let's look in there again.'
'We can't lose Kira now!'
shouted Okuda.
'Come on!'
The ronin began to feel afraid.
Where was Lord Kira?
Was he still in the mansion somewhere?
Or did he escape when the fighting began?
They ran through the family rooms, looking
everywhere.
In Kira's sleeping-room Oishi put his hand
on the bed-clothes.
'They're warm!' he shouted.
'The bed-clothes are still warm - he was here
not long ago!
Find him!'
CHAPTER FIVE
The Revenge
Oishi sent his men, in four groups, to look
everywhere - in the house, the kitchens, the
gardens, the courtyards, the guardrooms, under
the floors...
In the courtyard by the north wall, three
of the ronin found a wood store.
One of them, Hazama, went inside, and pushed
his spear deep into the wood.
There was a sudden cry, from under the wood.
Immediately, the three ronin began to pull
the wood out, and very quickly they found
an old man, dressed in white nightclothes.
'Old man, what is your name?' said Hazama.
The old man said nothing.
He sat on the snowy ground, with his hands
over his face.
'It's him,' said one of the ronin.
'Quick - blow your whistle.'
When they heard the whistle, all the ronin
came running, with Oishi at the front.
Oishi carried a light, and held it near the
old man's face.
'Yes, it's Kira,' he said to his men.
'See - here, on his head, that old cut.
It was a cut made by a sword...
Lord Asano's sword.
It's in the right place.'
Oishi stood up, and bowed deeply to the old
man.
'Lord Kira Yoshinaka, we are the samurai of
Asano Naganori.
We are loyal men, loyal to our master, and
so we are here tonight to take revenge for
his death.
Lord Asano committed seppuku, and so we ask
you, Lord Kira, to commit seppuku too - to
die bravely, with honour.'
On the ground in front of Kira, Oishi carefully
placed a long knife.
'Here, Lord Kira, is a knife.
Lord Asano's knife.'
But the old man did nothing.
He sat on the ground, shaking from head to
toe, not speaking.
Again and again, Oishi asked him to commit
seppuku.
Again and again, he showed him Lord Asano's
knife.
But Lord Kira did not move or put out his
hand to take the knife.
He did not want to take the road to death
with honour.
At last, Oishi Yoshio stood up.
He bowed again to Lord Kira; then he drew
his sword and cut off Lord Kira's head.
The ronin put a coat around the head and tied
it to a spear.
It was three o'clock in the morning, and their
long wait for revenge was finished.
'And now,' said Oishi, 'we must leave at once
and take the head to Lord Asano's grave at
Sengaku-ji.
We must do this last thing for Lord Asano,
and then we are ready for death.
'But before we leave,' he said, 'we must put
out the house fires.
We don't want to start a fire in the city.'
The house was full of dead bodies and crying
women, and there was no one to take care of
things.
Edo was a city of buildings made of wood,
and fire was a terrible danger.
They put out the fires, and forty-six ronin
left the mansion.
The forty-seventh ronin, a young man called
Terasaka, was now on his way to Hiroshima.
Oishi sent him there to take the news of the
attack to Daigaku, the brother of Lord Asano.
Two of the ronin carried the spear with Lord
Kira's head, and Oishi walked in front, with
Yoshida on one side and Chikara on the other
side.
They began their long walk to Sengaku-ji.
And in the streets of Edo, people came out
of their houses to watch.
CHAPTER SIX
The Punishment
The Asano family graves were next to the temple
at Sengaku-ji, and it was a ten-kilometre
walk there from Kira's mansion.
The ronin were afraid of attack from the Uesugi
guards, so they kept away from Edo Palace
and walked on the eastern side of the Sumida
River until the Eitai bridge.
Then they crossed the river.
Oishi sent two of the ronin to Edo Palace,
to take the news of the ronins' revenge to
the government.
In the first light of day more and more people
came out into the streets - talking and whispering
about the killing of Lord Kira and the revenge
of the forty-seven ronin.
The news ran like fire through the city.
And the people liked the news.
'What brave men!'
they said.
'What loyal samurai!
These ronin waited nearly two years to take
their revenge!
That is the samurai code!
They are true samurai, like in the old days.'
The ronin passed Zojo-ji temple, and began
to climb the hill to Sengaku-ji.
When they arrived at the temple, they washed
Lord Kira's head in the well (you can see
the well to this day at Sengaku-ji).
Then, slowly and carefully, Oishi placed the
head in front of Lord Asano's grave.
The forty-six ronin kneeled before the grave,
and Oishi spoke these words: 'For many years,
Lord Asano, we served you, we ate your food,
we lived in your castle.
You tried to kill your enemy, but you lost
your life.
We could not live under the same sky as your
enemy.
Last night we finished your work, and took
revenge for your death.
'Young and old, we, the ronin of Ako, are
your loyal servants.
We serve you, by sword and by spear, in life
and in death.'
***
For two days Kira's head lay on Lord Asano's
grave at Sengaku-ji.
Then the temple priests took it away and sent
it back to his family.
The Shogun's officers arrested the forty-six
ronin and took them to the mansions of four
different daimyo.
There, the ronin waited to hear their punishment.
Oishi, with sixteen of his men, went to the
Hosokawa mansion near Sengaku-ji.
To honour them, 1,400 samurai walked with
them through the snowy streets, and the people
of the city watched.
Now came a difficult time for the Shogun and
the government.
Killing was a crime, and in those days the
punishment for that crime was to cut off the
head.
But a death like that was a death without
honour.
Many people said this: 'The ronin are good
samurai - brave men, loyal to their master.
They were right to kill Kira and to take revenge
for their lord's death.
They followed the samurai code of honour,
so they must have a samurai death.'
But other people thought differently, and
said this: 'Lord Asano attacked Lord Kira
in the palace, and Asano died because of this
crime.
Lord Kira did not kill him, so there was no
need for revenge.
This was not a revenge killing, and the ronin
are just killers.
So they must die a killer's death.'
The government could not agree on the punishment.
For weeks they talked and argued, asked this
person and that person, talked and argued
again.
The ronin waited quietly in the four daimyo
houses.
They waited for death, one way or another.
At last, one day in March 1703, many weeks
after the death of Kira, the order came from
the Shogun's palace.
The ronin must die, but because of their loyalty
to their lord, they could die the samurai
death.
They could commit seppuku and keep their honour
as samurai.
That same day, in the four daimyo mansions,
the ronin got ready for death.
One by one, in the courtyards of the mansions,
the forty-six ronin committed seppuku.
Their bodies were put in graves at Sengaku-ji
temple, close to their master, Lord Asano
Naganori.
The forty-seventh ronin, Terasaka, arrived
back from Hiroshima after the death of the
other ronin.
He went at once to Edo Palace, and asked for
the same death as the other ronin.
But he was a young man, and the Shogun felt
sorry for him.
So Terasaka did not commit seppuku.
He lived to the great age of eighty-three,
but when he died, he wanted to be with the
other ronin.
So his grave is the forty-seventh grave at
Sengaku-ji.
Sengaku-ji today
Three hundred years later, people in Japan
are still talking and arguing about the story
of the Forty-Seven Ronin.
Every year, on December 14, there is a festival
at the Sengaku-ji temple to remember Lord
Asano's death and the revenge of his brave,
loyal ronin.
Thousands of people come every year to this
festival.
The way of the samurai is not forgotten.
- THE END -