CHAPTER ONE
The Future
Friday, 15th July 1988
Rankeillor Street, Edinburgh, Scotland
'The important thing in life is to make a
difference - to make a change to something,'
the girl said.
'Ah - you mean we have to change the world?'
the boy replied.
'No, not all of the world, we just have to
change the bit of it around us,' the girl
said.
She was silent for a moment, then she laughed
at herself.
'I can't believe I said that.
It's such a predictable thing to say, isn't
it?
But what are you going to do with your life?
What's your plan?'
'Well, my parents are coming to collect me
later today,' he told her.
'Then I'll go to France for a few weeks and
after that, maybe I'll go to China.'
'Oh, you're going travelling,' she said wearily.
'You're predictable too.
You've got too much money, that's your problem,
Dexter.
What you really mean is that you're running
away from real life.'
'Travelling broadens the mind, Emma,' he said
slowly.
He was trying to copy the girl's accent.
Suddenly, he leaned over her and kissed her.
'I think you're too broad-minded now,' the
girl said, quickly turning her face away from
him.
The girl was from Yorkshire, in the north
of England.
She was used to posh boys from the south making
fun of her soft northern accent.
Sometimes she didn't care, but now she suddenly
felt annoyed with the boy.
Everything was going wrong tonight.
'Anyway, I'm not talking about the immediate
future,' she told him.
'I'm not asking about tomorrow, I'm asking
what you want to be in twenty years from now.'
At first, the best answer he could think of
was 'I want to be rich and famous'.
But then he thought a bit more and spoke seriously.
'I don't ever want to be different from this,'
he said.
'I'd like to stay exactly as I am now.
Every fifteenth of July, I want to be just
like this.'
The girl was called Emma Morley.
The boy's name was Dexter Mayhew.
They were lying on the narrow bed in Emma's
room in a shared flat.
It was four o'clock in the morning.
The two young people didn't know each other
very well, but certainly this was a night
for thinking about the future.
It was the last night of their university
life in Edinburgh.
Earlier in the day, after four years, they
had finally graduated.
Soon they would go in separate directions.
Emma looked up at the boy as he leaned over
her.
She was a little annoyed with him, but she
still thought that he was handsome.
'Mm - handsome.
Perhaps "beautiful" is a better word,' she
thought.
And she knew that lots of the other girl students
agreed with her - especially the posh ones
from the south.
They all knew that he would get their clothes
off and get them into his bed.
His body was muscular and the skin of his
face was tight.
His eyebrows were slim and his lips were full.
'Yes, he's beautiful, but he looks a little
like a cat,' Emma told herself.
'I think I can imagine you when you're forty,'
she said unkindly.
'You'll have an expensive red sports car and
live in the most expensive part of London.
You'll be married to your third wife - no,
I'm wrong, your fourth wife.
There won't be any children.
You're too selfish for children.
No children, just three expensive divorces.'
'Well, Em,' Dexter began crossly.
'Who's "Em"?'
Emma quickly asked.
'Your friends call you "Em", I've heard them
call you that,' he said.
'Ah, yes, my friends call me that,' Emma replied.
'Can't I call you that?' he asked.
He sounded worried.
'Oh, all right then, Dex,' she said.
'Go on.'
'Well, if you think I'm so terrible why are
you sleeping with me?' he asked.
'Well, I don't think I really have slept with
you, have I?' she replied.
'You can choose either meaning of "sleep"
- I mean, we haven't been to sleep and we
haven't done anything else, have we?'
'No,' the boy said, 'no, we haven't quite
done that.'
Tonight Emma had wanted something different.
She wasn't sure what it was, but their names
sounded good together.
'Emma and Dexter,' she thought.
'Em and Dex.'
'Wait there,' Emma said.
'I'm just going to the bathroom.
Don't go away.'
She put on her thick glasses and walked towards
the door.
In the bathroom, Emma asked herself why she
was being difficult with the boy.
'He's certainly very bourgeois and he isn't
very clever, but I really like him,' she told
herself.
Emma had liked Dexter since she'd first met
him at a party two years before.
But she'd never got to know him and in just
a few hours he would be gone.
And he certainly wasn't going to ask her to
go to China with him.
It was a bit sad.
For the first time in four years she was with
a boy she really liked.
But she couldn't relax with him.
They had been kissing and talking for eight
hours now and she still didn't know what she
wanted.
Dexter, waiting in the bedroom, looked around
him.
He had been in so many rooms like this one
- rooms where girls like Emma lived.
These girls always wore t-shirts with political
slogans on the fronts.
There were always political posters on their
walls.
There were always CDs of political songs.
They were all the same, these girls with socialist
ideas.
They always thought that he was horribly bourgeois
and they always thought that being bourgeois
was bad.
Well, he had news for them.
He thought that being bourgeois was just fine.
Dexter hadn't really decided yet on a map
for his future life.
But he was twenty-three years old and he had
some ambitions.
He wanted to be successful at something - he
just didn't know at what.
He wanted to make his parents proud of him.
He wanted to meet lots of women.
He wanted to have lots of fun in his life
and he wanted never to be sad.
Thinking about fun and sadness, Dexter was
now feeling that this night had been a mistake.
There were going to be tears.
There were going to be angry phone calls.
Emma returned and lay down beside him again.
She had put on a t-shirt with a political
slogan on the front.
'Do you mind if we just cuddle, Dex?'
Emma said.
Dexter didn't think this was a good idea at
all, but he didn't say so.
'OK, if that's what you want,' he said, without
interest.
'I can't believe I just said "cuddle",' Emma
said, after a minute of silence.
'What a terrible bourgeois word for me to
use!
I'm sorry.'
'We must get some sleep,' said Dexter.
He was thinking, 'This must never happen again.'
There was daylight outside the window.
Dexter was still awake and he was looking
at Emma, who was sleeping next to him.
'I could leave quietly now, before she wakes
up,' he told himself.
'Then I don't need to see her again.
Will she mind?
Probably, girls usually do mind.
But will I mind?'
It was strange, but the answer to this was
not clear to Dexter.
There was something about Emma.
She was pretty, but she seemed to hate herself
for that.
The red colour of her hair was out of a bottle
and her hairstyle was awful.
Dexter guessed that Emma's hair had been cut
by Tilly Killick, the large, noisy girl who
lived in the other room in this flat.
'But never mind the hair,' Dexter thought.
'Her face is really pretty and her body's
amazing.'
Soon he decided that he would leave quietly,
never mind what Emma's face and body were
like.
'I'll probably never see her again,' he told
himself.
Dexter was about to get quietly out of bed
when Emma woke up.
'What are you doing later today?'
she asked, sleepily.
'Tell her you're busy!' said a voice in Dexter's
head.
'I don't have any plans,' he said aloud.
'Shall we do something together then?'
she asked.
'Yes, all right,' Dexter said.
A moment later, Emma was asleep again.
CHAPTER TWO
Real Life
Saturday, 15th July 1989
Wolverhampton, England and Rome, Italy
Emma Morley was writing a letter.
Stoke Park School, Wolverhampton
Hello Dexter,
How are you?
How is Rome?
How is La Dolce Vita?
(Try a dictionary!)
I know that some people call Rome 'the eternal
city' but I've been here in Wolverhampton
for two days now and they have felt eternal
to me.
So perhaps Wolverhampton should be called
by that name.
Ha ha.
Well, I decided to take the job I told you
about, so I'm working with Sledgehammer Theatre.
It's a Theatre-in-Education group.
For the past month, we've been touring schools
with a play about slavery.
Today we're performing it at this fine school.
Anyway, we try to show 11-13-year olds that
slavery was A BAD THING.
Aren't we brave and original!
Really, I don't know why I am being nasty
about my job.
A lot of the kids have never thought about
social problems of the past until now.
And now some of them - the ones that don't
throw things at us - are becoming really interested.
So I still think that we can make a difference
for people.
Emma was trying to be positive.
She had to try hard.
The last year had been full of mistakes.
After her graduation, she had stayed on in
Edinburgh.
But she had made a series of bad career choices.
There was the terrible all-girl band she had
played in.
There was her first novel, which she had stopped
writing.
There was her second novel, which she had
also stopped writing.
She had worked in shops, trying to sell things
to tourists.
But the tourists never really wanted the things
she tried to sell them.
So finally she had moved back to Yorkshire
to live with her parents.
That wasn't good either.
'But you've got a really good degree,' Emma's
mother said almost daily.
'Why on earth don't you use it to get yourself
a good job?'
From time to time, Dexter Mayhew became part
of her life for a few days.
At the end of the summer, she had gone to
stay at his rich parents' huge house in the
countryside.
But that had gone terribly wrong.
Emma had had too much to drink one evening
and had argued with Dexter's father about
politics.
She had shouted at him and told him he was
a bourgeois fascist.
Then, more recently, they had met up in London
for the birthday party of one of their friends
- a man called Callum O'Neill.
Callum had shared a flat with Dexter in Edinburgh.
He now had a successful business selling computers.
Dexter and Emma had spent the day after the
party together.
Most of the day they lay on the grass in Kensington
Gardens.
They drank wine from a bottle and they talked.
They never quite touched each other and Dexter
told her all about a wonderful Spanish girl
called Lola.
Emma decided that this was all their friendship
was ever going to be.
Clearly, Dexter didn't want to sleep with
her.
He wanted to tell her about the other girls
he slept with.
But strangely, Dexter also told her that his
mother had liked her very much.
'She says she has a good feeling about you
and me,' he'd said.
At the time, Emma hadn't understood the importance
of Dexter's words.
Emma didn't know that Dexter loved his mother
more than anyone in the world.
And she didn't know that Dexter's mother felt
the same about him.
Then Dexter had gone travelling again.
When he was away, Emma wrote him long letters.
He usually replied on postcards.
'We're just pen pals now,' Emma told herself.
'We'll never be anything more to each other.'
Emma got a job in a pub for a while, but living
with her parents was killing her mind.
When an old friend phoned and offered her
a job in his theatre group, she'd accepted
it immediately.
But now, after three months, Emma hated the
theatre group.
'I don't want to be here making a difference,'
she thought.
'I want to be in Rome.
I want to be with Dexter Mayhew.'
Emma made herself continue with her letter.
Anyway, I've got a new plan.
I've written a two-woman play about Virginia
Woolf and Emily Dickinson.
One of my friends from the theatre group and
I want to find somewhere in London where we
can stage it.
Do you remember my friend Tilly Killick?
We shared a flat in Edinburgh.
She lives in London now and she has a spare
room in her flat.
So I'll probably live there for a few months.
Are you coming back to London soon?
Maybe we could be flat mates?
Emma stopped writing.
Suddenly she felt nervous.
Then she wrote: It's all right, I'm just joking!
But I really miss you, Dex.
And she signed her name.
In Rome, Dexter was out with a Danish girl.
He was working as an English teacher and the
girl was one of his students.
She was nineteen.
'I have an exam on Monday,' the girl said.
'Test me on verbs, please, Dexter.'
'All right - the present continuous,' Dexter
replied.
'I am kissing, you are kissing, he is kissing...'
said the girl.
She showed him how to kiss too.
'But what would Emma Morley think about this?'
Dexter suddenly thought.
CHAPTER THREE
The Taj Mahal
Sunday, 15th July 1990
Camden Town, London and Bombay, India
'The restaurant opens in ten minutes and I
have a few things to tell you.'
Scott was the manager of Loco Caliente, a
Tex-Mex restaurant in Camden Town, North London.
The restaurant was one of a chain.
'First, these are the special dishes for this
lunchtime,' Scott went on when his staff had
stopped talking.
'Today's special soup is corn chowder.'
Several of the waiters pretended to be sick
and he stopped talking again for a few seconds.
'And today's other special dish is "an amazing
fish burrito" which contains "delicious pieces
of cod and prawns".
That's how the document from headquarters
describes it, anyway - and those are the words
you must use too.'
'It sounds really horrible,' said one of the
waiters, laughing.
'Look at it this way - we're bringing a taste
of the North Atlantic to the beaches of Mexico,'
said Emma Morley.
She sounded very tired as she made the joke.
As she tied her waitress's apron round her
waist she noticed someone she hadn't seen
before - a large man with curly, blonde hair.
He was wearing a waiter's uniform and he was
quite nice-looking.
'And now here's some good news at last,' said
Scott.
He pointed at the stranger.
'This is Ian Whitehead, who is joining our
happy team.
Ian - this is Emma.
She'll look after you today.
She's been here longer than all the others.'
Emma did not think that this was anything
to be proud of.
She gave Ian a little smile as one of the
waiters turned on the lunchtime music.
The first song was, of course, 'La Cucaracha'.
She asked herself once more what she was doing
here.
She asked herself once more what she was going
to do with her life.
Later, when Emma was showing Ian what he should
do, she asked him about himself.
'I need to be in London,' he said.
'I took this job because I need to earn some
money on the side.'
'Why?
What do you really do?'
Emma asked.
'Well...' he said, in a funny accent, 'really,
I'm a comedian!'
'A comedian!
What kind of comedian?' asked Emma.
'I do stand-up comedy in the evenings.
I do gigs at small comedy clubs, but they
don't pay me very much.'
Then he surprised her.
He asked her to go on a date with him that
evening - to one of the clubs.
She was touched, but she refused.
In Bombay, Dexter Mayhew was writing a letter.
Emma, Emma, Emma.
How are you?
What are you doing?
I'm in Bombay and it's raining.
It rains here even harder than it rains in
Edinburgh.
It's too wet to go out so I'm staying in my
hotel room.
I'm a bit drunk, are you surprised?
I've seen some amazing things here in India
and I've taken thousands of photos.
I'll show all of them to you very, very slowly
when I get back.
I showed some of them to a TV producer I met
a few days ago.
She's from London but she's making a film
here.
I think she liked me - she wants me to call
her when I get back to England.
Maybe she'll have a job for me in TV!
I'll need to work soon and I'm banned from
teaching English to foreigners.
I'm not sorry about that, I hated it.
But I was treated very badly.
That Danish girl was twenty-one!
What are you doing now?
Are you still sharing a flat with Tilly?
Are you still working at that horrible restaurant?
You need to leave that job, Emma.
Listen to me, Emma!
We need to do something about your life.
I'm drunk at the moment, so I'm just going
to tell you what I think.
You are clever.
And you are beautiful.
And you are loveable.
And you are SEXY!
You should be CONFIDENT!
I want to take you away from boring people
like Tilly Killick and Callum O'Neill, the
computer king.
Would you like to live with me when I get
back to England?
We would just be flatmates, of course.
Now, here's my plan to change your life.
Are you sitting down?
The shock might knock you over!
You should be here with me in India.
I'm going to wire you some money.
I've always wanted to wire someone some money
- it will make me feel important.
Use the money to buy a plane ticket to Delhi.
Then take a train to Agra and go to the Taj
Mahal.
Have you heard of it?
It's a big white building and it's named after
that Indian restaurant on the Lothian Road
in Edinburgh.
Be there exactly at noon on 1st August.
Stand under the dome with a red rose in your
hand.
I'll find you.
I'll be carrying a white rose.
Isn't that the greatest plan you've ever heard
in your life?
Well, Emma, I'm still drunk, but it's stopped
raining.
I'm going out now to meet some Dutch people
in a bar.
I met them earlier today.
They're all girls.
They're nice.
Don't forget - the Taj Mahal at noon on 1st
August.
I'll find you.
After he had finished the letter, Dexter took
a cold shower and soon he was feeling better.
He was almost sober now.
As he was dressing, he saw the letter, lying
on his bed.
Should he send it?
Suddenly he felt nervous.
He'd called Emma clever and beautiful.
He'd called her loveable.
He'd called her sexy!
He'd asked her to live with him.
Would she be angry with him?
Would she come to India?
Did he really want to see her that much?
He decided that he did.
He decided that he would post the letter that
evening.
He put it in his pocket and he went out.
Then he walked happily to the bar where his
new friends were waiting.
At about nine o'clock that evening Dexter
left the bar with one of his Dutch friends
- her name was Renee.
As they left, they bumped into a large German
girl with a huge backpack.
She was a student from Cologne and she was
called Heidi.
She was tired and cross, and she swore quietly
at Dexter - it had been a long day.
She crossed the room and sat down heavily
on the sofa where Dexter had been sitting.
A few minutes later she moved sideways across
the sofa and felt something hard pressing
into her leg.
She swore again.
There was an envelope between the cushions
of the sofa.
She pulled it out and looked at it.
Heidi opened the envelope and took out the
letter.
She read it to the end.
Her English wasn't very good, but she understood
most of the letter.
She realized that it was important.
It was the kind of letter she wanted someone
to write to her.
It was a beautiful letter.
She wanted this person called Emma to receive
it.
But there was no name written on the envelope.
And there was no address written on the letter.
What could she do?
Sadly, she realized there was nothing she
could do.
CHAPTER FOUR
A Career Opportunity
Monday, 15th July 1991
Camden Town and Primrose Hill, London
'Listen to me, please, everyone,' Scott McKenzie
shouted.
'The restaurant opens in ten minutes and I
have some things to tell you.
First, these are the special dishes for this
lunchtime.'
Scott stopped, looked around him and then
went on when his staff had stopped talking.
'Today's special soup is corn chowder.
And the special burrito is turkey.'
'Turkey's not a good idea in July,' said Ian
Whitehead wearily.
'Turkey's really for Christmas.'
He shook his head in despair.
This made Emma Morley laugh.
Ian was now Emma's best friend, but she rarely
laughed at what he said.
Scott looked at the two of them.
'Ian, you can clean the toilets today,' Scott
said.
'Emma, I need to talk to you in my office.'
Emma followed the manager into his office
and sat down.
'I'll come straight to the point,' Scott said.
'I'm leaving Loco Caliente soon.
I'm going to be the manager of a big, new
restaurant in West London.
Do you want to be the manager here when I
go?
It's a good career opportunity.
Head office wants someone who isn't going
anywhere.
Someone who won't go away travelling or leave
suddenly to start a more exciting job.'
And suddenly, Emma was crying.
'What's wrong, Emma?'
Scott asked.
'Has somebody upset you?'
'No, it's all right, Scott.
It's really nothing,' Emma told him.
'Don't worry, I'll be fine in a minute.'
'Go and rest in the staffroom,' said Scott
kindly.
'Give me your answer about the job tomorrow.'
A few minutes later Emma was alone in the
staffroom.
She looked around her in despair.
She knew that she couldn't leave her job.
She had to spend all her money on rent, so
she needed to take the manager's job.
But she didn't want to be a restaurant manager
all her life.
She still wanted to be a writer, or perhaps
a film-maker, or a painter.
She wanted to be something in the arts.
She spent lots of time writing - she mostly
wrote poems these days.
But nothing was working well for her.
Nobody wanted to publish her poems.
Emma knew that her mother was still trying
to find jobs for her in Yorkshire.
Some days, she thought she would go back there.
'I've had a battle with London and London
has won,' she told herself.
But she wasn't ready to stop fighting yet.
She needed to be in London.
Emma opened her handbag and took out her special
notebook.
The book had a beautiful cover and lovely,
thick, white paper.
It was where Emma wrote her poems.
Now she took out her best pen.
She thought for minute, then she started to
write a new poem about how she felt.
The poem she wrote was quite short and she
knew it was really bad.
She turned back through the pages of the book
and found an earlier poem called Daybreak
in Edinburgh.
She read it.
We lie here in the
Narrow bed and talk
About the future.
I
Look at him and think
'Handsome' - stupid word - and I
Ask myself the
Hardest question,
'Might it be the real
Thing, this time?
Outside the birds begin to sing and
Sunlight warms the curtain.
Emma looked carefully at what she had written.
'Can I really make the bad things in my life
seem better by writing about them?' she wondered.
She had just decided that she could not do
that because that poem was rubbish too, when
Ian came into the staffroom.
Ian looked angry and unhappy.
'Emma,' he said, 'your friend is in the restaurant
again the handsome one.
He wants to see you.
He's with a girl a different one this time.'
Ian had seen several of Dexter's girlfriends.
Dexter obviously liked to show them to Emma
and this clearly upset her.
It upset Ian too.
'He's a monster, Emma,' Ian said.
'No, he's not a monster, he's just an idiot.'
Emma sighed and went out into the restaurant.
Dexter was with a tall, thin girl with black
hair and expensive black clothes.
They were reading the menu aloud to each other
and laughing about it.
'Hello, Emma!'
Dexter said when he saw her.
'This is Naomi.
Will you have a drink with us?'
His voice told Emma that he was drunk.
'I can't do that, Dex, I'm working,' Emma
replied.
'Goodbye.'
She turned away and walked back to the staffroom.
Later, before leaving the restaurant, Dexter
left a handwritten note on his table.
Later in the day, after Emma had finished
work, she found Dexter lying on the grass
on Primrose Hill, a mile away.
The evening sun was warm and he was almost
asleep.
A half-empty wine bottle told her the reason.
Emma kicked his leg.
'Don't do that to me, Dexter,' she said angrily.
'Don't bring people into the restaurant to
laugh at me.
If you ever do that again, it's the end of
our friendship.'
'I'm sorry, Em,' Dexter said.
'I'm really sorry.
I apologize.'
Emma looked at him and decided that he meant
what he said - for now.
She sat down beside him.
'Won't your girlfriend be angry if she finds
out that you left a note asking me to meet
you?'
she asked.
'Oh, Naomi isn't really my girlfriend,' Dexter
replied happily.
'She's just someone I go out with sometimes.'
'I'm sorry, then,' said Emma.
'Clearly, I don't mean girlfriend, I mean
victim.'
She spoke sadly.
And she thought, 'Em and Dex, Dex and Em.
No, it's never going to happen now.'
She picked up the bottle of wine and drank
from it.
Dexter looked at her and he felt warm inside.
He often thought that Emma Morley was the
best person he'd ever known.
But he'd never really told her that.
And he didn't tell her that now.
For some reason, he couldn't make himself
tell her that.
CHAPTER FIVE
The Rules
Wednesday, 15th July 1992
The Greek islands
Dexter and Emma were lying sleepily on the
deck of a small ferry.
The two friends were travelling from the Greek
island of Rhodes to a smaller island.
They were going to stay there for a week and
they were both feeling happy.
Life was changing for them.
After a year as manager at Loco Caliente,
Emma had left her job.
In September she was going to start a college
course.
She was going to train to be a schoolteacher.
And Dexter had a job now.
He was working for a television company.
He'd started with small responsibilities - making
the tea, doing research for producers.
But now he was working as an interviewer.
He interviewed pop stars and actors on a programme
called The Bigger Picture.
He had a posh flat in Belsize Park - an expensive
part of north London.
He wore expensive designer clothes.
And he had a new girlfriend, his fourth one
after Naomi.
She was a beautiful and successful model.
Emma didn't really enjoy Dexter's television
appearances, but she always watched them.
For The Bigger Picture, Dexter had invented
a new character for himself.
He was a 'man of the people'.
When he interviewed pop stars and actors,
he spoke with a cockney accent.
Emma had never enjoyed Dexter's version of
a Yorkshire accent and she thought that his
'cockney' voice was even worse.
Emma liked Dexter to know that she wasn't
impressed by his television career.
She told him this often.
But all that was back in London.
Today they were happy.
Today, they were on a ferry among the beautiful
Greek islands.
They were on holiday together.
It had been surprisingly easy to arrange this
trip.
Dexter's girlfriend was very self-confident,
so she had no problems about his holiday with
another woman.
And Emma occasionally slept with people but
still didn't have a regular boyfriend.
So they had made their plans together and
they had decided on some rules of behaviour
for the holiday.
The Rules:
One: Separate bedrooms.
Two: No flirting.
Three: No sleeping together.
Four: No nudity.
Five: No board games.
Emma had decided on the first four rules.
Dexter had fought back with Rule Five.
Emma enjoyed playing board games, but Dexter
hated them.
The Rules had to be obeyed, Emma told herself
now, lying sleepily on the deck of the ferry.
The Rules made this holiday possible.
But Emma wondered if Dexter was going to be
able to obey them.
And she wondered if she was going to be able
to obey them.
They were half asleep when they heard an English
voice.
'It's him,' said a man.
'He's on TV on Fridays.'
'Oh, yes,' said a girl.
'He's called Dexter something.
You are that man who's on TV, aren't you?'
She was speaking to Dexter now.
And he was wide awake.
'Yep.
On 'oliday, are ya?' said Dexter in his pretend-cockney
accent.
'Yeah,' said the girl.
Dexter continued talking to her and didn't
take any notice of the man.
The girl was clearly impressed.
'Dexter, why do you speak like that?'
Emma asked when the couple had gone.
'You aren't a Londoner and you went to Winchester
College.'
'The TV viewers won't connect with me if I
don't seem like them,' Dexter explained.
'Not many of our viewers went to Winchester.'
'That's a very bad reason,' said Emma.
'And you've broken Rule Two already.
You were flirting with that girl.'
Emma was sitting at a table outside a small
cafe on the island and drinking coffee.
Dexter had gone to find them somewhere to
stay.
'Don't forget, we need two rooms,' Emma had
shouted after him as he set off.
And he'd looked back at her and shouted, 'Of
course we do!'
'She looks so lovely these days,' he told
himself.
'It's the contact lenses.
I hated those thick glasses she used to wear.
But now she looks great.
These rules aren't going to make life easy.'
But an hour later, when he returned to the
cafe, Dexter seemed very pleased.
'There's some bad news, Emma,' he said.
'I could only find one room on the island.
It's a wonderful room, but it only has one
bed.
But it's a very large bed.'
Emma believed that Dexter hadn't tried to
find two rooms.
She believed that Dexter had never meant to
And of course, she was correct.
'All right, let's go and see the room,' Emma
said wearily.
But when they got there, Emma loved the room.
The bed was a large one.
And there was a balcony.
They could stand on it and look out over the
sea.
'The room is fine, Dexter,' Emma said.
'We'll stay here.
And you'll stay on your own side of the bed,
won't you?'
Late that evening, Dexter and Emma walked
down to the beach.
The sun had disappeared and no one else was
there.
'Shall we swim, Emma?'
Dexter said.
By now, Emma could read Dexter's mind.
She could almost hear it working.
This wasn't difficult, because Dexter only
thought about a small number of things.
'We don't have swimsuits with us,' Emma replied
very slowly, speaking in the way people speak
to young children.
'We don't need swimsuits.
There's no one here,' Dexter said.
'I understand you too well, Dex,' Emma said.
'You just want to get my clothes off, don't
you?'
Dexter was silent.
'You swim if you want to, Dexter,' Emma went
on.
'I'm not going to show my body to the world.
And you've forgotten Rule Four.'
A moment later, Dexter had taken off all his
clothes and was running into the sea.
Emma suddenly felt stupid.
'Why can't I be free and uncomplicated like
Dexter?'
she asked herself.
'Why do I care who sees me?'
She quickly took off her own clothes and she
too ran naked into the sea.
Soon she was standing next to her friend.
He turned to face her.
'Can we talk about Rule Three, Em?'
Dexter said gently.
'You see, I really want you.'
For a moment, Emma felt wonderful.
He had said it at last.
And it was going to happen, here and now,
in the beautiful warm sea.
Dex and Em, Em and Dex.
It was going to happen.
And then Dexter said the wrong thing.
'Of course, it isn't personal.
I want nearly every woman that I meet,' he
added.
'That's my problem.
I can't escape it.
It's like a nightmare!'
'Oh, poor Dexter,' Emma said angrily.
'I feel really sorry for you.'
She was angry with Dexter and she was angry
with herself.
'You're a stupid, stupid woman,' she told
herself.
'You're stupid for thinking that he really
cared about you.'
But a moment later, it was Dexter who was
angry.
He was looking over Emma's shoulder at the
beach.
A boy was stealing his clothes.
'Stop!
Don't do that!'
Dexter shouted.
He started to run towards the beach.
'Those trousers cost me two hundred pounds!'
he shouted at Emma, who was laughing.
When they reached the beach, the boy, and
Dexter's expensive clothes, had disappeared.
He hadn't taken Emma's clothes.
When she had stopped laughing, Emma got dressed
and Dexter found a torn, blue, plastic bag
on the beach.
He held this in front of him as they ran back
to their room.
On the way, they passed the English couple
they had met on the ferry.
'I like the bag,' the man said.
'It's a great colour.'
He laughed mockingly.
Dexter didn't reply.
But when they got back to their room, Dexter's
anger had gone.
It was a beautiful evening.
And soon, the stars were bright in the sky.
He and Emma had some food, then they got into
the bed and lay in the dark.
They didn't touch each other, and they knew
that their friendship was unchanged.
'Tell me a secret, Em,' Dexter said.
'Tell me something about yourself that I don't
know.'
'Well, I don't want to make you more arrogant
than you already are,' Emma replied.
'But here's something you didn't know.
Before I first talked to you, when we were
students, I was in love with you.
And I used to write poems about you.'
'That was before you knew me,' Dexter said.
'Aren't you in love with me now?'
'Oh, now - things are quite different now,'
said Emma.
When she said that, Dexter started thinking
about his own secrets.
He'd never told Emma that he'd once slept
with Tilly Killick.
It had happened when he was visiting the flat
Emma and Tilly shared.
Emma had gone out to the shops for an hour.
He was never going to tell her about that.
He didn't know that Emma knew about it already
and it wasn't a secret at all.
'Tell me about those poems,' Dexter said quietly,
after a few minutes.
'What rhymed with Dexter?'
'Monster,' Emma replied quickly.
'It's a half-rhyme.'
'Em,' Dexter said a few minutes later, 'how
many rules did I break today?'
'Three,' Emma said.
'You broke Rules One, Two and Four.'
'And we nearly broke Rule Three,' Dexter thought.
'But we have eight more days.
Anything can happen in eight days.'
'Well, at least we didn't play any board games,'
he said aloud.
Emma was asleep.
CHAPTER SIX
Poison
Thursday, 15th July 1993
Belsize Park, London and Oxfordshire
Dexter Mayhew was sitting in his flat in Belsize
Park.
It was 10 AM and Dexter was very drunk.
He had been drinking all night with some new
friends.
Now that he worked in television, lots of
people wanted to know Dexter.
They all wanted to hear his stories about
the famous people that he interviewed.
They all wanted to drink with him.
So he was often drunk these days.
Usually, being drunk in the mornings didn't
matter.
Dexter worked in the afternoons and evenings
and he was always sober by then.
But this morning, the morning of 15th July,
it mattered very much.
Today he had to go to his parents' house in
the country, in Oxfordshire.
He was already late.
He knew, in part of his mind, that he wanted
to be late.
In fact, in that part of his mind, he didn't
want to go at all.
Because today, thinking about his parents
made him want to scream.
Dexter's mother, at forty-nine, was fifteen
years younger than his father.
Dexter liked his father and they usually got
on well together.
But his feelings about his mother were quite
different.
Dexter loved his mother more than anyone in
the world.
But now his mother was dying and Dexter knew
that she couldn't live much longer.
He needed to see her, but he was afraid.
He was afraid to see how close to death she
was.
So this morning, he needed to be strong.
He needed to make himself drive to his childhood
home.
And he needed to make himself behave normally
when he got there.
Dexter looked at the large parcel, wrapped
in brightly coloured paper, which he'd put
next to his front door.
He'd put it there so that he wouldn't forget
it when he went out, even if he was drunk.
The parcel was a present for his mother from
his good friend Emma Morley.
Emma and his mother were very different people,
but when they had met they had always enjoyed
each other's company.
And Stephen and Alison Mayhew had guessed
that Emma was a good friend to their son.
They hadn't really been offended at all when
Emma called Stephen 'a bourgeois fascist'.
Remembering this, for a moment Dexter wanted
to phone Emma.
The two of them had still never touched each
other, but he knew that she was his best friend.
Suddenly, he wanted to tell her that she was
a dear, wonderful person.
And he wanted to tell her how unhappy he was
about his mother's terrible illness.
But he knew what Emma would say.
'She'll know I'm drunk as soon as I start
to speak,' he told himself.
'She'll tell me that I mustn't drive.'
Dexter picked up his car keys and collected
Emma's parcel.
He locked the door of his flat behind him
and walked to his expensive, green sports
car.
An hour later, Dexter was still worrying about
his dying mother.
But he also knew that he was lucky to be alive
himself.
He had fallen asleep for a moment and had
almost crashed his car into a big truck.
He could still hear the noise of the truck's
horn in his aching head.
He wasn't far from his parents' house now,
but he had to stop for a while.
He slowed down and drove into a pub cark park.
It was a pub which he had often visited when
he was young.
He bought a glass of vodka and a glass of
beer and sat down.
He drank quickly and soon he was feeling better.
He walked outside into the sunlight and got
into his car.
In less than twenty minutes, he parked in
front of his parents' house, just as his father
opened the front door.
'I'd hoped you were coming earlier,' his father
said as Dexter got out of the car.
He looked angry and when Dexter tried to kiss
him on the cheeks, he moved quickly away.
At the television studios, everyone kissed
everyone else on the cheeks.
Dexter had forgotten for a moment that his
father lived in a different world.
'Your mother hoped you were coming earlier
too,' Stephen Mayhew added.
He looked carefully at his son, then he sighed
deeply.
'I'm sorry - I'm so sorry,' Dexter said unhappily.
'How is she, Dad?'
'You need to ask her that yourself,' Mr Mayhew
said.
'Go up to her room now.
I'll make us some lunch.'
Dexter walked slowly up the stairs, carrying
Emma's present.
He opened the door of his mother's bedroom
and went nervously inside.
Alison Mayhew was sitting up in her bed.
She was very thin and she looked very tired
and ill.
But she smiled when she saw her son.
'A present!
What have you brought me?'
she asked.
'The present is from Emma,' Dexter said.
'Let's open it.'
The parcel contained books - long, serious
books - Edith Wharton, Scott Fitzgerald, Raymond
Chandler.
'How kind she is,' Alison Mayhew said.
'I'm very grateful to Emma.
But please suggest to her that short stories
might be more useful in future.'
Dexter tried to laugh, but inside his head
he was screaming.
A few minutes later, he went downstairs to
the kitchen, where his father was making lunch.
Dexter picked up a glass of wine and drank
it quickly, then he refilled the glass.
'Dexter, please be careful,' his father said.
'You drink too much.
Alcohol is poison for you these days.'
'I've got a headache, Dad,' Dexter said.
'I've been working too hard.
I'm going to lie down for half an hour.
I don't need any food.'
He went upstairs to the room he had slept
in when he was a child.
A few minutes later he was unconscious on
his childhood bed.
It was evening when Dexter woke.
The whole afternoon had passed.
He went to find his father in the kitchen.
'I'm sorry, Dad,' he said.
'I didn't mean to sleep that long.
Why didn't you wake me?'
'It wasn't my job.
You're not a child any longer, Dexter,' his
father replied angrily.
'And you were so drunk, there wasn't any point
in waking you.
You don't think that your mother wanted to
see you like this, do you?'
'I'm sorry,' Dexter said again.
He looked around the room.
'Where did I put my car keys?
I have to go now.'
'I've got them and I'm going to keep them,'
his father replied.
'You must not drive when you're drunk, Dexter.
You'll kill yourself or you'll kill someone
else, which will be worse.
I'll drive you to the station now.
You can get the train back to London.
And you can come and collect your car at the
weekend, if you're sober by then.
Perhaps you'll be able to talk sensibly to
your mother then, too.'
Dexter tried to argue, but his father wouldn't
listen to him.
And he wouldn't talk to him on the way to
the station.
But as Dexter was getting out of the car,
the older man held his arm.
'Listen to me, Dexter,' Stephen Mayhew said
very seriously.
'Your mother was looking forward to your visit
today.
And now she's very upset.
She hasn't long to live, you must know that.
If you come here drunk again, I won't let
you into the house to see her.
Do you understand me?
I won't open the door to you.'
Stephen drove away and Dexter walked sadly
into the station.
When he was waiting for the train he tried
to phone Emma.
'Emma will understand me,' he told himself.
'I need to see Emma.'
But Emma wasn't at home.
He left a message on her answer phone.
He asked if they could meet later that evening.
He said he'd call again.
When he got back to his flat and called again,
Dexter still got the answer phone.
'Emma, where are you?' he said to the machine.
'I miss you.
I need you.
I'll try again later.'
Covent Garden and King's Cross, London.
Emma didn't get any of Dexter's phone messages
that evening because she wasn't at home.
When Dexter left his first message, she had
just left her flat in Earls Court, West London.
She was walking to the nearby Underground
station.
She was on her way to an Italian restaurant
in Covent Garden where she was going to meet
Ian Whitehead.
Emma had only seen Ian a few times since she
had left Loco Caliente to train as a teacher,
but they were still friends.
They sometimes talked on the phone.
And tonight he had invited her to meet him
for dinner.
They had been friends for three years, but
Emma had never slept with Ian.
She knew that he wanted to sleep with her.
She liked him, but did she want to sleep with
him too?
She didn't know and she wondered now how the
evening was going to end.
At the station, Emma bought a ticket and waited
for her train.
Soon, it arrived and Emma boarded it.
She sat and thought about how her life had
changed since she had met Ian.
She no longer shared a flat with Tilly Killick.
Now she lived on her own in the small rented
flat in Earls Court.
And now she was ready for a new career.
Tomorrow she was going to an interview for
a job as a teacher of English and Drama.
The job was in a comprehensive school in Leytonstone,
in a poor part of East London.
Emma was very confident about this job.
She had enjoyed her year at teacher training
college and she knew that she was going to
be a brilliant teacher.
Yes, her life had changed.
But Emma knew that her character had changed
too.
She had mellowed.
She no longer had a strong opinion about everything
that happened in the world.
Sometimes, she could even see that there were
two sides to any argument.
'I'm twenty-seven - perhaps that's the reason,'
she thought.
'Perhaps I'm getting old.
Perhaps I'm ready to compromise.'
When Emma arrived at the restaurant, she saw
that Ian was already there.
She hoped that this was the beginning of a
pleasant evening.
Later, she'd decide about what was going to
happen next.
They ordered food and wine and Ian started
to talk.
He seemed very nervous and Emma tried to help
him to relax.
But an hour later - at about the time Dexter
was leaving his second message on her answer
phone - Emma was feeling desperate.
Ian had been trying much too hard to make
her laugh.
She guessed that he was practising his stand-up
comedy act on her.
The problem was that everything he said was
a joke and it was impossible to have a conversation
with him.
This was driving her crazy.
She guessed that Ian was feeling desperate
too.
Everything he said made the evening worse.
In part of her mind Emma wanted to leave and
go home.
But in another part of her mind she felt terribly
sorry for Ian.
It was clear to her that he wasn't a good
comedian and that his ambition to have a career
in stand-up was just a dream.
At last, she couldn't listen to any more bad
jokes.
'Ian,' she said suddenly, 'will you be quiet
for a minute, please!
Will you just shut up!'
Ian looked very surprised and he stopped talking.
After a few minutes of silence, he asked quietly,
'Do you see your friend Dexter much these
days?'
Emma suddenly understood why Ian had been
so nervous all evening.
'No, we don't meet very often,' she replied.
'But we speak on the phone most days.
He's busy with his TV career and his girlfriends
- you know what Dexter's like.
He's always been a bit crazy and now he's
a bit more crazy, I think.
His mother is seriously ill and he's drinking
far too much.'
'I'm sorry to hear that,' said Ian.
Then, after a pause, he said, 'To be honest
I never liked him much.
I always thought that he took you for granted.'
They were both silent for a few minutes.
Then Ian spoke again.
'Well, we've finished the wine,' he said.
'Shall we have some brandy?'
By the time they left the restaurant, Emma
and Ian were both a bit drunk.
Outside the restaurant, Emma turned to Ian
and kissed him.
She had decided that tonight, she was ready
to compromise.
'Shall I come home with you?'
she asked quietly.
'Emma, that's a lovely idea,' Ian told her.
And when Dexter phoned Emma's number again
at midnight, there still wasn't anyone at
home.
Emma was at Ian Whitehead's and she was going
to stay there until morning.
Dexter was now feeling desperate.
So he called another number.
'Hi, Naomi, this is Dexter,' he said in his
television voice.
'I miss you, girl.
I need you tonight.
Can you find a taxi and come to my flat?
CHAPTER SEVEN
Show Business
Friday, 15th July 1994
Leytonstone and the Isle of Dogs, East London
Emma Morley got up early on 15th July.
Emma now lived in a rented flat in Leytonstone.
It was quite near Cromwell Road Comprehensive
School, where she taught English and Drama.
She had moved to the flat when she started
teaching at the school, in the autumn of the
year before.
Ian Whitehead spent much of his time at the
flat too.
Emma thought she was probably in love with
Ian.
'I am in love with him, aren't I?' she asked
herself daily.
And every day she told herself that she was
in love with him - yes, of course she was
in love with him.
And her parents liked him very much, especially
her mother.
That was important to her.
'It's good when people's partners and mothers
get on well,' she thought.
But Ian did take up a lot of space in the
little flat.
But Emma had a bigger problem than the size
of her flat.
Ian Whitehead and Dexter Mayhew - the two
men in her life - still didn't get on well.
Dexter didn't like Emma's friendship with
Ian even though he had his own girlfriends.
The truth was that Dexter needed Emma as an
emotional support but Ian didn't really understand
this need.
And Emma was especially important to Dexter
now that his mother had died.
Ian was also very jealous of Dexter, because
he didn't want Emma to have a best friend
who wasn't himself.
All this was a special problem on the 15th,
because when the evening came, Emma was really
needed in three places at once.
Tonight was going to be Dexter's big night.
Tonight, a new programme was going to be on
television and Dexter was one of the presenters.
This programme - Late at Night - was a much
more important one than The Bigger Picture
and perhaps it was going to make Dexter a
big star.
Another of the presenters - a glamorous woman
called Suki Meadows - was already a star.
The programme was going to be live and Dexter
wanted Emma to be at the television studio
to support him.
He no longer saw his other friends from university.
He no longer wanted to see them.
Callum O'Neill, whose computer business was
doing well, often called.
He left messages on Dexter's answer phone
but Dexter never called him back.
Emma was the only one of his old friends that
he cared about.
But tonight was going to be Emma's big night
too.
Emma was in charge of her school's end-of-year
drama production, the musical Oliver!
And the performance was happening tonight.
Of course this wasn't as important as Dexter's
programme, but clearly Emma had to be there.
She'd spent many weeks preparing the children
for the show and she had to be with them.
Tonight their parents were coming to watch
them.
And for their parents, they were all going
to be little stars, for one night at least.
Emma hoped it was going to make her the headmaster's
little star too.
Her teaching career - making a difference
- was just as important as Dexter's more glamorous
TV career, she thought.
She knew that Dexter didn't really believe
this.
And then there was Ian.
Ian was feeling ill today.
He didn't really want to go out at all tonight.
And he didn't want her to go out.
But she understood.
She loved him, didn't she?
And he was going to come to Oliver!
Even if he still felt ill.
He'd promised her that.
Before leaving to go to work Emma picked up
the phone and called Dexter's number.
She got his answerphone.
'Hi!
Speak to me!
Leave me a message!'
Dexter's 'cockney' voice said on the recording.
So she left him a message.
'Hi Dex, I'm sorry it's early for you,' she
said.
'You're probably not awake yet.
But some of us have jobs to go to.
I'm sorry I won't be with you at the studio
tonight, but I want to wish you luck.
I know you understand that it's my big night
too.
That's show business, Dex!
I'll speak to you later.
Lots of love to you.
Oh - and Dex - you really have to change that
answer phone message.'
Dexter Mayhew wasn't feeling good when he
arrived at the television studio on the Isle
of Dogs.
It was his father's fault.
His father had left a message on his answer
phone earlier in the day.
'I called to wish you luck for tonight,' his
father had said.
'I'll be watching the programme.
It's so sad that your mother isn't here to
see you.
She was so... proud of you.
Well, good luck Dexter.
And don't take any notice of the newspapers.'
When he'd heard the message, Dexter had gone
out and bought all the daily newspapers.
He'd opened the first one at the television
pages and read the headline.
IS DEXTER MAYHEW THE NASTIEST MAN ON TV?
Dexter had drunk some vodka to settle his
nerves as he read the story beneath the headline.
The story wasn't kind to him.
Dexter was a stupid, rich boy who'd been educated
at Winchester College but pretended to be
a cockney, the author wrote mockingly.
Dexter thought that he was popular with young
people, the author said, but really young
people just laughed at him.
They didn't connect with him at all.
Dexter had felt sick when he read this.
And he had had several more drinks before
he arrived at the television studio that evening.
In his dressing room at the studio, Dexter
sat quietly trying to relax.
He had told the producer of the show that
he wanted to be alone.
He was nervous.
He had been a TV presenter for several years
now, so he was surprised at how nervous he
felt.
He didn't know what he was going to say when
the show started.
When he thought about the whole hour the show
was going to last, his mind was suddenly empty.
Now, he was very frightened.
And the show was going to start in a few minutes.
He took a bottle of vodka from his overcoat
pocket.
There was a bottle of water on a table in
the dressing room.
Presenters usually took a bottle of water
onto the set with them.
The studio lights were always very hot and
they often needed to drink some water when
they were off-camera.
They couldn't speak clearly if their mouths
were dry.
But Dexter wanted something to clear his mind,
not something to wet his mouth.
He emptied the water into his washbasin and
refilled the bottle with vodka.
Then he put it back on the table.
It looked the same as before.
Nobody would know that he was drinking vodka.
'HEY THERE!' said a loud voice.
'WELL, HOW ABOUT ALL THIS?'
The owner of the loud voice was Suki Meadows.
Suki was already a popular presenter of late-night
TV shows.
Now she stood at the door smiling at Dexter.
She was a small, pretty, friendly person and
she was always cheerful.
Always!
It didn't matter what was happening around
her.
She was cheerful and she was noisy.
'Why does Suki always speak in capital letters?'
Dexter had sometimes asked himself.
But tonight he was thinking something else.
'The viewers all love her.
And she is very sexy,' he was thinking.
'And I'm sure she's crazy about me.'
Suki was wearing a very short skirt and a
shirt made of very thin cloth.
And she was holding her own bottle of water.
'COME HERE, DEX,' she said, entering the dressing
room.
She put her water bottle on the table next
to his and put her arms around him.
'YOU'RE GOING TO BE GREAT TONIGHT!
WE'RE GOING TO BE GREAT TOGETHER!
DEX AND SUKI, SUKI AND DEX!
WHAT A TEAM, DEX!'
And having wished him good luck in her own
way, Suki led Dexter out of the dressing room.
On the way, they picked up their water bottles.
Outside, on the set, they picked up their
microphones and inserted their earpieces.
They looked around them at the brightly coloured
set and the brightly dressed dancers who were
standing ready to begin the warm up before
the show.
Then the music started, the dancers danced.
When they had finished, Suki walked to the
front of the set and yelled to the audience.
'ARE YOU READY TO HAVE A GREAT TIME?
WELL, MAKE SOME NOISE FOR US!'
At that moment, Dexter realized that he was
hopelessly drunk.
Now it was his turn to speak and he couldn't
say anything.
He didn't know what to say.
This show was going to be a disaster.
Someone in the audience shouted, 'You useless
idiot!
Can't you speak?'
Dexter had an idea.
'Well, he's clearly been reading the newspapers,'
he shouted to the audience.
He tried to laugh.
A few of the audience laughed too, but not
many of them.
Dexter needed another drink to clear his head,
he told himself.
He took the top off his water bottle and drank.
It was water, just water.
At once he understood.
The bottles had got mixed up.
Suki had the vodka.
And she was taking the top off her bottle.
He wanted to stop her drinking, but it was
too late.
As she tasted the liquid, Dexter saw the shock
in her eyes.
And at that moment, the live programme began.
'We're live!
Say something Dexter,' the producer's voice
said in his earpiece.
But Dexter couldn't speak and Suki was coughing.
She recovered first, and she came to Dexter's
rescue.
'SORRY ABOUT THAT.
BUT AT LEAST YOU VIEWERS KNOW THAT THE PROGRAMME
IS LIVE!' she said.
Suki went on speaking.
Dexter tried hard to think clearly and after
a few minutes he was able to perform better
with Suki.
He wasn't very good, but he wasn't terrible.
And Suki was amazing.
She always spoke when Dexter didn't know what
to say and she tried to make Dexter look normal.
The show wasn't a disaster.
When the programme had finished, there was
a party for all the people who had appeared
in it, and their friends and relations.
Dexter stayed for the party, but he was quiet
and thoughtful.
People congratulated him, but they didn't
speak to him for long.
He ate lots of food and drank lots of wine,
but he wasn't happy.
He knew that he hadn't performed well.
He knew that Suki Meadows had rescued him.
And he knew that she had been the star.
Late in the evening, Suki came to sit next
to him.
'That went OK, didn't it?'
she said.
For the first time that day, she wasn't speaking
in capital letters.
'You saved us, Suki,' he said.
'I was trying to settle my nerves, but I drank
too much before the show.
I owe you an apology.'
'Yes, you do,' she replied.
'You have a problem with alcohol and we need
to talk about it.
You must understand this, Dexter - you won't
appear on this programme with me again if
you aren't sober.
And you must never bring alcohol onto the
set again.'
'What can I do to make you feel better about
me?'
Dexter asked her.
'Well, you can take me out for dinner next
week,' Suki said.
'Take me somewhere very expensive.
On Tuesday.'
Dexter thought for a moment.
He had promised to meet Emma on Tuesday evening,
but he could change that.
Emma was his best friend.
She was always there for him.
'All right,' he replied.
'We have a date.'
'Good,' said Suki, kissing him.
'And now, you must come and meet my mother.'
Dexter was feeling a bit unhappy on the Isle
of Dogs, but Emma was on top of the world
in Leytonstone.
Oliver had been a great success.
Of course there had been arguments and fights
among the children before the show.
That always happened.
They were excited and some of them were nervous.
But Emma had settled their nerves and when
the music began, they all worked together
and helped each other.
So the show had been wonderful.
Phil Godaiming, Emma's headteacher, was very
pleased.
People whose children could act and sing like
that were going to be proud, he thought.
They were going to speak well of the school
- and of its headteacher, of course.
At the party after the show the school staff,
and many of the proud parents of the cast,
congratulated Emma.
She drank her wine and smiled at everyone.
And late in the evening, Mr Godaiming came
to sit next to her.
'You're a wonderful teacher, Emma,' he said
quietly in her ear.
'And you look very beautiful tonight.
I have great plans for you next year.'
CHAPTER EIGHT
A Crisis
Saturday, 15th July 1995
Walthamstow, East London and Soho, Central
London
'I'm going out now, Ian,' Emma called.
Then she added carefully, 'Are you sure that
you don't want to come with me, darling?
Dexter will be pleased to see you, if you
do come.'
'No, I can't come tonight.'
Ian replied, entering the room.
'I've got things to do tonight, don't you
remember?
I'm performing at the House of Ha Ha.
You go on your own.
I'll be fine.'
This was the right answer, Emma thought.
She was quite glad that she was going to see
Dexter alone.
She wanted to talk to him about her relationship
with Ian Whitehead.
Emma was beginning to understand that she
had made a bad mistake about Ian.
They were living together now in a flat in
Walthamstow.
They had bought the flat together.
And that was the mistake.
Ian loved her very much, Emma knew this.
And she had told herself often that she really
loved him too and that she wanted to spend
her life with him.
But she now knew that it wasn't true.
She was no longer happy with Ian.
She just didn't love him.
She knew that Ian hated the success of her
career and that he hated the failure of his
own career.
He still wanted desperately to be a stand-up
comedian, but he only ever performed at pubs
and small comedy clubs.
Ian just wasn't very good at stand-up and
he didn't earn much money from it.
Emma was feeling trapped.
So she needed Dexter to understand.
She hoped it was going to be possible to talk
sensibly to him tonight.
She was feeling a little nervous about
that.
Perhaps talking about Ian wasn't going to
be easy.
In the past, it had been easy to talk to Dexter.
But now he had changed.
He drank far too much and he was more careless
than ever about people's feelings.
Ian wasn't Emma's only problem of course.
She was no longer enjoying her job much either.
She was a good teacher, she knew that.
But she got tired and she didn't have much
time to write.
She still wanted to be a writer, but when
she did write, the results were never very
good.
That was as bad a problem as her relationship
with Ian.
But the greatest problem for Emma was that
she knew, in her heart, that Dexter Mayhew
was the person she really loved.
So there it was.
Everything was a bit hopeless.
Ian's career wasn't what he'd hoped for and
her career wasn't what she'd hoped for.
She had a feeling that Dexter's career wasn't
quite what he'd hoped for either.
Suki Meadows was his girlfriend these days.
But she was now clearly the star presenter
of Late at Night.
Dex was definitely the number two person.
He wasn't very popular with the audience.
And nasty people often wrote cruel things
about him in the newspapers now.
Emma and Dexter were meeting for dinner at
an expensive restaurant in Soho.
It was the kind of place where fashionable
people ate - people in television, like Dexter
and Suki Meadows.
Emma hoped she was going to like it.
Dexter was waiting for Emma outside the restaurant.
He was talking on his mobile phone.
Emma heard his caller's voice quite clearly
as she arrived.
'TEN MILLION VIEWERS THIS WEEK, DEX!'
the voice said, very loudly.
'TEN MILLION!'
'Suki, let me explain something about telephones,'
Dex replied into the phone.
'You don't need to shout into them.
The phone does the shouting for you.
I have to go now,' he added when he saw Emma.
'I'll see you soon.'
'Dex, those things are so stupid,' Emma said,
pointing at Dexter's phone.
'Why don't you throw it away?'
'You'll have one in less than six months,'
Dexter replied, kissing her.
'You'll see.
I'm right.'
They went inside the restaurant and sat at
the bar where Dexter bought drinks.
After a few minutes, they heard a soft, female
voice behind them.
'Do you want cigarettes, sir?'
the voice said.
They turned to see a very tall, extraordinarily
beautiful girl.
The girl was dressed only in black underwear
and stockings, and she carried a tray containing
the cigarettes.
She had a fixed smile.
It wasn't a happy smile.
Dexter bought some cigarettes.
He spent a long time finding his money, so
that he could look at the girl's body.
Then the girl moved away.
'Why is she dressed like that, Dexter?'
Emma said.
'I don't know, Em,' Dexter replied.
'Perhaps all her ugly clothes are in the laundry.
You could look like that if you wanted,' he
added.
'You've got a great body.'
'But I don't want to look like that,' said
Emma.
Soon a waiter took them to their table.
They ordered drinks and when those arrived,
they ordered food.
Dexter was drinking quickly.
'And soon he'll be drunk - again,' Emma told
herself.
And she couldn't stop thinking about the cigarette
girl.
'Why am I eating in the kind of restaurant
where girls have to dress like that?'
she asked herself.
Then she asked Dexter the same question.
'This place is terrible, Dex,' Emma said.
'Haven't women made any progress in the last
hundred years?'
'You don't understand, Em,' Dexter said.
'Dressing like that gives her power over men.
She enjoys it.'
'Don't be stupid, Dexter,' Emma said.
'The owner of this place makes her wear those
clothes.
If she doesn't wear them, she'll lose her
job.
She only works here because she needs the
money, you can see that.
She has no power over anyone!'
'Well, you're still the same old Emma, aren't
you?'
Dexter said crossly.
'Emma, the angry, socialist feminist.
I thought that you'd mellowed, but clearly
I was wrong about that.
You never want to compromise, do you?'
After that, the evening got worse and worse.
Dexter frequently left the table to visit
the toilet.
Each time, he stopped to talk to the cigarette
girl.
The last time it happened, Emma saw him push
a piece of paper into her stocking.
Emma had no doubt that he was giving the girl
his phone number.
When he returned to the table, Emma decided
she had had enough of his behaviour.
She pushed the table away from her, spilling
their drinks, and ran up the stairs out of
the restaurant.
She could hear Dexter behind her, calling
her name.
She didn't turn round.
In the street, Dexter finally caught up with
her.
'Emma, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to upset you,' he said desperately.
Suddenly, Emma turned to face him.
'Dexter, whenever I see you now you're drunk,'
she said.
'I haven't seen you sober for three years.
I don't know you any longer.
You're obnoxious these days.
You were always a bit obnoxious, but now you're
totally obnoxious.'
'I'm just having fun, Emma,' Dexter replied.
'Well, it isn't fun for me,' Emma replied.
'Let's stop this now, Dexter.
You don't care about me.
We don't have to meet any more.'
'Emma, of course we have to meet,' Dexter
said desperately.
'We're Dex and Em, aren't we?
We'll always be Dex and Em.'
For a moment he was quiet.
He was thinking of the day of his mother's
funeral.
He was thinking of Emma's kindness to him
that day.
She had held him as he cried uncontrollably.
He had always taken her for granted, he knew
that.
'Why am I throwing all this away?' he was
asking himself.
But he knew that he couldn't stop himself.
'Dexter,' Emma said sadly.
'I love you very much and I probably always
will love you.
But I'm afraid I don't like you any longer.
I don't like the person that you've become.
I don't want to hear from you again.
Please don't try to contact me.'
She left him standing in the street and walked
away.
CHAPTER NINE
Things End
Monday, 15th July 1996
Leytonstone and Walthamstow, East London
At six o'clock on the last day of term at
Cromwell Road lx.
Comprehensive School, almost everyone had
gone home.
Only Emma Morley and Mr Godaiming, the school's
headteacher, were still in the building.
They were lying on the floor of Mr Godaiming's
office.
'I'll miss you very much during the holidays,
Emma,' Mr Godaiming said as they put on their
clothes.
'I'll miss our Friday afternoons together.'
'No you won't, Phil, you'll have Mrs Godaiming,'
Emma replied unkindly.
'You'll be fine.'
Emma wondered, as she spoke, why she always
felt so cross after their meetings in the
headteacher's office.
Afterwards she always felt unhappy and that
made her cross.
They collected their coats and books and the
headteacher locked the office.
As they walked to the school car park, Emma
was thinking hard.
She had been Phil Godaiming's lover for nine
months now and she was starting to worry about
this.
She was afraid that he was going to tell his
wife about their relationship and ask for
a divorce.
That was not what Emma wanted at all.
She didn't love Phil.
She had never really loved him.
For a short time, he had made her feel better
when her life had become very sad.
She wasn't seeing Dexter any longer and she
missed him.
And her relationship with Ian Whitehead had
gone wrong.
Phil had helped her to be confident during
the bad times.
But she certainly didn't want to marry him.
And she thought now that it was time for this
relationship to end.
As Mr Godaiming opened the door of his car,
Emma held his arm.
'Phil, I'm sorry but I don't want to be your
lover any longer,' she said.
'I feel bad about our relationship.
I feel bad about your wife.
I'm not happy.'
'You were very happy ten minutes ago, Emma,'
the headteacher said.
He laughed.
'No, Phil, you were very happy ten minutes
ago,' Emma replied sadly.
Phil Godaiming wasn't pleased to hear Emma's
words.
He'd enjoyed their meetings after school on
Fridays.
He argued for some time, but clearly, Emma
wasn't going to change her mind.
'We'll talk about this next term,' he said.
He got into his car, closed the door and drove
quickly out of the car park.
Emma travelled sadly home to Walthamstow on
the Underground.
On her way home, she bought some wine to drink
later.
She was going to spend the evening on her
own.
Ian Whitehead no longer lived with her.
They had ended their relationship after a
terrible argument.
They had argued about Ian's jealousy and his
selfishness.
At the end of their argument they had both
cried.
They had cried for each other and for the
end of their relationship.
But they both knew that it had to end.
It had all been so sad, Emma thought now,
as she sat in the train.
Late that evening, after she had drunk the
wine, Emma turned on her television.
The first person she saw was Dexter Mayhew.
Suddenly, Emma realized that it was exactly
a year since she had spoken to him.
She knew that Dexter's TV career hadn't been
very successful recently.
Viewers had never really loved him, it seemed.
They had only loved to hate him.
And nowadays most of them just hated him.
Dexter was now presenting a very late-night
TV show about computer games.
Few people watched it.
Emma did watch the show for a few minutes.
She thought that Dexter wasn't looking well.
His face was looking tired and he no longer
seemed confident.
Suddenly, Emma had a great feeling of friendship
and love for him.
She realized that for the last eight years,
she had thought about Dexter every day.
Now she knew that she wanted his friendship
again.
She wanted him to be her best friend again.
'I'll call him tomorrow,' she told herself.
'I really will call him.'
CHAPTER TEN
Resignation
Tuesday, 15th July 1997
Central London
The River Thames looked lovely on this warm,
sunny afternoon, Emma Morley thought.
It was a work day, but Emma wasn't at school.
Teaching had finished for the term but there
was a very important staff meeting happening
at the school.
Emma was needed there, but she didn't really
care about that.
She had phoned the headteacher's secretary
that morning and told her that she was ill
and had to stay in bed.
The woman clearly hadn't believed her.
Emma didn't care about that either.
Emma wasn't really ill at all.
In fact, she was feeling good.
And she had been to a meeting - a meeting
with a publisher.
At last Emma was feeling confident about something
she had written - a novel for young readers.
It was about a group of children at an East
London school.
The children were appearing in a school production
of Oliver! and the story was told by one of
the actors - a girl called Julie Criscoll.
Julie was a rude, angry, teenage girl with
a good heart.
The book was funny and touching.
Emma had included silly drawings and handwritten
pages in her text, so parts of it looked like
a schoolgirl's diary.
She knew that what she had written was really
good.
And now, other people thought it was good
too.
Perhaps soon, she was going to be a published
author.
Emma wanted to write and she wanted even more
to stop teaching.
She thought every day about resigning.
Her job at the school had been very difficult
for the last year.
Phil Godaiming had been angry because she
no longer wanted to sleep with him.
He'd tried to make her life difficult all
year.
And now she knew that she could write well,
Emma wanted to spend her life writing.
At her meeting this morning, she had told
the publisher about her ambitions.
The publisher had been helpful.
Emma's life was going to change.
As she walked by the river, her mobile phone
rang.
Emma did now have a mobile.
Dexter had been right after all.
Phil had given it to her during the months
when they'd been close.
'I want to be able to hear your voice at any
time,' he'd told her.
As she took the phone from her handbag, Emma
guessed that it was Phil phoning her now.
She wasn't wrong.
'So, you're ill in bed, are you?' he said
in his special loud, angry headteacher's voice.
'Well, I don't believe it.
I think you're outside, enjoying the sunshine.
I can hear the traffic noise.'
'Don't shout at me, Phil,' Emma said quietly.
'My name's Mr Godaiming, not Phil,' the man
replied.
'This is serious, you know that.
I told you that today's meeting was a very
important one.
There'll be trouble about this, Emma.
And if you don't want a relationship with
me, I won't protect you from trouble.
Your job is in danger.'
'No, it isn't,' Emma replied, laughing.
'I'm resigning from my job - now!
Do you understand?
I've resigned!
Goodbye, Mr Godaiming.'
She switched off her phone and for a moment,
she thought about throwing it into the river.
But after a few seconds, she put it back in
her bag.
CHAPTER ELEVEN
Dexter in Love
Wednesday, 15th July 1998
Chichester, Sussex
Dexter Mayhew was lying in bed with Sylvie
Cope at the end of a difficult day.
Recently, something strange had happened to
Dexter.
He had fallen in love.
He'd had many lovers but he'd never been in
love before.
And now the girl beside him was more important
to him than anything in the world.
He almost couldn't believe his luck.
Sylvie was tall, slim and beautiful, with
long, straight hair and a heart-shaped face.
She and Dexter had known each other for several
months and they spent lots of time together.
Every weekend they flew to a different European
city and they always had a wonderful time.
They spent lots of Dexter's money in expensive
shops.
Sylvie was excited to know Dexter in real
life, after seeing him on television.
But the truth was that Dexter liked Sylvie
much more than she liked him.
But Dexter actually enjoyed this.
It meant that Sylvie was different from his
other girlfriends.
Sylvie worked in marketing.
Dexter had met many of her friends, who also
worked in marketing.
He hadn't liked them and they hadn't liked
him.
Who cared?
And tonight, Dexter and Sylvie were staying
at the home of her parents in Chichester.
Today, Dexter had met the Cope family for
the first time.
Dexter hadn't enjoyed meeting the Copes much.
Sylvie's parents clearly didn't admire unimportant
television presenters and Sylvie's twin younger
brothers had mocked him openly.
But Dexter really didn't care about that.
Sylvie was on his side and that was the only
important thing.
Sylvie was on his side and now she was by
his side, in the big bed.
'I love you,' Dexter said to her quietly.
He'd never said these simple words to anyone
before.
'You're amazing!' he added.
But Sylvie was already asleep.
As Dexter lay awake, he realized that he wanted
to tell someone else about Sylvie and about
his good luck.
He wanted to tell someone he liked and trusted.
And suddenly, he knew who he wanted to tell.
It was someone he hadn't spoken to for three
years.
He wanted to tell Emma Morley.
CHAPTER TWELVE
Weddings
Thursday, 15th July 1999
Somerset, England
It seemed to Emma Morley that all her friends
were getting married this year.
As she drove to Somerset, in the west of England,
on the morning of 15th July, she thought of
the weddings she had been to recently.
Some of her friends from university had married
for the first time that year.
Some of them had married for the second time.
Watching these wedding ceremonies had made
Emma feel that she was growing old.
All the university friends she met at them
asked her if she had a boyfriend.
And they all pretended to be sad for her when
she said she hadn't.
But they all said she was looking better than
she had ever looked.
They were right.
She took better care of herself these days
and she even wore pretty clothes for these
occasions.
The best thing about these weddings for Emma
was that she had met Dexter Mayhew at several
of them.
At last they were speaking to each other again,
after more than three years of silence.
That was very, very good.
Of course, she had met Dexter's girlfriend
Sylvie too and perhaps that was less good.
But Dexter was clearly in love with the girl,
so Emma tried to be happy for him.
She had never seen Dexter really in love before.
This morning, Emma was driving to Somerset
for the marriage of Tilly Killick.
Tilly was getting married at a posh hotel
in the countryside.
Dexter had known Tilly during their university
days too, so he was going to be there and
Emma was looking forward to seeing him again.
She was driving an old car.
It was the first car she had ever owned and
it was the best she was able to afford.
Emma certainly wasn't a rich woman.
In fact, she was now living on a small advance
from a publisher and was writing her second
book about Julie Criscoll.
But the first book was going to be published
soon and the publisher expected it to sell
very well.
Emma had some problems with her car during
the journey and she was a bit late when she
arrived at the hotel.
The ceremony had already begun when she entered
the big marriage room, so she found a seat
at the back of the room.
As she was sitting down, Dexter Mayhew turned
round and saw her.
He smiled and waved his hand.
Dexter was sitting at the front with Sylvie.
He hadn't really been listening to the ceremony.
He had been counting the number of women in
the room he had slept with.
'It's five,' he thought.
'It's five in one room, including the bride.
It's a good score.
Is it a record?
Do I get an extra point for the bride?
And really, it's five-and-a-half if I count
that night with Emma.'
And as he thought this, he realized that it
was a bad thing to think.
He also realized that he wanted to talk to
Emma very much.
'I'll try to talk to her alone,' he thought.
'I need to tell her everything.'
After the ceremony, the party began.
Dexter left Sylvie with some friends and started
to look for Emma.
But the first person he met was Callum O'Neill.
The two men hadn't spoken for a long time.
Dexter had heard that Callum had sold his
computer business for a huge amount of money.
He had now started a new business - a successful
chain of sandwich shops.
Today, he was very expensively dressed in
beautiful, fashionable clothes.
Dexter remembered that at Edinburgh University,
Callum had worn the same pair of trousers
every day for three years.
How things had changed!
Callum had gone up in the world and Dexter
had come down.
'Dexter, old friend, you're still alive,'
Callum said.
'It's been a long time since I've seen you.
I stopped phoning you because you never returned
my calls.'
'Didn't I?'
Dexter said.
'Well, you know, I've been very busy with
my television programmes.'
He tried to sound confident.
'And are you still on television?
I haven't seen you on TV for a long time,'
Callum said.
'I'm usually in programmes for sophisticated,
late-night viewers,' Dexter said uncomfortably.
'Mm.
Perhaps you need a new career opportunity,'
Callum said.
'You could work for me, Dex.
I need a new manager.
Come and see me soon.
I'll buy you a good lunch - not sandwiches.
We'll talk about it.
Now, let's go and find your lovely girlfriend.
I saw you with her earlier and I want to meet
her.
Have you seen my girlfriend?
I won't ask you to meet her, I'm getting rid
of her soon.'
Much later in the afternoon, Dexter finally
met up with Emma.
'Let's go somewhere quiet,' he said.
'I want to talk to you.'
'Where's somewhere quiet?'
Emma asked him.
'Well, there's a maze here, I believe,' said
Dexter.
'It's a large one.
It would be nice to get lost in it.'
They found the entrance to the maze and they
walked inside.
They didn't stop until they reached the centre.
Then they turned to face each other.
'Well, isn't it strange?'
Emma began.
'These days, we only talk at other people's
weddings.'
'I'm sorry that I've been so obnoxious during
these last few years,' Dexter said quietly.
'I don't blame you for ending our friendship.
But I want us to be friends again now.'
'I'm sorry too, Dex,' Emma replied.
'Perhaps I didn't understand how badly your
mother's death had hurt you.
I didn't wait for you to start feeling better.
We were both to blame.'
'I'm a different person now, Em,' Dexter said.
'Sylvie has changed me.
I love her very much.'
He stopped speaking for a moment.
'Emma, there's going to be another wedding
soon,' he went on.
'Sylvie and I are going to get married later
this year.
And Sylvie is going to have a baby.'
For another moment they didn't speak, but
their faces showed their real feelings.
Then Emma knew that she had to say something
to hide her fee lings, at least.
'She's a lovely girl, Dex,' Emma said.
'It's marvellous news.'
'I think that fatherhood will transform my
life,' Dexter replied.
'I've almost stopped drinking already.
I'll be a good family man.'
'Well, that's good,' said Emma.
She laughed.
'Of course, you've just ruined any chance
of future happiness for me, but it's all great
news.'
She stopped for a moment.
'Don't worry,' she added.
'I'm only joking.'
And then they both laughed.
'The wedding will be in September,' said Dexter.
'Emma, will you help me write my speech for
the big day?'
'No, Dexter,' said Emma.
'Don't be an idiot.
Just look into your heart and write.'
Then they walked back towards the entrance
of the maze.
CHAPTER THIRTEEN
The Pleasures of Fatherhood
Saturday, 15th July 2000
Richmond, Surrey, England
Jasmine Alison Viola Mayhew - Dexter and Sylvie's
daughter - had been born on the third day
of the year.
She was always going to be the same age as
the century.
Dexter loved her dearly.
He wanted to do everything that was best for
her.
After work on 15th July, he was hurrying home
to the pretty house in Richmond where he and
his wife and daughter lived.
Richmond was ten miles west of London, so
Dexter was no longer a Londoner.
His flat in Belsize Park was rented to someone
else.
Dexter really had almost given up alcohol.
That was something he was proud of.
He often felt pressure to have just a small
drink, but he rarely gave in to it.
He had given in to pressure about something
else.
The pressure had come from Sylvie, who wanted
him to find a real job.
He had been getting very little TV work in
the last year, so finally he agreed to have
a meeting with Callum.
Sylvie really liked Callum and Callum wanted
to help them.
Callum had given Dexter a job.
One day, it might become a very good job but
at the moment Dexter wasn't enjoying it.
The problem was that Dexter had to 'start
at the bottom', as Callum said.
He had to make sandwiches.
He had to sell sandwiches in the shops.
He had to drive a van around London.
It was very menial work.
The worst thing about it was that he was frequently
recognized by people.
Customers in the shops often asked him why
he was no longer on TV and that hurt him.
He also worried that Sylvie was disappointed
in him.
She had pressured him about the job but he
felt she was angry that his TV career had
ended.
He worried that she was no longer very interested
in him.
They often argued these days.
And they hadn't made love for weeks.
Dexter was thinking about all this as he arrived
home.
But tonight he was going to prove to Sylvie
that he was a new person.
Tonight he was going to look after Jasmine
alone while Sylvie went out with friends.
It was going to be the first time Sylvie had
left the baby for more than a few minutes.
'I'm going out for a meal in Central London
with some of my girlfriends,' Sylvie had told
him.
'Then we'll stay at a hotel overnight.
I'll be back the next morning.
It will be all right, you'll see.'
'Yes, it will be all right,' Dexter told himself
now.
Sylvie looked tired and unhappy when Dexter
entered the house.
'What's wrong, darling?' he asked her.
'Oh, it's just been a bad day,' she replied.
'Jasmine hasn't slept at all.
She's been crying all day.
And life in the house gets very boring when
you aren't here.
I'll feel better when I get out of the house
tonight.
Now, are you sure you'll be all right on your
own with Jasmine?'
She tried to sound friendly, but Dexter knew
that she didn't really trust him.
'She thinks I'll start drinking,' he told
himself.
'But I will not!
I will certainly not!'
'We'll be fine,' he said.
'Don't worry about us.'
'If there's a problem, call me,' Sylvie said.
'But call my mobile, not the hotel number.
Do you understand?'
From the beginning, Dexter's evening was a
disaster.
Moments after Sylvie left the house, Jasmine
started to scream and she didn't stop.
She missed her mother.
She didn't let Dexter feed her.
Soon there was baby food all over her clothes
and she was wet through.
Dexter changed her clothes and laid her down,
but she refused to go to sleep.
Then she screamed when Dexter turned on the
television and saw the face of Suki Meadows.
Jasmine's scream was even louder than Suki's
voice.
Soon Dexter was desperate.
And soon he was walking to the wine shop in
the next street, with Jasmine in his arms.
When he returned home, Dexter opened one of
the bottles of wine he had bought.
As he drank, Jasmine finally went to sleep.
Dexter began to feel calmer, but he didn't
stop drinking.
He looked at the baby food, the baby clothes
and the baby toys that were all around him.
He felt trapped.
He drank some more wine.
'I need to talk to someone,' he told himself.
He tried to phone Emma Morley, but she didn't
answer her phone.
He waited for a few minutes and tried again.
Still she didn't answer.
Much later, and feeling desperate, he called
Suki Meadows.
'Hi, Suki, it's me - Dex,' he said.
'I saw you on TV earlier.
You were great.'
'DEX, HEY THERE!
WELL, HOW ABOUT ALL THIS?
I HAVEN'T HEARD FROM YOU FOR A LONG TIME,'
Suki shouted.
Suddenly she spoke quietly.
'In fact, it's been five years since we spoke.'
'Where are you, Suki?'
Dexter asked her.
'I'd love to see you.
There's so much to talk about.
I want us to be friends again.
Will you come to my house?
Get a taxi - I'll pay for it.'
'I'm at a party with some friends,' Suki said,
still speaking quietly.
'I'm not free.
When we were together, you treated me really
badly.
Do you remember that?
You can't just phone me after five years and
tell me to come to you.'
At that moment, Jasmine woke up and started
crying again.
'What was that noise?'
Suki asked.
'It's a baby... it's my daughter, Jasmine,'
Dexter said nervously.
'Didn't you know I had a daughter?
I married someone and -'
Suki said several very rude words and then
ended the call suddenly.
Dexter opened the other bottle.
Just before midnight, Sylvie used her mobile
phone to call Dexter.
She was sitting naked on the bed in her hotel
room.
They spoke for a few minutes, then Sylvie
ended the conversation and began to cry.
'He was drunk,' she said to Callum O'Neill,
who was sitting beside her.
'I knew he was going to be drunk.'
'Well, I've given him a job, there's nothing
else I can do about him,' Callum said.
'The question is - what are you going to do
about him?
And when are you going to do it?'
He turned on the television angrily and got
into bed.
CHAPTER FOURTEEN
Another Man
Sunday, 15th July 2001
Paris, France
Emma was waiting at the Eurostar station in
Paris.
She was waiting for Dexter to arrive on a
train from London.
She was a bit nervous.
They had only seen each other once since his
marriage to Sylvie had broken up.
On that occasion, they had spent the night
together.
That night, she had finally slept with him,
for the first and only time.
She thought now that it had probably been
a bad idea.
But he had been desperately unhappy and she
had wanted to help him in some way.
They'd both been a bit drunk.
Soon after, Emma had decided to get away from
England for a few months.
She had come to Paris for the spring and summer.
She wanted to spend her time writing.
Her Julie Criscoll books were a great success
and her publisher wanted more.
Now Dexter was coming to visit her for a few
days and she hoped that they could both forget
about that night and be good friends again.
But she had something to tell Dexter and she
was worried.
The train arrived and a few moments later
Emma saw Dexter walking towards her.
He was carrying a book.
He looked terrible - he'd lost weight and
his clothes were untidy and too big for him.
He looked desperately tired.
The end of his marriage to Sylvie had hurt
Dexter a lot.
Their divorce was going to be made final soon.
Sylvie and Jasmine had now gone to live with
Callum O'Neill.
That had made it worse for Dexter, of course.
'You didn't have to meet me,' Dexter said.
'Of course I had to meet you,' she said, smiling.
'You're a tourist.'
The two friends left the station and went
to a cafe near the river.
They sat down at a table outside it and Emma
ordered coffee for them.
Dexter put the book he had been carrying on
the table.
It was a copy of Big Julie Criscoll Against
the Whole World.
'It's great, Em,' Dexter said.
'I read it on the train.
I really enjoyed it.
It's the first novel I've finished in years.
There were hundreds of copies in the bookshop
at the station in London.
I'm really proud of you.'
'Well, thanks for that, but it's really a
book for eleven-to fourteen-year olds,' Emma
said.
She laughed, but she was touched.
'The publisher wants two more Julie Criscoll
books and there's going to be a TV show based
on them too,' she went on.
'I'm going to be...'
She stopped when she saw Dexter's face and
started to talk about something else.
They drank their coffee and then they walked
through the busy streets to Emma's flat.
As they walked, Dexter told Emma that he missed
his daughter desperately.
He saw her only once a fortnight, when Sylvie
brought her to visit him.
Emma's flat was on the fifth floor of an old
building.
They climbed the stairs and Emma opened the
door.
The flat was light and pleasant.
Emma went to the kitchen and Dexter looked
into the other rooms.
There was only one bed in the flat - a big
one.
Dexter saw the bed, sighed deeply, then he
hurried to the kitchen and put his arms round
Emma.
He started to kiss her wildly.
But after a moment, she pushed him gently
away.
'Dex, I have to tell you something,' Emma
said.
'I've got a friend here in Paris.
His name's Jean-Pierre.
I like him very much.'
Suddenly Dexter understood.
'You're seeing another man?' he said.
'A French man?
Oh, right.
But where am I going to sleep?
I need to find a hotel, don't I?
Or shall I just go back to London this evening?'
'You can sleep here, Dex.
I'll sleep at Jean-Pierre's flat,' Emma said.
Dexter just looked at her.
'Oh, Dexter, what did you think was going
to happen?'
'Well, we're lovers, aren't we?
I hoped that you and I...'
He stopped.
'Oh, Emma, you can't...
'
'Dexter, you're jealous,' Emma said laughing.
'I can't believe it.
This is so strange.
We were lovers for one night!
One night in thirteen years.
Think of all the girlfriends you've brought
to see me.
You always told me who you were sleeping with.
You didn't expect me to be jealous of them.
And now... and now...'
But she couldn't go on.
She saw the pain and the hopelessness in his
eyes.
She put her arms round him and kissed him
gently.
'Oh, Dexter,' she said quietly.
'I thought that I'd got rid of you.
I thought that you weren't going to be my
problem anymore.
All right, all right.
I'll phone Jean-Pierre and tell him that I'm
ill.
But Dexter, if you ever treat me badly and
go off with other people, I'll kill you.
Do you understand?'
CHAPTER FIFTEEN
Monday Morning
Monday, 15th July 2002
Belsize Park, London
At seven o'clock in the morning, Dexter Mayhew
and Emma Morley were lying awake in bed.
They were thinking their own thoughts.
They were now living together most of the
time.
Emma still kept her own flat, but at last
they were close friends and lovers as well,
and really, life was good for them both.
Emma's thoughts that morning were about the
15th July the previous year.
She thought about that and about what had
happened since then.
Dexter's visit to Paris had been difficult
at the start.
But she had quickly realized that she hadn't
really moved on from him and that probably
she wasn't able to move on from him.
So she'd finished her relationship with her
French boyfriend.
Dexter had stayed with her in Paris for the
whole summer and they'd returned to London
as a couple.
These days, Emma usually slept in Dexter's
flat in Belsize Park and during the daytimes,
she went to her own flat, two miles away.
She rode there on her bicycle and wrote her
books there.
Emma's series of books about Julie Criscoll
was selling very well.
The television version of them was popular
too, so Emma was almost rich now.
During the daytimes, Dexter now ran a successful
delicatessen and cafe in Highgate, another
fashionable part of north London.
Emma knew that he had hated doing menial jobs
when he worked for Callum O'Neill.
But now he seemed to enjoy doing the same
jobs for himself.
He enjoyed making the sandwiches and coffee
for his customers at the deli.
Most of the time, Emma was confident about
their future.
She loved Dexter and she loved his daughter
Jasmine, who often spent time with them.
The three of them were happy together.
This was good for Jasmine, because Sylvie
and Callum were not getting on well together.
But there was one little cloud in Emma's sky.
She was beginning to wish for a child of her
own.
And she wasn't getting any younger, of course.
Dexter already had a child and he wasn't so
happy with the idea of another one.
Sometimes they argued about this.
'Perhaps I need to find someone else,' Emma
sometimes thought when this happened.
But she never thought very seriously about
leaving Dexter.
One day, Emma had met Dexter's father again.
She remembered that meeting this morning.
'Of course I remember you, Emma,' Stephen
Mayhew had said.
'You called me a bourgeois fascist once.
I'm very pleased to meet you again.'
And he'd told her, 'Dexter is so much better
now that he has you with him.
Suddenly, I like my own son again.
It's wonderful.'
Now, as Emma stopped remembering things and
started to get up, Dexter spoke.
'Why do you still keep your own flat, Emma?'
he said.
'You can live here all the time.
You know that.'
'Dexter, are you asking me to be your flatmate?'
Emma replied, pretending to be surprised.
'It's taken you a lot of years, hasn't it?'
'Yes, I think I am,' Dexter said.
'And, yes it has.
But that's what I want.'
'The flat's really too small, Dex,' Emma said
after a few moments.
'Well, let's buy a house together, Em,' Dexter
said.
CHAPTER SIXTEEN
bigdayspeech.doc
Tuesday, 15th July 2003
Yorkshire, England
That's the place where I was bitten by a dog
when I was a little girl,' Emma said.
She pointed ahead.
She and Dexter were walking along a beach
on the Yorkshire coast.
The morning was hot, but there weren't many
people on the beach.
The school holidays hadn't begun yet.
'What kind of dog was it?'
Dexter asked.
He was trying too hard to sound interested.
Emma looked carefully at him.
Clearly, he didn't really want to know what
kind of dog had bitten her.
'Am I boring you, Dexter?'
she asked.
She sounded a bit cross.
'No, of course you aren't,' Dexter replied
wearily.
'Well, perhaps you are boring me a little
bit.'
'Ah, then you have four more days of boredom
to look forward to, don't you?'
Emma said.
She laughed.
She liked his sudden honesty.
'Poor Dexter,' she added.
Emma and Dexter were on holiday.
They had rented a small cottage in the Yorkshire
countryside for a week.
Each day they set out to visit places that
Emma remembered from when she was a child.
Today, after their morning at the beach, they
were going to drive inland.
Emma wanted to find a waterfall she remembered
from her childhood.
'It's a beautiful place, Dex,' she said.
'You'll love it.'
But that afternoon, they didn't succeed in
their search.
Emma's memory wasn't good enough.
After an hour they hadn't found Emma's waterfall.
So they found a pleasant spot in the sun and
lay down on the grass.
Soon, Dexter was feeling a bit sleepy.
'Look at that bird up there, Dex,' Emma said
suddenly, pointing to the sky.
'What kind of bird is it?
It's beautiful!'
Dexter did not look up.
'I'm too young to be a birdwatcher,' he said.
'Birdwatching is for middle-aged people.
And isn't birdwatching a very bourgeois thing
to do?
Next, you'll want us to move to the country.
Then you'll want us to cuddle in bed and call
each other "darling" and go to the shops together.'
For a moment, Emma thought about Ian Whitehead.
Calling him 'darling' hadn't meant that she
really loved him, had it?
'After that it's classical music - Beethoven
and that kind of thing,' Dexter went on.
'I've seen it happen to people, Em.
It's awful.'
Emma laughed and kissed him.
'It does sound awful.
Tell me again - why are we going to get married?'
she said.
'Well, we don't need to.
We could cancel the wedding,' Dexter said.
'Yes, but we've paid for it now,' Emma said.
'Can we get our money back if we cancel it?'
'I don't think so,' Dexter replied.
'Ah well, we'd better get married then,' said
Emma.
'I knew there was a reason.'
And she kissed him again.
Then she closed her eyes and thought about
their wedding.
They had chosen a day in November for the
ceremony.
Only a few close friends were going to be
there.
And finally she was going to be Emma Mayhew,
after all these years.
'I'll marry you if you promise you'll never
play golf,' she whispered.
That evening, they went to bed early.
Emma quickly went to sleep, but Dexter couldn't
sleep so he got up quietly and went downstairs.
He was thinking about Emma and about their
big day in November.
He was going to make a speech at the wedding
party.
He needed it to be just right.
Suddenly, he remembered something that Emma
had once said to him.
He turned on his laptop and opened a file.
Then he looked into his heart and made some
notes:
My wedding speech
1) I met Emma at University.
2) She called my dad a bourgeois fascist.
3) She can't cook.
4) We argue a lot - but laugh a lot too.
5) She's beautiful but she doesn't believe
it.
6) She gets on well with my lovely daughter,
Jasmine.
7) She even gets on well with my ex-wife.
Ha, ha!
(Leave five seconds for laughter here.)
8) Everyone loves her.
9) Our sudden romance lasted 15 years.
10) My wonderful mum loved Emma.
ALSO...
11) Say something nice about Dad and about
Emma's parents.
12) Say that it's my second wedding and I
need to get it right this time, etc.
He was reading what he had written when he
heard Emma's footsteps on the stairs.
He gave the file a name - bigdayspeech.doc
- and closed it.
'Sorry, I fell asleep,' Emma said from the
bottom of the stairs.
'But I'm awake now.
What shall we do?'
'I think I'd like to play a board game,' said
Dexter and he smiled.
CHAPTER SEVENTEEN
Too Late
Thursday, 15th July 2004
Belsize Park, London
It was breakfast time in Belsize Park.
'Well, it didn't happen this month, Dex,'
Emma said sadly.
'I'm sorry.'
'Please don't worry about it, Em,' Dexter
said.
'We'll go on trying.'
'I'll be thirty-nine next April,' Emma replied.
'Soon it will be too late.'
Dexter now wanted a baby as much as she did.
But it wasn't happening.
They were both beginning to worry.
'It really doesn't matter,' Emma told herself.
'We're a happily married couple.
That's the important thing.
And Jasmine's here a lot.'
She told herself this, but there was a hole
in her life now.
It made her sad and sometimes it made her
cross with Dexter for no real reason.
This morning she tried to be calm, but she
was quickly upset by something in the newspaper.
'Dex, I don't understand students these days,'
she said.
'They don't care about anything, do they?
When I was a student, we protested about things
like this.'
She put the newspaper down in front of him
and pointed at a story.
'Perhaps they're right not to protest,' said
Dexter wearily.
'We aren't all socialist feminist anti-fascists,
are we?
Some of us have other things to worry about.'
And that started the argument.
For ten minutes they were very rude to each
other.
Then, quite suddenly, Emma didn't want to
argue any longer.
'I'm sorry, Dexter,' she said.
'This isn't about students, is it?
It's about not having a baby.
I'm really upset about it.
I don't want to fight with you.'
By the time they left the house they were
almost friends again.
Emma was going to her flat to write.
Dexter was going to the deli, but he wasn't
in a hurry.
He now had help there.
A pleasant girl called Maddy worked as his
manager.
And a few other people helped at busy times.
'There's a house that I want us to look at
this afternoon,' Dexter said as they left
the flat.
'We really must buy one soon and I've got
a good feeling about this one.
I'll phone you with the address later.
It's in Kilburn.
Meet me at the house at five o'clock.'
So Emma got on her bicycle and rode off to
do her day's work.
At about lunchtime, Dexter phoned with the
address where they were going to meet.
'I'll see you there, darling,' Emma said.
'I'm sorry about this morning.
I love you.'
At four o'clock, Emma set off from her flat
to cycle to Kilburn.
It started to rain and soon the roads were
wet.
There was lots of traffic noise.
Emma didn't hear the car that came out of
a side street at high speed.
So she was surprised to be flying through
the air.
She landed by the side of the road.
When she opened her eyes, there were people
standing round her.
'Are you all right, Miss?' one of them asked.
Another was crying.
But Emma didn't speak.
She knew that she was certainly not all right.
Two thoughts passed through her mind as she
lay on the ground.
One was a memory of herself playing on a Yorkshire
beach.
She was with her parents and she was nine
years old.
The other thought was about Dexter.
She was going to be late for their meeting.
He was going to worry and he was going to
get wet.
Then Emma Mayhew died and everything she had
ever thought had gone.
CHAPTER EIGHTEEN
Three Anniversaries
Friday, 15th July 2005
London, England
The months had passed.
A year had passed.
Very early in the morning of 15th July 2005,
Dexter Mayhew was drinking in a club in Central
London.
It was the kind of club that stayed open very
late.
Dexter was alone.
Earlier, he had come to the club with Maddy,
his manager, and two of the other workers
from his deli.
Dexter had wanted them all to drink to the
memory of Emma at exactly midnight, at the
beginning of her anniversary day.
They had gladly come with him.
But soon after midnight the others had left
the club.
They needed to go home.
Maddy had tried to make Dexter go home too,
but he'd wanted to stay, and Maddy had left.
Now Dexter was very drunk.
Finally, Dexter left and walked to another
club, where he continued drinking.
Soon he got into a fight.
He knew that he wasn't going to win the fight.
He didn't want to win the fight.
He wanted to die.
The fight ended with Dexter lying unconscious
in the street.
When he woke, he found that someone had stolen
his money and his keys.
There was blood all over his clothes.
Somehow, he found his way back to Belsize
Park.
But outside his front door, he realized that
he couldn't get into the flat without his
keys.
He lay down and went to sleep on the ground.
Sylvie found him unconscious there in the
morning when she brought Jasmine for a visit.
Sylvie had ended her relationship with Callum
O'Neill and Dexter now got on quite well with
his ex-wife.
When she found Dexter outside his door, she
phoned his father.
She had her own keys, so she took Dexter into
the flat and washed him and found him some
clean clothes.
Later, Stephen Mayhew arrived and took Dexter
back to Oxfordshire.
Now that they had both lost their wives, they
understood each other better.
Dexter's father was gentle with him.
Saturday, 15th July 2006
London, England
The months had passed.
Another year had passed.
For Dexter, the second anniversary of Emma's
death wasn't as painful as the first one.
When the deli closed for the day, he decided
to spend the evening alone.
He wanted to look through Emma's books and
photographs.
He was going to keep some of them.
He was going to give some of them to her parents.
The others were going to her friends.
So in the evening, he sat with Emma's things
around him.
He thought about the previous anniversary
and he remembered a strange thing.
A few days after 15th July last year, he'd
received a kind letter from Ian Whitehead.
'When Emma left me, I hated you,' he had written.
'I wanted to die.
But after a few years I met someone else and
my life changed.
And now I'm happy again.
We have three children.
I know how you must feel without Emma, Dexter.
And I know that she loved you very, very much.
I used to think that you weren't good enough
for her.
But none of us was good enough for Emma.
And we have to go on for her.
Please take care of yourself.'
After that letter, Dexter and Ian had spoken
on the phone a few times.
But they both knew that they weren't going
to meet again.
Dexter spent a lot of the evening looking
at Emma's old photos.
He found some which Emma had taken on Arthur's
Seat in Edinburgh.
One of them had been taken by someone else
and showed both Emma and Dexter.
These photos had been taken on the first day
they had ever spent together.
Suddenly, Dexter felt terrible.
There were so many memories.
He started to cry, but he knew what to do.
He phoned his friend Maddy.
Talking to her made him calm again.
'Shall I come to you?'
she said.
'I can get a taxi.'
'No, it's all right.
I just wanted hear a friendly voice,' Dexter
told her.
'I'll be fine now.'
And soon, he felt much better.
Sunday, 15th July 2007
Edinburgh, Scotland
The months had passed.
One more year had passed.
On the third anniversary of Emma's death,
Dexter was in Edinburgh, with Maddy and Jasmine.
Dexter and Maddy were a couple now and they
were having a short holiday with Dexter's
daughter.
This morning, Maddy had told Dexter to take
Jasmine for a walk.
'I'll go to one of the art galleries,' she'd
said.
She'd guessed that Dexter wanted to visit
places from his past.
She'd also guessed that he wanted to talk
to Jasmine about Emma.
Jasmine was seven years old now and she walked
happily beside Dexter.
First they walked to Rankeillor Street and
for a minute, Dexter looked up at the window
of the flat where Emma used to live.
Then they walked through the streets towards
Arthur's Seat.
'Let's do some climbing,' said Dexter when
they reached the hill.
'There's a wonderful view from the top.'
'Did Emma come up here too?'
Jasmine asked him when they reached the top.
'Yes, we came here together,' Dexter replied.
'I have a photo of us both on the hill.
I'll show you it when we get back to London.'
'Do you miss Emma?'
Jasmine asked quietly.
'Yes, I miss her every day,' Dexter said.
'She was my best friend.
Do you miss her?'
'I think I miss her,' Jasmine said.
'But I was only four when she died.
I don't remember her very well.
She was nice, wasn't she?'
'She was very nice,' Dexter said.
'Who's your best friend now, Daddy?'
asked Jasmine.
'You are, of course,' Dexter replied quickly.
'Can we go down now?'
Jasmine said.
'I'm a bit tired.'
CHAPTER NINETEEN
The Past
Friday, 15th July 1988
Edinburgh, Scotland
Have you had someone in your room all night?'
Tilly Killick asked, when Emma Morley entered
the kitchen in their flat that morning.
'Oh, yes, it's only Dexter Mayhew,' Emma replied.
She tried to sound uninterested.
She was not very successful.
'It's only Dexter Mayhew!
You lucky person,' Tilly said.
She sounded a little jealous.
'Is he staying here all day too?'
'No, I think we'll go out after breakfast,'
Emma said.
'What shall we do?
Have you any ideas for a romantic day, Tilly?'
'Well, Arthur's Seat is a good place to go,
isn't it?'
Tilly said.
'You can be romantic there.'
So after breakfast, Emma and Dexter went out
into the city.
Emma took her camera with her and they bought
food for a picnic.
Dexter was worried about climbing Arthur's
Seat.
He was wearing expensive shoes and he didn't
want to ruin them.
'I don't climb mountains, Em,' he said.
'I'm not that kind of person.'
'Dexter, it's only a hill, it's not K2,' Emma
replied, laughing.
So they climbed Arthur's Seat and when they
reached the top they decided that it wasn't
really romantic.
There were too many people already there for
that.
But Dexter had never climbed the hill before
and he was surprised.
He enjoyed the view.
It made an impression on him.
This didn't often happen.
'I've lived in this city for four years,'
he said.
'Now this is my last day in Edinburgh.
Why haven't I been up here before?'
'Because you're not that kind of person,'
Emma replied.
They ate their picnic and then they sat quietly
together.
'Dexter,' Emma said after a few minutes, 'I
want to say something.
It's about last night.
I haven't done that kind of thing often and
I know that you were a bit drunk.
I know it was just one night, and that's it.
But I want to say that it was nice for me.
It was nice and you're nice, Dexter.
You're a nice person when you allow yourself
to be nice.
I really like you.'
Later, on their way back to the bottom of
the hill, they stopped to take some photos.
Someone took a photo of both of them together.
Then Emma walked with Dexter back to his flat.
They found Dexter's parents waiting for him
there.
'This is my friend Emma Morley,' Dexter told
his parents.
'Hello Emma, I'm Alison,' Dexter's mother
said.
'We're pleased to meet you.
Do you want to come for a drink with us?'
Emma looked at Dexter.
He looked unhappy and worried.
She made a quick decision.
'No, thank you,' she replied.
'That's very kind of you, but I have to get
back to my flat.'
Then she spoke to the boy.
'Have a nice life, Dexter,' she said quickly.
She turned and walked away.
'I'll probably never see him again,' she told
herself as she walked sadly along the street.
But a few minutes later, as she walked through
the city centre, she heard someone call her
name behind her.
She turned and saw Dexter.
He had been running and he was exhausted".
'My parents came early,' he said.
'I didn't have time to get your address and
phone number.'
Quickly, Emma wrote these on a piece of paper
and Dexter wrote his address and phone number
for her.
'Call me when I get back from France,' he
said.
'Come and stay with us for a few days.
I want to see you again.'
Then he kissed her gently and she kissed him.
They stood in the middle of the busy street
and people on their way home hurried around
them.
It was the sweetest kiss either of them ever
knew.
'Goodbye, Dex,' Emma said.
'Goodbye.'
'Goodbye.
Goodbye.'
- THE END -