ants and an expensive watch.
Everything was worth about $15,000."
"Don't tell me all this!" said Wood.
"Oh, it's all right," said Kernan.
"Everything is in my suitcase at the hotel.
And now I'll tell you why I'm talking.
Because it's safe.
I'm talking to a man I know.
You owe me a thousand dollars, Barney Woods.
You won't arrest me."
"I remember," said Woods.
"You gave me one thousand dollars.
One day I'll pay back the money.
The thousand dollars saved me.
They were putting my furniture out on the
street when I got home that night."
"You're a good, honest man," continued Kernan,
"and you can't arrest me because you owe me
money."
The waiter came and brought them some drinks.
Woods looked at the little gold pencil and
said, "I can't arrest you.
I didn't pay back the thousand dollars.
It's a bad situation for me, but you helped
me once, Johnny, and now I must do the same."
"I knew it," said Kernan smiling.
"I can judge men, Woods."
"I'm silent only because I owe you money,
otherwise you couldn't escape!" said Woods.
"I know I couldn't," said Kernan.
"That's why I knew I was safe with you."
"You see, Kernan, I'm a man first and then
a detective.
And now I'll let you go and I'll leave the
New York City Police.
I'll probably go and drive a truck.
I'll never be able to pay back the thousand
dollars."
"Oh, you can keep it," said Kernan.
"But I know you want to pay it back one day.
I was lucky that you borrowed it.
But let's change the subject.
Tomorrow I'm going to the West on the train.
I know a place where I can sell the jewels.
Have another drink, Barney, and forget your
problems.
Let's have fun tonight!
I'm in the hands of my old friend, Barney
Woods."
All evening Kernan told Woods many stories
about his successful wrongdoings and clever
criminal plans.
Woods became very irritated by this vicious
man.
"Be very careful, Kernan.
The newspapers could write about the Norcross
case again, because there were a lot of burglaries
and murders in New York this summer."
Kernan suddenly became angry.
"I don't care about the newspapers.
What can the newspapers do?
They can send reporters and photographers
to the scene of the crime.
They can write about it, but they can't catch
the burglar."
"Well, I don't know," said Woods slowly.
"Some newspapers do very good work.
There's the Morning Mars for example.
They helped to catch a criminal when the police
forgot about him."
"I'll show you," said Kernan, getting up confidently.
"I'll show you what I think of newspapers
in general and the Morning Mars in particular."
There was a telephone booth near their table.
Kernan went inside the booth and left the
door open.
He found a number in the telephone book and
phoned.
Woods sat quietly and looked at Kernan's cold
and arrogant face.
He listened carefully.
"Hello, the Morning Mars?
I want to speak to the editor."
He waited a few moments with his vicious little
smile.
"Are you the editor?
I am the man who killed old Norcross.
Wait!
This is not the usual crank call.
I killed the old man at 2.30 a.m.
Two weeks ago.
What?
You don't believe me?
You don't understand!
I'm giving you the biggest scoop in the history
of your boring, little newspaper.
What?
Really?
Well, you can't expect me to give you my name
and address, can you?
No, this is not a rival newspaper!
I killed old Norcross and I have the jewels
in a suitcase.
Well, I'm not going to tell you the name of
the hotel.
Now, listen, half of the second button on
Mrs Norcross' nightgown is broken.
I saw it when took the ring off her finger."
Kernan looked at Woods and said, "He believes
me now."
Then he started talking on the phone again.
"Hello, yes, I'm here.
What, you want to catch me in forty - eight
hours?
Stop being foolish!
Just continue writing your stories about divorces,
accidents and the dirty scandals you write
about."
Kernan hung up the phone and said, "He's really
furious now.
Well, Barney, let's go and enjoy ourselves
tonight!
We can have dinner and see a musical comedy.
I only need four hours sleep and then I'm
going West."
Kernan and Woods had dinner in a Broadway
restaurant and went to see a musical comedy.
Kernan spent a lot of money.
At half past three in the morning they went
to an all-night cafe.
Kernan continued talking in his fast, arrogant
manner.
Woods listened and thought sadly about the
end of his career as a detective.
But suddenly his eyes became bright.
"I wonder if it's possible," he thought.
"I won-der if it's possible!"
Outside it was early morning, The big city
was waking up.
Woods could hear the first noises of the day.
One of the noises were the cries of the newspaper
boys with the latest news - the Clarion Call.
Woods gave ten cents to a waiter and said,
"Buy me a Morning Mars, please."
When he got the paper he looked at the first
page.
Then he took a page out of his little notebook
and began writing with a little gold pencil.
"What's the news?" asked Kernan.
Woods showed him the piece of paper:
Please pay to John Kernan the thousand-dollar
reward that is mine for his arrest Barnard
Woods
"You teased them so much on the phone and
they put YOU on the first page of the Morning
Mars'.
Now, Johnny, you'll come to the police station
with me."
- THE END -