CHAPTER ONE
The Girl with a Future
On 1 July 1961, a baby girl was born at her
family home, in Sandringham, Norfolk.
Her parents, Frances and Johnnie Spencer,
couldn't decide what to call her at first.
They had two daughters already, and this time
they really wanted a boy.
Finally, they called her 'Diana'.
They didn't know that in the future the name
Diana Spencer would be famous all over the
world.
They could not guess how popular she would
be in her short but full life.
The Spencers are a very old English family.
They became rich a long time ago as sheep
farmers, and the family goes back to King
Charles II and King James II of England.
They have been friends and helpers of the
Royal Family for hundreds of years.
The house they lived in then, Park House,
was near the Queen's house at Sandringham,
so Diana grew up almost 'next door' to the
Royal Family.
Diana often visited them at Sandringham House
when she was a little girl.
The Queen's most important homes are at Buckingham
Palace in London, and Windsor Castle just
to the west of London.
But she also spends time at Balmoral Castle
in Scotland, and at Sandringham House, which
is in the east of England.
Later, people called Diana 'a fairy-tale princess'.
But her story was often a sad one too.
Her parents had the son that they wanted so
much in 1964 - they called him Charles.
But their marriage was unhappy, and soon terrible
fights began.
When Diana was only six, her mother, Frances,
ran away with another man, Peter Shand Kydd.
For a long time, the children could only visit
their mother at weekends.
Frances very much wanted her children to live
with her.
But their father was against the idea, and
so they stayed at Park House with him.
Other women came to the house to look after
the children, but they didn't usually stay
long.
The children made trouble for them - they
threw their clothes out of the window, or
locked them in the toilet!
The two smallest children, Charles and Diana,
were really unhappy.
Each night in bed, Charles cried for his mother,
and Diana lay there alone, listening to him.
She was too frightened of the dark house to
get out of bed and go to him.
But Diana and Charles were a loving brother
and sister.
As time went on, they often travelled by train
together to visit their mother.
Diana was always friendly with her two older
sisters, Sarah and Jane, but they had different
lives.
Johnnie Spencer tried to do his best for the
four children, and at Christmas they could
choose all the presents that they wanted.
There were too many presents, and not enough
hugs and kisses, they remembered later.
Diana loved her father, and wanted to look
after him.
She liked to help in the house too, and to
look after her animals.
She had a cat, Marmalade, and a dog called
Jill.
Like a lot of English girls, Diana learned
to ride a horse, but after she broke her arm
in an accident she was frightened, and didn't
want to ride again.
Like the children in many rich or old families
in England, the Spencer children went away
to school.
Diana went to Riddlesworth Hall School in
1970 when she was only seven.
She lived there during the term, and came
home in the holidays.
In 1974, she went on to her mother's old school,
West Heath School in Kent, which was on the
other side of London from Norfolk.
Her sisters Sarah and Jane were also students
there.
By then, her mother wasn't living in London,
but in Scotland.
She and her husband Peter had a large farm
on an island.
It was a wild and beautiful place, and Diana
had some lovely holidays there.
In Diana's young life, everything was always
changing, and she often felt alone.
She was very sad when her grandmother - her
father s mother - died in 1972.
Her grandmother was a very kind woman.
She looked after Diana a lot when her parents
separated.
Things changed even more in 1975 when her
grandfather died too, and the Spencer family
moved into the old family home at Althorp,
in Northamptonshire.
Diana's father was now Earl Spencer, Diana
became Lady Diana Spencer, and her brother
Charles a Viscount.
Later, he too became an Earl.
Until then, Park House in Sandringham was
the only home that Diana knew.
She didn't like going to Sandringham House
to visit the royal family much - she felt
strange in the royal house.
But she loved Park House, with its friendly
rooms and its big garden.
She could go swimming in the pool there, play
tennis, or hide in the tree-house.
The children didn't really want to live at
Althorp.
They didn't enjoy their visits there when
their grandfather was alive.
The house was large, dark and frightening,
with lots of old family pictures on the walls.
But as they grew up, they liked it more.
They enjoyed having their friends to stay
- it was a good house for parties!
At school, Diana made plenty of friends.
She was a good student, not especially clever,
but she enjoyed her lessons.
She liked English and painting, but she was
best at dancing and swimming.
It was soon clear that she would never go
to university, but she was helpful and kind.
She even won a cup for helpfulness!
As part of the school's charity programme,
Diana began to visit old or ill people in
the town near the school.
Usually, she talked to them, or helped with
their shopping.
This is perhaps where her love of charity
work began.
But she was not always quite so good.
Once she got into real trouble when she left
the school at night!
She planned to meet a friend outside the school
to get some sweets from her.
One of the teachers found her empty bed and
called the police!
The head teacher was very angry, but her parents
were secretly amused.
When Diana left West Heath School, she was
sixteen.
At first, she didn't know what to do.
Life at home was changing again because her
father had a new wife.
Her name was Raine, and she was the daughter
of Barbara Cartland, a famous writer of love
stories.
Diana and her brother and sisters were not
very pleased about the marriage.
They didn't want Raine as their second mother,
and were always fighting with her.
But Johnnie loved his new wife, and they were
very happy together.
And, in the end, Diana was pleased that Raine
was there to look after her father.
In 1978, a year after the marriage, Johnnie
became very ill.
The doctors thought that he would die.
Raine nursed him back to health, but it was
a long time before he was better again.
A little earlier, in 1977, Diana went off
to a very expensive 'finishing' school in
Switzerland because she didn't want to stay
at home.
Girls from rich families went there to learn
to cook, to speak French, and to look after
a home.
Diana only stayed there for six weeks, then
decided that she wanted to go back to England
to work.
In the past, girls from important families
like the Spencers never worked for money.
But times were different now, and Diana wanted
to be like other girls of her age.
'I can easily find a job,' she told her father.
He bought her a very nice flat in Coleherne
Court, Kensington, in the centre of London.
She asked a few friends to come and live with
her - one of them, Carolyn Pride, was an old
schoolfriend of hers.
This was the beginning of a really happy time
for Diana.
She was young and pretty.
She had good friends - both boyfriends and
girlfriends - and a nice flat and a car.
She was free to try and find her way in the
world.
What could she do for a job?
She loved children, and so she began to look
after babies and small children for her sisters'
friends.
Sometimes she cleaned their houses too, or
cooked meals for them.
She studied cooking again in London - she
was good at Russian soup: but she and the
girls in the flat ate chocolate most of the
time!
Then she found a job at the Young England
School for little children.
Here she was very happy, and her bosses were
very pleased with her work.
She was calm and kind with the children, and
always gave them plenty of love and hugs.
Soon there would be love in her life too - she
would find her prince and fill in love.
She would become the new Princess of Wales.
She didn't know this, of course, but she did
feel that she was getting ready for something
special.
Diana went to parties, and she had a lot of
friends, but she was never serious about a
man at that time.
'I had to keep myself tidy,' she said later,
'for what was coming.'
CHAPTER TWO
A Fairy-Tale Wedding
Prince Charles was taking a long time to choose
a wife.
He was already 32.
He always had plenty of girlfriends - Diana's
sister, Sarah, was once his girlfriend.
But he couldn't decide who to marry.
Charles was the future King of Britain, so
he had to choose well.
Not every beautiful woman makes a good queen.
Life in the Royal Family can be very hard
- the 'Royals' spend a lot of time in public.
She must also be a girl from a good family,
and Charles must be her first lover.
In February 1981, the news finally came out
that Prince Charles was getting married - to
Lady Diana Spencer.
The photos in the newspapers showed a pretty,
quiet girl with a sweet smile, and the reporters
soon began to call her 'Shy Di'.
Diana was the first English girl to marry
a Prince of Wales for five hundred years.
And in private, Prince Charles said that the
Spencers were 'more royal than the Royals'!
It seemed that Diana and Charles were perfect
together.
People in Britain began to look forward to
a fairy-tale wedding.
Diana grew up with the Royal Family, but for
a long time she didn't really know Charles.
There are a lot of families in the royal circle,
and also Charles was twelve years older than
her.
He was already a young man when she was still
a child.
But when Diana was sixteen, they met at a
country house party.
She was only a schoolgirl, and Charles was
more interested in his dog and his sport than
in her.
But from that time, Diana put a photo of Charles
by her bed.
They met at a few more parties, but it was
only in July 1980 that Charles began to look
at Diana with new eyes.
They were both staying with friends in the
country.
In the evening, Diana sat next to Charles
outside in the garden.
She was telling him that she saw him at a
funeral a year earlier.
'You looked so sad,' she said.
'I thought, "It's wrong that you're alone
- you need someone to look after you."'
Charles's heart opened to her, and from then
on he was seriously interested in her.
He asked her out for an evening of music,
with supper later at Buckingham Palace.
But he didn't give Diana much time - she only
had twenty minutes to wash her hair and get
ready!
'Maybe you'll be the next Queen of England!'
a friend told her.
Diana only laughed.
Then Charles asked her to go to Balmoral for
the Braemar Games, the Scottish sports which
happen every September.
Diana's sister Jane was now married to Robert
Fellowes, the Queen's personal secretary.
They had a small house in the royal park at
Balmoral, and Diana stayed there with her
sister and husband.
Prince Charles phoned her every day, and they
went for walks together.
Until then, no one guessed that the Prince
had a new girlfriend.
But, one day, Charles and Diana were fishing
down by the River Dee.
Suddenly they noticed someone on the other
side of the river.
It was a reporter from a newspaper looking
for royal news.
Diana quickly ran to hide behind some trees,
and used a mirror from her handbag to watch
him.
Two other photographers hurried to the same
place by the river.
They were all very excited, trying to see
this new woman in Charles's life.
Diana escaped from them that day.
But soon the reporters knew her name, and
it was in all the newspapers.
Now her life began to change.
The public wanted to know all about her, and
paparazzi followed her everywhere.
They followed her in her little red Mini-Metro
car.
They phoned her in the middle of the night
and waited for her outside the Young England
School.
Even when she agreed to a photograph, they
still made trouble.
The light was shining behind her skirt and
showed all of her long, beautiful legs!
It was a very difficult time for a shy young
girl, and the Royal Family didn't help her.
Even Charles was not amused by the photograph.
Diana began to understand that even famous
and popular people can be very much alone.
When Prince Charles finally asked her to marry
him, in February 1981, she agreed.
She arrived back at her flat very happy that
night.
Her friends were waiting for her.
They knew that it was something special!
Diana said, 'I've got news for you - but I
must go to the toilet first!'
So they all knocked on the toilet door until
she told them!
'I'm going to marry Prince Charles!'
she called out, half laughing and half-crying.
He gave her a beautiful blue ring, and they
were ready now for the photographs, the television
recordings and the public appearances.
Several times, they had to answer the question,
'Are you in love?'
'Of course!'
answered Diana.
But Charles was not so sure.
His answer always seemed to be, 'Yes - but
what does that mean?'
To the public, it was real love.
It was exciting news for Britain.
Here was a fairy-tale prince and princess,
bringing new colour and life into the Royal
Family.
Diana now moved into Clarence House, the Queen
Mother's home, and was safer there from the
reporters.
Everyone was getting ready for the wedding
- over ten-thousand presents arrived for Charles
and Diana!
She chose a young husband and wife, David
and Elizabeth Emanuel, to make her wedding
dress.
'She made coffee for us,' they remembered.
'Here was the future Princess of Wales, and
we were students not so long ago.
It was quite a surprise.'
But not everything was perfect.
At the centre of the fairy-tale, there was
a black shadow.
When Charles asked Diana to marry him, something
strange happened.
She suddenly felt, deep inside, that she would
never be Queen.
She also knew that she would have a difficult
job as Charles's wife.
This did not stop her.
But, just before the wedding, she became seriously
worried.
She suddenly understood that Charles's old
girlfriend, Camilla Parker-Bowles, was still
very important to him.
Diana found a present from Charles to Camilla,
and he often telephoned her.
Did Charles really love her, or was he still
in love with Camilla?
And Diana was no longer free.
The happy days in her flat with her friends,
and at work with the little children, were
all gone.
The 'royal machine' frightened her.
There were so many royal rules, and Buckingham
Palace was a 'dead' place to her.
No one welcomed her when she arrived at Clarence
House, and no one told her how to do things.
She still tried to enjoy herself.
She escaped to Australia for a quiet holiday
with her mother where none of the paparazzi
could find them.
Back at Clarence House, she wanted to go on
with her dancing, and so she asked her old
teacher to come and work with her.
But she knew that soon nothing would be the
same.
During one of her last lessons she said, 'In
twelve days' time, I shall no longer be me.'
She got thinner, and she even wanted to stop
the wedding.
Her sisters told her to go on.
'Bad luck - you've got to do it!
Your face is on the tea-towels now!'
they said.
So on 29 July 1981, Prince Charles married
Lady Diana Spencer in St Paul's Cathedral,
London.
It was a great day for England.
More than a million people were out on the
streets in the morning to wave as she went
by.
In Britain, everything stopped as people switched
on the television.
In many houses there were little parties as
families, friends and neighbours all sat down
together to enjoy themselves.
Diana arrived at St Paul's with her father.
The church was full of important people from
all over the world.
Not only was the British Royal Family there,
but there were other kings and queens from
Europe.
There was beautiful music, and the church
was full of flowers.
Diana looked wonderful in her long wedding
dress, which was almost white, with the skirt
very long at the back.
With flowers in her hands, and her heart full
of hope, she agreed to marry Charles.
'I will,' she said.
Charles put the wedding ring on her finger.
It was made of Welsh gold.
This gold was a present to the Royal Family
about fifty years earlier, and Diana's ring
was made of the very last piece.
Charles and Diana were now husband and wife.
They promised to stay together all their lives.
The crowds who were shouting 'Lady Di!
Lady Di!'
now changed the words to 'Princess Di!
Princess Di!'
They went back to Buckingham Palace, where
Charles kissed his new wife in public.
Then they left for their wedding holiday,
first at a house called Broadlands, then on
the royal ship, Britannia.
Diana was suddenly the world's favourite woman.
Her face really was on the tea-towels - and
on cups, glasses, spoons, and all kinds of
things that people bought at the time of the
Royal Wedding.
They wanted something to record and remember
that special day, the most important royal
day since Elizabeth became Queen in June 1953.
In some ways, Queen Elizabeth was still part
of a picture which was painted by the famous
Queen Victoria over a hundred years before.
In this picture, the Royal Family is a good
Christian family.
They show a polite face in public, and keep
all their problems secret.
Royal children must learn that their country
comes first, and their personal life second.
Sadly, this can also give us a Royal Family
which seems cold and far away.
Queen Elizabeth did try to make the Royal
Family more modern.
Once, most royal children studied at home,
but her son Prince Charles went away to school
and university.
In the 1960s television cameras recorded her
home and her family life for the first time,
so that people began to know the Royal Family
a little bit better.
But, in the end, it was not enough for modern
times.
So could the fairy-tale marriage possibly
have a happy ending?
Did Charles really love Diana when he married
her?
He probably tried to do his best at the time,
but it was difficult for him, too.
In the past, kings and princes married to
make the Royal Family stronger and to have
children.
Now Charles had to find the right wife for
the Royal Family, and marry for love.
Could Diana be the perfect royal wife, when
she was also a modern girl?
In 1981, we didn't ask ourselves these questions.
We all wanted to enjoy the fairy tale while
we could.
CHAPTER THREE
The Young Princess
In her new marriage, Diana was like a young
bird who was learning to fly.
At school, she was too shy to speak in public.
Now she was making public appearances all
the time as one of the Royal Family.
One of her first public visits was in May
just before she got married.
This was to Tetbury, a town near Prince Charles's
new country home at Highgrove in Gloucestershire.
Crowds of people came out to see Diana.
Dressed in a red suit, she walked through
the streets and smiled shyly as they gave
her bunches of flowers.
It took some time before she wasn't frightened
of these public appearances.
On one of the first that she made with Prince
Charles, he told her to walk over to the waiting
crowds.
'Talk to them,' he told her.
'I can't!
I just can't!'
she said.
But she had to, and after that, she found
it became easier and easier.
She was very natural, and everyone liked that.
People began to feel that they could talk
to her about their problems.
She was quickly becoming one of the most popular
women in the world.
Soon she was more popular than Charles.
He wasn't very pleased by this.
'I'm sorry I'm not my wife,' he said once
or twice to the crowds when he made visits
alone.
Everyone loved Diana because she was young
and beautiful.
During her first few years as a princess,
she learnt how to dress well, and people became
interested in her clothes.
After every appearance, the reporters described
what she was wearing.
There were photos in the newspapers recording
all her different dresses.
Before she got married, she still looked very
young.
Her face was round, and her clothes were nothing
special.
And when she first became Princess of Wales,
she still didn't always dress well.
Sometimes she wore dresses and hats that were
too old for her, like those for a 45-year-old
woman.
Then she became the well-dressed Diana that
we remember today.
She chose a lot of wonderful clothes - dinner
dresses, dance dresses, trousers, and suits.
She learnt to dress for all kinds of different
appearances - for special visits, for sports,
or for travel.
For public appearances, she had to wear clothes
that were comfortable, as well as beautiful.
She also had to remember how her enemy, the
wind, could blow those clothes about!
Diana began to buy from famous British clothes-makers,
which helped the clothes business in Britain.
Some of her favourites were Bruce Oldfield,
Zandra Rhodes, and Catherine Walker.
Sometimes she chose bravely - a low-cut, short
black dress, for example.
But she could also look like the perfect 'English
rose' in a pink, well-cut suit, or a long
white dance dress.
With her long legs, fair hair and wonderful
smile, she could look good in almost anything.
Then Diana became a mother too.
Before the baby was born, she felt sick a
lot of the time.
But she was healthy, and on 21 June 1982,
she went into St Mary's Hospital, London to
have her baby.
Charles stayed with her there, and the Queen's
private doctor looked after her.
At 9.03 p.m., the new prince was born.
Crowds were waiting outside.
'Nice one, Charlie!'
they shouted when they heard the news.
'He's got fair hair,' the proud father told
them.
At first the new parents couldn't agree on
names.
Charles wanted to call the baby Arthur, but
Diana preferred William.
On 3 August, in the Music Room at Buckingham
Palace, they gave their son the names William
Arthur Philip Louis.
Diana's first big public visit was to Australia,
New Zealand and Canada early in 1983.
Usually, royal babies and small children stayed
at home when their parents went to other countries.
When Prince Charles was only a little boy,
for example, his mother Queen Elizabeth went
away for several months.
And when they finally met again, she only
shook his hand.
Diana was a different kind of mother.
She wanted to keep her children with her,
and to give them plenty of love.
She wasn't afraid to hug and kiss them in
public.
So Charles and Diana took baby William with
them.
Great crowds came out to see the Prince and
Princess of Wales, and Diana quickly became
popular in those countries too.
She was always ready to do what people liked
best - on her first visit to Wales, she spoke
in Welsh.
Then, in New Zealand, she met a Maori woman,
and touched noses to say 'Hello', in the local
way.
Soon another baby was coming, and on 15 September
1984 Prince Harry was born.
When the family was in London, they lived
in a large flat at Kensington Palace.
It had four sitting- rooms, a dining-room,
and four bedrooms.
Diana chose all the colours and the furniture,
and tried to make it a real family home.
Here she looked after her boys.
She often played with them, and helped them
with their early lessons.
But it was important that they met other children
too.
Charles wanted William and Harry to study
at home with a private teacher, but Diana
didn't agree.
So in September 1985, William went to his
first school.
In 1987, he went on to Wetherby School.
On his first day, she took him there just
like any other mother, and together they met
his new teacher.
Diana was now a busy princess, wife and mother.
But she was beginning to work with charities
now too, which quickly became one of the most
important things in her life.
In 1982, the newspapers reported that Diana
was now working with five charities.
By the time that she was 24, she was working
with eighteen.
She began to visit people in hospital.
She wasn't afraid to meet people who were
dying.
And she began to meet people with terrible
illnesses like AIDS.
A lot of people were frightened that you could
catch AIDS by touching someone; Diana held
the hand of a man with AIDS to show that this
wasn't true.
The photographs of this helped people with
AIDS a lot.
She worked hard, but she still wanted to have
a good time too.
She practised a special dance secretly with
the famous dancer, Wayne Sleep.
Then, one night at the theatre, she suddenly
went up to the front to dance with Wayne.
She wanted to surprise Prince Charles!
The newspapers were full of it the next day.
Only Prince Charles was not so pleased.
In private, he told her that it was not the
right thing for a princess to do.
Diana now had a new friend in the Royal Family.
This was Sarah Ferguson, or 'Fergie', who
married Prince Andrew, Charles's younger brother,
in 1986.
She was a girl with a warm heart, but she
wasn't always sensible.
One night, just before they got married, Prince
Andrew was having a 'men only' party.
'Fergie' and Diana dressed up as policewomen
to try and get in!
Again, the Royal Family were not pleased with
Diana.
She was becoming too wild...
Few people knew that at this time Diana was
not happy.
She seemed to have the perfect life.
But inside she was in trouble.
She was helping other people, but she needed
help herself.
She was popular, a great favourite of the
people, and reporters photographed her everywhere.
But in private, she was alone with her troubles.
CHAPTER FOUR
The Woman Inside
In November 1982, the Palace told the world
that Diana was 'in the best of health'.
She did not have an eating illness, as some
of the newspapers were saying.
Diana began to look too thin even before she
got married.
People thought that she was just tired, or
growing up.
But in fact, Diana was getting ill.
She ate too much, then made herself sick.
She ate large meals out of the refrigerator
late at night.
She ate cakes and chocolate, and was sometimes
sick several times a day.
At first she looked thin because she kept
no food down inside her.
But in the end, she learnt to hide her illness
so that she looked fine.
In January 1982, Diana fell down some stairs
when her first baby was on the way.
It wasn't in the newspapers until a few weeks
later.
It was an accident, the Palace said.
It was only a few stairs.
The doctor visited her and she was fine now.
There was nothing to worry about.
But Diana tried to kill herself that day.
Life was too much for her.
She felt sick all the time before William
was born, and her new 'job' in the Royal Family
was very difficult.
Most of all, she felt that her husband wasn't
really interested in her.
On that day, he wanted to go out horse-riding,
and he wouldn't stay to talk to her.
After William was born, she felt very unhappy.
This happens to many women, of course, for
a short time after they have babies.
But Diana got worse, not better.
She sometimes cut herself with a knife, and
tried several more times to kill herself.
She was probably crying out for help.
Outside, she was still the perfect Princess
of Wales, but inside, she was hurting.
Before Prince Harry was born, the hospital
told Diana that the baby was a boy.
She didn't tell Charles.
He really wanted a girl.
When he first saw their new son, he told her
this.
Suddenly Diana felt that this was the end
of their marriage.
'Something inside me died,' she told her friends
later.
She married for love, but perhaps Charles
didn't.
Did his family push him into the marriage?
His real love, Camilla Parker- Bowles, was
already married, and he had to marry someone.
Perhaps he chose Diana only because she would
be the right sort of royal wife and mother.
Charles was still seeing Camilla when he was
married to Diana.
On their wedding holiday, Diana saw that Charles
still kept photos of Camilla in his pocket.
And during the marriage, Charles still gave
Camilla presents, and often telephoned her
privately.
The mother of Camilla's grandmother also had
a royal lover, King Edward VII.
Camilla, it seemed, was repeating the family
story.
But Charles and Camilla were friends, as well
as lovers.
They were the same age, and they were interested
in the same filings, like horses and the country.
Many women did not find Charles an easy man,
but Camilla seemed to understand him well.
Earlier, a lot of his girlfriends got tired
of him.
He could be warm one day, and cold the next.
He spent time with them, then disappeared
for a long time.
Even Camilla stopped waiting for him when
she was young.
She married another man, Andrew Parker-Bowles.
Charles and Diana were different ages, and
they liked different things.
He wanted to read books on their wedding holiday;
Diana wanted to enjoy the sun and the sea.
He wanted to talk about serious ideas, when
she wanted to give everything to their new
love.
It was soon clear to them both that they thought
and felt very differently.
In public, they were still husband and wife,
but in private they were sleeping in separate
bedrooms.
People were beginning to see that all was
not well.
In Canada in 1986, Diana fell down in public
because she was so ill and unhappy.
The same year, Prince Charles came home early
from their holiday in Majorca.
Then, in 1987, he went up to Balmoral alone
for a month.
He told the reporters that he had a lot of
work to do there.
Diana was working hard for the Royal Family
and the country, but she was still very unsure
of herself.
She was always waiting for Charles and the
Royal Family to say 'Well done!'
They never did.
But in 1988, life began to change for her.
She found that she could be strong.
A terrible accident happened when she and
Charles were on holiday in Switzerland with
a group of friends.
Snow came down from the mountains and killed
Hugh Lindsay, one of their best friends.
Diana was in bed with a cold at the time.
One of Charles's secretaries arrived back
at the house with the terrible news.
Diana decided what she needed to do.
She put all Lindsay's clothes into his suitcase.
She and Charles flew back to England with
the body.
Then Diana looked after Hugh Lindsay's wife,
Sarah.
The Lindsays only got married a few months
before the holiday, and Sarah was having a
baby.
And then Diana decided that it was time to
help herself, too.
Carolyn, her old schoolfriend, said, 'I'll
give you an hour.
If you don't go to a doctor, I'll tell the
world about your illness!'
Diana went to see a special doctor for help
with her eating illness.
'How many times have you tried to kill yourself?'
he asked her at once.
'Four or five times,' she said.
She was very surprised that he seemed to know
all about her so quickly.
In six months' time, he told her, she could
be a new person.
He visited her every week, and she began to
read books about the illness and to understand
herself better.
In six months, she was a new person, and she
was almost better.
It was the beginning of a new way of life
for her.
She had to help herself; Charles wouldn't
help her.
He didn't love her as she wanted.
And he never would.
She also learnt to give her love to the poor
and ill people that she met through her charity
work.
She had a special touch.
When she visited people in hospital, a hug
or a kiss from Diana seemed to help them greatly.
Sometimes she continued to visit people for
a long time until they were better.
She often wrote them kind letters later.
A lot of her charity work was with children,
and she was always happy and natural with
them.
At home, it was the beginning of the war between
Diana and the Royal Family.
It was difficult for people who worked for
Charles and Diana.
They had to decide which side they were on.
You had to be a 'Charles person' or a 'Diana
person'.
If you tried to be both, you quickly got into
trouble.
Diana began to think of 'Charles's people'
as 'the enemy.'
They now lived two separate lives in the family
too.
There was Diana's life, and Charles's life.
This was true even for the boys.
When Diana took them out, they went to modern
places that children like - water game parks
or the cinema.
They usually wore ordinary clothes like jeans
and T-shirts.
With Charles, they wore more grown-up clothes,
and did country things that he enjoyed, like
fishing.
The public began to think worse of Charles
when Prince William had a serious accident
at school in 1991.
Diana stayed at the hospital with him all
night but Charles went off to the theatre.
'How could he do that?'
people asked.
'What sort of a father is he?'
Charles loved his sons too, but perhaps he
didn't understand how to show it.
He did try to do better after that, but many
people were beginning to prefer Diana.
But not everyone.
'She's ill,' some people were saying.
'She needs to be in hospital.'
Or: 'She's trying to hurt the Royal Family.
They must stop her!'
Diana was beginning to make a new life for
herself.
It was difficult, and she was often unhappy,
but it was the only way out.
CHAPTER FIVE
The New Diana
The Queen called 1992 a 'terrible year'.
It began badly for Diana, too.
On 29 March, her much-loved father died.
She was on holiday in Austria, and she flew
home at once for the funeral.
Prince Charles flew back with her to England,
but she went to the funeral alone.
The newspapers, of course, were quick to notice
this.
It was a month for royal stories.
The Palace told the world that the marriage
of Prince Andrew and Sarah Ferguson was over.
Then a new book came out about Princess Diana:
Diana - Her True Story by Andrew Morton.
The book talked about Diana's eating illness,
and about how unhappy she was with Prince
Charles and the Royal Family.
It also talked about Prince Charles and Camilla
Parker-Bowles.
At first, everyone was very surprised.
Could it all be true?
In the end, people realised that most of it
was Diana's real story.
But there was another surprise coming for
her - and an unpleasant one.
Diana was beginning, secretly, to look for
a new love in her life.
She had to be very careful, because she and
Charles were still married.
The world would not think well of a royal
mother with other lovers.
Then suddenly, recordings of secret phone
calls between Diana and James Gilbey came
out.
Gilbey was an old friend of Diana's, but here
they were talking as lovers.
Someone recorded the conversations, the newspapers
said, two years earlier.
In them, Gilbey uses a special name for Diana
- 'Squidgy'.
He asks Diana to kiss him down the phone,
and says, 'Oh Squidgy, I love you, love you,
love you!'
Another lover was James Hewitt, the man who
taught Diana to ride again - she was still
afraid of horses after her accident as a child.
Will Carling, the sportsman, and his wife
ended their marriage because of Diana.
Then there was Oliver Hoare, who sold paintings.
Someone began to make silent phone calls to
his home; perhaps it was Diana, unhappy because
Oliver didn't want to talk to her.
We will probably never know everything about
her life at this time, but it's clear that
she was seeing other men.
Then in 1993 recordings of phone, conversations
between Charles and Camilla appeared, and
everyone now knew for sure that they were
lovers.
Charles was very unhappy about this, and at
first promised to live alone without women.
A year later, he talked about it all on television.
But he didn't stop seeing Camilla.
In the photos of 1992, Diana is often alone.
In one, she is sitting in front of the Taj
Mahal in India.
She is smiling, but she looks very small and
alone in front of the big white building.
In November 1992, Charles and Diana did make
a visit together to Korea, but they were clearly
unhappy.
Finally, in December they told the public
that they were separating.
Prince Charles would stay at Highgrove, and
Diana would live alone at Kensington Palace.
The children would spend time with both of
their parents.
The Queen's family was in trouble all around
her.
Just to finish the terrible story of 1992,
there was a serious fire at Windsor Castle,
the Queen's favourite home.
Everyone there, the Queen too, worked hard
to put it out.
But the Castle and the Royal Family would
never be the same again.
Diana's private rooms at Kensington Palace
were full of photos of William and Harry.
'They mean everything to me,' she said.
But now she couldn't be with them so much.
A lot of the time, they were at school or
with their father.
She even had to eat her Christmas dinner alone
while William and Harry spent Christmas day
with their father and grandmother.
But she was doing her best to help her sons
for their future as royal princes, and William
perhaps as the future King of England.
She decided that they needed to understand
some of the country's problems.
She took them to visit sick people in hospitals.
But she also took them out secretly to see
some of the dark and unpleasant places where
homeless people spend the night.
In 1995, William went to Eton, one of the
top schools in the country, but he didn't
forget the other side of life that Diana showed
him.
He later gave Diana the idea of selling a
lot of her dresses for charity.
Diana's new life had good times in it, too.
She had plenty of friends.
Many of them were famous, and some of them
were filmstars or popstars.
She was friendly with the popstars Elton John
and George Michael, and with Terence Stamp
and Richard Attenborough, the filmstars.
She knew Luciano Pavarotti, the Italian singer,
and others from the music and film world,
like Michael Jackson, Paul and Linda McCartney,
and Liza Minelli.
She often had lunch with friends.
An Italian restaurant, San Lorenzo in Kensington
was her favourite for a long time.
She still loved dancing and pop music, and
she went swimming or running every day to
keep in good shape.
Diana was very serious about her health now.
But she couldn't escape from the paparazzi.
Everywhere she went, they tried to take photographs
of her.
Sometimes they took photos secretly - you
could get a lot of money for a new photo of
Diana.
Suddenly, it was all too much for her.
In December 1993, she told the world that
she wanted to live quietly.
She would stop most of her work for charities.
She needed time for her children, and for
her private life.
It was not for long.
She soon came back because she wanted to get
on with her work, and be 'a mother to the
world', as one newspaper wrote.
And the story of Diana and Charles was not
over yet; in November 1995 she recorded her
famous appearance on television.
She talked openly to reporter Martin Bashir
about her life in the Royal Family, and she
was clearly hurt and angry about the past.
'There were three in this marriage,' she said
about Charles and Camilla.
And three, as she told us, is a crowd.
But she also talked about her future.
'I don't think many people will want me to
be Queen... because I do things differently,
because I don't go by a rule book.'
She worked, she said, 'from the heart, not
the head'.
But she wanted 'to be Queen of people's hearts'.
These were words which the world never forgot.
A lot of people that she helped will never
forget her either.
One of her favourite charities was Centrepoint,
which looks after homeless people.
Vincent Seabrook, a man of 27 now working
as a private guard, remembers her well.
He was living homeless on the streets when
Diana came past and stopped to talk to him.
'She got me something to eat and drink, listened
to me, and gave me the number for Centrepoint,'
he said.
She wasn't frightened of illness, or of people
who had serious problems with their bodies.
She was ready with a hug or a kiss for everyone.
A man who couldn't see wanted to know what
Diana was like.
'Is it all right if I touch your face?' he
asked.
'Of course you can,' she said.
He moved his hands over her eyes, nose and
mouth until he could see a picture of her
in his head.
'You're very pretty!' he said.
When someone was in trouble, she tried to
help them.
Once in hospital, she heard a woman crying.
The woman's son, Dean, was badly hurt in a
car accident.
Diana sat with the young man that night, and
visited him again later.
She even went to his house when he was better,
and met his children.
'What shall we call you?'
they all asked.
'Just Diana,' she said.
She often visited children's hospitals like
Great Ormond Street Hospital for Sick Children.
Victoria Hemphill, a young girl with a serious
heart problem, felt that the Princess was
her special friend, and kept photos of Diana
by her bed.
Diana often talked to her about William and
Harry, and the boys wrote to her.
'Dearest Victoria, I wanted to send you lots
of love while you were in hospital,' began
a letter from Prince Harry.
Diana had time for her friends who were in
trouble, too.
She helped a friend called Rosa when her baby
died, and gave time to another friend, Cosima,
when her marriage ended.
She knew what it was like to feel hurt inside.
She still travelled to other countries.
In 1994 she visited Zimbabwe, in Africa.
Photos show that she helped to give out lunch
to children in a special school.
She visited hospitals in Pakistan.
In India, she became friends with Mother Teresa,
who was famous for her work with poor people
who were dying on the streets.
Diana once said, 'I'm not frightened of dying,
if I can die happy.'
CHAPTER SIX
Her Last Days
After Diana's marriage finally ended in August
1996, she was a rich woman with over 17 million
pounds.
But she wanted to go on working.
She specially wanted to stop the use of landmines.
She visited Angola and Bosnia, where there
are still terrible problems with landmines
after the wars there.
She met people who lost legs or arms from
these landmines - not only men, but little
children too.
When she spoke out against the landmines,
not everyone agreed with her.
But Diana was still ready to speak from the
heart.
She had a good summer in 1997.
She visited her brother, Charles, in South
Africa.
She spent her birthday there, and enjoyed
a holiday with Charles and his family without
any of the usual trouble from the paparazzi.
There was only one sad time in the middle
of July, when she went to Italy for the funeral
of her friend Gianni Versace, the famous clothes-maker.
Something very special was happening in Diana's
life that summer too.
She had a new boyfriend.
This was Dodi Al Fayed, a film-maker, who
was 42.
The Al Fayeds are a Moslem family from Egypt,
but they live in England.
They are very rich; the famous London shop,
Harrods, and the Ritz Hotel in Paris belong
to Mohammed Al Fayed, Dodi's father.
The Al Fayed family and the Spencer family
were already friends.
Diana first met Dodi about ten years earlier,
but they didn't become good friends until
she went on holiday to France with the Al
Fayed family in July 1997.
Harry and William went too, and they all had
a wonderful time.
It was the best holiday for years, Diana said
later.
And soon Diana and Dodi became more than friends;
they fell in love.
They went away on holiday again at the end
of that month, but they were alone together
this time.
They visited Corsica and Sardinia in the Al
Fayeds' private boat.
The paparazzi soon knew that they were lovers.
And then, of course, they all wanted to get
pictures and stories of Diana and Dodi.
The man who took the first photos of their
kisses sold the pictures for a million dollars.
On 21 August, Diana flew back to France again
to start a third holiday with Dodi.
By now, they were deeply in love.
He gave her presents, and it's possible that
they planned to get married.
Dodi was married before, and had a lot of
girlfriends after that.
But he was very serious about Diana.
This third holiday ended suddenly because
of the paparazzi.
When their boat arrived at Sardinia, the photographers
ran after Dodi and Diana everywhere.
They even found them at a hotel where they
were staying secretly.
That was enough - the lovers decided to leave
at once for Paris.
They arrived on Saturday, 30 August.
Dodi had a small home in Paris, which they
tried to use secretly.
During the afternoon, Dodi went out to get
a very expensive ring which he was buying
as a present for Diana.
It was a ring that she would never wear.
The paparazzi knew Diana and Dodi were now
in Paris and were following them again.
They planned to eat dinner at a restaurant
in the city centre, but decided that it wasn't
safe there.
They went on to the Ritz, the hotel which
belongs to Dodi's father.
When they arrived at the Ritz, there were
already about 40 paparazzi waiting for them.
At last, just after midnight, they left the
hotel by the back door to go back to Dodi's
house.
They were trying to escape, and sent off another
car from the front.
But some of the paparazzi saw Diana and Dodi
as they drove off in their special Mercedes
car with their driver and bodyguard.
'You won't catch me!' said the driver, Henri
Paul, as he drove faster and faster; so did
the paparazzi, some in cars, and several on
very fast bikes.
There were cameras and lights everywhere,
as they tried to photograph Diana's car.
When the road came to the River Seine, it
went underground.
The car was now travelling very fast - perhaps
at over 160 km an hour.
It hit a wall.
The crash killed Dodi and the driver at once.
The bodyguard, Trevor Rees-Jones, was still
alive.
So was Diana - but she was very badly hurt.
It took more than an hour before they could
get her out of the crashed car.
They took her to hospital, where doctors tried
to save her life.
But it was no good.
She died at about four o'clock in the morning.
Soon telephones were ringing in Britain as
people heard the news and phoned to tell their
friends and families.
Some heard it on the television or radio at
the end of a long night's work, and it seemed
that it couldn't possibly be true.
At Balmoral, Prince Charles woke his sons
William and Harry to tell them the terrible
news.
That afternoon, Charles left Scotland by plane
with Diana's two sisters Sarah and Jane.
They flew to Paris together to bring her body
home.
During the week, newspapers, television and
radio were full of Diana's sad story.
People cried and left bunches of flowers for
her.
By the middle of the first day, there were
over a thousand bunches outside Kensington
Palace.
By the end of the week, it was like a sea
of flowers there.
With the flowers there were cards and letters:
'To our sweet Princess - Thank you for the
love you showed us all.'
'Queen of Hearts' and 'Princess of Love' were
words that came up again and again.
'We'll never forget you,' the letters said.
And during that week, the mystery about the
car crash was growing.
When Trevor Rees-Jones, the bodyguard, finally
woke up in hospital, he couldn't remember
the accident.
We now know that the driver, Henri Paul, had
too much to drink that evening - far too much.
But the paparazzi were driving too fast and
too near, and the photographers' lights were
too bright.
Did they make it happen, too?
And was there a second car in the crash?
Some people even thought that it was murder.
This was probably just a wild story, but there
was still a mystery about the crash.
Diana's funeral was on Saturday, 6 September
1997, one week after she died.
On Friday night, thousands of people went
to London.
They stayed out all night, waiting for the
morning, when her body would travel from Kensington
Palace to Westminster Abbey.
Kensington Palace Gardens were beautiful.
It was a warm night, and there were flowers
by every tree.
People of all ages sat quietly together in
little groups, remembering Diana.
Her funeral, like her wedding, brought famous
people together from all over the world.
Some were heads of governments, and others
were her friends.
Many were famous names from the worlds of
film and music.
All the Royal Family was there.
Princes Charles, William and Harry walked
behind Diana's body as it went into the church.
Her sons gave her white flowers with a card
that just said, 'Mummy'.
In Hyde Park, crowds of thousands watched
the funeral on a big screen.
Many cried as they listened to the words,
and heard some of Diana's favourite music.
Earlier that summer, Diana looked after her
friend Elton John at Gianni Versace's funeral.
Now he sang at her funeral.
It was a song that he once wrote about the
film star, Marilyn Monroe.
Marilyn and Diana were both 36 when they died.
Elton changed the words for Diana.
'Goodbye England's rose,' he sang.
She would always 'grow in our hearts'.
Then her brother, Charles, spoke about Diana.
He remembered how kind and beautiful she was.
'Today is our chance to say thank you...
We want you to know that life without you
is very, very difficult.'
He was very angry with the paparazzi who gave
her such a hard time.
And he promised to try and help her sons in
their future life.
The funeral car took Diana's body to the Spencer
family home at Althorp, in Northamptonshire.
People threw flowers in front of the car as
it went past.
At first, her family planned to bring her
to the local church at Althorp, but then they
decided against this.
Thousands of visitors could make life too
difficult for the small village.
So, finally, they took Diana to a small island
in a lake in the gardens of Althorp Park.
Here her body lies in private, but once every
year, visitors can come to see the place where
she rests.
Diana's life is over, but her story is not.
The way that she lived and died will change
many things.
Her life showed a new road for the Royal Family
to take.
She showed them a way to be nearer to the
British people and to help with real problems
in the modern world.
When she died, we all remembered that life
can be very short.
Every one of us has to do our best with the
time that we have.
'It's important to show love,' said Diana.
We need to remember this too.