THE VIRGINIAN
by Owen WISTER
CHAPTER I
Enter the Man
Some notable sight was drawing the passengers, both men and women, to
the window; and therefore I rose and crossed the car to see what it was.
I saw near the track an enclosure, and round it some laughing men, and inside it
some whirling dust, and amid the dust some horses, plunging, huddling, and dodging.
They were cow ponies in a corral, and one of them would not be
caught, no matter who threw the rope.
We had plenty of time to watch this sport, for our train had stopped that the engine might
take water at the tank before it pulled us up beside the station platform of Medicine Bow.
We were also six hours late, and starving for entertainment.
The pony in the corral was wise, and rapid of limb.
Have you seen a skilful boxer watch his antagonist with a quiet,
incessant eye?
Such an eye as this did the pony keep upon whatever man took
the rope.
The man might pretend to look at the weather, which was fine; or he
might affect earnest conversation with a bystander: it was bootless.
The pony saw through it.
No feint hoodwinked him.
This animal was thoroughly a man of the world.
His undistracted eye stayed fixed upon the dissembling foe, and the
gravity of his horse-expression made the matter one of high comedy.
Then the rope would sail out at him, but he was already elsewhere;
and if horses laugh, gaiety must have abounded in that corral.
Sometimes the pony took a turn alone; next he had slid in a flash among his brothers, and the whole of them like a
school of playful fish whipped round the corral, kicking up the fine dust, and (I take it) roaring with laughter.
Through the window-glass of our Pullman the thud of their mischievous
hoofs reached us, and the strong, humorous curses of the cowboys.
Then for the first time I noticed a man who sat on the high gate
of the corral, looking on.
For he now climbed down with the undulations of a tiger, smooth
and easy, as if his muscles flowed beneath his skin.
The others had all visibly whirled the rope, some of them even
shoulder high.
I did not see his arm lift or move.
He appeared to hold the rope down low, by his leg.
But like a sudden snake I saw the noose go out its length and
fall true; and the thing was done.
As the captured pony walked in with a sweet, church-door expression, our train moved
slowly on to the station, and a passenger remarked, “That man knows his business.”
But the passenger’s dissertation upon roping I was obliged to
lose, for Medicine Bow was my station.
I bade my fellow-travellers goodbye, and descended, a stranger,
into the great cattle land.
And here in less than ten minutes I learned news which made me
feel a stranger indeed.
My baggage was lost; it had not come on my train; it was adrift
somewhere back in the two thousand miles that lay behind me.
And by way of comfort, the baggage-man remarked that passengers often got
astray from their trunks, but the trunks mostly found them after a while.
Having offered me this encouragement, he turned whistling to his
affairs and left me planted in the baggage-room at Medicine Bow.
I stood deserted among crates and boxes, blankly holding my check,
hungry and forlorn.
I stared out through the door at the sky and the plains; but I did not see the
antelope shining among the sagebrush, nor the great sunset light of Wyoming.
Annoyance blinded my eyes to all things save my grievance: I
saw only a lost trunk.
And I was muttering half-aloud, “What a forsaken hole this is!”
when suddenly from outside on the platform came a slow voice:⁠—
“Off to get married again? Oh, don’t!”
The voice was Southern and gentle and drawling; and a second
voice came in immediate answer, cracked and querulous:⁠—
“It ain’t again. Who says it’s again? Who told you, anyway?”
And the first voice responded caressingly:⁠—
“Why, your Sunday clothes told me, Uncle Hughey. They are speakin’
mighty loud o’ nuptials.”
“You don’t worry me!” snapped Uncle Hughey, with shrill heat.
And the other gently continued, “Ain’t them gloves the same yu’
wore to your last weddin’?”
“You don’t worry me! You don’t worry me!” now screamed Uncle
Hughey.
Already I had forgotten my trunk; care had left me; I was aware of
the sunset, and had no desire but for more of this conversation.
For it resembled none that I had heard in my life so far.
I stepped to the door and looked out upon the station platform.
Lounging there at ease against the wall was a slim young giant,
more beautiful than pictures.
His broad, soft hat was pushed back; a loose-knotted, dull-scarlet handkerchief sagged from
his throat; and one casual thumb was hooked in the cartridge-belt that slanted across his hips.
He had plainly come many miles from somewhere across the vast
horizon, as the dust upon him showed.
His boots were white with it.
His overalls were gray with it.
The weather-beaten bloom of his face shone through it duskily,
as the ripe peaches look upon their trees in a dry season.
But no dinginess of travel or shabbiness of attire could tarnish
the splendor that radiated from his youth and strength.
The old man upon whose temper his remarks were doing such deadly work was combed
and curried to a finish, a bridegroom swept and garnished; but alas for age!
Had I been the bride, I should have taken the giant, dust and
all.
He had by no means done with the old man.
“Why, yu’ve hung weddin’ gyarments on every limb!” he now drawled,
with admiration.
“Who is the lucky lady this trip?”
The old man seemed to vibrate.
“Tell you there ain’t been no other! Call me a Mormon, would
you?”
“Why, that⁠—”
“Call me a Mormon? Then name some of my wives. Name two. Name
one. Dare you!”
“⁠—that Laramie wido’ promised you⁠—”
“Shucks!”
“⁠—only her doctor suddenly ordered Southern climate and⁠—”
“Shucks! You’re a false alarm.”
“⁠—so nothing but her lungs came between you. And next you’d
most got united with Cattle Kate, only⁠—”
“Tell you you’re a false alarm!”
“⁠—only she got hung.”
“Where’s the wives in all this? Show the wives! Come now!”
“That corn-fed biscuit-shooter at Rawlins yu’ gave the canary⁠—”
“Never married her. Never did marry⁠—”
“But yu’ come so near, uncle!
She was the one left yu’ that letter explaining how she’d got married to a
young cyard-player the very day before her ceremony with you was due, and⁠—”
“Oh, you’re nothing; you’re a kid; you don’t amount to⁠—”
“⁠—and how she’d never, never forgot to feed the canary.”
“This country’s getting full of kids,” stated the old man, witheringly.
“It’s doomed.”
This crushing assertion plainly satisfied him.
And he blinked his eyes with renewed anticipation.
His tall tormentor continued with a face of unchanging gravity,
and a voice of gentle solicitude:⁠—
“How is the health of that unfortunate⁠—”
“That’s right! Pour your insults! Pour ’em on a sick, afflicted
woman!”
The eyes blinked with combative relish.
“Insults? Oh, no, Uncle Hughey!”
“That’s all right! Insults goes!”
“Why, I was mighty relieved when she began to recover her mem’ry.
Las’ time I heard, they told me she’d got it pretty near all
back.
Remembered her father, and her mother, and her sisters and brothers, and her
friends, and her happy childhood, and all her doin’s except only your face.
The boys was bettin’ she’d get that far too, give her time.
But I reckon afteh such a turrable sickness as she had, that
would be expectin’ most too much.”
At this Uncle Hughey jerked out a small parcel.
“Shows how much you know!” he cackled.
“There!
See that!
That’s my ring she sent me back, being too unstrung for marriage.
So she don’t remember me, don’t she?
Ha-ha!
Always said you were a false alarm.”
The Southerner put more anxiety into his tone.
“And so you’re a-takin’ the ring right on to the next one!” he
exclaimed.
“Oh, don’t go to get married again, Uncle Hughey! What’s the
use o’ being married?”
“What’s the use?” echoed the bridegroom, with scorn.
“Hm! When you grow up you’ll think different.”
“Course I expect to think different when my age is different.
I’m havin’ the thoughts proper to twenty-four, and you’re havin’
the thoughts proper to sixty.”
“Fifty!” shrieked Uncle Hughey, jumping in the air.
The Southerner took a tone of self-reproach.
“Now, how could I forget you was fifty,” he murmured, “when you have
been telling it to the boys so careful for the last ten years!”
Have you ever seen a cockatoo⁠—the white kind with the topknot⁠—enraged
by insult?
The bird erects every available feather upon its person.
So did Uncle Hughey seem to swell, clothes, mustache, and woolly white beard; and without further speech
he took himself on board the Eastbound train, which now arrived from its siding in time to deliver him.
Yet this was not why he had not gone away before.
At any time he could have escaped into the baggage-room or
withdrawn to a dignified distance until his train should come up.
But the old man had evidently got a sort of joy from this teasing.
He had reached that inevitable age when we are tickled to be
linked with affairs of gallantry, no matter how.
With him now the Eastbound departed slowly into that distance
whence I had come.
I stared after it as it went its way to the far shores of civilization.
It grew small in the unending gulf of space, until all sign of its
presence was gone save a faint skein of smoke against the evening sky.
And now my lost trunk came back into my thoughts, and Medicine
Bow seemed a lonely spot.
A sort of ship had left me marooned in a foreign ocean; the Pullman was
comfortably steaming home to port, while I⁠—how was I to find Judge Henry’s ranch?
Where in this unfeatured wilderness was Sunk Creek?
No creek or any water at all flowed here that I could perceive.
My host had written he should meet me at the station and drive
me to his ranch.
This was all that I knew.
He was not here.
The baggage-man had not seen him lately.
The ranch was almost certain to be too far to walk to, tonight.
My trunk⁠—I discovered myself still staring dolefully after the vanished Eastbound; and at the same instant I became aware that
the tall man was looking gravely at me⁠—as gravely as he had looked at Uncle Hughey throughout their remarkable conversation.
To see his eye thus fixing me and his thumb still hooked in his cartridge-belt, certain
tales of travellers from these parts forced themselves disquietingly into my recollection.
Now that Uncle Hughey was gone, was I to take his place and be, for instance,
invited to dance on the platform to the music of shots nicely aimed?
“I reckon I am looking for you, seh,” the tall man now observed.
CHAPTER II
“When You Call Me That,Smile!”
We cannot see ourselves as others see us, or I should know what
appearance I cut at hearing this from the tall man.
I said nothing, feeling uncertain.
“I reckon I am looking for you, seh,” he repeated politely.
“I am looking for Judge Henry,” I now replied.
He walked toward me, and I saw that in inches he was not a giant.
He was not more than six feet.
It was Uncle Hughey that had made him seem to tower.
But in his eye, in his face, in his step, in the whole man, there
dominated a something potent to be felt, I should think, by man or woman.
“The Judge sent me afteh you, seh,” he now explained, in his
civil Southern voice; and he handed me a letter from my host.
Had I not witnessed his facetious performances with Uncle Hughey,
I should have judged him wholly ungifted with such powers.
There was nothing external about him but what seemed the signs
of a nature as grave as you could meet.
But I had witnessed; and therefore supposing that I knew him in spite of his appearance, that I was,
so to speak, in his secret and could give him a sort of wink, I adopted at once a method of easiness.
It was so pleasant to be easy with a large stranger, who instead
of shooting at your heels had very civilly handed you a letter.
“You’re from old Virginia, I take it?” I began.
He answered slowly, “Then you have taken it correct, seh.”
A slight chill passed over my easiness, but I went cheerily on
with a further inquiry.
“Find many oddities out here like Uncle Hughey?”
“Yes, seh, there is a right smart of oddities around. They come
in on every train.”
At this point I dropped my method of easiness.
“I wish that trunks came on the train,” said I.
And I told him my predicament.
It was not to be expected that he would be greatly moved at my
loss; but he took it with no comment whatever.
“We’ll wait in town for it,” said he, always perfectly civil.
Now, what I had seen of “town” was, to my newly arrived eyes,
altogether horrible.
If I could possibly sleep at the Judge’s ranch, I preferred to
do so.
“Is it too far to drive there tonight?” I inquired.
He looked at me in a puzzled manner.
“For this valise,” I explained, “contains all that I immediately need; in fact,
I could do without my trunk for a day or two, if it is not convenient to send.
So if we could arrive there not too late by starting at once⁠—”
I paused.
“It’s two hundred and sixty-three miles,” said the Virginian.
To my loud ejaculation he made no answer, but surveyed me a
moment longer, and then said, “Supper will be about ready now.”
He took my valise, and I followed his steps toward the eating-house
in silence.
I was dazed.
As we went, I read my host’s letter⁠—a brief hospitable message.
He was very sorry not to meet me himself.
He had been getting ready to drive over, when the surveyor appeared
and detained him.
Therefore in his stead he was sending a trustworthy man to town,
who would look after me and drive me over.
They were looking forward to my visit with much pleasure.
This was all.
Yes, I was dazed.
How did they count distance in this country?
You spoke in a neighborly fashion about driving over to town,
and it meant⁠—I did not know yet how many days.
And what would be meant by the term “dropping in,” I wondered.
And how many miles would be considered really far?
I abstained from further questioning the “trustworthy man.”
My questions had not fared excessively well.
He did not propose making me dance, to be sure: that would scarcely
be trustworthy.
But neither did he propose to have me familiar with him.
Why was this?
What had I done to elicit that veiled and skilful sarcasm about
oddities coming in on every train?
Having been sent to look after me, he would do so, would even
carry my valise; but I could not be jocular with him.
This handsome, ungrammatical son of the soil had set between
us the bar of his cold and perfect civility.
No polished person could have done it better.
What was the matter?
I looked at him, and suddenly it came to me.
If he had tried familiarity with me the first two minutes of our acquaintance,
I should have resented it; by what right, then, had I tried it with him?
It smacked of patronizing: on this occasion he had come off the
better gentleman of the two.
Here in flesh and blood was a truth which I had long believed
in words, but never met before.
The creature we call a gentleman lies deep in the hearts of thousands
that are born without chance to master the outward graces of the type.
Between the station and the eating-house I did a deal of straight
thinking.
But my thoughts were destined presently to be drowned in amazement
at the rare personage into whose society fate had thrown me.
Town, as they called it, pleased me the less, the longer I saw
it.
But until our language stretches itself and takes in a new word of closer
fit, town will have to do for the name of such a place as was Medicine Bow.
I have seen and slept in many like it since.
Scattered wide, they littered the frontier from the Columbia
to the Rio Grande, from the Missouri to the Sierras.
They lay stark, dotted over a planet of treeless dust, like soiled
packs of cards.
Each was similar to the next, as one old five-spot of clubs resembles
another.
Houses, empty bottles, and garbage, they were forever of the
same shapeless pattern.
More forlorn they were than stale bones.
They seemed to have been strewn there by the wind and to be waiting
till the wind should come again and blow them away.
Yet serene above their foulness swam a pure and quiet light, such as the East
never sees; they might be bathing in the air of creation’s first morning.
Beneath sun and stars their days and nights were immaculate and
wonderful.
Medicine Bow was my first, and I took its dimensions, twenty-nine buildings in all⁠—one coal shute, one water tank, the station, one store,
two eating-houses, one billiard hall, two tool-houses, one feed stable, and twelve others that for one reason and another I shall not name.
Yet this wretched husk of squalor spent thought upon appearances; many
houses in it wore a false front to seem as if they were two stories high.
There they stood, rearing their pitiful masquerade amid a fringe of old tin cans, while at their very doors began
a world of crystal light, a land without end, a space across which Noah and Adam might come straight from Genesis.
Into that space went wandering a road, over a hill and down out of sight, and up again
smaller in the distance, and down once more, and up once more, straining the eyes, and so away
.
Then I heard a fellow greet my Virginian.
He came rollicking out of a door, and made a pass with his hand
at the Virginian’s hat
.
The Southerner dodged it, and I saw once more the tiger undulation
of body, and knew my escort was he of the rope and the corral.
“How are yu’ Steve?” he said to the rollicking man.
And in his tone I heard instantly old friendship speaking.
With Steve he would take and give familiarity.
Steve looked at me, and looked away⁠—and that was all.
But it was enough.
In no company had I ever felt so much an outsider.
Yet I liked the company, and wished that it would like me.
“Just come to town?” inquired Steve of the Virginian.
“Been here since noon. Been waiting for the train.”
“Going out tonight?”
“I reckon I’ll pull out tomorro’.”
“Beds are all took,” said Steve.
This was for my benefit.
“Dear me,” said I.
“But I guess one of them drummers will let yu’ double up with
him.”
Steve was enjoying himself, I think.
He had his saddle and blankets, and beds were nothing to him.
“Drummers, are they?” asked the Virginian.
“Two Jews handling cigars, one American with consumption killer,
and a Dutchman with jew’lry.”
The Virginian set down my valise, and seemed to meditate.
“I did want a bed tonight,” he murmured gently.
“Well,” Steve suggested, “the American looks like he washed the
oftenest.”
“That’s of no consequence to me,” observed the Southerner.
“Guess it’ll be when yu’ see ’em.”
“Oh, I’m meaning something different. I wanted a bed to myself.”
“Then you’ll have to build one.”
“Bet yu’ I have the Dutchman’s.”
“Take a man that won’t scare. Bet yu’ drinks yu’ can’t have the
American’s.”
“Go yu’ ” said the Virginian.
“I’ll have his bed without any fuss. Drinks for the crowd.”
“I suppose you have me beat,” said Steve, grinning at him affectionately.
“You’re such a son-of-a ⸻ when you get down to work. Well, so
long! I got to fix my horse’s hoofs.”
I had expected that the man would be struck down.
He had used to the Virginian a term of heaviest insult, I thought.
I had marvelled to hear it come so unheralded from Steve’s friendly
lips.
And now I marvelled still more.
Evidently he had meant no harm by it, and evidently no offence
had been taken.
Used thus, this language was plainly complimentary.
I had stepped into a world new to me indeed, and novelties were
occurring with scarce any time to get breath between them.
As to where I should sleep, I had forgotten that problem altogether
in my curiosity.
What was the Virginian going to do now?
I began to know that the quiet of this man was volcanic.
“Will you wash first, sir?”
We were at the door of the eating-house, and he set my valise
inside.
In my tenderfoot innocence I was looking indoors for the washing
arrangements.
“It’s out hyeh, seh,” he informed me gravely, but with strong
Southern accent.
Internal mirth seemed often to heighten the local flavor of his
speech.
There were other times when it had scarce any special accent
or fault in grammar.
A trough was to my right, slippery with soapy water; and hanging from
a roller above one end of it was a rag of discouraging appearance.
The Virginian caught it, and it performed one whirling revolution
on its roller.
Not a dry or clean inch could be found on it.
He took off his hat, and put his head in the door.
“Your towel, ma’am,” said he, “has been too popular.”
She came out, a pretty woman.
Her eyes rested upon him for a moment, then upon me with disfavor;
then they returned to his black hair.
“The allowance is one a day,” said she, very quietly.
“But when folks are particular⁠—” She completed her sentence
by removing the old towel and giving a clean one to us.
“Thank you, ma’am,” said the cowpuncher.
She looked once more at his black hair, and without any word
returned to her guests at supper.
A pail stood in the trough, almost empty; and this he filled
for me from a well.
There was some soap sliding at large in the trough, but I got
my own.
And then in a tin basin I removed as many of the stains of travel
as I was able.
It was not much of a toilet that I made in this first wash-trough of
my experience, but it had to suffice, and I took my seat at supper.
Canned stuff it was⁠—corned beef.
And one of my table companions said the truth about it.
“When I slung my teeth over that,” he remarked, “I thought I
was chewing a hammock.”
We had strange coffee, and condensed milk; and I have never seen
more flies.
I made no attempt to talk, for no one in this country seemed
favorable to me.
By reason of something⁠—my clothes, my hat, my pronunciation, whatever
it might be, I possessed the secret of estranging people at sight.
Yet I was doing better than I knew; my strict silence and attention to the corned beef made me
in the eyes of the cowboys at table compare well with the over-talkative commercial travellers.
The Virginian’s entrance produced a slight silence.
He had done wonders with the wash-trough, and he had somehow
brushed his clothes.
With all the roughness of his dress, he was now the neatest of
us.
He nodded to some of the other cowboys, and began his meal in
quiet.
But silence is not the native element of the drummer.
An average fish can go a longer time out of water than this breed
can live without talking.
One of them now looked across the table at the grave, flannel-shirted Virginian;
he inspected, and came to the imprudent conclusion that he understood his man.
“Good evening,” he said briskly.
“Good evening,” said the Virginian.
“Just come to town?” pursued the drummer.
“Just come to town,” the Virginian suavely assented.
“Cattle business jumping along?” inquired the drummer.
“Oh, fair.”
And the Virginian took some more corned beef.
“Gets a move on your appetite, anyway,” suggested the drummer.
The Virginian drank some coffee.
Presently the pretty woman refilled his cup without his asking
her.
“Guess I’ve met you before,” the drummer stated next.
The Virginian glanced at him for a brief moment.
“Haven’t I, now?
Ain’t I seen you somewhere?
Look at me.
You been in Chicago, ain’t you?
You look at me well.
Remember Ikey’s, don’t you?”
“I don’t reckon I do.”
“See, now!
I knowed you’d been in Chicago.
Four or five years ago.
Or maybe it’s two years.
Time’s nothing to me.
But I never forget a face.
Yes, sir.
Him and me’s met at Ikey’s, all right.”
This important point the drummer stated to all of us.
We were called to witness how well he had proved old acquaintanceship.
“Ain’t the world small, though!” he exclaimed complacently.
“Meet a man once and you’re sure to run on to him again. That’s
straight. That’s no barroom josh.”
And the drummer’s eye included us all in his confidence.
I wondered if he had attained that high perfection when a man
believes his own lies.
The Virginian did not seem interested.
He placidly attended to his food, while our landlady moved between
dining room and kitchen, and the drummer expanded.
“Yes, sir!
Ikey’s over by the stockyards, patronized by all cattlemen that
know what’s what.
That’s where.
Maybe it’s three years.
Time never was nothing to me.
But faces!
Why, I can’t quit ’em.
Adults or children, male and female; onced I seen ’em I couldn’t lose
one off my memory, not if you were to pay me bounty, five dollars a face.
White men, that is.
Can’t do nothing with niggers or Chinese.
But you’re white, all right.”
The drummer suddenly returned to the Virginian with this high
compliment.
The cowpuncher had taken out a pipe, and was slowly rubbing it.
The compliment seemed to escape his attention, and the drummer
went on.
“I can tell a man when he’s white, put him at Ikey’s or out loose
here in the sagebrush.”
And he rolled a cigar across to the Virginian’s plate.
“Selling them?” inquired the Virginian.
“Solid goods, my friend.
Havana wrappers, the biggest tobacco proposition for five cents
got out yet.
Take it, try it, light it, watch it burn.
Here.”
And he held out a bunch of matches.
The Virginian tossed a five-cent piece over to him.
“Oh, no, my friend!
Not from you!
Not after Ikey’s.
I don’t forget you.
See?
I knowed your face right away.
That’s straight.
I seen you at Chicago all right.”
“Maybe you did,” said the Virginian.
“Sometimes I’m mighty careless what I look at.”
“Well, py damn!” now exclaimed the Dutch drummer, hilariously.
“I am ploom disappointed. I vas hoping to sell him somedings
myself.”
“Not the same here,” stated the American.
“He’s too healthy for me. I gave him up on sight.”
Now it was the American drummer whose bed the Virginian had in
his eye.
This was a sensible man, and had talked less than his brothers
in the trade.
I had little doubt who would end by sleeping in his bed; but
how the thing would be done interested me more deeply than ever.
The Virginian looked amiably at his intended victim, and made
one or two remarks regarding patent medicines.
There must be a good deal of money in them, he supposed, with
a live man to manage them.
The victim was flattered.
No other person at the table had been favored with so much of
the tall cowpuncher’s notice.
He responded, and they had a pleasant talk.
I did not divine that the Virginian’s genius was even then at
work, and that all this was part of his satanic strategy.
But Steve must have divined it.
For while a few of us still sat finishing our supper, that facetious horseman returned from doctoring his horse’s hoofs, put his head into the
dining room, took in the way in which the Virginian was engaging his victim in conversation, remarked aloud, “I’ve lost!” and closed the door again.
“What’s he lost?” inquired the American drummer.
“Oh, you mustn’t mind him,” drawled the Virginian.
“He’s one of those box-head jokers goes around openin’ and shuttin’
doors that-a-way.
We call him harmless.
Well,” he broke off, “I reckon I’ll go smoke.
Not allowed in hyeh?”
This last he addressed to the landlady, with especial gentleness.
She shook her head, and her eyes followed him as he went out.
Left to myself I meditated for some time upon my lodging for
the night, and smoked a cigar for consolation as I walked about.
It was not a hotel that we had supped in.
Hotel at Medicine Bow there appeared to be none.
But connected with the eating-house was that place where, according to
Steve, the beds were all taken, and there I went to see for myself.
Steve had spoken the truth.
It was a single apartment containing four or five beds, and nothing
else whatever.
And when I looked at these beds, my sorrow that I could sleep
in none of them grew less.
To be alone in one offered no temptation, and as for this courtesy
of the country, this doubling up⁠—!
“Well, they have got ahead of us.”
This was the Virginian standing at my elbow.
I assented.
“They have staked out their claims,” he added.
In this public sleeping room they had done what one does to secure
a seat in a railroad train.
Upon each bed, as notice of occupancy, lay some article of travel
or of dress.
As we stood there, the two Jews came in and opened and arranged
their valises, and folded and refolded their linen dusters.
Then a railroad employee entered and began to go to bed at this
hour, before dusk had wholly darkened into night.
For him, going to bed meant removing his boots and placing his
overalls and waistcoat beneath his pillow.
He had no coat.
His work began at three in the morning; and even as we still
talked he began to snore.
“The man that keeps the store is a friend of mine,” said the
Virginian; “and you can be pretty near comfortable on his counter.
Got any blankets?”
I had no blankets.
“Looking for a bed?” inquired the American drummer, now arriving.
“Yes, he’s looking for a bed,” answered the voice of Steve behind
him.
“Seems a waste of time,” observed the Virginian.
He looked thoughtfully from one bed to another.
“I didn’t know I’d have to lay over here. Well, I have sat up
before.”
“This one’s mine,” said the drummer, sitting down on it.
“Half’s plenty enough room for me.”
“You’re cert’nly mighty kind,” said the cowpuncher.
“But I’d not think o’ disconveniencing yu’.”
“That’s nothing. The other half is yours. Turn in right now if
you feel like it.”
“No. I don’t reckon I’ll turn in right now. Better keep your
bed to yourself.”
“See here,” urged the drummer, “if I take you I’m safe from drawing
some party I might not care so much about.
This here sleeping proposition is a lottery.”
“Well,” said the Virginian (and his hesitation was truly masterly),
“if you put it that way⁠—”
“I do put it that way.
Why, you’re clean!
You’ve had a shave right now.
You turn in when you feel inclined, old man!
I ain’t retiring just yet.”
The drummer had struck a slightly false note in these last remarks.
He should not have said “old man.”
Until this I had thought him merely an amiable person who wished
to do a favor.
But “old man” came in wrong.
It had a hateful taint of his profession; the being too soon with everybody, the
celluloid good-fellowship that passes for ivory with nine in ten of the city crowd.
But not so with the sons of the sagebrush.
They live nearer nature, and they know better.
But the Virginian blandly accepted “old man” from his victim:
he had a game to play.
“Well, I cert’nly thank yu’,” he said.
“After a while I’ll take advantage of your kind offer.”
I was surprised.
Possession being nine points of the law, it seemed his very chance
to intrench himself in the bed.
But the cowpuncher had planned a campaign needing no intrenchments.
Moreover, going to bed before nine o’clock upon the first evening in many
weeks that a town’s resources were open to you, would be a dull proceeding.
Our entire company, drummer and all, now walked over to the store,
and here my sleeping arrangements were made easily.
This store was the cleanest place and the best in Medicine Bow, and would have been a good
store anywhere, offering a multitude of things for sale, and kept by a very civil proprietor.
He bade me make myself at home, and placed both of his counters
at my disposal.
Upon the grocery side there stood a cheese too large and strong to
sleep near comfortably, and I therefore chose the dry-goods side.
Here thick quilts were unrolled for me, to make it soft; and no condition was placed upon me,
further than that I should remove my boots, because the quilts were new, and clean, and for sale.
So now my rest was assured.
Not an anxiety remained in my thoughts.
These therefore turned themselves wholly to the other man’s bed,
and how he was going to lose it.
I think that Steve was more curious even than myself.
Time was on the wing.
His bet must be decided, and the drinks enjoyed.
He stood against the grocery counter, contemplating the Virginian.
But it was to me that he spoke.
The Virginian, however, listened to every word.
“Your first visit to this country?”
I told him yes.
“How do you like it?”
I expected to like it very much.
“How does the climate strike you?”
I thought the climate was fine.
“Makes a man thirsty though.”
This was the sub-current which the Virginian plainly looked for.
But he, like Steve, addressed himself to me.
“Yes,” he put in, “thirsty while a man’s soft yet.
You’ll harden.”
“I guess you’ll find it a drier country than you were given to
expect,” said Steve.
“If your habits have been frequent that way,” said the Virginian.
“There’s parts of Wyoming,” pursued Steve, “where you’ll go hours
and hours before you’ll see a drop of wetness.”
“And if yu’ keep a-thinkin’ about it,” said the Virginian, “it’ll
seem like days and days.”
Steve, at this stroke, gave up, and clapped him on the shoulder
with a joyous chuckle.
“You old son-of-a ⸻!” he cried affectionately.
“Drinks are due now,” said the Virginian.
“My treat, Steve. But I reckon your suspense will have to linger
a while yet.”
Thus they dropped into direct talk from that speech of the fourth
dimension where they had been using me for their telephone.
“Any cyards going tonight?” inquired the Virginian.
“Stud and draw,” Steve told him.
“Strangers playing.”
“I think I’d like to get into a game for a while,” said the Southerner.
“Strangers, yu’ say?”
And then, before quitting the store, he made his toilet for this
little hand at poker.
It was a simple preparation.
He took his pistol from its holster, examined it, then shoved it between
his overalls and his shirt in front, and pulled his waistcoat over it.
He might have been combing his hair for all the attention anyone
paid to this, except myself.
Then the two friends went out, and I bethought me of that epithet which
Steve again had used to the Virginian as he clapped him on the shoulder.
Clearly this wild country spoke a language other than mine⁠—the
word here was a term of endearment.
Such was my conclusion.
The drummers had finished their dealings with the proprietor, and they
were gossiping together in a knot by the door as the Virginian passed out.
“See you later, old man!”
This was the American drummer accosting his prospective bedfellow.
“Oh, yes,” returned the bedfellow, and was gone.
The American drummer winked triumphantly at his brethren.
“He’s all right,” he observed, jerking a thumb after the Virginian.
“He’s easy. You got to know him to work him. That’s all.”
“Und vat is your point?” inquired the German drummer.
“Point is⁠—he’ll not take any goods off you or me; but he’s
going to talk up the killer to any consumptive he runs across.
I ain’t done with him yet.
Say,” (he now addressed the proprietor), “what’s her name?”
“Whose name?”
“Woman runs the eating-house.”
“Glen. Mrs. Glen.”
“Ain’t she new?”
“Been settled here about a month. Husband’s a freight conductor.”
“Thought I’d not seen her before. She’s a good-looker.”
“Hm! Yes. The kind of good looks I’d sooner see in another man’s
wife than mine.”
“So that’s the gait, is it?”
“Hm! well, it don’t seem to be. She come here with that reputation.
But there’s been general disappointment.”
“Then she ain’t lacked suitors any?”
“Lacked! Are you acquainted with cowboys?”
“And she disappointed ’em? Maybe she likes her husband?”
“Hm! well, how are you to tell about them silent kind?”
“Talking of conductors,” began the drummer.
And we listened to his anecdote.
It was successful with his audience; but when he launched fluently
upon a second I strolled out.
There was not enough wit in this narrator to relieve his indecency,
and I felt shame at having been surprised into laughing with him.
I left that company growing confidential over their leering stories,
and I sought the saloon.
It was very quiet and orderly.
Beer in quart bottles at a dollar I had never met before; but
saving its price, I found no complaint to make of it.
Through folding doors I passed from the bar proper with its
bottles and elk head back to the hall with its various tables.
I saw a man sliding cards from a case, and across the table from
him another man laying counters down.
Near by was a second dealer pulling cards from the bottom of a pack, and opposite him
a solemn old rustic piling and changing coins upon the cards which lay already exposed.
But now I heard a voice that drew my eyes to the far corner of
the room.
“Why didn’t you stay in Arizona?”
Harmless looking words as I write them down here.
Yet at the sound of them I noticed the eyes of the others directed
to that corner.
What answer was given to them I did not hear, nor did I see who
spoke.
Then came another remark.
“Well, Arizona’s no place for amatures.”
This time the two card dealers that I stood near began to give
a part of their attention to the group that sat in the corner.
There was in me a desire to leave this room.
So far my hours at Medicine Bow had seemed to glide beneath a
sunshine of merriment, of easygoing jocularity.
This was suddenly gone, like the wind changing to north in the
middle of a warm day.
But I stayed, being ashamed to go.
Five or six players sat over in the corner at a round table where
counters were piled.
Their eyes were close upon their cards, and one seemed to be
dealing a card at a time to each, with pauses and betting between.
Steve was there and the Virginian; the others were new faces.
“No place for amatures,” repeated the voice; and now I saw that
it was the dealer’s.
There was in his countenance the same ugliness that his words
conveyed.
“Who’s that talkin’?” said one of the men near me, in a low voice.
“Trampas.”
“What’s he?”
“Cowpuncher, broncobuster, tin-horn, most anything.”
“Who’s he talkin’ at?”
“Think it’s the black-headed guy he’s talking at.”
“That ain’t supposed to be safe, is it?”
“Guess we’re all goin’ to find out in a few minutes.”
“Been trouble between ’em?”
“They’ve not met before. Trampas don’t enjoy losin’ to a stranger.”
“Fello’s from Arizona, yu’ say?”
“No.
Virginia.
He’s recently back from havin’ a look at Arizona.
Went down there last year for a change.
Works for the Sunk Creek outfit.”
And then the dealer lowered his voice still further and said
something in the other man’s ear, causing him to grin.
After which both of them looked at me.
There had been silence over in the corner; but now the man Trampas
spoke again.
“And ten,” said he, sliding out some chips from before him.
Very strange it was to hear him, how he contrived to make those
words a personal taunt.
The Virginian was looking at his cards.
He might have been deaf.
“And twenty,” said the next player, easily.
The next threw his cards down.
It was now the Virginian’s turn to bet, or leave the game, and
he did not speak at once.
Therefore Trampas spoke.
“Your bet, you son-of-a ⸻.”
The Virginian’s pistol came out, and his hand lay on the table,
holding it unaimed.
And with a voice as gentle as ever, the voice that sounded almost like a caress, but drawling a very little
more than usual, so that there was almost a space between each word, he issued his orders to the man Trampas:⁠—
“When you call me that, smile.”
And he looked at Trampas across the table.
Yes, the voice was gentle.
But in my ears it seemed as if somewhere the bell of death was
ringing; and silence, like a stroke, fell on the large room.
All men present, as if by some magnetic current, had become aware
of this crisis.
In my ignorance, and the total stoppage of my thoughts, I stood stock-still,
and noticed various people crouching, or shifting their positions.
“Sit quiet,” said the dealer, scornfully to the man near me.
“Can’t you see he don’t want to push trouble?
He has handed Trampas the choice to back down or draw his steel.”
Then, with equal suddenness and ease, the room came out of its
strangeness.
Voices and cards, the click of chips, the puff of tobacco, glasses lifted to drink⁠—this level of smooth
relaxation hinted no more plainly of what lay beneath than does the surface tell the depth of the sea.
For Trampas had made his choice.
And that choice was not to “draw his steel.”
If it was knowledge that he sought, he had found it, and no mistake!
We heard no further reference to what he had been pleased to
style “amatures.”
In no company would the black-headed man who had visited Arizona
be rated a novice at the cool art of self-preservation.
One doubt remained: what kind of a man was Trampas?
A public back-down is an unfinished thing⁠—for some natures at
least.
I looked at his face, and thought it sullen, but tricky rather
than courageous.
Something had been added to my knowledge also.
Once again I had heard applied to the Virginian that epithet
which Steve so freely used.
The same words, identical to the letter.
But this time they had produced a pistol.
“When you call me that, smile!”
So I perceived a new example of the old truth, that the letter
means nothing until the spirit gives it life.
CHAPTER III
Steve Treats
It was for several minutes, I suppose, that I stood drawing these
silent morals.
No man occupied himself with me.
Quiet voices, and games of chance, and glasses lifted to drink,
continued to be the peaceful order of the night.
And into my thoughts broke the voice of that card-dealer who
had already spoken so sagely.
He also took his turn at moralizing.
“What did I tell you?” he remarked to the man for whom he continued
to deal, and who continued to lose money to him.
“Tell me when?”
“Didn’t I tell you he’d not shoot?” the dealer pursued with complacence.
“You got ready to dodge. You had no call to be concerned. He’s
not the kind a man need feel anxious about.”
The player looked over at the Virginian, doubtfully.
“Well,” he said, “I don’t know what you folks call a dangerous
man.”
“Not him!” exclaimed the dealer with admiration.
“He’s a brave man. That’s different.”
The player seemed to follow this reasoning no better than I did.
“It’s not a brave man that’s dangerous,” continued the dealer.
“It’s the cowards that scare me.”
He paused that this might sink home.
“Fello’ came in here las’ Toosday ,” he went on.
“He got into some misunderstanding about the drinks.
Well, sir, before we could put him out of business, he’d hurt
two perfectly innocent onlookers.
They’d no more to do with it than you have,” the dealer explained
to me.
“Were they badly hurt?” I asked.
“One of ’em was. He’s died since.”
“What became of the man?”
“Why, we put him out of business, I told you.
He died that night.
But there was no occasion for any of it; and that’s why I never
like to be around where there’s a coward.
You can’t tell.
He’ll always go to shooting before it’s necessary, and there’s
no security who he’ll hit.
But a man like that black-headed guy is (the dealer indicated
the Virginian) need never worry you.
And there’s another point why there’s no need to worry about
him: it’ll be too late.”
These good words ended the moralizing of the dealer.
He had given us a piece of his mind.
He now gave the whole of it to dealing cards.
I loitered here and there, neither welcome nor unwelcome at present,
watching the cowboys at their play.
Saving Trampas, there was scarce a face among them that had not
in it something very likable.
Here were lusty horsemen ridden from the heat of the sun, and
the wet of the storm, to divert themselves awhile.
Youth untamed sat here for an idle moment, spending easily its
hard-earned wages.
City saloons rose into my vision, and I instantly preferred this
Rocky Mountain place.
More of death it undoubtedly saw, but less of vice, than did
its New York equivalents
.
And death is a thing much cleaner than vice.
Moreover, it was by no means vice that was written upon these
wild and manly faces.
Even where baseness was visible, baseness was not uppermost.
Daring, laughter, endurance⁠—these were what I saw upon the countenances
of the cowboys.
And this very first day of my knowledge of them marks a date
with me.
For something about them, and the idea of them, smote my American heart,
and I have never forgotten it, nor ever shall, as long as I live.
In their flesh our natural passions ran tumultuous; but often in their spirit sat hidden a
true nobility, and often beneath its unexpected shining their figures took on heroic stature.
The dealer had styled the Virginian “a black-headed guy.”
This did well enough as an unflattered portrait.
Judge Henry’s trustworthy man, with whom I was to drive two hundred
and sixty-three miles, certainly had a very black head of hair.
It was the first thing to notice now, if one glanced generally
at the table where he sat at cards.
But the eye came back to him⁠—drawn by that inexpressible something
which had led the dealer to speak so much at length about him.
Still, “black-headed guy” justly fits him and his next performance.
He had made his plan for this like a true and (I must say) inspired
devil.
And now the highly appreciative town of Medicine Bow was to be
treated to a manifestation of genius.
He sat playing his stud-poker.
After a decent period of losing and winning, which gave Trampas all proper time for a
change of luck and a repairing of his fortunes, he looked at Steve and said amiably:⁠—
“How does bed strike you?”
I was beside their table, learning gradually that stud-poker has in
it more of what I will call red pepper than has our Eastern game.
The Virginian followed his own question:⁠—
“Bed strikes me,” he stated.
Steve feigned indifference.
He was far more deeply absorbed in his bet and the American drummer than he was in this game; but he
chose to take out a fat, florid gold watch, consult it elaborately, and remark, “It’s only eleven.”
“Yu’ forget I’m from the country,” said the black-headed guy.
“The chickens have been roostin’ a right smart while.”
His sunny Southern accent was again strong.
In that brief passage with Trampas it had been almost wholly
absent.
But different moods of the spirit bring different qualities of
utterance⁠—where a man comes by these naturally.
The Virginian cashed in his checks.
“Awhile ago,” said Steve, “you had won three months’ salary.”
“I’m still twenty dollars to the good,” said the Virginian.
“That’s better than breaking a laig.”
Again, in some voiceless, masonic way, most people in that saloon
had become aware that something was in process of happening.
Several left their games and came to the front by the bar.
“If he ain’t in bed yet⁠—” mused the Virginian.
“I’ll find out,” said I.
And I hurried across to the dim sleeping room, happy to have
a part in this.
They were all in bed; and in some beds two were sleeping.
How they could do it⁠—but in those days I was fastidious.
The American had come in recently and was still awake.
“Thought you were to sleep at the store?” said he.
So then I invented a little lie, and explained that I was in
search of the Virginian.
“Better search the dives,” said he.
“These cowboys don’t get to town often.”
At this point I stumbled sharply over something.
“It’s my box of Consumption Killer,” explained the drummer; “Well,
I hope that man will stay out all night.”
“Bed narrow?” I inquired.
“For two it is. And the pillows are mean. Takes both before you
feel anything’s under your head.”
He yawned, and I wished him pleasant dreams.
At my news the Virginian left the bar at once; and crossed to
the sleeping room.
Steve and I followed softly, and behind us several more strung
out in an expectant line.
“What is this going to be?” they inquired curiously of each other.
And upon learning the great novelty of the event, they clustered with
silence intense outside the door where the Virginian had gone in.
We heard the voice of the drummer, cautioning his bedfellow.
“Don’t trip over the Killer,” he was saying.
“The Prince of Wales barked his shin just now.”
It seemed my English clothes had earned me this title.
The boots of the Virginian were next heard to drop.
“Can yu’ make out what he’s at?” whispered Steve.
He was plainly undressing.
The rip of swift unbuttoning told us that the black-headed guy
must now be removing his overalls.
“Why, thank yu’, no,” he was replying to a question of the drummer.
“Outside or in’s all one to me.”
“Then, if you’d just as soon take the wall⁠—”
“Why, cert’nly.”
There was a sound of bedclothes, and creaking.
“This hyeh pillo’ needs a Southern climate,” was the Virginian’s
next observation.
Many listeners had now gathered at the door.
The dealer and the player were both here.
The storekeeper was present, and I recognized the agent of the
Union Pacific Railroad among the crowd.
We made a large company, and I felt that trembling sensation which is
common when the cap of a camera is about to be removed upon a group.
“I should think,” said the drummer’s voice, “that you’d feel
your knife and gun clean through that pillow.”
“I do,” responded the Virginian.
“I should think you’d put them on a chair and be comfortable.”
“I’d be uncomfortable, then.”
“Used to the feel of them, I suppose?”
“That’s it. Used to the feel of them. I would miss them, and
that would make me wakeful.”
“Well, good night.”
“Good night. If I get to talkin’ and tossin’, or whatnot, you’ll
understand you’re to⁠—”
“Yes, I’ll wake you.”
“No, don’t yu’, for God’s sake!”
“Not?”
“Don’t yu’ touch me.”
“What’ll I do?”
“Roll away quick to your side. It don’t last but a minute.”
The Virginian spoke with a reassuring drawl.
Upon this there fell a brief silence, and I heard the drummer
clear his throat once or twice.
“It’s merely the nightmare, I suppose?” he said after a throat
clearing.
“Lord, yes. That’s all. And don’t happen twice a year. Was you
thinkin’ it was fits?”
“Oh, no!
I just wanted to know.
I’ve been told before that it was not safe for a person to be
waked suddenly that way out of a nightmare.”
“Yes, I have heard that too. But it never harms me any. I didn’t
want you to run risks.”
“Me?”
“Oh, it’ll be all right now that yu’ know how it is.”
The Virginian’s drawl was full of assurance.
There was a second pause, after which the drummer said:⁠—
“Tell me again how it is.”
The Virginian answered very drowsily: “Oh, just don’t let your
arm or your laig touch me if I go to jumpin’ around.
I’m dreamin’ of Indians when I do that.
And if anything touches me then, I’m liable to grab my knife
right in my sleep.”
“Oh, I understand,” said the drummer, clearing his throat.
“Yes.”
Steve was whispering delighted oaths to himself, and in his joy
applying to the Virginian one unprintable name after another.
We listened again, but now no further words came.
Listening very hard, I could half make out the progress of a
heavy breathing, and a restless turning I could clearly detect.
This was the wretched drummer.
He was waiting.
But he did not wait long.
Again there was a light creak, and after it a light step.
He was not even going to put his boots on in the fatal neighborhood
of the dreamer.
By a happy thought Medicine Bow formed into two lines, making
an avenue from the door.
And then the commercial traveller forgot his Consumption Killer.
He fell heavily over it.
Immediately from the bed the Virginian gave forth a dreadful
howl.
And then everything happened at once; and how shall mere words
narrate it?
The door burst open, and out flew the commercial traveller in
his stockings.
One hand held a lump of coat and trousers with suspenders dangling,
his boots were clutched in the other.
The sight of us stopped his flight short.
He gazed, the boots fell from his hand; and at his profane explosion, Medicine
Bow set up a united, unearthly noise and began to play Virginia reel with him.
The other occupants of the beds had already sprung out of them,
clothed chiefly with their pistols, and ready for war.
“What is it?” they demanded.
“What is it?”
“Why, I reckon it’s drinks on Steve,” said the Virginian from
his bed.
And he gave the first broad grin that I had seen from him.
“I’ll set ’em up all night!” Steve shouted, as the reel went
on regardless.
The drummer was bawling to be allowed to put at least his boots
on.
“This way, Pard,” was the answer; and another man whirled him
round.
“This way, Beau!” they called to him; “This way, Budd!” and he
was passed like a shuttlecock down the line.
Suddenly the leaders bounded into the sleeping-room.
“Feed the machine!” they said.
“Feed her!”
And seizing the German drummer who sold jewellery, they flung
him into the trough of the reel.
I saw him go bouncing like an ear of corn to be shelled, and
the dance ingulfed him.
I saw a Jew sent rattling after him; and next they threw in the railroad employee,
and the other Jew; and while I stood mesmerized, my own feet left the earth.
I shot from the room and sped like a bobbing cork into this mill race, whirling my
turn in the wake of the others amid cries of, “Here comes the Prince of Wales!”
There was soon not much English left about my raiment.
They were now shouting for music.
Medicine Bow swept in like a cloud of dust to where a fiddler sat playing in a hall; and
gathering up fiddler and dancers, swept out again, a larger Medicine Bow, growing all the while.
Steve offered us the freedom of the house, everywhere.
He implored us to call for whatever pleased us, and as many times
as we should please.
He ordered the town to be searched for more citizens to come
and help him pay his bet.
But changing his mind, kegs and bottles were now carried along
with us.
We had found three fiddlers, and these played busily for us; and thus we set out
to visit all cabins and houses where people might still by some miracle be asleep.
The first man put out his head to decline.
But such a possibility had been foreseen by the proprietor of
the store.
This seemingly respectable man now came dragging some sort of
apparatus from his place, helped by the Virginian.
The cowboys cheered, for they knew what this was.
The man in his window likewise recognized it, and uttering a
groan, came immediately out and joined us.
What it was, I also learned in a few minutes.
For we found a house where the people made no sign at either
our fiddlers or our knocking.
And then the infernal machine was set to work.
Its parts seemed to be no more than an empty keg and a plank.
Some citizen informed me that I should soon have a new idea of noise;
and I nerved myself for something severe in the way of gunpowder.
But the Virginian and the proprietor now sat on the ground holding the keg braced,
and two others got down apparently to play seesaw over the top of it with the plank.
But the keg and plank had been rubbed with rosin, and they drew
the plank back and forth over the keg.
Do you know the sound made in a narrow street by a dray loaded
with strips of iron?
That noise is a lullaby compared with the staggering, blinding
bellow which rose from the keg.
If you were to try it in your native town, you would not merely be arrested, you
would be hanged, and everybody would be glad, and the clergyman would not bury you.
My head, my teeth, the whole system of my bones leaped and chattered at the din,
and out of the house like drops squirted from a lemon came a man and his wife.
No time was given them.
They were swept along with the rest; and having been routed from their own bed,
they now became most furious in assailing the remaining homes of Medicine Bow.
Everybody was to come out.
Many were now riding horses at top speed out into the plains and back, while the
procession of the plank and keg continued its work, and the fiddlers played incessantly.
Suddenly there was a quiet.
I did not see who brought the message; but the word ran among us that
there was a woman⁠—the engineer’s woman down by the water-tank⁠—very sick.
The doctor had been to see her from Laramie.
Everybody liked the engineer.
Plank and keg were heard no more.
The horsemen found it out and restrained their gambols.
Medicine Bow went gradually home.
I saw doors shutting, and lights go out; I saw a late few reassemble at the card tables, and the drummers gathered themselves together for sleep; the proprietor of the
store (you could not see a more respectable-looking person) hoped that I would be comfortable on the quilts; and I heard Steve urging the Virginian to take one more glass.
“We’ve not met for so long,” he said.
But the Virginian, the black-headed guy who had set all this
nonsense going, said No to Steve.
“I have got to stay responsible,” was his excuse to his friend.
And the friend looked at me.
Therefore I surmised that the Judge’s trustworthy man found me
an embarrassment to his holiday.
But if he did, he never showed it to me.
He had been sent to meet a stranger and drive him to Sunk Creek in
safety, and this charge he would allow no temptation to imperil.
He nodded good night to me.
“If there’s anything I can do for yu’, you’ll tell me.”
I thanked him.
“What a pleasant evening!” I added.
“I’m glad yu’ found it so.”
Again his manner put a bar to my approaches.
Even though I had seen him wildly disporting himself, those were
matters which he chose not to discuss with me.
Medicine Bow was quiet as I went my way to my quilts.
So still, that through the air the deep whistles of the freight
trains came from below the horizon across great miles of silence.
I passed cowboys, whom half an hour before I had seen prancing and
roaring, now rolled in their blankets beneath the open and shining night.
“What world am I in?” I said aloud.
“Does this same planet hold Fifth Avenue?”
And I went to sleep, pondering over my native land.
CHAPTER IV
Deep Into Cattle Land
Morning had been for some while astir in Medicine Bow before
I left my quilts.
The new day and its doings began around me in the store, chiefly
at the grocery counter.
Dry-goods were not in great request.
The early rising cowboys were off again to their work; and those to whom their night’s holiday had left any dollars
were spending these for tobacco, or cartridges, or canned provisions for the journey to their distant camps.
Sardines were called for, and potted chicken, and devilled ham: a
sophisticated nourishment, at first sight, for these sons of the sagebrush.
But portable ready-made food plays of necessity a great part
in the opening of a new country.
These picnic pots and cans were the first of her trophies that
Civilization dropped upon Wyoming’s virgin soil.
The cowboy is now gone to worlds invisible; the wind has blown away the white ashes of
his campfires; but the empty sardine box lies rusting over the face of the Western earth.
So through my eyes half closed I watched the sale of these tins, and grew familiar with the ham’s inevitable trademark⁠—that
label with the devil and his horns and hoofs and tail very pronounced, all colored a sultry prodigious scarlet.
And when each horseman had made his purchase, he would trail his spurs over the
floor, and presently the sound of his horse’s hoofs would be the last of him.
Through my dozing attention came various fragments of talk, and
sometimes useful bits of knowledge.
For instance, I learned the true value of tomatoes in this country.
One fellow was buying two cans of them.
“Meadow Creek dry already?” commented the proprietor.
“Been dry ten days,” the young cowboy informed him.
And it appeared that along the road he was going, water would not be
reached much before sundown, because this Meadow Creek had ceased to run.
His tomatoes were for drink.
And thus they have refreshed me many times since.
“No beer?” suggested the proprietor.
The boy made a shuddering face.
“Don’t say its name to me!” he exclaimed.
“I couldn’t hold my breakfast down.”
He rang his silver money upon the counter.
“I’ve swore off for three months,” he stated.
“I’m going to be as pure as the snow!”
And away he went jingling out of the door, to ride seventy-five
miles.
Three more months of hard, unsheltered work, and he would ride into
town again, with his adolescent blood crying aloud for its own.
“I’m obliged,” said a new voice, rousing me from a new doze.
“She’s easier this morning, since the medicine.”
This was the engineer, whose sick wife had brought a hush over
Medicine Bow’s rioting.
“I’ll give her them flowers soon as she wakes,” he added.
“Flowers?” repeated the proprietor.
“You didn’t leave that bunch at our door?”
“Wish I’d thought to do it.”
“She likes to see flowers,” said the engineer.
And he walked out slowly, with his thanks unachieved.
He returned at once with the Virginian; for in the band of the
Virginian’s hat were two or three blossoms.
“It don’t need mentioning,” the Southerner was saying, embarrassed
by any expression of thanks.
“If we had knowed last night⁠—”
“You didn’t disturb her any,” broke in the engineer.
“She’s easier this morning. I’ll tell her about them flowers.”
“Why, it don’t need mentioning,” the Virginian again protested,
almost crossly.
“The little things looked kind o’ fresh, and I just picked them.”
His eye now fell upon me, where I lay upon the counter.
“I reckon breakfast will be getting through,” he remarked.
I was soon at the wash trough.
It was only half-past six, but many had been before me⁠—one glance
at the roller-towel told me that.
I was afraid to ask the landlady for a clean one, and so I
found a fresh handkerchief, and accomplished a sparing toilet.
In the midst of this the drummers joined me, one by one, and
they used the degraded towel without hesitation.
In a way they had the best of me; filth was nothing to them.
The latest risers in Medicine Bow, we sat at breakfast together;
and they essayed some light familiarities with the landlady.
But these experiments were failures.
Her eyes did not see, nor did her ears hear them.
She brought the coffee and the bacon with a sedateness that propriety
itself could scarce have surpassed.
Yet impropriety lurked noiselessly all over her.
You could not have specified how; it was interblended with her
sum total.
Silence was her apparent habit and her weapon; but the American drummer
found that she could speak to the point when need came for this.
During the meal he had praised her golden hair.
It was golden indeed, and worth a high compliment; but his kind
displeased her.
She had let it pass, however, with no more than a cool stare.
But on taking his leave, when he came to pay for the meal, he
pushed it too far.
“Pity this must be our last,” he said; and as it brought no answer,
“Ever travel?” he inquired.
“Where I go, there’s room for a pair of us.”
“Then you’d better find another jackass,” she replied quietly.
I was glad that I had not asked for a clean towel.
From the commercial travellers I now separated myself, and wandered
alone in pleasurable aimlessness.
It was seven o’clock.
Medicine Bow stood voiceless and unpeopled.
The cowboys had melted away.
The inhabitants were indoors, pursuing the business or the idleness
of the forenoon.
Visible motion there was none.
No shell upon the dry sands could lie more lifeless than Medicine
Bow.
Looking in at the store, I saw the proprietor sitting with his
pipe extinct.
Looking in at the saloon, I saw the dealer dealing dumbly to
himself.
Up in the sky there was not a cloud nor a bird, and on the earth
the lightest straw lay becalmed.
Once I saw the Virginian at an open door, where the golden-haired
landlady stood talking with him.
Sometimes I strolled in the town, and sometimes out on the plain
I lay down with my day dreams in the sagebrush.
Pale herds of antelope were in the distance, and near by the
demure prairie-dogs sat up and scrutinized me.
Steve, Trampas, the riot of horsemen, my lost trunk, Uncle Hughey, with his abortive
brides⁠—all things merged in my thoughts in a huge, delicious indifference.
It was like swimming slowly at random in an ocean that was smooth,
and neither too cool nor too warm.
And before I knew it, five lazy imperceptible hours had gone
thus.
There was the Union Pacific train, coming as if from shores forgotten.
Its approach was silent and long drawn out.
I easily reached town and the platform before it had finished
watering at the tank.
It moved up, made a short halt, I saw my trunk come out of it, and then it
moved away silently as it had come, smoking and dwindling into distance unknown.
Beside my trunk was one other, tied extravagantly with white
ribbon.
The fluttering bows caught my attention, and now I suddenly saw
a perfectly new sight.
The Virginian was further down the platform, doubled up with
laughing.
It was good to know that with sufficient cause he could laugh
like this; a smile had thus far been his limit of external mirth.
Rice now flew against my hat, and hissing gusts of rice spouted
on the platform.
All the men left in Medicine Bow appeared like magic, and more
rice choked the atmosphere.
Through the general clamor a cracked voice said, “Don’t hit her in the eye,
boys!” and Uncle Hughey rushed proudly by me with an actual wife on his arm.
She could easily have been his granddaughter.
They got at once into a vehicle.
The trunk was lifted in behind.
And amid cheers, rice, shoes, and broad felicitations, the pair drove out of
town, Uncle Hughey shrieking to the horses and the bride waving unabashed adieus.
The word had come over the wires from Laramie: “Uncle Hughey
has made it this time.
Expect him on today’s number two.”
And Medicine Bow had expected him.
Many words arose on the departure of the new-married couple.
“Who’s she?”
“What’s he got for her?”
“Got a gold mine up Bear Creek.”
And after comment and prophecy, Medicine Bow returned to its
dinner.
This meal was my last here for a long while.
The Virginian’s responsibility now returned; duty drove the Judge’s
trustworthy man to take care of me again.
He had not once sought my society of his own accord; his distaste for what
he supposed me to be (I don’t exactly know what this was) remained unshaken.
I have thought that matters of dress and speech should not carry with them so much mistrust in our
democracy; thieves are presumed innocent until proved guilty, but a starched collar is condemned at once.
Perfect civility and obligingness I certainly did receive from
the Virginian, only not a word of fellowship.
He harnessed the horses, got my trunk, and gave me some advice about taking provisions
for our journey, something more palatable than what food we should find along the road.
It was well thought of, and I bought quite a parcel of dainties,
feeling that he would despise both them and me.
And thus I took my seat beside him, wondering what we should
manage to talk about for two hundred and sixty-three miles.
Farewell in those days was not said in Cattle Land.
Acquaintances watched our departure with a nod or with nothing, and
the nearest approach to “Goodbye” was the proprietor’s “So-long.”
But I caught sight of one farewell given without words.
As we drove by the eating-house, the shade of a side window was
raised, and the landlady looked her last upon the Virginian.
Her lips were faintly parted, and no woman’s eyes ever said more
plainly, “I am one of your possessions.”
She had forgotten that it might be seen.
Her glance caught mine, and she backed into the dimness of the
room.
What look she may have received from him, if he gave her any
at this too public moment, I could not tell.
His eyes seemed to be upon the horses, and he drove with the
same mastering ease that had roped the wild pony yesterday.
We passed the ramparts of Medicine Bow⁠—thick heaps and fringes of
tin cans, and shelving mounds of bottles cast out of the saloons.
The sun struck these at a hundred glittering points.
And in a moment we were in the clean plains, with the prairie-dogs
and the pale herds of antelope.
The great, still air bathed us, pure as water and strong as wine; the sunlight flooded the world;
and shining upon the breast of the Virginian’s flannel shirt lay a long gold thread of hair!
The noisy American drummer had met defeat, but this silent free
lance had been easily victorious.
It must have been five miles that we travelled in silence, losing
and seeing the horizon among the ceaseless waves of the earth.
Then I looked back, and there was Medicine Bow, seemingly a stone’s
throw behind us.
It was a full half-hour before I looked back again, and there
sure enough was always Medicine Bow.
A size or two smaller, I will admit, but visible in every feature,
like something seen through the wrong end of a field glass.
The Eastbound express was approaching the town, and I noticed the white steam
from its whistle; but when the sound reached us, the train had almost stopped.
And in reply to my comment upon this, the Virginian deigned to
remark that it was more so in Arizona.
“A man come to Arizona,” he said, “with one of them telescopes
to study the heavenly bodies.
He was a Yankee, seh, and a right smart one, too.
And one night we was watchin’ for some little old fallin’ stars that he said was due,
and I saw some lights movin’ along across the mesa pretty lively, an’ I sang out.
But he told me it was just the train.
And I told him I didn’t know yu’ could see the cyars that plain from his place, ‘Yu’
can see them,’ he said to me, ‘but it is las’ night’s cyars you’re lookin’ at.’ ”
At this point the Virginian spoke severely to one of the horses.
“Of course,” he then resumed to me, “that Yankee man did not mean quite
all he said.⁠—You, Buck!” he again broke off suddenly to the horse.
“But Arizona, seh,” he continued, “it cert’nly has a mos’ deceivin’
atmospheah.
Another man told me he had seen a lady close one eye at him when
he was two minutes hard run from her.”
This time the Virginian gave Buck the whip.
“What effect,” I inquired with a gravity equal to his own, “does
this extraordinary foreshortening have upon a quart of whiskey?”
“When it’s outside yu’, seh, no distance looks too far to go
to it.”
He glanced at me with an eye that held more confidence than hitherto
he had been able to feel in me.
I had made one step in his approval.
But I had many yet to go.
This day he preferred his own thoughts to my conversation, and so he did all the days of
this first journey; while I should have greatly preferred his conversation to my thoughts.
He dismissed some attempts that I made upon the subject of Uncle Hughey so that I had not the courage
to touch upon Trampas, and that chill brief collision which might have struck the spark of death.
Trampas!
I had forgotten him till this silent drive I was beginning.
I wondered if I should ever see him, or Steve, or any of those
people again.
And this wonder I expressed aloud.
“There’s no tellin’ in this country ,” said the Virginian.
“Folks come easy, and they go easy.
In settled places, like back in the States, even a poor man mostly
has a home.
Don’t care if it’s only a barrel on a lot, the fello’ will keep
frequentin’ that lot, and if yu’ want him yu’ can find him.
But out hyeh in the sagebrush, a man’s home is apt to be his
saddle blanket.
First thing yu’ know, he has moved it to Texas.”
“You have done some moving yourself,” I suggested.
But this word closed his mouth.
“I have had a look at the country,” he said, and we were silent
again.
Let me, however, tell you here that he had set out for a “look at the country” at the age of fourteen; and that by his
present age of twenty-four he had seen Arkansas, Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, California, Oregon, Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming.
Everywhere he had taken care of himself, and survived; nor had
his strong heart yet waked up to any hunger for a home.
Let me also tell you that he was one of thousands drifting and
living thus, but (as you shall learn) one in a thousand.
Medicine Bow did not forever remain in sight.
When next I thought of it and looked behind, nothing was there but the road we
had come; it lay like a ship’s wake across the huge ground swell of the earth.
We were swallowed in a vast solitude.
A little while before sunset, a cabin came in view; and here
we passed our first night.
Two young men lived here, tending their cattle.
They were fond of animals.
By the stable a chained coyote rushed nervously in a circle, or
sat on its haunches and snapped at gifts of food ungraciously.
A tame young elk walked in and out of the cabin door, and during
supper it tried to push me off my chair.
A half-tame mountain sheep practised jumping from the ground
to the roof.
The cabin was papered with posters of a circus, and skins of
bear and silver fox lay upon the floor.
Until nine o’clock one man talked to the Virginian, and one played
gayly upon a concertina; and then we all went to bed.
The air was like December, but in my blankets and a buffalo
robe I kept warm, and luxuriated in the Rocky Mountain silence.
Going to wash before breakfast at sunrise, I found needles of
ice in a pail.
Yet it was hard to remember that this quiet, open, splendid wilderness
(with not a peak in sight just here) was six thousand feet high.
And when breakfast was over there was no December left; and by the
time the Virginian and I were ten miles upon our way, it was June.
But always every breath that I breathed was pure as water and
strong as wine.
We never passed a human being this day.
Some wild cattle rushed up to us and away from us; antelope stared at us from a hundred yards; coyotes ran skulking through the sagebrush to watch
us from a hill; at our noon meal we killed a rattlesnake and shot some young sage chickens, which were good at supper, roasted at our campfire.
By half-past eight we were asleep beneath the stars, and by half-past
four I was drinking coffee and shivering.
The horse, Buck, was hard to catch this second morning.
Whether some hills that we were now in had excited him, or whether the better
water up here had caused an effervescence in his spirits, I cannot say.
But I was as hot as July by the time we had him safe in harness,
or, rather, unsafe in harness.
For Buck, in the mysterious language of horses, now taught wickedness to his side partner,
and about eleven o’clock they laid their evil heads together and decided to break our necks.
We were passing, I have said, through a range of demi-mountains.
It was a little country where trees grew, water ran, and the
plains were shut out for a while.
The road had steep places in it, and places here and there where
you could fall off and go bounding to the bottom among stones.
But Buck, for some reason, did not think these opportunities
good enough for him.
He selected a more theatrical moment.
We emerged from a narrow canyon suddenly upon five hundred
cattle and some cowboys branding calves by a fire in a corral.
It was a sight that Buck knew by heart.
He instantly treated it like an appalling phenomenon.
I saw him kick seven ways; I saw Muggins kick five ways; our
furious motion snapped my spine like a whip.
I grasped the seat.
Something gave a forlorn jingle.
It was the brake.
“Don’t jump!” commanded the trustworthy man.
“No,” I said, as my hat flew off.
Help was too far away to do anything for us.
We passed scatheless through a part of the cattle, I saw their
horns and backs go by.
Some earth crumbled, and we plunged downward into water rocking
among stones, and upward again through some more crumbling earth.
I heard a crash, and saw my trunk landing in the stream.
“She’s safer there,” said the trustworthy man.
“True,” I said.
“We’ll go back for her,” said he, with his eye on the horses
and his foot on the crippled brake.
A dry gully was coming, and no room to turn.
The farther side of it was terraced with rock.
We should simply fall backward, if we did not fall forward first.
He steered the horses straight over, and just at the bottom swung
them, with astonishing skill, to the right along the hard-baked mud.
They took us along the bed up to the head of the gully, and through
a thicket of quaking asps.
The light trees bent beneath our charge and bastinadoed the wagon
as it went over them.
But their branches enmeshed the horses’ legs, and we came to
a harmless standstill among a bower of leaves.
I looked at the trustworthy man, and smiled vaguely.
He considered me for a moment.
“I reckon,” said he, “you’re feelin’ about halfway between ‘Oh,
Lord!’ and ‘Thank God!’ ”
“That’s quite it,” said I, as he got down on the ground.
“Nothing’s broke,” said he, after a searching examination.
And he indulged in a true Virginian expletive.
“Gentlemen, hush!” he murmured gently, looking at me with his
grave eyes; “one time I got pretty near scared.
You, Buck,” he continued, “some folks would beat you now till
yu’d be uncertain whether yu’ was a hawss or a railroad accident.
I’d do it myself, only it wouldn’t cure yu’.”
I now told him that I supposed he had saved both our lives.
But he detested words of direct praise.
He made some grumbling rejoinder, and led the horses out of the
thicket.
Buck, he explained to me, was a good horse, and so was Muggins.
Both of them generally meant well, and that
was the Judge’s reason for sending them to meet me.
But these broncos had their off days.
Off days might not come very often; but when the humor seized
a bronco, he had to have his spree.
Buck would now behave himself as a horse should for probably
two months.
“They are just like humans,” the Virginian concluded.
Several cowboys arrived on a gallop to find how many pieces of
us were left.
We returned down the hill; and when we reached my trunk, it was
surprising to see the distance that our runaway had covered.
My hat was also found, and we continued on our way.
Buck and Muggins were patterns of discretion through the rest
of the mountains.
I thought when we camped this night that it was strange Buck should be again
allowed to graze at large, instead of being tied to a rope while we slept.
But this was my ignorance.
With the hard work that he was gallantly doing, the horse needed
more pasture than a rope’s length would permit him to find.
Therefore he went free, and in the morning gave us but little
trouble in catching him.
We crossed a river in the forenoon, and far to the north of us
we saw the Bow Leg Mountains, pale in the bright sun.
Sunk Creek flowed from their western side, and our two hundred
and sixty-three miles began to grow a small thing in my eyes.
Buck and Muggins, I think, knew perfectly that tomorrow would
see them home.
They recognized this region; and once they turned off at a fork
in the road.
The Virginian pulled them back rather sharply.
“Want to go back to Balaam’s?” he inquired of them.
“I thought you had more sense.”
I asked, “Who was Balaam?”
“A maltreater of hawsses,” replied the cowpuncher.
“His ranch is on Butte Creek oveh yondeh.”
And he pointed to where the diverging road melted into space.
“The Judge bought Buck and Muggins from him in the spring.”
“So he maltreats horses?” I repeated.
“That’s the word all through this country.
A man that will do what they claim Balaam does to a hawss when
he’s mad, ain’t fit to be called human.”
The Virginian told me some particulars.
“Oh!”
I almost screamed at the horror of it, and again, “Oh!”
“He’d have prob’ly done that to Buck as soon as he stopped runnin’
away. If I caught a man doin’ that⁠—”
We were interrupted by a sedate-looking traveller riding upon
an equally sober horse.
“Mawnin’, Taylor,” said the Virginian, pulling up for gossip.
“Ain’t you strayed off your range pretty far?”
“You’re a nice one!” replied Mr. Taylor, stopping his horse and
smiling amiably.
“Tell me something I don’t know,” retorted the Virginian.
“Hold up a man at cards and rob him,” pursued Mr. Taylor.
“Oh, the news has got ahead of you!”
“Trampas has been hyeh explainin’, has he?” said the Virginian
with a grin.
“Was that your victim’s name?” said Mr. Taylor, facetiously.
“No, it wasn’t him that brought the news. Say, what did you do,
anyway?”
“So that thing has got around,” murmured the Virginian.
“Well, it wasn’t worth such wide repawtin’.”
And he gave the simple facts to Taylor, while I sat wondering
at the contagious powers of Rumor.
Here, through this voiceless land, this desert, this vacuum,
it had spread like a change of weather.
“Any news up your way?” the Virginian concluded.
Importance came into Mr. Taylor’s countenance.
“Bear Creek is going to build a schoolhouse,” said he.
“Goodness gracious!” drawled the Virginian.
“What’s that for?”
Now Mr. Taylor had been married for some years.
“To educate the offspring of Bear Creek,” he answered with pride.
“Offspring of Bear Creek,” the Virginian meditatively repeated.
“I don’t remember noticin’ much offspring. There was some white
tail deer, and a right smart o’ jack rabbits.”
“The Swintons have moved up from Drybone,” said Mr. Taylor, always
seriously.
“They found it no place for young children.
And there’s Uncle Carmody with six, and Ben Dow.
And Westfall has become a family man, and⁠—”
“Jim Westfall!” exclaimed the Virginian.
“Him a fam’ly man!
Well, if this hyeh Territory is goin’ to get full o’ fam’ly men
and empty o’ game, I believe I’ll⁠—”
“Get married yourself,” suggested Mr. Taylor.
“Me! I ain’t near reached the marriageable age. No, seh! But
Uncle Hughey has got there at last, yu’ know.”
“Uncle Hughey!” shouted Mr. Taylor.
He had not heard this.
Rumor is very capricious.
Therefore the Virginian told him, and the family man rocked in
his saddle.
“Build your schoolhouse,” said the Virginian.
“Uncle Hughey has qualified himself to subscribe to all such
propositions. Got your eye on a schoolmarm?”
CHAPTER V
Enter the Woman
“We are taking steps,” said Mr. Taylor.
“Bear Creek ain’t going to be hasty about a schoolmarm.”
“Sure,” assented the Virginian.
“The children wouldn’t want yu’ to hurry.”
But Mr. Taylor was, as I have indicated, a serious family man.
The problem of educating his children could appear to him in
no light except a sober one.
“Bear Creek,” he said, “don’t want the experience they had over
at Calef.
We must not hire an ignoramus.”
“Sure!” assented the Virginian again.
“Nor we don’t want no gad-a-way flirt,” said Mr. Taylor.
“She must keep her eyes on the blackboa’d,” said the Virginian,
gently.
“Well, we can wait till we get a guaranteed article,” said Mr.
Taylor.
“And that’s what we’re going to do.
It can’t be this year, and it needn’t to be.
None of the kids is very old, and the schoolhouse has got to
be built.”
He now drew a letter from his pocket, and looked at me.
“Are you acquainted with Miss Mary Stark Wood of Bennington,
Vermont?” he inquired.
I was not acquainted with her at this time.
“She’s one we are thinking of. She’s a correspondent with Mrs.
Balaam.”
Taylor handed me the letter.
“She wrote that to Mrs. Balaam, and Mrs. Balaam said the best
thing was for to let me see it and judge for myself.
I’m taking it back to Mrs. Balaam.
Maybe you can give me your opinion how it sizes up with the letters
they write back East?”
The communication was mainly of a business kind, but also personal,
and freely written.
I do not think that its writer expected it to be exhibited as
a document.
The writer wished very much that she could see the West.
But she could not gratify this desire merely for pleasure, or she would
long ago have accepted the kind invitation to visit Mrs. Balaam’s ranch.
Teaching school was something she would like to do, if she were
fitted for it.
“Since the mills failed” (the writer said) “we have all gone to work and
done a lot of things so that mother might keep on living in the old house.
Yes, the salary would be a temptation.
But, my dear, isn’t Wyoming bad for the complexion?
And could I sue them if mine got damaged?
It is still admired.
I could bring one male witness at least to prove that!”
Then the writer became businesslike again.
Even if she came to feel that she could leave home, she did not
at all know that she could teach school.
Nor did she think it right to accept a position in which one
had had no experience.
“I do love children, boys especially,” she went on.
“My small nephew and I get on famously.
But imagine if a whole benchful of boys began asking me questions
that I couldn’t answer!
What should I do?
For one could not spank them all, you know!
And mother says that I ought not to teach anybody spelling, because
I leave the u out of ‘honor.’”
Altogether it was a letter which I could assure Mr. Taylor “sized up”
very well with the letters written in my part of the United States.
And it was signed, “Your very sincere spinster, Molly Stark Wood.”
“I never seen ‘honor’ spelled with a u,” said Mr. Taylor, over whose not
highly civilized head certain portions of the letter had lightly passed.
I told him that some old-fashioned people still wrote the word
so.
“Either way would satisfy Bear Creek,” said Mr. Taylor, “if she’s
otherwise up to requirements.”
The Virginian was now looking over the letter musingly, and with
awakened attention.
“ ‘Your very sincere spinster,’ ” he read aloud slowly.
“I guess that means she’s forty,” said Taylor.
“I reckon she is about twenty,” said the Virginian.
And again he fell to musing over the paper that he held.
“Her handwriting ain’t like any I’ve saw,” pursued Mr. Taylor.
“But Bear Creek would not object to that, provided she knows
’rithmetic and George Washington, and them kind of things.”
“I expect she is not an awful sincere spinster,” surmised the Virginian,
still looking at the letter, still holding it as if it were some token.
Has any botanist set down what the seed of love is?
Has it anywhere been set down in how many ways this seed may
be sown?
In what various vessels of gossamer it can float across wide spaces? Or upon what
different soils it can fall, and live unknown, and bide its time for blooming?
The Virginian handed back to Taylor the sheet of note paper
where a girl had talked as the women he had known did not talk.
If his eyes had ever seen such maidens, there had been no meeting of eyes; and if
such maidens had ever spoken to him, the speech was from an established distance.
But here was a free language, altogether new to him.
It proved, however, not alien to his understanding, as it was
alien to Mr. Taylor’s.
We drove onward, a mile perhaps, and then two.
He had lately been full of words, but now he barely answered
me, so that a silence fell upon both of us.
It must have been all of ten miles that we had driven when he
spoke of his own accord.
“Your real spinster don’t speak of her lot that easy,” he remarked.
And presently he quoted a phrase about the complexion, “ ‘Could I sue them if
mine got damaged?’ ” and he smiled over this to himself, shaking his head.
“What would she be doing on Bear Creek?” he next said.
And finally: “I reckon that witness will detain her in Vermont.
And her mother’ll keep livin’ at the old house
.”
Thus did the cowpuncher deliver himself, not knowing at all that the seed
had floated across wide spaces, and was biding its time in his heart.
On the morrow we reached Sunk Creek.
Judge Henry’s welcome and his wife’s would have obliterated any
hardships that I had endured, and I had endured none at all.
For a while I saw little of the Virginian.
He lapsed into his native way of addressing me occasionally as
“seh”⁠—a habit entirely repudiated by this land of equality.
I was sorry.
Our common peril during the runaway of Buck and Muggins had
brought us to a familiarity that I hoped was destined to last.
But I think that it would not have gone farther, save for a certain
personage⁠—I must call her a personage.
And as I am indebted to her for gaining me a friend whose prejudice against me might never have been otherwise overcome, I shall tell
you her little story, and how her misadventures and her fate came to bring the Virginian and me to an appreciation of one another.
Without her, it is likely I should also not have heard so much of the
story of the schoolmarm, and how that lady at last came to Bear Creek.
CHAPTER VI
Em’ly
My personage was a hen, and she lived at the Sunk Creek Ranch.
Judge Henry’s ranch was notable for several luxuries.
He had milk, for example.
In those days his brother ranchmen had thousands of cattle very
often, but not a drop of milk, save the condensed variety.
Therefore they had no butter.
The Judge had plenty.
Next rarest to butter and milk in the cattle country were eggs.
But my host had chickens.
Whether this was because he had followed cockfighting in his
early days, or whether it was due to Mrs. Henry, I cannot say.
I only know that when I took a meal elsewhere, I was likely to find nothing but the eternal
“sowbelly,” beans, and coffee; while at Sunk Creek the omelet and the custard were frequent.
The passing traveller was glad to tie his horse to the fence
here, and sit down to the Judge’s table.
For its fame was as wide as Wyoming.
It was an oasis in the Territory’s desolate bill-of-fare.
The long fences of Judge Henry’s home ranch began upon Sunk Creek
soon after that stream emerged from its canyon through the Bow Leg.
It was a place always well cared for by the owner, even in the
days of his bachelorhood.
The placid regiments of cattle lay in the cool of the cottonwoods by the water, or slowly moved among
the sagebrush, feeding upon the grass that in those forever departed years was plentiful and tall.
The steers came fat off his unenclosed range and fattened still more in his large pasture; while his small pasture, a field some eight miles square, was for several
seasons given to the Judge’s horses, and over this ample space there played and prospered the good colts which he raised from Paladin, his imported stallion.
After he married, I have been assured that his wife’s influence
became visible in and about the house at once.
Shade trees were planted, flowers attempted, and to the chickens
was added the much more troublesome turkey.
I, the visitor, was pressed into service when I arrived, green
from the East.
I took hold of the farmyard and began building a better chicken house, while
the Judge was off creating meadow land in his gray and yellow wilderness.
When any cowboy was unoccupied, he would lounge over to my neighborhood,
and silently regard my carpentering.
Those cowpunchers bore names of various denominations.
There was Honey Wiggin; there was Nebrasky, and Dollar Bill,
and Chalkeye.
And they came from farms and cities, from Maine and from California.
But the romance of American adventure had drawn them all alike to this great playground of young men, and
in their courage, their generosity, and their amusement at me they bore a close resemblance to each other.
Each one would silently observe my achievements with the hammer
and the chisel.
Then he would retire to the bunk-house, and presently I would
overhear laughter.
But this was only in the morning.
In the afternoon on many days of the summer which I spent at the Sunk Creek Ranch I would go shooting,
or ride up toward the entrance of the canyon and watch the men working on the irrigation ditches.
Pleasant systems of water running in channels were being led through the soil, and there was a sound of rippling here and there among the yellow grain; the green thick alfalfa grass waved almost, it seemed, of its own accord,
for the wind never blew; and when at evening the sun lay against the plain, the rift of the canyon was filled with a violet light, and the Bow Leg Mountains became transfigured with hues of floating and unimaginable color.
The sun shone in a sky where never a cloud came, and noon was
not too warm nor the dark too cool.
And so for two months I went through these pleasant uneventful days, improving the chickens,
an object of mirth, living in the open air, and basking in the perfection of content.
I was justly styled a tenderfoot.
Mrs. Henry had in the beginning endeavored to shield me from this humiliation; but when she found that I was inveterate in laying my inexperience of Western matters bare to all the world, begging to be enlightened upon rattlesnakes, prairie-dogs, owls, blue and willow grouse, sage-hens, how to rope a horse or tighten the front cinch of my saddle,
and that my spirit soared into enthusiasm at the mere sight of so ordinary an animal as a white-tailed deer, she let me rush about with my firearms and made no further effort to stave off the ridicule that my blunders perpetually earned from the ranch hands, her own humorous husband, and any chance visitor who stopped for a meal or stayed the night.
I was not called by my name after the first feeble etiquette
due to a stranger in his first few hours had died away.
I was known simply as “the tenderfoot.”
I was introduced to the neighborhood (a circle of eighty miles)
as “the tenderfoot.”
It was thus that Balaam, the maltreater of horses, learned to
address me when he came a two days’ journey to pay a visit.
And it was this name and my notorious helplessness that bid fair
to end what relations I had with the Virginian.
For when Judge Henry ascertained that nothing could prevent me from losing myself, that it was not uncommon for me to
saunter out after breakfast with a gun and in thirty minutes cease to know north from south, he arranged for my protection.
He detailed an escort for me; and the escort was once more the
trustworthy man!
The poor Virginian was taken from his work and his comrades and
set to playing nurse for me.
And for a while this humiliation ate into his untamed soul.
It was his lugubrious lot to accompany me in my rambles, preside over
my blunders, and save me from calamitously passing into the next world.
He bore it in courteous silence, except when speaking was necessary.
He would show me the lower ford, which I could never find for
myself, generally mistaking a quicksand for it.
He would tie my horse properly.
He would recommend me not to shoot my rifle at a white-tailed deer in the particular moment
that the outfit wagon was passing behind the animal on the further side of the brush.
There was seldom a day that he was not obliged to hasten and
save me from sudden death or from ridicule, which is worse.
Yet never once did he lose his patience and his gentle, slow voice, and apparently lazy manner remained the same, whether we were sitting at lunch together, or up in the
mountain during a hunt, or whether he was bringing me back my horse, which had run away because I had again forgotten to throw the reins over his head and let them trail.
“He’ll always stand if yu’ do that,” the Virginian would say.
“See how my hawss stays right quiet yondeh.”
After such admonition he would say no more to me.
But this tame nursery business was assuredly gall to him.
For though utterly a man in countenance and in his self-possession and incapacity to be put at a loss, he was
still boyishly proud of his wild calling, and wore his leather straps and jingled his spurs with obvious pleasure.
His tiger limberness and his beauty were rich with unabated youth; and that force
which lurked beneath his surface must often have curbed his intolerance of me.
In spite of what I knew must be his opinion of me, the tenderfoot, my liking
for him grew, and I found his silent company more and more agreeable.
That he had spells of talking, I had already learned at Medicine
Bow.
But his present taciturnity might almost have effaced this impression, had I not happened to pass by the
bunk-house one evening after dark, when Honey Wiggin and the rest of the cowboys were gathered inside it.
That afternoon the Virginian and I had gone duck shooting.
We had found several in a beaver dam, and I had killed two as they sat close together; but they floated against the
breastwork of sticks out in the water some four feet deep, where the escaping current might carry them down the stream.
The Judge’s red setter had not accompanied us, because she was
expecting a family.
“We don’t want her along anyways,” the cowpuncher had explained
to me.
“She runs around mighty irresponsible, and she’ll stand a prairie-dog
’bout as often as she’ll stand a bird.
She’s a triflin’ animal.”
My anxiety to own the ducks caused me to pitch into the water with all my
clothes on, and subsequently crawl out a slippery, triumphant, weltering heap.
The Virginian’s serious eyes had rested upon this spectacle of
mud; but he expressed nothing, as usual.
“They ain’t overly good eatin’,” he observed, tying the birds
to his saddle.
“They’re divers.”
“Divers!” I exclaimed.
“Why didn’t they dive?”
“I reckon they was young ones and hadn’t experience.”
“Well,” I said, crestfallen, but attempting to be humorous, “I
did the diving myself.”
But the Virginian made no comment.
He handed me my double-barrelled English gun, which I was about to leave deserted on the ground behind me, and
we rode home in our usual silence, the mean little white-breasted, sharp-billed divers dangling from his saddle.
It was in the bunk-house that he took his revenge.
As I passed I heard his gentle voice silently achieving some narrative to an attentive audience, and just as I came by the open window where he sat on his
bed in shirt and drawers, his back to me, I heard his concluding words, “And the hat on his haid was the one mark showed yu’ he weren’t a snappin’-turtle.”
The anecdote met with instantaneous success, and I hurried away
into the dark.
The next morning I was occupied with the chickens.
Two hens were fighting to sit on some eggs that a third was daily laying, and which I did not want hatched, and for the third time
I had kicked Em’ly off seven potatoes she had rolled together and was determined to raise I know not what sort of family from.
She was shrieking about the henhouse as the Virginian came in to observe (I suspect)
what I might be doing now that could be useful for him to mention in the bunk-house.
He stood awhile, and at length said, “We lost our best rooster
when Mrs. Henry came to live hyeh.”
I paid no attention.
“He was a right elegant Dominicker,” he continued.
I felt a little riled about the snapping-turtle, and showed no interest
in what he was saying, but continued my functions among the hens.
This unusual silence of mine seemed to elicit unusual speech
from him.
“Yu’ see, that rooster he’d always lived round hyeh when the Judge was a
bachelor, and he never seen no ladies or any persons wearing female gyarments.
You ain’t got rheumatism, seh?”
“Me? No.”
“I reckoned maybe them little odd divers yu’ got damp goin’ afteh⁠—”
He paused.
“Oh, no, not in the least, thank you.”
“Yu’ seemed sort o’ grave this mawnin’, and I’m cert’nly glad
it ain’t them divers.”
“Well, the rooster?” I inquired finally.
“Oh, him!
He weren’t raised where he could see petticoats.
Mrs. Henry she come hyeh from the railroad with the Judge afteh
dark.
Next mawnin’ early she walked out to view her new home, and the
rooster was a-feedin’ by the door, and he seen her.
Well, seh, he screeched that awful I run out of the bunk-house; and he jus’
went over the fence and took down Sunk Creek shoutin’ fire, right along.
He has never come back.”
“There’s a hen over there now that has no judgment,” I said,
indicating Em’ly.
She had got herself outside the house, and was on the bars of
a corral, her vociferations reduced to an occasional squawk.
I told him about the potatoes.
“I never knowed her name before,” said he.
“That runaway rooster, he hated her. And she hated him same as
she hates ’em all.”
“I named her myself,” said I, “after I came to notice her particularly.
There’s an old maid at home who’s charitable, and belongs to the Cruelty to Animals,
and she never knows whether she had better cross in front of a street car or wait.
I named the hen after her.
Does she ever lay eggs?”
The Virginian had not “troubled his haid” over the poultry.
“Well, I don’t believe she knows how. I think she came near being
a rooster.”
“She’s sure manly-lookin’,” said the Virginian.
We had walked toward the corral, and he was now scrutinizing
Em’ly with interest.
She was an egregious fowl.
She was huge and gaunt, with great yellow beak, and she stood
straight and alert in the manner of responsible people.
There was something wrong with her tail.
It slanted far to one side, one feather in it twice as long as
the rest.
Feathers on her breast there were none.
These had been worn entirely off by her habit of sitting upon
potatoes and other rough abnormal objects.
And this lent to her appearance an air of being décollete, singularly
at variance with her otherwise prudish ensemble.
Her eye was remarkably bright, but somehow it had an outraged
expression.
It was as if she went about the world perpetually scandalized
over the doings that fell beneath her notice.
Her legs were blue, long, and remarkably stout.
“She’d ought to wear knickerbockers,” murmured the Virginian.
“She’d look a heap better ’n some o’ them college students. And
she’ll set on potatoes, yu’ say?”
“She thinks she can hatch out anything.
I’ve found her with onions, and last Tuesday I caught her on
two balls of soap.”
In the afternoon the tall cowpuncher and I rode out to get an
antelope.
After an hour, during which he was completely taciturn, he said: “I reckon
maybe this hyeh lonesome country ain’t been healthy for Em’ly to live in.
It ain’t for some humans.
Them old trappers in the mountains gets skewed in the haid mighty
often, an’ talks out loud when nobody’s nigher ’n a hundred miles.”
“Em’ly has not been solitary,” I replied.
“There are forty chickens here.”
“That’s so,” said he.
“It don’t explain her.”
He fell silent again, riding beside me, easy and indolent in
the saddle.
His long figure looked so loose and inert that the swift, light
spring he made to the ground seemed an impossible feat.
He had seen an antelope where I saw none.
“Take a shot yourself,” I urged him, as he motioned me to be
quick.
“You never shoot when I’m with you.”
“I ain’t hyeh for that,” he answered.
“Now you’ve let him get away on yu’!”
The antelope had in truth departed.
“Why,” he said to my protest, “I can hit them things any day.
What’s your notion as to Em’ly?”
“I can’t account for her,” I replied.
“Well,” he said musingly, and then his mind took one of those
particular turns that made me love him, “Taylor ought to see her.
She’d be just the schoolmarm for Bear Creek!”
“She’s not much like the eating-house lady at Medicine Bow,”
I said.
He gave a hilarious chuckle.
“No, Em’ly knows nothing o’ them joys.
So yu’ have no notion about her?
Well, I’ve got one.
I reckon maybe she was hatched after a big thunderstorm.”
“In a big thunderstorm!” I exclaimed.
“Yes.
Don’t yu’ know about them, and what they’ll do to aiggs?
A big case o’ lightnin’ and thunder will addle aiggs and keep
’em from hatchin’.
And I expect one came along, and all the other aiggs of Em’ly’s set didn’t hatch out, but got plumb
addled, and she happened not to get addled that far, and so she just managed to make it through.
But she cert’nly ain’t got a strong haid.”
“I fear she has not,” said I.
“Mighty hon’ble intentions,” he observed.
“If she can’t make out to lay anything, she wants to hatch somethin’,
and be a mother anyways.”
“I wonder what relation the law considers that a hen is to the
chicken she hatched but did not lay?” I inquired.
The Virginian made no reply to this frivolous suggestion.
He was gazing over the wide landscape gravely and with apparent
inattention.
He invariably saw game before I did, and was off his horse and crouched
among the sage while I was still getting my left foot clear of the stirrup.
I succeeded in killing an antelope, and we rode home with the
head and hind quarters.
“No,” said he.
“It’s sure the thunder, and not the lonesomeness. How do yu’
like the lonesomeness yourself?”
I told him that I liked it.
“I could not live without it now,” he said.
“This has got into my system.”
He swept his hand out at the vast space of world.
“I went back home to see my folks onced.
Mother was dyin’ slow, and she wanted me.
I stayed a year.
But them Virginia mountains could please me no more.
Afteh she was gone, I told my brothers and sisters goodbye.
We like each other well enough, but I reckon I’ll not go back.”
We found Em’ly seated upon a collection of green California peaches,
which the Judge had brought from the railroad.
“I don’t mind her any more,” I said; “I’m sorry for her.”
“I’ve been sorry for her right along,” said the Virginian.
“She does hate the roosters so.”
And he said that he was making a collection of every class of
object which he found her treating as eggs.
But Em’ly’s egg-industry was terminated abruptly one morning,
and her unquestioned energies diverted to a new channel.
A turkey which had been sitting in the root-house appeared with twelve
children, and a family of bantams occurred almost simultaneously.
Em’ly was importantly scratching the soil inside Paladin’s corral when the bantam tribe
of newly born came by down the lane, and she caught sight of them through the bars.
She crossed the corral at a run, and intercepted two of the chicks
that were trailing somewhat behind their real mamma.
These she undertook to appropriate, and assumed a high tone with the bantam, who
was the smaller, and hence obliged to retreat with her still numerous family.
I interfered, and put matters straight; but the adjustment was
only temporary.
In an hour I saw Em’ly immensely busy with two more bantams, leading them
about and taking a care of them which I must admit seemed perfectly efficient.
And now came the first incident that made me suspect her to be
demented.
She had proceeded with her changelings behind the kitchen, where one of the irrigation
ditches ran under the fence from the hayfield to supply the house with water.
Some distance along this ditch inside the field were the twelve
turkeys in the short, recently cut stubble.
Again Em’ly set off instantly like a deer.
She left the dismayed bantams behind her.
She crossed the ditch with one jump of her stout blue legs, flew over the grass, and was at once among the turkeys,
where, with an instinct of maternity as undiscriminating as it was reckless, she attempted to huddle some of them away.
But this other mamma was not a bantam, and in a few moments Em’ly was
entirely routed in her attempt to acquire a new variety of family.
This spectacle was witnessed by the Virginian and myself, and
it overcame him.
He went speechless across to the bunk-house, by himself, and sat on
his bed, while I took the abandoned bantams back to their own circle.
I have often wondered what the other fowls thought of all this.
Some impression it certainly did make upon them.
The notion may seem out of reason to those who have never closely attended to other animals than man; but I am convinced that any community which
shares some of our instincts will share some of the resulting feelings, and that birds and beasts have conventions, the breach of which startles them.
If there be anything in evolution, this would seem inevitable.
At all events, the chicken-house was upset during the following
several days.
Em’ly disturbed now the bantams and now the turkeys, and several of these latter had died,
though I will not go so far as to say that this was the result of her misplaced attentions.
Nevertheless, I was seriously thinking of locking her up till the broods should
be a little older, when another event happened, and all was suddenly at peace.
The Judge’s setter came in one morning, wagging her tail.
She had had her puppies, and she now took us to where they were
housed, in between the floor of a building and the hollow ground.
Em’ly was seated on the whole litter.
“No,” I said to the Judge, “I am not surprised.
She is capable of anything.”
In her new choice of offspring, this hen had at length encountered
an unworthy parent.
The setter was bored by her own puppies.
She found the hole under the house an obscure and monotonous residence compared with the
dining room, and our company more stimulating and sympathetic than that of her children.
A much-petted contact with our superior race had developed her dog intelligence above its natural level, and
turned her into an unnatural, neglectful mother, who was constantly forgetting her nursery for worldly pleasures.
At certain periods of the day she repaired to the puppies and fed them, but came away when this
perfunctory ceremony was accomplished; and she was glad enough to have a governess bring them up.
She made no quarrel with Em’ly, and the two understood each other
perfectly.
I have never seen among animals any arrangement so civilized
and so perverted.
It made Em’ly perfectly happy.
To see her sitting all day jealously spreading her wings over some blind puppies was sufficiently curious; but when they became
large enough to come out from under the house and toddle about in the proud hen’s wake, I longed for some distinguished naturalist.
I felt that our ignorance made us inappropriate spectators of
such a phenomenon.
Em’ly scratched and clucked, and the puppies ran to her, pawed her with their fat
limp little legs, and retreated beneath her feathers in their games of hide and seek.
Conceive, if you can, what confusion must have reigned in their
infant minds as to who the setter was!
“I reckon they think she’s the wet-nurse,” said the Virginian.
When the puppies grew to be boisterous, I perceived that Em’ly’s
mission was approaching its end.
They were too heavy for her, and their increasing scope of playfulness
was not in her line.
Once or twice they knocked her over, upon which she arose and pecked them severely,
and they retired to a safe distance, and sitting in a circle, yapped at her.
I think they began to suspect that she was only a hen after all.
So Em’ly resigned with an indifference which surprised me, until I remembered that
if it had been chickens, she would have ceased to look after them by this time.
But here she was again “out of a job,” as the Virginian said.
“She’s raised them puppies for that triflin’ setter, and now she’ll be
huntin’ around for something else useful to do that ain’t in her business.”
Now there were other broods of chickens to arrive in the henhouse,
and I did not desire any more bantam and turkey performances.
So, to avoid confusion, I played a trick upon Em’ly.
I went down to Sunk Creek and fetched some smooth, oval stones.
She was quite satisfied with these, and passed a quiet day with
them in a box.
This was not fair, the Virginian asserted.
“You ain’t going to jus’ leave her fooled that a-way?”
I did not see why not.
“Why, she raised them puppies all right.
Ain’t she showed she knows how to be a mother anyways?
Em’ly ain’t going to get her time took up for nothing while I’m
round hyeh,” said the cowpuncher.
He laid a gentle hold of Em’ly and tossed her to the ground.
She, of course, rushed out among the corrals in a great state
of nerves.
“I don’t see what good you do meddling,” I protested.
To this he deigned no reply, but removed the unresponsive stones
from the straw.
“Why, if they ain’t right warm!” he exclaimed plaintively.
“The poor, deluded son-of-a-gun!”
And with this unusual description of a lady, he sent the stones
sailing like a line of birds.
“I’m regular getting stuck on Em’ly,” continued the Virginian.
“Yu’ needn’t to laugh.
Don’t yu’ see she’s got sort o’ human feelin’s and desires?
I always knowed hawsses was like people, and my collie, of course.
It is kind of foolish, I expect, but that hen’s goin’ to have
a real aigg directly, right now, to set on.”
With this he removed one from beneath another hen.
“We’ll have Em’ly raise this hyeh,” said he, “so she can put
in her time profitable.”
It was not accomplished at once; for Em’ly, singularly enough,
would not consent to stay in the box whence she had been routed.
At length we found another retreat for her, and in these new surroundings, with a new piece of work
for her to do, Em’ly sat on the one egg which the Virginian had so carefully provided for her.
Thus, as in all genuine tragedies, was the stroke of Fate wrought
by chance and the best intentions.
Em’ly began sitting on Friday afternoon near sundown.
Early next morning my sleep was gradually dispersed by a sound
unearthly and continuous.
Now it dwindled, receding to a distance; again it came near, took a turn, drifted to the other side
of the house; then, evidently, whatever it was, passed my door close, and I jumped upright in my bed.
The high, tense strain of vibration, nearly, but not quite, a musical note, was like the
threatening scream of machinery, though weaker, and I bounded out of the house in my pajamas.
There was Em’ly, dishevelled, walking wildly about, her one egg
miraculously hatched within ten hours.
The little lonely yellow ball of down went cheeping along behind,
following its mother as best it could.
What, then, had happened to the established period of incubation?
For an instant the thing was like a portent, and I was near
joining Em’ly in her horrid surprise, when I saw how it all was.
The Virginian had taken an egg from a hen which had already been
sitting for three weeks.
I dressed in haste, hearing Em’ly’s distracted outcry.
It steadily sounded, without perceptible pause for breath, and marked
her erratic journey back and forth through stables, lanes, and corrals.
The shrill disturbance brought all of us out to see her, and in the
henhouse I discovered the new brood making its appearance punctually.
But this natural explanation could not be made to the crazed
hen.
She continued to scour the premises, her slant tail and its one preposterous feather waving as she aimlessly went, her stout legs stepping high with an
unnatural motion, her head lifted nearly off her neck, and in her brilliant yellow eye an expression of more than outrage at this overturning of a natural law.
Behind her, entirely ignored and neglected, trailed the little
progeny.
She never looked at it.
We went about our various affairs, and all through the clear,
sunny day that unending metallic scream pervaded the premises.
The Virginian put out food and water for her, but she tasted
nothing.
I am glad to say that the little chicken did.
I do not think that the hen’s eyes could see, except in the way
that sleepwalkers’ do.
The heat went out of the air, and in the canyon the violet light
began to show.
Many hours had gone, but Em’ly never ceased.
Now she suddenly flew up in a tree and sat there with her noise still going; but it had risen lately several notes into
a slim, acute level of terror, and was not like machinery any more, nor like any sound I ever heard before or since.
Below the tree stood the bewildered little chicken, cheeping,
and making tiny jumps to reach its mother.
“Yes,” said the Virginian, “it’s comical.
Even her aigg acted different from anybody else’s.”
He paused, and looked across the wide, mellowing plain with the
expression of easygoing gravity so common with him.
Then he looked at Em’ly in the tree and the yellow chicken.
“It ain’t so damned funny,” said he.
We went in to supper, and I came out to find the hen lying on
the ground, dead.
I took the chicken to the family in the henhouse.
No, it was not altogether funny any more.
And I did not think less of the Virginian when I came upon him
surreptitiously digging a little hole in the field for her.
“I have buried some citizens here and there,” said he, “that
I have respected less.”
And when the time came for me to leave Sunk Creek, my last word
to the Virginian was, “Don’t forget Em’ly.”
“I ain’t likely to,” responded the cowpuncher.
“She is just one o’ them parables.”
Save when he fell into his native idioms (which, they told me, his wanderings had well-nigh obliterated until that year’s visit
to his home again revived them in his speech), he had now for a long while dropped the “seh,” and all other barriers between us.
We were thorough friends, and had exchanged many confidences
both of the flesh and of the spirit.
He even went the length of saying that he would write me the
Sunk Creek news if I would send him a line now and then.
I have many letters from him now.
Their spelling came to be faultless, and in the beginning was
little worse than George Washington’s.
The Judge himself drove me to the railroad by another way⁠—across the Bow
Leg Mountains, and south through Balaam’s Ranch and Drybone to Rock Creek.
“I’ll be very homesick,” I told him.
“Come and pull the latchstring whenever you please,” he bade
me.
I wished that I might!
No lotus land ever cast its spell upon man’s heart more than
Wyoming had enchanted mine.
CHAPTER VII
Through Two Snows
Dear Friend [thus in the spring the Virginian wrote me], Yours
received.
It must be a poor thing to be sick.
That time I was shot at Cañada de Oro would have made me sick if
it had been a littel lower or if I was much of a drinking man.
You will be well if you give over city life and take a hunt with me about
August or say September for then the elk will be out of the velvett.
Things do not please me here just now and I am going to settel
it by vamosing.
But I would be glad to see you.
It would be pleasure not business for me to show you plenty elk
and get you strong.
I am not crybabying to the Judge or making any kick about things.
He will want me back after he has swallowed a litter tincture
of time.
It is the best dose I know.
Now to answer your questions.
Yes the Emmily hen might have ate loco weed if hens do.
I never saw anything but stock and horses get poisoned with loco
weed.
No the school is not built yet.
They are always big talkers on Bear Creek.
No I have not seen Steve.
He is around but I am sorry for him.
Yes I have been to Medicine Bow.
I had the welcom I wanted.
Do you remember a man I played poker and he did not like it?
He is working on the upper ranch near Ten Sleep.
He does not amount to a thing except with weaklings.
Uncle Hewie has twins.
The boys got him vexed some about it, but I think they are his.
Now that is all I know today and I would like to see you poco
presently as they say at Los Cruces.
There’s no sense in you being sick.
The rest of this letter discussed the best meeting point for
us should I decide to join him for a hunt.
That hunt was made, and during the weeks of its duration something was said to explain a little more fully the
Virginian’s difficulty at the Sunk Creek Ranch, and his reason for leaving his excellent employer the Judge.
Not much was said, to be sure; the Virginian seldom spent many
words upon his own troubles.
But it appeared that owing to some jealousy of him on the part of the foreman, or the assistant foreman, he found himself
continually doing another man’s work, but under circumstances so skilfully arranged that he got neither credit nor pay for it.
He would not stoop to telling tales out of school.
Therefore his ready and prophetic mind devised the simple expedient
of going away altogether.
He calculated that Judge Henry would gradually perceive there was a
connection between his departure and the cessation of the satisfactory work.
After a judicious interval it was his plan to appear again in
the neighborhood of Sunk Creek and await results.
Concerning Steve he would say no more than he had written.
But it was plain that for some cause this friendship had ceased.
Money for his services during the hunt he positively declined to
accept, asserting that he had not worked enough to earn his board.
And the expedition ended in an untravelled corner of the Yellowstone Park, near Pitchstone Canyon, where he
and young Lin McLean and others were witnesses of a sad and terrible drama that has been elsewhere chronicled.
His prophetic mind had foreseen correctly the shape of events
at Sunk Creek.
The only thing that it had not foreseen was the impression to
be made upon the Judge’s mind by his conduct.
Toward the close of that winter, Judge and Mrs. Henry visited
the East.
Through them a number of things became revealed.
The Virginian was back at Sunk Creek.
“And,” said Mrs. Henry, “he would never have left you if I had
had my way, Judge H.!”
“No, Madam Judge,” retorted her husband; “I am aware of that.
For you have always appreciated a fine appearance in a man.”
“I certainly have,” confessed the lady, mirthfully.
“And the way he used to come bringing my horse, with the ridges of his black hair so carefully brushed and that blue
spotted handkerchief tied so effectively round his throat, was something that I missed a great deal after he went away.”
“Thank you, my dear, for this warning.
I have plans that will keep him absent quite constantly for the
future.”
And then they spoke less flightily.
“I always knew,” said the lady, “that you had found a treasure
when that man came.”
The Judge laughed.
“When it dawned on me,” he said, “how cleverly he caused me to learn the value of his
services by depriving me of them, I doubted whether it was safe to take him back.”
“Safe!” cried Mrs. Henry.
“Safe, my dear.
Because I’m afraid he is pretty nearly as shrewd as I am.
And that’s rather dangerous in a subordinate.”
The Judge laughed again.
“But his action regarding the man they call Steve has made me
feel easy.”
And then it came out that the Virginian was supposed to have discovered in some way that Steve
had fallen from the grace of that particular honesty which respects another man’s cattle.
It was not known for certain.
But calves had begun to disappear in Cattle Land, and cows had
been found killed.
And calves with one brand upon them had been found with mothers
that bore the brand of another owner.
This industry was taking root in Cattle Land, and of those who
practised it, some were beginning to be suspected.
Steve was not quite fully suspected yet.
But that the Virginian had parted company with him was definitely
known.
And neither man would talk about it.
There was the further news that the Bear Creek schoolhouse at length stood complete, floor, walls, and roof; and that a lady from
Bennington, Vermont, a friend of Mrs. Balaam’s, had quite suddenly decided that she would try her hand at instructing the new generation.
The Judge and Mrs. Henry knew this because Mrs. Balaam had told them of her disappointment that she would
be absent from the ranch on Butte Creek when her friend arrived, and therefore unable to entertain her.
The friend’s decision had been quite suddenly made, and must
form the subject of the next chapter.
CHAPTER VIII
The Sincere Spinster
I do not know with which of the two estimates⁠—Mr. Taylor’s or
the Virginian’s⁠—you agreed.
Did you think that Miss Mary Stark Wood of Bennington, Vermont,
was forty years of age?
That would have been an error.
At the time she wrote the letter to Mrs. Balaam, of which letter certain portions have been quoted in these
pages, she was in her twenty-first year; or, to be more precise, she had been twenty some eight months previous.
Now, it is not usual for young ladies of twenty to contemplate a journey of nearly two thousand miles to a country where Indians and wild
animals live unchained, unless they are to make such journey in company with a protector, or are going to a protector’s arms at the other end.
Nor is school teaching on Bear Creek a usual ambition for such
young ladies.
But Miss Mary Stark Wood was not a usual young lady for two reasons.
First, there was her descent.
Had she so wished, she could have belonged to any number of those patriotic
societies of which our American ears have grown accustomed to hear so much.
She could have been enrolled in the Boston Tea Party, the Ethan Allen Ticonderogas, the Green
Mountain Daughters, the Saratoga Sacred Circle, and the Confederated Colonial Chatelaines.
She traced direct descent from the historic lady whose name she bore, that Molly Stark who was not a widow after the battle where
her lord, her Captain John, battled so bravely as to send his name thrilling down through the blood of generations of schoolboys.
This ancestress was her chief claim to be a member of those shining
societies which I have enumerated.
But she had been willing to join none of them, although invitations
to do so were by no means lacking.
I cannot tell you her reason.
Still, I can tell you this.
When these societies were much spoken of in her presence, her very sprightly countenance
became more sprightly, and she added her words of praise or respect to the general chorus.
But when she received an invitation to join one of these bodies, her countenance, as she read the
missive, would assume an expression which was known to her friends as “sticking her nose in the air.”
I do not think that Molly’s reason for refusing to join could
have been a truly good one.
I should add that her most precious possession⁠—a treasure which accompanied her even if she went away for only one night’s absence⁠—was
an heirloom, a little miniature portrait of the old Molly Stark, painted when that far-off dame must have been scarce more than twenty.
And when each summer the young Molly went to Dunbarton, New Hampshire, to pay her established family visit to the last survivors of her connection who bore the name of Stark, no
word that she heard in the Dunbarton houses pleased her so much as when a certain great-aunt would take her by the hand, and, after looking with fond intentness at her, pronounce:⁠—
“My dear, you’re getting more like the General’s wife every year
you live.”
“I suppose you mean my nose,” Molly would then reply.
“Nonsense, child. You have the family length of nose, and I’ve
never heard that it has disgraced us.”
“But I don’t think I’m tall enough for it.”
“There now, run to your room, and dress for tea. The Starks have
always been punctual.”
And after this annual conversation, Molly would run to her room, and there in its privacy, even at the risk of falling
below the punctuality of the Starks, she would consult two objects for quite a minute before she began to dress.
These objects, as you have already correctly guessed, were the
miniature of the General’s wife and the looking glass.
So much for Miss Molly Stark Wood’s descent.
The second reason why she was not a usual girl was her character.
This character was the result of pride and family pluck battling
with family hardship.
Just one year before she was to be presented to the world⁠—not the great metropolitan world, but a world that would have made her welcome
and done her homage at its little dances and little dinners in Troy and Rutland and Burlington⁠—fortune had turned her back upon the Woods.
Their possessions had never been great ones; but they had sufficed.
From generation to generation the family had gone to school like gentlefolk, dressed like
gentlefolk, used the speech and ways of gentlefolk, and as gentlefolk lived and died.
And now the mills failed.
Instead of thinking about her first evening dress, Molly found
pupils to whom she could give music lessons.
She found handkerchiefs that she could embroider with initials.
And she found fruit that she could make into preserves.
That machine called the typewriter was then in existence, but the day of women typewriters had as yet scarcely
begun to dawn, else I think Molly would have preferred this occupation to the handkerchiefs and the preserves.
There were people in Bennington who “wondered how Miss Wood could
go about from house to house teaching the piano, and she a lady.”
There always have been such people, I suppose, because the world
must always have a rubbish heap.
But we need not dwell upon them further than to mention one other
remark of theirs regarding Molly.
They all with one voice declared that Sam Bannett was good enough
for anybody who did fancy embroidery at five cents a letter.
“I dare say he had a great-grandmother quite as good as hers,”
remarked Mrs. Flynt, the wife of the Baptist minister.
“That’s entirely possible,” returned the Episcopal rector of
Hoosic, “only we don’t happen to know who she was.”
The rector was a friend of Molly’s.
After this little observation, Mrs. Flynt said no more, but continued her purchases
in the store where she and the rector had happened to find themselves together.
Later she stated to a friend that she had always thought the
Episcopal Church a snobbish one, and now she knew it.
So public opinion went on being indignant over Molly’s conduct.
She could stoop to work for money, and yet she pretended to hold herself above the most rising
young man in Hoosic Falls, and all just because there was a difference in their grandmothers!
Was this the reason at the bottom of it?
The very bottom?
I cannot be certain, because I have never been a girl myself.
Perhaps she thought that work is not a stooping, and that marriage
may be.
Perhaps⁠—But all I really know is that Molly Wood continued cheerfully to embroider the
handkerchiefs, make the preserves, teach the pupils⁠—and firmly to reject Sam Bannett.
Thus it went on until she was twenty.
There certain members of her family began to tell her how rich
Sam was going to be⁠—was, indeed, already.
It was at this time that she wrote Mrs. Balaam her doubts and
her desires as to migrating to Bear Creek.
It was at this time also that her face grew a little paler, and her friends
thought that she was overworked, and Mrs. Flynt feared she was losing her looks.
It was at this time, too, that she grew very intimate with that great-aunt
over at Dunbarton, and from her received much comfort and strengthening.
“Never!” said the old lady, “especially if you can’t love him.”
“I do like him,” said Molly; “and he is very kind.”
“Never!” said the old lady again.
“When I die, you’ll have something⁠—and that will not be long
now.”
Molly flung her arms around her aunt, and stopped her words with
a kiss.
And then one winter afternoon, two years later, came the last
straw.
The front door of the old house had shut.
Out of it had stepped the persistent suitor.
Mrs. Flynt watched him drive away in his smart sleigh.
“That girl is a fool!” she said furiously; and she came away from
her bedroom window where she had posted herself for observation.
Inside the old house a door had also shut.
This was the door of Molly’s own room.
And there she sat, in floods of tears.
For she could not bear to hurt a man who loved her with all the
power of love that was in him.
It was about twilight when her door opened, and an elderly lady
came softly in.
“My dear,” she ventured, “and you were not able⁠—”
“Oh, mother!” cried the girl, “have you come to say that too?”
The next day Miss Wood had become very hard.
In three weeks she had accepted the position on Bear Creek.
In two months she started, heart-heavy, but with a spirit craving
the unknown.
CHAPTER IX
The Spinster Meets the Unknown
On a Monday noon a small company of horsemen strung out along the trail
from Sunk Creek to gather cattle over their allotted sweep of range.
Spring was backward, and they, as they rode galloping and gathering
upon the cold week’s work, cursed cheerily and occasionally sang.
The Virginian was grave in bearing and of infrequent speech;
but he kept a song going⁠—a matter of some seventy-nine verses.
Seventy-eight were quite unprintable, and rejoiced his brother
cowpunchers monstrously.
They, knowing him to be a singular man, forebore ever to press him, and awaited his own humor, lest he should weary
of the lyric; and when after a day of silence apparently saturnine, he would lift his gentle voice and begin:⁠—
“If you go to monkey with my Looloo girl,I’ll tell you what I’ll do:I’ll
cyarve your heart with my razor, andI’ll shoot you with my pistol, too⁠—”
then they would stridently take up each last line, and keep it going
three, four, ten times, and kick holes in the ground to the swing of it.
By the levels of Bear Creek that reach like inlets among the promontories of the lonely
hills, they came upon the schoolhouse, roofed and ready for the first native Wyoming crop.
It symbolized the dawn of a neighborhood, and it brought a change
into the wilderness air.
The feel of it struck cold upon the free spirits of the cowpunchers, and they told each other that,
what with women and children and wire fences, this country would not long be a country for men.
They stopped for a meal at an old comrade’s.
They looked over his gate, and there he was pattering among garden
furrows.
“Pickin’ nosegays?” inquired the Virginian and the old comrade
asked if they could not recognize potatoes except in the dish.
But he grinned sheepishly at them, too, because they knew that
he had not always lived in a garden.
Then he took them into his house, where they saw an object crawling
on the floor with a handful of sulphur matches.
He began to remove the matches, but stopped in alarm at the vociferous result; and
his wife looked in from the kitchen to caution him about humoring little Christopher.
When she beheld the matches she was aghast but when she saw her baby grow quiet in
the arms of the Virginian, she smiled at that cowpuncher and returned to her kitchen.
Then the Virginian slowly spoke again:⁠—
“How many little strangers have yu’ got, James?”
“Only two.”
“My! Ain’t it most three years since yu’ maried? Yu’ mustn’t
let time creep ahaid o’ yu’, James.”
The father once more grinned at his guests, who themselves turned sheepish and
polite; for Mrs. Westfall came in, brisk and hearty, and set the meat upon the table.
After that, it was she who talked.
The guests ate scrupulously, muttering, “Yes, ma’am,” and “No, ma’am,” in their plates, while their hostess told them of increasing families upon
Bear Creek, and the expected schoolteacher, and little Alfred’s early teething, and how it was time for all of them to become husbands like James.
The bachelors of the saddle listened, always diffident, but eating
heartily to the end; and soon after they rode away in a thoughtful clump.
The wives of Bear Creek were few as yet, and the homes scattered; the schoolhouse was only a sprig on the vast face of a world of elk and bear and uncertain Indians;
but that night, when the earth near the fire was littered with the cowpunchers’ beds, the Virginian was heard drawling to himself: “Alfred and Christopher. Oh, sugar!”
They found pleasure in the delicately chosen shade of this oath.
He also recited to them a new verse about how he took his Looloo girl to the schoolhouse for to learn her A.B.C.; and as it
was quite original and unprintable, the camp laughed and swore joyfully, and rolled in its blankets to sleep under the stars.
Upon a Monday noon likewise (for things will happen so) some tearful people in
petticoats waved handkerchiefs at a train that was just leaving Bennington, Vermont.
A girl’s face smiled back at them once, and withdrew quickly,
for they must not see the smile die away.
She had with her a little money, a few clothes, and in her mind a rigid determination
neither to be a burden to her mother nor to give in to that mother’s desires.
Absence alone would enable her to carry out this determination.
Beyond these things, she possessed not much except spelling-books, a colonial
miniature, and that craving for the unknown which has been mentioned.
If the ancestors that we carry shut up inside us take turns in dictating to us our actions and
our state of mind, undoubtedly Grandmother Stark was empress of Molly’s spirit upon this Monday.
At Hoosic Junction, which came soon, she passed the up-train bound back to her home, and seeing the engineer and the conductor⁠—faces that
she knew well⁠—her courage nearly failed her, and she shut her eyes against this glimpse of the familiar things that she was leaving.
To keep herself steady she gripped tightly a little bunch of
flowers in her hand.
But something caused her eyes to open; and there before her stood Sam
Bannett, asking if he might accompany her so far as Rotterdam Junction.
“No!” she told him with a severity born from the struggle she
was making with her grief.
“Not a mile with me. Not to Eagle Bridge. Goodbye.”
And Sam⁠—what did he do?
He obeyed her, I should like to be sorry for him.
But obedience was not a lover’s part here.
He hesitated, the golden moment hung hovering, the conductor cried “All aboard!” the train went,
and there on the platform stood obedient Sam, with his golden moment gone like a butterfly.
After Rotterdam Junction, which was some forty minutes farther, Molly
Wood sat bravely up in the through car, dwelling upon the unknown.
She thought that she had attained it in Ohio, on Tuesday morning,
and wrote a letter about it to Bennington.
On Wednesday afternoon she felt sure, and wrote a letter much
more picturesque.
But on the following day, after breakfast at North Platte, Nebraska, she wrote a very long letter indeed, and told them that she
had seen a black pig on a white pile of buffalo bones, catching drops of water in the air as they fell from the railroad tank.
She also wrote that trees were extraordinarily scarce.
Each hour westward from the pig confirmed this opinion, and when she left the train at Rock Creek, late upon that fourth night⁠—in those days
the trains were slower⁠—she knew that she had really attained the unknown, and sent an expensive telegram to say that she was quite well.
At six in the morning the stage drove away into the sagebrush, with her as its only
passenger; and by sundown she had passed through some of the primitive perils of the world.
The second team, virgin to harness, and displeased with this novelty, tried to take it off, and went down to
the bottom of a gully on its eight hind legs, while Miss Wood sat mute and unflinching beside the driver.
Therefore he, when it was over, and they on the proper road again, invited her earnestly to be his wife
during many of the next fifteen miles, and told her of his snug cabin and his horses and his mine.
Then she got down and rode inside, Independence and Grandmother
Stark shining in her eye.
At Point of Rocks, where they had supper and his drive ended, her face distracted his heart,
and he told her once more about his cabin, and lamentably hoped she would remember him.
She answered sweetly that she would try, and gave him her hand.
After all, he was a frank-looking boy, who had paid her the highest compliment that a boy (or
a man for that matter) knows; and it is said that Molly Stark, in her day, was not a New Woman.
The new driver banished the first one from the maiden’s mind.
He was not a frank-looking boy, and he had been taking whiskey.
All night long he took it, while his passenger, helpless and sleepless
inside the lurching stage, sat as upright as she possibly could; nor
did the voices that she heard at Drybone reassure her.
Sunrise found the white stage lurching eternally on across the alkali, with a driver and a bottle on the
box, and a pale girl staring out at the plain, and knotting in her handkerchief some utterly dead flowers.
They came to a river where the man bungled over the ford.
Two wheels sank down over an edge, and the canvas toppled like
a descending kite.
The ripple came sucking through the upper spokes, and as she felt the seat
careen, she put out her head and tremulously asked if anything was wrong.
But the driver was addressing his team with much language, and
also with the lash.
Then a tall rider appeared close against the buried axles, and took
her out of the stage on his horse so suddenly that she screamed.
She felt splashes, saw a swimming flood, and found herself lifted
down upon the shore.
The rider said something to her about cheering up, and its being all
right, but her wits were stock-still, so she did not speak and thank him.
After four days of train and thirty hours of stage, she was having
a little too much of the unknown at once.
Then the tall man gently withdrew leaving her to become herself
again.
She limply regarded the river pouring round the slanted stage, and a number of horsemen with ropes, who righted
the vehicle, and got it quickly to dry land, and disappeared at once with a herd of cattle, uttering lusty yells.
She saw the tall one delaying beside the driver, and speaking.
He spoke so quietly that not a word reached her, until of a sudden
the driver protested loudly.
The man had thrown something, which turned out to be a bottle.
This twisted loftily and dived into the stream.
He said something more to the driver, then put his hand on the saddle-horn, looked half-lingeringly at the passenger on the bank, dropped his grave eyes from
hers, and swinging upon his horse, was gone just as the passenger opened her mouth and with inefficient voice murmured, “Oh, thank you!” at his departing back.
The driver drove up now, a chastened creature.
He helped Miss Wood in, and inquired after her welfare with a hanging head; then meek as his own drenched horses, he
climbed back to his reins, and nursed the stage on toward the Bow Leg Mountains much as if it had been a perambulator.
As for Miss Wood, she sat recovering, and she wondered what the
man on the horse must think of her.
She knew that she was not ungrateful, and that if he had given
her an opportunity she would have explained to him.
If he supposed that she did not appreciate his act⁠—Here into the midst of these
meditations came an abrupt memory that she had screamed⁠—she could not be sure when.
She rehearsed the adventure from the beginning, and found one or two further
uncertainties⁠—how it had all been while she was on the horse, for instance.
It was confusing to determine precisely what she had done with
her arms.
She knew where one of his arms had been.
And the handkerchief with the flowers was gone.
She made a few rapid dives in search of it.
Had she, or had she not, seen him putting something in his pocket?
And why had she behaved so unlike herself?
In a few miles Miss Wood entertained sentiments of maidenly
resentment toward her rescuer, and of maidenly hope to see him again.
To that river crossing he came again, alone, when the days were
growing short.
The ford was dry sand, and the stream a winding lane of shingle.
He found a pool⁠—pools always survive the year round in this stream⁠—and having watered
his pony, he lunched near the spot to which he had borne the frightened passenger that day.
Where the flowing current had been he sat, regarding the now
extremely safe channel.
“She cert’nly wouldn’t need to grip me so close this mawnin’,”
he said, as he pondered over his meal.
“I reckon it will mightily astonish her when I tell her how harmless
the torrent is lookin’.”
He held out to his pony a slice of bread matted with sardines,
which the pony expertly accepted.
“You’re a plumb pie-biter you Monte,” he continued.
Monte rubbed his nose on his master’s shoulder.
“I wouldn’t trust you with berries and cream. No, seh; not though
yu’ did rescue a drownin’ lady.”
Presently he tightened the forward cinch, got in the saddle, and the pony fell into his wise mechanical
jog; for he had come a long way, and was going a long way, and he knew this as well as the man did.
To use the language of Cattle Land, steers had “jumped to seventy-five.”
This was a great and prosperous leap in their value.
To have flourished in that golden time you need not be dead now, nor even middle-aged;
but it is Wyoming mythology already⁠—quite as fabulous as the high-jumping cow.
Indeed, people gathered together and behaved themselves much
in the same pleasant and improbable way.
Johnson County, and Natrona, and Converse, and others, to say nothing of the Cheyenne Club, had been jumping over the moon for some weeks, all on account of
steers; and on the strength of this vigorous price of seventy-five, the Stanton Brothers were giving a barbecue at the Goose Egg outfit, their ranch on Bear Creek.
Of course the whole neighborhood was bidden, and would come forty miles to a
man; some would come further⁠—the Virginian was coming a hundred and eighteen.
It had struck him⁠—rather suddenly, as shall be made plain⁠—that he
should like to see how they were getting along up there on Bear Creek.
“They,” was how he put it to his acquaintances.
His acquaintances did not know that he had bought himself a pair of
trousers and a scarf, unnecessarily excellent for such a general visit.
They did not know that in the spring, two days after the adventure with
the stage, he had learned accidentally who the lady in the stage was.
This he had kept to himself; nor did the camp ever notice that he had ceased to sing
that eightieth stanza he had made about the A.B.C.⁠—the stanza which was not printable.
He effaced it imperceptibly, giving the boys the other seventy-nine
at judicious intervals.
They dreamed of no guile, but merely saw in him, whether frequenting camp or town,
the same not over-angelic comrade whom they valued and could not wholly understand.
All spring he had ridden trail, worked at ditches during summer,
and now he had just finished with the beef roundup.
Yesterday, while he was spending a little comfortable money at the Drybone hog-ranch, a casual traveller from the north gossiped of Bear Creek, and the
fences up there, and the farm crops, the Westfalls, and the young schoolmarm from Vermont, for whom the Taylors had built a cabin next door to theirs.
The traveller had not seen her, but Mrs. Taylor and all the ladies thought
the world of her, and Lin McLean had told him she was “away up in G.”
She would have plenty of partners at this Swinton barbecue.
Great boon for the country, wasn’t it, steers jumping that way?
The Virginian heard, asking no questions; and left town in an hour,
with the scarf and trousers tied in his slicker behind his saddle.
After looking upon the ford again, even though it was dry and
not at all the same place, he journeyed in attentively.
When you have been hard at work for months with no time to think,
of course you think a great deal during your first empty days.
“Step along, you Monte hawss!” he said, rousing after some while.
He disciplined Monte, who flattened his ears affectedly and snorted.
“Why, you surely ain’ thinkin’ of you’-self as a hero? She wasn’t
really a-drowndin’, you pie-biter.”
He rested his serious glance upon the alkali.
“She’s not likely to have forgot that mix-up, though.
I guess I’ll not remind her about grippin’ me, and all that.
She wasn’t the kind a man ought to josh about such things.
She had a right clear eye.”
Thus, tall and loose in the saddle, did he jog along the sixty
miles which still lay between him and the dance.
CHAPTER X
Where Fancy Was Bred
Two camps in the open, and the Virginian’s Monte horse, untired,
brought him to the Swintons’ in good time for the barbecue.
The horse received good food at length, while his rider was welcomed
with good whiskey.
Good whiskey⁠—for had not steers jumped to seventy-five?
Inside the Goose Egg kitchen many small delicacies were preparing,
and a steer was roasting whole outside.
The bed of flame under it showed steadily brighter against the
dusk that was beginning to veil the lowlands.
The busy hosts went and came, while men stood and men lay near
the fire-glow.
Chalkeye was there, and Nebrasky, and Trampas, and Honey Wiggin, with others, enjoying the occasion;
but Honey Wiggin was enjoying himself: he had an audience; he was sitting up discoursing to it.
“Hello!” he said, perceiving the Virginian.
“So you’ve dropped in for your turn! Number⁠—six, ain’t he, boys?”
“Depends who’s a-runnin’ the countin’,” said the Virginian, and
stretched himself down among the audience.
“I’ve saw him number one when nobody else was around,” said Trampas.
“How far away was you standin’ when you beheld that?” inquired
the lounging Southerner.
“Well, boys,” said Wiggin, “I expect it will be Miss Schoolmarm
says who’s number one tonight.”
“So she’s arrived in this hyeh country?” observed the Virginian,
very casually.
“Arrived!” said Trampas again.
“Where have you been grazing lately?”
“A right smart way from the mules.”
“Nebrasky and the boys was tellin’ me they’d missed yu’ off the
range,” again interposed Wiggin.
“Say, Nebrasky, who have yu’ offered your canary to the schoolmarm
said you mustn’t give her?”
Nebrasky grinned wretchedly.
“Well, she’s a lady, and she’s square, not takin’ a man’s gift
when she don’t take the man.
But you’d ought to get back all them letters yu’ wrote her.
Yu’ sure ought to ask her for them telltales.”
“Ah, pshaw, Honey!” protested the youth.
It was well known that he could not write his name.
“Why, if here ain’t Bokay Baldy!” cried the agile Wiggin, stooping
to fresh prey.
“Found them slippers yet, Baldy?
Tell yu’ boys, that was turruble sad luck Baldy had.
Did yu’ hear about that?
Baldy, yu’ know, he can stay on a tame horse most as well as
the schoolmarm.
But just you give him a pair of young knittin’-needles and see
him make ’em sweat!
He worked an elegant pair of slippers with pink cabbages on ’em
for Miss Wood.”
“I bought ’em at Medicine Bow,” blundered Baldy.
“So yu’ did!” assented the skilful comedian.
“Baldy he bought ’em.
And on the road to her cabin there at the Taylors’ he got
thinkin’ they might be too big, and he got studyin’ what to do.
And he fixed up to tell her about his not bein’ sure of the size, and how she was to let him know if they
dropped off her, and he’d exchange ’em, and when he got right near her door, why, he couldn’t find his courage.
And so he slips the parcel under the fence and starts serenadin’
her.
But she ain’t inside her cabin at all.
She’s at supper next door with the Taylors, and Baldy singin’
‘Love has conqwered pride and angwer’ to a lone house.
Lin McLean was comin’ up by Taylor’s corral, where Taylor’s Texas
bull was.
Well, it was turruble sad.
Baldy’s pants got tore, but he fell inside the fence, and Lin
druv the bull back and somebody stole them Medicine Bow galoshes.
Are you goin’ to knit her some more, Bokay?”
“About half that ain’t straight,” Baldy commented, with mildness.
“The half that was tore off yer pants? Well, never mind, Baldy;
Lin will get left too, same as all of yu’.”
“Is there many?” inquired the Virginian.
He was still stretched on his back, looking up at the sky.
“I don’t know how many she’s been used to where she was raised,”
Wiggin answered.
“A kid stage-driver come from Point of Rocks one day and went
back the next.
Then the foreman of the 76 outfit, and the horse-wrangler from the Bar-Circle-L,
and two deputy marshals, with punchers, stringin’ right along⁠—all got their tumble.
Old Judge Burrage from Cheyenne come up in August for a hunt
and stayed round here and never hunted at all.
There was that horse thief⁠—awful good-lookin’.
Taylor wanted to warn her about him, but Mrs. Taylor said she’d
look after her if it was needed.
Mr. Horse-thief gave it up quicker than most; but the schoolmarm couldn’t have
knowed he had a Mrs. Horse-thief camped on Poison Spider till afterwards.
She wouldn’t go ridin’ with him.
She’ll go with some, takin’ a kid along.”
“Bah!” said Trampas.
The Virginian stopped looking at the sky, and watched Trampas
from where he lay.
“I think she encourages a man some,” said poor Nebrasky.
“Encourages? Because she lets yu’ teach her how to shoot,” said
Wiggin.
“Well⁠—I don’t guess I’m a judge.
I’ve always kind o’ kep’ away from them good women.
Don’t seem to think of anything to chat about to ’em.
The only folks I’d say she encourages is the school kids.
She kisses them.”
“Riding and shooting and kissing the kids,” sneered Trampas.
“That’s a heap too pussy-kitten for me.”
They laughed.
The sagebrush audience is readily cynical.
“Look for the man, I say,” Trampas pursued.
“And ain’t he there? She leaves Baldy sit on the fence while
she and Lin McLean⁠—”
They laughed loudly at the blackguard picture which he drew; and
the laugh stopped short, for the Virginian stood over Trampas.
“You can rise up now, and tell them you lie,” he said.
The man was still for a moment in the dead silence.
“I thought you claimed you and her wasn’t acquainted,” said he
then.
“Stand on your laigs, you polecat, and say you’re a liar!”
Trampas’s hand moved behind him.
“Quit that,” said the Southerner, “or I’ll break your neck!”
The eye of a man is the prince of deadly weapons.
Trampas looked in the Virginian’s, and slowly rose.
“I didn’t mean⁠—” he began, and paused, his face poisonously
bloated.
“Well, I’ll call that sufficient.
Keep a-standin’ still.
I ain’ going to trouble yu’ long.
In admittin’ yourself to be a liar you have spoke God’s truth
for onced.
Honey Wiggin, you and me and the boys have hit town too frequent
for any of us to play Sunday on the balance of the gang.”
He stopped and surveyed Public Opinion, seated around in carefully
inexpressive attention.
“We ain’t a Christian outfit a little bit, and maybe we have
most forgotten what decency feels like.
But I reckon we haven’t forgot what it means.
You can sit down now, if you want.”
The liar stood and sneered experimentally, looking at Public
Opinion.
But this changeful deity was no longer with him, and he heard it variously
assenting, “That’s so,” and “She’s a lady,” and otherwise excellently moralizing.
So he held his peace.
When, however, the Virginian had departed to the roasting steer, and Public Opinion relaxed into that comfort which we
all experience when the sermon ends, Trampas sat down amid the reviving cheerfulness, and ventured again to be facetious.
“Shut your rank mouth,” said Wiggin to him, amiably.
“I don’t care whether he knows her or if he done it on principle.
I’ll accept the roundin’ up he gave us⁠—and say!
You’ll swallo’ your dose, too!
Us boys’ll stand in with him in this.”
So Trampas swallowed.
And what of the Virginian?
He had championed the feeble, and spoken honorably in meeting, and according to all the
constitutions and bylaws of morality, he should have been walking in virtue’s especial calm.
But there it was!
he had spoken; he had given them a peep through the keyhole at his inner man; and as he prowled away from
the assemblage before whom he stood convicted of decency, it was vicious rather than virtuous that he felt.
Other matters also disquieted him⁠—so Lin McLean was hanging
round that schoolmarm!
Yet he joined Ben Swinton in a seemingly Christian spirit.
He took some whiskey and praised the size of the barrel, speaking
with his host like this:⁠—
“There cert’nly ain’ goin’ to be trouble about a second helpin’.”
“Hope not. We’d ought to have more trimmings, though. We’re shy
on ducks.”
“Yu’ have the barrel. Has Lin McLean seen that?”
“No. We tried for ducks away down as far as the Laparel outfit.
A real barbecue⁠—”
“There’s large thirsts on Bear Creek. Lin McLean will pass on
ducks.”
“Lin’s not thirsty this month.”
“Signed for one month, has he?”
“Signed! He’s spooning our schoolmarm!”
“They claim she’s a right sweet-faced girl.”
“Yes; yes; awful agreeable. And next thing you’re fooled clean
through.”
“Yu’ don’t say!”
“She keeps a-teaching the darned kids, and it seems like a good
growed-up man can’t interest her.”
“Yu’ don’t say!”
“There used to be all the ducks you wanted at the Laparel, but
their fool cook’s dead stuck on raising turkeys this year.”
“That must have been mighty close to a drowndin’ the schoolmarm
got at South Fork.”
“Why, I guess not. When? She’s never spoken of any such thing⁠—that
I’ve heard.”
“Mos’ likely the stage-driver got it wrong, then.”
“Yes.
Must have drownded somebody else.
Here they come!
That’s her ridin’ the horse.
There’s the Westfalls.
Where are you running to?”
“To fix up. Got any soap around hyeh?”
“Yes,” shouted Swinton, for the Virginian was now some distance
away; “towels and everything in the dugout.”
And he went to welcome his first formal guests.
The Virginian reached his saddle under a shed.
“So she’s never mentioned it,” said he, untying his slicker for
the trousers and scarf.
“I didn’t notice Lin anywheres around her.”
He was over in the dugout now, whipping off his overalls; and soon he was excellently
clean and ready, except for the tie in his scarf and the part in his hair.
“I’d have knowed her in Greenland,” he remarked.
He held the candle up and down at the looking-glass, and the
looking-glass up and down at his head.
“It’s mighty strange why she ain’t mentioned that.”
He worried the scarf a fold or two further, and at length, a trifle more than satisfied
with his appearance, he proceeded most serenely toward the sound of the tuning fiddles.
He passed through the storeroom behind the kitchen, stepping lightly lest he
should rouse the ten or twelve babies that lay on the table or beneath it.
On Bear Creek babies and children always went with their parents
to a dance, because nurses were unknown.
So little Alfred and Christopher lay there among the wraps, parallel and crosswise with little Taylors, and little Carmodys, and
Lees, and all the Bear Creek offspring that was not yet able to skip at large and hamper its indulgent elders in the ballroom.
“Why, Lin ain’t hyeh yet!” said the Virginian, looking in upon
the people.
There was Miss Wood, standing up for the quadrille.
“I didn’t remember her hair was that pretty,” said he.
“But ain’t she a little, little girl!”
Now she was in truth five feet three; but then he could look
away down on the top of her head.
“Salute your honey!” called the first fiddler.
All partners bowed to each other, and as she turned, Miss Wood
saw the man in the doorway.
Again, as it had been at South Fork that day, his eyes dropped from hers, and she divining instantly why he had come after half a year, thought of
the handkerchief and of that scream of hers in the river, and became filled with tyranny and anticipation; for indeed he was fine to look upon.
So she danced away, carefully unaware of his existence.
“First lady, centre!” said her partner, reminding her of her
turn.
“Have you forgotten how it goes since last time?”
Molly Wood did not forget again, but quadrilled with the most
sprightly devotion.
“I see some new faces tonight,” said she, presently.
“Yu’ always do forget our poor faces,” said her partner.
“Oh, no! There’s a stranger now. Who is that black man?”
“Well⁠—he’s from Virginia, and he ain’t allowin’ he’s black.”
“He’s a tenderfoot, I suppose?”
“Ha, ha, ha! That’s rich, too!” and so the simple partner explained
a great deal about the Virginian to Molly Wood.
At the end of the set she saw the man by the door take a step
in her direction.
“Oh,” said she, quickly, to the partner, “how warm it is!
I must see how those babies are doing.”
And she passed the Virginian in a breeze of unconcern.
His eyes gravely lingered where she had gone.
“She knowed me right away,” said he.
He looked for a moment, then leaned against the door.
“ ’How warm it is!’ said she.
Well, it ain’t so screechin’ hot hyeh; and as for rushin’ after Alfred and Christopher, when their natural motheh
is bumpin’ around handy⁠—she cert’nly can’t be offended?” he broke off, and looked again where she had gone.
And then Miss Wood passed him brightly again, and was dancing
the schottische almost immediately.
“Oh, yes, she knows me,” the swarthy cowpuncher mused.
“She has to take trouble not to see me. And what she’s a-fussin’
at is mighty interestin’. Hello!”
“Hello!” returned Lin McLean, sourly.
He had just looked into the kitchen.
“Not dancin’?” the Southerner inquired.
“Don’t know how.”
“Had scyarlet fever and forgot your past life?”
Lin grinned.
“Better persuade the schoolmarm to learn it. She’s goin’ to give
me instruction .”
“Huh!” went Mr. McLean, and skulked out to the barrel.
“Why, they claimed you weren’t drinkin’ this month!” said his
friend, following.
“Well, I am. Here’s luck!”
The two pledged in tin cups.
“But I’m not waltzin’ with her,” blurted Mr. McLean grievously.
“She called me an exception.”
“Waltzin’,” repeated the Virginian quickly, and hearing the fiddles
he hastened away.
Few in the Bear Creek Country could waltz, and with these few it was mostly an unsteered
and ponderous exhibition; therefore was the Southerner bent upon profiting by his skill.
He entered the room, and his lady saw him come where she sat
alone for the moment, and her thoughts grew a little hurried.
“Will you try a turn, ma’am?”
“I beg your pardon?”
It was a remote, well-schooled eye that she lifted now upon him.
“If you like a waltz, ma’am, will you waltz with me?”
“You’re from Virginia, I understand?” said Molly Wood, regarding
him politely, but not rising.
One gains authority immensely by keeping one’s seat.
All good teachers know this.
“Yes, ma’am, from Virginia.”
“I’ve heard that Southerners have such good manners.”
“That’s correct.”
The cowpuncher flushed, but he spoke in his unvaryingly gentle
voice.
“For in New England, you know,” pursued Miss Molly, noting his scarf and clean-shaven chin, and then
again steadily meeting his eye, “gentlemen ask to be presented to ladies before they ask them to waltz.”
He stood a moment before her, deeper and deeper scarlet; and the
more she saw his handsome face, the keener rose her excitement.
She waited for him to speak of the river; for then she was going to be
surprised, and gradually to remember, and finally to be very nice to him.
But he did not wait.
“I ask your pardon, lady,” said he, and bowing, walked off, leaving
her at once afraid that he might not come back.
But she had altogether mistaken her man.
Back he came serenely with Mr. Taylor, and was duly presented
to her.
Thus were the conventions vindicated.
It can never be known what the cowpuncher was going to say next; for Uncle Hughey stepped up with a
glass of water which he had left Wood to bring, and asking for a turn, most graciously received it.
She danced away from a situation where she began to feel herself
getting the worst of it.
One moment the Virginian stared at his lady as she lightly circulated,
and then he went out to the barrel.
Leave him for Uncle Hershey!
Jealousy is a deep and delicate thing, and works its spite in
many ways.
The Virginian had been ready to look at Lin McLean with a hostile eye; but finding him now beside the barrel,
he felt a brotherhood between himself and Lin, and his hostility had taken a new and whimsical direction.
“Here’s how!” said he to McLean.
And they pledged each other in the tin cups.
“Been gettin’ them instructions?” said Mr. McLean, grinning.
“I thought I saw yu’ learning your steps through the window.”
“Here’s your good health,” said the Southerner.
Once more they pledged each other handsomely.
“Did she call you an exception, or anything?” said Lin.
“Well, it would cipher out right close in that neighborhood.”
“Here’s how, then!” cried the delighted Lin, over his cup.
“Jest because yu’ happen to come from Vermont,” continued Mr.
McLean, “is no cause for extra pride.
Shoo!
I was raised in Massachusetts myself, and big men have been raised there,
too⁠—Daniel Webster and Israel Putnam: and a lot of them politicians.”
“Virginia is a good little old state,” observed the Southerner.
“Both of ’em’s a sight ahead of Vermont. She told me I was the
first exception she’d struck.”
“What rule were you provin’ at the time, Lin?”
“Well yu’ see, I started to kiss her.”
“Yu’ didn’t!”
“Shucks! I didn’t mean nothin’.”
“I reckon yu’ stopped mighty sudden?”
“Why, I’d been ridin’ out with her⁠—ridin’ to school, ridin’ from school, and a-comin’ and a-goin’, and she
chattin’ cheerful and askin’ me a heap o’ questions all about myself every day, and I not lyin’ much neither.
And so I figured she wouldn’t mind.
Lots of ’em like it.
But she didn’t, you bet!”
“No,” said the Virginian, deeply proud of his lady who had slighted
him.
He had pulled her out of the water once, and he had been her unrewarded knight even today, and he felt his grievance; but he
spoke not of it to Lin; for he felt also, in memory, her arms clinging round him as he carried her ashore upon his horse.
But he muttered, “Plumb ridiculous!” as her injustice struck
him afresh, while the outraged McLean told his tale.
“Trample is what she has done on me tonight, and without notice.
We was startin’ to come here; Taylor and Mrs. were ahead in the buggy, and I was
holdin’ her horse, and helpin’ her up in the saddle, like I done for days and days.
Who was there to see us?
And I figured she’d not mind, and she calls me an exception!
Yu’d ought to’ve just heard her about Western men respectin’
women.
So that’s the last word we’ve spoke.
We come twenty-five miles then, she scootin’ in front, and her
horse kickin’ the sand in my face.
Mrs. Taylor, she guessed something was up, but she didn’t tell.”
“Miss Wood did not tell?”
“Not she! She’ll never open her head. She can take care of herself,
you bet!”
The fiddles sounded hilariously in the house, and the feet also.
They had warmed up altogether, and their dancing figures crossed
the windows back and forth.
The two cowpunchers drew near to a window and looked in gloomily.
“There she goes,” said Lin.
“With Uncle Hughey again,” said the Virginian, sourly.
“Yu’ might suppose he didn’t have a wife and twins, to see the
way he goes gambollin’ around.”
“Westfall is takin’ a turn with her now,” said McLean.
“James!” exclaimed the Virginian.
“He’s another with a wife and fam’ly, and he gets the dancin’,
too.”
“There she goes with Taylor,” said Lin, presently.
“Another married man!” the Southerner commented.
They prowled round to the storeroom, and passed through the kitchen
to where the dancers were robustly tramping.
Miss Wood was still the partner of Mr. Taylor.
“Let’s have some whiskey,” said the Virginian.
They had it, and returned, and the Virginian’s disgust and sense
of injury grew deeper.
“Old Carmody has got her now,” he drawled.
“He polkas like a landslide.
She learns his monkey-faced kid to spell dog and cow all the
mawnin’.
He’d ought to be tucked up cozy in his bed right now, old Carmody
ought.”
They were standing in that place set apart for the sleeping children; and just at
this moment one of two babies that were stowed beneath a chair uttered a drowsy note.
A much louder cry, indeed a chorus of lament, would have been needed to reach the
ears of the parents in the room beyond, such was the noisy volume of the dance.
But in this quiet place the light sound caught Mr. McLean’s attention,
and he turned to see if anything were wrong.
But both babies were sleeping peacefully.
“Them’s Uncle Hughey’s twins,” he said.
“How do you happen to know that?” inquired the Virginian, suddenly
interested.
“Saw his wife put ’em under the chair so she could find ’em right
off when she come to go home.”
“Oh,” said the Virginian, thoughtfully.
“Oh, find ’em right off. Yes. Uncle Hughey’s twins.”
He walked to a spot from which he could view the dance.
“Well,” he continued, returning, “the schoolmarm must have taken
quite a notion to Uncle Hughey.
He has got her for this quadrille.”
The Virginian was now speaking without rancor; but his words came with
a slightly augmented drawl, and this with him was often a bad omen.
He now turned his eyes upon the collected babies wrapped in various
colored shawls and knitted work.
“Nine, ten, eleven, beautiful sleepin’ strangers,” he counted,
in a sweet voice.
“Any of ’em your’n, Lin?”
“Not that I know of,” grinned Mr. McLean.
“Eleven, twelve.
This hyeh is little Christopher in the blue-stripe quilt⁠—or
maybe that other yello’-head is him.
The angels have commenced to drop in on us right smart along
Bear Creek, Lin.”
“What trash are yu’ talkin’ anyway?”
“If they look so awful alike in the heavenly gyarden,” the gentle Southerner continued,
“I’d just hate to be the folks that has the cuttin’ of ’em out o’ the general herd.
And that’s a right quaint notion too,” he added softly.
“Them under the chair are Uncle Hughey’s, didn’t you tell me?”
And stooping, he lifted the torpid babies and placed them beneath
a table.
“No, that ain’t thorough,” he murmured.
With wonderful dexterity and solicitude for their welfare, he removed the loose
wrap which was around them, and this soon led to an intricate process of exchange.
For a moment Mr. McLean had been staring at the Virginian, puzzled.
Then, with a joyful yelp of enlightenment, he sprang to abet
him.
And while both busied themselves with the shawls and quilts, the unconscious parents went
dancing vigorously on, and the small, occasional cries of their progeny did not reach them.
CHAPTER XI
“You’re Going to Love Me Before We Get Through”
The Swinton barbecue was over.
The fiddles were silent, the steer was eaten, the barrel emptied, or largely so, and the tapers extinguished; round the house and sunken
fire all movement of guests was quiet; the families were long departed homeward, and after their hospitable turbulence, the Swintons slept.
Mr. and Mrs. Westfall drove through the night, and as they neared their
cabin there came from among the bundled wraps a still, small voice.
“Jim,” said his wife, “I said Alfred would catch cold.”
“Bosh! Lizzie, don’t you fret. He’s a little more than a yearlin’,
and of course he’ll snuffle.”
And young James took a kiss from his love.
“Well, how you can speak of Alfred that way, calling him a yearling, as if he
was a calf, and he just as much your child as mine, I don’t see, James Westfall!”
“Why, what under the sun do you mean?”
“There he goes again! Do hurry up home, Jim. He’s got a real
strange cough.”
So they hurried home.
Soon the nine miles were finished, and good James was unhitching by his stable
lantern, while his wife in the house hastened to commit their offspring to bed.
The traces had dropped, and each horse marched forward for further
unbuckling, when James heard himself called.
Indeed, there was that in his wife’s voice which made him jerk
out his pistol as he ran.
But it was no bear or Indian⁠—only two strange children on the
bed.
His wife was glaring at them.
He sighed with relief and laid down the pistol.
“Put that on again, James Westfall. You’ll need it. Look here!”
“Well, they won’t bite. Whose are they? Where have you stowed
ourn?”
“Where have I⁠—” Utterance forsook this mother for a moment.
“And you ask me!” she continued.
“Ask Lin McLean.
Ask him that sets bulls on folks and steals slippers, what he’s done with our
innocent lambs, mixing them up with other people’s coughing, unhealthy brats.
That’s Charlie Taylor in Alfred’s clothes, and I know Alfred didn’t cough like that, and I said to you it
was strange; and the other one that’s been put in Christopher’s new quilts is not even a bub⁠—bub⁠—boy!”
As this crime against society loomed clear to James Westfall’s understanding, he sat down on the nearest piece
of furniture, and heedless of his wife’s tears and his exchanged children, broke into unregenerate laughter.
Doubtless after his sharp alarm about the bear, he was unstrung.
His lady, however, promptly restrung him; and by the time they had repacked the now clamorous changelings, and were
rattling on their way to the Taylors’, he began to share her outraged feelings properly, as a husband and a father should;
but when he reached the Taylors’ and learned from Miss Wood that at this house a child had been unwrapped whom nobody could at all identify, and that Mr.
and Mrs. Taylor were already far on the road to the Swintons’, James Westfall whipped up his horses and grew almost as thirsty for revenge as was his wife.
Where the steer had been roasted, the powdered ashes were now cold white, and Mr. McLean, feeling through his
dreams the change of dawn come over the air, sat up cautiously among the outdoor slumberers and waked his neighbor.
“Day will be soon,” he whispered, “and we must light out of this.
I never suspicioned yu’ had that much of the devil in you before.”
“I reckon some of the fellows will act haidstrong,” the
Virginian murmured luxuriously, among the warmth of his blankets.
“I tell yu’ we must skip,” said Lin, for the second time; and
he rubbed the Virginian’s black head, which alone was visible.
“Skip, then, you,” came muffled from within, “and keep you’self
mighty sca’ce till they can appreciate our frolic.”
The Southerner withdrew deeper into his bed, and Mr. McLean,
informing him that he was a fool, arose and saddled his horse.
From the saddlebag, he brought a parcel, and lightly laying this
beside Bokay Baldy, he mounted and was gone.
When Baldy awoke later, he found the parcel to be a pair of flowery
slippers.
In selecting the inert Virginian as the fool, Mr. McLean was
scarcely wise; it is the absent who are always guilty.
Before ever Lin could have been a mile in retreat, the rattle
of the wheels roused all of them, and here came the Taylors.
Before the Taylors’ knocking had brought the Swintons to their door, other wheels sounded, and here were Mr. and Mrs. Carmody, and Uncle Hughey with his wife, and close
after them Mr. Dow, alone, who told how his wife had gone into one of her fits⁠—she upon whom Dr. Barker at Drybone had enjoined total abstinence from all excitement.
Voices of women and children began to be uplifted; the Westfalls
arrived in a lather, and the Thomases;
and by sunrise, what with fathers and mothers and spectators and loud offspring, there was
gathered such a meeting as has seldom been before among the generations of speaking men.
Today you can hear legends of it from Texas to Montana; but I
am giving you the full particulars.
Of course they pitched upon poor Lin.
Here was the Virginian doing his best, holding horses and helping ladies
descend, while the name of McLean began to be muttered with threats.
Soon a party led by Mr. Dow set forth in search of him, and the Southerner
debated a moment if he had better not put them on a wrong track.
But he concluded that they might safely go on searching.
Mrs. Westfall found Christopher at once in the green shawl of Anna
Maria Dow, but all was not achieved thus in the twinkling of an eye.
Mr. McLean had, it appeared, as James Westfall lugubriously pointed out, not merely “swapped
the duds; he had shuffled the whole doggone deck;” and they cursed this Satanic invention.
The fathers were but of moderate assistance; it was the mothers who did the heavy work; and by ten o’clock some unsolved problems grew
so delicate that a ladies’ caucus was organized in a private room⁠—no admittance for men⁠—and what was done there I can only surmise.
During its progress the search party returned.
It had not found Mr. McLean.
It had found a tree with a notice pegged upon it, reading, “God
bless our home!”
This was captured.
But success attended the caucus; each mother emerged, satisfied that she had received her own,
and each sire, now that his family was itself again, began to look at his neighbor sideways.
After a man has been angry enough to kill another man, after the fire of righteous slaughter has raged in his heart
as it had certainly raged for several hours in the hearts of these fathers, the flame will usually burn itself out.
This will be so in a generous nature, unless the cause of the
anger is still unchanged.
But the children had been identified; none had taken hurt.
All had been humanely given their nourishment.
The thing was over.
The day was beautiful.
A tempting feast remained from the barbecue.
These Bear Creek fathers could not keep their ire at red heat.
Most of them, being as yet more their wives’ lovers than their
children’s parents
, began to see the mirthful side of the adventure; and they ceased
to feel very severely toward Lin McLean.
Not so the women.
They cried for vengeance; but they cried in vain, and were met
with smiles.
Mrs. Westfall argued long that punishment should be dealt the
offender.
“Anyway,” she persisted, “it was real defiant of him putting
that up on the tree.
I might forgive him but for that.”
“Yes,” spoke the Virginian in their midst, “that wasn’t sort
o’ right.
Especially as I am the man you’re huntin’.”
They sat dumb at his assurance.
“Come and kill me,” he continued, round upon the party.
“I’ll not resist.”
But they could not resist the way in which he had looked round
upon them.
He had chosen the right moment for his confession, as a captain
of a horse awaits the proper time for a charge.
Some rebukes he did receive; the worst came from the mothers.
And all that he could say for himself was, “I am getting off
too easy.”
“But what was your point?” said Westfall.
“Blamed if I know any more. I expect it must have been the whiskey.”
“I would mind it less,” said Mrs. Westfall, “if you looked a
bit sorry or ashamed.”
The Virginian shook his head at her penitently.
“I’m tryin’ to,” he said.
And thus he sat disarming his accusers until they began to lunch
upon the copious remnants of the barbecue.
He did not join them at this meal.
In telling you that Mrs. Dow was the only lady absent upon this
historic morning, I was guilty of an inadvertence.
There was one other.
The Virginian rode away sedately through the autumn sunshine;
and as he went he asked his Monte horse a question.
“Do yu’ reckon she’ll have forgotten you too, you pie-biter?”
said he.
Instead of the new trousers, the cowpuncher’s leathern chaps
were on his legs.
But he had the new scarf knotted at his neck.
Most men would gladly have equalled him in appearance.
“You Monte,” said he, “will she be at home?”
It was Sunday, and no school day, and he found her in her cabin
that stood next the Taylors’ house.
Her eyes were very bright.
“I’d thought I’d just call,” said he.
“Why, that’s such a pity! Mr. and Mrs. Taylor are away.”
“Yes; they’ve been right busy. That’s why I thought I’d call.
Will yu’ come for a ride, ma’am?”
“Dear me! I⁠—”
“You can ride my hawss. He’s gentle.”
“What! And you walk?”
“No, ma’am. Nor the two of us ride him this time, either.”
At this she turned entirely pink, and he, noticing, went on quietly:
“I’ll catch up one of Taylor’s hawsses.
Taylor knows me.”
“No.
I don’t really think I could do that.
But thank you.
Thank you very much.
I must go now and see how Mrs. Taylor’s fire is.”
“I’ll look after that, ma’am.
I’d like for yu’ to go ridin’ mighty well.
Yu’ have no babies this mawnin’ to be anxious after.”
At this shaft, Grandmother Stark flashed awake deep within the
spirit of her descendant, and she made a haughty declaration of war.
“I don’t know what you mean, sir,” she said.
Now was his danger; for it was easy to fall into mere crude
impertinence and ask her why, then, did she speak thus abruptly?
There were various easy things of this kind for him to say.
And any rudeness would have lost him the battle.
But the Virginian was not the man to lose such a battle in such
a way.
His shaft had hit.
She thought he referred to those babies about whom last night
she had shown such superfluous solicitude.
Her conscience was guilty.
This was all that he had wished to make sure of before he began
operations.
“Why, I mean,” said he, easily, sitting down near the door, “that
it’s Sunday.
School don’t hinder yu’ from enjoyin’ a ride today.
You’ll teach the kids all the better for it tomorro’, ma’am.
Maybe it’s your duty.”
And he smiled at her.
“My duty! It’s quite novel to have strangers⁠—”
“Am I a stranger?” he cut in, firing his first broadside.
“I was introduced, ma’am,” he continued, noting how she had flushed
again.
“And I would not be oversteppin’ for the world. I’ll go away
if yu’ want.”
And hereupon he quietly rose, and stood, hat in hand.
Molly was flustered.
She did not at all want him to go.
No one of her admirers had ever been like this creature.
The fringed leathern chaparreros, the cartridge belt, the flannel shirt,
the knotted scarf at the neck, these things were now an old story to her.
Since her arrival she had seen young men and old in plenty dressed
thus.
But worn by this man now standing by her door, they seemed to
radiate romance.
She did not want him to go⁠—and she wished to win her battle.
And now in her agitation she became suddenly severe, as she had
done at Hoosic Junction.
He should have a punishment to remember!
“You call yourself a man, I suppose,” she said.
But he did not tremble in the least.
Her fierceness filled him with delight, and the tender desire
of ownership flooded through him.
“A grown-up, responsible man,” she repeated.
“Yes, ma’am. I think so.”
He now sat down again.
“And you let them think that⁠—that Mr. McLean⁠—You dare not look
me in the face and say that Mr. McLean did that last night!”
“I reckon I dassent.”
“There! I knew it! I said so from the first!”
“And me a stranger to you!” he murmured.
It was his second broadside.
It left her badly crippled.
She was silent.
“Who did yu’ mention it to, ma’am?”
She hoped she had him.
“Why, are you afraid?”
And she laughed lightly.
“I told ’em myself.
And their astonishment seemed so genu-wine I’d just hate to think they had
fooled me that thorough when they knowed it all along from you seeing me.”
“I did not see you.
I knew it must⁠—of course I did not tell anyone.
When I said I said so from the first, I meant⁠—you can understand
perfectly what I meant.”
“Yes, ma’am.”
Poor Molly was near stamping her foot.
“And what sort of a trick,” she rushed on, “was that to play?
Do you call it a manly thing to frighten and distress women because
you⁠—for no reason at all?
I should never have imagined it could be the act of a person
who wears a big pistol and rides a big horse.
I should be afraid to go riding with such an immature protector.”
“Yes; that was awful childish.
Your words do cut a little; for maybe there’s been times when
I have acted pretty near like a man.
But I cert’nly forgot to be introduced before I spoke to yu’
last night.
Because why?
You’ve found me out dead in one thing.
Won’t you take a guess at this too?”
“I cannot sit guessing why people do not behave themselves⁠—who
seem to know better.”
“Well, ma’am, I’ve played square and owned up to yu’.
And that’s not what you’re doin’ by me.
I ask your pardon if I say what I have a right to say in language
not as good as I’d like to talk to yu’ with.
But at South Fork Crossin’ who did any introducin’?
Did yu’ complain I was a stranger then?”
“I⁠—no!” she flashed out; then, quite sweetly, “The driver told
me it wasn’t really so dangerous there, you know.”
“That’s not the point I’m makin’.
You are a grown-up woman, a responsible woman.
You’ve come ever so far, and all alone, to a rough country to instruct young children that
play games⁠—tag, and hide-and-seek, and fooleries they’ll have to quit when they get old.
Don’t you think pretendin’ yu’ don’t know a man⁠—his name’s nothin’, but him⁠—a man whom you were glad enough to
let assist yu’ when somebody was needed⁠—don’t you think that’s mighty close to hide-and-seek them children plays?
I ain’t so sure but what there’s a pair of us children in this
hyeh room.”
Molly Wood was regarding him saucily.
“I don’t think I like you,” said she.
“That’s all square enough. You’re goin’ to love me before we
get through. I wish yu’d come a-ridin, ma’am.”
“Dear, dear, dear!
So I’m going to love you?
How will you do it?
I know men think that they only need to sit and look strong and
make chests at a girl⁠—”
“Goodness gracious! I ain’t makin’ any chests at yu’!”
Laughter overcame him for a moment, and Miss Wood liked his laugh
very much.
“Please come a-ridin’,” he urged.
“It’s the prettiest kind of a day.”
She looked at him frankly, and there was a pause.
“I will take back two things that I said to you,” she then answered
him.
“I believe that I do like you.
And I know that if I went riding with you, I should not have
an immature protector.”
And then, with a final gesture of acknowledgment, she held out
her hand to him.
“And I have always wanted,” she said, “to thank you for what
you did at the river.”
He took her hand, and his heart bounded.
“You’re a gentleman!” he exclaimed.
It was now her turn to be overcome with merriment.
“I’ve always wanted to be a man,” she said.
“I am mighty glad you ain’t,” said he, looking at her.
But Molly had already received enough broadsides for one day.
She could allow no more of them, and she took herself capably
in hand.
“Where did you learn to make such pretty speeches?” she asked.
“Well, never mind that. One sees that you have had plenty of
practice for one so young.”
“I am twenty-seven,” blurted the Virginian, and knew instantly
that he had spoken like a fool.
“Who would have dreamed it!” said Molly, with well-measured mockery.
She knew that she had scored at last, and that this day was hers.
“Don’t be too sure you are glad I’m not a man,” she now told
him.
There was something like a challenge in her voice.
“I risk it,” he remarked.
“For I am almost twenty-three myself,” she concluded.
And she gave him a look on her own account.
“And you’ll not come a-ridin’?” he persisted.
“No,” she answered him; “no.”
And he knew that he could not make her.
“Then I will tell yu’ goodbye,” said he.
“But I am comin’ again. And next time I’ll have along a gentle
hawss for yu’.”
“Next time!