“I reckon,” he said, “I couldn’t be so good if I wasn’t bad onced
in a while.”
“Why, there’s a skunk,” said I, noticing the pretty little animal
trotting in front of us at the edge of the thickets.
“Oh, where is it? Don’t let me see it!” screamed Molly.
And at this deeply feminine remark, the Virginian looked at her with such a smile that,
had I been a woman, it would have made me his to do what he pleased with on the spot.
Upon the lady, however, it seemed to make less impression.
Or rather, I had better say, whatever were her feelings, she very naturally made no display of
them, and contrived not to be aware of that expression which had passed over the Virginian’s face.
It was later that these few words reached me while I was fishing
alone:⁠—
“Have you anything different to tell me yet?” I heard him say.
“Yes; I have.”
She spoke in accents light and well intrenched.
“I wish to say that I have never liked any man better than you.
But I expect to!”
He must have drawn small comfort from such an answer as that.
But he laughed out indomitably:⁠—
“Don’t yu’ go betting on any such expectation!”
And then their words ceased to be distinct, and it was only their
two voices that I heard wandering among the windings of the stream.
CHAPTER XXII
“What Is a Rustler?”
We all know what birds of a feather do.
And it may be safely surmised that if a bird of any particular feather has been for a long while unable to see other
birds of its kind, it will flock with them all the more assiduously when they happen to alight in its vicinity.
Now the Ogdens were birds of Molly’s feather.
They wore Eastern, and not Western, plumage, and their song
was a different song from that which the Bear Creek birds sang.
To be sure, the piping of little George Taylor was full of hopeful interest; and many other strains,
both striking and melodious, were lifted in Cattle Land, and had given pleasure to Molly’s ear.
But although Indians, and bears, and mavericks, make worthy themes
for song, these are not the only songs in the world.
Therefore the Eastern warblings of the Ogdens sounded doubly
sweet to Molly Wood.
Such words as Newport, Bar Harbor, and Tiffany’s thrilled her
exceedingly.
It made no difference that she herself had never been to Newport or Bar
Harbor, and had visited Tiffany’s more often to admire than to purchase.
On the contrary, this rather added a dazzle to the music of the
Ogdens.
And Molly, whose Eastern song had been silent in this strange land, began
to chirp it again during the visit that she made at the Sunk Creek Ranch.
Thus the Virginian’s cause by no means prospered at this time.
His forces were scattered, while Molly’s were concentrated.
The girl was not at that point where absence makes the heart
grow fonder.
While the Virginian was trundling his long, responsible miles in the caboose, delivering
the cattle at Chicago, vanquishing Trampas along the Yellowstone, she had regained herself.
Thus it was that she could tell him so easily during those first hours that they
were alone after his return, “I expect to like another man better than you.”
Absence had recruited her.
And then the Ogdens had reinforced her.
They brought the East back powerfully to her memory, and her
thoughts filled with it.
They did not dream that they were assisting in any battle.
No one ever had more unconscious allies than did Molly at that
time.
But she used them consciously, or almost consciously.
She frequented them; she spoke of Eastern matters; she found that she had acquaintances
whom the Ogdens also knew, and she often brought them into the conversation.
For it may be said, I think, that she was fighting a battle⁠—nay,
a campaign.
And perhaps this was a hopeful sign for the Virginian (had he
but known it), that the girl resorted to allies.
She surrounded herself, she steeped herself, with the East, to have, as it
were, a sort of counteractant against the spell of the black-haired horse man.
And his forces were, as I have said, scattered.
For his promotion gave him no more time for lovemaking.
He was foreman now.
He had said to Judge Henry, “I’ll try to please yu’.”
And after the throb of emotion which these words had both concealed and conveyed,
there came to him that sort of intention to win which amounts to a certainty.
Yes, he would please Judge Henry!
He did not know how much he had already pleased him.
He did not know that the Judge was humorously undecided which of his new foreman’s first acts
had the more delighted him: his performance with the missionary, or his magnanimity to Trampas.
“Good feeling is a great thing in anyone,” the Judge would say;
“but I like to know that my foreman has so much sense.”
“I am personally very grateful to him,” said Mrs. Henry.
And indeed so was the whole company.
To be afflicted with Dr. MacBride for one night instead of six
was a great liberation.
But the Virginian never saw his sweetheart alone again; while she was at the Sunk
Creek Ranch, his duties called him away so much that there was no chance for him.
Worse still, that habit of birds of a feather brought about a
separation more considerable.
She arranged to go East with the Ogdens.
It was so good an opportunity to travel with friends, instead
of making the journey alone!
Molly’s term of ministration at the schoolhouse had so pleased
Bear Creek that she was warmly urged to take a holiday.
School could afford to begin a little late.
Accordingly, she departed.
The Virginian hid his sore heart from her during the moment of
farewell that they had.
“No, I’ll not want any more books,” he said, “till yu’ come back.”
And then he made cheerfulness.
“It’s just the other way round!” said he.
“What is the other way round?”
“Why, last time it was me that went travelling, and you that
stayed behind.”
“So it was!”
And here she gave him a last scratch.
“But you’ll be busier than ever,” she said; “no spare time to
grieve about me!”
She could wound him, and she knew it.
Nobody else could.
That is why she did it.
But he gave her something to remember, too.
“Next time,” he said, “neither of us will stay behind.
We’ll both go together.”
And with these words he gave her no laughing glance.
It was a look that mingled with the words; so that now and again in the train, both came back to
her, and she sat pensive, drawing near to Bennington and hearing his voice and seeing his eyes.
How is it that this girl could cry at having to tell Sam Bannett she could
not think of him, and then treat another lover as she treated the Virginian?
I cannot tell you, having never (as I said before) been a woman
myself.
Bennington opened its arms to its venturesome daughter.
Much was made of Molly Wood.
Old faces and old places welcomed her.
Fatted calves of varying dimensions made their appearance.
And although the fatted calf is an animal that can assume more divergent shapes than any other known creature⁠—being sometimes
champagne and partridges, and again cake and currant wine⁠—through each disguise you can always identify the same calf.
The girl from Bear Creek met it at every turn.
The Bannetts at Hoosic Falls offered a large specimen to
Molly⁠—a dinner (perhaps I should say a banquet) of twenty-four.
And Sam Bannett of course took her to drive more than once.
“I want to see the Hoosic Bridge,” she would say.
And when they reached that well-remembered point, “How lovely
it is!” she exclaimed.
And as she gazed at the view up and down the valley, she would
grow pensive.
“How natural the church looks,” she continued.
And then, having crossed both bridges, “Oh, there’s the dear
old lodge gate!”
Or again, while they drove up the valley of the little Hoosic:
“I had forgotten it was so nice and lonely.
But after all, no woods are so interesting as those where you
might possibly see a bear or an elk.”
And upon another occasion, after a cry of enthusiasm at the view from the top of Mount Anthony,
“It’s lovely, lovely, lovely,” she said, with diminishing cadence, ending in pensiveness once more.
“Do you see that little bit just there?
No, not where the trees are⁠—that bare spot that looks brown
and warm in the sun.
With a little sagebrush, that spot would look something like
a place I know on Bear Creek.
Only of course you don’t get the clear air here.”
“I don’t forget you,” said Sam.
“Do you remember me? Or is it out of sight out of mind?”
And with this beginning he renewed his suit.
She told him that she forgot no one; that she should return always,
lest they might forget her.
“Return always!” he exclaimed.
“You talk as if your anchor was dragging.”
Was it?
At all events, Sam failed in his suit.
Over in the house at Dunbarton, the old lady held Molly’s hand
and looked a long while at her.
“You have changed very much,” she said finally.
“I am a year older,” said the girl.
“Pshaw, my dear!” said the great-aunt.
“Who is he?”
“Nobody!” cried Molly, with indignation.
“Then you shouldn’t answer so loud,” said the great-aunt.
The girl suddenly hid her face.
“I don’t believe I can love anyone,” she said, “except myself.”
And then that old lady, who in her day had made her courtesy to Lafayette,
began to stroke her niece’s buried head, because she more than half understood.
And understanding thus much, she asked no prying questions, but thought of the
days of her own youth, and only spoke a little quiet love and confidence to Molly.
“I am an old, old woman,” she said.
“But I haven’t forgotten about it.
They objected to him because he had no fortune.
But he was brave and handsome, and I loved him, my dear.
Only I ought to have loved him more.
I gave him my promise to think about it.
And he and his ship were lost.”
The great-aunt’s voice had become very soft and low, and she
spoke with many pauses.
“So then I knew.
If I had⁠—if⁠—perhaps I should have lost him; but it would have
been after⁠—ah, well!
So long as you can help it, never marry!
But when you cannot help it a moment longer, then listen to nothing but
that; for, my dear, I know your choice would be worthy of the Starks.
And now⁠—let me see his picture.”
“Why, aunty!” said Molly.
“Well, I won’t pretend to be supernatural,” said the aunt, “but I thought
you kept one back when you were showing us those Western views last night.”
Now this was the precise truth.
Molly had brought a number of photographs from Wyoming to show
to her friends at home.
These, however, with one exception, were not portraits.
They were views of scenery and of cattle roundups, and other
scenes characteristic of ranch life.
Of young men she had in her possession several photographs, and
all but one of these she had left behind her.
Her aunt’s penetration had in a way mesmerized the girl; she
rose obediently and sought that picture of the Virginian.
It was full length, displaying him in all his cowboy trappings⁠—the
leathern chaps, the belt and pistol, and in his hand a coil of rope.
Not one of her family had seen it, or suspected its existence.
She now brought it downstairs and placed it in her aunt’s hand.
“Mercy!” cried the old lady.
Molly was silent, but her eye grew warlike.
“Is that the way⁠—” began the aunt.
“Mercy!” she murmured; and she sat staring at the picture.
Molly remained silent.
Her aunt looked slowly up at her.
“Has a man like that presumed⁠—”
“He’s not a bit like that. Yes, he’s exactly like that,” said
Molly.
And she would have snatched the photograph away, but her aunt
retained it.
“Well,” she said, “I suppose there are days when he does not
kill people.”
“He never killed anybody!”
And Molly laughed.
“Are you seriously⁠—” said the old lady.
“I almost might⁠—at times . He is perfectly splendid.”
“My dear, you have fallen in love with his clothes.”
“It’s not his clothes. And I’m not in love. He often wears others.
He wears a white collar like anybody.”
“Then that would be a more suitable way to be photographed, I
think.
He couldn’t go round like that here.
I could not receive him myself.”
“He’d never think of such a thing. Why, you talk as if he were
a savage.”
The old lady studied the picture closely for a minute.
“I think it is a good face,” she finally remarked.
“Is the fellow as handsome as that, my dear?”
More so, Molly thought.
And who was he, and what were his prospects? were the aunt’s
next inquiries.
She shook her head at the answers which she received; and she also shook her
head over her niece’s emphatic denial that her heart was lost to this man.
But when their parting came, the old lady said:⁠—
“God bless you and keep you, my dear. I’ll not try to manage
you. They managed me⁠—” A sigh spoke the rest of this sentence.
“But I’m not worried about you⁠—at least, not very much.
You have never done anything that was not worthy of the Starks.
And if you’re going to take him, do it before I die so that I
can bid him welcome for your sake.
God bless you, my dear.”
And after the girl had gone back to Bennington, the great-aunt
had this thought: “She is like us all.
She wants a man that is a man.”
Nor did the old lady breathe her knowledge to any member of the
family.
For she was a loyal spirit, and her girl’s confidence was sacred
to her.
“Besides,” she reflected, “if even I can do nothing with her,
what a mess they’d make of it!
We should hear of her elopement next.”
So Molly’s immediate family never saw that photograph, and never
heard a word from her upon this subject.
But on the day that she left for Bear Creek, as they sat missing her and discussing her visit in the
evening, Mrs. Bell observed: “Mother, how did you think she was?”⁠—“I never saw her better, Sarah.
That horrible place seems to agree with her.”⁠—“Oh, yes, agree.
It seemed to me⁠—”⁠—“Well?”⁠—“Oh, just somehow that she was thinking.”⁠—“Thinking?”⁠—“Well,
I believe she has something on her mind.”⁠—“You mean a man,” said Andrew Bell.⁠—“A man,
Andrew?”⁠—“Yes, Mrs. Wood, that’s what Sarah always means.”
It may be mentioned that Sarah’s surmises did not greatly contribute
to her mother’s happiness.
And rumor is so strange a thing that presently from the malicious outside air came
a vague and dreadful word⁠—one of those words that cannot be traced to its source.
Somebody said to Andrew Bell that they heard Miss Molly Wood
was engaged to marry a rustler.
“Heavens, Andrew!” said his wife; “what is a rustler?”
It was not in any dictionary, and current translations of it
were inconsistent.
A man at Hoosic Falls said that he had passed through Cheyenne, and heard
the term applied in a complimentary way to people who were alive and pushing.
Another man had always supposed it meant some kind of horse.
But the most alarming version of all was that a rustler was a
cattle thief.
Now the truth is that all these meanings were right.
The word ran a sort of progress in the cattle country, gathering
many meanings as it went.
It gathered more, however, in Bennington.
In a very few days, gossip had it that Molly was engaged to a gambler, a gold miner, an
escaped stage robber, and a Mexican bandit; while Mrs. Flynt feared she had married a Mormon.
Along Bear Creek, however, Molly and her “rustler” took a ride
soon after her return.
They were neither married nor engaged, and she was telling him
about Vermont.
“I never was there,” said he.
“Never happened to strike in that direction.”
“What decided your direction?”
“Oh, looking for chances.
I reckon I must have been more ambitious than my brothers⁠—or
more restless.
They stayed around on farms.
But I got out.
When I went back again six years afterward, I was twenty.
They was talking about the same old things.
Men of twenty-five and thirty⁠—yet just sittin’ and talkin’ about
the same old things.
I told my mother about what I’d seen here and there, and she
liked it, right to her death.
But the others⁠—well, when I found this whole world was hawgs and turkeys to them, with a little gunnin’ afteh small game throwed
in, I put on my hat one mawnin’ and told ’em maybe when I was fifty I’d look in on ’em again to see if they’d got any new subjects.
But they’ll never.
My brothers don’t seem to want chances.”
“You have lost a good many yourself,” said Molly.
“That’s correct.”
“And yet,” said she, “sometimes I think you know a great deal
more than I ever shall.”
“Why, of course I do,” said he, quite simply.
“I have earned my living since I was fourteen.
And that’s from old Mexico to British Columbia.
I have never stolen or begged a cent.
I’d not want yu’ to know what I know.”
She was looking at him, half listening and half thinking of her
great-aunt.
“I am not losing chances any more,” he continued.
“And you are the best I’ve got.”
She was not sorry to have Georgie Taylor come galloping along
at this moment and join them.
But the Virginian swore profanely under his breath.
And on this ride nothing more happened.
CHAPTER XXIII
Various Points
Love had been snowbound for many weeks.
Before this imprisonment its course had run neither smooth nor rough, so far as eye
could see; it had run either not at all, or, as an undercurrent, deep out of sight.
In their rides, in their talks, love had been dumb, as to spoken words at least;
for the Virginian had set himself a heavy task of silence and of patience.
Then, where winter barred his visits to Bear Creek, and there was for the while no ranch work or
responsibility to fill his thoughts and blood with action, he set himself a task much lighter.
Often, instead of Shakespeare and fiction, school books lay open on
his cabin table; and penmanship and spelling helped the hours to pass.
Many sheets of paper did he fill with various exercises, and
Mrs. Henry gave him her assistance in advice and corrections.
“I shall presently be in love with him myself,” she told the
Judge.
“And it’s time for you to become anxious.”
“I am perfectly safe,” he retorted.
“There’s only one woman for him any more.”
“She is not good enough for him,” declared Mrs. Henry.
“But he’ll never see that.”
So the snow fell, the world froze, and the spelling-books and
exercises went on.
But this was not the only case of education which was progressing
at the Sunk Creek Ranch while love was snowbound.
One morning Scipio le Moyne entered the Virginian’s sitting room⁠—that
apartment where Dr. MacBride had wrestled with sin so courageously all night.
The Virginian sat at his desk.
Open books lay around him; a half-finished piece of writing was
beneath his fist; his fingers were coated with ink.
Education enveloped him, it may be said.
But there was none in his eye.
That was upon the window, looking far across the cold plain.
The foreman did not move when Scipio came in, and this humorous
spirit smiled to himself.
“It’s Bear Creek he’s havin’ a vision of,” he concluded.
But he knew instantly that this was not so.
The Virginian was looking at something real, and Scipio went
to the window to see for himself.
“Well,” he said, having seen, “when is he going to leave us?”
The foreman continued looking at two horsemen riding together.
Their shapes, small in the distance, showed black against the
universal whiteness.
“When d’ yu’ figure he’ll leave us?” repeated Scipio.
“He,” murmured the Virginian, always watching the distant horsemen;
and again, “he.”
Scipio sprawled down, familiarly, across a chair.
He and the Virginian had come to know each other very well since
that first meeting at Medora.
They were birds many of whose feathers were the same, and the
Virginian often talked to Scipio without reserve.
Consequently, Scipio now understood those two syllables that the Virginian had pronounced
precisely as though the sentences which lay between them had been fully expressed.
“Hm,” he remarked.
“Well, one will be a gain, and the other won’t be no loss.”
“Poor Shorty !” said the Virginian.
“Poor fool!”
Scipio was less compassionate.
“No,” he persisted, “I ain’t sorry for him.
Any man old enough to have hair on his face ought to see through
Trampas.”
The Virginian looked out of the window again, and watched Shorty
and Trampas as they rode in the distance.
“Shorty is kind to animals,” he said.
“He has gentled that hawss Pedro he bought with his first money.
Gentled him wonderful.
When a man is kind to dumb animals, I always say he had got some
good in him.”
“Yes,” Scipio reluctantly admitted.
“Yes. But I always did hate a fool.”
“This hyeh is a mighty cruel country,” pursued the Virginian.
“To animals that is.
Think of it!
Think what we do to hundreds an’ thousands of little calves!
Throw ’em down, brand ’em, cut ’em, ear mark ’em, turn ’em loose,
and on to the next.
It has got to be, of course.
But I say this.
If a man can go jammin’ hot irons on to little calves and slicin’ pieces off ’em with his knife,
and live along, keepin’ a kindness for animals in his heart, he has got some good in him.
And that’s what Shorty has got.
But he is lettin’ Trampas get a hold of him, and both of them
will leave us.”
And the Virginian looked out across the huge winter whiteness
again.
But the riders had now vanished behind some foothills.
Scipio sat silent.
He had never put these thoughts about men and animals to himself,
and when they were put to him, he saw that they were true.
“Queer,” he observed finally.
“What?”
“Everything.”
“Nothing’s queer,” stated the Virginian, “except marriage and
lightning.
Them two occurrences can still give me a sensation of surprise.”
“All the same it is queer,” Scipio insisted.
“Well, let her go at me.”
“Why, Trampas.
He done you dirt.
You pass that over.
You could have fired him, but you let him stay and keep his job.
That’s goodness.
And badness is resultin’ from it, straight.
Badness right from goodness.”
“You’re off the trail a whole lot,” said the Virginian.
“Which side am I off, then?”
“North, south, east, and west.
First point.
I didn’t expect to do Trampas any good by not killin’ him, which
I came pretty near doin’ three times.
Nor I didn’t expect to do Trampas any good by lettin’ him keep
his job.
But I am foreman of this ranch.
And I can sit and tell all men to their face: ‘I was above that
meanness.’
Point two: it ain’t any goodness, it is Trampas that badness
has resulted from.
Put him anywhere and it will be the same.
Put him under my eye, and I can follow his moves a little, anyway.
You have noticed, maybe, that since you and I run on to that dead Polled Angus cow, that
was still warm when we got to her, we have found no more cows dead of sudden death.
We came mighty close to catchin’ whoever it was that killed that
cow and ran her calf off to his own bunch.
He wasn’t ten minutes ahead of us.
We can prove nothin’; and he knows that just as well as we do.
But our cows have all quit dyin’ of sudden death.
And Trampas he’s gettin’ ready for a change of residence.
As soon as all the outfits begin hirin’ new hands in the spring,
Trampas will leave us and take a job with some of them.
And maybe our cows’ll commence gettin’ killed again, and we’ll
have to take steps that will be more emphatic⁠—maybe.”
Scipio meditated.
“I wonder what killin’ a man feels like?” he said.
“Why, nothing to bother yu’⁠—when he’d ought to have been killed.
Next point: Trampas he’ll take Shorty with him, which is certainly
bad for Shorty.
But it’s me that has kept Shorty out of harm’s way this long.
If I had fired Trampas, he’d have worked Shorty into dissatisfaction
that much sooner.”
Scipio meditated again.
“I knowed Trampas would pull his freight,” he said.
“But I didn’t think of Shorty. What makes you think it?”
“He asked me for a raise.”
“He ain’t worth the pay he’s getting now.”
“Trampas has told him different.”
“When a man ain’t got no ideas of his own,” said Scipio, “he’d
ought to be kind o’ careful who he borrows ’em from.”
“That’s mighty correct,” said the Virginian.
“Poor Shorty!
He has told me about his life.
It is sorrowful.
And he will never get wise.
It was too late for him to get wise when he was born.
D’ yu’ know why he’s after higher wages?
He sends most all his money East.”
“I don’t see what Trampas wants him for,” said Scipio.
“Oh, a handy tool some day.”
“Not very handy,” said Scipio.
“Well, Trampas is aimin’ to train him.
Yu’ see, supposin’ yu’ were figuring to turn professional thief⁠—yu’d be lookin’ around
for a nice young trustful accomplice to take all the punishment and let you take the rest.”
“No such thing!” cried Scipio, angrily.
“I’m no shirker.”
And then, perceiving the Virginian’s expression, he broke out
laughing.
“Well,” he exclaimed, “yu’ fooled me that time.”
“Looks that way. But I do mean it about Trampas.”
Presently Scipio rose, and noticed the half-finished exercise
upon the Virginian’s desk.
“Trampas is a rolling stone,” he said.
“A rolling piece of mud,” corrected the Virginian.
“Mud! That’s right. I’m a rolling stone. Sometimes I’d most like
to quit being.”
“That’s easy done,” said the Virginian.
“No doubt, when yu’ve found the moss yu’ want to gather.”
As Scipio glanced at the school books again, a sparkle lurked
in his bleached blue eye.
“I can cipher some,” he said.
“But I expect I’ve got my own notions about spelling.”
“I retain a few private ideas that way myself,” remarked the
Virginian, innocently; and Scipio’s sparkle gathered light.
“As to my geography,” he pursued, “that’s away out loose in the
brush.
Is Bennington the capital of Vermont?
And how d’ yu’ spell bridegroom?”
“Last point!” shouted the Virginian, letting a book fly after him: “don’t
let badness and goodness worry yu’, for yu’ll never be a judge of them.”
But Scipio had dodged the book, and was gone.
As he went his way, he said to himself, “All the same, it must
pay to fall regular in love.”
At the bunk house that afternoon it was observed that he was
unusually silent.
His exit from the foreman’s cabin had let in a breath of winter so chill that
the Virginian went to see his thermometer, a Christmas present from Mrs. Henry.
It registered twenty below zero.
After reviving the fire to a white blaze, the foreman sat thinking over the story of
Shorty: what its useless, feeble past had been; what would be its useless, feeble future.
He shook his head over the sombre question, Was there any way
out for Shorty?
“It may be,” he reflected, “that them whose pleasure brings yu’
into this world owes yu’ a living.
But that don’t make the world responsible.
The world did not beget you.
I reckon man helps them that help themselves.
As for the universe, it looks like it did too wholesale a business
to turn out an article up to standard every clip.
Yes, it is sorrowful.
For Shorty is kind to his hawss.”
In the evening the Virginian brought Shorty into his room.
He usually knew what he had to say, usually found it easy to arrange
his thoughts; and after such arranging the words came of themselves.
But as he looked at Shorty, this did not happen to him.
There was not a line of badness in the face; yet also there was not a line of strength; no
promise in eye, or nose, or chin; the whole thing melted to a stubby, featureless mediocrity.
It was a countenance like thousands; and hopelessness filled the
Virginian as he looked at this lost dog, and his dull, wistful eyes.
But some beginning must be made.
“I wonder what the thermometer has got to be,” he said.
“Yu’ can see it, if yu’ll hold the lamp to that right side of
the window.”
Shorty held the lamp.
“I never used any,” he said, looking out at the instrument, nevertheless.
The Virginian had forgotten that Shorty could not read.
So he looked out of the window himself, and found that it was
twenty-two below zero.
“This is pretty good tobacco,” he remarked; and Shorty helped
himself, and filled his pipe.
“I had to rub my left ear with snow today,” said he.
“I was just in time.”
“I thought it looked pretty freezy out where yu’ was riding,”
said the foreman.
The lost dog’s eyes showed plain astonishment.
“We didn’t see you out there,” said he.
“Well,” said the foreman, “it’ll soon not be freezing any more;
and then we’ll all be warm enough with work.
Everybody will be working all over the range.
And I wish I knew somebody that had a lot of stable work to be
attended to.
I cert’nly do for your sake.”
“Why?” said Shorty.
“Because it’s the right kind of a job for you.”
“I can make more⁠—” began Shorty, and stopped.
“There is a time coming,” said the Virginian, “when I’ll want
somebody that knows how to get the friendship of hawsses.
I’ll want him to handle some special hawsses the Judge has plans
about.
Judge Henry would pay fifty a month for that.”
“I can make more,” said Shorty, this time with stubbornness.
“Well, yes. Sometimes a man can⁠—when he’s not worth it, I mean.
But it don’t generally last.”
Shorty was silent.
“I used to make more myself,” said the Virginian.
“You’re making a lot more now,” said Shorty.
“Oh, yes.
But I mean when I was fooling around the earth, jumping from
job to job, and helling all over town between whiles.
I was not worth fifty a month then, nor twenty-five.
But there was nights I made a heap more at cyards.”
Shorty’s eyes grew large.
“And then, bang! it was gone with treatin’ the men and the girls.”
“I don’t always⁠—” said Shorty, and stopped again.
The Virginian knew that he was thinking about the money he sent
East.
“After a while,” he continued, “I noticed a right strange fact.
The money I made easy that I wasn’t worth, it went like it came.
I strained myself none gettin’ or spendin’ it.
But the money I made hard that I was worth, why I began to feel
right careful about that.
And now I have got savings stowed away.
If once yu’ could know how good that feels⁠—”
“So I would know,” said Shorty, “with your luck.”
“What’s my luck?” said the Virginian, sternly.
“Well, if I had took up land along a creek that never goes dry and proved upon it like
you have, and if I had saw that land raise its value on me with me lifting no finger⁠—”
“Why did you lift no finger?” cut in the Virginian.
“Who stopped yu’ taking up land?
Did it not stretch in front of yu’, behind yu’, all around yu’,
the biggest, baldest opportunity in sight?
That was the time I lifted my finger; but yu’ didn’t.”
Shorty stood stubborn.
“But never mind that,” said the Virginian.
“Take my land away tomorrow, and I’d still have my savings in
bank.
Because, you see, I had to work right hard gathering them in.
I found out what I could do, and I settled down and did it.
Now you can do that too.
The only tough part is the finding out what you’re good for.
And for you, that is found.
If you’ll just decide to work at this thing you can do, and gentle those
hawsses for the Judge, you’ll be having savings in a bank yourself.”
“I can make more,” said the lost dog.
The Virginian was on the point of saying, “Then get out!”
But instead, he spoke kindness to the end.
“The weather is freezing yet,” he said, “and it will be for a
good long while.
Take your time, and tell me if yu’ change your mind.”
After that Shorty returned to the bunk house, and the Virginian knew that the boy had
learned his lesson of discontent from Trampas with a thoroughness past all unteaching.
This petty triumph of evil seemed scarce of the size to count
as any victory over the Virginian.
But all men grasp at straws.
Since that first moment, when in the Medicine Bow saloon the Virginian had shut the mouth of Trampas by a word, the man had been trying
to get even without risk; and at each successive clash of his weapon with the Virginian’s, he had merely met another public humiliation.
Therefore, now at the Sunk Creek Ranch in these cold white days, a certain lurking insolence in
his gait showed plainly his opinion that by disaffecting Shorty he had made some sort of reprisal.
Yes, he had poisoned the lost dog.
In the springtime, when the neighboring ranches needed additional hands, it happened as the Virginian had foreseen⁠—Trampas
departed to a “better job,” as he took pains to say, and with him the docile Shorty rode away upon his horse Pedro.
Love now was not any longer snowbound.
The mountain trails were open enough for the sure feet of love’s
steed⁠—that horse called Monte.
But duty blocked the path of love.
Instead of turning his face to Bear Creek, the foreman had other journeys
to make, full of heavy work, and watchfulness, and councils with the Judge.
The cattle thieves were growing bold, and winter had scattered
the cattle widely over the range.
Therefore the Virginian, instead of going to see her, wrote a
letter to his sweetheart.
It was his first.
CHAPTER XXIV
A Letter with a Moral
The letter which the Virginian wrote to Molly Wood was, as has
been stated, the first that he had ever addressed to her.
I think, perhaps, he may have been a little shy as to his skill in the epistolary art, a little anxious lest any
sustained production from his pen might contain blunders that would too staringly remind her of his scant learning.
He could turn off a business communication about steers or stock cars, or any other of the subjects involved in his
profession, with a brevity and a clearness that led the Judge to confide three-quarters of such correspondence to his foreman.
“Write to the 76 outfit,” the Judge would say, “and tell them that my wagon cannot start for the roundup
until,” etc.; or “Write to Cheyenne and say that if they will hold a meeting next Monday week, I will,” etc.
And then the Virginian would write such communications with ease.
But his first message to his lady was scarcely written with ease.
It must be classed, I think, among those productions which are
styled literary efforts.
It was completed in pencil before it was copied in ink; and that first
draft of it in pencil was well-nigh illegible with erasures and amendments.
The state of mind of the writer during its composition may be gathered without further
description on my part from a slight interruption which occurred in the middle.
The door opened, and Scipio put his head in.
“You coming to dinner?” he inquired.
“You go to hell,” replied the Virginian.
“My jinks!” said Scipio, quietly, and he shut the door without
further observation.
To tell the truth, I doubt if this letter would ever have been undertaken, far less
completed and despatched, had not the lover’s heart been wrung with disappointment.
All winter long he had looked to that day when he should knock
at the girl’s door, and hear her voice bid him come in.
All winter long he had been choosing the ride he would take her.
He had imagined a sunny afternoon, a hidden grove, a sheltering cleft of rock, a running
spring, and some words of his that should conquer her at last and leave his lips upon hers.
And with this controlled fire pent up within him, he had counted the days, scratching
them off his calendar with a dig each night that once or twice snapped the pen.
Then, when the trail stood open, this meeting was deferred, put
off for indefinite days, or weeks; he could not tell how long.
So, gripping his pencil and tracing heavy words, he gave himself
what consolation he could by writing her.
The letter, duly stamped and addressed to Bear Creek, set forth
upon its travels; and
these were devious and long.
When it reached its destination, it was some twenty days old.
It had gone by private hand at the outset, taken the stagecoach at a way point, become late in that stagecoach, reached a point
of transfer, and waited there for the postmaster to begin, continue, end, and recover from a game of poker, mingled with whiskey.
Then it once more proceeded, was dropped at the right way point,
and carried by private hand to Bear Creek.
The experience of this letter, however, was not at all a remarkable
one at that time in Wyoming.
Molly Wood looked at the envelope.
She had never before seen the Virginian’s handwriting.
She knew it instantly.
She closed her door and sat down to read it with a beating heart.
Sunk Creek Ranch,
May 5, 188‒
My Dear Miss Wood:
I am sorry about this.
My plan was different.
It was to get over for a ride with you about now or sooner.
This year Spring is early.
The snow is off the flats this side the range and where the sun gets a chance
to hit the earth strong all day it is green and has flowers too, a good many.
You can see them bob and mix together in the wind.
The quaking-asps down low on the South side are in small leaf
and will soon be twinkling like the flowers do now.
I had planned to take a look at this with you and that was a
better plan than what I have got to do.
The water is high but I could have got over and as for the snow on top of the mountain
a man told me nobody could cross it for a week yet, because he had just done it himself.
Was not he a funny man?
You ought to see how the birds have streamed across the sky while
Spring was coming.
But you have seen them on your side of the mountain.
But I can’t come now Miss Wood.
There is a lot for me to do that has to be done and Judge Henry
needs more than two eyes just now.
I could not think much of myself if I left him for my own wishes.
But the days will be warmer when I come.
We will not have to quit by five, and we can get off and sit
too.
We could not sit now unless for a very short while.
If I know when I can come I will try to let you know, but I think
it will be this way.
I think you will just see me coming for I have things to do of
an unsure nature and a good number of such.
Do not believe reports about Indians.
They are started by editors to keep the soldiers in the country.
The friends of the editors get the hay and beef contracts.
Indians do not come to settled parts like Bear Creek is.
It is all editors and politicianists.
Nothing has happened worth telling you.
I have read that play Othello.
No man should write down such a thing.
Do you know if it is true?
I have seen one worse affair down in Arizona.
He killed his little child as well as his wife but such things
should not be put down in fine language for the public.
I have read Romeo and Juliet.
That is beautiful language but Romeo is no man.
I like his friend Mercutio that gets killed.
He is a man.
If he had got Juliet there would have been no foolishness and
trouble.
Well Miss Wood I would like to see you today.
Do you know what I think Monte would do if I rode him out and
let the rein slack?
He would come straight to your gate for he is a horse of great
judgement.
(“That’s the first word he has misspelled,” said Molly.)
I suppose you are sitting with George Taylor and those children
right now.
Then George will get old enough to help his father but Uncle Hewie’s twins will be ready for you about
then and the supply will keep coming from all quarters all sizes for you to say big A little a to them.
There is no news here.
Only calves and cows and the hens are laying now which does always
seem news to a hen every time she does it.
Did I ever tell you about a hen Emily we had here?
She was venturesome to an extent I have not seen in other hens
only she had poor judgement and would make no family ties.
She would keep trying to get interest in the ties of others taking charge of little chicks
and bantams and turkeys and puppies one time, and she thought most anything was an egg.
I will tell you about her sometime.
She died without family ties one day while I was building a house
for her to teach school in.
(“The outrageous wretch!” cried Molly!
And her cheeks turned deep pink as she sat alone with her lover’s
letter.)
I am coming the first day I am free.
I will be a hundred miles from you most of the time when I am not more
but I will ride a hundred miles for one hour and Monte is up to that.
After never seeing you for so long I will make one hour do if
I have to.
Here is a flower I have just been out and picked.
I have kissed it now.
That is the best I can do yet.
Molly laid the letter in her lap and looked at the flower.
Then suddenly she jumped up and pressed it to her lips, and after
a long moment held it away from her.
“No,” she said.
“No, no, no.”
She sat down.
It was some time before she finished the letter.
Then once more she got up and put on her hat.
Mrs. Taylor wondered where the girl could be walking so fast.
But she was not walking anywhere, and in half an hour she returned, rosy with
her swift exercise, but with a spirit as perturbed as when she had set out.
Next morning at six, when she looked out of her window, there
was Monte tied to the Taylor’s gate.
Ah, could he have come the day before, could she have found him
when she returned from that swift walk of hers!
CHAPTER XXV
Progress of the Lost Dog
It was not even an hour’s visit that the Virginian was able to
pay his lady love.
But neither had he come a hundred miles to see her.
The necessities of his wandering work had chanced to bring him close
enough for a glimpse of her, and this glimpse he took, almost on the wing.
For he had to rejoin a company of men at once.
“Yu’ got my letter?” he said.
“Yesterday.”
“Yesterday!
I wrote it three weeks ago.
Well, yu’ got it.
This cannot be the hour with you that I mentioned.
That is coming, and maybe very soon.”
She could say nothing.
Relief she felt, and yet with it something like a pang.
“Today does not count,” he told her, “except that every time
I see you counts with me.
But this is not the hour that I mentioned.”
What little else was said between them upon this early morning
shall be told duly.
For this visit in its own good time did count momentously, though
both of them took it lightly while its fleeting minutes passed.
He returned to her two volumes that she had lent him long ago and
with Taylor he left a horse which he had brought for her to ride.
As a goodbye, he put a bunch of flowers in her hand.
Then he was gone, and she watched him going by the thick bushes
along the stream.
They were pink with wild roses; and the meadowlarks, invisible in the grass, like
hiding choristers, sent up across the empty miles of air their unexpected song.
Earth and sky had been propitious, could he have stayed; and
perhaps one portion of her heart had been propitious too.
So, as he rode away on Monte, she watched him, half chilled by reason,
half melted by passion, self-thwarted, self-accusing, unresolved.
Therefore the days that came for her now were all of them unhappy ones, while
for him they were filled with work well done and with changeless longing.
One day it seemed as if a lull was coming, a pause in which he
could at last attain that hour with her.
He left the camp and turned his face toward Bear Creek.
The way led him along Butte Creek.
Across the stream lay Balaam’s large ranch;
and presently on the other bank he saw Balaam himself, and reined
in Monte for a moment to watch what Balaam was doing.
“That’s what I’ve heard,” he muttered to himself.
For Balaam had led some horses to the water, and was lashing
them heavily because they would not drink.
He looked at this spectacle so intently that he did not see Shorty
approaching along the trail.
“Morning,” said Shorty to him, with some constraint.
But the Virginian gave him a pleasant greeting, “I was afraid
I’d not catch you so quick,” said Shorty.
“This is for you.”
He handed his recent foreman a letter of much battered appearance.
It was from the Judge.
It had not come straight, but very gradually, in the pockets
of three successive cowpunchers.
As the Virginian glanced over it and saw that the enclosure it
contained was for Balaam, his heart fell.
Here were new orders for him, and he could not go to see his
sweetheart.
“Hello, Shorty!” said Balaam, from over the creek.
To the Virginian he gave a slight nod.
He did not know him, although he knew well enough who he was.
“Hyeh’s a letter from Judge Henry for yu’ ” said the Virginian,
and he crossed the creek.
Many weeks before, in the early spring, Balaam had borrowed two
horses from the Judge, promising to return them at once.
But the Judge, of course, wrote very civilly.
He hoped that “this dunning reminder” might be excused.
As Balaam read the reminder, he wished that he had sent the horses
before.
The Judge was a greater man than he in the Territory.
Balaam could not but excuse the “dunning reminder,”⁠—but he was
ready to be disagreeable to somebody at once.
“Well,” he said, musing aloud in his annoyance, “Judge Henry
wants them by the 30th.
Well, this is the 24th, and time enough yet.”
“This is the 27th,” said the Virginian, briefly.
That made a difference!
Not so easy to reach Sunk Creek in good order by the 30th!
Balaam had drifted three sunrises behind the progress of the
month.
Days look alike, and often lose their very names in the quiet
depths of Cattle Land.
The horses were not even here at the ranch.
Balaam was ready to be very disagreeable now.
Suddenly he perceived the date of the Judge’s letter.
He held it out to the Virginian, and struck the paper.
“What’s your idea in bringing this here two weeks late?” he said.
Now, when he had struck that paper, Shorty looked at the Virginian.
But nothing happened beyond a certain change of light in the
Southerner’s eyes.
And when the Southerner spoke, it was with his usual gentleness
and civility.
He explained that the letter had been put in his hands just now
by Shorty.
“Oh,” said Balaam.
He looked at Shorty.
How had he come to be a messenger?
“You working for the Sunk Creek outfit again?” said he.
“No,” said Shorty.
Balaam turned to the Virginian again. “How do you expect me to
get those horses to Sunk Creek by the 30th?”
The Virginian levelled a lazy eye on Balaam.
“I ain’ doin’ any expecting,” said he.
His native dialect was on top today.
“The Judge has friends goin’ to arrive from New Yawk for a trip
across the Basin,” he added.
“The hawsses are for them.”
Balaam grunted with displeasure, and thought of the sixty or seventy
days since he had told the Judge he would return the horses at once.
He looked across at Shorty seated in the shade, and through his uneasy
thoughts his instinct irrelevantly noted what a good pony the youth rode.
It was the same animal he had seen once or twice before.
But something must be done.
The Judge’s horses were far out on the big range, and must be found and driven
in, which would take certainly the rest of this day, possibly part of the next.
Balaam called to one of his men and gave some sharp orders, emphasizing details, and enjoining haste, while the Virginian
leaned slightly against his horse, with one arm over the saddle, hearing and understanding, but not smiling outwardly.
The man departed to saddle up for his search on the big range,
and Balaam resumed the unhitching of his team.
“So you’re not working for the Sunk Creek outfit now?” he inquired
of Shorty.
He ignored the Virginian.
“Working for the Goose Egg?”
“No,” said Shorty.
“Sand Hill outfit, then?”
Balaam grinned.
He noticed how Shorty’s yellow hair stuck through a hole in his
hat, and how old and battered were Shorty’s overalls.
Shorty had been glad to take a little accidental pay for becoming
the bearer of the letter which he had delivered to the Virginian.
But even that sum was no longer in his possession.
He had passed through Drybone on his way, and at Drybone there
had been a game of poker.
Shorty’s money was now in the pocket of Trampas.
But he had one valuable possession in the world left to him,
and that was his horse Pedro.
“Good pony of yours,” said Balaam to him now, from across Butte
Creek.
Then he struck his own horse in the jaw because he held back
from coming to the water as the other had done.
“Your trace ain’t unhitched,” commented the Virginian, pointing.
Balaam loosed the strap he had forgotten, and cut the horse again
for consistency’s sake.
The animal, bewildered, now came down to the water, with its
head in the air, and snuffing as it took short, nervous steps.
The Virginian looked on at this, silent and sombre.
He could scarcely interfere between another man and his own beast.
Neither he nor Balaam was among those who say their prayers.
Yet in this omission they were not equal.
A half-great poet once had a wholly great day, and in that great day he was
able to write a poem that has lived and become, with many, a household word.
He called it The Rime of the Ancient Mariner.
And it is rich with many lines that possess the memory; but these
are the golden ones:⁠—
“He prayeth well who loveth wellBoth man and bird and beast.
He prayeth best who loveth bestAll things both great and small;For
the dear God who loveth us,He made and loveth all.”
These lines are the pure gold.
They are good to teach children; because after the children come
to be men, they may believe at least some part of them still.
The Virginian did not know them⁠—but his heart had taught him
many things.
I doubt if Balaam knew them either.
But on him they would have been as pearls to swine.
“So you’ve quit the roundup?” he resumed to Shorty.
Shorty nodded and looked sidewise at the Virginian.
For the Virginian knew that he had been turned off for going
to sleep while night-herding.
Then Balaam threw another glance on Pedro the horse.
“Hello, Shorty!” he called out, for the boy was departing.
“Don’t you like dinner any more? It’s ready about now.”
Shorty forded the creek and slung his saddle off, and on
invitation turned Pedro, his buckskin pony, into Balaam’s pasture.
This was green, the rest of the wide world being yellow, except only where Butte Creek, with
its bordering cottonwoods, coiled away into the desert distance like a green snake without end.
The Virginian also turned his horse into the pasture.
He must stay at the ranch till the Judge’s horses should be found.
“Mrs. Balaam’s East yet ,” said her lord, leading the way to
his dining room.
He wanted Shorty to dine with him, and could not exclude the
Virginian, much as he should have enjoyed this.
“See any Indians?” he enquired.
“Na-a!” said Shorty, in disdain of recent rumors.
“They’re headin’ the other way,” observed the Virginian.
“Bow Laig Range is where they was repawted.”
“What business have they got off the reservation, I’d like to
know,” said the ranchman, “Bow Leg, or anywhere?”
“Oh, it’s just a hunt, and a kind of visitin’ their friends on
the South Reservation,” Shorty explained.
“Squaws along and all.”
“Well, if the folks at Washington don’t keep squaws and all where they belong,” said Balaam,
in a rage, “the folks in Wyoming Territory ’ill do a little job that way themselves.”
“There’s a petition out,” said Shorty.
“Paper’s goin’ East with a lot of names to it . But they ain’t
no harm, them Indians ain’t.”
“No harm?” rasped out Balaam.
“Was it white men druv off the O.C. yearlings?”
Balaam’s Eastern grammar was sometimes at the mercy of his Western
feelings.
The thought of the perennial stultification of Indian affairs at Washington,
whether by politician or philanthropist, was always sure to arouse him.
He walked impatiently about while he spoke, and halted impatiently
at the window.
Out in the world the unclouded day was shining, and Balaam’s eye travelled across the
plains to where a blue line, faint and pale, lay along the end of the vast yellow distance.
That was the beginning of the Bow Leg Mountains.
Somewhere over there were the red men, ranging in unfrequented
depths of rock and pine⁠—their forbidden ground.
Dinner was ready, and they sat down.
“And I suppose,” Balaam continued, still hot on the subject, “you’d claim Indians
object to killing a white man when they run on to him good and far from human help?
These peaceable Indians are just the worst in the business.”
“That’s so,” assented the easy-opinioned Shorty, exactly as if
he had always maintained this view.
“Chap started for Sunk Creek three weeks ago.
Trapper he was; old like, with a red shirt.
One of his horses come into the roundup Toosday.
Man ain’t been heard from.”
He ate in silence for a while, evidently brooding in his childlike
mind.
Then he said, querulously, “I’d sooner trust one of them Indians
than I would Trampas.”
Balaam slanted his fat bullet head far to one side, and laying his spoon down (he had
opened some canned grapes) laughed steadily at his guest with a harsh relish of irony.
The guest ate a grape, and perceiving he was seen through, smiled
back rather miserably.
“Say, Shorty,” said Balaam, his head still slanted over, “what’s
the figures of your bank balance just now?”
“I ain’t usin’ banks,” murmured the youth.
Balaam put some more grapes on Shorty’s plate, and drawing a
cigar from his waistcoat, sent it rolling to his guest.
“Matches are behind you,” he added.
He gave a cigar to the Virginian as an afterthought, but to his
disgust, the Southerner put it in his pocket and lighted a pipe.
Balaam accompanied his guest, Shorty, when he went to the pasture
to saddle up and depart.
“Got a rope?” he asked the guest, as they lifted down the bars.
“Don’t need to rope him. I can walk right up to Pedro. You stay
back.”
Hiding his bridle behind him, Shorty walked to the riverbank, where the pony was switching his long tail in the shade; and speaking
persuasively to him, he came nearer, till he laid his hand on Pedro’s dusky mane, which was many shades darker than his hide.
He turned expectantly, and his master came up to his expectations
with a piece of bread.
“Eats that, does he?” said Balaam, over the bars.
“Likes the salt,” said Shorty.
“Now, n-n-ow, here!
Yu’ don’t guess yu’ll be bridled, don’t you?
Open your teeth!
Yu’d like to play yu’ was nobody’s horse and live private?
Or maybe yu’d prefer ownin’ a saloon?”
Pedro evidently enjoyed this talk, and the dodging he made about
the bit.
Once fairly in his mouth, he accepted the inevitable, and followed
Shorty to the bars.
Then Shorty turned and extended his hand.
“Shake!” he said to his pony, who lifted his forefoot quietly
and put it in his master’s hand.
Then the master tickled his nose, and he wrinkled it and flattened
his ears, pretending to bite.
His face wore an expression of knowing relish over this performance.
“Now the other hoof,” said Shorty; and the horse and master shook
hands with their left.
“I learned him that,” said the cowboy, with pride and affection.
“Say, Pede,” he continued, in Pedro’s ear, “ain’t yu’ the best
little horse in the country?
What?
Here, now!
Keep out of that, you deadbeat!
There ain’t no more bread.”
He pinched the pony’s nose, one quarter of which was wedged into
his pocket.
“Quite a lady’s little pet!” said Balaam, with the rasp in his
voice.
“Pity this isn’t New York, now, where there’s a big market for
harmless horses.
Gee-gees, the children call them.”
“He ain’t no gee-gee,” said Shorty, offended.
“He’ll beat any cow-pony workin’ you’ve got.
Yu’ can turn him on a half-dollar.
Don’t need to touch the reins.
Hang ’em on one finger and swing your body, and he’ll turn.”
Balaam knew this, and he knew that the pony was only a four-year-old.
“Well,” he said, “Drybone’s had no circus this season.
Maybe they’d buy tickets to see Pedro.
He’s good for that, anyway.”
Shorty became gloomy.
The Virginian was grimly smoking.
Here was something else going on not to his taste, but none of
his business.
“Try a circus,” persisted Balaam.
“Alter your plans for spending cash in town, and make a little
money instead.”
Shorty having no plans to alter and no cash to spend, grew still
more gloomy.
“What’ll you take for that pony?” said Balaam.
Shorty spoke up instantly.
“A hundred dollars couldn’t buy that piece of stale mud off
his back,” he asserted, looking off into the sky grandiosely.
But Balaam looked at Shorty, “You keep the mud,” he said, “and
I’ll give you thirty dollars for the horse.”
Shorty did a little professional laughing, and began to walk
toward his saddle.
“Give you thirty dollars,” repeated Balaam, picking a stone up
and slinging it into the river.
“How far do yu’ call it to Drybone?” Shorty remarked, stooping to investigate the
bucking-strap on his saddle⁠—a superfluous performance, for Pedro never bucked.
“You won’t have to walk,” said Balaam.
“Stay all night, and I’ll send you over comfortably in the morning,
when the wagon goes for the mail.”
“Walk?” Shorty retorted.
“Drybone’s twenty-five miles. Pedro’ll put me there in three
hours and not know he done it.”
He lifted the saddle on the horse’s back.
“Come, Pedro,” said he.
“Come, Pedro!” mocked Balaam.
There followed a little silence.
“No, sir,” mumbled Shorty, with his head under Pedro’s belly,
busily cinching.
“A hundred dollars is bottom figures.”
Balaam, in his turn, now duly performed some professional laughing,
which was noted by Shorty under the horse’s belly.
He stood up and squared round on Balaam.
“Well, then,” he said, “what’ll yu give for him?”
“Thirty dollars,” said Balaam, looking far off into the sky,
as Shorty had looked.
“Oh, come, now,” expostulated Shorty.
It was he who now did the feeling for an offer and this was what
Balaam liked to see.
“Why yes,” he said, “thirty,” and looked surprised that he should
have to mention the sum so often
.
“I thought yu’d quit them first figures,” said the cowpuncher,
“for yu’ can see I ain’t goin’ to look at em.”
Balaam climbed on the fence and sat there “I’m not crying for
your Pedro,” he observed dispassionately.
“Only it struck me you were dead broke, and wanted to raise cash and
keep yourself going till you hunted up a job and could buy him back.”
He hooked his right thumb inside his waistcoat pocket.
“But I’m not cryin’ for him,” he repeated.
“He’d stay right here, of course. I wouldn’t part with him. Why
does he stand that way? Hello!”
Balaam suddenly straightened himself, like a man who has made
a discovery.
“Hello, what?” said Shorty, on the defensive.
Balaam was staring at Pedro with a judicial frown.
Then he stuck out a finger at the horse, keeping the thumb hooked
in his pocket.
So meagre a gesture was felt by the ruffled Shorty to be no just
way to point at Pedro.
“What’s the matter with that foreleg there?” said Balaam.
“Which? Nothin’s the matter with it!” snapped Shorty.
Balaam climbed down from his fence and came over with elaborate
deliberation.
He passed his hand up and down the off foreleg.
Then he spit slenderly.
“Mm!” he said thoughtfully; and added, with a shade of sadness,
“that’s always to be expected when they’re worked too young.”
Shorty slid his hand slowly over the disputed leg.
“What’s to be expected?” he inquired⁠—“that they’ll eat hearty?
Well, he does.”
At this retort the Virginian permitted himself to laugh in audible
sympathy.
“Sprung,” continued Balaam, with a sigh.
“Whirling round short when his bones were soft did that. Yes.”
“Sprung!” Shorty said, with a bark of indignation.
“Come on, Pede; you and me’ll spring for town.”
He caught the horn of the saddle, and as he swung into place
the horse rushed away with him.
“O-ee! yoi-yup, yup, yup!” sang Shorty, in the shrill cow dialect.
He made Pedro play an exhibition game of speed, bringing him round close to
Balaam in a wide circle, and then he vanished in dust down the left-bank trail.
Balaam looked after him and laughed harshly.
He had seen trout dash about like that when the hook in their
jaw first surprised them.
He knew Shorty would show the pony off, and he knew Shorty’s
love for Pedro was not equal to his need of money.
He called to one of his men, asked something about the dam at the mouth of the canyon, where the main irrigation ditch began,
made a remark about the prolonged drought, and then walked to his dining-room door, where, as he expected, Shorty met him.
“Say,” said the youth, “do you consider that’s any way to talk
about a good horse?”
“Any dude could see the leg’s sprung,” said Balaam.
But he looked at Pedro’s shoulder, which was well laid back; and he admired his
points, dark in contrast with the buckskin, and also the width between the eyes.
“Now you know,” whined Shorty, “that it ain’t sprung any more
than your leg’s cork.
If you mean the right leg ain’t plumb straight, I can tell you
he was born so.
That don’t make no difference, for it ain’t weak.
Try him onced.
Just as sound and strong as iron.
Never stumbles.
And he don’t never go to jumpin’ with yu’.
He’s kind and he’s smart.”
And the master petted his pony, who lifted a hoof for another
handshake.
Of course Balaam had never thought the leg was sprung, and he now took on an
unprejudiced air of wanting to believe Shorty’s statements if he only could.
“Maybe there’s two years’ work left in that leg,” he now observed.
“Better give your hawss away, Shorty,” said the Virginian.
“Is this your deal, my friend?” inquired Balaam.
And he slanted his bullet head at the Virginian.
“Give him away, Shorty,” drawled the Southerner.
“His laig is busted. Mr. Balaam says so.”
Balaam’s face grew evil with baffled fury.
But the Virginian was gravely considering Pedro.
He, too, was not pleased.
But he could not interfere.
Already he had overstepped the code in these matters.
He would have dearly liked⁠—for reasons good and bad, spite and
mercy mingled⁠—to
have spoiled Balaam’s market, to have offered a reasonable or even an
unreasonable price for Pedro, and taken possession of the horse himself.
But this might not be.
In bets, in card games, in all horse transactions and other matters of similar business, a man
must take care of himself, and wiser onlookers must suppress their wisdom and hold their peace.
That evening Shorty again had a cigar.
He had parted with Pedro for forty dollars, a striped Mexican
blanket, and a pair of spurs.
Undressing over in the bunk house, he said to the Virginian, “I’ll
sure buy Pedro back off him just as soon as ever I rustle some cash.”
The Virginian grunted.
He was thinking he should have to travel hard to get the horses to the Judge by the 30th;
and below that thought lay his aching disappointment and his longing for Bear Creek.
In the early dawn Shorty sat up among his blankets on the floor of the bunk house and saw the various
sleepers coiled or sprawled in their beds; their breathing had not yet grown restless at the nearing of day.
He stepped to the door carefully, and saw the crowding blackbirds begin
their walk and chatter in the mud of the littered and trodden corrals.
From beyond among the cottonwoods, came continually the smooth unemphatic sound of the doves answering each other invisibly; and
against the empty ridge of the river-bluff lay the moon, no longer shining, for there was established a new light through the sky.
Pedro stood in the pasture close to the bars.
The cowboy slowly closed the door behind him, and sitting down on the step, drew
his money out and idly handled it, taking no comfort just then from its possession.
Then he put it back, and after dragging on his boots, crossed to the pasture, and held a last talk with his
pony, brushing the cakes of mud from his hide where he had rolled, and passing a lingering hand over his mane.
As the sounds of the morning came increasingly from tree and plain, Shorty glanced back to see that no
one was yet out of the cabin, and then put his arms round the horse’s neck, laying his head against him.
For a moment the cowboy’s insignificant face was exalted by the
emotion he would never have let others see.
He hugged tight this animal, who was dearer to his heart than
anybody in the world.
“Goodbye, Pedro,” he said⁠—“goodbye.”
Pedro looked for bread.
“No,” said his master, sorrowfully, “not any more.
Yu’ know well I’d give it yu’ if I had it.
You and me didn’t figure on this, did we, Pedro?
Goodbye!”
He hugged his pony again, and got as far as the bars of the pasture,
but returned once more.
“Goodbye, my little horse, my dear horse, my little, little Pedro,”
he said, as his tears wet the pony’s neck.
Then he wiped them with his hand, and got himself back to the
bunk house.
After breakfast he and his belongings departed to Drybone, and Pedro from his field calmly watched this
departure; for horses must recognize even less than men the black corners that their destinies turn.
The pony stopped feeding to look at the mail-wagon pass by; but
the master sitting in the wagon forebore
to turn
his head
.
CHAPTER XXVI
Balaam and Pedro
Resigned to wait for the Judge’s horses, Balaam went into his office this dry,
bright morning and read nine accumulated newspapers; for he was behindhand.
Then he rode out on the ditches, and met his man returning with
the troublesome animals at last.
He hastened home and sent for the Virginian.
He had made a decision.
“See here,” he said; “those horses are coming.
What trail would you take over to the Judge’s?”
“Shortest trail’s right through the Bow Laig Mountains,” said
the foreman, in his gentle voice.
“Guess you’re right.
It’s dinnertime.
We’ll start right afterward.
We’ll make Little Muddy Crossing by sundown, and Sunk Creek tomorrow,
and the next day’ll see us through.
Can a wagon get through Sunk Creek Canyon?”
The Virginian smiled.
“I reckon it can’t, seh, and stay resembling a wagon.”
Balaam told them to saddle Pedro and one packhorse, and drive the bunch of
horses into a corral, roping the Judge’s two, who proved extremely wild.
He had decided to take this journey himself on remembering certain
politics soon to be rife in Cheyenne.
For Judge Henry was indeed a greater man than Balaam.
This personally conducted return of the horses would temper its tardiness, and, moreover, the sight of some New York visitors would be a good thing
after seven months of no warmer touch with that metropolis than the Sunday Herald, always eight days old when it reached the Butte Creek Ranch.
They forded Butte Creek, and, crossing the well-travelled trail which follows down to Drybone, turned
their faces toward the uninhabited country that began immediately, as the ocean begins off a sandy shore.
And as a single mast on which no sail is shining stands at the horizon and seems to add a loneliness to the surrounding sea, so the long gray line
of fence, almost a mile away, that ended Balaam’s land on this side the creek, stretched along the waste ground and added desolation to the plain.
No solitary watercourse with margin of cottonwoods or willow thickets flowed here to stripe the dingy, yellow world with
interrupting green, nor were cattle to be seen dotting the distance, nor moving objects at all, nor any bird in the soundless air.
The last gate was shut by the Virginian, who looked back at the pleasant trees of
the ranch, and then followed on in single file across the alkali of No Man’s Land.
No cloud was in the sky.
The desert’s grim noon shone sombrely on flat and hill.
The sagebrush was dull like zinc.
Thick heat rose near at hand from the caked alkali, and pale
heat shrouded the distant peaks.
There were five horses.
Balaam led on Pedro, his squat figure stiff in the saddle, but
solid as a rock, and tilted a little forward, as his habit was.
One of the Judge’s horses came next, a sorrel, dragging back
continually on the rope by which he was led.
After him ambled Balaam’s wise pack-animal, carrying the light
burden of two days’ food and lodging.
She was an old mare who could still go when she chose, but had been schooled by the
years, and kept the trail, giving no trouble to the Virginian who came behind her.
He also sat solid as a rock, yet subtly bending to the struggles of the wild
horse he led, as a steel spring bends and balances and resumes its poise.
Thus they made but slow time, and when they topped the last dull rise of ground and looked down on the long slant of ragged, caked earth to the crossing of Little Muddy, with its single tree and
few mean bushes, the final distance where eyesight ends had deepened to violet from the thin, steady blue they had stared at for so many hours, and all heat was gone from the universal dryness.
The horses drank a long time from the sluggish yellow water, and
its alkaline taste and warmth were equally welcome to the men.
They built a little fire, and when supper was ended, smoked but a short while and in silence,
before they got in the blankets that were spread in a smooth place beside the water.
They had picketed the two horses of the Judge in the best grass they
could find, letting the rest go free to find pasture where they could.
When the first light came, the Virginian attended to breakfast,
while Balaam rode away on the sorrel to bring in the loose horses.
They had gone far out of sight, and when he returned with them,
after some two hours, he was on Pedro.
Pedro was soaking with sweat, and red froth creamed from his
mouth.
The Virginian saw the horses must have been hard to drive in,
especially after Balaam brought them the wild sorrel as a leader.
“If you’d kep’ ridin’ him, ’stead of changin’ off on your hawss,
they’d have behaved quieter,” said the foreman.
“That’s good seasonable advice,” said Balaam, sarcastically.
“I could have told you that now.”
“I could have told you when you started,” said the Virginian,
heating the coffee for Balaam.
Balaam was eloquent on the outrageous conduct of the horses.
He had come up with them evidently striking back for Butte Creek,
with the old mare in the lead.
“But I soon showed her the road she was to go,” he said, as he
drove them now to the water.
The Virginian noticed the slight limp of the mare, and how her
pastern was cut as if with a stone or the sharp heel of a boot.
“I guess she’ll not be in a hurry to travel except when she’s
wanted to,” continued Balaam.
He sat down, and sullenly poured himself some coffee.
“We’ll be in luck if we make any Sunk Creek this night.”
He went on with his breakfast, thinking aloud for the benefit of his companion, who made no comments,
preferring silence to the discomfort of talking with a man whose vindictive humor was so thoroughly uppermost.
He did not even listen very attentively, but continued his preparations for departure, washing the
dishes, rolling the blankets, and moving about in his usual way of easy and visible good nature.
“Six o’clock, already,” said Balaam, saddling the horses.
“And we’ll not get started for ten minutes more.”
Then he came to Pedro.
“So you haven’t quit fooling yet, haven’t you?” he exclaimed,
for the pony shrank as he lifted the bridle.
“Take that for your sore mouth!” and he rammed the bit in, at
which Pedro flung back and reared.
“Well, I never saw Pedro act that way yet,” said the Virginian.
“Ah, rubbish!” said Balaam.
“They’re all the same.
Not a bastard one but’s laying for his chance to do for you.
Some’ll buck you off, and some’ll roll with you, and some’ll
fight you with their fore feet.
They may play good for a year, but the Western pony’s man’s enemy,
and when he judges he’s got his chance, he’s going to do his best.
And if you come out alive it won’t be his fault.”
Balaam paused for a while, packing.
“You’ve got to keep them afraid of you,” he said next; “that’s
what you’ve got to do if you don’t want trouble.
That Pedro horse there has been fed, hand-fed, and fooled with
like a damn pet, and what’s that policy done?
Why, he goes ugly when he thinks it’s time, and decides he’ll
not drive any horses into camp this morning.
He knows better now.”
“Mr. Balaam,” said the Virginian, “I’ll buy that hawss off yu’
right now.”
Balaam shook his head.
“You’ll not do that right now or any other time,” said he.
“I happen to want him.”
The Virginian could do no more.
He had heard cowpunchers say to refractory ponies, “You keep still, or
I’ll Balaam you!” and he now understood the aptness of the expression.
Meanwhile Balaam began to lead Pedro to the creek for a last
drink before starting across the torrid drought.
The horse held back on the rein a little, and Balaam turned and
cut the whip across his forehead.
A delay of forcing and backing followed, while the Virginian,
already in the saddle, waited.
The minutes passed, and no immediate prospect, apparently, of
getting nearer Sunk Creek.
“He ain’ goin’ to follow you while you’re beatin’ his haid,”
the Southerner at length remarked.
“Do you think you can teach me anything about horses?” retorted
Balaam.
“Well, it don’t look like I could,” said the Virginian, lazily.
“Then don’t try it, so long as it’s not your horse, my friend.”
Again the Southerner levelled his eye on Balaam.
“All right,” he said, in the same gentle voice.
“And don’t you call me your friend. You’ve made that mistake
twiced.”
The road was shadeless, as it had been from the start, and they
could not travel fast.
During the first few hours all coolness was driven out of the glassy morning,
and another day of illimitable sun invested the world with its blaze.
The pale Bow Leg Range was coming nearer, but its hard hot slants and rifts suggested no sort of freshness, and even the pines that spread
for wide miles along near the summit counted for nothing in the distance and the glare, but seemed mere patches of dull dry discoloration.
No talk was exchanged between the two travellers, for the cowpuncher had nothing to say and Balaam was
sulky, so they moved along in silent endurance of each other’s company and the tedium of the journey.
But the slow succession of rise and fall in the plain changed
and shortened.
The earth’s surface became lumpy, rising into mounds and knotted systems of steep small hills
cut apart by staring gashes of sand, where water poured in the spring from the melting snow.
After a time they ascended through the foothills till the plain below was for a while concealed, but came again into view in its
entirety, distant and a thing of the past, while some magpies sailed down to meet them from the new country they were entering.
They passed up through a small transparent forest of dead trees standing stark and white, and a little higher
came on a line of narrow moisture that crossed the way and formed a stale pool among some willow thickets.
They turned aside to water their horses, and found near the pool a circular spot of ashes and
some poles lying, and beside these a cage-like edifice of willow wands built in the ground.
“Indian camp,” observed the Virginian.
There were the tracks of five or six horses on the farther side of the pool, and they
did not come into the trail, but led off among the rocks on some system of their own.
“They’re about a week old,” said Balaam.
“It’s part of that outfit that’s been hunting.”
“They’ve gone on to visit their friends,” added the cowpuncher.
“Yes, on the Southern Reservation. How far do you call Sunk Creek
now?”
“Well,” said the Virginian, calculating, “it’s mighty nigh fo’ty
miles from Muddy Crossin’, an’ I reckon we’ve come eighteen.”
“Just about. It’s noon.”
Balaam snapped his watch shut.
“We’ll rest here till 12:30.”
When it was time to go, the Virginian looked musingly at the
mountains.
“We’ll need to travel right smart to get through the canyon tonight,”
he said.
“Tell you what,” said Balaam; “we’ll rope the Judge’s horses
together and drive ’em in front of us.
That’ll make speed.”
“Mightn’t they get away on us?” objected the Virginian.
“They’re pow’ful wild.”
“They can’t get away from me, I guess,” said Balaam, and the
arrangement was adopted.
“We’re the first this season over this piece of the trail,” he
observed presently.
His companion had noticed the ground already, and assented.
There were no tracks anywhere to be seen over which winter had
not come and gone since they had been made.
Presently the trail wound into a sultry gulch that hemmed in
the heat and seemed to draw down the sun’s rays more vertically.
The sorrel horse chose this place to make a try for liberty.
He suddenly whirled from the trail, dragging with him his less
inventive fellow.
Leaving the Virginian with the old mare, Balaam headed them off, for Pedro was quick, and they came jumping down
the bank together, but swiftly crossed up on the other side, getting much higher before they could be reached.
It was no place for this sort of game, as the sides of the ravine were ploughed with steep channels, broken with jutting
knobs of rock, and impeded by short twisted pines that swung out from their roots horizontally over the pitch of the hill.
The Virginian helped, but used his horse with more judgment, keeping as much on the level as possible, and endeavoring to anticipate the next turn of the runaways before they made it, while Balaam attempted to follow them close, wheeling
short when they doubled, heavily beating up the face of the slope, veering again to come down to the point he had left, and whenever he felt Pedro begin to flag, driving his spurs into the horse and forcing him to keep up the pace.
He had set out to overtake and capture on the side of the mountain these two animals who had been running wild for many weeks,
and now carried no weight but themselves, and the futility of such work could not penetrate his obstinate and rising temper.
He had made up his mind not to give in.
The Virginian soon decided to move slowly along for the present, preventing the wild horses
from passing down the gulch again, but otherwise saving his own animal from useless fatigue.
He saw that Pedro was reeking wet, with mouth open, and constantly
stumbling, though he galloped on.
The cowpuncher kept the group in sight, driving the packhorse in front of him, and watching the tactics of the sorrel, who had now undoubtedly
become the leader of the expedition, and was at the top of the gulch, in vain trying to find an outlet through its rocky rim to the levels above.
He soon judged this to be no thoroughfare, and changing his plan, trotted down to the bottom
and up the other side, gaining more and more; for in this new descent Pedro had fallen twice.
Then the sorrel showed the cleverness of a genuinely vicious
horse.
The Virginian saw him stop and fall to kicking his companion
with all the energy that a short rope would permit.
The rope slipped, and both, unencumbered, reached the top and
disappeared.
Leaving the packhorse for Balaam, the Virginian started after them and
came into a high tableland, beyond which the mountains began in earnest.
The runaways were moving across toward these at an easy rate.
He followed for a moment, then looking back, and seeing no sign of Balaam, waited,
for the horses were sure not to go fast when they reached good pasture or water.
He got out of the saddle and sat on the ground, watching, till
the mare came up slowly into sight, and Balaam behind her.
When they were near, Balaam dismounted and struck Pedro fearfully,
until the stick broke, and he raised the splintered half to continue.
Seeing the pony’s condition, the Virginian spoke, and said, “I’d
let that hawss alone.”
Balaam turned to him, but wholly possessed by passion did not seem to hear,
and the Southerner noticed how white and like that of a maniac his face was.
The stick slid to the ground.
“He played he was tired,” said Balaam, looking at the Virginian
with glazed eyes.
The violence of his rage affected him physically, like some stroke
of illness.
“He played out on me on purpose.”
The man’s voice was dry and light.
“He’s perfectly fresh now,” he continued, and turned again to
the coughing, swaying horse, whose eyes were closed.
Not having the stick, he seized the animal’s unresisting head
and shook it.
The Virginian watched him a moment, and rose to stop such a spectacle.
Then, as if conscious he was doing no real hurt, Balaam ceased, and turning again
in slow fashion looked across the level, where the runaways were still visible.
“I’ll have to take your horse,” he said, “mine’s played out on
me.”
“You ain’ goin’ to touch my hawss.”
Again the words seemed not entirely to reach Balaam’s understanding,
so dulled by rage were his senses.
He made no answer, but mounted Pedro; and the failing pony walked
mechanically forward, while the Virginian, puzzled, stood looking after him.
Balaam seemed without purpose of going anywhere, and stopped
in a moment.
Suddenly he was at work at something.
This sight was odd and new to look at.
For a few seconds it had no meaning to the Virginian as he watched.
Then his mind grasped the horror, too late.
Even with his cry of execration and the tiger spring that he
gave to stop Balaam, the monstrosity was wrought.
Pedro sank motionless, his head rolling flat on the earth.
Balaam was jammed beneath him.
The man had struggled to his feet before the Virginian reached the
spot, and the horse then lifted his head and turned it piteously round.
Then vengeance like a blast struck Balaam.
The Virginian hurled him to the ground, lifted and hurled him
again, lifted him and beat his face and struck his jaw.
The man’s strong ox-like fighting availed nothing.
He fended his eyes as best he could against these sledgehammer
blows of justice.
He felt blindly for his pistol.
That arm was caught and wrenched backward, and crushed and doubled.
He seemed to hear his own bones, and set up a hideous screaming
of hate and pain.
Then the pistol at last came out, and together with the hand
that grasped it was instantly stamped into the dust.
Once again the creature was lifted and slung so that he lay across
Pedro’s saddle a blurred, dingy, wet pulp.
Vengeance had come and gone.
The man and the horse were motionless.
Around them, silence seemed to gather like a witness.
“If you are dead,” said the Virginian, “I am glad of it.”
He stood looking down at Balaam and Pedro, prone in the middle
of the open tableland.
Then he saw Balaam looking at him.
It was the quiet stare of sight without thought or feeling, the mere
visual sense alone, almost frightful in its separation from any self.
But as he watched those eyes, the self came back into them.
“I have not killed you,” said the Virginian.
“Well, I ain’t goin’ to do any more to yu’⁠—if that’s a satisfaction
to know.”
Then he began to attend to Balaam with impersonal skill, like
someone hired for the purpose.
“He ain’t hurt bad,” he asserted aloud, as if the man were some nameless patient; and then to Balaam
he remarked, “I reckon it might have put a less tough man than you out of business for quite a while.
I’m goin’ to get some water now.”
When he returned with the water, Balaam was sitting up, looking
about him.
He had not yet spoken, nor did he now speak.
The sunlight flashed on the six-shooter where it lay, and the
Virginian secured it.
“She ain’t so pretty as she was,” he remarked, as he examined
the weapon.
“But she’ll go right handy yet.”
Strength was in a measure returning to Pedro.
He was a young horse, and the exhaustion neither of anguish
nor of overriding was enough to affect him long or seriously.
He got himself on his feet and walked waveringly over to the
old mare, and stood by her for comfort.
The cowpuncher came up to him, and Pedro, after starting back
slightly, seemed to comprehend that he was in friendly hands.
It was plain that he would soon be able to travel slowly if no
weight was on him, and that he would be a very good horse again.
Whether they abandoned the runaways or not, there was no staying
here for night to overtake them without food or water.
The day was still high, and what its next few hours had in store the Virginian could not say, and he left them to take care of themselves,
determining meanwhile that he would take command of the minutes and maintain the position he had assumed both as to Balaam and Pedro.
He took Pedro’s saddle off, threw the mare’s pack to the ground, put Balaam’s saddle on her,
and on that stowed or tied her original pack, which he could do, since it was so light.
Then he went to Balaam, who was sitting up.
“I reckon you can travel,” said the Virginian.
“And your hawss can.
If you’re comin’ with me, you’ll ride your mare.
I’m goin’ to trail them hawsses
.
If you’re not comin’ with me, your hawss comes with me, and you’ll
take fifty dollars for him.”
Balaam was indifferent to this good bargain.
He did not look at the other or speak, but rose and searched
about him on the ground.
The Virginian was also indifferent as to whether Balaam chose
to answer or not.
Seeing Balaam searching the ground, he finished what he had to
say.
“I have your six-shooter, and you’ll have it when I’m ready for
you to. Now, I’m goin’,” he concluded.
Balaam’s intellect was clear enough now, and he saw that though the
rest of this journey would be nearly intolerable, it must go on.
He looked at the impassive cowpuncher getting ready to go and tying a rope on Pedro’s neck to lead him, then he looked at
the mountains where the runaways had vanished, and it did not seem credible to him that he had come into such straits.
He was helped stiffly on the mare, and the three horses in single file
took up their journey once more, and came slowly among the mountains.
The perpetual desert was ended, and they crossed a small brook,
where they missed the trail.
The Virginian dismounted to find where the horses had turned off, and
discovered that they had gone straight up the ridge by the watercourse.
“There’s been a man camped in hyeh inside a month,” he said,
kicking up a rag of red flannel.
“White man and two hawsses. Ours have went up his old tracks.”
It was not easy for Balaam to speak yet, and he kept his silence.
But he remembered that Shorty had spoken of a trapper who had
started for Sunk Creek.
For three hours they followed the runaways’ course over softer ground, and steadily ascending,
passed one or two springs, at length, where the mud was not yet settled in the hoofprints.
Then they came through a corner of pine forest and down a sudden
bank among quaking-asps to a green park.
Here the runaways beside a stream were grazing at ease, but saw
them coming, and started on again, following down the stream.
For the present all to be done was to keep them in sight.
This creek received tributaries and widened, making a valley
for itself.
Above the bottom, lining the first terrace of the ridge, began the pines, and stretched back,
unbroken over intervening summit and basin, to cease at last where the higher peaks presided.
“This hyeh’s the middle fork of Sunk Creek,” said the Virginian.
“We’ll get on to our right road again where they join.”
Soon a game trail marked itself along the stream.
If this would only continue, the runaways would be nearly sure
to follow it down into the canyon.
Then there would be no way for them but to go on and come out into their own
country, where they would make for the Judge’s ranch of their own accord.
The great point was to reach the canyon before dark.
They passed into permanent shadow; for though the other side of the creek shone
in full day, the sun had departed behind the ridges immediately above them.
Coolness filled the air, and the silence, which in this deep valley
of invading shadow seemed too silent, was relieved by the birds.
Not birds of song, but a freakish band of gray talkative observers, who came calling and croaking along through
the pines, and inspected the cavalcade, keeping it company for a while, and then flying up into the woods again.
The travellers came round a corner on a little spread of marsh, and from somewhere in the middle of it rose a
buzzard and sailed on its black pinions into the air above them, wheeling and wheeling, but did not grow distant.
As it swept over the trail, something fell from its claw, a rag of
red flannel; and each man in turn looked at it as his horse went by.
“I wonder if there’s plenty elk and deer hyeh?” said the Virginian.
“I guess there is,” Balaam replied, speaking at last.
The travellers had become strangely reconciled.
“There’s game ’most all over these mountains,” the Virginian
continued; “country not been settled long enough to scare them out.”
So they fell into casual conversation, and for the first time
were glad of each other’s company.
The sound of a new bird came from the pines above⁠—the hoot
of an owl⁠—and was answered from some other part of the wood.
This they did not particularly notice at first, but soon they
heard the same note, unexpectedly distant, like an echo.
The game trail, now quite a defined path beside the river, showed no sign of changing
its course or fading out into blank ground, as these uncertain guides do so often.
It led consistently in the desired direction, and the two men
were relieved to see it continue.
Not only were the runaways easier to keep track of, but better
speed was made along this valley.
The pervading imminence of night more and more dispelled the lingering afternoon, though there
was yet no twilight in the open, and the high peaks opposite shone yellow in the invisible sun.
But now the owls hooted again.
Their music had something in it that caused both the Virginian and
Balaam to look up at the pines and wish that this valley would end.
Perhaps it was early for night-birds to begin; or perhaps it was that the sound never seemed to fall behind, but moved abreast
of them among the trees above, as they rode on without pause down below; some influence made the faces of the travellers grave.
The spell of evil which the sight of the wheeling buzzard had begun, deepened as evening grew, while ever and again
along the creek the singular call and answer of the owls wandered among the darkness of the trees not far away.
The sun was gone from the peaks when at length the other side
of the stream opened into a long wide meadow.
The trail they followed, after crossing a flat willow thicket by the water, ran into
dense pines, that here for the first time reached all the way down to the water’s edge.
The two men came out of the willows, and saw ahead the capricious
runaways leave the bottom and go up the hill and enter the wood.
“We must hinder that,” said the Virginian; and he dropped Pedro’s
rope.
“There’s your six-shooter. You keep the trail, and camp down there” ⁠—he
pointed to where the trees came to the water⁠—“till I head them hawsses off.
I may not get back right away.”
He galloped up the open hill and went into the pine, choosing
a place above where the vagrants had disappeared.
Balaam dismounted, and picking up his six-shooter, took the rope off
Pedro’s neck and drove him slowly down toward where the wood began.
Its interior was already dim, and Balaam saw that here must be their stopping-place tonight, since there was no telling how
wide this pine strip might extend along the trail before they could come out of it and reach another suitable camping-ground.
Pedro had recovered his strength, and he now showed signs of
restlessness.
He shied where there was not even a stone in the trail, and finally
turned sharply round.
Balaam expected he was going to rush back on the way they had
come; but the horse stood still, breathing excitedly.
He was urged forward again, though he turned more than once.
But when they were a few paces from the wood, and Balaam had got off preparatory
to camping, the horse snorted and dashed into the water, and stood still there.
The astonished Balaam followed to turn him; but Pedro seemed to lose control of
himself, and plunged to the middle of the river, and was evidently intending to cross.
Fearing that he would escape to the opposite meadow and add to their difficulties, Balaam, with the idea of turning him round, drew his
six-shooter and fired in front of the horse, divining, even as the flash cut the dusk, the secret of all this⁠—the Indians; but too late.
His bruised hand had stiffened, marring his aim, and he saw Pedro fall over in the water then rise and struggle
up the bank on the farther shore, where he now hurried also, to find that he had broken the pony’s leg.
He needed no interpreter for the voices of the seeming owls that had haunted the latter hour of their journey, and
he knew that his beast’s keener instinct had perceived the destruction that lurked in the interior of the wood.
The history of the trapper whose horse had returned without him might have been⁠—might still be⁠—his own; and he
thought of the rag that had fallen from the buzzard’s talons when he had been disturbed at his meal in the marsh.
“Peaceable” Indians were still in these mountains, and some few of them had for the past hour been
skirting his journey unseen, and now waited for him in the wood which they expected him to enter.
They had been too wary to use their rifles or show themselves, lest these travellers should be only part
of a larger company following, who would hear the noise of a shot, and catch them in the act of murder.
So, safe under the cover of the pines, they had planned to sling their silent
noose, and drag the white man from his horse as he passed through the trees.
Balaam looked over the river at the ominous wood, and then he looked at Pedro, the
horse that he had first maimed and now ruined, to whom he probably owed his life.
He was lying on the ground, quietly looking over the green meadow,
where dusk was gathering.
Perhaps he was not suffering from his wound yet, as he rested on the ground; and into his
animal intelligence there probably came no knowledge of this final stroke of his fate.
At any rate, no sound of pain came from Pedro, whose friendly
and gentle face remained turned toward the meadow.
Once more Balaam fired his pistol, and this time the aim was
true, and the horse rolled over, with a ball through his brain.
It was the best reward that remained for him.
Then Balaam rejoined the old mare, and turned from the middle
fork of Sunk Creek.
He dashed across the wide field, and went over a ridge, and found his way along in the night till
he came to the old trail⁠—the road which they would never have left but for him and his obstinacy.
He unsaddled the weary mare by Sunk Creek, where the canyon begins, letting her drag a rope and find pasture
and water, while he, lighting no fire to betray him, crouched close under a tree till the light came.
He thought of the Virginian in the wood.
But what could either have done for the other had he stayed to
look for him among the pines?
If the cowpuncher came back to the corner, he would follow Balaam’s
tracks or not.
They would meet, at any rate, where the creeks joined.
But they did not meet.
And then to Balaam the prospect of going onward to the Sunk Creek
Ranch became more than he could bear.
To come without the horses, to meet Judge Henry, to meet the guests of the Judge’s, looking as he did now after his
punishment by the Virginian, to give the news about the Judge’s favorite man⁠—no, how could he tell such a story as this?
Balaam went no farther than a certain cabin, where he slept,
and wrote a letter to the Judge.
This the owner of the cabin delivered.
And so, having spread news which would at once cause a search for the Virginian, and having constructed such sentences to the Judge as would
most smoothly explain how, being overtaken by illness, he had not wished to be a burden at Sunk Creek, Balaam turned homeward by himself.
By the time he was once more at Butte Creek, his general appearance
was a thing less to be noticed.
And there was Shorty, waiting!
One way and another, the lost dog had been able to gather some
ready money.
He was cheerful because of this momentary purseful of prosperity.
“And so I come back, yu’ see,” he said.
“For I figured on getting Pedro back as soon as I could when
I sold him to yu’.”
“You’re behind the times, Shorty,” said Balaam.
Shorty looked blank.
“You’ve sure not sold Pedro?” he exclaimed.
“Them Indians,” said Balaam, “got after me on the Bow Leg trail.
Got after me and that Virginia man.
But they didn’t get me.”
Balaam wagged his bullet head to imply that this escape was due
to his own superior intelligence.
The Virginian had been stupid, and so the Indians had got him.
“And they shot your horse,” Balaam finished.
“Stop and get some dinner with the boys.”
Having eaten, Shorty rode away in mournful spirits.
For he had made so sure of once more riding and talking with
Pedro, his friend whom he had taught to shake hands.
CHAPTER XXVII
Grandmother Stark
Except for its chair and bed, the cabin was stripped almost bare.
Amid its emptiness of dismantled shelves and walls and floor, only the tiny
ancestress still hung in her place, last token of the home that had been.
This miniature, tacked against the despoiled boards, and its descendant, the angry girl with her hand on an open
box-lid, made a sort of couple in the loneliness: she on the wall sweet and serene, she by the box sweet and stormy.
The picture was her final treasure waiting to be packed for the
journey.
In whatever room she had called her own since childhood, there it had also lived and looked at her,
not quite familiar, not quite smiling, but in its prim colonial hues delicate as some pressed flower.
Its pale oval, of color blue and rose and flaxen, in a battered, pretty gold frame,
unconquerably pervaded any surroundings with a something like last year’s lavender.
Till yesterday a Crow Indian war-bonnet had hung next it, a sumptuous cascade of feathers; on the other side a bow with arrows had dangled;
opposite had been the skin of a silver fox; over the door had spread the antlers of a blacktail deer; a bearskin stretched beneath it.
Thus had the whole cozy log cabin been upholstered, lavish with trophies of the
frontier; and yet it was in front of the miniature that the visitors used to stop.
Shining quietly now in the cabin’s blackness this summer day,
the heirloom was presiding until the end.
And as Molly Wood’s eyes fell upon her ancestress of Bennington, 1777, there flashed
a spark of steel in them, alone here in the room that she was leaving forever.
She was not going to teach school any more on Bear Creek, Wyoming;
she was going home to Bennington, Vermont.
When time came for school to open again, there should be a new
schoolmarm.
This was the momentous result of that visit which the Virginian
had paid her.
He had told her that he was coming for his hour soon.
From that hour she had decided to escape.
She was running away from her own heart.
She did not dare to trust herself face to face again with her
potent, indomitable lover.
She longed for him, and therefore she would never see him again.
No great-aunt at Dunbarton, or anybody else that knew her and her family, should
ever say that she had married below her station, had been an unworthy Stark!
Accordingly, she had written to the Virginian, bidding him goodbye,
and wishing him everything in the world.
As she happened to be aware that she was taking everything in the world
away from him, this letter was not the most easy of letters to write.
But she had made the language very kind.
Yes; it was a thoroughly kind communication.
And all because of that momentary visit, when he had brought
back to her two novels, Emma and Pride and Prejudice.
“How do you like them?” she had then inquired; and he had smiled
slowly at her.
“You haven’t read them!” she exclaimed.
“No.”
“Are you going to tell me there has been no time?”
Then Molly had scolded her cowpuncher, and to this he had listened with
pleasure undisguised, as indeed he listened to every word that she said.
“Why, it has come too late,” he had told her when the scolding
was over.
“If I was one of your little scholars hyeh in Bear Creek schoolhouse,
yu’ could learn me to like such frillery I reckon.
But I’m a mighty ignorant, growed-up man.”
“So much the worse for you !” said Molly.
“No. I am pretty glad I am a man. Else I could not have learned
the thing you have taught me.”
But she shut her lips and looked away.
On the desk was a letter written from Vermont.
“If you don’t tell me at once when you decide,” had said the
arch writer, “never hope to speak to me again.
Mary Wood, seriously, I am suspicious.
Why do you never mention him nowadays?
How exciting to have you bring a live cowboy to Bennington!
We should all come to dinner.
Though of course I understand now that many of them have excellent
manners.
But would he wear his pistol at table?”
So the letter ran on.
It recounted the latest home gossip and jokes.
In answering it Molly Wood had taken no notice of its childish
tone here and there.
“Hyeh’s some of them cactus blossoms yu’ wanted,” said the Virginian.
His voice recalled the girl with almost a start.
“I’ve brought a good hawss I’ve gentled for yu’, and Taylor’ll
keep him till I need him.”
“Thank you so much! but I wish⁠—”
“I reckon yu’ can’t stop me lendin’ Taylor a hawss.
And you cert’nly’ll get sick schoolteachin’ if yu’ don’t keep
outdoors some.
Goodbye⁠—till that next time
.”
“Yes; there’s always a next time,” she answered, as lightly as
she could.
“There always will be. Don’t yu’ know that?”
She did not reply.
“I have discouraged spells,” he pursued, “but I down them.
For I’ve told yu’ you were going to love me.
You are goin’ to learn back the thing you have taught me.
I’m not askin’ anything now; I don’t want you to speak a word
to me.
But I’m never goin’ to quit till ‘next time’ is no more
,
and
it’s ‘all the time’ for you and me.”
With that he had ridden away, not even touching her hand.
Long after he had gone she was still in her chair, her eyes
lingering upon his flowers, those yellow cups of the prickly pear.
At length she had risen impatiently, caught up the flowers, gone with them
to the open window⁠—and then, after all, set them with pains in water.
But today Bear Creek was over.
She was going home now.
By the week’s end she would be started.
By the time the mail brought him her goodbye letter she would
be gone.
She had acted.
To Bear Creek, the neighborly, the friendly, the not comprehending,
this move had come unlooked for, and had brought regret.
Only one hard word had been spoken to Molly, and that by her
next-door neighbor and kindest friend.
In Mrs. Taylor’s house the girl had daily come and gone as a
daughter, and that lady reached the subject thus:⁠—
“When I took Taylor,” said she, sitting by as Robert Browning
and Jane Austen were going into their box, “I married for love.”
“Do you wish it had been money?” said Molly, stooping to her
industries.
“You know both of us better than that, child.”
“I know I’ve seen people at home who couldn’t possibly have had
any other reason. They seemed satisfied, too.”
“Maybe the poor ignorant things were!”
“And so I have never been sure how I might choose.”
“Yes, you are sure, deary.
Don’t you think I know you?
And when it comes over Taylor once in a while, and he tells me I’m the best thing in his life, and I tell him he ain’t merely the best
thing but the only thing in mine⁠—him and the children⁠—why, we just agree we’d do it all over the same way if we had the chance.”
Molly continued to be industrious.
“And that’s why,” said Mrs. Taylor, “I want every girl that’s
anything to me to know her luck when it comes.
For I was that near telling Taylor I wouldn’t!”
“If ever my luck comes,” said Molly, with her back to her friend,
“I shall say ‘I will’ at once.”
“Then you’ll say it at Bennington next week.”
Molly wheeled round.
“Why, you surely will. Do you expect he’s going to stay here,
and you in Bennington?”
And the campaigner sat back in her chair.
“He? Goodness! Who is he?”
“Child, child, you’re talking cross today because you’re at outs
with yourself.
You’ve been at outs ever since you took this idea of leaving
the school and us and everything this needless way.
You have not treated him right.
And why, I can’t make out to save me.
What have you found out all of a sudden?
If he was not good enough for you, I⁠—But, oh, it’s a prime one
you’re losing, Molly.
When a man like that stays faithful to a girl ’spite all the
chances he gets, her luck is come.”
“Oh, my luck! People have different notions of luck.”
“Notions!”
“He has been very kind.”
“Kind!”
And now without further simmering, Mrs. Taylor’s wrath boiled
up and poured copiously over Molly Wood.
“Kind!
There’s a word you shouldn’t use, my dear.
No doubt you can spell it.
But more than its spelling I guess you don’t know.
The children can learn what it means from some of the rest of
us folks that don’t spell so correct, maybe.”
“Mrs. Taylor, Mrs. Taylor⁠—”
“I can’t wait, deary.
Since the roughness looks bigger to you than the diamond, you
had better go back to Vermont.
I expect you’ll find better grammar there, deary.”
The good dame stalked out, and across to her own cabin, and left
the angry girl among her boxes.
It was in vain she fell to work upon them.
Presently something had to be done over again, and when it was
the box held several chattels less than before the readjustment.
She played a sort of desperate dominos to fit these objects in the space, but here were a paperweight, a portfolio, with two wretched volumes that no chink would
harbor; and letting them fall all at once, she straightened herself, still stormy with revolt, eyes and cheeks still hot from the sting of long-parried truth.
There, on her wall still, was the miniature, the little silent
ancestress; and upon this face the girl’s glance rested.
It was as if she appealed to Grandmother Stark for support and
comfort across the hundred years which lay between them.
So the flaxen girl on the wall and she among the boxes stood a moment face to
face in seeming communion, and then the descendant turned again to her work.
But after a desultory touch here and there she drew a long breath
and walked to the open door.
What use was in finishing today, when she had nearly a week?
This first spurt of toil had swept the cabin bare of all indwelling
charm, and its look was chill.
Across the lane his horse, the one he had “gentled” for her,
was grazing idly.
She walked there and caught him, and led him to her gate.
Mrs. Taylor saw her go in, and soon come out in riding-dress; and she watched
the girl throw the saddle on with quick ease⁠—the ease he had taught her.
Mrs. Taylor also saw the sharp cut she gave the horse, and laughed grimly to herself
in her window as horse and rider galloped into the beautiful sunny loneliness.
To the punished animal this switching was new!
and at its third repetition he turned his head in surprise, but was no more heeded
than were the bluffs and flowers where he was taking his own undirected choice of way.
He carried her over ground she knew by heart⁠—Corncliff Mesa, Crowheart Butte, Westfall’s Crossing, Upper
Canyon; open land and woodland, pines and sagebrush, all silent and grave and lustrous in the sunshine.
Once and again a ranchman greeted her, and wondered if she had forgotten who he was; once
she passed some cowpunchers with a small herd of steers, and they stared after her too.
Bear Creek narrowed, its mountainsides drew near, its little falls began
to rush white in midday shadow, and the horse suddenly pricked his ears.
Unguided, he was taking this advantage to go home.
Though he had made but little way⁠—a mere beginning yet⁠—on this trail over to Sunk Creek, here was already a Sunk
Creek friend whinnying good day to him, so he whinnied back and quickened his pace, and Molly started to life.
What was Monte doing here?
She saw the black horse she knew also, saddled, with reins
dragging on the trail as the rider had dropped them to dismount.
A cold spring bubbled out beyond the next rock, and she knew
her lover’s horse was waiting for him while he drank.
She pulled at the reins, but loosed them, for to turn and escape now was
ridiculous; and riding boldly round the rock, she came upon him by the spring.
One of his arms hung up to its elbow in the pool, the other was crooked beside his head, but the
face was sunk downward against the shelving rock, so that she saw only his black, tangled hair.
As her horse snorted and tossed his head she looked swiftly at
Monte, as if to question him.
Seeing now the sweat matted on his coat, and noting the white
rim of his eye, she sprang and ran to the motionless figure.
A patch of blood at his shoulder behind stained the soft flannel shirt, spreading down
beneath his belt, and the man’s whole strong body lay slack and pitifully helpless.
She touched the hand beside his head, but it seemed neither warm nor cold to her; she felt for the pulse, as nearly as she could remember the doctors did, but could
not tell whether she imagined or not that it was still; twice with painful care her fingers sought and waited for the beat, and her face seemed like one of listening.
She leaned down and lifted his other arm and hand from the water, and as their ice-coldness reached her senses, clearly she saw the patch
near the shoulder she had moved grow wet with new blood, and at that sight she grasped at the stones upon which she herself now sank.
She held tight by two rocks, sitting straight beside him, staring, and murmuring aloud, “I
must not faint; I will not faint;” and the standing horses looked at her, pricking their ears.
In this cup-like spread of the ravine the sun shone warmly down, the tall red cliff was warm, the pines were a warm film and filter of green; outside
the shade across Bear Creek rose the steep, soft, open yellow hill, warm and high to the blue, and Bear Creek tumbled upon its sunsparkling stones.
The two horses on the margin trail still looked at the spring and trees, where sat the
neat flaxen girl so rigid by the slack prone body in its flannel shirt and leathern chaps.
Suddenly her face livened.
“But the blood ran!” she exclaimed, as if to the horses, her
companions in this.
She moved to him, and put her hand in through his shirt against
his heart.
Next moment she had sprung up and was at his saddle, searching, then
swiftly went on to her own and got her small flask and was back beside him.
Here was the cold water he had sought, and she put it against
his forehead and drenched the wounded shoulder with it.
Three times she tried to move him, so he might lie more easy, but his dead weight was
too much, and desisting, she sat close and raised his head to let it rest against her.
Thus she saw the blood that was running from in front of the
shoulder also; but she said no more about fainting.
She tore strips from her dress and soaked them, keeping them cold and wet upon both openings
of his wound, and she drew her pocketknife out and cut his shirt away from the place.
As she continually rinsed and cleaned it, she watched his eyelashes,
long and soft and thick, but they did not stir.
Again she tried the flask, but failed from being still too gentle,
and her searching eyes fell upon ashes near the pool.
Still undispersed by the weather lay the small charred ends of a fire
he and she had made once here together, to boil coffee and fry trout.
She built another fire now, and when the flames were going
well, filled her flask-cup from the spring and set it to heat.
Meanwhile, she returned to nurse his head and wound.
Her cold water had stopped the bleeding.
Then she poured her brandy in the steaming cup, and, made rough by
her desperate helplessness, forced some between his lips and teeth.
Instantly, almost, she felt the tremble of life creeping back,
and as his deep eyes opened upon her she sat still and mute.
But the gaze seemed luminous with an unnoting calm, and she wondered if perhaps he could not recognize her; she watched this internal clearness of his
vision, scarcely daring to breathe, until presently he began to speak, with the same profound and clear impersonality sounding in his slowly uttered words.
“I thought they had found me. I expected they were going to kill
me.”
He stopped, and she gave him more of the hot drink, which he took, still
lying and looking at her as if the present did not reach his senses.
“I knew hands were touching me.
I reckon I was not dead.
I knew about them soon as they began, only I could not interfere.”
He waited again.
“It is mighty strange where I have been. No. Mighty natural.”
Then he went back into his revery, and lay with his eyes still
full open upon her where she sat motionless.
She began to feel a greater awe in this living presence than when it had been his body with
an ice-cold hand; and she quietly spoke his name, venturing scarcely more than a whisper.
At this, some nearer thing wakened in his look.
“But it was you all along,” he resumed.
“It is you now. You must not stay⁠—”
Weakness overcame him, and his eyes closed.
She sat ministering to him, and when he roused again, he began
anxiously at once: “You must not stay.
They would get you, too.”
She glanced at him with a sort of fierceness, then reached for
his pistol, in which was nothing but blackened empty cartridges.
She threw these out and drew six from his belt, loaded the weapon,
and snapped shut its hinge.
“Please take it,” he said, more anxious and more himself.
“I ain’t worth tryin’ to keep. Look at me!”
“Are you giving up?” she inquired, trying to put scorn in her
tone.
Then she seated herself.
“Where is the sense in both of us⁠—”
“You had better save your strength,” she interrupted.
He tried to sit up.
“Lie down!” she ordered.
He sank obediently, and began to smile.
When she saw that, she smiled too, and unexpectedly took his
hand.
“Listen, friend,” said she.
“Nobody shall get you, and nobody shall get me. Now take some
more brandy.”
“It must be noon,” said the cowpuncher, when she had drawn her
hand away from him.
“I remember it was dark when⁠—when⁠—when I can remember.
I reckon they were scared to follow me in so close to settlers.
Else they would have been here.”
“You must rest,” she observed.
She broke the soft ends of some evergreen, and putting them beneath his head, went to the
horses, loosened the cinches, took off the bridles, led them to drink, and picketed them to feed.
Further still, to leave nothing undone which she could herself manage, she took the horses’
saddles off to refold the blankets when the time should come, and meanwhile brought them for him.
But he put them away from him.
He was sitting up against a rock, stronger evidently, and asking
for cold water.
His head was fire-hot, and the paleness beneath his swarthy skin
had changed to a deepening flush.
“Only five miles!” she said to him, bathing his head.
“Yes. I must hold it steady,” he answered, waving his hand at
the cliff.
She told him to try and keep it steady until they got home.
“Yes,” he repeated.
“Only five miles. But it’s fightin’ to turn around.”
Half aware that he was becoming lightheaded, he looked from the
rock to her and from her to the rock with dilating eyes.
“We can hold it together,” she said.
“You must get on your horse.”
She took his handkerchief from round his neck, knotting it with her own, and to make more
bandage she ran to the roll of clothes behind his saddle and tore in halves a clean shirt.
A handkerchief fell from it, which she seized also, and opening,
saw her own initials by the hem.
Then she remembered: she saw again their first meeting, the swollen river, the overset stage, the unknown horseman who carried her to the bank on his saddle and went
away unthanked⁠—her whole first adventure on that first day of her coming to this new country⁠—and now she knew how her long-forgotten handkerchief had gone that day.
She refolded it gently and put it back in his bundle, for there
was enough bandage without it.
She said not a word to him, and he placed a wrong meaning upon
the look which she gave him as she returned to bind his shoulder.
“It don’t hurt so much,” he assured her (though extreme pain was clearing his
head for the moment, and he had been able to hold the cliff from turning).
“Yu’ must not squander your pity.”
“Do not squander your strength,” said she.
“Oh, I could put up a pretty good fight now!”
But he tottered in showing her how strong he was, and she told
him that, after all, he was a child still.
“Yes,” he slowly said, looking after her as she went to bring his
horse, “the same child that wanted to touch the moon, I guess.”
And during the slow climb down into the saddle from a rock to which she
helped him he said, “You have got to be the man all through this mess.”
She saw his teeth clinched and his drooping muscles compelled by will; and as he rode and she walked to lend him support, leading her horse by a backward-stretched left hand, she counted off the distance to him
continually⁠—the increasing gain, the lessening road, the landmarks nearing and dropping behind; here was the tree with the wasp-nest gone; now the burned cabin was passed; now the cottonwoods at the ford were in sight.
He was silent, and held to the saddle-horn, leaning more and more against his two hands clasped over it; and just
after they had made the crossing he fell, without a sound slipping to the grass, and his descent broken by her.
But it started the blood a little, and she dared not leave him
to seek help.
She gave him the last of the flask and all the water he craved.
Revived, he managed to smile.
“Yu’ see, I ain’t worth keeping.”
“It’s only a mile,” said she.
So she found a log, a fallen trunk, and he crawled to that, and from there crawled to his
saddle, and she marched on with him, talking, bidding him note the steps accomplished.
For the next half-mile they went thus, the silent man clinched on the horse, and by
his side the girl walking and cheering him forward, when suddenly he began to speak:⁠—
“I will say goodbye to you now, ma’am.”
She did not understand, at first, the significance of this.
“He is getting away,” pursued the Virginian.
“I must ask you to excuse me, ma’am.”
It was a long while since her lord had addressed her as “ma’am.”
As she looked at him in growing apprehension, he turned Monte
and would have ridden away, but she caught the bridle.
“You must take me home,” said she, with ready inspiration.
“I am afraid of the Indians.”
“Why, you⁠—why, they’ve all gone. There he goes. Ma’am⁠—that
hawss⁠—”
“No,” said she, holding firmly his rein and quickening her step.
“A gentleman does not invite a lady to go out riding and leave
her.”
His eyes lost their purpose.
“I’ll cert’nly take you home. That sorrel has gone in there by
the wallow, and Judge Henry will understand.”
With his eyes watching imaginary objects, he rode and rambled and it was now the
girl who was silent, except to keep his mind from its half-fixed idea of the sorrel.
As he grew more fluent she hastened still more, listening to head off that notion of return, skilfully inventing questions to engage him, so that when she brought him to her gate she held him in a manner subjected, answering faithfully
the shrewd unrealities which she devised, whatever makeshifts she could summon to her mind; and next she had got him inside her dwelling and set him down docile, but now completely wandering; and then⁠—no help was at hand, even here.
She had made sure of aid from next door, and there she hastened, to find the Taylor’s cabin locked and silent; and this meant that parents and
children were gone to drive; nor might she be luckier at her next nearest neighbors’, should she travel the intervening mile to fetch them.
With a mind jostled once more into uncertainty, she returned
to her room, and saw a change in him already.
Illness had stridden upon him; his face was not as she had left it, and the whole body, the splendid supple
horseman, showed sickness in every line and limb, its spurs and pistol and bold leather chaps a mockery of trappings.
She looked at him, and decision came back to her, clear and steady.
She supported him over to her bed and laid him on it.
His head sank flat, and his loose, nerveless arms stayed as she
left them.
Then among her packing-boxes and beneath the little miniature,
blue and flaxen and gold upon its lonely wall, she undressed him.
He was cold, and she covered him to the face, and arranged the pillow, and
got from its box her scarlet and black Navajo blanket and spread it over him.
There was no more that she could do, and she sat down by him
to wait.
Among the many and many things that came into her mind was a
word he said to her lightly a long while ago.
“Cowpunchers do not live long enough to get old,” he had told
her.
And now she looked at the head upon the pillow, grave and strong,
but still the head of splendid, unworn youth.
At the distant jingle of the wagon in the lane she was out, and
had met her returning neighbors midway.
They heard her with amazement, and came in haste to the bedside; then Taylor
departed to spread news of the Indians and bring the doctor, twenty-five miles away.
The two women friends stood alone again, as they had stood in
the morning when anger had been between them.
“Kiss me, deary,” said Mrs. Taylor.
“Now I will look after him⁠—and you’ll need some looking after
yourself.”
But on returning from her cabin with what store she possessed of
lint and stimulants, she encountered a rebel, independent as ever.
Molly would hear no talk about saving her strength, would not be in any room but this
one until the doctor should arrive; then perhaps it would be time to think about resting.
So together the dame and the girl rinsed the man’s wound and wrapped him in clean things,
and did all the little that they knew⁠—which was, in truth, the very thing needed.
Then they sat watching him toss and mutter.
It was no longer upon Indians or the sorrel horse that his talk seemed
to run, or anything recent, apparently, always excepting his work.
This flowingly merged with whatever scene he was inventing or living
again, and he wandered unendingly in that incompatible world we dream in.
Through the medley of events and names, often thickly spoken, but rising at times to grotesque
coherence, the listeners now and then could piece out the reference from their own knowledge.
“Monte,” for example, continually addressed, and Molly heard her own name, but invariably as
“Miss Wood”; nothing less respectful came out, and frequently he answered someone as “ma’am.”
At these fragments of revelation Mrs. Taylor abstained from speech,
but eyed Molly Wood with caustic reproach.
As the night wore on, short lulls of silence intervened, and
the watchers were deceived into hope that the fever was abating.
And when the Virginian sat quietly up in bed, essayed to move his bandage, and looked steadily
at Mrs. Taylor, she rose quickly and went to him with a question as to how he was doing.
“Rise on your laigs, you polecat,” said he, “and tell them you’re
a liar.”
The good dame gasped, then bade him lie down, and he obeyed her with that strange double understanding
of the delirious; for even while submitting, he muttered “liar,” “polecat,” and then “Trampas.”
At that name light flashed on Mrs. Taylor, and she turned to Molly; and there was the girl
struggling with a fit of mirth at his speech; but the laughter was fast becoming a painful seizure.
Mrs. Taylor walked Molly up and down, speaking immediately to
arrest her attention.
“You might as well know it,” she said.
“He would blame me for speaking of it, but where’s the harm all
this while after?
And you would never hear it from his mouth.
Molly, child, they say Trampas would kill him if he dared, and
that’s on account of you.”
“I never saw Trampas,” said Molly, fixing her eyes upon the speaker.
“No, deary.
But before a lot of men⁠—Taylor has told me about it⁠—Trampas spoke
disrespectfully of you, and before them all he made Trampas say he was a liar.
That is what he did when you were almost a stranger among us,
and he had not started seeing so much of you.
I expect Trampas is the only enemy he ever had in this country.
But he would never let you know about that.”
“No,” whispered Molly; “I did not know.”
“Steve!” the sick man now cried out, in poignant appeal.
“Steve!”
To the women it was a name unknown⁠—unknown as was also this deep inward
tide of feeling which he could no longer conceal, being himself no longer.
“No, Steve,” he said next, and muttering followed.
“It ain’t so!” he shouted; and then cunningly in a lowered voice,
“Steve, I have lied for you.”
In time Mrs. Taylor spoke some advice.
“You had better go to bed, child. You look about ready for the
doctor yourself.”
“Then I will wait for him,” said Molly.
So the two nurses continued to sit until darkness at the windows
weakened into gray, and the lamp was no more needed.
Their patient was rambling again.
Yet, into whatever scenes he went, there in some guise did the throb of his pain evidently
follow him, and he lay hitching his great shoulder as if to rid it of the cumbrance.
They waited for the doctor, not daring much more than to turn pillows and give what other ease they could; and then, instead of the doctor, came
a messenger, about noon, to say he was gone on a visit some thirty miles beyond, where Taylor had followed to bring him here as soon as might be.
At this Molly consented to rest and to watch, turn about; and once she
was over in her friend’s house lying down, they tried to keep her there.
But the revolutionist could not be put down, and when, as a last pretext, Mrs. Taylor urged the proprieties
and conventions, the pale girl from Vermont laughed sweetly in her face and returned to sit by the sick man.
With the approach of the second night his fever seemed to rise and master him more completely than they
had yet seen it, and presently it so raged that the women called in stronger arms to hold him down.
There were times when he broke out in the language of the roundup,
and Mrs. Taylor renewed her protests.
“Why,” said Molly, “don’t you suppose I knew they could swear?”
So the dame, in deepening astonishment and affection, gave up
these shifts at decorum.
Nor did the delirium run into the intimate, coarse matters that
she dreaded.
The cowpuncher had lived like his kind, but his natural daily thoughts
were clean, and came from the untamed but unstained mind of a man.
And toward morning, as Mrs. Taylor sat taking her turn, suddenly he
asked had he been sick long, and looked at her with a quieted eye.
The wandering seemed to drop from him at a stroke, leaving him
altogether himself.
He lay very feeble, and inquired once or twice of his state and how he came here; nor
was anything left in his memory of even coming to the spring where he had been found.
When the doctor arrived, he pronounced that it would be long⁠—or
very short.
He praised their clean water treatment; the wound was fortunately well up on the shoulder, and gave so far no bad signs; there were not any bad signs; and the blood and
strength of the patient had been as few men’s were; each hour was now an hour nearer certainty, and meanwhile⁠—meanwhile the doctor would remain as long as he could.
He had many inquiries to satisfy.
Dusty fellows would ride up, listen to him, and reply, as they
rode away, “Don’t yu’ let him die, Doc.”
And Judge Henry sent over from Sunk Creek to answer for any attendance
or medicine that might help his foreman.
The country was moved with concern and interest; and in Molly’s ears its words of
good feeling seemed to unite and sum up a burden, “Don’t yu’ let him die, Doc.”
The Indians who had done this were now in military custody.
They had come unpermitted from a southern reservation, hunting, next thieving, and as the slumbering spirit roused in one or
two of the young and ambitious, they had ventured this in the secret mountains, and perhaps had killed a trapper found there.
Editors immediately reared a tall war out of it; but from five Indians in a guardhouse waiting punishment not even an editor can
supply spar for more than two editions, and if the recent alarm was still a matter of talk anywhere, it was not here in the sickroom.
Whichever way the case should turn, it was through Molly alone (the doctor told
her) that the wounded man had got this chance⁠—this good chance, he related.
And he told her she had not done a woman’s part, but a man’s part, and now had no more to do; no more till the patient got well,
and could thank her in his own way, said the doctor, smiling, and supposing things that were not so⁠—misled perhaps by Mrs. Taylor.
“I’m afraid I’ll be gone by the time he is well,” said Molly, coldly; and the discreet
physician said ah, and that she would find Bennington quite a change from Bear Creek.
But Mrs. Taylor spoke otherwise, and at that the girl said: “I
shall stay as long as I am needed.
I will nurse him.
I want to nurse him.
I will do everything for him that I can!” she exclaimed, with
force.
“And that won’t be anything, deary,” said Mrs. Taylor, harshly.
“A year of nursing don’t equal a day of sweetheart.”
The girl took a walk⁠—she was of no more service in the room at present⁠—but she turned without going far, and Mrs. Taylor spied
her come to lean over the pasture fence and watch the two horses⁠—that one the Virginian had “gentled” for her, and his own Monte.
During this suspense came a new call for the doctor, neighbors profiting by his visit to Bear Creek; and
in his going away to them, even under promise of quick return, Mrs. Taylor suspected a favorable sign.
He kept his word as punctually as had been possible, arriving after some six hours with a confident
face, and spending now upon the patient a care not needed, save to reassure the bystanders.
He spoke his opinion that all was even better than he could have
hoped it would be, so soon.
Here was now the beginning of the fifth day; the wound’s look was wholesome, no
further delirium had come, and the fever had abated a degree while he was absent.
He believed the serious danger-line lay behind, and (short of the
unforeseen) the man’s deep untainted strength would reassert its control.
He had much blood to make, and must be cared for during weeks⁠—three,
four, five⁠—there was no saying how long yet.
These next few days it must be utter quiet for him; he must not talk nor hear anything likely to disturb
him; and then the time for cheerfulness and gradual company would come⁠—sooner than later, the doctor hoped.
So he departed, and sent next day some bottles, with further cautions regarding
the wound and dirt, and to say he should be calling the day after tomorrow.
Upon that occasion he found two patients.
Molly Wood lay in bed at Mrs. Taylor’s, filled with apology and
indignation.
With little to do, and deprived of the strong stimulant of anxiety and action, her
strength had quite suddenly left her, so that she had spoken only in a sort of whisper.
But upon waking from a long sleep, after Mrs. Taylor had taken her firmly, almost severely, in hand, her natural voice had
returned, and now the chief treatment the doctor gave her was a sort of scolding, which it pleased Mrs. Taylor to hear.
The doctor even dropped a phrase concerning the arrogance of strong nerves in slender bodies, and of undertaking
several people’s work when several people were at hand to do it for themselves, and this pleased Mrs. Taylor remarkably.
As for the wounded man, he was behaving himself properly.
Perhaps in another week he could be moved to a more cheerful
room.
Just now, with cleanliness and pure air, any barn would do.
“We are real lucky to have such a sensible doctor in the country,”
Mrs. Taylor observed, after the physician had gone.
“No doubt,” said Molly.
“He said my room was a barn.”
“That’s what you’ve made it, deary. But sick men don’t notice
much.”
Nevertheless, one may believe, without going widely astray, that illness, so far from
veiling, more often quickens the perceptions⁠—at any rate those of the naturally keen.
On a later day⁠—and the interval was brief⁠—while Molly was on her second drive to
take the air with Mrs. Taylor, that lady informed her that the sick man had noticed.
“And I could not tell him things liable to disturb him,” said she,
“and so I⁠—well, I expect I just didn’t exactly tell him the facts.
I said yes, you were packing up for a little visit to your folks.
They had not seen you for quite a while, I said.
And he looked at those boxes kind of silent like.”
“There’s no need to move him,” said Molly.
“It is simpler to move them⁠—the boxes.
I could take out some of my things, you know, just while he has
to be kept there.
I mean⁠—you see, if the doctor says the room should be cheerful⁠—”
“Yes, deary.”
“I will ask the doctor next time,” said Molly, “if he believes
I am⁠—competent to spread a rug upon a floor.”
Molly’s references to the doctor were usually acid these days.
And this he totally failed to observe, telling her when he came,
why, to be sure!
the very thing!
And if she could play cards or read aloud, or afford any other light distractions, provided
they did not lead the patient to talk and tire himself, that she would be most useful.
Accordingly she took over the cribbage board, and came with unexpected
hesitation face to face again with the swarthy man she had saved and tended.
He was not so swarthy now, but neat, with chin clean, and hair and mustache
trimmed and smooth, and he sat propped among pillows watching for her.
“You are better,” she said, speaking first, and with uncertain
voice.
“Yes. They have given me awdehs not to talk,” said the Southerner,
smiling.
“Oh, yes. Please do not talk⁠—not today .”
“No. Only this” ⁠—he looked at her, and saw her seem to shrink⁠—“thank
you for what you have done,” he said simply.
She took tenderly the hand he stretched to her; and upon these
terms they set to work at cribbage.
She won, and won again, and the third time laid down her cards
and reproached him with playing in order to lose.
“No,” he said, and his eye wandered to the boxes.
“But my thoughts get away from me. I’ll be strong enough to hold
them on the cyards next time, I reckon.”
Many tones in his voice she had heard, but never the tone of
sadness until today.
Then they played a little more, and she put away the board for
this first time.
“You are going now?” he asked.
“When I have made this room look a little less forlorn.
They haven’t wanted to meddle with my things, I suppose.”
And Molly stooped once again among the chattels destined for
Vermont.
Out they came; again the bearskin was spread on the floor, various possessions and ornaments went back into
their ancient niches, the shelves grew comfortable with books, and, last, some flowers were stood on the table.
“More like old times,” said the Virginian, but sadly.
“It’s too bad,” said Molly, “you had to be brought into such
a looking place.”
“And your folks waiting for you,” said he.
“Oh, I’ll pay my visit later,” said Molly, putting the rug a
trifle straighter.
“May I ask one thing?” pleaded the Virginian, and at the gentleness of his
voice her face grew rosy, and she fixed her eyes on him with a sort of dread.
“Anything that I can answer,” said she.
“Oh, yes.
Did I tell yu’ to quit me, and did yu’ load up my gun and stay?
Was that a real business?
I have been mixed up in my haid.”
“That was real,” said Molly.
“What else was there to do?”
“Just nothing⁠—for such as you!” he exclaimed.
“My haid has been mighty crazy; and that little grandmother of
yours yondeh, she⁠—but I can’t just quite catch
ahold of these things”⁠—he passed a hand over his forehead⁠—“so many⁠—or else one right
along⁠—well, it’s all foolishness!” he concluded, with something almost savage in his tone.
And after she had gone from the cabin he lay very still, looking
at the miniature on the wall.
He was in another sort of mood the next time, cribbage not interesting
him in the least.
“Your folks will be wondering about you,” said he.
“I don’t think they will mind which month I go to them,” said
Molly.
“Especially when they know the reason.”
“Don’t let me keep you, ma’am,” said he.
Molly stared at him; but he pursued, with the same edge lurking
in his slow words: “Though I’ll never forget.
How could I forget any of all you have done⁠—and been?
If there had been none of this, why, I had enough to remember!
But please don’t stay, ma’am.
We’ll say I had a claim when yu’ found me pretty well dead, but
I’m gettin’ well, yu’ see⁠—right smart, too!”
“I can’t understand, indeed I can’t,” said Molly, “why you’re
talking so!”
He seemed to have certain moods when he would address her as
“ma’am,” and this she did not like, but could not prevent.
“Oh, a sick man is funny. And yu’ know I’m grateful to you.”
“Please say no more about that, or I shall go this afternoon.
I don’t want to go.
I am not ready.
I think I had better read something now.”
“Why, yes.
That’s cert’nly a good notion.
Why, this is the best show you’ll ever get to give me education.
Won’t yu’ please try that Emma book now, ma’am?
Listening to you will be different.”
This was said with softness and humility.
Uncertain⁠—as his gravity often left her⁠—precisely what he meant by what he said, Molly proceeded
with Emma, slackly at first, but soon with the enthusiasm that Miss Austen invariably gave her.
She held the volume and read away at it, commenting briefly, and then, finishing
a chapter of the sprightly classic, found her pupil slumbering peacefully.
There was no uncertainty about that.
“You couldn’t be doing a healthier thing for him, deary,” said
Mrs. Taylor.
“If it gets to make him wakeful, try something harder.”
This was the lady’s scarcely sympathetic view.
But it turned out to be not obscurity in which Miss Austen sinned.
When Molly next appeared at the Virginian’s threshold, he said
plaintively, “I reckon I am a dunce.”
And he sued for pardon.
“When I waked up,” he said, “I was ashamed of myself for a plumb
half-hour.”
Nor could she doubt this day that he meant what he said.
His mood was again serene and gentle, and without referring to his singular words
that had distressed her, he made her feel his contrition, even in his silence.
“I am right glad you have come,” he said.
And as he saw her going to the bookshelf, he continued, with diffidence: “As regyards
that Emma book, yu’ see⁠—yu’ see, the doin’s and sayin’s of folks like them are above me.
But I think” (he spoke most diffidently), “if yu’ could read me
something that was about something, I⁠—I’d be liable to keep awake.”
And he smiled with a certain shyness.
“Something about something?” queried Molly, at a loss.
“Why, yes.
Shakespeare.
Henry the Fourth.
The British king is fighting, and there is his son the prince.
He cert’nly must have been a jim-dandy boy if that is all true.
Only he would go around town with a mighty triflin’ gang.
They sported and they held up citizens.
And his father hated his travelling with trash like them.
It was right natural⁠—the boy and the old man!
But the boy showed himself a man too.
He killed a big fighter on the other side who was another jim-dandy⁠—and
he was sorry for having it to do.”
The Virginian warmed to his recital.
“I understand most all of that.
There was a fat man kept everybody laughing.
He was awful natural too; except yu’ don’t commonly meet ’em
so fat.
But the prince⁠—that play is bedrock, ma’am!
Have you got something like that?”
“Yes, I think so,” she replied.
“I believe I see what you would appreciate.”
She took her Browning, her idol, her imagined affinity.
For the pale decadence of New England had somewhat watered her good old Revolutionary blood too, and
she was inclined to think under glass and to live underdone⁠—when there were no Indians to shoot!
She would have joyed to venture Paracelsus on him, and some lengthy rhymed
discourses; and she fondly turned leaves and leaves of her pet doggerel analytics.
Pippa Passes and others she had to skip, from discreet motives⁠—pages which
he would have doubtless stayed awake at; but she chose a poem at length.
This was better than Emma, he pronounced.
And short.
The horse was a good horse.
He thought a man whose horse must not play out on him would watch the ground he was galloping
over for holes, and not be likely to see what color the rims of his animal’s eye-sockets were.
You could not see them if you sat as you ought to for such a
hard ride.
Of the next piece that she read him he thought still better.
“And it is short,” said he.
“But the last part drops.”
Molly instantly exacted particulars.
“The soldier should not have told the general he was killed,”
stated the cowpuncher.
“What should he have told him, I’d like to know?” said Molly.
“Why, just nothing.
If the soldier could ride out of the battle all shot up, and tell his
general about their takin’ the town⁠—that was being gritty, yu’ see.
But that truck at the finish⁠—will yu’ please say it again?”
So Molly read:⁠—
“ ‘You’re wounded!
‘Nay,’ the soldier’s prideTouched to the quick, he said,‘I’m
killed, sire!’
And, his chief beside,Smiling the boy fell dead.”“
‘Nay, I’m killed, sire,’ ” drawled the Virginian, amiably; for
(symptom of convalescence) his freakish irony was revived in him.
“Now a man who was man enough to act like he did, yu’ see, would
fall dead without mentioning it.”
None of Molly’s sweet girl friends had ever thus challenged Mr.
Browning.
They had been wont to cluster over him with a joyous awe that
deepened proportionally with their misunderstanding.
Molly paused to consider this novelty of view about the soldier.
“He was a Frenchman, you know,” she said, under inspiration.
“A Frenchman,” murmured the grave cowpuncher.
“I never knowed a Frenchman, but I reckon they might perform
that class of foolishness.”
“But why was it foolish?” she cried.
“His soldier’s pride⁠—don’t you see?”
“No.”
Molly now burst into a luxury of discussion.
She leaned toward her cowpuncher with bright eyes searching his; with elbow on knee and hand propping
chin, her lap became a slant, and from it Browning the poet slid and toppled, and lay unrescued.
For the slow cowpuncher unfolded his notions of masculine courage and modesty (though he did not deal in such high-sounding
names), and Molly forgot everything to listen to him, as he forgot himself and his inveterate shyness and grew talkative to her.
“I would never have supposed that!” she would exclaim as she
heard him; or, presently again, “I never had such an idea!”
And her mind opened with delight to these new things which came
from the man’s mind so simple and direct.
To Browning they did come back, but the Virginian, though interested,
conceived a dislike for him.
“He is a smarty,” said he, once or twice.
“Now here is something,” said Molly.
“I have never known what to think.”
“Oh, Heavens!” murmured the sick man, smiling.
“Is it short?”
“Very short. Now please attend.”
And she read him twelve lines about a lover who rowed to a beach
in the dusk, crossed a field, tapped at a pane, and was admitted.
“That is the best yet,” said the Virginian.
“There’s only one thing yu’ can think about that.”
“But wait,” said the girl, swiftly.
“Here is how they parted:⁠—
“Round the cape of a sudden came the sea,And the sun looked over the mountain’s
rim⁠—And straight was a path of gold for him,And the need of a world of men for me.”
“That is very, very true,” murmured the Virginian, dropping his
eyes from the girl’s intent ones.
“Had they quarrelled?” she inquired.
“Oh, no!”
“But⁠—”
“I reckon he loved her very much.”
“Then you’re sure they hadn’t quarrelled?”
“Dead sure, ma’am. He would come back afteh he had played some
more of the game.”
“The game?”
“Life, ma’am. Whatever he was a-doin’ in the world of men. That’s
a bedrock piece, ma’am!”
“Well, I don’t see why you think it’s so much better than some
of the others.”
“I could sca’cely explain,” answered the man.
“But that writer does know something.”
“I am glad they hadn’t quarrelled,” said Molly, thoughtfully.
And she began to like having her opinions refuted.
His bandages, becoming a little irksome, had to be shifted, and this turned their
discourse from literature to Wyoming; and Molly inquired, had he ever been shot before?
Only once, he told her.
“I have been lucky in having few fusses,” said he.
“I hate them. If a man has to be killed⁠—”
“You never⁠—” broke in Molly.
She had started back a little.
“Well,” she added hastily, “don’t tell me if⁠—”
“I shouldn’t wonder if I got one of those Indians,” he said quietly.
“But I wasn’t waitin’ to see!
But I came mighty near doing for a white man that day.
He had been hurtin’ a hawss.”
“Hurting?” said Molly.
“Injurin.’
I will not tell yu’ about that.
It would hurt yu’ to hear such things.
But hawsses⁠—don’t they depend on us?
Ain’t they somethin’ like children?
I did not lay up the man very bad.
He was able to travel ’most right away.
Why, you’d have wanted to kill him yourself!”
So the Virginian talked, nor knew what he was doing to the girl.
Nor was she aware of what she was receiving from him as he unwittingly
spoke himself out to her in these Browning meetings they had each day.
But Mrs. Taylor grew pleased.
The kindly dame would sometimes cross the road to see if she
were needed, and steal away again after a peep at the window.
There, inside, among the restored home treasures, sat the two: the rosy alert girl, sweet as
she talked or read to him; and he, the grave, half-weak giant among his wraps, watching her.
Of her delayed home visit he never again spoke, either to her or to Mrs. Taylor; and
Molly veered aside from any trend of talk she foresaw was leading toward that subject.
But in those hours when no visitors came, and he was by himself in the quiet, he would lie often sombrely contemplating the girl’s
room, her little dainty knickknacks, her home photographs, all the delicate manifestations of what she came from and what she was.
Strength was flowing back into him each day, and Judge Henry’s latest messenger had brought him clothes and mail from Sunk Creek and many
inquiries of kindness, and returned taking the news of the cowpuncher’s improvement, and how soon he would be permitted the fresh air.
Hence Molly found him waiting in a flannel shirt of highly becoming shade, and with a silk
handkerchief knotted round his throat; and he told her it was good to feel respectable again.
She had come to read to him for the allotted time; and she threw around his shoulders
the scarlet and black Navajo blanket, striped with its splendid zigzags of barbarity.
Thus he half sat, half leaned, languid but at ease.
In his lap lay one of the letters brought over by the messenger: and though she was midway in a book that engaged his full
attention⁠—David Copperfield⁠—his silence and absent look this morning stopped her, and she accused him of not attending.
“No,” he admitted; “I am thinking of something else.”
She looked at him with that apprehension which he knew.
“It had to come,” said he.
“And today I see my thoughts straighter than I’ve been up to
managing since⁠—since my haid got clear.
And now I must say these thoughts⁠—if I can, if I can!”
He stopped.
His eyes were intent upon her; one hand was gripping the arm
of his chair.
“You promised⁠—” trembled Molly.
“I promised you should love me,” he sternly interrupted.
“Promised that to myself. I have broken that word.”
She shut David Copperfield mechanically, and grew white.
“Your letter has come to me hyeh,” he continued, gentle again.
“My⁠—” She had forgotten it.
“The letter you wrote to tell me goodbye.
You wrote it a little while ago⁠—not a month yet, but it’s away
and away long gone for me.”
“I have never let you know⁠—” began Molly.
“The doctor,” he interrupted once more, but very gently now,
“he gave awdehs I must be kept quiet.
I reckon yu’ thought tellin’ me might⁠—”
“Forgive me!” cried the girl.
“Indeed I ought to have told you sooner! Indeed I had no excuse!”
“Why, should yu’ tell me if yu’ preferred not? You had written. And you speak” (he lifted
the letter) “of never being able to repay kindness; but you have turned the tables.
I can never repay you by anything!
by anything!
So I had figured I would just jog back to Sunk Creek and let
you get away, if you did not want to say that kind of goodbye.
For I saw the boxes.
Mrs. Taylor is too nice a woman to know the trick of lyin’, and
she could not deceive me.
I have knowed yu’ were going away for good ever since I saw those
boxes.
But now hyeh comes your letter, and it seems no way but I must
speak.
I have thought a deal, lyin’ in this room.
And⁠—today⁠—I can say what I have thought.
I could not make you happy.”
He stopped, but she did not answer.
His voice had grown softer than whispering, but yet was not a
whisper.
From its quiet syllables she turned away, blinded with sudden
tears.
“Once, I thought love must surely be enough,” he continued.
“And I thought if I could make you love me, you could learn me
to be less⁠—less⁠—more your kind.
And I think I could give you a pretty good sort of love.
But that don’t help the little mean pesky things of day by day that
make roughness or smoothness for folks tied together so awful close.
Mrs. Taylor hyeh⁠—she don’t know anything better than Taylor
does.
She don’t want anything he can’t give her.
Her friends will do for him and his for her.
And when I dreamed of you in my home⁠—” he closed his eyes and
drew a long breath.
At last he looked at her again.
“This is no country for a lady. Will yu’ forget and forgive the
bothering I have done?”
“Oh!” cried Molly.
“Oh!”
And she put her hands to her eyes.
She had risen and stood with her face covered.
“I surely had to tell you this all out, didn’t I?” said the cowpuncher,
faintly, in his chair.
“Oh!” said Molly again.
“I have put it clear how it is,” he pursued.
“I ought to have seen from the start I was not the sort to keep
you happy.”
“But,” said Molly⁠—“but I⁠—you ought⁠—please try to keep me happy!”
And sinking by his chair, she hid her face on his knees.
Speechless, he bent down and folded her round, putting his hands
on the hair that had been always his delight.
Presently he whispered:⁠—
“You have beat me; how can I fight this?”
She answered nothing.
The Navajo’s scarlet and black folds fell over both.
Not with words, not even with meeting eyes, did the two plight
their troth in this first new hour.
So they remained long, the fair head nesting in the great arms, and the black head laid against it, while over the silent
room presided the little Grandmother Stark in her frame, rosy, blue, and flaxen, not quite familiar, not quite smiling.
CHAPTER XXVIII
No Dream to Wake from
For a long while after she had left him, he lay still, stretched
in his chair.
His eyes were fixed steadily upon the open window and the sunshine
outside.
There he watched the movement of the leaves upon the green cottonwoods.
What had she said to him when she went?
She had said, “Now I know how unhappy I have been.”
These sweet words he repeated to himself over and over, fearing
in some way that he might lose them.
They almost slipped from him at times; but with a jump of his mind he caught
them again and held them⁠—and then⁠—“I’m not all strong yet,” he murmured.
“I must have been very sick.”
And, weak from his bullet wound and fever, he closed his eyes
without knowing it.
There were the cottonwoods again, waving, waving; and he felt
the cool, pleasant air from the window.
He saw the light draught stir the ashes in the great stone fireplace.
“I have been asleep,” he said.
“But she was cert’nly here herself.
Oh, yes.
Surely.
She always has to go away every day because the doctor says⁠—why,
she was readin’!” he broke off, aloud.
“David Copperfield.”
There it was on the floor.
“Aha! nailed you anyway!” he said.
“But how scared I am of myself!⁠—You’re a fool.
Of course it’s so.
No fever business could make yu’ feel like this.”
His eye dwelt awhile on the fireplace, next on the deer horns, and
next it travelled toward the shelf where her books were; but it
stopped before reaching them.
“Better say off the names before I look,” said he.
“I’ve had a heap o’ misreading visions.
And⁠—and supposin’⁠—if this was just my sickness fooling me some
more⁠—I’d want to die.
I would die!
Now we’ll see.
If Copperfield is on the floor” (he looked stealthily to be sure that it was), “then she was
readin’ to me when everything happened, and then there should be a hole in the book row, top, left.
Top, left,” he repeated, and warily brought his glance to the
place.
“Proved!” he cried.
“It’s all so!”
He now noticed the miniature of Grandmother Stark.
“You are awful like her,” he whispered.
“You’re cert’nly awful like her. May I kiss you too, ma’am?”
Then, tottering, he rose from his sick-chair.
The Navajo blanket fell from his shoulders, and gradually, experimentally,
he stood upright.
Helping himself with his hand slowly along the wall of the room, and round to the opposite wall with many
a pause, he reached the picture, and very gently touched the forehead of the ancestral dame with his lips.
“I promise to make your little girl happy,” he whispered.
He almost fell in stooping to the portrait, but caught himself
and stood carefully quiet, trembling, and speaking to himself.
“Where is your strength?” he demanded.
“I reckon it is joy that has unsteadied your laigs.”
The door opened.
It was she, come back with his dinner.
“My Heavens!” she said; and setting the tray down, she rushed
to him.
She helped him back to his chair, and covered him again.
He had suffered no hurt, but she clung to him; and presently
he moved and let himself kiss her with fuller passion.
“I will be good,” he whispered.
“You must,” she said.
“You looked so pale!”
“You are speakin’ low like me,” he answered.
“But we have no dream we can wake from.”
Had she surrendered on this day to her cowpuncher, her wild man?
Was she forever wholly his?
Had the Virginian’s fire so melted her heart that no rift in
it remained?
So she would have thought if any thought had come to her.
But in his arms today, thought was lost in something more divine.
CHAPTER XXIX
Word to Bennington
They kept their secret for a while, or at least they had that special joy of believing
that no one in all the world but themselves knew this that had happened to them.
But I think that there was one person who knew how to keep a
secret even better than these two lovers.
Mrs. Taylor made no remarks to anyone whatever.
Nobody on Bear Creek, however, was so extraordinarily cheerful
and serene.
That peculiar severity which she had manifested in the days when
Molly was packing her possessions, had now altogether changed.
In these days she was endlessly kind and indulgent to her “deary.”
Although, as a housekeeper, Mrs. Taylor believed in punctuality at meals, and visited her offspring with discipline
when they were late without good and sufficient excuse, Molly was now exempt from the faintest hint of reprimand.
“And it’s not because you’re not her mother,” said George Taylor,
bitterly.
“She used to get it, too.
And we’re the only ones that get it.
There she comes, just as we’re about ready to quit!
Aren’t you going to say nothing to her?”
“George,” said his mother, “when you’ve saved a man’s life it’ll
be time for you to talk.”
So Molly would come in to her meals with much irregularity; and her
remarks about the imperfections of her clock met with no rejoinder.
And yet one can scarcely be so severe as had been Mrs. Taylor,
and become wholly as mild as milk.
There was one recurrent event that could invariably awaken hostile
symptoms in the dame.
Whenever she saw a letter arrive with the Bennington postmark
upon it, she shook her fist at that letter.
“What’s family pride?” she would say to herself.
“Taylor could be a Son of the Revolution if he’d a mind to. I
wonder if she has told her folks yet.”
And when letters directed to Bennington would go out, Mrs. Taylor would inspect every one as if its
envelope ought to grow transparent beneath her eyes, and yield up to her its great secret, if it had one.
But in truth these letters had no great secret to yield up, until one day⁠—yes;
one day Mrs. Taylor would have burst, were bursting a thing that people often did.
Three letters were the cause of this emotion on Mrs. Taylor’s part; one addressed to Bennington, one to Dunbarton,
and the third⁠—here was the great excitement⁠—to Bennington, but not in the little schoolmarm’s delicate writing.
A man’s hand had traced those plain, steady vowels and consonants.
“It’s come!” exclaimed Mrs. Taylor, at this sight.
“He has written to her mother himself.”
That is what the Virginian had done, and here is how it had come
about.
The sick man’s convalescence was achieved.
The weeks had brought back to him, not his whole strength yet⁠—that could come only by
many miles of open air on the back of Monte; but he was strong enough now to get strength.
When a patient reaches this stage, he is out of the woods.
He had gone for a little walk with his nurse.
They had taken (under the doctor’s recommendation) several such little walks,
beginning with a five-minute one, and at last today accomplishing three miles.
“No, it has not been too far,” said he.
“I am afraid I could walk twice as far.”
“Afraid?”
“Yes. Because it means I can go to work again. This thing we
have had together is over.”
For reply, she leaned against him.
“Look at you!” he said.
“Only a little while ago you had to help me stand on my laigs.
And now⁠—” For a while there was silence between them.
“I have never had a right down sickness before,” he presently
went on.
“Not to remember, that is. If any person had told me I could enjoy such a
thing⁠—” He said no more, for she reached up, and no more speech was possible.
“How long has it been?” he next asked her.
She told him.
“Well, if it could be forever⁠—no.
Not forever with no more than this.
I reckon I’d be sick again!
But if it could be forever with just you and me, and no one else
to bother with.
But any longer would not be doing right by your mother.
She would have a right to think ill of me.”
“Oh!” said the girl.
“Let us keep it.”
“Not after I am gone. Your mother must be told.”
“It seems so⁠—can’t we⁠—oh, why need anybody know?”
“Your mother ain’t ‘anybody.’ She is your mother. I feel mighty
responsible to her for what I have done.”
“But I did it!”
“Do you think so? Your mother will not think so. I am going to
write to her today.”
“You! Write to my mother! Oh, then everything will be so different!
They will all⁠—” Molly stopped before the rising visions of Bennington.
Upon the fairytale that she had been living with her cowboy lover
broke the voices of the world.
She could hear them from afar.
She could see the eyes of Bennington watching this man at her
side.
She could imagine the ears of Bennington listening for slips
in his English.
There loomed upon her the round of visits which they would have
to make.
The ringing of the doorbells, the waiting in drawing-rooms for the mistress to descend and utter her prepared
congratulations, while her secret eye devoured the Virginian’s appearance, and his manner of standing and sitting.
He would be wearing gloves, instead of fringed gauntlets of buckskin.
In a smooth black coat and waistcoat, how could they perceive
the man he was?
During those short formal interviews, what would they ever find
out of the things that she knew about him?
The things for which she was proud of him?
He would speak shortly and simply; they would say, “Oh, yes!” and “How different you must find this from Wyoming!”⁠—and then,
after the door was shut behind his departing back they would say⁠—He would be totally underrated, not in the least understood.
Why should he be subjected to this?
He should never be!
Now in all these half-formed, hurried, distressing thoughts which
streamed through the girl’s mind, she altogether forgot one truth.
True it was that the voice of the world would speak as she imagined.
True it was that in the eyes of her family and acquaintance this lover of her choice would be examined even more like a specimen than are
other lovers upon these occasions: and all accepted lovers have to face this ordeal of being treated like specimens by the other family.
But dear me!
most of us manage to stand it, don’t we?
It isn’t, perhaps, the most delicious experience that we can
recall in connection with our engagement.
But it didn’t prove fatal.
We got through it somehow.
We dined with Aunt Jane, and wined with Uncle Joseph, and perhaps had two fingers given to us
by old Cousin Horatio, whose enormous fortune was of the greatest importance to everybody.
And perhaps fragments of the other family’s estimate of us subsequently
reached our own ears.
But if a chosen lover cannot stand being treated as a specimen by the
other family, he’s a very weak vessel, and not worth any good girl’s love.
That’s all I can say for him.
Now the Virginian was scarcely what even his enemy would term a weak vessel; and Molly’s
jealousy of the impression which he might make upon Bennington was vastly superfluous.
She should have known that he would indeed care to make a good impression; but that such anxiety on his part would be
wholly for her sake, that in the eyes of her friends she might stand justified in taking him for her wedded husband.
So far as he was concerned apart from her
, Aunt Jane and Uncle Joseph might say anything they pleased,
or think anything they pleased.
His character was open for investigation.
Judge Henry would vouch for him.
This is what he would have said to his sweetheart had she but
revealed to him her perturbations.
But she did not reveal them; and they were not of the order that
he with his nature was likely to divine.
I do not know what good would have come from her speaking out to him, unless
that perfect understanding between lovers which indeed is a good thing.
But I do not believe that he could have reassured her; and I am
certain that she could not have prevented his writing to her mother.
“Well, then,” she sighed at last, “if you think so, I will tell
her.”
That sigh of hers, be it well understood, was not only because of those far-off
voices which the world would in consequence of her news be lifting presently.
It came also from bidding farewell to the fairytale which she must leave now; that land in
which she and he had been living close together alone, unhindered, unmindful of all things.
“Yes, you will tell her,” said her lover.
“And I must tell her too.”
“Both of us?” questioned the girl.
What would he say to her mother?
How would her mother like such a letter as he would write to
her?
Suppose he should misspell a word?
Would not sentences from him at this time⁠—written sentences⁠—be
a further bar to his welcome acceptance at Bennington?
“Why don’t you send messages by me?” she asked him.
He shook his head.
“She is not going to like it, anyway,” he answered.
“I must speak to her direct. It would be like shirking.”
Molly saw how true his instinct was here; and a little flame
shot upward from the glow of her love and pride in him.
Oh, if they could all only know that he was like this when you
understood him!
She did not dare say out to him what her fear was about this
letter of his to her mother.
She did not dare because⁠—well, because she lacked a little faith.
That is it, I am afraid.
And for that sin she was her own punishment.
For in this day, and in many days to come, the pure joy of her love was vexed and clouded, all
through a little lack of faith; while for him, perfect in his faith, his joy was like crystal.
“Tell me what you’re going to write,” she said.
He smiled at her.
“No.”
“Aren’t you going to let me see it when it’s done?”
Then a freakish look came into his eyes.
“I’ll let yu’ see anything I write to other women.”
And he gave her one of his long kisses.
“Let’s get through with it together,” he suggested, when they were
once more in his sickroom, that room which she had given to him.
“You’ll sit one side o’ the table, and I’ll sit the other, and
we’ll go ahaid; and pretty soon it will be done.”
“O dear!” she said.
“Yes, I suppose that is the best way.”
And so, accordingly, they took their places.
The inkstand stood between them.
Beside each of them she distributed paper enough, almost, for
a presidential message.
And pens and pencils were in plenty.
Was this not the headquarters of the Bear Creek schoolmarm?
“Why, aren’t you going to do it in pencil first?” she exclaimed,
looking up from her vacant sheet.
His pen was moving slowly, but steadily.
“No, I don’t reckon I need to,” he answered, with his nose close
to the paper.
“Oh, damnation, there’s a blot!”
He tore his spoiled beginning in small bits, and threw them into
the fireplace.
“You’ve got it too full,” he commented; and taking the inkstand,
he tipped a little from it out of the window.
She sat lost among her false starts.
Had she heard him swear, she would not have minded.
She rather liked it when he swore.
He possessed that quality in his profanity of not offending by
it.
It is quite wonderful how much worse the same word will sound
in one man’s lips than in another’s.
But she did not hear him.
Her mind was among a litter of broken sentences.
Each thought which she began ran out into the empty air, or came
against some stone wall.
So there she sat, her eyes now upon that inexorable blank sheet that lay before her,
waiting, and now turned with vacant hopelessness upon the sundry objects in the room.
And while she thus sat accomplishing nothing, opposite to her the
black head bent down, and the steady pen moved from phrase to phrase.
She became aware of his gazing at her, flushed and solemn.
That strange color of the seawater, which she could never name,
was lustrous in his eyes.
He was folding his letter.
“You have finished?” she said.
“Yes.”
His voice was very quiet.
“I feel like an honester man.”
“Perhaps I can do something tonight at Mrs. Taylor’s,” she said,
looking at her paper.
On it were a few words crossed out.
This was all she had to show.
At this set task in letter-writing, the cowpuncher had greatly
excelled the schoolmarm!
But that night, while he lay quite fast asleep in his bed, she
was keeping vigil in her room at Mrs. Taylor’s.
Accordingly, the next day, those three letters departed for the
mail, and Mrs. Taylor consequently made her exclamation, “It’s come!”
On the day before the Virginian returned to take up his work
at Judge Henry’s ranch, he and Molly announced their news.
What Molly said to Mrs. Taylor and what Mrs. Taylor said to her,
is of no interest to us, though it was of much to them.
But Mr. McLean happened to make a call quite early in the morning
to inquire for his friend’s health.
“Lin,” began the Virginian, “there is no harm in your knowing
an hour or so before the rest, I am⁠—”
“Lord!” said Mr. McLean, indulgently.
“Everybody has knowed that since the day she found yu’ at the
spring.”
“It was not so, then,” said the Virginian, crossly.
“Lord! Everybody has knowed it right along.”
“Hmp!” said the Virginian.
“I didn’t know this country was that rank with gossips.”
Mr. McLean laughed mirthfully at the lover.
“Well,” he said, “Mrs. McLean will be glad.
She told me to give yu’ her congratulations quite a while ago.
I was to have ’em ready just as soon as ever yu’ asked for ’em
yourself.”
Lin had been made a happy man some twelve months previous to
this.
And now, by way of an exchange of news, he added: “We’re expectin’
a little McLean down on Box Elder.
That’s what you’ll be expectin’ some of these days, I hope.”
“Yes,” murmured the Virginian, “I hope so too.”
“And I don’t guess,” said Lin, “that you and I will do much shufflin’
of other folks’ children any more.”
Whereupon he and the Virginian shook hands silently, and understood
each other very well.
On the day that the Virginian parted with Molly, beside the weight of farewell
which lay heavy on his heart, his thoughts were also grave with news.
The cattle thieves had grown more audacious.
Horses and cattle both were being missed, and each man began
almost to doubt his neighbor.
“Steps will have to be taken soon by somebody, I reckon,” said
the lover.
“By you?” she asked quickly.
“Most likely I’ll get mixed up with it.”
“What will you have to do?”
“Can’t say. I’ll tell yu’ when I come back.”
So did he part from her, leaving her more kisses than words to
remember.
And what was doing at Bennington, meanwhile, and at Dunbarton?
Those three letters which by their mere outside had so moved Mrs.
Taylor, produced by their contents much painful disturbance.
It will be remembered that Molly wrote to her mother, and to
her great-aunt.
That announcement to her mother was undertaken first.
Its composition occupied three hours and a half, and it filled
eleven pages, not counting a postscript upon the twelfth.
The letter to the great-aunt took only ten minutes.
I cannot pretend to explain why this one was so greatly superior
to the other; but such is the remarkable fact.
Its beginning, to be sure, did give the old lady a start; she
had dismissed the cowboy from her probabilities.
“Tut, tut, tut!” she exclaimed out loud in her bedroom.
“She has thrown herself away on that fellow!”
But some sentences at the end made her pause and sit still for
a long while.
The severity upon her face changed to tenderness, gradually.
“Ah, me,” she sighed.
“If marriage were as simple as love!”
Then she went slowly downstairs, and out into her garden, where
she walked long between the box borders.
“But if she has found a great love,” said the old lady at length.
And she returned to her bedroom, and opened an old desk, and
read some old letters.
There came to her the next morning a communication from Bennington.
This had been penned frantically by poor Mrs. Wood.
As soon as she had been able to gather her senses after the shock of her daughter’s eleven pages and
the postscript, the mother had poured out eight pages herself to the eldest member of the family.
There had been, indeed, much excuse for the poor lady.
To begin with, Molly had constructed her whole opening page with
the express and merciful intention of preparing her mother.
Consequently, it made no sense whatever.
Its effect was the usual effect of remarks designed to break
a thing gently.
It merely made Mrs. Wood’s head swim, and filled her with a sickening
dread.
“Oh, mercy, Sarah,” she had cried, “come here.
What does this mean?”
And then, fortified by her elder daughter, she had turned over
that first page and found what it meant on the top of the second.
“A savage with knives and pistols!” she wailed.
“Well, mother, I always told you so,” said her daughter Sarah.
“What is a foreman?” exclaimed the mother.
“And who is Judge Henry?”
“She has taken a sort of upper servant,” said Sarah.
“If it is allowed to go as far as a wedding, I doubt if I can
bring myself to be present.”
(This threat she proceeded to make to Molly, with results that
shall be set forth in their proper place.
)
“The man appears to have written to me himself,” said Mrs. Wood.
“He knows no better,” said Sarah.
“Bosh!” said Sarah’s husband later.
“It was a very manly thing to do.”
Thus did consternation rage in the house at Bennington.
Molly might have spared herself the many assurances that she gave concerning the
universal esteem in which her cowpuncher was held, and the fair prospects which were his.
So, in the first throes of her despair, Mrs. Wood wrote those
eight not maturely considered pages to the great-aunt.
“Tut, tut, tut!” said the great-aunt as she read them.
Her face was much more severe today.
“You’d suppose,” she said, “that the girl had been kidnapped!
Why, she has kept him waiting three years!”
And then she read more, but soon put the letter down with laughter.
For Mrs. Wood had repeated in writing that early outburst of
hers about a savage with knives and pistols.
“Law!” said the great-aunt.
“Law, what a fool Lizzie is!”
So she sat down and wrote to Mrs. Wood a wholesome reply about putting a little more trust in her own flesh and blood, and reminding her among other things that General Stark
had himself been wont to carry knives and pistols owing to the necessities of his career, but that he had occasionally taken them off, as did probably this young man in Wyoming.
“You had better send me the letter he has written you,” she concluded.
“I shall know much better what to think after I have seen that.”
It is not probable that Mrs. Wood got much comfort from this
communication; and her daughter Sarah was actually enraged by it.
“She grows more perverse as she nears her dotage,” said Sarah.
But the Virginian’s letter was sent to Dunbarton, where the old
lady sat herself down to read it with much attention.
Here is what the Virginian had said to the unknown mother of
his sweetheart.
Mrs. John Stark Wood,
Bennington, Vermont.
Madam:
If your daughter Miss Wood has ever told you about her saving a man’s life
here when some Indians had shot him that is the man who writes to you now.
I don’t think she can have told you right about that affair for she
is the only one in this country who thinks it was a little thing.
So I must tell you it, the main points.
Such an action would have been thought highly of in a Western
girl, but with Miss Wood’s raising nobody had a right to expect it.
“Indeed!” snorted the great-aunt.
“Well, he would be right, if I had not had a good deal more to
do with her ‘raising’ than ever Lizzie had.”
And she went on with the letter.
I was starting in to die when she found me.
I did not know anything then, and she pulled me back from where
I was half in the next world.
She did not know but what Indians would get her too but I could
not make her leave me.
I am a heavy man one hundred and seventy-three stripped when
in full health.
She lifted me herself from the ground me helping scarce any for
there was not much help in me that day.
She washed my wound and brought me to with her own whiskey.
Before she could get me home I was out of my head but she kept me on my horse somehow and
talked wisely to me so I minded her and did not go clean crazy till she had got me safe to bed.
The doctor says I would have died all the same if she had not
nursed me the way she did.
It made me love her more which I did not know I could.
But there is no end, for this writing it down makes me love her
more as I write it.
And now Mrs. Wood I am sorry this will be bad news for you to
hear.
I know you would never choose such a man as I am for her for I
have got no education and must write humble against my birth.
I wish I could make the news easier but truth is the best.
I am of old stock in Virginia.
English and one Scotch Irish grandmother my father’s father brought
from Kentucky.
We have always stayed at the same place farmers and hunters not
bettering our lot and very plain.
We have fought when we got the chance, under Old Hickory and in Mexico
and my father and two brothers were killed in the Valley sixty-four.
Always with us one son has been apt to run away and I was the
one this time.
I had too much older brothering to suit me.
But now I am doing well being in full sight of prosperity and not too old
and very strong my health having stood the sundries it has been put through.
She shall teach school no more when she is mine.
I wish I could make this news easier for you Mrs. Wood.
I do not like promises I have heard so many.
I will tell any man of your family anything he likes to ask one,
and Judge Henry would tell you about my reputation.
I have seen plenty rough things but can say I have never killed for
pleasure or profit and am not one of that kind, always preferring peace.
I have had to live in places where they had courts and lawyers so called
but an honest man was all the law you could find in five hundred miles.
I have not told her about those things not because I am ashamed of them
but there are so many things too dark for a girl like her to hear about.
I had better tell you the way I know I love Miss Wood.
I am not a boy now, and women are no new thing to me.
A man like me who has travelled meets many of them as he goes
and passes on but I stopped when I came to Miss Wood.
That is three years but I have not gone on.
What right has such as he? you will say.
So did I say it after she had saved my life.
It was hard to get to that point and keep there with her around
me all day.
But I said to myself you have bothered her for three years with your love and if you let your love
bother her you don’t love her like you should and you must quit for her sake who has saved your life.
I did not know what I was going to do with my life after that but I supposed I
could go somewhere and work hard and so Mrs. Wood I told her I would give her up.
But she said no.
It is going to be hard for her to get used to a man like me⁠—
But at this point in the Virginian’s letter, the old great-aunt
could read no more.
She rose, and went over to that desk where lay those faded letters
of her own.
She laid her head down upon the package, and as her tears flowed
quietly upon it, “O dear,” she whispered, “O dear!
And this is what I lost!”
To her girl upon Bear Creek she wrote the next day.
And this word from Dunbarton was like balm among the harsh stings
Molly was receiving.
The voices of the world reached her in gathering numbers, and
not one of them save that great-aunt’s was sweet.
Her days were full of hurts; and there was no one by to kiss
the hurts away.
Nor did she even hear from her lover any more now.
She only knew he had gone into lonely regions upon his errand.
That errand took him far:⁠—
Across the Basin, among the secret places of Owl Creek, past the Washakie Needles, over the
Divide to Gros Ventre, and so through a final barrier of peaks into the borders of East Idaho.
There, by reason of his bidding me, I met him, and came to share
in a part of his errand.
It was with no guide that I travelled to him.
He had named a little station on the railroad, and from thence
he had charted my route by means of landmarks.
Did I believe in omens, the black storm that I set out in upon
my horse
would seem like one today.
But I had been living in cities and smoke; and Idaho, even with
rain, was delightful to me.
CHAPTER XXX
A
Stable on the Flat
When the first landmark, the lone clump of cottonwoods, came at length in sight, dark and blurred in the gentle
rain, standing out perhaps a mile beyond the distant buildings, my whole weary body hailed the approach of repose.
Saving the noon hour, I had been in the saddle since six, and
now six was come round again.
The ranch, my resting-place for this night, was a ruin⁠—cabin,
stable, and corral.
Yet after the twelve hours of pushing on and on through silence, still to have silence,
still to eat and go to sleep in it, perfectly fitted the mood of both my flesh and spirit.
At noon, when for a while I had thrown off my long oilskin coat, merely the sight of the newspaper
half crowded into my pocket had been a displeasing reminder of the railway, and cities, and affairs.
But for its possible help to build fires, it would have come
no farther with me.
The great levels around me lay cooled and freed of dust by the
wet weather, and full of sweet airs.
Far in front the foothills rose through the rain, indefinite
and mystic.
I wanted no speech with anyone, nor to be near human beings at
all.
I was steeped in a revery as of the primal earth; even thoughts
themselves had almost ceased motion.
To lie down with wild animals, with elk and deer, would have made my waking dream complete; and since such dream could not be,
the cattle around the deserted buildings, mere dots as yet across separating space, were my proper companions for this evening.
Tomorrow night I should probably be camping with the Virginian
in the foothills.
At his letter’s bidding I had come eastward across Idaho, abandoning my hunting
in the Saw Tooth Range to make this journey with him back through the Tetons.
It was a trail known to him, and not to many other honest men.
Horse Thief Pass was the name his letter gave it.
Business (he was always brief) would call him over there at this
time.
Returning, he must attend to certain matters in the Wind River
country.
There I could leave by stage for the railroad, or go on with
him the whole way back to Sunk Creek.
He designated for our meeting the forks of a certain little
stream in the foothills which today’s ride had brought in sight.
There would be no chance for him to receive an answer from me
in the intervening time.
If by a certain day⁠—which was four days off still⁠—I had not
reached the forks, he would understand I had other plans.
To me it was like living back in ages gone, this way of meeting my friend, this choice
of a stream so far and lonely that its very course upon the maps was wrongly traced.
And to leave behind all noise and mechanisms, and set out at ease, slowly, with one packhorse, into the wilderness, made me feel
that the ancient earth was indeed my mother and that I had found her again after being lost among houses, customs, and restraints.
I should arrive three days early at the forks⁠—three days of
margin seeming to me a wise precaution against delays unforeseen.
If the Virginian were not there, good; I could fish and be happy.
If he were there but not ready to start, good; I could still
fish and be happy.
And remembering my Eastern helplessness in the year when we
had met first, I enjoyed thinking how I had come to be trusted.
In those days I had not been allowed to go from the ranch for so much as an afternoon’s ride
unless tied to him by a string, so to speak; now I was crossing unmapped spaces with no guidance.
The man who could do this was scarce any longer a “tenderfoot.”
My vision, as I rode, took in serenely the dim foothills⁠—tomorrow’s goal⁠—and nearer in the vast wet
plain the clump of cottonwoods, and still nearer my lodging for tonight with the dotted cattle round it.
And now my horse neighed.
I felt his gait freshen for the journey’s end, and leaning to pat his neck I noticed his ears no
longer slack and inattentive, but pointing forward to where food and rest awaited both of us.
Twice he neighed, impatiently and long; and as he quickened his gait still more, the packhorse did the same, and
I realized that there was about me still a spice of the tenderfoot: those dots were not cattle; they were horses.
My horse had put me in the wrong.
He had known his kind from afar, and was hastening to them.
The plainsman’s eye was not yet mine; and I smiled a little as
I rode.
When was I going to know, as by instinct, the different look
of horses and cattle across some two or three miles of plain?
These miles we finished soon.
The buildings changed in their aspect as they grew to my approach, showing their
desolation more clearly, and in some way bringing apprehension into my mood.
And around them the horses, too, all standing with ears erect, watching
me as I came⁠—there was something about them; or was it the silence?
For the silence which I had liked until now seemed suddenly to
be made too great by the presence of the deserted buildings.
And then the door of the stable opened, and men came out and
stood, also watching me arrive.
By the time I was dismounting more were there.
It was senseless to feel as unpleasant as I did, and I strove
to give to them a greeting that should sound easy.
I told them that I hoped there was room for one more here tonight.
Some of them had answered my greeting, but none of them answered this; and as I
began to be sure that I recognized several of their strangely imperturbable faces
, the Virginian came from the stable; and at that welcome sight
my relief spoke out instantly.
“I am here, you see!”
“Yes, I do see.”
I looked hard at him, for in his voice was the same strangeness
that I felt in everything around me.
But he was looking at his companions.
“This gentleman is all right,” he told them.
“That may be,” said one whom I now knew that I had seen before
at Sunk Creek
; “but he was not due tonight.”
“Nor tomorrow,” said another.
“Nor yet the day after,” a third added.
The Virginian fell into his drawl.
“None of you was ever early for anything, I presume.”
One retorted, laughing, “Oh, we’re not suspicioning you of complicity.”
And another, “Not even when we remember how thick you and Steve
used to be.”
Whatever jokes they meant by this he did not receive as jokes.
I saw something like a wince pass over his face, and a flush
follow it.
But he now spoke to me.
“We expected to be through before this,” he began.
“I’m right sorry you have come tonight. I know you’d have preferred
to keep away.”
“We want him to explain himself,” put in one of the others.
“If he satisfies us, he’s free to go away.”
“Free to go away!” I now exclaimed.
But at the indulgence in their frontier smile I cooled down.
“Gentlemen,” I said, “I don’t know why my movements interest
you so much.
It’s quite a compliment!
May I get under shelter while I explain?”
No request could have been more natural, for the rain had now
begun to fall in straight floods.
Yet there was a pause before one of them said, “He might as well.”
The Virginian chose to say nothing more; but he walked beside
me into the stable.
Two men sat there together, and a third guarded them.
At that sight I knew suddenly what I had stumbled upon; and on the
impulse I murmured to the Virginian, “You’re hanging them tomorrow.”
He kept his silence.
“You may have three guesses,” said a man behind me.
But I did not need them.
And in the recoil of my insight the clump of cottonwoods came
into my mind, black and grim.
No other trees high enough grew within ten miles.
This, then, was the business that the Virginian’s letter had
so curtly mentioned.
My eyes went into all corners of the stable, but no other prisoners
were here.
I half expected to see Trampas, and I half feared to see Shorty; for poor stupid Shorty’s honesty had
not been proof against frontier temptations, and he had fallen away from the company of his old friends.
Often of late I had heard talk at Sunk Creek of breaking up a certain gang of horse and cattle thieves
that stole in one Territory and sold in the next, and knew where to hide in the mountains between.
And now it had come to the point; forces had been gathered, a long expedition made, and here
they were, successful under the Virginian’s lead, but a little later than their calculations.
And here was I, a little too early, and a witness in consequence.
My presence seemed a simple thing to account for; but when I
had thus accounted for it, one of them said with good nature:⁠—
“So you find us here, and we find you here. Which is the most
surprised, I wonder?”
“There’s no telling,” said I, keeping as amiable as I could;
“nor any telling which objects the most.”
“Oh, there’s no objection here.
You’re welcome to stay.
But not welcome to go, I expect.
He ain’t welcome to go, is he?”
By the answers that their faces gave him it was plain that I
was not.
“Not till we are through,” said one.
“He needn’t to see anything,” ’ another added.
“Better sleep late tomorrow morning,” a third suggested to me.
I did not wish to stay here.
I could have made some sort of camp apart from them before
dark; but in the face of their needless caution I was helpless.
I made no attempt to inquire what kind of spy they imagined I could be, what sort of rescue I
could bring in this lonely country; my too early appearance seemed to be all that they looked at.
And again my eyes sought the prisoners.
Certainly there were only two.
One was chewing tobacco, and talking now and then to his guard
as if nothing were the matter.
The other sat dull in silence, not moving his eyes; but his face
worked, and I noticed how he continually moistened his dry lips.
As I looked at these doomed prisoners, whose fate I was invited to sleep
through tomorrow morning, the one who was chewing quietly nodded to me.
“You don’t remember me?” he said.
It was Steve!
Steve of Medicine Bow!
The pleasant Steve of my first evening in the West.
Some change of beard had delayed my instant recognition of his
face.
Here he sat sentenced to die.
A shock, chill and painful, deprived me of speech.
He had no such weak feelings.
“Have yu’ been to Medicine Bow lately?” he inquired.
“That’s getting to be quite a while ago.”
I assented.
I should have liked to say something natural and kind, but words stuck against my will, and I stood
awkward and ill at ease, noticing idly that the silent one wore a gray flannel shirt like mine.
Steve looked me over, and saw in my pocket the newspaper which I had
brought from the railroad and on which I had pencilled a few expenses.
He asked me, Would I mind letting him have it for a while?
And I gave it to him eagerly, begging him to keep it as long
as he wanted.
I was overeager in my embarrassment.
“You need not return it at all,” I said; “those notes are nothing.
Do keep it.”
He gave me a short glance and a smile.
“Thank you,” he said; “I’ll not need it beyond tomorrow morning.”
And he began to search through it.
“Jake’s election is considered sure,” he said to his companion,
who made no response.
“Well, Fremont County owes it to Jake.”
And I left him interested in the local news.
Dead men I have seen not a few times, even some lying pale and terrible after violent ends, and the edge
of this wears off; but I hope I shall never again have to be in the company with men waiting to be killed.
By this time tomorrow the gray flannel shirt would be buttoned
round a corpse.
Until what moment would Steve chew?
Against such fancies as these I managed presently to barricade my mind, but I made a
plea to be allowed to pass the night elsewhere, and I suggested the adjacent cabin.
By their faces I saw that my words merely helped their distrust
of me.
The cabin leaked too much, they said; I would sleep drier here.
One man gave it to me more directly: “If you figured on camping
in this stable, what has changed your mind?”
How could I tell them that I shrunk from any contact with what they were
doing, although I knew that only so could justice be dealt in this country?
Their wholesome frontier nerves knew nothing of such refinements.
But the Virginian understood part of it.
“I am right sorry for your annoyance,” he said.
And now I noticed he was under a constraint very different from
the ease of the others.
After the twelve hours’ ride my bones were hungry for rest.
I spread my blankets on some straw in a stall by myself and rolled up in them; yet I
lay growing broader awake, every inch of weariness stricken from my excited senses.
For a while they sat over their councils, whispering cautiously, so that I was made curious to hear them by
not being able; was it the names of Trampas and Shorty that were once or twice spoken⁠—I could not be sure.
I heard the whisperers cease and separate.
I heard their boots as they cast them off upon the ground.
And I heard the breathing of slumber begin and grow in the interior
silence.
To one after one sleep came, but not to me.
Outside, the dull fall of the rain beat evenly, and in some angle
dripped the spouting pulses of a leak.
Sometimes a cold air blew in, bearing with it the keen wet odor
of the sagebrush.
On hundreds of other nights this perfume had been my last waking remembrance;
it had seemed to help drowsiness; and now I lay staring, thinking of this.
Twice through the hours the thieves shifted their positions with
clumsy sounds, exchanging muted words with their guard.
So, often, had I heard other companions move and mutter in the
darkness and lie down again.
It was the very naturalness and usualness of every fact of the night⁠—the stable straw, the rain outside, my familiar blankets, the cool visits of the
wind⁠—and with all this the thought of Steve chewing and the man in the gray flannel shirt, that made the hours unearthly and strung me tight with suspense.
And at last I heard someone get up and begin to dress.
In a little while I saw light suddenly through my closed eyelids,
and then darkness shut again abruptly upon them.
They had swung in a lantern and found me by mistake.
I was the only one they did not wish to rouse.
Moving and quiet talking set up around me, and they began to
go out of the stable.
At the gleams of new daylight which they let in my thoughts went to the clump
of cottonwoods, and I lay still with hands and feet growing steadily cold.
Now it was going to happen.
I wondered how they would do it; one instance had been described to me by a
witness, but that was done from a bridge, and there had been but a single victim.
This morning, would one have to wait and see the other go through
with it first?
The smell of smoke reached me, and next the rattle of tin dishes.