And next time I’ll have along a
gentle hawss for yu’.”
“Next time!
Next time!
Well, perhaps I will go with you.
Do you live far?”
“I live on Judge Henry’s
ranch, over yondeh.”
He pointed across the mountains.
“It’s on Sunk Creek.
A pretty rough trail;
but I can come hyeh to see you in
a day, I reckon.
Well, I hope you’ll cert’nly
enjoy good health, ma’am.”
“Oh, there’s one thing!”
said Molly Wood, calling
after him rather quickly.
“I⁠—I’m not at all afraid of horses.
You needn’t bring such a gentle one.
I⁠—was very tired that day,
and⁠—and I don’t scream as a rule.”
He turned and looked at her so that she
could not meet his glance.
“Bless your heart!”
said he.
“Will yu’ give me one o’ those flowers?”
“Oh, certainly!
I’m always so glad when people like them.”
“They’re pretty near the
color of your eyes.”
“Never mind my eyes.”
“Can’t help it, ma’am.
Not since South Fork.”
He put the flower in the leather band of
his hat, and rode away
on his Monte horse.
Miss Wood lingered a moment,
then made some steps toward her gate,
from which he could still be seen;
and then, with something like a toss of
the head, she went in and shut her door.
Later in the day the Virginian met Mr.
McLean, who looked at his hat and
innocently quoted, “ ‘My
Looloo picked a daisy.’
”
“Don’t yu’, Lin,” said the Southerner.
“Then I won’t,” said Lin.
Thus, for this occasion,
did the Virginian part from his lady⁠—
and nothing said one way or another about
the handkerchief that had disappeared
during the South Fork incident.
As we fall asleep at night,
our thoughts will often ramble back and
forth between the two worlds.
“What color were his eyes?”
wondered Molly on her pillow.
“His mustache is not bristly like
so many of them.
Sam never gave me such a
look at Hoosic Junction.
No.⁠ ⁠
… You can’t come with me.⁠ ⁠
… Get off your horse.⁠ ⁠
… The passengers are all staring.⁠ ⁠
…”
And while Molly was thus dreaming that
the Virginian had ridden his horse into
the railroad car, and sat down beside
her, the fire in the great stone chimney
of her cabin flickered quietly,
its gleams now and again touching the
miniature of Grandmother
Stark upon the wall.
Camped on the Sunk Creek trail,
the Virginian was telling
himself in his blankets:⁠—
“I ain’t too old for education.
Maybe she will lend me books.
And I’ll watch her ways and
learn⁠ ⁠… stand still, Monte.
I can learn a lot more than
the kids on that.
There’s Monte⁠
⁠…
you pie-biter, stop.⁠ ⁠
… He has ate up your book,
ma’am, but I’ll get yu’.⁠ ⁠
…”
And then the Virginian was fast asleep.
CHAPTER XII
Quality and Equality
To the circle at Bennington,
a letter from Bear Creek was always a
welcome summons to gather and hear of
doings very strange to Vermont.
And when the tale of the changed babies
arrived duly by the post,
it created a more than usual sensation,
and was read to a large number of
pleased and scandalized neighbors.
“I hate her to be where such things can
happen,” said Mrs. Wood.
“I wish I could have been there,”
said her son-in-law, Andrew Bell.
“She does not mention who played the
trick,” said Mrs. Andrew Bell.
“We shouldn’t be any wiser if she
did,” said Mrs. Wood.
“I’d like to meet the
perpetrator,” said Andrew.
“Oh, no!”
said Mrs. Wood.
“They’re all horrible.”
And she wrote at once,
begging her daughter to take good care
of herself, and to see as much of
Mrs. Balaam as possible.
“And of any other ladies
that are near you.
For you seem to me to be in
a community of roughs.
I wish you would give it all up.
Did you expect me to laugh
about the babies?”
Mrs.
Flynt, when this story was repeated to
her (she had not been invited in to hear
the letter), remarked that she had
always felt that Molly Wood must be a
little vulgar, ever since she began to
go about giving music lessons
like any ordinary German.
But Mrs. Wood was considerably relieved
when the next letter arrived.
It contained nothing horrible
about barbecues or babies.
It mentioned the great beauty of the
weather, and how well and strong the
fine air was making the writer feel.
And it asked that books might be sent,
many books of all sorts,
novels, poetry, all the good old books
and any good new ones
that could be spared.
Cheap editions, of course.
“Indeed she shall have them!”
said Mrs. Wood.
“How her mind must be starving
in that dreadful place!”
The letter was not a long one,
and, besides the books,
spoke of little else except the fine
weather and the chances for outdoor
exercise that this gave.
“You have no idea,” it said,
“how delightful it is to ride,
especially on a spirited horse,
which I can do now quite well.
”
“How nice that is!”
said Mrs. Wood, putting down the letter.
“I hope the horse is not too spirited.”
“Who does she go riding with?”
asked Mrs. Bell.
“She doesn’t say, Sarah.
Why?
”
“Nothing.
She has a queer way of not mentioning
things, now and then.”
“Sarah!”
exclaimed Mrs. Wood, reproachfully.
“Oh, well, mother, you know just as well
as I do that she can be
very independent and unconventional.”
“Yes; but not in that way.
She wouldn’t ride with poor Sam Bannett,
and after all he is a suitable person.
”
Nevertheless, in her next letter,
Mrs. Wood cautioned her daughter about
trusting herself with any one of whom
Mrs. Balaam did not thoroughly approve.
The good lady could never grasp that Mrs.
Balaam lived a long day’s journey from
Bear Creek, and that Molly saw her about
once every three months.
“We have sent your books,”
the mother wrote; “everybody has
contributed from their store⁠—
Shakespeare, Tennyson,
Browning, Longfellow;
and a number of novels by Scott,
Thackeray, George Eliot,
Hawthorne, and lesser writers;
some volumes of Emerson;
and Jane Austen complete,
because you admire her so particularly.”
This consignment of literature reached
Bear Creek about a week
before Christmas time.
By New Year’s Day, the Virginian
had begun his education.
“Well, I have managed to get through
’em,” he said, as he entered
Molly’s cabin in February.
And he laid two volumes upon her table.
“And what do you think of them?”
she inquired.
“I think that I’ve cert’nly earned a
good long ride today.”
“Georgie Taylor has sprained his ankle.”
“No, I don’t mean that kind of a ride.
I’ve earned a ride with just us two alone.
I’ve read every word of both
of ’em, yu’ know.”
“I’ll think about it.
Did you like them?”
“No.
Not much.
If I’d knowed that one was a detective
story, I’d have got yu’ to try
something else on me.
Can you guess the murderer,
or is the author too smart for yu’?
That’s all they amount to.
Well, he was too smart for me this time,
but that didn’t distress me any.
That other book talks too much.”
Molly was scandalized,
and she told him it was a great work.
“
Oh, yes, yes.
A fine book.
But it will keep up its talkin’.
Don’t let you alone.”
“Didn’t you feel sorry
for poor Maggie Tulliver?”
“Hmp.
Yes.
Sorry for her, and for Tawmmy, too.
But the man did right to drownd ’em both.”
“It wasn’t a man.
A woman wrote that.”
“A woman did!
Well, then, o’ course she talks too much.”
“I’ll not go riding with you!”
shrieked Molly.
But she did.
And he returned to Sunk Creek,
not with a detective story,
but this time with a Russian novel.
It was almost April when he brought it
back to her⁠—and a heavy sleet storm
lost them their ride.
So he spent his time indoors with her,
not speaking a syllable of love.
When he came to take his departure,
he asked her for some other book
by this same Russian.
But she had no more.
“I wish you had,” he said.
“I’ve never saw a book could tell the
truth like that one does.”
“Why, what do you like about it?”
she exclaimed.
To her it had been distasteful.
“Everything,” he answered.
“That young come-outer,
and his fam’ly that can’t understand
him⁠—for he is broad gauge,
yu’ see, and they are narro’ gauge.”
The Virginian looked at Molly
a moment almost shyly.
“Do you know,” he said,
and a blush spread over his face,
“I pretty near cried when that young
come-outer was dyin’, and said about
himself, ‘I was a giant.’
Life made him broad gauge,
yu’ see, and then took his chance away.”
Molly liked the Virginian for his blush.
It made him very handsome.
But she thought that it came from his
confession about “pretty near crying.”
The deeper cause she failed
to divine⁠—that
he
, like the dying hero in the novel,
felt himself to be a giant whom life had
made “broad gauge,” and
denied opportunity.
Fecund nature begets and squanders
thousands of these rich seeds in
the wilderness of life.
He took away with him
a volume of Shakespeare.
“I’ve saw good plays of his,” he remarked.
Kind Mrs. Taylor in her cabin next door
watched him ride off in the sleet,
bound for the lonely mountain trail.
“If that girl don’t get ready to take him
pretty soon,” she observed to her
husband, “I’ll give her a
piece of my mind.”
Taylor was astonished.
“Is he thinking of her?”
he inquired.
“Lord, Mr. Taylor, and why shouldn’t he?”
Mr. Taylor scratched his head and
returned to his newspaper.
It was warm⁠—warm and
beautiful upon Bear Creek.
Snow shone upon the peaks of the Bow Leg
range; lower on their slopes the pines
were stirring with a gentle song;
and flowers bloomed across the wide
plains at their feet.
Molly and her Virginian sat at a certain
spring where he had often
ridden with her.
On this day he was bidding her farewell
before undertaking the most important
trust which Judge Henry had
as yet given him.
For this journey she had provided him
with Sir Walter Scott’s Kenilworth.
Shakespeare he had returned to her.
He had bought Shakespeare for himself.
“As soon as I got used to readin’ it,”
he had told her, “I knowed for certain
that I liked readin’ for enjoyment.
”
But it was not of books that he
had spoken much today.
He had not spoken at all.
He had bade her listen to the meadowlark,
when its song fell upon the silence like
beaded drops of music.
He had showed her where a covey of young
willow-grouse were hiding
as their horses passed.
And then, without warning,
as they sat by the spring,
he had spoken potently of his love.
She did not interrupt him.
She waited until he was wholly finished.
“I am not the sort of wife you want,”
she said, with an attempt of airiness.
He answered roughly, “I am
the judge of that.”
And his roughness was a pleasure to her,
yet it made her afraid of herself.
When he was absent from her,
and she could sit in her cabin and look
at Grandmother Stark,
and read home letters,
then in imagination she found it easy to
play the part which she had arranged to
play regarding him⁠—the part of the
guide, and superior,
and indulgent companion.
But when he was by her side,
that part became a difficult one.
Her woman’s fortress was shaken by a
force unknown to her before.
Sam Bannett did not have it in him to
look as this man could look,
when the cold lustre of his eyes grew
hot with internal fire.
What color they were baffled her still.
“Can it possibly change?”
she wondered.
It seemed to her that sometimes when she
had been looking from a rock straight
down into clear sea water,
this same color had lurked in its
depths.
“Is it green, or is it gray?”
she asked herself, but did not turn
just now to see.
She kept her face toward the landscape.
“All men are born equal,”
he now remarked slowly.
“Yes,” she quickly answered,
with a combative flash.
“Well?”
“Maybe that don’t include women?”
he suggested.
“I think it does.”
“Do yu’ tell the kids so?”
“Of course I teach them what I believe!”
He pondered.
“I used to have to learn about
the Declaration of Independence.
I hated books and truck when I was a kid.”
“But you don’t any more.”
“No.
I cert’nly don’t.
But I used to get kep’ in at recess
for bein’ so dumb.
I was most always at the tail
end of the class.
My brother, he’d be head sometimes.”
“Little George Taylor is my
prize scholar,” said Molly.
“Knows his tasks, does he?”
“Always.
And Henry Dow comes next.”
“Who’s last?”
“Poor Bob Carmody.
I spend more time on him than on all
the rest put together.”
“My!”
said the Virginian.
“Ain’t that strange!”
She looked at him, puzzled by his tone.
“It’s not strange when you
know Bob,” she said.
“It’s very strange,” drawled
the Virginian.
“Knowin’ Bob don’t help it any.”
“I don’t think that I understand
you,” said Molly, sticky.
“Well, it is mighty confusin’.
George Taylor, he’s your best scholar,
and poor Bob, he’s your worst,
and there’s a lot in the middle⁠—and you
tell me we’re all born equal!”
Molly could only sit giggling in this
trap he had so ingeniously laid for her.
“I’ll tell you what,”
pursued the cowpuncher,
with slow and growing intensity,
“equality is a great big bluff.
It’s easy called.
”
“I didn’t mean⁠—” began Molly.
“Wait, and let me say what I mean.”
He had made an imperious
gesture with his hand.
“I know a man that mostly wins at cyards.
I know a man that mostly loses.
He says it is his luck.
All right.
Call it his luck.
I know a man that works hard and he’s
gettin’ rich, and I know another that
works hard and is gettin’ poor.
He says it is his luck.
All right.
Call it his luck.
I look around and I see folks movin’ up
or movin’ down, winners
or losers everywhere.
All luck, of course.
But since folks can be born that
different in their luck,
where’s your equality?
No, seh!
call your failure luck,
or call it laziness,
wander around the words,
prospect all yu’ mind to,
and yu’ll come out the same
old trail of inequality.”
He paused a moment and looked at her.
“Some holds four aces,”
he went on, “and some holds nothin’, and
some poor fello’ gets the aces and no
show to play ’em; but a man has got to
prove himself my equal
before I’ll believe him.”
Molly sat gazing at him, silent.
“I know what yu’ meant,”
he told her now, “by sayin’ you’re not
the wife I’d want.
But I am the kind that moves up.
I am goin’ to be your best scholar
.
”
He turned toward her,
and that fortress within
her began to shake.
“Don’t,” she murmured.
“Don’t, please.
”
“Don’t what?”
“Why⁠—spoil this.”
“Spoil it?”
“These rides⁠—I don’t love you⁠—I can’t⁠—
but these rides are⁠—”
“What are they?”
“My greatest pleasure.
There!
And, please, I want them to go on so.”
“Go on so!
I don’t reckon yu’ know
what you’re sayin’.
Yu’ might as well ask fruit to stay green.
If the way we are now can keep bein’
enough for you, it can’t for me.
A pleasure to you, is it?
Well, to me it is⁠—I don’t know
what to call it.
I come to yu’ and I hate it,
and I come again and I hate it,
and I ache and grieve all over when I
go.
No!
You will have to think of some other way
than just invitin’ me to keep green.
”
“If I am to see you⁠—” began the girl.
“You’re not to see me.
Not like this.
I can stay away easier than
what I am doin’.”
“Will you do me a favor, a great one?”
said she, now.
“Make it as impossible as you please!”
he cried.
He thought it was to be some action.
“Go on coming.
But don’t talk to me about⁠—don’t talk in
that way⁠—if you can help it.”
He laughed out, not permitting
himself to swear.
“But,” she continued,
“if you can’t help talking that way⁠—
sometimes⁠—I promise I will listen.
That is the only promise I make.”
“That is a bargain,” he said.
Then he helped her mount her horse,
restraining himself like a Spartan,
and they rode home to her cabin.
“You have made it pretty near
impossible,” he said,
as he took his leave.
“But you’ve been square today,
and I’ll show you I can be square
when I come back.
I’ll not do more than ask you if
your mind’s the same.
And now I’ll not see you
for quite a while.
I am going a long way.
But I’ll be very busy.
And bein’ busy always keeps me from
grievin’ too much about you.”
Strange is woman!
She would rather have heard some other
last remark than this.
“Oh, very well
!”
she said.
“I’ll not miss you either.”
He smiled at her.
“I doubt if yu’ can help
missin’ me,” he remarked.
And he was gone at once,
galloping on his Monte horse.
Which of the two won a victory this day?
CHAPTER XIII
The Game and the Nation⁠—Act First
There can be no doubt of this:⁠—
All America is divided into two classes⁠—
the quality and the equality.
The latter will always recognize the
former when mistaken for it.
Both will be with us until our women
bear nothing but kings.
It was through the Declaration of
Independence that we Americans
acknowledged the eternal
inequality of man.
For by it we abolished a
cut-and-dried aristocracy.
We had seen little men artificially held
up in high places, and great men
artificially held down in low places,
and our own justice-loving hearts
abhorred this violence to human nature.
Therefore, we decreed that every man
should thenceforth have equal liberty to
find his own level.
By this very decree we acknowledged and
gave freedom to true aristocracy,
saying, “Let the best man
win, whoever he is.”
Let the best man win!
That is America’s word.
That is true democracy.
And true democracy and true aristocracy
are one and the same thing.
If anybody cannot see this,
so much the worse for his eyesight.
The above reflections occurred to me
before reaching Billings,
Montana, some three weeks after I had
unexpectedly met the
Virginian at Omaha, Nebraska.
I had not known of that trust given to
him by Judge Henry, which
was taking him East.
I was looking to ride with him before
long among the clean hills of Sunk
Creek.
I supposed he was there.
But I came upon him one morning in
Colonel Cyrus Jones’s eating palace.
Did you know the palace?
It stood in Omaha, near the trains,
and it was ten years old (which is
middle-aged in Omaha) when
I first saw it.
It was a shell of wood,
painted with golden emblems⁠—the
steamboat, the eagle,
the Yosemite⁠—and a live bear ate
gratuities at its entrance.
Weather permitting, it opened upon the
world as a stage upon the audience.
You sat in Omaha’s whole sight and dined,
while Omaha’s dust came and
settled upon the refreshments.
It is gone the way of the Indian and the
buffalo, for the West is growing old.
You should have seen the
palace and sat there.
In front of you passed rainbows of men⁠—
Chinese, Indian chiefs,
Africans, General Miles,
younger sons, Austrian nobility,
wide females in pink.
Our continent drained
prismatically through Omaha once.
So I was passing that way also,
walking for the sake of ventilation from
a sleeping-car toward a bath,
when the language of Colonel Cyrus Jones
came out to me.
The actual colonel I had
never seen before.
He stood at the rear of his palace in
gray flowery mustaches and a Confederate
uniform, telling the wishes of his
guests to the cook through a hole.
You always bought meal tickets at once,
else you became unwelcome.
Guests here had foibles at times,
and a rapid exit was too easy.
Therefore I bought a ticket.
It was spring and summer since I had
heard anything like the colonel.
The Missouri had not yet flowed into New
York dialect freely,
and his vocabulary met me like the
breeze of the plains.
So I went in to be fanned by it,
and there sat the Virginian
at a table, alone.
His greeting was up to the code of
indifference proper on the plains;
but he presently remarked,
“I’m right glad to see somebody,”
which was a good deal to say.
“Them that comes hyeh,”
he observed next, “don’t eat.
They feed.”
And he considered the guests
with a sombre attention.
“D’ yu’ reckon they find joyful digestion
in this swallo’-an’-get-out trough?”
“What are you doing here, then?”
said I.
“Oh, pshaw!
When yu’ can’t have what you choose,
yu’ just choose what you have.”
And he took the bill-of-fare.
I began to know that he had something on
his mind, so I did not
trouble him further.
Meanwhile he sat studying
the bill-of-fare.
“Ever heard o’ them?”
he inquired, shoving me
the spotted document.
Most improbable dishes were there⁠—
salmis, canapés, suprêmes⁠—all perfectly
spelt and absolutely transparent.
It was the old trick of copying some
metropolitan menu to catch travellers of
the third and last dimension of
innocence; and whenever this is done the
food is of the third and last dimension
of awfulness, which the cowpuncher knew
as well as anybody.
“So they keep that up here still,” I said.
“But what about them?”
he repeated.
His finger was at a special item,
Frogs’ legs à la Delmonico.
“Are they true anywheres?”
he asked.
And I told him, certainly.
I also explained to him about Delmonico
of New York and about
Augustin of Philadelphia.
“There’s not a little bit o’ use in lyin’
to me this mawnin’,” he said,
with his engaging smile.
“I ain’t goin’ to awdeh anything’s laigs
.
”
“Well, I’ll see how he gets out of it,”
I said, remembering the odd Texas
legend.
(The traveller read the bill-of-fare,
you know, and called for a vol-au-vent.
And the proprietor looked at the
traveller, and running a pistol into his
ear, observed, “You’ll take hash.”)
I was thinking of this and wondering what
would happen to me.
So I took the step.
“Wants frogs’ legs, does he?”
shouted Colonel Cyrus Jones.
He fixed his eye upon me,
and it narrowed to a slit.
“Too many brain workers breakfasting
before yu’ came in, professor,” said he.
“Missionary ate the last leg
off me just now.
Brown the wheat!”
he commanded, through the hole to the
cook, for someone had ordered hot cakes.
“I’ll have fried aiggs,”
said the Virginian.
“Cooked both sides.”
“White wings!”
sang the colonel through the hole.
“Let ’em fly up and down.”
“Coffee an’ no milk,” said the Virginian.
“Draw one in the dark!”
the colonel roared.
“And beefsteak, rare.”
“One slaughter in the pan,
and let the blood drip!”
“I should like a glass of
water, please,” said I.
The colonel threw me a look of pity.
“One Missouri and ice for the professor!”
he said.
“That fello’s a right live
man,” commented the Virginian.
But he seemed thoughtful.
Presently he inquired,
“Yu’ say he was a foreigner,
an’ learned fancy cookin’ to New Yawk?”
That was this cowpuncher’s way.
Scarcely ever would he let drop a thing
new to him until he had got from you
your whole information about it.
So I told him the history of Lorenzo
Delmonico and his pioneer work,
as much as I knew, and
the Southerner listened intently.
“Mighty inter-estin’,” he said⁠—“mighty.
He could just take little old o’rn’ry
frawgs, and dandy ’em up
to suit the bloods.
Mighty inter
-
estin’.
I expaict, though, his cookin’ would give
an outraiged stomach to
a plain-raised man.”
“If you want to follow it up,”
said I, by way of a sudden experiment,
“Miss Molly Wood might have some
book about French dishes.”
But the Virginian did not turn a hair.
“I reckon she wouldn’t,” he answered.
“She was raised in Vermont.
They don’t bother overly about their
eatin’ up in Vermont.
Hyeh’s what Miss Wood recommended the
las’ time I was seein’ her,”
the cowpuncher added,
bringing Kenilworth from his pocket.
“Right fine story.
That Queen Elizabeth must have cert’nly
been a competent woman.
”
“She was,” said I.
But talk came to an end here.
A dusty crew, most evidently from the
plains, now entered and drifted to a
table; and each man of them gave the
Virginian about a quarter
of a slouchy nod.
His greeting to them was very serene.
Only, Kenilworthwent back into his
pocket, and he breakfasted in silence.
Among those who had greeted him I
now recognized a face.
“Why, that’s the man you played cards
with at Medicine Bow!”
I said.
“Yes.
Trampas.
He’s got a job at the ranch now.”
The Virginian said no more,
but went on with his breakfast.
His appearance was changed.
Aged I would scarcely say,
for this would seem as if he
did not look young.
But I think that the boy was altogether
gone from his face⁠—the boy whose freak
with Steve had turned Medicine Bow
upside down, whose other freak with the
babies had outraged Bear Creek,
the boy who had loved
to jingle his spurs.
But manhood had only trained,
not broken, his youth.
It was all there, only obedient to
the rein and curb.
Presently we went together
to the railway yard.
“The Judge is doing a right smart o’
business this year,”
he began, very casually indeed,
so that I knew this was important.
Besides bells and coal smoke,
the smell and crowded sounds of cattle
rose in the air around us.
“Hyeh’s our first gather o’ beeves on the
ranch,” continued the Virginian.
“The whole lot’s shipped through to
Chicago in two sections
over the Burlington.
The Judge is fighting the Elkhorn road.”
We passed slowly along the two trains⁠—
twenty cars, each car packed with
huddled, round-eyed, gazing steers.
He examined to see if
any animals were down.
“They ain’t ate or drank anything to
speak of,” he said, while the terrified
brutes stared at us through their slats.
“Not since they struck the
railroad they’ve not drank.
Yu’ might suppose they know somehow what
they’re travellin’ to Chicago for.”
And casually, always casually,
he told me the rest.
Judge Henry could not spare his foreman
away from the second gather of beeves.
Therefore these two ten-car trains with
their double crew of cowboys had been
given to the Virginian’s charge.
After Chicago, he was to return by St.
Paul over the Northern Pacific;
for the Judge had wished him to see
certain of the road’s directors and
explain to them persuasively how good a
thing it would be for them to allow
especially cheap rates to the
Sunk Creek outfit henceforth.
This was all the Virginian told me;
and it contained the whole
matter, to be sure.
“So you’re acting foreman,” said I.
“Why, somebody has to have
the say, I reckon.”
“And of course you hated the promotion?”
“I don’t know about promotion,”
he replied.
“The boys have been used to seein’
me one of themselves.
Why don’t you come along with
us far as Plattsmouth?”
Thus he shifted the subject from himself,
and called to my notice the locomotives
backing up to his cars,
and reminded me that from Plattsmouth I
had the choice of two trains returning.
But he could not hide or belittle this
confidence of his employer in him.
It was the care of several thousand
perishable dollars and
the control of men.
It was a compliment.
There were more steers than men to be
responsible for; but none of the steers
had been suddenly picked from the herd
and set above his fellows.
Moreover, Chicago finished up the steers;
but the new-made deputy foreman had then
to lead his six highly unoccupied
brethren away from towns,
and back in peace to the ranch,
or disappoint the Judge,
who needed their services.
These things sometimes go wrong in a land
where they say you are all born equal;
and that quarter of a nod in Colonel
Cyrus Jones’s eating palace held more
equality than any whole
nod you could see.
But the Virginian did not see it,
there being a time for all things.
We trundled down the flopping,
heavy-eddied Missouri to Plattsmouth,
and there they backed us on to a siding,
the Christian Endeavor being expected
to pass that way.
And while the equality absorbed
themselves in a deep but harmless game
of poker by the side of the railway
line, the Virginian and I sat on the top
of a car, contemplating the sandy
shallows of the Platte.
“I should think you’d take
a hand,” said I.
“Poker?
With them kittens?”
One flash of the inner man lightened in
his eyes and died away,
and he finished with his gentle drawl,
“When I play, I want
it to be interestin’.”
He took out Sir Walter’s Kenilworth once
more, and turned the volume over and
over slowly, without opening it.
You cannot tell if in spirit he wandered
on Bear Creek with the girl
whose book it was.
The spirit will go one road,
and the thought another,
and the body its own way sometimes.
“Queen Elizabeth would have played a
mighty pow’ful game,”
was his next remark.
“Poker?”
said I.
“
Yes, seh.
Do you expaict Europe has got any queen
equal to her at present?”
I doubted it.
“Victoria’d get pretty nigh slain sliding
chips out agaynst Elizabeth.
Only mos’ prob’ly Victoria she’d insist
on a half-cent limit.
You have read this hyeh Kenilworth?
Well, deal Elizabeth ace high,
an’ she could scare Robert Dudley with a
full house plumb out o’ the bettin’.”
I said that I believed
she unquestionably could.
“And,” said the Virginian,
“if Essex’s play got next her too near,
I reckon she’d have stacked the cyards.
Say, d’ yu’ remember Shakespeare’s
fat man?
”
“Falstaff?
Oh, yes, indeed.”
“Ain’t that grand?
Why, he makes men talk the way
they do in life.
I reckon he couldn’t get printed today.
It’s a right down shame Shakespeare
couldn’t know about poker.
He’d have had Falstaff playing all day
at that Tearsheet outfit.
And the Prince would have beat him.
”
“The Prince had the brains,” said I.
“Brains?”
“Well, didn’t he?”
“I neveh thought to notice.
Like as not he did.”
“And Falstaff didn’t, I suppose?”
“Oh, yes, seh!
Falstaff could have played whist.”
“I suppose you know what you’re talking
about; I don’t,” said I,
for he was drawling again.
The cowpuncher’s eye rested a
moment amiably upon me.
“You can play whist with your brains,”
he mused⁠—“brains and cyards.
Now cyards are only one o’ the
manifestations of poker
in this hyeh world.
One o’ the shapes yu fool with it in when
the day’s work is oveh.
If a man is built like that Prince boy
was built (and it’s away down deep
beyond brains), he’ll play winnin’ poker
with whatever hand he’s holdin’
when the trouble begins.
Maybe it will be a mean,
triflin’ army, or an empty six-shooter,
or a lame hawss, or maybe just nothin’
but his natural countenance.
’Most any old thing will do for a fello’
like that Prince boy to play poker
with.”
“Then I’d be grateful for your definition
of poker,” said I.
Again the Virginian looked
me over amiably.
“You put up a mighty pretty game o’
whist yourself,” he remarked.
“Don’t that give you the
contented spirit?”
And before I had any reply to this,
the Christian Endeavor began to
come over the bridge.
Three instalments crossed the Missouri
from Pacific Junction,
bound for Pike’s Peak,
every car swathed in bright bunting,
and at each window a Christian with
a handkerchief, joyously shrieking.
Then the cattle trains got the open
signal, and I jumped off.
“Tell the Judge the steers was all right
this far,” said the Virginian.
That was the last of the deputy
foreman for a while.
CHAPTER XIV
Between the Acts
My road to Sunk Creek lay
in no straight line.
By rail I diverged northwest to
Fort Meade, and thence
, after some stay with the kind military
people, I made my way on a horse.
Up here in the Black Hills it
sluiced rain most intolerably.
The horse and I enjoyed the country and
ourselves but little;
and when finally I changed from the
saddle into a stagecoach,
I caught a thankful expression upon the
animal’s face, and returned the same.
“Six legs inside this jerky tonight?”
said somebody, as I climbed the wheel.
“Well, we’ll give thanks for not havin’
eight,” he added cheerfully.
“Clamp your mind on to that, Shorty.”
And he slapped the shoulder
of his neighbor.
Naturally I took these
two for old companions.
But we were all total strangers.
They told me of the new gold excitement
at Rawhide, and supposed it would bring
up the Northern Pacific;
and when I explained the millions owed
to this road’s German bondholders,
they were of opinion that a German would
strike it richer at Rawhide.
We spoke of all sorts of things,
and in our silence I gloated on the
autumn holiday promised
me by Judge Henry.
His last letter had said that an outfit
would be starting for his ranch from
Billings on the seventh,
and he would have a horse for me.
This was the fifth.
So we six legs in the jerky travelled
harmoniously on over the rain-gutted
road, getting no deeper knowledge of
each other than what
our outsides might imply.
Not that we concealed anything.
The man who had slapped
Shorty introduced himself early.
“Scipio le Moyne, from
Gallipolice, Ohio,” he said.
“The eldest of us always
gets called Scipio.
It’s French.
But us folks have been white
for a hundred years.”
He was limber and light-muscled,
and fell skilfully about,
evading bruises when the jerky reeled
or rose on end.
He had a strange, long,
jocular nose, very wary-looking,
and a bleached blue eye.
Cattle was his business,
as a rule, but of late he had been
“looking around some,”
and Rawhide seemed much on his brain.
Shorty struck me as “looking around” also.
He was quite short, indeed,
and the jerky hurt him almost every
time.
He was light-haired and mild.
Think of a yellow dog that is lost,
and fancies each newcomer in sight is
going to turn out his master,
and you will have Shorty.
It was the Northern Pacific that
surprised us into intimacy.
We were nearing Medora.
We had made a last arrangement
of our legs.
I lay stretched in silence,
placid in the knowledge it
was soon to end.
So I drowsed.
I felt something sudden,
and, waking, saw Scipio
passing through the air.
As Shorty next shot from the jerky,
I beheld smoke and the locomotive.
The Northern Pacific had
changed its schedule.
A valise is a poor companion for
catching a train with.
There was rutted sand and lumpy,
knee-high grease wood in our shortcut.
A piece of stray wire sprang from some
hole and hung caracoling about my ankle.
Tin cans spun from my stride.
But we made a conspicuous race.
Two of us waved hats,
and there was no moment that some one of
us was not screeching.
It meant twenty-four hours to us.
Perhaps we failed to catch the train’s
attention, though the
theory seems monstrous.
As it moved off in our faces,
smooth and easy and insulting,
Scipio dropped instantly to a walk,
and we two others outstripped him and
came desperately to the empty track.
There went the train.
Even still its puffs were the separated
puffs of starting, that bitten-off,
snorty kind, and sweat and our true
natures broke freely forth.
I kicked my valise, and then
sat on it, dumb.
Shorty yielded himself up aloud.
All his humble secrets came out of him.
He walked aimlessly round, lamenting.
He had lost his job, and
he mentioned the ranch.
He had played cards, and
he mentioned the man.
He had sold his horse and saddle to catch
a friend on this train,
and he mentioned what the friend had
been going to do for him.
He told a string of griefs and names to
the air, as if the air knew.
Meanwhile Scipio arrived with extreme
leisure at the rails.
He stuck his hands into his pockets and
his head out at the very small train.
His bleached blue eyes shut to slits as
he watched the rear car in its smoke-
blur ooze away westward
among the mounded bluffs.
“Lucky it’s out of range,” I thought.
But now Scipio spoke to it.
“Why, you seem to think you’ve left me
behind,” he began easily,
in fawning tones.
“You’re too much of a kid
to have such thoughts.
Age some.”
His next remark grew less wheedling.
“I wouldn’t be a bit proud to meet yu’.
Why, if I was seen travellin’ with yu’,
I’d have to explain it to my friends!
Think you’ve got me left, do yu’?
Just because yu’ ride through this
country on a rail, do yu’ claim yu’ can
find your way around?
I could take yu’ out ten yards in the
brush and lose yu’ in ten seconds,
you spangle-roofed hobo!
Leave me behind?
you recent blanket-mortgage yearlin’!
You plush-lined, nickel-plated,
whistlin’ wash room,
d’ yu’ figure I can’t go east just
as soon as west?
Or I’ll stay right here if it suits me,
yu’ dude-inhabited hotbox!
Why, yu’ coon-bossed face-towel⁠—”
But from here he rose in flights of
novelty that appalled and held me
spellbound, and which are not for me
to say to you.
Then he came down easily again,
and finished with expressions of
sympathy for it because it could never
have known a mother.
“Do you expaict it could show
a male parent offhand?”
inquired a slow voice behind us.
I jumped round, and there
was the Virginian.
“Male parent!”
scoffed the prompt Scipio.
“Ain’t you heard about them yet?”
“Them?
Was there two?”
“Two?
The blamed thing was sired by a
whole doggone Dutch syndicate.”
“Why, the piebald son of a gun!”
responded the Virginian, sweetly.
“I got them steers through all right,”
he added to me.
“Sorry to see yu’ get so out o’
breath afteh the train.
Is your valise sufferin’ any?”
“Who’s he?”
inquired Scipio, curiously, turning to me.
The Southerner sat with a newspaper on
the rear platform of a caboose.
The caboose stood hitched behind a mile
or so of freight train,
and the train was headed west.
So here was the deputy foreman,
his steers delivered in Chicago,
his men (I could hear them) safe in the
caboose, his paper in his lap,
and his legs dangling at
ease over the railing.
He wore the look of a man for whom
things are going smooth.
And for me the way to Billings
was smooth now, also.
“Who’s he?”
Scipio repeated.
But from inside the caboose loud laughter
and noise broke on us.
Someone was reciting “And it’s
my night to howl.”
“We’ll all howl when we get to Rawhide,”
said some other one; and they howled
now.
“These hyeh steam cyars,”
said the Virginian to Scipio,
“make a man’s language mighty nigh as
speedy as his travel.”
Of Shorty he took no notice whatever⁠—no
more than of the manifestations
in the caboose.
“So yu’ heard me speakin’ to
the express,” said Scipio.
“Well, I guess, sometimes I⁠—See here,”
he exclaimed, for the Virginian was
gravely considering him,
“I may have talked some,
but I walked a whole lot.
You didn’t catch me squandering no speed.
Soon as⁠—”
“I noticed,” said the Virginian,
“thinkin’ came quicker
to yu’ than runnin’.”
I was glad I was not Shorty,
to have my measure taken merely by my
way of missing a train.
And of course I was sorry that I
had kicked my valise.
“Oh, I could tell yu’d been enjoyin’ us!”
said Scipio.
“Observin’ somebody else’s scrape always
kind o’ rests me too.
Maybe you’re a philosopher,
but maybe there’s a pair of us
drawd in this deal.
”
Approval now grew plain upon the
face of the Virginian.
“By your laigs,” said he,
“you are used to the saddle.”
“I’d be called used to it, I expect.”
“By your hands,” said the Southerner,
again, “you ain’t roped
many steers lately.
Been cookin’ or something?”
“Say,” retorted Scipio,
“tell my future some now.
Draw a conclusion from my mouth.”
“I’m right distressed,”
answered the gentle Southerner,
“we’ve not a drop in the outfit.”
“Oh, drink with me uptown!”
cried Scipio.
“I’m pleased to death with yu’.”
The Virginian glanced where the saloons
stood just behind the station,
and shook his head.
“Why, it ain’t a bit far
to whiskey from here!”
urged the other, plaintively.
“Step down, now.
Scipio le Moyne’s my name.
Yes, you’re lookin’ for my brass earrings.
But there ain’t no earrings on me.
I’ve been white for a hundred years.
Step down.
I’ve a forty-dollar thirst.
”
“You’re certainly white,”
began the Virginian.
“But⁠—”
Here the caboose resumed:⁠—
“I’m wild, and woolly,
and full of peas;I’m hard to curry above
the knees;I’m a she-wolf from Bitter
Creek, andIt’s my night to ho‑o‑wl⁠—”
And as they howled and stamped,
the wheels of the caboose began to turn
gently and to murmur.
The Virginian rose suddenly.
“Will yu’ save that thirst and take
a forty-dollar job?”
“Missin’ trains, profanity, or what?”
said Scipio.
“I’ll tell yu’ soon as I’m sure.”
At this Scipio looked
hard at the Virginian.
“Why, you’re talkin’ business!”
said he, and leaped on the caboose,
where I was already.
“I was thinkin’ of Rawhide,”
he added, “but I ain’t any more.”
“Well, good luck!”
said Shorty, on the track behind us.
“Oh, say!”
said Scipio, “he wanted to go on that
train, just like me.”
“Get on,” called the Virginian.
“But as to getting a job,
he ain’t just like you.”
So Shorty came, like a lost dog when
you whistle to him.
Our wheels clucked over
the mainline switch.
A train-hand threw it shut after us,
jumped aboard, and returned
forward over the roofs.
Inside the caboose they had reached the
third howling of the she-wolf.
“Friends of yourn?”
said Scipio.
“My outfit,” drawled the Virginian.
“Do yu’ always travel outside?”
inquired Scipio.
“It’s lonesome in there,”
returned the deputy foreman.
And here one of them came
out, slamming the door.
“Hell!”
he said, at sight of the distant town.
Then, truculently, to the Virginian,
“I told you I was going to
get a bottle here.”
“Have your bottle, then,”
said the deputy foreman,
and kicked him off into Dakota.
(It was not North Dakota yet;
they had not divided it.)
The Virginian had aimed his pistol at
about the same time with his boot.
Therefore the man sat in Dakota quietly,
watching us go away into Montana,
and offering no objections.
Just before he became too small to make
out, we saw him rise and remove himself
back toward the saloons.
CHAPTER XV
The Game and the Nation⁠—Act Second
“That is the only step I have had to take
this whole trip,” said the Virginian.
He holstered his pistol with a jerk.
“I have been fearing he would
force it on me.”
And he looked at empty,
receding Dakota with disgust.
“So nyeh back home!”
he muttered.
“Known your friend long?”
whispered Scipio to me.
“Fairly,” I answered.
Scipio’s bleached eyes brightened with
admiration as he considered
the Southerner’s back.
“Well,” he stated judicially,
“start awful early when yu’ go to fool
with him, or he’ll make
you feel unpunctual.”
“I expaict I’ve had them almost all of
three thousand miles,”
said the Virginian, tilting his head
toward the noise in the caboose.
“And I’ve strove to deliver them back
as I received them.
The whole lot.
And I would have.
But he has spoiled my hopes.”
The deputy foreman looked again at Dakota.
“It’s a disappointment,” he added.
“You may know what I mean.”
I had known a little,
but not to the very deep,
of the man’s pride and
purpose in this trust.
Scipio gave him sympathy.
“There must be quite a balance of ’em
left with yu’ yet,” said
Scipio, cheeringly.
“I had the boys plumb contented,”
pursued the deputy foreman,
hurt into open talk of himself.
“Away along as far as Saynt Paul I had
them reconciled to my authority.
Then this news about gold
had to strike us.”
“And they’re a-dreamin’ nuggets and
Parisian bowleyvards,” suggested Scipio.
The Virginian smiled gratefully at him.
“Fortune is shinin’ bright and blindin’
to their delicate young eyes,”
he said, regaining his usual self.
We all listened a moment
to the rejoicings within.
“Energetic, ain’t they?”
said the Southerner.
“But none of ’em was whelped savage
enough to sing himself bloodthirsty.
And though they’re strainin’ mighty
earnest not to be tame,
they’re goin’ back to Sunk Creek with me
accordin’ to the Judge’s awders
.
Never a calf of them will desert to
Rawhide, for all their dangerousness;
nor I ain’t goin’ to have
any fuss over it.
Only one is left now that don’t sing.
Maybe I will have to make
some arrangements about him.
The man I have parted with,”
he said, with another glance
at
Dakota
, “was our cook, and I will ask yu’
to replace him, Colonel.”
Scipio gaped wide.
“Colonel!
Say!”
He stared at the Virginian.
“Did I meet yu’ at the palace?”
“Not exackly meet,” replied
the Southerner.
“I was present one mawnin’ las’ month
when this gentleman awdehed
frawgs’ laigs.”
“Sakes and saints, but that
was a mean position!”
burst out Scipio.
“I had to tell all comers
anything all day.
Stand up and jump language hot off
my brain at ’em.
And the pay don’t near compensate for the
drain on the system.
I don’t care how good a man is,
you let him keep a-tappin’ his presence
of mind right along,
without takin’ a layoff,
and you’ll have him sick.
Yes, sir.
You’ll hit his nerves.
So I told them they could hire some fresh
man, for I was goin’ back to punch
cattle or fight Indians,
or take a rest somehow,
for I didn’t propose to get jaded,
and me only twenty-five years old.
There ain’t no regular Colonel Cyrus
Jones any more, yu’ know.
He met a Cheyenne telegraph pole in
seventy-four, and was buried.
But his palace was doin’ big business,
and he had been a kind of attraction,
and so they always keep a live bear
outside, and some poor fello’, fixed up
like the Colonel used to be, inside.
And it’s a turruble mean position.
Course I’ll cook for yu’.
Yu’ve a dandy memory for faces!”
“I wasn’t right convinced till I kicked
him off and you gave that shut to your
eyes again,” said the Virginian.
Once more the door opened.
A man with slim black eyebrows,
slim black mustache,
and a black shirt tied with a white
handkerchief was looking steadily from
one to the other of us.
“Good day!”
he remarked generally and without
enthusiasm; and to the
Virginian, “Where’s Schoffner?”
“I expaict he’ll have got his
bottle by now, Trampas.”
Trampas looked from one to the
other of us again.
“Didn’t he say he was coming back?”
“He reminded me he was going for a
bottle, and afteh that he didn’t wait
to say a thing.”
Trampas looked at the platform and the
railing and the steps.
“He told me he was coming
back,” he insisted.
“I don’t reckon he has come,
not without he clumb up ahaid somewhere.
An’ I mus’ say, when he got off he didn’t
look like a man does when he has
the intention o’ returnin’.
”
At this Scipio coughed,
and pared his nails attentively.
We had already been avoiding
each other’s eye.
Shorty did not count.
Since he got aboard, his meek seat had
been the bottom step.
The thoughts of Trampas seemed
to be in difficulty.
“How long’s this train been started?”
he demanded.
“This hyeh train?”
The Virginian consulted his watch.
“Why, it’s been fanning it a right smart
little while,” said he,
laying no stress upon
his indolent syllables.
“Huh!”
went Trampas.
He gave the rest of us
a final unlovely scrutiny.
“It seems to have become a
passenger train,” he said.
And he returned abruptly
inside the caboose.
“Is he the member who don’t sing?”
asked Scipio.
“That’s the specimen,”
replied the Southerner.
“He don’t seem musical in
the face,” said Scipio.
“Pshaw!”
returned the Virginian.
“Why, you surely ain’t the man to mind
ugly mugs when they’re hollow!”
The noise inside had dropped
quickly to stillness.
You could scarcely catch
the sound of talk.
Our caboose was clicking comfortably
westward, rail after rail,
mile upon mile, while night was
beginning to rise from earth
into the clouded sky.
“I wonder if they have sent a search
party forward to hunt Schoffner?”
said the Virginian.
“I think I’ll maybe join their meeting.”
He opened the door upon them.
“Kind o’ dark hyeh, ain’t it?”
said he.
And lighting the lantern, he shut us out.
“What do yu’ think?”
said Scipio to me.
“Will he take them to Sunk Creek?”
“He evidently thinks he will,” said I.
“He says he will, and he has the
courage of his convictions.”
“That ain’t near enough courage to have!”
Scipio exclaimed.
“There’s times in life when a man has got
to have courage withoutconvictions⁠—
without them⁠—or he is no good.
Now your friend is that deep constitooted
that you don’t know and I don’t know
what he’s thinkin’ about all this.”
“If there’s to be any gunplay,”
put in the excellent Shorty,
“I’ll stand in with him.”
“Ah, go to bed with your gunplay!”
retorted Scipio, entirely good-humored.
“Is the Judge paying for a carload of
dead punchers to gather his beef for
him?
And this ain’t a proposition worth a
man’s gettin’ hurt for himself, anyway.”
“That’s so,” Shorty assented.
“No,” speculated Scipio,
as the night drew deeper round us and
the caboose click-clucked and click-
clucked over the rail joints;
“he’s waitin’ for somebody else
to open this pot.
I’ll bet he don’t know but one thing now,
and that’s that nobody else shall know
he don’t know anything.”
Scipio had delivered himself.
He lighted a cigarette,
and no more wisdom came from him.
The night was established.
The rolling badlands sank away in it.
A train-hand had arrived over the roof,
and hanging the red lights out behind,
left us again without remark
or symptom of curiosity.
The train-hands seemed interested in
their own society and lived
in their own caboose.
A chill wind with wet in it came blowing
from the invisible draws,
and brought the feel
of the distant mountains
.
“That’s Montana!”
said Scipio, snuffing.
“I am glad to have it
inside my lungs again.”
“Ain’t yu’ getting cool out there?”
said the Virginian’s voice.
“Plenty room inside.”
Perhaps he had expected us to follow him;
or perhaps he had meant us to delay long
enough not to seem like a reinforcement.
“These gentlemen missed the express at
Medora,” he observed to his men, simply.
What they took us for upon our entrance I
cannot say, or what they believed.
The atmosphere of the caboose was charged
with voiceless currents of thought.
By way of a friendly beginning to the
three hundred miles of caboose we were
now to share so intimately,
I recalled myself to them.
I trusted no more of the Christian
Endeavor had delayed them.
“I am so lucky to have caught
you again,” I finished.
“I was afraid my last chance of reaching
the Judge’s had gone.”
Thus I said a number of things designed
to be agreeable, but they met my small
talk with the smallest talk you can
have.
“Yes,” for instance, and “Pretty well,
I guess,” and grave strikings of matches
and thoughtful looks at the floor
.
I suppose we had made twenty miles to the
imperturbable clicking of the caboose
when one at length asked his neighbor
had he ever seen New York.
“No,” said the other.
“Flooded with dudes, ain’t it?
”
“Swimmin’,” said the first.
“Leakin’, too,” said a third.
“Well, my gracious!”
said a fourth, and beat his
knee in private delight.
None of them ever looked at me.
For some reason I felt
exceedingly ill at ease.
“Good clothes in New York,”
said the third.
“Rich food,” said the first.
“Fresh eggs, too,” said the third.
“Well, my gracious!”
said the fourth, beating his knee.
“Why, yes,” observed the Virginian,
unexpectedly; “they tell me that aiggs
there ain’t liable to be so rotten as
yu’ll strike ’em in this country.”
None of them had a reply for this,
and New York was abandoned.
For some reason I felt much better.
It was a new line they adopted next,
led off by Trampas.
“Going to the excitement?”
he inquired, selecting Shorty.
“Excitement?”
said Shorty, looking up.
“Going to Rawhide?”
Trampas repeated.
And all watched Shorty.
“Why, I’m all adrift missin’
that express,” said Shorty.
“Maybe I can give you
employment,” suggested the Virginian.
“I am taking an outfit across the basin.”
“You’ll find most folks going to Rawhide,
if you’re looking for company,”
pursued Trampas, fishing for a recruit.
“How about Rawhide, anyway?”
said Scipio, skillfully
deflecting this missionary work.
“Are they taking much mineral out?
Have yu’ seen any of the rock?”
“Rock?”
broke in the enthusiast who
had beaten his knee.
“There!”
And he brought some from his pocket.
“You’re always showing your rock,”
said Trampas, sulkily;
for Scipio now held the conversation,
and Shorty returned safely to his
dozing.
“H’m!”
went Scipio at the rock.
He turned it back and forth in his hand,
looking it over; he chucked and caught
it slightingly in the air,
and handed it back.
“Porphyry, I see.”
That was his only word about it.
He said it cheerily.
He left no room for discussion.
You could not damn a thing worse.
“Ever been in Santa Rita?”
pursued Scipio, while the enthusiast
slowly pushed his rock
back into his pocket.
“That’s down in New Mexico.
Ever been to Globe, Arizona?”
And Scipio talked away about the
mines he had known.
There was no getting at Shorty
any more that evening.
Trampas was foiled of his fish,
or of learning how the fish’s heart lay.
And by morning Shorty had been carefully
instructed to change his mind
about once an hour.
This is apt to discourage all
but very superior missionaries.
And I too escaped for the
rest of this night.
At Glendive we had a dim supper,
and I bought some blankets;
and after that it was late,
and sleep occupied the
attention of us all.
We lay along the shelves of the caboose,
a peaceful sight I should think,
in that smoothly trundling cradle.
I slept almost immediately,
so tired that not even our stops or
anything else waked me,
save once, when the air I was breathing
grew suddenly pure, and I roused.
Sitting in the door was the lonely
figure of the Virginian.
He leaned in silent contemplation of the
occasional moon, and beneath it
the Yellowstone’s swift ripples.
On the caboose shelves the others slept
sound and still, each stretched or
coiled as he had first put himself.
They were not untrustworthy to look at,
it seemed to me⁠—except Trampas.
You would have said the rest of that
young humanity was average rough male
blood, merely needing to be told the
proper things at the right time;
and one big bunchy stocking of the
enthusiast stuck out of his blanket,
solemn and innocent, and I laughed at
it.
There was a light sound by the door,
and I found the Virginian’s eye on me.
Finding who it was, he nodded and
motioned with his hand to go to sleep.
And this I did with him in my sight,
still leaning in the open door,
through which came the interrupted moon
and the swimming reaches
of the Yellowstone.
CHAPTER XVI
The Game The Nation—Last Act
It has happened to you,
has it not, to wake in the morning and
wonder for a while where
on earth you are?
Thus I came half to life in the caboose,
hearing voices, but not the
actual words at first.
But presently, “Hathaway!”
said someone more clearly.
“Portland 1,291!”
This made no special stir in my
intelligence, and I drowsed off again to
the pleasant rhythm of the wheels.
The little shock of stopping next brought
me to, somewhat, with the voices still
round me; and when we were again in
motion, I heard: “Rosebud!
Portland
1,279
!
”
These figures jarred me awake,
and I said, “It was 1,291 before,”
and sat up in my blankets.
The greeting they vouchsafed and the
sight of them clustering expressionless
in the caboose brought last evening’s
uncomfortable memory back to me.
Our next stop revealed how
things were going today.
“Forsythe,” one of them
read on the station.
“Portland 1,266.”
They were counting the
lessening distance westward.
This was the undercurrent of war.
It broke on me as I procured fresh water
at Forsythe and made some toilet
in their stolid presence.
We were drawing nearer the Rawhide
station⁠—the point, I mean,
where you left the railway
for the new mines.
Now Rawhide station lay
this side of Billings.
The broad path of desertion would open
ready for their feet when the narrow
path to duty and Sunk Creek was still
some fifty miles more to wait.
Here was Trampas’s great strength;
he need make no move meanwhile,
but lie low for the immediate temptation
to front and waylay them and win his
battle over the deputy foreman.
But the Virginian seemed to find nothing
save enjoyment in this sunny September
morning, and ate his
breakfast at Forsythe serenely.
That meal done and that station gone,
our caboose took up again its easy
trundle by the banks of the Yellowstone.
The mutineers sat for a
while digesting in idleness.
“What’s your scar?”
inquired one at length inspecting
casually the neck of his neighbor.
“Foolishness,” the other answered.
“Yourn?”
“Mine.”
“Well, I don’t know but I prefer to have
myself to thank for a
thing,” said the first.
“I was displaying myself,”
continued the second.
“One day last summer it was.
We come on a big snake
by Torrey Creek corral.
The boys got betting pretty lively that I
dassent make my word good as to dealing
with him, so I loped my cayuse full tilt
by Mr. Snake, and swung down and catched
him up by the tail from the ground,
and cracked him same as a whip,
and snapped his head off.
You’ve saw it done?”
he said to the audience.
The audience nodded wearily.
“But the loose head flew agin me,
and the fangs caught.
I was pretty sick for a while.
”
“It don’t pay to be clumsy,”
said the first man.
“If you’d snapped the snake away from yu’
instead of toward yu’, its head would
have whirled off into the brush,
same as they do with me.”
“How like a knife-cut your scar looks!”
said I.
“Don’t it?”
said the snake-snapper.
“There’s many that gets fooled by it.”
“An antelope knows a snake is his enemy,”
said another to me.
“Ever seen a buck circling round
and round a rattler?”
“I have always wanted to see
that,” said I, heartily.
For this I knew to be a
respectable piece of truth.
“It’s worth seeing,” the man went on.
“After the buck gets close in,
he gives an almighty jump up in the air,
and down comes his four hoofs in a bunch
right on top of Mr. Snake.
Cuts him all to hash.
Now you tell me how the buck knows that.
”
Of course I could not tell him.
And again we sat in silence for a while⁠—
friendlier silence, I thought.
“A skunk’ll kill yu’ worse than a snake
bite,” said another, presently.
“No, I don’t mean that way,” he added.
For I had smiled.
“There is a brown skunk down in Arkansaw.
Kind of prairie-dog brown.
Littler than our variety, he is.
And he is mad the whole year round,
same as a dog gets.
Only the dog has a spell and dies but
this here Arkansaw skunk is mad right
along, and it don’t seem to interfere
with his business in other respects.
Well, suppose you’re camping out,
and suppose it’s a hot night,
or you’re in a hurry,
and you’ve made camp late,
or anyway you haven’t got inside any
tent, but you have just bedded
down in the open.
Skunk comes travelling along and
walks on your blankets.
You’re warm.
He likes that, same as a cat does.
And he tramps with pleasure and comfort,
same as a cat.
And you move.
You get bit, that’s all.
And you die of hydrophobia.
Ask anybody.
”
“Most extraordinary!”
said I.
“But did you ever see a
person die from this?”
“No, sir.
Never happened to.
My cousin at Bald Knob did.”
“Died?”
“No, sir.
Saw a man.”
“But how do you know they’re
not sick skunks?”
“No, sir!
They’re well skunks.
Well as anything.
You’ll not meet skunks in any state of
the Union more robust
than them in Arkansaw.
And thick.”
“That’s awful true,” sighed another.
“I have buried hundreds of dollars’ worth
of clothes in Arkansaw.”
“Why didn’t yu’ travel in a sponge bag?”
inquired Scipio.
And this brought a slight silence.
“Speakin’ of bites,” spoke up a
new man, “how’s that?”
He held up his thumb.
“My!”
breathed Scipio.
“Must have been a lion.”
The man wore a wounded look.
“I was huntin’ owl eggs for a botanist
from Boston,” he explained to me.
“Chiropodist, weren’t he?”
said Scipio.
“Or maybe a sonnabulator?”
“No, honest,” protested the man with the
thumb; so that I was sorry for him,
and begged him to go on.
“I’ll listen to you,” I assured him.
And I wondered why this politeness of
mine should throw one or two of
them into stifled mirth.
Scipio, on the other hand,
gave me a disgusted look and sat back
sullenly for a moment,
and then took himself out on the
platform, where the Virginian
was lounging.
“The young feller wore knee-pants and
ever so thick spectacles with a half-
moon cut in ’em,” resumed the narrator,
“and he carried a tin box strung to a
strap I took for his lunch till it flew
open on him and a horn toad hustled out.
Then I was sure he was a botanist⁠—or
whatever yu’ say they’re called.
Well, he would have owl eggs⁠—them little
prairie-owl that some claim can turn
their head clean around and keep a-
watchin’ yu’, only that’s nonsense.
We was ridin’ through that prairie-dog
town, used to be on the flat just after
yu’ crossed the south fork of Powder
River on the Buffalo trail,
and I said I’d dig an owl nest out for
him if he was willing to camp
till I’d dug it.
I wanted to know about them owls some
myself⁠—if they did live with the dogs
and snakes, yu’ know,”
he broke off, appealing to me.
“Oh, yes,” I told him eagerly.
“So while the botanist went glarin’
around the town with his glasses to see
if he could spot a prairie-dog and an
owl usin’ the same hole,
I was diggin’ in a hole I’d seen
an owl run down.
And that’s what I got.”
He held up his thumb again.
“The snake!”
I exclaimed.
“Yes, sir.
Mr.
Rattler was keepin’ house that day.
Took me right there.
I hauled him out of the
hole hangin’ to me.
Eight rattles.
”
“Eight!”
said I.
“A big one.
”
“Yes, sir.
Thought I was dead.
But the woman⁠—”
“The woman?”
said I.
“Yes, woman.
Didn’t I tell yu’ the botanist
had his wife along?
Well, he did.
And she acted better than the man,
for he was losin’ his head,
and shoutin’ he had no whiskey,
and he didn’t guess his knife was sharp
enough to amputate my thumb,
and none of us chewed,
and the doctor was twenty miles away,
and if he had only remembered to bring
his ammonia⁠—well, he was screeching out
’most everything he knew in the world,
and without arranging it any, neither.
But she just clawed his pocket and
burrowed and kep’ yelling,
‘Give him the stone, Augustus!’
And she whipped out one of them Injun
medicine-stones⁠—first one I ever seen⁠—
and she clapped it on to my thumb,
and it started in right away.
”
“What did it do?”
said I.
“Sucked.
Like blotting-paper does.
Soft and funny it was, and gray.
They get ’em from elks’
stomachs, yu’ know.
And when it had sucked the poison out of
the wound, off it falls of
my thumb by itself!
And I thanked the woman for saving my
life that capable and keeping
her head that cool.
I never knowed how excited she
had been till afterward.
She was awful shocked.
”
“I suppose she started to talk when the
danger was over,” said I,
with deep silence around me.
“No; she didn’t say nothing to me.
But when her next child was born,
it had eight rattles.”
Din now rose wild in the caboose.
They rocked together.
The enthusiast beat his knee tumultuously.
And I joined them.
Who could help it?
It had been so well conducted
from the imperceptible beginning.
Fact and falsehood blended
with such perfect art.
And this last, an effect so new made with
such world-old material!
I cared nothing that I was the victim,
and I joined them; but ceased,
feeling suddenly somehow
estranged or chilled.
It was in their laughter.
The loudness was too loud.
And I caught the eyes of Trampas fixed
upon the Virginian with
exultant malevolence.
Scipio’s disgusted glance was upon
me from the door.
Dazed by these signs,
I went out on the platform to get
away from the noise.
There the Virginian said to me: “Cheer up!
You’ll not be so easy for ’em that-
a-way next season.”
He said no more; and with his legs
dangled over the railing,
appeared to resume his newspaper.
“What’s the matter?”
said I to Scipio.
“Oh, I don’t mind if he
don’t,” Scipio answered.
“Couldn’t yu’ see?
I tried to head ’em off from yu’ all I
knew, but yu’ just ran
in among ’em yourself.
Couldn’t yu’ see?
Kep’ hinderin’ and spoilin’ me with
askin’ those urgent questions of yourn⁠—
why, I had to let yu’ go your way!
Why, that wasn’t the ordinary play with
the ordinary tenderfoot
they treated you to!
You ain’t a common tenderfoot this trip.
You’re the foreman’s friend.
They’ve hit him through you.
That’s the way they count it.
It’s made them encouraged.
Can’t yu’ see?”
Scipio stated it plainly.
And as we ran by the next
station, “Howard!”
they harshly yelled.
“Portland 1256!”
We had been passing gangs of
workmen on the track.
And at that last yell the Virginian rose.
“I reckon I’ll join the
meeting again,” he said.
“This filling and repairing looks like
the washout might have been true.
”
“Washout?”
said Scipio.
“Big Horn bridge, they say⁠—four days ago.
”
“Then I wish it came this
side Rawhide station.”
“Do yu’?”
drawled the Virginian.
And smiling at Scipio,
he lounged in through the open door.
“He beats me,” said Scipio,
shaking his head.
“His trail is turruble
hard to anticipate.”
We listened.
“Work bein’ done on the road,
I see,” the Virginian was saying,
very friendly and conversational.
“We see it too,” said
the voice of Trampas.
“Seem to be easin’ their grades some.”
“Roads do.”
“Cheaper to build ’em the way they want
’em at the start, a man would think,”
suggested the Virginian, most friendly.
“There go some more I-talians.”
“They’re Chinese,” said Trampas.
“That’s so,” acknowledged the
Virginian, with a laugh.
“What’s he monkeyin’ at now?”
muttered Scipio.
“Without cheap foreigners they couldn’t
afford all this hyeh new
gradin’,” the Southerner continued.
“Grading!
Can’t you tell when a flood’s
been eating the banks?”
“Why, yes,” said the Virginian,
sweet as honey.
“But ’ain’t yu’ heard of the improvements
west of Big Timber, all the way
to Missoula, this season?
I’m talkin’ about them.”
“Oh!
Talking about them.
Yes, I’ve heard.”
“Good money-savin’ scheme, ain’t it?”
said the Virginian.
“Lettin’ a freight run down one hill an’
up the next as far as she’ll go without
steam, an’ shavin’ the hill
down to that point.”
Now this was an honest engineering fact.
“Better’n settin’ dudes squintin’ through
telescopes and cipherin’ over one
percent reductions,”
the Southerner commented.
“It’s common sense,” assented Trampas.
“Have you heard the new scheme
about the water-tanks?”
“I ain’t right certain,”
said the Southerner.
“I must watch this,” said Scipio,
“or I shall bust.”
He went in, and so did I.
They were all sitting over this
discussion of the Northern Pacific’s
recent policy as to betterments,
as though they were the
board of directors.
Pins could have dropped.
Only nobody would have cared
to hear a pin.
“They used to put all their tanks at the
bottom of their grades,” said Trampas.
“Why, yu’ get the water
easier at the bottom.”
“You can pump it to the top,
though,” said Trampas, growing superior.
“And it’s cheaper.”
“That gets me,” said the
Virginian, interested.
“Trains after watering can start down
hill now and get the
benefit of the gravity.
It’ll cut down operating expenses a heap.”
“That’s cert’nly common sense!”
exclaimed the Virginian, absorbed.
“But ain’t it kind o’ tardy?”
“Live and learn.
So they gained speed, too.
High speed on half the coal this
season, until the accident.”
“Accident!”
said the Virginian, instantly.
“Yellowstone Limited.
Man fired at engine driver.
Train was flying past that quick the
bullet broke every window and killed a
passenger on the back platform.
You’ve been running too much with
aristocrats,” finished Trampas,
and turned on his heel.
“Haw, hew!”
began the enthusiast,
but his neighbor gripped him to silence.
This was a triumph too serious for noise.
Not a mutineer moved; and I felt cold.
“Trampas,” said the Virginian,
“I thought yu’d be afeared to
try it on me.”
Trampas whirled round.
His hand was at his belt.
“Afraid!”
he sneered.
“Shorty!”
said Scipio, sternly,
and leaping upon that youth,
took his half-drawn pistol from him.
“I’m obliged to yu’,” said
the Virginian to Scipio.
Trampas’s hand left his belt.
He threw a slight, easy look at his men,
and keeping his back to the Virginian,
walked out on the platform and sat on
the chair where the Virginian
had sat so much.
“Don’t you comprehend,”
said the Virginian to Shorty,
amiably, “that this hyeh question has
been discussed peaceable
by civilized citizens?
Now you sit down and be good,
and Mr. Le Moyne will return your gun
when we’re across that broken bridge,
if they have got it fixed
for heavy trains yet.”
“This train will be lighter when it gets
to that bridge,” spoke Trampas,
out on his chair.
“Why, that’s true, too!”
said the Virginian.
“Maybe none of us are crossin’ that Big
Horn bridge now, except me.
Funny if yu’ should end by persuadin’ me
to quit and go to Rawhide myself!
But I reckon I’ll not.
I reckon I’ll worry along
to Sunk Creek, somehow.
”
“Don’t forget I’m cookin’ for
yu’,” said Scipio, gruffy.
“I’m obliged to yu’,” said the Southerner.
“You were speaking of a job
for me,” said Shorty.
“I’m right obliged.
But yu’ see⁠—I ain’t exackly foreman the
way this comes out, and my promises
might not bind Judge
Henry to pay salaries.
”
A push came through the
train from forward.
We were slowing for the Rawhide station,
and all began to be busy and to talk.
“Going up to the mines today?”
“Oh, let’s grub first.”
“Guess it’s too late, anyway.”
And so forth; while they rolled and roped
their bedding, and put on their coats
with a good deal of elbow motion,
and otherwise showed off.
It was wasted.
The Virginian did not know what was going
on in the caboose.
He was leaning and looking out ahead,
and Scipio’s puzzled eye never left him.
And as we halted for the water-tank,
the Southerner exclaimed,
“They ’ain’t got away yet!”
as if it were good news to him.
He meant the delayed trains.
Four stalled expresses were in front of
us, besides several freights.
And two hours more at least before the
bridge would be ready.
Travellers stood and sat about forlorn,
near the cars, out in
the sagebrush, anywhere.
People in hats and spurs watched them,
and Indian chiefs offered them painted
bows and arrows and shiny horns.
“I reckon them passengers would prefer a
laig o’ mutton,” said the Virginian to a
man loafing near the caboose.
“Bet your life!”
said the man.
“First lot has been stuck here four days.”
“Plumb starved, ain’t they?”
inquired the Virginian.
“Bet your life!
They’ve eat up their dining cars and
they’ve eat up this town.
”
“Well,” said the Virginian,
looking at the town,
“I expaict the dining-
cyars contained more nourishment.”
“Say, you’re about right there!”
said the man.
He walked beside the caboose as we puffed
slowly forward from the water-
tank to our siding.
“Fine business here if we’d only
been ready,” he continued.
“And the Crow agent has let his Indians
come over from the reservation.
There has been a little beef brought in,
and game, and fish.
And big money in it, bet your life!
Them Eastern passengers
has just been robbed.
I wisht I had somethin’ to sell!
”
“Anything starting for
Rawhide this afternoon?”
said Trampas, out of the caboose door.
“Not until morning,” said the man.
“You going to the mines?”
he resumed to the Virginian.
“Why,” answered the Southerner,
slowly and casually,
and addressing himself strictly to the
man, while Trampas, on his side,
paid obvious inattention,
“this hyeh delay, yu’ see,
may unsettle our plans some.
But it’ll be one of two ways⁠—we’re all
goin’ to Rawhide, or we’re
all goin’ to Billings.
We’re all one party, yu’ see.”
Trampas laughed audibly inside the door
as he rejoined his men.
“Let him keep up appearances,”
I heard him tell them.
“It don’t hurt us what
he says to strangers.”
“But I’m goin’ to eat hearty either
way,” continued the Virginian.
“And I ain’ goin’ to be robbed.
I’ve been kind o’ promisin’ myself a
treat if we stopped hyeh.
”
“Town’s eat clean out,” said the man.
“So yu’ tell me.
But all you folks has forgot one source
of revenue that yu’ have right
close by, mighty handy.
If you have got a gunny sack,
I’ll show you how to make some money.
”
“Bet your life!”
said the man.
“Mr.
Le Moyne,” said the Virginian,
“the outfit’s cookin’ stuff is aboard,
and if you’ll get the fire ready,
we’ll try how frawgs’ laigs go fried.”
He walked off at once,
the man following like a dog.
Inside the caboose rose
a gust of laughter.
“Frogs!”
muttered Scipio.
And then turning a blank
face to me, “Frogs?”
“Colonel Cyrus Jones had them on his bill
of fare,” I said.
“ ‘Frogs’ legs à la Delmonico.’
”
“Shoo!
I didn’t get up that thing.
They had it when I came.
Never looked at it.
Frogs?”
He went down the steps very slowly,
with a long frown.
Reaching the ground, he shook his head.
“That man’s trail is surely hard
to anticipate,” he said.
“But I must hurry up that fire.
For his appearance has given me
encouragement,” Scipio
concluded, and became brisk.
Shorty helped him, and I brought wood.
Trampas and the other people strolled off
to the station, a compact band.
Our little fire was built beside the
caboose, so the cooking things might be
easily reached and put back.
You would scarcely think such operations
held any interest, even for the hungry,
when there seemed to be nothing to cook.
A few sticks blazing tamely in the dust,
a frying-pan, half a tin bucket of lard,
some water, and barren plates and knives
and forks, and three silent men
attending to them⁠—that
was all.
But the travellers came to see.
These waifs drew near us,
and stood, a sad, lone,
shifting fringe of audience;
four to begin with; and then two
wandered away; and presently one of
these came back, finding
it worse elsewhere.
“Supper, boys?”
said he.
“Breakfast,” said Scipio, crossly.
And no more of them addressed us.
I heard them joylessly mention Wall
Street to each other,
and Saratoga; I even heard the name Bryn
Mawr, which is near Philadelphia.
But these fragments of home dropped in
the wilderness here in Montana beside a
freight caboose were of no
interest to me now.
“Looks like frogs down
there, too,” said Scipio.
“See them marshy sloos full of weeds?”
We took a little turn and had a sight of
the Virginian quite active
among the ponds.
“Hush!
I’m getting some thoughts,”
continued Scipio.
“He wasn’t sorry enough.
Don’t interrupt me.”
“I’m not,” said I.
“No.
But I’d ’most caught ahold.”
And Scipio muttered to himself again,
“He wasn’t sorry enough.”
Presently he swore loud and brilliantly.
“Tell yu’!”
he cried.
“What did he say to Trampas after that
play they exchanged over railroad
improvements and Trampas put
the josh on him?
Didn’t he say, ‘Trampas,
I thought you’d be afraid to do it?’
Well, sir, Trampas had
better have been afraid.
And that’s what he meant.
There’s where he was bringin’ it to.
Trampas made an awful bad play then.
You wait.
Glory, but he’s a knowin’ man!
Course he wasn’t sorry.
I guess he had the hardest kind of work
to look as sorry as he did.
You wait.”
“Wait?
What for?
Go on, man!
What for?”
“I don’t know!
I don’t know!
Whatever hand he’s been holdin’ up,
this is the showdown.
He’s played for a showdown here before
the caboose gets off the bridge.
Come back to the fire,
or Shorty’ll be leavin’ it go out.
Grow happy some, Shorty!”
he cried on arriving,
and his hand cracked
on Shorty’s shoulder.
“Supper’s in sight, Shorty.
Food for reflection.
”
“None for the stomach?”
asked the passenger who
had spoken once before.
“We’re figuring on that too,” said Scipio.
His crossness had melted entirely away.
“Why, they’re cowboys!”
exclaimed another passenger;
and he moved nearer.
From the station Trampas now came back,
his herd following him less compactly.
They had found famine,
and no hope of supplies until the next
train from the East.
This was no fault of Trampas’s;
but they were following
him less compactly.
They carried one piece of cheese,
the size of a fist, the weight of a
brick, the hue of a corpse.
And the passengers, seeing it,
exclaimed, “There’s Old Faithful again!”
and took off their hats.
“You gentlemen met that
cheese before, then?”
said Scipio, delighted.
“It’s been offered me three times a day
for four days,” said the passenger.
“Did he want a dollar or a
dollar and a half?”
“Two dollars!”
blurted out the enthusiast.
And all of us save Trampas fell into
fits of imbecile laughter.
“Here comes our grub,
anyway,” said Scipio,
looking off toward the marshes.
And his hilarity sobered away in a moment.
“Well, the train will be
in soon,” stated Trampas.
“I guess we’ll get a decent
supper without frogs.”
All interest settled now
upon the Virginian.
He was coming with his man and his gunny
sack, and the gunny sack hung from his
shoulder heavily, as a full sack should.
He took no notice of the gathering,
but sat down and partly emptied the
sack.
“There,” said he, very businesslike,
to his assistant, “that’s all we’ll
want.
I think you’ll find a ready
market for the balance.”
“Well, my gracious!”
said the enthusiast.
“What fool eats a frog?”
“Oh, I’m fool enough for a tadpole
!”
cried the passenger.
And they began to take
out their pocketbooks.
“You can cook yours right hyeh,
gentlemen,” said the Virginian,
with his slow Southern courtesy.
“The dining-cyars don’t look like
they were fired up.”
“How much will you sell a couple for?”
inquired the enthusiast.
The Virginian looked at
him with friendly surprise.
“Why, help yourself!
We’re all together yet awhile.
Help yourselves,” he repeated,
to Trampas and his followers.
These hung back a moment,
then, with a slinking motion,
set the cheese upon the earth and came
forward nearer the fire
to receive some supper.
“It won’t scarcely be Delmonico style,”
said the Virginian to the passengers,
“nor yet Saynt Augustine.”
He meant the great Augustin,
the traditional chef of Philadelphia,
whose history I had sketched for him at
Colonel Cyrus Jones’s eating palace.
Scipio now officiated.
His frying-pan was busy,
and prosperous odors rose from it.
“Run for a bucket of fresh water,
Shorty,” the Virginian
continued, beginning his meal.
“Colonel, yu’ cook pretty near good.
If yu’ had sold ’em as advertised,
yu’d have cert’nly made a name.
”
Several were now eating with
satisfaction, but not Scipio.
It was all that he could
do to cook straight.
The whole man seemed to glisten.
His eye was shut to a slit once more,
while the innocent passengers
thankfully swallowed.
“Now, you see, you have made some money,”
began the Virginian to the native who
had helped him get the frogs.
“Bet your life!”
exclaimed the man.
“Divvy, won’t you?”
And he held out half his gains.
“Keep ’em,” returned the Southerner.
“I reckon we’re square.
But I expaict they’ll
not equal Delmonico’s, seh?”
he said to a passenger.
“Don’t trust the judgment of a man as
hungry as I am!”
exclaimed the traveller, with a laugh.
And he turned to his fellow-travellers.
“Did you ever enjoy supper at
Delmonico’s more than this?”
“Never!”
they sighed.
“Why, look here,” said the traveller,
“what fools the people of this town are!
Here we’ve been all these starving days,
and you come and get ahead of them!”
“That’s right easy explained,”
said the Virginian.
“I’ve been where there was big money in
frawgs, and they ’ain’t been.
They’re all cattle hyeh.
Talk cattle, think cattle,
and they’re bankrupt in consequence.
Fallen through.
Ain’t that so?”
he inquired of the native.
“That’s about the way,” said the man.
“It’s mighty hard to do what your
neighbors ain’t doin’,”
pursued the Virginian.
“Montana is all cattle,
an’ these folks must be cattle,
an’ never notice the country right hyeh
is too small for a range,
an’ swampy, anyway, an’ just waitin’ to
be a frawg ranch.
”
At this, all wore a face
of careful reserve.
“I’m not claimin’ to be smarter than you
folks hyeh,” said the Virginian,
deprecatingly, to his assistant.
“But travellin’ learns a man many customs.
You wouldn’t do the business they done at
Tulare, California, north
side o’ the lake.
They cert’nly utilized
them hopeless swamps splendid.
Of course they put up big capital and
went into it scientific,
gettin’ advice from the government Fish
Commission, an’ suchlike knowledge.
Yu’ see, they had big markets for their
frawgs⁠—San Francisco,
Los Angeles, and clear to New York afteh
the Southern Pacific was through.
But up hyeh yu’ could sell to passengers
every day like yu’ done this one day.
They would get to know yu’ along the line.
Competing swamps are scarce.
The dining-cyars would take your frawgs,
and yu’ would have the Yellowstone Park
for four months in the year.
Them hotels are anxious to please,
an’ they would buy off yu’ what their
Eastern patrons esteem as fine-eatin’.
And you folks would be sellin’
something instead o’ nothin’.”
“That’s a practical idea,”
said a traveller.
“And little cost.”
“And little cost,” said the Virginian.
“Would Eastern people eat frogs?”
inquired the man.
“Look at us!”
said the traveller.
“Delmonico doesn’t give yu’ such a treat!”
said the Virginian.
“Not exactly!”
the traveller exclaimed.
“How much would be paid for frogs?”
said Trampas to him.
And I saw Scipio bend
closer to his cooking.
“Oh, I don’t know,” said the traveller.
“We’ve paid pretty well, you see.”
“You’re late for Tulare,
Trampas,” said the Virginian.
“I was not thinking of
Tulare,” Trampas retorted.
Scipio’s nose was in the frying-pan.
“Mos’ comical spot you ever struck!”
said the Virginian, looking round
upon the whole company.
He allowed himself a broad
smile of retrospect.
“To hear ’em talk frawgs at Tulare!
Same as other folks talks hawsses or
steers or whatever they’re
raising to sell.
Yu’d fall into it yourselves if
yu’ started the business.
Anything a man’s bread and butter depends
on, he’s going to be earnest about.
Don’t care if it is a frawg.”
“That’s so,” said the native.
“And it paid good?”
“The only money in the county was right
there,” answered the Virginian.
“It was a dead county,
and only frawgs was movin’.
But that business was a-fannin’ to beat
four of a kind.
It made yu’ feel strange at
first, as I said.
For all the men had been cattlemen at
one time or another.
Till yu’ got accustomed,
it would give ’most anybody a shock to
hear ’em speak about herdin’ the bulls
in a pasture by themselves.”
The Virginian allowed himself another
smile, but became serious again.
“That was their policy,” he explained.
“Except at certain times o’ year they
kept the bulls separate.
The Fish Commission told ’em they’d
better, and it cert’nly
worked mighty well.
It or something did⁠—for, gentlemen, hush!
but there was millions.
You’d have said all the frawgs in the
world had taken charge at Tulare.
And the money rolled in!
Gentlemen, hush!
’twas a gold mine for the owners.
Forty percent they netted some years.
And they paid generous wages.
For they could sell to all them French
restaurants in San Francisco, yu’ see.
And there was the Cliff House.
And the Palace Hotel made it a specialty.
And the officers took frawgs at the
Presidio, an’ Angel Island,
an’ Alcatraz, an’ Benicia.
Los Angeles was beginnin’ its boom.
The corner-lot sharps wanted something
by way of varnish.
An’ so they dazzled Eastern investors
with advertisin’ Tulare frawgs clear to
New Orleans an’ New York.
’Twas only in Sacramento frawgs was dull.
I expaict the California legislature was
too or’n’ry for them
fine-raised luxuries.
They tell of one of them senators that he
raked a million out of Los Angeles real
estate, and started in for a bang-
up meal with champagne.
Wanted to scatter his new
gold thick an’ quick.
But he got astray among all the fancy
dishes, an’ just yelled right out before
the ladies, ‘Damn it!
bring me forty dollars’ worth
of ham and aiggs.’
He was a funny senator, now.”
The Virginian paused,
and finished eating a leg.
And then with diabolic art he made a
feint at wandering to
new fields of anecdote.
“Talkin’ of senators,”
he resumed, “Senator Wise⁠—”
“How much did you say
wages were at Tulare?”
inquired one of the Trampas faction.
“How much?
Why, I never knew what the foreman got.
The regular hands got a hundred.
Senator Wise⁠—”
“A hundred a month?”
“Why, it was wet an’ muddy work, yu’ see.
A man risked rheumatism some.
He risked it a good deal.
Well, I was going to tell
about Senator Wise.
When Senator Wise was speaking of
his visit to Alaska⁠—”
“Forty percent, was it?”
said Trampas.
“Oh, I must call my wife,”
said the traveller behind me.
“This is what I came West for.”
And he hurried away.
“Not forty percent the bad years
,” replied the Virginian.
“The frawgs had enemies, same as cattle.
I remember when a pelican got in the
spring pasture, and the herd
broke through the fence⁠—”
“Fence?”
said a passenger.
“Ditch, seh, and wire net.
Every pasture was a square swamp with a
ditch around, and a wire net.
Yu’ve heard the mournful,
mixed-up sound a big bunch
of cattle will make?
Well, seh, as yu’ druv from the railroad
to the Tulare frawg ranch yu’ could
hear ’em a mile.
Springtime they’d sing like girls in the
organ loft, and by August they were
about ready to hire out for bass.
And all was fit to be soloists,
if I’m a judge.
But in a bad year it might
only be twenty percent.
The pelican rushed ’em from the pasture
right into the San Joaquin River,
which was close by the property.
The big balance of the herd stampeded,
and though of course they came out on
the banks again, the news had went
around, and folks below at Hemlen eat
most of ’em just to spite the company.
Yu’ see, a frawg in a river is more
hopeless than any maverick
loose on the range.
And they never struck any plan to brand
their stock and prove ownership.
”
“Well, twenty percent is good enough for
me,” said Trampas, “if
Rawhide don’t suit me.”
“A hundred a month!”
said the enthusiast.
And busy calculations began
to arise among them.
“It went to fifty percent,”
pursued the Virginian,
“when New York and Philadelphia got to
biddin’ agaynst each other.
Both cities had signs all over ’em
claiming to furnish the Tulare frawg.
And both had ’em all right.
And same as cattle trains,
yu’d see frawg trains tearing acrosst
Arizona⁠—big glass tanks with wire over
’em⁠—through to New York,
an’ the frawgs starin’ out.”
“Why, George,” whispered a woman’s voice
behind me, “he’s merely deceiving them!
He’s merely making that stuff up
out of his head.”
“Yes, my dear, that’s
merely what he’s doing.”
“Well, I don’t see why you imagined I
should care for this.
I think I’ll go back.”
“Better see it out, Daisy.
This beats the geysers or anything we’re
likely to find in the Yellowstone.”
“Then I wish we had gone to Bar Harbor as
usual,” said the lady,
and she returned to her Pullman.
But her husband stayed.
Indeed, the male crowd now was a goodly
sight to see, how the men edged close,
drawn by a common tie.
Their different kinds of feet told the
strength of the bond⁠—yellow sleeping-
car slippers planted miscellaneous and
motionless near a pair of Mexican spurs.
All eyes watched the Virginian and gave
him their entire sympathy.
Though they could not know his motive for
it, what he was doing had fallen as
light upon them⁠—all
except the excited calculators.
These were loudly making their fortunes
at both Rawhide and Tulare,
drugged by their satanically aroused
hopes of gold, heedless of the
slippers and the spurs.
Had a man given any sign to warn them,
I think he would have been lynched.
Even the Indian chiefs had come to see in
their show war bonnets and blankets.
They naturally understood nothing of it,
yet magnetically knew that the Virginian
was the great man.
And they watched him with approval.
He sat by the fire with the frying-pan,
looking his daily self⁠—
engaging and saturnine.
And now as Trampas declared tickets to
California would be dear and Rawhide had
better come first, the Southerner let
loose his heaven-born imagination.
“There’s a better reason for Rawhide than
tickets, Trampas,” said he.
“I said it was too late for Tulare.”
“I heard you,” said Trampas.
“Opinions may differ.
You and I don’t think
alike on several points.”
“Gawd, Trampas!”
said the Virginian, “d’ yu’ reckon I’d be
rotting hyeh on forty dollars if Tulare
was like it used to be?
Tulare is broke.”
“What broke it?
Your leaving?”
“Revenge broke it, and disease,”
said the Virginian, striking the frying-
pan on his knee, for the
frogs were all gone.
At those lurid words their untamed child
minds took fire, and they drew round him
again to hear a tale of blood.
The crowd seemed to lean nearer.
But for a short moment it
threatened to be spoiled.
A passenger came along,
demanding in an important voice,
“Where are these frogs?”
He was a prominent New York after-dinner
speaker, they whispered me,
and out for a holiday in his private
car.
Reaching us and walking to the Virginian,
he said cheerily, “How much do you want
for your frogs, my friend?”
“You got a friend hyeh?”
said the Virginian.
“That’s good, for yu’ need
care taken of yu’.”
And the prominent after-dinner speaker
did not further discommode us.
“That’s worth my trip,”
whispered a New York passenger to me.
“Yes, it was a case of revenge,”
resumed the Virginian, “and disease.
There was a man named Saynt Augustine got
run out of Domingo, which
is a Dago island.
He come to Philadelphia,
an’ he was dead broke.
But Saynt Augustine was a live man,
an’ he saw Philadelphia was full o’
Quakers that dressed
plain an’ eat humdrum.
So he started cookin’ Domingo way for
’em, an’ they caught right ahold.
Terrapin, he gave ’em,
an’ croakeets, an’ he’d use forty
chickens to make a broth
he called consommay.
An’ he got rich, and Philadelphia got
well known, an’ Delmonico in New
York he got jealous.
He was the cook that had the say-
so in New York.
”
“Was Delmonico one of them I-talians?”
inquired a fascinated mutineer.
“I don’t know.
But he acted like one.
Lorenzo was his front name.
He aimed to cut⁠—”
“Domingo’s throat?”
breathed the enthusiast.
“Aimed to cut away the trade from Saynt
Augustine an’ put Philadelphia back
where he thought she belonged.
Frawgs was the fashionable rage then.
These foreign cooks set the fashion in
eatin’, same as foreign
dressmakers do women’s clothes.
Both cities was catchin’ and swallowin’
all the frawgs Tulare could throw at
’em.
So he⁠—”
“Lorenzo?”
said the enthusiast.
“Yes, Lorenzo Delmonico.
He bid a dollar a tank higher.
An’ Saynt Augustine raised
him fifty cents.
An’ Lorenzo raised him a dollar.
An’ Saynt Augustine shoved her up three.
Lorenzo he didn’t expect Philadelphia
would go that high, and he got hot in
the collar, an’ flew round his kitchen
in New York, an’ claimed he’d twist
Saynt Augustine’s Domingo tail for him
and crack his ossified system.
Lorenzo raised his language to a
high temperature, they say.
An’ then quite sudden off
he starts for Tulare.
He buys tickets over the Santa Fe,
and he goes a-fannin’ and a-foggin’.
But, gentlemen, hush!
The very same day Saynt Augustine he
tears out of Philadelphia.
He travelled by the way o’ Washington,
an’ out he comes a-fannin’ an’ a-foggin’
over the Southern Pacific.
Of course Tulare didn’t
know nothin’ of this.
All it knowed was how the frawg market
was on soarin’ wings,
and it was feelin’ like
a flight o’ rawckets.
If only there’d been some preparation⁠—a
telegram or something⁠—the disaster
would never have occurred.
But Lorenzo and Saynt Augustine was that
absorbed watchin’ each other⁠—for,
yu’ see, the Santa Fe and the Southern
Pacific come together at Mojave,
an’ the two cooks travelled a matter of
two hundred an’ ten miles in the same
cyar⁠—they never thought
about a telegram.
And when they arruv, breathless,
an’ started in to screechin’ what they’d
give for the monopoly,
why, them unsuspectin’ Tulare boys
got amused at ’em.
I never heard just all they done,
but they had Lorenzo singin’ and
dancin’, while Saynt Augustine played
the fiddle for him.
And one of Lorenzo’s heels did
get a trifle grazed.
Well, them two cooks quit that ranch
without disclosin’ their identity,
and soon as they got to a safe distance
they swore eternal friendship,
in their excitable foreign way.
And they went home over the Union
Pacific, sharing the same stateroom.
Their revenge killed frawgs.
The disease⁠—”
“How killed frogs?”
demanded Trampas.
“Just killed ’em.
Delmonico and Saynt Augustine wiped
frawgs off the slate of fashion.
Not a banker in Fifth Avenue’ll touch one
now if another banker’s
around watchin’ him.
And if ever yu’ see a man that hides his
feet an’ won’t take off his socks in
company, he has worked in them Tulare
swamps an’ got the disease.
Catch him wadin’, and yu’ll
find he’s web-footed.
Frawgs are dead, Trampas, and so are you.
”
“Rise up, liars, and salute your king!”
yelled Scipio.
“Oh, I’m in love with you!”
And he threw his arms round the Virginian.
“Let me shake hands with you,”
said the traveller, who had failed to
interest his wife in these things.
“I wish I was going to have
more of your company.”
“Thank yu’, seh,” said the Virginian.
Other passengers greeted him,
and the Indian chiefs
came, saying, “How!”
because they followed
their feelings without understanding.
“Don’t show so humbled,
boys,” said the deputy foreman to
his most sheepish crew.
“These gentlemen from the East have been
enjoying yu’ some, I know.
But think what a weary wait
they have had hyeh.
And you insisted on playing the game with
me this way, yu’ see.
What outlet did yu’ give me?
Didn’t I have it to do?
And I’ll tell yu’ one thing for your
consolation: when I got to the middle of
the frawgs I ’most believed it myself.”
And he laughed out the first laugh I
had heard him give.
The enthusiast came up and shook hands.
That led off, and the rest followed,
with Trampas at the end.
The tide was too strong for him.
He was not a graceful loser;
but he got through this,
and the Virginian eased him down by
treating him precisely
like the others⁠—apparently.
Possibly the supreme⁠—the most American⁠—
moment of all was when word came that the
bridge was open, and the Pullman trains,
with noise and triumph,
began to move westward at last.
Everyone waved farewell to everyone,
craning from steps and windows,
so that the cars twinkled with hilarity;
and in twenty minutes the whole
procession in front had moved,
and our turn came.
“Last chance for Rawhide,”
said the Virginian.
“Last chance for Sunk Creek,”
said a reconstructed mutineer,
and all sprang aboard.
There was no question who had
won his spurs now.
Our caboose trundled on to Billings along
the shingly cotton-wooded Yellowstone;
and as the plains and bluffs and the
distant snow began to grow well known,
even to me, we turned to our baggage
that was to come off,
since camp would begin in the morning.
Thus I saw the Virginian carefully
rewrapping Kenilworth,
that he might bring it to its owner
unharmed; and I said,
“Don’t you think you could have played
poker with Queen Elizabeth?”
“No; I expaict she’d have
beat me,” he replied.
“She was a lady.”
It was at Billings, on this day,
that I made those reflections
about equality.
For the Virginian had been equal to the
occasion: that is the only kind of
equality which I recognize.
CHAPTER XVII
Scipio Moralizes
Into what mood was it that
the Virginian now fell?
Being less busy, did he begin to “grieve”
about the girl on Bear Creek?
I only know that after talking so
lengthily he fell into
a nine days’ silence.
The talking part of him
deeply and unbrokenly slept.
Official words of course came from him as
we rode southward from the railroad,
gathering the Judge’s stray cattle.
During the many weeks since the spring
roundup, some of these animals had as
usual got very far off their range,
and getting them on again became the
present business of our party.
Directions and commands⁠—whatever
communications to his subordinates were
needful to the forwarding of
this⁠—he duly gave.
But routine has never at any time of the
world passed for conversation.
His utterances, such as,
“We’ll work Willo’ Creek tomorro’
mawnin’,” or, “I want the wagon to be at
the fawks o’ Stinkin’ Water by
Thursday,” though on some occasions
numerous enough to sound like discourse,
never once broke the man’s true silence.
Seeming to keep easy company with the
camp, he yet kept altogether to himself.
That talking part of him⁠—the mood which
brings out for you your friend’s spirit
and mind as a free gift or as an
exchange⁠—was down in some dark cave of
his nature, hidden away.
Perhaps it had been dreaming;
perhaps completely reposing.
The Virginian was one of those rare ones
who are able to refresh
themselves in sections.
To have a thing on his mind did not keep
his body from resting.
During our recent journey⁠—it felt years
ago now!⁠—while our caboose on the
freight train had trundled endlessly
westward, and the men were on the ragged
edge, the very jumping-off place,
of mutiny and possible murder,
I had seen him sleep like a child.
He snatched the moments
not necessary for vigil.
I had also seen him sit all night
watching his responsibility,
ready to spring on it and fasten
his teeth in it.
And now that he had confounded them with
their own attempted weapon of ridicule,
his powers seemed to
be profoundly dormant.
That final pitched battle of wits had
made the men his captives and
admirers⁠—all save Trampas.
And of him the Virginian did not
seem to be aware.
But Scipio le Moyne would say to me now
and then, “If I was Trampas,
I’d pull my freight.”
And once he added, “Pull it kind of
casual, yu’ know, like I wasn’t
noticing myself do it.
”
“Yes,” our friend Shorty murmured
pregnantly, with his eye upon the quiet
Virginian, “he’s sure
studying his revenge.”
“Studying your pussycat,” said Scipio.
“He knows what he’ll do.
The time ain’t arrived.”
This was the way they felt about it;
and not unnaturally this was the way
they made me, the inexperienced
Easterner, feel about it.
That Trampas also felt something about it
was easy to know.
Like the leaven which leavens the whole
lump, one spot of sulkiness in camp will
spread its dull flavor through any
company that sits near it;
and we had to sit near Trampas at
meals for nine days.
His sullenness was not wonderful.
To feel himself forsaken by his recent
adherents, to see them gone over to his
enemy, could not have
made his reflections pleasant.
Why he did not take himself off to other
climes⁠—“pull his freight casual,”
as Scipio said⁠—I can explain only thus:
pay was due him⁠—“time,”
as it was called in cow-land;
if he would have this money,
he must stay under the Virginian’s
command until the Judge’s ranch on Sunk
Creek should be reached;
meanwhile, each day’s work added to the
wages in store for him;
and finally, once at Sunk Creek,
it would be no more the Virginian who
commanded him; it would be
the real ranch foreman.
At the ranch he would be the Virginian’s
equal again, both of them taking orders
from their officially
recognized superior, this foreman.
Shorty’s word about “revenge” seemed to
me like putting the thing backwards.
Revenge, as I told Scipio,
was what I should be thinking about
if I were Trampas.
“He dassent,” was Scipio’s immediate view.
“Not till he’s got strong again.
He got laughed plumb sick by the
bystanders, and whatever spirit he had
was broke in the presence of us all.
He’ll have to recuperate.”
Scipio then spoke of the
Virginian’s attitude.
“Maybe revenge ain’t just the right word
for where this affair has got
to now with him.
When yu’ beat another man at his own game
like he done to Trampas,
why, yu’ve had all the revenge yu’ can
want, unless you’re a hog.
And he’s no hog.
But he has got it in for Trampas.
They’ve not reckoned to a finish.
Would you let a man try such spite-work
on you and quit thinkin’ about him just
because yu’d headed him off?”
To this I offered his own notion about
hogs and being satisfied.
“Hogs!”
went on Scipio, in a way that dashed my
suggestion to pieces;
“hogs ain’t in the case.
He’s got to deal with Trampas
somehow⁠—man to man.
Trampas and him can’t stay this way when
they get back and go workin’ same
as they worked before.
No, sir; I’ve seen his eye twice,
and I know he’s goin’ to
reckon to a finish.
”
I still must, in Scipio’s opinion,
have been slow to understand,
when on the afternoon following this
talk I invited him to tell me what sort
of “finish” he wanted,
after such a finishing as had
been dealt Trampas already.
Getting “laughed plumb sick by the
bystanders” (I borrowed his own not
overstated expression) seemed to me
a highly final finishing.
While I was running my notions off to
him, Scipio rose, and,
with the frying-pan he had been washing,
walked slowly at me.
“I do believe you’d oughtn’t to be let
travel alone the way you do.”
He put his face close to mine.
His long nose grew eloquent in its
shrewdness, while the fire in his
bleached blue eye burned
with amiable satire.
“What has come and gone between them two
has only settled the one point he
was aimin’ to make.
He was appointed boss of this outfit in
the absence of the regular foreman.
Since then all he has been playin’ for is
to hand back his men to the ranch in as
good shape as they’d been handed to him,
and without losing any on the road
through desertion or shooting or
whatnot.
He had to kick his cook off the train
that day, and the loss made him
sorrowful, I could see.
But I’d happened to come along,
and he jumped me into the vacancy,
and I expect he is pretty near consoled.
And as boss of the outfit he beat
Trampas, who was settin’
up for opposition boss.
And the outfit is better than satisfied
it come out that way,
and they’re stayin’ with him;
and he’ll hand them all back in good
condition, barrin’ that lost cook.
So for the present his point
is made, yu’ see.
But look ahead a little.
It may not be so very far ahead
yu’ll have to look.
We get back to the ranch.
He’s not boss there any more.
His responsibility is over.
He is just one of us again,
taking orders from a foreman they tell
me has showed partiality to Trampas
more’n a few times.
Partiality!
That’s what Trampas is
plainly trusting to.
Trusting it will fix him all right and
fix his enemy all wrong.
He’d not otherwise dare to keep
sour like he’s doing.
Partiality!
D’ yu’ think it’ll scare off the enemy?”
Scipio looked across a little creek to
where the Virginian was helping throw
the gathered cattle on the bedground.
“What odds”⁠—he pointed the frying-pan at
the Southerner⁠—“d’ yu’ figure Trampas’s
being under any foreman’s wing will make
to a man like him?
He’s going to remember Mr. Trampas and
his spite-work if he’s got to tear him
out from under the wing,
and maybe tear off the
wing in the operation.
And I am goin’ to advise your folks,”
ended the complete Scipio,
“not to leave you travel so much alone⁠—
not till you’ve learned more life
.
”
He had made me feel my inexperience,
convinced me of innocence,
undoubtedly; and during the final days
of our journey I no longer invoked his
aid to my reflections upon this especial
topic: What would the
Virginian do to Trampas?
Would it be another intellectual crushing
of him, like the frog story,
or would there be something this time
more material⁠—say muscle,
or possibly gunpowder⁠—in it?
And was Scipio, after all, infallible?
I didn’t pretend to understand the
Virginian; after several years’
knowledge of him he remained
utterly beyond me.
Scipio’s experience was not
yet three weeks long.
So I let him alone as to all this,
discussing with him most other things
good and evil in the world,
and being convinced of much further
innocence; for Scipio’s twenty odd years
were indeed a library of life.
I have never met a better heart,
a shrewder wit, and looser morals,
with yet a native sense of decency and
duty somewhere hard and fast enshrined.
But all the while I was wondering about
the Virginian: eating with him,
sleeping with him (only not so sound as
he did), and riding beside him
often for many hours.
Experiments in conversation I
did make⁠—and failed.
One day particularly while,
after a sudden storm of hail had chilled
the earth numb and white like winter in
fifteen minutes, we sat drying and
warming ourselves by a fire that we
built, I touched upon that theme of
equality on which I knew him to hold
opinions as strong as mine.
“Oh,” he would reply,
and “Cert’nly”; and when I asked him
what it was in a man that made him a
leader of men, he shook his head
and puffed his pipe.
So then, noticing how the sun had brought
the earth in half an hour back from
winter to summer again,
I spoke of our American climate.
It was a potent drug,
I said, for millions to
be swallowing every day.
“Yes,” said he, wiping the damp
from his Winchester rifle.
Our American climate,
I said, had worked remarkable
changes, at least.
“Yes,” he said; and did not
ask what they were.
So I had to tell him.
“It has made successful
politicians of the Irish.
That’s one.
And it has given our whole race
the habit of poker.”
Bang went his Winchester.
The bullet struck close to my left.
I sat up angrily.
“That’s the first foolish thing I
ever saw you do!”
I said.
“Yes,” he drawled slowly,
“I’d ought to have done it sooner.
He was pretty near lively again.”
And then he picked up a rattlesnake
six feet behind me.
It had been numbed by the hail,
part revived by the sun,
and he had shot its head off.
CHAPTER XVIII
“Would You Be a Parson?”
After this I gave up my
experiments in conversation.
So that by the final afternoon of our
journey, with Sunk Creek actually in
sight, and the great grasshoppers
slatting their dry song over the
sagebrush, and the time at hand when the
Virginian and Trampas would be “man to
man,” my thoughts rose to a
considerable pitch of speculation.
And now that talking part of the
Virginian, which had been nine days
asleep, gave its first yawn
and stretch of waking.
Without preface, he suddenly asked me,
“Would you be a parson?”
I was mentally so far away that I
couldn’t get back in time to comprehend
or answer before he had repeated:⁠—
“What would yu’ take to be a parson?”
He drawled it out in his gentle way,
precisely as if no nine days stood
between it and our last real
intercourse.
“Take?”
I was still vaguely moving in my distance.
“How?”
His next question brought me home.
“I expect the Pope’s is the biggest
of them parson jobs?”
It was with an “Oh!”
that I now entirely took his idea.
“Well, yes; decidedly the biggest.”
“Beats the English one?
Archbishop⁠—ain’t it?⁠—of Canterbury?
The Pope comes ahead of him?”
“His Holiness would say so if
his Grace did not.”
The Virginian turned half in his saddle
to see my face⁠—I was,
at the moment, riding not quite abreast
of him⁠—and I saw the gleam of his
teeth beneath his mustache.
It was seldom I could make him smile,
even to this slight extent.
But his eyes grew, with his next words,
remote again in their speculation.
“His Holiness and his Grace.
Now if I was to hear ’em namin’ me that-
a-way every mawnin’, I’d sca’cely
get down to business.
”
“Oh, you’d get used to the pride of it.”
“ ’Tisn’t the pride.
The laugh is what would ruin me.
’Twould take ’most all my attention
keeping a straight face.
The Archbishop”⁠—here he took one of his
wide mental turns⁠—“is apt to be a big
man in them Shakespeare plays.
Kings take talk from him they’d not stand
from anybody else; and
he talks fine, frequently.
About the bees, for instance,
when Henry is going to fight France.
He tells him a beehive is
similar to a kingdom.
I learned that piece.”
The Virginian could not have expected to
blush at uttering these last words.
He knew that his sudden color must tell
me in whose book it was he
had learned the piece.
Was not her copy of Kenilworth even now
in his cherishing pocket?
So he now, to cover his blush,
very deliberately recited to me the
Archbishop’s discourse upon
bees and their kingdom:⁠—
“ ‘Where some, like magistrates,
correct at home.
⋮Others, like soldiers,
armèd in their stings,
Make loot upon the summer’s velvet buds;
Which pillage they with merry march bring
homeTo the tent-royal of their
emperor:He, busied in his majesty,
surveysThe singing masons
building roofs of gold.’
“Ain’t that a fine description
of bees a-workin’?
‘The singing masons building
roofs of gold!’
Puts ’em right before yu’, and is
poetry without bein’ foolish.
His Holiness and his Grace.
Well, they could not hire me for
either o’ those positions.
How many religions are there?
”
“All over the earth?”
“Yu’ can begin with ourselves.
Right hyeh at home I know
there’s Romanists, and Episcopals⁠—”
“Two kinds!”
I put in.
“At least two of Episcopals.”
“That’s three.
Then Methodists and Baptists, and⁠—”
“Three Methodists!”
“Well, you do the countin’.”
I accordingly did it,
feeling my revolving memory slip cogs
all the way round.
“Anyhow, there are safely fifteen.”
“Fifteen.”
He held this fact a moment.
“And they don’t worship a whole heap o’
different gods like the ancients did?”
“Oh, no!”
“It’s just the same one?”
“The same one.”
The Virginian folded his hands over the
horn of his saddle, and leaned forward
upon them in contemplation of
the wide, beautiful landscape.
“One God and fifteen religions
,” was his reflection.
“That’s a right smart of religions
for just one God.”
This way of reducing it was,
if obvious to him, so novel to me that
my laugh evidently struck him as a
louder and livelier comment
than was required.
He turned on me as if I had somehow
perverted the spirit of his words.
“I ain’t religious.
I know that.
But I ain’t unreligious.
And I know that too.”
“So do I know it, my friend.”
“Do you think there ought to be fifteen
varieties of good people?”
His voice, while it now had an edge that
could cut anything it came against,
was still not raised.
“There ain’t fifteen.
There ain’t two.
There’s one kind.
And when I meet it, I respect it.
It is not praying nor preaching that has
ever caught me and made me ashamed of
myself, but one or two people I have
knowed that never said a
superior word to me.
They thought more o’ me than I deserved,
and that made me behave better than
I naturally wanted to.
Made me quit a girl onced in time for her
not to lose her good name.
And so that’s one thing I have never done.
And if ever I was to have a son or
somebody I set store by,
I would wish their lot to be to know one
or two good folks mighty well⁠—men
or women⁠—women preferred.
”
He had looked away again to the hills
behind Sunk Creek ranch,
to which our walking horses had
now almost brought us.
“As for parsons”⁠—the gesture of his arm
was a disclaiming one⁠—“I reckon some
parsons have a right to tell
yu’ to be good.
The bishop of this hyeh
Territory has a right.
But I’ll tell yu’ this:
a middlin’ doctor is a pore thing,
and a middlin’ lawyer is a pore thing;
but keep me from a middlin’ man of God.”
Once again he had reduced it,
but I did not laugh this time.
I thought there should in truth be heavy
damages for malpractice on human souls.
But the hot glow of his words,
and the vision of his deepest inner man
it revealed, faded away abruptly.
“What do yu’ make of the
proposition yondeh?”
As he pointed to the cause of this
question he had become again his
daily, engaging, saturnine self.
Then I saw over in a fenced meadow,
to which we were now close,
what he was pleased to
call “the proposition.”
Proposition in the West does,
in fact, mean whatever you at the moment
please⁠—an offer to sell you a mine,
a cloudburst, a glass
of whiskey, a steamboat.
This time it meant a stranger clad in
black, and of a clerical deportment
which would in that atmosphere and to a
watchful eye be visible for
a mile or two.
“I reckoned yu’ hadn’t noticed him,”
was the Virginian’s reply
to my ejaculation.
“Yes.
He set me goin’ on the
subject a while back.
I expect he is another missionary
to us pore cowboys.
”
I seemed from a hundred yards to feel
the stranger’s forceful personality.
It was in his walk⁠—I should better say
stalk⁠—as he promenaded along the creek.
His hands were behind his back,
and there was an air of waiting,
of displeased waiting, in his movement.
“Yes, he’ll be a missionary,”
said the Virginian, conclusively;
and he took to singing,
or rather to whining,
with his head tilted at an absurd angle
upward at the sky:⁠—
“ ‘Dar is a big Car’lina nigger,
About de size of dis chile or p’raps a
little bigger,By de name of Jim Crow.
Dat what de white folks call him.
If ever I sees him I ’tends for to maul
him,Just to let de white folks seeSuch
an animos as heCan’t walk around the
streets and scandalize me.’
”
The lane which was conducting us to the
group of ranch buildings now turned a
corner of the meadow,
and the Virginian went on
with his second verse:⁠—
“ ‘Great big fool, he
hasn’t any knowledge.
Gosh!
how could he, when he’s
never been to scollege?
Neither has I.But I’se come mighty nigh;
I peaked through de door as I went by.’
”
He was beginning a third stanza,
but stopped short; a horse had
neighed close behind us.
“Trampas,” said he, without turning his
head, “we are home.”
“It looks that way.”
Some ten yards were between ourselves and
Trampas, where he followed.
“And I’ll trouble yu’ for my rope yu’
took this mawnin’ instead o’ your own.”
“I don’t know as it’s your rope I’ve got.”
Trampas skilfully spoke this so that a
precisely opposite meaning
flowed from his words.
If it was discussion he
tried for, he failed.
The Virginian’s hand moved,
and for one thick, flashing moment my
thoughts were evidently also
the thoughts of Trampas.
But the Virginian only held out to
Trampas the rope which he had
detached from his saddle.
“Take your hand off your gun, Trampas.
If I had wanted to kill yu’ you’d be
lying nine days back on the road now.
Here’s your rope.
Did yu’ expect I’d not know it?
It’s the only one in camp the stiffness
ain’t all drug out of yet.
Or maybe yu’ expected me to notice
and⁠—not take notice?
”
“I don’t spend my time
in expectations about you.
If⁠—”
The Virginian wheeled his
horse across the road.
“Yu’re talkin’ too soon
after reachin’ safety, Trampas.
I didn’t tell yu’ to hand me that rope
this mawnin’, because I was busy.
I ain’t foreman now;
and I want that rope.”
Trampas produced a smile as
skilful as his voice.
“Well, I guess your having mine proves
this one is yours.”
He rode up and received the coil which
the Virginian held out,
unloosing the disputed one on his
saddle.
If he had meant to devise a slippery,
evasive insult, no small trick in cow-
land could be more offensive than this
taking another man’s rope.
And it is the small tricks which lead
to the big bullets.
Trampas put a smooth coating of
plausibility over the whole transaction.
“After the rope corral we had to make
this morning”⁠—his tone was mock
explanatory⁠—“the ropes was all strewed
round camp, and in the hustle I⁠—”
“Pardon me,” said a sonorous voice behind
us, “do you happen to
have seen Judge Henry?”
It was the reverend gentleman in his
meadow, come to the fence.
As we turned round to him he spoke on,
with much rotund authority in his eye.
“From his answer to my letter,
Judge Henry undoubtedly expects me here.
I have arrived from Fetterman according
to my plan which I announced to him,
to find that he has been absent all
day⁠—absent the whole day.”
The Virginian sat sidewise to talk,
one long, straight leg supporting him on
one stirrup, the other bent at ease,
the boot half lifted
from its dangling stirrup.
He made himself the perfection
of courtesy.
“The Judge is frequently
absent all night, seh.”
“Scarcely tonight, I think.
I thought you might know
something about him.”
“I have been absent myself, seh.”
“Ah!
On a vacation, perhaps?”
The divine had a ruddy facet.
His strong glance was straight and frank
and fearless; but his smile too much
reminded me of days bygone,
when we used to return to school from
the Christmas holidays,
and the masters would shake our hands
and welcome us with:
“Robert, John, Edward,
glad to see you all looking so well!
Rested, and ready for
hard work, I’m sure!”
That smile does not really please even
good, tame little boys;
and the Virginian was nearing thirty.
“It has not been vacation this trip,
seh,” said he, settling
straight in his saddle.
“There’s the Judge driving in now,
in time for all questions yu’
have to ask him.”
His horse took a step,
but was stopped short.
There lay the Virginian’s
rope on the ground.
I had been aware of Trampas’s quite
proper departure during the talk;
and as he was leaving,
I seemed also to be aware of his placing
the coil across the cantle
of its owner’s saddle.
Had he intended it to fall and have
to be picked up?
It was another evasive little business,
and quite successful,
if designed to nag the owner of the
rope.
A few hundred yards ahead of us Trampas
was now shouting loud cowboy shouts.
Were they to announce his return to those
at home, or did they mean derision?
The Virginian leaned,
keeping his seat, and,
swinging down his arm,
caught up the rope, and hung it on
his saddle somewhat carefully.
But the hue of rage spread over his face.
From his fence the divine now spoke,
in approbation, but with
another strong, cheerless smile.
“You pick up that rope as if you were
well trained to it.”
“It’s part of our business,
seh, and we try to mind
it like the rest.”
But this, stated in a gentle drawl,
did not pierce the missionary’s armor;
his superiority was very thick.
We now rode on, and I was impressed by
the reverend gentleman’s robust,
dictatorial back as he proceeded by a
shortcut through the meadow to the
ranch.
You could take him for nothing but a
vigorous, sincere, dominating man,
full of the highest purpose.
But whatever his creed,
I already doubted if he were the right
one to sow it and make it grow in
these new, wild fields.
He seemed more the sort of gardener to
keep old walks and vines pruned
in their antique rigidity.
I admired him for coming all this way
with his clean, short,
gray whiskers and his
black, well-brushed suit.
And he made me think of a powerful
locomotive stuck puffing on a grade.
Meanwhile, the Virginian rode beside me,
so silent in his volcanic wrath that I
did not perceive it.
The missionary coming on top of Trampas
had been more than he could stand.
But I did not know, and I
spoke with innocent cheeriness.
“Is the parson going to save us?”
I asked; and I fairly
jumped at his voice:⁠—
“Don’t talk so much!”
he burst out.
I had got the whole accumulation!
“Who’s been talking?”
I in equal anger screeched back.
“I’m not trying to save you.
I didn’t take your rope.”
And having poured this out,
I whipped up my pony.
But he spurred his own alongside of me;
and glancing at him,
I saw that he was now
convulsed with internal mirth.
I therefore drew down to a walk,
and he straightened into gravity.
“I’m right obliged to yu’,” he laid his
hand in its buckskin gauntlet upon my
horse’s mane as he spoke,
“for bringing me back out o’ my
nonsense.
I’ll be as serene as a bird
now⁠—whatever they do.
A man,” he stated reflectively,
“any full-sized man,
ought to own a big lot of temper.
And like all his valuable possessions,
he’d ought to keep it and not lose any.”
This was his full apology.
“As for salvation, I have got this far:
somebody,” he swept an arm at the sunset
and the mountains, “must have made
all that, I know.
But I know one more thing I would tell
Him to His face: if I can’t do nothing
long enough and good enough to earn
eternal happiness, I can’t do nothing
long enough and bad enough to be damned.
I reckon He plays a square game with us
if He plays at all, and I ain’t
bothering my haid about other worlds.
”
As we reached the stables,
he had become the serene bird he
promised, and was sentimentally
continuing:⁠—
“ ‘De sun is made of mud from de bottom
of de river;De moon is made o’ fox-fire,
as you might disciver;
De stars like de ladies’ eyes,
All round de world dey flies,
To give a little light when
de moon don’t rise.’
”
If words were meant to conceal our
thoughts, melody is perhaps a still
thicker veil for them.
Whatever temper he had lost,
he had certainly found again;
but this all the more fitted him to deal
with Trampas, when the
dealing should begin.
I had half a mind to speak to the Judge,
only it seemed beyond
a mere visitor’s business.
Our missionary was at this moment himself
speaking to Judge Henry at the door
of the home ranch.
“I reckon he’s explaining
he has been awaiting.”
The Virginian was throwing his saddle off
as I loosened the cinches of mine.
“And the Judge don’t look like
he was hopelessly distressed.”
I now surveyed the distant parley,
and the Judge, from the wagonful of
guests whom he had evidently been
driving upon a day’s excursion,
waved me a welcome, which I waved back.
“He’s got Miss Molly Wood there!”
I exclaimed.
“Yes.”
The Virginian was brief about this fact.
“I’ll look afteh your saddle.
You go and get acquainted
with the company.”
This favor I accepted;
it was the means he chose for saying he
hoped, after our recent boiling over,
that all was now more
than right between us.
So for the while I left him to his
horses, and his corrals,
and his Trampas, and his foreman,
and his imminent problem.
CHAPTER XIX
Dr.
Macbride Begs Pardon
Judge and Mrs. Henry,
Molly Wood, and two strangers,
a lady and a gentleman,
were the party which had been driving in
the large three-seated wagon.
They had seemed a merry party.
But as I came within hearing of their
talk, it was a fragment of the
minister’s sonority which
reached me first:⁠—
“… more opportunity for them to have the
benefit of hearing frequent sermons,”
was the sentence I heard
him bring to completion.
“Yes, to be sure, sir.”
Judge Henry gave me (it almost seemed)
additional warmth of welcome for
arriving to break up
the present discourse.
“Let me introduce you to the
Rev. Dr. Alexander MacBride.
Doctor, another guest we have been hoping
for about this time,”
was my host’s cordial explanation
to him of me.
There remained the gentleman with his
wife from New York, and to these I
made my final bows.
But I had not broken up the discourse.
“We may be said to have met already.”
Dr.
MacBride had fixed upon me his full,
mastering eye; and it occurred to me
that if they had policemen in heaven,
he would be at least a
centurion in the force.
But he did not mean to be unpleasant;
it was only that in a mind full of
matters less worldly,
pleasure was left out.
“I observed your friend was a
skilful horseman,” he continued.
“I was saying to Judge Henry that I could
wish such skilful horsemen might ride to
a church upon the Sabbath.
A church, that is, of right doctrine,
where they would have opportunity
to hear frequent sermons.”
“Yes,” said Judge Henry, “yes.
It would be a good thing.”
Mrs.
Henry, with some murmur about the
kitchen, here went into the house.
“I was informed,” Dr. MacBride held the
rest of us, “before undertaking my
journey that I should find a desolate
and mainly godless country.
But nobody gave me to understand that
from Medicine Bow I was to drive three
hundred miles and pass no
church of any faith.”
The Judge explained that there had been a
few a long way to the right
and left of him.
“Still,” he conceded,
“you are quite right.
But don’t forget that this is the newest
part of a new world.”
“Judge,” said his wife,
coming to the door, “how can you keep
them standing in the
dust with your talking?”
This most efficiently did
break up the discourse.
As our little party, with the smiles and
the polite holdings back of new
acquaintanceship, moved into the house,
the Judge detained me behind all of them
long enough to whisper dolorously,
“He’s going to stay a whole week.
”
I had hopes that he would not stay a
whole week when I presently learned of
the crowded arrangements which our
hosts, with many hospitable
apologies, disclosed to us.
They were delighted to have us,
but they hadn’t foreseen that we
should all be simultaneous.
The foreman’s house had been prepared for
two of us, and did we mind?
The two of us were Dr. MacBride and
myself; and I expected him to mind.
But I wronged him grossly.
It would be much better,
he assured Mrs. Henry,
than straw in a stable,
which he had tried several times,
and was quite ready for.
So I saw that though he kept his vigorous
body clean when he could,
he cared nothing for it in the
face of his mission.
How the foreman and his wife relished
being turned out during a week for a
missionary and myself was not my
concern, although while he and I made
ready for supper over there,
it struck me as hard on them.
The room with its two cots and furniture
was as nice as possible;
and we closed the door upon the
adjoining room, which,
however, seemed also untenanted.
Mrs.
Henry gave us a meal so good that I have
remembered it, and her husband the Judge
strove his best that we should
eat it in merriment.
He poured out his anecdotes like wine,
and we should have quickly warmed to
them; but Dr. MacBride sat among us,
giving occasional heavy ha-ha’s,
which produced, as Miss Molly Wood
whispered to me, a “dreadfully
cavernous effect.”
Was it his sermon, we wondered,
that he was thinking over?
I told her of the copious sheaf of them I
had seen him pull from his wallet
over at the foreman’s.
“Goodness!”
said she.
“Then are we to hear one every evening?”
This I doubted; he had probably been
picking one out suitable
for the occasion.
“Putting his best foot foremost,”
was her comment; “I suppose they have
best feet, like the rest of us.”
Then she grew delightfully sharp.
“Do you know, when I first heard him I
thought his voice was hearty.
But if you listen, you’ll
find it’s merely militant.
He never really meets you with it.
He’s off on his hill watching the
battlefield the whole time.
”
“He will find a hardened pagan here.”
“Judge Henry?”
“Oh, no!
The wild man you’re taming brought
you Kenilworth safe back.”
She was smooth.
“Oh, as for taming him!
But don’t you find him intelligent?”
Suddenly I somehow knew that she didn’t
want to tame him.
But what did she want to do?
The thought of her had made
him blush this afternoon.
No thought of him made
her blush this evening.
A great laugh from the rest of the
company made me aware that the Judge had
consummated his tale
of the “Sole Survivor.”
“And so,” he finished,
“they all went off as mad as hops
because it hadn’t been a massacre.”
Mr. and Mrs. Ogden⁠—they were the New
Yorkers⁠—gave this story much applause,
and Dr. MacBride half a minute later
laid his “ha-ha,” like a heavy
stone, upon the gaiety.
“I’ll never be able to stand seven
sermons,” said Miss Wood to me.
“Talking of massacres,”
⁠—I now hastened to address the already
saddened table⁠—“I have
recently escaped one myself.”
The Judge had come to an
end of his powers.
“Oh, tell us!”
he implored.
“Seriously, sir, I think we grazed pretty
wet tragedy but your extraordinary man
brought us out into comedy safe and
dry.”
This gave me their attention;
and, from that afternoon in Dakota when
I had first stepped aboard the caboose,
I told them the whole tale of my
experience: how I grew immediately aware
that all was not right,
by the Virginian’s kicking the cook off
the train; how, as we journeyed,
the dark bubble of mutiny swelled hourly
beneath my eyes; and how,
when it was threatening I know not what
explosion, the Virginian had pricked it
with humor, so that it burst in
nothing but harmless laughter.
Their eyes followed my narrative:
the New Yorkers, because such events do
not happen upon the shores of the
Hudson; Mrs. Henry, because she was my
hostess; Miss Wood followed for whatever
her reasons were⁠—I
couldn’t see her eyes;
rather, I felther listening intently to
the deeds and dangers of the man she
didn’t care to tame.
But it was the eyes of the Judge and the
missionary which I saw riveted upon me
indeed until the end;
and they forthwith made plain
their quite dissimilar opinions.
Judge Henry struck the table
lightly with his fist.
“I knew it!”
And he leaned back in his chair with
a face of contentment.
He had trusted his man,
and his man had proved worthy.
“Pardon me.”
Dr.
MacBride had a manner of saying “pardon
me,” which rendered forgiveness
well-nigh impossible.
The Judge waited for him.
“Am I to understand that these⁠—a⁠—
cowboys attempted to mutiny,
and were discouraged in this attempt
upon finding themselves less skilful at
lying than the man they
had plotted to depose?”
I began an answer.
“It was other qualities,
sir, that happened to be revealed and
asserted by what you
call his lying that⁠—”
“And what am I to call it,
if it is not lying?
A competition in deceit in which,
I admit, he out did them.
“It’s their way to⁠—”
“Pardon me.
Their way to lie?
They bow down to the greatest in this?”
“Oh,” said Miss Wood in my
ear, “give him up.”
The Judge took a turn.
“We-ell, Doctor⁠—” He
seemed to stick here.
Mr.
Ogden handsomely assisted him.
“You’ve said the word yourself, Doctor.
It’s the competition, don’t you see?
The trial of strength by
no matter what test.”
“Yes,” said Miss Wood, unexpectedly.
“And it wasn’t that George Washington
couldn’t tell a lie.
He just wouldn’t.
I’m sure if he’d undertaken to he’d have
told a much better one than Cornwall’s.”
“Ha-ha, madam!
You draw an ingenious
subtlety from your books.”
“It’s all plain to me,” Ogden pursued.
“The men were morose.
This foreman was in the minority.
He cajoled them into a bout of tall
stories, and told the tallest himself.
And when they found they had swallowed it
whole⁠—well, it would certainly take the
starch out of me,” he concluded.
“I couldn’t be a serious
mutineer after that.”
Dr.
MacBride now sounded his strongest bass.
“Pardon me.
I cannot accept such a view, sir.
There is a levity abroad in our land
which I must deplore.
No matter how leniently you may try to
put it, in the end we have the spectacle
of a struggle between men where lying
decides the survival of the fittest.
Better, far better, if it was to come,
that they had shot honest bullets.
There are worse evils than war.”
The Doctor’s eye glared
righteously about him.
None of us, I think, trembled;
or, if we did, it was with
emotions other than fear.
Mrs.
Henry at once introduced the subject of
trout-fishing, and thus happily removed
us from the edge of whatever sort of
precipice we seemed to have approached;
for Dr. MacBride had brought his rod.
He dilated upon this sport with fervor,
and we assured him that the streams upon
the west slope of the Bow Leg Mountains
would afford him plenty of it.
Thus we ended our meal
in carefully preserved amity.
CHAPTER XX
The Judge Ignores Particulars
“Do you often have these visitations?”
Ogden inquired of Judge Henry.
Our host was giving us whiskey in his
office, and Dr. MacBride,
while we smoked apart from the ladies,
had repaired to his quarters in the
foreman’s house previous to the service
which he was shortly to hold.
The Judge laughed.
“They come now and then through the year.
I like the bishop to come.
And the men always like it.
But I fear our friend will scarcely
please them so well.”
“You don’t mean they’ll⁠—”
“Oh, no.
They’ll keep quiet.
The fact is, they have a good deal better
manners than he has, if he only knew it.
They’ll be able to bear him.
But as for any good he’ll do⁠—”
“I doubt if he knows a word of science,”
said I, musing about the Doctor.
“Science!
He doesn’t know what Christianity is yet.
I’ve entertained many guests,
but none⁠—The whole secret,”
broke off Judge Henry,
“lies in the way you treat people.
As soon as you treat men as your
brothers, they are ready to acknowledge
you⁠—if you deserve it⁠—
as their superior.
That’s the whole bottom of Christianity,
and that’s what our missionary
will never know.
”
There was a somewhat heavy knock at the
office door, and I think we all feared
it was Dr. MacBride.
But when the Judge opened,
the Virginian was standing
there in the darkness.
“So!”
The Judge opened the door wide.
He was very hearty to the
man he had trusted.
“You’re back at last.”
“I came to repawt.”
While they shook hands, Ogden nudged me.
“That the fellow?”
I nodded.
“Fellow who kicked the
cook off the train?”
I again nodded, and he looked at the
Virginian, his eye and his stature.
Judge Henry, properly democratic,
now introduced him to Ogden.
The New Yorker also meant
to be properly democratic.
“You’re the man I’ve been hearing
such a lot about.
”
But familiarity is not equality.
“Then I expect yu’ have the advantage of
me, seh,” said the Virginian,
very politely.
“Shall I repawt tomorro’?”
His grave eyes were on the Judge again.
Of me he had taken no notice;
he had come as an employee
to see his employer.
“Yes, yes; I’ll want to hear
about the cattle tomorrow.
But step inside a moment now.
There’s a matter⁠—” The Virginian stepped
inside, and took off his hat.
“Sit down.
You had trouble⁠—I’ve heard something
about it,” the Judge went on.
The Virginian sat down,
grave and graceful.
But he held the brim of his
hat all the while.
He looked at Ogden and me,
and then back at his employer.
There was reluctance in his eye.
I wondered if his employer could be going
to make him tell his own exploits in the
presence of us outsiders;
and there came into my memory the Bengal
tiger at a trained-animal show
I had once seen.
“You had some trouble,”
repeated the Judge.
“Well, there was a time when they maybe
wanted to have notions.
They’re good boys.”
And he smiled a very little.
Contentment increased in the Judge’s face.
“Trampas a good boy too?
”
But this time the Bengal
tiger did not smile.
He sat with his eye fastened
on his employer.
The Judge passed rather quickly on
to his next point.
“You’ve brought them all back,
though, I understand,
safe and sound, without a scratch?”
The Virginian looked down at his hat,
then up again at the Judge, mildly.
“I had to part with my cook.”
There was no use; Ogden
and myself exploded.
Even upon the embarrassed Virginian a
large grin slowly forced itself.
“I guess yu’ know about it,” he murmured.
And he looked at me with
a sort of reproach.
He knew it was I who had told
tales out of school.
“I only want to say,”
said Ogden, conciliatingly,
“that I know I couldn’t
have handled those men.”
The Virginian relented.
“Yu’ never tried, seh.”
The Judge had remained serious;
but he showed himself plainly
more and more contented.
“Quite right,” he said.
“You had to part with your cook.
When I put a man in charge,
I put him in charge.
I don’t make particulars my business.
They’re to be always his.
Do you understand?
”
“Thank yu’.”
The Virginian understood that his
employer was praising his
management of the expedition.
But I don’t think he at all discerned⁠—as
I did presently⁠—that his employer had
just been putting him to a further test,
had laid before him the temptation of
complaining of a fellow-workman and
blowing his own trumpet,
and was delighted with his reticence.
He made a movement to rise.
“I haven’t finished,” said the Judge.
“I was coming to the matter.
There’s one particular⁠—since I do happen
to have been told.
I fancy Trampas has learned
something he didn’t expect.”
This time the Virginian evidently did not
understand, any more than I did.
One hand played with his hat,
mechanically turning it round.
The Judge explained.
“I mean about Roberts.”
A pulse of triumph shot over the
Southerner’s face, turning it savage
for that fleeting instant.
He understood now, and was unable to
suppress this much answer.
But he was silent.
“You see,” the Judge explained to me,
“I was obliged to let Roberts,
my old foreman, go last week.
His wife could not have stood another
winter here, and a good position was
offered to him near Los Angeles.”
I did see.
I saw a number of things.
I saw why the foreman’s house had been
empty to receive Dr. MacBride and me.
And I saw that the Judge had
been very clever indeed.
For I had abstained from telling any
tales about the present feeling between
Trampas and the Virginian;
but he had divined it.
Well enough for him to say that
“particulars” were something he let
alone
; he evidently kept a deep eye on the
undercurrents at his ranch.
He knew that in Roberts,
Trampas had lost a powerful friend.
And this was what I most saw,
this final fact, that Trampas had no
longer any intervening shield.
He and the Virginian stood
indeed man to man.
“And so,” the Judge continued speaking to
me, “here I am at a very inconvenient
time without a foreman.
Unless,” I caught the twinkle in his eyes
before he turned to the Virginian,
“unless you’re willing to
take the position yourself.
Will you?”
I saw the Southerner’s hand grip his hat
as he was turning it round.
He held it still now,
and his other hand found it and
gradually crumpled the soft crown in.
It meant everything to him:
recognition, higher station,
better fortune, a separate house of his
own, and⁠—perhaps⁠—one step nearer to
the woman he wanted.
I don’t know what words he might have
said to the Judge had they been alone,
but the Judge had chosen to do it in our
presence, the whole thing
from beginning to end.
The Virginian sat with the damp coming
out on his forehead,
and his eyes dropped from his
employer’s.
“Thank yu’,” was what he managed
at last to say.
“Well, now, I’m greatly relieved!”
exclaimed the Judge, rising at once.
He spoke with haste, and lightly.
“That’s excellent.
I was in some thing of a hole,”
he said to Ogden and me;
“and this gives me one thing
less to think of.
Saves me a lot of particulars,”
he jocosely added to the Virginian,
who was now also standing up.
“Begin right off.
Leave the bunk house.
The gentlemen won’t mind your sleeping
in your own house.”
Thus he dismissed his new foreman gayly.
But the new foreman, when he got outside,
turned back for one gruff word⁠—“I’ll
try to please yu’.”
That was all.
He was gone in the darkness.
But there was light enough for me,
looking after him, to see him lay his
hand on a shoulder-high gate and vault
it as if he had been the wind.
Sounds of cheering came to us a few
moments later from the bunk house.
Evidently he had “begun right away,”
as the Judge had directed.
He had told his fortune to his brother
cowpunchers, and this was their answer.
“I wonder if Trampas is shouting too?”
inquired Ogden.
“Hm!”
said the Judge.
“That is one of the particulars I
wash my hands of.
”
I knew that he entirely meant it.
I knew, once his decision taken of
appointing the Virginian his lieutenant
for good and all, that,
like a wise commander-in-chief,
he would trust his lieutenant to take
care of his own business.
“Well,” Ogden pursued with interest,
“haven’t you landed Trampas
plump at his mercy?”
The phrase tickled the Judge.
“That is where I’ve landed him!”
he declared.
“And here is Dr. MacBride.”
CHAPTER XXI
In a State of Sin
Thunder sat imminent upon
the missionary’s brow.
Many were to be at his mercy soon.
But for us he had sunshine still.
“I am truly sorry to be turning you
upside down,” he said importantly.
“But it seems the best
place for my service.”
He spoke of the tables pushed back and
the chairs gathered in the hall,
where the storm would presently
break upon the congregation.
“Eight-thirty?”
he inquired.
This was the hour appointed,
and it was only twenty minutes off.
We threw the unsmoked fractions of our
cigars away, and returned to offer our
services to the ladies.
This amused the ladies.
They had done without us.
All was ready in the hall.
“We got the cook to help us,”
Mrs. Ogden told me, “so as not
to disturb your cigars.
In spite of the cowboys,
I still recognize my own country.”
“In the cook?”
I rather densely asked.
“Oh, no!
I don’t have a Chinaman.
It’s in the length of after-dinner cigars.
”
“Had you been smoking,”
I returned, “you would have found
them short this evening.”
“You make it worse,” said the lady;
“we have had nothing but Dr. MacBride.”
“We’ll share him with
you now,” I exclaimed.
“Has he announced his text?
I’ve got one for him,”
said Molly Wood, joining us.
She stood on tiptoe and spoke it
comically in our ears.
“ ‘I said in my haste, All men are liars.’
”
This made us merry as we stood among the
chairs in the congested hall.
I left the ladies, and
sought the bunk house.
I had heard the cheers,
but I was curious also to see the men,
and how they were taking it.
There was but little for the eye.
There was much noise in the room.
They were getting ready to come to
church⁠—brushing their hair,
shaving, and making themselves clean,
amid talk occasionally
profane and continuously diverting.
“Well, I’m a Christian,
anyway,” one declared.
“I’m a Mormon, I guess,” said another.
“I belong to the Knights of
Pythias,” said a third.
“I’m a Mohammedist,” said a fourth;
“I hope I ain’t goin’ to hear
nothin’ to shock me.
”
And they went on with their joking.
But Trampas was out of the joking.
He lay on his bed reading a newspaper,
and took no pains to look pleasant.
My eyes were considering him when the
blithe Scipio came in.
“Don’t look so bashful,” said he.
“There’s only us girls here.”
He had been helping the Virginian move
his belongings from the bunk house over
to the foreman’s cabin.
He himself was to occupy the
Virginian’s old bed here.
“And I hope sleepin’ in it will bring me
some of his luck,” said Scipio.
“Yu’d ought to’ve seen us when he told us
in his quiet way.
Well,” Scipio sighed a little,
“it must feel good to have your
friends glad about you.”
“Especially Trampas,” said I.
“The Judge knows about that,” I added.
“Knows, does he?
What’s he say?”
Scipio drew me quickly out
of the bunk house.
“Says it’s no business of his.”
“Said nothing but that?”
Scipio’s curiosity seemed
strangely intense.
“Made no suggestion?
Not a thing?”
“Not a thing.
Said he didn’t want to
know and didn’t care.”
“How did he happen to hear about it?”
snapped Scipio.
“You told him!”
he immediately guessed.
“He never would.”
And Scipio jerked his thumb at the
Virginian, who appeared for a moment in
the lighted window of the new
quarters he was arranging.
“He never would tell,” Scipio repeated.
“And so the Judge never made a suggestion
to him,” he muttered,
nodding in the darkness.
“So it’s just his own notion.
Just like him, too, come to think of it.
Only I didn’t expect⁠—well,
I guess he could surprise me
any day he tried.
”
“You’re surprising me now,” I said.
“What’s it all about?”
“Oh, him and Trampas.”
“What?
Nothing surely happened yet?”
I was as curious as Scipio had been.
“No, not yet.
But there will.”
“Great Heavens, man!
when?”
“Just as soon as Trampas makes the first
move,” Scipio replied easily.
I became dignified.
Scipio had evidently been told
things by the Virginian.
“Yes, I up and asked him
plumb out,” Scipio answered.
“I was liftin’ his trunk in at the door,
and I couldn’t stand it no longer,
and I asked him plumb out.
‘Yu’ve sure got Trampas
where yu’ want him.’
That’s what I said.
And he up and answered and told me.
So I know.”
At this point Scipio stopped;
I was not to know.
“I had no idea,” I said,
“that your system held so much
meanness.”
“Oh, it ain’t meanness!”
And he laughed ecstatically.
“What do you call it, then?”
“He’d call it discretion,” said Scipio.
Then he became serious.
“It’s too blamed grand to tell yu’.
I’ll leave yu’ to see it happen.
Keep around, that’s all.
Keep around.
I pretty near wish I didn’t
know it myself.”
What with my feelings at Scipio’s
discretion, and my human curiosity,
I was not in that mood which best
profits from a sermon.
Yet even though my expectations had been
cruelly left quivering in mid air,
I was not sure how much I really
wanted to “keep around.”
You will therefore understand how Dr.
MacBride was able to make a prayer and
to read Scripture without my being
conscious of a word that he had uttered.
It was when I saw him opening the
manuscript of his sermon that I suddenly
remembered I was sitting,
so to speak, in church,
and began once more to think of the
preacher and his congregation.
Our chairs were in the front line,
of course; but, being next the wall,
I could easily see the cowboys behind
me.
They were perfectly decorous.
If Mrs. Ogden had looked for pistols,
daredevil attitudes,
and so forth, she must
have been greatly disappointed.
Except for their weather-beaten cheeks
and eyes, they were simply American
young men with mustaches and without,
and might have been sitting,
say, in Danbury, Connecticut.
Even Trampas merged quietly
with the general placidity.
The Virginian did not,
to be sure, look like Danbury,
and his frame and his features showed
out of the mass; but his eyes were upon
Dr. MacBride with a creamlike propriety.
Our missionary did not
choose Miss Wood’s text.
He made his selection from another of the
Psalms; and when it came,
I did not dare to look at anybody;
I was much nearer unseemly
conduct than the cowboys.
Dr.
MacBride gave us his text sonorously,
“ ‘They are altogether become filthy;
There is none of them that doeth
good, no, not one.’
”
His eye showed us plainly that present
company was not excepted from this.
He repeated the text once more,
then, launching upon his discourse,
gave none of us a ray of hope.
I had heard it all often before;
but preached to cowboys it took on a new
glare of untimeliness,
of grotesque obsoleteness⁠—as if someone
should say, “Let me persuade you to
admire woman,” and forthwith hold out
her bleached bones to you.
The cowboys were told that not only they
could do no good, but that if they did
contrive to, it would not help them.
Nay, more: not only honest deeds availed
them nothing, but even if they accepted
this especial creed which was being
explained to them as necessary for
salvation, still it might not save them.
Their sin was indeed the cause of their
damnation, yet, keeping from sin,
they might nevertheless be lost.
It had all been settled for them not only
before they were born,
but before Adam was shaped.
Having told them this,
he invited them to glorify the
Creator of the scheme.
Even if damned, they must praise the
person who had made them
expressly for damnation.
That is what I heard him prove by
logic to these cowboys.
Stone upon stone he built the black
cellar of his theology,
leaving out its beautiful park and the
sunshine of its garden.
He did not tell them the splendor of its
past, the noble fortress for good that
it had been, how its tonic had
strengthened generations
of their fathers.
No; wrath he spoke of,
and never once of love.
It was the bishop’s way,
I knew well, to hold cowboys by homely
talk of their special
hardships and temptations.
And when they fell he spoke to them of
forgiveness and brought
them encouragement.
But Dr. MacBride never thought once of
the lives of these waifs.
Like himself, like all mankind,
they were invisible dots in creation;
like him, they were to feel as nothing,
to be swept up in the potent
heat of his faith.
So he thrust out to them none of the
sweet but all the bitter of his creed,
naked and stern as iron.
Dogma was his all in all,
and poor humanity was nothing but
flesh for its canons.
Thus to kill what chance he had for being
of use seemed to me more deplorable than
it did evidently to them.
Their attention merely wandered.
Three hundred years ago they would have
been frightened; but not
in this electric day.
I saw Scipio stifling a smile when it
came to the doctrine of original sin.
“We know of its truth,”
said Dr. MacBride, “from the severe
troubles and distresses to which infants
are liable, and from death passing upon
them before they are capable of sinning.
”
Yet I knew he was a good man;
and I also knew that if a missionary is
to be tactless, he might almost
as well be bad.
I said their attention wandered,
but I forgot the Virginian.
At first his attitude might
have been mere propriety.
One can look respectfully at a preacher
and be internally breaking
all the commandments.
But even with the text I saw real
attention light in the Virginian’s eye.
And keeping track of the concentration
that grew on him with each minute made
the sermon short for me.
He missed nothing.
Before the end his gaze at the
preacher had become swerveless.
Was he convert or critic?
Convert was incredible.
Thus was an hour passed before I
had thought of time.
When it was over we took it variously.
The preacher was genial and spoke of
having now broken ground for the lessons
that he hoped to instill.
He discoursed for a while about trout-
fishing and about the rumored uneasiness
of the Indians northward
where he was going.
It was plain that his personal safety
never gave him a thought.
He soon bade us good night.
The Ogdens shrugged their
shoulders and were amused.
That was their way of taking it.
Dr.
MacBride sat too heavily on the Judge’s
shoulders for him to shrug them.
As a leading citizen in the Territory he
kept open house for all comers.
Policy and good nature made him bid
welcome a wide variety of travellers.
The cowboy out of employment found bed
and a meal for himself and his horse,
and missionaries had before now been
well received at Sunk Creek Ranch.
“I suppose I’ll have to take him
fishing,” said the Judge, ruefully.
“Yes, my dear,” said his wife, “you will.
And I shall have to make his
tea for six days.”
“Otherwise,” Ogden suggested,
“it might be reported that you
were enemies of religion.”
“That’s about it,” said the Judge.
“I can get on with most people.
But elephants depress me.”
So we named the Doctor “Jumbo,”
and I departed to my quarters.
At the bunk house, the comments were
similar but more highly salted.
The men were going to bed.
In spite of their outward decorum at the
service, they had not liked to be told
that they were “altogether
become filthy.”
It was easy to call names;
they could do that themselves.
And they appealed to me,
several speaking at once,
like a concerted piece at the opera:
“Say, do you believe babies go to hell?”
⁠—“Ah, of course he don’t.”
⁠—“There ain’t no hereafter,
anyway.”⁠—“Ain’t there?”⁠—“Who told
yu’?”⁠—“Same man as told the preacher we
were all a sifted set of sons-of-guns.
”⁠—“Well, I’m going to stay a Mormon.
”⁠—“Well, I’m going to quit
fleeing from temptation.”⁠—“that
’s so!
Better get it in the neck after a good
time than a poor one.”
And so forth.
Their wit was not extreme,
yet I should like Dr. MacBride
to have heard it.
One fellow put his natural soul pretty
well into words, “If I happened to learn
what they had predestinated me to do,
I’d do the other thing,
just to show ’em!”
And Trampas?
And the Virginian?
They were out of it.
The Virginian had gone straight
to his new abode.
Trampas lay in his bed,
not asleep, and sullen as ever.
“He ain’t got religion this trip,”
said Scipio to me.
“Did his new foreman get it?”
I asked.
“Huh!
It would spoil him.
You keep around that’s all.
Keep around.”
Scipio was not to be probed;
and I went, still baffled, to my repose.
No light burned in the cabin as
I approached its door.
The Virginian’s room was quiet and dark;
and that Dr. MacBride slumbered was
plainly audible to me,
even before I entered.
Go fishing with him
!
I thought, as I undressed.
And I selfishly decided that the Judge
might have this privilege
entirely to himself.
Sleep came to me fairly soon,
in spite of the Doctor.
I was wakened from it by my bed’s being
jolted⁠—not a pleasant thing that night.
I must have started.
And it was the quiet voice of the
Virginian that told me he was sorry to
have accidentally disturbed me.
This disturbed me a good deal more.
But his steps did not go to the bunk
house, as my sensational
mind had suggested.
He was not wearing much,
and in the dimness he
seemed taller than common.
I next made out that he was
bending over Dr. MacBride.
The divine at last sprang upright.
“I am armed,” he said.
“Take care.
Who are you?”
“You can lay down your gun, seh.
I feel like my spirit was
going to bear witness.
I feel like I might get an enlightening.”
He was using some of the
missionary’s own language.
The baffling I had been treated to by
Scipio melted to nothing in this.
Did living men petrify,
I should have changed to
mineral between the sheets.
The Doctor got out of bed,
lighted his lamp, and found a book;
and the two retired into the Virginian’s
room, where I could hear the
exhortations as I lay amazed.
In time the Doctor returned,
blew out his lamp, and settled himself.
I had been very much awake,
but was nearly gone to sleep again,
when the door creaked and the Virginian
stood by the Doctor’s side.
“Are you awake, seh?”
“What?
What’s that?
What is it?”
“Excuse me, seh.
The enemy is winning on me.
I’m feeling less inward
opposition to sin.”
The lamp was lighted,
and I listened to some
further exhortations.
They must have taken half an hour.
When the Doctor was in bed again,
I thought that I heard him sigh.
This upset my composure in the dark;
but I lay face downward in the pillow,
and the Doctor was soon again snoring.
I envied him for a while his
faculty of easy sleep.
But I must have dropped off myself;
for it was the lamp in my eyes that now
waked me as he came back for the third
time from the Virginian’s room.
Before blowing the light out he looked at
his watch, and thereupon I inquired
the hour of him.
“Three,” said he.
I could not sleep any more now,
and I lay watching the darkness.
“I’m afeared to be alone!”
said the Virginian’s voice presently
in the next room.
“I’m afeared.”
There was a short pause,
and then he shouted very loud,
“I’m losin’ my desire afteh the sincere
milk of the Word!”
“What?
What’s that?
What?”
The Doctor’s cot gave a great crack as he
started up listening,
and I put my face deep in the pillow.
“I’m afeared!
I’m afeared!
Sin has quit being bitter in my belly.”
“Courage, my good man.”
The Doctor was out of bed with his lamp
again, and the door shut behind him.
Between them they made it long this time.
I saw the window become gray;
then the corners of the furniture grow
visible; and outside,
the dry chorus of the blackbirds began
to fill the dawn.
To these the sounds of chickens and
impatient hoofs in the stable were
added, and some cow wandered by loudly
calling for her calf.
Next, someone whistling passed
near and grew distant.
But although the cold hue that I lay
staring at through the window warmed and
changed, the Doctor continued working
hard over his patient in the next room.
Only a word here and there was distinct;
but it was plain from the Virginian’s
fewer remarks that the sin in his belly
was alarming him less.
Yes, they made this time long.
But it proved, indeed, the last one.
And though some sort of catastrophe was
bound to fall upon us,
it was myself who precipitated the
thing that did happen.
Day was wholly come.
I looked at my own watch, and it was six.
I had been about seven hours in my bed,
and the Doctor had been about seven
hours out of his.
The door opened, and he came in with
his book and lamp.
He seemed to be shivering a little,
and I saw him cast a longing
eye at his couch.
But the Virginian followed him even as he
blew out the now quite superfluous
light.
They made a noticeable couple in their
underclothes: the Virginian with his
lean racehorse shanks running to a point
at his ankle, and the Doctor with his
stomach and his fat sedentary calves.
“You’ll be going to breakfast and the
ladies, seh, pretty soon,”
said the Virginian, with
a chastened voice.
“But I’ll worry through the
day somehow without yu’.
And tonight you can turn your wolf
loose on me again.”
Once more it was no use.
My face was deep in the pillow,
but I made sounds as of a hen who
has laid an egg.
It broke on the Doctor with a total
instantaneous smash, quite like an egg.
He tried to speak calmly.
“This is a disgrace.
An infamous disgrace.
Never in my life have I⁠—” Words forsook
him, and his face grew redder.
“Never in my life⁠—”
He stopped again, because,
at the sight of him being dignified in
his red drawers, I was making the noise
of a dozen hens.
It was suddenly too much
for the Virginian.
He hastened into his room,
and there sank on the floor with his
head in his hands.
The Doctor immediately slammed the door
upon him, and this rendered me easily
fit for a lunatic asylum.
I cried into my pillow,
and wondered if the Doctor would
come and kill me.
But he took no notice of me whatever.
I could hear the Virginian’s convulsions
through the door, and also
the Doctor furiously making
his toilet within three feet of my head
; and I lay quite still with my face the
other way, for I was really afraid
to look at him.
When I heard him walk to the door in his
boots, I ventured to peep;
and there he was, going out with his
bag in his hand.
As I still continued to lie,
weak and sore, and with a mind that had
ceased all operation,
the Virginian’s door opened.
He was clean and dressed and decent,
but the devil still sported in his eye.
I have never seen a creature
more irresistibly handsome.
Then my mind worked again.
“You’ve gone and done it,” said I.
“He’s packed his valise.
He’ll not sleep here.”
The Virginian looked quickly
out of the door.
“Why, he’s leavin’ us!”
he exclaimed.
“Drivin’ away right now in
his little old buggy!”
He turned to me, and our eyes met
solemnly over this large fact.
I thought that I perceived the faintest
tincture of dismay in the features of
Judge Henry’s new, responsible,
trusty foreman.
This was the first act
of his administration.
Once again he looked out
at the departing missionary.
“Well,” he vindictively stated,
“I cert’nly ain’t goin’ to run afteh him
.”
And he looked at me again.
“Do you suppose the Judge knows?”
I inquired.
He shook his head.
“The windo’ shades is all
down still oveh yondeh.”
He paused.
“I don’t care,” he stated,
quite as if he had been ten years old.
Then he grinned guiltily.
“I was mighty respectful
to him all night.”
“Oh, yes, respectful!
Especially when you invited him to
turn his wolf loose.”
The Virginian gave a joyous gulp.
He now came and sat down on the
edge of my bed.
“I spoke awful good English to him most
of the time,” said he.
“I can, yu’ know, when I cinch my
attention tight on to it.
Yes, I cert’nly spoke a
lot o’ good English.
I didn’t understand some of it myself!”
He was now growing frankly
pleased with his exploit.
He had builded so much
better than he knew.
He got up and looked out across the
crystal world of light.
“The Doctor is at one-
mile crossing,” he said.
“He’ll get breakfast at the N-lazy-Y.”
Then he returned and sat again on my bed,
and began to give me his real heart.
“I never set up for being
better than others.
Not even to myself.
My thoughts ain’t apt to
travel around making comparisons.
And I shouldn’t wonder if my memory took
as much notice of the meannesses I have
done as of⁠—as of the other actions.
But to have to sit like a dumb lamb and
let a stranger tell yu’ for an hour that
yu’re a hawg and a swine,
just after you have acted in a way which
them that know the facts would
call pretty near white⁠—”
“Trampas!”
I could not help exclaiming.
For there are moments of insight when a
guess amounts to knowledge.
“Has Scipio told⁠—”
“No.
Not a word.
He wouldn’t tell me.”
“Well, yu’ see, I arrived home hyeh this
evenin’ with several thoughts workin’
and stirrin’ inside me.
And not one o’ them thoughts was
what yu’d call Christian.
I ain’t the least little
bit ashamed of ’em.
I’m a human.
But after the Judge⁠—well, yu’ heard him.
And so when I went away from that talk
and saw how positions was changed⁠—”
A step outside stopped him short.
Nothing more could be read in his face,
for there was Trampas himself
in the open door.
“Good morning,” said Trampas,
not looking at us.
He spoke with the same
cool sullenness of yesterday.
We returned his greeting.
“I believe I’m late in congratulating you
on your promotion,” said he.
The Virginian consulted his watch.
“It’s only half afteh six,” he returned.
Trampas’s sullenness deepened.
“Any man is to be congratulated on
getting a rise, I expect.”
This time the Virginian let him have it.
“Cert’nly.
And I ain’t forgetting how much I
owe mine to you.”
Trampas would have liked
to let himself go.
“I’ve not come here for
any forgiveness,” he sneered.
“When did yu’ feel yu’ needed any?”
The Virginian was impregnable.
Trampas seemed to feel how little he
was gaining this way.
He came out straight now.
“Oh, I haven’t any Judge
behind me, I know.
I heard you’d be paying the boys this
morning, and I’ve come for my time.”
“You’re thinking of leaving us?”
asked the new foreman.
“What’s your dissatisfaction?”
“Oh, I’m not needing anybody back of me.
I’ll get along by myself.”
It was thus he revealed his expectation
of being dismissed by his enemy.
This would have knocked any meditated
generosity out of my heart.
But I was not the Virginian.
He shifted his legs, leaned back
a little, and laughed.
“Go back to your job,
Trampas, if that’s all your complaint.
You’re right about me being in luck.
But maybe there’s two of us in luck.
”
It was this that Scipio had preferred me
to see with my own eyes.
The fight was between man
and man no longer.
The case could not be one of forgiveness;
but the Virginian would not use his
official position to
crush his subordinate.
Trampas departed with something muttered
that I did not hear,
and the Virginian closed intimate
conversation by saying,
“You’ll be late for breakfast.”